Hello everybody and welcome to handmade here on the show, Rico to
complete game live on stream.
We are doing some sort of I guess I guess I don't know what you want
to call it.
We're doing some improvements to our code.
We've done a bunch of work to kind of Define some good stuff with the
debug system.
And now, I'm in the process of trying, to consolidate it down into
some things that are like, really kind of easy to use, Clear concise,
the code is nice and not too.
Complicated or stringy and we just started doing that and I want to
continue doing that today.
If you are following along at home today is 211.
You want to take day to 10 source code and start with that?
That is the source code that I am starting with here and let's just
dive right into it because like I said we're kind of just doing code
architecture work here and so there isn't anything in particular to
discuss.
We just kind of have to start looking at the code and figuring out the
sorts of
Of things that we want to do with it, right?
So where we left last time is we were sort of cleaning up the code to
choose.
All that sort of all the debug stuff that we were doing.
We did some neat things.
Now you can actually dump debug bitmaps but we still have some more
stuff to do there in terms of getting the all of the debug stuff
working as kind of a unified system.
So I wanted to do something to start out with the debug stuff is kind
of you know, it's fairly verbose in here.
There's a fair bit of it, you can kind of see how much there is.
I kind of want to take this stuff and maybe start breaking it up just
a little bit more.
As far as the debug system is concerned.
I don't feel like any of this stuff in here is really all that, you
know, it's stuff that really gets exposed to the rest of the program.
Any particular way, right?
If you take a look at where we're doing handmade, debug .h trying to
remember exactly where we put that in here.
Let's see.
Where is my handmade?
Debug .h?
All right.
Yes.
So, handmade debug .h, only even appears inside handmade debug dot
CPP, right?
And so what I want to do is is since the system is completely
isolated.
What I want to do is be able to have a header where I pull out all
this stuff for the debug system, and kind of keep that in a sort of
own place that I can look at it a little more carefully, right?
That's something that I would like to do,
As during this process or that is, if I could manage to take a drink
of water without spilling me to swing it all over myself, which is
sort of a separate programming challenge that, you know, apparently, I
failed.
So, what I'd like to do is I feel like handmade debug dot h, since
that's already taken, I guess.
I
Really care what the name of it necessarily is, but maybe I'll just
say handmade debug macros or handmade debug interface or something
like this.
That.
And then, I can sort of take this stuff and I can put it in there,
right?
So all of this stuff that was in there, that's all that sort of debug
annotation things that are happening.
Just going to throw them in there and they needed here.
I'm just going to include it.
And again, this doesn't do anything at all.
It's completely useless thing that I'm doing.
There's nothing to it.
It doesn't change the coding.
Anyway, all I'm doing is breaking these things off into a single file
for my own logical benefit, right?
It's just, so I can see stuff and know that I'm not like looking
through all this going.
Like, okay, there's a bunch of platforms stuff in here.
Oh, there's the debug stuff, right?
So this is the, you know, just this literally all it is is just so I
can kind of have a little better.
And understanding of what's happening there, right?
So again, that changes it.
Not at all.
So let's come back here and I believe at the end of the stream
yesterday, what we had done is sort of try to set us up so that debug
variable no longer actually is a thing anymore, right?
And so if debug variable is no longer a thing anymore, really, if you
take a look at what's going on here, the primary thing that's going on
here is this Karis our name, right?
The caressed are named that
That Kara star name is something that will have to be sort of looked
up differently.
But other than that, there really isn't anything that we still need
the debug variable for.
So I'm going to try, just pulling the, debug are variable out
entirely.
And what I'm going to do here is anywhere that we were previously
doing something with the debug variable, I'm instead going to use the
debug event right now.
So I'm just going to again, this is just me attempting this I don't
know what's going to go on.
Exactly in here, but we're just going to give it a shot and we'll see
what happens.
I want to find everywhere.
We do struct debug variable.
Can't remember how this goes, exactly.
Maybe something like this.
Is that right?
See, no, maybe the dot operator.
No, thought there was some way to get it to actually search for that,
but I don't know.
I guess there isn't.
I thought we looked this up before, to be honest with you,
But maybe not.
Anyway.
I want to get rid of these forward, Declarations of it.
One of the wonders of CNC plus vs.
The fact Jeff, the forward, declare things, which is always kind of
nuts and silly.
But anyway, yeah.
So if we take a look here, we just kind of have this concept that now,
debug variable links just have events that they're backing.
And I feel like
Since a debug variable Link at this point points to it.
And we can sort of start to simplify things down a little bit, right?
Okay.
So debug interactions are now would just be talking about debug
events, I guess, right?
And that's all that.
That would be happening there.
And then in here, whenever we're talking about a debug variable and
we're trying to protect for really talking about converting a debug
event to text, right?
Like so, and like I said, we're going to have to have ways of getting
at those names.
Now, there is one thing we could do right?
Which is we could try to make, we could leave the debug variable thing
and oh, he's like d cash, the name every time, but I'm just going to
see if we can get away without doing that, right?
That's that's what I'm going to try to do and I don't actually know if
I'll be able to do it, but I'm going to try to do that.
So if we look and we see a debug event somewhere,
We should be able to find see here.
We should be able to find how we were getting at those records to
begin with, right?
So, let's see here.
Do do, do, do, do, do, it's actually called Source.
I think so, this right here, you can kind of see how this works if we
want to get sort of the source from something, all we have to do is
kind of look up.
Event translation unit.
And then the debug record index that gives us what we're looking for.
And then that particular thing will give us back like the block name
that we're looking for, right?
Because that's a debug record and the debug record has the string in
it.
So if we wanted to do something like get event name, right?
Or something like that or we could even just call this get name
because we're passing a debug event.
So we know what we're talking about here.
All we need to do is say, okay, the result of that is just whatever
the events block name is, right, and that's it.
So that seems reasonable enough.
And so now anytime we want to know the name of something we can just
say get name and with the debug event and then we've got it.
So everywhere in cure that I was previously doing VAR name, I should
just be able to put the name in and it's everyone's happy and fine and
dancing around like jubilant children but not bratty children,
actually, you know, children who are nice, you know, and reasonable
people.
Oops, that was supposed to be source.
Okay, so yeah, I'm really that's all there is to it.
There's not a lot more than I do here again.
Really.
We can just now basically remove a bunch of the dereferencing light.
You can see that we're starting to flatten out there was just a lot of
that sort of dereferencing going on.
And now again, we're just kind of collapsing that down into a nice,
you know, more straightforward way.
Again, this is just that sort of smooth kind of polishing operation
where you're trying to get things into, you know, a better
circumstance and hopefully we set ourselves up.
You know, hopefully we're not polishing the turd at this point.
Hopefully, we're polishing something that will polish down into a nice
little beautiful gem.
A little beautiful.
You know, you know, I don't even, I don't even know why I'm saying
these things.
This is not teaching anyone programming.
So, yes, don't pay attention to what I'm saying, to pay attention to
what I'm doing.
I'm just
Just trying to make it.
So that, again, we're sort of removing unnecessary and direction,
we're removing unnecessary cruft from things.
And again, that's that's normally not that difficult to do.
But in a lot of places that can be relatively complex, like in this
system, it's very complicated to has a lot of moving parts to it and
so that's why I'm kind of taking like that your approach of like sort
of smoothing it over over time.
So anyway, anyway, you can see again, I'm just continuing to flatten
continuing to flatten these things out and a lot of cases.
It's as simple as just.
In fact I probably could just do this.
Take VAR and replace it with an event would probably be.
Oops would probably be fine as a thing to do.
So, here we go.
There's that event.
You know what, VAR arrow is probably just going to do that
transformation, just about everywhere.
And this case these are all that was our radial menu.
So with that was, we should re-enable that
Time soon.
It'd be nice to have a menu again.
Alright, okay, so we got VAR.
That's actually going to be event.
Passing now and debug variable to text, not found, did I change it to
debug event to text or something?
Debug
Event to text.
I did well shows you what I know I guess I was more proactive about
that than I thought I was going to be
All right, so again, same stuff here.
This is just changing party event and it looks like we don't really
need to change a lot of these things.
So there we go.
Yeah.
All right.
This again is going to be a direct reference so that should be fine.
Nothing else.
Particularly we're going on there.
This is debug event.
This is also a tea party event.
And same thing here again, just flattening that and Direction out.
So now we're just working directly on those events and everything is
fine.
So in here, we are creating these events.
I think that should actually probably be fine.
The VAR type equals type, debug type 2 uh that's all fine again.
VAR name is not a member of debug event.
That is true.
So in this case, this is a little bit wonky, right?
When we're creating variables here, we don't really have the ability
to store an additional name in them in that way.
Right?
But what I can do is I can extend the concept of the debug variable
very trivially.
I tried the debug event, right?
So we got here, debug event, I can extend the concept of debug event.
Easily to support this because since these are variables of any kind
and there's a union if I want something, you know, like that would
have a name associated with it.
I can do that by just creating a variable.
That's a name type, right?
I can also create arbitrarily arbitrary additional debug records in
some kind of special translation unit level or something like that.
Where I push additional ones on and I can do other things like that if
I want to.
So I'm not sure exactly how I want to approach that.
But again, you can kind of see that this is the place where the
collapsing is going to be difficult for us.
Because if we remove the concept that this has a name pointer in it,
things get a little bit harder.
Now, there is something we could do here if we wanted to, that would
make this a little bit.
had more flexible and I don't know if we want to or not, but we could
actually also say that debug events,
You know, eventually we could sort of move away from the concept that
there was a debug record index at all, right?
We could say that the debug event just stores the foreigners directly
in it and the cost is essentially more again, more throughput traffic,
right?
It makes these things a little bit bigger Jimmy.
But we certainly could do that.
So right now we have things like the location in the source code but
maybe we don't care that much about what the location of the source
code is or something like this.
And you can imagine a storing right into the clock.
You can imagine a storing a name directly in here.
And moving away from the debug record index entirely because the debug
record index, at some level has caused us nothing.
But pain is just kind of a pain of a, you know, it's kind of an
annoying thing to have to have dealt with, right?
So we could actually decide to kind of go that route and stop having
the concept of the debugger could index.
If we don't really care about that aspect of it very much anymore,
right?
If that's not something we really care about, that's certainly
something that we could figure out ways around, right?
And so at the cost of increasing the structure size a little bit,
Which at this point we don't really have to worry about it all because
it's piggy.
But assuming that we were actually in the future, going to try to
compress this down a little bit by only storing.
What we actually need the story here which is basically would be a
just a very simple thing that would happen in the actual push.
All we could sort of start to work around that particular part of it
right.
I'm not sure what I want to do about that yet.
I really don't know.
So what I might do for the moment is I might say let's just finish
this phase by sort of getting rid of that notion at the moment, right?
And instead what I'm going to do is I'm going to say, okay, when I
push one of these debug event things on here, right?
Maybe I'll 0 struck that guy.
So I know it's cleared out and I'm not going to deal with the name
thing yet.
That's not just, that's just not going to be something that I actually
deal with that.
Okay, so we'll take a look at that sin because I may want to do that
and we'll see what we want to do there.
Okay, so we have debug variable link.
I've got a thing where I'm talking about the debug variable and I
don't have one of those.
So I'm just going to again, continue to move those over to be events.
So everywhere we're doing that, that all just will work actually, even
though it's still called VAR ago.
Debug events, same thing here, you look at that
And and yeah, coralie, so good.
So again, this is really just me changing this name, but that's mostly
it not much that has to happen there.
Okay, that's again, just the fact that that bar would have to be this
event.
And that's just about it.
Okay so now we're going to have some things that don't have hoops.
That's not good.
Where are we in here?
Oh, well, yeah, so that's actually probably quite reasonable thing to
have happen.
We don't actually support some of those guys, some of those types yet,
so it's entirely possible going to type that we don't recognize.
So let's see what that is Type 2, is that something we should
beginning?
Handmade debug, oops.
Sorry interface.
So type 2 is 0 1, 2.
That's an end block.
Well why would we be getting?
Why would we be calling this on and block though?
That that does seem maybe a little bit odd to me, to be completely
honest.
That seems just just a little strange.
So whatever type we are and here.
Why are we seeing an end block type, right?
I verify that, that's the case.
And bought.
Yes.
So yeah, that just that's looks buggy to me.
I don't know that we should have any of those in our actual hierarchy.
Right?
Like the hierarchy just should not be having anything of that type.
I don't think.
So what I'm going to do here, just just temporarily is I'm going to
take a look and see why I'm going to see if I could figure out why
we're getting that happening.
So in here where we do this, I'm going to assert that when I store
this event here, I'm going to start that there are type is not equal
to debug type en Bloc.
which ensure it should definitely not be and then when we do the push,
when we do the create, debug variable, or sorry collate,
That's not it.
Here it is.
When we do these, when we create these variables and we pass the type
in, I'm also going to start here that the type is not equal to en
Bloc.
Oh
huh.
I know what I've got to do.
I know exactly why that's happening.
It's because when we did this collapse, I never went through and stop
doing this.
So it's actually just a VAR group, right?
We're storing it in a you ate.
So now we don't want to do this thing where we leave the top part
because we're not segregated.
These are all the same type.
Remember, I did this segregation, we're going to you ate now.
So now this stuff can just be part of the regular thing so that's
actually none of that.
Checking code is actually necessary in this will probably be okay.
So, anyway, there we go.
That's all good.
And again, we're just getting a little bit simpler each time, which is
exactly exactly what I want.
Okay.
So now we got to address our name situation and at some point, like I
said, I kind of wanted to start moving away from those debug records
because they actually causes a fair bit of pain, it was an interesting
experiment and I was happy to do it.
Because he was that when we're talking about those counters, you know,
stuff like that, but it seems like they're just ending up being more
trouble than they're worth to me, right?
And if I can't come up with a really good reason to keep them that, I
just don't think we should especially in this phase of the
architecture where we see what the thing is that we need to do and
they're really, I don't know of any reason why we need to do them
right.
I just don't see I'm not feeling any particular, overriding reason why
those things have to be in there they just don't seem to serve a
purpose, right?
So, I think I might want to kind of move away from the little bit, and
let's take a look and see, realistically speaking.
What what I can do along those lines, right, okay.
So, first things first, let me get rid of that and block check there.
So, first things first, let's just see what happens if we just
straight-up, replace it.
Let's see what happens inside the debug platform stuff, right?
Let's see what happens if I just soup.
Mountain platform anymore, I moved into interface.
Let's see if I just straight-up replace that stuff with something
simpler than it was.
Right?
So instead of a debug record index, we're just going straight up have
a car star, which is just a name for.
Now I just that's just what we'll have.
We're just going to have a name.
So we start the clock, we throw the name, we throw the core index TC
and we store the
Elation unit and type right?
Although translation unit can go away now to probably right.
I think that can go away.
So now we literally just have these and then we'd have an extra we're
having some extra stuff here I guess at some level right because this
is this is to you and 16 and then we have a you ate you almost want
this core index to be a uh write something like that.
But yeah.
Or we could just say we don't have more than 256 threads, but
unfortunately we can't really do that because we want to use the
windows thread IDs and sometimes
Those are bigger.
So yeah, that's that's not really what you would want.
I'm going to leave that as a u-32 for now maybe.
Then now I don't know, I kind of want to keep that small and I think I
wanted maybe try to fit these into something smaller just again, so I
can keep that track down a little bit but we'll deal with that a
little bit later.
I'm going to say something here like to do.
Expand this out and pack it better question mark, right?
Okay, debug record index, not a member, you're correct.
So all of these guys are going to now, be upset because we've removed
the debug record index stuff from them, but we don't really care about
that.
And in fact, if you want to just make this, some kind of super fatty
nonsense thing, that's just kind of crazy.
And we just store all the same data for the moment.
We could actually even see what that looks like.
By just saying, you know what, let's just go, let's just get
absolutely piggy.
In fact, you know what here it comes.
Pig hap.
It's pick out time, let's pick it out.
Let's just get piggy.
So instead of what we were doing before, where the debug record had
this stuff just you know, forget about it, forget about it, we're just
going to stuff that right on in there.
Everything's in there.
The whole thing, every thing is in there everything not some of it not
a little bit of it.
The whole thing is their whole thing.
Is there every last bit, it's all there.
That's the point.
So anyway, we do this.
And now, what I'm going to do is every time we do one of these things
where we have the debug record, right?
That sort of concept of this debug record thing, we're just going to
say, that's just not a thing anymore.
We don't care about that, right?
Do you buy?
Records are gone?
They don't exist.
We don't we never heard of them, we don't want them here.
We don't like anything like that.
So we're just going to get rid of those, then they're gone.
Okay, so I'm going to keep pushing through that, oops, that's not
supposed to be a preprocessor command.
So I'm going to
To keep pushing through that.
And I'm just going to remove all notion of debug record from anything
that we do in here, right?
So here is US getting the debug record out of this.
I don't want that anymore.
So I'm going to get rid of all of that.
I'm going to just say, we don't have anybody record anymore.
And now this stuff is just stored directly on the event, right to heck
with that sort of thing that we were doing before it just doesn't
matter.
So when we're doing begin block here, and we do record, debug event up
in here, that's going to actually be the
The.
That we want to record all of all of the this stuff.
So in fact, you know what that can actually just kind of, I think go
right up in here, right, I believe.
Anyway,
Something like that.
And so this needs to take this record, debug event needs to take what
the file, the line.
And the block name actually are.
So every time you record a debug event, you would just pass those
things in.
You would do something like, you know, file name, line number and
block name.
So just be like file line block, something like that and these guys
would just be, you know, file
Lime and block, right?
And so in here, we do record debug event, we would do file
Klein actually no.
I think about you know, and since those are all macros, I could just
even leave them that way I guess for the most part.
So, really, the only thing I have to pass in is the name because that
doesn't actually that doesn't actually change.
But I think these would be fine.
Actually, I think this is actually fine, there's really no reason.
I can't just leave it that way, right?
So, yes, so record, debug event.
Now needs just needs to take that block name, right?
But that's really about it.
So, whatever the block,
Name is block name in it.
There it is.
This stuff goes away.
So goodbye.
So, begin block is just a record, debug event for the begin block
debug event, right?
Really, really straight forward now and let's see.
Anything else that happens here, begin block have to have a counter,
the counter name.
I don't know if we want to touch that just yet, but we might be able
to get rid of some of that stuff too eventually.
So, let's see here, let's start compiling, where we at and block.
Not an official record you like about.
That is true.
That's true.
We did not in end.
Block pass enough stuff.
So end block calls, record, debug event.
We need a name for that block and I don't know what it should be.
Probably just end block for now, but we could pass something more
intelligent there later, if you wanted to, I guess,
All right, so debug record index doesn't need to get stored anymore.
Record index isn't even a thing, right?
And so, in some sense, this part can just go away as well, right?
So record index can be deleted.
Record to begin with, doesn't need to pass a counter.
The counter is now in the longer relevant, right?
So record debug event, right?
It just doesn't need to be in there for any particular purpose, at
least not that I can tell, right?
So yeah, unless we just wanted to put a counter in there.
Which late we might want to do later but not for all debug events.
So I'm going to leave the part that actually gets those out just in
case it becomes an issue, right?
But otherwise we're not going to deal with that, okay?
So
Again, don't need to pass it, begin block, counter counter that stuff,
I think, well, we'll just leave it and get rid of it here.
All right, so translation unit is going to go away as well.
Goodbye translation unit, let's see here.
Cannot convert from direct fight, debug type to Cara star.
Where's my Duo type, debug type, where is that?
Begin.
Debug, begin data, block, debug begin data block.
Yeah, so cure again, we have these counters.
We don't definitely don't care about counters for any of this stuff.
So really this, this sort of thing where we're doing record, debug
event.
This stuff can be simplified pretty dramatically and the block name
again.
Can just be I guess passed in here.
We shouldn't that be a string is version of the value.
Wouldn't that?
Isn't that supposed to be what that it?
Why weren't we?
What?
Why are we doing that before?
I don't understand what was happening there.
That just seems dumb.
That, that seems kind of stupid, right?
I mean, I don't know that seems kind of dumb anyway.
Well, you know, if it's done, it's done.
Sometimes you're dumb and you just gotta live with that.
That's just, you know, that's your little situation.
You got to deal with.
All right.
So, let's see.
We got close data, block, their gourd, debug event, that's going to
pass.
There ain't no value to pass.
So this is just a, you know, and block and data block of thing.
And then this guy here, this is just
Again, that could pass the name and we can get rid of this, right?
We also certainly don't care about that anymore, that doesn't even
exist.
So let's see, get name now, doesn't have to exist either get name is
just the name that the event has, right?
So that's easy, the translation unit stuff, 4 for matching these
things.
All we really have to do is match the thread ID.
Now this, this could, you know, again we could sort of do a to do.
Here.
Have counters for blocks so we could put the counters just in the
blocks for the extra layer of security.
Make sure they match and I might do that.
That seems like a pretty good idea.
We'll see.
So Source now goes away and anything that was coming from Soros can
actually just be retrieved guess we got draw a rectangle.
Check in there and get rid of that.
Anything that we have from Soros can just be changed now to just the
event.
So I guess allocate open debug block, doesn't
Need to take a source anymore like that can go away and anywhere
that's talking about these sources, right?
That's something that doesn't actually ever need to be stored pretty
much at all right.
And yeah, get record from not even a thing anymore for the most part.
So, let's see.
I don't know what that was actually being used for if anything.
So it's just looking to see whether
The matching blocks parent record matches.
The one that's closing.
So again that's just that's just a way of making sure that these
things line up I guess.
So I guess that's I don't know why we're checking that particular one,
I guess, just so we can unique have an idea of what the uniqueness is
of this.
So we probably could just use the name, right?
So we could just say that these two names would have to be the same,
right?
If we wanted to do that.
At least that seems like the most logical thing.
On the scope to record front, right?
Because the name is now a unique string that we can use to identify.
If not that the string is unique is the pointer is unique, right?
So we can just actually use that to determine look what the scope to
record is.
So I'm pretty sure you could just do the scope to record.
Is actually just a caressed are, right?
And so in here we would say is the matching block parent we could say.
I guess we don't know if it's actually true.
So I should say, if the matching block parent
I need to get the name from and I just need to.
I just need some way of saying that you know the name equals 0 or I
should say the match name equals zero and if the match name sorry it's
a matching block parent.
You know, is valid then it's going to be the matching block parent
name, right or whatever but otherwise or event name, whatever it is
that's going to be otherwise is going to be 0.
Right?
And that's the name that I want to check against here.
So that's tough.
The debug open block stuff, right?
Where we're talking about the the thing to match.
So this is an open d block, and we're talking about the parent there
that opened above apparent in here.
We used to be looking at this.
We're now would be we looking at like the opening event.
And we be talking about that its name.
Right.
So yeah, something like that.
Okay, so
We don't care about any of this, that goes away, we don't need.
That would be block name.
We don't need to record these guys anymore.
That's not relevant.
Like, we don't need that record Source.
We do probably want a typical event though, so this region probably
does want an event to go with.
It would be my guest, right?
That seems like a thing.
We would want to do.
So in these, like, debug regions where ever they ended up, let's see
region.
Yeah.
So, when we're paying pointing to the debug record here, this is
something where we would want to maybe capture out some information.
Now when we talk about the region, those like we talked about copying
these things out.
I don't know if we want to copy the whole thing out or not like we
could just point to a debug event.
It depends if we want to store them as we're kind of doing the
round-robin thing so I could put it to do here that says, like do we
want to copy these out in there?
You know, entirety or not?
And I don't know but I'm just going to store the event here like so.
Although I probably should be the opening event.
That'd be my guess.
Yeah.
So let's see just getting rid of some more of these things here.
So the region this is actually going to be debug event and this would
just be region event, right?
And all that stuff will still work.
Debug record index?
Yeah, that's not something we know anymore so I don't really know what
we want to do there.
Obviously, we could do something where we're just like, okay, the
color index is you know, whatever the pointer is or something like
this.
There's really no, particularly great way to take a look at that, but
I guess we could say.
Yeah, the opening event block named just converted to you.
It's
Dean is going to be the color for now because we just wanted a stable
value for color, basically, something we could use to look stuff up.
So sources are gone so it's going to get rid of them, they're not
relevant all the stuff that was coming from them is now coming from
the event type, right?
And so let's take a look here at debug State scope to record scope.
To record is just going to be what what is the what is the hot record?
What is the hot record?
It's a debug record.
So I
Don't really want a hot record anymore.
What I really want is a hot event, right?
And so wherever hot record is happening which apparently it never gets
set in here, but that's okay.
Then, you know, whatever the hot event is we would set that it to the
hot event block named there that would work.
For our purposes and event but it doesn't look like that.
Ever actually gets set at the moment for all I can tell.
So record counts again.
Don't care about these at all.
So now I believe this stuff doesn't have to happen anymore, which is
pretty great because it was a bunch of janky code that I don't want to
deal with.
All right.
So now in theory again, we're kind of getting
A lot closer to what we want to do here.
I feel like
some degree though.
I do feel like we have a few things that are not still, not totally
ideal in how this is working.
First of all, we made a bunch of concessions to that stuff that I feel
like we can maybe get rid of now, right?
So, let's continue the cleanup because, man, I like cleaning up code.
Let's get rid of translation unit index, because I'm pretty sure we
don't need translation you next time anymore.
It's gone.
So translation unit index.
and,
That's all good.
Right.
So we don't need that anymore.
And now we also could potentially get rid of some of this other stuff
here in interface.
See.
So we just don't need debug records.
Be, they're gone.
So, anything that was referring to those before.
Could can go away.
Don't know how we got get controller.
This this I cut I cut and paste it a little bit too far there and made
debug.
Debug table game, get controller.
There we go, so cat controller.
I think should not be there.
That was a bad place to put that.
That should be where game input.
Is that should be like here, right?
Okay, so anyway, so continuing to move forward here.
I'm trying to see what else I might want to do with what we're doing.
I don't know why we have the concept of a thread ID corinda
Is that just because we wanted the platform code to be able to fill
that out as a unit, it doesn't look like it, right?
So why do we have a thread ID core index?
That's why.
Does that, is it?
Why is that a thing?
Does anyone know why that's a thing?
Like, is there a reason that we don't just do that?
Does anyone know
I am going to do the only way I ever know how to figure that out and
that's to just do it, right?
Why do we have that?
I have no idea.
Sure doesn't look like a very good reason to me, right?
So, that all looks pretty good against Al is working nicely there.
And I am pretty happy with that.
I think that's good.
So we're getting there again.
Continuing down sort of that road.
So we got translation units.
I'm just going to go ahead and grab for translation because I feel
like anywhere that we were doing something with a translation unit now
we should stop doing them right.
And hey there's a to do and just go standard one time hash table.
Complexity seems to be causing problems.
That is true.
It is right.
And so I think
I think this is starting to look a lot better to me.
I would say I'm going to take a look at handmade optimized.
Oops, and made optimized wanted to make sure that nothing in here was
doing anything.
Yeah, so this nonsense can go away.
That's just, you know, not necessary anymore in here.
I believe we got some more nonsense.
It's happening there.
Let's see.
I'm just going to look and see if I can find anything that was
nonsensical there.
So there we go, debug records main count.
So this this is also nonsense, right?
Not necessary at all.
So, I think that's good.
Think that's all fine.
Okay, so again, we got that out of there and that feels really good
because that was just kind of annoying code and just not really that
necessary.
As you saw we were able to pull it out for really not really very much
cost.
So if you take a look at what's going on in here, I feel like we could
probably like I said pack or simplify this a little bit more
unfortunately at the moment.
Like it's like I'm not even sure it's really super worth doing it that
way but it's clear that we don't really need.
You know, if you look at this we've got to
To.
We've got 64, 64, 64, 32 32, and then an eight, you know, one bite,
right?
Which is not, you know.
Not really what we want.
to say the least, but
that's just how that goes now.
When we have the file name, block named thing here really the file
name.
Block name is, is kind of a probably a semi redundant that like we
could use just one pointer to store these two pretty trivially right
by just like concatenating them together or something like that.
So, if we wanted to reduce the size of debug event, we could also do
something like make this file like how file named in an alternator
than blocked in the null Terminator.
And I don't know if that would be reasonable or not, but I'm going to
just
You there.
Nope.
You know, to save space, we could put these two strings back-to-back
with a null Terminator in the middle, right?
All right.
Okay, so now we can go back in here where we were doing collate, debug
records and or Kool-Aid, Group whatever, blah, blah blah previously.
I got rid of this name situation here but now if I want to I can
totally add it back in, right?
If I want to do that.
And now we won't have nulls in that location anymore like you can see.
Now we've got hot entity again which is kind of what I had wanted it
to say.
So that's one way of doing that.
But the other way, the other thing to there is that, you know, we
probably could do, we probably could have made it so that you don't
have to have a custom name for that the event.
For that open block, probably could have been the actual open block
itself and that seems a little bit more enticing to me.
We've got this begin data block thing.
Here, there is the word hot entity.
Why am I copying the string again, right?
If you take a look at when I do that group create right?
So in, in open in this
Walk thing, right?
Not that one in this video, I think what I'm opening this.
Debug block right here is all the stuff I'm doing.
Why, don't, look why am I creating another VAR?
When there's already a VAR there, right?
This is just a holdover kind of from the fact that we needed a
variable when we didn't have them.
But now it's very was an adventure.
The same thing we can just get rid of that entire concept, right?
That can just go away because this vark here that was being passed.
We can just pass the actual one.
We're actually on.
Right.
So we can just do that and now we don't have to allocate one of those
strings ever.
That doesn't ever actually occur, right?
That's not a thing we're ever going to see.
Whatever.
So that it's kind of nice as well.
So when we do that, you know, we're in good shape.
The other thing that's kind of interesting here is if I take a look at
this, we do a collate, create grouped variable now and we copy the
event on to it.
Well, that's just totally stupid.
Why are we allocating another one of these when we already have the
one that has all the stuff in it that we actually wanted, right?
So instead of collate create group variable.
Really all we need to do is do this, that's it, right?
I mean that's that's all we actually needed to do was to take whatever
the debug event was that came in.
We just need to have that to whatever the block group is, right?
And the Block in this case is thread first, open data block.
So it's really just that that's the entirety of what we were actually
doing.
The whole thing, right?
That's it.
Make sense.
So now, you know, in theory,
R.
Of course, that didn't go as planned.
That was not what I wanted to have happen.
Oh, and that's of course, because now, we have this actual group that
were adding here is not labeled of our group, right?
It's labeled an open data block right, but that's just because of the
holdover of the concept that an that an open data block and of our
group or different things, but they're not different things anymore.
Not for us, right there.
Now, the same thing, right?
This VAR group is actually
That open data block.
That's all it is.
So we could say that we just get rid of that VAR group concept
entirely, and every place we were doing that, we could just call it an
open data.
Block, we probably be fine, right?
oops, gotta actually
we run the program.
Not quite.
End block.
And why is an envelope being added?
Did I?
Oh, did I do what I did just moments ago?
Did I do it again?
Let me see if I did it again.
Where are you?
Okay, so, what did I do here?
So we do open data block, why is closed data block getting pushed on
there?
That doesn't make much sense to me, says closed data block, is here
that never gets pushed.
So, why would that be an open data block?
Why would we ever?
Why would that have caused that to occur?
Hmm.
hmm, I say I would like to know why I'm going to find out why by using
the debugger
Always good to use the bugger.
All right, so let's see.
Oh yeah that's not that's not what it.
Yeah, my bad.
Open data block, debug type.
Open code block.
Convert type open block.
Is undefined.
What is the actual one?
We're looking at here?
I got confused.
It was by the fact that I had typed in the wrong thing into the watch
window.
So the event type is one and that in here would mean that it's a begin
block.
So I'm not sure how a begin block.
Got pushed on there.
The begin block.
Ah,
well no, I still don't know how that would get pushed on there.
How does that get pushed on there that's not ever getting added?
So there's that begin block end block.
How does it, how do you get a Depot type of you?
Look, how does that ever get in here?
I don't understand.
I don't understand why is it happening?
Why why why
Very, very suspicious.
Very suspicious to me.
Well, first of all, I'm gonna get rid of this because we don't
actually need that anymore.
And let's see.
Cool, they crave real group and adverbial group these are happening.
I'm gonna do a little assertion here.
I'm going to say, I want to assert that.
The Link Event type is not equal to debug type open block or begin
block.
So it's not getting added there.
Who is actually calling me debug Drive menu.
Yeah, you're just going to call me with that.
Are you just gonna go ahead and call me?
Where are we in the hierarchy here?
What's our stacked look like?
And what's ours actually, I should say what's the stack depth as well.
Sacked at this one.
Let's see here.
Event.
That's actually the Sentinel probably, well know.
Let's see here.
Here to Raider.
Link.
So, our event.
Get rid of interface p.
That's this open block for get render entity basis P.
That definitely should never have been added.
Right?
I mean that should never be added to the.
That should never been added to a data group.
So that's really strange to me.
How did it get in there?
I don't understand.
Add variable to group should be the only way that that actually
happens, right?
And when that is called, I'm asserting that it's never begin data,
block type, so that's pretty strange.
I guess it could be the case.
That.
Well, no.
Because
When those events are wiped out I guess it could be the case that as
those events are getting written, am I am I not properly.
Every time we spin around, am I not properly synchronizing the
flushing of these two things?
That could actually be.
That actually seems like something that's probably true, right?
I could see that being the case.
Meaning, if I'm currently you know this the sort of one thing that we
have not addressed yet.
In our hack Enos is this sort of situation where we're doing the like
frame count, you know greater than cool.
Whatever.
And then we like do the restart collation thing.
You know that part if I was to do we start collation on every frame?
I'd be interested to see if that actually change things, right?
Meaning if I did something where we just did this, for example and we
collate every time, does that prevent the problem.
Yeah.
So that was just an overriding problem was what was happening there.
So yeah.
So that's problematic and of course we will.
Yeah, we'll get to fixing that part.
In maybe even tomorrow we're getting, we're getting down to it.
Try to get in good shape here.
All right, so now at least I know what the bug is.
Let's do this.
To do need to unify the display cash or the collation paging out with
the vents paging out now that they are the same thing, okay?
All right, so let's go ahead and go to the Q and A in case.
Anyone has any questions about what we were doing here?
Not much in the way of questions today.
Looks like
H WD 2 are 0.
Will you get back to game of the Dakota next week?
I have no idea.
Probably not.
No, I wouldn't expect.
So,
do you ever wear the piggy hat at work?
Know it kind of just sits here on the desk for handmade hero.
K.
What would be the thing that would impress you on a programmers
resume?
I don't know.
I don't read resumes much.
I think I like what I would, I like watching people stream their
programming.
I can usually tell based on watching that if they're good or not, you
know, so I probably would want to see a twitch stream and I'd want to
see how you program on Twitch stream.
I'd like to see like, you know, 5:00 at which streamed programming,
that I can just go browse through and see what I think of your coding.
You know.
Bit off topic but when will you do the OD e stuff?
You mean the ordinary differential equation?
You mean just for drag I think there is only one place that we had OD
e a need for an OD e so far, which is just, which is basically for
drag, right?
it's usually just it, you know, you
You need to phrase things in terms of e to the X for drag, right?
So so typically, well, are for any OD stuff.
So, all the OD stuff is is just
If you have something that's like you know, you've got F of t or
something equals e to the T, you know, this is like or there's
constant like the actual e.
Not I'm not making up the letter e.
I mean, the actual e0 in mathy, right?
Then the derivative of T and my math is so Rusty these days but you
know is related to its own self, right?
Meaning the function.
The ee2 a power, right?
When you take the derivative of it still retains the same form as it
had originally, right?
And so, when you have something like drag where you have, you
Eat a function, you have a function which has its own derivative in
the function.
You need to you know, you need to be able to use this sort of this
fact about E2 help you solve those equations.
So that's that's all the OD e stuff that we will do is the fact that
we have a thing where we've got okay.
F Prime of T, equals some constant times, F double Prime.
Of, I'm sorry.
F double Prime of T.
Equals some constant times?
F Prime of T, right?
We've got the acceleration, which is this term, right?
The second derivative equals some constant, which is basically the
drag constant, right?
In fact, let me just draw this out a little bit better for you.
So this is like the acceleration of the object, the drag coefficient
and the velocity.
Right?
And so if you want to compute this stabili where you're going to
compute, what F Prime, and if you want to be able to compute F of T
and F Prime of T, right?
If you want to compute these two from this equation, you have
different ways of doing it.
One is, you can numerically integrate it where you just like assume
some actual values for these things.
And and then just do it numerically, which is not accurate, right?
It's not going to be exact.
It's just an approximation to it.
Or what you can do is actually integrate this up by assuming that that
means that drag is a function of e because it appears that its own
derivative.
So you know that it actually is and drag is such a simple equation,
you know, that that's that ends up being possible, I hope that makes
some sense.
So that's all we that's really that, you know, if you're looking for a
real, you know, hardcore information on um, a knowing OD, he's
ordinary differential equations.
This is not really going to be.
It's there's not going to be much of it on handmade hero.
So you probably going to have to take some initiative ongoing learning
that yourself.
I'm not really an OD e person so it's like, you know, I'm not really
the person to give you a lot of information on that anyway, but yeah.
And yeah, sorry.
Will you send the stream is correct?
I wrote that poorly.
It's it's actually that
It's been a long time, like I say, my math is really rusty.
T is obviously the act.
The dependent variable is that that's actually what your Pat, you
know.
That's that's actually the varying variable that it's the variable.
So it's the constant that's in here that actually moves out, right?
So, yeah, and you can kind of see, you can see why drag is so easy to
if you look at these things because if I write this again, without the
scribbles, on top of it, right?
I'm going to use C for the constant instead since that's what I was
using over here for no apparent reason.
Right.
You can see that like this form here.
If you take E2, the some constant times, the dependent variable, if
you take us derivative you get this right, oops.
If you, if you have some, it looks like that.
And then you look at what this looks like, it's the exact same.
It's this equation down here.
Exactly, right.
So you would just replace if this is your coefficient of drag, you
could just imagine like, okay, I've got my, this is my actual
function.
So now I would know what these were right.
Yeah, like I said I'm the wrong one to teach it.
I you know I don't know pseudonym 73 here, I don't think today but
like you really want someone who's more into that side of Matt that
field than me to teach you OTE.
So I'll literally just do the bass like the most barest thing to get
the drug working.
And that's about all I that's about as far as I can take you.
Because I just don't, I just don't have the
Matisse to do a good job.
Let's see.
Next, I'd bring her ex.
I see a lot of branching in your code, aren't you?
Trashing the caches, and the branch predictor ever thinking about
running, a Chase through cash grind.
So first of all, I mean at the risk of stating the obvious
You know, branching is what makes a game a game, right?
Like branching is is
Branching is what creates the actual Behavior, right?
So you know, you really don't want to be thinking until your game is
running and does all the things you want to do.
You definitely don't want to be thinking about whether you're trashing
a branch predictor or whether the fact that you have branches going to
cause a cash problem.
First thing I would say is in general, the caches trashing, the
Hashes per se, I don't know that the kinds of branching we're doing
have all that money effect on the cash as they may have problems for
the cache itself.
That like the
sort of the short-term fact of like okay, you know, if the branch is
mispredicted, May load a little extra memory that it didn't have to
load or something like this but that's you know,
That's really not something that you're going to.
Thinking about 99% of the time, right?
That is such a small performance Thing by comparison to what you would
normally probably be dealing with.
Its, there's very limited types of code that we're going to be doing a
mirror where you're actually, whatever care about that.
So, really in terms of the branch predictor side of things, a, you
know, the branch predictor.
A is pretty good, but be the thing to remember is where we're doing.
The branching tends to be in places where the only alternative to
doing the branching would be for you to bundle these into arrays of
similar types, right?
And so you could process like all your three twos together or
something like that.
Like, that's not really an option, there's no option, there's nothing
you could do, right?
There's nothing you could do in your code that would prevent you from
having to go.
I've got a menu filled with things, their head erogenous, like is what
you're in here, what you're seeing in here, right?
There's no way you could really do anything that's going to prevent
some kind of an indirection.
You could do an indirect jump or you can do a branch but they're both
going to be something that's a dependent variable operation, right?
And so what's the alternative, like, what do you think you're going to
change this code to do?
To get rid of those branches.
Right.
There isn't something.
You're either going to have a switch statement or you're going to have
a function call through an indirect through a v table.
And both of those things are not predictable by the
By the compiler and certainly not by the processor until it actually
sees what the value is.
It's going to actually use, right?
so,
And you have been soaking up so much of the stream as a catch-up.
I realize that I'm writing these of code first nowadays.
It's really streamlined by implementation brain.
Just want to say, thanks debate was great too.
Well, thank you very much.
I'm very glad you enjoyed them and I'm glad that the use of showed
first stuff is helping.
Grand Dragon been learning about x86 assembly.
And what am I CSS?
Has, is there any way to force the compiler to use a register for a
certain variable, instead of a place on the stack?
Well, yes, and no, you can't actually use the register key word.
But I don't know if it works in in x64 anymore.
I don't remember.
So I guess I just don't know.
I just don't know if this still works.
In x64.
So I mean all I can say is that there is a way to tell the compiler.
You would like something to be kept in a register.
I just don't know if it actually obeys that in x64 ever.
If it might be honest things, it just doesn't use anymore, but you can
Yeah, so I guess you could give it a try I guess.
Is what I'm saying.
Your mileage may vary.
Culver fly just asking, but is it worth while to put so much effort on
the debug some of this stage?
There's a lot of things you're doing right now that I'm not sure how
it will help in the future maybe just because I've never program games
before, but if I, as a new beginning prayer were to work on this,
she's just going as far as you're going right now or proceed on the
gaming part to see what I need first before doing it.
Well.
I guess what I would say about that is like I said, when we started
the debug stuff, I wanted to take this opportunity to show how to do
this kind of programming.
So I'm definitely doing something a little more.
Elaborate than is necessary, right?
I mean, if all you care about is the bare minimum thing.
So I would say that, you know, yeah, if you're a total novice, should
you be spending a lot of time on this?
Maybe the answer is no, but the other question is maybe the answer is?
Yes, because this is something you should know how to do right here
and it's a very safe way to play around with this and you should be
able to do this kind of code.
Right?
So, I don't know.
That's a tough question to answer.
I guess, I would say
It depends what your goals are, for whatever you happen to be doing at
the time.
That's what I would say, right.
Mr.
Fourth dimension.
Well, if you would just replace the branches polymorphism.
Yeah, good point, because polymorphisms free, the processor.
Just does it for you, right?
K what's more impressive?
Previous products and practical experience versus a college degree?
Are you asking me personally or in the industry?
Because I don't know.
Industrywide.
You'd have to kind of I don't know, right?
So
I guess what I would say is for me, personally, I don't care if you
went to college, it has absolutely no bearing on anything in my
opinion.
So college degree means almost nothing that doesn't mean that.
It might not be a good idea to get a college because of all the stuff
you might learn when doing it.
So maybe the college degree is going to get, but the fact that you
got, it doesn't actually mean a thing to me, I want to see, I want to
see the code, right?
I want to see what you're actually doing and how you're doing it.
Things would make a Jelly Bean or the register key word.
Yeah.
That I mean like I said, that's my assumption.
I think it kind of used to work like I remember you could do some
things with it in the old days.
But just my assumption these days is that you know, the compiler would
take it as a hint as at best, you know.
So
So you know, the sort of what you were suggesting or like maybe you
know you want to tell the compiler juicing specific and x86 code and
it has to do it.
That I don't think you can do.
I don't know of a way to tell it to do that.
Looks like we're pretty good with questions.
Oh, and I didn't answer quite at the final thing.
About the person asked the branch first thing they were saying, have
you ever considered running a Chase through cash grind?
And was why I want to say about that is like
That now is not a particularly useful time to do that.
So analyzing cash usage is something that's a very fine-tuned
optimization process, right?
So while you do want to kind of have the back of your mind, if you're
doing something very significant that's going to have serious
architectural, Implement implications for your program, that will
force bad cache Behavior.
Something that maybe is something to think about earlier.
But in general thinking about
Cash usage.
While you're just trying to construct the main portion of your program
is just usually a complete waste of your time because you go through
so many iterations of how things are arranged if you then add thinking
about caches to that process, when 99% of that code will not even take
enough time to matter at all.
What it does to the cash, is your falling.
Pray to the standard canoe thing which is premature opposition through
it.
All you know, you're spending tons of mental energy on something that
is irrelevant.
So what you want to do in terms of thing about catches, you want to
delay that till the point where you're ready to go?
What is my primary data flow through here?
Okay.
How do I make that?
How do I, you know, make that sort of a nice cash current thing and so
you really don't want to be thinking about that.
Until you are actually concentrating on performance, which is now
we're doing at this.
Especially not going to do it in a debug system, right?
Like this code doesn't even get run on the end user's machine.
So thinking about the branches in it is kind of ridiculous, right?
All right, I think I don't see any more cues.
I'm going to wind down.
Save our Mischief Blackboard.
I know why that's up.
Okay, thank you, everyone for joining me, for another episode of
handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, if you would like to
follow along with a handmade hero development at home, you can do so
by pre-ordering the game on handmade here at org and it comes to the
source code.
So you can play around with it and learn from it and do other stuff
experiment.
And so on, we also have a patreon page, want to support the video
series.
We have a forum site if you want to ask questions or see an
antidepressant guy maintained by the community, so you can catch up on
past episodes and original
Tweet bot that lets, you know, when special events are happening and
the general schedule for the week, if you want to catch a stream live
and speaking kind of dream life will be back here next week.
And we'll be back here on Monday for the last week of handmade hero
before I will probably be off for two weeks since I will be out of the
country and unable to stream.
So next week, will kind of be the last week of work for and then
before we have a brief break
So that's the situation.
Hope to see you back here on Monday, until then have fun coding.
And I will see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.