Hello, everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The the show, I forgot about the fact that that would just be looking
looking straight back at us.
They're from the free stream.
Um, welcome to handmade hero.
The show where we code a complete game live on stream on Twitch.
No engines, no libraries.
It's just us.
And we do all of the code for the game, not just a little bitty tippy
top at the, you know, but the whole thing
And right now we're in the middle of doing something that I want to do
for a while.
But you know, everything in due course, you can't rush things.
And so it's kind of come to the point where now we can finally do it
and that is to get ourselves off of bitmaps and wav files and switch
over to a proper asset file system that we can sort of use.
And when I say file system, I don't mean a file system like FAT32.
I mean an asset file which you know
no a system for using the asset file where we can load all of our
resources for the game out of it, all of our assets, for the game, out
of it, and it defines all of the things that we need to know about
those resources in order to run the game.
And so we started on that yesterday and now today, I think we will
probably will get a chance to go ahead and actually write out an asset
file and I don't know whether we'll get a chance to read it in as
well, but I think between today and tomorrow, we should be in a good
shape, kind of have everything
you know, roughly spect and working
So let's Dive Right In There.
Today is day, 1, 48.
So if you would like to follow along at home, you should unpack day
147 source code into the directory where you're going to be working.
If you would like to follow along with us, and remember, be a
programmer, not a faux grammar.
All right, we'll just put that away.
Okay, so where were we?
Let's get back to where we were.
Here we go.
What I did.
And you remember yesterday, I did a little bit of, I simplify the
asset system a bit.
We had added some unnecessary complexity in there and I removed it
when I saw it.
So that was a good thing, but it took up some time yesterday, but this
is where we're at at the moment.
You know, all these things are loading in off of disk as individual
files in that sort of stuff.
Oh, that's no good.
Looks like the simplification I did yesterday, has some kind of a
problem with it but I'm sorry, I thought we tested this.
I thought we tested this
But it looks like.
Looks like this is going this this doesn't look like that's related
actually.
This looks like we have a bug in our estimation of when the sound is
going to stop, right?
Because look at this playing sound.
Samples played is one entire buffer over, right?
800.
And it's only 48.
That's interesting.
We should probably
I'm sorry, it's actually under.
That's what I meant to say, sorry.
So it didn't quite end where it was supposed to end.
So, input samples were supposed to have ended, but it didn't actually
go there and this was something that we had taken a look at earlier.
So we should probably debug this before we take a look at the asset
thing because if it's a transient kind of error here, we don't really
know.
You know, we want to make sure that we understand what it actually is
rather than just assuming that it will happen again later at a
convenient time because we don't know that it will
So, let's take a look at what happened here.
What did we actually?
See occur.
We looked at chunks to mix and chunks remaining in sound and they were
actually going to be disparate now.
I assume that they aren't anymore because chunks to mix actually got
modified
Let's see if that's actually the case.
Yeah, chunks remaining in sound.
So it's interesting about that is even at this point these things
should have been equal, right?
These things should have been equal and they're not.
So where did we?
Where does that?
Actually get updated?
We got a sort of page this back into our brain here, but chunks to mix
doesn't get touched anywhere, right?
Like if you look at what happens, here we come in here.
We say chunks to mix if it's greater than chunks remaining and
And right, and that's the only way input samples ended could have been
set to true.
So we're assuming that this actually happened, right?
Because otherwise, input samples ended would not be set to true and we
would not be able to end up in this part of the code, right?
So, in order for that to have been set to true, it means that chunks
to mix and chunks remaining in sound would have had to have been equal
here.
So the only way that I could think of what would have happened, oh,
it's the volume.
So we must have had a volume change.
Ah yeah.
You can see the bug.
Right guys, do you see the bug?
This is kind of an interesting kind of bug.
And I feel like this sort of.
Oops, this begs the description here where I should talk about this,
kind of a bug and point out a good way that we should probably try to
avoid it.
I would say if we can, I don't know if we can or not.
So,
here is what I would say about this.
Why did this bug happen?
And first, I'll say with the bug, is for people who don't already know
what the bug is.
You know what?
Let me also move it over to the side where my head isn't.
So we have more room.
All right.
So if you take a look at what happened here, when we do our audio
mixing, we wanted to know how far we should mix in the sound.
And we do that by looking at how much we could mix how much we want to
mix, see if
Would run our samples.
If we would have run out of samples, we set weeks or to truncate the
amount we're going to mix.
We also look at the volume change and if the volume changes we're
going to we're going to end.
We also have that as a stopping criteria, right?
And then what we do is we just let this thing loop as many times as it
needs to finish the various sort of sections different sections that
it needs to go through and all that sort of stuff, right?
Well, the bug is when we figure out if the, if the
I was going to end, right?
We say that input samples, ended equals true.
And we set the chunks to mix to be how much it would take to get to
that point.
But we then go ahead and potentially stop earlier than that, when the
volume change would have ended, which means that at that point input
samples ended will not necessarily be true, right?
And so the problem that we have here is we're recording this match and
assuming that it's going to stay true even though we have other things
that might cause it to not actually be true.
We had this bug for both volumes any.
At the same time, we even put a to do here for it's the same bug.
Now we have three different ways in which this could happen, three
different things where we don't know exactly when they're going to
end.
And so that's kind of, you know,
That's kind of just underscoring.
Why?
This sort of structural way that that we've chosen to trigger this
stuff here is maybe not a good idea because we've already seen
basically three well two different types of bugs or two different bugs
that can arise from the exact same thing, right?
so, the question is,
Could we come up with a could be, come up with a better way, right?
And I think that the better way here would probably be to say, well,
you know, if we have chunks remaining and sound
And we know that we're setting chunks to mix to be equal to that,
right?
Since we're not modifying either of those two things.
We're not modifying the chunks remaining in sound when we do chunks to
mix.
And that kind of pulls through here, right, what we could do is
instead of testing input samples ended, we could just say, if these
two things are equal at the end, then we know that we actually
That it actually ended right?
We could just make that be the definition of input samples ended,
right?
If those two things were equal and I think we kind of did that before,
and we had reasons why we didn't necessarily want to do it because of
the way that we were actually processing the loop.
We're using the sample position I guess actually was what it was and
that was a little bit touchy because that thing was getting updated in
various ways since we know that
Chunks.
The mix is a fixed amount and we will advance by exactly that amount
through the loop.
It feels like this might be the smarter way to do it, right?
And so then volume ended would be pretty much exactly the same thing.
And so what we would do is volume ends at, or something like that,
would be what we would record.
And then so instead of saying volume ended, you know, set of doing
this right?
We would, we would just do this, we would say, okay, this was the
actual value that we set chunks to mix too.
So if
At the end chunks to mix is still equal to that, then we know that
that particular volume ended right.
Does that make sense?
So really what I'm doing here is I'm saying, let's make the criteria
that we actually care about.
Let's make that be the thing that actually gets used, right?
And I feel like that should be a little bit a little bit better,
right?
I feel like that should be more in line with what we wanted, if that
makes sense.
Let's see.
So let's go ahead and make this operate over that array.
And this one is what.
Whoops, that's not good volume and at and let's see if that's a little
bit clearer.
So I'm a little more comfortable with that.
And and really, what that's doing is that's just saying, well, if
You've got these things that are actually dependent on a particular
variable, instead of introducing these secondary variables, where we
might make a mistake in how they set their state, because that state
is really not representing the actual end condition, can we go ahead
and bake it down?
So that it's actually checking the real condition, which is this
chunks to mix.
That is the thing that we as we go through this code, right chunks to
mix is the thing that we're actually updating to represent how far we
really need to go.
So if that's the Primal piece of data, having the end conditions,
operate on that, Primal piece of data means that, as long as the
algorithm is working, RN check will work.
Whereas the other way, there are these ancillary values which have
nothing to do with how the algorithm actually function that we were
just setting.
Those can easily become out of sync with the algorithm or we can
misunderstand how they might be set or forget one of the things.
And so it really does help if you can
To try and condense code that way so that it's actually working with
the with the specific conditions that are actually important and not
have it be about sort of the separate things that you're sort of
setting.
And, you know, I think that will be.
I think this will be an easier routine for us to the bug now that
we've gotten rid of that additional state, so that's good.
I'm glad we caught that, that's pretty cool.
And you'll also notice another point,
Just while we're talking about debugging things, you'll notice that
probably we never would have known about that bug.
We would just have maybe a little audio error because all that would
have happened is our sound with stops in.
So the only reason we even knew that that happened is because we
placed this a certain here to check.
And so again that's why if you're not used to using asserts you know
again I'm not the kind of person who tells you to stick a lot of stuff
in the code.
That's extraneous, right?
I'm very sparing that way but you'll notice I do often sick ass.
Shirts in there and I actually stick Less asserts in this code.
What I'm on stream because we have a limited amount of time and I
don't always have the ability to kind of relax as much as I would like
to into the programming and think about it, because I'm talking all
sorts of things.
So I even put in less probably than I would.
In my normal code.
Assert is something I really do recommend.
It is not one of those things like const where I find that, it's just
kind of a waste of typing.
It doesn't really catch bugs asserts.
Catch bugs, and they catch the
It bugs you care about catching they catch bugs like this where we
never would have caught that we never would have even known about
that.
It just there would have been a little audio scratch at the end of
sound sometimes or something.
They've gotten truncated in just the right way.
One time he'd like what was that?
And it's like these little hard to find bugs.
That is exactly what assert does for you.
And so I really would like to every time it happens.
I try to point it out where it's like that is a bug that would have
been really
really hard to ever find if you had to put a certain there,
So asserts, they are your friend and like and they're a good tool to
because you can fine-tune them to catch the kind of Errors you make.
As you see yourself, making it, you know, the more you code, the more
you'll know the kinds of bugs you will make and it's not the same for
everybody mean.
There's some kind of bugs that everyone has is just complicated,
whatever, but there's other types of bugs and const, is that way to
write.
Like, I don't necessarily know that other people might not actually
Catch a lot of bugs with cons, I catch.
No bugs with Khan so I don't type it.
Really, but assert is as kind of flexible that way, right?
You can choose to put in the asserts that catch the kinds of bugs that
you find yourself making, right and so as you get a little bit more
familiar, if you're a newer programmer as you get more familiar with a
kind of mistakes you make in whatever the language is that you happen
to be using
And the type of code that you have to be writing.
It's a good idea to get familiar with that and learn to place the
proper asserts to safeguard yourself against the mistakes that you
tend to make you can think of it.
Kind of like, you know, like a rock climber places bolts and like you
know as they go up the ascent to prevent themselves from falling,
that's very much.
The way you kind of want to think about asserts.
It's like know yourself know how you tend to screw up.
and let the asserts be a way that you
Can guard against the mistakes that you're going to make.
Because every programmer I don't care how experienced they are, how
good they are, will make mistakes and a lot of being effective at
programming is knowing what they might be and how to catch them and
recover from them quickly, right?
So again, can't stress that enough.
It's a very good thing to learn how to do and that was an example of a
very helpful.
Assert that caught a bug that you know may have just shift in the game
for all we know like that could have totally gone out, right?
And we always would have had a little glitch in there, so, yeah.
So that's cool.
That's a good thing.
And let's now go back to what we were doing which is we wanted to make
our handmade asset processor, right?
Basically, a little test piece of code, it's called test asset Builder
and we were in the process of getting this working.
So what we wanted to do, if you remember from yesterday is right now
in the game, we basically just fo build a bunch of
That's in the middle of the game, like, we just say, okay, we're at
startup, we're just like, build a fake asset structure like that has a
bunch of Assets in it that we want and just use file names to say
where to go grab those assets off of the actual directory structure on
disk when you need them, right?
And so that's how we were doing things.
Well, we want to transition to is a single big file that we can just
open a single handle to seek around in it as necessary, and grab the
assets out.
And the file itself will contain all
All the information we need to quickly grab things and all of the
metadata we need.
So that all of this stuff that we're currently having to annotate in
here, inside the game, all just goes into the file and can be produced
offline.
So to facilitate this process and again, what I'll do is I'll actually
make that asset file for us taking all of the art that you action did
and putting it in there and that sort of stuff.
I'll actually do that as a separate thing so we'll just have one but
because I want to show the complete process here.
We want to see
Check out that file right, eight example writer and example reader for
it so that we've done all of that on Stream So that anyone who wants
to duplicate that stuff can write.
All right?
So
Let's keep going what we want to do now.
And since this stuff again, we're just kind of putting things out
here.
So what we ended up doing here was, you know, we had cut and pasted
this code a little bit too early.
So what I think I might do is just go back because we, this was before
the simplification that we did in here, where we got rid of sort of
the debug information.
In fact, I guess inside, handmade asked that we now have some stuff
that isn't necessary, right?
We don't need bitmap and sound count anymore.
Do we right?
They're just, they're just totally unnecessary.
It's only asset count.
That matters, I think.
Yeah.
So what we should be able to do now is we should be able to
This code here, right?
That's now been greatly simplified, so it should be much easier for us
to.
We should be able to do that and paste that into the asset bundler
here and have it all work out.
Now, I do need to go re-enable building it because I think we turn
that off yesterday.
So let's go ahead.
There's that asset Builder.
Here we go.
And so all I'm going to do here is I'm going to go ahead and I guess
why even fight it.
Let's just go ahead and make game assets.
Be a thing off we go right, there we go.
And all of this stuff can can just kind of live in there and it should
compile that way you don't have to even do the replacement.
So V2 align percentage, I'm just going to quickly change that to these
two.
So we don't have to pull in the mass stuff unnecessarily since I don't
want to bother doing that.
It is the thing of bitmap ID.
And so we can also pull this guy's in from howling assets.
They sound ID and bitmap ID.
Serve.
Go and then I think we should be good to go here.
So all right.
So we don't need to do push strings anymore because we're not doing
Dynamic code real reuse or anything here so that can just be file name
directly and I guess we also have to fix this.
Asset stuff.
Here, we need to go ahead and put in the union like we had before so
we can store the the sort of bitmap and sound info as well likes like
so.
So there we go.
And yeah let's go ahead and compile that a line percentage is now
going to be one of these guys, right?
So we've got
It's set this way.
And again, we don't care about Arenas or anything here, because we
won't have to deal with any of that.
And next, I need to play dot value.
Must have it.
So isn't the roofs isn't next idea to play?
Isn't that a sound idea?
What, why did that not work?
Next idea to play.
What was the problem there?
Sound.you.
Next idea to play dot value.
Let's have a class Union struct.
It does though oh no we remove that.
It looks like so.
All right sound ID.
All right, so asset tag ID that is probably something that should go
in the common area.
And remember, we made a place for this.
It was type ID here, right?
So it can kind of go in there.
We're, we're, we're defining, those sort of permanent things.
And then, I think we may be good to go.
So, what I'm going to do here is, leave this
Pretty much intact.
I'm going to make a little you can see this, this is a little pattern,
I will occasionally use.
So if we go ahead and take the game assets structure, like so if I was
to do this right then all of these guys which are expecting a pointer,
I have to go change them right to pointers but since I was keeping the
code basically the same, what I can do is just put an underscore under
it, and take the a dress like that and now write it all.
Doesn't it, you know, none of it needs.
To to do that, right?
So that's just a little that's just a little like sleight of hand that
I will occasionally do.
So all right a bitmap assets.
These guys need to default to zero I think or is it point five?
I think it's point, five is what they do default to but I'll
double-check what we were actually defaulting to
Yeah, it's point five point five, see it right there.
So I think that's really most of what we would need to do.
I suppose, I could have been clever and done that a slightly different
way, but maybe maybe we don't want to be all that clever all the time.
So, let me go ahead and change hero line here to here, 0, line, 0,
comic, hero, a line one.
And
And we will be done with that.
I went, can't see what happens behind my head.
All right, there we go.
And what is this saying?
Cannot force an idea to asset star.
That is true.
In fact, this code now just needs to we already.
This is just because this code was copied before we sort of finished
doing the port yesterday.
So if I just go like this, I think will be good, right?
If I just go ahead and use the new code, we should be good.
And then we'll need the is valid zall though.
I don't really know.
In fact, I don't really know if we care about that.
I could just do this.
Last music is a star 0 as well.
Alright I think that's it.
Just about F open this function or variable may be unsafe consider
using F open S instead.
Yeah thank you for the helpful learning but no this is not a high
security operation here.
My friend, this is a offline asset processor.
So in test asset Builder.
I would like to go ahead and disable that warning.
I guess they're saying, I just pound to find this to disable that
warning.
So there we go.
And off we go.
Okay, so we're now building our test asset Builder so that's good.
but we're not actually read anything out and we also need to do one
thing, which is
You know, I might want an h-file for this, so I think I'm going to
have an h-file where I can quickly view these things.
So there we go.
Now, I've got an h-file in here.
Make that look like that.
All right, lb include test asset Builder .h.
Lovely.
So really what we need to do now is just initialize game assets,
right?
So right in here we want to initialize anything in here that we want.
So bitmap, count and sound count and infos.
These are all like we don't care about any of that stuff anymore that
stuff's gone.
And so we really only have to deal with these guys.
So
Got tag counts and we've got these guys.
That's that's it, though.
That's all we're going to have to deal with.
So we've got assets.
And that is all right now.
So the asset counts going to default to 1 because obviously we have a
sort of a null asset at the beginning, I guess, how did we?
And I guess used s account.
How did we actually initialize these in the original one?
I wonder.
Let's see.
Debug used asset count.
Yeah.
So we could even do this a slightly different way as well, but I'm
going to set this to this.
We're going to, we're going to play around with this a little bit in a
second here.
But let's go ahead and set that up.
Okay, so what I would like to do now, right?
Is, I would like to go ahead and start thinking about how we're
actually going to write these out, right?
And so, what we have to think about is we now have like a table.
Basically, we have this game,
Such thing in our goal is we have all of the assets to find in here.
What we want to do is process, you know, go through all those assets
and write out a giant file, which has the directory information we
need, which is this metadata stuff here, right?
Like all this, all the assets, tough, the info, that the part of it
that's info related, right?
We want to write that out and then once we have that we want to write
out actually all that the actual physical data, right?
We want to write out the actual bitmap data in the actual sound data
all into one file so that it can be accessed right?
That's what we're trying to do is just kind of merge all those things
together and with the directory that could be loaded, right?
So
let's start, let's just start the
Thing that I want to do is make a handmade asset file dot h, which is
going to, I guess, you know what, I'm not going to call it that.
I'm gonna call it handmade file format.
.H think that file formats dot h and this is just going to be a thing
that defines the file formats that we actually use, right?
And again, I want to go ahead and make a pragma pack like we normally
do.
I assume we did a pragma pack or somewhere we had 10, you know, where
we probably had one.
We probably had one in the bitmap code.
Right?
See did we?
Where is that?
Let's take a look crap.
Oh, you know what?
That's because we moved to the renderer, right?
For the for the asset file I should say.
There it is.
So if you remember, see when you define a structure, introduces
padding to make sure things are aligned and the padding can be
different depending on, you know, the circumstances, obviously.
And we don't want it to introduce any of that padding, right?
So what we want to do is to find things exactly how they're going to
be in the in the file.
And so we want to enclose our definition of our file format
structures.
We want to enclose them inside.
A pragma pack push and pop.
So that we know that the exact format that we specify in these trucks
is going to be what's actually written to disk right?
So the first thing that we should probably do is we said that we're
going to have a handmade.
Remember we sort of said in here when we when we did that that test
asset Builder we said that it was going to be an h.h.
a file.
So we probably want to have an h.h., a header something that starts
the file so that if you were to open one of these files, you could
test to see by looking at the header whether or not it was actually a
handmade hero file or not.
This is a very common thing in file formats, and you've seen it
already in the file formats that we've talked about so far, right?
If you look back at the stuff that we've loaded in handmade in handy
here already, right?
You can see that, we have always done these sort of things like oh,
when we load the, the header in of this wave file, you should always
see this like riff chunk header and this wave ID these sort of values.
We predefined
Right there, just nothing more than just specific values that are
stuck in the file to let you know that it is.
What it says it is that you know, it is in fact a WAV file, right?
And so we know that like, for the wav files, it always starts off with
the letters are iff, and then a size, and then the letters, wave412,
it's a WAV file.
Right?
So we know that we're expecting to see that and, you know, do you
absolutely need that?
No, but it's just this nice kind of thing.
For error, checking where your code can always look to see when it
opens up a file, does it see these things that it's expecting to see
if not you can raise an error and it just helps him to bugging, you
know, to sort of say, oh, you know, I think there's a problem here
because we're opening this file and it's garbage or whatever we could,
you know, at least you can tell whether it was actually the right kind
of file or whatever.
And so, these are typically called Magic values is what they're
called.
They're called Magic values because they have no actual reason for
being there.
It's not like the value was picked to mean something.
Instead, it's just a purely magic random value that you pick that
lets, you know, that it is, you know, such and such a file.
So what we might want to do is put in a magic value their right and
the magic value we could just pound to find to be like some you know,
we're going to have a specific pattern that we always expect to see at
the beginning.
Bang of a handmade hero file.
Now unfortunately, H is not something that we can really represent
because you know as you know hexadecimal stops at F, right?
So handmade hero is not really possible and I'd love to make the thing
be like, you know, something, something like that, you know, but
there's really no way that we can do that.
So I don't know what the magic number.
Really should be.
It's a good question.
I guess what we could do is take up a letter from the the rift code
Playbook or to our sorry, take a play from the rift code Playbook
here, and just use ASCII characters to say something that seems like a
totally reasonable thing to say.
And we could just say that we wanted to make a similar thing to this
here, where we were going to do like, okay, let's do an h.h., a code
and since we are
I guess since we are little endian the way that they do it in.
Rif is good.
It's going to be like the first thing first, and that's, that's all
fine.
So we will make an h, a code and the HHA code could just be HHA and
handmade hero asset file.
So there we go.
HAF that can be our magic value.
So we'll just stick that at the beginning of the file and that just
lets everyone know that this is
Is a handmade hero file, lest they be confused about that, right?
So I think that's all we really want to do.
Some people like to put a version number in here, right?
I don't know how much we care about that because I don't know that
we're going to rev versions of these things in that way, but we could
sit
Free to stick it in there.
We could stick it in there and we could do version
Say this is version 0 and so those would just be prescribed values
that are set to HAF and 0 on disk when we write it out.
And so then after that, really all, we're looking for now.
Is we need some way of starting to Define where our data is.
And so if you take a look you know I realize maybe some people have
done this before so I want to come take it a little slow.
This is really very basic stuff we're doing here.
but if it's your first experience with defining your own file,
it may be kind of confusing, right?
So I just want to kind of underscore what's going to happen here so
that you can kind of, you know, attach it to something mentally.
So what's going to happen, right?
When we load in one of these files we're going to load in a chunk at
the beginning of the file.
Let's say.
Right?
That is that header?
And based on, what's in that Chunk, we need to be able to know how to
get at more data.
So we have that magic value and we have that version, right?
And those are just there to sort of verify that the thing that we're
about to load, we have the capability to delude like that.
It is a handmade hero file in the first.
And that it is the version that we expect it to be because you know,
if this is a thing that supports version 0 is trying to load some
handmade hero file from the future, that's like am a Hero version 7.
Well, that's not going to work, right?
So those are there for our verification purposes.
So then the rest of the header, what we want to do is when we load
this, we're then going to be stuck.
Basically, we've just got a header, we don't know what else is in the
file or where it is, or a mess up.
So the next thing that we need in that header is some information
about where in the file we would look for other things.
And also some information about how many other things there are or
things like that.
So that we can prepare our memory in the game to load it in, right?
Because we want to, we don't want to have to do like parsing of it or
we don't want to waste a lot of time because we are controlling the
format of this file.
We are pre-processing it to make sure that it's efficient for us to
use.
And so, what we want to do is we want to just like, give the game the
maximum out of information, it can get so that it can be very
When it loads, these things in, right?
And so that's the next part that we want to do here.
And we already sort of know what we need to put, right?
Because we know we have assets and we know we have tags, right?
And so what we want to do is we want to put information in here that
will sort of tell us, you know, where are the assets, where are the
tags?
How many of them are there, right?
And so, I, you know, was aware of this sort of stuff when we were kind
of working on the asset file system, I've done these sorts of things,
a lot of times before it's tough.
I
I just kind of know how it goes right, and what sorts of things, I
So, if you look at the way that I've set this up, it's already set up,
kind of like it would be in a file.
There's like a block of tags and a block of assets right?
And a block of asset types and you can just imagine how we're going to
do this.
We can pretty much just do a fairly direct sort of way of writing
these out, right?
So, let's go back to the test Builder here, right?
And take a look at what we actually have to work with.
So, we've got some number of tags and we know that we're probably not
going to have more than four billion tags, right?
So having a tag count, that's 32-bit is probably going to be more than
enough same with assets.
We know that there's probably going to be less than 4 billion assets.
How do we know this?
Because even if each asset was only one k--,
In size that would be 4 terabytes, right of gameplay footprint.
And well, maybe sometime 10 years in the future.
Everyone will Snicker at the fact that we thought four terabytes was a
lot but as far as handmade Heroes concerned for a terabytes is never
going to happen.
So we pretty much know that 4 billion which is the maximum number.
We could set in in a 32-bit unsigned integer.
We pretty much know that 4 billion is going to be fine for the number
of things that we have.
Now, it wouldn't necessarily be fine for the total size.
We may want a total asset.
Footprint size of greater than 4 gigabytes, right?
That's not out of the question.
So in terms of talking about places in the file, the file may need a
64-bit offset to say where and it you are.
But in terms of how many of something of a actual individual assets,
there are a 32 bit value should suffice.
Okay, and then we've got asset types, right?
And sort of what I said about the asset types is those are going to be
done a little bit differently.
So when we say here, we kind of have asset type entry count.
And the reason that I said that is if you remember from the previous
day what I said is that we have this asset type table and I want to
actually allow it to say what the asset types are.
That are represented in that table rather than just assuming that they
are 01.
You three four whatever because we may have only certain asset types
represented and we may add new asset types or who knows what goes on
there.
And so what I want to do is just allow that to be a little bit
different, right?
So, we have a tag count and asset count and asset type entry count,
and that's really all that there is that's going to have to be in this
file and everything else.
Will presumably be offsets off of that, right?
And so what we need, then, again, in addition is once, we have that
information, we need to know where we would find those things.
And so, what I want to do is say that there is like, you know, tag
array offset and asset array offset.
Right?
And a, you know, an asset type entry array offset, right?
And, I guess I don't have to say array,
could just say,
That right?
And so the idea here is you read the header.
You know how many of each of the things you're going to have and then
these offsets will tell you where in the file you actually need to go
to get that those those arrays, right?
Hopefully, that makes reasonable good sense, right?
So then what we need to do is we need to actually Define some of
these.
So stored on disk, what does a tag look like?
And for now, these are basically, these are mostly just going to be,
you know, cut and paste, right?
Because we're not really storing much in the game about these things.
So they're going to look very similar, right?
So we have a tag offset, right?
And this is basically going to be, you know, this, this offset in the
file is going to store something like
Yes, right.
It's going to store an array of these guys.
The asset offset here is going to store it, h FH, h a asset, and
asset, count of those.
And same thing here, HHA asset, type entry.
And I guess I don't really need to say entry no sense being overly
verbose like so right.
And we could even pluralize these, there we go.
and so,
Kind of like that as well, or I could even just do it this way.
Who knows?
We'll see how it goes anyway.
So, if you take a look at basic what we're doing here, we're just sort
of, defining on disc the sorts of stuff that we want store and how
it's going to be stored.
So, that's all easy enough.
And so now, we just need what each of these things actually would be
storing in it, right?
And so, here we go, the asset type.
Like I kind of said already is just going to be the type ID for that
asset type.
And then it's going to
You like the first asset index and then the asset count, right?
So it's going to be basically the same, right?
Oh, I guess we did one pass last.
So that's how we did it.
So it's going to be basically the same right.
Except we're also going to store the type ID.
So it's not just going to be implicit in the load there, right?
And then for our H, h.h.
a asset, our HHA asset.
is going to store basically what we've written here in the Builder
because I guess, like, I already kind of did it,
But here, right?
So it has what its first tag is it has one.
It's what the one pass the last tag is it's got where.
It's actual data is stored, right?
Whatever that happens to be.
And then it needs to store.
Whatever the info is that we're going to store about these things and
this is going to be a little bit different, right?
So these it's going to, we're going to have HHA like bitmap and an ha
sound, right?
Like so, and what we can do here is just these are probably fine as
they are, right?
We kind of know the next day to play.
We know the sample count, these are all the same.
The difference here is, we're not going to have a file named in either
of these cases, right?
So, for right now we don't have much else that maybe we would need to
know.
Although actually you know what we do.
We actually do because the other thing that we have here is we have
the width and height.
So we have the dimensions right of the bitmap because remember once we
include the bitmap data directly in the file, we will no longer
actually know what those dimensions are if we don't store them.
Because the reason that we have them now is because when we load the
bitmap file, we look at the header, right?
But we won't be loading.
Bitmap files anymore will be loading data directly out of our file,
right?
So yeah.
So I think that's pretty much it, right?
And you can sort of see what we've got here.
It's not particularly complicated, but there it is right.
Okay.
So yeah, not not a whole lot to it.
I'm going to go ahead and say let's let's organize it this way for now
I think that's everything that we would really need and you know we
could store what type of asset it was here but it's kind of just
implicit in how the game references it, so we don't really even need
to do that.
We may need to do that over here.
But we wouldn't necessarily need to do that over here so we'll see if
we want to include those or if we don't want include those right?
But the way that would look as in here we would include a type field.
That says, is this a bitmap or is this a sound in the, you know, in
the asset field.
Right?
So there we go.
So that's that really
Yeah, I can't think of anything else.
So let's just start, let's start writing it out.
So if we come down here, let's go ahead and compile.
If you come down here, we need to include this handmade file format,
study age, right?
Handmade file formats dot h.
There we go, and I will just go ahead and start writing this out.
So the first thing that we need to write out is the header, right?
And so we need one of these guys, but there is a little bit of a
caveat here, right?
Here is the header and so if I want to actually set this, I can set it
all up.
I can say the magic value is, you know, the h a magic value.
I can say that the version is the H version.
But then I got a problem which is that I don't really necessarily know
some of this information.
I do know the tag count, right?
So I can say that the tag count is the assets tag count, right?
I do know the asset count right, oops, count assets, asset count, and
I do know the asset type count as well.
Well I don't even really know if I do because we don't know which of
those might be filled.
So we don't necessarily know that, right?
We don't necessarily know that but what I definitely don't know at
this point is I don't know necessarily where these things are right.
So I don't know what the offsets in the file are right.
You know where it where are the tags going to be?
Where are the asset types going to be right?
Where are the assets going to be?
I don't actually know, right?
I have no idea where those are going to be.
So you know, I could start writing in code to compute the layout here.
I could be like, oh you know what?
These are going to go at a particular location and maybe I should do
that just to show you what that looks like and then I'll show you some
ways to avoid having to do that.
So maybe today will do that.
And then maybe maybe this will be a good way to bring down today.
I'll do it that way.
And then tomorrow I'll kind of show you.
Okay, we can save some work there, right?
And maybe that'll be a good, a good thing to show.
That's, that's now I think about, that's probably a good idea.
So yeah, so asset type count.
We're not really sure how many of them actually got used for now.
I guess what I could do is just say that we're going to have an all,
you know, have an entry for all of them, but I'm going to put you do
there, which is like to do.
You know, do we really want to do this sparse miss or something?
So then, yeah, if I was going to compute these, right, where do the
tags go?
Well, we can just put the tags.
We're going to write the
Our in, right?
So the header is, is however, big, it is right?
The header is this big.
So, we know that the first place in the file, we can start to write an
array, would be after the header.
So that's where that would be right?
And then the asset types would go wherever the you know where ever the
tag array started.
It's going to go tag count number of tags passed it.
Right.
So you know something like this where I'm going to say all right, you
know, I've got this many
he tags that come after it, so that
That's there and then the assets right are going to come after that.
So it's going to be wherever that was plus however, many asset types,
there were right.
So however, many we said they were going to be of that times the asset
entry their type.
So, so that is where the things are going to be in the file.
You can see that basically, I have to kind of do a bunch of math, kind
of in my head there, which might be a little error prone.
But for a file so far.
Are
Files, very simple.
You know, we could you know we don't even really need.
Maybe we don't need to actually address that but there's ways we can
certainly make that better if we do decide to write.
So that's the header and, you know, now I can write the header, right?
I can go ahead and say, all right, let's write the header out, F.
Right is the equivalent to right file, like we were using in the
platform layer, and it allows you to say, I want to write something of
a specific size.
And here it is, right?
So you give it.
Information.
And and and it goes ahead and writes it right now, there's a weirdness
to it.
It's kind of annoying.
In fact sometimes I don't like using, right?
I like using the slightly lower level ones and I'll show you what is
weird about it.
So I, but just so you kind of if you ever choose to use it yourself,
what you can see is instead of, you know, you pass it the pointer
which is like what I'm going to write and you pass it.
The file handle that you wanted to write it to which all makes good
sense, right.
It's almost exactly.
Like we did in the winter to layer, but then you've got two different
sizes.
You have account in a size and the way that F rate is defined is that
it will try to write, you know.
This many things of this size from that pointer and it will return to
you.
Write a value that's representative of that.
So if you look, it's the return value.
Isn't how many bytes that were written?
It's the number of elements that were written.
So if you set the size of 21,
Then you will actually get back the number of bytes written, but if
you set the size of something else, you'll get it / that right.
It's just I don't know why they probably had a good reason.
I don't really know.
So yeah, so we probably want to do is say oh the size is you know we
just want to write out one whole Big Blocks.
We probably want to say, write out a single unit of this size, right?
That's just blam, just write it out and you're done, okay?
So we're going to do that, right?
You know, we should also do it.
Just verify them, can open the file right now.
So I'm going to go ahead and do a printf here and say, error couldn't
open file, right, whatever.
So,
So that's going to write out the header and, of course, the way that
the C runtime works is it keeps sort of an idea of where in the file
you are.
So you start out writing at the zero with b, and after you write the
header, your then pointing to the thing, immediately after it right in
the file.
So, it's kind of a streaming, right Paradigm.
Which by the way, I absolutely
Of the concept of streaming.
Just the concept that file handles have a position was just the worst
thing.
So bad it's so bad but yeah what do you do anyway so that's how that
works.
So you'll notice that when we set what you know, you'll notice that
even though we're specifying two numbers, they're both just sighs.
Nothing.
Here is said we're in the file to Reich and that's because it's just
implicit that it starts out wherever the file handle was.
And when you write it, it moves that far forward and then you right at
the next position and you can seek in the file.
But if you want to do a seek and a right together, it's two separate
commands instead of it being one command, in my opinion, that should
never ever ever happen ever.
Any circumstances it was a very bad idea.
It's the worst possible way for a file system to work what you want is
you always specify the location and the size.
And the reason for that is because you don't want the hidden state of
this file position.
You want to introduce that at a later level because otherwise it
causes all sorts of problems with like threading, where two people
use, the same file handle and they got the pointers are now.
They, you know, one guy uses it and it's the wrong place.
And you can't queue up the rights because you'd have to save where the
file handle was in order.
To figure out where the person thought they were writing at the time
there, but it's just it's awful.
So yeah, really don't like it.
Just using it because I wanted to write this simple app here and I
said, I would show to use the C runtime library and it's totally fine
to use, but just be aware that.
It's just a bad, bad, bad API.
The worst idea for file API that we've ever had and unfortunately,
it's the default.
What do you do?
All right, so what we want to do now is write out these actual arrays.
We've got three arrays to write out.
We've got to write the tags array, right?
So we want to write out the tags array here, right?
And
Flexo.
And then we want to write the asset types array.
And then we want to write the assets right now.
What you can see here.
These question marks here which are the sizes that we're going to
write, we actually already know what those are because we use them up
here, right?
So what we want to do is we probably want to reuse that work and just
say, okay, we've got some sizes here and I guess we, these sizes have
to be restricted to you 32s at the moment because we're using a
32-bit, right?
But that's, that's fine, but all will be.
So right here, we have the tag array size, right?
Tag array size.
So and then here we have the asset type asset type
Side array size, right?
A sit tight.
Sighs.
And then finally, we didn't do the assets one because we didn't
actually need to put anything after it, but we will eventually.
So, we have the asset array size and that's just going to be the
header asset, count X size of ha asset.
And I guess, let me see.
File formats.
Here, it's tags, tag asset type count, so that should be
I want that to be lined up.
There we go.
Okay.
So now we actually know what the sizes are, right?
This is the tag array size.
This is the asset array size and this is the oops.
This is the asset type array size and these are the assets, right?
And so now what we really need to do is we just need to actually build
these guys, right?
We need to actually build
The actual arrays here that we're going to write out.
So we can compile and we should everything should be fine.
But we haven't actually, you know, we haven't actually constructed
these asset array as a type array.
So yeah, so that's it.
Really?
And that would give us a file that who's had its headers structured
properly, right?
But we need to actually produce those.
So let's take a look at what we've got here.
Now, if we actually just made these be exactly if we actually just
produce these by using the hhha in the tag stuff.
So we can do that for some of our stuff for tags.
For example, we could totally do that, right?
So if we make this be an h.h., a tag instead, right?
And got rid of asset tag, nothing would change, right?
I think everything would just be fine.
Right?
And so then assets tags is just the thing we constructed in memory is
actually exactly the thing that we actually wanted, right?
It's just totally, it's just totally the right thing, right?
So that's that's totally easy.
Totally fine.
So then the question is, well, what else can we do that with right
asset type?
That thing here we could totally do it with that as well, right?
Because what we could do is just
Well, that array, we're kind of going to have to compress so well, no,
you know what, we totally could now we could totally do it with that
as well, we could totally do with that as well.
So, let's go ahead and do that as well.
I'll just get rid of asset type here and change this to HHA.
What did I call that in here?
It's just asset type yet.
It is hsas at type, right?
And we do know that we can never have more than asset count of these.
So, what I'll do here is just call this
This in fact, I'll start to break these out.
Little bit more, right?
So we have the tags, we have the assets, we have the asset type count
as well.
What I can do here and these these ones also can, these can sort of
start to go away and we can clean that up a little bit, but if I go
ahead and do that, then I can also do this assets asset type array
like so.
So I'm going to go ahead and just do that asset types.
Right.
So yeah, if I do it that way, then what I'd have to do though is when
we are actually doing the entries here, what is, what are we talking
about?
Right, she say Jas it tight.
Yeah.
So if I actually do it that way, the only thing that we would have to
change is when we do begin asset type right.
When we do this type ID here, when we set what these are only thing I
would have to do is just store it, right?
Are the type because that's the only thing that we actually changed in
the in the entire thing, right?
So now our asset type array also conforms to the file format because
it's actually storing the type ID because the rest of the stuff was
the same, right?
So the only thing that we had to do is stick what type of asset we
were talking about into that array.
And so now we've done that.
So the only thing that's a little bit squirrelly is, is that assets
because those
Those are the ones that actually store two different things right,
depending on what we're doing.
And so, let's just go ahead and comment that out for a second since
we're out of time.
So that
This code, let's actually just step through it quickly because I want
to I want to sort of show you what we're doing here.
If I go ahead and do M SW W, builds test, asset Builder, EXE,
Oops, I think, I think I maybe did a not-so-good batch file.
Yes.
You'll notice we made a little batch file so I could type Ms Dev
instead of Devon's because I'm so used to typing it.
All right, we didn't pass any arguments to it.
I think that's the way you do that, right?
There we go.
So when I actually call that it didn't actually passed the fact that I
wanted to open that file,
All right, so what I want to do here, I've just I've created sort of a
new debug environment by opening by launching with the test asset
Builder, instead of our normal XZ because I just want to kind of Step
through this.
So if I go ahead and set this, this guy's directory to be looking at
our standard handmade directory, the way that we do, right?
Handmade data like so then if I start step through here,
oh,
No, debug for the file.
Do you want to cook tuna bugging?
No.
Did I not specify a debug info?
What happened?
- Z?
Scott z7.
So why does it not have debug info?
Dare I ask
Where's the compilation line to build our social link common Linker
Flags incremental.
No opt ref, seems a little odd, doesn't it?
Like, where's the
Where's the wires?
Are no, debug info.
Oh, do we like delete?
Ah,
Because we delete the PD bees here.
So we really probably want to push this up like so there we go.
We were deleting the pdb is because that's part of our little build
process that we're doing.
All right?
So here we go.
We come through here and we're going to generate all our assets,
right?
Just the same way that we were doing them before so or not.
What is the problem?
Assert, debug asset about less than asset?
Ah, I guess I should mention
And fix.
So in the way we were doing it before our asset count in the, in the
game was actually doing the total number of these things that you
could have at all.
So these asserts are no longer actually meaningful, right?
Because asset count actually tracks the actual number.
So really what I think we should do here.
Sorry for going over time.
Sometimes you know how it is.
I just I'm in the middle of something and you got to do it.
I think what we really want to do here is just get rid of those if
that makes sense.
And go ahead and clean those
Out because what we really want to do is just have it be, you know,
always using actually the asset count itself, instead of having that
debug value, right?
It's just, it's just whatever the actual asset things are.
So there we go, because we need, we need that count for our other
stuff as well.
So see tag count.
What is this?
This is just asset count.
And then these guys go away, all right?
So now we can get rid of those assertions because I believe this will
always be, you know, that's never going to actually be possible.
Oh, you know what I could do?
I could do array count assets right since those are static arrays.
Now do we have any more of those assertions anywhere?
Yes, we've got one right above it.
So that is this one right here, right?
Because those remember, we were dynamically allocating those in the
actual game whereas now they're just static arrays.
So okay, we've defined everything here and we can take a look right.
This is the assets sort of meta structure that we've created here.
So like you can look here's all the tags, right?
That we've made for, you know, for whatever looks like we don't have a
whole lot.
Lot of different tag types being used best as we can really play with
the tags much.
And we've got the asset types to find here in this array, right?
And then we got the assets themselves and it looks like those are
valid and all that stuff, right?
So now we're going to come through here and actually do right out the
file.
So the first thing we do is we prep that header, right?
And you can see it here.
Is that magic value, right?
And we can even see if we tell the debugger.
I'd like to look at that as, you know, an actual care.
So you can see the H AF that we wanted there.
And so, you know, here, we're prepping the header saying there's 13
tags 17, asset types, 51 assets, and then the offsets we haven't
specified yet, right?
So there, you know, the header itself is,
Before bytes long.
So you can see that the asset tiger is going to start on the 44th bite
and then the type array is going to start after that.
The assets are gonna start after that and then we're just going to
write them out.
So that writes out the header that writes out the tag array that
writes out the asset type array and we have it.
Finished the assets yet we have closed the file and exit and that is
our asset file, right?
Not done yet.
But that is the entire process and you can pretty much see.
It's really not very
Very complicated.
We're really just going to basically do that again tomorrow.
And there you can see the the test dot out file that we have produced
now.
I don't actually know if I have anything on here that can view.
I don't know if I have a hex editor on this, we may have to download a
hex editor.
I could use emacs is hex editor is like the worst, the worst, it's
just awful.
You know, this is not a long-term solution, but whoa.
What just happened there?
Am I missing something?
Is that actually, how did we manage that?
Is that actually what though that's test dot out I want test that ha I
was going to say I almost freaked out there's like how did that
happen?
So I'm going to try hexyl mode.
I don't recommend doing this at
It's awful.
But, you know, just to give you some perspective on what happens.
So this is looking at the actual file that we wrote out in HEX in a
hex editor.
So we can just see what the actual data is.
You can kind of see that we got exactly what we expect, right?
Remember a you 32 is 4, bytes long.
So here are those for a b 1, 2, 3 4 and they are HAF, right?
Then we have the version number, which was also for B and it's just
set to 0.
So there are the 40 bytes.
And you can just go ahead and read these directly out, right?
Then we have the tag count, right?
That was in there as well and you can see.
Now remember, it's little endian, right?
So the lowest order thing comes first so that 0 D is, that's the tag
count, right?
If it was more, if the, if we had a lot more tags, you would see
numbers up in here as well, right?
But we only have a very small number of taxa far, right?
So, there's a tag count and you can just see that it, you know, it
getting written out here and then we wrote,
You know, the various these are the, this is like tiger a out here and
the asset type array, right?
And so that's all we're doing, you know, really, really
straightforward.
It's really just a question of taking the stuff in memory and writing
it out.
We're doing the simplest possible file format stuff and so that's
like, you know, that's all we're trying to accomplish right now.
Now, I don't actually remember how to get out of hexyl mode.
I remember it's you can't alt k-kill buffer.
Yes, thank you.
All right, so I guess we'll go ahead and go to questions.
So let me go ahead and start the Q&A and tomorrow, we can go ahead and
finish up writing those things, right?
So if you have questions, please pray.
Fix them with q: and so that I can see them.
And yeah, if you have a question about what we're doing, if you have
an off topic question, please save it for tomorrow's pretty stream.
Gaston, five, why is he positioned for a stream?
A bad idea.
So essentially, it's because it's hidden state.
That is easy to get wrong and you always should know where you're
actually are going to be.
So I'll give you a couple examples, right?
So, let's suppose I say, right?
You know, you know, chunk a right.
I'm just going to say right a, and we know that means chunk, and then
I'm going to say, right?
Be okay.
This is the stream position way of doing things, I say, write a I say
right, be right.
This is the bad way.
Here is the good way.
if I instead say right,
You know, location a a right location B.
Be okay.
So I'm saying this is good and this is bad, right?
And so the question is why?
Well the answer is this always works in all circumstances, no matter
what you want to do.
So if your API looks like this where you say, right the location and
the size, right?
This will always work.
This only works for single-threaded, very simplistic, use cases, and
I'll give you some examples.
So let's say, I want to have this be, you know, if I'm just exiting,
the simple basic single threaded, right?
So I come through and here is my file, right?
And I say, I want to write a and here's location a and I happen to
know the file pointer is pointing there.
So it writes in a and we're happy, right?
I then
And I see be and I'm like, okay be goes here and that happens to be
where I want to be and so it's all good, right?
That's the stream version.
That's what you want to have happen now.
Suppose, I now do something where I say, oh, you know what, I want to
queue up my rights, right?
I want to queue up where the rights are going to be, right?
And so these are going to get added to a queue.
So I go ahead and I add right a and I add right.
Be I say, you know, I do add and add.
Well the problem now is let's suppose that Q maybe that Q is an out of
order Q, right?
Maybe maybe this gets added such that it's going to pop off first.
So now what happens is, when they pop these things off, it pops off be
first, right?
It's like a stack, let's say so it pushes a, it pushes be, it pops
off.
Be, that means b gets written first at location, a witch and it's
longer.
So, who even knows where a ends up a ends up somewhere out here.
And now, I've got things in the wrong order and in the wrong place,
right?
So not good.
So already even in a single-threaded case.
If you queued, you'd already have to start storing this information.
So behind the scenes, if you did have a streaming concept it's going
to have to record where the stream at thought you were writing anyway,
right?
So that's just going to happen so that's going to happen.
So that's that's that right now.
Let's suppose it's multi-threaded because now things get even worse,
right?
If it's multi-threaded I don't even know what's going to happen here,
So let's suppose
Close that my entire interface to the operating system?
I guess the other way to say it is in this case, I could fix this by
saying, okay all cues have to be first in first out, right?
And then this case would work, right?
I just guarantee that if I pushed a first, then a comes first and then
B and then I don't then I don't need to store this right.
But let's suppose that I then say, okay, we're going to have things be
multi-threaded right?
Yeah, because that would still allow me to do this, right?
Say, I want to fix that, right?
And I want to do something where it's multi-threaded.
So I don't know what the file handle is actually, where the streams
actually going to point, right?
I don't know.
So I want to be able to say, well, let's always make sure the file
handle points to where a is and always make sure the file handle
points to where B is right.
So, I write a thing that's like seek to location a.
Write a seek to location, B.
Right?
Be right.
So I'm saying well alright, you know, it's multi-threaded.
And so, I don't know you or, you know, I want to do these out of
order, right?
Or I don't know what order they're being done in.
So we're basically saying, oh, okay, I can emulate the good API by
just doing, you know, the Cyrano is it has seek and it has right?
So, I'll just, I'll seek to where I want to write.
And then, alright, I'll seek to where I want to write and then I'll
write, right?
Surely that will fix the problems that we were going to you know the
any problems that we were going to see because it makes sure that I'm
always at the location that I think I'm going to be at, right?
Well the problem is multi-threading totally breaks this
Because if you seek to here right and then you expect to write at that
location at any time.
If this was thread, be right?
Here's here's another thread.
I guess I'll do well I could do thread just to avoid confusion.
Here's thread to and here's the red one.
If thread one executes, it seek, but then gets preempted and thread to
starts, executing executes, its seek.
Then does the right?
And then we pop back to this guy at some point, and he tries to do his
right, his right?
Will this seek doesn't matter anymore because it got overwritten by
this one, right?
And so, it's absolutely critical.
That the Sikhs always be bundled directly with the right in that low
in the, in the actual part of the API that actually does the
operation, right?
Because otherwise, no matter what you do, if you have to do this at
some point, you will break in a multi-threaded scenario, right?
So that's awful.
It's just really, really bad.
Never never never ever, ever API do that?
It's awful.
Now, if you then want to, if you want streaming Behavior higher up in
the API, you can always make a little thing that's like, you know,
struct
my stream, right?
That's like you 64 position, you know, file handle, or whatever it
right.
I mean, you know, file,
File or whatever, right?
And you just issue your rights through this thing.
It looks at what the position was issues the proper right in this
format, right to the, to the, you know, that needs to happen and then
increments position by the amount.
And now, you know, that because this is unique to your thread, you
will never have to deal with the other problem, right?
So, that's the right way to do it in my opinion, because then,
another way to say this would be, if you do it this way, it means only
people who actually
We care about the streaming part ever deal with it.
Whereas if you do it this way at your lowest level, what that means is
that most people who don't really care about streaming because most of
the time you're loading chunks out of a file in a multi-threaded way
and I'm getting this back this batch whatever, right?
If you do it this way, what you then we'll have to do, is you'll have
to proliferate the number of operating system handles.
You actually have, if your operating system works this way, right?
Because if your operating system only allows you to do seek, right?
That means that every thread has to have a separate actual operating
system handle to the file because there's no other way to make it
thread safe, if you don't do that, right?
Whereas, if your operating system API is just always,
+ + contents, right?
Then, all you have to do is it's a few places that you actually want
streaming.
You just implement it right?
And then everything is nice and clean and you only need one handle to
the file.
No matter.
How many people are accessing it, right.
You never need multiple OS handles.
So yeah, so I hate I really hate this.
I never ever like this.
And I almost always never abandon almost never actually use much of
this sort of thing in.
Exactly.
This way, I find that when I actually do want to do something like
this, usually wants to be more complicated anyway.
So the crappy one that's built into the OS for me, I ever want, I
don't want that one.
It's not good, right?
So I find that it's I even typically even if the OS has the streaming,
I have to duplicate that streaming myself because I want more
abilities than it gave me or whatever.
And I want where I want to be more convenient, right?
If I'm if I'm going through the trouble of making this API where I'm
going to, I'm saying that having the ability to talk about things
lining up.
Certain ways is beneficial.
I typically want more than what the OS gives me.
So hopefully that gives you some
some sort of what's around looking for perspective on just why I have
an aversion to it.
Are you concerned that trusting the file format?
Could have security concerns each you.
Someone could say they've made some modded assets and give out a
specially crafted H file, that runs arbitrary code.
No, I am not really concerned about that.
Pretty much at all.
and the reason for that,
Is this is not like this code is not going to be designed for
security, right?
Like, we are not going to try to make this a mission-critical kind of
app, so it's just assumed that, you know, if you, if you are for some
reason, running handmade hero with elevated privileges on your machine
or whatever, you know, all bets are off.
I have no.
It's going to do, it's not my responsibility, it's a game.
It's not you know meant it's not going to be put through the kind of
The analysis that you would need to do in order to have that be true,
right?
So yeah, so I'm not concerned about that.
About the fuzz testing aspects of it if that makes sense.
What we and what I would suspect would be the case in general is that
I guess what I would say about that is
It should be the case, like, let's say, Microsoft was competent,
right?
It should be the case that you would never even remotely.
Have to think about what you just said, right?
Because it's a game.
It doesn't need to send email, it doesn't even need to connect to the
internet.
But you know, whatever it doesn't need to write to anything on the
hard drive other than a small area to do save files, right?
It needs to do is essentially nothing and it would have been trivial
for Microsoft for many years to make Windows, such that it could run a
game with no risk to the user.
It would have actually been very, very easy for them to do that.
Pretty much the only thing that isn't
About that is the GPU security part of it, right?
But they have chosen to make it almost the opposite of that they
basically chosen to make it so that you can't really even install a
game.
Most of the time without having administrator privileges and you,
oftentimes have to run it with elevated privileges anyway.
And so it's kind of sad that this is even something you have to think
about because what you're talking about could easily happen.
Like most games can be given data files, that would allow them to
execute arbitrary code like pretty much all of them, right?
But I really just don't think that is the game developers
responsibilities.
That is what an operating system is supposed to do.
And I am not really willing to spend a ton of time cleaning up after
Microsoft's fault because they're the ones who charged you $199 for
software whose job.
It was to make sure you did not have to trust random game developers
to be Security, Experts.
And they are the ones who should be fixing this, right?
And I think it's unrealistic to expect game developers in general, to
even have the security expertise.
Necessary to know whether they've covered all the angles, could we do
some work, some reasonable work, to try and Bulletproof the handmade
hero asset, file against that kind of thing.
Yes.
Should we consider ourselves qualified to actually say that?
It can that it is, you know, bulletproof.
Absolutely.
Not, I'm not a security researcher.
I have no idea all the things that could be happening there.
And so, you know, to really do a thorough security audit on our code,
I think, is way out of the question and definitely not something that
I would ever want to undertake certainly, it's way beyond my sort of
Area of expertise.
Thank sense.
What is the main difference between using a search in your code and
writing separate test functions programs, that check your results and
when do you choose one over the other?
So asserts are the preferred method typically in game development
because most of the time in game development, it is difficult or
impossible to write actual inclusive tests, like tests that actually
cover, all of the things you might want to do.
So most of the time in game development, you'll be dealing with
asserts because writing separate test code is infeasible.
It's not to say that you couldn't write separate Tesco that test some
things but those things are usually the least interesting things
they're going to be the things that are least likely to be the bugs
that you will actually have trouble.
Finding
and so a search are a lot more valuable because you could put them
everywhere and they catch bugs at runtime.
When things are actually happening in real scenarios, not fake
scenarios that you've created in your test programs to try to see if
you can find bugs.
Now, when you would actually use a test function, it's when you would
like to bulletproof something in anticipation that the bugs in it will
be subtle or hard-to-find.
So, for example, let's suppose that what we wanted to do was really
make sure our mixer didn't have any bugs in it.
Well, we could easily write some test code that would pass a bunch of
different kinds of buffers to the mixing code to see if we can get it
to fail.
And what I would point out there is we probably would still use the
assertions in a lot of cases to find where the bugs are.
And so, the test code, in some sense is almost there to try to make
the asserts happen, right?
We're trying to force the code into a situation where it's going to
hit uncomfortable places for it.
That are not exercise that frequency frequently that will cause that
assertion, right.
examples of places where I have written test code in the past memory,
allocators,
Database queries to use the term loosely like, like like the actual
code that implements handling a date.
It like the database code basically is when we put it math functions
like when we Implement a math function, let's say we were to
implement, you know, our own cosine, you know, verifying that it
actually lines up with the cosine that we think that's a very common
place to write test code.
So there are places and we might we might do that on.
Made here a couple times as well.
Well, multiple threads pose any problems to reading the assets file.
No, and that's one of the reasons why I like I was saying I like to
make things be always talking about reading from a particular
location.
So when we have threads that will read from the asset file, they will
always issue.
Used to the operating system that are like I need to read this
location for this much memory, right?
For this much size.
It's C++ that introspection with this.
Be a place where you would use it to introspect the types.
You want to include in the asset pack.
Probably not like you're you're right in that.
This is the type of code that maybe you might use introspection for in
the sense that like writing things to disk write, is a typical place
where you want to stretch code for our purposes.
I
I've kind of architected it so that we get a ton of Leverage from a
very small number of things.
So we really just have tags assets and asset types and they're so
simple that any code that you might use introspection for is probably
just going to be dead weight.
So the time that what you're talking about would come into fruition a
little bit more would be like let's say that this was not going to be
a game that was procedurally generated and it said it was going to be
a game where it was very heavily authored.
So we were thinking they're gonna be
Of level designers doing a lot of level design.
So we've got all of these things of like oh there are traps and traps
.22 script code that runs on the Trap which acts as think right?
You might start to have a proliferation of structured stored types.
And at that point you can leverage introspection to take some of the
heat off you for writing that file IO code.
In our case the file a Coke is gonna be so simple that while you could
have used some introspection for it.
It's probably just not going to save you that much time in practice,
right?
And so yeah just to answer a question there.
It's like what you're saying is totally right.
It's just in our game.
We've kind of just don't part of it.
That's the procedural generation aspect of it and because we're smart
about it.
A smart about how we organize things, we just don't have that much
work to do here, but it is the kind of a place where in a game that
needed more from its backing store where you were, yes, you absolutely
could benefit from the C++ having intersection if it did.
Are there any specific times your stream start and end?
Yeah.
Actually, there are if you go to handmade hero dot-org, the Tweet bot,
that's there.
You can click on tweets, you can either subscribe to this or just
check it.
And you can see when the way that it works at the beginning of the
week, it will show you the schedule and that will tell you when it
will be live.
And usually, what we do is we're on stream anywhere from
Five to 30 minutes beforehand just kind of hanging out and chatting.
But then at the scheduled start time, here we usually try to start
programming sometime around there and you can also see that during,
you know, each
A it will send out a reminder.
So if you just wondering what the stream is for that day, it typically
there's a tweet that will tell you that and so that's usually the
easiest way to know if you're just on the web or whatever.
Why not just read the entire file in as a string and parse it.
As you please, then do the same for writing.
So for writing anything goes.
And like I said, we're not really concerned with writing the asset
file, we're just going to assume that we've spect an asset file.
And there's some thing that will produce an asset file in that format,
right?
And like I said, I'll take care of bundling all the assets that we
actually have up and writing them out into the file.
And that's how we'll distribute the artists that's for hitting here
anyway.
So writing doesn't matter, do whatever you want, it doesn't you can be
super inefficient.
It can run overnight.
Who cares, right?
If you're actually if you're doing a game that's developed in a sort
of different way than we're doing it here like where you have a lot of
you want to do rapid art, turn around which we don't you know,
yangshin and I don't even work in the same office, right?
So there's no such thing as fast asset turn around there and and she
you know kind of does it as a Contracting job.
She doesn't run the game or anything.
Because we don't have a game to run yet because we're doing it in this
sort of weird our night things.
There's all these reasons why we're a little bit different, it's the
nature of the project but you might care about how assets got into the
game a little bit differently.
If you're trying to do fast asset, turn around, but what I would point
out but there is usually the way you handle that is you have a special
mechanism for handling the fast asset turn around because you want to
be as fast as possible.
So, typically, when you're talking about optimizing, the writing part
of things,
You end up having a separate thing where you're right out of band
data.
Like you know it'll just grab Junctions PSD file directly and update
the Assets in place in memory or something.
You wouldn't repack it into the asset file to do fast turnaround for
her.
So that's that's a whole separate wing of discussion.
That's not relevant.
So I'm just going to tackle the part of your question.
It's about reading.
And you said, why not just read in the entire file as a string and
parse it as you please?
The answer is because the file is going to be many gigabytes long.
Right?
We it may be bigger than the memory of the machine.
It could be a queen who knows?
We want to support a 32 gigabyte asset file.
We want to support a Grand Theft Auto sized asset footprint, right?
Will we ever have that?
I don't know, but we want to support it and so there's no such thing
as reading it in.
As a string, like that's totally off the table, you know?
There's no question that's not going to happen, right?
And so what we want to do is have an asset family, just has some
binary data up front that we can just flat load.
And that that binary data that we flat load will be, you know, two,
three megabytes tops.
That just is a giant thing.
That tells us everything about all the assets without actually,
including the data for the assets, which is the big part, right?
The actual bitmaps.
The actual sounds
Are not there.
So it's just that, that's that header.
The arrays.
We grab that in and then that tells us where we find anything that we
need.
And so then what we do is remember we wrote an asset streaming system,
our game already streams assets, so all we then need to do is have the
asset streaming system will just now use that little directory
whenever it says, oh, I need this asset.
It will just go jump into that part of the file.
Grab just the piece that needs and continue running.
And so, that way we can have arbitrarily large files.
They will always be instantaneous, no, loading times, no nothing.
It will be just be totally perfect streaming all the time.
And that's what we want.
Another option is to memory map the file and then do as you will
although they may not work on other consoles I guess.
Okay.
So the reason you don't want a memory map of file is you can no longer
run in 32 bit.
So memory mapping a file requires that you're able to actually map the
whole file into memory and on a 32-bit processor.
So on people who are running say Windows XP or running Windows 7, 32
bit, which admittedly is a dwindling portion of the folks but you know
again if we poured the Raspberry Pi it ain't dwindling potentially.
Yeah, you know, point being it's less and less people, unless you're
talking about say China, China runs a huge number of XP machines and
they're all 32 bit.
So your depends who you're targeting.
But the point is if you rely on memory mapping, that means that your
memory that your file can is really only going to be able to be, you
know, a gigabyte or something or less.
It's got to be, it can't really be very large because it's got to fit
in the actual memory space of the machine.
On a 64-bit machine, you have plenty of address space so you can
memory map.
The biggest file that you ever wanted because of course it's just
memory mapping the file.
It's not loading the whole file, right?
And so that's fine.
And you always have plenty of address based on 64-bit but the reason
that's a memory map is 32-bit, it doesn't work.
Maybe someday everything will always be 64 bit and always yellow
memory mapping that way.
And you can do that.
Second reason not to memory map, you have no idea when the operating
system will choose to put pull that stuff in or what the cost may be
to doing that, right?
So being able to, so if you think about how you have to do that, you
have to have a background thread where the background thread is going
to go poke the memory and that stall until the operation gets it in
there, right?
That's like how it's going to be structured.
That's just a lot more implicit than I want it to be, but I'd rather
be a just be able to issue the operating system, a stream of like,
load this block, this block, this block, this block, this block, let
me know when they come in right and that's just really nice and clean
and it's it's telling you is what I actually want to do rather than
memory mapped files where it's just kind of implicit what I
to do.
And it also gives me control over what amount of memory is actually
used to store stuff from the file because windows will.
Then just start saving if it's memory map that file.
It will start randomly making decisions about what gets evicted.
It might start using up memory.
I actually wanted for me and make that for the file and swap out.
I cared about him a hero when I didn't need it to store that stuff.
Right.
So we lose a lot of control.
So so I would really recommend against memory mapped files.
I don't think they're very good idea unless you have a really clear
plan of what you think you want to do with them and why you think
they're going to be good, right?
Do the Molly rocket artists, ever interact with the asset Packer or is
it a no?
Is it automated somehow if they immediately want to preview how their
artworks and game?
So that's actually separate thing the at Molly rocket.
It's a totally different code base.
So it's a very different thing.
But yes, in fact, one of things I'm working on right now at work is is
making the turnaround is doing some things that make turn around even
easier than it than it would otherwise be
I was taught to use exceptions because it does not convolute the code
with the error checking code.
So that's kind of a pretty wide open topic.
I guess what I would say is, I do not know.
I literally do not know a single good programmer who thinks exceptions
are a good idea.
I literally do not know one because there's a lot of things
programming practices that, you know, different programs, different
opinions on.
And I can find a good programmer who has an opinion one way or a good
present.
I literally don't know of one now.
Maybe I'm just not thinking of the right print, maybe there's someone
who does who I do think it's a good programmer who just never
mentioned it to me but literally I just don't know anyone.
And so, without going into too much detail, I guess what I would say
is exceptions, are C++ exceptions are something you should just never
use and some time on him in here, maybe we can go into why that's
true.
There's a lot of reasons, but they are categorically bad and you know,
we can go into Y at substring when we have more time already over time
here.
But suffice to say, if you just want to rule of thumb, never ever, use
them ever under any circumstances.
They're never
Good idea.
See him 73, just a clarification.
When I said, memory mapped file, I meant as an addition as an
alternative to F, read nozzle, turn to streamed loading.
Oh okay, yes, that's okay.
I see what you're saying.
So I guess I must have missed the part of the discussion.
I'm not sure why that came up is a queue.
Then it was with somebody talking about because we don't even call it
freed anywhere.
So I'm not sure.
But yes so pseudonym 73 is saying if you're going to load a whole file
into memory and yeah, that's true.
you know, if you're going to load a whole file into memory, then
memory mapping kind of gives the
Operating system the knowledge of what you're doing with it, so it can
sort of be more efficient, right?
It can go, okay, I understand that he wants to access this whole file.
I can just say here's a block of memory, that's going to map that file
to it, you know.
And at that point you can, you know, you can avoid having double
copies and things like this.
All right.
Looks like we are done.
I would wrap it up for today.
Let's go ahead and Save.
Okay, okay.
And we've created a new debugging Target as well.
So, we'll go ahead and save that and our bill directory along with
win32, handmade.
All right, thank you, everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always.
Today, we had a little bit of unexpected sound debugging, but I'm kind
of glad that we took a look at that and I think we made a good change
there and then we got our asset files writing out partially, we set up
a little bit more work to do.
So I think tomorrow what we'll do is we'll just kind of finish up with
that.
What we need to do now is we need to handle the actual asset part.
In order to do that, what we want to do is well load in the bitmaps,
in the wav files that the assets.
You and then we want to kind of write them out as we go and that'll be
kind of interesting.
You can sort of see how that's going to work and then we will be done
with writing out our asset file and we can switch over to reading in
the asset file.
Which won't be very difficult.
But it will take us a little bit of time to do that because although
you know sort of we can do sort of a test pass on it pretty quickly.
What I want to do is then take that opportunity to show you how to go
do proper file IO in Windows.
Because if you remember correctly, the only file I/O that we
Actually, have in our platform layer right now is called debug because
it's just the debug version.
And I said I wanted to wait a little while before we showed how to
plan it properly.
So that's also something that we're going to do now because I want to
show you how to properly do overlapped IO in Windows because there's
different ways you can do it.
And I'd like to show you what I think is probably the cleanest way
that you can do it in a game and it makes things kind of easier on you
and and it's very efficient through Windows as well.
So that's what we'll be doing for the rest of the week.
And I think it's a pretty good thing.
You know, I'd like to Target, you know, I think by the end of the
week, we'll probably be in pretty good shape.
And we'll have our asset file, working relatively cleanly.
So I think we're in good shape.
I think that's pretty cool.
So hopefully you'll join me for some more asset programming.
That's it for our programming, we will be doing it tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time, just like today, right here on Twitch.
If in the meantime you would like to play around the source code at
home.
Please remember that.
Anyone who pre-orders?
The game gets the source code every night after I'm done with it.
It gets uploaded and you can download it from send out.
You'll get a little Link in your email.
You can download it.
So if that interests, you head over to handle your rhetoric, you can
do that.
And also on he made here at Orange, you got these other options up
here.
We talked about the Tweet bottom today's stream, it's a thing that
allows you to know when it's going to be scheduled.
So that's a good place to check out if you want to catch a stream
live, we also have a forum site.
Where you can go watch annotated episodes from the past.
So you can kind of see like you know if you missed stuff, if you're
new to the series, you can see older episodes.
What we've been doing every last piece of code that we wrote for this
game is fully committed by me up there.
And there's members of the community who have gone through an
annotated with time markers, which is kind of amazing that they've
been doing that.
It's really kind of a pretty big undertaking and they've done an
amazing job doing that.
It's pretty awesome.
So, check that out.
It's also got a forum site.
You can ask questions.
It's got a
ports to Mac and Linux you want to follow along on different
platforms.
There's just great stuff up there.
Check it out members of community done.
Some really awesome things.
We also have patreon page if you want to support this video series,
it's always very much appreciates place.
You can subscribe, and that's about it.
So I guess that's enough handmade hero for today.
I will see you guys tomorrow, until then have fun programming.