And let's get started.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we coded complete game live on Twitch, no engines and no
libraries.
This is an educational stream, we go through.
Absolutely everything that is required to make a game Run and run.
Well and right now we are right in the middle of a pretty interesting
topic, which is Cindy optimization basically, how to optimize code to
run wide, Vector units inside your processor.
And, you know, basically what we're going to do today is we're gonna
spend a little
Time, the Blackboard just explaining the basics.
What Cindy is how you use it.
And then we're going to go start to actually do some code in some D so
that people can kind of understand how that works.
Before I do that.
If you want to follow along with the code today, we are on day, 1 15.
So if you download that source, code file, if you pre-ordered the game
on hand right here at org, if you download the source code file, you
should be able to unpack day 114 source code.
And see exactly where I am right now.
So I'm going to go ahead and open us up here.
Here we go.
And you can see here is where we're at right now.
And basically, all of these routines are running through our new flat
and function that we did yesterday.
We basically took the entire function
That we were working with for rendering there and we flattened it out
so that we could see exactly all the stuff that it was doing, right?
So here is the inner loop and you can see that we've got sort of this
flattened version here, that shows us all of the operations.
We actually need to do flattened out, no function calls here,
flattened out so that we could figure out what we do for optimization.
All right, so first I'm going to talk about the assembly stuff and
then we're going to go ahead and take a look at it in the
Road.
So again, here we go.
Day 115.
Let's talk about 70 and this is going to be 70 on x64 for now.
Right there is some D also,
On arm processors is called Neon.
But anyway,
all right, so what is simply as we said before it stands for single
instruction
Multiple data.
And it means that for every instruction that the processor decodes, it
is actually going to do what that instruction tells it to do on more
than one piece of data at once, right?
And so, if you think about the typical way, that you might understand
a piece of code, you might see a thing that says b equals a plus a.
And the way that we typically understand that in C is to
late itself into some kind of instruction, the processor that might
look something like,
An add instruction where you have a destination register of be and you
know, to Source registers of a and a depending on how your posture
looks at may look nothing like this but point being, we understand
there to be some concept that we have two registers write an A and A B
register and we are telling the processor to take the contents of the
a register.
Add it to another to the contents of the tip of itself, right?
And put the result in the B register, right?
So this
C Code maps.
Very directly to this code in the processor usually one or two
instructions or something like that.
I'm very straightforward, right?
Sometimes there's, there's this concept of a ternary, operator
operation versus a binary operation, which is how many of these
registers it takes as inputs.
And so the reason I was kind of hesitating to say that it always looks
this way is because sometimes if you have to Source if you have Source
0 Source, 1 and dest, sometimes processors, don't operate that way.
In fact, x 64 processors have
Don't operate this way.
Sometimes the source and the desk.
The, the destination has to be one of the sources.
So sometimes you have to do like add ba and it puts the result in B.
And so what you have to do first is load the contents of a into the B
register.
So something like this actually looks like, you know, a move that
loads the contents of a register in to be and then an ad that adds A
and B which effectively puts in to be a plus.
Say right.
Just a little aside, their turn and reverses binary operations.
And again, turn to read this means, three inputs.
Binary means to write and I shouldn't say inputs registers.
All right, but Insanity.
We don't talk about this kind of operation much.
What we usually talk about is an operation that looks like this.
It's the same math, but it basically is operating spread across
multiple values at the same time.
Okay.
And so we no longer talk about saying b equals a plus, a, what we
talked about is a family of values called be equal, a family of
values, called A Plus, another family of values, right?
And so this example, that I've given here is 4 wide right?
Because it happens on four things at once and they all have the same
operation done to them.
These things are often called Lanes.
Which I think is more of kind of becomes from the hardware side of
things, but these are often called lanes, and this operation is
assembly operation, single instruction.
Meaning it's just telling it to do an ad but multiple data, there are
four pieces of data.
Now, there are a couple different kinds of this, right?
There's SSC and
On but you've heard right?
SSE is an x 64 thing.
Arm is a sorry, neon is an arm thing and these are four wide recently
Intel introduced a VX which is eight wide.
But exactly the same kind of thing, right?
It's still doing this only.
Now it's eight values of said and they also announced avx-512, which I
think isn't actually technically here and consumer processors until
the end of the year, but that's 16 wide, right?
So just
Keeps getting bigger.
Okay so
What are these things in terms of, you know, like how do we, how do we
use this, what's going to have to happen here, right?
So what typically happens here, is we want to, you know, because it
looks like this because every time we issue an instruction it's going
to do that.
Same thing four times.
What we want to do is find entire groups of code, right?
That we want to operate on that, you know, that one entire code path
that we can.
Do on four things at once.
Okay?
And so the reason that we were talking about doing for pixels at once
in our render Loop is because each pixel has the exact same things
happen to it right?
Like this cool set of things has to happen for all the pixels.
Right?
And so since this whole thing has to happen for every pixel, write
this for, I Loop here for x equals x Min X, less than x, Max Plus with
X.
We could instead choose to do this, right?
Right.
Based on.
Doing four of them at once.
So, typically what you'll do the most simplest Cindy thing you can do
is take a loop such as this one.
And instead of going by one thing at a time, you can go at by four
things at a time, right?
So we'll just start at x equals X.
Men, will do X less than equal to X Max and will do X plus 2 equals 4,
right?
So we'll go, you know, will move by forward time.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
And then it's a simple matter of translating all of these into some D
instructions which will show how to do in a second, but that's the
basic idea.
So, what we would be doing here to make this Cindy site style,
There's a couple things I want to talk about just real briefly.
Again, I want to get this done maybe in the next ten minutes, so we
can go look at the code.
So what ends up happening when you look at this is because we are
going to be four wide.
Basically what happens is you can think about the for wideness of it
if we were doing four pixels right here are the four pixels that we
would be doing if we were to load out of the frame buffer and operate
on the frame buffer.
Probably right.
We wouldn't necessarily have to do it this way, but it's one way to
think about it.
We load in four pixels, right?
We do those then we load
The next four pixels, and we do those and so on.
But I wanted to mention briefly a couple things that differ CPU vs.
GPU here
is that right now in our code, our frame buffer is stored.
Such that pixels are contiguous in X, right?
I don't know if you remember.
But like, basically we have a pointer to some row of pixels and the
pixels just go in order rgba rgba rgba rgba right.
And what's important to remember about that is probably right.
That is not the most efficient way to organize.
The pixels that were actually operating on and it's fact it's not the
way that gpus often up organize this pixels so often times, they use
something.
I'm going to call it.
I'm gonna say Swizzle but often you know that term is thrown around in
a lot of different contexts.
So maybe I'll try not to harp on the term too much but basically what
happens is if you think about how this ends up working if you operate
on for
Pixels at a time.
The thing that you start to have to worry about is operating on
pixels.
A lot of pixels you didn't actually need to operate on, right?
So let's say that we have a rectangle, right?
And it's somewhere on the pixel grid, right?
And we're filling it in.
Now, if you look at what happens here, we're going to have to load
things.
We're going to load these pixels in and operate on them.
Right?
And depending on what the granularity is, how we choose to break up
the memory.
Even if we got lucky and we can do it so that we start right on the
the, you know, the right on the first pixel of the thing.
And we do four at a time.
Then next one we do right?
You can see that we're going to waste two pixels at the end of it,
right?
We're going to calculate those but we're not actually ever going to
Use them because they're outside of the rectangle.
So they'll fail the inclusion test and we won't actually write
anything to them, right?
Hope that makes some sense.
So, what often happens is, if you look at how shapes fill shapes
filler on a display, and the typical ways that 3D and 2D Graphics
work, you typically don't have long slivery things.
So, like long, slivers,
Tend to not be common.
You don't tend to have really long, thin things.
Look like that for Sprites, right?
You tend to have blocks that are roughly, you know, rectangle shapes.
That's what games tend to do.
And similarly, in 3D you tend to have lots of triangles that are
fairly well, formed there aren't like, usually a lot of triangles that
are like super thin, like this, right?
Sometimes there are, but it's just, it's not the common case.
So because long some servers aren't common.
You end up with stuff that looks like this a lot and you end up
burning a lot of pixels when you do it this way.
So
What they try to do to minimize that is they will often rearrange the
memory so that instead of storing things continuously like this, they
actually store it so that for contiguous pixels actually mapped to a
block that looks like this.
Right?
So, one sim D, once 170 element actually is ABCD where it's like, this
ABCD in a block.
And that way, if you look at what happens there you can see, you get
much better.
Tiling in fact, in this case you basically get perfect tiling you
waste.
No pixels.
But the maximum pixels, you could waste around the edges, just one
row, you know, you can't waste a double row and if you think about
this, it gets much more important when it's for why it's not perhaps,
as important, but it gets much more important when you start thinking
about these being huge, right?
Let's say you were to implement this using this avx-512 instruction
set, that Intel will be putting in consumer processor.
It's coming at the end of the year, I think.
Sometime soon.
Well, that would be this gigantic long 16 wide thing.
That burns a ton of pixels over here, right?
And just gets worse and worse as you get wider.
And so, what you'd rather do, right?
Is you'd rather have it packed that into a block which will burn a lot
less pixels on the outside, right?
So I don't know that we're going to actually do that because at for
wide, it's not clear, you know, we'll have to take a look and see
whether we want to bother rearranging our frame buffer for it but
that's basically a data organization thing.
It won't actually affect how we write this loop at all.
Like literally at all, it would only affect just sort of maybe the way
that we Loop over things, and how we pick the starting point.
But the actual instructions on the inside, we'll all be the same
because they're all doing the same.
Aim for Pixel operations but it's worth understanding basically how
you kind of are loading in those things that are lined.
So let's talk about one more thing that we probably don't have to deal
with too much at the moment.
But you probably see basically this
You've probably seen this.
I just want to mention what it is.
Basically, this is structure.
Of arrays.
S0 a versus array.
Of structures.
OS.
This is what C makes easy.
This is what you actually wanted for 70 and we can talk about why that
is.
So remember C is in my opinion, a pretty great language actually for
its day, but the important part here, being for its day and
unfortunately, in its day, there was no big emphasis on Cindy, right
processors?
Pretty much
Putting on single pieces of data and see did not need to worry about
generating Cindy instructions.
At least I don't think they were at all worried about that at the
time.
So what happens is C, makes it very easy to do something like struct.
You know, float X float, why float Z float W, right?
Or I guess maybe more to the point here, RG, b, and a right.
So, there's a color C, makes it pretty easy to type that in and work
with that.
That's what you expect to see in a sea program.
And in most kinds of programs actually, because a lot of people just
inherited
That method because, you know, C, sharp or something, comes from C,
Java comes from C, in terms of its structural nature.
They all look that way.
But if you remember how this works typically we want to do the same
operations on the same sorts of things.
And so what we actually want when we talk about things we want to talk
about for ours together and Four G's together and Four B's together
and forays together.
So that's actually what we wanted to see but this is what the language
tends to do, right?
So when you have a array of structures such
As in C, we will often see color star colors, you know, which is just
some array of colors values that we want to operate on.
The problem that we see is that they're typically packed rgba.
But when we do operations on the, we want to do something like a times
are right?
We want to do something like, you know, our Prime equals a times are
right.
That's what we want to do, but the actual values as they appear in
memory, aren't for RS, 4 G's for bees.
Or A's.
So in order to get them into this format, when we load these things
out of memory they're not in the format that a Sim deregister expects
right?
A Sim deregister is going to expect these this way and instead they're
this way and so on the load before you start doing your operations you
end up with a bunch of fiddly instructions.
Designed to grab all of the Ours from adjacent elements and put them
into one packed register.
And then do the same with the geez and the bees and the A's and so on,
right?
And so, let's talk about that.
Well, I should finish this.
So structure of a raise is when you do things the opposite way, you
say struct colors, instead of color, and you have float star, our
float star G, float star be float, star a right, which you can see is
exact same data, but it, flips it around.
So, instead,
Of one array.
Instead of a ray of colors.
Again, array of structures, you have a structure that has different
arrays in it and these are just a bunch of ours in sequence, right?
And bunch of G's in sequence and that way when you actually go to
gather the data it's already in the format that you want.
It's already packed together by type by look, which channel you're
talking about.
And so that brings us to the final thing that we want to talk about
which is how this stuff actually works.
So how this stuff actually works much like we were talking about
before where I sort of said this this situation here right where we
have, you know, operations that that work on these values Sim D is
basically the exact same sort of thing.
So inside the processor, you know, before we were talking about, you
may have a thing that's like, okay I want to take, you know, some
memory location somewhere.
And I want to move it into this register inside the processor and
again that the register inside the processor, right?
Is some 64-bit wide thing, right?
What is going on some 64-bit wide thing?
Right.
And so I'm going to grab memory 64, bits of memory and I fill it in
here, right?
And oftentimes, we're doing less than that.
So like if we're going to load in, you know, some 32-bit, integer it,
maybe it only goes in the bottom 32 bits or something like that,
right?
And then we do those things.
Like I said, where we do ads, you know, maybe we do an ad of a and a
two, a, which just takes this.
Register adds it to itself.
And you know, like I said baby it's just a it's a binary Apso, it just
takes a register, adds it to itself and you know sort of double
Value.
That's in there, right?
So, the way Cindy works is exactly the same as this, it's just that
the registers are wider now, right?
So, there are 128 bits wide instead of 64 bits wide and when you load
something in it, just loads that 128 bits, right?
So if I say, I want to move something to my SIM deregister, whatever
that Cindy register is for memory.
It's going to go and grab 128 bits and stick it in here.
Okay?
Then there are going to be
Operations, which operate on that.
So for example, I may have a thing that does that ad.
And instead of just saying, what the ad is, instead of just an add
instruction, in addition to the part of the instruction that says what
you're doing, which is ADD.
There's also a thing, which says, how you're doing it.
So it may say like this, you know, might be just you know, an integer
add but this one is like, okay, I'm going to say that this is 4 wide
floating point, right?
You know so I want to treat the register as if there's for floating
Point values in it.
It and add them separately, right?
It might do something different, which is ADD 8, signed integers,
let's say which
Treat this register as eight pact signed integers in their right.
And each one of those would be 16 bits, right?
So the instructions now have in addition to what the operation is such
as add subtract, multiply whatever they have, what you are thinking
the register had in it basically, right.
And that allows the processor to know which units you know which
operation in the unit to tell it to do.
Should it should it treat these as separate entities?
Dude, you know, as going by 16s.
So, treat them as going by fours.
Are they floats, whatever?
All those sorts of things?
And so, as you can see, from this, once you get things into the
register, it's basically exactly the same thinking about programming.
It's exactly the same as thinking about programming, regular
instructions, you're just issuing math operations that you want to
have happen between things that are in registers and you go.
So it's really mostly about this, this this startup part here and also
when you store things that it really comes down to thinking about the
same.
And that is, how do I fill up the 128 bits and how do I write them out
later?
Right?
And that's where this array of structures versus structure rates comes
into play, and the reason that it comes into play, pretty heavily on
Intel is because they do not know why.
But they just did not support any kind of strided loading.
Okay.
So for example,
On the neon architecture, on AMD, what they can do is you can actually
issue a load instruction which says load every fourth bite, you know,
into my into my sim deregister as the pieces of the same deregister,
right?
So if you have a pact rgba rgba kind of a thing, right?
Like this.
And I say, I shouldn't say every fourth bite, every fourth float and
you want to load that in.
It's not a big deal.
Basically, you just say the stride of this thing, right is is going to
be
What is that?
That's 4 times.
4 times, 4.
So 16, it's just going to be 16, bytes?
Right?
You say the slightest thing is 16, bytes and I want to load from this
address, it grabs the first our and puts it in the grabs.
A second are puts it in.
Third are and forth are right, so it's no big deal, you can just load
them out, that's fine.
But SSE, there is no such thing.
There's only loads that load contiguous stuff.
So when you issue one of these moves to
Well, one of your registers you are going to get whatever was in
memory coming out into the processor like that.
That's just what you're going to get.
So what you have to do, if you don't use sort of this this structure
where things are already packed in the order that you want them in the
registers if you have
In this format, you have to do a bunch of reorganization.
So when you load them in, you then have to shuffle things around.
So they end up in the right place and SSE actually has operations for
this, that can help you but they're not that great.
So there's these unpack instructions and pack instructions and stuff
like this that are used to help you sort of smush things down, or a
blow them back out again and interleaved and different ways.
And you can do it will see
It's really annoying, but point being that is why this this format is
preferred, by Intel over this formats because their chip doesn't have
good handling for that.
Sort of transposition is often what's called, that makes sense.
So,
All right, I think that's about enough to understand what we're doing
here.
Hopefully you're clear on that.
I mean really what we're talking about is pretty basic we're just
talking about registers in the processor that when you issue something
like an ad, it does not have to add the entire B to the entire B, it
can basically break them up into lanes.
That get treated independently, which is I mean, like I said, really
all we're talking about here, it's just it's that straightforward and
so, you know,
Hopefully, that's pretty clear.
How that works?
So, we have a compiling program here, I'm going to take just one
second.
I'm going to turn off optimization so we can take a look at the
unoptimized code, right?
So the processor, I mean, so the compiler is not doing anything fancy
for us here, right?
I want to show you what this actually looks like before we do anything
else, significant to it, right?
So,
If I go in here, I'm just going to at the top of this.
This thing.
I'm going to show you just a little bit of how this works.
So, first of all, I don't know.
If you remember, we were taking a look at this on the screen the other
day, a very handy thing.
The Intel intrinsics guide, I want to show you how to use that because
I never remember the mnemonics for some of the some of them, I
remember that are simple like add or whatever but I never remember
them.
We're going to be using this extensively so you probably want to know
this site.
It's really handy.
I don't know who
Didn't L wrote it, but it's way easier than using the, the
architecture manual, which is what I used to do.
In fact, someone on the stream told me about this back, I guess when
we first talked briefly about Cindy, someone told me about this and
it's pretty great.
And furthermore, it allows you to isolate down the instructions to
only the ones that we are targeting.
So, for example, we're trying to Target an sse2 processors, which if
you target sse2, that covers basically all the processors anyone runs
games on right now for Intel
So, if we check those two, we can see all of the instructions that we
can actually use, right?
And when I say instructions, this is the actual instruction over here.
The mnemonic for the instruction.
This is actually what's called an intrinsic.
We've talked about these before.
We have them in a handmade intrinsic .h out here, right?
Where we're trying to get the processor to do stuff.
Basically, these are intrinsics that the that, that the compiler uses
to, if they're basically things specified by Intel, which are supposed
to tell the compiler to produce a specific Assembly, Language
instructions.
So that the programmer in see can say what Cindy stuff.
They want to have happen.
So it's basically like programming in a pseudo Assembly Language.
It's not quite Assembly Language because you're not doing register
allocation or specifying, registers your just specifying values, but
you are specifying the instructions.
So it's like, instruction, specification without register
specification, that makes sense.
So, these are the instructions that we have.
And these are the data types, these little underscore underscore em,
64 and 128, whatever that refers to one of the reddest, like,
basically, a type.
That is the same as what the register would hold, right?
And the difference between these, this is just a stupid thing.
These are all exactly the same type, mmm, 128.
I am 21:28.
All of those are the same.
They're just, they introduced this week sort of typing model, and I
really wish.
I've done that.
It's really annoying.
But basically, they introduced sort of pseudo typing.
So if you're executing, what would be an integer instruction, like
that's treating the register.
As if it contains integers, it expects the Type M 128.
I but if you're issuing a instruction that expects something that is
floating point, it's an M1 28, it's purely arbitrary.
The processor does not distinguish between these two things in any
way, and I really wish they hadn't done that.
It's super super annoying.
One of the
Most annoying things in programming Cindy.
But what do you do?
So anyway,
So, the way that you get one of these right is your use that
underscore underscore and 128 that I showed you over there.
Right?
And you can basically say, you know, here is a here's a value and you
can even do something like just initialize it to a constant, right?
So cure is me initializing this thing to the value 1.0, right?
And there's a couple different ways you can do this.
Mmm set 1.
PS basically says take this scalar value 1.0 and replicate it to all
four lanes.
Of the same day.
Right?
I can then say something like some equals.
Mmm.
Well you know what?
I'll do this value.
A and B, right?
I'll make two and then I'll do add PS value, a value p and as you can
see here, I'm just setting 11 all the full four lanes.
Evaluate should be equal to 1.
All four lanes of value B should be equal to 2 and then I want the
process to add them together, right?
That's all I'm going to do now.
When we compile this it happens to compile properly, I think.
That's because maybe we have the intrinsics or a specified in.
I don't know if that's true.
I'm not sure.
I guess, to be honest with you I'm not sure why though.
I'm not sure why those are defined typically you have to do a pound
include like, you know, xmm intron dot h or there's there's like emm
intron .h.
There's a file that you have to include to do that, but it looks like
it's already getting included in our train.
I don't remember when we did that or why, but we're already including
it so so we're good to go.
All right, and these intrinsics will basically work on all x64
compilers for the most part.
Like, if you these are not actually stick to Microsoft Visual Studio,
these are specific to the Target.
So actually on llvm, you could also use, mmm, set, 1p, S and M 128.
These will actually work on both their the same because until specify
the format for the intrinsic.
So that's kind of nice.
All right, so if I go ahead and compile this, you can see it compiled
fine.
I want to go ahead and go into that render function.
Why is it never loaded?
Draw a rectangle.
Hopefully quickly draw Tango hopefully quickly.
So, and I'm going to go ahead and run to their and now I'm going to go
into the disassembly so you can see what it looks like, right?
So,
Here's a disassembly.
And if you can see in the register window, right?
The registers window, these are those CMD registers, right?
And this first, these first 8 here are the ones that were introduced
originally with SSE.
And then these additional registers are ones that were introduced
later as they started to expand that destruction set so you can
actually turn them on separately.
Like if I if I turn off well,
Maybe not.
So in theory, it was supposed to change the display but it didn't do
that.
Let me see why it didn't do that.
I don't know why.
There we go.
Mmm.
much better so you can see well,
I'll be completely honest with you.
This is probably the worst possible way to view these registers I
could possibly imagine.
So ignore these.
These are basically yet.
We don't actually want to look at these for now.
I do not know why they put them there.
These were the actual registers that were in SSE.
These are the rest registers that were expanded.
So, as you can see, they basically added eight more registers to the
to the processor and I guess this is just, this is their attempt,
really?
Lousy attempt at showing us, the floating Point values that are in
there, so, I believe that this Maps like this guy Maps out to this,
right?
So xmm 00 is like this floating point value shown here, right?
Because remember, these are for wide.
So there's one value, there's one value, there's one value.
There's one value, right?
And so this is the these
The, for floating Point values that are in XM 0, these are the four
values that are in xmm one, right?
So it's excellent 10 X-Men, 1 1, right?
So it's just showing us what the components are.
So you can see here, this move APS instruction, it basically grabbed
out of a constant location which is where it's stored this 1.0 F.
When we compile the program into XM M 0.
So now we have one one, one one loaded across all four lanes right
1111.
Excuse me.
Because we're in debug mode, it then goes ahead and stores that to the
stock for absolutely no reason.
In fact, I've really no reason why it's doing that, but that's what it
did.
It then goes ahead and loads the exact same value right back in again
again, the horrors of debug output like, literally this was just
stored in the stack and then read back from the stack.
Why you would have to read back something from the stack that you
already started the sock, I have no idea but then again I'm not an
assembly jockey, maybe there's some reason why you would ever want to
do that.
Anyway, point being,
It's just big.
This is basically just a bunch of really annoying stuff that didn't
need to happen.
You can ignore it completely.
This is the only instruction we actually cared about.
And in release mode, that's probably, the only instruction we would
have had their, we then go ahead and load in the other value which is
to write and it does the same ridiculous nonsense and
Oh, the debug compiler.
I mean jeez how card could it have been to write that but I suppose
it's trying to write it out to the stack so it's easy to inspect in
the debugger.
I don't even know why it's doing that.
It's crazy town anyway so then you can kind of see what it's doing.
Here it loads in value a finally into an actual register and then it
does what's called an OP from memory which is it doesn't add
instruction with the the register.
That loaded with a and the quantity B, which it just does directly out
of memory, right?
And so, there it is and it produced as you can see for results, 1 2, 3
4, right 3333.
That's, that's it.
That's MD in a nutshell, if the compiler wasn't absolutely nuts, you
would only have basically this one, instruct.
Well, honestly, you'd have this, this is what you have, right?
You'd have one to move it into the register another, to add with that.
Memory location because Intel processor, support memory Ops a lot of
processors don't but Intel supports memory Ops.
We're basically instead of having to move something into a register,
you can actually say just operate directly like grab the red, grab the
memory and do the op which, you know, doesn't actually require it
going through the register.
Doesn't require like naming it to an actual register.
So that's all we're talking about.
And so, as an example of how to do multiple of these, we can also use
a separate intrinsic, right?
Which we could set something, that's actually got four values.
so, let's say we want to
Set these guys, I'll do 100 here thousand and are, right?
So that will actually now show how to do for ads with just those
instructions.
Here we go.
So now you can see I'm going to skip right to the good part.
So here's the actual operations that the processor would actually need
to do.
We take that value a and we loaded into this xmm register so you can
see it here.
4 3, 2, 1, like so now you'll notice
Actually, the ordering there is a little suspicious, right?
I always forget this it bites me every time.
In fact, it bit me last night actually when I was doing witness code
optimization stuff, it only takes a second to figure out, so it's not
a bad bug, but I always think of it as least significant first to last
significant took two most significant.
So I think of it as loading one into the low register to hire to the
low part to hire three higher for higher.
But the wait until specified, this intrinsic was backwards.
So they actually put the most significant byte, as the first
parameter.
So, it actually loads in, in reverse order from what you see here,
right?
It's like normally, if it was loading on a memory, it would load here,
here here here.
So if the memory order was this way, it would load one, two, three,
four.
But it actually does.
This intrinsic specify to do it the opposite way.
So it actually loads for in to hear it.
Does it the way it?
Would it prints out, right?
It does it the way you would read?
Out the register in a debugger.
And so just something to point out there.
Anyway, so we do this set, you can see we loaded for three, two and
one in there, and then we're going to do the op from memory.
So it's going to do be directly and there's the op and now you can see
what it did, right?
It's got 1,000.
Excuse me, it's got 1, plus 100 plus 23, plus 1000, and 10,000 plus 4,
right?
So computed all four of those results.
All right.
So that's literally all we're talking about with Cindy, okay?
That's, that's it right?
There's, there's nothing more complicated going on there.
Hopefully, it's pretty clear.
What's happening, very very straightforward.
The trick, in fact, and when you are, when you're translating math
code, it's usually super easy.
I mean, it's usually as simple as
Want to do an ad you type, mmm, ad PS, like it's that dumb and then
things are for.
Why the all of the Finesse all the hard part comes in the like
preambles.
Usually it comes in saying, okay, you know, I got data in this format
and I got a munch it over to this format or I need to operate on it in
this other way.
So I gotta rotate it or rearrange it.
So typically what you're talking about when you do Cindy programming,
when you say like oh I gotta send the optimize this routine.
You're not talking about
Translating plus into mmm.
Add PS because that's brain-dead and super easy.
Usually what you're talking about is how to structure the data so that
you don't waste all your time, fussing with it and and you'll kind of
see as we go through what I'm, what, I mean by that, right?
So let's take a simple example here, right?
Let's just take one set of things that we're doing and turn them into
Cindy Cindy, right?
So right now we've got this srgb to linear brightness face thing.
And you can see that this is just a bunch of multiplies, right?
In fact if we were to simplify this down a little bit more, this
Square function, if we were to get that square function out of there,
right, take it take the square function out it would look like this,
right?
Make sense.
That's that's what that's what we're really talking about, right?
So, if I take a look at this, right, we're all running fine.
This is the actual code that's being executed, and hopefully, you can
see that this should be pretty simple to Cindy eyes, right?
That would be pretty.
That would be pretty straightforward.
Although now that I think about it, we probably want to do one step
before hand.
We got what we got, 20 minutes left, let's do one step before hanging
so make it easier to think about I'll leave.
For one second but that's right.
I mean you can kind of see this as just a bunch of multiplies that's
all that is right.
All right, so the first thing that I was going to say is well before
we actually do any of that I guess I have to fix my Loop right to run
over pixels and batches of for, right.
That's kind of just obvious.
So if I'm going to do pixels in batches of, for, I'm going to need to
modify the way I Loop over X for now.
So let's, let's actually start by doing that and there's some things
that kind of go along with that that we kind of have to talk about as
well.
All right, so there's some things with like alignment and stuff like
that.
So I'm not really going to talk too much right now because it's not
the focus of today's episode about how to get this data out
efficiently or any that stuff.
We're just going to do the simplest possible thing for the loading
right now, and then later on, we're going to have to look probably a
little more closely at this, for some other, for other reasons.
But for right,
Now, let's just stick with talking about this very straightforward.
So what I want to do first is I want to say, all right, I'm starting
an X-Man and I'm going to go by by fours, right?
So I'm going to, I'm going to do it this way, right?
So I'm going to do 4 pics that time.
Now, if I just literally just do that, right?
You can see what happens here, right?
Which is that everything basically works fine.
But I'm I'm a little too, I'm smooshed, right?
And that's just because down at the bottom when we
Advanced a pixel.
We're only advancing one pixel at a time, right?
So if I actually change to advancing four pixels at a time, now, when
I run it, we should in theory.
And we do basically get you know kind of a screen door version of this
here, right?
Which is as we go we're advancing 4 pixels at a time trying to think.
Did I miss anything else?
Sir, I don't think I did.
That's what we should have been able to do, right?
We read out the pixels.
We advance for Pixel at a time.
I think that's still correct.
It's not correct.
I think that's right.
This is less than X Men.
It's not exactly what I expected to see.
I would have
Back to the Sea.
Always there be a little bit of tree there.
It's a little bit weird.
Why is that?
That is just weird.
That's not what I expected to see.
I'm a little bit weirded out by that is there are some other thing
we're doing that means that that is not proper because that should
have just been more of a screen door effect than it was.
So I'm a little weirded out by that.
So pixel plus equals 4 it's advancing 4, pixels is pixel pixel is a
you and 32.0 right?
So that will advance for pixels at a time.
We're going by for in X so it's knows what the correct x-coordinate is
and loads that out.
So yeah, I'm not sure, that's not what I would have expected to see.
I'm going to keep going here, but I'm a little weirded out by that but
okay.
All right.
And then in here, I'm just going to go ahead and say, you know, the
very stupidest thing.
I'm going to say p and X or something like this.
And I'm going to actually Loop over the four pixels, which again, this
is actually just adding insult to injury in going to make our routine
slower.
But, like I said, at the moment, I'm actually not.
That's not the thing that I'm actually concerned about.
At all.
I'm just trying to structure this so that we can start to work on it.
So I'm going to go through these four here and I guess inside here I
will go ahead and
And do the plus + pixel.
And so hopefully now we will get back to drawing everything.
There we go, all right now, excuse me.
So as you can see in that in that screenshot fact Let me show that one
more explicitly there.
You can see kind of in here that we are blocky.
Right?
You can see that that we are that we're basically just spread out for
Pixel wide and the
Reason for that is we're incrementing X at all here, right?
So the actual value, the actual x value is not getting incremented as
we step through those four different pixels.
And so, if we wanted to fix that, we could just go ahead and say, all
right, we've got our like X iterator on the outside, but the actual x
value that we're actually using is, is computed separately.
So that's going to be equal to X Plus DX I, right?
So now we're actually
Away.
Oops.
Area.
Sorry, little out of it today.
It's early morning.
Alright, so now we're back to drawing the right things, but we're
doing Loops in terms of for.
And the thing that I want to call your attention to, in addition is
there's a little artifact to pay attention to here.
And this will come into play a little bit later, which is that, if you
look on the side of the screen, right?
You can see that we're over writing our boundary by a little bit,
right?
You can see the stuff that's over here.
Come on, to the screen over here.
Okay.
Now why that's happening is because we're still going by 4 pixels even
if we pick the the rightmost pics of the screen, we're overriding by
50 pixels which wraps around on to the next row.
It does that make sense.
So what that means is that technically, we're over writing, we're
overriding our row by a little bit.
Now, like I said, I don't want to worry about that stuff at the
moment, we're just going to talk about the, the Straight Ahead Cindy
stuff.
So, all I'm going to do is prevent us from since we're only going to
ever write down to the other side of the screen, I'm just gonna
Prevent that by clipping a slightly here, right?
So what I want to do is take that with Max and that height Max where
did those go?
These guys here, let's see yeah I'm going to temporarily assume that
the the buffers are smaller than they actually are.
Right?
So I'm going to put it to do in here Casey
So once we actually talk about more of how we're going to do loading
stuff and we fix that, I'm just going to go ahead and make sure that I
guess we could do it by -3.
I'm going to make sure that we don't have that happen.
By just pre clipping things to be a little bit to have a little bit of
a border.
So now we just don't fill that part of the screen, right?
And now we're fine.
And again, that's just a to prevent us from over writing the memory in
wondering, what the hell is going on there, right?
All right.
So now let's talk about the Cindy, part of things, right?
So when we do these four operations,
Excuse me.
Like I said, what we want to do here is we want to be able to do all
of these things.
Essentially four wide.
We're going to ignore some of the tricky stuff with the loading and
stuff for now, like I said, but once we get down to here, maybe we
would like to start doing things in actual widths of for, right?
So what we could do is we could take this first part here.
This p and X part, right?
And we could start by critic having that off, so that we do these
operations for times.
But then not these ones down here, right?
And then
I'm going to essentially sort of bracket if you will the routine like
so.
Let's see here.
Yeah, like this, we go.
Again, this is kind of since I'm normally, I would not do this the way
that I'm doing it.
I would not do it in these stages.
I just go ahead and write it, Cindy kind of directly because this is
sort of a wasted work that I'm doing if that makes sense, but I kind
of want to show it to you step-by-step and so it's I think we're
spending a little extra time to just kind of go through and do it in a
series of Transformations, so that you can kind of see it a little
more explicitly.
Right.
All right.
So what I'm doing is I'm breaking this up into multiple Loops here.
Okay, there we go.
And I'm going to get rid of the fill pixel timer because we're going
to stop actually having that particular piece of data in a second
here.
So what I want to do is I want to go ahead and Loft these things out
so that I can basically execute a loop and make a bunch of values.
And then execute another loop that's going to be in Cindy that uses
those values.
And then finally X Cube, one more Loop that does
The retirement.
And basically, what I've done here is, I've separated the memory
loading stuff, which I don't want to talk about yet, from the actual
just computation, like all of this.
You can see in here is just straight computations, not much is going
on.
Now, the destination load I would like to be in the memory part,
right.
So, we'll put that in there as well, so and so, here we go.
This isn't going to compile because obviously tons of these things,
you know, now only exists inside here.
So what I need to now do is just transform stuff.
So that these are put all of this stuff here is put into external sort
of registers, right?
External variables.
So we have the outputs of this routine here that we actually need, are
the dest and the Texel values, right?
So, I'm going to put those in here.
So we've got Texel AR and that's four floats, right?
So a g, a b, a and then we've got the
B, c d.
And again, don't worry that like I know this looks kind of ugly and oh
my God, he's having to do all this stuff again.
You don't have to do any of this stuff.
I'm just want to get this code into something where I can show you
just one isolated part of it and work our way out when you actually
put them on Sunday, none of the stuff that I'm doing right here.
And you'll see that once we finish this routine, you'll see that none
of this stuff is in there.
So this is literally just setting up the code so that it runs in
multiple chunks so that I can show you how to optimize one chunk
without having talked about the others so, so please do not be
nervous.
None of this has to do with
Deprogramming.
This is literally just a rigid transformation that I'm doing here.
All right, so I'm going to go ahead and you know what?
Let's just rectangle, this stuff.
There we go.
And so all I'm going to do is I guess I'm going to use, I to say which
one of these were using i-i-i-i-i-i-i-i-i-i-i-i.
This.
And then we're just going to Loop over eye.
There we go.
Okay, so let's go ahead and compile that whereas our first error,
let's get rid of that guy.
Okay.
So well as you can see all I did was I just made place to store all
the stuff that we load and then we load it.
All right, so we load all our textiles in we load all our destination
in.
So with this is just a loop that does all the loads.
Now there's one more thing that we need to know, right?
And that's basically just a like
Should fill or something, right?
Which is we just need to know which one of, you know, whether we're
filling it or not.
So we just need to know.
Should fill I equals false, right?
Or if we're inside here, should feel like was true, right?
So, basically, what we need to do is just this, right?
We've got a should fill value and then only if we should fill it, do
we actually bother to load all the rest of the stuff out of it, right?
It looks like that.
That makes sense pretty straightforward.
So basically what we want to do here is we then want to Loop through
these things again.
Right?
Let's go ahead and do that.
And now I just want to do these operations on each of the things that
were actually talking about, right?
So I've got my eye here.
Like so.
And again just totally straightforward.
I'm not doing anything at all.
Other than converting this routines to run in a series of batched of
batches of four.
And none of the stuff like I said would be necessary if you just
already knew somebody programming, you wouldn't bother doing any of
these things that I'm doing here.
It's literally just a set us up to make sure we can properly do what
we need to do.
What's funny, is, like the code to show how to do, it is actually more
complicated than the code that actually just does it, but that's,
that's just how things go sometimes.
Oops, I didn't mean to do that.
I don't think.
Okay and f x.
So FX comes out of here as well.
Although FX is just he X for that value.
Right?
So we need f x.
So we need we need, let's see.
We need an, we need just FX.
Which ones do we need down here?
Looks like we only need FX.
So, we also need to compute FX and FY, right?
so, these guys
are also that way.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
so, now we've got down to desk and desk, obviously, also,
Structured this way.
And put that together.
We go and the output.
So what it needs to write out here is Blended, so blend, it is also
done this way.
Like so let's go ahead and get that out.
All right.
And last but not least you actual pack.
Set think we're basically done with that.
You're too Blended.
Yeah.
Now.
Oops, that's not good.
What did I make?
I made I have made a grievous error of some kind.
In my in my transformation here.
Exercise should fill equals.
What is that problem there.
X x is less than texture with.
What is the texture with?
Is 81.
So it's right on the boundary.
Why has that?
Why have half that happened?
Equals X 60 X, qu with -2, so, that should not actually be possible.
So, I think I actually made a mistake here when I was doing my
Transformations.
Oh, it would help if I actually tested the show should fill value.
There we go.
So it looks like I messed up.
Oh yes.
So we're testing, the should fill value, but then I'm not actually
doing the test for the should fill value out here.
So got to fix that as well.
Should fill, I
There we go.
All right, so now we should be back.
I think to where we started and it looks like we are for the most part
although for some reason we're still that's kind of interesting.
We're still pixelated.
In certain circumstances.
She makes very little sense.
What did I do wrong here?
I'm not sure.
I must have not one of the things that I'm doing, I did not apparently
actually do wide properly, so let me just go ahead and check make sure
that they're all happening the way I think they should be happening.
All right.
So we compute our should fill value based on the current X and that is
actually doing x.
I plus I write which is this value here.
So that should be correct.
Loading things in
And come through here, compute the blend Factor TX, that's all good.
Oh,
Wait.
But why, that's weird, how we always been doing that, where we have
our index.
And then we do our in, through, to cast here, that's kind of stupid.
Where are these used somewhere?
Yeah, so that's that's what we did.
That's what we did wrong.
So this is this was a poorly named thing.
I'm going to call this actual X and fix that, right?
Let's go ahead and Cascade that down.
Okay.
Well no.
That wasn't it.
So, I guess this is literally only used here.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
All right, well we're still busted.
I did not fix the problem, but that was kind of just an interesting
thing.
Alright, so keep going, like I said, I had a bug in when I do my
transformation.
So let's go ahead and keep looking for it.
So grab out the pixel position, take a look at the exhibition
relative, the origin.
I'm going to do that four times, we compute the use and Vees, but we
don't store those, we just store whether or not.
It was a valid for that particular pixel.
We compute the texture X texture.
Why, and we use those to look up and we record basically, where we are
for the blend factors, right in th in the t, x- x.
Auntie.
Why - why we then go ahead and look up each of the samples and we load
in the destination.
Ah, that's our problem.
Yeah, we need to actually load in the pixels.
From the right place.
So we weren't actually implementing the pixel by the iso.
We have to load in the for different destinations.
We go through, do the Ops on the destination and then at the end, we
write each one out, and I could actually change this now to look a
little bit more proper.
So now we're actually incrementing by forests on the pixel as well.
So there we go.
And now, we're back to good or at least some semblance of good.
As you can see.
There we go.
All's well, so, you know what?
I think we're basically out of time.
So I feel like we should probably stop and tomorrow.
We're now in a position to actually do the Cindy optimization.
So, tomorrow we can do is I shouldn't say something opposition.
I say just to write this Insanity.
So basically tomorrow, what we'll do.
We'll pick up again.
At 9 a.m.
we'll, just go ahead and take these.
So for example.
Now, that we have our loading isolated and we have these guys as, as
for floats, it's pretty trivial for us to go ahead and change.
One of these four floats to actually be Cindy, right?
And in fact, it's extra easy to do that on MSNBC because of the way
they Define, the M 128 structure.
In fact I can sort of show you one sort of interesting aspect of it.
So let's go back.
It's real quickly about, you know what Rod time?
I'll end there, and I'll show you the stuff that's going to show you
tomorrow because we did all the work we need to do to get there and we
showed how the Cindy stuff works.
So, tomorrow will actually go ahead and write that core part of the
routine and Cindy, which, at this point now will be really really
straightforward for us to do.
In fact, you could almost do it as homework if you wanted to.
But
We'll do it tomorrow morning at 9 a.m.
all right.
So for now, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A so that I can basically
answer any questions that anyone has.
Would it be faster to unpack pistols using a union of an inch 32, with
a struct of four in Tate's instead of doing four shifts and mass per
pixel?
I do not know.
I never actually unpack things that way in real life.
Or at least never.
When I actually care how fast they go, so you have to time it.
My suspicion would be probably not.
My suspicions would be that.
The compiler is smart enough to do, which, when you're compiling with
O2, I suspect the compiler.
Turns it into whatever it thinks is faster either way.
But I don't know, you have to time it.
Why don't we go y less than 2 and X less than 2 and go through in
blocks instead of a line.
Well, so the reason is because of the way the loads work in Cindy.
We when we issue a single command will be able to load 4 pixels at
once.
In a line, we wouldn't be able to load blocks at a time, right?
Because if we load blocks at a time, we actually have to do both
loads.
So see if I can explain this here.
It doesn't really matter.
I mean, we could do the blocks at a time, but basically, right, if I
imagine what I've got in memory,
Right.
This is memory.
Okay, and here's the register.
When I issue a load, a single load instruction will load this stuff in
right.
It will load this.
Right.
One move APS will grab this whole set of four pixels and put it into a
register.
If we wanted to do blocks, so the next row as well, right?
We have to do to move aps's.
For every time we were going to process, so we actually we have twice
the memory.
Fetches going on right now because they're going to be cache coherent.
That may not be the end of the world, but I just don't feel like we
necessarily want to do that.
Like I mean we'd have to actually know that we were going to start
saving a lot of time with those with those overhangs which maybe we'll
test and find out if we do or not.
But even if we were going to do that, I suspect what we do is
rearrange the frame buffer to be in that sort of Blocky format.
And then just do at the very end when we live
It will be output to the screen or whatever we Swizzle it then.
About.
So I'm not sure about that.
We could do that but again you have to be aware that once you do that,
you're issuing two instructions to do the loads instead of one.
Is it better if we calculate, if the pixel should be filled and cue it
up and only do the calculations once we hit four of them.
So, that's an excellent question.
And the answer is, it depends.
Doing that requires a lot of instructions.
Okay, and the reason it requires a lot of instructions is because
knowing how to do that packing.
Imagine all the stuff you have to do, right?
You need to have a counter that counts where you're putting things
when you load them you have to load them into a particular Channel and
then when you're done, you have to write them out.
If to remember what memory addresses you've got them from and and
outrun them out.
44 wide.
It almost certainly would be a lose.
Right.
But if you were say 64 wide,
it might be a win.
And there's actually, this is actually a topic that has a lot to do
with how much stuff you're doing internally, right?
So right now, you know, this is the the math Ops basically in here at
this is them, there's not very many of them, right?
I mean there's there's you know I don't know.
Something like 60.
My pops in here, maybe 32 math Ops.
I like that.
I don't know.
Not very many.
Yeah.
3032 Ops, maybe something like that.
And so the amount that you're saving, when you avoid Computing pixels,
you don't need to compute is not that great.
If This Were a super conflict Shader then it starts to become more.
Like you can start to spend more Cycles doing that packing and
unpacking.
And you still, you do a huge.
You do a big savings there, right?
And so, what it really boils down to is the cost trade-off between
doing the all the logic.
That's it.
Go,
The pack and then unpack, two different memory locations.
All that logic, it's a trade-off between that and the savings that you
get by not Computing pixels.
You didn't need to compute, right?
And so right now, we're kind of at the worst case for that because
actually our pixel computation is very inexpensive by comparison.
But if you got out to some crazy fader that was doing all sorts of
ridiculous stuff, it might become more important that make sense.
No questions.
Oh, and by the way, for the hmh, but I am not using an unknown
keyboard that I had lying around anymore.
I switched it out like I'm using a DOT the Das Keyboard three that I
used to have in the living room.
This was my, this was a gift from Jeff, actually, he had a Das
Keyboard.
3 is his Das Keyboard 3 and then he switched to some other keyboard
and I was like, I really like the dust covers for you.
So I asked him if I could have it and he said, yes.
So I'm actually using that's what I'm actually using right now.
I really love the Das Keyboard 3s.
I wish they'd kept making these.
I've never had a problem with one and I love the feel.
So
Sorry, maybe this is off topic.
Would it be correct to say?
Anyone coding in Java by default is not making use of any of the Cindy
stuff?
Or do you think the jit compiler is smart enough to make use of it in
certain circumstances?
Maybe with some analysis of the bytecode?
You know, I don't program in Java so I don't I'm not really qualified
to say.
I feel like you know if you're programming in Java, most of the time
that's probably the least of your worries is whether things Cindy
wide.
But, you know, it wouldn't be out of the question for the jit compiler
to do it.
And I also feel like I mean by now I feel like job has got to have
some way of specifying Cindy instructions.
I mean there's got to be there's got to be some Library you can use or
something that's like are not library but like you know, extension
that you can use that basically extends the bytecode for Cindy, if
not, that's crazy that they don't have that.
How often do you optimize for cash basis versus optimizing with Cindy?
I got the impression that cache misses are by far the most important
things to look out for.
So they are in the art.
Basically what it boils down to is.
What does the structure of the data look like, right?
And so in our case we do have some some question about cache, misses
right?
We're doing Texel fetches and those can result in the cast mixes but
on the whole when we're doing rectangle, a rectangle we should in
theory and we'll have to find out but we should be able to get it down
so that they're really just aren't a lot of cache misses this code
because its operating on a large number of pixels, all of which are
typically
Very contiguous in memory write cache.
Misses tend to be more about chasing pointers and other sorts of
things where you can't predict what the next piece of memory is that
you're actually going to go get but in our case we often will know
exactly what the next piece of memory is that we're going to go get
and so cache.
Misses are going to be less of an issue for this type of code
probably.
So I guess
So operating wide is very, very, very important to us, because
typically we're going to do something like loading, two pieces of
memory from very known, very contiguous locations, and then doing 60
math operations on them or something like this 60 might be a little
money, but something like that.
And so, we really want to make sure that those 60 operations are done
wide, so that we don't pay for x 60 in cost, right?
So, for this particular type of code where we're filling a large
blocks of known pixels in a contiguous order, especially when we're
talking about rectangular Blitz as opposed to like little tiny
triangles and stuff.
Cache misses are probably going to be less of a concern in this code
than they typically would be in optimizing other sorts of code that
you met randomly need to optimize in a game.
Culver fly.
I will send your best regards to Jeff.
Absolutely.
Schedule-wise how many more weeks until we are done with optimization
of the renderer who knows hard to say.
Will you be covering more than order Texas whistling?
Probably not just because I don't know that we actually need any
sizzling for the render.
I could all mean I'll mention it briefly we order we already mentioned
the concept of putting things into blocks, right?
But textures whistling is less important for us because we don't
actually access Textures in the way the GPU typically would.
So we wouldn't actually I don't think get any benefit from it.
Basically, what, what he's talking about is the fact that Textures in
on gpus are typically not stored as contiguous pixels and not even as
contiguous blocks.
And the reason for that is because textures are much more random
access on on a GPU than they are here.
So, typically on a GPU, you know, if you've got a texture, you know
you're talking about triangles that are mapped.
You know, like this sort of a thing, right?
So they're grabbing from just a portion of the texture and they're
putting that on the screen.
And so typically what you want to do is you want to make sure that the
your access pattern into the memory of the texture.
Is optimized for this Behavior.
We don't actually have that problem.
We are pretty much always bleeding our entire bitmap right?
And so we don't really have to think too hard about how we're storing
our bitmaps.
I don't think so.
Probably the way we have them right now would be fine and if it wasn't
fine probably just going in blocks of 2 by 2 would be totally
sufficient.
And we don't have to do anything more complicated than that.
But gpus
Harder time of it because they are dealing with something that's not
just typically Brit bleeding rectilinear strip rights to the screen.
Possibly a noob question, have you ever run into problems with
floating Point arithmetic?
And what are some good approaches to avoiding those problems?
That is not a noob question, that is actually a very real problem and
happens all the time.
Some good approaches to avoiding those problems, are one to try and
avoid having the problem in the first place and you saw me do that,
right?
One of the things that we did is we use that same region concept to
make sure that we always simulate things around the origin.
And we don't try to have a giant world, that's like 100,000 units in
all directions and doing floating Point math out there where the
Precision starts to break down.
So one way to get around, having to worry, about floating-point
arithmetic, problems is to make sure that you're always doing things
in in very small scales, right?
That don't involve very large things that will have catastrophic
cancellation problems, stuff like that.
so that's one way to deal with it, but obviously there's also the
other problem where no matter
Your scale is, if you're doing certain floating-point things, you may
run into problems.
And the answer there is it's just really pretty tough if you actually
are having real, floating-point arithmetic problems, even when you
make sure that your stuff is well conditioned and you're not doing
sort of this, you know, expecting the floating Point Unit to handle
more than what its Precision has.
Then you're into the world of having to actually become more of a
floating-point expert.
And there's a couple of references that you should know about there.
So this, whatever computer scientist should know about floating Point
values.
This, this is a PDF, it's kind of famous.
It might be a little bit old at this point but it's still probably a
good thing to go to.
So if you, if you grab this PDF and you read it and you actually spend
some time trying to understand it, it'll probably put you in some
pretty good shape to understand what's going on when you have floating
Point operation problems.
So I do highly.
I recommend taking a look at it.
Similarly, you can then go a step up from that in terms of
Time investment.
You can read the two books by Foreman Acton
Which is real Computing Made Real.
Let's see here, is this.
Yes, real Computing Made Real and basically the form and active books.
He has other one called numerical methods.
That usually work.
This one right here and you can see it's called numerical methods that
work technically, but you can see, it says, usually in there, right?
And it's warm and acting always kind of had a sense of humor.
And so, he's actually his methods, pretty much always work.
But he was kind of joking about about that because he talks about
people doing bad, things numerically, and so on these
Two books are great.
So basically the two books by Foreman actin I would highly recommend
taking a look at it looks like the this is kind of cool.
Looks like there's a only a ten dollar you could buy real computer
memory of for only $10 on Kindle which is good.
I don't know if the Kindle edition is any good, A lot of times the
conversions to Kindle a pretty awful, but yeah.
So, those are some books that I would definitely check out.
I definitely check out this PDF as well because it's got a lot of
information there.
And so basically, if you, if you can't set yourself up for success and
just not care about floating-point arithmetic, if you actually are in
a situation where you have to care about it, and there isn't a good
way to structure the way you're doing your operations to avoid it,
then you are definitely in the realm of halfing to understand what's
mechanically literally happening on the CPU at those funny.
Point values, which that PDF and those books will be the way to
probably gain enough information to start a tackle those problems, but
that's not a new question.
That's more of an advanced question.
Honestly, once you're into that, that sort of stuff,
Any other questions?
Anyone.
No.
And starchy Pancakes.
Yes, sse2 is very standard.
One of the things that we didn't talk about was too much is how I
picked sse2.
I think I mentioned it on an earlier stream, but the steam Hardware
survey
I think covers this stuff, so it's something to potentially take a
look at
So if you want just kind of a baseline of like I'm going to ship a
game on a PC.
Basically, you know that your audience typically looks like steam
users.
If you're shipping the kind of games where you care about a bunch of
optimization stuff, right?
You're talking about a higher end game, you're not talking about Match
3 game or something where nobody cares.
So if you take a look here at the the CPU,
Side of things.
Is it?
This one?
That's the type of processor.
How do I get more physical CPUs until CPU speeds?
I don't know.
I thought this one.
Here we go.
Other settings.
So this is an example of what you could use.
And it's not perfect, right?
It's just the steam Hardware survey but it's, you know, it's one of
the only source of information.
We really have about what Gamers have.
And if you take a look at this, you can kind of see like, okay.
You know, sse4 4.2.
And for a are look, a little sketch, right?
Like, you couldn't guarantee that all of your users, if you sold your
game on Steam, for example, which is where you'd probably be selling
it at the very least would would be able to run the game, right?
But if you take a look at sse2, and then also to a large extent sse3,
although I don't remember if there's really all that much in sse3,
that anyone cares about, but
But at the very least, you can see you're not really losing any one,
right?
So, if you say that this game requires us to see to, it's totally
fine.
If you say it requires us to see three, probably still, totally fine.
If you say it requires sse4 of some flavor, especially for a accrue
least.
According to steam Hardware survey, not a good sign, right?
Just not not what you would want.
That's just going to be a lot of Gamers who can't run your game.
So hopefully that's
Yeah, hopefully, that makes some sense.
Is there a way to track how memory gets stored to the cash?
So not not exactly.
Meaning, there isn't until doesn't give you access to their
super-secret simulation tools that they have, which would actually
tell you that information.
Basically, you know, Intel has internally, uh, simulation of their
processor.
Everyone has this
We're basically, they could run the processor in a simulation and view
exactly what it will do, right?
And that would tell you exactly how the cache is getting used and so
they can do it but you can't do it.
So if you really need to know how the cash is being used, you have to
be friends with somebody until probably unless they've since then
changed her mind and released it publicly.
I don't think they do.
I think it's a competitive problem for them because if they release
it, then people may look at what they're doing and or might sue them
for patent infringement or something.
Who knows, right?
Like
Giving out a simulation how the processor works.
Could open up all kinds of problems for Intel I suppose, so they
probably have plenty of reasons not to do that, so I'm assuming they
don't.
But that's one way you could do it, right?
Is, if you have a friend at Intel be like, can you run this code on
your super-secret processor stuff and you know if they said yes, then
they could give you back some traces.
That would tell you what was happening in lieu of that.
There are some things that the average person who does not have secret
access to Intel stuff can do basically.
Processor itself has performance counters on it and I don't know.
There's a good listing for these things, maybe maybe in here.
You know, I don't really know what the best way to get access to these
are but you know, it'd be something like one of these.
Can you can you load this for me?
There we go.
So let's see.
Where is the?
Here we go.
So you can kind of see in here and I don't really know what I'm
looking at here to be honest with you.
This is not exactly what I wanted but point B.
So here you go, you can kind of see what this is doing here.
There's basically like this is a little library that gives you access
to a bunch of information about what the processor is doing.
Some of them being L3 cache.
Misses L2 cache misses L3 cache hits L2 cache hits.
So basically there's
there's, you know, there's
Ways you can see how many times you are missing the cash and how many
times you are hitting the cash within a section of code.
And so while you can't see exactly what happened to the cash.
Phil you know what lines?
Got Phil, what lines got evicted, whatever.
You can get aggregate statistics, which often times is enough, right?
Oftentimes all you really want to know, is did I really miss the cash?
A bunch, right.
And was I missing the L3 or the L2 or whatever?
Right?
And so that is information that you can get, if that makes sense.
But explicitly, what happened with the cash is not super possible
without it without insides that?
Off topic.
Do you know, if J, I will have extensions or method for using Cindy,
that's not really off topic.
That is on the topic of 70.
Yes, he already has kohi already implemented in j.i.
stuff that changes array of structures to structure of arrays.
So he already set it up for Cindy to do automatic simply
Transformations for you, which is pretty awesome.
He, I don't think necessarily has actually gone in and done Cindy,
like, intrinsic stuff, because that's a little more low level.
But, you know, obviously he's thinking about that.
So I suspect he would add that eventually, just it's not quite there
yet.
How much do you need to think about the intrinsic instructions while
programming or does the compiler usually take care of that?
Is this the big difference between using canoe and Intel compiler for
example?
I'm sorry, I'm not sure I super understand what you're asking there.
Could you be more specific?
I will wait a second.
See about the more specific part.
Yeah, I don't know what the, I don't know these days.
What the easiest way is to do this stuff.
You know, it may be that you just go ahead and Link in one of these
things.
I don't know.
I haven't looked at that recently.
Nice.
I'd like to get something like this.
I'd even I'd use this at work, too.
If I was, if it worked reasonably.
Well, I'm always skeptical of some of these until libraries though
because they tend to be really weird but you know,
This is, this is the kind of data that you want when you're optimizing
stuff, right?
You want to be able to to get the those cache misses and be able to
bracket two pieces of code to see how those cache misses have happened
over the course of the Run.
I think he's essentially asking how proficient compilers are
automatically emitting Cindy instructions.
They are not very proficient at emitting them unfortunately.
So at the very least you usually have to give them some help
So, here is a documentation on auto, vectorizing and llvm, vectorizing
is what they mean.
Vectorizing is the phrase, they use to talk about producing wide
operations, right?
Because you can think about it, that is a vector, right?
It's a vector of four things, or eight things or whatever.
So Auto vectorization means taking code, that was scalar and turning
it into wide turning into Vector.
So you can see, like, you know, you can say stuff here about what you
want to do.
Then you kind of give it these like hints and stuff and you hope that
it does a good job.
But basically you know what it tries to do is it tries to take things
that look like this and turn them into vectored stuff, right?
And you know, you can read about stuff that has to do here.
How it's a does, its loads and that sort of things and basically how
everything works and you can kind of see you know here's their
performance graph.
So on about who did a better job, you know, vectorizing some stuff,
and that sort of thing and this I believe is pretty old documentation
potentially.
I think this actually hasn't the documentation hasn't changed in a
year or more.
So, you know, it might be a little bit better even than it, that
suggests.
But so, it's in there and you can try turning it on.
I don't know very much about
Microsoft's, but I pretty sure they've had an auto vectorizer in there
as well.
I just don't remember the specifics of that, but I think they do.
So they're in there and, you know, I don't know, your mileage may
vary.
You could play with them and see how they go.
Typically, what I find and this may just be me, but that auto
vectorization, is not really that useful.
And the reason for that is because typically, if you haven't
structured your code to work with Cindy, then there's not that much
the compiler can actually do to help you because typically, your stuff
just isn't getting.
Loaded and stored out in efficient enough.
Way to make the auto vectorization, actually work on x64 anyway.
And so I find that typically the work that goes into 70 programming is
not this this part is easy so you might as well just do it and make
sure the compiler doesn't screw it up.
The hard part is reorganizing the data and the like unpacking and
packing steps, which the compiler tends to be the worst at.
And so typically I find that the compiler has some help you that much
and really it's not because
It couldn't necessarily figure out how to do an M&M add PS, it's
because figuring out the do an M, Ed.
PS is the easy part.
Anyone can just type it in and it's really not an issue, you know,
it's as easy as just changing it from, you know, a plus b, 2 m, Ed PS
parentheses 8, comma B.
You know, anyone can do that in the compiler is not really saving you
very much time there.
The problem is those that set up in the, the shutdown of the routine,
basically.
And so that's that's the issue, usually?
Do you have to take the instruction cache into account or is it large
enough typically not for sort of the lighter-weight optimizations like
what I tend to do?
If you're a super hard carve score Optimizer.
Yeah.
You tell you you do you have to think about it?
At least, depends on the routine, whether it'll be a problem or not.
But it does basically mean that sometimes routines that are larger but
potentially more efficient or actually slower than routines that are
smaller and a little less efficient, that's what
And some practice, but again, like at the level that I tend to
optimize things, that's not the sort of thing I start thinking about,
because I don't take it to that level.
But if you're a super hardcore Optimizer, you probably do think about
that.
How does intrinsic some parallel processing work together?
Does each CPU have registers to do intrinsics?
If so, could we increase X fill the number pixel rendering and our
computer if we compute in parallel?
Yes.
So typically, they're completely separate you.
They don't interact in any way.
So, basically, anything that you can do with a bunch of intrinsics on
One processor, you could then just do on another processor as well.
Totally separately.
So we will actually probably take advantage of this when we
We optimize for multi-threading a little later on.
We will probably basically bin things into rows or something like this
and have our different processors operate on different regions of the
screen or something like this, right?
All right, think that's about it.
Look like there's any more questions.
So I'm going to go ahead and wrap things up.
Close these down here.
Alrighty, thank you everyone for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
I wasn't a pleasure coding with you.
As always tomorrow, we will start actually writing our actual routine
in Cindy because we've looked at how it works.
We've talked about it, we've restructured the routine for it.
And so now all we really have to do is put in some intrinsics to
actually start using some Sim decode and we'll do that tomorrow.
And I suspect we'll probably actually finish it tomorrow as well.
It's really pretty straightforward but we won't get to is those pre
and post ambles the load in the store because that's a lot more
complicated.
And that will what will
To pick up on next week.
So I hope you'll come back and join me.
Nine a.m.
tomorrow when we actually go through and and Cindy eyes the math
block,
Again it's pretty straightforward.
You could almost do it for homework but there's a couple things I
didn't quite show you yet so you know, maybe not don't, don't worry
too much if you're not ready to do that yet, we will do it tomorrow.
So thank you, everyone.
And I hope to see you back here tomorrow in the meantime, if you do
want to follow along with the source code at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero dot org and it comes with the
source code.
Just use the little pre-order button here, and that will take care of
it.
We also have a forum site where you can ask questions if you miss the
Q&A and want to ask some questions stuff like that, it's good place to
do it.
Also Sports a Mac and Linux ante the episode
Stuff like that.
There's also a patreon page where you can support the video series,
always very much, appreciate if you want, subscribe to that.
And finally, there's a tweetbot that helps you keep up to date with a
schedule.
If you want to catch the live stream, which again would be very
important say for today, where we had to move the livestreams time due
to unforeseen consequences.
So basically if you do like catching the stream live and you want to
be kept up to date on when it's going to be on any given day, the
tweetbot is the place to go.
So thanks again for joining me.
I hope to see you back here again.
9 a.m.
tomorrow until then have a wonderful day and I will see you guys
later.
Take it easy everyone.