And start recording.
Hello everyone and welcome to handmade Heroes show where we code a
complete game live on Twitch.
You know, one of the things that is a problem.
When you are trying to develop a game that's for educational purposes,
like this one is and so your streaming every last little bit of the
development.
You only get one hour a night to work on it.
And you also have to talk the entire time.
So,
It's a lot harder to program than it normally would be, so you have a
pretty big head wind there and it makes it so that it's a lot harder
to get as much done in an hour as you normally would, and that's
unfortunate.
So there's it's tough.
However, once in a while, you actually get a pretty big windfall from
this process and to say the least, that is exactly what happened
yesterday.
Because yesterday, we had a bug
That is a relatively difficult bug.
I would say it was a it was a pretty tricky one and I did not
immediately think of really any Avenues.
So we were going to have to today start by like starting starting
going.
All right let's see what all our assumptions are.
Let's start trying to validate them.
Let's capture enough information that we can start validate each one
and start looking for the culprit blah blah, right?
But instead the the sort of Hardcore viewers of handmade hero.
Today.
Found the bug, I mean I don't know that they found the bug, but from
reading the forum's people were posting like we think this is where
the bug is, we think we found it.
And when I read what they wrote, I think it's a pretty solid guess.
Like, I was like, that sounds a lot.
Like it could be the bug.
So, I think, in the same way that the stream takes away, a lot of
productivity, because of the nature of what it is once in a while you
get a pretty
Boost.
Because if it were just me and it was in real life and I started to
bugging this, I could have been debugging it for several hours and
instead it was just like you just have all these sub, it's like having
a bunch of programmers in the office.
You can just call over and be like, hey, I got this bug.
You guys want to look at it and like they all start looking at it and
like somebody finds it or whatever, right?
So let's talk about that, let's just Dive Right In and see if they
found it.
I think they probably did like I said when I looked at as like that's
pretty good and I think it indicates something that we should probably
do as well and I'll talk about that just as soon as we look at the
bug.
So it's day 1 87 today so if you want to follow along at home day, 186
is the source code to unpack.
That's the code.
I'm starting with today.
So if you preorder the game on a m dot org unpacked a 186 is source
code day 187's.
The The Code 4
That.
So let's talk about what was happening and we'll sort of talk about
They thought the bug was so, here we are.
And as you can see, we get what looks like a pretty valid profile.
Carpeting at the beginning, we're actually seeing as those things
scroll by when it sort of started, we were seeing some reasonable
profiles but then unfortunately after that initial wave, we don't see
anything.
It's kind of interesting here as I read launch it now I still don't
see anything so you only get some right at the beginning and I think
part of that is probably also because the first time you run it caches
are cold the
Takes longer all that stuff and those delays, I think we're probably
helping us out.
So we Tracked Down The Bug.
Yesterday, we actually did kind of look at what the bug actually was.
And we knew what the bug was.
We just didn't know what was causing it.
So what the bug was is that we are sort of doing this this thing that
per thread.
As we go through, we look every time we open a timing block, we keep
track of that.
And then we look for the clothes, the the matching clothes block for
it and then we kind of retire that.
So you keep like a little stack for every thread as you open blocks,
the stock gets a little higher.
As you close them, it gets a little lower and what we found was that
seem to be working just fine up until some point when we got a bunch
of debug records that look like they had opens with no match and
closes.
And that was a little bit of a Puzzler and one of the things that's
generally true I find because, you know, like I was saying on the pre
stream, I've been programming for a long time and program for 30
years.
One of the things that's generally true when you're debugging
something, is that?
Because I programmed for so long, usually, I did bug things in 10, 20
minutes, something like this, even if it's a relatively hard bug,
because I kind of know what the problems could be right, and I go look
for
And it's one of them and we fix it and you've seen that happen a bunch
of times on the stream, but every so often, even if you've been
programming for this long, at least if you're anything like me you
still get bugs that are stumpers.
You get a bug to the Stamper and it stumps you and you're like, I just
don't know what's going on and it does it can take hours, it can take
days.
Sometimes to find these bugs.
And sometimes it turns out that it legitimately just was that hard.
I've had times when the compiler was outputting bad code, that's, I
mean that just takes a long time to track down, right?
You've had I've had times when the operating system has a bug in it,
so things that are just fundamental are flawed and you go look for
them and you're like that actually probably was going to just take a
couple of days.
It was that hard, right?
but other times,
The bug is not so complicated.
Right.
It's a very simple bug.
And so the question is, why did that bug take so long to find?
When these other bugs, which are comparatively simple did not.
And again the reason there is because of that intuition the reason is
because you make certain assumptions about what is true, in your code
and your debugging ability from years of experience, usually ends up,
being built up around.
What are the sorts of things that are probably going to be the case
here?
I will go look for them and the bug usually ends up.
Being there and you're like, okay and so you're debugging process,
typically boils down to checking things that allow you to narrow in on
that field of possibilities.
But what you don't do, during that time, he's check all the other
things in the program because some of those could be wrong, but
obviously you can't check them all and the where you draw that line
between what you assumed to be true and what you believe to be up in
the air and they need to be verified the stumper bugs.
Come when you are unable to draw that line correctly.
You have carved something out of consideration that is actually where
the bug lies, right?
It's just like trying to find anything else in the real world if you
lost your keys and your trying to find them and you don't find them
for a long time, even though they turn out to be in a place that was
totally reasonable.
The reason is because you just don't think that the keys could
possibly have been somewhere, right?
But then it turns out, you're like, oh, right, they could have
They're right.
Because obviously if you're going to look for your keys, you can't
look everywhere in the world.
You have to make some guesses about where they might be.
And so the times when you find your keys and it's easy is because you
guessed correctly after a few tries, some of the places they could
have been and you found them, right?
But if it's in that really tricky place,
That yeah it turns out you were there with the keys.
You just never, you didn't remember, right?
You never look there.
You don't find them for days or who knows what happens or you don't
find them at all?
And so this bug is definitely one of those kinds, right?
And so, what the, what the folks on the on the forums are staying and
we'll see if they're correct.
What they were saying is that we were tripped up by our translation
unit Index, right?
Because if you remember how this works we tried out something new.
And this again is kind of probably a little bit indicative of why I
guessed poorly on where the bugs might be or where that line should be
drawn.
We tried a new thing they haven't tried before and I don't know how
effective it is, right?
And that was using.
In fact, I'll just open up the code so you can case you don't
remember, which is using this sort of counter system to have a unique
ID for each of our debug locations, right?
It was pretty cool, it's interesting.
I've never tried it before and it was just a consequence of having
very small.
Of translation units because normally you can't do that because you
have a large number of translation units since we have only three, it
was well within the realm of accomplishments so we tried it.
What that means is that we need a translation unit number in order to
figure out which debug record actually goes.
In what place, right?
So if we have a debug record index tells us uniquely for a translation
unit, which debug record.
We're looking at without the translation.
Unit index being correct.
We don't actually know which debug record it is.
We have to have a translation at zero one or two to say, whether it is
in the main code, the optimized code to the platform layer, right?
And that was a concession that we had to make in order to try out this
counter system.
Well, it turns out,
Remember, I had actually started out doing it correctly, I had made
record debug event, I think or something similar to it, a macro, which
is what I want to do eventually anyway.
But I switched it to an inline function at one point so that we could
watch it and have an easier time to bug a.
Well, there's a problem with that.
The problem with that is that if it is an inline function, if we're
not building within lining on everywhere,
And even if we are, I guess I'm not really sure what the rules would
be for this in C++.
But the compiler is certainly free to actually not in line that
function.
If it doesn't in line that function than what's going to happen is
there's going to be a version of it generated in every translation
unit, right?
So every transfers that calls it.
So we have three translucent translation units.
Each of them calls, record, debug event.
What that means.
Is there going to be a version of record
I meant thrown into each of those translation units.
However, when it comes time to link the Linker is only going to use
one of them because that's how the Linker works.
It does not.
Does not try to keep them separate.
And, at least that, as far as I know, it does not necessarily try to
keep them separate so it's totally within its ability, like it's
allowed as far as I know.
And again, I'm not really a C++ language learner these days because I
don't pay much attention to it so maybe I don't even know if that's
true.
It could be that the in line is supposed to always make sure there's
one per translation or something like that but what they were
hypothesizing on the forums and I guess people actually check this
out, was it what's happening is it's
Generating a different record debug in.
But in record, debug event for each translation unit, putting the
correct translation unit in there.
But then at link time, it's actually throwing out one of them, so that
no matter which translation unit is actually calling in to record
debug event.
It's only ever using one of the translation units, what that means,
we'll have conflicting debug record indices, which will make it look
like something is being opened and closed in a pattern, that's totally
not correct.
T' for what could actually.
Be happening there.
That was their hypothesis.
It certainly sounds like a very good guest to me and it turns out that
there's actually a pretty easy way for us to determine that.
What we can do is just see if the translation unit index ever actually
equals something other than 0 or 2.
Right?
So optimized our to translation units optimized and Main get compiled
together.
We should be seeing translation units of both 0 & 1 when we run
through our debug event
So what I'm going to do is take a look and see some in the wrong
function here.
When we're actually spending over them, I just want to see if we see
both of them or not, if we see both of them, then it might, it might
suggest that that's not actually the case, although it still could be
for various other reasons.
But I'm going to just see if that's the case if we don't see ever
translation unit 1.
Then we know yep that's exactly what happened.
We're only getting one version of record debug event and that's
throwing us off.
So that's at least a bug if not the bug and it seems like a very
likely culprit for the bug.
so, let's take a look here when we run through these, I'm going to do
in assert
That the event translation unit is not equal to 0 that should fire
right away, right?
Because we believe we should have translation unit 0 ones in there and
we do so that's fine and now we're going to see about translation unit
1 and I apophysis here would be that would not fire.
It does.
So first of all we've learned that there are sometimes at least where
translation unit 1 is happening.
Now I'll double-check translation unit to as well but I assume that
means we've got all three translation units happening right okay so
it's not necessarily clear to me yet.
What the that the what they think is the bug is the bug because we are
getting translation unit 1 which is the optimized translation unit,
but we don't necessarily still know whether all of the paths from
That optimized one are actually getting the correct translation unit
even so.
So what I'd like to do is take a look at handmade optimized here.
I'd like to see what the time functions actually are.
So there's a time there's two of them, right?
There's there's this one here.
Right.
And there's this one here.
So it's possible that one or the other of them is not actually
recording it properly.
I'm going to go ahead and just step into that function and see and you
know what else I'm going to do to make it a little bit easier on us.
I'm going to see if this bug Repros in fully unoptimized mode.
So if I actually turn off optimization in all the paths so we're not
building optimize at all, what happens, right?
Let's find out.
So, that's very interesting right there that alone starts to suggest
that perhaps that that is actually true because if the region can't
went up that suggests that maybe we're actually getting a more
accurate.
Would run in there.
But that's sort of a separate thing.
We're gonna have to figure out something to do about this because I
don't like having to sort of make these.
We're gonna have to figure out some way of making it cleaner way of
storing these things.
But anyway, okay, we'll go here and see
And hey look, it does not actually seem to Repro in debug mode.
Which again starts to kind of suggests that that could actually be the
case that it's the translation.
Unit thing is maybe optimizing, one of them welding it into the code
and the other ones calling out.
So we are still getting some ones and some zeros out of there, right?
I don't know but it could also just because of the speed.
I really just don't know at this point.
Again just trying to investigate to see whether or not that makes
sense.
So, it looks like I do have to have this guy on full optimizations, or
at least something Beyond, no optimizations in order for it to have
him.
Record properly.
There he is.
And the bug is obviously happening.
No question there.
We're not seeing anything.
So let's go ahead into handmade optimized here.
What I'm going to go ahead and do is I'm going to I'm going to go in
here and I'm going to set a breakpoint in draw a rectangle quickly.
So draw rectangle quickly.
I'm going to do a run.
And inside this run, I'm going to see if I can if I can actually look
at the code that's being executed to find out what's happening again,
with that with that timing block, right?
I want to see what the actual thing is that it does.
I guess I can't really there it is.
I don't need multiple threads on this.
So I'm going to do the same thing that I did before and freeze all the
other threads that are running.
And so I am going to just take all these guys who are running our
other stuff here.
I'm going to freeze those guys so that they are frozen and then I'm
going to step into this guy.
So, here we are on record debug event, right?
It's getting written out.
I'm going to take a look here at our Global debug table, so that I can
have some sort of an idea of what's getting recorded.
You can see here where we are in that in that list 5924 40, that's
been incremented already.
So we're looking at something in Array 0.
That is
Near 59 to 440.
So it's going to be like, let's say I've been here for 39, something
like that and I'm going to take a look at this guy's.
So let's take a look as we right through here.
You know what, the other thing we could do is to, there's another way
we could actually figure this out.
I want to take a look and see where it thinks we are.
So there we are in handmade temp dot DL.
I'm just trying to figure out if there is a fork or debug event.
So, you can actually see.
I think we're basically, we're basically seeing exactly what what we
expect to see if the bug is what they said.
It is we're actually in a function right now so this was not in lined.
So it is highly possible that these things got collapsed, right?
So let's take a look and see what it right to the translation unit.
Let's see if we can see that happen.
I don't know if we can or not the debug record index should have
gotten written in here.
I'm not seeing it.
I'm wondering if maybe
I'm still off by a little bit here.
I'm not sure.
Don't know how many of these I need to look at.
Let's take a look at these guys here.
None of them appear to actually been updated and I can't really look
at that.
Oh well you know what?
I can just look at the disassembly and see what that actually
executed, right?
So it looks like it moved to re x r ax, the keyword pointer here and
then it moved a b pointer and it moves zero, that's the wrong
translation unit.
Right.
So they totally nailed it.
So I didn't actually look at who the people are on the forums who
found it, but good work, guys.
I mean that you're right on the money.
That's exactly what the problem is right there, right?
And so, the fact that it chose to throw out, that guy is exactly why
we had the problem.
Now, you know, the trivial fix for this, obviously there's a very,
very simple fix for this, which is just to make this a macro and then
it has to be expanded in line.
You know, I can or you could do a force in line would be the way to do
it.
And so, if I did something like this, right?
And then
C, backslash region.
I could probably get away with just doing that and that may fix the
problem.
Just straight away.
You know, let's find out.
And it does.
So that was it it was just a problem with our translation
traditionalist.
But here's what I'm thinking, just based on that,
First of all, we should take a moment.
We really need to reverse all the shame.
Maybe like if the owl of Shame is backwards or something that's like
an owl of success.
Like you guys have found that that was a great job finding that
Like, well done, because that's a tricky one.
Like again, it was the compiler doing something.
In particular that, you know, we weren't thinking it could do and in a
way that's like, kind of subtle.
And so, you know, I mean, that was that was good work.
So good work to everyone at found that that was really, really well
done.
And like I said that probably saved a lot of stream time because I
would have had to go through piece by piece until I Came Upon that.
It would have taken a very long time, so that's pretty awesome.
However, so we should definitely say that.
But the other thing that I would like to mention is I think for me
that may be the straw that breaks the camel's back as far as the camel
of using the per translation.
Unit stuff is concerned.
Because again it was an experiment.
It's something I've never tried before.
I think it probably does have some useful aspects to it, but I feel
like that kind of bug is very subtle.
It was because of complexity that we had to introduce
In order to use the counter.
And I just don't feel comfortable relying on something like that when
kind of now I know.
All right, there's some cut.
There's there was enough, Jank Enos and you know if there's tankiness
that's not the end of the world, but it's janking is that we've now
seen cause of subtle bug that to me suggests, it's time to say, this
is not a reliable way to do this, right?
And that's fine, you know, that's not the end of the world.
You got to experiment, you got to try stuff out.
This was a new thing.
I had not tried it.
For I just feel like I'm kind of, I'm feeling on the side of.
I don't love it, I don't like it.
It introduced too much complexity for what should have been, a
relatively simple thing.
And I don't think it saves enough in return to really be at least for
what we're doing for this purpose to really be worth that extra
complexity because the complexity has costs like we just saw right?
So that's my feeling on it.
Now we don't have to fix
It right now because that is a suitable fix for now.
But I do feel like that's something, you know, I would like to just
say here that I would like to switch away from the translation unit
indexing and just go a more standard one time hash table.
Because the complexity seems to be causing problems.
So, yeah.
So I'm a little, I'm a little worried about that, I don't like it and
I think that for me, that's that would suggest that I would not do
this this way, again, it's working now so, you know, maybe we just
leave it for now.
But I think, you know, if we had another bug in it, I would say, let's
replace it.
Let's not even to bucket.
Let's just replace it.
It's not and then we'll do a bug, it rather than kind of having a keep
on to us.
But like my, my eyes on that.
I don't like it.
I don't like how that went down.
And, you know, even though I'm kind of aware of that as like a
possible, kind of bug.
I just don't, I don't have enough confidence in it.
So that's it though.
I mean that was the bug and so I believe, now we're in reasonable
shape.
We just have a bunch of work.
We have to now do to actually go.
That kind of derailed, it's a bit actually get back to what we were
trying to do which was produced some useful visualizations here.
So, the first thing that I'd like to do is I don't think we want to
produce regions if the Region's can't really be seen, you know what I
mean?
So, I think one thing we could do just right off the bat is when we're
going to add a region.
Like when we do an ad region, I'd like to do something where we test
to see if the number of clocks is even going to be enough to show up.
You know we should have some kind of a notion of what the min max T
difference would have to be in order.
Refer to actually be included.
And so, what I'd like to do there is I'd like to create those Min and
Max tease like so,
Something like this.
And then I'd like to check them so that I can see whether or not I
believe that it is something worth recording.
So I guess what I'd say is if the max T minus the Min to, you know, is
not greater than like our T threshold.
Then I would like to just ignore it.
I should say see if it's greater than T threshold.
Then I'll keep it.
so, the threshold t,
I don't know, probably something like this.
Like if we imagine having the bar divided into hundreds, something
less than a hundredth of a bar, does not seem like a useful thing to
add.
So I'm going to just see if that makes things a little more usable,
right.
Because basically there were all these little tiny invisible bars in
there that we're just like little tiny Snippets of time and those
don't seem like things that are particularly useful to add.
Okay, so let's think about this a little bit more.
So here we go, here's our dude.
And if we take a look now to we're running pretty slowly, you know?
And of course, the running slowly.
A lot of that is just the debug, the debug frame stuff.
So what I'd like to do is make sure we can compile it out.
First of all, right, I'd like to be able to compile out the debug
stuff, and I'd also like to be able to be able to switch the viewing
of it on and off.
Just so we can make sure that we kind of have that stuff under control
as well.
All right.
So what would we do here right now?
We would want something where these blocks and stuff, we would want
some way of having these things turn, you know, basically off and on.
So what I want to do is have some kind of an if statement here, right?
That's like, you know, if timer or if
Debugging is enabled.
I don't know perfect profile enabled if profile so we've got I don't
know.
We've got a build in here.
We have our little handmade defines, I believe.
Yeah, we've got him here and I'd like to be able to see those a little
bit more easily.
So I think I'm going to move those out.
I think I'm going to try this set, common compiler Flags.
I'm going to go ahead and say that.
So, that way, I can see our settings.
There.
In fact, maybe I'll put it at the end as well, so we can see more of
the settings.
So, we got 132, we've got slow, we've got internal, and I'm going to
just say we've got profile.
Is another switch we can flip.
So if we have handmade profile turned on, then we do this stuff.
Otherwise,
I want to be able to just vaporize these so that these things are not
ever actually inserted into the code, they're just like not there,
right?
So time function, just expands to nothing time to block expands to
nothing.
Begin block, end block, expand to nothing, so that no matter what
anyone is doing, no matter what they think they're doing nothing
happens, right?
So, you know, by default we build, we got
Profiler on and there's the profiler.
But if I then say go into that build that bat and I say turn the
profile off and recompile.
That code should be literally gone, right?
So it's just not there and you can see that even though we're still
like we haven't turned off the display of it at all, you can see that
we're back to running nice and fast, right?
We've got our performance back and everything and nothing is actually
showing up in the graph, which is what we'd expect, because there are
no debug records.
There are no debug events in the log.
Nothing is happening.
So when it goes to draw it,
Nothing to look at, so that's good.
But now, once we have the profile on which is what we want to do, at
the moment, we need to start having some way of interacting with the
sky, right?
Is what I think we need to do.
Now, the other thing that I would like to do here, I'd also like to
know, so we're pretty slow, right?
Like I'm looking at.
Look at how slow we are right now, right?
And I'm not sure how much sense that makes I feel like something.
Weird is up, you know what I mean?
Because that framerate feels really slow to me.
Like, you can see it's dramatically slower than it was before, right?
I mean, hopefully you guys can see on the stream, how much slower that
is.
But if we look over here,
At our profile.
Our profile doesn't actually back that up.
So I want to figure out.
I feel like we're drawing it wrong or something is a little off.
Because if you think about it, if you look at how much time this stuff
is taking in theory, the top of the chart like the entire size of the
chart with something like 30 frames a second, right?
So even though if we're missing that right, which you can see that we
are missing it several
In a lot of cases, even if we're missing that, we're missing it by a
very little bit, most of the time, right?
There's not, there's not much going on there.
So the question is, if we're only missing 30 frames a second by little
bit, why isn't the game running at like 15 frames a second?
And instead looks like it's running it like you know five frames a
second or two frames a second or something like this.
Why is it so much slower?
And maybe I'm just wrong about that.
Maybe I
I have a.
I'm misjudging that speed but I feel like that's something to take a
look at.
So, all right, there's a pretty easy way that we can actually do
something about that.
If we go ahead into win32 handmade dot CPP, you know, we had a frame
rate counter in here, right?
We did like a query performance counter kind of a thing.
So see here, win32 get wall.
Fuck.
So, one thing that we can do is, we can do something where we try to
show these these wall clocks a little bit better as well, right?
We know our flip wall clock, we've got our encounter as well, so we
have the ability to pass that thing in.
And so maybe, you know, we have this thing before that we were sort of
passing to the debug system.
Maybe that's something we should pass to the debug system as well.
Write something that sort of says
here is a wall clock time so you can just validate your our dtsc
measurements against that wall clock time.
And make sure they at least make some semblance of sense.
Right?
Seems like pretty reasonable to me.
So that's something we could do there.
And also another thing that we can do is we can have the you know, we
can then say here's what the here's what the actual are dtsc's total
were for the whole block, right?
Because we know, you know, we know that here's the frame marker, we
could basically say that like at the frame marker here.
The wall clock time.
So we can look and say we have a relatively reasonable guess as to how
many cycles elapsed and how much wall clock time elapsed.
So that those two things can be correlated, right?
That seems like pretty reasonable to me.
So in
To do that.
What I would like to do.
I suppose, we could move the frame marker down to the beginning.
I don't know, which is the best place for it.
I guess, you know, the frame marker.
When we insert that frame marker, it be nice to be able to insert the
time, the wall, the wall clock, s, you know, right in there.
I don't know how realistic that would be for us to actually do.
But if you take a look at these debug events, I suppose it's not
entirely out of the question that we couldn't Union it and put it on
our 32 in there, since we don't care.
For example, about the thread ID or the core
In the debug record index, we don't care about any of that for the
wall clock, right?
We could imagine doing something where we have at our 32 that will
right in there for the, for the debug frame marker.
So, begin block and end of the lock.
They will actually use these but, you know,
Say, the debug record index or maybe the core index in the thread ID,
those are actually a youth or do to, you know, for I'm sorry an R32
for the frame marker, we could do that.
I don't know if that makes the most sense but it seems pretty
reasonable.
So let's take a look at what would happen if we did that.
If we did that, let's do something.
Like, I don't know, thread ID and a core index, we could do something.
Like struct debug event or thread ID core Index, right?
You still don't get the core index, we don't have a way to get that
the moment, so kind of a useless value but even so so if we do this,
put it there,
I don't know what we'll call that something like this.
Then it here we can have wall clock time.
And then we can just keep running into the stream there.
What our actual records are?
And our frame marker here, can take whatever that is.
So we have went through to get wall clock.
And so I can just go ahead and stick that in there.
So up the frame marker will call went through to get wall clock with
three to get wall clock.
I believe just returns s for us, right?
Hmm.
No, it doesn't.
I need, I need to convert it.
I need to actually convert it to S.
So what I actually want is something like inline R32 with who to get
wall clock, s something like this.
And that would divide by query performance frequency, right?
I said, would say let's divide result.
We want to call went through to get wall clock.
I suppose.
Global perf count.
Frequency is what?
64-bit.
Yeah, so all I have to do.
I think is just take quad part from the get wall clock.
That'll give me the 64-bit, integer representing the clock time.
Here's the perf frequency.
If I divide those two, I guess I could do you know, full 64-bit
divided on the to
That would just get me back a wall clock time stamp and that would be
that.
Now maybe that's not the smartest idea because maybe get a little bit
less Precision that way if we wanted to do it the other way round.
I guess we would just do something right where we do to get well,
clock, where we would pass just the elapsed time.
So the frame marker actually says, how much time was elapsed since the
previous frame.
And again, if we want to do that, then we would basically be in the
business again of doing sort of a diff between the two, if that makes
sense.
So trying to do a diff between the two
She's me like the first time through.
We would say, let's say we have large integer, but we've got last
counter already, but I guess we'll do what.
Supper one frame marker.
Could probably clean this up.
In fact, what does last count or even two?
It's just the end of that frame.
It's like at the bottom of it, right?
You know, we could probably even just piggyback on that.
I'm not going to deal with that for now though.
Well, we'll worry about restructuring this Loop when we come through
and do sort of the final pass on it and try to make something that's
more ship oriented and less Dev oriented for the win32 main Loop that.
So, I'm just going to go ahead and say,
That we have that, I might say that, we initialize it to 0 and then
when we come through here, I'm going to do like something like frame
marker seconds.
Elapsed, I'm going to set that to zero.
I'm going to say that the first one just gets that there that there
was no seconds.
Elapsed.
That's just a it's just a hard marker.
That doesn't actually count.
Although also looking at that, it's kind of like well that might give
us that might give us an impetus to sort
Of use the existing one because that means that our first frames time.
Is that the first time as a meaningless value?
I don't know.
It's really tough decision.
I kind of want both, you know?
Well, I know how long the frame took
And I guess if I wanted a time to Startup code, I should time that
separately.
I don't know.
This is just a really hard decision, it's a really hard decision, I
feel like there's no good answer because what I'm thinking in my head
is I also would like to know how long it was between the startup of
the program and when we actually got here which was it just that I
might want to like have these sort of way points marked a little more
explicitly.
I suppose it's not the end of the world.
I'll go ahead and move it down at the bottom for now.
But that's warrants further consideration that's all I'll say about
that.
Okay, so if I come through here there should be a way for me now kind
of to know I've got the end counter last kind of close encounter.
So I know at this point what the difference between these two guys was
so I have a rough estimate of that and I can just do something where I
say like okay those guys are going to be
You called, if I look at this, when we're calling debug frame and
that's doing a bunch of work there.
So I kind of need to count that right as part of the time in this
Frame, I think that would be more appropriate.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to actually have went
through to get wall clock.
Oh and that's actually interesting.
So that actually also explains why our profile isn't isn't lining up.
We're not timing the time spent collating debug records, which is
probably very substantial.
So we'll see that in a second anyway.
Hey we already found the problem.
So anyway, here is our and clock.
And here's our static setting, our last counter.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to go ahead and set here
went through to get seconds elapsed.
And I'm going to ask for the seconds elapsed between last counter and
encounter.
So now I'm actually passing the through their frame marker.
Obviously just does the standard thing that it does it does a record
debug event but that debug event is setting.
The standard things that we set in a debug index in a debug event.
Right now, what we want to do is we want to actually set a frame time,
right?
So we want, like seconds elapsed here,
you know, I'm saying and so we want
This value and the debug event to be set instead of the one that did
get set.
So what I'm going to do there is I'm going to say like okay when we do
record debug event,
we're going to need to do essentially the same set of operations here.
And we're going to need to kind of know.
We're going to we're going to have to know that we only set these in a
you know in certain circumstances.
So how would I do that?
I think the easiest way to do that would probably be
Septum maybe more towards the end, you know, set them.
Here or something like this.
And then only, and then have that be something that's actually code.
Have that be something that's actually may be done by the macro
itself, right?
Done by the whoever's calling it, because I'd like to keep this.
I'd like to keep this part the same, you know what I mean?
So, what I would say is okay, there's a pound of fine here, which is
like record, debug event common, something like that.
It's going to do all of the stuff that we know that we always do,
which is this
But then record debug event.
Just does this.
Oops.
We're groups cord index event type that just gets done.
And so that in frame marker, we can do exactly the same thing, but set
the event parameters differently, right?
Clock is not the one I wanted for indexes, but I actually so something
like that.
And then what we can do is do sort of it slightly differently here.
Record.
Debug event record index event type.
There we go.
We'll do the common part and then we can also now
Do this part as seconds elapsed.
Okay.
So, moving on to many actual parameters for record, debug event
common.
Is that true?
Let's see, yes it is.
Keep those up there.
There we go.
And now in theory we should be able to have these guys.
Oops.
Have these guys come out of the Union?
Like so, so that's all good.
And now, inside this, debug event, frame marker, we now have the
ability for our current frame wherever that frame maybe can actually
specify a seconds elapsed and that seconds elapsed can actually be
based on the actual wall clock time.
So, now, for every frame, we know that again, in the end clock, and we
also know,
Seconds elapsed.
So that allows us to line up our wall clock time, current frame needs
to actually have one of those
So here's a debug frame wall seconds elapsed maybe it's what we'll
call it well seconds elapsed.
And when we actually create one of those
So yeah, the only problem with that is we take the begin clock from
this one, not the end clock.
So if we do have frame markers that happen at the end, we do have to
do it like this, right?
Something like that.
So we do have to do something where we say, like, oh, okay, we'll
remember what the what the clock is.
That's, that's actually fine.
That's not a problem.
That just means that this part happens a little bit differently.
So instead what we do,
Yeah, is we'd have to, okay?
You can see why that's a little annoying, right?
It means that we see the frame marker after we've already collected
all the information for that frame.
You know what I mean?
So, it doesn't really cause us much of a problem, but it does mean
that, you know, when we see a frame marker, what we're doing is
saying, if we had a current frame, all the information for the frame
actually happens there, right?
So if we had a current frame, all the stuff actually occurs here, if
that makes sense.
Like what that that wall s of locks that comes in that actually goes
with the, with the event, that we've sort of been we've been writing
to and then when we see it, we then create a new frame that's going to
be for all the events that come after we know what the begin is.
Which is now.
But this is for the next frame, right?
It's not the frame that we, it's not the frame that represents this
event and then the rest of the stuff can stay the same, but we don't
know what the wall seconds.
Elapsed is yet we have no idea.
It could be anything.
So just it just cast switches up.
How that works a little bit, but I think that's good.
Okay, so
Last night, it's going on here.
I know what happened there.
Keyboard was not responding.
I'm sorry, Dave, I can't I can't save the file so we got about 10
minutes left on the clock, if I remember correctly.
Sorry, about 10 minutes late.
So let's see what's going on here?
That's probably a bug.
What's going on here?
Current frame.
Region, count 2048.
Well.
Are we just not cycling.
Our region properly, current frame equals the next one.
Clock range from Rescue L.
Yeah that but that
I don't know why we have so many regions.
That doesn't seem quite right.
See here, region cap.
Like could there even be that many regions.
Seems odd.
Okay, so now, well, there's a couple things.
So now, we can at least see that this line.
We can, we can see this line being longer than it was before.
So, what's odd about that is?
I didn't actually change that piece of information yet, right?
I did move the frame marker down but this is still not being.
This is not be encountered in there, so that's a little bit odd that
that
Got but that changed shape, right?
That's a bit strange.
I'm not sure exactly what to make of that.
That feels like, I just did something stupid.
Could be that kind of day.
After all, I got off easy because other people on the stream already
found the bug.
So I didn't have to really work very hard.
Maybe it's making me lazy, right?
Because you can see
We're running the same code as before, there really isn't any reason
why that should now be a different shape.
This is just the main line code, but it's waiting for the, it's got a
long tail here, right?
The, the those two guys are the end, guys.
And here we've got frame weight and frame display, and I don't really
understand why those would have elongated themselves.
Like, I don't understand why those would have gotten larger, we're not
counting this stuff.
If we do count this stuff that will do now,
Let's take a look here.
Also, I don't know if n cycle count, that's the Cycles left.
That doesn't really need to be done anymore, right?
Because we now got cycle counts all over the place.
There's really no read meat for us to be doing that in the platform
layer.
Okay, so at the very least, now we can see this is more representative
of the frame rate, right?
So that's good.
I'm a little concerned about why these vote These Bars change sighs.
So I guess we'll have to keep drilling down to that.
But now you can see to that debug collation, just takes a huge amount
of time and it makes some sense because we had just a crazy number of
events it was looking through.
What was it like on the first frames there?
Like 500,000 Avengers on like that but then it was down to you know
it's tens of thousands of events and that's just a lot of
Of stuff to iterate through.
And we're not doing it in necessarily particularly smart way.
There's, you know, we have a ton of stuff we could think about their
but point being at least that's getting to be a slightly more
realistic picture now, but what I would like to do is I would also
like to now use that sort of, that sort of, for lack of a better term
wall clock time that we sent down there.
I'd like to once we have that now that we know like how many seconds
left for frame, I'd like to draw that in there so that we could sort
of see you know, here's the milliseconds per frame that's actually
happening there, right?
Right.
So what I'd like to do is when we do our debug overlay stuff,
And here.
I could just print out some information about the frames, like, for
example, because we now we have this van stuff.
So, when we, when we do our debug overlay, I could even do something
like this, right here.
We have the debug State and we have those frames when we're drawing
them.
In fact, I've got the font info here as well.
Right.
What I could do is say, let's, let's actually do a little bit of a
debug text line.
Vortex line.
This guy right here, what I'd like to do is I'd like to make him I
guess I only have five minutes left so maybe I shouldn't go too far.
Maybe I'll just call it once and then we'll worry about.
I was going to put it underneath each frame, I'll just call it with
the actual
yeah, for now, I'll call it with the with just the actual
single line with the may be the most recent frame, but what I'd like
to do is I'll abstract that out and then we'll call the the frames out
by having the actual milliseconds per frame kind of down along the
bottom, right?
So, here, if I did something like what we had there, I could do, you
know,
Well seconds per frame, there it is or maybe like last frame time,
something like that.
And then you here I could just say the debug state
give me frame 0.
What is it?
Wall seconds, elapsed.
That's the number of seconds.
So if I want the number of milliseconds, right, I could just multiply
by 1000 and then I've got it.
I could also just truncate that but we might as well just show it like
so something like that.
And then presumably we could get our MS X out there.
So there we go.
So you can see here what we think our frame times are.
Now that's not the last frame time that would.
That was the first frame time for a while there, so you can kind of
see what the frame times are here.
That it's odd how it climbed up like that too.
But I suppose that's, you know, it's not that odd actually, because as
we draw more things, the frame time goes up, because there's more
calls to draw a rectangle and other nonsense like that.
But yes you can see.
Now, what the what the last frame time is up there.
It's pretty expensive, right?
And if we actually turn off show drawing the debug stuff.
So, if I go in and instead of doing like the collation, if
If I if I just don't draw.
So let's say, I just in here, I say just draw that debug line and
don't try any of this stuff, right?
I'm curious to know what the frame time is.
I shouldn't I should.
Also probably do the actual last frame time, but you can see even with
drawing off.
It's the collation that really is pretty pricey.
They're, you know, even if we don't draw any of the results, collating
alone just takes a tremendous amount of our time.
Because when that's off, when collisions not happening, we just have a
lot less to deal with.
Now, I guess the other thing is we don't really know that it's
collation.
I suppose we do.
Way to turn off, call a specifically, could just also be the cost of
recording the debug events.
So we probably want to check test that as well.
And, you know, that's something we could also do just, just to see
here in terms of like doing the debug collation.
Unfortunately, without looking at the wall clocks, we wouldn't
necessarily know, but, you know, I guess one really easy.
Way to test that is in the platform code, since we have frame marker
as a separate thing.
Well, we
I'd do is have record debug event.
Not actually do anything, right?
So I could just say, you know what, instead of all this stuff I'm
going to do an undef here on time to block or time function and time
block, right?
And I'm going to find them to not do anything.
So that way, we would still have anything that was using the other
functions, right?
So anything that anything that's actually using frame marker will
work.
Right frame marker would just work.
Because no one's touching that but all the rest of the stuff will not
work.
So, yeah, in fact, that's the stuff that's actually in handmade
profile already.
So I suppose, I could just turn him a profile often we'd still get the
frame markers, which is kind of nice.
I don't know that, we actually want to leave it that way.
To be honest, but I guess since it's already there.
Let's just see what happens.
I turn it off.
Yeah, so I mean you can just see that
We turn it all off, completely.
Of course, that's still doesn't tell me.
It doesn't tell me how much time.
It just tells me that.
Yeah, because I need to actually put the records in there.
Get the frame marker ones out of it, that's a little rough.
So I'm not sure I think we're just about at, I'm not sure.
I actually probably need some other way of measuring the frame just to
see.
Because the problem is with collation, if we don't look through all
the records, we aren't going to know.
We aren't going to know.
What the frame time was since that's how we're currently displaying
the frame time, right?
So it's hard for us to get a bead on exactly which part of that.
It's costing us.
So, in here, right here is our debug State stuff.
You know, if I were to just go ahead and say don't call it the debug
records, we won't know what the frame time is.
So we'd have to have a second way so I could print it out or something
like that, right?
But didn't like that, I guess, because this never gets into
Last.
So we could, you know, we could print it out in some way, but in like
in Winter do handmade or something like that, which I guess is the
only real way that we can figure out one way or the other, which is
costing which goes at the profiles on
And we don't do.
Any of this?
And you know what?
I could also do it this way, if you book State frame count,
That would allow me to do this as well, Weber State frame count on
this one.
So, now that it's actually the last frame, right?
Because we're we were having that problem before.
Okay, so if we do that,
Then you know, we can.
Well I mean, we can kind of see the fact that it is the collation I
mean it would be nice to print it out but that's still running at a
very nice frame rate.
Very, very nice frame rate.
So looks like recording the info, not necessarily such a bad thing.
Collating it currently is not being done very well.
The collation is, clearly costing us a lot.
so we know, you know, now we know something,
All right, I'll go ahead and bring it to the Q&A.
This is good.
We're finally at a place where it's taken a while again.
No thanks to that extra complexity of the translation unit thing which
you know you live and learn.
First time, you try something often times.
You don't necessarily know what the reuter wrong or right reasons to
do something are.
But yeah, it looks like we've got all our information.
Now, it's coming through relatively reliably, we could focus on,
actually displaying it and useful ways and putting it in maybe a
little bit of UI there so we can kind of navigate through it, start to
drill down on the data so that's good better late than never we had a
nasty bug.
The costs two days is true but at least, you know, With a Little Help
from from the forums in fact, we were able to keep
To not too much time so that is the power of having multiple
programmers, I guess.
All right, let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
I feel like that's probably it's probably pretty easy to understand
what we did there I guess.
But just in case you guys have questions about that lets go to the Q&A
and and see what people have to say.
Please put a cute: in front your questions so I can answer it.
Quarter on what's your favorite bug of all time man?
You know the problem is I just I don't write them down and so like you
know I probably do have a favorite bug of all time and I probably
don't remember it.
Donna.
I'm sorry.
Yeah, I wish I could recall it but I don't know.
Serge RGB often when I'm debugging or Sergey RGB perhaps often when
I'm debugging.
I have to stop myself from changing stuff at random because of mental
laziness hoping for an.
Even number of signers, do you ever have that urge?
If so has a diminished, as you become more experienced
So, I guess what I would say is, yeah, that definitely changes over
time.
And I think the reason that that changes over time is because as you
program for longer, you tend to realize that it always comes back to
bite you, it just always does, right?
If you care about quality, you know if you're someone who just chips
it and doesn't care, you know then maybe not but assuming that you
care about the quality of the software which granted like I complain
about this dream all the time.
Very few people seem to I think I've said before that, you know
I actually don't have that high of a quality bar on my code, compared
a lot of people.
I know and yet and yet these days it seems like most people's code is
below my Quality Bar which is which is kind of scary.
That's not that's that's a canary you didn't want to see died in the
mine if that makes sense.
But so I think, you know, if you have a reasonable Quality Bar,
It just always comes back to bite you and so what you end up at the
end you end up with it's not that you don't have the urge to just
change stuff inmate working.
It's that you tend to do those changes more as investigatory changes
and if one of them fixes it you don't just move on you then go.
Okay.
Wait why did that fix it?
Let me go verify that.
That really that I understand why that actually fixed it.
That's really the difference and in fact you can see that pretty
Directly, if you go.
If let's if we go to my blog here that actually happened on some early
witness stuff here.
It's this one.
So I wrote a thing about a bug actually and here it is.
And then I thought, I knew what the bug was, I went on Christmas
break, I came back from it and it turned out the bug was something
else.
And the only reason I found that out was because it was nagging at me
that I didn't think the fix should actually have fixed it.
You know, I fix it just for Chris Rick.
I went away and while I was actually on Christmas break, I was like
this just doesn't add up.
And then when I came back, I was able to verify that.
In fact, it was a different bug and it was just the fix I had done had
masked this other bug that was in there.
So I think that's a valuable skill to learn is just going, you know,
it's experimentation while you're debugging is is actually good.
Because if you hit upon something, that fixes the bug, that's very
important information.
The problem is, don't stop there.
Make sure you then go.
Why did it fix the bug?
Can I prove that this fix is actually the correct fix?
And not something that hides the bug?
And if I can't, I'm not done yet, right?
That's really the only change that has to happen.
Your intuitive desire, to kind of fiddle and see if it fixes it isn't
necessarily bad.
It's don't let that be the end.
Captain craft.
Doesn't it go against your philosophy of write the code as you need it
to make a debugger like this before, the game needs much debugging?
Well, no, because again, we already have performance counters.
We had to write those for the renderer.
I already don't know where the time is being spent in this game.
I have no idea, right?
And I don't want to be in a situation where I'm constantly not knowing
and not having that sort of heads-up of like what's going on.
So I actually see this as an essential part of the programming, I see
myself as needing it now.
I don't see this as being a like, oh, this will come in handy later.
I see this is like I don't have any situational awareness, right?
It's like, I'm trying to drive a car, but the windshield has been
blacked out, right?
And so, like, I feel like it is something that I need.
Now that said, I don't actually have a philosophy of write the code as
I need it, I would not describe My Philosophy necessarily as that way.
I would describe it as write the code when I know what I, what I know
what I need, right.
If I know what I need.
Then I
Write that code if I don't know what I need, then that's a bad time to
write the code, right?
But if I know I need something just because I'm not necessarily using
it at that immediate moment doesn't mean, it might not be something I
choose to write.
If I think that it will be a nice thing to have earlier rather than
later.
Right.
I don't think there's like only one right time to put debugging into
the project, right?
I feel like it's a thing that pays dividends at all times and since I
know I'm going to have to do it sometime or another.
I might as well do it.
Now when I can when
It can pay dividends the entire time.
Instead of waiting till we have like, this really overwhelming need
for it and doing it then because I miss out on being able to use it
all the rest of the time.
And I had to, and I had to spend the time to write it either way.
You know what I mean?
Our connects is there any way to keep familiar with old code?
Or is it working with or is working with a frequently, the only way?
Yeah, I mean, I don't really know any shortcuts there, you know, I
mean, I write a lot of code.
I've never actually sat down to try and really measure it, but like, I
would say that
You know, in a given day, I usually write like thousands of lines of
code.
So there's just no way that I'm going to remember at all.
It's just not going to happen and so,
You you you do kind of have to go back and play with the old code and
sometimes you have to budget sometime, you have to be like you know, I
got to open up the subsystem.
I yes, I wrote it.
Yes.
I understood it very well at the time.
No, I don't remember it.
Right.
And now I gotta go in there and I know I'm going to spend a day or two
being very unproductive and I ain't going to write a thousand lines of
code that day like no thousands of lines of code coming out those days
because I'm literally just going to be trying to figure out how all
this kind of complicated stuff worked
And you know, and you try to minimize that by, you know, keeping your
programming style saying keeping your name's reasonable, trying to
clean things up.
So they're not completely disastrous all the time.
So that, you know, it's like if this function doesn't read cleanly,
it's not doing what it should do.
Like, I'll take a second to kind of maybe fix it before I leave.
That part of the code for a long time.
I'll be like, okay, this is really janky.
Let me see if I can just
kind of put it into a state that reads more cleanly, that doesn't have
as many
Weird special cases if I can do that and leave myself in a better
position coming back to it.
You know, maybe I would spend the time to do that whereas, you know,
did the code really need that to happen.
Possibly not.
So there are some things you can do when you're like, okay, I know
this is complicated system.
I know this is hard code to understand.
Maybe there are a few things I can do to make it easier on myself by
spending a little more time than was necessary to get the code to a
good place, get it to a like really good place, you know, like over
over deliver on the quality, like, you know, imagine
Imagine this, you know, maybe I'll look at the code and say, okay this
is good enough for what I'm doing right now, but I know I could do
better.
Maybe I will choose to do that better spend the extra two days to do
that extra betterness because then I know when I come back to it later
it'll be easier for me to pick back up, you know, you can do stuff
like that.
Everything in programming is a trade-off, right?
Everything is always a trade-off and sometimes you may decide that the
right trade-off to make is to spend a little bit more time now to do a
little bit better job on this code, then you were going to do.
Then what you need to do because when you come back to it later you
feel like you need that, it'll save you that time you know and only a
really experienced can let you make those decisions.
Well it's not like there's a magic thing.
Because by the same token, you could go nuts and over engineer
something and then you just wasted like three weeks doing a bunch of
extra work and it turns out to not matter at all, right?
And that would have been bad decision.
So it is definitely a litmus test.
It's a thing that's hard to know what is done at any given time for
peace code.
What?
What constitutes done?
It is difficult.
Amy 95 Mark actually found the bug and Andre has K actually figured
out why it is causing what was happening by looking at the assembly.
The compiler decided not to inline, the call in the Constructor, and
inline it in the destructor.
So the start marker is wrong and the end marker is right.
Yeah.
Like I said, you guys did a great job on that that saves a ton of time
and that would have taken a long time for me to find on stream.
There's no question.
Okay.
So it just decided
It decided to inline in one place, but then the other place, it
actually did end up using the shared routine throughout now, why it
didn't make two different routines because they're two different
translation because it was marked in line.
I don't know why that means.
If it was marked static, it would have worked, right?
Because it wouldn't have been able to share them.
I assume
that's really weird.
In fact, to be honest, are we sure that's not a compiler bug because
Because how was it allowed to merge?
Those two functions when they're not the same.
That's really kind of weird.
Stephen last.
Oh yeah, it did look like I did move for a marker below that you're
right.
Let me see about that.
Yeah, you're correct.
Yeah.
So this guy
Yeah, this guy is technically outside that range.
So this is yet another reason to, to, like, get rid of that and just
use the hash table because then we wouldn't have this problem either.
You know,
So, I don't know.
It's not a particularly difficult thing to fix.
Just this one.
But yeah, it does move past that to do, right?
Because we could put it down here and just say if Global deal on
table,
I feel like that would be fine.
Right.
I feel like that would just work to put it down there.
Yeah.
Do you really care about compilations or just threads hash, the thread
IDs?
Yeah, we don't actually so compilation units.
We don't care about it.
All we were just using it so we could use counter as a unique ID.
So, what I would like to do, I think at this point is get rid of that
and just hash the file line number.
That's that's what we actually want, right?
So, we just have to file and line number and we do it once, and it
would just store it in a static right there, right?
So that's, you know, that's fine.
So that's what we would do.
Do you write code for this project off stream?
Know I everything that I've ever done.
Any time I've ever touched the files for this project, it is on
stream, that's the goal of the project is to not have a single thing
happen.
Dream.
So even when I read the forums and people are talking about the code,
I just say my recollection of it is blah but I don't even look at it,
really because I try to keep it so that everything I do is is captured
If I don't have a credit card, is there another way to buy it?
Well, it supports PayPal, so anything you could use it like you can
use a bank account with PayPal if you're trying to buy.
If you're talking about handmade hero you can you can buy it with
anything that supported by PayPal or stripe, but I think stripe like
sports credit card.
So you have to probably use PayPal.
I think stripe was talking about adding Bitcoin support.
They did but send owl the purse.
The actual fulfillment thing for ordering.
It has an added support for that yet.
As far as I know.
So you still can't use Bitcoins yet?
You brought up your devlog, do you think that writing a devlog is good
for the writer, the readers or both?
I don't know.
I haven't thought much about it.
It sounds like the debugger is not only a tool to find out what's
going wrong.
But to detect when things are going wrong, is that a fair assumption?
I never thought of it a bug or something that keeps me situationally
aware.
That sounds like a great idea.
Yes, that is exactly what this code that were writing is for you.
Remember I said this, when we were talking about what we're doing for
the, when I introduced the concept of debug code, it's for two
purposes, is to help you find bugs that are hard to find.
And it's to help.
You know, when there are bugs, that are hard to know, are there,
right?
Things like performance problems in particular, are very difficult to
know are happening or where they are happening without a lot of
situational awareness.
The same is true of memory problems.
There's just a lot of things that you may not even know our broken
your game, just runs a little worse and you chalk it up to something
else.
Like oh that's just the GPU.
Slow or something, you know who knows?
Right.
But that's not what it was, right?
And so part of what we're trying to do here is instrument the code in
ways that we can use all the time.
And we've got a little ways to go before we get there, but we're
trying and so hopefully we'll get to the point where we can start
start using that more reliably.
All right, we have come to the end of the Stream.
It's true.
That's why things down.
Thank you for everyone for joining me for
Another episode of handmade hero and thank you particularly to, I
guess they're listed here at Mach Andreas k for figuring out the bug
in their own times.
That we did not actually have to spend nearly as much time as we would
have had to spend on stream looking into it.
They pretty much found the Smoking Gun and were like, here it is.
So that was pretty awesome.
Thank you very much, guys for that.
That really helped out a lot and I hope you guys had fun.
Finding it.
Those are pretty kind of neat bug, and I'm still not sure.
I got to go look now to see.
Whether is that, if the I don't really understand why the compiler was
actually allowed to do that, but I guess it must have to do with
inline functions being merged by name without having to verify that
through the same or something.
Maybe the spec allows that I don't know.
Point being that was a little odd.
It wasn't what I would expect it to be able to do but maybe it's an
edge case.
It's actually out either way we found it and thank you very much for
the help.
Until next time, if you would like to follow along at home to the
source code, you can always pre-order handmade hero the game on him, a
hero dot org and it comes to the source code even now while we are
working on it.
So you could follow along at home and play with the source code, do
your own experiments that sort of thing.
We also have a forum site, you can go to ask questions if you have
questions about what you saw on the series and want to ask them but
didn't get a chance to ask some lives.
Good place to do it.
We also have anti depe sewed.
Guide up up there.
You can use to watch the series.
It's easier to jump around in community members.
Have like marked it up with time markers and stuff so you can figure
out where stuff happens.
It's pretty cool.
We have a patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, you can subscribe to that and
we also have a tweet bot.
The tweetbot will tweet the schedule, so if you want to catch a stream
live, you can always check it out.
It tells you when it is going to be live and seeing everyone's going
to be alive tomorrow.
5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time right here on Twitch, we will start playing
around with how to get our debug visualization to be faster and more
useful to us.
Now, that we are collecting our events properly, we're going to try to
make them a little more usable.
Make them a little more useful.
So that's what we'll be doing.
Hope hope you'll come back.
Join me for that, until then have fun programming, and I'll see you
guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.