Start recording.
And hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero of the show.
We could have complete game live on Twitch.
This is I don't even know which day this is its day to 20.
And we are going to be sort of cleaning up some of our debug code
basically like reintegrating.
Some of the things we've written so that they all kind of work
together as they currently stand, that's really all we're doing and
it's mostly just, you know, kind of thinking things through and
And like merging things together.
So I'm just going to get right into it.
There's not a whole lot of preamble to it.
It's just basically, you know, code code mushing which is what you
kind of have to do.
After you do a big architectural thing.
You kind of have to start mushing everything together and making sure
everything plays well,
With each other.
So, yeah, if you want to follow along at home today, is 220, you want
to unzip 219 source code into a directory and that is what I'll be
working with.
So if you want to follow along, that's where you should be at.
Let's see where we ended up.
If I remember correctly, we're sort of at the point where we were even
having the hierarchies automatically construct themselves.
So, you know, that was all nice and good.
Yeah, so that is where we were at and you could
Could even expand and collapse them like so, but we didn't quite you
can see here.
We weren't at the point where we were clipping the names to be more
reasonable that you can you'll note that like the name is still the
giant name from before so we might want to fix that although it's
obviously not a super important piece of this whole thing but we
probably want to fix that.
And then we probably also want to do a couple things here.
Like start looking at this piece of
of code because remember we wrote this thing where you could like
highlight entities like we had now and you could actually integrate
those into the debug you I in fact we still got that.
Like you can still pick like a bunch of of entities and stuff like
that and that information gets dumped into the debug system but we
don't really we haven't really gone back and integrated that into sort
of the new way that we're doing things.
So we probably want to go make that work in a convenient way as well.
I'm
I'm thinking about, for example, you know how we have these like
drop-down menus, I'm not drop down menus.
These collapsible things here.
So I feel like what we would want to do is make it so that like you
know, when I select some of these things, instead of it like randomly,
you know, dumping and us as we have no idea what's going on here.
Like this one here, for example, just dumps the first one I guess.
Right.
Out out here.
Something nonsensical like that what we would want to do presumably is
have dumped to a particular location.
In in the debug hierarchy.
So that if you expanded to there, you would see the data of that
thing.
And if you dumped multiple of them, presumably would show up like
maybe in
In there with each one of them being expandable or something like
this, right?
You can imagine they're, you know, obviously something more reasonable
than what's going on right now and so that maybe would be a good thing
to look at today.
So because because really, we've got that.
And then the other thing that we would do is the profiler is getting
the profiler back in here.
So those are the two things that we would really want to do.
So I'd like to sort of dive in there and just focus on getting this
stuff out.
Out, because that's really the, the useful stuff.
So we can kind of get the debug system into a place where we can
basically sign off on it for now and say that it's you know
architecture Ali were relatively happy with it and then from then on
if we want you know to add things to the about system.
It's clear like how it works and where they would get at it and stuff
like that.
So let's go ahead and and keep going on that because that's the point.
I'd like to get two relatively soon so we can move on from the debug
system to some other stuff.
Not sure exactly.
I what but, you know, some other stuff.
All right.
So where are we at here?
If you remember this, debug value stuff, right?
You can see how we did this thing where we're like, debug begin data
block and then we would output this, like, simulation entity or
something like that, right?
And we have the ability to Output entity, debug ID.
You can see that happening here and that's kind of interesting because
that's like sort of a unique ID for this entity.
That's a thing where the entity itself.
That's like the grid, right?
And so what I'm kind of looking at here and I am just curious about
this is like I wonder if we could just unify these two systems and
say, okay, data blocks as well, we'll just be kind of grades and
they'll go into the system and then they'll have places where they
kind of come out, or that sort of thing, that might be kind of
interesting, right?
Then everything kind of all of our good stuff would be kind of
unified, and I don't know that seems kind of neat.
So there's something to be said for that the other
I'm thinking of us here when we do begin data, block you can you'll
notice we have simulation entity that could be How We Do sort of the,
the block name, right?
If we did something, like I'm just thinking cure, you can see in cure,
we've got simulation a, i render a right.
If we wanted this to show up under here as like whichever entity is
currently selected, you know, we could do something like saying
simulation.
Underscore.
Oops summation R square like highlighted under the or something like
highlighted entity, or just even just entity something like that.
And then when these things come get dumped out, we could make sure
that they go into, you know, that location.
And what's interesting about this, like I said to is, we also have an
entity debug ID that we can make, which unique, which is a unique
pointer, that we know what identify this.
Particular.
So,
What's kind of interesting about that is that allows us to sort of
bundle up this data in a way that we now know like, hey we we can tell
the difference between this and a tea and some other entity in the
debug system without it having to intrude into the game at all.
And so that's kind of interesting as well.
So, I think that's what I want to play with today.
I just want to sort of get that part of things integrated in properly,
so we'll see what kind of damage we can make on that problem today.
So, here's the deal.
Look system and I believe, Mark, debug value is the one that we're
using right now for, like, that's the one that were using, for
switchable value.
Like like, you know, like debug switches basically, like things that
turn on and off debug features in the code and that sort of thing.
So, so this stuff, the debug value stuff doesn't come in through this
path because it's something this is inherently something defined by
the debug system.
Rolled entirely by the debug system for all intensive purposes.
This here where we have begin block, end block, and then open data
block, close to block.
These are the things which have, I guess for lack of better term, they
have single points in the code where they come from, right, but they
have multiple points in the frame that generate data.
So, for example, begin block end block any time a function with ask
with that, one of our little timer scopes
Gets hit in the course of running a frame.
It's going to generate a, begin block and block pair, right?
So, those are two places in the code, the begin block and end block
Point.
Those are only two places in the code, but there could be literally
thousands of pieces of data generated on it.
If that code, gets run inside up a loop or called multiple times by
the controlling code that sort of thing.
Right?
And the same is true for open data block and close data block, right?
There's only one place in the code that the data block comes from
currently, right?
I mean, you know, they'll be
eventually, they'll be more but at the moment we only have one which
is this one right here.
This is the only data block that we have.
So, technically, there's only one place in the code, but if many
simulation entities were selected than many simulation in these data,
would get dumped, and they'd all be done from the same point in the
code right there.
All being dumped from this location in the code.
It's just getting called in a loop, so you get multiple blocks.
So that's sort of differentiates.
This, if you will from the other things that we were doing, which were
the debug values, which inherently only exist in one place.
They are only on or off, for example, for a particular point in code,
it's whether or not that particular point in code is like, active or
something.
Or for, you know, like the debug camera distance.
There's only one of those.
So, these are different in that there's and of them.
And so, what that means is, what we
Do is we want to store the debug blocks that come through which is
what we were doing before.
We want to just store the data that comes through.
And then when we're printing out the hierarchy inside the one, the
single location that's supposed to dump this data, which will be
defined by this.
Presumably, right.
We want to have perhaps a little listing in there which kind of says
like okay here is a single location.
But here's the like 12 times it was called and you can pick which one
you know, you want to see and we
We have this entity, debug ID think here, which we can use to label
them potentially, I don't know if we also and I would suspect we
probably would want to do something.
Probably would will also want to pass like a friendly index.
Here something that's not necessarily supposed to be unique, but that
is supposed to be like more printable.
So for example, you could imagine us doing something like that.
We're passing the storage index of the entity that seems like a pretty
reasonable thing, right?
And I don't know.
So that's something to think about.
I'm going to just leave that as an open question, for now.
That's just in terms of making things pretty.
But it's just a, it would be like a user helpful feature.
That would allow the user to see something more understandable than
just some giant pointer nonsense, garbage value that they like, well,
okay, I can see if two of them are the same if I really tried.
But I, it's not friendly like entity 6240.
Yeah, that doesn't necessarily mean anything, but at least I know,
It's like a more human.
Our sample number then like 0 X8, 091 a you know, whatever some
gigantic string of things, which is what a pointer is liable to be.
And that isn't sequential in any way because it's just, you know, well
I guess it would be kind of sequential because we're allocating them,
probably sequentially, but you get my drift.
They don't monotonically increase by one.
Increase by like a stride.
So, yeah.
So that's what I want to take a look at inside open data, block here,
you can kind of see that we're like doing this allocate open debug
block and then, you know, cure, we kind of deallocate that open debug
block.
So as we open blocks, we like create sort of a place for storing that
information and that's good and all.
But I think probably what we want to do is I think we probably want to
change instead of doing it this way, where we do do, you know open
allocate open, debug lock and deallocate open debug block.
I wonder if we
Just push these guys out to basically be stored in the same kind of
rolling format that we were storing the other guys.
Where we just kind of start chaining them onto onto a an element,
right?
Because right now, if you take a look, we've got debug element, right?
And we have these stored events here, like, so,
Well you know what we could do instead is just kind of you know stack
up those you know, stack up these open debug boxes, they come in as
part of the element.
As part of the events or something like this, you know, I'm just kind
of thinking out loud here because if we have a debug stored event,
right?
I'm just trying to think inside this, debug element as we get these.
If I just wanted to store kind of like these, these debug blocks as
the same sort of thing, you could imagine making this, you know, this
debug element thing kind of tight, right?
So it's got different things that can store.
They can store like an event if that's what's the most, you know,
intelligent thing for to store or a
Store like a data block or can store whatever and then when you go
through and we free events to clear out frames, we could just have you
know that that do its thing.
Now since all of these things come in as events it's possible that
what I could do is just actually stack them all up on here.
So for example, you know, if you think about how this works
I've got this stuff here where I'm doing all these debug values.
I could just stack all of those up on this one data block, right?
I could just stack them all up on there and that could could just
work, you know, the only
Issue.
I would see with that is well you know what, I don't think there is an
issue with that.
I think I can maybe just do that.
I,
I think that may just work.
And so basically you know, when I come in here, if this was something
that came from debug value, I think what I could do is just whatever
the debug element was, that's open right now.
I can just store it on there.
And since this simulation entity thing tells me where the location of
it is in theory, I can it will all just work right?
Like it's like I think it's kind of like I said kind of collapsing
down kind of nicely to everything sort of working for the same system
get group for hierarchical name.
I think at this point, we'll just work because in here in our event
index loop, we're going to see this debug begin data block happen.
It's going to get its element right here.
We're going to end up in this code, right?
And we're going to
Know which element it is.
So the open debug block instead of doing any kind of additional work
here that it might, otherwise do like creating a variable group, or
any of this sort of thing.
I suspect that what we can do is just say forget all that.
Don't even bother with that.
We don't need any of it.
Really?
You can just do what we were doing before.
And then in here, just take the debug element store that debug
element.
Right.
Why did it do?
I don't know what I did, but it did just there.
Right?
And so if the open debug block has, which elements it was, when we
opened it then here, when we do this, this store event, then what we
can do is override, which element is its storing to write?
Because if you take a look at what happens on or maybe not, why can't
I jump story element outdoor event.
Sorry,
If you take a look what happens inside story event, right?
Where
Passing up the element and what we do here is we just do the sort of
freeing that we need to do we then come through and go.
Okay, you know store, whatever the event was that we were told to
store.
So, in theory, I think all we need to do is say, oh, if there is an
open debug block at this time, just instead of storing this to the
element, it would have stored to store it to store it underneath the
underneath the data block,
That's it, right?
And again, sorry to belabor this, but I feel like this is very
complicated code, and I just want to make sure people understand it.
Because sometimes, I don't know, I don't necessarily know how well
you're seeing the code versus have a limestone, the code.
I don't know those two states.
And so if you already totally get it, then I apologize for belaboring
it, but sometimes I feel like it just may be a little confusing for
people.
And so I just want to make sure that they have a reasonable handle on
it when the code was running.
Right?
The reason that we're seeing these guys here is because
Nothing is going through the same code path.
Now.
So all of those debug value calls, right?
Like these calls
Here.
Are just going through the path that we wrote for this expandable
stuff.
Everything is going through the same patch, which is great.
But this is not what I really wanted these guys to do.
Obviously, I wanted them to kind of be contained in something.
In the data block, was meant to say that all of these things go
together, right?
And so, what I want to do is be able to bundle those guys up in a more
convenient way.
So all I'm going to do is say, okay, when you open a data block, then
from then on out, anytime we were going to see something that was a
debug value, which is here.
The data block is open.
Then let's just send it.
Let's just stick it on to that data blocks element.
So it chains on there.
Then when we go to print it out, we'll just pull off all the stuff
that's on that element and use that and display it.
However, we want, right?
Because now we know that they are data block based, right?
And not individual lines that are unrelated to each other.
So that's all I'm going to do.
I think that's it.
And so if I want to do that, I don't think we need any of this stuff
at the
Emmett.
There may be something that we have to do, if, if data blocks spammed
a frame, but hopefully, that doesn't matter anymore.
I don't really know.
I hope that doesn't matter anymore.
We'll have to think about that a little bit later.
Anyway, so when we allocate an open debug block, right?
And do this sort of little dance here, then, all we really need.
Is those open debug blocks that were tracking things?
We just need those to store an element so that we, you know, that it
knows which element we were talking about.
So if we do this, right, we could we could do that.
Now we don't even really need to pass that because it gets the event
right here.
So in theory we could just get
At the event, we could get the element from the event but we might as
well just store it.
We don't keep doing that look up every time because it seems like it's
kind of annoying if that's the case, right?
So I'm just going to pass the element here.
I might even pass it first, so I might say like do it like this.
And then here, I'm just going to say the element is stored as it is,
right?
And I feel like we also have an opening event.
Does that get stored anywhere else?
No, it doesn't.
So that's fine.
So, let's just make this happen.
And I think this is going to be good.
So in here again, we just passed the element.
We already have it everywhere that we might need it, so it's really
easy to do and that's nice.
So let's put that in here.
There we go.
So yeah.
Yeah.
I like that.
And so here what I'm going to do is say all right, if we've got one of
these guys that we're going to override the element, so storage
elements equals element and if there is a first open data block, then
the storage element equals that data blocks element instead and then
we store it.
So now in theory, if I run this what we should see happen is those
guys should go away that did not
Work at all to say, the very least.
So good job, that's great.
Fantastic.
Everyone's done a fantastic job.
Oh
That would probably be why you have to actually pass the value you
calculate.
So there we go.
Now we've got a problem which is obviously that this this guy here,
the simulation dude.
That's an issue because it's you know we sort of switched from using
strings.
We now string ice things so we don't really want to pass strings
anymore to stuff and I don't know if we might have to redo that macro,
but it looks like we don't.
And so we
I want to work that way and now we can kind of see here.
All right?
We've got simulation, but we still have this sort of problem where
Well that's so I was going to talk about the fact that we now have to
go into the thing that walks these and actually print out blocks of
them.
But we have a different problem, which is there should have been one
more like group here which was the expandable for entity and we didn't
get that.
And I guess now that I think about it it does make a little bit of
sense that we didn't or does it.
I think it does make sense that we didn't.
The reason we didn't is because inside open data block, we never
actually called story event.
Well, no, but that's not true.
So,
When we open the data.
We're calling get element from event, which means that it should
create a new element for this guy, which means it should do the
hierarchical name thing.
So, I'm not sure why we weren't seeing simulation and then entity
under simulation.
I guess it might be because we didn't explicitly say that this was a
group, that's probably why.
Yeah, that does make sense.
So we need to explicitly state that this is going to be a group itself
because when a data Block, it's opened, it doesn't
Necessarily it's not going to create a group for that.
It's going to create a group for all of its parents, but it's not
going to create a group for that name itself because it's assuming
that that name will be a value that you're going to insert, but that's
not what's going to happen here.
So really what we need to do?
I guess is we need to say in here when we do this sort of stuff when
we do get group for higher cool name.
So get group for higher cousin the name.
When we do this right, you can see what happens.
We get a name in here and that name is going to be simulation
underscore entity.
It's going to do the first underscore thing and if there is one, it's
going to create a new group, but if there isn't, it's not.
So the first time it's going
Do that.
It's gonna do it for simulation the next time.
Mr.
Gonna have entity.
It's not going to create one.
So we need to actually create a group for entity and we can do that
pretty easily, right?
We can do that with with this sort of a thing here.
We just have to actually make sure that happens when we actually go to
do it.
And so I'm trying to think of what the easiest way to make sure that
happens would be, I suspect, what we could do to save code.
Here is just to like
Something like, you know I want to create all the way down even to the
end.
So even if they're you know I want to create the last name as a group
as well.
Instead of just all of the names leading up to the last name, right?
Create final name group, write something like that.
So, you can if you want to say, hey, the last one I want to do as
well.
So this would be something like even if we didn't find a first
underscore, we could do something like if we want to create the final
name group and you know first underscore is not a thing.
Then we just say like okay pretend first underscore is the actual
whole name and that way it'll create whatever that remaining part is
for us.
I think that's probably what we want to do.
That seems like the easiest way to get what we want and I don't see
any reason to make it, any more elegant than that.
It seems like we can just use kind of the
The obvious thing and it should be fine.
I don't think we'll get into too much trouble with it.
Famous last words, right?
So, anyway, let's take a look at that.
So, in here, at element to group, we don't care about that stuff at
all.
And so,
You know what?
Now that I think about it.
We don't even need to do that.
We just need a way to make our element into a group itself which is
actually trivial
Okay, I take it back.
That was that was premature, that's not even necessary.
That was just kind of being being stupid.
So yeah, so I think actually all we would have to do is when we add
one of these things here, right?
It's going to add a debug variable link and by default, it's going to
set it to be an element.
All we actually have to do is change it to a group.
So I think it's actually a lot easier than what I just said.
I think all we actually have to do is make sure that that element
itself becomes a group
And that should be it.
Yeah.
All right.
So I'm just I'm that was a stupid.
I'm just that was just like not necessarily what I said and we can
sort of ignore it and and move on with our lives.
So, okay, inside this debug block, I'm going to, I'm going to set a
breakpoint there and verify that's actually doing what I thought it's
doing.
And then I'm going to sort of, I'm going to make that become the group
and I'm going to make things add it to to that name.
Let's see here.
Where are we?
No.
All right.
There we go.
So what I want to do is I want to stop right here.
Okay, so if we do allocate open, debug block.
The element that we end up with here.
Should in theory, be let's see grid 618.
I assume that's the right one.
Let's just let's just make sure here.
So here's the element, I guess we don't know where it is in the tree
at the moment.
So that's a little bit unfortunate because it means, I can't really go
see what it decided to do.
But you can see the block name is simulation to be.
So we're at the right one, but I can't see what it decided to do.
Tree wise with that.
Meaning the get hierarchical groups tough.
I don't have any insight into what it actually decided to do with
that.
Since that's not something we can actually get at here.
That's just like a separate part of things I suppose.
What I could do is take a look at the debug State and walk it.
I don't know how smart that is of me to do but you know we could try
anyway.
So if we're going to do that, here's the
route group, there's the Sentinel.
So if I take a look at what's in there,
Let's see, we've got an element.
Here, which is handsome fee 2074.
And what comes after that guy?
Let's see 2067.
Yes.
Oh, and I wouldn't even necessarily know
What the name was, right?
Hmm.
Hmm, well, I guess I can just go in till we get simulation as the guy.
It's kind of interesting the way that this looks, it's not exactly
what I was expecting.
But anyway, so none of these people have any children at.
All right now, is that, is that true?
That doesn't make any sense to me.
Like, how are all these values in that?
All of them should be having descendants?
Shouldn't they?
You can see how many we got here.
Do do right to their right.
That's the
that's the first one.
Hmm.
All right.
Well that's not what I was expecting because I don't understand why
nobody got any children, someone should have gotten children, right?
Because the children are supposed to be filled in.
But these are all values that were not filled in with children.
And we're stead filled in with elements, which is not
What Casey was expecting, not the case of expecting at all.
So let's see where this is handmade 2074.
So that's in
Oh, those are performance markers.
Okay, alright, that's cool.
So yeah, I guess what I can say here is, this didn't do what I would
have expected because I would have expected by this point since the
element name, the event name that's being done here, right?
We can even look at it in here is simulation underscore entity.
I would have expected that simulation underscore entity would have
made this guy get placed.
So that one of these things in the route group would have had
children, write it in this.
Call get element from event with simulation underscore entity in
theory.
I would have expected you know this to trigger and make that happen
but I guess it didn't.
I'm going to set a breakpoint there because this curious that's I
guess I'm not understanding exactly what is doing prep at the moment
so there's ground chunks recompute on change let's see here.
Renderer ground chunks checkerboards rendered camera.
And I feel this hero, familiar Falls hero, you space Out Lines.
Simulation entity.
All right.
So here's simulation entity.
Where is the first underscore?
Right.
That is the first on a square.
That's what I would have expected.
Let's see here.
And we've got first underscore - name and yeah.
All right, so I can go in here and I'm going to, you know, kind of go
one one further down.
So, the theory now I should just have entity, right?
Or not.
Oh no.
Sorry that's not what happened.
This is just creating this is just creating the group for this guy, so
that's fine.
Do you do comparing lots of names of things?
Let's take a look.
These are all the links in the chain.
Yep.
So that's interesting.
I should probably break out of here.
When we find the result there's no need for us to keep spinning
through here.
Once it's found, right?
So that's kind of annoying.
But so here's the one that found simulation use space outlines is the
one that it found which of course is still correct.
Because remember, it's only the first 10.
So that's actually the correct thing.
If just simulation and this one should in theory have a sentinel with
children and it does.
There they are.
So, that's what we wanted.
That actually worked.
Okay, except I should go in to create group get or create group with
name.
Get were create group.
This right here should have a break.
All right, so once we come out of there, right?
Then we in here, we won't find an underscore.
So this should just, you know, after it scans, it'll just return and
not do anything, which is what we'd expect.
And so, now we have the simulation group and then we're going to add
an element to it, right?
So in theory, we should add an element that has that name, right?
It should have the name.
It should have the full name.
Of the dude.
Right.
It is getting hot in here.
I don't mind saying.
So mmm.
Mmm.
So we did put it under simulation.
But I'm not sure which name it's going to use.
I guess it would use its event name.
And that's why we see what we see.
Okay, so actually now I fully understand it that took a little while.
So, what happens here is, this name is only if only if it's an
expandable group, does it have its own name, right?
Because if you remember, how we did this inside, handmade debug dot h.
If you remember how these things actually are created, when we have
groups, the groups have names but a debug variable by itself, that is
not a group.
Does not have a name.
So, a debug element its name
Defined by whatever the events it has in it.
And if there are no events and it doesn't know what the name is, only
the grid.
Oops, only the grid might tell you,
Right.
So what we want to do here, I mean we have a couple different things
we could do.
Actually, we could say that links we could promote the names up to the
links so that they always do have names.
And so the name actually is known without having to look through to
see what the event is.
But the other thing that we could do is make it so that well the debug
element
yeah, it gets
just used as that first event to tell it which one it is, which seems
maybe like a reasonable thing to do.
So, here's what I'm going to propose.
Is that I propose we store the event, right?
So I think we want to store the event here, right?
So, when we create a note open, debug block, we want to store it.
We want to store it to the element, like so, and that way, the first
event like or rather each chunk of events in here.
inside are
Inside our simulation entity, although I'm not sure why I didn't show
entire simulation.
Each set of events.
There is going to be like, one of these open data block ones.
And so, then when we go to to display them, we can actually just put
in, we can use the name of the event, which is the open data, block
event, to sort of list them, so that should be relatively
straightforward and I assume.
So, you know, when we're drawing them in here, right?
I'm assuming that what's going on is we've got this sort of stuff, we
do debug event to text
I meant to text probably, doesn't look at open data.
Blocks is my guess.
Yeah, it doesn't.
So that's why we were never seeing that but, you know, so temporarily.
We could just do this.
And now we would
Right.
Although that's still not what I would have expected.
Oh
Sorry, put it in the wrong place.
My bad.
Yeah, although so still not what I expecting.
So when in fact why did that?
That's weird.
Why did that change anything?
That's a bit strange, right?
If I get rid of that, do I still have that not happen?
Okay.
So the only reason it wasn't showing up before was because I wasn't
moving this because I probably never selected anything.
Somehow.
I got, I just got through it up here, like I probably just went like
this.
First, I couldn't do it that time either.
There it is, right?
But as soon as I do there it pops up.
Okay?
That's a little more reassuring.
Okay, I thought it was going nuts there for a second.
So yeah, but the question is, I should now be seeing this open data
block, but I'm not which I don't necessarily understand why that is,
because I should see that event on there.
I guess I do know why that is as well, that's because we are only ever
seeing the most recent event, so that makes sense as well.
So we just actually have to do the work, so if I wanted to I could do
this, right?
Excuse me, if I wanted to, I could do this.
I suppose.
What is the glow?
God do it for free it.
Obviously.
So, if I wanted to, I could do that.
And then we'd see the end data block, right?
Because it's reading them in opposite order, but that's not actually
write what we want to do.
What we want to do is go in and, and actually display these guys with
some intelligent way.
so, what we want to do is when we crawl them,
We want to start looking inside them, right?
And so in order to do that, what I would want to do is I would want to
go to debug drumming menu.
And when we hit one of these.
So in here, when we're like, okay, you know, if it's got children,
then great otherwise, let's take a look at what's going on here.
Well, we know, presumably the that if it doesn't have children, that
it has an element.
And so what we could do is take a look now and see if the element
itself.
Is a debug beta blocker or not.
Right.
So we're looking at the event the get event from link.
Just looks at the at the final one.
So I think what we probably want to do here is start looking at the
like the, you know,
At the Stream.
Of events that are in there.
I suppose what we could do is if we did add the end events as well.
We could use that to determine that.
Oh if it's the end data block than what we've got here we'll just
parse backwards to the first begin.
I'm not sure which of those, not sure that that's the smartest thing
to do, but but we could now we'll just try it that way.
We'll see what happens, right?
Again all I'm saying here is that like well you know if we go in here
and we're going to print out one of these, what we do is go, okay
let's see what kind of event it is.
First we look in we see like okay it's you know one of these guys are
whatever we just check.
Okay.
Is it one of those data block?
Begin data block ends, rather.
Hurt data block, what's it called?
Your theory?
I named it so I should remember.
Don't remember?
Was just looking at it, too.
It's just called clothes.
I like how we have beginning end and then open and close.
Why do we have other that?
Which one is it again and open?
Close are we, are we going to pick?
I guess.
Not.
So you know what we could do here is go.
All right, you know, we've got one of these guys.
And so what we're going to do is we're going to have, you know, this
sort of thing called from from inside here.
So we could just make this be like, you know, a recursively called the
thing.
So maybe there's just, you know, internal void debug draw, you know,
Element or something like this.
Or I should say event, something like that.
I don't know.
I guess element is really what we would want.
So we want debug draw element.
We would
take this code right here.
Sort of grab it out.
Like so.
And then we would call it.
From here.
And so in this code, when we come down here,
And we have debug draw element.
Presumably, then when we get to, like one of these open data block
closed data block, sorts of things, what we would want to do is we
would want to sort of, parse the, the tree that's there.
And so, I suppose, we also probably want debug draw event here and
that's going to be sort of a, a thing which cannot actually iterate in
any way.
Because as far as I can, think of,
Well let's let's do let's see I could be wrong about that.
Okay, I am wrong about that.
Long as it's a debug stored event.
We can just chain through the next pointer so that that presumably
works.
But again, if we're starting at the most recent one that wouldn't
necessarily work, so yeah.
I don't know.
This is a little touchy, it's a little touchy.
I think you end up with something like this.
Anytime you have such complex stuff so it's I'm not too unhappy about
it but it is it's a little it's just a bit touchy.
Because of the way that these things are stored, right?
Because I want to sort of be able to print out an element because it's
the thing that has sort of the first and last.
But then once I'm iterating inside an element, I want to be able to
print out an event.
An event can't have those extra things.
It doesn't know any of this information, so it's a little bit wonky,
if that makes sense, but that's okay.
You know, I'm okay with that.
But what I am going to do is I'm going to change this debug draw
element thing.
I want this to work off of a stored event for the moment I think at
least that's my assertion.
and it kind of feels like also,
looking at this, it also feels a little bit to me, like,
you would kind of want these chained in the opposite direction, but I
guess there's not much you can do about that since you're freeing from
one end, you're freeing from the oldest end anyway, this kind of
probably not much you're ever going to be able to do about that.
So, that's probably just an unfortunate fact of life.
You would pretty much have to doubly linked these if you wanted to be
able to walk them from either direction, right?
So I don't know, so we'll see how it goes but if it turns out that
that's, you know, something we need to be able to do then.
So be it.
All right, so let's go ahead and take a look at this here.
So, if we're looking at debug draw element,
Debug draw event can draw any of these sorts of things.
So in fact, all of this stuff, so all of this stuff is really be about
drug event and really, all that's going to happen here and this this
is I guess doesn't really need well, we'll see, let's do that.
Like so will do.
Hey bud, draw event.
Here.
Okay, so really what I would need to do here is figure out all the
stuff that this needs.
I'll make sure that gets passed through.
and then, inside your element, what I want to do is I want to check
first to see what kind of an element I'm looking
In case it's going to be one.
That's kind of got sort of this extra data associated with it.
And I suspect that that is where this will come into, right?
I suspect that we'll want to promote this.
The profile thing we'll want to sort of promote that out as well into
a selection based on the element because most of these other people
are just printing out a single event thing.
Whereas the elements looking at things across time.
So we just kind of need to turn the crank on this, a little bit, to
get it into a state, where it's a little more.
A solid what it's actually looking for.
So I'm going to actually look at the oldest event instead here.
I'm going to go ahead and say like okay.
Whatever the oldest event is still just a oldest event, I'm going to
take a look at that and so what I need is, I need here the element, if
there is an oldest event, then we're going to do some stuff with it,
right?
Based on what type it is and the sort of things that I'm going to
handle here.
Are people who need you no more specific information and I'm guessing
that like pretty much like I said, this guy will probably get moved
out here.
In fact, I think I may just go ahead and do that right now.
That's going to be handled out here because that's going to be like a
specialized print out.
Again, if it turns out to be a close datablock than this is, like, a
piece of data that we're putting out.
And then finally, if we've got anything else, I guess that just gets
passed through where we'll do the most recent one instead, right?
So we'll do this, if we don't, if it's something that we don't want to
handle in any kind of special way, so that seems reasonable.
There we go.
And let's see what I need to grab.
Compilation lines here.
So, we need the debug State.
Obviously, we probably need the layout as well, right?
I would assume let's take a look here.
I'm assuming, I need to pass that with me, so let's get that in there.
That may be it though.
All right.
Open.
We need the tree that we're currently iterating as well.
Why isn't that in the layout?
I feel like that should probably be in the layout.
In fact it looks like the debug States also in the layout.
So really, I feel like the layout is the thing that needs to happen
here and that should just come out of the way out.
Debug tree.
Makes sense something like that.
And so, the layout don't know where that's at.
So in here, I also want a debug tree tree like so and then when we're
actually doing that I'm going to set that equal to whatever the tree
is that we're on.
And that way that doesn't actually need to get passed down either.
So it's just be that
And everybody would be fine with it.
There wouldn't be any kind of weirdness, so that's fine.
That means this takes a debug layout as well or just a layout.
And it's going to pass that through, right?
And yeah.
All of these guys.
Unfortunately also are going to need to do like
Anyone who's a DOT here, it's going to have to be an arrow.
But that's about it.
Okay?
So the link that we're doing here, I guess.
I don't know when we do a debug draw event, that's probably something
that should also be in the layout.
So as you go down it you set the link to be whichever one you're in.
I would think because the layout presumably needs to know as you kind
of iterate through.
That's just my guess, the only thing I'm not sure about.
Is whether you know, that that's the only thing that's a little ugly
about that is when we do it we probably to be honest.
Like these guys probably want the debug ID to be passed in so they're
not necessarily looking at that that information.
Like we probably want this to happen is what I would expect and if I
look at VAR link interaction, you can kind of see that like all it's
doing, right?
Is creating the debug ID from those two and then getting the event.
But we already know what the event actually is.
So I feel like, actually this is kind of this is kind of just like
Jank and we should probably just get rid of it.
So, I think, probably what we want to do is this instead.
So when we do debug draw element here, right?
We probably want to do something like at this point in the code,
generate the debug ID.
Something like that.
In fact, I guess we could,
Like this.
And then sort of further down that further down that road.
We may want to actually like make that more specific.
So when we come into here and we're doing debug draw element, right?
We have the debug ID and here's the debug ID that's going to use Loops
like so
Hm.
And you can kind of see, we would need an item interaction here again.
So we need like this, this sort of stuff.
I don't really know what interaction we even had for these all I guess
it was like a sizeable.
It was a sizing element.
I guess was the thing that we had.
But yeah, so when we create this item interaction here, this is going
to use that debug ID, right?
So it's really just going to be
You know, the standard kind of interaction but with that debug ID and
this is the element.
And in fact I don't even know what that was doing before because there
wouldn't actually yeah, look take a look at that.
You can see what I'm saying about how this was kind of janky before
because the D, by D wants to sort of be unique for any place for any
tree and for any place in the hierarchy.
So I think we kind of want to clean that up a little bit.
So anyway, when we call debug draw event and we pass in the debug ID,
that means it would give us the opportunity to pass in different ones
as we iterate over this.
Right, so I think that's how we want to do it, so we can hear when
we're passing this in.
Again, this would just be this would just use the same ID as as we're
expecting nothing changes, right?
But in this one, we'll use a different debug ID.
And then the rest of these guys like borrowing contraction here, the
rest of these guys will actually do something more sensible.
So when we create an item interaction, I guess.
This is the one that we would use, right?
You're trying to think, if there's any, I guess, really what we want
to do is probably instead of calling this a varlet interaction, we
probably just want to call it on something, a little more sensible
like an event interaction.
Right?
And that way when we do it here, we just expect to be past the debug
ID because that's just something that should be being passed in.
So it's like, okay.
That's what we actually wanted.
We store the debug ID like that and it takes the event, right?
Like that.
Now why are we don't pass a stored event here?
I don't know, I feel like that's what we should actually be doing
there but we can always change that pretty trivially so we can leave
that like that for now.
But it does seem a bit strange
Okay, so now this is a little bit simpler because now we can just do
like okay Auto modify variable or whatever.
We're going to pass their right and and that's all good.
So we'll pass the item attraction, that's all fine.
And then this can go away.
And then again, this right here, anytime we had a violent interaction,
like before, now we can just say like okay, these are actually going
to be event interactions and you know, they'll
Will actually take the debug ID and the event like so right.
That way, we don't have any more of this sort of weird, like creating
it all the time.
And that also means the tree doesn't actually have to be passed down
anymore, right?
So we can actually avoid having that get out into
into this part of the
Code as well.
So I think that's better.
I'm going to leave that like that, right.
And I guess this is technically looks like that because like I said,
it's not doing a sort of anymore, don't really know why because they
think it should be doing historic event but that's fine.
No.
So, as we could do it this way to stored event, and then we can just
do this Torrid event, debug event, been distorted, and then that way
this code doesn't have to change, which is nice as well.
Okay, render group.
I still believe render group is probably just available off of the
debug state.
So I don't know that we have to pass that in that seems unnecessary.
So we'll just do it like that.
Let's see here.
Begin element rectangle.
So layout now no longer needs to be a sanded, right?
Because we were passing in the pointer so that's fine.
So, let's take a look here.
And so in this case, when we're doing counter thread list, we still,
we need, we would still need to grab the view.
In fact, we could do that for any of these.
Obviously we could always do the create a getter create view so we
could still get the view we get even past that view in if we wanted
to.
I'm not sure that we do but then you wouldn't have to look it up
twice.
Which again would be kind of nice, I suppose.
So here's the debug state.
I am and that up, there's the item interaction which is now just this.
And I guess I don't know what it would necessarily be again I'm not
sure, I don't actually know that what is the default?
I don't know that there is a deep under action for profiles at the
moment so I might just leave that out temporarily until we go finish
implementing or try to restore that I guess you might say because I
really don't know.
We want to implement some picking for the profile stuff but I don't
really know if that was ever really doing anything special for us.
So,
In this case, get event from link is not at all.
We want here in this case, we're just going to presume.
We do most recent event for now, and I do wonder if get event from
link now is sort of not necessarily get revenge from link, right?
So let's just get rid of that.
And that.
And this.
So it takes the debug ID and the element that it should draw, I guess
is what it would need to do.
So we just pass that.
But we don't know the element apparently.
Ah, right.
There we go, too many things called element.
All right, so now, I believe we're in a position to just print this
guy out because we've sort of reset this code.
Although I only got like, a couple minutes left here, because we're
right at the end.
So what I need to do now is I need to be able to just draw.
440 Boudreau event.
I need to be able to Loop over the stuff that's inside one of these
blocks, right?
So what I want to do here is say, okay, let me Loop through everything
that's inside this, this particular data block and draw each of them,
right?
And the debug ID is going to change each time for every, for every one
of these.
Right?
So if you look, and we've got our debug ID getting returned for Stuff.
At least I assume we do.
Should have ways of there we go.
So for debug ID from link we would now have another way of creating
one which would be like you know it passes the tree in which means we
would need the tree here presumably but it would be something like
okay you know it's it's a particular story event instead of a
particular link.
I guess, I'm not sure.
But probably.
So, we'll be something like this, I think.
And that would differentiate from things in the tree.
We'll see how it goes.
So, yeah.
So this guy does need a debug tree at the moment, just because we do.
Oh, well yeah, I mean now we could get it from the debug idea, but I
don't know that we want to be quite that slide.
So here's the like new dbid, right?
And that's just going to be whatever the tree is plus, whatever the
stored event that we're on, is
Like so.
And here, what we want to do is we want to kind of just Loop through
these, right?
So you want to say, whatever the element boldest event is, we want to
Loop through all of them and we're not really going to want to see all
of them, but I'm going to start with that and we're going to want to
do some UI.
Presumably to make, you be able to pick which ones you're trying to
look at.
Because they'll be in chunks, basically.
And so when we get to a close, if we look at the oldest event and we
see actually if it's the oldest event it'll be an open data block,
right?
So we want to do here is say okay.
as we go through the events, we could even I guess do it this way
where we say
As we're displaying It Go from the oldest event for words and pick
like whatever the last open block was, right?
So the last open block and that's going to equal.
We're going to, you know, obviously we'll start with us.
And then as we go from oldest event for words.
if the the type equals,
Open data block.
Then the last open block equals that one.
We're just finding the last lecture chunk.
And so then what we'll do is we'll say okay, we'll start from last
open, block
And we'll go to the end.
And so here will actually print these guys out which is to say that
will create something from the stored event.
And I guess I'm just calling this event at the moment.
And then we just draw it.
I think that's really it.
Don't know that there's much else to say.
So now you can kind of see, all right?
This is now doing what we expect here.
Our simulation entity, when we hit it, this is the open data block.
We're drawing all the things in there and then we're kind of ending
now.
That's showing us the last one, obviously, right?
Whichever one that is.
And it's a little wonky.
There's some things in it, that are probably a little odd.
So like I'll just point them out.
So if I select this guy here and then I
Change the size of this guy, which I don't know if I can or not.
Maybe I can't say if I.
Yeah.
So I think like one of the things that's a little wonky right?
Is this.
This thing doesn't quite work in terms of knowing, which because the
store identity isn't a stable ID, right?
The stored energy to something that's getting cycled through every
frame.
Which one this is is going to change for the debug IDs.
So I feel like that's
still not quite right.
Right, we need some other way of differentiating.
Those two guys, I guess what I could do is use, for example, the grid,
Of them potentially.
So even though it's different times through the loop, that's probably
what we want from.
The other ideas, we want it to be from, whichever location.
It came from, that's probably true.
So it might be the open data block.
It'd be like the open data blocks and plus the location.
It's kind of tricky.
So,
The open data block itself has an ID, right?
And then identifies the whole thing.
But then we would also want to know like which one inside it.
It's like we need almost an additional level of debug ID although at
the same time now I think about it maybe that's not entirely true
because actually we only use the first part of the debug ID.
So
I guess you can actually do this.
It's not too much of a problem.
What you actually do is say okay
When I want to create the debug ID for something in this circumstance.
Oops.
This is the wrong place.
When I want to create the debug ID for something in the circumstance,
what I need to do is I need to be able to take one of these.
Right, which is getting created here.
Write debug pointer ID.
I need to just be able to take one of these and merge it with the
Which one of these values is actually being printed?
Right?
And so that means the events grid would be one of them presumably.
So like the event the particular event we're on, that's got a grid and
that'd be one of them.
But then the other thing that we would need to do is combine that in
some way with which data block we were in.
So we could do that.
Maybe we should.
That makes the debug idea is a little more complicated though.
But you know,
Again, something to think about.
It wouldn't be from stored event, write, debug ID.
This one would be from from grid.
For now.
Like so, but again something worth thinking about a little bit from
squid.
Like so.
and I think,
That'd be fine now, right?
And so now that's stable, even when we're looking at different
entities,
And maybe that's what we want.
Maybe that's better than having it be unique printed.
Because you probably want to be able to do that.
So I guess that's actually, you know, that that may be actually what
we want to have happened.
I could see that being being reasonable and so yeah, so that's kind of
nice.
Yeah, we're out of time.
So I saw this should just go to the Q&A, but now we've got these sort
of things, sort, of the beginning of the of the mush.
And that seems pretty reasonable to me.
That's looking like reasonable, mush wise, I would say,
So yeah, we're getting there.
I'm gonna go ahead and go to the Q&A.
All right, let's see.
We got about 20 minutes for Q&A so you guys have cues.
Playing flavored.
What is the debug collator of the debug co-leaders thing?
That takes the Deep, the all the debug buffer, like the debug buffer,
basically just is the game, just write stuff out to it, you know,
multiple threads at a time.
They can all just dump stuff into the D buffer, but it doesn't mean
anything yet.
It's just raw data like, hey, at this particular point in time, I
started doing this function, at this particular point in time, I
stopped at this particular point in time, this value was this
And the color dust gathers, it all together and puts it into a format
that allows us to actually do stuff.
So the whole thing is like I said, it's a fairly complicated
architectural thing.
It's just an exercise in fast ways to dump data out to a buffer.
Then can be later turned into a reusable UI that we can use to inspect
stuff.
And I think, like I said, we're almost at the point where we have
everything mush together and once that's the case, we can really just
play with the UI for a little bit.
And get something pretty easy to use here which is really.
The end goal is just some nice thing we can use to always inspect our
data.
Like we'll be able to pick entities and look at their bitmaps and
stuff like that.
And it'll be pretty clean because we're already almost to that point,
but we need a little bit.
Further.
Let's see.
Someone is talking about.
Someone is Forum link.
Let's take a look.
This is issues for compiling on Linux in order to compile a me hero on
Linux and OS X.
There are some issues that need to be fixed.
I'm looking for volunteers to bring these issues to cases attention
during the Stream.
Okay.
How do you seen clang?
Seem unhappy with casting?
A pointer directly to a
16 or 32-bit number cast from pointer to smaller type u-32 AKA
unsigned in losses information.
This needs to be addressed in three places.
Parse member instead of Professor get her creep.
Debug view for collate, debug records in handmade.
Debug dot CPP.
Okay, so that's kind of lame.
Is that something you can turn off in Jesus?
Because I don't actually that's not actually an error, right?
That's like totally Legal C code.
Right.
You're allowed to cast from a bigger value to a smaller value that's
just like straight up.
Okay?
So I'm not sure about that, but let's see.
There's some leftover copy pasta in handmade platform.sh.
Okay, so let's take a look at that, handmade platform, no th
It's in an end if I guess there's something after the end.
If oh, yeah.
That is to go away, okay?
There is an empty method in handmade debug control reaches end of
non-void function, Place rectangle.
Okay.
And Sprint.
If s is not supported and needs to be replaced, this will be solved.
Once the dependency of SDI is removed, which Casey, hopefully will do
soon.
Well, we're probably not gonna be able to do that right now because I
have to teach people how to print out numbers and stuff.
But yeah, so guess what I would say is I don't really like the idea of
changing the code for compiler complaining, about something that's not
actually illegal like casting a pointer to a u-32 should be totally
legal.
So that's kind of stupid.
but,
I guess like if we have to do that, we can do that.
I don't like it.
But okay, so I guess in here, they were saying, where is it?
Purse member needs to do something but I don't know.
Wait where this is?
You 32 at.
Okay, so we can here.
Basically what has to happen is we have to I assume do something here,
which is like
You know.
Here is the address of the thing.
What we want to do is like, winter to you 32.
Right, I guess.
And then that's going to create an error.
And it handmade platform.sh where we have like little macros or
something when we Define the stuff we would do something like, okay.
Pound Define pointer.
Do you 32 pointer would just be like
Memory index and then you 32.
So we just cast it first to a number then to a u-32
Right.
And so then they said the other problem was in the color index.
So cool, ladybug records, color index.
So in here, looks like region color index, that's code, is probably
gone.
Yes, I don't think that codes there anymore that one that they were
asking about and then hash index.
In here with these, I guess we'll just do pointer to you 32 pointer to
you 32.
Okay.
and so that is that
so,
So, there we go.
Colonel dragon, how do game devs?
You work with typically handle temporary, non shipping sound effects.
How did they handle them?
Can you be more specific?
Do you mean do you mean the I'm sorry I'm not sure what you mean.
Obviously, there's no difference between an on shipping sound effect
and a regular sound effect in terms of the engine code, typically
unless you're talking about something more subtle.
So
Are you talking about like licensing or something?
Playing flavored.
Will there be a passive strip unused code from handmade hero?
Probably not I mean someone might do that eventually but I don't know
that I would do it because typically you don't do that when you're
making a game you don't stop and try to figure out what all the code
you didn't use our and then remove it because if I don't get called,
doesn't get called.
You don't really have to care, right?
But we might do that for posterity at some point, you know, after the
game is ships.
K.
What do you think about working constraints and having limited
resources?
I think it makes for a great less lousy code and forces them to
actually care about what they're doing.
I agree with that.
unfortunately programming languages, sometimes make it hard to really
do that, but
Next, you can we get rid of the build error, something about
introspection of structs, that doesn't seem to affect anything we can,
but we have to change the simple preprocessor.
So the simple preprocessor, what that Eric, I think assuming you're
talking about this.
What happens, there is the preprocessor is looking and it's finding
this.
Right?
And it's like, hey in fact it's this to do right here, it can't it's
not smart enough to look at its own pound to find and know that it's
like, you know, shouldn't be doing that.
So in this simple food processor when it sees introspect,
Here, instead of calling Parsons respectable.
What we need to do is go like was I inside a pound Define, right?
And if I was inside a pound to find, don't process this thing.
Does that make sense?
And so you can certainly cheese it, right?
You could cheese it out if you wanted to the cheese version without
adding any complexity would probably be like
So when it does the open / am and then it does parse introspection
params like when it does Parshin inspection programs in here.
If it sees just the word params, right that you know, are you know,
you could do this
If it just sees ignored and caps, then don't do it, right?
Something like that.
And so if it's like something like this, maybe you could imagine
And again, this is kind of super janky, but this whole thing was
janky.
I just want to kind of show the basics of it.
So it's not, you know, I wouldn't necessarily say this is the way you
would want to do it, but it's certainly one way you could do it.
so in this case, we'd say, okay,
if token, what Kokanee
Something like that.
So that, that sells it for you, because then it just knows.
Oh, I'm just I'm just parsing the pound to find that.
That's all that was.
The seismic you missed region.
Color index, equals opening event blocking.
Did I because I didn't think it was there anymore.
Right.
Because this this is not this code is not compiled in.
This is just this is non code.
I mean I can change it.
Just prophylactically if you want in case we re enable it but we're we
don't even have those regions anymore.
So I'm pretty sure that code is going to get deleted.
Insofar as how many lines are we at?
I don't know.
Fifteen thousand.
looks like,
15,000.
Hmm.
Wonder what that means.
So 220.
so,
so we do Jimmy.
On stream, we average about 70 lines, an hour.
For whatever.
That's worth.
Probably nothing.
Come on dragons.
Sure, what's a quickly to produce temporary sound effects to, for
example, figure out where when they should be played,
You know, I'll be honest with you.
That's
That's a question.
I guess I really don't know the answer to I have the benefit of,
knowing how to make sound effects.
So the way I handle it is I just make a temporary sound effect.
If I want one.
and,
You know, I'm trying to think of other people, like, when I've seen
John Blow do it.
He typically does the same thing.
Like, he'll he'll just like, go get sound effects off the web or
something?
That are close enough to what he wants.
I'm just play them.
so, if you literally have no idea how to like, do a
Fact or edit a sound to be more.
What you need.
That's probably going to be tough.
So, I don't know.
I don't know.
The size of not stripping unused code, is how GTA hot coffee happened,
that's true.
But if you think about it, that's kind of one of those things that's
like just the like stupid.
That whole thing is absolutely ridiculous.
Right?
This is a game where if you want to like, you can have sex with a
prostitute and then kill her afterwards to take the money back.
That was fine.
That was not that did not warrant rating.
The game any worse than em in the eyes of the ESRB wonderful,
beautiful ratings agency.
As far as I'm concerned is like, absolutely ridiculous.
But having consensual sex with your girlfriend.
Because it showed nudity was was worth rating more than him.
That's the ESRB for you, right?
That's the like ridiculous world.
We live in, we're showing people actually just engaging in a sexual
activity.
That normal humans, do that is not against the law in any way.
Is actually totally fine.
To do in the real world that will prevent your game from from being
able to be sold in stores, but you can do anything that you want to,
that's against the law as long as it's just violent, right?
And that's fine.
And this is the, this is what the world has decided, it's like, okay,
right?
And it's really messed up.
It's like, it's really messed up in the head.
It's why I absolutely hate this trend of having, like, ratings bodies,
like the mpa in the SRB, because they rate stuff in a way that in no
way, reflects the actual moral values, you might want someone to have
It's absurd.
Let's see.
K.
If a programming job wasn't available to you, what type of work would
you be interested in doing other than programming for a living?
I don't know.
Legal of some kind judge, can I be adjudged?
I get to be a judge.
I would like to be a judge.
Act binary.
What do you think of DLC?
I'm okay with deal.
See if it's actually.
I'm okay with expansion packs.
Let's put it that way.
I don't like the idea of like dicing up a game into tiny little parts
and making you just buy the ones you want.
I don't think that's very artistic.
I don't think that's a very good for a creative industry.
Personally,
That sounds like more how you like by a car or something.
It's very utilitarian and I don't I don't feel like it leads to good
art.
I don't feel like it leads to like,
it's not going to give you.
It might give you Transformers.
By Michael Bay.
It's probably not going to give you, you know Pulp Fiction right for
Shakespeare in Love.
It's not going to give you something great but it could give you
something that satisfies a certain checklist of stuff like I wanted
explosion.
So I bought them here.
They are.
Right.
So I'm not really okay with the like oh I bought the like fatality for
like this particular character cause I wanted to be able to do it.
I don't think that leads to good coherent like
Works.
But I do think that DLC, in terms of a way for a player to purchase an
expansion of a game is a reasonable funding model.
Like if a team especially for Indies, I think it's worth it because
it's like, like Binding of Isaac or something like that.
If you have a game like that, where it's like, okay, you know, we
don't know how well this is going to sell, we don't know what's going
to happen here, right?
Especially when they first made it, it's like maybe we can only afford
to do like four months of work on this game.
But then it turns out that like everyone really loves this game and
everyone wants more of it, and it's a game that can be expanded, like
it's made for that sort of thing.
Then it makes sense to say, okay, well if you spend five bucks, you
can get this pack that like ads like tons of new items and rooms and
stuff that seems like a very fair thing to me because it helps fund
the development of the game in a useful way.
And it doesn't, it's not in such a granular way as to like destroy the
actual like ability of the work to cohere.
You know what I mean?
So so I'm not against DLC in general, but I'm not.
I'm not in favor of like all kinds of jealousy because some DLC is
just ridiculous.
And I don't think leads to a very healthy development model, if you,
if you take it that way.
And as for MMO seems, that's my name is, I have never played an MMO,
so I have no opinion.
All right.
I'm going to wind down.
Okay, let's see here.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home the source code,
you can always pre-order the game on handmade hero dot or kit comes
with a source code.
You can download every night and play around with whatever the
currency of the chorus base is as I have it.
We also have a forum site, you can go to if you'd like to ask
questions about the series or view our antidepressant guide stuff like
that, we have a patreon page, you can go if you want to pledge support
to the series, so he's very appreciated.
We also have a tweet about the Tweet schedule to you, which
You will want to pay attention to this week because I actually don't
know what's going on with witness development right now.
I may have to go down there.
I may have to fly down there or something depending on the
circumstances for doing some finally work.
Optimizations on the PS4 and stuff like this.
So at any time I may have to just like suspend handmade hero for a few
days if I have to go down to San Francisco.
So I don't know what the status is of that.
I will post something to tweet about as soon as I know.
So the schedule that's being post on the teapot right now is what the
schedule will be, if that doesn't happen, but if that does happen,
then I will tweet about it and there will be a break in handmade hero
for the number.
It's that has to happen so just be advised that that's a possibility
that's just the reality of shipping a game and the Witnesses in its
final weeks of development, as you know, they announced the ship data.
Well back, there's not much time left so you know anything that's
going to get in there.
For the first initial release of the game is going to have to be in
the relatively soon, and if Jon needs help on something, then I'm
going to have to go help.
So that's that be advised, otherwise, if that doesn't happen, I'll
Be back here again, 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard time tomorrow.
Hope to see you all here until then please have fun coding on your own
and I'll see you guys in the unit.
Take it easy, everyone.