Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream and you know we have a
bit of a treat today.
I don't mind telling you yesterday Alan updated for coder with a ton
of really good stuff and so we're like we're in it's pretty awesome.
I actually switched to it at work and I programmed all day today with
it and it's like totally great.
I'm pretty excited about this new build, it's like way way better than
the previous bill that has all sorts of things in it that, that I
needed.
So
I copied it during the pre stream.
I copied the new for a coder into our directory.
So today's programming will be taking place courtesy of and I don't
ever remember the version number so I'm just going to look what we
taking place courtesy of for coder version.
Vert I don't know.
How do you tell the version?
I love patreon dearly.
I think they're a great service, but I never know how to use the site.
I never know.
I have no idea.
It's always that like they change the layout and I'm and I get totally
lost.
Maybe if I just go to the regular for a coder side it'll tell me the
version.
I don't even know maybe if I just launched for a coder.
That'll tell me the version.
I have no idea.
It's a good question.
Let's try that.
Hyah, so there you go.
That's the easy way.
So this programming today is brought to you by for coder Alpha, 4.0
poor, 4.0.2 super.
And I'm assuming that the for is because it's for a coder, which is
hilarious, by the way.
That's so, so funny since it's an alpha, you know, there has not been
a major release yet so that's pretty great.
Anyway, that is is, is pretty great news because
Like I said, there's a lot of changes in there that I was looking
forward to.
So anyway, that's what.
What's going on today.
Today is day two, fifty six.
So we now need exactly 9 bits to store the day number of handmade here
which is certainly women to some good.
If you are trying to follow them home, you want to use the day 255
source code.
I am today just going to get our profile view working because we did
the structural work yesterday.
And now I think, probably mostly, we just have to do
Debugging and then some beautification and it should be somewhat
usable already.
We made a lot of progress yesterday on it.
So I'm going to go ahead and get started on that and I'll show you
where we ended up.
Let me go ahead and
Handmade hero here.
Codebase.
Oops, not poor.
And made that prj and let's build.
Okay, so here we are in handmade hero.
The current state of affairs, you can see in here, the profile view,
we can drag out the block, but this is just complete nonsense here.
And so something about the way that we are recording.
Our values is obviously busted.
And what's interesting about it, it's kind of a neat.
Eat bug, you can see that.
It's sort of periodic in nature.
So the way that we're recording the, the way that we're collating, the
this information per frame is somehow busted in a way that our use of
the absolute clocks must be broken.
Such that we're like, you know, when we do, there are 64 bits of
tracks and move them down to 32 is or whatever we're doing something
stupid.
So, we end up with a value that actually, you know, it matters where
you are, an absolute time.
What?
The bar graph looks like so I imagine this will be a kind of fun bug
when we actually go see what it is.
I'm going to go ahead and see if I can figure it out right now.
In fact, so, the first thing I'd like to do actually, before we go any
further, I just want to review the code that we wrote, because we
haven't had a chance to really look at it.
We sort of just wrote it all yesterday and then ran it once.
That's all we did.
And so I'd like to go ahead and
And sort of analyze that a little bit.
And let's.
So let's go ahead and search down to where we were recording this
information.
So we had this this concept of this profile node that we were building
and this is the code actually here, up that draws it.
I'm not going to look at that code, quite yet.
I want to look first at, just the code that records it and see what I
think about the recording process as we go.
So, the time when something gets recorded as a profile block is
When it encounters the, like, the opening statement.
So, for example in, you know, inside handmade hero, right?
If we were in timed block, for example, you can see right here, this
time function, call that opens a Time block.
So that right when we get to this line, basically, is when we're going
to record one of these begin blocks.
So later when we're collating, that's what we're seeing there.
And then when this goes out of scope, it's a little utility that's got
a Constructor Destructor.
So that when it goes out of scope down,
Down here, we will get the en Bloc and that's the paired version that
comes out right here.
So when we see this begin block, what we do when we come through here
is, we will look to see whether or not we have a out like a basically
a parent scope.
So was there something that was already open as a profile block on
this thread, right?
And it's very important that we do it per thread because we may have
many threads
executing at once and if we do any kind of profiling in those
different things,
Heads, we can't just look at a single like Global variable or a single
piece of state that says, what's the open block because each thread
has its own open profile block, potentially possibly many of them as
it goes down.
So we kind of have to, you know, respect that.
So that's why during collation, we look to see what thread are we
talking about right now and does that have a block that's already
open?
So if it does have a block that's already open, we pick as the parent
event, whatever the profiling node was that, we made for that block
and we take
Okay, as its clock basis.
Meaning the the beginning thing that everything else will be relative
to we take as that clock basis, whatever its opening events clock was
because it just it's a, it's a requirement obviously that any clock
that happens out, you know, when I open a block the our dtsc counter
that we're using for profiling has to continuously go up.
So once we pass a particular block, any block that opens after that
block had better.
Have a late
Clock value.
If it doesn't, something's gone horribly wrong.
And in fact, we could assert that maybe we should in here just to make
sure that we like not doing something weird and we haven't messed up
our recording.
Because if we ever saw clock value, that went backwards.
That would be really bad and weird, right?
And our dtsc is going up.
Probably buy something like 4 billion a second, which means it would
take four billion seconds to wrap.
So, that means we'd have to leave the machine running for a really
long time to ever see a rep.
So we're probably not going to ever deal with that in any meaningful
way that we care about.
And so we just should not see clocks, go backwards.
You know?
No no standard run.
Should ever see a clock, go backwards.
So assuming that we
We did that correctly.
That would be a clock basis here on the other hand, if it turns out
that there is no parent event.
That means that there wasn't a root profiling node and that's just at
the profiling node for the whole frame, the one that everything kind
of goes inside of, right?
And what that what that means for us is that we need to create the
route profiling event for our for this Frame so that we can store
things at that top level, right?
So what we do there is we store a synthetic event that we just don't
have any information in it and then we initialize
That profile node to basically be nothing other than a like a duration
which is however, long, the frame act.
Okay, well there's the bug right there.
You guys see the bug?
You see it.
Does anybody see the bug besides me?
I don't know.
There's too much lag in so I can't even really look at the track.
Because, you know, there's tons of lock on there.
So I already see the bug or
One of the bugs.
Anyway, the bug is pretty simple.
The bug is that we are using the end clock value before it's ever been
written, right?
Because the collation frame is the frame that we're currently using.
And so, obviously, there would be no way for us to ever actually do
anything.
Right there be no way for us to ever actually compute a duration
because no one's ever written the end clock value in here.
So that's just a bug that we're going to have to fix and it seems to
me like probably what we need to do is just set this duration at some
other time.
So assume that this duration is 0 for now.
And there might be another bug in here to which we'll talk about in a
second here.
But essentially, what we need to do is when the, the collage
And frame is finalized and it's actually added as a frame.
That's probably the time when we need to do it.
So here we are at a frame marker boundary and we're recording the end
clock.
That is a time when we could do this, that is the time.
But we can say, if this collation frame,
if this collation frame has a root node or root profile node,
Then at that point we can actually do this particular operation.
Right.
Go ahead and put that in here.
So yeah route profile node that's going to be whatever the duration
was here.
That's going to equal this sort of change.
And yeah that's all there is to that.
Let's see, left of profile node must have class struct Union, debug
stored events star user instead.
Agree with that.
There we go.
So that is the the appropriate fix for that because we were trying to
compute the duration before we ever could.
Now there's one other thing, which is that the clock basis we never
set.
And so that's a bug as well.
The clock basis here, we have to set so, you know, it's set to the
open Event in this case.
But in the case, where we don't have an open event, we would want to
set it to the, the initial clock for the frame, which we do know,
right?
So those, it just those
You were wrong.
Like we just didn't do it right.
There's nothing else to say about that.
It was not a subtle bug, it was just an obvious bug which is fine.
And hey, now that we've done that we're getting what probably what
looks to be like a much more plausible profile result here.
And in fact, if we go ahead and re-enable, our ability to sort of Step
through here, we can actually also pause.
I suppose.
Although, you know what, I don't know if our
I don't know if we have the ability to pause our profile data so we're
probably going to need to do that at some point.
So we can sort of pause stop collecting profile data that makes sense.
So in here, we added it, we have the ability that I just don't think
we have any control over at the moment.
What we want to do here is be able to hover over this thing and and be
able to see what these blocks actually are.
And we sort of have that functionality already but I if zeroed it out
because we don't actually know at the moment.
Anyway, how to print out stuff like that.
So I'm just going to go grab that code that we had before and, and try
to turn it back on like this is it right?
This is it right here.
So I'm going to turn this back on and you can see that our current
problem is is just that we don't have this information.
The way that it was before.
Now what I can do however is since we know some information about this
region, we know the cycle count
Out.
And all the rest of the information like the grid information, all
that stuff, we actually know all that.
So I think probably all we'd have to do to have a semi usable print
and we probably don't we probably wanna do something a little fancier
in the future but just as beginning we can just say here's the you
know cures the quid that it came from and then we've got obviously the
profile node has the duration and that's all we would need to print
out for the Cycles.
So you know that's
That's really all that is right.
So now I think if we go in here and open this back up again I should
be able to ask what one of these things is.
So that's the frame display time.
And, you know, back here in the in the corner of this little tiny one
is executable refresh time.
Whatever that guy's.
That's debug collation in there, I guess.
Yeah, so the other thing that I going to have to do is I'm going to
have to make it so that we can see, like we don't have a way of
consistently coloring, these things such that we would know that they
wouldn't all amount to the same colors.
And in fact, the thing that I'm doing right now is really stupid
because I'm using a pointer and then I'm nodding by the array count.
But you know, that pointers are never going to have any information in
their bottom bit.
So that's just, you know, arbitrarily stupid for people who don't
You just might not be something you would ordinarily, think of if
you're new to to low-level programming.
So I'll just I'll just point out what I'm saying because it's probably
slightly interesting at least.
So you know, what did I do here?
You know, what did I sort of scoot in here?
Well, I just wanted some way to randomly pick a color that might be
different for each one of these things.
Now obviously we're going to have a lot more things in here than we
can assign unique colors to anyway.
So we're going to want to draw a border around the box that allows us
to sort of
see where the regions are.
So that's like a separate thing.
Going to have to do one way or the other but it would still be nice to
sort of randomize the color.
So what I did is, I said, well, whatever the pointer to the quit is we
know that no two people can point to the same grid, because if they
both point the same grid, that means they both have the same grid
string and that means it's not a very good good string now is it?
So we obviously know that that's not the case, but what I did is I
just took the value that the pointer is the actual numerical value of
the pointer right?
Whatever.
Bite it was pointing to and I modded it by the array count, which is
how many colors we had.
And I just said, well, whatever that is, you know.
So it's just basically like wrapping through this
Right 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10, 11 12, whatever and then back to the
beginning and keep at it through again, right.
So the problem with that is that if you take a look at what the
distribution of these values actually, is you're not going to get any
information in the low bits because a pointer is usually going to be
aligned to a 4, byte boundary, right?
Because as you know we typically for whatever you know alignment you
reasons in the past.
We typically have pointers that are aligned, not to a bite, right?
They typically don't go up by one, two, three, four, five.
They're typically aligned to a d word, which is a 4, byte boundary or
perhaps even to acquire like one of the SSE size things, depending on
how the allocator is going.
In our case, they're mostly going to be 4 bytes because our allocator
we defaulted to 4 B alignment.
So that would be d word aligned, right?
And so, you know, 0 1 2
Two, three, four, five, six, seven, whatever.
You never see.
One two or three you only see 0 and for University 56.
We only you know these are the only values we actually see coming in
through these pointers.
So the color array count is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12.
It happens to be a perfect multiple of 4, right?
So what that means is, we're only going to ever use three colors out
of this thing, because we're never going to have a point of this, not
on a 4, byte boundary.
And we're never gonna
And this isn't the, you know, this isn't a prime.
This is why you might want a prime number of colors in here, right?
So what I'm going to do because I'm super cheesy and weird is I'm
going to go ahead and say, let's make this, a non multiple of 4 so
that it will have more of a beat frequency to it.
In fact, if we could make it Prime that would be great right now.
It's 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 and so really there's 12 entries in it
if we wanted to 11 would be prime so I could just make it so that
We don't use this last value, right?
And hey look all of a sudden now we can actually see the different
zones because we're actually taking a look at we're actually using
more than three values of the colors, right?
So now we're getting a much more stable view of our profile and this
is already super informative, right?
Just looking at this.
You can kind of see how our frame time breaks down.
You'll notice that this giant sort of fluorescent bar here is our
frame display time, and that is US waiting for the vertical.
Refresh, right?
So, what's happening right now in our code is, we are doing a bunch of
work.
This is the work in here, right?
And I'll guess I'll we learn even more actually from this right here
is our input processing code, right?
If that makes sense right through there.
I don't know why that's so long.
It's kind of interesting.
That is long.
I wonder if that's if that's actually correct.
Oh, you know what, that might be correct.
Hold that thought.
Anyway, let's move on, hold that thought because that's an interesting
thought.
So this is our input processing.
Here is the actual game code all sitting right in there.
Right here is the debug collation, which I said is very expensive
because we're turning through, you know, a lot of stuff in there
typically.
So like, let's let's actually look in the more.
This this will look even worse, right?
This is the, the worst case for it.
Oh, but it's not on top.
Before I go any further than that, let's actually go ahead and use our
Z biasing here because we need our profile to be on top.
Remember we had to do the thing where they sort the rectangles we
sorted, like our Sprites of they would be on top for the debug code.
We need to do that same thing for our display here.
Otherwise we're never going to see it.
So I don't know if you remember this but basically like our renderer
sorts everything from front to back, if we don't make sure that the
debug stuff is sorted all the way to the front.
Then we
This problem, right?
So let's go ahead and switch over to.
Handmade ready group.
And inside handmade render group.
We have that Z bias concept there.
Oops.
Somewhere.
Don't we do we
Sort bias.
That's what I meant.
So we have that sort by this concept.
And what I think I'd like to do is I'd like the sort bias I think to
be part of the transform, right?
Because we've got this concept of an object transform and the object
transform gets passed through, and I think that's a more appropriate
place to do it so that you don't have to pass with every call.
You could just whatever that object transform was, it's in there.
So like right here, for example, I'm going to go ahead and say that
inside this object.
For him.
I don't know why we have.
It would be nice if I'd said why we want to move this out to its own
thing, ladies and gentlemen, when you write it to do, maybe you should
actually give yourself enough information.
Actually do it later.
No worries.
Anyway in here, I'm going to go ahead and say that there's a sort
bias.
and that way, inside the object transform,
We can pass in when we set that up, what we want that sort bias to be
and then instead of dealing with it here, the sort key when it's
computed will automatically take that into account and that way we can
sort of get rid of this, this weird, like, pass through Behavior
that's happening there.
And so, when we do that, get render entity basis P.
You can see it's Computing, the sort key down at the bottom.
What we can do is we can
Adjust that sort key right here.
So you can see the way we're doing it.
We're basically taking the the Z and sort of sorting Things based on
some sort of like, hacking us that made it.
So that upright things sorted one, way, and flat things, sort of the
other way because we're in two and a half d, right?
And we subtract y.
So what we can do with our sort bias here is we can just say like,
okay we're just going to start off with the sort bias, so whatever the
object, transform sort biases.
That's going to be our initial, our initial bit and then the sort key
gets computed based on the rest of it.
So yeah.
So there you go.
Hopefully that makes sense.
So then down here, where we've got this sort of weird nonsense that
we're doing right, where we have this sort by a stuff happening.
We want to go ahead and
Make this part of the troops.
Make this part of the transform.
And I don't know whether I want to do a front and a black backplane
transform, but I easily could.
So up here, for example, I can just say, you've got, like, there's
this
Default flat transform, right.
I'm going to call this.
Maybe I'm going to call this like main transform and Shadow transform.
And I may make these, I may want these to actually just be things that
are in the debug system for real.
Like I may want them to just be stored in debug state.
In fact, I probably do
but for now,
I'm just going to say okay, the text transform sort of bias or soft
bias.
Not what I wanted.
I'm just going to make these two arbitrarily huge numbers, so they
always sort to the front.
And that way, we've got the shadow transform and the text transform
and we can put all of those things on separate planes by just picking
which transform, we use.
Right?
So as you can see this, that won't fix a problem because we haven't
put it in the other routine yet.
So when we,
Split switch into here.
We're still wrong.
But so now what I'm going to
Is, I'm just going to make these first-class citizens of the debug
system itself, so I can.
Oops, that's not what I want.
So I can always use them in all the debug routines without having to
set them up and they'll just be there.
So, here in the debug state, I'm just going to put them right.
Put them right in here.
So they're always usable and I don't know, we might actually want, I
don't know if we want another one, which is like,
And there's the textures from the shadow transform and there's
probably like, you know, in order there's probably something like a
backing transform, which is like the we probably want several
transforms and we just picked which layer so they're basically layers
that we can use.
Right.
So yeah.
So now I just go and add that to add that to wherever we.
I need I have a bunch of work.
I got to do on my for coder config as you know, I switch to modal
editing and
Um I kind of like emacs or super buggy so I never really tuned.
Oh my keys and stuff to be very good in my modally Max and I just
poured that straight out of for a coder.
Now that for a coder is like what I'm editing in everywhere.
I need to spend some quality time, maybe if I'm lucky this weekend,
I'll have some time to do it.
Like tuning my how all my keys work because I spend too much time now
trying to do edits and now that I can program for a coder and see
emacs, of course I always had to program in emacs list now that I can
Graham for a coder and see, I'm going to be able to make really great
keybindings, I think.
And so I'm kind of looking forward to being able to do that and I hope
I can do that soon because I'm so much.
I'm not even close to as fast as I used to be when I wasn't doing when
I didn't, have the modal key bindings.
Which is just, that's, you know, what happens when you've been
programming your whole life non-modal, they switch to Modo, it's hard
to make yourself be the same speed, right?
Okay.
But that's neither here, nor there.
Let's go ahead and
Get these initializations going here, and there we go to books date.
I think that should do it.
I guess I'll put this back in transforming here as well.
Oops, back Young.
Sounds vaguely Vietnamese.
There we go.
Back in transform, sort of bias, is going to be like not as much
really know what my algorithm is here for how these things are being
assigned.
They just have to be numbers are larger than any other value that the
game might use.
If that's it.
Yeah, that's all for that.
And now I need to go actually use this transform up in the profile
code, right?
So in draw a profile in
now, what I need to
Do is make it so that my push Rex can use this.
Thankfully, I already take a transform with the push for X, so, that's
kind of nice and what that means is I can just go ahead and pass the
debug State vacuum transform here and then all the rectangles that get
drawn will go through that.
And that's nice.
But we should probably also take a look at anything else.
Like, here's another one.
I don't even know what this is doing here.
But let's go ahead and put this in here, back in transform and under
Cleared identifier, that's because it's debug state.
And I think the the look grabby B, like all that stuff is also going
to have to be kind of rendered properly.
So you can see here like like all this stuff, right?
Like all that stuff needs to be in there too.
So when we do end, element that stuff's got to be in there.
So what is these are good?
This is just like corners and stuff.
So I'm going to go ahead and make this be
you know, just transform.
In fact, I guess I can just do this to be cheesy.
There we go.
So let's take a look at this and see if that helps at all.
So here we are viewing the profile as before, I'm now going to hit the
spacebar and and there we go.
So now we've still got our profile view and that's pretty great,
right?
So let's take a look at our timings.
Now, you can see that this is the amount of time.
You're spending in the game update.
This is the amount of time.
We're spending an input processing.
This is the amount of time that we can't even hover over.
That's like, executor refresh.
Another junk like that.
This is the amount of time or swing, a debug Coalition which again is
substantially more in the game because there's a lot more things to do
in there.
And here is that frame display which is us just waiting for the
vertical, refresh and the graphics card like who know?
We don't know.
We don't know how much of that time is the graphics card actually
doing work and how much of the time is it's just waiting for the V
blank because obviously you know, we don't we don't have insight into
that and to be clear it's it's not it's overlapped as well.
So
Really what's happening with that code is a little bit slightly
different.
Right?
If you if you really want to talk about what's happening there it's
probably something more like you know we take that profile there.
Right?
And we sort of got like, oh well there's there's this, and then
there's this.
And this and this part here is the, the frame display.
And so you can imagine this sort of stacked.
In by frame like here is frame 0 that is going to repeat itself,
right?
And you can see that it's jittery which is very common on you know
modern machines are very you know there's a lot of they're not like
the machines in the old days where everything took exact amount of
time, thanks to caching and during power and different.
You know, every threads interrupted.
You know, that brings to the pre-empting you all this stuff.
You're never getting very stable frame timings anymore.
So you do expect the Jitter and you get it but roughly we're going to
have the same thing.
Repeat right, so this time here, this time here we're not doing any
work because we've already finished all the work we had to do and now
we're just waiting and we could go start on the other frame but we
really don't want to get too many frames ahead.
Right?
And we already know that we can do a whole frame in less than the
amount of time.
It takes for the graphics card to a for the, for the 60 frames.
A second update.
Anyway, so we're really just waiting here, but what I wanted to
Precise is right here, right?
Where we call swap buffers.
It's not.
It's it's sort of wrong to think about what happens there, as the
graphics card.
Then draws the frame and then waits for the V blank.
Right.
That's the tempting.
That would be what would be tempting to think about but that's not
what actually is happening.
What actually is happening?
Probably is, if you imagine that this is frame 0
Right then actually on frame or rather, let's let's not pretend that
let's pretend frame zeros back here.
Let's pretend this is frame you know like five and this is frame 6.
What's actually happening is this waiting for the V blank is actually
something that's happening from framed for.
So you're actually waiting for frame for to display, right?
Potentially.
You may actually be waiting for frame for to display and what you're
actually kicking off here is frame 5 to be displayed here, right?
And so the graphics card, maybe one frame ahead of you if it wants to
be and technically, it could be 2 frames ahead of you if it wanted to
be.
So you don't unless you've gone and profiled it and determined that
that is literally what's happening, don't assume that.
What's
Going on.
Is you call swap buffers?
It draws the frame in here and then it displays waits for the V blank
here.
What may happen is you call swap buffers here, it draws the frame
here, right?
Displays the previous frame here in the middle of having drawn this
Frame, and then waits for you to submit the next one after that.
And then we'll display this guy here.
So it's really staggered a lot of the time and it's important to kind
of understand that.
What's happening only because if you want to kind of understand
problems, you may have or performance things, you may see down the
line.
It's important to understand that the graphics card in the CPU are not
necessarily operating in lockstep.
They're two different processors.
That can be going asynchronously and they may decide to stagger their
operations specifically.
So each of them has like, if you look at how this works, each of you
now has one sixtieth of a second,
To do your work by adding a frame of latency there, you can do 16, as
worth of work on both the CPU and the GPU without reducing the frame
rate.
Now, you do add a frame of latency, right?
So it's not as good as if everyone was in lockstep but you know, it's
still pretty good.
It's better than reducing the frame rate to 30 frames a second.
Right?
You'd much rather have one frame of latency at 60 frames a second.
No frame to latency at 30 frames a second because one you just get a
bonus extra frame every time right for the same effective amount of
latency.
So it's hopefully that makes some sense to you.
It's just something to be aware of, it's not super relevant to
handmade hero.
We don't have to you don't have to like understand it that well or
anything.
But that's that's just what's going on there.
So what I wanted to point out here because I just wanted to point out
how useful profiles profiling are is, and why I want to spend some
time showing you how to build a debug system
And why I want to have one to begin with all we have done, right.
The only thing we did so far is just show the top level debug stuff.
I haven't even done the thing yet where I click and can go in here
right?
I haven't even done that.
So that literally all we're doing is is just showing the very top
level.
Already.
We're seeing this thing right here which is that input processing is
taking us what is that 2 million Cycles?
Right?
And so think in your head, two million Cycles.
Well, you know what?
At least talked about Cycles before, right?
We've talked about the fact that a cache Miss maybe cost 100 200
cycles and that's really bad, right?
That's like super long.
It's longer than any instruction we met.
We always talk about that missing the cash.
You know we mentioned that and we're like we really don't want to miss
the cash or whatever people say that that's what they're talking about
but what they're talking about when this the cash is it a million
Cycles?
It's 100 Cycles or something, right?
So we're looking at that.
Number.
And we're like, what are we doing?
That's going to cause that much time to be taken doing input
processing.
Right, we're collating.
2000d bugs of events here, right?
Reprocessing, two thousand things.
We're updating a ton of entities or updating hundreds of entities here
all the stuff it's debug code, right?
That's all.
We have an optimized, any of it, it's all whatever.
None of this is optimal.
And yet, we're seeing a suitably sized chunk when compared to these
things.
We're seeing a suitably sized chunk of two million cycles for in
processing.
Where is that going?
And that should be called, right?
You should immediately be like what's going on.
I don't understand what how that could be possible.
I think I know what it is because
you program long enough and you tend to have a hunch about these sort
of things and I think we even mention it on streem way back when, but
you probably have forgotten by now because it was mentioned in
passing.
Some of you may know if you're experienced programmer out there on
Windows you probably know exactly what I think it is as well, doesn't
mean we're right?
So we think it is.
So let's just start by, I'm going to sort of approach this as if I
don't.
Immediately know exactly what to comment out and just kind of show you
how we might go about finding that.
Now that we've got some tools.
Well, here's our input processing, right?
So even if I just don't want to think about this very hard.
Well, what I can do is I can just start narrowing the scope of my
timing blocks.
I know that anything that took that time has to come between that
begin and this end down here, right?
So I can pretty much just tell you right off the bat that if I was to,
You know, subdivide this, I could immediately eliminate certain pieces
of the code as being potential culprits, right?
And so, even if I didn't think, I already knew exactly what it was.
I take this same approach and go, let's divide and conquer.
Let's just add some more profiling blocks in here and that way we can
see who it is, that might be taking this time.
So I'm just going to go ahead and sort of make these blocks.
Are I'm going to go ahead and say time block and I'm
Going to call these things.
Some stuff, whatever they are.
So this is going to be.
What is this?
This is a clearing.
This is like controller clearing.
That's our code, right?
Where it's only us there.
This is win32 message processing.
Right.
Let's get some up in here.
What have we got?
Let's break this up in some.
So here is keyboard messages here.
This is the mouse processing, I guess, right?
So this is X block Mouse processing or Mouse position in here.
We've got some
Keyboard messages.
And then down at the bottom, we've got Xbox.
Strollers.
Yeah.
And that's it.
So that's what we're doing.
Oops.
New keyboard controller.
These guys obviously have to be kind of Loft it up a little bit.
I could do a begin block, end block around them, but I think I'm not
going to bother.
In fact, you know what I'll do.
I don't think this is a problem.
So I'm just going to assume it's not will see it because if it, if
it's part of that outer bit there, right?
All right, so now what I want to do and I'm going to, I'm kind of
using this to motivate the next thing right now.
When I run this those blocks will be timed, right?
But of course, I won't actually be able to see them and the reason is
because we're only showing the top level, right?
So you can kind of see that.
Here's that block of input processing, but I can't actually I can't
actually look at what's inside it and
What I'd like to do is go implement the ability to narrow in on a
region and figure out what's going on inside that region, right?
And so hopefully, you can now see why I want that.
Because once I know that a particular block is expensive.
I want to be able to put blocks inside it and see what the different
parts take.
Now we could do this by just not having this block to begin with,
right?
I could go ahead and do that and in fact, I suppose to make it so that
we
I can kind of finish the train of thought.
Maybe I'll do it that way, so you can, we can see it if I did this,
then these would all be at the top level, but you can see why I want
them to be nested, right?
So it's easier for us.
So we don't have to constantly put everything at the top level, but
let's take a look now at what's actually taking the time and hey, what
a surprise, my suspicion is correct.
The Xbox controllers are taking two million Cycles to pull
And you may ask yourself, why does it take two million Cycles to pull
an Xbox controller?
I'm no idea.
Do not know how they managed to write code that takes two million
Cycles to figure out whether an Xbox controllers.
They're considering the fact that it already knows whether the Xbox
controller is there or not, because that's how you would have written
the hid driver.
If you had any idea what was going on at all.
So, I have no idea what they're doing in there, but what you can
determine from that profile just like shooting fish in a barrel.
Right is
Holding the Xbox controllers is taking all of our time.
So we are spending 2 million cycles of frame.
To not get Xbox controller input, right?
There isn't even an Xbox controller plugged in and I will spare you.
I will spoiler warning at this point and just tell you that this is a
well known bug with Xbox controllers.
I have no idea why they have never fixed it.
But the problem with the Xbox controllers is that when you call
xinput, get state, if the Xbox controller is plugged in it will
operate
Efficiently.
So if you call Xbox controller, get state with a controller index of
say, 0 and there is a controller index in slot 0, then you will
complete immediately and it will not shut up on your profile.
If you can call xinput get state with slot zero and there isn't it.
Controller occupying that slot.
It will take I think whatever two million Cycles divided by 4 is it'll
take you know five hundred thousand Cycles just to tell you that there
is no
Xbox controller there.
Right?
Really heinous bug, obviously, I reported this bug to them in 2008, I
believe.
And well,
You can see how how fast they jumped on that one going on a decade.
Anyway, that's that's the state that's just the that's the reality of
it.
So we will have to work around that bug and there's various ways that
we can choose.
So we're at work around that bug.
One thing that we can do, that's a simple fix that isn't perfect.
Is to only pull one Xbox controller per frame.
If it's
Plugged.
So, all of the controllers that are plugged in, we pull every frame
because presumably, they're being used for the game and we want the
input and we know that they don't stall when they're plugged in.
But every time they
every time there's one that's not plugged in.
We can just not ask that for that state.
We can instead of asking, you know, when there's three controllers
aren't plugged in asking for all their see, all three state every
frame, we only ask every third frame, right?
So we asked like the first one on frame one.
Second, when a frame to 31 on frame 3, thereby reducing the stall
count from potentially two million Cycles down to 500 thousand Cycles
right now.
Again, not perfect because we're still
Losing five, hundred thousand cycles and we don't really want to lose
five thousand Cycles.
Five hundred thousand Cycles.
Now, if we have other things that can be multiplexed, we could do it
even less frequently.
Meaning we could ask only every 10 frames of 20 frames, right?
But that doesn't really help us unless we have something else that
only needs to happen.
Every so often that is going to happen.
That we can also Multiplex right?
Because otherwise all we've done is ensure that we're going to have
one really bad frame, where we lose 500 thousand Cycles, every so many
frames and moving a potential hiccup out to only be every so many
frames is not a great thing, right?
We don't we don't want that.
So if we were going to try and solve the problem all the way, what we
need to do is try to use a different method for figuring out whether
or not the Xbox controllers,
Are plugged in or not and one way we could do that.
For example, was try to monitor some sort of device change
notifications that we might get to tell us if an Xbox controller gets
plugged in or not, right?
So what I'm going to do here is I'm just going to set us up for doing
that at some point in the near future.
I'm just going to go ahead and say, well, okay, we know that we've got
this X User Max count nonsense Happening Here, Right?
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to say, let's introduce a piece
of permanent storage backup here outside the main Loop.
Before we start any everything.
And what I'm going to do is say Okay, since we don't know, we'll just
say Xbox controller present and I'm going to say that we've got this
array of assuming that none of the Xbox controllers are present for
now, except for the first one.
Right?
And so in the future will try to actually keep that up to date.
But what we'll do now is say, oh okay, what we'll do is we'll only get
the X will only do exit input get state.
If that Xbox controller present array.
Is is true.
So everybody else who's not set to True, won't, you know, go through
this path and they'll be marked as not connected, right?
So down here, when it says, control is not available, say Xbox
controller, present is whatever the one is whatever controller index
were on, will set it to false.
Right.
And so what we could even do in fact, you know, it will do here.
What we could do is set them all to True at the beginning.
I don't know why.
I said the that's, I don't know what I was doing there.
What I could do here is actually do controller index equals zero
controller index,
Is less than X User.
Max tap and controller index.
Plus plus inside here, I could just set these all too true.
And then if you so basically what this turns our game into is this
turns our game into a game where you have to have the controller
plugged in at startup, in order for it to work, you can't plug it in
after the fact, which is not what we want.
So this is not a solution.
Right.
This is a definite to do, which is like monitor Xbox controllers for
chain for being plugged in after the fact.
So we want to go ahead and add something that will undo.
This will basically like say oh when I get some other kind of change
notification will re pull and see but for the moment we'll do is we'll
assume they're all present and then as soon as we ask and find out
that they're not will
Stop pulling them ever again, right?
So like I said, that'll be fine for if they're plugged in beginning.
It won't handle when they're plugged in it, which is not what we want.
So we still want something else there, but let's go ahead and see how
that affects our profile.
Look at that.
Look at how much nicer that is now, right?
So now there's none of that nonsense going on, right?
Because we're never going to pull that joystick if it's not there and
so that's great, which is what we wanted.
So like I said, we have a little bit more work to do there and that's
to do is very important.
So don't forget about it, you know, that's why we put these two dudes
in here.
And so if the platform layer, when we go through to do find our sort
of final shipping pass on it, we're going to want to go study up and
figure out how to get some
Word notifications that we can use to reset that array and re-query.
But for now, this will avoid having a giant 2 million cycle time sink
where Microsoft is sitting around figuring out that there aren't any
Xbox controllers over and over and over and over again at Great
expense to us.
So,
now that that's taken care of, let's get back to the input processing.
Sub Loop stuff that we were talking about before, so yeah.
Let's see.
So now what I want to do is go back to focus on what I was trying to
talk about with the profiler before.
And so, here is, you know, here is our profile, you know, actually,
it's kind of interesting to I'm kind of curious.
Can we do?
We do the software renderer do we actually get anything?
Not sure why.
That's, that's weird that seems weird, doesn't it?
Not sure why that's all pink will have to go look at that, because I
feel like when we turn on the other renderer, we should still see
something reasonable in here, and you can see that when we did it, the
lane count increased.
So it did the profiler properly recorded that there were other
It's doing things, but it doesn't seem to have worked properly.
I don't know why this is not rendering correctly, I don't know if
that's something to do with the Sorting or something like that.
That's real weird.
Roll.
Yeah, that reminds me one thing that I wanted to check, you know, how
we were.
Had that sort of bug where this is in the software renderer when we
played it through opengl, it looks weird.
I was wondering about that and I was thinking, I wonder if we ever set
srgb on The Source texture, I can't remember if we did or not and I
just wanted to look so when we do
Do I think that's an opengl potentially?
But I can't remember.
So let's take a look.
Like that white, you know, it was getting that white look to it and
what I couldn't remember is when we were to do opengl display bitmap
when we do, okay?
So there it is.
So when we do GL text image to D, what I what I was thinking is our
frame buffer is now srgb, I believe, but the texture that we're
submitting, we're telling it that it's linear RGB.
And so I was wondering if our
Problem was actually this that we weren't submitting an srgb 8
texture, if that makes sense.
And I don't know, I wasn't sure if maybe that was the problem because
I was thinking maybe it was doing non srgb reads.
And hey look that's what the problem was.
Yeah.
Cool.
The other thing that I wanted to fix their.
So that's perfect.
So now we can switch between the software renderer and the hardware
renderer, it's kind of weird.
Isn't it?
Kind of interesting that are are fonts, look different,
I guessing that's because our we probably weren't accurate with pixel
centers.
I'm guessing that's the only thing I can think of, but it's kind of
cool that we can switch between software and Hardware rendering it
basically the exact same result.
That's kind of cool, right?
The other thing I was going to say is I don't know why that kind of
got a wild hair about that.
Just I saw it and I remembered I was thinking about it.
So hopefully you guys see what I was what I was doing there, right?
For gamma correction, when we render, we render with gamma correction
such that we load images in, we gamma correct the values, we do all
our blending operations, then we undemocratic the values and stored
them back to the frame buffer, what that means.
I,
A i gamma corrected values?
That's wrong.
We map from a gamut.
From a gamma curve space to a linear space.
We do all our bunny operations and then we map from the linear space
back to the gamma corrected to the gamma encoded, space, the curved
space, right?
And what was happening.
When we did our opengl display bitmap, where I think that use opengl
to display to the screen instead of using GDI to do.
So, is when I set what format the texture was, when I
It when I take the results of the software renderer which are gamma
encoded and I sent them to opengl, I didn't tell opengl, they were
gamma encoded.
So when it went to do the the the rendering of the image, it was
reading it as a texture and writing it to the frame buffer.
The frame buffer is marked as srgb.
The textures not.
So it's reading in linear what?
It thinks are linear values.
Even though their gamma curve values, it's applying the gamma curve.
Him when it coffees them to the frame buffer, right?
But it never applied the inverse gamma curve when it read them because
it thought they were linear to begin with.
So we were doing only half of a mapping which basically re squares are
gamma, which is why everything was so bright, right?
It recurs, it curves a curve, right?
It like takes things that were already gamma corrected and tries to
get back at them again.
So, I believe that was the only bug with that.
There's another bug in here, though, which is that when we do GL bind
texture and we set it to texture one.
Now, when we switch between those two, remember we've allocated a
bunch of textures for use in the games when it's in Harbor renderer,
so we can no longer just assume that we can use texture one.
So what we want to do is we want to like reserve one texture at
startup for the case, where we would like to do opengl.
Map display, right?
We essentially just want some way of setting up a global texture
handle for use for this blip through.
And so, in order to do that and you can see, I don't know if you guys
saw it, there's a way you can actually see the bug happen with it.
So oh, not in the profile.
Sorry, it's in here.
So watch this.
Watch the background layer when I do this.
Do you see what happens?
and if you can see that, I'll do it one more time in case you couldn't
So, here's the hardware.
Renderer write books for looks correct.
Switch to software rendering.
Obviously that looks correct.
That's always going to look correct because that's not using any
textures.
It's just bleep using 12 blit to the screen, and then back.
And you notice there's this weird thing in the background there.
That's the image that and you can even see the text.
I don't know if you can see it.
You could see like
That's the image that we put into that texture, that the software
rendering made over writing the texture, the that we had sent down the
graphics card to use for Hardware, rendering for that backplane,
right?
And so, we need to make sure that we use a separate texture for that
backplane rendering so that if we want to switch between hardware and
software.
Rendering, we are not romping an existing texture.
So in order to do that, all I need is I need to allocate a texture
from the graphics card at runtime handle and say this is the one
that's going to use for that, right?
And so, I'm going to say here that we've got one of those.
So I'm going to say that we essentially have some handle here that we
know we're going to reserve and I'm going to say that we pass it in
when we do open gel display bitmap, I'm going to pass in here like
whatever that put texture is and so when we bind that texture in I'm
just going to have that get Bound in here like so so that we will
never try to submit over someones existing texture and that way that's
just a little bit saner.
I think.
so in win32, in it, open gel
In here, once I'm done with everything.
And we've got open gel initialized, I'm going to go ahead and say,
okay, let's get that.
Let's, let's do a gen textures call to just give us one of those and
then we'll pass that in when we do the display call.
So that we know that it's that will always work.
Opengl display bitmap, put texture.
Okay.
So now we should go through a reserved handle that will not get
parceled out to somebody else.
So there's the software under, and there's back to the hardware
renderer there, and you can see that now.
We don't have that bug anymore.
So that's just a nice just getting rid of a bug that we would have had
otherwise.
So yeah, you can see that we're a little sloppy about pixel centers,
in the software renderer, which maybe we should go fix some day,
probably not till the games done.
Because we like I said, we don't need the software renderer, the
software renderer is just
It was about teaching how those things work, but someday be nice to go
back and like really be rigorous about the pixel centers and make sure
that everything is exactly right because we're really good with our
with our interpolator, right?
You can see how good we look, we look just as good as the graphics
card in because we did like but correct, bilinear, filtering and
correct.
Grammar correction, all that stuff, so, that's pretty cool.
But our pixel centers, we never talked about that and we never even
did anything.
We never.
Actually did that, right?
And it's not hard to get right necessarily.
It doesn't like
I mean it doesn't cost too many extra operations right thing to get,
right?
It's just you have to think through the math and do it properly.
So they all right.
How much time you got?
We got no time.
All right, so we've got our path.
Clear ahead of us.
Everything's working great right now.
Next week, we're going to make that profile view.
Be ten times cooler will make it so that you can navigate down.
The hierarchy will make it.
So it shows the top used things because now we're sort of, I think
we're on a roll, we've got what we need.
And that's what we'll do for next week.
I'm going to go ahead and take some Q&A now, because I would like to
take some Q and A now, and, and yeah.
That's, that's all good.
Oh my God, in sohbat.
It's about his amazing.
All right, so anyway, let's take some cues here.
Can't remember what opengl considers the center of the pixel.
So the way opengl works with pixel centers is that like the, they
picked it.
So that if you specified the bottommost pick,
All coordinates is act like 0 0 and the topmost width and height.
So like one passed it with 0 0 and 1, 1 texture coordinates, you'd get
a one-to-one blit, I believe that's how they ended up specifying it
out which was like, not the way that d3d did it originally.
But they've fixed now, it was a very smart the way opengl did.
It was a very smart way.
I think it was right.
I mean I'm not really a super Jeep you guys so you know,
Maybe there's reasons why you wouldn't want to do it that way, but it
seemed like a very sane definition of it.
And so what they did was they basically made it.
So that bilinear filtering and texture and pixel coverage lined up
exactly and that I don't know that just was kind of cool.
Anyway, it doesn't matter point being
Is Rob a synonym for clobber.
Yes.
Sure.
Do mean it will the
Opening cutscene be narrated?
Yes in fact I said I had it voice-acted but I didn't like the voice
acting so I'm still look, I'm going to probably get someone else to do
it.
Some point or Domina could you elucidate further on the waiting for
vsync in the profiler?
I'm not sure what you mean by elucidate further.
But what I am trying to say about that staggering is just that when
you are waiting for vsync what that
Actually means is, you're waiting for the GPU to tell you to proceed,
that may have nothing to do with when the vertical blanking occurs.
It just means that you are far enough ahead of the GPU that it doesn't
want you to submit any more stuff right now, right?
Meaning swap buffers, what's going to happen is you're going to call
swap buffers and the graphics card might return immediately.
It might just be like, okay even though it hasn't displayed a frame,
then you'll get to the next time you call swap buffers and call it
again and that time it might be like, okay, wait a second.
We haven't finished this playing the other frame yet.
We're still waiting for vsync.
So I'm just going to hold you there for a little bit, right?
Because the gravatar won't let you just submit an infinite number of
frames.
That's not going to happen, it's going to stop once.
A certain amount behind.
So then at that point, it probably is true that you will be roughly
around the vsync because it's like, okay, I cleared that frame out and
now we're moving on to the next one.
Like whatever that's one thing, but who knows that may not be true,
right?
It may be that it's only once it sinks something down to be pending
for vsync, you can start on the next one.
And really, what you're getting is waiting for that transition to
occur or, who knows, you might you might be staggered from the Visa
and quite a bit.
And so I don't have anything special to add.
There is not a problem that I've studied extensively.
I can't tell you what, you know, amd's driver does or Nvidia driver
does specifically or anything like that.
I just wanted you to be aware.
That calling swap buffers is not the same as saying wait for the
vertical, retrace and display this Frame.
What it's saying is here is the opengl commands.
That constitute.
This Frame, I trust, you will wait until the appropriate V blank to
display it.
And I also trust that you will
Put my thread to sleep here.
If I'm too far ahead of you, that's really what it's actually saying,
but none of it has anything to do with return.
Immediately after the V Blank, That's not necessarily guaranteed and
may often times, not be what happens.
Kubrick Caleb.
I actually prefer the fonts that the software renderer produces.
Is there anything we can do to make them look that way in GL?
Well, to be honest, since I haven't actually looked at what's going
on.
I don't really even know why they're looking one way or the other way.
Part of.
It may also be that the gamma curve in our software.
Renderer is approximate, whereas the one in the hardware is snot and
around the alpha, is his part.
It is going to have effects there.
So it may be that if we re-encode the fonts to, with a proper srgb
curve, which is some point, I actually will do in the asset Packer.
It may be that they look more correct there.
Butt out.
Like I said, we've kind of have to look we have to look into it.
Hmm.
Leaving seven recommended entry.
Level programming language for aspiring game.
Does I would see that?
I've said this multiple times before on the, on the stream.
In fact this is sort of gets Sean, Barrett said something on.
When he was talking to Abner on, handmade the handmade Dev like
interview thing that I kind of wanted to follow up on because I hope
he wasn't talking about me when he was talking about it because I've
Always said exactly the opposite of this.
But he was saying that people were worried or that people had been
saying that the fact that programmers of today have like JavaScript
and these sorts of things and they start on them, that they'll be
lousy programmers.
And that's totally not true.
And he said exactly what I think is the right thing, which is that
nobody started programming in c or like very few people did like
nobody starts by programming Assembly Language, that's very unusual.
Maybe in the old old old days, the old old
Old days, certainly not certainly before I was born, they would have
been right but all the rest of us, we all started in Easy language to
like we started in basic or like some kind of like logo would have
been another language.
We started everyone starts in an easier language usually I mean or at
least most of the time.
And so you should feel free to start programming in whatever language
you feel.
Is the one you enjoy programming in and will do.
Because the important thing about learning to program is doing it a
lot.
And so you want to start in a pregnant language that you get into
quickly and enjoy programming in.
And then when you're ready, you want to transition out of that
language into higher harder core language, if you want to be an engine
death, right?
Now the thing that I don't know if Sean was reacting to this or not,
but the part that I do think is true.
And that I've said multiple times that maybe, I don't know if maybe he
thinks about this differently.
The thing I do think is a problem nowadays.
Is that nowadays you don't really have to transition to a harder core
programming, language.
Meaning you could just keep programming in JavaScript and make kind of
janky slow programs but that you can still shift because they won't be
any worse than like what Google ships or something, right?
Because they ship like janky slow mail program on
JavaScript or whatever, right?
So you can go make a living now and you can go make a
Repetitive app in a number of domains without ever actually learning
to program any better than in something like JavaScript, you know what
I mean?
And that I think is bad because it means it takes away some of the
incentive for people to go learn more harder, core programming, and
unfortunately, machines and programming has not been abstracted to the
point yet where you can actually do that and not produce crappy
programs, right?
Right.
And so, that is a part that I'm very worried about.
Not the entry-level part, the entry-level part, you should use
whatever you want, any language you want, but you will start
programming in is a good language to start with.
But what you want to do eventually, is if you're going to be serious
about programming, you want to move past that into a language that has
low-level control like see does.
Where you're thinking about actual memory that has real pointers and
that sort of thing you want to get there.
And I do worry that.
Now, there's less push for people to get there and people may stay
with languages that don't have that like, Java or anything, you know,
those sorts of things which I don't, I don't think that's good.
I don't think we're at the point in Computing, history, where you can
be that sloppy and someday we might get there, you know, someday we
might get to the point where
Higher level languages are so good that you'd ever have to think about
these sorts of things again because we like, boiled it all down and
it's perfect or something or like we invent some crazy.
New super fast computers that are like thousands and thousands of
times faster than what we have today and so maybe it doesn't matter
but I don't know.
So that's just a clear that up.
Hopefully, that's a pretty complete answer to that.
Question.
Long billion is there?
Anything that can be done to help make it easier to hover?
Click on the debuggers?
Listen, are you talking about the profiler?
If so then yes.
What I want to do with that and we have this before, I just don't
remember to be honest with you, I don't really remember how it worked
but we just have to have a pause.
So that's all I was going to do but I don't remember.
It's this debug State, pause thing, but I just don't know if I think,
maybe we just don't have any way to pause right now.
So all we need is something that sets, debug pause to true and then it
will stop collating new timing information, and whoo, it won't be
right?
We can just so when we're like, what's going on, we can hit pause will
be able to scroll through the different frames.
Find the one we look here about in Hover trivially, so.
So I think we've got that covered out.
I don't think we're going to have too much trouble with that.
Like I said, we kind of already did that.
We just have to re-enable it.
Um, let's see.
In sohbat, is knocking it out of the park, by the way, today.
Ginger Bill are all the textures transferred every frame.
No the only textures that are transferred are ones that are freshly
loaded off disk.
That makes sense.
So it, in fact, I can I can show you the I'm assuming you're asking.
I'm assuming you're not asking if opengl conceptually transfers them
all every frame, obviously that's not true.
But if you're asking, if we do them every frame, you can see our
opengl render Loop here which is very, very simple.
And what happens is it just does a bind texture and binds the texture
handle for the bitmap that it that is in memory.
and what we do is in the asset system when we load a texture,
You can see here, that anytime we're done loading, a texture off.
Disk, we immediately asked the platform layer to download it.
So that's all happening on a background thread.
And once it's down there, it's down there.
So that's actually why now like if we run this so you know, like the
cutscene for example, there's a ton of texture data there is like, you
know, each one of these seeing some of them have you know, five six,
seven 1080p bitmaps.
That would have to get transferred.
There was a stutter there when we first implemented it and we did
download all the textures on the first frame of the cutscene
Now, we do that in the background.
And so we've got relatively smooth, I believe at this point switches,
I don't see any hitches anymore.
So right, right now actually, like, as we're moving through this
cutscene, it's looking ahead and going, oh, we need these other
textures, they're getting loaded it off the disk and downloaded while
we're watching this part of the cutscene, right?
So it's all sort of streamed in as it goes.
Which is cool, which is pretty cool.
Right.
In the debug view, I will we be able to click on a frame and have it
blit that frame?
Definitely not because in order to do that, we would have to read back
the frame from the frame buffer, every frame and save it which were
definitely not going to do.
That's basically like writing our own OBS recorder.
which while an interesting exercise is really not appropriate for him
a hero because
I mean, do we really need it?
Could you explain in what consists the dynamic resolution.
Text to rescale viewport rescale at the moment we don't really handle
a dynamic, resolution much.
All we just are always at the moment rendering at 1080P and putting
the screen so that's you know.
That's just something that we will look at a little bit more when
we're closer to shipping.
Dude, in basement one, are we going to have it auto?
Pause on Long frames?
No, I don't think so, we'll probably have some things with it's easier
for us to see that.
There was a long frame, but I don't think will Auto pause maybe Auto
jump to a long frame.
Hardware to row.
What about checking for memory leaks?
Yeah, we can I probably will do some of that.
I don't know how soon we would do it because I'll be honest, I don't
think we've got a lot of memory leak potential in this game.
So while we do want to do some for final checking it ain't it ain't
really that big a deal, right?
So I don't know that memory leaks is going to be a huge problem for
Us in other contexts maybe it would be in this context.
I don't think it's really going to be huge, so we probably will do a
little bit of that.
But at the moment,
I don't think it's going to be super relevant.
It's not high on my list, but do that way.
At what at which point should you make the transition from a more
basic language like JavaScript over to a language?
Like C I would say once you have gotten to the point,
like, I would say, once you've gotten to the point where you
understand how to
G in Java Script like,
And you're not confused by it.
So like, you know, you understand if statements and while loops and
how to make a structure, like a thing with some structured data in it,
you know, once you can like, I can write a program in JavaScript.
I understand how it works.
I can, you know, step through it and like Chrome's thing or whatever
and I see what it's doing.
I'm not confused about it.
Once you're at that point, then I would say can probably move to see.
But you want to kind of like
because, you know, this see has
once you move into the realm of controlling everything yourself, you
just have a lot more things.
You have to keep in your head and you have to understand how your
memory is laid out, and how you're using it, and how it works.
You know, how all that stuff comes together.
And so, you know, the idea behind starting with this a language like
JavaScript or, you know, something, whatever else, basic, you know,
doesn't matter, something.
Whatever that simple language is the idea with starting with those
In four languages is to let you practice on a subset of what
programming is, right?
It's like if you've never programmed before, you don't know how an if
statement works, you don't know what an else Clause is or why you
would care.
You don't know what a function is, you know, what a return value is,
right, and learning what, all those things are, and how to use them,
more importantly, so that they become a, you know, sort of more
natural to you to think through here is the problem I want to solve
how do
Do I use all those constructs to solve that problem?
It's just, it's helps to start in a language where you're not thinking
about memory and you're not thinking about how do I interface with
Windows or you're not thinking about, like, all the things that we do.
Think about on handmade hero, removing those from the problem allows
you, it's like putting training wheels on a bicycle, right?
It's letting you get part of the things done and used to it so that
your brain is ready with that.
So that when you take the training wheels off, instead of it being
like having to learn everything,
It once you can just learn now that new part, right?
Which is like the direct memory control and you know, sort of the the
more the more nuanced stuff that you have to understand when you're
programming in c.
And so I think it for everybody's going to be different, but that's
what you're looking to do.
So once you sort of get familiar with the basics of programming, then
you can move on to a different language.
You certainly don't have to go an expert in JavaScript.
And because, who cares, right?
So you don't need to go learn a ton about JavaScript specifically
because it doesn't matter.
You just want to practice those Basics the programming, fundamentals,
because they're the same in every language, right?
and off you go now, JavaScript does have one annoying thing which
That it's dynamically typed.
And so one problem with starting with with JavaScript is that it won't
help you catch those errors.
You know, one of the nice things about sees you say something is an
integer if you then try to use it as a string, you get a compiler
error, write in JavaScript, it just sort of works, and it does the
wrong thing in your program as a bug, or not sure why, right?
And so, you know, there's probably a real good language for learning
programming.
And and it's probably not JavaScript, but I don't know if it what it
is or if it's even has been really made yet.
But you know
That's that's that.
Alright I think I'm going to go have dinner now.
Let's see if there's any other two cones.
Dude, and basement.
Sorry have a Fail-Safe to see when we stutter to pause this.
Amanda Beckett, unfortunately, you can't really do it that way, right?
Because it's too late after you have have the stutter to debug the
code because the state has moved past there.
So all you can do is look at your debug out.
Look at your debug streams.
And that since we record forever, we don't have to pause immediately.
If we see a stutter we can just like pause if we if that's what we
want to do right now.
We can pause and then scroll back to it, right?
So we'll be able to do that as necessary but I don't think we want to
it to automatically happen because then it'll keep happening when
we're in the middle of something and that's not where we're trying to
look at or whatever, right?
But you can't run for it.
Unless you do a whole bunch of other stuff.
I don't even remotely want to go into right now.
You can't jump back and debug the stuttered frame.
So,
all right.
All right.
Let's close this and minimize.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here at or get comes with the source
code so you can play around with it yourself and learn from it.
We also have a forum site.
You can go to ask questions a patreon page.
You can go to.
If you want to subscribe to support the video series and a tweet bot
that tweets the schedule at you.
So you can catch the stream live and it will be live next week again,
check the
Tweet.
But over the weekend for what the schedule will be because I don't
know exactly what it will be next week.
Just yet, I usually try to post it Monday morning.
So everyone
It was what the schedule will be for the week.
We also of course are using a new editor on stream written by Alan
Webster from the handmade hero chat.
In fact mr.
Fourth dimension if you type for a coder into Google, you will have
the top hit as this patreon page.
If you want to use the editor that we're now using on handmade hero
and help fund its development.
You can subscribe to his patreon page and I think
It's the five dollar level gets you, the extensible version of it
every month which he updates quite frequently despite being still in
school which is pretty awesome.
And it every every time if you're a handmade hero, if you have the
handmade hero source code as well in the Mist directory, I keep my for
code or customization file for a quarter Casey, so you can use my
customizations and look at how it got my other set up if you want to.
So check that out, that's about it.
Have a
Good weekend, programming everyone and I'll see you on the internet.
Take it easy.