Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero, the show where we CO2
complete game live on stream here on Twitch.
You know, we don't use any engines, we don't use any libraries, we're
kind of just like going rogue, if that makes sense.
But I think it's important that everyone have the experience one time.
A seeing?
Absolutely everything that's involved building a game.
It really makes people a lot more flexible as programmers and lets
them do a lot of things that they couldn't do.
Otherwise is means that basically anything that you want to be able to
do you can
You don't have to rely on someone else for it.
So it's kind of cool and honestly it's also kind of a lot of fun.
I don't know if you're the kind of person who likes you know, just
likes to program then it's kind of fun to be able to get down and do
stuff yourself without having to go through kind of like all these
weird like Amorphis layers and so right now what we're actually doing
is we're just we postponed some debugging till today because yesterday
we had just finished up when the stream is over.
And I didn't want to start debugging something at that time, because I
felt like that would just go really long.
So, what we had done is we added a bunch of stuff to our asset
processing system and asset loading system to allow so, save out, like
font metadata, basically, like all like that, the tables of bit Mak
lifts, and all this other stuff.
And so, we finished all that, but we didn't have a chance to actually
go to bucket and get it working.
We probably forgot some stuff we probably made some mistakes because
it was a bunch of stuff both.
Sides of the asset process of processing and on the game side it.
So we want to do today is just go over that code again.
Make sure it's working properly, step through it, find any problems.
That sort of thing is get that up and running and then we'll have sort
of the first pass of all of our font stuff.
Actually, mostly done.
And then I think we'll probably do for the rest of the week is go back
through it.
Add a few things that I think we want to add clean up a few things
basically just kind of Tidy it up so that we can kind of say, all
right, we've got fonts.
Now we probably don't really need to do much else with them.
We're happy and we can move on to debug overlays which was another one
of our big sort of to do items and one of the main reasons that we
wanted to do fonts now was so that we could have those even though we
don't really actually have any need for text in the game at the
moment, although we probably will
Later on.
So let's go ahead and get that.
That party started.
Today is day.
1, 72.
So, if you would like to follow along at home, and you pre-ordered the
game on handmade hero dot-org, unpacked a 170, ones, source code, into
a directory.
That's the source code.
I'm starting with right now and that's what you're going to want to
start with if you're trying to follow along with me.
All right.
So let's go ahead and build and if I remember correctly, nothing, in
particular, went wrong.
Our fonts just didn't show up.
So we weren't having like a crashbug, but something is broken.
Such that the fonts are not loading sufficiently in a way that the
actual game can use.
So some part of
Either our packing process or are loading process is making a critical
error and so it just thinks that there aren't any fonts or something
like this happens, right?
So, our job now is to go through and find out where that error or
series of errors are, I'm going to go ahead and start with the asset
processor, just because I want to actually do a quick first pass.
Check to make sure that I actually believe that our fonts are even
getting stored into the file at all.
And that there's
You know, actually data in the bitmaps that sort of thing.
So I want to just do a quick pass on that and see what I believe to be
happening there.
Now, I think, what I'll do just to make life a little easier on
myself, is, if you remember correctly, we have the ability to write
out multiple files from the asset Builder, right?
And you can see it happening here.
And so, what I think I'll do is I'll do something where I just write
fonts like this.
So I'm going to go ahead and write fonts as a separate file.
And that way, what I can do is I can even move.
Temporarily to first.
And so, then I can try it like first and last, and so on, because
first, it's kind of a privileged position.
It means that the bitmap IDS will actually line up, right?
And so, that takes another thing, sort of a little bit out of the out
of the equation, potentially.
Well, no, that's not actually true.
I take it back.
That doesn't mean that.
So, that's okay.
But point being, I want to sort of isolate it in that way, because if
we isolate it in that way, it means that I don't have to step through
a bunch of unrelated assets that I don't care about in order to get to
the ones that I'm trying to.
To debug because obviously all the rest of the assets are working,
just fine, we're looking at them in the game so we really don't need
to think about that too much, right?
They are not causing our problem.
So what I want to do is kind of clip that out.
I'm going to make thought asset file writer thing here, right?
Like so.
And then I'll go ahead and do a write.
H a the right H.
It's a will just write like, you know, test fonts or something like
that.
Yeah.
And so then I think that will give us a an asset build process.
Let's go ahead and actually run out here, right?
You can see we have just three hhas at the moment, if I go ahead and
run the test asset Builder.
Now I've got 44, I should
For and there you go.
So you can kind of see those those there and it seems like everything
was relatively what we would expect before the fonts were included in
test two.
So they were, it was a 7, MB file.
We now have dropped that down to a little under 1, MB.
And that other six megabytes that was missing has popped up here and
test Fanta.
Aha seems like totally rational thing to do.
Everything looks fine so far.
Okay, so let's go ahead and step into our test asset Builder looks
like, actually there were already on that there, so that's good.
Let me, I'm just gonna step through that font writing process, so that
I can just verify to my
Of the things are doing what I think they should be doing rather than
just assuming that everything is working properly.
Since we already know, there's at least one problem can't really hurt
to check.
So there's our code Point count.
It's 127 again, the ASCII code that we're going up to is 126 so that's
exactly what I would have expected.
Here, we are allocating some space for that and that's not cleared out
all at the moment.
So it's just going to be a bunch of garbage.
You can see that it's actually been initialized because we're in the
debug a situation.
Debug
Malik in the C, runtime Library, Microsoft, C, runtime Library
clearest to that C&D C&D, C&D C&D C&D.
You can see it there.
And so that's what we're looking at there.
We're going to go ahead and load this aerial that ttf we're going to
force it to be added already would have been added because it's in the
windows font directory, but in case it hasn't been.
So there's that height of 128, that's the height we're asking for.
For this particular font eventually we're going to want to send that
down here.
That's something.
We'll like I said, when we kind of go through and Polished,
We're going to want to be able to ask for different size fonts, so
we'll probably make that be something that you passed a load file.
But for right now we're just sticking with one test case.
This will go ahead and load that font out and we can see that we
actually did get a font back, so that's good.
So we know that low didn't fail.
We're going to put that into the global font device context.
Let's take a look at that.
That looks like it is a valid context.
Now as well.
We're then going to get the text metrics Outlets, see about those test
matches.
Do they look like what we would expect and they do.
There's that height of 128, the sn2.
Decent.
Look like they line up.
So that looks like we got back our text metrics.
No funny business there.
The code Point count.
Again, we're just storing it, so that's fine.
There it is.
The line Advanced.
All we did was do that height plus the the external letting.
So that's just going to be a little bit higher than the height which
is what we see.
So that's all fine, the bitmap IDS and the horizontal Advanced.
We then allocate some arrays of sufficient size to hold, what we
expect to be seeing there.
So that's all good.
Then we come back and now we've got our debug font.
And so that's that's seems totally fine everything.
There looked like exactly what we would have wanted to have happen.
So nothing surprising.
Nothing to be concerned about yet.
In my opinion we're then going to go ahead and add an asset type of
font.
We Begin that asset type like so we add the font asset in here.
Let's see what that ends up looking like here is the result of that
asset.
Add, it's got an ID of one.
It's the first thing in the file.
That's what we'd expect as there's nothing else in this file.
We have the HHA which is the actual data.
It's got the tag range which is what we would expect.
Again, it's not a bitmap.
It's not a sound.
It is a font here.
Is that font data and the font it looks exactly like what we wanted to
look like.
So that's good, the source itself points back to that font.
It looks
Like, yeah, there it is all good.
So that seems totally kosher don't mind that at all.
Totally happy with it.
We're then going to go and start recording this font list.
And those Fang clips, of course,
Are the actual bitmap images of the characters in the font so we're
going to Loop over each of those.
We're going to go into add character asset which of course is going to
add that character.
This particular code Point, whatever the code point is to the sort of
packing list.
Basically, it's going to say, here's what those are.
I don't know why are aligned percentage is set there.
That's that's you know before we go any further, I'm just going to fix
that character.
Don't have that.
That's a bug.
I mean, it's not a bug because it just gets overwritten later, but it
doesn't make any sense to make it appear as like, you know, someone
was coming in reading this code afterwards, didn't know what was going
on.
They'd be like, I don't understand.
And so we don't want that.
So what we probably want to do is set these guys to just zero or
something here and make a note that they get set later.
Write something like note set later by extraction.
Right.
So that's all good.
You know.
I do wonder about one thing here, which is that?
That's, that's okay.
Because that gets written at the right time.
I wanted to make sure that the wine percentage would actually get a
written before it gets written to disk, but it will.
All right, so anyway, we've got the asset Source here which is the
font that it was coming from and the code point that it's supposed to
extract those both look good.
So let's resume, let's resume our debugging step so I'm going to just
run us back up to there.
Go through here.
We add those guys in and now we've got another asset set up here.
It's going to be a glyph, right?
There's that font again it's pointing to the correct font.
It's particular code point.
The code Point 33 is that is that actually corrects that the first one
probably.
Yeah, it looks like that is the first one, so that's all good.
And then we go ahead and record, whatever asset ID.
We got back to is what we would expect.
We stick that into the debug font bitmap IDs and we keep going.
So if I was to look now at the debug font bitmap IDs and I were to
just look at how many of them there actually, were right, like 128 or
whatever.
We can see them all there, right.
And you can see in here that we've got a bunch of invalid values,
stored in these places where we're not writing out characters, and
that's something that I want to address a little bit later on because
it later on, I want to Only Store the actual ranges that are used and
so we're going to make that glyph look up, be a little bit more.
Kate eventually.
But for now I only care about the characters were actually using and
here they are.
So they're kind of just doing their thing and that's all good.
So off we go, okay, we get to the end and now we're going to go ahead
and write that ha that's a bunch of boilerplate stuff that we already
know works.
Just fine.
Except now you know we want to check out the new parts we added.
So the front part and then we want to double-check the glyph part as
well.
So here we are checking out the font part.
Let's see if this appears to
Write out the information in the manner that we would expect it to do.
So here, is it pulling out the font?
Does that font look like the font that we believed it to look like?
Yep.
That's all what we'd expect.
Let's take a look at the that bitmap table as well, right?
There's that bitmap table.
Oops.
Gotta go past the actual value that we were expecting to see.
There are those those numbers are there.
The horizontal advance?
It would be harder for us to verify, certainly, but we could start, we
could look at the, you know, a random thing out of it like, say this
this value, something like that.
You can see if those numbers made any sense that doesn't look very
reassuring that as a horizontal Advanced number does not look great to
me.
I don't know how you feel about it that that looks problematic
actually.
Is there anything in here?
Set to anything reasonable?
So so I don't love the horizontal Advanced that's, that's not looking
good.
That's really not looking good.
So I think what I'd like to do is oh I know where that is because it's
not set yet.
We in fact can't write out that until we actually load these with it
Maps, right because the glyph bitmaps they're set in there.
Hmm.
All right, so that's a big problem for us.
That's a big problem for us.
Only for our testing purposes.
When we actually do the kerning table extraction, it wouldn't be a
problem for us at all.
But what that means is this test that I was using was bogus because
since the table won't be set, until after you start the glyphs, we
can't do any sort of writing it there.
So this is a meaningless thing that I put in there that was just dumb
and so we don't want to do that.
What we'd rather do is to do Casey.
You know, eventually pull real kerning tables.
And I guess what we want to do here is just go ahead and set all
everything inside that table, right?
The entire table.
Like, so,
There we go.
So there's our code Point index, and there's are other code point.
Next, we'll just set absolutely everything in there to just be
whatever the text metric with of a character is, right.
So that result text metric TM with I think was a vet, which is just,
you know, some random one of those.
It's just, it's just the maximum width of a character.
We'll just stuff that in there.
So that we know it's at least, a not a completely ridiculous value.
And I'm not crazy about that being called result now.
So I'm going to go ahead and call result,
Aunt again, so that everything's kind of the same there.
I thought there was a team with what was it called?
There was like, a, something like that.
That told me, sort of the width of a character's, Max width, or
something.
Average character with, there we go, Max character with.
So, we'll just say Max character width for now.
Since we're not going to do this, we're going to pull out something
better later.
So there is Max character with and we're sticking that in our
horizontal Advanced.
So that's all good.
Alright, so there we go.
We've already found one bug.
That's good.
Good bug hunting.
I feel like.
So, let's take a look.
Now, again, at what we're about to write out and see, okay, so that's
a much more reasonable value, right?
That actually is something that makes some sense.
Good.
Okay, so we're writing out our code points or writing out our
horizontal advance and now they both look actually more correct to me.
So that's good off they go.
And now, let's take a look at when we actually go and do.
Okay.
That's
Doesn't make any sense to me.
Why are there two fonts appearing in here?
So I think we've got another bug here.
Yep, that's not supposed to be font.
That's supposed to be fog lifts.
So we got, we got to bugs right off the bat.
So this is good, this is pretty good.
This is good bug hunting.
I feel like we're we're not wasting our time with this.
Stepping we are, we are actually doing something useful.
All right, so we got font vs.
You've got those two that was just a typo there.
So when we add the character, we just want that to be fun glyph.
And then we're better, right?
Again, in a language with proper support, for discriminated, unions.
It would have just given us an error on that.
What you going to do?
We're not in one of those languages.
Woe Is Us.
I need to get back to where I was stepping.
I was stepping through here, like so, there's that first spot, we
wrote out.
Okay.
Now, that's what I expecting now, we're just writing out.
Glyphs we come in to write out this glyphs.
We're going to select the the stuff into our device context, so that
looks good.
So, what we wanted, we Memphis
Set the global font B which are also pointed properly.
There we do kind of our our standard stuff here everything's good.
Looks like we're writing everything out.
But let's get to the end there.
Get those aligned percentages set.
All right, so this looks pretty good.
Now I feel like this looks better and that's just the standard bitmap
running path.
So presumably that path is Not Unusual.
All right, so yeah, how we doing now, there's our test fonts
Seems like everything's fine.
And you notice the size went up or actually, I guess went down because
it didn't have to write out those huge tables.
Many times I guess.
I'm not sure why the size went down to be honest with you but it did
go down.
Probably.
Yeah because it have to write out those tables every time, I don't
know.
Anyway so the size is now 1 Megabyte used to be six and we know we've
removed some bugs.
Let's go ahead and double check the run and see where we're at.
We were still not loading but we might as well double-check and see.
Yeah, still not loading.
So now let's go over to our actual
loading code and see what we're able to load, right?
So see what comes out on the other end, right?
So we're going to skip loading the font for the moment we're going to
actually start by looking at just loading out of the file to begin
with.
And so I'm going to kind of Step through here and see when we do our
offset or bitmap ID offset.
That's really the only thing that happens in here especially so I just
want to see what that's going to be.
So when we hear, when we get to the first
Glyph in the file, right?
Or the, the array of glyphs in the file, that, that is the time when
it has to snap that offset.
So what it does here, that says, okay asset, count, 26, that's where
we actually needed to be.
It actually thought it was going to be indexed, to was where it would
be.
So, what we need to do is we need an offset, right of
If it's 26 and to wean off set of negative 24, right?
So let's see what we actually get as an offset.
Barf on bitmaps that is positive 24.
Yep.
Did the subtraction the wrong way around?
Oh he's good.
Well, maybe try to make an excuse that, that was at the end of the
stream.
I was kind of just randomly trying to go fast or something, but
honestly, I think that was just dumb.
And so here's the reason why that was dumb, you always know what order
your subtracts go in in terms of semantics.
Semantically speaking, you know, because the thing that you're trying
to go to comes first and the thing that you're coming from goes last
semantically, you always know.
That's true.
You don't even have to think about the math semantically.
You just know that's true.
I'm not trying to go from the asset index that I had to the asset
count.
What I'm trying to do is get to the asset index from
The asset cap, right?
We have our current, our current, when we're trying to get back to
what the what, the first asset index is right.
So, that's what we actually want to happen.
I think, let me think about that for a second to make sure that's
true.
You let no, I take it back.
I think I wasn't stupid semantically that is that is what it is,
right?
We're trying to get to the asset count.
From this first asset index, it's going to give us a listener to.
We had 24, ya know, my past meet know.
I absolve past me.
He did it semantically, right?
He's totally fine.
Right.
So that's good.
So it's positive 24.
That was just, that was actually just present.
Me being stupid past, me was fine, present me.
On the other hand could use some work, right?
So anyway, see as you get older, you get one day.
You get one day stupider.
So anyway, asset, count for type and all this other stuff.
Down here doesn't actually do anything related to the font stuff that
I could think of.
So I think really all we need to know is that that bitmap ID offset
was fine because basically whatever the asset county is that's where
the first one of these glyphs is going to get loaded.
And so, adding 24 to the values that come back is actually, what I
think we should have done, so that looks correct to me, right?
That that actually looks correct to me.
So what we do need to do now though is, we need to actually go
Go to bug that load that font loading code, right?
So where is that guy?
The bitmap load sound load font.
All right, so when we go to load font, okay, try that one more time.
Load fonts.
Well, apparently load font doesn't get called.
So that doesn't sound good if we want our font to be loaded, I'm just
going to go out on a limb here and say that we would need the font to
actually be loaded.
That would probably explain why it doesn't work.
All right, we probably never had any code to actually get the font.
Isn't that amazing?
Okay.
And we don't we just call get fine.
Nobody ever triggers a load.
Well so what we really want to do here is we want to go through our
render group, right?
So, what we want to do here is we want to go through our render group
to use that font, right?
And that's better too, because it's really the thing that should be
passing that generation ID, right?
So if we look at the render group, let's go in here and click our push
bitmap call for example, right in the push.
Call you can kind of see it doing its thing, right?
And what we want to do there is do like a push font I guess, right?
Where we basically say in this render group right now we're going to
use this font, you know?
Don't mind us.
What's going to happen, right?
So there's that font ID, there's the render group.
We come through here and say the exact same thing.
We were saying here, right?
Although actually well no, I guess that's right.
So we're going to grab that loaded font.
We're going to return the loaded font.
We're going to do a get bitmap call.
That's not true.
I'll get font call.
To get the actual font out, right?
We're going to see whether or not we have it.
If we don't have it, we're going to load it.
Right.
And yeah, I guess we'll sort that it doesn't run in the background to
make sure.
But then assuming that the font is there,
we're totally fine because we don't actually do any processing with
it, right?
So that seems fair that seems fair right load font identifier not
found, okay?
Let's see, load font immediate is immediate actually used.
So immediate is actually used here but even though we don't really
support it so we could have swore to meet.
We should go unify these soon.
There's too much boilerplate in here.
We'll do that right after we finish loading this font someone to
remind me if I don't do it.
Assuming, all right.
So load font, just needs to be brought up here.
I think, right?
Like so something like this.
That should do it.
And yeah.
Need to change that to a font ID certainly.
And this needs to be a font ID as well.
Here we go, load font actually Returns the font that it loaded or
something, what is it?
No, cannot convert our 24-bit message on Tidy.
That's a good point.
We are
So now let's try to make load font work.
Feel like now load font should work right?
oh, one last thing actually need to call would font I mean pushed on
and now we can get rid of this as well, okay?
Read endure grip.
There we go.
Okay.
So, here we go.
Are going to go ahead and load this stuff here.
I guess we'll just let it load first.
Hey look.
There we go.
So we're getting closer.
That's, I can't expand a actually be the right amount of space for
all.
I know, I don't think it is, but at the moment since we have not set
up the kerning tables properly, at least now we know we're a little
bit closer there to what we wanted to do.
So we're off to a reasonable start, so let's do that.
Let's let's start going checking on the kerning stuff, just to see
what's actually going down there.
When we actually use the kerning values here when we do get line
advance for
Sorry, when we do.
Get horizontal Advanced repair.
I feel like our Advanced X.
It's just added directly, right?
So all we're multiplying by the only thing we're multiplying by his
car scale.
And car scale is just equal to font scale when there's no, when
there's no control codes in there, right?
So I feel like, as long as font scale is set to 1, then we're just,
we're just using whatever those values are actually set to be.
So what I think I'd like to do is I'd like to go to the test as a
builder and actually pull out the actual kerning information that
makes sense.
Pull that out first and set that to what we believe to be correct.
And then go back and check the values so that were actually working
with something real.
So instead of TM Max care with where we're setting the horizontal
Advanced to just some random value.
I would like to.
Now start pulling out that font that font data
Right?
So in order to do that, it's a little wonky in Windows.
If I remember correctly.
It's that's not what I wanted.
I wanted the functions is that not forthcoming?
That's not forthcoming.
The help.
Used to be so good for Windows and then they made it web-based and
it's awful in that way, that everything that go ends up being
web-based is always awful.
It used to have a nice sink table of contents over here and all these
other good things and now it's just doesn't know that stuff.
Is there anywhere?
Anyway, I wanted to list of font functions.
That's, that's it right there.
So let's take a look at that.
I think what we want to do is probably get the widths and then we want
to get the kerning tables as well.
So, where are those think?
It's here?
Let's take a look, right.
So the get kerning pairs, which means the character
Paris of the currently 65 specify device context, that's what we want.
We say, how many of them we want?
If the font has more than that, it returns an error.
Okay.
And then it just comes back with that kerning pair.
Okay, does it ever tell us how many times he's referred as the number
cream?
Press return.
2500 awesome.
So how do we know how many it has?
How many how do we know how many kerning pairs?
It even has you got to tell us that.
I feel like you should tell us that because we want to get them.
All right?
I mean I want to know.
It seems pretty pretty obvious that I would want to know, does it come
in the text metrics?
Let's see, I don't see it in here.
I don't know.
So does it say, let's see in, get creating Paris, is it?
Tell me.
Let's see.
There must contain at least a nice structure specified by the end.
If this parameter is no, the function, returns a total number of,
okay, so I actually can get it.
I just have to pass null first, right?
Okay, so let's start doing this, right?
I need to know how many it's going to give me.
So first, I call it with completely bogus values, right?
I just say the, HDC which I have my Global thought context.
It's already been selected in there.
I need to send the number of students don't know, and I need to send a
null value so I can get it back.
So, this is the kerning pair count, right?
Then I need to allocate space to store that kerning table, right?
So I need to do kerning pair
And is get creating pairs in a w.
Kind of a guy.
I wonder.
I'm going to just do it that way first, even though, I don't know
that, that it actually matters.
But it'll give me an error if it's not if it's not an aw kind of
function.
All right.
So the kerning pair count that's now how many of those I need.
So here is my current a like hurting pairs.
I'll just allocate right.
However, many of those told me I needed
and then I will free them.
After we're done using.
Right after that, I can just get them.
So there's the cunning pair count, there's the crowning Paris.
Get all the kerning pairs.
And then I can Loop over them.
Right.
Okay, so then I just say d word, kerning
pair index.
and for each of those,
I will do something.
But what that something is, is going to depend on what the screening
pair thing returns, right?
So here's the current pair it, screening Paris plus the index.
And now we need to know what is that evident, right?
Okay.
Oh, Windows.
16, bits of you got to love people who don't use utf-8, right?
When we 16 bits of code point but that's fine.
All right, so we have the first and the second, right?
We have the, I current amount which is how many pixels it needs to be
to be adjusted by.
But what's it relative to the amount?
This pair will be current if they appear side by side in the same font
and size this value is typically negative because parent usually
results in sugars, being set more tightly.
Normal device.
That's a lot of junior size.
Depends, the current mapping mode, right?
So what we need to know is how far we would advance for a particular
character, first, right?
Which we don't actually know yet.
And so what we need to do, right, is we need to initialize this table
to be correct in that sense.
So yeah.
A little rough anyway.
What we want to do in here now is we want to go ahead and yank that.
Assuming that the pair is in range, right?
So if the the first thing in the pair,
Right.
And the second thing in the pear.
Are both in range.
So if this is less than whatever, my font code Point, count is, and
this is less than whatever my code Point.
Count is, then we're good to go, right?
First second good point Camp.
So assuming that the ranges are good, then we are good to go.
So then we would just use the first one this way, right?
Because that's the code point and this is the other code Point index.
Like so we would then know that, whatever that adjustment is.
I current him out.
We would subtract
That right.
So, basically, what this does is, it says, okay, for every pair which
which is saying it, Windows is saying, I need to adjust the kerning on
these two characters for every pair will look up where that pair is on
our table.
And we'll subtract well, I guess it said it would be negative so we
don't you subtract we just add the current value and if it's negative,
it will, you know, adjust it, right?
And so, what we need to do in order to finish this, that's really all
we need to do to extract the Korean Paris.
We need to finish.
This is actually initialize the
Table with something reasonable, right?
We need to initialize the table with how far Windows would think we
would advance for that character in the absence of any specific
kerning information because all of the kerning is given relative
To a default advance.
So the question is, what is that?
Default advance and I have absolutely no idea.
I think, oops, it might be.
It might be in here, right?
The widths of consecutive characters and specified range from the
current font.
Oops.
Maybe not get care.
ABC with, there we go.
Okay.
So what would that give us?
That gives us ABC.
ABC, be a BCC.
I feel like those could have been named a little bit better, guys.
I feel like they could have been
Okay, the a spacing is the distance to add the current position before
drawing the character glyph, the be spacing, is the width of the drawn
portion of the character glyph, and the Sea spacing is the distance to
add to the current position to provide white space to the right of the
character glyph.
Okay, so basically what we would want to do is add all three of those
together.
Presumably.
And then since there is a if there is an empty space spacing thing
going on there, then that means our ABC a value technically we want to
get that in the glyph thing and move the alignment Point backwards by
that spacing, right?
So we actually want to do two things with this.
If I'm reading that correctly, write what that says to me.
what that says to me, is this given me the data like,
It's given me the data like this.
A b c.
I might have called this pre post and width or something, but they
thought that ABC was the coolest thing to do.
Especially when you're in the middle of a font system where a b and c
means something man, way to go anyway, let's leave that annoyance
aside for the moment and just say let's go ahead and use this.
So when we go ahead and print one of these out, we're going to assume
that the Abe the a with is baked into the character.
So it's out of position.
It's going to
That a with over, that's what's going to put it.
So we want it we want to sum these together, right?
We want to sum the a with the be with and the sea with together
because that's the total amount of advancement that there's going to
be right.
So I'm just going to go ahead and give this a shot.
I'm going to say, maybe it'll work, maybe it won't.
We'll find out in a second.
So I'm going to say go ahead and get care ABC, widths, here, we're
going to again, use exactly the same process that we did before.
We'll get the global device context.
We'll use the First Care last care, which is going to be the code
Point Count Their right.
And then we will go ahead and take that l p.
ABC thing which is going to be a series of these, a b, c structs,
right?
So these are our ABCs now.
I know my ABC's next time.
Won't you sing with me?
Okay, so there's our ABCs, what?
I don't know is how you find out how many of those are, alright.
No, you don't, you specify how many there are?
So we're fine.
So we're totally fine.
So all we need to do is actually allocate some space for this and then
get rid of it at the end, which is pretty simple, right?
So here we go.
Here's our ABCs what we go ahead and Malik these guys, right?
Same way we were before size of ABC.
Time's the code Point count.
So that's that
And then we get rid of it later once we're in here.
What we need to do is set this to, you know, basically whatever
whatever the the actual width value that we want it to be is, right?
So for every code point we're just going to sum up whatever its ABC
set was, right?
So here is you know this ABC is just going to be whatever the code
point is.
We're just going to Flat set the entire table to start with, for that
character.
We're set the entire thing to just be whatever that
Is Right?
Which again was just ABC, ABC be
Like so.
Right?
So that should just about do it.
I'm going to convert these to float.
Since that's the way, we're storing our table.
And now I'm going to run it and see if we can get a table.
That's a little more representative of something, resembling anything,
or we could just crash, because crashing is also awesome.
Everyone loves crashing.
So that's good too, right?
Not exactly sure.
What the crash problem was there.
Oh wait.
Is this?
I want that to be a w though so that's actually W and w.
Okay, there we go.
And I don't know, are these ABCs are the ABCs A W thing as well?
I don't know.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go look because that would
also cause us to be allocating like two little memory or whatever,
right.
So I'm going to go ahead to do we have it.
SDK SDK director on here.
Microsoft sdks Windows, right?
Let's see here, I don't know where the stuff is.
That doesn't look useful.
That looks a little more useful.
Let's find out.
Work earning pair is starters.
I should probably show you guys how to do this with Dev Studio,
actually, because that can be actually a little more handy.
But all right, at the moment I'm just gonna take a look at her.
So kerning pair does not have a two different kinds.
Oh, there's an ABC float.
Well, excuse me.
So it looks like it looks like we're good to go.
So get kerning pairs W.
What's the difference?
These two functions don't even
They take exactly thing.
Why do they even have two different ones?
That's kind of weird, right?
Where's the get text ABC?
Where its function.
Let's take a look at that.
Just want to make sure test asset folder.
Let's see here.
Get Carrie, we see risk.
It care is ABC wits and there are two of those but they again, also
take exact same thing.
I don't even understand.
I wonder what?
I wonder what the point of that is not know why they broke those up.
Huh, well yeah, anyway no matter.
Let's go to bug the crash anyway, but that's just a little weird.
Not sure.
I understand the reasoning behind that.
All right.
So, what's?
Let's see.
We got our ABCs there.
We get our ABC with that seems fine.
We go through each of them in order there and compute our setting
values.
Let's go ahead and jump forward.
Interesting.
So it believes us to be writing off the end.
There is that actually true?
What exactly what did we do wrong?
We're allocating code Point.
Count, squared's worth of space for our horizontal advance.
I feel like,
That should have been fine.
No.
That doesn't seem busted.
That would suggest that this guy is potentially over writing the
memory.
See if that's true.
That is true.
So, this guy is expecting me to give him more memory than I gave him.
Oops, I should probably make that be consistent there.
Not that those values differ at all.
So that's interesting.
So this guy is writing off the end.
Why is he writing off the end?
We're allocating code Point counts worth of
He's?
Which seems like what he would want, right?
Is there anything in the docks about this?
A pointer to an array of ABC structures that receives the character
within logical units.
This array must contain at least as many ABC circus.
As there are characters in The Range specified by, you Frisk are and
you'll ask are parameters.
It's last care.
Not count.
So technically, this is minus one because it's actually using that as
the actual last care.
Okay, well, don't know why they did that but I guess that was just the
way it goes.
Usually I do one pass last count, specifically for that reason.
But so let's go over here and see where we're at now with the kerning
table, that's not entirely.
Bonkers potentially assuming we extracted it correctly, which I don't
know if we did.
Alright, so that looks a lot nicer.
It's still not quite right.
We got a couple of things we want to do.
First of all, we have to address that.
That giant space there.
And there's a reason for that that we should talk about in a second,
but talking about this.
What I would like to say is we need to do that thing with the ABC with
that, I said, we need to do.
We need to bake that a width in first.
So so let's go ahead and do that because, yeah, we are drawing the
character glyph right at our, you know, wherever we're trying to
Output the font, but they basically want to include some additional
spacing there if that makes any sense.
Right.
So we need to start getting a little more serious about that.
So, in test that set builder when we extract that glyph, we need to be
a little bit more.
Sort of.
We need to be a little more precise about that, right?
So what we need to do here is we need to do get care, ABC, widths
For this particular code point, right?
We don't actually need to allocate anything for this.
We can just say, we want the ABC for this guy and just just extract
one.
So be just the code Point itself, right?
And then pass just a pointer to that struck, since it only needs to
get one out so we can just go ahead and select the font into our
device context.
Go ahead and get the care ABC with so now we have them.
And now we know what that precept is going to be.
So we come in here and we do that font drawing and so that's all good.
And then what we need to do is when we come down to the end and we're
going to set up that align percentage, right?
We need to to change the way this works.
Instead of
One pixel in we're actually one pixel in plus, whatever the ABC with
is, is where where you would actually draw it, which means that the
alignment needs to be back from there, right?
See if I can show you what I mean by that, right?
So what's going to happen is we're going to have a particular location
where we want to draw the font, right?
This is the X Le x coordinate where we're gonna try to trying to draw
the font.
We're going to draw the glyph.
Windows is specifying a
Sort of a spacing, that's where that supposed to be, right, and that
spacing, you're supposed to move.
You're supposed to add before you start drawing the glyph.
You're supposed to add that spacing, right?
So that's that a that a with.
So what we want to do is make it so that the alignment point is
actually moved backwards from where it normally would be, which is
here move backwards by that - A so that then when we draw it here,
Just automatically gets moved forward properly, right?
So we're just taking all of that into that into the the alignment
percentage there right now.
There's another way we probably could do this, which maybe we will see
about second, might be a more robust way to do it.
I'm not sure which one is technically more, correct.
Probably, the way that I'm going to say in a second but let's just do
it.
Let's just do this for now.
For starters.
Okay, so let's build our assets assets have been built.
Let's go ahead and run our game and so now the kerning starting to
look pretty good.
Right?
It's not, you know, the world's best kerning but at the end of the day
Windows has awful kerning on all of its fonts.
I mean they're absent, the kerning is absolutely garbage on windows so
that may actually be correct.
I don't know what I would like to do is take a look just to see how
far off we are.
To see what would happen if I actually just picked this font that we
are using, which is Ariel right.
And I just said, yeah, give me aerial 128.
Let's see what that looks like.
And and see.
That's a little, well course, that's 128 points.
So what we actually need to do is find roughly what that's like in
pixels.
So let's see.
96 something like that?
Maybe there we go.
So I'm just going to take a look at what
Thinks the kerning should be by just trying to Ballpark it to be
relatively close, and then we'll see how are creating lines up to what
in theory is supposed to be the kerning?
All right.
Okay, so it looks like our kerning is well okay let's let's try to
size that so that it's as close as possible to the right size first.
That looks pretty close.
To me.
Yeah.
That looks pretty close.
So, if we take a look at what's going on there, amusingly enough.
Honestly, they're kerning looks like worse than our kerning, even
though we're pulling our kerning from their tables.
So like we're not quite exactly extracting the curtain correctly but
because Windows kerning is so darn bad.
You can't actually tell if that makes sense.
Let's try one with more egregious, kerning errors in.
It rendered group 2.
Output.
again just awful I mean that kerning is just terrible just straight-up
horrid but that's
That's what it says to do.
So we're pretty darn close to having correct support for the kerning
of the fonts proportionally.
Speaking,
and then we'll have to go find some fonts on the internet that we can
use.
Because oh my God, the kerning on this font is is just plain horrid.
You know, maybe segoe is better but I don't know if they, I don't know
if they shipped to go until Windows 8.
I know they had real font ographers working on so go doesn't mean they
didn't mess it up I suppose.
But let's see, let's see how the house to go condensed looks kerning
wise.
Oh, who just what is, what nobody wants to see that.
That's not a thing.
God.
Totally deflating.
Anyway.
Windows fonts.
Make a font Agra for cry.
Alright, anyway,
What I was going to say and we've got a few minutes left on the
stream.
We did what we wanted to do today, which is get that working.
But
Yeah.
That man just seeing how bad that kerning is, just gets me depressed.
It's like you had one job, right?
All you had to do was make it to the letters, didn't look absolutely
horrid.
When they were lined up in like the couldn't even do that anyway.
So all right putting that aside putting the absolutely grotesque and I
don't mean grotesque in the font sense.
I don't mean hoop.
I don't mean this protest which is fine right?
Grotesque is
Ali-A totally fine thing to call your font.
I don't mean that grotesque.
I mean this
Task, right?
I mean the grotesque which is like
which is commonly a repulsively ugly or distorted, which is what I
actually mean as far as the kerning is concerned.
So anyway, moving on from there.
The reason that I was saying is I don't think we're quite extracting,
the current incorrectly which is kind of a hilarious joke at this
point because extracting the current incorrectly from Windows means
that your kerning is awful.
But leaving that aside for now.
If we were going to extract the current incorrectly, what I mean to
say here is that when we do load glyph bitmap, what we're doing is
we're finding the bounding box of the font glyph ourselves right but
the bounding box of the font glyph is going to be offset from where
Windows thinks it was drawing the van, right?
Windows were telling it to draw the font x equals zero, right?
We're telling it to draw out there.
It's already included that a width, I suspect, right?
So it's already will do the pre step it'll draw the a here, or
whatever.
It's going to draw it, right?
And then we will go through and find that bounds ourselves, right?
Then we're adding the a with back in.
However, there's something that this won't capture if the font lift
itself includes spacing that's
Not in the a with.
So let's say, for example, we did that same process.
So, here's where we were told to draw the font.
Here is the a spacing, but now the glyph itself just starts over here
because we're searching for The leftmost Edge manually.
We will then clip out that space effectively, right?
Because we're only preserving this space.
So what I was thinking is maybe we'll just take the distance between
the edge of the glyph, The Edge, where we were, where we told it to
draw and where it actually Drew
Right?
We could try taking that and seeing what that actually is.
And we may have to write, we may want to do something a little fancier
there.
Let's take a look at what function were calling, and what it's thinks
that would do when we actually output text that way.
Right text out.
W is what's going to do that.
And so that, that was the thing that I wanted to kind of find out.
So let's see here.
So texts that W.
How will that actually output our fonts?
I don't know, it'll actually tell us.
Let's see here.
Interpreters of the reference point, depends on the context, line,
mode, and application can retrieve this mode bikes on.
Get text-align, can alter this mobile phone.
I said, text-align, you can use the following values for text
alignment.
Only one flag, me chosen.
So Baseline bottom top Center left, right?
No eight dates, EP RTL reading or update, CP.
So the Revit will be the left edge of the bounding rectangle, right?
Which I'm assuming is this
Yeah, of the bounding rectangle so I assume it will put it there.
I assume it will just put it there, right?
So let's let's
Let's just try.
We should probably do a structured test for this.
Maybe we should do this tomorrow because I think we should do a more
constructive test and see what happens because I'm just, I'm just not
sure what it's actually doing.
And so if we come in here to load glyph bitmap, when we actually get
the, the information out in the ABC with, okay, so there's an ABC with
of 10.
Actually, I just, I just lucked out basically, it's ten 10 nine,
right?
Because I looked out what I want to see now at a spacing an a spacing
of 10, when we actually do the text out, and we see where we, where we
hid, our Min, where was the Min?
It was at 10, so it's pretty clear.
It seems that, that, that a width is included, right?
So that's what that's the information I needed to know.
So what that means to me is, we could actually get rid of this concept
altogether.
If we wanted to, we could really just say, we don't need that.
That anymore, right?
And then when we come down here, what we do is we'd say, whatever that
minhwa X was right.
The Min X, oops up here, where we do that, right, that Min ex tells us
how far over we need to step.
That tells us what the alignment Point actually was right.
So, let's just, let's just try that and see how we do there.
Again, I don't know how much we really care.
Well, if we can go get some non Windows fonts basically because
presumably windows isn't loading truetype fonts wrong.
I mean, maybe they do that to, who knows nothing would surprise me at
this point but assuming that they're actually loading the troop a
place correctly.
Then if we just go get some non Windows fonts and load those, we could
maybe find some fonts that had proper kerning information in them,
right?
Who knows, maybe.
Maybe not.
So let's I should probably
I've gotten rid of my notepad that was a little bit premature.
I admit that
game update and render.
There's that font.
Let us switch it back to Ariel.
Like so here we go regular and take a look at what we see.
Okay, that's
That looks pretty good in most places were clipping a little bit, do
see that clipping there on the a, so some clipping on the A and that
looks like because it moves backwards, you can even see the insertion
point there.
You can see that the a moves backwards, can you see?
Can you see that?
Don't know if you guys can see that.
I don't know if we have zoom in, I feel like I got zoom in working at
some point.
Maybe I didn't go well.
Couple do it.
So can you see that?
How there's the a there, right?
And you see how were clipping off a little bit?
We'll check out where the insertion point is.
It's right at the clip point.
Right.
I don't know if I can actually I guess I can't visualize that but it's
so I think what's happening is when we do our text out it's actually
clipping on the text out when we're probably never seeing that.
So I feel like we should also do an additional thing.
Right?
When we do that packing, we should give Windows the ability to move
the font backwards to some degree, right?
So, we would want to have something in here that was like, you know,
Free Step X and just let it go, 128 characters in or something like
this.
So that if it wants to move backwards, it could I don't know if it
will
But I'm just going to try it.
I'm just going to see if I can get it to do that, right?
And so, then we do text our Exile, just say, hey man, go ahead, you
can go forwards there, right?
And then when we actually look in, cure will say, okay.
It's whatever the Min ex was is going to be, it's actually, it's
actually not the the Minix, right?
It's going to be the pre step, whatever.
That was.
We have to subtract that out from that from that Min X, right?
So if the
Next is further than the pre step.
That's fine, right?
If that makes sense.
So, yeah, I think that's correct.
That may still be wrong.
I will have to draw that out, and we're kind of out of time.
So I'll have to draw that out tomorrow and make sure we're actually
doing something reasonable there.
But yeah.
Oh dear.
That's not so good.
What happened there?
Oh, right.
The reason for that is we also have to expand our search radius by
that much.
So when we do our bound with whatever the size c x that comes back,
has to include that pre step X in it.
Otherwise we won't ever look right.
We should probably well,
So since is the asset Packer, we could just look over the whole thing
and be like doesn't matter right?
Well that was weird look like a drip properly and then it drew it
wrong.
Was that just me?
Did you see that?
Oh, some of them are wrong in some of them are right, is what it
actually looks like.
So, yeah, I did the priest up there, which is good.
So I assume that I didn't mess anything up.
If I just set it back to zero, right?
We'd still be fine.
So maybe I'll leave that, as tomorrow's task to get that working.
Yeah, I don't want to go any further into the Q&A.
So let's just assume we have some work to do.
In getting that that current extraction just right but basically I
don't think that should be too much else and then we're more or less
done with Van extraction and we just want to go do some things with
font ranges if that makes sense.
So let's go to the Q&A.
If you've got questions, ask them now.
Put a queue coal in front of them and I will try to answer them.
Robbie, could you use another text sample?
Like a vaw etat?
Yeah, I mean we could do whatever we want, right?
Where am I text line?
You wanted a vaw a Tha right?
Oops, didn't mean to do that.
Oh wow.
That's crazy.
I didn't know that about Ariel.
But I guess that is that is that my mess up.
Or is that really how it looks?
That's really how it looks.
Whoa.
So the slant on the W is different than the slant on.
The a is that true of helvetica?
Don't think I have a helvetic on here.
Ariel is based off of helvetica.
It's a really lousy version of helvetica.
I don't have a helvetica, I'm here.
Helvetica.
tubby, you a
Do they line up?
Copy image.
Gimp.
Kim Kim.
Come on gimp.
You can do it.
All right, so if one were to do so one word to grab you,
And paste you in here.
Okay.
That's how it.
We was in helvetica.
WoW.
Did not know that.
Know it now.
Learn something new everyday.
BK buggy, how do you know so much about fonts?
I don't really know that much about fonts but obviously since you
know, I work with Graphics, you know, a fair bit of my job is working
with Graphics.
You kind of want to know enough about fonts to make sure that you're
not doing anything, really stupid, you know?
So I just I know enough about typography to not make
Mistakes and in so doing, you're going to learn a fair bit, right?
You're going to learn enough to know.
Like okay, what are the, you know, what's kerning?
What's letting what's in the center with the D Center?
What's a ligature?
Look, you got it, you just just what you need to know if you write
font code, right?
So I don't really know that much about fonts.
Like I can't even identify fonts by looking at them you know like
people who know a lot about font they can just be like, oh yeah that's
a block because I can tell because I know fonts, you know,
Colonel Dragon, do you typically license fonts for use in games or
just a loophole about?
Rendering that to bitmaps mean, you can just use whatever you want.
I believe the loophole means, you can just use whatever you want, but
I will also point out that you actually have some pretty good options.
That you not even involve the loophole.
So Google fonts I believe are all licensed.
All of these fonts.
And when I say all of, I mean, like, there's seriously like 1,400
fonts or something like this.
All of this stuff.
There's just like a massive massive numbers of fonts in here.
Like these are all fonts.
Every single one of these is a font, right?
And as far as I know, all of these fonts are actually under a license,
which would just let you use them for commercial use.
No loophole required, right?
So I don't actually know,
Each font family directory contains the appropriate license for the
faucet.
Directory, the font file themselves, okay, let's sing an offshoot
metadata most of the fonts, use Sil open front license, right?
And so I think like I made us go into one all the ofl ones use the
open font license.
I think, right?
So there's the license right few tours, any person.
Well swing, but my first reaction conditions.
Now, the farmers are very visual components.
They may not be sold by themselves, they can be bundled or sold with
any software provided that each topic.
Hence the above copyright notice and this license, no modified version
of the fonts are used for.
Observe font name.
The name of the cupboard holes are the authors of the font shut up.
You two remotes 50 soon.
Parted and whole mood should be entirely misplaced.
That may not be sure under any other license.
So basically like, as long as you minimally comply, I mean, basically
all you have to do is just basically credit them and don't try to sell
the font by itself and then some stuff you obviously wouldn't do like
try to use the font author as a promoter of your product which I don't
think any game would ever really do.
So as long as you did those you can actually use any of these fonts
and be fully licensed even outside.
Of the u.s.
so you wouldn't even need to rely on the loophole.
So my guess is unless you have a really specific reason why you need
some other font, I would actually start here and see if you can find a
font that you would consider acceptable.
For use in your product because then you don't need the legal
loophole.
It's just, that's a font.
That's fully licensed to you.
Abner Cumbre is fonts a topic you enjoy.
I'm going to say yes and author once wrote, If Music is the subjective
application of physics than font, rasterization is almost certainly
the subjective application of computer science.
Do you agree?
I mean.
I don't know.
I don't know that that statement contains.
Something really to agree or disagree with.
It's very abstract.
Click the games.
Probably doesn't make sense to look at kerning for lowercase to
uppercase.
I doubt, many fonts bother with those cases.
Well, they should, right.
I mean, at the, very least, if you do not bother it, like, that's
really sloppy.
As I guess what I'd say if you didn't because what if your name is
like, you know, vandevander for example,
Well, you kind of wanted the end of the day to be current together
properly, right?
You don't want to just because your last name contains a mix right for
Deboer, right?
There's a lot of names that there's a lot of times when you write
things that have mixed case, you don't have to be a programmer to hit
that, you know,
But Times New Roman be any better.
I don't know if the kerning on maybe
James Woodman.
What are some examples of font typesetting systems that can do
kerning?
Well is new text, the only game in town.
Knuth stack is is probably one of you.
I mean, I mean, let's just, we can start with the fact that there's
multiple layers to it.
Like for example, your font may have ligatures for ffi but Windows
might not use them right?
And so there's that's because like the text control doesn't parse the
ffi and turning into the right code point, right?
So saying whether you do kerning well or not is at two levels.
There's like, do you do kerning well at the like mechanical level.
And then do you do kerning well-meaning like your default stuff, your
default printing, actually takes into account the right code Point
stuff.
And most of that is out of Windows is hands to some degree, because
you're not, it's not
Parsing your your text for you.
Write your kind of responsible for doing that.
So it's hard to say right whereas Tech because it's the whole system
it does that correctly.
Like if you do an FF I in Tech and the font has an SFI ligature, it'll
do the ffi ligature because it just looks and it goes on.
So it's typhus fi off, I go right.
but yeah, as for systems that typeset well,
And Duke earning well, I think Windows is kerning is probably not
awful under the hood.
It's more that the fonts they ship have really bad.
Kerning is my guess because I don't know that there's anything
particularly rather Kearney it's not great.
They are some things in there that I probably wouldn't have done the
way they did them but you know it's not like they don't have the
support, right?
So yeah, I don't really know what to say about that.
Specifically
Yeah.
BK buggy.
Hmm.
Good point.
More game designers should have a guy gal.
Who knows about fonts, because I see a lot of games where it's hard to
read.
Quest text chat text.
Yeah, unfortunately game developers are not known for their quality
typography skills.
That is true.
To be fair to them either as anybody else.
You would think that like web browsers would totally nail the
typography, their typography is often awful.
And so even people whose entire job it is to display pages of text
typically get it.
No.
Better than games do.
So I wouldn't necessarily point the finger at game developers but
could everyone stand to use a little bit more about fonts.
Yes.
Probably because it's one of the primary things we do.
I will see
When our game comes out for Molly rocket, it's got the best
typesetting system I've ever seen.
So you may enjoy that, it can do some pretty amazing stuff.
Abner Cumbre regarding the abstract text.
I agree, which is why I axe asked, given your experience, maybe you
could have read more into that, than I could.
Yeah.
I mean, it's one of those statements that's like, I don't disagree
with anything in particular but it's so nonspecific and there's so
many issues that it raises I, you know, I don't really know what you
know if that's what if I really agree with what they meant to say or
not, you know.
Robbie the down left corner of the a is cut, but you search bounds by
the pixels.
So why did this happen?
No.
So remember this.
I turned off that giving it the extra space.
Right.
That's what I was about to try and fix but we needed to do some more
work.
That was, where are we here?
That was the priest FX case.
And so what I believe is happening there is that Windows is drawing it
clipped because it doesn't have enough space.
So we need to like move it over into the middle of the bitmap so that
it can draw off the left side and then we can pick it up.
Quarter Tryin.
Have you played facade or and are met the designers?
No I have not met the designer as I tried to play it when it first
came out but it like wouldn't run on my machine or something like
that.
I think I mentioned this before.
So I'd like I'm aware of it and I saw you know, roughly what it did or
whatever, but like I haven't actually played it myself.
So yeah, Robbie tomorrow will be all about figuring out why our a is
clipped.
I mean, I think I already know why I is clip but it'll all be about
actually getting that to happen the way it should.
I think all we need to do is just get the free step thing working but
you know, we have to actually figure out what I messed when I did
that.
I messed something else up, right?
And I don't actually know what so that has to be fixed.
Yeah, I don't know what it was.
Because everything works off of men X here.
See, I don't know.
We'll find out.
We will take a look and we will find out is size.
CX used somewhere else.
No.
It's not.
So, I don't know.
I dunno.
Actually.
Yeah, the reason is because we were clearing everything to White.
Which we should not have done, we should have third everything to
Black.
So it was finding that white clear.
I think that must have been held it.
Let me ask.
So, let's just see that may actually be the bug, right?
It's a holdover from when we were testing things, probably
Yeah, so we were finding our own stuff.
We drawn in there.
Hey look, that's fine.
So yeah, there's bears are a is back correct now, so that's good.
Right.
It looks like RV might be clipped as well.
Is it also giving us the wrong Dimensions Envy.
Do you see how the V looks like?
It might be clipped there too.
Right, I want to see what happens with that calc.
Oops, not calc.
You guys see that, right?
It's not just me.
Okay.
Yeah, I can't I can't quite tell if that's flipping.
Oh yeah, the width is based off the backward side.
Man.
Oh man, these guys.
Alright, so yeah, I think we also want to expand the width, right?
So you want to do like the priest FX and the bound with actually
probably wants to double that, right?
We probably want like that, right?
So that we're going to search wide as well.
Because that with they're giving us back is totally bogus too.
So this allows her to be that pixels lot.
Now I don't know if maybe we should use the ABC widths to do that for
us so that we don't have just an ad-hoc constant in there, but now you
can see RV doesn't have that little clip.
Right?
And so that's that's a little bit better.
And that's looking pretty good, right?
I mean by good I mean awful but that's not our fault.
That's the fonts fault.
so,
Robbie you said Molly Rockets upcoming game has crazy font functions.
Can you say
Example about what about font.
Can you see one example?
What about fonts can be crazy?
Just wondering?
No, it's a surprise.
Quarter Tron.
What's behind the curtain?
What?
Curtain of this?
This is just the window.
It's just blocking out the light so you can see me, okay?
Garland.
Oh, Bloom facade was kind of interesting.
One time.
I type 0.
The first thing I said to the guy, when you open the door and he just
scowled, shut the door in my face and then the game faded to Black and
ended.
All right, not necessarily A high-quality store experience, but yeah.
It's a roguelike.
In that sense.
All right.
Looks like we're at the end of the questions.
So there's our current state of fonts, you can pretty good.
Actually, those are looking pretty good.
You know I'm saying feel like those are pretty good-looking fonts.
I hope we have I don't know.
I want to looks like I just want to make sure we have our Edge or
edges.
Correct.
I hope we do.
But yeah, that's looking pretty good relatively happy with that.
All right, folks, we will go ahead and close things down here and yeah
and we will pick things up again tomorrow, but that's pretty good work
today.
I think we are at the point where our fonts are looking pretty good,
pretty good fonts you know I'm saying at least as good as the
materials were getting
Can't can't Draw Font better than the thought you get.
So yeah.
All right.
Okay everyone.
Thank you so much for joining me for another sort of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home with the source
code, you can do.
So by pre-ordering the game at handmade hero dot-org, it comes with
the source code and I upload the latest version every night after
we're done working on it here.
So if you want to check that out you can do that on here made here at
or we also have a forum site.
You can go to which is a place to ask questions and you can also get
community pour some mac and Linux Community.
Anted episode guide, that sort of thing.
NG there's a patreon page.
You can subscribe to if you want to support the video series and we
also have a tweet bot, which tweets the schedule at you.
If you want to know when it's gonna be live.
And speaking of when is going to be live, we will be back here
tomorrow, same time, same place, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time right here on Twitch.
When we will go, double-check the kerning stuff just to make sure
that's okay.
And then, we'll sort of start broadening our fonts tough to handle
multiple, ranges, and just kind of get it better setup for language,
support, that sort of thing.
So we just want a couple days of that of cleanup and maybe the thing
we could
Do is turn back on stb.
Truetype
And, and make sure that we support the library path, for people who
want to use a library support that as well, because we did the work,
the most of the work for it.
We might as well finish that off.
So that's about it.
Thanks for joining me.
Hope to see you back here again.
Tomorrow, till then have fun programming and I will see you guys on
the internet.
Take these everyone