Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
This is the show where we CO2 complete gain live on stream on Twitch.
We don't use any engines or libraries.
We are actually in the process of creating an entire game from scratch
so that you can see the entire development process and know
absolutely.
Every last piece of code that goes into making a game run from the
engine up to the gameplay and everything in between.
Now, right now, we're in the middle of finishing up a change to the
way that we're doing assets.
He had some preliminary stuff in there that would just load assets off
of disk from BMP and wav files.
But now we've kind of made things a lot more Consolidated and we have
a way of building our own asset pack files, which can be easily
transmitted stored, sent traded anything else that you might want to
do with them and those asset files contain all of the data necessary
to run the game.
And in fact, you could have multiple asset files, it would merge the
assets together and stuff like this, and the ass.
The file itself contains all the bitmap data, all the wave data, all
of the metadata, that's required to know what those things are and all
sorts of other good stuff like that.
So that is what we have already done actually and really all we're
doing now is converting it so that our asset streaming system runs on
top of that instead of ever accessing the BMP and wav files directly.
We already did the port to it, but we loaded the whole file at once.
So what we're doing now is we're just kind of cleaning up the platform
epi
My things so that we can get that data asynchronously from the
operating system and not have to load the whole file startup.
That's what we're doing.
And that is what we are going to do today.
So if you would like to follow along at home and you have pre-ordered
the game on handmade hero dot org today is day, 1, 52.
And so if you want to unpack day, 150 ones source code into a
directory, that is what we would be programming on today.
So please go ahead and do that.
If you would like to follow along, if you would not like to follow
along that you just don't have to worry about that.
All right, so here we go.
Where did we leave things?
Well if you remember, we left things where we had almost finished,
porting everything over but there were a couple last little things I
wanted to do first.
So what I wanted to do was get rid of this old sort of notion that we
had to do what we were loading.
Because what I sort of pointed out was that the only reason we
previously had to have two different paths for whether we were loading
a bitmap or a WAV file out of in our previous asset system was
cuz we actually got data from those files like the dimensions of the
bitmap or the number of samples from the WAV file.
And so we had to have two different paths because we had to actually
know what we were working with.
Now that we've moved to the asset file, all of that metadata has been
pulled out into an upper level that we've already loaded.
So, really, when we go,
Get data, we really don't have to do anything.
We already know exactly what's going to be the layout of the data and
everything is perfectly set in place for us.
So what we can do instead is just use a single piece of code that just
loads bits off the drive, basically.
And all we have to do is when we know we need the bitmap, it's or we
know, we need the Sound Table, B just issue the same kind of a
synchronous load.
Either case to say here's the range of B.
Here's where I want you to put them in memory and that's it, right?
We don't actually need
Need anything else from that system?
So I already did that for the bitmap loading code, right?
It's this stuff right here and I already if zeroed that out.
So we're just running off of this sort of load asset.
The standard load asset work stuff, right?
So we already finished this in fast, we can just get rid of this.
I don't think we need it anymore for anything, so we already got rid
of that and we transition bitmaps to using this load asset work but we
haven't done yet is we haven't gone and done the same thing for audio.
So what I'd like to do is do the same thing for
Audio, get rid of this load sound work thing, right?
Just get rid of that and get rid of load sound work the function as
well, right?
So that load sound will work precisely the same way that load bitmap
Works where it sets up what it needs first.
And then it just goes ahead and issues the load for the data and waits
for that to arrive.
Okay, so in load sound work, what were we doing?
Well, we were setting up like the sample count and the channel count
and these sorts of things.
Again, I don't know that we need.
Need that.
Oh, well, I guess we do because we have that loaded sound.
We have this thing, so we have to copy those out of the HHA asset into
here.
Now, I do wonder why we bother copying these things out.
It kind of seems like, maybe we could just use them directly most the
time, but maybe that's not true.
We can cross that bridge when we come to, it certainly, it doesn't
really hurt to copy anything out.
So either way, not really a big deal.
So anyway, what we need to do first is we need to take a look at that
load bitmap function I guess.
And see all the stuff that it does, because we're going to want to do,
basically the
Same stuff that it does, right?
We're going to want to do this.
So in here, right, where we do this, this loud sound work.
Push, we're going to need this to turn into a load asset work push.
And so what's the stuff that stays the same?
Oops.
That's was a bit of a speedy jump there too fast for me.
So when we push one of these load assets, things on the task is the
same thing, right?
Nothing changes there at the assets.
Lots, it doesn't matter.
Whether it's a sound a bit map, slot slot, still the same the file
handle again is 0 just because we haven't done that work.
Yet of actually doing the file load stuff.
So we're going to have to if that's like the platform looking stuff.
We're going to be focusing on after we finish this the offset again.
No difference here.
It's just going to be whatever the asset says it's offset.
Is the memory size will compute.
And second destination is going to be steps, the sound sample data,
right?
So, that's going to be the we can even introduce a sound memory thing
here.
If we wanted to the final state is going to be asset loaded just like
before.
And then though the slot that we actually have here, right?
We're going to want to do that slot sound equals sound sort of a thing
where we kind of say alright and that point so that you're pointing to
the correct thing and we already fixed this stuff here.
When we when we did get bitmap, we already fixed.
Get sound to check to see whether or not the asset state was loaded
and if it was then go ahead and do it.
Now, one thing that I should mention here actually, I think this is
probably something we should do now that I think about it because we
kind of cheese to this.
It's a little cheesy and so I want to go ahead and uncheck use this
just slightly which is to say that really what we wanted to do was
probably something more like this because I did it with a ternary
operator, which is obviously more expedient but the problem of the
ternary operator is really we need to put in a thing here which is
that we want to complete previous reads before future reads here.
Right?
Because what could happen is the compiler could have moved this thing.
The compiler could move this.
Read up above this check and
And we would have an incorrect data situation, right?
So we don't really want that to happen.
We want to make sure it reads this thing first.
So that there's no possibility that.
This thing got red before it was completed, right?
And again, don't know that I have to think about that for a second to
determine whether I thought that was ever actually a possibility on an
Intel chip.
But remember, we won't necessarily only be working on Intel chips.
If we do Port this game eventually to something like Raspberry Pi or,
you know, any kind of like an Android device or something, that we're
going to be probably looking at an ARM device and armed.
Isis are potentially going to have something else, who knows?
Although I think they have strong memory writing as well.
So again, don't really know that we care about this, but I should
write it that way just in case because it doesn't incur any of a speed
difference here and this can just compile away to nothing if that
turns out to be necessary.
So that's fine.
Now, I'm going to go ahead and take a look and make sure that we
actually have one of those cause I don't think we do at the moment.
Yeah.
So, basically, compute previous reads before future reads would be a
read barrier.
We're here.
I don't actually know what that would be on on llvm.
So I feel like I'm going to put it to do here and say not sure.
I guess I can get rid of that.
Yeah, to do other compilers.
So yeah, I don't really know.
This is a full memory barrier and so I'm just gonna go ahead and put
that in here, but I'm going to say, you know, does llvm have real read
specific barriers yet?
I don't know.
So, somebody who works on llvm more often than I do, you know, could
could go ahead and tell us
If they've added something that would allow us to specify, hey this is
a reed barrier.
Not a right barrier guys.
Okay.
So yeah, that's all I wanted to check their I just want to make sure I
think that's a more reasonable thing to do because remember this is an
inline function.
So this could get this code could get slotted into something and get
rearranged all over the place and we really don't we really want to
make sure that the compiler isn't going to do anything speculative
ever.
I don't know that it really could, but since we're not checking the
value of slot,
I feel like it couldn't because doing that access it.
What if this was sort of saying whether slot was valid but it's
accessing office lat.
I don't know, like I said, kind of crazy but I feel like it just it's
safer to write things the the real way that you intend them to be and
put in the barriers when you actually think there is a barrier because
it really can't hurt in that case, right?
All right.
So back to our main back, to our main event here.
Let's go back to getting our load, our loads now
Working.
So what I want to do is I want to do is essentially the exact same
stuff here, where I'm going to pull out the info in, you know, and I'm
going to pull out the sound stuff like so.
And so that we coming here, all of this stuff will work properly.
I'm gonna get rid of all of this, right?
But I'm going to go ahead and add this push struct here.
I'm gonna keep that.
Where I go ahead and say, all right, my loaded sound.
Is going to be a new sound.
I'm going to do a push truck tan to the memory arena there for that,
and that sound is going to be what we set up here.
So I've got to initialize it to point to things that make some sense,
right?
And I also have to do like this computation here right?
Where I compute the memory size that it's going to take, right?
And then, when I actually do this stuff here again, I'm going to use
the exact same thing.
So now we're completely symmetric pretty much in how we're doing
everything I can get rid of that, because that's the same.
And that's that's really about it.
I think right?
I don't know why I'm not 100% certain.
Why?
This is down here.
Oh, I know why this is, this is basically, this is, you know, remove
this.
As soon as we actually load things, this is our little like, hey,
right now we're just letting the whole file start up to make sure
things are working properly.
So that's going to be the same thing here, where we're going to have
to sort of oops.
Sort of make that work out.
Right.
So okay, so let's put that though.
I kind of want to put that up here, I think probably and I'm going to
kind of put that up here as well.
Yeah, that looks a little bit better to me because of what we're going
to do in a second.
Okay.
So I think most of that's good.
We just have to start thinking about the sound now to get the sound
stuff, right?
And here's the loaded sound thing.
So some of its pretty obvious what we would do, right?
The sample count is
Going to come out of that info structure.
There's really nothing.
Interesting that's going to happen there.
The channel count is going to do it.
Exactly.
Same thing.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to Loop over those
channels and we're going to make sure that those channels are point.
You know, that the sample pointers Point into the right location in
memory for once we load it in.
So the first thing we want to do again.
So I just got to rearrange this here.
The first thing you want to do is figure out how much memory were
actually in a need for everything, right?
And so, we're going to want that channel count.
We're going to take the channel count, we're going to multiply it by
the number of
of samples because we know we have the same number of samples in each
Channel and then we're going to multiply it by the size of a sample.
That's a total memory.
We would need right.
Channels, time samples times that in 16, right times, that the size of
the sample,
Okay.
And since we load on a line from this thing, I don't think there's
actually even anything we need to do alignment wise, although, you
know, if we were going to start doing fancy things with alignment,
they would start doing them here.
Right?
So, that's the memory size that we actually need, which means that the
sound memory, that we're going to want, is going to be allocated here.
So, I'm going to want that, that push sighs.
They're going to allocate the sound memory.
Again, this is kind of just mirroring, exactly what was happening.
In load bitmap where we do the push size here to get it out of that
that assets Arena, right?
So we're just providing space for ourselves right?
And then what we're going to do is right after that because we're not
really going to use it.
We're going to go ahead and well you know what I could do?
Even I could just copy.
I could just straight-up copy this as well, right?
I could say oh okay, copy into sound memory, right?
Whatever the contents were here.
So I could I could actually make it exist in the right place in memory
to by just copying it out of the asset file and into the sound memory
location.
Now, I don't remember if we ever actually made a copy function I don't
know that we ever actually did.
We made a zero function right but we never made a copy function out,
think so like mem copy we don't actually have I don't I don't think
any way I could be wrong.
But I am not wrong, we just don't have one.
So if we wanted a simple copy function, again, probably not something
that we're going to use in practice very much.
But, you know, if we want to have one, it's pretty straightforward,
right?
We just have to have something for a memory index.
That's going to be the size to copy, right?
Then we need like a source and a desk like so.
And then we would just do something like the source I probably.
Do it like this, maybe where we just get it by pointer to each one.
Yeah, and the reason that I say, we probably wouldn't use this too
much or at least not.
A lot of cases where we might care.
The reason that I say that is because, you know, usually if you're
going to copy stuff, I would have a little more knowledge of what it
was.
We were copying and we would know whether it was aligned or not, we
would know whether it could be copied in like 128 byte chunks or not.
I'm sorry 128-bit chunks or not to make it faster, you know, stuff
like that.
So, you know, this is kind of, you know, a really just just sort of a
throwaway copy.
It's not something that we would ever call when we actually
Really cared how fast something was being copied, if that makes sense,
because we were in, in those situations, we would almost always have
architected things to know that we could do a very fast job without
even doing a checking.
We could do it very fast job doing the copy properly, right?
So yeah, so I'm just going to go ahead and do the dumbest possible
thing here.
You know, there you go.
That's that's mem copy, right?
Not a whole lot, not a whole lot to it.
You're just going to take two pointers Advance them by the number that
you wanted a copy and put one of the other, right?
So the majority of this function is just casting to au8 if that makes
sense.
Just so that we know we moved by B.
So yeah, we'll go ahead and do that copy.
And then we're going to Loop through the channels
like, so, all right, I'll take a look at the channel count and for
each Channel index,
We will have our sample pointer.
So the samples for that channel are going to be equal to whatever the
sound memory is currently at.
Right?
So
sound at and I guess I could just do this in samples, like so,
So, whatever the sound is currently at, I could go ahead and make that
be where we're pointing.
And then after we use one, we just Advance, however, big the channel
sizes, so we could say, like, you know, Channel size, equals sample
count, right?
Like that.
And so we just Advance my other channel size.
Yeah, so that that lines us all up properly for doing the load and all
of that good stuff and I think that's basically all we have to do and
so this can now be you know, down in here.
All right, so we've got sound memory, equals push sighs.
They'll that stuff we got to actually have the memory pointer.
Now we don't really need the memory pointer.
In fact, I guess we shouldn't bother with that.
I could just say void star memory goes push size, right?
And
Then use it like that because we really don't care.
So it doesn't actually matter because that we don't have to store what
that actually was.
It's only actually getting used here for copying and so on and so
that's going to do the loading.
Assuming that we didn't, you know, fudge it up.
That all sounds good, although I hear a little click Enos there.
I don't love the clicking - I feel like there's a little something
janky going on there, and I'm not sure, right.
I feel like there is a little click Enos, that's okay.
Because we probably should do some sound debugging.
There was some other thing that some was mentioning on the forums, by
the way, that we probably should take a look at some point.
So we might want to do some sound debugging there, but I just want to
double check here.
I want to see if there's anything specific that might be going on.
That I just recently, introduced sample count.
Let's see sound at memory that know that looks reasonably good
restore.
The sample kind of the sound?
Yeah, I don't know, I don't know that it's likely to necessarily be
there.
Yes, I thought that might be a mixer side thing, but I don't know.
We'll check that stuff out when we kind of go check out a couple
things in the sound mixer at some point.
All right.
So I think that's all we really need to do there.
I think load sound, work is not really necessary at this point.
We can kind of go ahead and get rid of it looks like, yeah, this was
doing exact same thing stuff here.
So there wasn't really anything else that happens in there because
that all looks good.
Yeah so that all looks good.
So now we've simplified things down
Quite a bit actually, right?
Because now we only have that one load asset work thing and we also
all of this stuff is now not necessary, right?
This is just all not used.
So, really what we're looking at here, just, you know, to underscore
kind of how awesome this is in terms of, you know, architecting
things.
Well, and getting a lot of bang for the buck.
Is what we've basically got now is a filed that's five hundred lines
of code that does streaming of bitmap assets and sound Assets in the
background including streaming music.
For 500 lines of code and it matches tags so you can have arbitrary
descriptions from the game to the asset system, right?
That's 500 lines of code.
That's pretty darn great.
Considering the fact that some of those lines are also about to go
away because I'm about to simplify this a little bit further when we
no longer have to do the old reading and memory thing.
Oh and hey guess what?
These guys are also gone to right because those all moved to the asset
prep.
So there you go.
430 lines of code for the entire asset streaming system.
Background loading streaming music.
That's pretty darn.
Awesome.
I have a feeling that if you were to look in a commercial engine, it
would not quite be so straight forward, anyway.
Okay, so let's figure out what's going on here.
In terms of the best way to move this, now, to actually reading data
directly from the platform, right?
Because you can see, we pretty much already wrote the code for it.
We just have to go Implement.
You know what has to happen there on the window side of things.
So if we were to take a look at this, what would happen is, you know,
Would any what I could also do?
I could do a copy here of the bitmap memory to get rid of the the
over, right?
So something like this, I would say that and memory size also this
would let me check to make sure our copy was working properly, which I
don't actually know that it is right if our bitmaps look screwed up.
Yeah, so there's definitely a bug in the Audio.
I can hear the click.
So we know there's a bug in the audio.
We definitely have to.
I'm going to put a little to do there.
That's something we should do.
As soon as we're done with this stuff, I would doesn't need to be
attended to now, but if we definitely should do it.
Fix clicking bug at end of samples.
It could have also been something we introduced in the asset
processor, right?
Because we don't know that we were actually clean to the asset
processor.
We haven't really tested hardly any of the stuff, right?
You're right.
We're just kind of putting it all in place and saying, okay,
everything works.
Right?
And now maybe we had to go through and and find the little lurking
buggers.
All right, so everything looks good.
Here we've got the copies and place and they can just be removed.
So basically, what would
In fact, we could just do this, we could do this now.
So if we just go ahead and remove these guys, right if they just go
away, we'd be left in in Terror land where we're actually using the
assets, but we don't have them, so they're just blank or whatever
they're going to be right.
And so that's fine.
But the game still runs just fine.
So now what we need to do is figure out how to get this stuff to work,
right?
We need to have we need to get this stuff to work.
And the way that we need to get this stuff to work is, we need to be
able to actually get these file handles because you notice what
happens if I do now.
If I run it now is will just crash because we don't actually have file
handles, right.
We've just got a zero sitting in there for the file handle so there's
no right.
It's as soon as it tries to actually doing the file handles, never
even going to get to the stub calls in the file layer.
It's just going to crash as soon as it tries to to do you reference
that.
So, what we need to do is figure
Out a way to actually get the file handle here to actually get that
out, right?
So,
in order to
that what we need is, we need to be able to grab the asset and get the
asset to have a
An index to says which file it came from.
Right?
And so I think like I said before, what I realized after we wrote this
and I was saying this, as we saw, it happen is when we load the tag
array, the tag array is totally awesome because it just flat loads
directly in and we can use the tags directly.
So tags, just load directly in its good assets.
Since they need to refer to tags, that doesn't really work.
The assets have to be re based their values have to be rebased with a
point to the correct place in the
You're a right and that's what we were doing right here, right now you
can see us adding that tag base in.
And so what I think I'd like to do here is I'd like to say, okay, so
what we saw was that h.h.
h.h.
a tags are correctly loaded you know, are correct to be loaded
directly but assets that just didn't work, right?
That was not.
We know we tried it again, like, electrician things.
I say we got a try.
We got to see what's going on.
And we saw that really assets, they change contents as they move from
the drive into memory.
And so, what we've got to do is we've got to make the asset structure,
I think we want to pull it back from having it be its own thing.
And we want to kind of make that be something that actually lives in
the correct.
You know, in the correct sort of lives in a different state.
So what?
I don't know.
Now and you can understand my dilemma here because I don't really have
A lot of information to go on.
Well, I don't know he's does it make sense to make a new asset struct
or should it just be part of the assets lat right.
And I really don't know because it's hard to say you know, whether you
want to actually have the assets lot bother to have, you know, any
more information and do we ever actually access that, info part, the
stuff, the the tags because I'm saying is the tags were sort of out
asking for a separately.
So I kind of figure out like I think I want to leave a
set as a separate thing because it seems like the times that we're
using asset are not the same times that we're using assets, lot.
There's only some occasionally when they're used together.
but a lot of times they're just not
Like when you're looking for an asset, you never look at the assets,
lot.
You only look at the actual asset itself to see what the tags are.
And so that whole walk is walking a bunch of assets.
I don't need to pull in their slot and their pointers.
We never need to look at that, right?
So I feel like I'm going to do it this way, right?
And then you know I'm going to have the first tag index here and I'm
going to have the one pass last tag.
I index
And that's fine.
And then what I'm also going to have is I'm going to have the, the
file Index.
Right?
So what file did it come from?
So that way, when we need to load it, we actually know which file
we're going to load it out of right.
And that seems like something that's that that we would want to know.
Okay?
So we also need to know.
It's data-offset, right?
And then we've got some kind of a little straggler here, you know?
We've got some kind of a like, well, we've got 32, you know, we got a
64, and then a 64, and then a 64 we need we need like something else
here.
I don't know if this is pad preserved.
You know, I don't know that there's anything else we need to actually
store there but that's what's going to happen.
So anyway, here we go.
We're going to grab those assets out.
We're going to copy out the data that we need.
So there's data offset.
Right.
And I should put the file next up there.
So there's the data offset.
There's the file index and we know the file index because We're
looping over the file, so we just, we've got that right.
We know exactly which foul came from.
We know the data offset because that's from the AHA asset that we are.
You know basically pulling the data off the drive from
Like so, yeah.
And and really
We're wait a minute, right?
So we actually didn't have this guy yet because we were, it was the
same dude, right?
It was the same, dude.
So what we need to do is this, we need to First make that, you know,
get that ha asset, which is the HHA asset array plus the asset index.
Yeah, for this array.
So this is a little bit, it has a little bit more Funk to it, right?
There's a little bit more Funk there.
So basically this is it looks like this, right?
I believe.
So we're going to iterate from 0 to the number that are for this
particular asset type, right?
And the index for that, in fact, I think probably we could get rid of
all of this notion entirely here and just say it's at like that,
right?
It's the asset count comes in.
Like so, yeah, yeah, that looks kind of better to me, right?
Yeah, sir that's account is less than assets us account.
This could be less than or equal to though I feel like then that would
still be valid so I'm not sure what was that.
What was going on there?
Why would this always be less than?
Does that make sense?
I don't understand that because wouldn't this be equal to asset count?
When we were done and how would this, how is this assertion?
Not firing?
You know what?
So this was just wrong.
It's because we hadn't run this path yet, right?
That's the only reason,
I was working at all.
Because this is we had not run this path yet.
So yeah II assert myself that this was just bogus and never would have
worked.
So really what we want to do is assert this, you know, up here
something like assert that the asset count at the moment is less than
the asset count now and then we increment it and say okay that's the
one we're actually using and then we get rid of this, right?
So that way we're kind of stepping through the thing and going okay
for each of these assets, we're going to fill it out and we fill it
out in here and that pretty much gives us all the stuff that we
actually wanted file index.
What is that one passengers and the pad?
Which we don't care about?
So yeah, that's a little bit more what we want.
And then what we need to do is we need to have the hahha asset array,
which we would use just a load these things into a temporary place,
right?
We're just loading them as temporary information.
Because we don't actually have not actually block loading them into
the HHH.
H.h., a asset array anymore because we don't have a giant hhas a
direct.
Yeah.
So what we would do here is say, okay, we're going to read that data
and we're going to put it in the AHA asset array like.
So and that HHA asset array is going to be something that we need to
allocate as temporary memory, right?
In fact, we only really need it for right here.
So basically that's that's it would be could literally happen right
here where we just do like a push of the temporary, and then we would
do a pop down here.
So we would do in temporary memory.
So basically I'm just need, I just need something to hold these guys
while we read them.
So I'm just going to go ahead and actually create this h.h.
H.h.
a asset.
It's kind of
Alpha, I should have picked things that are easier to say on stream,
you know what I mean?
But yet, so I'm going to begin the temporary memory.
I'm going to go ahead and get that array.
And that's just going to be, you know, enough room to store these
guys.
Exactly.
Right.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And obviously I should probably just use the transient Arena because
that's exactly what it is for.
So it would probably be you know, trance State Tran Arena, right.
Let's see here.
Where's that at asset array?
So, there we go.
And that's really all I would need to do except for the fact that I
don't remember how I wrote begin temporary memory in this one.
I guess that's how we do it temp them.
So and that would do it and temporary memory and Men.
Yeah.
Okay, so moving news.
Sing along, we need to kind of look at what other stuff was going on
in here.
That might be necessary for the asset.
Right?
So if I look at the file format hhas, at let's see what's actually in
there that we might need.
So we have the bitmap and the sound info, and we still need that that
information, right?
So, yeah, I feel like I guess actually, so all of this stuff we still
need, right?
Right, so, I guess I could also do it this way to avoid having to
bother like, knowing all the stuff that was in there.
Exactly.
I could just say that the asset just has one of these, right?
And then, has the file index or something, right?
So it's just on augmented guy or something like this, right?
And that seems like something we that that's kind of back to the way
that we had it before and that just basically allows us to add more
stuff in there, right?
If that makes sense.
So let's take a look.
So that would just be again going kind of back to what we were doing
here where we you know had a little bit of a yeah.
So I guess I would do like that.
And then wherever it wants HHA asset.
We just do asset.
Aha like that, right?
Only now, we can also get it.
Our file index, which is sort of the information.
That's not the same as the what's in the file, right?
Oh, and I would have to actually access the handle so I guess I would
hear go.
Hmm.
How do I want to do that?
I guess I would say.
Well, I guess I just get it directly always, so I decided to get file
handle for something like that, right?
Where I just get, get the file handle.
There we go.
And that would just allow me to check it.
That's really all I was interested in.
There we go.
And now hopefully you guys can see this.
I mean, if you hadn't, you know, if this is, you know, if you haven't
been watching every day, then this probably won't be something that
you just really noticed.
But you can see I kind of went back and forth on one part of this
architecture, right?
Like whether or not the HSA was embedded in a set or whether it was
not whether the separate one or not, right?
Look we did a couple different ways.
We did it both ways with the tags, we've both the assets and I've kind
of settled on looking at the actual requirements or what had to
happen.
It became obvious like what what the types actually were, right?
Right.
It became obvious that like, okay, we actually process it process
assets as we load them, but we don't process tags.
And so that tells me the thing that it is that I actually needed to
know right about how to do the architecture.
And again, that's why, you know, that's why you do it this way.
That's why architecture should be experimental.
Not design a front because design up front, you're never going to get
all those things.
Never ever, ever going to get them.
I've never seen any programmer, the very best programmers.
I've worked with never even try to do that sort of stuff, because they
know it's
Simply not possible.
And so you never ever want to like think that you're just going to
think of all these things up front.
You can just try a couple things and make sure that you know, your
coding style is fast and fluid.
You can go through these experiments and then just don't, you know,
calcify the code base until you know, that you're happy with sort of
the way things seem to be flowing through it.
And then you're at a good place, right?
So, yeah.
Okay, moving on, let's go ahead and finish this stuff up here.
So that's HHA.
That is also an ha.
What else we got here the assets, right?
That's going to be well, this this guy is going away.
All right, we don't have this anymore.
In fact, we don't have any of this stuff anymore.
That's all going away.
Goodbye HHA, contents.
And so now what we've got is we've just got this get file handle for.
It's a kind of obvious function, right?
Get file handle for is just taking whatever the file index.
Is it's going to look up in our array of files, which is right here,
right?
So it's going to take that assets.
And a file index.
And first you know, I mean we want to just assert the fact that you're
not trying to access a completely bogus file handle.
Right.
So will assert that file.
Index is less than assets file count just to make sure
And then, what we want to do is go assets, files file index, that file
handle it just handle showing that handle is the thing we actually
wanted to return?
Oops.
So that's it right?
Nothing particularly fancy going on there but that gets the file
handle.
Yeah, what did I oh, it's game assets.
Sorry my bad.
yeah, so that
Too many different asset.
Assert sorts of things.
That is basically that I don't think I have much else.
I want to do with that.
And so now if we assume that when we actually loaded the files,
We were actually going to get their file handles, I think we would be
good to go and so, I think we can now start to work on this code in
Earnest and actually get it to be working.
So yeah.
Can I convert one for married to a star that's totally reasonable.
Here we go.
Data-offset, right?
These are part of the AHA now.
Like so, and now we don't really have to do anything particular here.
We can just sort of do something like this, right?
And then we can just rebase those.
X.
So now whatever we were going to have in the AHA.
We copy over and then we just rebase just the tag portion of it.
And so I think that's just about all the things that we would actually
need.
Unfortunately this code is we have no idea if it's any good or not?
Right.
We don't really know anything about this code, we don't know.
We haven't ever run it.
It could have tons of bugs in it.
So we're pretty much going to have to do something a little bit nasty
here which is we're going to
Have to do this sort of doubly, unsure, right?
Because we've got this code which we just kind of wrote as the usage
code.
We don't know if it's got its own bugs, right?
Mistakes.
I made typos or just logic errors.
Whatever?
Right.
We don't know if that works but we also won't have any idea whether
our platform file IO code works.
And so when you're doing something this, you have a couple choices one
is, you can choose to try to test one of them.
And so in this case, what we could do is write test code to test our
platform, reading code.
Another one is you could choose to try and test this outer coat but
that would be pretty particularly difficult.
I think, right?
So pretty much you test the file code when you're sure it was working
properly, then you'd move on to debugging this code.
But what I'm probably going to do is just do the whole thing and debug
them together.
And the reason for that,
Because the file code is so simple, that I don't think I'll have
trouble verifying that it is working as we debug.
And so what I'm doing is I'm making a judgment call, I'm making the
Judgment call that the time.
It would take me to write the test code to test the file IO is longer
than the amount of time.
It will take me to manually verify that it is working as part of the
debugging process, right?
And so a lot of people ask about test-driven development and that I'm
just trying to give you some background into how that works.
If your default answer is always one of the other, then you may waste
a lot of development time doing the wrong, one of the two, right?
And so, you kind of have to make judgment calls about those sorts of
things, and determine what your priorities are and what your goals
are, for any particular step in development, and that is really what
informs you as to, whether you should write a test or not, not some
kind of dogmatic thing of like, you should always do test for you, we
shouldn't do test or something like this, right, tester.
Tool.
And you always need to think of him that way and they give you certain
benefits, and they have certain drawbacks and you need to just like
make that trade-off just like everything else in programming.
It's all about the trade-offs and knowing how to make them effectively
and efficiently.
All right, so let's go to handmade platform.
I've actually guess we don't need to do.
We already did the spec work.
So let's go to handmade win32, handmade and implement the functions
that we have not implemented yet, right?
Because we basically spammed out.
These these functions right here with three, if you get all files of
type, begin went through to get all files of type end with three to
open file win32, read data from files.
Can win 3-2 file error, right?
So those were our functions that that were at the platform layer was
using.
I'm sorry that the platform nonspecific code was using to call down to
get file stuff.
We need it.
And so we want to do here is we want to actually Implement these so
that we can, you know, we can actually do exactly what these files
were supposed to do.
We'll do a very simple version of it first and then we'll make a
slightly better one in terms of implementing it in its completeness,
I'll show you kind of what
I'm thinking of they're all right.
So we already know how to do this stuff because we already wrote it.
All right.
We just wrote it in different way.
So here you see we have debug platform read entire file.
So really, all I really wanted to do was have, you know, debug
platform read.
Entire file was really mostly what we actually wanted to have happen,
right?
So when we call win32 open file, right?
Really?
All I'm going to do is split these into two pieces.
So, we've got the one here where I'm going to go ahead.
Read the file like this one, for example, right?
We've got this.
We've got the read file stuff happening.
There we go.
And we've got sort of this with three to open file stuff happening.
So what I want to do now is I just want to go ahead and make win32
open file do just the just the file open part of things and then I'll
scroll through got the clothes handle here which I can go ahead and
and put in, you know what, we Never Close Our file handles.
like,
We just don't because we keep them up in forever.
So I feel like we actually don't need clothes handle.
I could do a thing here.
Just a note, right?
That we have a close handle here, in case we want to do it at some
point in case you want something that clothes.
Like, I don't think it's like some kind of update in place, sort of
thing.
But anyway, so we have like open file, right?
We just have went through to close file or something like that, and it
would be, you know, something like this.
But for now,
We don't actually want to do that because we never close our files,
right?
Okay, so in with today, to open file, we go ahead and do a crate for
create file on some file that we're trying to open.
We check to see whether we've loaded it and we get the file size.
Now, I want to go ahead and look at him a platform and just see what
it is that I'm actually supposed to do.
I return a platform file handle I guess.
And I guess we never need to even know the size.
So really this get file size.
E^x thing is really not relevant.
We really don't need that.
And so really the entirety of what we're doing is just this file
handle thing, right?
So I'm just going to define a struct here, which is the platform file
handle struct for win32.
And so what I'm going to do there is I'm going to put in the handle,
right?
This is the win32 handle for our handle, you know, basically it's the
colonel handle for our handle.
We have kind of like a two layers of handle essentially.
And then we also have an error code, right?
Like had error something like that.
And the reason that we have to do this, right?
I guess I already kind of spec this out, so enough to do that.
So here's platform file handle, hears that struck, right?
So what I can do is just just put that in here.
So we know that we have like the the regular this is this is sort of
the the generic part, right?
If you will will just I don't know what we want to do, call that H.
And then we have the win32 handle down here, right?
So we already have the has are a stuffed spoken for basically.
So, all I have to do here is I go.
Okay, I've got the result.
The result is going to be a platform file handle, right?
And we'll just assume that it's, you know, nothing.
And then we're going to return.
All right and I suppose you know another thing I could choose to do is
I could change the meaning of has errors.
I could I could make the meaning of Hazzard as actually be that it
doesn't have arrows so it's initialized to 0 meaning that we don't
know if it's right yet and then we set it to True when we load it and
I kind of like that.
So I think I might say that's actually no errors like that.
I like that a little bit better.
Yeah, I kind of like that a little bit better.
So what we do here is we assume that we have an error which is that we
couldn't load the file, right?
And then if we actually can then that is when we would set the result,
no errors, right?
So we can do result, you know, win32 handle, we can do it like this,
right?
And we could set, I guess we could set it like this.
Something like that.
And that makes this kind of really nice.
Very, very simple function, right?
Nothing particularly confusing going on there.
Very, very clean, very simple, right?
And these guys would all operate on one of these things like so.
And when we return, the result, we wouldn't return.
This whole result.
Obviously, I guess this is actually what?
Well, you know, what?
This would actually have to be an allocation, right?
Because we need to return a pointer to that thing.
So we actually do need to allocate this, you know, basically from from
our win32 heat or whatever, right?
So this is actually something like a heap, a lock, right?
Where we just going to grab some memory?
That's win32 specific, and it's not memory that we're ever going to
give back, you know, if that makes sense.
It's memory that its memory that were
Yeah, that we're never going to get back.
Because we never close the file handle.
If we did, we would get rid of it.
We could also use Virtual alkanes said since that way, we keep it to
just using virtual lock normally, you probably wouldn't use Virtual
Alec for something so tiny.
But again, just to keep it to since we didn't bother writing any kind
of generic stuff in here.
There's really no reason why we couldn't do it that way.
It's totally fine to do it this way, right?
But the reason for that is going to take up a ton of memory just for
this simple file handle.
And so that's not something you would normally do if you if you were
actually going to be doing anything fancy here, right?
Right.
so,
I can put it to do there as well, which is that if we want someday
make and actual Arena used by win32 to subdivide out that space.
But again, don't really care about that.
It's not really relevant, it's never going to affect anything.
Because the number of file handles is going to be pretty small, right?
You know, on the order of 10 would be a large number of asset files
for us to process.
So that doesn't seem particularly particularly interesting either way,
right?
So that's fine.
And we can go ahead and do our win32 handle stuff then at that point
assuming that the result actually worked out, right?
And then of course we can cast this because it is a platform file
handle.
Because that's what begins with.
All right, so that looks all pretty reasonable to me.
We've got the allocation
And like I said, we were about 12 minutes over.
I think when we started.
So we want to go to 612.
That would be an hour.
So that's all good.
I think that's fine for reading into that file handle their, I like
that.
We then do read data from file read data from file is going to assume
that it got one of these, right?
So it's again I'm going to go ahead and look at the at the platform
here to see what exactly this gets what it takes us.
It's a parameters.
So, when we do
Read data from file.
We have a source here, right?
So I'm going to go ahead and do handle equals source.
Like so and then we've got the offset and the size and so on, right?
So what we got to do here, we've got two steps.
Like I said, we've got to do, we don't need allocating memory or
anything.
We're just going to read like this.
And when we do the read file, we're going to do the the file size,
right?
So we're going to do the size and then we're going to do the the
offset we have to do as a Sikh, right?
Like we actually have to do a seek to get that.
Because right now read file works exactly the same way again.
Horrible Epi is when you it's really a bad API when you have a
location in a file that you have to use.
Remember I talked about this with every and that sort of stuff.
So we want to do is we want to do a read that has an offset in the
size.
So really read file is not quite what we want or rather this method of
calling read file is not exactly.
We want what we want to use is actually the overlap Tayo.
Parameter.
So, let's go back here and we didn't talk about this when we
originally did it, because we didn't use it.
But if you take a look, read file has this thing called LP overlapped,
right?
And the lp overlap structure, is a structure.
You can optionally pass in and you can actually use this to specify
more stuff, right?
And what's interesting about it is, if you look at the overlapped
struct, what did
Actually has in it is it has the offset from which you would like to
read the data.
Okay?
And so even though read file in its normal incantation does not let
you specify where you want to read the data from.
If you actually use the overlapped portion of it, which is normally
used to kick off background reads, right?
If you actually use this portion of the win32 API where you pass the
overlaps truck, you can get the correct API for file reading out of
it.
So again, yeah, it look, may look at first blush, like the colonel
Windows kernel, didn't implement the right file, read API, but they
actually secretly.
Did you just have to know about this overlapped guy at the end here,
right?
So what we actually want to do,
Is we actually want to use one of these overlaps trucks.
We want to set the overlap structure what we need.
So we'll go ahead and say overlapped, you know, struck here, clear it
to zero and then we want to set our offset in our offset high, right?
So we want to set overlapped offset and overlapped offset.
High like so.
And so those are going to be those.
This offset that we have here.
Remember this is a 64-bit value.
So what you want to do here
No, is we want to basically take this thing and mask off part of it,
right?
We want to say, okay, the low part of it is just going to be, you
know, the value masked off the high part of it is just the value
shifted down by 32 and then masked off, right?
And that's how we would get that.
And then so if we take a look here at what's going to happen, you can
see it says, you know, okay we've got a point overlap, a parchment
over the structure is required if was with file flag overlap.
We are not actually doing that so we don't actually care about that.
If the H files open with overlap, it point to a valid unique overlap
blah blah blah.
We don't care about that because again, we're not using it for
background stuff just yet for an h-file that supports B offsets.
If you use this parameter, you must specify a byte offset which to
start reading from the file device.
Also survived the off,
And also at high is what we set and for an eight felt it doesn't it
doesn't matter.
But obviously this h-file does that would be if you open like a stream
or something but assuming you open a file on disk it obviously has the
ability to seek around so that's fine.
And that's all we really need to set.
So basically we can go here and do H file L buffer.
Right, we could sell this stuff.
Exactly.
We used to except now we can set that offset and offset hi.
So we don't have to worry about seeking which is what we would really
like to avoid.
Because we want this to be multi thread safe, we don't want to have to
issue SQL.
Commands that might seek somewhere and then have some other thread try
to seek somewhere else and read at the same time which would be a
disaster, right?
So that's all good.
We've got the destination where we want to put it.
So the only sticking point is the fact that windows cannot do Reed's
bigger than 4 gigabytes.
Don't ask me why?
I just know that they can't and so there's actually you know just this
thing.
Are we will probably have to do the same operation that we were doing,
where we safe, truncate down first and say, okay we're going to
change.
We're going to assume that will never actually get something that's
going to be too big for us because chances are no asset, no
individual, no assets, no individual asset in the asset file should
ever be that large but you know, we'll leave the possibility open that
someday there would be and
Then we just have to upgrade this winter to platform layer to handle
it, right?
So we're going to a safe truncate there.
So that we know that, you know, will get in assert if we ever try to
push that boundary and some bad way and then we will go ahead and keep
the rest of it.
Yeah, as is basically, so this right here, file read succeeded, right?
And this right here, is means that we've got an error, right?
And so this is going
to be something where we set the error in the in,
in the actual, where's it go?
It's went through.
Thought it's this guy right here, right?
This is where we're actually going to call ourselves and just say
there is a file error, the file error was on this handle and it was
that read file failed.
All right, so that's what happened.
Whether you do file error is really not doing anything at the moment.
It's really just saying that that that no error is function, right?
You can see again in platform here.
The only thing that was supposed to do when we did file error, is it
supposed to take the handle and what the message was?
So, really, all we're doing is, we're nearing the message for now.
Although we could do an output debug string, right?
Of the message.
If you wanted to something like this, you know, if handmade internal
You could output that.
Something like this.
Right?
If we happen to be the internal build, we could speed up the video
Port later on, we have more debug information, maybe we'll do
something a little fancier there, I don't know, but what we do know is
that no errors is going to become false, there will now be errors as
soon as you call this function, even once there's an error on the
stream, right?
So that's over.
now, what we also could do here, again is say
Errors we could say platform file no errors on the source and we could
just avoid ever trying to do any reads as well.
If we know that the if we've already gotten into a failure State,
basically we would not try to do anymore reads on that handle because
who knows what would happen.
So, we'll just ignore any request to read on a bad handle, if that
makes sense.
All right, so I think that's mostly it.
Let's take a look.
We got to figure out where we get the file name from, right, but I'm
going to hard code that for now.
Let's see.
No errors is not a member.
You are correct about that.
I don't actually remember what the value was there.
What is the name of that value?
H.
Don't ask me why I called it h.
I don't know.
So, file name, we don't have win32 handle.
We do have put in the wrong thing, there file handle, for this, we do
have that.
That's just the handle went through to handle like so.
And that cannot convert a parameter.
That is true because it would have to be H, right?
All right, so the file name, what I'm going to do now is I'm just
going to full-on cheese that out.
I'm just going to say that the file name.
You know, this stuff is always going to be complete nonsense here,
right?
So what we're going to do is totally cheese this out so that we can
test the loading.
So I'm going to do is I'm just going to say that when we have a file
group, the file count is 1.
Duke AC actually implement this, right?
And that's already and then we come in here.
We're just going to assume that we're always loading that same file,
right that we're loading.
Our handmade
Data, we're going to load that test on, aha, right?
Does that make sense bouquet?
See do we implement this?
Okay, and hey, I capitalized file named differently in two different
cases.
I do that all the time and so now what we want to do is just kind of
start stepping through it a little bit.
I think we're pretty much done with the stream for today, because
we're about only a minute or two left.
So what I want to do is just quickly step through this, but we're
going to have to basically shut things down and leave them in a
nonworking State, because there's basically no chance that the stuff
all worked correctly the first time, right?
That's totally out of the question.
So what we want to do is just kind of
A quick step through and then we'll hold off on any real debugging
till next time, right?
Okay, so the file count is 1, which is what I said.
I wanted to be, we're going to step through their will grab out the
first file, right?
Well actually, it's just getting at the destination for the first file
that we got that tag base, which is set to 0.
Remember, we got a rebase our tag, so that's what we base, the pointer
set of the tags.
So the first thing we're going to do is we got to read out
Wait a minute.
What, what is going on here?
We haven't read the header yet.
That's just banana cakes, right?
Did you see that?
Who wrote that?
I don't know who wrote that, but whoever wrote that whoever snuck in
here and wrote that ridiculous code.
You know, don't do that, right?
I'm writing all this really good code and then someone comes in and
puts this Ridiculousness in there.
I don't know what's going on, right?
Clearly.
Some kind of no more Imp in the machinery.
So yeah, this is what reads the header.
So obviously the asset type array size that's cannot be computed here,
right?
That is something that can only be computed after the header actually
gets red.
And I don't know why anyone thought something other than that, was
going to happen, all right?
Try it one more time.
So we coming here, we zero out the file header.
We try to open the file.
So there it is.
Let's see if we were able to open the file.
Looks like we were oh sorry.
That was just allocating that the point, the memory for, it will go
ahead and create the file and do we actually get one?
We did.
So are no errors.
Should be set to 1 which is true.
So, that's good.
We come through here.
We tempt to read data from the file, we see whether we have any
errors, we didn't, so we grab out our Winthrop.
To handle, right?
We take a look at overlapped and we set that to where we are trying to
read from which is this case happens to be 0 because we're going to
first thing we're looking to file size which is 44, that should be 1H,
a headers worth of file.
Right?
What is it file?
Header?
Isn't there?
An h.h.
a header?
H.h., a header.
So, just somebody want to tell me why I can't take the size of that.
What, what is the deal with that?
All right, well anyway looks like we read it properly.
So, that's good.
Oh, awesome.
I know why that was.
It's because we were in a different part of the code that didn't have
h a header compiled into it.
And so the the debugger felt that it was fine to just not tell us what
that was.
That's hilarious.
Right?
Because remember this is handmade dot exe and this is handmade tempt
up, dll.
And so it was using only the symbols from handmade that exe to look up
what was in the watch window at that time?
Are the people who make this product, you can tell if they do
debugging, they're not very good at it which I guess, you know, would
be the joke anyway.
Anyway, so
Point being, we're going to go ahead and get the the asset type array
size here, which is just however, many there are 20 for.
Okay, that's fine.
And I guess you know what, I should also look and see.
This is the first time we're looking at us loading the header, right?
So there's the magic value and stuff, there's the version number,
there's the tag count, there's the asset type count ass account, that
all looks relevant, you know, reasonable, you know, nothing too
ridiculous there.
So let's read we're going to read in.
In now, the asset type array.
We're going to make sure that the magic value in the version match.
They do.
We're going to go ahead and add the totals to our asset tag counts.
That's fine.
Off we go.
We're going to end.
There we are going to push the arrays on.
We're going to load our tags assuming that we load the tags in here,
right?
We've got a, we're going to load into the the tag array.
However, many there are right at the offset for the tag base, which we
kind of did up here.
Where is that tag base file?
Tag?
Basis, always attack at.
Yeah, that looks right.
It's set up there.
So that's good.
We come through here.
We grabbed the the asset.
Can't we go through?
We we looks like we're just going to look through and however many
types of assets.
There are right.
We go through every file for every asset type we then look to see if
we're still reading, okay?
From this particular file, we go ahead and grab the asset type array
for that particular asset type right.
You read it in and looks like it didn't have any for that which is
correct, its asset type 0 and that should just go a pace presuming
Lee.
Yeah.
That should just go till it reads, all the assets of that type, which
presumably would only happen once for any given file and then it will
go through.
All right, so that looks fine.
But of course, we did not actually get the number of assets that we
thought we would get.
We loaded 50 and we expected 51.
That's actually fine because now that I think about it, the first
asset is the null asset and that asset would not actually be stored
anywhere, if I'm not very much mistaken.
Right.
I think that's correct.
So that's kind of interesting.
So I don't know.
We got to figure out what we want to do about that.
I'm going to go ahead and and kind of zip past this particular error
for the moment.
There's set next statement and let's run I don't think anything good
holy cow dude.
Well, it doesn't quite work correctly because I don't see any Shadows.
But that was.
Awesome.
So now we're streaming out of the asset file.
Wow, okay, so we've got a little bit of work to do that.
It's not quite correct yet.
So we've got some work to do but man that was pretty good, right?
All right, so you got to do that.
I also have to wanted to put it to do in here to do Casey Primacy
numbers for asset files.
But let's go ahead and go to the Q&A for now because I think we've
done enough programming for today.
Yeah, that was kind of crazy that that worked at all.
Given how much stuff we wrote and we had only one really stupid thing
in it, which was the fact that asset type array was going to compute
it above where it should have been, but that was pretty good.
All right, so if you have questions, now is the time for the Q&A.
Please ask questions.
Put a q: in front of them.
If you have questions about what we did on the stream that you just
saw and you're confused about anything.
You saw happen.
Now, would be a great time to ask that question.
Put a q: in front of it, and I will answer it.
Effector streams a bit behind.
Okay, I will.
I will.
Yeah.
What do you use when you need something more Dynamic than Arenas,
default to Virtual Alec malloc something completely different?
The answer there is well first of all, you're actually probably going
to see that in a second Ron a second and in you know next week
probably honestly.
Because we do have one place in our code which needs something more
Dynamic and that is the asset memory management because the assets
themselves are dynamically sized.
And so as we pull them in and out of memory, we will want to try and
manage a block of memory coherently so that we can pull them in and
out.
Like I said, we have like a sea of virtual memory system problem,
where we need to make that work, right?
So you will.
Yes, do something like that.
But really, what I would say is a general-purpose allocator is totally
fine to have in your program.
We just, this is probably the only place that we really need it, which
is why you haven't seen me right one.
But there's nothing wrong with a general-purpose allocator.
What you would typically do is, you would say, how much memory do you
want?
The general purpose, I'll character use in general.
You'd make a block for that and then you just let it general-purpose
allocate out of there, right?
Right.
And so if you literally just don't know what your memory location
patterns are that is what you would do.
But 99% of the time, you know, exactly what your memory location
pattern is.
And so, what I try to kind of communicate to people is most of your
stuff can operate on an arena,
Should.
Because it's way way faster than a general-purpose alligator, right?
And way cleaner because you don't have to free individual things, you
can just free the whole thing as a group and that is actually probably
the most valuable part of it.
Because it means you don't have to worry about memory leaks or any of
this stuff.
It's just all together and works, right?
But if you actually have Random Access patterns going, a random
allocation patterns going on, there's nothing wrong with
general-purpose alligator.
It's totally fine.
Insofar as how.
Handmade are you going to go on the Linux version?
Probably not to handmade.
And the reason for that is Linux is extremely temperamental in terms
of its support for stuff.
And so we will probably try to do the thing that most games do, which
might be writing through sdl, it might be just writing through it
might be like looking at sdl because I think that's what most came
ship with.
I don't know and looking at which Services they're using and try to
use those same services.
Because basically Linux is very, very bad at application
compatibility.
And so we need to try and do whatever it is that most people are doing
because I think that's the only chance we really have of running
reliably.
So I suspect what we'll do is we'll like look at sdl go this is what
most games are probably doing how can we, you know, let's let's write,
you know, let's write to those apis, whatever they are like also or
pulse or I don't know what they use for sound, you know, and whatever.
You know, however, they interface with x's how will try to interface
with x.
What Squirtle kind of off topic.
But you usually have that much luck.
Not getting bugs.
Yeah, there's usually a well, there is a bug, right?
The Shadows didn't show up and that's usually, you know, I've been
programming for long enough that the times when I actually have stuff
that's just crazy.
Buggy is actually pretty low.
Because, you know, I just, I know how to avoid a lot of stuff and in
my head I'm tracking the right things, I guess, you know, but
everything's got some bugs, you know.
Like I said, there's no shadows in this one.
There's probably other.
Near that just hasn't reared its head yet, right?
There's like a hidden bug in there, you know, and so, you know yeah.
I mean these days like you seen on the stream.
A lot of times something works the not necessary the first time but
very close to the first time, that is pretty typical.
If you've been programming for, well it's not typical if you haven't,
right?
If it's if you're new to programming, that is not what will happen
because your brain isn't used to tracking all this stuff.
It needs to track, but even when you get to the point where I am,
where you've been programming.
So old, you know, you're old and crusty.
You've been programming so long.
You don't make
a lot of those basic mistakes.
You're still making mistakes.
So I guarantee you that, you know, there's mistakes in the code, we
just wrote and we will have to find them.
It's just as you
And more and more.
You will just have a lot less of them.
Every time you do something, right?
They'll be a little more subtle, only.
The subtle bugs will be there.
Only the non-obvious bugs will be there or whatever, right?
But that's just the nature of the game.
And like I said, you'll if you make a lot of, if you have a lot of
problems getting stuff to work the first time and you're tearing your
hair out, that's probably an experience thing that will go away as you
program more, but I don't know.
Anyone who writes?
Correct code the first time, no matter how, you know, all the time, no
matter how great they are.
It doesn't happen.
It doesn't happen for me.
It doesn't happen for anyone, I know.
So it's like there's a limit to what you'll be able to do in that
respect but it's fine.
You know, you can usually get to a place where it's okay and you don't
have too much and there's not too much to my going to do.
Do you usually Define an API just by implementing it or do you try to
define the interface first?
Plain flavored?
That.
Please tell me that you missed the past couple streams.
Please tell me that you missed all the streams.
In fact, I know you haven't though, because I've seen your ass
question before.
What do I always say?
What do I always say, right?
The usage coach.
You know what?
That's not in big enough.
Where's my pen?
What day is today, day?
Oops, day.
150 to write the
Usage.
Code.
First.
This is the thing that you should be doing.
Always, always, always, always right?
The usage code first.
Like the only time I can think of where maybe you wouldn't write the
usage code first is if you literally have no idea, how the thing
you're calling works, you might need to experiment a bit to figure out
what you're actually even trying to build down to the lower level.
But even then, as soon as you know how it works.
Like as soon as you learned how the win32 file apis work at all,
immediately back to the regular code and write the usage code, first
always write the usage code first.
That's exactly what we did, right, you notice.
There was not a single piece of code in here, right?
I it would say we're just stubs and I had them all stubbed out and I
was like this is exactly what's going to have to happen.
Is these things are gonna have to do what they say they do, right?
Because I wrote the usage code first and then I just went over and
said that's the API.
And that is how you always, always, always always do it.
You write the user code first that defines the API and then you refine
the API based on things that have to happen.
When you do the implementation, like the implementation can then say,
Oh I can't quite support.
What the best API would have been for some reason, performance
something.
So I had to make a slight change and then you back Port that.
But you always, always, always always 100% of the time you never ever
do anything other than write, the usage code.
First that defines the
Pass API and then you modify it only slightly from there based on your
experience.
Implementing it.
That is what you must absolutely must do.
Can you cools?
Okay, now we real done.
Press question, super dumb like, nuking my non-existing reputation and
locking it down at the level of atomic dust.
What is usage code?
Basically everything down the line that awaits to be fed data, okay.
So, two things about that.
First of all, that is not a dumb question.
Second of all, don't worry about asking dumb questions.
Because, for example, if plane favorite had, not asked that question.
That was not a dumb question.
It was a smart question.
I was just disappointed because I
Him to have heard on the previous three me saying that, right?
It is much better to ask that question so that we can re go over it
and drill it in because this is really one of the most important
things in programming.
You can never really asked that question enough.
If you haven't internalized it yet, if you haven't internalized,
something about what I said, please ask those questions because you
must internalize it.
It is the most important thing.
There are plenty of things we do on the stream.
That maybe you don't internalized or don't have to internalize, or it
will take you a long time sir.
This is the one you must internalized.
It is so important.
So I will explain what usage code is.
All right so in this case,
What we had was we knew we had an asset file, and I wanted to read in
the data from that asset file and use it.
That's what I was trying to accomplish.
I knew I needed a new API on the platform side for that because we had
never defined a platform API for actually working with files that stay
open, right?
The only thing that we have in the platform there were saying that
reads a whole file in in memory at once and that's exactly what we're
not trying to do.
We're trying to read little pieces out.
So the question was, what new API should I put on.
Platform layer.
Right?
What new API should I use their?
So, a couple questions.
How did I know that was the API?
How did I know that?
That side of the code was the API and not this side, right?
Well, the reason is because, which one will get reused, right?
Which one is like a new little language that we're defining that
people who want to do something will use again?
No one's going to use this again, right?
It's a piece of code, that's entirely self-contained inside this
allocate game assets thing, right?
It's not an
Yeah, it's a whole list of things we're doing to put ourselves into a
correct position.
So we know this isn't an API, right?
The API was this function and we've already got it, right?
So the other side is the thing that we might use multiple times,
anytime we need to read a file, we need this API to work, right?
And so what we want to do is since we know that it might be something
that gets reused, right?
We know that it's something that we might need to use multiple times
in this place, you know, anytime our code needs to call to the
platform, how to get file stuff.
It's gonna have to do this.
What we want to do is make sure that it's set up to be as easy as
possible for our code, on the use of side to use it so that it fits
slots in nicely in the Apu API.
What we want.
And also so that the part of the code that's written multiple times,
which is the part that calls the API will be as clean as possible
because there's only going to be one implementation of the API.
But, potentially, multiple people who call it, right?
And in fact, you can see that already, how many calls to read data
from file?
Are there already in just our asset loading system?
Right?
Look at all those.
So we want to make that call.
Easy to do and do the correct thing?
And we don't care how complicated this is because we only write it
once when you write something five times in one place and once
somewhere else, right?
It's the summer else that you want to be more complicated because you
want the most complicated stuff to be constructed in debunked once.
Whereas, if I were to push complexity or ugliness out of this somehow
into here, I would have multiplied the complexity and the error-prone
is of that thing times five.
Okay.
And that is the crucial thing to understand about API design.
You need to push the complexity and the error-prone things down into
where they are written the fewest number of times.
Okay, so that is how you define who's on which side of an API
boundary, who is the person who is doing something once, and who is
the person who's doing it many times, right?
That is what that is, right?
It's the caller going to the Kali, okay?
So that's how we know the call should be going that direction.
That's how we did that.
And so what I say by writing the usage code is okay.
Now what I want to do a lot of people, what they do, a lot of
programmers, what they do is then they go, okay, I need an API for
reading files.
Okay, let's go make a thing for reading files, right?
And they open up an h-file and they're like doodlee.
Do you know, file API and they're like, I don't know.
Let's make something that reads a file.
So we make a Bool here and I say, you know,
You file and that's going to take like the the file to read write and
it's going to take the size of the phyllo and I need to seek, you
know, things have a seek in file apis, right or whatever.
And they write some API out and then they go in the implement it.
We're still, they might implement it and then test it.
So they spent a tremendous amount of time developing this thing,
right?
At least the amount of time that we actually needed to take and then
plus potentially much more and they have no idea if it actually does
what they want.
They have no idea because they have never actually written any code
that actually uses it.
They're just going on like some vague cloudy notion in their head
about what this API might do because what are the capabilities that
could have, right?
It's like
like, I don't know, it's a file API.
What can files do?
Let's just start making stuff that files do right?
Bad, bad bad.
What you actually want to do if you want are on the other side of the
API, pretend you have no idea what the API is.
You don't even know what it.
You have no idea.
You just need to get the entire notion of it out of your head.
And then what you do is you just write the code, you were trying to
write at the time that you decided you needed this API and you write
exactly what you want it to do for you.
And you can see that that was exactly what.
I did on stream, right?
I went through here and I said, okay,
here's what we're going to do.
I'm going to start writing the code as if I'm writing the actual final
asset loader.
What do I want to do?
I want it to get all of the HHS out of, you know, that this game can
run.
So I just flat-out said that right?
I just flat-out said, get all the files of the type right because I
don't need the API to expose how that's done and that's crucial,
right.
We could have started, fiddling all sorts of stuff in here with like
okay, open a directory, like
Give me a path to a directory and iterate the files in the directory.
That would have been awful because then we're exporting all of these
Notions of what a directory is, how to iterate over them.
What happens?
Then when we want to iterate over h, a files that are in two
locations, like the person's memory card and their console hard drive
or something.
Right now, all of a sudden that has to be bubbled up into the, the
app, and it has to be the app, has to know how to do that for all the
possible platforms of, oh, it's a Cloud State.
Like, there's all the stuff that happens there, we don't want that.
Right?
So what instead I'm doing is I'm saying,
What do I actually want?
What do I actually need the platform layer to tell me?
I just needed to tell me?
What are all the H files?
I could open, that's all I need, right?
So, give me those back.
And then I said, okay, for each one of those, I need you to give me
the header, right?
How am I going to get that?
Well, I need to read data from it, right, and I also going to need the
asset type array, so I was like, okay, that's the same thing, right?
I just I don't need two different calls for that.
I can tell they're the same call, cause I'm just like, well, I'm just
reading data from a file.
Here's where I want to read it.
There's so much.
I wanna read put it here, right.
Right?
So I defined that and of course, yeah, I needed a way to open the
file.
So I said, hey, give me a handle the file because I need a way to
reference this, right?
I need to way to go from the list of files to a specific file.
So that's what I typed, right?
Then at the end I was like, well, okay, I need some way to tell you.
I'm done right?
I'm done with this iteration and really, I could have not written
that.
And then later we could have ping-pong back when the API and the other
side says, oh, I kind of need to know when I'm done and then I
Didn't we could have done that but I just kind of knew from intuition.
I was like, well, I should probably announce what I'm done so that
because it's going to be some Resource Management probably on the side
and it probably would like to know, right?
So I that was just a courtesy call, really, but we could have left
that out and then we would have implemented.
The win32 thing saw that we needed to know when it was done and came
back here.
So you didn't you didn't need to know.
You didn't need to have the experience that I've had a no.
Oh, I've been planned these sorts of things before do it.
You could have left that out and you would have ping-pong back here
and go.
Okay, now I'll make a slight change to the way I wrote the code just a
in this one line, right?
We come down here.
Everything else I needed was entirely based off of stuff we already
had right?
Oh, and the platform, no file errors.
That was perfect.
I was like, oh, you know what?
I don't want to check the error value on every file because I don't
care which one's of them failed.
If any of them failed, the game's over, right?
I can't keep operating on half a red file, that's not going to work,
right?
So then I know I don't want these things to reflect like this is
wrong.
I don't want this to return a Bool because I'm never gonna look at
that fool.
What I wanted to do is remember,
Number if it ever had a problem.
And if it had the problem, then I'm just going to stop, right?
I'm just going to say, okay, that files done.
We're never touching it again.
Don't look at it.
Don't don't breathe on it.
Don't you know, do anything?
Don't try to coax it back to the light.
It's done.
Right report.
An error to the user and say, bro, your files are messed, right?
You got problems.
I did the little like, you know, who has two thumbs and a corrupt file
system.
This guy
I guess I did guns guns are not the same as the air.
Well, okay, sorry, my I'm not very, very good, bro.
I don't even like football, right?
Like that doesn't work.
So, anyway, point being
That's what we did and that is the example of writing the usage code
first.
It means write the thing that you were trying to do write it as if you
have the API that makes the most sense for that code.
Get that code into a nice.
Well reading like it looks nice and clean.
It does all the things you wanted to do it just in the way you want
them done and then at that moment when you're like, that looks good.
That's what I'm happy with.
I could ship this.
I believe this would be good that is when you then cut and paste these
API.
Balls into a new file and that defines the API right there, and that's
again.
Exactly did on the stream.
It was a little more complicated than it normally is because I had to
make it go through the platform layer.
So normally we would just cut paste them into directly to see filings
influence them right there, right?
So it's a little quicker that way normally, but so we had to give that
little layer of like how to route them through because it's
platform-specific but that was it right?
So hopefully that answers the question and again do not feel
self-conscious about asking questions about that.
It is absolutely the most important thing there.
Is no question about that.
That is not worth asking if you don't understand, because you have to
understand that to be a good programmer, and there's so many
programmers who don't understand it.
So many most, I would say, most people who make their living as a
programmer, do not understand that, and it is like the number one
cause of bad code.
The number one cause there are plenty of causes but that is the one
that you absolutely must get, right?
And it is so prevalent that it is not done correctly.
That really honestly.
It is like number one headspace thing for sure.
Do you feel that a lot of the common programs they have bloated code
and or that coders need to learn to simplify barebone their code?
I don't know if I'd say Bare Bones.
But yes not like most of the code is written.
Today is massively bloated.
Gaston 5 doesn't anticipate the usage of the API, required Decades of
work.
I don't know that I'd say that obviously, you get better at it over
time, but
Not really because you can talk it out, right?
Like here's an example.
Let's, let's talk about an example of something.
Like, if you didn't know it, right?
So, if you didn't know anything about the game asset file at all,
right?
And you, I just asked you to describe to me in English, what was going
on, right?
You would have said something like what?
I wrote for the API, right?
You would have said, you know?
Well, okay, first, I need to know what all the, you know.
Those are that I'm going to load, right?
You would have said like okay then I need to load the headers of each
file because I need to know what's in them, right?
You know so I got a load that right, then I need to allocate space to
store everything.
Right.
Then, I need to load in the tags, right?
We have the tags.
Then I need to load in the assets, right?
And when you look at what you type out, what you just think, if
through, like what does that have to do?
It Maps like really close, right?
I'm like, okay first, I need to know what files going to load.
We did that right.
Then I need to go through them and load the headers, which is what we
did, right?
And as I'm typing, this
I have all the things that I needed except for these parts.
Right.
So it's not hard to figure out what part is the API.
It doesn't take Decades of experience for that because it's just as
soon as you couldn't do something like as soon as I say first, I need
to know if I lose.
I'm going to load I'm like, well, wait, we don't have any way to get
that.
We have no way to get that, right?
That's the first API call, right?
So there it is.
I was just like, I don't have any way to get that I baited up, right?
That's when like Snuffleupagus comes over.
Like your imaginary friend is there and he's whatever you want them to
be right.
It's like I don't know how to write any code that does this with what
we currently have because I don't have those services.
So I just made it up right.
Snuffleupagus gets the files, we then start writing.
I knew how to do the rest of this stuff, right?
I'm like, okay, I'm assuming that I got back the set of files.
I don't know what they look like, I don't care.
So I'm just going to say I got an array Loop over it because we can
always change this, and we don't care, right?
It could be anything if the platform layer.
In fact, when we go and implement this, we may change the
implementation that it doesn't matter.
The important part is just this Loop that I can Loop over them
somehow.
So I just wrote the simplest possible thing.
And there we go.
When I go through your, I'm like, okay, I've gotta open the file like,
I've got to actually have a way to talk about the file.
So I need a way to translate the index.
Of the file that I'm, you know, when I'm looping over these, I have to
translate the index right into an actual thing I can make requests of.
And so, again, I don't have any way to do that.
So Snuffleupagus comes and gets it to me.
So, I just said platform, open file.
All right, there we go.
It's going to.
I don't know what's going to do.
I still don't know what's gonna be having implemented it, right?
I've no idea how Snuffleupagus the file, he just gets it, he pulls it
out of snout, I don't care.
The point is, I know that I've got a file group and it has some number
of files in it.
So I'm just going to say,
I need file 5.
Get it for me, right?
Same thing here.
I'm like, I want to read the header.
How are you the header?
I don't know.
We don't have any way to read the header stuff.
August, read the header.
That's what this call was, right?
We could have called it read the header and then later, when I typed
in read the asset array, I would have been like oh hey these are the
same call, right?
They're both just something that takes an offset a size at a thing
because that's what I do and again you don't need to necessarily know
anything about a file API to do that.
You just have to know.
I need to get this data out of the file.
Are you get the data from this offset, this much of it.
I need to
Here, that's all you need to know.
That's all I wrote, right?
Just exactly that.
Just straight ahead.
Didn't think anything about it.
Because anything that I would think about it.
Just going to complicate it.
What I want to do is tell Snuffleupagus exactly what I wanted.
I don't want to think about what stuff is going to have to do.
I just want to think about what I wanted Snuffleupagus to do I say
Snuffleupagus, get me the file is that the end of the thinking, right?
Snuffleupagus, read this part of the file.
That's the end of the thinking.
And then later on the second pass through, right?
We can always fine tune those to reflect the needs of Snuffleupagus.
Certainly, I don't think, I'm neglecting stop loving us.
But the first pass on the right, the use of code, we don't think about
stuff like this.
You just going to show up and do what we want.
Right?
And so again that's the crucial part of it and if you weren't, if you
don't have very much experience, maybe you type in something here,
that's like, impossible to fulfill your just like you say something
that can't happen.
When you go to do the implementation, you'll find that out and then
that's a fine time to just refine it.
So you don't have to
Hundred percent, right?
And so that's the thing that I want to.
It's a very mental, very English, you know, process a logistical
simple thinking process that's kind of like what you would do in the
real world.
I want to do this, I'm gonna do this.
I'm gonna do this and every time you say that I want to do something
and you don't have a way to do it.
That's a new API, right?
And that's the usage code.
Can you kill says so basically when you're about to make shoes for
Monster you don't assume how many legs are toes.
It has you just let it stop around and then use the footprints to make
the shoes.
That's pretty much exactly, right?
Hmm.
James Woodman suggestion call this Snuffy oriented programming
Snuffleupagus oriented programming.
I would be totally psyched if for some reason, right, the use of code
first became called Snuffleupagus oriented programming, I would be
more than happy to to.
I don't know how you spell that Snuffleupagus.
so, let's just say,
So, it's stopped.
Right.
This code was written using Snuffleupagus oriented programming,
something like that.
All right, all right.
We are over time because well, frankly, the question that someone
thought was stupid, none of those questions were stupid.
They were actually very good and I'm very happy.
They were asked because I feel like every so often it's very good to
restate.
This because again, we talked about a lot of stuff on here, there's a
lot to learn and it really it doesn't, it doesn't help learning to say
something once and then just let it sit forever and assume that people
just magically pick up all the important stuff.
That's
How learning works, right?
Learning works by seeing something multiple times.
And so it's always good to reinforce these things and go.
Hey, you know what, we talked about right in the usage code, let's
talk about it again because if there's one thing we can never talk
about too much, it's that right?
And so I think that was very good.
I'm glad we went over that.
Hopefully if you had some kind of confusion in your mind about how
this stuff worked, hopefully we've gotten a little closer now to you
going like, oh okay, I get it.
Like that's how I can do this this process.
And you know, the closer the
the more you do it, the better you'll get at it and the more you'll
see how helpful it really is, I use it everyday even in code that I've
written before
Always do it this way because everything is a little bit different and
there's always room for improvement and everything and so I always
like to kind of revisit that usage code and go okay.
What can I do here?
What's this problem?
Trying to say like how do I want this to work?
Let me refine the apis even further.
I constantly revisit that and always think about the usage code.
So, I always write it first and I always keep it in mind later as I'm
doing stuff.
How can I make the users code better?
Because again every time usage, code happens, many times API code
happens once.
So if you can make
Improvements there you're saving yourself a lot of problem and these
frustration and bugs and everything, you know, if you can push the
complexity into the single use code rather than the multi-use code.
All right, so that said, let's go ahead and wrap up for today.
Let's see here.
Close this down our stuff lepidus orange.
Look at that.
That was so cute.
Well Snuffleupagus image from my childhood there.
I'm so old that Snuffleupagus was still completely imaginary.
Like he wasn't no one had seen him but big bird.
I feel like that's not true anymore, but yeah.
So anyway, okay, we'll go ahead and close up Lagos and the read file
function.
Thank you everyone for joining me, for another episode of handmade
hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you, as always, if you know, if you
are someone who likes to play around with things like to experiment,
and you would like to play around with a hero source code, you can
always get it.
If you preorder handmade Hero on hand a hero to org.
It comes to the source code.
So you can go ahead and play around with it at home and learn from it,
and it's pretty handy way to do that.
We also have a forum site.
We can go to ask questions
And we had also has an entire episode guide stuff like that.
I highly recommend checking it out.
It's got ports to Mac and Linux by the community, as well.
If you're trying to follow along a different platform, we have a
patreon page, want to just support the video series.
So as much appreciated it's a place, you can subscribe just to support
the video series.
We also have a tweetbot the tweets, the schedule at you.
So if you would like to be aware of, when we're going to be doing the
live streams, you know, which days of that week and what hours of
stuff, the tweetbot has got your back.
So,
Check that out.
It's the right way to go.
So, thanks everyone for joining me.
We will be back here again.
Tomorrow, 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time, pacific, daylight time.
Sorry, and I will also be speaking this Thursday at the Intel Buzz
Workshop.
So for any of you who are in Seattle, who want to come by and say hi,
that's going to be happening this Thursday as well.
And so hopefully I'll see some people there that maybe watch The
Stream.
So until tomorrow,
I'll see you guys in the internet.
Have fun programming and have a good rest of your Monday.
Take it easy, everyone.