Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show recode a complete game live on stream.
We do not use any engines, we do not use any libraries.
This is an educational project designed to show the entire set of
actual code, that it takes to run a game from start to finish.
And so, whatever it is that you're interested in, we cover it at some
point and if you're interested in being a generalist, which is
generally what I am put intended, then this is the sort of stuff that
you would, it be?
It to know at a minimum certainly in order to be a good game
development generalist, which is I think a pretty good thing to be
because hey game development, generals can do just about anything on a
project and you can do an entire project by yourself which is also
pretty handy so that's all pretty cool as well.
But today we would like to possibly finish up our audio code that
we've been working on for a week or two and I don't even know how long
we were kind of I guess something like six, six or seven days, I don't
know.
So six seven hours of audio coding.
Not very much but audio is very simple.
So we got done most of the stuff that I wanted to get done and we
don't have any particular Advanced super Advanced effects or anything
that we needed to do for this particular project.
So, you know, we didn't have to get to too much into signal
processing, anything like this.
So what we'd like to do today is kind of wrap that up and we more or
less finished it yesterday, but I had found that, we shouldn't
actually do things eight wide because the fact that we're doing
variable rate and so what I ended up wanting to do
Is changing over to be for wide.
So what I want to do is make that change today just go through
everything, kind of make sure it's all kosher and then we can pretty
much call our audio done and move on to assets pack file stuff, which
is something that we would really like to get to because it's kind of
holding up.
Well honestly, it's holding up pretty much us, checking off the asset
system, permanently from our list and so we really want to get that
done.
So
Let's pop over to the code.
And I would mention that if you are someone who has pre-ordered the
game today is day, 1, 45 6, rather.
So you want to unzip, they 145 source code.
If you're trying to follow along at home and you would like your code
to match mine at the start.
So here we go.
Let's take a look at where we left things, I think everything is still
in good working order.
It's just a little janky internally in terms of How It's structured.
Yep, are panting still working, all that good stuff, so no real
issues, one thing.
I did want to mention is since we can't do alignment,
On reads anymore.
Because if you remember I was saying, I would like to align on Reed's
since we can't align on reads because we support pitch bending.
What I wanted to point out is that I had mentioned that we weren't
going to bother supporting
Beeping sounds, but since we are not going to bother doing aligned
reads, that me is not true anymore.
So we now can totally support looping sounds and what one of the
things that we would want to do to support looping sounds properly.
I noticed this the other day, and I mentioned it even, but we just
didn't have a chance to get to it.
Is this code right here when our samples played advances past the end
of the sample count that.
So it goes over the end and we say, oh, we may have to play another
sound if
We want to support looping sounds.
All we have to do is make next idea to play point to ourselves.
Right?
So, for example, you know, if I just just show you what I mean because
we support streaming streaming and looping is really the same thing,
right?
Streaming is just saying, oh, when I get to this buffer, I need to
play another buffer.
That's like the next part of this song.
Well, looping is just doing the same thing but pointing at the same
chunk over and over, right?
So now that we're not going to do alignment, it's pretty trivial for
us to support looping, sounds, if you want
You all we would have to do is in here, right?
Where we do this sort of stuff, right, where we've got our, our asset
stuff going over all the samples and chaining them together, right?
So you can see me doing this, this next idea to play.
So, if you're right, chaining them together, what we could do, is if
we wanted to, we could take one of our bloops and make our bloops do
the same thing.
So let's take out the varied bloops that we've got here so that we're
only working on one.
Bloop and what we would do, right?
Is we just
Say, okay, you know, grab out the bloop when we when we actually do it
and then set that next idea to play properly, right?
So, when we come in here, we would say, okay, whatever that that slot
ID was for the bloop, the thing that comes after the bloop is actually
going to be the bloop itself, right?
Like so.
And then it would just keep on playing and playing and playing, right?
And so, you know,
So, again, looping since we're not gonna Force the mixture to be
aligned, really, really simple.
We've basically, we had already essentially engineer at the support
for.
We just didn't think of it as that at the time, but because streaming
and looping, or basically the same, we get it for free.
So if people want to add Loop sounds, they can I don't like Loop
sounds.
So I don't think I'll probably use that.
Feature.
But it's their right.
And so what I wanted to point out in relation to looping and I care
about it, more from the streaming side of things, is that, if you look
at what's going to happen here, when samples played runs, over the
sample count and it's time to go to the next sound if we don't have to
go to next sound, that it doesn't.
Right?
But if we do have to go to a next sound, then samp setting samples
played 20 is only correct in the case where we actually ended right on
a sample boundary which is going to be the case for 121 playback
perhaps but it would not be the case if we're doing some kind of a
pitch Bend and so really what we would rather do here is take samples,
played and subtract the sample count from it.
So that it leaves, whatever fractional overhang was in there, still
there, right?
Again, not necessarily something, you'll ever actually be able to hear
as an audio glitch, if you don't get just the right circumstances to
accentuate it perhaps, but just worth noting that that's, I believe a
more correct way of looking at the problem that makes sense.
Yeah.
So that's you know, just something I wanted to mention.
So I think that's mostly all there is to talk about with respect to
the looping stuff by just forgotten to mention it.
And we were kind of caught up and stuff yesterday so I didn't have a
chance to.
But what I'd like to do here is just go ahead and go through this
Loop.
Like I was saying and sort of pull down the the eight- of it and and
change it over to just working with sample account.
For instead of sample count,
Exams.
Okay, so for going in for is at a time, I'm going to delete that and
I'm going to go through here and and take a look at the 8.
So when we do total samples to mix, we're going to switch it down to
four, right?
Which is good when we do our our loop again, We're looping over for us
now.
And so now we're just going to have D volumes are, you know, all of
this stuff is going to be
Based on force, not on AIDS, right?
So now if we take our Master volumes here, our master volume is not
going to change because that's just a replicated value.
But our volume changes actually can be a little bit simpler now.
Excuse me.
Our volume changes can be a little bit simpler.
Now there's there's also something that I would probably want to do to
change our naming scheme.
So our sample count for maybe we should have also like maybe we should
just call this a chunk count or like a bin count or something, right?
I don't know what we want to call it, but we want to call like a chunk
of for this thing so that we can stop using the forest suffix, which I
think, is possibly bad, right?
So maybe I'll actually call that the chunk count something like,
That right.
All right, so we'll say how many chunks are there going to be in our
in our thing.
And we want to again, make sure that the the sample count is a line
That as well, right?
So when we come in here, I'm going to change it.
So I'm going to do, I'm going to call this total chunks to mix, and
we're going to call this chunk count.
Like we did up there and then we'll say, while we have chunks left to
mix, will keep going.
All right?
So we go in here to the loaded sound, we have our volume, we have our
change in volume over time, and then we have our D volume, which is
going to be the volume change.
For one with right.
So maybe we'd call this D volume chunk, something like that and D
sample chunk, right?
Just to unpack that for which was getting really pretty confusing.
Especially when we had master volume for, which doesn't really make
any sense.
So I'm just going to call these master volume, 0 and master volume 1,
which is a lot nicer because we don't really need to differentiate
them any further than that.
Then we've got volume here and volume is actually just going to be.
I think we really can just call it.
Regular volume, right?
Because the place where we actually used volume
Again later when we're looking at it here, I think we could always
have just used the first element.
We could always just do the math in the first element of that SSE so I
don't know that we actually ever need to store volume multiple times,
right?
Because really we're just doing math that we already did.
So I feel like what we want to do here is actually just switch to
having volume 0 and volume 1.
And that's all I really want there to be right and we'd have D volume
chunk as well, right?
And I think that means we could probably get rid of this stuff in
addition, right?
Yeah, well, so we'll take it one step at a time but again, I think we
can kind of clean up a lot of this.
So that's really, that's really all I want to be doing today is just,
you know, take care of all that stuff.
So it's not all janky in here.
Okay, so if we have the volume chunk, there we go.
And we've got that for left and right channels.
Looks like, well, this is actually just a volume 1.
And this is chunk one, right?
So, we'll actually see which one's of these, we actually need, but go
ahead and change those there.
There we go.
And I think that should do it for now, right?
So basically we have, you know, we could even look at it in terms of
channels, right?
So here's channel, right?
This is Channel Zero.
And this is Channel One.
And that all looks fine, nothing particularly weird going on there.
So I think that's okay.
Out.
So we're going to assert that the samples played is not ever below the
zero account and that's fine for now.
So then we're going to have a new value to samples to mix for the
chunk.
So it's actually going to be chunks to mix, right?
And this is going to be total chunks to mix.
Like, so we're then going to do real remaining real sample.
So this is just going to be the same thing, but it's going to be
chunks, right?
Real chunks are raining and sound.
We're going to take the sample count.
We're going to subtract, how many that we have played from that sample
count and then we're going to divide by whatever the the Delta is /
chunk, right?
I believe, that's correct.
Yeah.
Is that right?
Do you sample chunk is for time?
Sample?
Yeah, so that's how much we're going to do and then
And in here, we've got samples remaining.
So this is just going to be chunks remaining in sound, and this is
real chunks remaining in sound, and that should be it, right?
So this is Chunks to mix.
And that's chunks to mix.
And this is Chunks.
And chunks, so that all looks good, the volume ending check.
I guess doesn't really have anything specific going on here.
So this is D volume chunk and this is volume chunk count, I guess,
right?
And then we've got our samples to mix.
So that's our chunks to mix.
And our volume sample count is just our volume truck.
Okay, let's do a little compiled here to see where we're at sample.
Count for is really just chunk count.
D volume.
8 is D volume chunk.
And then we're down.
Okay, so that's all good.
So in here and I guess,
No, I think about it.
We have this to do here handle stereo.
We should probably just do some of these to do is we should probably
take care of that to do and this to do.
So after I finish this week through will take care of those two, dues
as well so we can handle that way.
You can handle stereo sounds not that we can actually use them yet
because we don't have the at them in the actual asset system.
I mean they're supported by the SM but not by the wave loader is
basically what I would say.
So anyway, we're doing the handle stereo thing, that's all well and
good.
Good.
What we would like to do here is make sure all of this stuff works
properly.
Now, what we can do, is our sample value now gets a lot easier, right?
Because now that we're doing this, in chunks to mix, we're kind of, we
don't have all of that annoying stuff where we had to do everything
twice, which is nice.
Right.
So now we can have just our zero in 1 Min are two channels types,
which is exactly, which is really what we would like, right?
So that's all good.
So here we go.
Let's load those guys in again, we can get rid of half of it nicely.
And you can see going ahead and doing these guys here, right?
We've got our volume 0 and our volume 1 and our sample value.
So that's just a lot nicer to read, right?
So that's just our multiply accumulate happening there, and that's all
good.
So, let's see.
We've got our stores and those are all good as well, but we only have
to do half of them now.
We can update these guys just singly because we're only writing out
for Paris now.
And when we update these guys, we can just think of them as 0 and 1.
So that's all good as well.
So these are do volume chunk the volume chunk and I think that's all
good.
So yeah, let's take a look.
You sample chunk as well there.
Let's take a look at where that's at, right?
These guys have to be
B.
How to calm down a little bit there.
D Volume 8 is divine chunk.
And now we're down here.
So now we're just doing, this is just renaming.
Basically chunks to mix chunks to mix.
We've got total chunks to mix, chunks to mix and yeah, I think that's
basically it.
Not a lot more to it.
So, let's see where we're at.
That's no good.
What do we do?
What heinous crime have we committed ladies and gentlemen, in our
fussing with the sound code.
So let's see where we're at here.
Total chunks to mix is 96 chunks to mix?
Drinks, Romanian sound or 0.
So the sound is over,
Right.
Trunks remaining in sound is zero.
So we won't mix anything.
Did we mess up our end condition?
Potentially, you may have.
Yeah.
So this is kind of a little bit janky here, right?
When we compute it, our ending,
This is, this is not.
This is not going to, this is not going to do it anymore.
Now that we're not, we kind of wrote that back when we were doing non
non floating-point playback, right?
So we're going to have to be a little bit more.
Careful about that to be sure.
So let's go ahead and Mark that guy in here.
Clean up a few more things and then we'll go through and do our 32
dues.
This is not an acceptable.
Check for the end, right?
Okay, so now I just want to simplify this guy a little bit, I just
want to go through here and see what we can do.
In terms of simplifying, things potentially a little bit so it looks
like we can just make that in there.
There we go.
Yeah, so I'm going to take a quick spin through here and see if maybe
some of these things don't have to be duplicated anymore.
So there aren't so many different things sort of flapping around.
That makes sense.
So let's see.
Yeah.
The first thing I would observe.
Is that if you look here, we're storing volume here.
And then we're storing it again here and we really don't need to do
that, right?
We don't need to keep incrementing to it.
That guy.
So these are really temporary values to some degree.
That should probably only be used to set up these things here, right?
At least that's what I would suspect.
And so if we take a look down here, like where we're actually
updating, these guys, we should be able to not do that anymore, right?
Like,
This should be able to go away for starters and then here where we're
actually using that volume.
Right?
What we could do there instead is the current volume that we want to
write back.
We could just write out the individual.
Just, you know, we could just grab out the one that we want, right?
So we could just go ahead and grab out the actual individual values
from the same date.
Like so,
Yeah, so what do we call those volume 0 and volume 1?
Yeah.
So that would get us out of the business of updating that variable,
which seems good to me, right?
Of course I got to actually address it properly.
So yeah.
I think that's probably what we would want to do there.
And looking at that I mean it's probably nice to still do it.
Deep to do D volume.
This way though, and volume just because you know it makes it easier
to initialize these guys just by having them.
So leave those temporary as temporary calculation
Want to get them out of the actual Loop.
So they're not being used anymore.
That seems like a good idea to me anyway.
And you know, and because they're used up here in the startup or
whatever.
So I just want to take it out of the loop that all seems pretty good.
I don't see anything else immediately obvious that I would want to get
rid of
I suppose the other thing we could do is actually just store, the
volume is somebody's butt that seems to Overkill.
So let's see here, we have not done the we're still on our sort of our
simpler path, right?
Where we do the the just the basic loads before.
And so if we wanted to do something a little fancier here,
Like supporting the lerp, which I guess we decided we couldn't really
hear it.
So, I don't know if we want to bother supporting the lip, but maybe we
should just write the code in there just because, you know, so if you
want to want to do the lerp Implement of the way we did it here, where
we've got an alert from sample, 0 to sample one, right?
We would want to do something where we loaded sample value, 0.
And that's again.
To be sort of a truncation here, right?
So this is going to be a floor.
And we probably want to save those things.
So we'd have to do this sort of thing, right?
We have to do a sample index where we would, actually, I guess we
could do it this way, right?
We're Loops, that's not good, where we would actually go ahead and
grab these guys out, right?
So we do, you know, this sort of thing.
Oops.
So that way we actually know what they are, so we can do the Frac and
all that stuff, right?
So if we have these guys, we would also need to do I guess.
Well, the frak is going to be
Yeah, so we would also need to do like sample pose, right?
We'd want to do that as well, right?
So we do like sample pose, zero equal sample position.
And then we would do our sample.
Index is going to be that sample post rounded down and then our Frac
right is going to be whatever that sample position is, oops, whatever
that it's a pollution is - the florid value.
Right.
So again just duplicating this code right here.
So we have to do this for all four of the samples, right?
Because we're going to have a different Frac for each of them as well.
Now what we could
You is, we could widen that as well, which I guess, maybe we would
like to do, right?
So you could imagine me doing something like this.
I'd say, okay, I've got well, I guess I've got one of these, right?
And I do sample pose, and that's going to be equal to M set RPS, and I
want to set it to like, sample, position, sample, position, sample
version.
I want to basically set it to be the, you know, the various
deposition.
And I'll just put them into a wide thing themselves.
Write something like this.
So now I've got the sample positions wide and I've got, you know, the
first sample, second sample, third sample, for example, right?
And then I can just wrap, I could floor them all together, right?
For this case, I guess truncate them all together.
Right?
So we got sample.
Index is going to be convert P.
It's like CVT PS.
What is it called that?
I think that's what it is.
Forgot.
We moved it over to optimized.
Yeah.
So you can see here, you know, when we're doing our
When we're doing our linear blend here where we want to get the
fractional values and stuff, you can see this is the truncation,
right?
That we were doing.
So we want to do exactly the same thing here, right?
Where you just want to truncate these values so that we're taking them
and figuring out what their closest actual index is right, and then
I'm going to do again.
Exactly the same thing we do here, right?
It's literally the same exact thing for a linear blend.
Whether you're doing it in graphics are doing and sound.
What we want to do is figure out what the
Actual value is and the fractional value again is just going to be
subtracting that sample index from the original sample pose that we
had so that we can see like, how much they were off.
Right.
So we that kind of nice because that means we can do that whole thing
sort of together, right?
And that gets us out of the business of having to do any of this other
Ridiculousness right now.
Unfortunately, the thing that that does not get us out of the business
of doing is doing the loads, so we have to actually do the loads.
Again, which is really too bad but there's really not much we can do
if we want to support the arbitrary pitch, Bend, I'm not sure there's
really much of a way around it.
So when we come in here and we want to get a sample value, you know, I
guess I'm not sure what we want to call it sample value.
The, the one we're going from then we're going to.
So maybe we'll call the floor and ceiling like sample value F and
Sample value C.
So when we load these guys in here, we need to get them out of the
sample Index, right?
But the sample index is not something.
You can actually address directly, right?
That's, that's a thing.
That's an integer now, right?
It's an M1.
A tie.
So, what we would need to do there is again, do exactly the same sort
of tricky thing we did before where we're sort of addressing into it
and saying, oh, I want to get you remember, I just did it down here,
right?
Where I sing it, I want to be able to get something out of the Sim
devalue.
So I'm just going to go ahead and say all right give me that value.
Give me the value of this guy.
As if he were an in 32 and then we'll grab the zero with one, right?
So let's do that.
And that should do it.
I think we're grabbing those guys and then what we have to do since
that's our sample index.
We have to also, grab whatever the thing is on the other side of it,
right?
So the seat, the ceiling value.
So, we would need to do, you know one one over that number, right?
To fetch into the next one.
And so, that's really it for that.
I think that gets our floor and our ceiling values load it in
properly, and then we just need to actually take some action.
So, this stuff is now
All represented in Cindy's, so we don't need that and we don't need
that anymore.
All we need to do now is just this part right here, where we do the
actual lurk, and of course, LARPing is pretty simple.
As we know, lerp is just the, oops, it's just an ad of two things that
have been multiplied by the slurping coefficient, right?
So we want to take that sample value floor.
And so and we want to take
that sample value ceiling.
Right.
And what we want to do now is we want to multiply these by whatever
the appropriate fractional values are, right?
So the fractional value, we multiply directly times the ceiling to
move toward it, right?
As a fraction goes up, we blend in more of see.
And what we want to do is have inverse of the fractional value 2
multiplied by F and so you remember how to do that, right?
We just subtract it from 1, right to get it to be an inverted value.
And that performs the lerp.
So all we really need now is that constant?
We need a one.
We don't have a one right now, right?
We had a zero, I guess I will stick of these up here is little
constants just in case, anyone wants them.
So weeps have a one and a zero now.
And so now we can do that, that lurk.
So let's see if this compiles it does.
Of course, it doesn't mean it works quick check just make sure
everything makes some sense.
We've got the sample pose here and we're just setting that to be
sequential samples.
moving by D sample which of course May mean we're not moving a whole
sample index at a time it's just sequentially where we're sampling
from
It could be more than one sample time.
Could be anything, really?
We then grab our sample index out of it by essentially truncating, the
value, which is a floor in this case because we're, you know, we're
positive numbers.
We then take the fractional value to figure out how far we are by
taking the number that we just floored converting it back to real and
subtracting it from the original sample, post to get just the
fractional portion, we then go ahead and grab out those samples,
right?
We grab out the actual sample locations.
Then the their neighbor to their right.
And then we do the lerp, right?
We multiply the fluoride sample value by the inverse of the fraction
and the sample value that will ceiling by the fraction to do that
standard again.
Standard blend equation.
Everyone should be super comfortable that by now because we've done it
so many times, all right?
And let's just double check by setting, some kind of a really weird
sample rate on this particular sound here, just to make sure that we
get something weird.
So it all sounds pretty good.
We just got that nasty little bug.
We also have to take care of
So that all seems fine, but we have obviously somewhat reduce that, we
might want to take care of here.
So let's, let's think about our today's.
So the first one is that sea bed with her termination condition is way
too sloppy and that's not acceptable.
We're going to hang in here all the time if we leave it like that.
So that's no good.
So, what we want to do here, first of all, I think before we actually
clean it up the
Lesion is we want to do the same thing we did with volume ended which
is that we want to set.
Instead we want to set sound finished.
Here we essentially want something that says like you know, input
ended or something like that and then we'll use input ended like input
samples ended, right?
So that we can know that that we either did or did not expect
ourselves to end.
And the reason I'm doing
Doing that is because there's a bunch of kind of finicky meth in here.
And while we do want to go through and make sure that we get it as
correct as we can.
But we don't want our to do is have our program hang if we made a
mistake somewhere because it's very easy to have a mistake in there.
That's hard to find that we don't see but that's some player some poor
player finds because they did something we didn't test or whatever and
happens to getting exactly what condition.
So it would rather do is say that up here, right?
Just like we did with the volume we want.
Want to be able to say that the input samples ended like this, right?
So that we say, okay, when we do our chunks to mix, we're going to
expect it to do the total chunks.
In the buffer, if we have to stop early because we don't think we'll
have enough samples in our input buffer.
Well that's fine, but remember that.
So that we will actually exit appropriately.
When we get down here, instead of checking some things that we just
hope will line up based on the math that we did.
But we have no idea if they actually will write.
Or we know what we have, not hard guarantee that they actually will
write.
And so that's, that's, I think better there, right?
And I just
Had this in a case that was crashing will try that case.
Again, not really a comprehensive way to do it but just to make sure
So that, okay.
And that's actually kind of interesting.
Whoa, that's not what I would expect it at all.
So I was going to say I could expect that to be slightly off because
of this thing here.
But yes, is that getting triggered?
A my triggering that in a dumb way?
I want I'm going to actually put that assertion a little further down
because I want to want to kind of take a look here.
I want to do this right?
Because I was going to say we could have an off by one.
They're certainly because of what we just witnessed or input sample
played and so we do want to fix that, but I that was a very large
number.
So I would like to know why we were
Okay, so I'm just putting the assert, I put the assert in a place
where I'd be able to inspect the things.
I actually wanted to inspect, if that makes sense.
So, let's see.
Loaded sound.
Has a sample count of 480,000, really.
Okay.
I'm not sure, I believe you.
That sounds like an unusually round number.
Oh, you know what?
But that's okay.
That's fine.
Because this is probably one of the music chunks, and we did set those
to be 10 seconds of peace, I believe.
So that's that's what it should have been, that's fine.
And so, let's take a look at playing sound.
See what that is and samples played.
Wow, that is just not even close, right?
That is not even remotely close.
So that could just because our math is sloppy, right?
But I would like to see what the actual situation is here.
Before we before we conclude that if you would.
So, let's see.
Chunks remaining in sound is 312 894.
74 5.
So we round that down.
2313, right?
I guess that rounded up.
Sorry.
2313 and the chunks to mix.
120 Chimes.
Ringing sound.
313.
So the chunks to mix was something, I guess we don't really have a way
of seeing what it was before hand.
If that makes sense.
This total chunks to mix been updated at this point.
It has unfortunately but that's okay, we can reconstruct it.
So chunks to mix and total chunks to mix.
So we'll chunks to mix + trunks to mix.
360 was the actual number there.
So that's how many we had to go and what we said was, well, we think
we've only got 313 so it makes sense that we would have to stop early
right now.
What's weird is why we thought we had to stop that early, but I could
be just missing something obvious here.
Saudi Sam.
Apple chunk.
Is just exactly what you would think.
It would be the samples played in the sample count.
So yeah, when we look at that number, I mean, I guess what I'm saying
is, there's definitely a serious bug in here, I think because they
should be no way for it to be that far off of where it would actually
need to be, right.
yeah, I'm gonna, I'm gonna
Take a look at this guy.
So chunks to mix is 480, total chunks to mix is also for it, as you
would expect remaining chunks and sound here is 63 157, that's how
many chunks are left in the sound according to this.
So, let's see if that actually makes some sense if that's a reasonable
thing to think about.
So we've got 480, thousand is how many samples there are, right?
And presumably there's been none played yet, right?
Because I stepped ready beginning.
So none of been played.
So if we want to know how many
These are going to be, we want to be able to see whatever, you know,
D, sample chunk tells us is going to be the number of chunks in here.
So let's see how many that's going to be right.
Let's see here.
If we said D sample, chunk so divide P sample chunk.
How many deep of these are there?
That's 63 thousand.
One hundred fifty Seven point eight.
Okay?
So, that's the value that we're actually seeing.
so if we were going to see how many of these
Chunks were going to do if this is the number of chunks were going to
do how many samples would we actually consume at that rate like where
would playing sample actually be so we'd want to multiply it up.
I do sample Chuck again and hey not surprisingly we get the exact
right answer so that's all seems pretty good I guess the question.
Now is what happens once we do some rounding in here.
So chunks remaining in sound right?
Many chunks.
Is it think we're meeting in Sam's 63 158
Yeah.
All right.
Well,
Let's go ahead and jump right to the bad case, and we'll see where
we're at.
All right.
So, here we are at the bad case.
We are asked to do 480 chunks, we believe there to be 313 chunks left
that we could actually do.
And so is that a again a reasonable value to think about so are
loaded.
We know are loaded one.
Has four for an 80,000 are playing sound is that 47 76 to 1781, right?
So let's take a look for
This where we at.
So we believe we have somewhere around that many samples left to play.
And so, let's take a look at what the actual if we take a look at
that.
Actual value, 2 3, 7 8 to 18 and 99, 99, write x d sample, Charming, /
D, sample trunk, right?
What, what?
What is happening?
All right.
Some kind of heinous nastiness happened with the cut and pasting
there.
We won't ask.
We'll just assume that Visual Studio is doing something fantastic.
So that's how many we think we're going to have.
And so as we increment that, if we'd go ahead and take that actual
number 9 to 3 if I 5654 509 or whatever and multiply it by D sample
chunk.
We get exactly the right value so that's good.
If we are to multiply it by what we routed up to again super duper
close.
So yeah, that that seems like everything was done properly.
So what's our problem here?
We're not doing any volume LARPing.
We start out at samples played, which is this?
Which is what we think it should be right.
And then we're going to add as we go.
So you know what?
Honestly, I wonder if this might just be a case of
Of the accumulator.
If you remember, I said this very early on.
I said the accumulators may not actually have enough precision and we
might have to do them as things that divide themselves out rather than
actually doing an accumulation every time because the error, as it,
accumulates can get up to the point where it's actually significant.
So I don't know.
We'll see.
So, what we expect the sample position to actually be, right?
We would expect the sample.
Mission after we're done to be something like 47 7621 78 1.
+ 2 3, 7 8 8 Loops 805, right?
So that's what we would expect to see and Sample position is going to
get chunks, chunks to mix going to be done, 313 times, right?
It's going to be done this D.
Sample chunks was going to add and I'm just betting that that's all
that's happening here, right?
So, when we come down here, let's see what samples are.
And actually is, here we go, sample position.
So yeah, really not.
It's not close enough.
I mean, it's bad enough.
I think we should probably concerned about although that is not nearly
as bad as what we were observing before.
So what what actually happened in the case we were looking at, I
wonder if I just sort of Miss looked at something, because it seems
like what I was seeing was was way way worse than that, right?
Yeah.
Anyway, so let's see here.
So loaded sound.
We've got playing sounds and sound samples played with this.
So, yeah, I feel like playing sound samples.
Played, you can ignore that.
You can ignore that disassembly.
Set next statement, go to source code.
So what I want to do is just see what that ends up being.
Yes, so that's more what I would have expected but that's not what I
remember seeing last.
I remember it being way off.
Now, maybe we just hit a different case but that is exactly what I was
worried about.
When I was saying before about that problem, where you're going to
have this, this nasty situation of the accumulator is not going to be
precise enough.
And that definitely does look like a problem.
All right, so I'm not sure exactly what we should do about that.
I'll have to think about it.
What we can do is we can make the since the sample position is
actually relatively important to us.
What we could do is we could spend
The money we could spend the money on making sample position.
Actually, the accurate.
That's not particularly hard to do.
Right.
We could totally do that whether we want to do that, I don't know.
But if we did want to do it, I can show you how we would do that.
And then I guess I would just have to think about whether it's what we
want to do.
So here's how you would spend the money to do that.
So when we come through here, we end up with this, you know, this D
sample chunk which is basically saying how much we want to move.
Overtime, right?
And for something like volume, that's totally fine because we don't
care for a little bit off when we get to the end.
No one's going to be able to tell.
But with the sample position since we care about things like where
buffers end and all that sort of stuff, we may want to be more careful
about that.
And so what we want to do here is basically change up to saying that
we instead of a sample position that's accumulated over time and where
the floating point or you can build up what we want to do is say we
have a begin sample position and that we have
And Sample position, right?
And our begin sample position is just going to be equal to samples
played, right?
And our n sample position is just going to be whatever our begin
sample position was.
And we would like it to come out to be whatever.
The, the actual ending was that we have in mind up here, right?
In fact, what we could do is move this up here and actually do this
calculation exactly perfect as well, right?
So we could say,
Well, the begin sample position should be, you know, samples played
the N sample position should be whatever the begin sample position
was, you know, plus you know, the chunks to mix times the D sample
chunk, right?
Like so on.
In fact, that's probably fine now.
I think we can only be off by a little bit, so never mind.
We don't have to do it.
If we don't have to do it that exact we can just do it like this down
here.
So the chunks to mix, we multiply by the do sample.
Chunk, that will give us the beginning in the end, right?
And then instead of saying
Position being an accumulator.
What we would do here is we would just get rid of that concept
altogether.
We would get rid of the accumulator, we would say that this was going
to be n sample position, right?
So we just hop right to it there.
And then sample position would just be single we back compute as we
step, right?
So the way that we would do that is we say, well, we know that Loop
index goes from zero to chunks to mix, right?
So what we want to do is have some way of quickly recovering what the
samples played should be.
I don't start with sampler to be
Based on that Loop index.
So, you want to take the loop index and we basically want to multiply
it by a coefficient, right?
Which is, you know, one over chunks to mix, basically, right?
That makes sense.
So that as it moves towards chunks to mix, we
We get closer and closer to 1, we get we get closer closer to whatever
the value is that we wanted, right?
In fact, we don't really want image.
That would that would move from 0 to 1.
We still have to multiply, we still have to blend between these two
guys.
So what we can actually do is I guess we can do that a little bit more
straightforward.
What we can do is, is this right plus Loop index see which is just
whatever we would have to multiply Loop index by, to move it to n
sample position, right?
And so, what's that going to be right?
Well, we know that we're going to have it range from zero to chunks to
mix - one like the final one is going to be chunks to mix.
Minus 1, right?
And this n sample position, of course we don't want to actually end
there that's like one past where we want to end, right?
Because the chunks to mix, that's how many we will be at, after we do
the last one not before.
So I believe that Loop in this coefficient is just going to be
whatever.
The final, whatever the and Sample vision is - the beginning sample
position.
So however far we have to go / whatever the
Chunks to mix is right and that way we can just take Loop index.
And and with a multiplying an ad here, we can just go ahead and
reconstructs a position entirely and we don't have to accumulate it,
right.
I think that's a little bit more correct.
Let's take a look.
So, let's see.
Here is our bad case again.
Let's see how we do this time.
So we come through here and we're going to end C and put sample.
Oops, that's not what I meant to do input sample, and it's we come in
here and let's see our samples played, that's perfect right.
Where we thought it should be.
That's great.
Yeah.
So hopefully that makes some sense what I did there and I'm going to
explain it just kind of really simply on the on the Blackboard for a
second just so people understand because it's pretty useful thing for
people to know.
So let me just go ahead and say it pretty pretty straightforward here.
So accumulation
Versus I guess I should say accumulation versus explicit.
I don't know what you want to call the, the other kind, I think about
it.
So, if you have something like, we had, where we need to the sample
position and that's that operation right?
There's two ways that we could phrase it.
So, we have some value, right?
We have taught, you know, we have some Loop index, I guess we'll just
call it.
And, you know, for any given I were coming out with some value, right?
And this case, it's the sample position, right?
So in this case we've got our F of I is going to be the sample
position.
Now, if you can just there's there's different ways that we could
choose to compute this right?
One way that we could choose to compute It Is by picking whatever the
first thing is.
So whatever.
F of 0 is right?
And then adding I
Times the times, whatever the the the Delta is right.
Whatever the Delta is from from, you know, from one from one to the
next, right?
So, we can always say, okay, we can start at the first value and we
can recover any one of these values right by just multiplying,
whichever one we are on by however much.
The change is per per step, right?
That's when we do it another way to do it, right?
Is saying that, well, whatever the f of I is, it's just recursive,
right?
So F of 0 is going to equal something and F of I is just going to
equal, you know, it's you know what they inductive I guess is what
this was be called.
You know, like those inductive proofs that might be a reasonable name
for it, it's just going to be whatever the previous one was right.
Plus the delta
Does that make sense?
And so we were using this method here.
We were basically saying okay we're going to start F of 0 at some
value, right?
Whatever it is, right?
The samples played.
And then anytime we need an f.
I we're just going to assume that we kept whatever the previous one
is, and we're going to add in whatever the Delta is.
So we would have loops, you know, we have our for Loop here, right?
And what we would do is we would say something like, oh at the top, we
would just say, you know, whatever our value is.
Equals something and then in here we would say our value equals
whatever the Delta is, right?
So that would correspond to this this kind of a construction, right?
That's this is how we would do it.
And the problem with that is every time you do an addition like that,
you can have a rounding error, right?
Because floating-point only has a certain amount of precision.
And so when you're dealing with numbers, like we were with like 9 1,
.9, F was like the step size or whatever.
They're when you're dealing with with a fractional stuff like that.
You get rounding error every time you do that.
And we know that these numbers are like, you know, 400 right?
Or something like this, right?
So we have 400 rounding errors building themselves up, as we do this,
This right, rounding error rounding, error rounding, error rounding,
error, rounding error, rather.
So you do an operation like this, once you don't necessarily care,
that's got rounding error.
You an operation like this eight hundred times, and each one depends
on the previous one.
You compound, the rounding, error, rounding, error, rounding, error,
rounding error.
And hey, when you get to the end, it's not where you expect it to be
by quite a bit.
On the other hand, if we were to do it like this, then we only have
rounding error in a couple places.
We only have rounding error on this.
Add this multiply and the original storage amount of these values,
which by the way we had here as well, right?
So, we had rounding error, just in Computing, the values to begin with
that didn't change between the two.
And so this one just has, you know, to rounding errors in it and this
one has the loop count number of rounding errors in it.
And so, you know, sometimes you care and in this
Particular case, we care.
As you can see, from it actually happening in practice.
So, in this case, it's free free for us to do the
calculations this way.
And so, since we are doing that since we, since we have found that a
reasonable thing to be concerned about it seems like maybe the things
that are done that way, should just be all back computed right?
Because we could do the same thing here, right?
For our volumes.
Instead of having them be a human errors which would also be highly
erroneous.
Potentially what we could do is make them into the M1, 28 for volume.
Zero and volume one here at that are just computed this exact same
way.
So they're mmps is of whatever the begin volumes are and then we just
multiply D volume chunk, right?
MLPs by again, whatever this, this sort of
A value based on the loop index basically, right?
So we're at the Q&A.
Well, you know what?
That I won't do that.
I will do it tomorrow.
If we rescue a, you know, exactly what I'm about to do.
So anyone who wants to do that tonight, for homework can go ahead and
do that, but it is time for the Q&A now.
So let's go ahead and do that.
And then what I'd also like to do.
So I'll move that up there so I guess.
Do Casey, move volume here to explicit.
And the other thing we would want to do there is make sure that we are
always think.
Well I think that's all good.
Yeah.
I think that's all good but we could do is double we could just be
absolutely sure here we can say if playing sound samples played is
less than zero equals zero just to just to add a little bit extra.
The unnecessary security.
All right.
Does anyone have any questions on that please prefix the questions
with Q: so that I will see them.
You folks know the drill
Girl, Linda Bloom says you're a rad dude.
Technically.
No not anymore.
I don't work for rad anymore.
I used to work for rad.
And and so that would have made me a rad dude, but nowadays, I'm a
normal dude.
What would you recommend as a good tutorial Source or area to learn
how to code?
Well, to be honest, I don't know.
I it's on my list of things to do some day to make a good tutorial
series for brand new people, which is, you know, handmade Heroes kind
of for people who sort of know how to program.
And so you know, the the day one of handmade hero is still fairly
assumes.
You know, some familiarity with programming.
There is a five-part intro to see series that I did as a test stream
before handmade hero but it's, you know, it's only five days so it
doesn't really cover everything.
Thing that would actually need to be covered.
So,
you know, someday there's probably a good hundred day series or
something to do, which is just like introduction to programming for
people who've never done it before but I don't know what's good in Leo
of that.
Robot chocolate Dino, is your Cindy clear 20 faster than a memset?
So I would assume just thinking off the top of my head, I would assume
that they would both be the same speed but I don't know.
That's my assumption.
And the reason I say that is just because the majority of the time of
that clear is going to be just streaming out the memory.
So I would assume that no matter how you did it, it would be fine, we
might be a little faster.
We could maybe a little bit faster because we know that the things are
aligned and memset might have to test for us to say that they were
aligned.
But you know, I mean, if you want to look, if you if you want to get
some perspective on what it's doing,
In there, you can certainly try and see what ends up happening.
So you know if
I was to come in here and actually do the same stuff, right?
So, if I wanted to mess that, you know, death zero with chunk count X
size of mmm 128, like, so.
And I think that's the format for memset quite remember.
But if we, you know, if we did something like that,
See here.
Sorry I got a little business.
I'd so if we did something like that you should be able.
Well I got actually have memset better.
What is it?
Memory .h.
Yeah there we go.
So you know we can take a look at these guys just to get a feel for
what it's actually happening.
And so if we take a look in here, you can see what's going on, right?
We're just doing move aps's in a loop like, so, right.
And I'll be honest, I I don't really understand why it looks like
that, but so you can see this is the instruction stream, right?
For that.
That's happening.
All right so you can watch it.
Go.
So to get some idea of what's involved.
That's, that's what's involved.
I think for the most part, right?
And we could we can grab this out, put it into the scratch buffer.
That's that's what's actually right getting executed.
And we could so you can see you can see exactly what it's doing to
write.
Its incrementing the values and then
I'm storing them out.
So you can see here, it's taking rcx.
And storing it in a temporary, right?
Rcx is the pointer the desk 0 pointer.
It's an incrementing, the dussehra pointer and then using the old
value that it kept the temporary to do the store.
Then it goes ahead and again, gets a temporary for for our, for our BX
and and does the exact same thing now.
You know, I'm not really an x 64 guy.
If Fabien were here, I would ask him why it's doing it that way,
because it feels like you just rearrange these and just do xmm word
pointer rcx, right?
And then add to our CX afterwards, so that you can get rid of this
mauve.
But I suspect assuming, I mean, the compartment just be dumb, right?
And that made us just been a
But thing to do, but assuming that that's a smart thing to do, it may
be that there's a good reason why you don't want to do that because
you want to like overload.
You know, you want this ad to be overlapped with the move APS and so
you want both values live or something.
I don't know.
So, anyway, but that's the entirety of the code for our memset.
So now what we can do, is look at the code for the memset in the C
library,
Which is here.
And so, so, here we go.
Into that and you know, we're going we're going there.
So yeah, I mean just looking at this I guess I would say, I think we
probably should be either the same speed or faster because their Loop
is not not doing aligned and it's not doing wide.
So you know are we going to be faster?
Because it's probably just Bound by memory.
Anyway, are we going faster?
I don't know but I don't.
We could be slower, right?
Because I mean, look at this.
That's just, you know, that's definitely doing things less efficiently
than we were doing them if that makes sense.
So, and just to give you a comparison there, again, I don't
necessarily know the nature of your question.
Just trying to give you some perspective on how you could investigate
things like this.
So, you know, looking at this
So you look at how this is, this is working.
It's doing some kind of nastiness here, where I guess it decided that
it could write out several of these at a time, right?
You can see it.
Doing, writing out to rcx that RC X plus eight, then R CX plus 16.
So it's writing out like, you know, it 388 B values of time and then
it's moving.
Forward and writing backwards you know it's writing the you know - 28
- 20 - 18 negative 10 negative 8 so it's writing up right?
And so they're writing eights at a time and we're writing 16s and they
really don't have much less business.
Now what they do do is they do a little bit wider.
So you know, they have less iterations of the loop to do.
Because here's they're doing, we're writing 16s at a time they're
writing.
One, two, three, four.
So they're writing for different 16s at a time so they might get more
of a win for having from having less business to do with increments
because they have reduced the number of increments, right?
So there's that as well.
So you know, that's that's I guess what I'd say is you know now you
have some perspective on who's doing
If you really want to know which one's faster though same answer as
always, you got to time it and you got to time it in real world
scenarios.
So you would have to actually go in here and you know,
have passed something that actually did and if 0 around these two
guys, you know that did did this sort of thing actually get it in a
big enough thing the matter and then actually time it
But yes, so hopefully that gives you some perspective though, and you
saw, I did that, right?
So if you want to just get an idea of who's doing, what you can just
step into this assembly in an optimized build you notice.
I switched it optimized for us because otherwise the compiler, who
knows if I was going to do, but that would, you know, gives you just a
little bit perspective, what's going on?
If you actually didn't want to get down to the bottom of it of who's
really going to be faster again, you're going to have to time it.
But now at least you know who does what
Do you have a public style guide?
I guess I don't know what a public style guide is.
No.
I guess would be the answer.
I'm looking to learn something other than Java so I can have diverse
knowledge.
Any recommendations on how to go about doing that.
Well, I guess my recommendation would depend on what was that you were
trying to to diversify towards.
So like handmade hero for example, what we do here would be really
good for you if you were trying to diversify into like more low-level
programming and knowing exactly what the computer actually does with
the code that you write and how you manage memory and how you do a
bunch of things like that.
Because Java is usually about abstract you know being very abstract in
those ways.
You know you're on a virtual machine, you have all these other things,
you don't really connect with the CPU and stuff like that.
So you know, that's a good thing.
But you know, that may not be what you're trying to diversify into it,
what you're trying to diversify into.
It's like I want to try writing in a pure functional language or
something, right?
I want to know what that's like, or, right?
There's a lot of different Avenues you could explore.
I want to know what a declarative - like I like
Want to go play around prologue for a while because right, that would
really mess with your head.
So I think the the answer there really has to be about what do you
actually want your diverse diversity to be about?
And if it really is just every, a little bit of everything, then I
would say you probably want to do all sorts of stuff.
Do a little tiny product and ml do a little bit, you know, watch a
little handmade hero, do a little of this.
Do a little of that, right?
Go follow the instructions for making your own operating system on
Raspberry Pi.
You know, do do a whole bunch of different small things.
If all you want is just general diversity but if you have a particular
Avenue that you're looking at, when you're like I want to diversify
more in this direction, then I would say, think about what that is and
what kinds of projects you could do.
That would be most directly speaking to that.
At what point did you first feel like you could easily write software
independently?
I would say that I probably when I was 16.
and then I lost it again when I was 18 because I started doing
object-oriented programming, which is awful and then I gained it back
again, probably around twenty one, twenty two, when I switch back to
not just during programming,
Why is the sample index floating point?
Is it for the pitch shifting?
Yeah it is for the pitch, shifting it so that we can have the sample
back samples playback at an arbitrary rate.
Why do gaming companies like riots or Blizzard Entertainment to use?
C++ over all the rest would the other is not work.
So I mean, honestly, the answer there usually has to do with control.
I would say the way to look at C and C++ and why they are prevalent in
the game.
Industry is usually about risk management and control if you write,
you know, think about the scale at which these people are operating,
okay?
You take a game like League of Legends because you mentioned dry it.
There are many billions of dollars a year riding on that game for Ryan
entertainment, right?
I mean, it is, it is economically.
A massive, massive product
Now, if you program in C or C++ then, you know, one very basic thing
and that is that you pretty much will never have any unexpected thing
that you did not create.
Cause your game to slip or crash, or not run on a bun feels machines
or whatever, right?
You know, that that can't happen with your piece of code.
Now, it can still happen with the graphics driver and don't get me
started on that.
But what, you know is C and C++, is you compiled?
To a binary and everything that's happening in the game.
You wrote.
now, if on the other hand, you were to write it in say python
You now have no idea, right?
You could get to some part of your development process and all of a
sudden, something about pythons, internals starts rearing, its ugly
head.
And now, all of a sudden, you have absolutely no ability to actually,
do whatever it is that you need to ship your game because something,
in the core of python that you were using is, is busted, right?
And now your team suddenly has to shift from being an expert in League
of Legends, which is what they were suppose to be programming and you
have to switch over to being an expert on Python and write your own
python interpreter or take the open-source one and change it or do all
the other sort of things, right?
And so I suspect that since games have always been about important
hard performance, things 30 frames per second, 60 frames per second
maximizing.
You know, the impact that the technology has on the player experience,
all these sorts of things that other Tech other domains don't tend to
care about very much and don't have Central to their being
I would say that because of that.
They sort of probably, you know, I think that the industry grew up
with a very deep.
And I think probably well-founded mistrust of these technologies that
are meant to save programmer Time by saying, well, we don't really
know what happens in there is some memory, it's gets used and there's
some interpreters and they do some stuff, right.
And so, the C and C++ part is about that connection between knowing
that what you write controls directly with the CPU does, and you have
a very easy path of reasoning about what it will cost to do every
individual thing and there are no surprises so you can't get to a
point and then suddenly something you do that's very simple.
Completely changes the performance dynamics of your game that doesn't
happen, right?
Whereas in pretty much all the other prevalent languages Java, C sharp
python, it's not true because there's a virtual memory.
I'm sorry, there's a virtual machine underneath.
If you there's a garbage collector underneath you, who dares like all
kinds of built-in types that God knows what they do, blah blah blah,
right?
And so really I think that is what underlies, the mindset.
I think that game developers would like higher-level language stuff,
but I think they would like to have it in a way that doesn't pose
those risks, which are real and if you don't believe me, you can go
read, like the Minecraft maintainer as talking about how there's huge
hiccups in the performance because of the Java garbage collector
running and what they tried to do to work around
Didn't know Bob lot, right?
And all this sort of stuff.
So you know, I think that's, that's the thing and if your project
never happens to hit those things then you know, that's okay.
And so if you're a tiny developer and you're just making a game and
you're like I want to use C sharp and you know, you go use it and even
if maybe you do encounter some problems, maybe that's not the end of
the world, right?
But your Riot and two billion dollars or something,
Is riding on you guys, not hitting these snags that cause serious
problems or not doing whatever.
And you don't want that risk.
And I think they just, you know, the people who work on the stuff,
just don't want to accept that they don't want, except that level of
uncertainty and that loss of control.
And that's also why you'll see some very paradoxical things happen in
the game industry.
Like people will write their own scripting language or something.
That has all the same drawbacks but from their perspective, that's
okay.
Because they made those decisions and they are an expert in that
scripting language implementation because they wrote it and so they're
not afraid of hitting some mysterious problem in someone else's
technology that was unforeseen.
Right.
You might think of it almost like a Titanic iceberg thing.
If you like, there's plenty of icebergs, right?
In C sharp
And there's plenty of icebergs in Java performance icebergs.
If you are some little dinghy with a little outboard motor and you're
like just tooling around out there.
Your parental care.
If you hit the iceberg, like your little guy.
I'll get kind of stuck on there and you just like push it off and then
you'll like go away, right?
If you're the Titanic you can't afford to hit that Iceberg like it's
really costly.
And so I think that's just the case with you know, AAA development
where you're like if we are doing this massive scale development and
we have all of these risks already that are separate things and all
this other stuff, we are not willing to take on a language that we
know, has these dangers in it.
Because we can't prove to ourselves ahead of time that we won't hit
them and we don't want to take on the burden of managing someone
else's entire development system.
If we find out that there is a problem and then have to go be the ones
to fix it, right?
So I would say that, you know, is probably the way to look at it,
that's an opinion.
Obviously the truth is probably much more complicated and varies
across many studios.
And so there is no Pat answer that really can satisfy.
All of the reasons that people use C++ versus using some of their
language, but I feel like that's a fairly solid one.
That is at least.
Least somewhat widely applicable, which is just that programmers.
You care a lot about performance and know that they have to hit 30 60
frames a second.
On a diversity of Platforms in a lot of scenarios and need that
control.
Just don't feel comfortable based on the track records of these
languages embracing them in that way.
And that may change in the future but right now it's still kind of the
case pretty much for all the major
for all the AAA game studios that are out there.
So Sean McGrath says, no League of Legends is written in Flash.
So I guess, there you go.
So there there's, there's an answer for you.
League of Legends is written in Flash which is, which is totally not
that.
I've never actually played League of Legends.
So I don't know.
I just assumed that, right?
You C++, because you asked the question that they did, but I don't
know anything about Riot themselves.
I guess I do know that Blizzard Entertainment wrote World of Warcraft
and C++, but
I believe and I could be wrong about this but I believe that Blizzard
Entertainment used.
C sharp for Hearthstone.
Right because it or something, didn't they use Unity for Hearthstone
or something?
Which I and unity C sharp, right?
I mean obviously the underlying stuff is all C++, but some portion of
the game heart, like the game part of our Stone written in C sharp.
So, you know, that's an example of a AAA studio and that's not, you
know, one of their sort of Tripoli titles in the 3D Graphics, sensor,
whatever.
But it is a major release from them, right?
It's a it wasn't a minor release.
It was a
Was a real thing.
So you know they were obviously willing to accept C sharp for the at
least the game side of the code assuming that I'm remembering that
correctly.
That that just seems to be my recollection.
I don't know anything about League of Legends, if it was really
written in Flash, that's hilarious because League of Legends.
It's funny to think of the fact that Binding of Isaac, can't run
properly and Flash.
And it's just that one thing, whereas League of Legends, this is big
game and that worked in Flash.
That's crazy.
If that's true.
They must be much better at flash, I guess Than The Binding of Isaac
folks for our something, I don't know.
That's, that's kind of wild.
All right, Shawn.
You've now been you've been corrected.
They say no League of Legends was written in C.
Plus only the login client is in flash.
We'll look, I don't know what Riot rights in.
I have no friends at Riot, even I guess I have friends that ride right
now but they were not involved in League of Legends.
I would be shocked to learn.
That was written in Flash.
Like I wouldn't have been shocked to learn.
It was written in like, C, sharp or something, but flash is so slow.
Like, I would be kind of shocked if it could have been written in
Flash, because Flash is Flash is like kind of on the worst end of that
Spectrum, right?
Like, like C sharp is a lot more thought
Through then flashes, you know.
Yes, it has garbage collection.
Yes, whatever.
And you know, is it something I would rely on?
No, but there's a real big difference between relying on flash and
Lansky sharp.
But yeah, so I would be shocked to learn that League of Legends was
actually written in Flash.
I would be pretty surprised.
So yeah.
Also, there is a new version of Binding of Isaac that is not in Flash.
Well, yeah, but it's Binding of Isaac rebirth, right?
You can't actually get in a version of the original Binding of Isaac.
That's, not in Flash, which I wish you could, because I really like
the original and wasn't.
I wasn't much for the new one, so I wish that I could get the original
in non-flash but I guess what I'll just do is I'll wait 10 years to
computers are so fast that it can actually run a 2-D game.
2-D game at frame, right.
And then I'll be able to run the original, I guess.
SMC McGrath.
SSS, Mr.
McGrath are is Flash, though.
Aaron flash are basically the same, right?
Like are is just the packaging, the, the packaging for Flash because
Binding of Isaac was written in are as well, in that sense like you
can when you get the Standalone it it'll come with it comes in are for
him but that's not
It's really no difference between those two things that I know about.
Gaston five, what's the difference between arbitrary and random?
I guess I'm not sure what context you mean in?
Random and arbitrary can mean very different things in certain
contexts I suppose.
But I'm not sure what the context is that you're asking.
Those are always just adjectives and what they apply to makes a big
difference.
I'm trying to guess.
I think that air has the same runtime.
I believe that it's the same runtime as
that's just the normal flash, interpreter that you would install if
you download it from Adobe.
As far as I know, they don't maintain two separate run times but I
could be wrong about that.
Gaston 5 in the mathematical sense.
Well, so in the mathematical sense, Something That Is Random.
is actually has a bunch of properties like, you know, non
predictability and even distributions and or you know, these sorts of
things
So it's arbitrary.
Just means that you didn't care.
Like there was no reason for it, right?
So I don't know, I guess you'd have to ask student him 73.
If there's a mathematical definition of arbitrary.
There might be a rigorous.
Mathematical definition for arbitrary, but I don't know that I've ever
seen arbitrary used in a precise way.
What would you rather write a game in Java or C sharp eye?
If I had if for some reason, my situation was that I could only write
a game in Java or C sharp like that was what I had to do.
I would quit the game industry.
That would that would be the end of it.
Like I have no interest in programming in either of those languages
ever for any reason.
So if that's what I had to do I just quit and go do something.
I do something else with my life before I would write in one of those
languages they hold absolutely no interest.
Have you ever smoked weed and programmed?
I have never smoked weed.
Actually.
So no, it is legal here in Washington state.
So I guess that would be a pretty easy thing to do.
But I just I have never done it.
Sorry.
Jonathan Blow says that the Axiom of choice is kind of about
arbitrariness and is kind of controversial.
So there you go.
Hey, so John, if you're on the stream, can we do a reverse question?
Because all the way at the beginning of the stream?
Somebody asked me if I had designed the game before hand, because
designing it on stream.
Seems like it would be a bad idea, basically, because it would be too
much trial and error, right?
Or designing on the Fly, basically.
And what I said was, I designed the game ahead of time but just
because I'm not a game designer.
So I don't want the stream to be about game design because I don't
really have much to say in that regard.
So that's why I designed it ahead of time, but my feeling from
listening to you,
Well, as other designers that I respect, is that actually designing on
the Fly is a very important skill.
Like it's I felt like the question was operating on a mistaken premise
and I wanted somebody who really knew game design to weigh in on that
because I don't feel like I'm qualified to answer.
But that was my feeling was just that I felt like it was necessary to
correct the assumption that that sort of
Emergent design, where you're playing around with the design is
somehow not good because it felt to me, like what I had heard from
from you and others was that actually, that is a very important skill
and you definitely need to develop it and be able to do that if you're
a good designer.
So I just throw that question out there.
If you happen to be interested in typing in the answer, it's kind of a
yes or no question some degree I guess.
Okay, so let's go through the last couple questions here.
But wait, Johnny answered.
So he says I think designing on the Fly is very important.
Yes.
If you know everything you're going to do before you start, you
probably aren't doing something very interesting.
I think.
So yeah, that that is that is what I assumed was the answer from
having heard you and other people describe things.
But, you know, I just didn't really know myself because I'm not.
I don't really have those skills.
So
I hope the person who asked the question is still listening there.
You have a very definitive answer so so design on the Fly is actually
something you do.
I think want to learn to do, if you're going to be someone, I know
certainly personally if I was going to hire a game designer, I would
want to see that skill like I feel like it's really important but you
know, not having done game design much myself.
I feel like I should defer to experts on that.
And John also says for me and a lot of people whose games I like the
ideas behind the game are just enough to get you into a territory of
interestingness, but then you have to explore that territory which you
can't have done before you go there, which to me, sounds like a very
excellent way of putting it, right?
I mean, in some sense it's like saying, you know, I want to go explore
this forest or whatever.
Well you don't know exactly all the
That you're going to find there, you just have a feeling that it's
going to be interesting because you saw it and it looked kind of cool
from the outside, right?
So I don't know.
It seems, it seems to make good intuitive sense.
I don't know.
Let's see.
Why do you say 00 is awful?
Well, I think we've covered this quite a bit there.
I don't know that there's a really succinct way to say why but the the
general root of it is that programming is about telling a CPU what to
do.
And there is no concept of object orientation inside a CPU, like, it's
not a thing.
And so fundamentally.
What writing code is about is actually about figuring out what the
process is like what is the CPU going to do, right?
What's it actually going to do?
And then from when you figure out what the CPU has to do from there,
the objects are actually kind of obvious, right?
So the order of programming is figure out what the CPU is supposed to
do, figure out what the data needs to look like the support.
And that in turn is your definition of your objects, right?
And usually I don't even bother with the object part of it because I
don't even I think autosar.
So unimportant that I just think those bags of data, right?
So that's why we use structs on handmade hero because it's just like
the whole notion of an object in general I think is overblown and so
that process is the opposite of how object-oriented encourages you to
think, object-oriented encourage you to think it means in the word
object oriented.
It encourage you to think from the other direction.
Even so from the objects down to the CPU.
And that is very kind of productive because it has nothing to do with
the program.
Actually needs to do and you don't have to take my word for it.
Most people can actually census by intuition.
Most people, if you ask them to write code, to do a particular thing,
and you don't tell them about objects or a train or any faster.
If you just try to teach them basic stuff House of yours, they will
actually write relatively good code after a while.
They'll be like, oh, here's the things I need to do and I do them in
order invariably whenever I see people who
To do object oriented program.
It's massively over complicated and there's all of this additional
business in there.
That doesn't actually help the CPU actually do things and tends to get
in the way.
And in the worst case it's like slows things down or makes things more
brittle or make things harder to work with than the code.
And so what I usually like to say is just the project problem with
object-oriented programming is not the objects.
It's the oriented, it's the fact that you're orienting around the
objects, I don't care if the code has objects in it or not.
It's the orientation around the objects as the problem with
object-oriented programming and that focus on thinking, that things
have to become.
That they have to be encapsulated.
That is the goal is all unnecessary.
Baggage that gets in the way of good programming.
And so that's the reason that I don't like object-oriented and it's
also unfortunate something that's kind of sometimes hard to explain.
Because people seem to think that
That like certain single things that might show up in object-oriented
programming.
Sometimes means you're doing ab training programming.
Like, I actually had someone say to me, specifically, I'll give you
example.
The fact that I have functions where I take a thing as a first
parameter as the pointer is object oriented programming.
So they would consider like you know output playing sounds to be
object-oriented because it has audio State as the first parameter and
it's a function that kind of like logically live
If the audio state, right?
If that's where your brain is, I don't know what to say.
Usually those people just get a mute on Twitter so I never have to
hear from them again because I don't even know how like I don't know
where you go with that, right?
And if the person is super nice about it fine, but it never is, right?
The people who make those comments are usually like to make it in a
very snide and annoying way, which you know, is fine.
If you're trying to go argue with some somebody who actually cares
about arguing,
About as far as I'm concerned, people who are program, our journey
programming, who are really dedicated to that method and want to argue
about it.
I just assumed they'd let them right.
Like I it's hey it less competition for me for fright.
I would rather at some level other programmers program poorly as job
security.
It's I'm not going to argue with them about it.
Yeah.
But maybe that's a mistake because it means you know, maybe that's
that's why all the
The stuff that I try to use on daily basis is all broken.
I don't know.
So who knows.
So yeah.
So that's, you know, object-oriented programming in a nutshell for me.
It's the oriented part that I don't like.
But it's I'm not some kind of weird fanatic.
I do like other kinds of programming, like I the functional
programming I think is very good.
I try to do things in a functional form often times, even in C, which
is not a functional language, but obviously, it supports the ability
to write things that are functional because you can just not have
side.
Effects.
Right?
So I do like there.
I think there are a lot of saying programming methodologies.
I don't I'm not a zealot who thinks there's only one right way to
write a program.
I'm what I am zealous about is that object-oriented is not a right way
so I'm more of a like anti oop I'm not necessarily Pro.
Some other thing as exclusive, I think there's a number of good attack
skills for how you program.
Data oriented programming, very interesting, functional style is very
interesting.
Are all like techniques that can work together, whatever.
I think of things in terms of compression.
I've said, many times compression oriented programming.
I think those are all great things and I hope people learn to do them.
It's really just just object-oriented, just happens to be really bad,
and I've never found anything useful or good about it and so, I'm kind
of zealously against it.
Because I find that so many people think it's a good idea and have
absolutely, no, actual evidence of that.
Like, I've never actually been able to see someone show me here is
The place where this was a really good way to think about this problem
and so it's like not right?
But yeah, but I'm not a zealot for some other particular thing, I
think there's a lot of good techniques out there programming wise.
And actually I think good programmers tend to have more than one
attack skill, right?
They tend to have a lot of different ways that they think about
programming and they pick which ones they want to use based on the
circumstances and how things are going.
I think.
Will hand me here support physics, simulation and rendering in
different threads.
So it already does actually, like, rendering ground chunks happens on
a separate thread front, while the simulation is occurring right now,
so that, that already happens.
B3z man 41.
You make it sound like those things.
We just have no purpose.
They're great for other things than Game Dev.
I disagree.
I don't like them for anything.
Not just game development, so, you know, if you like them, that's
great.
You know, you should use whatever language you want to use, but I am
not going to use them.
Shoot him 76.
As arbitrary as the bottom element of a mathematical lattice see as
well.
Systems blog Cliff, 2012 0212 too, much theory for details.
So hopefully whoever is asking that question did actually look up that
for details.
What do you do?
In order to help prevent carpal tunnel syndrome?
Does it get real bad?
Anything particular you try and avoid?
I don't really know anything about carpal tunnel syndrome.
I've never had carpal tunnel syndrome.
if I don't wear these my wrist braces, I get tendonitis in like right
here typically and for whatever reason we're in Greece braces, I don't
But I've never really had carpal tunnel syndrome, which I think is
where you start to lose some some feeling hero.
The other thing I have is, if I don't keep my my wrists and arm like
also elbow, like and shoulders, I find, I do get a little, like, nerve
impingement up here stuff.
And I start to lose some feeling in my fingers.
But carpal tunnel is about, is about nerve restriction in here.
And I've never really had that.
My understanding is that is not as common in men it's much more common
in women because they have narrower I guess passage for the nerves in
here whereas men.
Have a wider one.
And so my understanding was actually a lot of times like like people
think they have carpal tunnel syndrome maybe but they haven't actually
determined that.
That's actually what they have.
So a lot of times if a guy thinks they have carpal tunnel syndrome, I
would say make sure that's actually what you have.
If you or if you think you might have that because what you may have
something else, right?
And then trying to fix carpal tunnel syndrome isn't going to help you
because that's not what you have, right?
So you want to make sure you actually know, if you're having hand
issues, you want to make sure.
Sure that, you know, whether you have like tendonitis or a nerve
impingement somewhere, or carpal tunnel or whatever, first before you
try to do it, which can be tough to diagnose but you can try things,
try experiments, you know, keeping various areas, warm aligning, you
know, changing the alignment of how you're doing things wearing braces
on different parts.
Try to figure out what does and does not affect it is definitely worth
doing before you try to cure something that you don't maybe
necessarily have.
Well something that you do have is going unchecked, which can be a
problem.
Let's see, I miss part of the stream.
So you may have answered this.
Do you know of any opengl resources that actually explain why they are
doing what they are doing the arc synthesis tutorials?
I try to mention because I think those are pretty good but honestly,
no, I really don't.
It's under documented.
It's definitely under documented
Guest 05.
So by what you said, can I conclude that you have not written a game?
Design document.
Well, yes and no.
I actually do have a fair bit of game design stuff.
I don't like I said, I'm not a formal game designer, so I don't really
know very much about writing a game design document because you put
that in capital letters like it was a very specific thing.
Sounds like the kind of thing.
A producer wants where it's like 150 pages and
Lots of verbose verbosity.
Third your aha.
So 0 is kind of like when you design a game ahead.
Yeah, I mean, and like I tried to impress, hopefully, in fact, the
stream, we've mentioned it many times.
Now, I just my understanding from really good game designers is that
you don't want to design a game up front like that.
Like, that's not how you do it.
And the same is true of code.
The reason I'm doing that I have made here is I, you know, I'm not a
game designer that's that's not my skill set.
And so I tried to put together a design that I'd be like, okay, here's
a
Has of things that we'd have to implement, you know, it'll be
interesting hopefully but you know it's I'm not a game designer.
I can't promise you anything about handmade hero being some amazing
game design because that's just, that's not what I do.
Can made here as a programming project, it's a game.
It's about game development knocking design.
And so, you know, if and I will, when we get to the game part of
things, you know, like I said maybe today, 200 250 somewhere around
there.
I'm not sure when we'll switch over to doing mostly game work and not
really doing the engine stuff anymore.
What what I will say often and just to make sure everyone knows is
like, it's still about game programming.
Even at that point, right?
I'm showing how to implement a bunch of game design things.
And I've picked the game design things to try to make it so that we
have to
You a lot of the same kinds of code that we would have to do in any
intricate sort of advanced game design, but I'm not trying to show you
how to game design.
I do not think you would want to make a game design up front like that
if you were actually trying to make a game and it was about making a
great design.
And so, you know, that's a whole different skill set that you will
need to learn from someone else's stream because I do not know
anything about games.
Zayn and I cannot help you there.
I can only show you how to make a game from a design that someone else
does.
And hopefully that will be enough for anyone to work with who has
design skills.
And if you don't have design skills, there's nothing I can say other
than beg John to do a tutorial or beg.
Someone else who's a great game designer to to do a tutorial or
something because there's
Nothing I can do to help you there.
That there's nothing I can do.
Is this project plan to be a game playable for real in quotes or more
like, quote, how I create games.
I'm not sure what you mean, but this game will be should be totally
professional programming throughout meaning, when you actually play
it, it will feel expertly tuned, the code will run extremely smoothly,
you know, no loading screens.
No craziness, everything streamed, everything's super responsive.
It should be absolutely top-notch code wise and yankton's also doing
some pretty fantastic art for it.
So I think it will also look very good.
The only thing like I said is not a game designer and the design is
specifically selected to force us to do a bunch of programming things.
So, game design wise, it will be relatively traditional, don't expect
anything, crazy, groundbreaking or whatever in the design.
Because that is off-limits for this project.
Since we are talking about oh programming languages, I must ask how do
you feel about Pearl?
Haven't used much Pearl.
I think I wrote it.
Like one or two Perl scripts, but
I didn't think it was particularly noteworthy, but I didn't spend
enough time with it to form an educated opinion.
Do you feel Minecraft is a success because of the idea rather than the
execution for the first time ever?
Well I don't know that that you could say that Minecraft was the first
time that something was successful because of an idea rather than the
execution, I think they're probably have been games in the past that
were successful because of their idea rather than their execution.
But yeah, probably.
I mean, you know, there's a lot of things about Minecraft that could
have been executed better than they were but like anything else.
If you have a unique enough thing that you make, and it happens to hit
that sweet spot of something that people really want to play.
Then you can get a lot of slack in the execution, right?
And so, you know that's great, if you can do it personally,
I haven't played Minecraft.
I don't really know much about it so I don't really have an opinion
about why it was successful or anything I just know that.
Obviously if you look at screenshots of Minecraft obviously you could
have imagined a much more polished version of that game.
But you know whether that's how relevant that is, I don't know.
You could also Imagine a less polished version of it, right?
So they did polish it to a certain degree.
So, I don't know.
All right, think we've come to the end.
We've come to the end of the questions.
Someone asked dynamically generated Maps.
Yes, the maps will be dynamically generated there, in fact, already
dynamically generated.
We just don't have any actual code to generate interesting Dynamic
Maps, but it actually does generate the map at the beginning.
It's just stand in.
So it's a really boring map.
All right, all right, everyone.
I'm going to wind its down.
I'm going to wind it down.
So, let's go ahead and close this guy.
And switch over here.
Alright everyone, thank you for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home you can always
do.
So if you preorder the game on handmade here at org, you can get the
source code, which I upload every night after I am done.
So, if you'd like to play around with it and experiment, do whatever
you want to do there.
As part of learning to program, you can do.
So
And also we have a forum site if you want to ask questions there, we
also have a patreon page, you can go to.
If you would like to support the video series that we do here.
And we also have a tweetbot that tells you when the video series is
live on Twitch, so you can plan to be here.
If it's something that you want to catch live, that's the place to do
it.
I will be back here again.
Tomorrow, 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight time.
I think the mixer is basically done.
I would like to move
I'm out too explicit since it seemed like that was useful thing to do
and maybe we should support stereo sounds which would just be calling
that Loop twice in the case where we have stereo.
So I don't know.
You know, I think maybe one more day would be a good idea and we'll
take a look.
So let's go ahead and plan on doing one more day audio tomorrow and
then probably move on to the asset pack file stuff, which I think
should be pretty straightforward because we've pretty much already
done, the vast majority.
Any of the work that we need to do for it.
So it's going to be a bit like shooting fish in a barrel.
Now why fish would be in a barrel and why you would feel the need to
shoot them at that point?
I don't know.
But that's just what the saying is.
So until tomorrow everyone have a good one and I will catch you guys
on the internet.
Take it easy.