Hello, everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show Rico to complete game live on stream no engines, and no
libraries just like a lot of furious typing.
Sometimes not that Furious and drawing on the Whiteboard.
It's actually a Blackboard because it's a black backdrop but, you
know, it is
We are going to try and finish up our sparse, Unicode support today.
We basically did all of the thinking for it on Friday, but we did not
finish the actual code because we had a bunch of things, we kind of
had to switch around and so that's all I'm gonna do today.
We're just going to get that that all finished up day 175.
So if you are following along with the source code, if you preorder
the game on handmade hero dot-org, day 174 is source.
Code is the source code.
You want to start with.
That's a source code that I'm going to be starting with.
Today and so that is the source code that you yourself should start
with.
If you would like to be in lockstep your own, your very own home
version of handmade hero if you would like to follow along.
All right.
So where we sort of start stopped is we did not quite get to the point
where I think I was where I was even sort of satisfied that we had
finished doing the test asset Builder.
Stuff modifications that needed to happen.
So I'm going to go ahead and just take a walk through that.
Make sure that everything is actually done.
Because I suspect, we probably didn't quite finish, a bunch of it, and
just make sure that everything is, at least, at a certain level of
completion before I ever tried to load anything in on the other side,
right?
Okay.
So here we go.
I think I moved everything out to the outer side.
Yes, I did.
So, in the H file here, we have our loaded font in the loaded font.
We
Storing the stuff sort of non sparsely.
Right.
So you can kind of see we have our our tables here where we're going
to store the glyphs that's actually going to be sparse.
Then we're going to have our horizontal Advance which is not I guess
necessarily going to be
Going to be sparse, right?
Because it's going to be what it's going to actually be this way.
So, we have the horizontal Advanced is not quite sparse.
It's sparse along one dimension, but not along the other because we
don't know how many glyphs the users going to add.
We kind of left it so that the user.
Oh, good.
The next wants me to update right now.
You know what, I'm in the middle of a stream, so we've got that and
then we have to write it out.
And then we also have this glyph index from code Point thing which is
basically a translation table on the
Ian table allows us to go from a particular Unicode code point.
So this is not sparse again.
It's like well, I shouldn't say, it's not sparse, I'm saying that a
little bit wrong.
This is sparse right?
It's
Dense.
Horizontal Advance is sparse and one axis dense in the other glyphs is
dense.
Just period.
It's just the, the the ones that are actually being used stacked one
on top of each other and that's it, right?
So we've got all that and then when we actually store the stuff, we
store for each individual font, Cliff, we store whatever the code
point is for that Fang Cliff, right?
So now we're remembering.
And we're going to store that in the HHA as well.
And so that's all relatively sane.
Let's go ahead and take a look at everything to make sure that that I
feel like we, it's at least passes some sort of a sniff test.
Here's load font inside the load font.
We go ahead and load it all up.
We return the loaded font thing back, you know.
So it's like that way.
Everything's wrapped up in that struct.
So we can have multiple fonts if you want to and so on, we do our
select object to put it in.
There we go.
Ahead and do our
Spliff count in the max with count is just saying like, hey go ahead
and assume we're not going to have more than that, but users never
gonna send us more than that.
And you know cross your fingers.
This is only in the asset processor so we could always up it to it's
not a runtime thing.
So then we go in through here and we're talking about the the rest of
the cliff stuff, right?
So we say, how many of the loaded fonts are there going to be for the
maximum number of code points that we might have, right?
And this doesn't
This doesn't make any sense, right?
I don't think loaded, we don't want a loaded font for each of those,
right?
That doesn't make any sense.
Glyph index from code Point size is supposed to be one of these,
right?
There you go.
Yeah, this is why I like to use, you'll notice.
Did you see what the bug is there?
You will notice that in the actual code, I do this stuff for a reason,
right?
Just push array, you notice.
It does like the Typecast and it passes the count and then it uses
size of the same type.
That's like, a way of sort of, adding a little bit of type safety to
these sorts of things so that you can get the same thing as you would
get in a stronger type thing like like with a new or whatever.
Right.
And so that's just the kind of bug that you can avoid by doing it this
way.
That's why in the real code, I tend to be careful about that sort of
thing present as it processes.
Like a throwaway test things.
So I don't care.
Just since it happened, I'm just kind of like taking that opportunity
to point out its handy, right?
It's a handy thing that can catch errors for you.
All right, a really kind of prevent you from making them in the first
place.
Not so much, catch them, but they don't happen because since it's
based on taking the right size and returning the right,
So, anyway, we grab one of those, that's all good.
We clear it and that's important because we need to basically get rid
of them all up front, right?
We also kind of need, you know, we don't have yet, you know, looking
through this, we don't have a null glyph, which we kind of would like
to have.
So we got to think about that in a second.
But all right, we've got our font Cliffs here.
We Malik.
However, many glyphs there are going to be
Which is the matter of her me there.
Maximally could be
We allocate those and that's fine.
We go ahead and do a squared version of that for our horizontal
Advanced is so I guess the horizontal the horizontal Advanced actually
is dense on both axes.
Ah, I see it's dense, but it leaves some extra room, because it's
based on the Mac Swift count, not the actual growth count.
So it's got, like, sort of, it's like a sub-sub rectangle.
Inside a larger rectangle.
That's fine, we allocate that.
And we clear that as well.
All right, so that all seems totally fine, but like I said, our glyph
count is kind of a little bit wrong in some sense because we want to
reserve a no glyph, right?
We want we want to do something like Reserves.
Is for the null glyph, right?
So I want to say that glyph count, you know, actually equals 1.
So the like the zeroth glyph is it's not actually used and then
there's these actual glyphs themselves.
I would want to, you know, sort of set that zeroth Cliff to something
meaningful.
Right?
And those are, those are based on where's that those are based on.
HHA font glyph which is the thing that we're actually storing in the
file.
And so what I want to do is set the Unicode code point to something
that I, you know, I'm never going to use and I want to set the bitmap
ID also to something that says it clearly invalid, right?
So that's just to give space there to make sure that glyph 0 is is
never actually used for anything, right?
So, I think that's better.
Okay?
In finalized font kerning.
Let's see what we do here.
We go ahead and get those kerning pairs for all of our fonts, right?
We then go through each individual pair, we look to see for each one
of them.
Well, you can kind of see that this is a little bit wrong to write for
each one of them.
We just make sure that they're valid code points.
Assuming that they are.
We look them up but then we don't actually check to see whether
Not equal to 0 because only if the first is not equal to 0, you know,
and the second or I guess either of them, I guess it wouldn't be a
problem if one of them was equal to 0, I suppose because you're
sitting like 04 the current tail, but I think we never want anything
to current with r0 with glyph because that's the null if we don't
really want anything to Kermit that I can't think of a reason why we
would want to do that.
So I think we want to say anything where the pair itself is not
actually relevant to
To us, we wouldn't want to touch because we just be meaning.
We be incrementing a meaningless entry in this table and at worst, we
would mess something up.
So I feel like we just want to kill any, any sort of chance of that do
anything in this last van, TC.
Yeah, this is just making sure that we can actually use the font d.c.
that since.
Now it's getting reused, it just sets up the basic one that we need,
and that's all fine.
And look glyph bitmap.
Let's see our Cliff index.
We take a look at the code point there.
I don't know.
Do we actually set that?
Let's make sure that we always set the code Point assume there's a
setting call in here that sets.
It looks like that is true.
So oops so it goes ahead and sets the Unicode code point.
It sets the bitmap ID and then it sets that look up for the sparse
look upset.
It's the glyph index.
There we come through and we do our standard thing.
We're still looking at the code Point here, which is what we want,
because we're supposed to pass the regular Unicode over to Windows.
So it's going to go ahead and do that.
Happy birthday Windows, have a little party there it will go ahead and
produce the font for us.
We do all that nonsense.
Then after we're done, we come through and we say alright, let's go
ahead and see what the character with this.
And then we go through the other glyph index.
All through every other glyphs,
There is, and we update.
This is kind of stupid.
If we don't want to do other glyph and X being 0, we might as well
just start the loop at one pretty easy to do.
I would think right?
Unless for some reason, well,
I guess we need to do it here.
But is that still true care Advanced my screen change?
Well, I'll leave it that way.
I assume we did that to fix some of the kerning, and we had to do a
bunch of stuff to make sure we were kind of lining up with windows.
So, I guess I won't do that anyway.
So, in here, we're working strictly with glyph indices, so that we'd,
so no one should have to go through the translation table and they
don't, so, that's good.
And so, I feel like that's probably all fine and good.
Yeah.
So that should be it.
It I feel like that's relatively sane when we're actually running it
out.
We finalized the font kerning.
When we write the fonts out we go through each one here we say okay
we've got the size.
However big each individual,
Yeah.
Hover big.
Each individual just going to be, we write them all out.
We then go through the horizontal Advanced and we say, we're going to
write it out row by row because we only write out a portion of the
road.
Obviously, we leave their space at the end, that's not used.
So we only write out, however, many there actually were a glyph.
We write that and we advance by the max lift count, because that's
actually how many there are per row.
So this is just like a bitmap, a subject blit, basically, that we're
doing there.
And that, is it really right?
I mean,
That is.
That is all she wrote.
And so I think that's fine looking over the in it code.
Do we ever initialize the font DC we do?
And yeah,
Yeah, everything else looks kind of fine.
What's our error here?
Oh, that's good.
Bitmap ID.
Sarah.
That.
All right, so that's going to do our font nonsense so I'm going to go
ahead and run the actual asset filter as well.
Let's go ahead and run that see what it does.
Who knows what it did?
We have no idea.
Of course we just wrote out some data, happy birthday and if we go
into handmade data, we can at least inspect everything.
So so it doesn't look particularly unusual.
It wasn't like something disasters happened but you know,
I really don't know.
We, you know, we're just were kind of just Flying Blind here to say
the least.
All right?
So when we go to load Assets, Now things are a little bit different
than they used to be.
Obviously, when we load the bitmap indices that part is still pretty
much the same.
So all of this, you know, the bitmap part of this didn't change, but
when we go to load the font loading, the font is going to be a bit
different.
I think, let's take a look at the
file format here now.
And so now we have the glyph count, the Ascender height, the descender
height, the external letting right.
And then we've got, we've got this stuff, and then we've got the
Unicode code point for our for each glyph, okay.
Now.
Before these were directly addressed, they can no longer be directly
addressed.
And so, when we do our loading, right?
You can see here, we load in the table of the horizontal Advanced and
then we load in the table of the code points.
This is no longer correct.
The code Point size is not a thing anymore, right?
This thing is not a thing anymore.
Actually, what this is, is our glyphs eyes.
Right.
And we've got to go ahead and read that in HHH fonts cliff and you
know that's that's that's all fine and good but hoops.
But when we actually load these in now, we've got a dense glyph.
Table is, of course, a problem for us and that dense dense Cliff table
actually needs to be like unpacked in some sense, right?
Because we know what, all the bitmap IDS are and what their
corresponding Unicode code points are, but we don't have a table that
actually lets us get from a Unicode code point, which is what the user
is going to be like typing in, you know, we don't have a way.
Well, we're not actually
Doing a typing in but that's what the asset language pack, whatever
the source code is probably going to want to be in Unicode for
convenience.
so,
You know, I feel like we need to keep it that way.
So we need a table that's going to map from Unicode code points to our
glyphs, right?
Which basically is the inverse basically taking this dense table and
making it sparse again, right?
And so when we load the font, what we would also like to do is make
sort of that Unicode mapping table, the problem with making that
Unicode mapping table is it's going to be pretty big, right?
We know that we could fit a basically, a 16-bit index.
Let's see how big this is going to be, how many of those, those
Unicode code points?
Did we say there was going to be oops, would be here.
I want to load up.
This guy.
So, how many do we say there was going to be?
I think it was this.
So it's, this is how many Unicode code points there are.
And so, if we were going to to actually have the entire table, it
would be a 2, MB lookup table.
Right.
You know, it's not fabulous.
So what I would say is we should start with the 2, MB lookup table.
But we kind of want to keep our eye on it and say well in the future,
could we do a range space?
Look up
Or should we switch to like a binary search?
Because remember, these are going to be sorted or rather, we could
always sort these.
It would be free for us to sort them by Unicode code point.
I think they are currently going to be basically, by Unicode code
Point probably, but maybe not exactly.
So we'd have to sort them or something.
We could do something like a binary search or some kind of other
clever range, based search, kind of a thing or something like this.
So, you know, a 2 MB, lookup table isn't great, but
Initially.
So, I think though, what I would like to do is start with that.
And then, you know, as we, when it becomes necessary to do.
So we'll try to do something smarter there but to get it working and
also probably for a while we would want to use that because that's
more of a late later stage thing, when we're actually totally sure
that everything is doing what we wanted to do.
That would probably be the right time for that, right?
But yeah, but binary search might be better because you never really
know like just just having the less memory footprint and then having
the slower search may still be better because the castle usage or
because of, you know, this, the less purely less code, be executed.
It's really hard to say and I don't pretend to know that answer in
advance.
So off we go, let's say that.
That is going to be
There we go.
And I'm going to add an additional thing here because now we sort of
got the glyph size.
So we're going to put that on here.
The size total right is actually going to have one more thing in it
which is going to be like the the Unicode map and that's just going to
be purely.
You know, one of these you sixteens because we know we don't have we
know we could have more than 256 glyphs in a font.
We know we won't have more than 64,000 lifts in a font so that's going
to be times the maximum Unicode code point which actually I
Is we need to pull out of test asset Builder, where it is at the
moment and actually have that be in our file format or in our asset
category, right?
So that's, that's our our Max Unicode code point.
So there we've, you know, we've allocated that mapping table.
The other thing that we could do and, you know, this might be a
smarter thing.
So this, this might, this might get us out of a little bit of a jam.
Oh well.
Not really, but but I mean, here's your just something, I'll throw out
there.
Another thing that you could do is we could say in the AHA, just just
to save us some trouble on the, on the ASCII side of things.
For wider sets of things, it doesn't really help that much, but we
could do it this way.
We could say, one Past
Highest code point, right?
Like that and then we would know that that we could just use that.
And so we would never have to have a map that was bigger than that,
right?
That's something we could do.
So let's let's do that.
Seems like a reasonable thing to do.
Let's just go ahead and do that.
And in the test asset Builder, it's pretty easy for us to, you know,
account for that.
All we have to do is in the
The in the loaded font, right?
We just have
Here, you know, one passed last one, past highest code point, right?
And then, when we load the font,
we just initialize that to zero and every time we use, you know, every
time we use something,
From the, let's see where it is from like load.
Like actually we could do it in add character asset.
Every time we use one, we just say, you know, if whatever the value is
that we're actually using, whatever the code point is that we're
using, if that code point is, is ever greater than or equal to the
highest code point, we would just
Set them like so right another way to do it would be to say oh I guess
this a if one pass the highest code point is less than or equal to
code point.
Then we want to make it equal to co point but plus one, we always want
to be higher.
Okay.
So that would you know, that would solve that problem.
Presumably.
For us one past Max font code Point.
Why is that not
Undeclared identifier, I put it in in handmade file format, study H,
did I not
What, where did I put it?
Where did I put that?
Seriously, seriously.
I could have sworn.
I got pasted that.
That is one of those like on stream.
Fundus has it got deleted?
Oh, duh.
Hi.
I'm I'm it's genius day here at handmade hero.
Right?
I I was just like, oh, I don't need it anymore.
Well, I need it in the asset.
Packer duh, fantastic.
Yeah, that was, that was pretty smooth.
I am a professional programmer.
All right, there we go.
My mommy says, I'm very good at programming, so loaded, font does not
have that glyphs.
That's true.
It doesn't.
And then in here, we need that Unicode map.
So, let's just finish this up.
We've got the Unicode Map size.
We're going to go ahead and do our acquire assets memory on that.
So we have to take that Unicode Map size and put it in there.
Map size.
Oh, actually, it doesn't go in.
There goes right there.
So the data size is, this is what it loads.
And then the size total, this is what we actually want to have extra
sort of for it, if that makes sense.
And that Unicode map is just going to go right after, you know, right
after the horizontal Advanced.
So that's just going to be
This sort of thing, right?
U16 star.
Plus.
Horizontal band size.
And by the way, just to make a note of this.
So this is some kind of fiddly like pointer alignment stuff, right?
It's like, oh, I'm basically sub allocating out of this thing, a bunch
of extra stuff and because there's very little of it.
Like I'm just doing it three times one for each asset type.
I didn't go ahead and make a system for doing that in cases where you
do a lot of this.
I always make it a system for it and like, you know, if I do that a
lot in allocating
I'm doing these like some brake.
I just make a thing that does it for me.
It makes it less error-prone and it's easier to type.
But at this point, the amount that I foresee us doing is so low that I
just don't feel, it's worth it to go do that.
But, you know, just throwing it out there.
That's something I would do in a code base where I was going to do
more of this sort of thing.
Anyway so that's how that's going to work.
And then we need to make our loaded font actually have any of this
stuff.
You 16 Unicode map where we are and the code points are now glyphs and
the glyphs are now HHA font glyph, right?
And I think that's most of it.
The destination is going to start by.
Loading into here.
Code points is not a member of loaded font.
You are correct.
So I think is that actually it I think that's it.
Now we have one problem which is that nobody actually builds that
Unicode mapping table.
And so what we want to do after we allocate that when we do load asset
work directly you know after we do read data from file and the data
comes back we need to actually or we really want to prep that data if
it's a font and so we can in load asset work, we can have a little
thing here with says like
Additional work to do or something.
And I think I rather than having two different ones of these or well,
you know what, we could just make two ones of these.
We could just do something like that, right?
Could do it like this, where we do load asset work directly and then
Then here well no because we don't want the state till we've mapped it
properly.
So I guess what I would say is after this, I do a little switch
statement and I just say, okay, if there's something else to do here,
you know, finalize, type or something, or finalized operation.
And then I just do, you know,
Something like this.
Maybe even something like this.
You know I'm load asset work finalized, operation finalized, none.
And then, finalize asset.
Bonk.
and I guess we don't really store anything else in here so I could
just say, okay yeah we're good with that and so if it's none,
Nothing to do.
And if it's font, we got to build that mapping table.
Yeah.
So, how do we build the mapping table?
Well, it's pretty simple, right?
There's almost nothing to it.
We know that we've got some number of glyphs like.
So we know that the 0 glyph is special so we don't care about that
cliff.
So we can just go through them and we can say, okay for all the glyphs
in this font and first of all, I guess we need to actually have the
font but that's okay.
We've got it right here, right in the the asset as it is.
I guess that does bring up the question though.
Does the asset have its header?
It does.
And so the header has the loaded font in it so I can get the
information that I actually need just wanted to make sure that was
actually true.
So the loaded font
Just comes from saying, whatever the asset is that we were going to
work on.
And you know what?
I should probably do as well.
Here is, I should should say we should only do this if we actually
loaded, right?
Because if we didn't load that, that is probably not a very sensible
thing to do, right?
At least, that would be my assumption and in fact we might want to
clear.
Well, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, I think it's fine.
All right, anyway, so when we finalize the font and we grab a the the
header out of here, we should be able to just grab go right to the
font, right?
So there's the asset, there's the header and then the header has the
font so that font will give us the list of assets.
So the loaded font for example,
Oh, but you know what?
We need.
The info is
All right, which we don't actually have.
We need the asset info and we don't have the asset info GE, you can
kind of see right.
Well, is that true?
I don't know, we've got it right here.
I don't know why I'm freaking out.
I've got it right here.
No problem.
HHH, HHH a font.
Let's go ahead and grab that as well.
So, the ha4 that is just there.
And so now we can do
HHH, dark lift count.
Go through every single glyph.
Right?
HHH h.h., a font glyph, glyph equals work.
Asset.
That's not true.
I did this for a reason font glyphs with index.
That gives us out the particular glyph.
We then just have to go the glyph code point.
which is actually called Unicode code point, I believe,
Unicode code point.
so, the code point,
We want to set that member of the table.
We could also assert it.
It's a assert that it's less than the fonts maximum one you know one
past highest code point.
So we do that, we then inside the table for this font.
So, in font Unicode map in that location, we just store the glyph
index and now we have unpacked the table, right?
We had a dense table of glyphs and we just are now sort of mapping it
out into the Unicode space.
So this thing is Giant and sparse and this thing is dense.
Now, in order to fill all the zeros in that I probably ahead of time,
right?
Want to just clear it.
So when we actually are in here and we acquire that asset to memory,
what I would like to do at that point is I would like to clear out
everything in the whereas that's load sound.
I want load font.
There it is.
I want to do a clear.
So I want to do a zero size after we get it so zero size the Unicode
map.
We have a zero array.
You don't.
We don't do.
You know what we do now?
Yeah, you feeling that I think that's pretty good idea.
Can't think of a reason not.
Seems like a good idea now.
That way, we can just say, Okay, 0, this array, we knew that we have,
however, many glyphs there were there or Unicode, impasse is code
Point.
Although, you know what?
Now I think about it, although I want that in this case, I that was
dumb.
I don't really need it because I already have the, the size already
computed because I'd do the layout, so that's fine.
But still I do like having that.
Okay, so let's go ahead and set this.
Now here's the finalized operation.
Excuse me.
And
Header as a pointer.
Let's see.
Ehhh assets cannot convert to H font.
That's true.
And the Unicode map right to glyph index.
Here I says we got to convert that down to 16 so I'll also do an
insert that the glyph index is or rather that you 16 glyph at index
equals glyph index just so we know that it didn't overflow.
And now we have to actually do the lookup.
That's not particularly difficult but I do want to do before then just
to make sure I don't forget though is that when we load this we now
need to add that finalize up.
So we have this sort of work finalized, right?
And that's going to be finalized asset none in all the cases other
than the font, right?
Don't ask me why, let's see.
Here we go and you can see this is again remember I've said that this
is kind of boilerplate e and that's why I wanted to do so you can see
like this is just stupid.
You don't want to have to do all this every time.
So that's something that that I would like to change when we get a
chance.
Anyway, so okay there we've got our code compiling, probably not
fantastically awesome but it's at least compiling.
And that what we have to do is we have to fix anything.
Wear something passes in a code point because
Is when something passes in a code point.
We want to actually talk about a glyph instead, right?
And so, we have get horizontal Advance.
We have get bitmap for glyph and we want those to start dealing with
glyphs.
So, we want this to be pre of glyph, right?
Like, so and glyph.
so, in here, we want
To be pre of glyph.
Glass.
And so when this when you do get clamp code Point, really?
All I want to do is change that to like get glyph from code point.
Right?
So we pass in those code points and that's fine.
Then there's the code Point again.
And so in here we say you know what, it's not a code Point anymore,
it's a glyph.
Thank you very much then in our font code points,
Becomes Funk lifts.
The glyph, and it's a bitmap ID.
And then in here, we just are going to against a get glyph from code
point.
This becomes get glyph from code point.
It takes a font.
Like so, and I'm not sure.
I think that's just how that's going to go.
Pretty much exactly.
Okay.
And so everything in here looks fine, except these guys have to pass
the font, which they'll do.
Yeah.
So that's all good.
Everyone's happy.
The values being offset, like, it should be, so that's all good.
Now, if we do get Cliff from code point, now we have to actually
implement it.
So the result is going to be the glyph index.
First, we check to see
Whether or not the code Point Falls within the range of code points.
So we'd have to check to see one passed.
Last one, past has code Point, assuming it does, we then want to just
the glyph index is assumed to just be whatever the fonts Unicode map
says, it is at that point, right?
And then, you know, we could also assert here that the result is going
to be less than the total glyph count of that font.
Because we know we're never allowed to look up something past that,
get glyph from code point.
Future money from Xin there.
An extra from does not actually make it any better people.
Yeah.
What can I say?
All right and now we got to debug.
We got 15 minutes left for debugging so whoops got actually
Rerun the asset Packer as well.
Build test asset Builder.
Off we go, and let's just take a benchmark and say, where are we at?
Like what's actually happening here?
We're going to crash what's going to happen.
Let's see.
So we don't crash oddly enough but we do not get any fonts, right?
So nothing on the screen.
All right, so let's start.
By taking a look at the load.
And see if we can see what's going on with the load, right?
And to do that, what I'd like to step into first is I'd like to step
into
load font.
Wherever you come out, come out wherever you are.
No, there we are.
Here we go into load font.
I'm going to take a look at what some of these sizes and what some of
these info values say so I can get a little bit of a heads up.
Well, that is not helpful and of course, we pretty much know exactly
why that is.
It's because I track that value bunch and then I never actually
bothered to write it out.
So it is unsurprising that it is not such anything meaningful, because
if you don't actually set a value, it turns out it doesn't set its
self.
Shocking that I know but it turns out, you know what you gonna do?
You learn something new every day.
So, okay, in here, when we're setting the thought stuff, where is my
file formats nhj font?
So really this was just me being dumb is basically what what this
boils down to, right?
Because the font itself.
Already got written out, I guess.
At that point.
So, when did we actually
Does this never actually remember where it's actual font as but it's
backing font asset actually, was it?
Looks like it doesn't
Right, there's no way to get from this guy to the actual font which is
what we want, right?
Right.
So you can see in here, we like set a bunch of this stuff, but we
never record that in the loaded font.
So the loaded font has like no idea.
You know what?
It's fine to set it here.
I guess because of our weird order thing but it's not great.
You can see that it's kind of a little bit janky.
Not the facet Packer isn't like super janky to begin with but yeah.
Okay, let's try that one more time, this time.
Can I actually have some fonts, please?
There we go.
Okay, so 32,000 is the highest listed code point and I want to see if
that's a reasonable highest list of code Point.
Let's find out.
So add character asset.
So, the High Assistant could point should be this, right?
The highest of these for obviously these guys are all super low.
So if I was going to place that in here, hey look, that's exactly
right.
So that's good.
Now I feel a bit better about things, so we're going to allocate that
nonsense.
It's pretty big unfortunately, but that's just how it goes sometimes,
right?
So off we go, we allocate, we're going to do the work here.
I'm gonna go ahead and set another breakpoint so I can hop to the
The thread that's going to actually unpack this guy.
Or not, as the case may be.
that's,
oh,
another stupid bug.
You can see that I didn't check that properly.
This is supposed to be assuming there are no file errors.
Much better.
Okay, so let's hop back in.
There we go, through the glyphs, one by one.
Here we go.
And so, let's just take sanity check.
See if these glyphs make any sense, or if they're just totally bogus,
that looks exactly right.
So totally fine with that.
Let's keep going here.
Oh hey in our font is back.
So that's good news and it seems to be rendering totally fine.
I guess.
At this point it would make sense for us to maybe try to put some of
those good points there.
Like maybe put our little owl back in.
Now that we did the work to try and get it out, that seems like a
reasonable reasonable thing.
So, let's test our Unicode, let's test our Unicode here, debug text
line,
so in here, when we do all this, I guess what we could do is in that
sort of ridiculousness where we were doing,
The at stuff here in here we could do this is so janky.
Like this is the Janka stuff but people, you guys made me do this.
You egg me on and now you're like making me egg further, right?
You know why you doing that?
So what we could do here is we could just have it so that if you do
that in a string you can print a Unicode thing.
I don't love it at all.
I do not love it but yeah you know can't believe I'm about to do this
but
I can't believe them.
I can't believe I'm doing this.
All right, here it goes.
Here goes people, it's just getting weirder by the second in here.
So, if you see it, followed by for hexes or something like this,
right?
It'll output that Unicode code point.
I guess.
Totally ridiculous.
But that's just the way it goes.
And so when we look at that with an I could do is say okay the actual
code point is going to be some ridiculous nonsense like this.
Get hex at one.
Get up 0.
Or.
You see where this is going, right?
You see this?
What you made me do.
So, there you go.
And if I get the hex for each of these and then I just shift it up.
So the first one is the first year the first four bits.
The next one, the next verb.
It's the next one is the next verb.
It's, and then finally there, we now can do a full 16 bit utf-16 which
for our testing purposes, gives us all the things we needed so we
could do that.
All we need to do is Implement is hex and get hex and like I said, I
can't believe I'm doing this but here it goes.
So is hex is going to return a Boolean, right?
For my character.
and all that's going to do is say, you know, if care is greater than
or equal to 0 and Care is less than equal to 9 or
Same thing but from you know, a through f.
And if it is well I can just say that that's the result, really,
right?
Okay, then if we need to actually do get hex.
From a character, we just do.
You 32 results, zero-turn result.
And all we're going to do.
There is say, alright, if the character is greater than equal to 0 and
the character is less than equal to 9 same, exact test, right?
We're going to do one thing, if it's
Not right.
We're going to check the other range assuming it is.
We just do results equals care - 0.
Assuming that it is here, we do care - A and we add 0 XA to it.
Right.
It seemed reasonable.
Yeah.
Okay so that's completely absurd but I just did and I'm not proud of
it but sometimes you know desperate times call for desperate measures
or something, something like that.
All right.
So what I'd like to do is just I just all I'm doing is testing to see
if our handmade owl line works at all.
So I'm just
Going to stack those guys up one after the other.
Right that's it.
And then I'm going to step in to see what that does in the in is hex
nonsense.
This this that's there.
So I'll scroll down here and we'll just go ahead and do this.
We'll see if we ever actually hit it, we did not hit it.
So that means we've got a bug in that
In the is hex part of it, right?
No, we don't.
I'm just stupid.
Well if I still have a bug but as going to say we only used capital
letters.
There we go.
All right, so what I'm going to do is I'm going to make this the first
thing
and now when I run it, it that should be the first one that we get to
the book.
It should be like the literally, the very first character, right?
There's app.
And there's what's coming.
So let's go into is hex.
It's a zero.
The result is one.
That's good, there's is hex.
Oh, I forgot the 0x.
Duh.
That's not supposed to be there.
Alright, one more time.
One more time.
All right, let's see.
There we go.
Code Point.
What is the code point?
F0 C 5 that's wrong, isn't it?
and of course,
Just get can't catch a break today.
Although I guess in all seriousness just dropping something this
ridiculous as in that quickly.
Of course, we read them the highest one comes first right in the
in-text so.
But there we go.
I think that works now.
Now does the Font work?
I don't know.
Oh right, we got to advance.
Yeah.
So if we're going to advance by that, we would then suck up that code.
Point.
We would add two apps for things, right?
We'd move forward by four.
So it's there but it's not kerned properly.
I guess is what I would say.
Like, I can't imagine that's how it's intended to be current.
but everything looks right and so I don't know if that's just a case
of
Our work to try and line things up.
Doesn't jive properly with
with how that works or whether there's a bug in our table or
something.
Although there's a bug in the table, you'd think these guys would be
current wrong and they're not
So, I don't know, but I would consider that pretty darn successful.
We pretty much did everything that we needed to do.
So I'm going to go to bed.
Go, go ahead and go to the Q&A, but we may have to do at some point
another spin through the kerning just to like figure out if there's a
way to extract it from Windows that where we can have our precise
alignment and then still also do the other one.
so, yeah, if you have any questions about what we did, go ahead and
put
Go ahead and put a q: front of them and then go ahead and ask but
that's, that's pretty darn good.
I'm happy with that.
There's our little fancy characters.
And yeah, and they're all look, they look pretty pretty reasonable.
I'd say
yeah, I just wish that windows or true type was had better like
Kerning information because I feel like well it might not be true
types.
Fault.
It might be just the way that the fonts end up getting authored.
but that whole thing about us having to find the actual left margin
because it's not actually what the font says it is and stuff is just
Colonel Dragon.
So are we done with the fonts?
Now, moving on to other parts of the debug?
Well, except for the fact that these are current wrong,
so I feel like that, I feel like we should figure out why that is
and I feel like,
because I feel like,
Like it could be that they're reporting their ABC what's wrong or that
we're interpreting them wrong or something.
But like, that's not correct.
Criminal Dragon.
So are we done with fans now?
Just one food.
So what will be moving on to next week?
Well, we got to do the actual debug code now, right?
We have fonts for displaying debug code and so we should do our debug
code.
So, we'll spend, you know, a couple weeks on that making a bunch of,
like, debug Biz stuff that so we can see, you know, our memory layout
and our thread activity, you know, are perf that sort of stuff.
It's must have been asked so many times.
I couldn't locate a FAQ.
There are actually I think the Bots will answer the question for you
about the gloves.
Any chance you could use a different font for the editor hard to tell
the difference between zeros and eight?
No I mean that's this is the font I tend to I'm pretty used to so it's
probably what I will end up you know.
I don't want to switch to a different font, really
Manic the nobody is, it's possible that that's how it's supposed to be
current.
I really don't think so.
I mean.
You know we can check what Windows is reporting by putting it in here,
right?
And so you know if we look at
At actually, I guess do we already have the jtech for owl and there's
no, it's not.
So we looked it up, right?
And we said that we wanted to do this one.
You know?
So there it is and you can see that they like it.
It's basically Mah.
No space.
As far as I can tell,
you know, it doesn't really even look current to me, to be honest.
I feel like it's possibly not current about know.
And so, I don't know what, you know, maybe we're missing some thing
that we should be taking into account, or maybe I don't know, it's
but, but we've got some problem here.
And so I feel like we should debug that
Maybe it's just twitch but the letters in red.
A bit off on the edges.
Well, so there's a couple things.
We need a zoom.
We need to zoom tool.
I really should get a good zoom tool, but you can kind of see here.
What's going on on the edges?
And like, remember right now, we're not doing anything to try.
Look, we're not using any hinting.
So all of the edges are going to be Alpha Blended a little bit, right?
Just however, they ended up lining up when we did them and we also
don't I don't know that we've actually done any work to ensure that
they're going to be exactly one to one.
Look, we haven't tested the renderer to make sure that it's not
introducing some extra stuff there.
But
I would say based on looking at it.
I would say.
Well.
I would say that we probably have a well,
Like it doesn't make sense that there's that many Alpha Blended pixels
coming off the edge, you know.
That's a bit weird.
But I'm not 100% certain.
I think about how that even would happen.
Well now that that's plausible, I got to find someplace that's like
Smoking Gun.
Implausible
I feel like that is probably like I feel like we're probably not
exactly one to one on the free blit and we're getting a little extra
blur, a little more blur from the bilinear than we should.
And so that's like a thing we could test out in the renderer for
example, right?
but I feel like
Might be a basic question.
But why do we need our own font rendering?
Doesn't Windows have its own font rendering functions?
We could call.
No, so we can't because we would not be able to Port the game at that
point, right?
If we don't render the fonts ourselves, then when we would run on a
different platform like Mac or Linux, or
Our Xbox or whatever.
First of all that platform may not have a fun system like when we when
we do our Raspberry Pi 1 for example.
We don't know that it's going to have any font support at.
All right?
In fact when we do the one that we boot directly, you won't have any
thoughts for it.
So there's nothing to call but also even on ones where there is
something to call, we don't know that it'll behave the same way and so
it will introduce a difference.
In the way, our game looks across the platforms, which we don't want.
Write a game is fundamentally an artistic medium, right?
Right?
It's got art.
We make the art, we tune the art and so we want the game to look the
same everywhere.
We want it to be rendered the same everywhere.
We don't want it to look different on a Mac than on a PC because they
have two different underlying font systems, right?
And we also don't want to introduce the unreliability of like, does
that, you know, who knows, they update the operating system and now
our fonts are broken or all kinds of weird stuff like that, right?
I saw you were wearing something around your forearms.
Is that to treat tendonitis?
Yes, it is for from for tendonitis.
I don't get them when I wear the braces after coin.
Bray people don't understand why a fun training.
Some can be complex because they think in terms of pixels
Any comments on this?
I guess I don't understand the question.
Because they think in terms of pixels.
Yeah, I could, can you elaborate on that perhaps a little bit?
Can you check if your numbers are mono space?
For example, 11111 should be the same with this 99999.
Yes, we could check that pretty easily.
You're sure that they're mono space in Ariel.
I actually don't know.
It would make sense, but I don't actually know
So they are definitely not taking up the same space.
I would also ask the question,
What font is this?
That's not the same font.
Somehow we got set to Arial black.
I don't know how that happened.
so it is not the this is not a mono spaced font so
we are correct.
as far as the pain is concerned,
What happened to zoom it?
I don't know.
Yeah, didn't we did I thought?
Yeah, I thought we went over this as well.
Where is zoom?
It.
I don't know, is it?
do we have any kind of
I don't know.
I don't, I don't know.
I don't know what happened.
I thought we settled the zoom issue but
I don't know.
Not a question, but zooming is just on desktop.
So it's over here somewhere.
Of course it is.
I don't remember how to use it, unfortunately.
Whoa.
Well, that doesn't work.
I tried.
I failed.
Control one.
There we go.
Yeah, I can't tell we should we should look at these bitmaps directly,
which we can do a little bit later to see whether what the actual
bitmap that we're getting out of Windows.
Actually is because I don't know, this may be what we're getting from
them, it may not be and so we have to we'll have to see
All right.
the ones that nice don't line up the same way in game and in Notepad
Well.
There is the ones.
And like I said, we are a little off.
We know we're a little off on the kerning, we never quite had it
exactly what Microsoft specified.
That also looks slightly.
I don't know that we have the size.
Exactly.
Right either.
Because this isn't points, right?
So there's that but it's pretty darn close.
And that is almost exact so I don't know.
We're quite close we never quite got it.
Exactly right.
When we once we wanted to do the like line up with the left Edge flush
thing because then we kind of have to back solve for some stuff that
wasn't exactly right but
How do you have the background black and mischief?
I don't know.
I just said it.
I don't remember.
I remember it not be.
I just, I just was like an option or something.
How do you prefer to Traverse trees Loops or recursion?
Why I'll use recursion?
If I'm lazy.
And I don't care too much about it because it's usually easier to
write.
But if it's something important, I use a loop, because it's way, way
way, way faster and more reliable than recursion.
If you want to start your own game product, you start from scratch,
use Frameworks API sdks, or use an engine, custom made by you or one
that already exists.
I mean, you use what you think is the best choice for the project,
right?
Just like everything else.
It depends on what you're trying to make if you're trying to make
something that's exactly, like something that already had been made.
You know, if you're trying to make a first person shooter that's a lot
like unreal then, the Unreal Engine is probably a pretty good choice,
right?
If you're not your mileage, may vary, or if you have specific things,
you you, that are going to cause problems for you based on the way
that those engines do things or stuff like that.
You know.
But why not one?
They don't let it flow to each other, though.
Yes, but that's intentional because we actually do proper left
alignment now, right?
And they don't.
So, if you take a look at what happens here, right?
They, this is what we, I went out of my way.
Do you can see that they don't left align their text, right?
And so we wanted to be able to left align our text.
And so that's why these don't want to that's intentional.
That was part of the test.
Instant Kafka any plans to add scripting or modding hooks.
No.
because you're supposed to edit the source code, this is an
educational project
You are supposed to go.
And edit the source code.
It comes with it.
Is that it?
Cuba Caleb off topic.
How do you grow up with your emacs and fig it's just ask Apex to bring
up the prompt and then I type G.
I don't have it bound to a hop key.
All right, that's all she wrote.
Under Cambridgeshire.
Some reasonably think of the screen as a grid of pixels and that font
rendering is directly Plastering that font on the screen.
So NVM they just haven't understood Beyond bitmap fonts.
Well and that is that is to the for the most part correct.
If you're talking about like a systems like we have where we're
building bitmap fonts, the thing that is hidden in that is that if you
don't want your father to be monospaced you have
You have a bunch of awareness of the typography like how big
characters are how they go next to each other and all that sort of
stuff, right?
And so that's where the complexity comes in.
If you just want a monospaced font then that is true.
You just Plastering a thing on there, go to town but assuming that you
want to actually have some, it doesn't look awful, you gotta know the
rest of the typography and actually account for it.
All right.
What font to use an e Max.
It's I think it's called
Liberation mono.
Nick Rolfe.
Why did he use glyph index from code Point, instead of an array of
mostly null pointers to achieve sparseness, because it most the array
of pointers would have been four times lighter.
Right.
So a pointer is 8, bytes and a 16-bit index is 2, bytes.
And so when you're talking about a table that has 30 plus thousand,
sixty thousand entries in it, whatever it is.
Right?
Or I guess in this case was like 38,000 something that you don't want
to multiply that number to be 24 times larger than it should have
been, right?
It's just wasting a ton of cash bandwidth.
And so I didn't want to do that.
Mr.
Fourth dimension.
How valuable do you think non monospaced fonts would be in say an
editor?
I think they are.
Obviously the right choice for an editor and the only reason that we
don't use them for editors is because editors are so dumb, they don't
know how to line up text properly, right?
There's never been like literally there's no case ever except for
numbers in like tabular numbers were you ever want monospace?
It's always worse.
So
You know.
It's just because editors don't understand the code and can't lay it
out properly.
But you would never use a monospace font if your editor, actually knew
what it was laying out type of graphically speaking.
Could you recommend a website?
Or YouTuber that could teach me coding.
I really want to learn
Honestly I don't really know of one that teaches programming from from
the ground up, I'm sure there are a bunch they're probably not
fabulous and so I don't know necessarily wanted to say, oh yeah, this
is a good one.
You should go follow it.
Handmade here is obviously a little bit on the like, okay, we assume
you already know how to program.
Now, we're just going to talk about how you program a game.
And so, I don't know of the thing.
That's like a nice on-ramp kind of thing.
Was like, I wanted to start programming in general, right?
Armenia.
If, if people are sort of shocked to hear me say that monospace fonts
and useful, like, like, literally, what is if it was easier to read
monospaced fonts?
That's what everything would be type set in.
Right?
But it's not like in the history of mankind.
No one has ever gone.
I wish you'd keep these things - faced, right?
People always prefer to read proportionally spaced fonts.
It just looks nicer on the eyes and it helps further distinguish
letters from each other because letters have width again, instead of
the letters all being artificially, stretched out to fit in this
space, that makes it more difficult for you to recognize words at a
time, you know.
So, I mean, maybe I'm wrong because, you know, it's not like I have
the option to actually use one but it's so, it would be so strange if
somehow programming, which is all.
Just just text was somehow the one thing that was easier to read
monospaced and novels throughout history like have always, you know,
are so different in some weird way.
That's like those should be proportional, right?
It doesn't make sense like either Mah.
No space is easier to read or proportionally as an, it should be
easier to read.
where it shouldn't be like, oh, because code is
Has some symbols in it.
It's different.
I mean, it doesn't
It just doesn't stand to reason.
You know, it doesn't stand to reason.
I'd like to limit the scope of my functions to be defined, only where
there used.
How do you work around?
The fact that c doesn't have locally defined functions to use
functors?
I don't really care about that.
I mean, there isn't really, I don't know of any particular downside of
then like the occasional name Collision or something, there's really
no.
Digital.
I don't find the scope scoping, it problem at all, I would like to be
able to do
You know.
I don't want to, I don't want to say Lambda functions because that's
not really true.
But basically, you know, something like a Lambda function where it
could access the stack of anak of an enclosing function, kind of a
thing.
I would like to have had that feature C++ recently added it and it's
all messed up the way they always do.
But, you know, if that had been in the original, see, I think it would
have been nice and clean and would have been useful.
Constantinople vertical Chris or navigation is easier to follow in a
mono font.
I mean, I guess marginally but I don't find I mean I work on text
documents and I don't find that to be a problem.
Super Caleb tried to use grep in emacs the program crashed.
Yep.
That's that's the modern editors for you.
How do you handle introspection metadata to build your editor
inspection tools?
You're talking about in like a, my normal engine at Molly rocket.
We have a meta programming system that does that for me.
Looks like that's about it.
All right, I'm going to wind its down.
Yay, fonts.
Yay.
Okay, thank you everyone for joining me for this episode of handmade
here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want to follow along at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here at Oregon.
It comes with a source code every night.
So while we are doing development, you can play around with it
yourself and learn from it do experiments and so on, if you want to do
that, that's a mighty rhetoric.
It's also got some handy buttons.
You might be interested in, there's a forum site which has stuff like
Community ports, to Mac and Linux and formed ask questions and a
community anti depa sewed guy.
That's people have been working.
Only hard on actually you should check it out if you're trying to
catch up with old episodes, there is a patreon page.
If you want to support the video series, you can subscribe to that.
It's always much appreciated.
And then we also have a tweetbot which treats the schedule.
So if you're trying to catch the series live, that's the place to
check out the schedule for the week.
And that's about it, that's it for the week because this is packs
weak.
So, I decided we just want to finish up the fonts and then we'll let
it rest for a week and we'll come back here.
So we'll be back on Monday.
Same time.
Same place, 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time.
On Monday, I believe.
But always check that tweetbot because that's got the most up-to-date
information.
So if you want to win the series lab, that's the place to check.
It is definitive until then have a good week of programming and I will
talk to you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.