That's that's really critical.
All right, we are ready to start here.
Look at that time, Ur stream, begins Now, ladies and gentlemen, the
timer actually worked.
All right, so I wasn't that sick last night, I guess ladies and
gentlemen.
Thank you for joining me.
Welcome to day 3 of handmade hero.
I'm a little bit sick and I apologize but I have some cough drops
here.
So I am going to try to get by we'll see if I don't need them.
I won't use them because I'm afraid they might make some some weird
sounds with the microphone.
But we'll see what we can do.
All right, let's get started.
If you remember from last time, we were at the point where we had just
gotten a win32 window up, but we had not really finished our
application.
And so there's some things that we have to tidy up first.
And then we need to start drawing to our window the way that we
actually want to to start developing our own renderer meaning
something that will allow us to make our own buffer of
Souls that we can write, you know, basically our render any way that
we want to work on.
And then we need to basically give that to Windows so that it will
display it in our window for us.
And this won't necessarily be the most efficient way to, to render
things on Windows.
Because nowadays, everything goes through the 3D graphics card.
But before we ever do anything involving the 3D graphics card or any
of that stuff, like I said, I want to show you how to write everything
from scratch yourself.
And so what we're going to do first is we're going to use a slightly
slower method which is we're going to
do all the rendering ourselves and then we're going to put it to the
screen.
Okay.
So this is sort of in some sense going back to the old days when this
was actually how you had to write a renderer because there really
wasn't much in the way the graphics card could do for you.
You wrote everything yourself to a buffer and then you just hold the
graphics card.
Hey, this is the buffer that you need to display.
And so that's basically what we're doing and that's the first step in
learning how a renderer works.
Here we go.
I'm going to open up emacs.
And by the way, I should say this.
I haven't said it yet in the Stream.
But if you are someone who has gone to the website and has pre-ordered
the game, then you will actually have a zip file.
That looks something like, where are they hear something like this?
Basically, you will have a zip file.
That's got this stuff.
Here.
And what you want to do is you want to look inside your zip file and
they'll be day numbers, day zero on day zero zero to it's and so on.
So if you are watching this video again sometime in the future, you
will want to grab day to which is the day before this unzip that and
that is the version of the source that we are starting with.
So to make sure everyone's in sync.
Please make sure you do that but truck before trying to follow what's
going on here because otherwise your source code will be out of date.
So we've got one source file so far.
It's win32 handmade dot CPP and
This right here is our window callback.
Now you'll remember.
You did.
Last time was we made a little message Loop here.
And windows basically has a message Hugh for our application that it's
tough things in and we have to pull them out one at a time, translate
them and dispatch them and then we will get them in our window call
back.
Now.
We also talked a little bit in the Q&A.
I believe about why we have to have a call back at all.
Because if we're the people who are pulling the messages off the queue
down here.
Well, why can't we just call whatever function we want?
And the reason as we saw in the Q&A is because windows
Serves the right to call us back at that window, call back.
Anytime it wants to, it does not have to do it inside this dispatch
message.
That's the sort of mental model that they were going for, is that they
call us back inside, dispatch message, but of course, Windows things
get crazy.
So they started having places where it calls us out of the middle of
nowhere.
So anytime we call into a Windows function, no matter what it is.
We kind of have to be ready for it to potentially cause back in there.
Okay.
So what we did and where we left off is something that we don't
Which is not really sufficient for our purposes.
Basically, we had two things that we had to fix one, is that you'll
notice.
And those of you tried at home.
I'm going to go ahead and launch the debugger here so they can take a
look at our at our program.
So for those of you who are following along at home, you know, that
when you run this application, you end up in a circumstance, where
there is really nothing you can do with it.
You cannot close it.
I mean, you can resize it and see our black white alternating pattern
that we decided to have in there, just to make sure things were
working, you know, you can do all that but you cannot close the
Do.
And so really, there's no way to exit this application without going
back to the debugger and hitting shift F5, or, you know, going into
debug here and hitting stop debugging.
And that is because we are not yet handling, the clothes message.
Okay.
So in order to handle the clothes message properly, there's a couple
things that we have to do.
The first thing is, we want to go back here and take a look here at
the Loop that we created.
That's pulling these get messages off.
Now, if you remember, if we go back to msdn and we looked at this the
other day, but if you go back to msdn, the documentation for get
message is very explicit about what's going to happen when we call it.
It says, in fact, it even gives some sample code down here.
It basically says that there's a possibility of a return value of,
Zero.
If the WM quit message is posted, which is basically a way of Windows
telling us that it wants our app to exit, right away.
But there's also the possibility of a negative 1 which means there was
some kind of error in the get message and we should exit as well.
So given those two things we checked for greater than 0.
What that basically means is that if we want to exit this application
at the moment, what we will have to do, is basically get this thing to
go ahead and get a WM quit message, and there's a really easy.
E way that we can do that.
We can actually tell Windows to just go ahead and post a quick message
right on our cue.
There you go.
Now, if you take a look at post, quit message in msdn again, always
get used msdn.
And by the way, I'll mention one other thing that someone wrote in and
told
About, that's pretty important.
When you go to msdn.
We have not had this happen on the live stream, but somebody had it
happen at home where sometimes it'll come up with the documentation
for Windows mobile or something.
And the reason that you care about that is because the documentation
that we want has stuff like this in it, which says, which version of
the desktop Windows you want to use in order to support it.
Right?
So we need to know that information and we also need to know.
I said, sorry I said that poorly.
It says, what the minimum supported desktop version is so we know
What our game can ship on minimally.
So Windows 2000 professionals the earliest thing we could ship on no
problem there?
No one else.
No one's using anything before XP these days.
But you also have the library and the dll name here, which we need to
use to resolve unresolved symbols.
And we saw that in the previous stream.
So make sure you are actually looking at the desktop version of
Windows, which should stay here.
If you're not seeing things like, minimum, supported client, Windows
2000, professional or some other desktop version, then you need to
make sure that you can switch to that.
And I think
Use a desktop technology is here developed desktop.
I don't know, I msdn changes.
So frequently, it's hard to say hopefully, sometime during the stream
will have the mobile and come up, and I can sort of fuss around with
it and get us to the right place, but there you go.
All right.
So post quick message, basically post an exit code is part of the quit
message.
And the exit code is just something that if we were posting this quit
message in some kind of an error situation.
It's basically just a way that we can sneak a little numeric value
into that quick message.
And if you look at the quick message, WM quit, it's basically a thing
here that just you know is opaque to us.
But when we do that post quick message, it'll be able will be able to
get this exit code back out.
If we really wanted it.
Now, we don't care about any of this stuff because we're a game and
games don't
Back with Windows in hardly at all, basically, but if we did care, we
would start to think about.
Oh, do we need to pass error codes, back and all these sorts of
things.
We don't care about that at all.
We want to do is post a WM quit message in response to WM close so
that we will fall out of this Loop.
Now, there's two things we could have done here and I will show you
how to do the second one as well because it's probably a little more
proper, even though again as a game.
We don't really care.
So let me compile that.
Let's go ahead and here and we'll go ahead and set a break point on
that line.
Here's our handmade Hero app.
When I close it.
You will notice we get this post, quit message.
And when I hit F10 to step over that, I'm going to set another
breakpoint down here.
Just so we can see when I go ahead and step over that.
It has now posted that WM quit in our queue.
And what we will find is that eventually.
Now we will actually get that WM quit message.
So this message result will come back as false eventually.
Now remember, there's other messages in the
Q.
So it won't come back right away.
But after a while when we hit F5, we will get in a situation that
message result is in fact false or 0 and we hit our brick break breaks
us out of the infinite for Loop, which is this guy right here and it
ends the program.
Now, you may be asking me for ready to ask me or if you are one of
those people out there who is very, very
C++ focused or object-oriented focused, you may be having a fit right
now and that is okay.
I apologize for that.
I hope that it does not cause you too much mental anguish, but
you will be upset because you will note that I did not close my
window.
Now, one of the things that people like to do a lot in object-oriented
programming languages is they like to make sure that they always have
completely symmetric construction and destruction, or acquisition and
release of their resources.
And what that means is that, every time you make something such as
create wind, oex, where we made a window or register window class,
where we registered a window class.
You want to make sure that if there is some way,
Clean that up that you do, so.
They do that even if there is no need to clean it up.
Now, I would love to rag on people who do that.
I'd love to say some disparaging things right now.
But here's the honest truth.
I was one of those people.
I was one of those people for a good, probably, three years of my
life, and I wrote code like that all the time.
It's the only way I programmed.
Everything was written.
Exactly.
That way.
It's some people call it resource acquisition is initialization.
Other people might just think of it as having everything wrapped in a
class.
Constructor and Destructor, there's a lot of different methodologies
that sort of have this same thing at their core, but they all boil
down to that same thing.
And so they would never want me to do something like creating a window
that I had no plans for destroying but later on as I programmed more
and started to ship a lot more real world applications and cared about
performance a lot and cared about a lot of things that I didn't care
about or know about during the times when I programmed like that.
Basically what I found is that that is a really bad way to program.
And the reason is because it is almost always the case that things are
better Acquired and released in Aggregate.
And what that means is that instead of thinking about things
individually, you always think of them as part of a group that gets
handled together and that is the way to think about things and what
that means.
Is you can't be myopic and look just, you know, what?
The T wasn't doing it.
You're asking me of cheating cheating on.
On my almond milk with the T.
The T wasn't doing it.
We're switching the almond milk.
There it is.
All right.
Sorry for the interruption.
It has to happen.
Now.
And again anyway, what you need to do is stop looking at things in
that myopic way that focuses on the individual creation and
destruction of one resource and start thinking about creation and
destruction and acquisition and releasing in waves.
Now, you don't have to worry about that too much because we're going
to be getting into those sorts of things a lot more later when we have
a lot more resources to deal with.
But right now, the reason that I want to bring it up is because what
we're doing right here is we're creating this window.
Now, we know that as long as our game is running, we are going to
leave this window.
Do created.
And if we ever do destroy it, for any reason, we're going to recreate
it.
Right?
Right back again, right immediately.
And the reason is because we can't display our game without a window.
So, we know, as long as the games running, there's a window.
When we exit this application, windows will bulk clean up all of our
Windows.
All of our handles, all of our memory, everything gets cleaned up by
windows.
So, if we actually put in code, that closes our window before we exit,
we are wasting the users time.
I know it sounds strange say it that way, but that is the truth.
If you've ever had one of those applications where you try to close it
and it takes a while to close down your like, what is going on.
All I ask you to do is close.
Well, honestly a big cause of that is this sort of thing.
It's thinking it has to go through and free all its resources.
Annually and tidy everything up.
When in reality a lot of those things if they had been thought about
as in terms of waves, it would have closed like that.
Just something to think about again.
I apologize to object-oriented programs out there who are having a fit
right now.
What can I say?
I'm sorry.
That's just not the way I could.
All right.
So we are letting our window die.
The reason I said, there's a little bit of an oddity here is because
we handled the WM close message and not the WM destroy message.
We left the WM destroy message floating sort of blowing in the breeze
if you will.
And so if you want to be a little more appropriate, if you're a little
more clean here, you could do something like this where you pass both
of them or if you want to satisfy, even the the sort of try to tidy,
everything up, sort of way of doing things.
You could even call.
Destroy window, which closes your window and kills it right here, or
you can do something even more pernicious.
And it is probably honestly what I am going to recommend that we do
which is that we are going to instead talk about actually having a
variable that controls the loop down at the bottom so that it will
exit on its own.
So basically what we're going to do here is inside our statement that
used to be infinite Loop.
We are basically just going to say while we are running and this will
give us a global Boolean flag that we can go ahead and kill.
Anytime we want to and we're going to talk about this in one quick
second.
But basically what we're going to do here actually going to initialize
this in the way that I normally do.
What we're going to do is we're basically going to have a giant a
Boolean Global that says whether we're still running and when we go to
close the app or if our window gets destroyed, for some reason, we are
going to set it to false so that we exit.
Now in the future, we probably will not actually do these things
directly.
What we will probably do instead.
Ted, and the reason that I'm setting up this, this Boolean here is we
will probably only really do this.
This setting thing setting running to false somewhere else.
We'll have to do it somewhere else.
So for now it's going to be a global but in the future we may move it.
So this is a global for now.
And the reason I say that is because the user may try to close our
application and we may not want to actually close the application.
We may want to pop up something inside the game that says are you sure
you want to exit or something like that?
In case they may lose.
Progress in their game.
If it's like some kind of a rogue like situation where we're not
Going to save it, we may need to do something there.
So we probably want exit here and with WM destroy that is what happens
when our window gets destroyed and honestly, we may want to
trick-or-treat that case as an error.
Let's say our window gets destroyed, somehow that we did not foresee.
We may want to flag that and go try to recreate our window later.
So I'm going to do both of these as well.
And really, this whole structure is going to be largely placeholder
code for when we come back, a little later and handle this with a
message and or I should say to the user and handle, this as an error,
recreate window.
We will want to come in here.
When we do the second pass on the Windows platform later, which will
be much later when we're going through and tighten your into up and
making it super good for
I think we may want to do those things.
All right, so let's talk about this Global.
I am not averse to Global variables.
But I am also not a huge fan of them either.
The Dogma that says you should never have a global variable.
I certainly don't buy into but there is a reason that Dogma came about
and a lot of the points are pretty valid.
Basically, something will be trying to do to avoid making mistakes.
Is we will be trying to avoid having code.
That should not be touching things, touch those things for lack of a
better term.
And so the more we can make our code, very clear about what it can and
can't access the better and that is where Global variables really pose
a problem.
Because since anyone can touch it at any time, it makes it rather
difficult for us to see.
So this is something that in our Windows code right now is totally
harmless.
It is just a thing that controls exiting from the loop.
Our Windows code is always going to be a little bit janky because it
is interfacing with Windows, and windows is not designed particularly.
Well, it's not a very good API.
So I am not concerned about doing things like using Global's in the
win32 platform layer.
Most of our code will not be in that layer.
And most of our code will not be touching anything that are Global in
there to say the least.
They will not even really know that it is there.
So it is not really that big of a deal but even so I will probably
move this out of levels at some point just so I can have a much
clearer idea of exactly who
You can change running and when so that said, watch for me talking a
little bit more about Global's in the future because we will have some
more things to say possibly even on this very episode.
But for now, we're going to go ahead and use them because a lot of
times you will use things as you'll ever code up into a working State,
and then you sort of solidify it down.
You may start to pull things out that were Global or pull things that
were in functions out of them or those sorts of things.
And that's what we're going to do.
So we're going to have to go in here.
We are at will start running basically.
Ali right before we go into our while Loops, we're going to set
running equal to true.
Now.
One thing that you lacked want to note is that static, we saw it once
before we used it in here and this was to say that it persisted now,
it's very confusing and see because static actually means different
things.
Depending on where you put it is not a particularly good.
Keyword.
And so one of the things that I actually like to do and I'll start
doing this right now is to really define static into two different
keywords.
And I use the one that I actually mean so if I have a local variable
that is local, persist.
I will use that.
And if I have a global variable I will usually do something like this.
There you go.
So let's call them that and let's actually put those in place.
So instead of typing static.
I just rename that.
So you can see this is a locally persistent thing.
It means that it stays around and it but it is still locally scoped in
here, right?
Whereas this thing right here.
This is a global variable right?
There you go.
And now you can actually see what those are instead of looking at
static because static means two different things.
In this case.
What static meant was it meant that this value would stay the same
after it, exited the scope.
So normally what would have happened is every time
The scope it would have set it to whiteness again because it would
have been a local variable if it looked like this.
That's what it would do.
But as soon as I declare it static, it means it actually allocate
space to store it for now and ever.
So it assigns whiteness to it the first time.
But then immediately after that, it starts, assigning other things to
it, and those things will persist the next time it comes to this code.
It will not do this initializer.
It will not do it.
And so it will retain the value that it had.
So when we wanted to do this kind of toggle where we toggle things
back and forth, that was a really kind of convenient, way to do that.
Now, we're going to rip that out because I hate using local persist.
In fact, one of the reasons that I do this exactly.
This way is so I can search for things like all the times when I use
data to do local precise because I don't mind if there are Global
variables.
But I do mind if there are these and I like to be able to get rid of
them.
Now, if that weren't enough for you, in terms of confusion, the other
thing that static does, it has one more meaning, what it does is it
basically can define a function as being local to the file.
That it's
So we can be basically used to say don't allow this function be called
from any other file other than the one that is in.
And by file I actually mean translation unit and that's actually going
to be important in the future.
But for now you can just think of it as source file.
But to be continued.
And so usually what I will do is I will say something like internal or
internal function, right?
I usually just use internal.
So.
All right, that is our some pound Defiance just to change the word
static into something that we can actually remember and use a little
bit better and search for more importantly, when we need to clean up
our code base.
And so, what I'm going to do now is I'm going to say that well, oh, I
forgot the thing that I was going to tell you as well there, which is
that.
The other thing that's interesting about static that it
Is automatically for you.
Is that if you use set up to declare Global variable, it is
automatically initialized to zero.
So if I were to type this or this, I would basically because false
always evaluates to 0.
Basically that is exactly the same as just not saying anything.
I do not have to initialize to zero, it is initialized to Zero by
default.
If it
Static.
So there you go.
Okay.
So if we were to take a look at this, now we could go in here and
oops.
Static macro redefinition.
Oh, duh.
That's good.
This is the sort of thing that happens on a stream.
When you are too busy explaining things.
You put your stuff in the wrong order.
My apologies.
Awesome.
Yeah.
There we go.
So anyway, yeah, defines.
Oh, man.
It is a sick day.
So defines always go in this order.
That is just a completely yet.
Hopefully, everyone knew that already because I think we covered those
but just in case they didn't pound Define, since I already made the
mistake, I might as well have to explain it.
Again.
That is my Penance pound.
If I know he's
Thing, you are trying to turn trying to define a new and then takes a
thing you want to be.
So it translates this into this and I had them reversed which is
absolutely no good.
So, there you go.
All right.
So if we take a look at this now and we run this application, we can
close our application by hitting the close button and it closes just
like we wanted to.
And basically what will happen.
There is it will set running equal to false and we will exit right
out.
And again, all we will do is basically let windows clean up everything
for us because it's going to do that whether we like it.
It or not.
And if it's going to do that, then we might as well let it.
So we now have fixed, the only problem that we actually had with our
application, which is that you could not close it and you can close it
now.
Very exciting.
We still have two things to handle here, activate a pin, WM size, but
we are going to get to those in a second.
But we really need to focus on now is the fact that we can't really
paint anything meaningful.
Now, basically, what we have to do here, when we did our paint, you'll
notice that what we had to do was use GDI to paint things.
And GDI is Windows as Graphics API.
And like I said, we want to do everything from scratch.
So we want to interface with GDI as little as possible.
Basically, what we want it to do is take a bitmap that we have already
rendered using our own code and all of our own techniques and just
display it to our window.
In order to do that.
We have to basically ask Windows to allocate a bitmap buffer for us
that we can write into something that's in a format, that is
comfortable with us, handing back to it.
Then we will right into it and tell it.
To go ahead and display.
Now, this involves a bunch of Windows stuff and I wrote down all of
the things that I wanted to remember to tell you.
So I'm going to open my notebook here and hope that I don't, they're
kind of a little scatter shot in the notebook, but hopefully I'll
remember them all as we go through it.
So here's what we're going to do.
Let me give you the big picture.
Basically, what we are going to do is we are going to ask windows at
some point.
And I'm going to go ahead and just kind of type these out here as
functions.
We
we are going to have a function that's basically called resized image
section.
And dip section is is the name.
It's called d.
I be device-independent bitmaps.
That is actually the name that Windows uses to talk about things that
you can write into as bitmaps that it can then display using GWT.
Die.
Okay.
We are going to have a function that basically resizes, a dip section
or initializes it if it's never been created before.
And basically what that what we will do is every time we get a WM size
message, which says that our Windows size has changed, we will
basically call that.
So we will basically force it to create an entirely new div section.
That is the correct size.
So it is the size of the entire window.
Now we won't quite probably want to do exactly that because since our
Game is going to be a 2-D game and we will be wanting to render
potentially at fixed resolutions.
What will eventually probably do is only pick a size.
That is a reasonable size for our rendering that matches how we have
done our source art, that also corresponds to roughly how big the
window is, but for now, we can just go ahead and actually create it to
be the full window size.
And then, once our games render is up and running, we can start to
think about those other things and control them.
So, what we will do here is we will call resize.
The obsession and of course, what we have to do in that call is we
have to basically know what the actual size of the window is that we
ended up with after WM size.
And the way to do that is the thing called, get client wrecked.
Now, get client wrecked is a very simple function.
If you remember we had a, we had some experience with wrecked before,
it was right here.
Basically, it's a thing, which basically says, here is a left a top, a
bottom and a right.
It is, it is a lot like something you might see in.
Smell like in CSS.
It is basically defines a rectangle on the screen and Loops.
That's not where I want to bet it all.
And basically, what we're going to do is we're just going to go ahead
and grab the rectangle for our window.
And the reason that it's called, get client wrecked instead of
something else, like get window wrecked.
Which also, ye also exist is this just gives us the part of our window
that we actually can draw into because if you look at a window, so for
example, let's say I go take note pad over here, you can
See that the actual part you can draw into is like in here and then
there's this like border frame thing and that's actually all being
handled by Windows.
Right?
So there's not a whole lot we want, we don't want to touch any of
that.
So we just want to know the size of the part that we can actually draw
it too.
Right?
And now if we were full screen when we go, you know, because we're
going to want to go full screen eventually when we're full screen that
doesn't matter because there is no border around the wind or anything
like that.
But until then, when we're using one that has a little bored of you
can resize, we have to take account for that.
Or I should say take that into account grammar.
Alright, so we are going to ask for the rectangle.
You can see.
It takes an LP wrecked.
And like I said, long pointer to erect.
That's the Hungarian notation coming back there.
So we have our window wrecked or I should say.
Maybe our client Rex in some indirect, is technically something else.
In Windows is the whole window.
Not just the area, you can draw.
I'm going to go ahead and get that out and that will give us just like
we did down here that will give us our width and our height.
So basically we can just subtract the right from the left and the top
from the bottom.
Sorry, the left from the right and the top from the bottom saying that
correctly.
We are going to go ahead and do that to produce the width and the
height of the buffer that we need to fill the whole window.
That's basically how big we will need it to be.
So we're going to go ahead and call oversized dip section and choose
We are going to pass it that within that height.
So in here, we are going to get a width and a height.
And we will basically need to build that buffer using Windows to to
give us a buffer that we can draw into.
Then what we will do once we have our dip section size properly.
We will actually in paint instead of calling this.
This Pat.
But thing here, which is not really anything that we want to do.
We will do the begin paint.
And we will use the rectangle that it passes us to basically.
We update that rectangle with whatever the contents of our buffer was.
So we're basically going to create a buffer in WM size because we
always get that anytime the size of the window changes.
We're going to create that buffer.
We're going to draw to that buffer during our game loop.
We're going to keep drawing whatever the state of the game is into
that buffer.
And then anytime we need to Windows need this to repaint.
We're going to blip from that buffer into the window where base going
to copy.
What's in our buffer or rather going to ask Windows to do the copy.
Since it's the only thing that can actually write to the screen like
that.
We're going to ask it to copy.
From our buffer into the space occupied by our window.
Now we will also be forcing redraws at, say, 30 frames a second.
In order to do animation.
We will be for splitting.
So we will, we will not only be painting inside WM paint, which is
just a message we get when Windows.
Think some part of our window is dirty, like it went off the screen
and came back or some other window was obscuring, it and went away.
So we won't only be painting in paint, but it's one of the places
we'll paint, okay.
How do we do that?
Well, well, you know what?
I'm gonna make a sub function first.
So, inside here in between our begin paint and our end paint.
I am going to go ahead and say, like update window like this and
actually, that I believe is actually a reserve Windows thing.
So I probably can't call it update window, but that's actually okay.
Because you know, what I like to do normally is I actually like to
prefix my stuff with win32 so that the platform layer it.
So it's clear.
What is wind.
32 stuff and what isn't?
So that's okay.
We'll just call it that and then our names won't collide with Windows
names.
Windows has a lot of names to collide with.
Okay.
So when we basically get our X Y width and height here out of the
rectangle that Windows after us to repaint, we will go ahead and pass
them like this to our update function.
And of course, since now, we actually will need the window handle
because we're going to actually get to the window.
We're going to pass it that window handle as well so they can update
it.
And then we are going to go ahead.
Head and erase this.
Stuff here.
So that got rid of our locally persist thing.
Which, like I said, I don't like and I wanted to get rid of.
So, we're going to now move this up here into an actual function.
The function takes an H wind, right?
The window handle.
It takes the X and the Y that are going to be the upper corner of that
thing.
I prefer X Y, width and height, instead of the top left bottom thing.
That's just that's just me.
So, I don't use the naming convention that Windows uses where it's
right left top bottom cetera.
I use an X Y width and height.
I just think it's a little clearer for me.
Me, it's easier for me to remember.
And here we are going to update it.
So what we actually want to do here is we are just going to call a
function that is called, I believe.
Where is it?
Let's see.
So jib section.
Can we get a dip section?
There we go.
Guess we should start by creating one.
So we are going to have to call create David section to get it.
So we might, as well start with that as well.
We're going to need.
Create them section to ask Windows to make us one of these bitmaps and
we are also going to need the function to blit it.
Which what is the best way?
There's a couple ways or stretch, TI B to device, but that actually
changes the scale.
Hmm.
Which one did I use?
Turn.
Remember which one?
I normally use, I guess.
Stretch stretch.
Well, it would be the right thing to use.
So this is a quandary.
So this is the one I was thinking of using stretch, TI b 2.
Vice.
Let's see.
Where is it?
I guess it's not even to device.
I think it's just stretched.
GI B.
Yeah, there it is.
Stretch GI B.
So this is the one I was thinking of, and I'll tell you what, that one
is and then we can maybe think about whether that's actually what we
want.
So with this one basically does is this one takes our dip section.
The thing that I was taking we're going to we're going to create our
device-independent bitmaps section and it Blitz it but it allows us to
scale it at the time and I was thinking that would be a good idea
because then we could always render to the same size and then we would
just, you know, scale it up to the size of
Window and I don't know.
So that maybe you know what?
I think, that's probably what we're going to want to use in the end.
So I'm going to just go ahead and use that one now and allow Windows
to do some scaling in there.
If we want it to in the future.
I'm going to use another kill rectangle.
People like that in the previous string, kill rectangle, is fun thing,
get rid of those at those specifiers.
Okay, so I'm going to, I'm going to actually start with that because I
think that's what we're going to want to use in the end because
basically like I said, if we decide to use a fixed size buffer or a
couple different fixed size buffer,
Us to do our rendering and we want Windows kind of blow it up to the
size of window or Shrink it down to the size of the window, depending
on the circumstance.
We're going to need stress GI B.
So, I think I'm just going to go with that.
And it turns out to be a bad call later.
We will change it.
All right.
So all this function does, it's very very straightforward.
It is a rectangle to rectangle copy and I'm going to explain
coordinate systems a little bit later on.
But, you know, basically for right now, if you could think about two
rectangles, we're just going to copy one rectangle to the other.
And in this particular case, the rectangles can be different sizes.
So we're going to take a rectangle of one size in one buffer and copy
it to rectangle of another size in another buffer doing scaling along
the way if we need to.
Oh, you know what?
And here's one thing that I forgot.
We don't really want the window here.
Do we, we want that device context because we already had the device
context right here.
So, rather than having to get the device context from the window,
which we could do.
Let's just go ahead and pass that in there because that's the thing
that we actually have to pass two windows.
So there we go.
There's our device.
East.
So we will go ahead and put our device context in their first
parameter.
Now, we need the destination rectangle.
So the destination X, the destination.
Why the destination with and the destination height and basically that
is some subsection of our window, so we are going to pass it.
Basically the exact things that we got from our see paint.
So basically this is the rectangle that Windows wants us to fill,
right?
That is the the part of the window that needs.
To get redrawn.
So we're going to blit to that, basically, right then we basically
have our source here, our source, r x, y width, and height that we are
bleeding from.
And since we are going to start by just making everything exactly.
The same size are back, buffer.
We the same size as our window.
This is exactly the same.
We are basically having two buffers.
One is our window that we're drawing two and one is the the buffer
that we are actually drawing our stuff into with our renderer and we
are just going to copy one from the other, exactly the same.
Then we have to pass basically a pointer to the b and a pointer to the
bitmap info.
You have to do some extra stuff here.
You don't know what any of these things are yet because we haven't
talked about them, and we're going to talk them about them in a minute
when we actually create the, the resize dip section.
But for now, I just wanna look at these two additional parameters that
control how stretch TI B work.
So, let's take a look at msdn.
Again, go down.
Here.
You can see that.
Basically the usage tells you what kind of a picture, this is that you
have done.
What kind of a buffer?
Offer you have made.
There are two kinds of buffers.
One is palletized and one is RGB now.
You all know what RGB colors are probably because you have all seen
them before in a paint package or something similar.
I'm going to bring up color cup which by the way, is a great for
utility that everyone should have in their machine.
I absolutely love it, but I'm just bringing it up because these little
RGB things or this little guy that you see in Windows all the time or
any kind of Color Picker, like this just shows an RGB color, which is
basically three values from 0 to 255.
That say, how much red, how much green and how much blue are in a
particular color.
We'll talk a lot more about colors much later in the series.
But for now, you are all very familiar with that.
Well, that is what this is.
So if you want to make a back buffer, that is basically color
specified in that fashion where every individual pixel has an RGB
value, then you want to pass this and that is what we're going to do.
So we are going to put that in there.
There we go.
Okay.
But I will quickly say what this is.
What is a pallet?
A palette is if you would like to be more indirect.
So let's say instead you would like to only use say 16 colors total 0
1, 2 3, 4 5 6 and so on.
And so what you want to write into your buffer, for example are just
numbers that correspond to some color kind of like Pantone matching or
basically some paint chips where you've enabled them 0 through
something.
In this case, 16 bits of 0 through 65,000.
Basically, you then have a palette which is specified in RGB per
color.
So / index color.
So basically it's in directed one time.
So you're basically saying the things that I actually put in this
buffer just refer out essentially to another buffer that will tell you
what the color is.
And this was done back in the day to make things smaller.
It was, it's basically a way of compressing, the size of the buffer
because since an RGB value is, at least three 8-bit values one.
R14 G14 be, that's 24 bits.
You could get away with less by using an 8-bit or 16-bit palletize
mode where you basically just use say eight bits to say what color
you're going to do.
And then those eight bits told you to look up in a table of colors
that were specified as our GPS.
You don't have to worry about that at all because those days are kind
of long gone.
Although they sometimes come back when you're doing things like
texture compression.
But fortunately for us, we don't have to deal with that.
We can actually do direct RGB writing into our buffer, which is much,
much more convenient.
So, finally, we have a raster, operator, raster Opera.
Okay, too sick to talk today, raster operation code and the raster
operation code, is something that says what kind of bitwise operations
you want to do.
Now.
If you remember from the intro stream, there are a lot of bitwise
operations, things like X, or things like and those sorts of
Stuff.
And if we go look where it says there are documented in bit blit, you
can see those here and basically, all this does is it says what to
actually do to that the destination?
Now all we wanted to do, we didn't want it to do any fancy bit
operations.
We just want to basically overwrite the destination with the source.
We just want to copy.
And so what we're going to do is actually just use Source copy, which
is defined exactly as that.
It is a numerical code, that tells stretch bullet, to go ahead and
copy the thing directly.
There you go.
So that's really all
All we're going to do with stretch.
Put that will update our window for us.
This will get a little more complicated as we start to handle other
things.
But all we really need to do now.
If we want to update our window, as we've got to find a place to get
these bits and the bitmap info from.
And the way we're going to do that is through create dip section.
This is the part where you actually create the back buffer because
obviously to put that back buffer to the window.
We have to actually make it in the first place and you can see the
things that are involved here.
First.
There is a bitmap info structure and we'll talk about that.
That is there is a h bitmap, which is a handle to a bitmap that it
returns to us.
So this is
Our bitmap handle that is coming, back to us from created section.
Thank you, creative section for that.
We are going to need a device context, but you know what that device
context is not going to come for?
Where you think it's going to come from.
It's going to be a little bit bizarre, but we'll get to that.
And then we're going to have to look at a couple of these other things
here.
We have, we have some other things that we've got to specify.
So let's go to the msdn and check out what our options are create did
section.
Okay, here we go and create tip section.
We have to get a device context and I'll talk a little about, but
we're going to get that in a second.
We have to passepartout a bitmap info.
And that bitmap info is going to be something that we fill out.
So this is an easy thing to do.
Will, just go ahead and pass that and we'll fill this out in a second.
There we go.
The, I usage parameter.
So what is I usage again?
This is the exact same thing.
That's asking us when we created it wants to know is it going to be
palletized?
Or is it going to be RGB?
And since we're bleeding in RGB?
Use RGB and stretch lit.
We need to use RGB here as well because that is what we wanted.
Right?
Then.
We have a pointer to the bits.
And so, this is actually the big moment.
This is the actual memory.
This is the bitmap memory that we are going to receive back from
Windows that we can finally drawn to with our own renderer.
That is the big thing that we wanted.
That's what we really wanted out of this whole platform layer.
And that's what we're about to get finally after two days.
So the H section
Ian, excuse me is basically something that's used.
If you want to do something Fancy with your dip section, that's sort
of doing it out of core and writing it into I guess into a file or
something because we don't care about any about this stuff.
We just want to allocate one in memory for us.
We don't want to back it with a file or do any of this stuff.
I don't actually know if that I don't actually know.
If it does back with a file, it may just actually use some kind of
memory mapping for it.
I don't know.
I've never actually used this parameter so I don't care at all about
that and we're not even spend any time on it because time is of the
essence.
On this dream.
And finally, we have an offset which is referencing this thing.
So since we know that we are not passing this thing and it's ignored,
if this is no, we can ignore that as well.
So there is our creative section call.
It will create the tip section for us and pretty much that does
everything we want to do.
Except we did not fill out the bitmap info that we are passing to it.
So what on Earth is a bitmap info?
Again, this is all the vagaries of programming on Windows.
It's a bit esoteric and
I don't blame you for going.
What on Earth is going on here.
It's just the way it goes.
Here we are on the bitmap info.
So we have a bitmap info header.
It's called dot BMI header and we have an RGB quad, which is BMI
colors.
Now.
This is a little syntax that's used in Old School.
See.
And I'm basically, if you define an array, at the end of something, it
allows you to make it variable length, you can basically keep on going
off.
The end of this thing, you know, access.
Otherwise, I'm not even going to begin to talk about that, and how
that works or anything like that.
Because we don't care about that right now.
And I don't think you should really, I, don't really recommend ever
doing it either.
But if you really care about it, sometime in a Q&A, I will tell you
what's going on there because it's, it's super janky and weird.
But it works if you think about it.
Anyway, we don't care about this because we are not using a pelletized
buffer.
Like I said before, we are using RGB values and we'll see how those
work in just a little bit.
Probably tomorrow stream will be a lot about that.
But anyway, this is basically where the palette goes.
It's something, it's a, it's a variable.
Sighs array that will contain all of the colors that you plan to
reference in your buffer.
And since we don't plan to reference any colors, we plan to write the
colors directly into the pixels where they belong.
We don't have to worry about that at all.
So BMI header is really the only thing that we need to know about and
because we are going to have to fill that out in order to specify what
we want.
So,
In here, you will see all of the things we have to specify so bi size.
It says the number of bytes required by the structure.
So that's basically Windows asking us to put into the structure itself
how big the structure actually is.
Now that makes some sense probably because maybe they want us to
include like this, if we had one of them or whatever.
Sometimes Windows, just want you to make to pass the side of things so
they can tell what version of the API, it was that called them.
But basically, what we need to do here, is it use that size of
function that we saw before, where we can get?
Sighs of things.
We saw that in the intro stream to basically just find out the size of
the structure itself.
So hey, whatever the bitmap info structure is now, do they want the
size?
What you do?
They want the size of ladies and gentlemen, do they want the size of
this, or do they want the size of this?
That's the real question number of bytes required by the structure.
It doesn't say.
Mmm-hmm.
An application should use information from the S.
Isomer to locate the color table in a bitmaps or a structure.
Oh, here is the clue.
We needed.
It says, the color table which is, which is
I believe this right here.
It says the color table is the thing that comes the bi sighs.
Yes, VI sighs after.
So that's this is exactly what we want.
Okay.
So if you, if you were in the in the intro stream you remember us
doing something.
Exactly like this.
We basically took a pointer to.
We cast it to a care star which is exactly what they're doing.
Here.
That is Windows pound to find forecasts, are we cast it a pointer to a
character and we added a memory offset to it to get to a new place in
memory.
People who people who remember the stuff for the intro stream, you are
very happy right now because that is exactly need to know.
So now we know what that size parameter actually, is the size
parameter is how big the header is so it can skip to the color table
which to me suggests that it should only be this size.
It should only be this thing here and it should not include the color
table.
So we're going to go ahead and use just the size of the header
portion, like that.
Next field.
We need is the width.
We know what the width is because that is getting called right here.
We know what the height is.
So that is right there.
We know what the planes are because that is sort of a, that is a an
old-school notion.
Basically bit planes used to be when you would specify.
Couple chunks of memory that get combined to give you the color.
We don't have to do that anymore.
Thankfully, all of the pixel RGB values are not stored in like a red
plane at Green Planet.
Blue plane or or something where you have one bit per each part of the
red value or anything like that.
We don't have to worry about that.
Thankfully.
Everything is actually per pixel packed together, nowadays and you
can't even touch by anything other than one apparently says this value
must be set to 1, so we don't have to worry about that.
We don't have planes.
We only just have our back buffer.
So that's good.
We'll talk a little bit more about these things when we decompress
maybe on the Friday stream, we go back over everything.
I will talk a little bit of the history of some of those things for
everyone.
But for now, I want to keep going.
The bit count is the number of bits per pixel.
Now, 24 is actually how many we need, but I'm going to
Ask for 32 for reasons that will become clear in a little later.
The reason I say 24 is because we need 8 B, 4 red, 8 B, 4, Green 8,
that's for blue.
Just like you would see and say HTML or something like that.
We want an 8-bit color for each for now, and I'm going to actually ask
for 32 because I want things to be d word a line, but you don't have
to worry about that just yet, because we're going to talk about
alignment totally separately.
All right, that would involve Us opening up the Intel architecture
manual, which is always fun.
Ladies and gentlemen, you will enjoy it.
I promise you.
So we can then say what kind of compression we want.
And we do not want this compressed at all, because what we want to do
is be able to write to it as fast as possible and lit from it as fast
as possible.
We do not want it to be doing any fancy compression.
So it's going to be thinking about things at all, trying to compress
them.
We do not want that.
So we're just going to cut past bi RGB for the format.
Sorry.
What was the actual format name?
It is bi compression.
Bi compression.
There we go.
Sighs image.
What on Earth is that the size in bytes of the image this may set to
be the guest to be zero.
So basically that's just going to that is just going to be show up.
If you actually have to have a compression format, where Windows
wouldn't know how big the thing was going to be, because you were
going to do some pressure on it spells per meter is sort of totally
useless for us.
Why would we need to know that at all?
That is something is only if you were actually using some kind of
print output pixels per meter.
We don't even have anything.
That so can we can we set those 20, ladies and gentlemen, is there a
way to set those 20?
I feel like they could both be set to 0 so I'm going to set them to
zero for now.
Hoping that does not mind because that is basically for printing and
that sort of stuff where you have an actual or something, where you
actually care about the physical size.
We don't even know what the size is of our display at this point.
So we're in no position to say how many pixels per meter there are on
it because we don't know anything about that.
Clear use the number of color indexes.
Okay.
This is how many colors are used in the color table.
I just said we don't have a
color table.
So we don't care about that at all either.
And finally, bi-color important also not care about because we do not
have any of that index pallet stuff.
Okay, this should actually go through and allocate our bitmap memory
for us, but we will not know until we actually try if we've done
everything, right, but I want to point out something that we now need
to handle and that is we actually need to free.
Well, we need to get our device context first.
So we need to do that too, but we actually need to free this thing.
Before we create a new one.
Because like I said before.
If you go down here and you look at the WM size command, you will note
that we basically have a resize deep section call will happen.
Every time we WM size.
So if we allocated new memory for our buffer, every time that would be
bad.
So, what we actually want to do is just right before we create, our
new dip section.
We could free the old dip section.
Or we can wait and see if we can get our new one first.
And if we can't, we can keep using our old one.
It's tough decision.
It is a tough decision, ladies and gentlemen, because basically
there's a bunch of trade-offs either way, depending on how we do it.
I am going to go ahead and say what we will actually do is we will we
will actually free after will create ours first and then free after
the reason that's a little touchy is because if we needed the memory
from the first one or two, get them.
From the second one because it was occupying too much memory.
It would be kind of shooting ourselves in the foot.
So maybe the other thing we could do is if we fails yeah, yeah, this
is hard.
So, you know what?
We're going to put you do here and we're going to say bulletproof this
and we're actually going to just do a free straight up free first.
So basically what we'll say is bulletproof this maybe don't free first
free after then free first.
If that fails maybe we'll get that shot.
Bit later just to be a little more resilient depending on the
circumstances.
Okay.
So what we're going to do here is basically right here.
We will free it, three our jib section, but then down here.
We will create the new one that we can then use to draw.
So we're going to have to remember a couple things as we can see down
here.
We need that bitmap info which is this thing, right?
So this guy is going to have to be persistent.
So let's go ahead and put him out here, right?
He's going to have to stick around forever.
There you go.
I now that will also clear him to 0.
So that means all of these guys are cleared for us for free.
Right?
Don't actually do any of that, clear for us, for free out, in bitmap
info.
Then we've also got this bitmap memory right here, which is void start
again.
These little variables, will probably not last long.
We are going to make them ungh Lobel in just a little bit.
But for now to keep things simple and to make sure that we are on time
for the day.
We are going to go ahead and use them because they are going to use
sort of across multiple things that do not share.
Are a context that we can easily get to but I'll show you a little
trick of that a little bit later.
And then finally, we are going to probably need.
That bitmap handle because without that bitmap handle, we would not be
able to free it.
So I must do this as well.
So there we go.
And what I'm going to do is I am going to say bitmap handle Global
variable.
There we go.
I am going to say at the top of this if we want to free our dip
section.
Basically, what we're going to have to do is if we actually have our
it mapinfo initialized and since this is the first thing we
initialize, I'm gonna go ahead and switch on that.
I'm going to say if that's actually initialize.
Then we assume that we will have to actually get rid of the stuff.
I don't know if bitmap handle actually something I can test for as
well.
Let's take a look at that.
What is that actually find to be inside windows?
I don't know if that's thing.
We can test on, let's take a look bitmap H bitmap typedef.
It is a handle.
So I don't know if that'll come back as invalid handle value or what?
That is a good question.
Let's take a look at create dip section and see what it says.
Return value is on failure because I don't actually remember.
Doo doo doo.
There.
It is takes a little while and I missed you in sometime.
Okay, let's see.
Return values is exceeds.
The function there.
Turned volumes of data to do at the function fails, return value is
null.
Okay.
So basically, this will initialize, the null, which is good.
And we can also say, if bitmap handle, that means we've got one and so
we will have to delete that bitmap handle note, GD, is a little wonky.
The way that that works is basically when it creates a bitmap handle
which is going to actually track the memory for us as well.
It actually deletes everything through the same call if I remember
correctly.
So basically you actually pass bitmap handles to delete object,
instead of something like delete bitmap and it just figures out what
type it was.
So you can actually see here in the remarks actually tells us this
now.
And I'm looking at it, the system closes the handle to that memory
when you later delete the dip by calling delete object function.
So, yeah, I guess basically, you know, they just wanted to make an
only one delete call and you just pass everything to it and it's an H
GD.
I robbed that it expects to get so we may
Yet, we may actually have to cast this if Windows wants us to pass it
to it because basically, we actually have a h bitmap and, you know, I
don't think it's going to do that on a test for us, but we'll find
out.
In fact, let's just find out right now.
That was fine.
Okay, that's totally fine.
Oh, and I also forgot.
Here.
These are all in the BMI header, right?
These are all the in the header that we're setting here because this
actual bitmap info thing.
Didn't have any any actual stuff in it.
So, there we go.
Okay, so we're going to go ahead and delete this object here.
And there's another thing we're going to actually have to do in this
case.
That'll happen in a second.
But the other thing that we have to do now is figure out where we're
going to get this device context because we have a device context.
We need to actually go ahead and create a device context that we can
actually.
Use to create our dip section.
What it's going to do with that device context is it's going to create
a bitmap that's suitable for use with that device context.
So in order to do that, basically we have to first get a device
context, that is something we can use to put to the screen because
that is what we're trying to do.
And the way that we do that is we use a thing called get compatible DC
and we pass it zero.
Now.
I know that's a little bit odd and probably a little confusing to
everyone.
This is again the vagaries of windows, but basically what happens here
is sorry, we see basically what happens here is we can ask Windows to
give us back a device context that's compatible.
With something, right?
And you can see if I actually pass it in here.
Remember, device context of the things that we use to draw in Windows.
You can see the pastebin, we do create Capitol DC.
We pass it, another, HDC and say, hey, we need you to basically make
something that we could use to draw in a way.
That's that's compatible with this other thing that we're trying to
use and that's important to us.
Because basically, we have something we want to draw into that.
We're going to try and get to the screen.
And so, what you want to do is create a device constants, compatible
with the screens device context, even though we are not drawing with
this.
Device contacts.
I know it's crazy.
I didn't make this stuff up.
Fortunately, once we're done with it.
We're gonna be done with it.
Oh, no, the five-minute warning.
Well, it's good to know that the app is working.
We may need a little more in five minutes.
We may have to go in the Q&A today.
That'd be sad, but we might need a little bit more just to get to the
point where we're actually putting the screen, but we're almost there.
If we get a device contest compatible with bling to the screen, we can
then use it and we will want to
Actually.
You know what?
That's not, that's not entirely true.
That's not entirely true.
We want to just actually keep this around, is the thing we want to
actually keep this device context around because, why not, right?
So, we can actually create a compatible DC for this thing and leave it
selected.
Hmm.
I really wish that five-minute warning wasn't up, because there's a
bunch of stuff that we should.
Probably, that we should probably explain here.
I wonder if we have to break this into.
That would be sad.
Because we're so close.
It's that moment of indecision.
Do you go into the Q&A and you finish it or do you stop?
And wait?
Huh?
Well, I'll tell you what, we'll do, we'll make a compromise and make a
slight compromise.
What we will do is we will call create compatible DC here and will
actually create a DC that's compatible with something, basically
compatible with the, with, with the screen.
So, will actually call create compatible DC with zero, to make a
device conducts that we can use that we can keep.
So instead of having to release it.
We will just keep it.
And this will be part of the package that we will eventually wrap up
into a nice little thing that we can use for doing this stuff.
So this is our bitmap device context that we can use from then on and
if we know that we have done our stuff before we will not need to make
it because I believe we can just use the same one forever, and that
should be fine.
But we could also shut it down and created a new each time.
I don't know.
We'll see you in a second point being.
We will probably end the stream here because there is so much to talk
about in here.
So many new things that we did that.
I think we really want to basically have, we want to have enough time
to actually go through everything and and talk about sort of
decompress, a little bit, all the stuff that I did.
So I'm not going to blow through the Q&A.
We're going to stop and we're going to actually do real rendering
tomorrow because we basically done almost all of the work for it.
So tomorrow we can just start fresh and start drawing things right
away, which seems like probably
Better solution.
So, hopefully, everyone's okay with that.
We were almost there.
But at the last minute it was passive.
We grasp defeat from the jaws of Victory if you will, so, all right.
I'm just going to clean up this V.
We change the name of that to win32 resize tip section.
So now we have a thing where we actually do call in and we do resize,
our dip section, but unfortunately, we don't actually do anything with
our dip section.
So that is not particularly exciting basically.
What we've done now is we've made it so that when we go in to do our
resize, we check to see whether or not we already have a bitmap
handle.
If we do have a bitmap handle.
We need to delete that bit about handle.
So we go ahead and we do that, but if we do not have a bitmap handle,
that means this is a time.
Well, you know, I can make this a little cleaner.
Actually.
Let's just see say also if we don't have a bitmap device context, we
will also create one of those and we never probably need to free that
when I don't think we'll have to double check later.
We start to do testing whether we would have to change create a new
one.
If someone unplugged Monitor, and plugged a new one in and set to a
different display resolution or something like that.
We may have to, I don't know.
So it's a good question, is whether we should create a new one or not
here.
So I'm going to go ahead and put it to do down here.
Should we recreate these under certain special circumstances?
And we'll take a look a little bit.
We'll take a closer.
Look at that.
When we do the final stuff.
We filled out our BMI header.
We ask for our dip section and we should have gotten back our memory.
So let's take a look and see if that actually worked.
If it actually gave us the back buffer that we wanted.
So we come in here.
We hit the resize.
Obviously, this is inside rwm sighs call.
So we came in here and we, by the way, you can always double click in
here to move throughout the various parts of the stack.
This is where we are in the stack right now.
So basically this is in fact, you know, and I'll just go ahead and
step through it explicitly for you so you can see it.
So basically what happens is we come in here we get a double size
message.
We get the size of the window by getting the client wrecked and you
can see the client rectum here.
Right.
There's the left top right and bottom we can turn out of hexadecimal
display here and see that our window is 1424 by 729.
A very interesting resolution indeed, but that is what Windows
created.
As we didn't ask for anything.
In particular, you'll remember we said use default, so it did, there
we go.
There's our width and height up the Q&A begins.
Now we're in trouble, but I said, we're going to call it for today.
Anyway, so anyway, point being that we got our sized correctly.
You can see we actually did our math there, with the knife, we go into
the resize.
We don't need to, we don't have a bitmap handle yet.
So we don't need to delete object.
We don't have a oh, that's a bug right there.
My bad, we wanted to do this.
If we don't have a bitmap device context, right?
Because basically, we want to create one if we don't have one.
So we need to do, basically this not equal to 0.
If we do not have one empty shorthand for that, you can do also is
just not that thing, right?
So there we go.
Okay, glad we stuck through that caught an obvious bug right away.
One.
Nice part about stepping through your code.
Is you get to catch some stupid mistakes that you will then have to go
in and go.
Oh, yeah.
So we go ahead and create one of those.
Let's see if we got back something valid.
We did.
We are going to go ahead and fill out our structure.
Let's take a look at that and make sure it looks like what we think it
should look like before we go any further.
There.
It is.
Everything looks good.
32 bits per pixel, one plane.
That is the size.
Wanted this is the size of the bitmap info header, which looks good.
And now we will see if we get a bitmap handle back and we did.
Let's see if we got our bitmap memory back.
We got that too.
So it looks like we have succeeded in getting our back buffer.
But unfortunately we are not actually going to be able to use it.
Sorry about that.
Unfortunately, we are we are up still got that break point in there.
Let's get rid of that.
Don't want to break every time we resize our window.
So there is our window, it is
Sizing at the moment.
And presumably it is, it is actually doing what it's supposed to do.
Although we have to do some actual work in here are testing to see if
that's true.
We can also take a look in the excuse me.
We can also take a look here in the task manager by hitting Ctrl
shift.
Escape, bring up the task manager.
One thing that I like to do periodically, especially when I read
something like that, that's going to be doing some kind of finicky
things.
Where it's like, oh, it's sometimes lots of free this thing and
sometimes it doesn't cause it's doing something clever or thinks it's
cool.
I do a lot of things to double-check.
Make sure that everything is is kosher and so one of the things that I
want to look at is is what our memory footprint looks like.
So, let's go ahead and see if we can find our application here.
What do we call this?
We called it win32 handmade.
So there it is.
We can see are working set right there, which is basically how much
memory we are using at the time.
And I am going to go ahead and go nuts with this to make sure that we
are not leaking anything.
And you can see that we do not appear to be.
So that is good.
If that number
If like was going up like crazy or something like that, then that
means we would be leaking something, but it looks like we are in good
shape.
Okay, so, I'm sorry.
We didn't quite get to draw into it.
We did all the work to get it.
It's kind of like,
You know, doing doing all the work and not getting paid, and that's a
little disappointing.
But the good news is tomorrow.
We will be able to start right away with drawing and that is the fun
stuff.
Ladies and gentlemen, that is the part where we actually start working
on the game game.
So I'm going to go back and stick to our schedule.
Even though I really want to go do that.
I'm going to stick to the schedule and say let's open it up for Q&A.
I will, I will go ahead and start taking questions now.
Let's see.
Where are we?
Stretchy B.
Take a pointer to the pixel data.
You don't need to bother with great tips section.
Just allocate an array yourself.
I do not believe that's actually truce as sylvain, unfortunately, so
you can't just allocate anything you want and pass it back to Windows.
The reason for that is that it is going to be padded in a very
specific way.
That is the way that Windows wants it to be for doing the blit and it
has to be associated.
With a particular bitmap handle.
Basically, basically, it's not as simple as that is.
I guess the way I would say it will look at this a little bit more,
but, but here, see if you can
Okay.
So basically what happens here, is this guy when he when he allocates
that right?
We are going to we are going to get back memory that Windows actually
wanted us to use.
And as far as I know.
We cannot just willy-nilly decide to do it in a particular way.
Maybe that's not true.
If that's actually true that we don't have to have Windows do it.
That would be pretty awesome.
I mean we could certainly try it.
In fact, I guess since we're in the Q&A, we could totally try it on.
If you want me to, if you want me to go nuts here, we could totally
try it.
I'm I'm not optimistic that what you're saying is true, but
I mean we could test it.
Now.
The problem too is if we test that it works that doesn't actually mean
that it's the right thing to ship because you never know like maybe
you need a, I don't know.
I'm torn.
But you know what?
It's pretty easy for us to test.
So we could just test it.
We could just go ahead and say allocate the actual bits and then try
to Blind them and see if that works.
Let's, let's, let's, you know what?
I'm not going to actually do that.
I'm going to see if there's any actual.
Asian here about where those bits have to come from because it may
actually tell us what the case is here.
Let's find out.
Okay, this function do blah blah blah.
See, I'm just worried.
So here's what I here's I guess what I'll say, I'm pretty sure that we
could if we wanted to pass it, our own data that we created and yes,
it probably would allow us to paint to the screen.
I'm
Just not sure it would paint to the screen quickly.
It might go through basically a slow path if that makes sense.
I know I'm not explaining this very well.
But basically I thought you wanted Windows usually to allocate it in
its own way with its own layout and padding.
So that you would basically guarantee that it could that it knew, it
could be on the fast path and it didn't have to do any weird stuff to
make it happen.
But maybe that's not true and it's hard to figure out necessarily
where I would look for that.
Kind of thing in the documentation.
Obviously, we cannot step into windows and see, I've always done it by
using Create compatible, DC and having it, do it, but I'm not sure.
I wonder if Raymond Chen has something to say about this, because that
would be pretty awesome.
Let's see what the rest of the chap.
Does anyone else have an opinion on here?
Let's see.
I didn't stop a little comparing.
That's true.
I'm no longer going to split them.
I'm just going to do one, one and a half hour thing and people can
stop if in the middle.
Let's see.
Does anyone know does anyone know?
No, it doesn't look like it doesn't look like anyone has a definitive
answer.
I don't know.
So, so let's let's say s sylvain.
Let's let's say that that I will actually try to ask someone with
Windows internals knowledge and and I will try to ask them and if we
can't ask them, then what I will do is we will just we will just test.
Both we will just test both and see which if there's any speed hit to
either of them and we can also try that on lots of different peoples
machine.
Maybe so that we can see whether it's something that's safe to ship or
not, because honestly, I just don't know.
I don't think I've ever tried it without letting Windows allocate the
memory itself, and I'm just a little bit nervous about it because I
can't vouch for the fact that it will work.
Does create dibs.
Sorry.
Create compatible to see have to happen.
And we will take a look at that.
Okay, it's good point though.
It's an excellent point.
Thank you for bringing that up.
Because hey if that is the case, then we can just get rid of this,
this part right here.
This piece of the code, we can just create the bitmap header and we
can allocate the memory ourselves and off we go.
So no harm.
No foul.
Let's take a look at the questions.
Doo-doo-doo-doo-doo-doo-doo think we covered some of this.
These are will you be using sleep?
Yes, we will.
When we find that we complete the game Loop into Quick a time, and we
want to yield back sometime to the system so that we don't melt down
the CPU.
We will, you sleep.
Do do do.
Also, could you go back?
How you got Visual Studio to cooperate?
Yes, for those of you who missed it on the earlier stream.
If you are in a situation where we're Dev studio is not cooperating
with your build that you're using outside.
What you type is, you type Dev em, and then you type, the name of the
executable, you are trying to debug.
So, in this case, we put that in build win32.
Handmade exe was where it was.
So if I just do that line, it will go through and it will it will open
the eggs and started to bugging session for us.
That's all you.
Have to do, there's no no magic to it.
And then once you do that, if you go into tools options in here,
there's a start-up.
And if you set at startup to last loaded solution, you won't even have
to do that anymore.
Because once you have one up, it'll just always bring that one back up
again.
So that's kind of Handy.
Our other windowing systems less crazy to work with no.
Honestly know the weird thing about all this is honestly, you know, it
looks crazy and it is crazy.
You know, I am never going to defend the design of the windows API
because always should have had to do is just say we're a game, give us
a back buffer and it should have like how many people write games with
back bumpers?
There were so many of those at the time nowadays.
They use 2D graphics cards but back then.
When did it and so it should have just been one thing, it was like,
hey, guess what?
You enter win, Maine and you make a call.
That's like I'm a game and it just sets everything up for you
correctly.
And there's so many reasons why operating system should do that.
Because they would basically lead to far fewer bugs because everyone
who makes a game, doesn't know.
All the minutiae windows.
I don't know.
All the minutiae Windows.
No one who shipped a game ever knows all the moves, your windows.
And so they will miss something or whatever that they were supposed to
do to handle like a certain key combinations going.
And so it's just bad.
So yeah, it's I'm not
To defend the design of the windows API at all.
It's bad news, but basically everything is bad news.
I mean, you know, you go write a game in HTML5 and it's a nightmare.
The stuff that goes on there.
Take a look at the audio API for that.
It's awful.
I mean, there's just, there's so many things wrong with most of these
platforms that picking on Windows is not that productive because while
they are bad in some ways are almost less bad than some of the things
that people have been making.
Several decades later and what's that excuse, you know, in 20 years or
whatever.
Since, you know, the last major, rev of the win32 API, what's the
excuse people?
You know, I mean things should be really clean nowadays and they
aren't and so I don't really, you know, I whine about window certainly
because I don't like using it anymore than anyone else.
But at the end of the day, it's it's no worse and even sometimes
better A lot of times than some of the newer stuff and that is frankly
just depressing because I
I'd rather live in a world where operating systems were getting easier
to work with everyday not harder.
And what's funny about that is even Windows itself is also getting
harder to work with every day.
As they've started revving, their API in ways that make it worse,
which is crazy.
So, I don't know.
That's why I'm still using a lot of the old school functions to is
because, man, the new functions are even more ridiculous.
Let's see.
This is entirely related today.
But are you going to do a more detailed intro to sealed series
alongside this?
Yes, I would like to do that some day.
The only problem is my voice.
I don't know how much voice I got in me.
If I start trying to do other stuff in parallel with this, maybe we
could take a week off and do a more detailed in terms of seriously,
but probably have to be do a real intro to see it might have to be a
couple weeks.
And I don't know when we're going to have time to do that.
So it's a good question.
I would say watch the regular intro to see one and do a lot of reading
on the side like read KN are the C programming language or just
practice in any
Actually, it's practice programming if you're unfamiliar with it and
read up about see, it shouldn't be that hard to sort of get into most
of it because the stuff that I do in the intro to see is all sort of
showing you how it all ties together.
Like, you know, looking at memory and looking at those sorts of things
that are the sorts of things that people aren't used to doing if
they're working in languages that aren't low-level like C is.
And so I think that maybe I hope that people will be able to educate
themselves about see a little bit if they're used to some other
programming language in the meantime now, but yes, I would like to do
a real beginners.
Intro to see where we take it real slow and go through absolutely
everything, but I don't know when realistically I will be able to do
that because there's only so much I can record without my voice going.
Let's see.
Your to-do can explain.
What?
Exactly is a void star pointer to nothing.
Yes, I can and we will get to that a little bit more detail.
When we Act start to draw.
The reason it was a void star was actually because we don't want to
specify the type that were pointing to.
So if you remember a pointer is just a value that says a number which
is the offset in memory where something is right.
And so if I actually someone saying I forgot to move Chrome to the
side we need to
Like this doc Chrome on the side there, I guess or something and leave
it there.
So people can look at the code of the same time.
I got to learn to do that.
People have been asking for that and I should do that.
But anyway, if we go in here and take a look, which we should do if we
take a look at that void start.
This is a pretty interesting thing that happened here.
So let's talk about it.
Basically, we've got a situation where we want Windows to give us back
some bitmap memory basically, right?
And that bitmap memory.
It doesn't know the
Format of the bitmap memory.
Because remember we pass stuff?
Like what kind of compression to use and and whether it was palletized
or not.
And so the function, great dip section can only have one function
signature C does not allow you to say stuff.
Like this one function could take 60 an unsigned short star or an
unsigned in star or an Ensign care star, so
Three and blah.
Blah, blah, right.
You can't do that.
The only thing she can do is use void star.
And what void star means is some kind of pointer.
It says I want a pointer but I don't care what it points to so
anything is fine.
Right?
And so basically what we're doing when we say void started saying
we're going to get back at pointer, but we don't actually know that
the format of the thing to which it is pointing and later.
What we'll do is we'll cast it to the format that we actually want to
use at the time and because this is
Is a bitmap that we're going to be jumping through and writing to and
different ways.
We will probably actually cast it to more than one thing.
Depending on the circumstance.
We will cast it to a car star, which is an 8-bit value pointer to an
8-bit value.
When we want to move around in it to find a location in it, so that we
can do arithmetic on it.
And then we will probably cast it to a unsigned int, which is a 32-bit
value when we actually want to poke at the individual values because
that will allow us to write the RGB and a values, which is actually
Arginine X values, but whatever.
We're going to write those directly as one chunk probably and we'll
even do some more stuff.
That's even crazier later.
Probably but point being, that is what avoid, sorry.
So what happens in here when we call create dip section is, you'll
notice.
We're not just passing avoid star.
We're not passing a pointer to B that memory.
We're passing a pointer to the pointer to bitmap memory, right?
Because right here, you can see I use the address operator to take the
address of the bitmap memory.
So basically what's happening is if you go into the department,
Bugger, if I run to that line right here, we are about to call create
dip section.
You can basically see that bitmap memory is just all zeros and I am
passing address of bitmap memory.
Right?
So I am passing it.
The address of the pointer that I would like Windows to then go over
right with the new pointer that points to the memory that it
allocated.
And this is a very standard trick that people do in see all the time
basically what it boils.
Down to is, you have a function and you want to return more than one
value value from it, right?
And that's exactly what happened here.
Right?
Creative section needs to be able to return a bitmap handle, but it
basically also needs to be able to return this bitmap memory.
So I wouldn't necessarily do it this way.
But the way that a lot of people do do it is they just pass in the
address of more memory like more variables than take the address of
them and say,
Here's where I want you to stick.
Those other return values that you couldn't stick on the stack because
C only, lets you have one return value.
Now.
The reason I say, I wouldn't necessarily do it that way is because,
see, really does.
Let you do multiple return values.
It lets you do multiple return values like this struct create dib
section result.
And this is how I probably would have done it.
Now granted.
This is an API barrier that has some certain requirements.
So I'm not necessarily fall out the windows people for not doing it
this way because there's other reasons that play there.
But if this was internal to our own code, let's say I would probably
not do it that way.
I would put the bitmap result in here.
Let's say and I would put the memory results.
So here is the memory and actually this was called that I think this
is a handle I should say, right?
And then what I would do is when I Define create dip section, I would
Define it to work like this.
So basically in here, we pass the device context, we pass the
It mapinfo, we pass the the usage code and we pass the other stuff
here and here, but we never pass the address to bitmap memory.
Because basically what happens is create dip section will return a
struct.
That has both things in it.
I like that way better personally and there's really no reason not to
do it because C does, let you return structures by value and that is
the way that I prefer to return multiple things.
So it's clearer and no one's taking addresses of things and so on.
Now,
There can be performance problems with this potentially.
So you don't want to necessarily do this.
If this thing was going to be huge for some reason, but if it's only
two values for all, I know this actually might be more efficient.
It depends on the circumstances, right?
So, basically, I would say that this is a pretty sane way to do two
small return values.
I would rather do it this way, then do it.
The way that they did.
Okay, we're back to yes.
Looking at the questions.
I'm sorry.
I can't get to everyone's questions at this point.
There are so many viewers on the stream.
That is both a blessing and a curse.
It is so nice to see so many people on the stream, but it does mean
that in 30 minutes.
I am just I'm just randomly picking questions, and maybe we're going
to have to do something someday.
Where somebody who some kind soul out there will basically watch the
questions and try to select the most interesting ones or something.
I'm just basically randomly picking what I happen to see people.
Let's see, do do do.
Do, do any new thoughts on?
I am gooey.
Since you made that video a few years ago.
I assume the UI in this game will be.
I am I am the person who actually coined that phrase.
It is true and I made that weird little video and it seems like it's
been something that's a little bit more popular nowadays.
However, we are not going to get to that to a little bit later on.
We are going to probably do some IM stuff.
I should say.
We probably
Almost certainly will in the course of the stream deal.
With I am gooey like things and I will actually for the first time
talk a little bit about the philosophy of, I am gooey in later on in
these streams because I never really did a good job of explaining to
people.
How I am gooey, really was supposed to work.
And when I go look at a lot of I am gooey discussions while I'm very
glad to see that the technique caught on because I think it's good.
A lot of them tend to miss the point a little bit and that is my fault
for doing a bad job explaining it.
And it was probably also because I
Did that video pretty early on in my understanding of how I am Jewish?
Work.
And so I should probably set that record straight and I will do that
sometime during this series, that will be a lot of fun.
I look forward to it.
So SL then follows up.
He says after a cursory glance at the stress GI B Source, it looks
like at the stretch of its sorts.
Are you a Microsoft person?
That is pretty awesome.
If you can look at the source, it looks like it's fine to pass around
buffer.
However, if it's not d word aligned, it'll make a local copy.
That's fine because we could easily ensure that it was d word aligned.
That would be great.
We're going to put it to do based on S silvanus.
You know, I got to say this is a great thing about doing public
programming.
I mean, you don't have someone who can check the window source for you
just right off the bat like that.
That's that's crazy.
Based on S Sullivan's, suggestion.
Maybe we can just allocate this our cells and that would be great
because that would remove.
This right here, we could get rid of me.
Just this would turn into a memory allocation and we could get rid of
this entirely.
That would be fantastic as Silvan.
Thank you very much for doing that.
We will we will test it.
I appreciate the fact that yes, he's saying it's complicated code and
he didn't look at that carefully.
So maybe that's not true.
We don't know yet.
But you know what Co gramming is always an exploration exploration.
I never know everything that's going on.
That should be totally obvious and neither does any other
We're out there that I know basically you are always exploring.
That's one of the reasons that I like the idea that this game is also
going to be about exploration because that is what programming is
about.
There's always more to learn and so, you know, this will be a learning
experience.
I've shipped so much code in my lifetime that actually always asks
windows for this memory.
And now if it turns out that you don't have to do that.
That is awesome.
That's just something that I don't have to do anymore and it's kind of
cool.
That's got that be great.
So, we'll find out.
Let's see.
Doot, doot.
Doot.
When will The Source be up for download?
It's always up for download right after the video, pretty much.
I push it pretty much immediately.
So if you download say like an hour, after the video ends, you will
get this source.
Let's see.
What else we got.
When using emacs, I find it hard to use, meta key with f and B to skip
words, how do you do it so fast, I use the Bindings that I have in my
team x file, which is hold down control and use the arrow keys.
Much, much better.
How come that not equal to 0 is true in C and the return values remain
and functions is 0 if everything is okay.
Yeah, that's a darn good question.
All right, so basically,
The way things work in C is C, is defined as saying that something is
true.
If it is not 0 and it is false, if it is 0 and I think that's a great
idea.
That is the way it should work.
I have no complaints about that.
However, what did happen with the c runtime library and which has been
picked up by a lot of people, not their fault.
They're just trying to be compatible C.
Runtime library is a lot of times, they will do something where they
will do, do the thing, you know, like this.
They Define a function and then there is
Is an integer that is going to come back and that integer is the error
code.
So the error code is 0 if there is no error right and then in here,
you know, if something went wrong with what we did, the error code
becomes, let's say negative 2 or if some other thing went wrong, then
the error code becomes 12 and there's a table of error codes and you
can check them.
That is what often happens and
The reason they're doing that is so that they can snuggle a little bit
of information in there.
That's not just whether the thing succeeded, but whether it's exceeded
or but whether it failed in a particular way if you will.
And so the reason that that's kind of confusing is because now when
you're out in the code and this is what the the person the question
was addressing, if I do something like, result, equals do the thing.
Like this and then I do if result that looks like I'm testing to see
whether do the thing succeeded but it's not it's actually testing
whether it failed because if it succeeded it'll be 0 and if it failed
it'll be something else.
So you have to test that which looks bizarre and it's not the way you
would test anything else.
For example, if you want to know if a pointer was no, it would be the
other way round.
It would be that way.
So it leads to confusion.
I try never to do this.
I try to handle error codes in a different way, but what can you do?
That is just the way that some people program, and it is the way, the
C runtime lot of programs.
And you have to be aware of.
It's also how Berkeley sockets work, I believe.
So, if you're using like, socket Library, it tends to work that way.
It's just, there's a lot of things that work that way and not much you
can do about it.
Let's see.
Pre Aunt CC didn't allow return structs.
So that's 0.
Is that Sean Barrett?
That would be fabulous with Sean.
Barrett was here.
Sean.
Barrett is for those of you who do not know him.
He is a pretty story and programmer.
Actually, in fact, the thing that you would probably most recognized
of his, he wrote the the renderer and again, this is in the days when
there was no 3D Hardware, so he wrote from scratch, the 3D renderer
for thief, the Dark Project, which is a very famous game, and of
course, is a lineage that still exist.
They still ship these games to this day.
Obviously, they use gpus and all kinds of crazy.
stuff now, but he is the fellow who wrote that renderer and a
Excellent programmer.
He wrote the stb libraries as well, which are things that everyone
should take a look at.
I again, I'm teaching something where I where I program everything
from scratch so I won't be using them.
But when you are looking around to see what libraries are available,
once, you are comfortable with stuff and can make good decisions about
what to use.
Those are some ones to look at.
They do a lot of great stuff in a very concise way, compact way that
doesn't create headaches for you, which is what a lot of libraries do.
So, yes.
Anyway.
Thank you very much for for
For watching Sean.
And basically, what I would say is I know almost nothing about pre
ANSI C.
And Sean is telling us that pre ANSI C didn't allow return struck.
So that thing that I showed would not have been allowed way way back
when like several decades ago before the ANSI standard standardized.
See.
And so maybe that explains why that didn't catch on initially because
people couldn't do it and then later when it became possible to do it,
maybe people didn't rethink how
They might do return values when they had multiple things because that
wasn't possible.
So that's a pretty interesting thing.
Obviously.
I think I've always programmed in things that supported ANSI C.
So I don't know that I've ever had to Wrangle with that but I don't
know.
It could be some time way back when I was doing it, but that's okay.
I've started doing relatively recently probably in the Wrath last 15
years or so.
Anyway,
Let's see.
Any reason you put the type in the line above the function name.
It is a force of habit.
Probably not a fantastic habit, but I just like to separate the two
out so I can see what the type is there.
I don't know why I do it.
I started doing it back when I used to be absolutely crazy.
C++, programmer, one of the funny things about doing stuff like this,
where I show kind of the old school dirty style of programming, where
you just get in and you do the code, is that I get
Sometimes male, obviously, from people who are livid at the fact that
I am not using all kinds of crazy.
C++ has Em's like like REI or like templates or the standard template
library.
And the hilarious thing about it is I think they think that I've never
used those things, but that is not the case.
I used to use all of those things and my code was a mess with them.
They were everywhere.
And I, you know, I actually like them at the time.
What can I say?
I've learned that I do not like the way that
Code comes out when you do those things, but I used to do use that
stuff a lot.
And one of the things that is true, when you have crazy templates and
all the sorts of other sorts of stuff, you end up with things where
you have, like, a template line with a ton of stuff and some return
values, and then all this stuff and my functions were getting out, to
be these huge things that were just absurd.
And the like, the way I have my stuff set up to highlight is the the,
you know, the parameter is kind of keep that keep that alignment
there.
I was, there was like no room for my stuff.
Tough.
And so I think that's basically when I started, I would break the
template line, plus the type on.
One line and the function name and parameters on to the next one like
that.
So alright with that are a stream is now over.
Ladies and gentlemen, I am truly sorry that we did not quite get, we
were so close.
If s Sylvan had had, I guess if I if SL and I had been friends and we
had talked about this quite some time ago and I had known that, I
don't have to do that.
Then I would not have been shy because I could have just a
Located here, and I wouldn't have been like, oh, I got to start
talking to you about what a create compatible.
DC is.
Now we can actually just get rid of that entirely potentially.
So thank you.
S sylvain.
You almost saved the day.
You certainly did add quite a bit to the stream, but unfortunately,
like I said, I don't check during the chat because I wanted you to see
me, make those mistakes, and see how how that goes.
Also.
I think it's good to see me make mistakes because that way people know
that, you know, programmers, who have been programming for a long
time.
Make a ton of mistakes because you will make a ton of mistakes.
You will feel like you are just stupid or something.
You are not or you are and we are all as well.
Either.
We're all stupid or nobody stupid one of the other, but the point is a
lot of mistakes are made and certainly a lot of them are made by me.
And so I want you to see those.
So I apologize for that fact.
I just think it's a good way to run the Stream.
So anyway SL van, thank you for that.
I'm sorry that I did not happen to check it before but that meant we
missed a little bit.
What we want to do, which is just draw a little something to the
bitmap so that we could see that it was worth.
Working.
But what we will do is we'll pick that up tomorrow and then we will
have an entire 60 minutes where we can do nothing but draw to our
bitmap and I think that will be pretty awesome.
Anyway, so it's a really good place to break even though I was hoping
we would get a little bit further.
Thank you so much for joining me.
It's an absolute pleasure, as it always is.
I'm sorry that I was sick.
I wish that I wasn't obviously and hopefully I will recover soon so
that I will not make weird Delirious mistakes when coding.
And also, if anyone
Any additional questions that they would like covered perhaps on the
next.
The next round tomorrow Night's Dream.
You can go to handmade hero dot-org and there is an email, a question
button.
Also, I would like to remind everyone that twitch is now also
temporarily archiving these streams.
So in addition to the archive button that you can push to get to the
YouTube ones, which I upload those take a little while for YouTube to
process, which means that sometimes you can't get to them right after
the stream ends.
So if you
Watching.
You can go to Twitch, and twitch will actually have on here.
No, don't start.
Don't start streaming me for reals.
It will actually have a little thing where you can go to past
broadcast.
I believe you just click on the handmade hero button there and you
click on past broadcasts and you can grab streams even before they've
ended, it looks like maybe I don't actually know how this works to be
honest with you, but point being.
If you want to start watching right away and not wait for YouTube.
That's actually not that you have.
Now.
These won't stay around forever twitch.
Clear.
Out after about a couple weeks I think so you need to use those
archives for getting the older episodes, but that will be another tool
you can use.
If you want to get things right away.
I think that's it for tonight.
Thank you so much for joining us and tomorrow.
It's going to be a new day.
Ladies and gentlemen, we're going to actually draw such a the screen.
I'll be honest with you.
I'm pretty excited about it.
So, please tune in tomorrow 8:00 p.m.
And we will do some some rendering finally.
I can't wait.
Thanks everyone for joining us and I will see you tomorrow.
Row.