Are you okay?
Hello everyone.
Welcome to handmade hero the show where we could a complete game from
scratch live on Twitch.
We of course do not use any engines or libraries, we write everything
from scratch so that we can have one full path through an entire game.
So we've seen at literally all the code from the thing that puts the
pixels on the screen, all the way up to high level stuff like AI.
We've tried to basically say we're going to cover every last bit of
it.
So right now what we're doing is we're kind of wrapping up some stuff
that we did.
We're at a point where we need to kind of decide what sort of things
were going to push into.
So, you know, we're probably going to do on today is do some sort of
remaining issues and then maybe try to think about what the next big
step is that we want to make because we've been trying to do is
basically build out, essentially a prototype, functional version of a
game engine that has all the
Pieces in it so that we can see how they all fit together so that we
can start to make sort of final implementations of individual pieces
as necessary.
And this is a very flexible process.
Obviously we've done some parts.
That may be totally what we end up shipping.
Like we've done some parts that maybe are just fine.
We've got other parts where we sort of said okay yeah this this is
kind of a bad version or a half-baked algorithm but we know that it
does the things that we needed to do so later we
Come back and do a good industrial strength pieces of code here and be
done with it, right?
And so our goal in this passed through things because we need
something start with is to get a sort of a version of everything in
the game that we want happening, everything that we think the engine
needs to do so that we can start writing the game.
And if we need to add things later, that's always fine too.
And if we need to build out pieces of the engine, that need to the end
up needing to be better or more complicated, than what we thought.
That's all
Fine.
And that's all totally par for the course.
But what I wanted to do first was make sure of course the released
have one pass through because it's very important to be able to see
how things work by experimentation and exploration.
Before you try to go spend a lot of time building, robust code for any
individual purpose, for example, with the renderer, we want to get to
a point where we know how we want to use the renderer with before we
would actually write industrial-strength renderer because otherwise,
Guys, we would run the risk of writing a renderer that doesn't do the
things that we need to do or doesn't do them quickly.
So if we know what those things are right ahead of time, we know how
the interface looks, we know how everything should flow through there.
That just puts in a much better position to succeed.
And the same is true for everything else.
The Collision detectors, the same way we've kind of been working on
what the, what needs to happen there and how that needs to work path,
finding things like that, that we're going to probably talk on the
future.
Those are the same kinds of things.
We need to know what our needs are.
And how our code wants to use things like pathfinding before we would
want to go and write some really nice system that does fancy stuff,
right?
So that's what we're doing today is we're sort of continuing down that
road and so we don't have any specific bullet point item, but we've
got some things that we can take a look at.
So that's that's kind of what we were going to do.
All right, so let's take a look.
If you are coding along at home today is Day 70, which means you will
want to.
If you pre-ordered the game, you should have got Link in your email.
And that link should allow you to download the zip file which has Zips
inside it.
It's like are you know, matroska dollar whatever they call them little
nesting dolls, you can open up that zip file and there will be a zip
for day, 69, which was yesterday if you unzip that into a directory,
you'll be starting off with exact same code that I'm starting off with
now.
And so if you want to follow,
Long at home.
That's that's the way to do it.
All right, so I wanted to say something at the outset today, I don't
know.
Maybe this will be the something that we do today because it just it,
it's not really something that necessarily I would be concerned about
right now, but I thought of it and I thought that it might be a neat
thing to just kind of show for, you know, sir because it's a
programming thing.
Let's put it that way.
So basically, you know, we were talking yesterday
and we implemented some stuff about base Collision rules list, right?
It was a list where I could add rules to it.
And it would allow people to either Collide or not Collide based on
the rules, right?
And so, one of the things we did was like, you know, when, when
something hits something else, you can tell it to keep going.
And the reason we did that was, we wanted to have projectiles, like
that that little test projectile that I added the other day to be able
to go through that guy.
But still have the event recorded.
So we wanted him to be able to recognize the fact that it hit our
little torso monstar.
There we want people to respond to that as a collision event, but we
didn't actually want the Collision system to do anything about it.
The, we want to let it, you know, let them direct I'll sail through.
So we added that but then we also want it to no.
Don't keep giving us notifications about the fact that these two guys
are touching because we don't care.
We only want to know when it.
And so we wanted a system for adding rules.
So what we did is we made a little hash table that you could add
things into, and we said, all right, when two objects touch each
other.
If the response to that Collision says, I don't want to hear about
this anymore.
It just can add a rule to that table and then it will never get that
response anymore.
Now, we don't know if that's actually a good way to handle this.
It was just sort of something that I thought I was.
Like let's try it that way and so we made that little hash table but
we did have a
A thing that I mentioned which was I was like, I'm not sure how we
pull things out of this hash table.
Right.
I'm not sure how we clear this hash table effectively because there
was a very specific point which was basically a go ahead and jump to
it, which was that, for example, with things like the sword are sword,
going to quote that you throw their when it, you know, when it starts
traveling, we want to say, okay, it's got a collision rule.
It can't collide with the hero at all and when it hits them, the
monstar, we want it to just go ahead and
Do that once.
So on collision, will add a rule for that.
Obviously that's not going to work.
If we do that every time, this sort of storm because we keep adding
more and more rules and every time it went through a different monster
that be a new rule and we just proliferate the number of rules.
We just have thousands of rules as the player played the game so there
need to be a time when the rules are removed.
So we have this clear Collision rules thing but the problem was in
order to clear the Collision rules for a particular
For a particular entity, there was no good way to find where those
rules exist in the hash table.
Because the hash table was essentially a duel in the lookup, hash
table, where you pass, two indices, The Entity one, The Entity, you
know, in any Collision, there's two entities, entity a entity be.
And the way we made the hash table work is we just look it up on
entity a, right?
So, if the entity that you're happy,
To be clearing, always showed up as entity, a, well that would work
fine.
But if sometimes, it shows up at nndb, there'd be no way to use the
hash table to quickly, find those entries and remove them and that's a
problem, right?
so,
I said, well,
We need an effective to do here, need to make it better data structure
that allows removal of collision rules without searching the entire
table.
I was thinking about it afterwards, when I was walking to work, and I
realized there actually was a really obvious solution.
We could have used here, we could have made a trade you and still used
exactly the same hash table but had Direct removal of entries, right?
Sorry, I'm so sick today.
Hmm.
It's also allergy season here.
Spring has come very early to Seattle.
It's been an extremely Sunny normally.
We have a rainy season and we didn't really, it's been really sunny
and nice in Seattle, which is good in some sense.
But it also means I think that the trees are pollinating me which
never goes well anyway.
So what I was thinking is we did we could have made a trade-off that
That work and I wanted to talk about it and maybe we could maybe we'll
implement it, I don't know.
But basically, here we go, let's say here, we are on Day 70.
So we've got a hash table, right?
Hash, Hash Hash Hash Hash.
And the problem is, however, we compute the hash key, right?
So we've got incoming, we've got an index a and an index, be right.
And however, we insert this into this table, we're going to have a
problem.
If we want to be able to clear all of the entries, that involve some
entity e because we don't know how to compute.
The hash key just for me and it doesn't matter what rule we pick,
right?
If we only inserted them using a, then if he happens to show up in the
b key, we can't find it right without searching, but if we base the
insertion off, be the same would be true of a, if we base it off the
combination of A and B, then we can't find it at all.
It doesn't matter if it's a or b, we can't find it.
Because when we look up on E, we don't know how to produce a combined
hash key from that, right?
So the question is given a hash table that supposed to store things
that you look up on a and b?
How do you make it so that we can just look up on one of them?
And without it being too onerous, allow removal, right?
How do we do it?
So there's actually a couple different ways that we can do it, and I
mentioned, one of them and I want to mention the other one which is
kind of amusing.
The reason it's kind of amusing is because it would work without a
hand coded structure, right?
So basically, if you think about it, we've got this hash table, right?
And in the hash table, we've got an external chain, right?
And so we've got basically, this is just a pointer.
These are Pointers in here, they're not
Entries and these are the actual entries.
So these store like a bee, you know, another, A and B, whatever.
I guess we should call this c and d, right?
And so, you know, somewhere else down here.
I may have something which was a rule that was, that was like, C and
A.
And so, that's the problem there.
The problem is, is that the a shows up secondarily.
So if I was going to look, even if I do it off of a, I'm going to find
this one.
I'm not going to find that one, but I should have removed them.
Both right?
So another option that we could do is we could add two more pointers
right to these which are basically ways of chaining off of the
elements, right?
We could put another chain through here which is that every one of
these guys also has two pointers on them.
Right?
And those pointers point two for each of the slots like a linked list
through the hash table.
Right.
So basically on the see, you know, we come through here, it would
point to this guy on the a it would point to this guy or whatever,
right?
So that you could go through them and remove them.
So we'd store with each entity a pointer into the hash table, so that
to the first thing that have them, or we would just look up in the
hash table, some way.
I don't know, right?
But you see that, this gets pretty messy because we have to add two
pointers to everything.
And when we get there, how do we remove it?
Because
Let's say we end up with this guy.
If we point to this guy, we don't actually know which hatch slot he
was in.
So removing it, we don't know how to fix up this pointer because we
can't get back.
Right?
So it's kind of ugly and confusing and it's like, what do you do,
right?
So there's another option and I just want to point it out because it's
kind of interesting how it works.
And one of the things I want to show on the stream again, and that's
why I've been writing all the data structures by hand, for example,
as I want to show how to write data structures because oftentimes if
you are fast that if you don't, you know, if your answer to how you
store stuff is not always, just open up the standard template library
and grab something.
If you actually code them by hand, a lot of options, open up to you.
If you have that kind of practice and that facility with the
instructors, it means you can make purpose-built stuff in cases where
you need it, right?
And so in this case, if we have another way of thinking about it,
but,
When you actually think about it, too.
You'll also, this is not a good.
This is not a good demonstration of reasons to code things by hand,
because this is the actual method that I thought of as something that
would work.
Even if you were using a off-the-shelf component to store them, I'm
pretty sure anyway,
I don't actually know.
But I assume you could combine.
Yeah.
You could, you could combine like an STL map and an STL list to do
this.
Let's say.
So what I realized was well
You know, we're if we're going to spend some extra storage like two
extra pointers, right?
And and we do to exercise and then still get a system where we don't
even know how it would work.
Right to extra pointers on a 64-bit system is like 16 bytes, right?
Because each one is 8.
Bytes each point is 8, bytes.
So that's pretty expensive, right?
Concerning the fact that these were two un.
So actually, there was only eight bytes here and then the Boule, you
know, was another four bytes or whatever.
But we could have made that smaller if we wanted.
To.
We could even probably snuggle it in some way by using the high
bidder, some weird stuff like this.
So, these were actually pretty small these things, then there was an
eight by pointer to the next field was actually, you know, pretty big.
So adding this though
Wouldn't.
We're not quite double the size but it would make a size quite
considerably more.
So the question is, if we were going to to go that big, if we were
going to look at two x sized things, which is what you have to do, if
you were going to start to do some of that, chaining version is there
something else you could do?
That would be much easier and work more in a more straightforward
fashion and the answer is yes, I think there is so when we insert a
and b and we know that we want to be able to search for e,
In our hash table.
What we could do?
Is we could say, whenever we do an insertion, instead of inserting
just on a key, like, what we're doing now that we're doing just based
on a or on something else like that, insert it based on a so insert it
this in a position based on a.
So this would be the A's hash lat, right?
So here is the a b that we insert, right?
So that goes in there, then insert it on be as well.
So if this is where B goes be Collision rules, go right?
Also inserted here, right?
And we insert it the other way round if we want to as well, right?
So we just insert, we insert the two versions.
We insert a b and we insert be a right now.
If we want to remove something entity e, we can look up on end of the
E.
And we know that no matter whether it was in this position or this
position, we know that we will find, let's say we come in,
We get B, which before would have failed.
We know that we will find one of the two in the pair.
When we look
When we find that one, we now have the information necessary to remove
the other one because this gives us the a that we didn't have.
So we can then do the removal by calling the exact same routine on the
pair flip the other way round.
Right?
So the algorithm for doing this removal then becomes pretty
straightforward.
We do one pass on the removal of a b that will
Remember, all the things we remove go on to the free list, right?
Here's the free list that will put the things on the free list, right?
So be a goes, it gets inserted onto the free list, and here's where
the free list was before and and be a goes on here, right?
All we have to do now is basically grab a pointer to that free list.
Remember before we start before we do that pass, remember the top of
the free list beforehand.
Whatever it was.
So this is the previous top of the
Free list.
We just Loop through from there to until we get to the top of the free
list.
We Loop through and call remove on the reverse of each of these
things.
Problem solved.
Now we have direct removal from our hash table, right?
It works.
In all the, in all the cases, there's nothing weird there and we don't
actually have to write a different routine, right?
It's totally fine.
So that's kind of interesting and it's a neat way to do this.
So I mean that might be the best way to do it after, I mean, I don't
know, right?
And again there's a there's a cost to it.
It doubles the entry count to our hash table, right?
So if this thing was really big, then then that would probably be a
bad solution, right?
Like if this if
Concerned about the storage cost, for this hash table.
That wouldn't be good.
We don't really know if we're concerned about that yet.
So it's a little premature to even say one way or the other I suspect
we probably will never be concerned about it because compared to our
add a start asset size, I suspect this probably will be pretty tiny.
But we now know that for a to excise cost, we could totally make that
happen, right?
And then we wouldn't have to bother
sorting the indices when we look them up either, we just look up,
whatever.
However, they came in because we know we'd always find the rule, no
matter which order.
We look things up because they're both in there, right?
So I thought I'd point that out because it was just kind of neat, and
I'll put a note in here as in case.
So if we do decide that we want do that eventually we can
Say one way to make removal easy, would be to always add both orders
of the pairs of storage indices to the hash table.
So, no matter which position The Entity is in.
You can always find it then when you do your first pass through for
removal, you just remember the original top.
Of the free list.
And when you're done, do a pass through that list.
Pass through all the new things on the free list and remove the
reverse of those.
Pears.
So you go, so I was kind of happy with that and I was like, I should
probably talk about that in stream because it's kind of fun.
All right, so,
Let's take a look here.
Somebody reported a bug.
That was I'm very glad they caught because this would be one that, you
know, I don't even know.
It might never have B us, but if it had been us, we would have been
very grumpy because it would have taken a long time to find because we
just wouldn't have thought to look here for a while.
Probably.
So in our ad radius to remember which
I basically wrote to enlarge or rectangle, we these are wrong, right?
It's supposed to be that we add the width and the height, and subtract
the width and the height respectively, but I had type.
I totally typed them in wrong total typos.
And so that would never have cause us any problems with the way we're
using it now, because we were passing the same value for a wh.
But if we ended up in the case eventually, where we were weren't
Ain't doing that right where we were passing different values for wh
it would have stopped working properly.
And we would have been like, what is happening, right?
So, thankfully, someone who had been working along with the videos,
notice.
They were like, wait, is that right?
And I'm like nope, that is not right?
So again thank you to everyone who actually does go and work through
the code.
It's really awesome to have that help again.
Like it's hard those are mistakes that you know I that's a mistake I
would make
Just day-to-day programming, even right?
Sometimes you make typos, but I definitely even make them at a higher
rate on the stream to because my concentration is split between the
explanation in the code.
And so it really is helpful.
When people point out stuff like that because it's not that
interesting usually to show how you find a bug like that, right?
It's like oh it was just a typo and we were right.
And so, you know, it does save us time on the stream if people can
point out like, oh hey, you know, you made a typo here.
It's like, that's probably better than watching me to bug it.
It most of the time because, you know, like I said, I try to show
debugging on the stream for any hard problems.
Obviously it's good.
And so, I always do all the debugging myself, which is how I think it
should go, but it is helpful to have people, write in and catch those
things.
I think because, you know, we don't need to hunt down every typo on
the street.
Alright, that's it for my to do notes.
I got so you had a little post it to remind myself of those two
things.
So that's it for that.
So now we got to talk about a couple things.
First of all, we got talking about where we're at now.
We've got a couple things to do.
So, you know, one of the obvious things that we need to fix, is
sorting, we're not sorting.
So, we draw just in whatever any order which allows this do.
You know, this guy goes behind those trees, which is nonsensical.
I've been kind of putting that off just because I think that's just
best to go in the render and it's not really causing us any
consolation.
It's annoying me and probably people on the stream but it's
Not really impeding our ability to code forward.
So I'm not going to do that till we get to the render because the
render is going to have to do that and we might as well just put that
in the right place instead of packing it in now for no apparent
reason, right?
So when we're actually going through working on the renderer we'll
just do that and that won't be too long anyway so there's that so I'm
going to continue to put that off.
The other thing that we need to do is give our monstar some behavior
and also figure out what we want to do when like a month star dies.
For example, those sorts of things.
So that's on the table.
We also have to start thinking about a couple things like so world how
we're going to sew
I added that Collision real stuff and I said this would might be
interesting because you can add those rules.
We're going to need something a little fancier to, you know, in the
Collision detection department.
And I'm wondering, if maybe we should do, even though, you know, the
time might not be right to do the full closures, ha, I'm wondering if
we need to just even go a little further on that.
Because here's another thing that I was thinking about.
So, with our Collision rules, it was an interesting thing and I kind
of like the fact we implemented it we may use it, it may be a good
thing but I
Wonder if we're going to maybe have to lean more heavily on some kind
of a system that does have a little bit more of a geometric
interpretation.
Because one of things I was thinking about is let's say we want to
make a pressure plate to step on, right.
One way to do that, would be to make the pressure plate.
Entity we step on it, right?
And you know, it opens a door.
Look at removes some enemies or something, right?
So I can get walk through a door.
In fact, maybe that's what we should make.
The problem with that pressure plate is that I need to add a collision
rule so that I don't keep getting called back about the fact that I
stepped on the pressure plate.
Potentially like maybe I only want to get notified once that I stepped
on it.
Well.
Obviously we can use a collision rule for that.
It would work fine.
But when do you remove the Collision rule Collision rules are really
only effective if there's a defined time like with this sword thing
that I was talking about a defined time window where they operate in
so that they can get removed because if they never got removed like
with a pressure plate, I step on it.
How do I know when to remove that Collision rule, right?
And I guess you could say as well when you step off the pressure
plate, we could remove the Collision rule but I don't know how to know
when we would step off the cushion.
The the pressure plate if our whole definition of doing Collision,
testing is based on these rules.
Now, maybe what we could say is well, okay, we have two ways of
testing things.
The question sector, which is something we would have any way, which
is are two things overlapping currently.
And then there's the weather things go into or out of stuff.
But if we go that route and that has to work properly, then we might
as well maybe just use that for most of the things we have entry and
exit you know ideas of collision.
Do we even need the rules anymore?
At that point?
Or can we just use those and the answer is?
Well, I don't know, maybe we still want the rules for extra
robustness, because in the case of
S of where things are kind of numerically.
Fiddly, maybe we don't want
Accidentally record multiple hits.
I don't know, but those are just the kind of things I was thinking
about.
And so I don't know if maybe we want to go back through the Collision
detection, one more time, clean those things up.
And maybe say, all right, let's get a real notion of entry and exit in
here, which you probably want to have anyway and maybe start using
that for some of the things.
I don't know.
So those have been the kind of things that are on my mind right now
and I'm not sure which ones we should do, I guess maybe.
Maybe just for a little bit of a change of pace.
Maybe let's go do pathfinding or something and then, we'll, we'll come
back and maybe we'll do some Collision detection after that.
I don't know.
I think about that.
It's just something to think about.
So, for example, like one thing that we could do is, we could go ahead
and Implement having the familiar be able to get through a more
complicated, sort of, you know, having the familiar be able to get to
us even through.
More complicated sort of arrangement of trees, right?
So we can make a more complicated Arrangement or week.
I could just do this sort of thing and then we could see that it could
find its way around, right.
So that's a pretty difficult problem in might take us a while so that
might be a good thing for us to do to write.
So I'm just thinking aloud here because we're getting to the point
where we need to sort of pick a new major thing to do.
All right?
So
beyond all of that obviously is also animation.
That's the last thing that we definitely need to do and that would be
like getting this guy to hop.
I've kind of been everywhere all the time.
I've been like, oh, we should go do animation next year, summation X
but I never actually quite get to it.
We keep deciding that there's something else we might want to do ahead
of time.
And so I don't know.
That's the other thing that we could go get that we could go tackle
and that's going to be, you know, kind of a whole
Separate branches.
Well I should probably be listing these things out, right.
So let's go ahead and take a little piece of handmade dot h here.
And I'm going to go ahead and say put it to do up here.
So let's see.
We want to do animation, right?
So we want to do our animation.
I guess what I would say is animation should should probably lead into
rendering because animation will motivate our renderer quite a bit.
You know that would include particle systems probably as well systems
and skeletal animation basically what we want here.
So this is kind of our graphical effects sort of a stuff that we got
to do.
So, we'd want to put in some of that, and then that will lead directly
into rendering.
So we know that these two come in this order because we'd want to have
animation going first so that we have a bunch of motivation to get our
rendering doing the things that we need to do.
So, for example, when we add
Animation in there, were we're going to want to rotate pieces of the
guy and we're not gonna be able to do that right?
Because our bitmap drawing code right now doesn't support that and so
that's going to be like animations going to be this nice thing where
there's all these requirements we generate and then that's going to
lead replacing the renter were like okay we know we need scaling, we
know we need rotation and then we you know know what we have to build
for the renderer so I think we probably want to put animation off
until basically the last thing we do before the renderer and the
renderer probably
Is the last thing we do before we start actual coding.
So the game goes here, right is what I would say.
So the game, I would say, we probably also want to push off the entity
system until then because the entity system is going to come up
concurrent with the game.
And so I would say that like,
Really the only stuff we need about the a system right now is all the
scalability stuff and how that sort of goes and so probably, what
we'll do is we'll leave our piggy entity right now are giant entity
thing that doesn't really do anything in terms of being smart about
anything.
We'll just leave that and then so basically the entity system will be
what we do this.
You know, the game we start doing the game, you know, World Generation
and the entity system will kind of come up together as we build that
game.
And those will be components that, you know,
Evolving continuously, throughout that time right now for World
Generation, we do need one thing up here before we do any of this
stuff which is like rudimentary World Jen.
So basically no quality, just what sorts of things.
We do.
And so right now we have essentially no ability to generate world's
whatsoever.
We just make a bunch of connected rooms.
So what we would want to do, here is a rudimentary World.
Jen that basically did what we need to do to actually make real world
stuff.
So if we look out here, right,
We don't have any ground cover.
The trees are all in a weird line.
Like, you know, it's there like wall rooms, you know, it doesn't make
any sense.
We don't have any notion of like where stuff is or any of that stuff.
So we'd want to make a screen that looked sort of like, the game
should look with trees and rocks, placed in the in reasonable.
You know, not like using good algorithms, but just some trees, some
rocks, some grass down there.
So it was like, a full looking screen so we know roughly what we have
to do to make that happen.
so that
we want that so that we at least know how that's going to work roughly
so that when we do World Generation, what we're focusing on here is
just going to be okay in this particular situation World Generation,
we're just focusing on how do we make algorithm?
That generate the kinds of Worlds that we want and that will come up
with any system?
But not how do we actually write the code?
To support World Jen, right?
So we probably want to do that here, right?
And that'll do stuff like placement of background things,
connectivity.
Probably just, you know, non-overlapping things like that.
Just some basic stuff.
So we know what has to happen.
So that we make sure that our structures of things support the kinds
of careers that we need.
Okay, so I already said we needed some AI stuff here.
Right.
So we need like pathfinding
And then we I guess need like a i storage for lack of a better term
but you know, for things that are supposed to have some agency in the
world, we're going to need some notion of what it is that they're
trying to do at any given time, right?
And those might be variably sized.
Like if a guy has some goals, he's trying to accomplish or whatever
standard sorts of things, you know, you might see in a game, eai
We probably want to figure out, you know, what do we have a plan for
that?
Is there anything we need to plan for that?
Or is it just, hey, there's a linked list somewhere or whatever like
doing is there?
Is there anything special we have to do to make that happen?
Just make sure that there isn't anything strange and weird there that
we got to deal with.
Yeah.
So that all looks good.
Collision detection, we sort of got the Collision detection problem,
which is hey, you know, on collision detection.
Do we need entry exit, right.
What about what's, what's the plan for robustness?
So we don't get stuck in things that sort of stuff and and I guess
shape definition, you know, we don't know exactly how we want to do
that.
So that's something.
Let's think about what else we got here.
It's nice to have this list so we can basically kind of look at all
the things that we need to do.
We've got some stuff.
Oh, I guess.
One thing.
Do is Implement multiple SIM regions per frame, right?
So basically like get, you know, a rudimentary thing going where we've
got these images and now, that's in multiple things.
And in that would be entity, you know, per entity clocking, right?
So, we know when things have been updated, and how far they need to
get updated for each individual step and and maybe Sim region merging
for multiple players.
Right?
So if you imagine two players are playing in their different places in
the world and they come close together and we want to simulate them in
one region, maybe so, you know, I don't know.
Stuff like that.
It's pretty easy for us to merge those things.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
What else do we got here?
What am I forgetting?
Let's think if I were playing this game.
Yeah, I just kind of I guess we have one sort of thing which is
metagame save game, right?
Which is basically just saying like Okay, we need some story about
Do we even, you know, do even allow savegames.
Do we allow save games probably?
Yes, right.
Just not just only for pausing basically.
So since this game is supposed to be, you know, Rogue alike right.
We don't want the user to be able to actually save their game
volitional e, but we may want them to be able to, like close
The game in the middle of playing and then come back later and
continue.
So, you know, we might want that or, and, or crash recovery as well,
right?
Like, if the game crashed because remember, even if we do a perfect
job and have no crash bugs in the game when we ship it, there's always
the graphics driver to go ahead and help you out and crash anyway.
so, it's usually nice if you can
To build something into the game where if it crashes, because even if
it's, you know, like I said, there is no way to ensure Windows game.
For example, won't crash, because even if you're perfect somehow
you've made a perfect program, someone else will just go ahead and
crash for you.
So it's nice.
If we can maybe save the game periodically in some nice way.
So, like continuous save for crash recovery would be a nice feature to
have because it means that especially if you want to scale the game up
to 20 hours of play time for tea.
As a play time, if we do weird stuff like long and generate huge
worlds to take a really long time to play.
It would be nice for the person to know that 30 hours in the only way
they can lose all that work is if they're bad at the game and die, and
not because the graphics driver crashed, right?
So be nice if they could load up and only be like one room back from
where they were, you know, a couple, you know, you know, 30 seconds or
a minute back from where they were just something that allows that
would kind of be nice, right?
So thinking about how we want to do, you know, persistent online
Locks etcetera, right?
Thinking about how we want this structure to work.
That's something that we probably want in the game for sure.
And so just, you know, it's not anything magical, but it would just be
nice to kind of go through and go.
Let's think about how
Going to handle this because we do have some kind of nasty elements of
that, like are saved games might be huge, right?
Because if we generate the whole world every time,
And that world may be fairly expensive to generate and the user may be
able to modify large amounts of things in the world.
We do have some things, you know, we may have to do some creative
stuff there, it may not be obvious how to make all that work, well,
right?
At the very least, even if we have a giant save file like, hey, for a
giant world, you know, the savegame files, 60 megabytes or whatever,
right?
Even if we do that, we
And say that's just the way it is.
So forget Cloud saves right, the save game file on the local machine
for saving that play session.
If even if we do that, we wouldn't be able to save continuously 60
megabytes of data.
That's too much traffic.
Probably to not impact the framerate at all.
So, what we'd want to do is maybe only save incrementally or
something.
Like, we'd want to have some smart stuff that did like.
Okay, we only update the part of the save game.
We actually need to update or something like
This right.
And so, I don't know.
So that's one way to think about it.
And the other thing is, you know, we probably want to split them apart
because if we have to have giant, save files to support huge
modifiable worlds, or something like that, then we certainly don't
want the persistent stuff to be part of that, because we would want
the persistent stuff like unlocks to be part of a cloud save system,
which isn't going to want to upload, 60 MB every time, right?
So we'd want to split that off so that, you know, your Steam account
or something, whatever can sink your persistent part, at the very
least because we know we could make that small because the number of
like unlocks or whatever, is it going to be 60 megabytes, that's going
to be, you know, you know, 200k or something at, you know, worst-case,
right?
So yeah.
So got most of the stuff here, let's seek out the metagame.
We've got.
So we've got a I so let me know rudimentary monstar Behavior example.
So all right you know what else we got Z.
So we want to clean up things by using Vector 3, we want to figure out
how you go up.
And down.
And how is this rendered, right?
Like how do we show going into something going and or going up?
It
You know, and it might be interesting to to ask people on the stream
people who have played a lot of games might be interesting to ask to
what are good examples of games 2D.
Where you can go up and down stuff and it looks good to do it.
You know, like I think about Binding of Isaac or something.
They really, you can't ever really go up.
So they never have to deal with the fact that you walk upstairs and
then switch to another level or something.
And you can't really go down either because when you go down something
it just shows us a little like jump up and go animation and then it
just cuts so they never really show you going down into something
either.
And so I don't know like render wise how we want to what we want.
To show in terms of somebody walking up a stairs or something, you
know, what do we want to do?
Obviously we can do something real cheesy, where you just, you know,
touch the stairs and instantly, you're on the next screen or
something.
But is there some better rendering, like some better way of animating
that that looks nicer or something?
You know, what do we want?
Think of?
Is there a game that did it particularly?
Well, that we should be looking to, for guidance, you know, that sort
of thing.
So there's that.
So yeah, we want to kind of get our Z situation.
That's not particularly hard, but it's something we should go through
and do trying to think
What else we got here?
Architecture.
Exploration is here.
And then this is you know, production basically.
What do you guys think?
Am I forgetting stuff?
And I don't, I don't know.
I would say out of these things, you know, some of them are big, some
of them are small.
I would basically say that that's, that's a pretty rough one.
I'm not sure how we're going to do it.
That's pretty tough I would say.
Yeah, I would say this one's probably going to be a pretty big one.
These are probably not except maybe this one will see.
Yeah, yeah.
So let's say we've got got some hard work to do here, some of this is
pretty easy.
Some of its not if anyone I should check the stream, o.o audio.
Yeah.
Somebody said audio.
so,
Got sound effect triggers ambient sounds and music.
I guess are things, we should sort of get in there audios usually
pretty trivial, it's just not that hard, especially not in a game like
this one.
Where, let's be honest, we don't have a huge budget for this game so
we don't need to do something like make a huge Studio editing system
where people can dial all kinds of crazy, dials and have weird
Facts of stuff.
It's like, you know, we're going to have the money for basically
buying sound effects that play, When the Game needs them to play and
music that plays, you know, an ambient sounds like, oh, there's
running water, we play the running water, right?
We're not going to have the ability to have like a sound guy.
Be sitting there doing all kinds of sound scaping stuff for needs to
happen so we're probably not going to have that much work to do on
audio, you know, will support the basics and then we'll be able to
kind of put the assets in but there's
Not going to probably be a whole lot more than that.
Although I guess we could play around with some of it later.
There's always places to add stuff but yeah, we need the basic audio.
What else?
What else we got?
I should take a look at the stream here and see if anyone else has
ideas ideas.
Doesn't look like anyone else mentioning anything in particular on
there.
So we go through it one more time, make sure we've got everything.
Which of the metagame we can go, I guess.
So one thing.
Yes, we start up.
We've got the metagame, they're sort of, I guess there's sort of a
so,
In the metagame I guess there's one of the thing we might think about.
So, there's kind of the concept of you know, how do you enter a save
slot or whatever?
Like
This kind of this concept when you start playing, you know do I want
to have multiple versions of my like this persistent unlocks and stuff
right?
What if I want more than one version of those persistent unlocks the
simplest example.
Being if I'm playing on the same game you know as as Garland oh Bloom
because we are sharing computer you know like it's the living room
computer or something and
And he and I are like both want to play this game and were like, let's
do this, but he wants to keep his savegame separate from mine so that
he can unlock stuff separately from me, or whatever, right?
And we can, each play the game without having to play the other
person, say file.
So if we go in there and you know, do that, what's a, what's a, what
does that impact?
The implications for that in the game?
How do we make sure we keep those separate and what's the way that
they get picked?
Because
Has maybe we want the game, maybe we want that to all work.
Games, there's not like a menu, it just kind of like, you know, you
have your character than the first thing you do is move to, you know,
that you can imagine like, a spatial version where you like, walk down
three, there's three different stairs or something and you go down the
one, that's the save slot that you wanted to play on.
If we want to do something like that, there has to kind of be this
notion of multiple worldy things where it's like, we're in a world
that isn't really a real world.
It's a world that for picking worlds, and then we picked one and now
we have that were right.
Right, there's this kind of thing that goes on there that creates
complexity in the code.
And so we probably, before we go any further to would want that to
work properly.
Right?
So that's will get that in there as well.
Let's see anything else.
Any in-game you?
I needed.
Hopefully not.
I hate in-game you.
I I'm so I'm hoping that we won't have any in-game UI.
That's my, that's my hope.
I mean we may float a few things I guess.
That's one thing we could do which is like just a floating thing for.
Well, you know I'm hoping we don't have any I guess that's what I'd
say.
I'm hoping that we don't have any of that so I'm just going to see if
we can get away without it.
Logging should be on the list so I guess.
Yeah, debugging write, debug code should be on the list.
So, yeah, logging diagramming switches sliders that sort of thing,
right?
Some kind of stuff for getting debugging working.
Let's see.
Can we please do gooey?
So I guess we'll do a little gooey here.
We'll do a little
Gooey.
But only a little, because games.
Games with gooey are.
I don't really like
So, I don't know.
I mean, I feel like we'll do, you know, if you want to do handmade
some point, you do handmade like a RollerCoaster Tycoon or one of
those old games that had like tons of Windows that with that, where it
was like, it looks like some kind of a nap, right?
That's where you kind of want to do the GUI coating but so we'll see.
But yeah, Maps is a good point.
Maps is a good one.
I'm not sure how we want to do maps.
I wonder if we could.
Yeah, Maps is interesting.
Maps is very interesting.
Yeah, let's go ahead and add that.
App display.
Magnets, how they work?
So basically yeah map display.
I thought a little bit about that and that actually may be a
technological problem.
Meaning maybe we really do kind of want to think about that a little
bit.
And I'm going to go ahead and put that underneath rudimentary real Jen
like so.
Because I do have some thoughts about that.
And so, yeah, let's think about that.
Will you be carrying multiple items?
So, yeah, my I've got ideas about how I want to do that.
Let's put it that way.
So I think we can get away with very little UI in the game if none at
all.
But yeah, we'll get to that part later.
I don't think map is a good point.
And map is a thing that's Q&A time.
I think, I think we're done mostly with this.
Because it's a pretty good list.
Yeah, so let's sort lets you know, I started a little late so let's
just take a couple minutes and let's sort this because we're starting
fresh next week.
I've see will be starting Monday time for a new topic.
Let's think about what we want to do here.
So I would say that like Z and multiple SIM regions is kind of an
example of cleaning up, sort of stuff.
So I think I might say, let's just do, let's do this stuff.
Let's do this stuff next week.
Maybe try to do some of this because we're going to take the week off
the following.
We know the first week of March, I said, we take off, give people a
chance to catch up and stuff.
I'm going to be traveling that week, so it'll be easy.
They'll be best for everyone because people have been asking for a
week off, they'll get a week off, I won't have to.
For how to stream from locations, where the internet might be even
less likely to get to Twitch than it is here.
So that might be a good one.
So maybe we start with these next week because we don't want to start
something big next week.
Be right in the middle of it, and then take a week off, that seems
bad.
So maybe we stick with things that are just stuff.
We've already done that, we just need to clean up.
Get them off the list, get them done, right?
So maybe we break it up, we try to do that.
And then, you know, if we break in the middle of that and for a week
it doesn't matter because these are things.
We've already mostly done.
So we're just kind of like updating them and that that would be fine,
right?
Then if we take a look at this stuff, I guess I would say metagame and
save game maybe would be a good thing to think about.
They kind of go together with rudimentary Royal gen like you know
right like making worlds and
And how we persist things that's kind of to me, those kind of go
together, right?
Audio is just totally a separate thing.
As is debug code, these are totally separate entirely separate.
So maybe we put, maybe we put these up here and, you know, like that
maybe we'd be do debug cut enough.
I really care about doing debug code that early on
It's hard to say.
It's really hard to say.
Yeah.
All right.
And then we would sort of do it in this order.
This would be, this would be the order.
I don't know what you guys think about this.
So basically, we do this stuff which I don't think I'll be too much
work.
Pretty straightforward.
This would be creating all new code which is just stuff that allows us
to debug our stuff more easily.
This would sort of be finishing up that Collision detection code.
I wonder if
I feel like that's probably a little bit more of a cleanup thing to,
so maybe let's let's let's do it in this order, right.
So here's our clean up stuff, right?
And maybe maybe we do that first because I don't like leaving it
broken and we sort of haven't really finished that stuff.
So maybe we just kind of do one more pass in the Collision detection.
Get that stuff.
Feeling good, right?
Then we do this stuff, we do this stuff.
Yeah.
I like I like, I like the way this is.
Galloping, let's move AI down to here.
So that, that kind of dovetails into the animation system and well.
Okay, yeah.
And and AI in the, the world Jen kind of go together to because the
pathfinding may have to, kind of understand some of those things.
All right?
So that that's looking pretty reasonable.
Yeah, I like that.
That looks like a pretty good hit list.
I feel like by the time that we got through all of this stuff we would
basically have what amounts to a completely playable engine thing, you
know, that's pretty decent actually, and that certain components are
not industrial strength
But we'd be in perfect position to go ahead and start doing exactly
that which is going through and making things industrial-strength.
So we started on the renderer, which is the only real huge one and
then we could actually go through and do you know, do it for reals?
That seems pretty good.
I could see that can see that being good.
All right, so I'm happy with that.
Let's go ahead and go to the Q&A.
I don't know.
They'll be much Q&A today because of the fact that basically what we
did is sort of do our planning.
But, you know,
I can't predict whether they'll be cure or not.
So I'll go ahead and hit the little Q&A button.
Is please prefix your questions with Q: so I can see them and please.
Well you know what, I don't even care just ask whatever questions you
want today but I reserve the right to say that something is a pre
stream question into a skit on pre stream instead.
Yeah, go ahead and leave that up there.
Isn't doing this list thinking, too.
Far ahead are thinking too far according to your compression oriented
programming.
You look ahead with this table for weeks ahead.
No, because I often do stuff like this.
I don't feel like this really has anything to do with the programming.
If that makes sense.
This is just listing the things.
We know we would need to have right, so this isn't a schedule.
We don't have to stick to this in any way but it's just like guidance.
It's like okay what do we do?
Like I was at a point today where I was like, I'm not
What we do next, this is just a list we can come back to any time,
we're at that point, where were like, okay, we finished thing X, we're
pretty happy with where it is.
We don't think we need to go any further on it right now.
What do we do next?
We can just pull something off the list, right?
So we go back to the list and go, what else we got?
Oh, right.
We know we wanted to, you know, get Z handling.
Let's go start looking at Sea handling, right?
And so definitely don't think of this list as something we have to do
in order.
At any time, you can go ahead and ignore this entirely.
All right, it's just sitting there as sort of a brain dump where we're
like these are all the things that are gonna have to get done at some
point.
So that we just kind of don't forget them, right?
And I just kind of wanted to get that out there.
So yeah, so definitely don't think of this as something that has to be
adhered to and I pretty much in guarantee you that it won't be like
they'll be plenty of things in here where we're like, oh we started
working construction and we noticed this thing.
Let's go do that or whatever, but just kind of was a nice little plan
where I can can say.
Okay now I know all the
Major areas.
So when we get to a point and we're not sure what we should do next,
we just grab something and say.
Alright, let's do that because we've sort of said, oh yeah, we
probably should do that at some point.
In the get, hash from Storage index function, you do some bit
twiddling to map.
Hash value into hash index.
Is there a reason that you didn't just compute hash index, as hash
index equals hash value mod array count.
Yes.
So mod is very expensive, compared to.
And so, basically, a mod requires integer division, right?
And integer division is slow compared to an end.
In and is usually one of the fastest operations, the CPU can do.
It's rare that like an and takes really any time at all.
And so for the most part
reason to avoid mod is because you don't want, if the whole point of
the thing that you're doing is to make accesses quick, you typically
don't want to have a mod in there now,
That said really, we don't know which one is the most appropriate for
any given situation.
So just to show the example of the person was talking about they were
saying this, right?
Hash bucket.
Why are we doing it?
And instead of a mod
And so really, we don't know, because it may be that using a, non
power of 2 size is better for a particular circumstance, because if,
when you do this, look up, if this stuff isn't in the cache, then it's
probably true that the mod cost is not expensive enough to matter,
right?
Because the memory fetching to get the hash table into memory.
If it wasn't in the cache at the time is
To dominate that runtime, right?
And so really this is just, I tend to write them as Anne's to begin
with just to make sure that I'm not relying on mod, but sometimes when
we go back in there, we might decide that mod is fine.
And that it's that we would rather have the non power of 2 sighs for
some other reason.
And so really the answer is just, it's a trade-off.
It's a trade-off between complete flexibility of sizing versus the
cost to the CPU to compute the hash bucket,
And trade-offs like that or not something we really can make up front.
We have to see how they run in practice on our Target platforms.
And then the side chances are
This will not really be an important part of the program.
Anyway, and really, you could probably use both either one because
chances are we just won't be dealing with Collision rules enough to
make them be an important part of the runtime cost of the system, but
it's worth understanding those trade-offs anyway, because sometimes
they are sometimes your hash tables are very important.
So that's just something to think about.
And that's, that's why I tend to write them this way and also, because
obviously, I learned programming at a time when the cost was far more
exaggerated than it is.
Now when obviously, when I started programming, the concept that you
would do an integer, divide ever was kind of ludicrous, like you never
ever, ever, ever wanted to do an integer divided into divide was a
disaster because in those days memory accesses
It was a similar cost to doing an instruction memory, wasn't the super
slow thing, compared to the processor that it is now.
And so, you know, you had these situations, we're doing a mod,
literally meant that, you know, the code got 40 times slower or
something, right?
Because it was so expensive to do that that divide or something.
Whereas, now that's not necessarily the case, because things don't
work that way.
And so, the trade-off change and again, the only really way to know is
to have a good sense of what your target platforms.
Are am actually test to see if you care,
Right now, the familiar lags behind since move slower than the player.
There may be, many legitimate situations where the player and the
familiar may be.
Separated have you considered implementing a proportional?
Integral derivative controller for its speed.
Well again we're not trying to code a familiar at this point, right?
We just wanted something in there so we can see what the architecture
should look like.
We don't need to make a good familiar because that'll be for later on
when we have the whole game running and we're implementing the
familiars and how we
Nothing to work for Chanel.
Integral derivative controllers are interesting, except they do have
some drawbacks and so you know, we'll probably use them for some
things.
I don't know about the integral part is usually not as interesting for
games.
Proportional derivative controller, as are usually more fun because
they have sort of a little more springy.
Unpredictable behavior.
That usually is a little more fun and games.
So proportional derivative controller might be more likely than
proportional.
Integral derivative controller like the
Integral term we probably wouldn't use but also for things that we
want to have very predictable, Behavior, proportional, integral
derivative controllers.
Actually, probably also aren't what I would use for that.
I would probably use sort of direct direct spline interpolation.
So hard to say but that's coming down the road.
My connection drop.
Could you briefly go over the solution for the kitchen table again?
Actually you can just watch it on YouTube.
These get uploaded immediately after so you can watch Day 70 again and
see my complete explanation.
Do we have to do, is eat or Z?
Sorting for a game like this.
Can't we just sort on the y-axis and do things to simulate climbing,
stairs, change the velocity as the character moves up, something like
stairs, and what have you?
So, that's what I mean, when I say Z, sorting though is sorting on the
y-axis.
Obviously, once you sort on the y-axis, though, like once we do the
Sorting to handle the fact that, you know, I should be behind these
trees instead of in front of them once we do that.
Sort.
It's free.
Usually for us to also sort by Z correctly as well.
Because you know when you're doing a sort, you can make the sort, be
the sort comparison be compound.
It doesn't just have to sort on one thing, so we'll get Z sorting for
free when we do the, why sorting as well, probably.
So the problem isn't so much the Sorting though, the problem is what
should happen when the guy goes up and down stairs.
Like what do we want to look like, right?
It's a presentation issue.
Not a
What issue?
I'm sure we'll be able to code whatever it is.
We said to think about what it should look like when it goes up and
down the stairs, like like, how does that work?
You know, it's just kind of go up them a little and then it flips to
the next one or it's just, it's what should it look like, you know,
and I'm not sure.
I heard you talking about animation see right down a skeletal system.
Do you have plans on importing from a premade program or making an
animation program for the artists to use?
So I don't know whether we'll just kind of make the animation be
procedural mostly, which I think is probably what we'll do.
But I also I noticed this thing.
Where is it?
Yeah, this thing looked kind of interesting.
It was like a little skeletal animation thing, that was pretty cheap,
there's like 60 bucks and there's a free version so people would be
able to do simple things in it without having to pay as well.
So that seemed like a potentially,
Uh, potentially reasonable tool to import from because it could do
skeletal animation authoring and then we could load it right?
But I don't know that will actually use any authored animations.
If we do, that's probably what I look at that was the tool that came
to mind because I saw that that was released recently and looked like
a low-cost thing that could output data files that we could use for
the game, but I don't know that we actually will need that.
It may be that all of our animation is always procedural.
So, I don't know.
We'll see.
For the list superfish.
So superfish, I have a text file on computer which has all of my game
design things that I want in the game in super fish is already on
there.
I added it when I tweeted about it the other day.
So so there will be a superfish enemy and I think what we'll try to do
at the superfish enemy, my thought about that was the superfish enemy
will be like a mimic, like indirect Dungeons and Dragons like, you
know, a chest that attacks you or whatever.
It'll basically
Do you like, it'll impersonate other things?
And because that's basically, you know, it's basically root
certificate of you.
So it'll impersonate things and then turn into a monster.
When you try to use those things that you normally would that to me is
super fish.
Asset loading management is missing from the list.
You are correct.
That is a good one.
Thank you.
Where's my handmade .h?
There it is.
That is a good one, so we totally should do that.
How do we want to do that?
So we probably want to do that.
Probably want to do that in here.
Asset streaming that in there.
Yeah.
What 2-D game.
Can you think of that did good Z movement?
I personally always liked Prince of Persia.
When he climbed the steps at the end of the level.
I don't know that's why I was thinking like I can't think I'll go
watch some Prince of Persia videos, I don't know, I None kind came to
mind really actually
Prince of Persia, doesn't is a little hard because Prince of Persia
was not top down or isometric.
So going up was much more logical to them because it was actually up
on the screen was actual upright, so they had an easier time of it,
where it's clearer.
I think to the player, what's going on because there aren't three, you
know, axes basically.
Have I seen watch people co.com?
Yes, someone sent it to me, I thought it was kind of funny, that's
that, it started like a month or so after we started doing handmade
hero and the things that they put on there, they've never put us on
there.
But we have way more viewers than anything that I saw on there.
So I feel like we're, I feel like we're being snubbed or something.
I don't really feel like we're being snow.
But it was kind of funny.
I was like, well, alright, you could watch these people code, but
we've got the real actions over here, on handmade here, on my friends.
We know where the stuff that.
What is your opinion on using existing code?
Someone else wrote as a learning tool, totally fine.
I actually don't have any problem with using like, I don't think it's
anything wrong with using libraries or engines.
That's just not the goal of this series, right?
You know, I feel like there was too much of the sort of.
I'm not really sure how to program and I'm making a game in something
going on.
And so, I thought it was important to have a Counterpoint that was
like, let's
Something where we show how you actually can code everything because I
feel like you want like both of those things especially because, you
know, I see a lot.
Games.
I play a lot of games where I'm like, it's pretty clear that the
person who made this doesn't really know how to program at all.
Because there's these obvious really bad programming mistakes in it.
And the game would have been ten times better.
If they just know how to do this one thing, it would have taken them
like two hours to do this thing or whatever.
Right?
And you know instead it's this really bad experience as a result.
And so I thought like it was important to put something out there with
it was like hear a thing that shows how to do all the real coding for
reals.
With a z.
So that maybe there'd be more information out there about that.
Even when people go to use a premade engine or existing code, they
know what's going on.
So they can fix those obvious mistakes that I keep seeing games all
the time.
Now by people who just use an engine but don't really know how to
program, you know, I'm so
Spread his file format is completely open and documented.
Yeah, exactly.
So that's why I was thinking.
It might be a good one to use.
If we decide we need animations that are authored.
But I think doing procedural animation is more interesting because
it's more about code, which is what the series is about.
So I feel like we may just want all our animation to be procedural.
Do you want to have quests in the game?
In this case, how are you planning to Define them?
Well, that's, that's really more of a thing.
When you're just building the game, that doesn't, that isn't really an
architecture concern.
To me, Lisa, doesn't sound like something that would imply much in the
architecture that we wouldn't already have.
So I don't think we need that to be in architecture.
Exploration pass where everything sort of brought up and running.
I don't I don't think that would really have any bearing on it,
really?
I think we dropped the check for entity.
Equals hit entity, inclusion, code last time.
Or did I miss something?
No, you may be right because I think I may have forgotten to put it in
the place where it should have gone.
That's a good point.
Let me double-check cuz I think I said I was going to put it somewhere
in that I didn't actually put it somewhere.
So when we do, this should Collide should have had it in here, and I
think we may have forgotten to do that.
So, yes, you're correct.
This should have looked like that.
So that we don't waste time checking against itself.
So we only want to do Collision, if a equals, if a is a different
entity than be, so that's a good thing.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you for catching that.
Will you patent the monstar pathfinding algorithm?
Of course?
You can't just make an algorithm, you have to patent the algorithm
because you're so brilliant.
That you've come up with this brand new algorithm.
No one's ever thought of before, you should be the only person who can
use it for 17 years.
Yeah, I hate patents.
In case you didn't know that, I think they're absolutely ridiculous.
I have no idea.
who came up with the idea, but
Whoever came up with the idea for patents.
Yeah.
An idea that has ruined so many things.
For Z axis movement, would it be feasible to resize the Sprite to be
larger as they move up and then resize the Sprite to be smaller once
it reaches the level while doing some Parallax stuff on the wall
textures for the second resize.
I don't know.
I'm not sure.
I know exactly what that would look like.
What you're saying.
I think making the guy get larger would be a little bit wrong because
if you think about.
So, if you think about what's happening here, right?
Going upwards is not actually moving you closer to the camera.
Really?
Like that's going upwards, right?
And that would not make sense if he got bigger there because it's kind
of going like, what is this?
Looks like it's sort of perpendicular to the camera as far as the
viewers concerned.
So I
think scaling the guy up would really make sense if we were straight
top down
Then I think it would look correct to make the guy get bigger as he
went up the stairs.
But since we're kind of head on in that sort of Zelda e style where
for some reason even though you're sort of top down, you're still
seeing everyone side on who knows how this game convention happened,
but that's how we do things in the game world, nowadays.
I feel like that's probably not what we would want.
Just my guess hard to say, though.
I think Pokemon 3rd, gen first, gen did, good stuff with the Z axis.
what is 3rd gen / 1st Gen mean
Post a link.
If you can post a link to a video either on the handmade here, our
forums, or on the chat here, if you happen to have it handy.
So I can look at that because I don't know which I don't follow
Pokemon super closely.
so, I'm actually know that that one
Will the monster encounters be random based like Final Fantasy Dragon
Warrior, or will they be more static Zelda, style Zelda style?
So the idea is, you know, you walk around and fight monsters that are
actually on the map.
You're walking around on not like you kind of touch a sort of
Representative monster and go into a monster battle.
I was thinking that former not the latter,
Should there be a time limit as well as a distance limit on the sword
possibly.
But that's much more straightforward to implement.
That doesn't involve the clothes intact or anything.
So if we want to add stuff like that later we can do that again.
The sword was just an example object.
We're not trying to make it good.
We're just trying to do some stuff to see what would be necessary in
the Collision system.
So basically like, you know,
I did the movement constraint because it basically puts something into
the Collision architecture.
Time constraint would be as simple as during the update called
looking, how much time was left, which is really easy, right?
So, I didn't really feel the need to test that, but it'd be pretty
easy for us to put in.
And I don't think it really has any bearing on on things.
Minish Cap handles the Z actually.
Well okay, I'll check out some Minish Cap videos.
How exactly does your question sorting plug-in work?
Basically it just anything with a q: or see me.
Oratory or handmade hero?
I think shows up on my screen.
I believe Ultima Online did some stuff with Z axis, but I'm not sure
if it's good though, you know, II saw I've solved my online back in
the day, I never really played it myself, but I saw people play it at
the gas powered games office, in fact, but I never really played it
myself.
They probably would have had a doozy stuff though, wouldn't, they have
because they had houses I think that had like upper right like that,
you know,
Upper, floors and stuff.
And so they had to be able to go upstairs to get things in the
downstairs.
And so, yeah, I should probably take a look.
I don't you might be bad like you said, but at least I would know.
What's the biggest game project?
You personally worked on.
Personally worked on, would have to be the witness because most of the
games that have code in it, that I wrote was licensed.
So I didn't work on the game directly write, like, you know, there are
much bigger games that had my character animation system in them, when
I worked at Rad, but I work on the game.
I worked on the characteristic and then they license characters
animations before the game.
So the witness is probably the game that I've like, worked directly on
code.
That's only for that.
I'm not licensed.
That would be the one.
That's the largest because that game is huge.
Now, John is not kidding when he says it's big.
It is
It is a big game if you choose to try and solve everything it's not
one of those games that forces you to solve everything.
But if you choose to tackle all of the problems that it presents to
you all the puzzles, it's huge
no remark on handmade animations or did I miss that?
So I don't consider animations being any more handmade just because
they've been made in art tool.
In fact I consider those less handmade because then there's a tool in
between us in the animation so I feel like if we do procedural
animations that's actually a lot more interesting code wise and a lot
more handmade loading animations.
From a tool is just an import problem.
It's like can you parse a file format?
We already showed how to do that with bmps so I'm not sure there's
really and we'll do it.
With web files at the very least for the sounds.
And then we'll probably when we get to stuff when we get to shipping
stuff, we'll have to do compression for assets because I'll be too
big.
So we'll have some more of that.
So I'm not sure it's interesting to parse another file format.
so, unless we find
We really need to be able to import these animations.
For some reason, it doesn't seem like an interesting aspect to me.
I've been writing my own platform layer in my own code and I found
that I've been poisoned by your approach, I have, I have poisoned
somebody.
Okay, by this.
I've been heading down a path.
Very similar to yours, simply through knowledge of a possible solution
to it.
This leads me to a very narrow way of thinking about problems.
Do you run into this as well?
How do you break through the wall?
It takes me a very long time to get solutions that fit my needs when I
see someone else's.
Well, first of all a, it's very good question.
I see what you're saying, you don't really mean poisoned in a bad way.
You mean in some sense, you mean biased.
I guess like you are biased towards a solution that I have presented
because hey it's a solution and now you know, a solution.
So when you go to do something, you use the solution that you know,
and I am definitely not one of those people who believes that.
I should tell you a solution and then you should go do the solution
that I told you.
That is definitely not the
goal for this stream.
The goal for this stream is to show you how to solve problems and to
encourage you to solve them in whatever way you feel works best for
you.
That's totally, that would be my dream scenario of people coming away
from the stream, not with a prescriptive list of do, X, Y and Z
because Casey said so that is not so interesting, right?
What's much more interesting is 0.
We watched how Casey solve these problems, I get how to solve
programming problems.
Now, I'm going to go solve my own problems in my own way.
Doing my own stuff.
That's way better, right?
Because now, you can solve problems that.
I didn't show you how to solve.
Now, you can solve problems, I did show you how to solve but in
different ways and maybe get better Solutions or at least different
solutions.
You know, either one is fine because they kind of increase the options
that we have in programming, which is always good.
Right.
More options of how to solve problems is always a good thing because
each one of them probably makes different trade-offs and then people
will be able to pick from different solutions based on the trade-offs.
But the question of how you learn to do that,
You know, without being biased.
Because you know, I showed a solution or you read someone else's
solution online and go.
Okay, I should do that.
It's tough, right?
I try to show as much as possible, how I work through things and
I don't know really what to say Beyond, that's how I do it.
Right?
Is I look at problems, like oh what are the what are the things I want
to get out of this?
What are the benefits?
What are the drawbacks, what's wrong?
You know, one way of asked say setting it up, is, what's wrong with my
Approach with this current approach, right?
Like look at how I did the platform layer and instead of thinking
about it as a solution think of just okay, what is wrong with this?
What don't I like
About this architecture.
What are the things that I think are causing problems are what?
You know is you can't come up with anything then maybe it's a bad
thing to even be spending your time on, right?
I mean maybe it's just fine but if you can come up with things then I
would say you know that's obviously the first step come up with some
problems you think it has once you have those problems, then you can
start focusing on what our design changes that would alleviate these
problems.
Problems.
How would I code something that didn't have these problems and push
towards that?
That seems like a pretty sane way.
To go about it.
If you can't come up with problems for an approach that I presented,
I think, then you're going to be in tough shape in terms of guiding
your approach towards making a different solution, because it's hard
to make a different solution without having a goal, right?
You need a goal.
You need to say, here's some stuff.
Casey solution didn't do or things that I didn't like about it,
because that's what kind of gives you the, the metric, the goal to
sort of start iterating towards it gives you something to work.
And you kind of need that it's hard to come up with a different
solution, strictly by measuring it against whether it's not my
solution, right?
Or someone else is solution because that just is an aimless Wanderer
and you're liable to not really get anywhere, interesting.
If all you want to do is be different.
So I think what you want to do
Is pick different goals and then achieve those goals and see how
achieving those goals changes, the solution.
That would probably be my recommendation.
She is me.
All right, my voice is is going, so we should probably end things
shortly.
But yet.
Let me see if there's anything else on here.
How long do you think a good game should be?
I'd say 20 hours is minimal.
Well, I guess what I would say is that's a game design question.
That's game design question and I'm not really qualified to answer it.
But what I would say is I think as a player I would probably object to
the question because I don't think game should be about length.
I think they should be about the experience.
And I think a game should be as long as the experience warrants.
I don't think a 20 hour minimum as a definition for a Dame is good
because I don't think quantity has anything.
To do with quality in certain circumstances.
It is about quantity.
I think Binding of Isaac is good because I play it.
You can play it for 20, 40, 80 hours, whatever, and it evolves with
you.
And in some sense, that's sort of where I would like to see this game,
go as well.
I'd like to see this game, be a game that's about many play throughs,
so yeah, 20 hours of handmade hero play, makes sense to me, because
it's about that kind of thing.
But at the same time, you know, if you're talking about an interactive
story, kind of
variance, or if you're talking about, you know, a game that's not
about
Learning Jamie systems like that.
And seeing how they evolve, then, 20 hours.
Why do I want to take 20 hours?
You know, why do, why do I want length?
As a thing when I go to a movie, I don't want the movie to be 20 hours
long.
I want it to be a nice good story told in two hours, right?
Maybe three.
And so I feel like
When you're trying to do other things with a game than expose deep
Dungeons and Dragons, like interaction systems or something.
I think that those games don't necessarily want to be super long, you
know, if you're playing The Walking Dead or whatever or whatever those
games like a Telltale Game or something like that, I don't think I
want that to be, you know, 20 hours long I think I want that to be
less than that.
You know, I would say that I don't I don't love the question.
I think that it should more be about how long should an individual
game be?
That should be the question.
Was this game the right length for the game design?
Did this game design have 20 hours worth of good stuff or not?
And a lot of times I feel like there are games that do take 20 hours
like Final Fantasy is a great example of a game that takes
XT H to play, even though there was only five hours of gameplay in it,
right?
Like I would say that you could condense Final Fantasy 10 down to five
hours of awesome gameplay.
Instead, they spread it out over 70 and that wasn't better, right?
I don't think that was better because I play, you know, I did a lot of
battles where I did exactly the same thing and as a player that's just
not that interesting.
I want to do that, I want to experience.
The evolution of those battles and forcing me to play through 100 of
the same battle to get to a point where now it's time to change up my
strategy because I got new things and I'm finding new monsters.
I don't I don't think that adds to a game.
I think that's basically just wasting the players time, right?
And so I feel like asking that question for every game is a good idea.
Does this games game design actually benefit from this extension of
gameplay or doesn't it?
And let's make the game, the right size because some games should be
20 hours.
Some games should be two hours and some games should be somewhere in
between some games, should be 80 hours, right?
And I think that's the way to ask that question.
All right, so let's let's go ahead and wrap things up.
I think we've done a good bit of talking for today.
So, thank you everyone for joining me for handmade hero.
Kind of wrapping up the week.
I think we
Some good stuff today.
So that kind of went out.
We've got a bunch of stuff we can pick from Monday.
We can open up that list.
Pick something from the list and go to town and kind of start our next
aspect of exploration, which I like I said, I think it's been going
pretty well.
I like the way things are shaping up in the game so far, we haven't
had any real serious things that the called me to kind of go.
Like, we haven't really addressed this thing.
So we're kind of getting there.
I'm happy about the way things are going.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm pretty optimistic.
So I like it.
I like what we broke down on the list.
I think all those things are useful things to do and I think they'll
be fun to tackle and we'll see where it leads us.
So as always, if you would like to follow along at home, you can
always pre-order the game.
It comes with the full source code right now, you can always download
the source code.
I upload it every time after we finish.
So if you'd like to play around with it at home or if you just like to
follow along with the code as we code on the stream, that's a good way
to do it.
You can pre-order it on handmade here at dot org.
If you'd like to support the video series, we also have a patreon.
You can subscribe to you, click.
Sling for that.
And we've got a news in Forum site, which is pretty cool.
It's got a bunch of resources up there question-and-answer boards and
stuff like that.
It's got pork Sports to Linux Mac, Android iOS that Community people
have done that.
You can check out got a Time coded episode guide, so that's all really
good.
I highly recommend checking it out and also if you want to be kept up
to date on the schedule, you can check out our little tweetbot.
Subscribe to the Tweet bot will tweet the schedule at you.
So you know, if you want to know when the streams are ya.
So thank you very
Much for joining me.
We will be back here again, Monday for our last week of coding before
break.
And so, yeah, next week will be our last, our last coding before we're
on break for a week, people been asking for it, and we give the people
what they want.
They wanted to break, they'll get a break.
So thank you everyone for joining me.
Hope to see you back here on Monday.
Check out the tweetbot for the schedule.
I suspect it'll probably be 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard time standards lot on Monday, but in if it's not
going to be I will post it.
So thanks everyone for joining us and I will see you next week.