Hello everyone, and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we code a complete game live on stream.
We have been implementing a more full 3d pipeline for the game, which
allows easy to be handled by the back end.
So we can use things like z-buffer.
Previously, we handled everything like that at the head end and only
fed the graphics card or our software, renderer perfectly sorted,
things that were already ready to draw and it didn't have to do.
Any work like that?
But we've decided to go to Z buffer because I thought there were too
many drawbacks with the other approach.
And so that's what we're doing right now.
We've done the work of moving the projection code over to open Jill's
transfer matrices as a first step in making sure that that stuff works
correctly.
But we still have a little bit more work to do in terms of actually
getting ourselves to the point where we are able to use that as an
actual able to use that actual system.
So, before we get
Too far down that path of trying to debug and trying to get working a
system that uses the z-buffer for doing our sorting.
I decided last time on stream that what I wanted to do was have a way
of rotating the camera around in three dimensions.
Not because we actually need this in the game for any particular
reason.
But actually, just because what we do need to do is be able to for
debugging purposes.
See what things actually look like geometrically.
When we're trying to figure out what we may have done wrong.
When we're de bugging things because we're going to have bugs as we
try to work in 3D and we need ways of inspecting.
What's going on to give ourselves more information about what the bugs
are, right?
So what I wanted to do is I just wanted to go ahead and build some
code that would allow us to rotate the camera around and be able to
see the world geometry from different angles even though it's flat.
Being able to see exactly how those flat pieces were lined up and how
they were stacked on top of each other and stuff like that.
Just to give us some greater Insight basically into what was going on.
So that's what we're doing today is day 362.
So you want to unpack day 361 source code.
If you're trying to follow along at home, I'm going to go ahead and
open up the project here.
Oops.
There we go.
And I am going to.
Show where we're at.
You can see here.
We are now running through open jails projection and everything is
working just fine.
Except for the fact that obviously, because we took sorting out of the
mix, we no longer run the sort and so everything is just flashing like
crazy.
The reason it's flashing like crazy is because the order in which we
send down entities changes every frame.
And since without having enabled the z-buffer we end up.
In a situation where we don't actually have any stable order, that
these things are drawn it.
So they're drawn in a random order and very specifically that is what
we are actually going to be fixing by switching to Z buffer as well.
Right?
We've removed the sort but now we need to put the Z buffer in to do
that.
But again before we get to trying to make that work properly because
that's going to require us sending down things.
In a, particularly specific sent to constructing our Sprite cards,
basically, in a very specific way.
You'll see
Is necessary to make sure that that works properly.
Before we get into that business, I want the ability to view the world
from multiple angles because I want to be able to debug it basically.
And we probably want this code anyway because we may find, you know, I
don't know but we may find that we want different angles for the game.
You know we may we may want to run the game straight top down but we
may want to run the game slightly tilted.
You know, we have to see what looks better.
So having the camera rotation code,
There is probably just a good idea in general because it allows us to
experiment with that, in terms of the look of the game as well, and we
don't know upfront, which exact way is, is going to be our preferred
way.
So having that rotation ability, is kind of nice for that reason, as
well.
So, let's go ahead and switch up here.
And and take a look at where we had started on this stuff now.
Hopefully, you remember everything from last week because it took a
long time to go over, so I can't really go over it again.
So I'm just going to assume that you remember, all of the stuff that
we did with these matrices here.
And there was only one thing that I didn't really talk about with the
matrices.
I talked about how to multiply them, I talked about how to make a
rotation Matrix and we made three of the rotation matrices for the
Cardinal angles, and we talked about having to transpose matrices.
So that they would be able to
To pass through opengl properly.
Because opengl by default takes non transpose matrices, unless you
call the transferred versions of the call it when we get to shaders,
will be able to will have a little bit more flexibility there as
you'll see.
But that's separate issue.
Anyway.
And then, of course, we have our projection Matrix construction and
our projection Matrix right now is very simple, but it works, right?
It does the exact same operation that we were doing, previously in the
main game code for producing the coordinates,
For the X Y coordinates, and we verified that by producing the same
game screen basically.
That we were getting before.
So we pretty much know that we've got that under control.
But now, let's take a look at these rotation matrices.
Talk about what's supposed to happen here in order to get our camera
doing what I suggested that I want to do and talk a little bit more
about the other aspects here.
Because we got a talk about the translation portion which again is not
very complicated, but we just to mention it.
And then also the idea of composing matrices together,
all right, so first of all, let's just talk very, very briefly about
what we
To do and about translation, matrices.
And then we'll talk about why Matrix concatenation works properly.
So that you can kind of understand a little more specifically, why?
That is the case.
All right, so let's talk about Matrix.
Multiplication.
Okay.
So you've seen me do it a couple times before just in terms of like
sort of sketching it out or mentioning it but we've never really dived
into detail and we've never really used it extensively in the code at
all for any particular reason but we basically had a, you know, have
had things where we talked about and I think I guess what I did is I
think I said C equals a b, it's sort of, I think what I wrote the
other day which is just to say that, you know I was just mentioning
the fact that we have this idea that if
We have all of these matrices if we have a and b, for example, we can
use matrix multiplication, which is denoted by putting the two
matrices together, symbolically.
This is how it's written, much like scalar multiplication is written
by putting the two variables next to each other in math, notation.
Obviously, in computer, notation we put a star in between them so
they're a little bit different there but still hopefully everyone
understands math notation well enough to see where that comes from.
So when we say,
Sequels a b.
What we're saying is that there is some way to produce a matrix C by
multiplying a matrix a and Matrix B.
And what we did last time on the stream is I showed how to produce the
Matrix C from Matrix, A, and B and hopefully that was very clear but
what might not be very clear from that is what it does or why you want
to use it, right?
Because I said that, what it does is it produces a combined transform,
right?
But I didn't really say how it was doing that or why it was doing that
and it's relatively important not to treat things in programming, like
black boxes that you don't understand.
Because oftentimes, when you're trying to do intricate things or new
things or develop new algorithms, it's crucial that you be able to
understand how things are working at a fundamental level because
otherwise you will miss the important.
Trinity's and be unable to solve bugs and have all other sorts of
problems because you don't really know what's going on.
Whereas really knowing what's going around, allows you to analyze the
complete workings of a program and make important improvements to it.
Make new algorithms or find difficult to find bugs.
So basically the combined algorithm entire the combined Matrix is
produced by doing matrix multiplication.
The question is, what does that mean?
What does it mean to combine two?
Transforms.
And why are they combined in the way that I will explain?
They are combined.
So first of all, let me start by just stating, what actually happens
here for people who don't know who aren't familiar with it in math
notation.
We typically have written something and I think you've seen me write
it this way before.
I'll do something like a times B times P equals c times P, right?
And it's sort of saying like Okay if we were going to take a point and
we're going to transform it by these two matrices somehow, then this
Matrix C would do the same transform to the point, right?
And so what we could,
Glean from this, right?
Is that some definition of the transform that happens when I
transferred by b and a is represented by C?
Now the first question might be, is it always order independent?
Or, you know, does if I say CP equals a BP, right?
What does that say about CP and B.A.P, for example, right?
Because one thing that we know from scalar,
Russian is that if I was to write the scalar version of this, right?
If I was to write, C equals a b, we know that that also equals be a in
straight scalar multiplication, in a normal scalar space.
Like, the kind we work in in high school algebra, right?
So what we would first possibly think, if we were just trying to
extend our understanding of multiplication directly from scalar
multiplication, we would probably think that these were going to be
equal to each other, right?
And that we
Just say that a B&B a well, it just does both transforms.
It doesn't matter what order they're in.
That is true in certain circumstances depending on the structures of
the matrices, but it is not true.
In other circumstances.
Matrix multiplication is actually ordered dependent and the reason
that it is ordered dependent is because you produce a different set of
products depending on which order you put.
The
Aziz and you can actually see this by doing it yourself.
If you made a matrix, a b, c d like this.
And then make another Matrix ijkl, right?
Or something like this.
And I was to multiply these two together.
We all know what we would get even if we just were looking at the
first term of this Matrix, we would end up with IJ, right?
And I'm sorry, AI in this case, plus BK.
And then this, you know, get product over here product over here, and
in the next row down, we would get in.
This is just what we did.
Yes.
Last time I was dream, right?
For those of you who missed it, you want to go back and watch that.
We'd know we get these two terms here, right?
But if I was going to flip the order of these around, so same exact
matrices, but I'm just going to multiply them in the opposite order
here, right?
So here I've got this Matrix times this Matrix here, I've got them
opposite, write this Matrix,
I am multiply it by this Matrix here.
You can see immediately that we get completely different terms, right?
We get an AI and that's in common but then right away we get a
different term here.
It's a CJ term, right?
And the CJ term previously would not have occurred in this column at
all, right.
It was a CI term is where that showed up and similarly when we get to
the next one.
Same thing we get an AK plus a CL.
Come here, right?
And you can see that K is nowhere to be found in terms of a van, a
term here.
And yeah, I mean you get the idea, right?
It's like it's very, obviously a different set of products.
I guess I don't need to belabor that point, so because of that when we
do matrix multiplication, we must be very mindful of the order because
as you can see, only through extreme happenstance when these matrices
happen to have very specific structure that just so happens to lead
them to produce the same products in those places.
Will we get the same results?
You know, one example would be if the Matrix is diagonal for example,
if there were no terms on the outsides of these, right?
So if there were just zeros all through here, then what we get is
something very akin to scalar multiplication because the diagonals
always line up in the same place, right?
So, we would get a, I hear and we would get a I here again, because we
always have that product of the diagonal appearing down the diagonal,
in the result, right?
So, if everywhere else is,
Zero.
And you just have to ask me cheese, then the order ceases to matter in
most cases because the diagonal products line up, right?
No matter which way you do it.
And hey, you know what's kind of interesting about that just as an
aside, what does it is a matrix that just has terms down the diagonal,
right?
Well, that is a scaling Matrix, right?
You remember, we talked about these a long time ago if I have an X Y
that's coming in here point, I'm multiplying by then that's just a
Why?
It's just a scale on the incoming thing.
It's two coefficients that scale the incoming thing.
What do we know about scaling?
While scaling, as a transform is order independent?
If I make something twice as large and then I make it four times large
again, it's just eight times larger.
Same is true if I make something four times larger and then two times
larger again still eight times larger, right?
And so one of the interesting really kind of fascinating things about
matrices and again,
aye, you know, I mathematically speaking, historically you can see why
they were relevant to solving problems and why we started using them
to create structure.
For notating complex systems like this is because that actually
captures something true about the operation scaling is order
dependent.
I'm sorry, order independent, you can scale in any order, it doesn't
matter.
And the math also captures that similarly things that do matter order
wise, for example, rotation rotation in three dimensions, is order
dependent it matters, which order you do the rotations in in Matrix
math, it actually happens that that order dependence is preserved
properly and so they are very powerful Tools in that sense in that.
Capture mathematically the same things that occur in the real world
and that's very important.
So now let's take a look at why the order dependence is important for
us and how it captures the transform dependents.
Like I said, something like scaling that's only diagonal.
It doesn't have any order dependence, and that's exactly what we want.
But for something like rotation, we do want that to capture that order
dependence because with rotations, because they are not a clean
euclidean operation.
What you end up having is if you rotate something one way, and then
from that point, do a rotation again, in the, you know, if I have a
world space rotation this way, and I play another rotation space
rotation this way, it's not the same as if I did.
To in the opposite order, it might be.
Sometimes depending on the choice of axes, it might result in the same
thing, but oftentimes, it will result in a different final
orientation.
That's just true about rotations in three dimensions that has nothing
to do with game programming.
Obviously, we care about and game playing but it is not a construct.
It's not an artificial contract.
That's just actually how real three-dimensional objects behave in the
real world.
So what happens with matrix multiplication is remember, I talked quite
a bit.
About the concept that in a matrix you can have the X, the Y, and the
Z axes of the space.
You're talking about.
They go in The Columns of the Matrix corresponds to placing something
in the world at that x, y&z axis reference frame, right?
So, you know, we've got something that looks like this.
Let's say I've got a y, axis, and x axis and Z axis, and you,
And see here in my Matrix.
I would put the three values for the z-axis here.
I will put the 3 for the Y down here and the 3 for the X down here, we
talked about this quite a bit and the reason for that of course is
when a, if these are my axes let's say and I've got a pxpypz for my
point that comes in the reason for that is of course this produces
this equation.
P XA, X py pz AZ.
Which is just reinterpreting the point P.
Along these axis, right?
It's saying go the x-coordinate go that far along the x axis, the y
coordinate, go that far along the y axis, the Z coordinate, go that
far along the z-axis, right?
So it makes perfect sense.
Why
That works with the point transform.
So now the next question is well if it makes perfect sense for the
point transform, the why does it work for putting two rotations
together?
Let's say or a rotation and a scale together?
Well, you can see quite easily.
Why a rotation and a scale would work, right?
Because the same thing applies here.
If I have a matrix
That's a rotation.
Here's my rotation Matrix and then I have a remote location.
I mean, a matrix, that's a scale.
Here is my SX /.
That's a lowercase S.
I know it's hard to tell because there's no difference between that
and an uppercase s, but it's supposed to be right.
Then what you're going to see happen here is, you know, when I create
the product, when I look at the SX, well what's going to go, you know,
in this in this part here?
Well, it's just going to be
Whatever the x coordinate of the x axis is X SX, the same will be true
for each one of these, right?
The y-coordinate will just be times of the ax axis will just be times
the SX, right?
Because the SX will just multiply everything in this column, right?
And the Sy multiplies everything in the next column and so on, right?
So what we end up with is the exact same structure of the Matrix, but
just now every column has been multiplied by the
The scale that we were trying to apply.
Right.
And so, what that means is that we have applied the scaling Matrix to
The Columns of the rotation Matrix, which are the axis of the
rotation, right?
Which produces exactly what we want, a reference frame that, you know,
if it used to look like this, now, it looks like a scaled version of
that which is exactly what we were trying to do, right?
We were trying to rotate and scale.
Well, now we have a matrix, which does both right it?
Exactly those axes which are the rotation axes, scaled by the scale,
we were trying to apply, right?
So that's a pretty easy combination there.
Same thing is true, but it's a little harder to see because there's
just a lot more numbers involved.
Scale is nice because it just goes down the diagonal.
It's really simple to see.
But if I have the same sort of situation where I've got an ax,
And a y in an AZ.
and then up here, I've got another Matrix, that's a b x, a b y and it
BZ
then again, we sort of can see in this case that we're going to have
a combination of these values.
But without dropping the scalar, it's pretty difficult to understand
how these things combined, right?
It's like, well, okay, I've got an axis here and I, you know, I've got
an axis here.
What exactly is happening there?
It's like, I'm not sure, right, the
X coordinate of BX is multiplying a x the whole way down, right?
But then the y-coordinate of BX is also multiplying a why the whole
way down, right?
And it's like wait, what's going on?
Well, we can draft a scalar and just do it out, but I would also
encourage you and hopefully at this point, if you want to do that, you
can go do that on your own.
And you've seen me do multi, master replication.
So many times on how many are you should be have a pretty cold, so you
should be able to do it.
But if you just think about this briefly, remember that matrix
multiplication.
And Vector multiplication are exactly the same thing, right?
What do we say last week about The Columns of the Matrix?
That's on the right hand of the multiplication.
So if we're doing a times B, what did we say about The Columns of
this, right?
We said it could have as many as it wants.
Excuse me.
And why can it have as many as it once well, because we go columns and
be for producing a term.
Rose in a which means that to produce the entire one entire row of the
output.
We have only ever used and consumed one row of B to do so.
There is no need for us to ever use this row again.
It is irrelevant right for the next column, it will never be touched.
So, essentially, what we can think of is we can think of each of these
Matrix multiplications column applications as a separate Vector,
right?
And you already just saw me do that.
If I had said a x, a y AZ, where The Columns of this Matrix and I
said,
We're multiplying by a point XYZ, right?
And this is the point P, here is the Matrix a and this is the
equation, you know, P Prime equals AP, right?
Here's my P.
Prime right here, that I'm producing.
Will we know exactly what this is.
We just said that this is this Vector, right?
Not a matrix by a vector is X ax.
Plus YP y plus Z, oops.
Hey, y plus z a z.
Right.
It's just a point that's made by going X along a x y along a y&z along
AZ.
Right?
That's one column Vector.
Well, that's exactly what would happen here, right?
It's just be X transformed by a.
That's what's going to be produced here, right?
Just like this is a transformed by P.
That's what there.
result is so we can write the resulting matrix by just saying, hey,
this Matrix a, it's
A time's the BX, right?
Like I don't know what the probably I should not have used the capital
letters for both the vector and the Matrix.
This was bad notation but I did so.
Oh well it's a times.
Let's make that a lowercase B.
I guess I don't know it's a times and you know, maybe these are
lowercase A's all of a sudden return that always happen.
It's a time's the BX Vector Plus
Sorry, eh heh.
Yeah, a times BX, Vector plus KT, plus.
Well, I'm totally flustered by my change to lowercase toy through me.
It's a times b x in the First Column, it's a times b, y in the second
column, and it's a times b z in the third column, right?
That's just what we actually produced.
And so you can see right away just from reading that off.
Now that we've figured out what it was.
As you can see just by reading it off that produces the set of axes
represented by The Matrix be transformed by a.
So it's it's applying a as a transform to be right?
And that Clues us directly in on the order of May of interpretation of
interpreting Matrix products, right?
If I have some big long series here and I'm like, all right, I'm going
to produce
Something at the end of this right, some composite Matrix Q or
whatever, right?
And I've got q, p Prime is a times B times c times, D times, c times F
times p.
And the question is, what order if I am looking at Q or even, if I'm
just looking at this equation, what order are these transforms
performed in?
You know, and again, if it's something like scaling, I don't care what
order it's in, it doesn't matter.
But for some like rotation, I do so assume that these some of these,
at least,
In here, have a rotation or some other thing is sheer something that
who's ordered dependent, what order are they going in conceptually?
And the answer, you can see here, is that, it's always the second term
in a product, the, the further to the right.
That is, the one that's applied first, and it's the one further to the
left.
That's being done to it, right?
It's saying, I start with the F and that is the first transform that
would be applied.
I'm going to apply e2f.
right, so is this then e dcba so if you read left to right, right,
You're actually reading them in the wrong order of conceptual
application.
Conceptually they're actually getting applied this way, right?
You start with the thing you're working on and you go backwards from
that.
And this ends up being the last transform, that gets applied.
And again, that comes directly from this interpretation here where you
can see exactly why that occurs.
Now again that saying that what order they get applied in that I'm not
trying to speak to some mathematical thing here.
What I'm trying to speak to is a conceptual thing.
When these transforms are represents re when these matrices are
representing transforms in 3D,
We as humans have a concept of what order the transforms are going in
because that is a conceptual thing and it matters, like I said, the
rotation order matters.
So what I'm saying here, when I say that they are applied in this
order, I'm not trying to talk about a mathematical order of
application.
What I'm trying to say is when the math is performed, as the math is
performed by the definition of matrix, multiplication.
The result conceptually is that the order of transformation, the
appearance of how the transform will occur is in this order, whereas
if you flipped the order, you would get a different resulting
transform.
That was as if the transform had been applied in a different order,
right?
So, there you go.
So that's matrix, multiplication and and its effect and why it's
effective that way.
Now, to more things we have to cover,
First translation and this one's the easy one.
So translation we already know how to do it.
We do it all the time, right?
We take a point.
We want to produce a new Point that's offset by something.
What do we do?
Well, we just add an offset, right?
So we just have some offset that gets added in here, right?
We don't know what it is, just some Vector 3 dimensional Vector.
We said to whatever we want and that offsets the point, right?
So I've got some offset, let's say that offset is a.
And in here, I want to offset this point by a
Then we know that I've got a point P.
I've got that a that I could think of, as a vector that starts at p
and points in some direction and has a length.
We end up at P Prime which is just going along.
They're right.
We know exactly what that is.
We understand that very well.
We do it all the time in handmade hero.
So now the question is, well, I want to capture that but in a matrix
because I want to be able to produce these Composites here.
We're not only do I have rotation and not only do I have scaling, but
I also have position.
Incorporated into that operation, right?
So, I want the whole thing.
And so, what I can do, if I want to do that is I can take advantage of
the 4 by 4 th of these matrices.
And this is where you start to see that 4 by 4, element come into
play.
And I mentioned this before,
Previous stream if we were to just have an X, right?
A Y and the Z axis.
This is our 4 by 4 Matrix, right?
If we were just to have a 3 by 3 which is this upper part here, right?
And maybe just because we're doing that we're you know maybe I'll be a
little more explicit just this one time when we're talking about it
here, if we
Talk about having the x-axis.
Oops.
Y axis.
And Z axis.
So if we were to just take this 3 by 3 and pretend, The Matrix was
just three by three, right then what you can see from this and we
talked about this before, is that everything that comes in as a point,
right?
And Let Me Maybe, maybe I shouldn't have done that.
So close to the equation just moved out there.
Move it down a little bit.
Let's do it right here.
Okay.
All right.
So if we were to have this and I have an incoming Point like this,
what you can see from the equation that results is that you never
really get an opportunity to put any translation in here.
Because when I do this multiplication out, what I will end up getting
in each of my components is unfortunately that leaves no room for a
translation, right?
So my X
And it of the result is going to be P X XX + py x.
I'm sorry, Y X.
Plus p z z x, right?
That's what we're going to get there.
And similarly, we get the exact same thing.
In all of these Loops.
So good, PX, X Y P.
Why, why why pz z y?
And finally, pz R, PX x z py.
Isaiah.
Peezy.
ZZ.
So, you can see here this creates exactly what we wanted.
In terms of a vector equation, for reinterpreting things around
rotated, or scaled axes.
Because you can see how to pull out the PX, py and pz from here.
And when we rewrite that we just get PX times that x-axis right plus
py times that y-axis, + pz x and z axis, right?
You can see that the pz is all
Come in here and we said zxy.
There's that Vector, Right?
Py is coming here, right?
So this this just produces exactly this and that's great for rotation
and scaling and sharing and everything else.
That's just axial manipulation.
But the question is where is the origin, right?
The origin hasn't changed at all here.
There's no fundamental displacement because every term that we had in
our transform is multiplied by something in the input.
So there is no offset.
That just comes in.
We need a term over here.
That's not X, anything in X or Y or Z right in order to get that in
there.
And so this is where that augmentation to 4x4 comes in handy.
Yet again, it was good for the projection for the synthetic divide
idea.
And it's also useful here because what we pretend when we do these
transforms is that our three-dimensional points are augmented by a 1.
So we use that fourth coordinate.
And we stick a 1 in there and we use that one to ensure that we can
add something at the end of our matrix multiplication and get a valid
translation out of it.
So what you can see is that one will he
The things in each of these positions.
So if I have a translation X translation, Y and a translation Z here
then what will happen is that will just get tacked on to the end 1
times translation, x 1 times translation, y1 times translation, Z lo
and behold that's just adding the translation Vector onto the end,
right?
And that is what produces the 4x4 structure for a translation,
rotation scale, sheer Matrix, right?
This part down here is not used because that only comes into play,
when we actually start needing to do perspective, right?
You saw me use it.
So I'm gonna use this one when we start to use perspective.
So it does come into play.
But it's really this part, that's the important part for our purposes.
When we're talking about 3D transforms, we don't need any of this down
here.
Most of the time.
and in fact, a lot of people when they Implement pipelines just
Implement just this part and they hard-code all of the multiplication
to assume 0 0, 0 1 on the bottom, and they only have stuff that takes
care of the bottom, when they actually use, when they actually go to
do perspective,
Like, at the very, very end, right?
Because you can
You know.
You just wasted a lot of operations.
If you were always treating those, as if they could be set, something
else and you never set them something else.
But anyway, so that's how that works and you can see that's how are
matrices are constructed.
So now we have the ability to construct a rotation, you know, by by
looking at this, we can construct a rotation scaling.
And translation, which is really all we ever do in handmade Arrow.
That's all we do.
Now, we could also do shearing and I maybe we do some sharing, we
could also do sharing again.
Because since we have control over the axes, we can share the axes as
well.
So we actually also have shearing here
And by the way, the scaling is non-uniform, right?
So we can scale the X y&z separately as well, we can create matrices
that do all of these things and now because I made some
multiplication, we can also combine them all.
So we can just make matrices at do whatever we want, and we can
combine them all together and we want to transform something.
We can transform it all the way from wherever it starts to the very
end of every transform that needs to happen all with one Matrix and
that's pretty great, right?
It saves a ton of work.
In terms of manipulating the points around.
Okay, so that's all real good.
And everyone's happy and everything's fantastic, right?
but,
We've got 11 more problem.
There's something that we have not addressed this entire time and
we've never had to address it because we always sort of did just the
one part of it that was relevant by hand in the hand made her a
pipeline, but because we're now going to be talking about a real
camera transform.
We have one more thing that we have to get, right?
Hopefully, all of that was fairly easy for everyone to understand and
work out.
If it's not, we'll try to tackle it in the Q&A.
But the thing that we have never really made explicit because we never
had to is the concept of a camera transform.
And a camera transform is not the same as an object transform.
It is the same.
In the sense that mathematically, it's can still be represented by a
matrix because any transform that we probably want to do in three
dimensions for rigid transforms.
Like this is usually capable of being represented in a matrix.
Obviously nonlinear transforms or not, that's a whole separate thing.
But any kind of basic transform like this can be represented so it can
be represented in the Matrix.
But conceptually
It is very different from an object transform and so let me take a
brief second to explain what I mean by those two things.
So an object transform.
Is a transform.
And again these are purely conceptual, right?
So the math is the same regardless of what you're doing, but we're
just talking about conceptualizing these things when you're trying to
understand what's happening here.
And and more importantly, I suppose when you have a goal, you want to
achieve and you need to do it with a transform, how you conceive and
construct that transform.
An object transform is the kind that we've been talking about so far,
which is looking at a matrix like this.
It's looking at a matrix where the x axis is here.
The y axis is here, the Z axis is here, it's got 0 0, 1 here.
And we've got a translation component like that.
Okay.
That's an object transform.
And what an object transform is, is it's a transform that takes
something from the origin and a route coordinate system, right?
So it's like I've got X Y and Z and I'm thinking about some shape, you
know, I don't know what it is.
I've got some like maybe a little, I don't know.
Like a triangle here.
It's aligned there, right?
Here's my triangle.
I'm taking it as its defined in a base coordinate system.
Are all the axes are cardinal and there's no scaling.
You know, I'm conceiving of it.
Just defined as it is and I'm transforming it such that the axes of
this Matrix and the origin offset of this Matrix become the new way
that is being interpreted, right?
So now say this Matrix is a, this is a x, a y, AZ and 80 right now.
This may have been.
This is like sort of the route, the basics.
Y z coordinate system.
I'm taking it from there and I'm putting it into some new coordinate
system, right?
As defined by the the contents of that Matrix.
So this 1000 before, now the origin, the base of that is at 80 and all
of my axes are now whatever.
The axes were specified as over here, right?
And so when we conceptualize a matrix by looking at its columns,
We are talking about it as if it as if we are conceiving it.
We are conceptualizing this Matrix as this process because remember, a
matrix is just a bag of numbers at the end of the day, right?
It's just a bag of numbers and a rule about how we multiply them
together so it was purely my conceptualization of the Matrix and how I
explained it to you.
That is why we picked it out in terms of
Columns, right.
We there's
The Matrix that says it has to be picked out in terms of columns, it
just so happens that if you conceive of the Matrix and columns like
that, then the meaning of the Matrix is clear, for those columns,
right?
That's one way we can analyze what a matrix does is by looking at the
columns and saying those columns.
if we were to apply this Matrix to a geometric shape, the points of a
geometric shape in series,
Those columns would form the new coordinate system for that shape and
that fourth column in the homogeneous coordinate way would form its
origin that is what will happen to those numbers in The Matrix if we
conceive of them as columns and that's a very useful way to look at it
because often times that's exactly what we want to build.
We want to build an object transform.
So we know that we can stuff those coordinates in here in that way to
produce.
This result.
Right?
And that's great.
I think.
however,
there's more than one way to conceptualize the parts of a matrix,
right?
This.
We might call the column picture.
It's the way of looking at a matrix that focuses on the columns and
what that means and the column picture produces an object transform,
write the column way of looking at it.
Looks at it as if it is this process.
But we could alternatively look at the row picture.
Right?
The row picture is what happens if we take the other slice, what if we
looked at what the rows of a matrix mean, right?
Cutting the other way.
And if we look at the row picture, then we get a camera transform.
And the reason this is important for us to understand is because
that's what we actually want to make right now in handmade hero.
When I turn off this Blackboard and go to the code, that's what I got
a tie pin.
Right.
So what does that mean?
Well, if we go back here,
I've conveniently sort of oops, that's not right.
This is a point I've conveniently written this entire thing out for
one of the of the for one column, right?
For a vector
And that's really all I need to explain the row picture to you.
I'm sorry.
I'm really I'm kind of sick today.
I am very like throat cloggy so I can't.
Clear My Throat.
It's tough talking sometimes.
So, what I encourage you to do before it to get to the cam picture was
to pull out the columns, right?
I was saying, oh okay, you know, here's the PX term and you can see
the X y&z terms coming into an X Vector here, y Vector, Z, you know,
and Z Vector here.
But what if we were to look at this?
Right?
What if we were to look at it the other way?
Well, this also looks like something for those of you who, you know,
Remember all of your handmade hero, what does that look like to you,
right?
If looking at it this way, looks like something we can pull columns
out of, what does this look like?
I'll give you a second.
Well.
Let's take a look P XX X py, Y XP, Z, ZX, right that to me.
And then of course the 11 TX, right?
That to me, looks an awful lot like the dot product that we've talked
about right or inner product.
Why does it look a lot like an inner product because a matrix
multiplication is just a series of inner products at the end of the
day, right?
Each position in the output is just a DOT product of the column of the
of the right-hand term times, the row of the left-hand term, right so
while I can think of it the way I was thinking of it before as being a
series of column editions that's the column picture.
I can also think of it as a series of dot products and that's the row
picture of the incoming.
Matrix of the, the left hand side Matrix, right?
This term is the dot product of the column of B with the row of a
right.
It's basically like a row dot product added with a column, right?
And we do that every one of the terms in the resulting Matrix is what,
whatever, the corresponding row of a times, whatever the corresponding
column of B, it's that dot product, that's what it is, right?
So if I instead want to,
Is this Matrix as thinking about what the rows of it mean.
So now let's say we've got our x axis instead of sticking our x axis
in the column.
What if we stuck our x-axis in the row, right?
We'll leave the translation out of it for the moment.
Right.
What if we did that?
Well, now when we have PX py and pz coming in right, which is just R
Vector p, and here's our, a and we'll do a x.
A y is e 4r.
For rotation, there for our, for our axis component.
Now, when we do this, right?
The result is actually just the ax dot product ID with P, right?
Plus the TX translation term.
A y dot product with p, plus the translation term, AZ dot product,
with p plus translation term, right?
There's a 1 there.
That's exactly what we get and really, we can just write this the
whole way out if I wanted to include the t x t YT, Z in the row.
It would just be a x transpose P if the TX was in there, right?
Because it's still a DOT product.
The whole way I've just chosen to leave the translation separate again
because we're trying to think about this means conceptually.
It's easier to keep translation as a separate translation because that
is what it actually does.
Because this term is 1, there is no contribution of P here, right?
So this is a different way of conceptualizing.
What happens in The Matrix so if we were to write both of these out so
you could kind of see them because it that it's works.
Every time you do matrix multiplication both of these things is
happening.
Conceptually, it's which one you choose to focus on, right?
Is to understand what the Matrix is doing.
You can think about it, two different ways, right here is a way and
I'll write it.
So let's let's write it this way and I'll just do the 3 by 3.
We'll leave out the
You can see that it was, it was the same, in either case, there
doesn't really matter, right?
Here's the row picture.
Here's row of x times p.
And maybe I'll just write it this way.
Right, here's the row picture.
Here's the column picture.
Okay.
The row picture produces a vector that is the rho dot parted with the
Hoops with the incoming point.
The column picture.
And I guess I won't bother.
Because I'm a space.
Let's just say we're multiplying by this again the column picture
produces a combination of the columns.
Right.
This and this are the same result, right?
Because this is could be the same exact Matrix, the same bag of
numbers exactly the same.
But in terms of how we want to conceptualize what it does, we can
think of matrix multiplication and this, in this case Matrix times a
vector, but again major times a vector is just the same as Mitchell's
location because again, multiplication by The Matrix is just taking
The Columns of the right-hand side and doing the Matrix
It's warm to them conceptually, right?
So they're the same thing.
Just one does more.
We can conceptualize the same bag of numbers two different ways.
One way is to say, let's pretend that we had axes on the rows of this
Matrix that each bag of numbers, that was three across, was going to
be one of our axes X Y & Z.
Well, if that's the case, then the operation of what this Matrix does,
to those axes.
Is it dot products?
The incoming point with each of them and the result is the dot product
in the x-coordinate.
It's the dot product, with the x axis in the y, coordinate is adopt
the y axis and the Z coordinate.
Its adopt pipe with the Z axis.
That's the row picture.
And that's a camera transform.
I'm going to tell you why in a second.
On the other hand, if we take a look at this picture, the column is
just a combination of the columns, you know, scaled by the incoming
point, right?
That is exactly, you know, sort of, again, exactly some reason, these
two are equivalent values, the result is the same.
The two vectors are exactly the same.
It's just how we're choosing capsize them if instead we conceptualize
the axes as whatever was in The Columns, right?
Then that's the column picture.
And that's that object transform that we already know and are very
familiar with, right?
Because this is exactly what we already know.
And what we've done many many times on handmade hero.
So now the question is just okay, so if I want to make a transfer
Matrix and I'm trying to make a transfer Matrix, that encapsulated
object transform.
I know I just put things in the X, I know I put my x and y and z-axes
Into The Columns of a matrix and then I can just use it as a
transformation that will do an object transform, it'll move a point
from the origin coordinate system out to wherever those.
Axes are where their origin is where they axes are.
Along those axes Etc, right?
So the question is, what is the camera transform and why does this do
it right?
What's this other row picture because hopefully you all agree with me
that this is definitely a different way.
We could interpret the math but how does this different interpretation
of the result?
How does this different grouping, how we've chosen to summarize the
terms of what happens when you multiply a matrix times?
A vector?
How does that end up giving us any insight into how we produce a
camera transform and what even is a camper transform, right?
And that's the part that I want to get to here.
So let's talk about that.
And hopefully that will become clear.
What we wanted to do with an object transform, is we wanted to take
something right from, you know, it's there's really isn't a good word
for this necessarily, but we can say its native space, right?
Or sometimes it's called object space, right?
We're talking about that space again.
This just the like untransformed unperturbed space where we've just
got the, you know, 000 here.
And we've got the x y&z axis here, right?
We're trying to do with that object transform is we're trying to take
some things defined here, I don't know.
Some point, some shape, a polygon, who knows what it is and we're
trying to transform them out to any other thing.
Like maybe these axes are all bent around and they're super weird and
they're scaled all weird.
Right?
And the origin moved somewhere but we still want this shape to be
existing there and so it's just a transform that does that place.
Moment, right?
You might even think of it as a placement transform.
It places something in the world with a certain set of axes, right?
Well, a camera transform it, something it does.
The opposite of that, a camera transform is something that we
conceptualize and often want to do where we have some stuff out in the
world, right?
and we've got some, you know,
we've drawn many times.
We've got some Observer here and they want to view this thing, right?
They want to see this thing.
Well, in order to do any of that stuff that we were doing those
projections, right?
Remember all those projections where we set up the similar triangles,
right?
And we were projecting all the things down on there.
We talked about that just last two weeks ago.
I don't know whatever all that stuff.
All of that assumed that we were already in the space of the camera,
right?
We assumed that all everything had been rotated and moved so that it
was sitting in front of the camera and the cameras.
Coordinate system was native all of that stuff was just assumed
because,
You know, we did things like saying, oh yeah, okay, the x-coordinate
of this thing on the screen right?
Is going to be equal to the x coordinate of this thing in World space.
You know over like the Z coordinate of the thing in World space or
whatever, right?
it assumes that the
Of the screen, the out, the result.
In X is based solely on the input in x.
And the only way that that is true is if we already moved, you know,
this is on an angle here, right.
The x-coordinate on the screen is some complex equation of X and Y.
Going this way right to produce that x coordinate.
So we've just been assuming this whole time, that before you did any
of that projection stuff that we talked about that, you would already
transformed the world so that it was nice sitting right in front of
the camera, right?
Where x coordinates were on the x axis and Y coordinates were on the
y-axis.
We worked assuming that the x-axis and y-axis its themselves, right?
Here's the x-axis.
The y-axis comes out of the screen.
This is the Z axis.
Right.
We weren't assuming that those axes were all bent in World space
somewhere like rotated around.
We assume that all that was taken care of, and that was never a
problem on handmade hero because we never rotated the camera on
handmade hero.
The whole world was just always constructed perfectly in line with the
cameras, X and y-axis, right?
We never conceived of it, being tilted, the world like being tilted
relative to the camera, we never conceived it being spun like this,
right?
So we never had to do a camera transform other than just a simple
offsetting of Z, right?
All we ever did was assume that the camera was looking down on the
world, right?
Here's the world and here's the camera.
And so all we ever did was like plus or minus Z to move the camera
like higher or lower.
That's all we did.
We never tried to make the camera like come over here and view the
world from the side.
And that's exactly what we need to do now.
So, a camera transform is one that undoes transforms.
In some sense, you could say, right the world is out there,
everything's in World space but our camera is implying some other
space and we want to take a tilted space a rotated space and offset
space, the space of the camera and we want to make it the origin.
We want to make 00 appear here.
We want to make its axes, be the Cardinal axes so that it is
Eat the camera is perfectly straight in World space.
It's x axis lines up with the world x-axis.
It's y-axis is the world's y-axis, right?
So we're moving the whole world so that the world X Y and Z axes.
Now, correspond to the cameras, axis, moving everything else so that
the camera can be at the center of the world pointing in exactly the Z
direction, right?
Or the opposite, the Z Direction.
In this case,
that's what we need to do.
And we never done anything like that before, right?
We did this with position and it was very simple.
We never did it with rotation.
How do we do with position?
Well, the way that we did it with physician with saying, well,
alright, you know,
Here's the origin of the world.
Here's a point that I'm trying to view.
Here's the camera.
Right?
If I want the camera to be as if it was at 0, 0 0, right?
All I have to do is subtract whatever the cameras position is, right?
If I subtract C from C, right?
It becomes 0 and this becomes C write that c - c is 0 so I just
subtract C from everything, right?
So I have P, minus C is here and hey look at that we get the world.
Right.
Moved back to the origin for the camera.
So for translation, it's very simple.
We just negate it right?
That's all we had to do was take wherever the camera was negate that
and that is the transform.
We applied to all the points of the world to move them back.
So that the cameras at the origin that I think we did do on handmade
hero, right?
So in some sense we had a little bit of a camera transform.
It just wasn't really much of a transform.
It was just an offset.
So we could, we could avoid having to think about the more complicated
aspects of how we view things, right?
So we now we need the second picture, we need or rather I should say
we need the the other operation we need to figure out how if we had a
set of rotated axes how would we go about moving the world so that it
lined up with them, right?
So let's say you know obviously we know how to do translation.
Let's leave that aside for a second.
Let's say here we are.
Okay, and the camera is looking this direction.
Okay, so here's the x-axis.
Here's the y-axis, but the camera is looking this direction and maybe
I shouldn't say looking this direction because in 2D, it's hard to say
looking looking with is going down, the Z axis in our 3D.
So let's be a little bit more specific here.
Let's say that this is the cameras.
X axis.
And this is the cameras y-axis, okay?
And so, what that means is, if we had a point, let's say that there
was a point that was right here.
Okay, well, if we wanted to produce the version of the world, where
the cameras axes were aligned with the with the world axes, this whole
thing has to rotate back down this way, right?
We want to make it so that CX is here and see why is here which would
put this point somewhere over here.
Right.
Probably like right there, something right?
It would rotate down this way.
How do we do that?
Right, how do we do that?
And so, to make this a little bit clearer, I'm going to draw it on two
diagrams, right?
There's one
Here's to.
So what I effectively want to do is I want to turn this into this.
Here's my pee and here's my P Prime groups.
Right.
So remember everything that we've been thinking about so far we've
been doing this, we've been taking something from An Origin centered
coordinate system and moving it out somewhere else, right?
Like when we were rotating our Sprites, we were thinking about the
Sprites being defined in this space and we're doing them out this way.
So that now we could rotate our Sprites, right?
That's the object transform.
And now we need to figure out how to do the opposite thing.
We need to do that camera transform, which is we've got the world, all
rotated out and weird, and we need to move it back so that it aligns
with our camera, right?
So, how do we do it?
Well,
If you take a look at what we need to produce here, it gives us a
pretty big clue.
What are the coordinates of P?
Prime in this case, right?
Well, the coordinates of P Prime, if Cy + CX are the new axes, right?
It's just the perpendicular sort of.
If I measure what P Prime is.
It's the perpendicular measure of P Prime against those axes, right?
That's how we've been doing coordinate system since day one on
handmade hero.
You go out along.
Access to the x coordinate, you go out along the y, axis to the y
coordinate and you arrive at the point.
And the opposite is also true.
If I want to reverse engineer, what the coordinates are, I just have
to look at where my point is, projected onto those axes and that is
the coordinates of the point, right?
We've done this on handmade here.
Already way, way back when it is the inner product.
Or dot product.
Right.
That is how we measure things.
Do you remember it?
When we have a vector,
Right.
Here's my Vector, a and some other Vector B.
if I want to take the dot product or if I take the dot product of
these two, it is equal to the length of a
Time's the length of B times the cosine of angle between them.
Right now, we did this many May times on handmade hero.
Hopefully, you can dig back and remember it, but this is the inner
product right here.
What does that do for us?
Well, if we suppose that a is unit length,
Which we can make it because this is an axis.
If we want to measure things along an axis, this could be an axis
axes, we can just set them up to be unit length, right?
We know we can make things unit, length, if a is unit length, then a
transpose B, this term goes away because it's a 1, right?
And multiplying by one does nothing.
We just get the length of B times the cosine of theta.
What is that?
Well, if you imagine this right, triangle, right?
What we would get in this case,
is this distance, right?
Why?
Because the cosine of theta for a right triangle, right?
The cosine of theta is the ratio of the hypotenuse of the triangle to
this side.
Right?
You could say the interior side, the side along the angle, right?
The sign is out here, right?
And so, whatever the length of the hypotenuse is, in this case, that's
the length of B, right?
Because that b is the long side of the triangle.
We know that the length of this side is just the length of the
hypotenuse times.
The cosine and the length of this side is just the length of the
hypotenuse times the sign.
Right.
so, if we want to measure,
A vector a point along an axis somewhere if that axis is unit length,
the dot product, gives us precisely that it gives us precisely the
distance along so what can you see in this diagram now?
Well, I know what these two axes are and I know I could make them unit
length.
Even if they weren't unit length, I mean our camera probably going to
have unit length access to begin with anyway.
You're probably not going to be scaling the world up and down by some
weird camera transform, right?
It's probably going to be like to begin with but even if they were not
to make them unit length and if their unit length, then all I have to
do is take the dot product of the point in World space, with those
World, space camera axes.
And I get exactly what I needed.
I get exactly the coordinates of this point in the cameras space as if
the camera was itself, the world space.
And that's exactly what I needed that.
Undoes the rotation and produces this from this.
That is exactly our camera transform.
Wouldn't it be nice if there was some way with a matrix to take all of
our camera axes and Dot product incoming points with them?
Wouldn't that be swell?
Yes, it would be swell.
And it is literally that, right?
It is exactly what happens when you put your axis coordinates into a
matrix as the rose.
Not the columns.
So instead of taking your X, Y and Z of the x-axis and putting them
along the column.
You take your X y&z the excess to put them on the row, Y axis, x y, z,
yr, z axis XYZ.
It does exactly that.
It produces the three dot products of the incoming point, with the
three.
These that you have specified and that is exactly what we wanted to
do.
That is exactly the equation that I used to produce this result.
Okay.
So that's where we get to sort of the final understanding of a
transfer Matrix, right?
Which is that the rose,
Our camera, axes.
And the columns.
Our object taxes.
And you can look at them, either way you can use them either way,
right?
now, those of you who
Like to inquire into things, a little more deeply are, probably
naturally asking the question at this point.
How is that possible?
What does that even mean?
Why is it that I can look at a matrix this bag of numbers, right?
And I can choose to put things in the columns and it does one kind of
transform and I can choose to put things in the rows and it does a
different transform.
And yeah, I saw you do the math but isn't that weird?
It's just weird, right?
It's spooky that that works.
How's that working?
Right.
Well, here's where that transpose.
As a little bit of insight to the scenario, right?
One thing we know about Matrix transposing, is that it does exactly
the flip between these two things, right?
If I have a matrix where I put x y,
And Z Down The Columns, right?
If I was to transpose that Matrix
I would get this.
Right, I mean all I'm doing is exactly on the diagonal stays unchanged
but in each case, the, the two pieces of what was their swap, right?
So in, you know, and I'll do it out just in case, it's not clear
enough I guess, XX, XY XZ y, XY.
Y YZ ZX z y.
ZZ if I transpose this Matrix I just get it.
You know these swap these swap these swap, right?
I'm just flipping the indices of the things transfers like we've done
many times before XX.
XY, XZ, y XY, y YZ, Z XZ, y ZZ
Right.
It does exactly this this operation, the transpose flips, the rows and
columns and produces the The Matrix with them in the other location,
right?
When the other sort of Orient, I don't know what the right way to say
it.
Is it takes the columns things that we're going columnar and makes
them go row, right?
So what do we know about that sort of transpose thing?
Way back.
When on handmade hero, you have to do a deep dig here and go back and
watch that episode.
We said that for an orthogonal Matrix
The inverse is the transpose.
And we spent like a whole episode or two trying to show, how that was
true.
When we went through a bunch of different things where we tried to
kind of like demonstrate ways in that in which, that worked, right?
Well, here we get finally to how this stuff is actually working
internally, right when we look at what actually happens here.
The camera transform in the object, transform our, the opposite type
of transfer, right?
We end up in a situation where we take a camera and we move it from,
you know, a camera transform of the thing that moves something from
World space back into like, sort of an Origins system for the axes and
the opposite.
Juvenile transfer May takes things from a place where they're defined
around the origin and the axis system, basic Essence and moves them to
a different axis system and different origin, right?
And the only difference between those two
Is whether we put things in the column, or whether you put things in
the road, the reason for that is specifically that we are inverting
the transform.
That's what we're actually doing here, right?
And we're inverting the transform.
By transposing it because hey these happen to be unit axes that I was
talking about there, right?
That dot product thing, only works if these things are unit, actually,
if they're not there's an inverse thing that has to happen with
scaling and it's not worth us going into that right now, but it can
structure continues the further you dive into it.
It's not arbitrary.
So when you actually happen to have a bunch of unit actually, sir, and
you flip them like that, you actually get the opposite transform,
which is exactly what we see when we put things into rows or into.
Eames right.
A math actually works out very deeply in this way.
It actually the structure follows all the way through and it keeps
going even if you start talking about things where you have shear and
scale and stuff like that, it just becomes more complicated than
simply transposing.
There's more to the inverse and there's more to that but that's
basically what it is.
So the reason that this happens to work is actually because inverting
a transform is by definition solving, the equations that lead to this,
right?
If I have an object transform and I do the inverse of the Matrix which
is something we haven't really covered in much depth.
If I do the inverse of the Matrix, I get the opposite transform,
that's what inverse means.
It's the thing that would take the result of the previous transform
and turn it back into the original input, right?
You know.
If I have P Prime equals AP write the inverse of the Matrix is the
thing that would have done the opposite operation.
If we start with a point and we multiplied by a matrix and get a
result if we inverted that Matrix we could multiply by the result and
get back the input, right?
Well in this case, all we're doing is taking advantage of in some
sense.
The fact that a inverse equals a transpose.
In the case where we have nice unit axes, that me,
Eat at right angles like we do in the case of what we're working with
right?
And so because of that, it just so happens that the inverse transform.
Therefore is very easy to conceptualize and use.
All we have to do is go from putting things in columns to putting them
in rows because the transform is the inverse.
It is the inverse operation in this limited case.
That is not important to understand for the purposes of what we're
doing.
But for people who want to dig deeper into the math and get more
acquainted with linear algebra, just thought I'd point that out as an
interesting Avenue to look down and understand all.
We really care about in handmade hero is the fundamental activity,
which I just showed, which is that we want a bunch of dot products and
putting things in the Roses.
What gets us those dot products, right?
Okay.
So now let's put it all together.
What we want to do is we want some rotations, right?
We've got a rotation Matrix.
We've got a rotation Matrix around X, right?
Around why, whatever?
So we've got some rotations that we might want to do to the camera.
Right?
We want to do something where we're saying like Okay let's apply
rotation zero, that's a private station one, maybe even rotation to, I
don't know.
I think we're probably only going to have two rotations, right?
And then we want to take those rotations.
We probably want a translation as well, right?
And we want to
Combining these.
So let's talk about how we're going to actually do this.
All right, so we've got a situation where we've structured our world
so that this is the Z axis that comes out of the plane, right?
And then we've got sort of our x-axis, and our y-axis, look like this,
right?
And the camera kind of looks down on the world, right?
By default.
So that's what we're dealing with.
So what we want to do here is we would like to allow ourselves to
rotate this camera around.
Right?
We would like to have a way for us to produce a rotated version of
this camera with rotated.
Axes.
You know, I'm saying and we'd like to be able to produce multiple of
these rotations because what we might want to do is like rotate the
camera down to here but then also rotate it around, right?
So we would like to be able to orbit the camera around the world,
right?
So with this is typically called
We like to be able to orbit the camera around the world this way and
end this way, right?
And this is I don't really know what you would call that specifically
this.
I think this one's awesome called Azimuth but don't know what you call
this one.
Typically because we're kind of, we're rotating around it, right?
And all this time we want to be looking kind of in at the world,
right?
So we're trying to kind of have the camera, be able to spin around the
the world.
And always be looking kind of back at work at like this Focus point,
right?
Whatever the point in the world here is that you know where the center
of the room that were on, let's say we want to be able to spin it all
around and all around vertically as well.
We just want to be able to do that.
And, and get a view that matches that, right?
So what we need to do in order to do that is we need to produce two
things, right?
Because we just showed how we could, you know, how we can work through
the math for doing camera transfer, we need to produce two things.
First of all, we need to produce the axes of the camera.
Right?
Because we need to know what those are in order to produce the camera
transform.
So, wherever the camera ends up, we need to know where its axes are
and we know what those look like for any given point.
We have an idea of what we're trying to get here.
If this is the x y&z of the world, right?
And the camera is out here, we know that if the cameras looking this
direction, we know Z goes the opposite direction of that, right?
Because member Zee comes back at the camera in our traditional form.
So we know that Z comes back at it.
Why is pointing up right?
And X is pointing out to the side.
So we know that for any camera out here, that's viewing the world this
way.
You know, here's our I point looking out, we know that Z comes out at
us and we know that our X Y is like that sort of like if the director
holds up his hand like that, you know, that's our x y
That we're looking at.
So we know, we need to produce something like that.
So we need to produce those axes.
And then, we also need to produce the position, right?
So we need to be able to orbit our camera around and be able to
produce that that position as well, so that we can transform the world
to be around that, right to be centered around that.
So we need to do both of those things.
So, how do we do that?
Well, we can do.
All of this now with the transform stuff that we wrote and I think we
I don't think we wrote a vector transform so we're going to have to
probably just quickly go do that.
It's a much simpler case than the Matrix transform because it's just
doing one column basically, but we haven't written.
So we would have to write it.
Okay.
So bugging me stuck on the zipper.
So we can actually do all of this with what we wrote relatively easily
because we know where the camera starts, right?
We know that the camera starts up here here at Loops.
I don't know why.
That was why supposed to be easy?
We are the camera starts up here.
The z-axis points towards it and we know that sort of the the y-axis
and the x-axis are look like that, right?
So, what we could do if we wanted to, we know this point we know that
it's just X and Y 0, right?
We know it's zero zero and then it's however, far the camera is off of
zero.
It's our high up the cameras, right?
So it's just the height of the camera.
So we know how to start out where we are.
So then to rotate it around all we would have to really do is build a
rotation Matrix, right?
And apply that rotation Matrix to the point.
Once we have a rotation Matrix we can rotate it.
And so if we want to do for example let's say we want to do an extra
Tatian so that would pitch us up and down, right?
Maybe the mouse pitch is up and down so we can lean this way, right?
That is just going to be a rotation about the x axis so we can have
One Theta that's like an X axis rotation.
And we can produce that Matrix we can take this point.
This is the camera point to start with, right?
That's our point.
And we can apply that X rotation Matrix to the point that would rotate
the the point around and we would get the new location of the camera.
Right.
Furthermore, we know what the cameras axes are.
We know the cameras axes are just the basic axes there.
Just z y and x, right?
The cameras axes are aligned with the the world axis, right?
So if we want to know what those camera axes are, when we do the
rotation, we can do the same thing to the axes, right?
So we could take the cameras axes and multiply each of them, but hey,
the camera is actually is just the identity Matrix, right?
It's just 1 0, 0, 0, 1 0 0 0 1.
So, really the axis of the camera are just the Matrix, right?
It's just, hey, what is that camera Matrix?
Well, it's the rotation Matrix times, the starting camera Matrix, this
is the identity Matrix.
It doesn't have any rotation in it.
It's just straight up and down, right?
so, this term goes away and this is just RX
Right.
So we know that what we produce for our transformation is also is the
axes.
If we know what the axes are, then we can directly put those axes
into our into our Matrix and produce the dot products that we wanted,
right?
Okay.
so,
I feel like I've thrown a lot at you here and I do apologize for that
but we've got one last thing to cover before we can type in the code.
Hopefully all of that made sense and hopefully it's clear what we
would do here, right?
But we have one more problem.
And that is combining.
Translation.
And rotation.
In camera transforms.
Right?
So this gets a little trickier.
Why is it get a little trickier?
Well look what happens when we multiply our matrix by a point with
translation?
We get.
What I've said many times before.
We get a result that is p x times X Plus p y times y plus p z times Z
Plus t.
Okay.
That's what we get.
If we want to make this a camera transform, like we said before, it's
fairly straightforward.
What happens with our axes?
We just flip them around.
and we get the measure that we wanted, we get
X transpose p.
Y transpose p, z transpose P.
Plus t.
Right?
And that's exactly the measure we wanted.
Problem is
Do you see the problem?
You see the problem, maybe, you don't see the problem.
You probably don't see the problem because you've never looked at this
stuff before, and it's pretty hard to see problems.
We've never looked at stuff before.
This is the problem, the problem is in both cases, the translation
component is just add it at the end.
Why?
Because it's the same transfer, right again, when we look at these
things differently, we're like, well, we can stuff some stuff in here
and get a different conceptual result.
It's still a matrix, multiply the end of the day, it's still only
does.
Thing.
And we can conceptualize that thing in different ways to learn how to
construct, matrices that do things we want.
But at the end of the day, the math isn't changing underneath.
And what we know is that the translation always gets out at the end.
So the question is for a camera transform?
What does the translation have to be?
We would like it to be the negative of the camera position, wouldn't
we?
Because just like in the object transform, we put the object's
position.
And here and it places things out in the world.
We would love to have this be the cameras position, right?
And we could just set it to be negative and then it would be 0
subtract the camera position.
Great.
Right?
Not great.
Why is it not great?
Because the thing we wanted was the opposite of this transform.
And by doing the opposite of this transform, what we would have needed
to have done, right?
Is we would have needed to have subtracted.
Before we took the measure.
So, what we really wanted was X transpose P - camera.
Y transpose P - camera position, right?
Z transpose P - camera position.
That's what we wanted.
We wanted
If we have this right, I'll draw that picture again.
Here's the camera, here is the point, the axis of the world look like
this.
And maybe they're out here, right?
What we wanted to do was we wanted to measure this point from the
origin, which we said, was at the camera right along the axes along
these axes.
That's what we were trying to do.
But what this is going to do, right?
What this transforms going to do is it's going to measure them along
the axes before.
This becomes the
In.
So this is going to be the origin prior to
You know, before we do that subtraction, this is going to be the
origin, right?
So what we're really going to do is we're going to measure it along
this axis.
So rather than getting the distance here we're actually going to get
the distance here.
Right.
It's not what we wanted, right?
It's a problem because while it's correct in terms of the rotation
it's going to do which is fine, right?
The rotation will come out uncorrected but the position will all be
wrong because it's measuring around the wrong origin.
So the question is, how do we turn this into this, right?
How do we make that happen?
Well, lucky for us.
The dot product is distributive.
It's a Distributive operator, right?
It's just scalar so we can actually turn this into an equation.
That's easier to work with.
This can actually be turned into X transpose.
P, minus X transpose, c.
Y, transpose P.
Minus the Y transpose.
C z.
Transpose P.
Minus Z.
Transpose P c--.
Write this.
Is this, right?
These are the same equation.
I just distributed this out, so if we have to shoehorn our transform
into this actually, not so bad.
This is this Vector.
So, this Vector simply has to equal this, which means that all we have
to do to construct this Matrix is stuff into the T component, the
cameras position, pre negated, and Dot product ID with our
Maxi's right.
And hey, what is this?
Well, it's just the Matrix time.
See
Right?
It's just the Matrix times C.
So all we really need to do is first transform the camera position by
The Matrix and negate it stuff that into the transform.
And then when we multiply the point by this composite transform, it
will produce the residual terms we needed to make ourselves compute
this instead of this
Does that make sense?
Hopefully, it makes some sense.
So we need to do that or our positions will come out wrong.
So let's take a look at how we build that.
Right.
Let's take a look at how we build the camera transform.
So let's say I've got a in line here.
I'm going to do, I don't know why it's in line actually.
And I want to build a camera transform the way I want to build that
camera transform is.
I want to assume that I'm going to have a set of axes that I'm going
to use and I
Going to have a position that I want to use, right?
And I want to produce the 4x4 that does that.
So I'm going to have the x axis.
I'm going to have the y-axis from going to the Z axis and I'm going to
have the position.
How would I construct this?
Well, first I can construct my, my axes and in fact, you know, I might
make this because we're probably going to want this as well, which is,
we can do columns, 3 by 3.
And Rose 3 by 3.
Where I just pass in.
In both cases, what I want the access to be, and then we can produce
the column version or the row version of that Matrix.
So again, in this case, we just produce the result here,
In this case, it's just the column picture.
So again I'm just well here I'll do it out this way so it's a little
clearer for you.
I need some way of hinting to for coder, but doesn't need to do that.
There we go.
One extra, we go.
So again, I'm just putting these in in column order.
As you can see, exactly, like we wrote the math on the Blackboard.
And hope that you can see that looks really clean.
It's just the X down.
X-axis goes down the column.
First Column.
Y goes down.
The second Z goes down the third, right?
And then, we just kind of return that as our column Matrix
same thing with rose 3 by 3,
All we're going to do.
Here is reverse that, right?
So in this case, I'm going to do XY XZ on the columns y x by y YZ ZX z
y.
ZZ
And there's the row picture.
Right?
Okay so what I know
For producing this camera, transform is all.
I really need to do is I need to stuff these into the columns, right?
So I know that I start with the rose 3x3 picture where I just put
those in.
Now, I've got a matrix that does nothing other than just undo the
rotation implied by those X Y and Z axes.
So, it's the rotation part of the camera transform, but it doesn't do
the position yet.
Right.
So, like I said, what we need to do is we need to produce
for our Vector weird.
My there was, here we go.
I need to produce the negated
Its form of this so that I can stuff that into the translation
component, right?
And in order to do that, I need to multiply the position by The Matrix
itself.
So I need to do like R times P right to produce a new vector.
And again, I want to negate that as well.
So this is the like camera P.
We're going to use put that in there and furthermore, I probably want
the ability to do something like this.
Right, where I can just set the translation components component of a
matrix.
And go from there.
Now, the other thing that I could probably do here, I guess, I don't
know how I want to do it.
It depends how I want to do this.
I haven't really thought about it yet, but maybe maybe set
translations a bad word in this case.
Maybe maybe I'll just say Translate.
But that something not sure.
I haven't decided exactly how I want to do that.
Haven't thought about it much but you know, if I have something like
this where I say, I've got a matrix a and I want to do a translation
of it.
The result again is just a and then for the components of the result,
I just want to be able to say
Like the terms, get get added here, right?
So I'm just modifying that final part.
This part right here, I want to put the translation in there.
Okay.
So for my camera transform, all I really want to do is I just want to
be able to set the translation in the column which is currently
nothing.
I want to set that to be equal to the negative of the transform of the
incoming point that I'm given by by The Matrix itself right to produce
that residual term that I need to correct for.
So the only thing I don't have to make that work is I just need some
way of multiplying a vector times The Matrix, which right now I don't
Have.
But, like I said, these are actually exactly the same operation.
If I have only a V3 here, right?
Where I don't actually have a matrix, I've just got a point then I can
produce that result pretty easily as well.
All I have to do here in this case is produce those dot products, and
I can assume like I was doing before that the, the component in the W
component of my Vector is 1.
And I can just make that in here when Sophie three because I know it
would be one.
But the other thing I can do and I often like to write it this way, is
allow the person who's passing it in to specify the W in case for some
reason, they wanted a different W.
So in most cases it's 1.0 but in other cases we could make the W
coordinate be something different right?
And so again for this
Matricide location.
We do exactly the same thing we were doing before.
Only in this case, we don't have to have one of the four.
I Loops we just do the contraction as it regularly is written and in
this case we probably want to write it out longhand because we're
going to be using the the W specifically here, right?
So in this case, I've got this are, I know that I can produce the RX
by taking the the PX times.
The PX times the the first element of the Matrix, right?
And then again, we're going across the columns of the Matrix in this
point at this.
In this case, we're going down the rows of the point and across the
columns.
Oops, I missed one here, like so.
And then again,
And then finally got that W coordinate and you know this is all that
PW.
Right.
And this is just something that, you know, we would have a w result.
But in this case, we're not going to return that W result because
we're just doing it for a vector.
So we end up with just these equations and again,
They are exactly the same the whole way down just we use a different
row of a each time.
Again this is exactly like we did it on the Blackboard.
It's just the you know that standard contraction of the point XYZ
Point XYZ and in this case we continue to the W which were specifying
manually, x, y, z, w, x, y, z, w, and off we go.
Now, the problem here is that if I use this as an operator star, I
can't specify any additional parameters here, because operator star is
just written in C like this.
And there's
Way to provide an external an additional option to it.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to make that be sort of a special
case operation there.
which is just to say that the result equals
You know, the transform.
Where we do a times p with 1.0.
and then, I'm going to make this
Be a function you can just call.
So if you do want to specify the W coordinate you can if you don't
want to specify the W coordinate you don't have to, it'll either be
defaulted to 1.0 in that case, or it'll always default to 1.0 if you
call it with operator Star, right?
so,
In this case, we've got a slight problem here, which is that even
though this is the way we would notate it in math, we don't have a
negation operator for a matrix.
It would work if we wanted to I suppose.
But I you know we really just want to tell it.
Hey, multiply this first.
If you could don't apply, the negation operator first and that solves
that problem.
All right.
I'm not 100% sure.
Why that
I'm not super clear on why it couldn't figure out how to do that, to
be honest with you, that seems busted to me.
Like, it should have been able to figure out that that got applied
afterward, but somehow it didn't and I'm not sure why.
That seems really suspicious.
Do I have something to find wrong.
I don't know.
So I'm wondering about that I guess I don't remember how you Nuri -
binds two things.
Maybe you know re- binds before multiplication and I guess it must
because that's what we're seeing here, right?
The parser is choosing to bind the - to the are rather than the r
times p.
But you know, what do you do?
Anyway, so that's a thing that creates the camera transform.
And at that point, we actually have a transform.
We can send down to opengl because that is actually the camera
transform.
We could use to transform the World by wherever we wanted to transform
the world, right?
We can do anything, we want there and similarly if we want to we can
also take a look at this.
At these matrices and some other ways.
If we want to we can extract vectors from these matrices, right?
If we want to, you can imagine a doing something like this where we
could pass a matrix in and we could get a result out of it, where we
just said like, okay I want to get out a column of a
And we can make that be an index as well.
so we could say oh yeah, which one
Let's see.
And the same would be true of rows.
So if we want to extract either these things from a matrix, we can
That as well.
And this is fairly typical when you make little math libraries like
this.
We're writing this, mostly not for performance, right?
We're writing this math.
This is more for utility.
It's just to be flexible and easy-to-use largely because we don't
expect to use it.
So heavily that we would end up in a situation where we cared about
lots of little issues like that.
But yeah you can start to see it sort of come together, and this is
how this sort of thing, typically works, right?
So now we have the ability to specify this stuff.
Oops.
Yeah.
And once we have the ability to specify the stuff we can actually use
it now in our opengl system and there's a little bit that we have to
do here.
You can kind of see.
I'll show you in a second.
You can see right now
The way that we're setting up our projection matrices is we're
actually just sort of specifying a focal length and we're having the
GL system, create the Matrix on the fly when it goes to process things
that are used by things that sort of fall under that transform.
But what we would like to do now.
For rather obvious reasons I think is we'd like to go ahead and expand
this transform to say hey why don't we just have the clip rect specify
the 4x4 itself, right?
Like why don't we just have before by four?
Passed down by the cliprect so that we can start to pack our whole
camera, transform right in there, you know what I mean?
So that we don't have to do any of this stuff, right?
That we can pack all this stuff in and not have to do the transfers
ourselves, right?
So let's go ahead and make that change and I think we may be out of
time and so we've built all the stuff we need and tomorrow we can just
play around with getting the camera orbiting and working in.
That'll be a good, that'll be a good accomplishment for the weekend.
I think.
Given how much mass stuff we had to cover.
All right, so let's go take a look at how that works inside render
group, right?
We have this sort of concept where we're pushing on the clip Rex and
we pass the focal length.
So when we do our push cliprect here,
you can see that happening.
See here, there it is.
You can see it takes the focal length of the final parameter.
And in this case, what we'd like to do, let's just take a look at the
baby step of rather than recording the focal length.
Right.
What we could do instead is we can try to put this whole thing.
In here.
Right?
So the only part that will save on the outside is the transpose
because the fact that we have to transpose it is strictly because of
the opengl fixed function pipeline which will probably get rid of
eventually anyway.
And even if we didn't get rid of it, there is an extended function we
can call called Geo load transpose Matrix which would take it in the
correct order, the math order that we have it stored in right now.
So we know what this safe ratio is, right?
Because it's the same thing.
We've got the width and height here, we can just do the / them produce
the safe ratio.
We know what the focal length is because someone's passing that into
us.
So, rather than store it here, I'm just going to go ahead and say,
rekt dot transform, maybe maybe we'll still just call it project
equals projection BC.
And that's it.
So then we come out here.
We would just say, okay, the clip projection Matrix?
Our projection Matrix is that we need to feed to opengl is just loops.
It's just the transpose of that.
That's what I was trying to do.
Yeah.
And this stuff goes away.
So then the only thing that we have to do now is just have it replace
that focal length that we were specifying before.
Although, I don't know where that went.
Where is our clip brick structure?
There it is.
So here, when we push on our clip, rect instead of pushing on this the
focal length, we now push on the transform itself.
Okay, so hey good.
We got the same thing we were getting before.
That's exactly what we wanted because now we've got sort of that
ability to specify the entire transform and, you know, I guess we
could at this point if we wanted to since we've got just a few seconds
left, we could just throw some Saucy, Saucy Unison here, if we wanted
to, and take a look at where this is actually been called from
But take a look.
Here it is.
So we're passing the camera transfer and focal length here.
What we could do again is just passed some more robust transform here.
In fact, we could make it so that we pass the whole transform down,
and then we could produce inside this camera, transform the actual
transfer that we're trying to use and pass that down, that might be
the right thing to do.
I'm not sure how many places call this.
In fact, it looks
Almost nobody does call.
It cutscenes should have called it, but I guess it doesn't because it
just uses the debug one.
Is that true?
Is there a reason, our cutscene doesn't call Pushbullet brush?
How does it set the focal length?
So we've just got it so that inside here you call prospective, and it
calls set camera transform, which itself pushes the clip.
Rect
There you go.
So we kind of want to, you know, at this point we probably want to go
ahead and disentangle these little bit.
So I am going to stop here for today because I think we want to go
ahead and do that tomorrow.
I'm going to go to the head.
Go ahead and go to the Q&A, but we're at least set up for it.
And we're going to want to do a little more fussing here.
I think, with this pretty soon, because we want to disentangle this
now that we've got a pretty clear way of setting that camera
transform.
I think we want to clean up how that's being called in the exterior
code.
Let's see.
Can you interpolate if you wanted a smooth rotation about a point or
axis over time?
You can.
But again, interpolation is sort of a separate Topic in terms of how
you want to go about doing that.
So if you want to interpolate rotations, you have a number of ways of
doing it.
If your rotations are coming from angles, for example, then you can
obviously smoothly.
Relate those angles, right?
And if you want to interpolate those angles, then you can just produce
whatever you want to produce from them.
They can just be smoothly, interpolated right?
If you don't want to do that and you just have to you know you just
have two matrices that you need to construct.
and you need to interpolate between those, then you're kind of in the
whole world of angular interview,
In which is where quaternions come in.
Where all those sorts of things come in, those become more difficult
topics to talk about.
Because that's when you start to have to deal with all of the problems
that are inherent with rotation.
And fortunately, on handmade here, I don't think we really have to
deal with most of that stuff, but it's kind of a topic unto itself,
right?
If that makes sense.
Let's see.
Gary, Johansson there have been some problems with trolls causing
flame wars in the chat.
I forget who dedicate the manager of the trap to.
Oh yes.
If you want a moderated chat, you can actually go to the moderated
chat.
It is on the handmade Network server.
You can go there, it's handmade networks, IRC server and
I'll show you how to do that now.
So this is handmade networks IRC server.
And you saw how I got to there.
You can just put handmade Network RC in there and so if you want a
moderated chat, you can go here and and they maintain a moderated chat
for you to use and that's yeah, there's 44 people on the moderated
chat right now.
In fact.
Mention about six months ago, I think that you have new artwork.
What's the plan with adding that?
I'd probably right after we don't the 3D stuff.
I just wanted to kind of show how to make that modification to the
pipeline if that makes sense.
Did you know beforehand that you're going to discard the Sorting code?
Did you do all that for the sake of teaching a variety of techniques?
Well, yes and no.
I mean no I didn't know beforehand that I was going to discard the
Sorting code, but I sort of, like I said, I try to structure the
Stream So that we actually go through each constructive process of
like, you know,
I didn't think there was any point.
Let me put it this way in just me knowing exactly how I want to do
everything and just doing it that way, because that's not really very
useful.
Programming wise, I was trying to show how you, you know, keep pretty
flexible code and you can modify the code and change your decisions
and re-evaluate decisions stuff like that was very important.
So I didn't know ahead of time going into it, which things I would
decide that I wanted to do differently from how I actually did it.
But what I wanted to do was show some number of those through the
course of the stream.
And I was just fairly certain that since normally I program 3D games.
And I'm programming 2D game here for handmade hero.
I assumed that, you know, they would naturally come up, right?
So, you know, that's that's just that's just what I wanted.
The stream to be about.
You know, I wanted to show how actual programming goes not, here is
just how to type in a bunch of code.
I already know how to write or whatever I wanted to show.
Like, oh, well, let me try this as solution.
Okay, didn't like that for these reasons.
Let's revisit it and so on.
See if there's any other questions that I missed.
You think so?
All right, if there are no other questions than I, guess we can close
the stream for the day.
Do I know anything about direct x 12?
Yeah, I mean, so DirectX.
12 is not something that I looked at for itself.
Very explicitly Vulcan obviously I know a lot more about because I was
on The Advisory board for it and, you know, they're very similar but
I've never really bothered with DirectX 12.
Because I don't really know that I'm ever going to care about the
distinction between Vulcan and DirectX, 12, we'll see.
How it shakes out?
It could be that DirectX.
12 becomes somewhat of a necessity on Windows if you know, for
whatever reason, Microsoft, you know, PESA mises, Vulcan in some way
or whatever else happens, you know, small things like that have
happened in the past where there's a reason to use say DirectX on
Windows, even if you use opengl everywhere else or, you know, that
sort of thing because it is the one that's maybe more specifically.
It's the one that's more specifically supported by Microsoft, so I'd
say.
But assuming that, you know, Vulcan is competitive in terms of
compatibility and supports on Windows, then I don't really see any
reason to use direct x 12.
It's basically just doing the same things that Vulcan does, but it's
doing them in a way that you can't share code with our anywhere else,
right?
so,
When are you going to do?
Whoop, I don't program a new penny more.
Obviously, I used to a long time ago, I guess probably.
Last time I do programming with maybe 2001 roughly, maybe 2,000 or so,
but I don't find it to be very good and so I tend to not use really
any object oriented programming traditional patterns.
I guess I would say, although, sometimes you end up with things where,
you know, the the object-oriented version of something and the
procedural
Something that isn't explicitly trying to be object-oriented,
sometimes they have similar aspects to them.
Obviously, depending on how you choose to isolate things that make
sense.
If I ever heard of design patterns?
Yes, of course, I've heard of design patterns.
I even read the first book.
That was called design patterns.
It's not a very good book, unfortunately.
Try unit testing your code.
So we can actually see if something is working.
So unit, testing is obviously something that's useful in specific
circumstances where you actually have a specific defined test that you
want to verify and that you don't feel like you can verify some other
way.
So sometimes it's useful, sometimes, it's not in games, it's often
times not a very good idea to rely on unit testing and the reason that
it's a good idea, not to rely on you testing, it's because most of
your bugs happen in non unit.
Rio's, most complicated bugs in game.
Are not unit testable.
And so, you know, unit testing is something you can use.
Like, for example, if I wanted to make sure that the math code, we
just typed in is working properly.
I can write a unit test for it and verify that it is and that's a
perfectly reasonable thing to do.
If you don't think that you are able to debug those problems in
progress in any other way.
However, if you can, to bug them in other ways, then you're wasting
your time by writing unit tests, because the only benefit to unit
tests is
If they will save time, right?
There's no other point to them.
Because if you write unit tests and you don't catch bugs in the unit
tests any faster than you would have caught them in the wild, then
basically you just spent a lot of time writing code that no one used,
you know, so like everything else unit tests have their place and I
use them when they're appropriate and in this case, they're not useful
to what we're doing at the moment, but if they were then we would use
them.
With the Molly rocket team be at Emerald City ComiCon, this year,
possibly storing tortoise in terms of profiling.
How would you tell when you were hitting upper bounds of CPU, PCI, bus
and GPU?
Obviously, we already have a CPU, profiler wondering more about PCI
bus and GPU.
Well, so,
There's a couple things that you have to do sort of as Baseline, but
to get just a rough picture.
You actually can see the GPU PCI bus stuff fairly straightforwardly to
get sort of a high-level picture of it by using a GPU, profiler of
which there are many.
So for example, you can use n cite that Nvidia ships which is a tool
that's pretty decent and you can see timeline
Use that show you where the CPU is waiting on the GPU and, and vice
versa.
And so if you go and take a look at a tool like that, you can get a
sort of high-level picture of those problems, but obviously I would
say that, you know, that's for the basic process.
If what you're trying to do is get super aggressive and maximize every
last little thing then there's all sorts of additional stuff you
probably have to look at and it's a pretty complicated problem
involves a lot of experimentation and that sort of thing.
But if you're just trying to get reasonable you know you're trying to
make sure that you're doing a reasonable job, scheduling things across
the PCI bus that will tell you what you need to know.
so,
Zen Mystic, we use Vulcan in your game at all.
Will it still be two new on release or do some kind of tutorial on it?
I don't know.
I couldn't tell you.
I don't love Vulcan like I said it, I don't love the design but you
know, it is what it is.
So I'm not super excited to show how to use it because it's like, you
know, it's a little disappointing, but you know who knows we will use
opengl for the time being because our game will run plenty fast.
On opengl since it is a 2-D game and we're not trying to micromanage
memory usage and stuff like this, which is, you know, micromanaging
overlap, and transfer and locking and memory and all that sort of
stuff is, obviously the place where you start to really want the kind
of manual stuff that you need either from Vulcan or DirectX, 12, or
opengl, 4.5 a zdo.
Which, you know, we could go that route as well, which is basically
extensions to opengl, which allow you to
Do a lot of the same sorts of stuff you do in Vulcan, and so, you
know, will we need to doing that stuff?
No.
Might we show how to do some of it at some point because it's just
useful for educational purposes.
Maybe but doing a whole Vulcan Port doesn't seem like maybe a very
good use of time because most of, that's just minutiae that's about
how Vulcan works and I'm not sure that that's the most productive
tutorial link time.
Frank do you think writing my own ring zero driver would bypass VA see
you're talking about a ring 0 driver for what windows?
I mean, yeah.
If
Here's the thing, right?
It used to be that ring.
Zero was Ring zero.
So if you wrote something at ring zero you could do anything that you
wanted but the reality is that's not true anymore, right ring?
Zero is not the lowest level of access, you know, there's ring - one,
there's ring - to now, right.
There's I don't do operating systems programming.
So I don't even keep track of the crazy ring, this of it all.
But when they decided to go to hypervisors,
And VMS and all these sorts of things and that became a very
important, you know, segment of the market ring zero kind of went out
the window.
So I mean,
you know, if you're talking about writing a ring 0 driver for
something, it gives you certain, you know, it gives you certain
privileges that you certainly don't have when you're not in ring 0.
But at
Same time, increasingly and I don't even keep up with this in Windows.
Obviously, there's tons of things that are unbiased passable even at
ring zero, right?
Because just from a security standpoint, you know, ring zero isn't
doesn't get full access to the machine anymore and there's there's,
you know, layers below that that you know, are not going to be are not
going to going to be by passable to you.
Just because you're at ring zero.
Without an exploit.
Soaring tortoise.
Is there any way to do that from our own code or do we have to rely on
external tools?
So, you're talking about the GPU profiler.
There are some ways you can do that, but it largely depends on the
circumstance.
So if you're talking about with opengl, oops, that's not as high as
well.
That you can actually get a couple of different things.
Timer query, I think is what it's called.
Here we go.
So you can do some stuff here where you can insert things into the
stream and you can look at the timestamps and and and get other piece
of information back and then there might be some counters, you can get
from Nvidia.
I can't remember all of these there are ones.
You can get, let me put it to you that way.
That's who we got here.
So, you can see these ones for the AMD that are being exposed here for
the parentheses, your mileage may vary, right?
Obviously, if you so what happens when you install something like n
site is it actually Institute turns on like debug features of the
driver that you want to use and, you know, to what extent?
You can turn those on yourself.
I'm not sure.
I usually just use a tool for those purposes when I need to do it.
So I've
Look to see whether you can actually get all the same stuff you get
from nsight.
So I don't know.
Right.
Probably, you can get a lot of that stuff yourself.
The reason I say that is because there's a fair bit of, of third-party
tool Edge, which, which does do stuff like performance analysis.
So, I'm assuming that stuff is exposed in ways that it
Maybe manufacturer-specific but are still exposed.
So I guess that's what I would say.
Graham says near the beginning of the stream.
The back of my chair fell off.
I spent the entire stream fixing my chair.
It feels more solid now and squeaks less but I'm afraid to lean back
on it.
Yeah well you know I mean it depends how confident you are in your
past job man.
Like maybe you did a really good job and you can lean back on it or
maybe not.
Sorry, interests.
Not sure if anyone has mentioned this, but Mac OS, X doesn't support
opengl core profile with opengl one point x functions.
This means that if using Geo begin at center of the max version of Geo
allowed is 2.1.
Yeah.
And you know, since we decided to do actual 3D, you know, and uses
ibuffer stuff instead of doing mostly just software rendering and then
the opengl equivalent of software rendering, right?
We'll probably
Actually moved off the fixed function pipeline because the fixed
function pipeline is ancient.
It's not used anymore by anybody except in circumstances, like, what
I'm doing here to just show how to do stuff without having to dive
into really, like more specific things that are necessary to given
time.
So, you know, we'll probably end up with an opengl three-point X, you
know, situation in the, in the opengl back end, by the time we're done
with this, which is not much
Right.
Looks like we've got no more questions so I think we are done so
that's good.
Made here, can you name one of those exploits for my driver?
Aha, well, so probably not that exist at the moment, right there used
to be some
Exploits to get past to get past the the ring - one protections but
you know they get fixed very rapidly security.
Researchers are constantly finding them and then people, you know,
patch them.
So the best one that I saw was that there was that one that they use
the Aperture map.
To there was the old memory, the memory aperture mapping thing that
they use to to bypass the protections.
I don't remember.
if I don't know, if I can find it,
let's see.
I think this might be it.
Just is there a link to the I just want the video.
Yes, this is it this is the one that I remember being super awesome.
If you're interested in these sorts of exploits, obviously if you want
to actually do an exploit that bypasses everything, you've got to have
like a zero-day exploit, right?
If security researchers know about it already, then they've patched.
The operating system and everything else.
So those exploits are not relevant anymore, but if you're just
interested in them from, which I think they're very interesting, I
never do this kind of work.
So it's very interesting to me to see what kinds of stuff people have
to come up with, to find these crazy exploits.
This apic overlay, it Maps, this aperture.
This memory access aperture in, in a way that chips have always done
on the x86 and they figured out a way to use it.
To get to ring - 2 and its really great.
I would highly recommend watching the video
because he does a great job explaining it to.
Here it is.
I would highly recommend watching this video.
It's really, really cool.
And it shows an example of how these kind of exploits take shape.
This is an amazing one.
There's probably lots of them if you follow blackhat stuff.
Probably lots of them, I don't.
So I only know of the ones that were particularly amusing that people
kind of passed around.
So,
can you give Sean M and Sean B's streams a plug before you go please
certainly I can for those of you who are looking for more programming
action
I'll go ahead and bring those up for you.
Here we go.
Ah, my goodness.
This is all getting crazy.
Okay, let's get that one.
Just feel that, right?
We go.
That's the, that's not what I want.
I want the twitch, I want the twitch people.
Because nothing's too, right?
Yeah.
I just happened to remember it.
All right, so what the person on the chat was asking is that I
mentioned these two other streams, there's two other programmers who
stream pretty often also Jonathan Blow stream obviously naysayer 88 is
another great one.
In fact we'll go ahead and bring that one up here.
So in terms of programming streams, this is Jonathan Blow stream.
I see made braid in the witness.
He often times shows work these doing on his own language and
compiler.
That's necessary idiot.
It's a great stream to follow nothing's too.
That's John Barrett, the guy who wrote the renderer for thief, the
Dark Project, hero Tiggy at Rod, game, tools and bunch of stuff.
He is programming like a voxel engine like, you know, like Minecraft
or that.
Whatever is showing how to write one of those and that's heat streams
that nothing's to on Twitch.
And then Sean McGrath retina Mobic, he's the guy who wrote em plus
plus has engine and also the whole thing for dyad among a bunch of
other stuff and he often streams development of his MOBA on the SS
McGrath twitch Channel.
So that was all that.
The the person on the stream was talking about.
And hopefully that's, that's good.
All right?
All right.
We're down to the last question down to the ask questions.
Would have ring zero driver Bap.
Bypass the anti-cheat protection of Destiny.
I've never looked at the anti-cheat protection for Destiny.
I don't even think you would need a ring 0 driver for the anti-cheat
protection of Destiny.
Unless they have a ring zero driver, which maybe they do.
I don't know, I've never looked that, I've never even played Destiny,
so I don't even have an instant and I'm gonna have it installed
version of Destiny.
But I'll be honest with you, I thought Destiny was only on consoles.
Can you get a PC version of Destiny?
Yeah.
Like I mean, what are you even talking about?
Because
I'm not sure I get how this would help you until Destiny 2.
There is no PC version, right?
I don't know, I don't play Destiny so I couldn't tell you but I didn't
think there was a PC version of Destiny.
So I'm not sure how you would be bypassing anti-cheat on something
that doesn't exist.
Okay.
Insofar as says that Sean and Sean, the to Sean's, I just mentioned
are doing a specific stream today and he posted the Twitter link to
it.
I did not know about that stream.
So, I guess it says that it'll be live on Twitch in about a half an
hour and that was posted at 12:30.
So I guess at 1 p.m.
that would start, it doesn't say which channel it will be on.
So I guess, I don't know, but presumably one of those too.
How do I read the RAM memory on an Xbox or a PS4?
You have the weirdest questions.
These have almost nothing to do with game programming at all.
Probably be better served asking on a game cheat tutorial stream, but
the answer of how you read RAM memory on an Xbox or a PS4.
I'm assuming you mean, if you're not running on that system, and the
answer there is, you need, you know, like a logic analyzer is
something.
You mean, you know, I don't know if you've ever seen that, there's
people who create Hardware that you basically can attach to other
Hardware.
It is designed to scan it and see what it's doing.
And you don't want to go down that road, right?
Like that.
That's just
But you know, you can see, there's, there's if you want to see a
really great example of this.
I would highly recommend checking out again.
This is trying to remember some stream, some stuff that I saw a long
ago but there's a great scene where
Alto getting the alto running again.
This.
so, I don't know if this is
oh God, the browser has crashed.
Ladies and gentlemen.
It's all over.
well, I was trying to show you
I don't know if this is the one, this might not be the one, because
there was a YouTube do.
This looks like the one though.
I don't know where the YouTube video is.
They have a video of it, but this is a pretty fun one.
That's sort of a easier problem.
It's much older Hardware.
So it's easier to analyze, but it's really fun to watch them.
If you watch them trying to get this old Alto, obviously the alto is a
computer that from very, very, very long ago.
It was from Xerox, Parc the people who basically invented the
graphical user interface, it was their machine that they created and
there are still some that still work in existence and someone was
trying to take one and restore it to working order.
And of course that can be hard because chips can fail, things can
corrode context?
Get old components burn out and you have to refurbish them.
And so one of the things that you see a lot when they do this is they
put a lot of logic analyzer probes on various pins and then they have
Hardware that they can record all of the information going across
those pins and reverse engineer.
What's going wrong?
And it's really cool to watch.
And so that is kind of the
Way in which those sorts of things happen.
If you can't run on the machine and you need to analyze it, it's
really cool.
Strong interest.
I'm not sure if anyone has mentioned this, but in the cutscene shot,
six, layer 3 and 4 are both at Z equals 3.
Layer 3, should be it.
3.01.
Instead they are for is the child tears.
And layer 3 is the child.
Can you do want to?
Well, I was going to say we probably don't want to deal with that
right now, but I could try to put an issue in for that.
I guess the first thing I would ask those starring, tortoises.
Why do you think that's a problem?
That they're equaled.
Like storing tortoise.
Can is there a particular bug that you're seeing?
The tears are behind the child, so you can't see them.
So we should be able to just swap the order in which they're drawn
them though, right?
As well.
But there we go.
That way when we were cleaning out github's later on.
We can we can take a look at that.
All right.
Odessa who's got a question just at the end here, will the order of
matrix?
Multiplication be reversed if we use transpose, matrices and vectors
So I guess I'm not sure exactly what you're asking.
But I guess you're saying, well the conceptual order, if that makes
sense.
And so let me just draw this out and I'll see if I'm answering the
question that you're talking about.
I might not be because I'm not sure, I totally understand what you're
asking, but
So, what you can see, in this case, right is you've got AC b.
D are the vectors here, right?
So, in the case, where you're doing this transform, you end up with x
times, AC plus y times, BD
Right.
And this is the standard picture and now you're asking, if you used
everything transposed, I think it's what you're saying.
So if everything was transposed, then what ends up happening is, you
can see
That you run into a problem right away in terms of the order which I
am assuming, it's kind of what you were getting at.
But at this was transformed right transposed?
It would be like so,
And of course Straight Ahead matrix multiplication of the form that
we're doing, doesn't work when you have the wrong number of rows.
If the, if the number of rows of this doesn't match the number of
columns of this, which in this case it doesn't, right?
There's a missing row that we would need to form our products.
So we can't do that.
And we pretty much have to.
Do it this way, right?
And when we do it this way, what we see from our result, right?
Is that, when we do our multiplication, in this case, we get a b x y.
So X, plus b.
Y, as the first term of our vector and the second term over Vector.
Oops, that's it.
Hey, P.
And the second term of our Vector is CX.
Plus d, why?
Right.
And so you can see in this case, in terms of what we're producing,
it's actually still the same.
Product in a sense because you can see what the exes are multiplying
their multiplying AC so it's still ex-ac plus y, BD, which is the same
thing.
Right.
So
I don't know if this is what you were trying to get at, but your
intuition is correct that the reading of something multiplied, in this
order with column, vectors is the same as the reading of it in the
opposite order using row vectors.
Because as you can see, the row Vector ends up on the other side of
the Matrix, right?
And so, if you were to string them all together, you would get the
opposite order depending on which way you go.
Was that what you were asking?
Just used disused.
Just want to know if that answers the question.
That's what it's asking earlier, okay.
Yes, it's worth noting also that I think some people do do it that
way.
Math is pretty explicit about this sort of thing, and I wish suited
him 73 were here, he's not as you know, he is the, you know.
He's the expert on those sorts of things, but what I would point out
is is typically in math notation.
if you write something like this,
this is different.
Conceptually.
so, if
It's something as a column Vector people, typically consider this to
be different than.
If you write as a row Vector there, they're actually mathematically
different for obvious reasons, like we just sort of showed what way
they are, what way they end up getting X matrices and on which side
they are.
And there's these things called covariant and contravariant vectors.
You can see here and covariant and contravariant vectors are often
written in those opposite ways.
So oftentimes like you can see here you got a row Vector for a
covariant and a column Vector for a contravariant.
However, math people decided to do it because that's the way they
chose to organize the things originally, right?
Then that's how the math works out.
I don't go down the math Road very far.
As you know, I am not a mathematician, I'm a programmer and I know a
bunch of math because I have to know it to do my job but I'm not
excellent at it.
I'm not a math person.
There's a lot of programmers who are much better at math than I am.
And so, I won't try to give you some kind of an opinion about whether
it's more appropriate to wrote.
Write the equations, we're writing.
As column vectors or not, I simply go with the convention that most
well-respected math programmers, that I know choose to write their
points as column vectors and things.
Like normals are other kinds of by-product vectors are written as Rose
and so I do as well.
But I am not the kind of Saucy math person who really can claim to
have their own opinion about something like that because I'm just not
deep enough.
Into, you know, tense or mathematics or geometric algebra?
Any of these are the sorts of things where, you know, if you were real
expert in those things, you probably have strong opinions about these
sorts of decisions and how they go.
And so if you're somebody who feels like you want to know more about
that, I would highly recommend maybe digging deeper into the
literature there and going finding some more mathematically minded.
People who write about this sort of thing, so that you can form your
own opinion about it.
Don't listen to
Me on anything like that.
All right, folks, I'm going to wrap it up.
I will.
Because all this down.
Thank you everyone for joining me for this sort of handmade hero.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you would like to follow along at home, of course, you
can always pre-order the game, it does come with the source code.
And that's on handmade hero dot-org.
Also, there's a bunch of helpful links are, you can go to the forums
what you saw on today's stream actually that the handmade Network
folks.
Do, it's a great place to ask questions.
If you've got questions, we have a patreon page from support the video
series, we have a schedule bot.
If you want to win, the series is live, will tweet the schedule every
weekend and
We've got an episode guide for trying to catch up with old episodes.
That's about it for today.
I'll be back here tomorrow.
10:00 a.m.
same time, same place.
Hope to see everyone there for that until then have fun programming.
I'll see you guys on the internet.
Take it easy, everyone.