Hello everyone and welcome to handmade hero.
The show we could complete game live on stream.
We are in the middle of enabling our game to sort of work in 3D, not
really for any particular 3D reasons because it is a 2-D game.
But after going down the road of sprite sorting, I just decided that
it wouldn't really have the throughput that I was looking for even
though it was conceptually nice.
And so, I wanted to find a way to use the GPU more effectively.
Four more sort of heavy, heavy primitive counts and that sort of thing
that I thought we might want.
So I decided even though I had not really wanted to go down that road
particularly much because I was trying to keep things focused on 2D, I
decided to switch to 3D just so we could have that.
And so basically what we're doing right now is just finishing that
switch.
I want to talk a little something that I did last week because I
realized after the fact that we probably don't really need to worry
about it as much as I thought we were going to have to worry about it,
because I was kind of thinking about things.
In a way that I probably didn't really need to and I'll talk a little
bit about that in a second.
But let me first explain what I did at the end of the stream last time
today is day 366 so you're going to want to.
You want going to want to grab that day 365 out of the source like
archive.
If you want to follow along with what I'm doing, that is the code to
start with.
Let me go ahead and show you what I'm talking about.
So here is the build from last week and you can kind of see here that
what I'm doing is I'm just drawing.
These three Sprites so that they're always facing the camera.
And I did that kind of at the end of last dream and I wanted to talk
about a little bit of that just in a second here.
So let me let me give you a little bit of a explanation of what I did
because I kind of threw it in, at the end of last week's dream just to
say, oh, we could do it this way, and I never really talked about it.
So let me just talk about that really briefly, what I threw in there
because you notice I didn't really even do any math to do it.
I didn't have to write.
Blackboard, I just got typed it in in 10 seconds and it worked, fine.
So, you know, how did I do that?
What was that and why was it so easy or simple to do?
So let me go ahead and get some space here on the drawing board.
So, here's day 366.
And so, this is camera.
Facing.
Cards.
So, the deal with this is the camera facing cards are sort of what we
need to do in order for Sprites, not to lie down flat.
Now if you take a look at for example the ground the ground right now
is lying down flat, right?
You can kind of see that you know those even I don't have it.
Throw on them at the moment.
So it's hard to maybe relate them back to the trees per se, but those
are just filled areas that could be filled with the texture.
And they, you know, form a flat kind of plane.
When the camera moves around that plane is still the plane.
Right.
And you can kind of see that the plane is behaving in 3D as it
normally would as if it was sort of a flat sheet and the problem if we
do that obviously,
with the Sprites that we have, and I'll go ahead and and just actually
make this happen here so you can see.
So if I don't
If I don't allow any of the Sprites to stand upright, then you know
you can see what happens to the trees in this case, right?
They're just kind of stuck flat on the ground and you can see the
z-fighting care.
All of this stuff is stacked directly on top of each other.
So you end up with the Precision of the z-buffer, the iterator sort of
giving you random results as to who's in front of whom.
And so, if we look here, you can kind of see what happens if
everything lies down, right if I want these trees to appear, you know,
if this is the view
Of the game we're going to typically take and I want these trees to
appear as they were probably intended by the artist.
You know, I don't want them lying down flat.
So I want to have a way of having them appear as as if the artist you
know, exactly the way the artist drew them in a flat camera facing
way, right?
And so I want them to always be aligned with the screen and you can
see it leads to some odd effects, as I kind of, you know, flip around
here because the
Trees.
Look like they're always turning to face us because that's exactly
what they are doing.
We only have one view of the Sprite, so, no matter where we look,
we're always going to see that one view, but other than that, it
produces a very nice 3D version of this bright because you can see,
it's always providing the right aspect ratio and the right alignment
with the screen to give us that Sprites actual image to make that
Sprites image look correct.
Right?
So the question here is, how do I, you know, how did I do that?
And the answer is just that if I want to draw a camera facing card,
well, what do I know about my projection?
Right?
Well, my projection Matrix is the thing that's going to take, right?
I've got a camera here.
And, you know, I've got an X and a z and a y of the camera and the
camera is, you know, looking out into the world, right and their stuff
out in the world, you know, maybe there's a cube sitting out here and
I'm viewing it, right?
And what we will know about this camera.
Is that anything along the z-axis, right?
Is going to determine a certain depth information and it's going to
affect our perspective divide such that the further back you are, you
know, the further you are a negative Z relative to where the camera is
Remember this is in camera space here.
I'm talking about things on the cameras axis,
So, if I go along, Z the further, I go - Z the smaller things get so
things that are back here going to appear very small things that are
up here going to appear big and so the perspective Distortion is
happening along that z-axis.
However, if you think about what happens to the XY plane, so the plane
that the X and Y axes are in everything in one XY, plane,
Has no varying Z component, right?
That's the definition of the XY plane.
In this case is that the Z component is the same everywhere and I
could move that plane anywhere.
I want along the z-axis, right?
And as long as I'm still talking about a plane aligned with the X and
y-axes everything in the plane, has the same Z coordinate.
That means there's no Distortion as to the elongation of one part of
something in the plane versus another, this
Kurt right of the plane.
And this part of the plane are going to appear.
Exactly the same distance away from the viewer, okay?
It's not going to get elongated in some weird way where if I was
talking about a plane that was say, not that way like a plane that was
sort of this way, right?
Then this part would appear much further away than this part which
would appear closer, right?
And so if I were to draw something on that, non XY plane,
And it would warp, right?
I would get you know if I was looking at it here's my screen and I'm
looking at these things, something aligned to the XY plane looks like
that, it looks like a Sprite card that's facing the camera, which is
what we would want something that's drawn on this plane would look
more like this, right?
This back part would get shrunk down, you know, because it's further
away in z.
So what that means is, if we want to draw things which retained their
rectangular, right angle nature, when pushed through the perspective,
projection, it's actually very simple.
We just need to keep them on the XY plane, right?
And more specifically any XY plane, it doesn't matter what the Z can
be, the Z can be anything as long as it's the same on all of them,
right?
So now comes the question.
How do we produce points that are on an XY plane relative to the
camera, right?
Because remember, we're sending down these points in World space.
Right.
We're sending down these things in the same space as everything else.
Including where, how the camera specified that world's face might be
some other thing that's like over here, right?
And has different axes.
These are the camera axes, but the world axes.
Where everything else is specified in terms of and the origin of the
world and everything else.
This is the cameras position, right?
These could be totally different, they don't have to coincide in any
way.
The axes don't have to point in any
Similarly, the position can be different whatever, right?
Even the scale could be different if we wanted.
So the question becomes if we're submitting things in World space, how
do we produce things that are on an XY plane in camera space, right?
Because we don't know what the XY axes are in that space in world
space, right?
We don't, we need to be able to talk about XY planes in World space
that are XY planes in the camera space.
So the X and Y axis of the world, don't help us here, right?
They don't tell us the information but lucky for us.
We know the cameras, XY axes because we use that we passed the X and Y
axis down to create our camera transform in the first place.
So, what that means is we still have the camera X and Y axis, lying
around.
So all we have to do, if we want a Sprite card to be facing the camera
properly is, we just have to go ahead and make sure that the axes, we
use to construct the Sprite, or the X and Y, axes of the camera object
itself.
Those two axes will tell us exactly what a constant X Y plane would
look like in World space because they are the two spanning axes of
that space, right?
The Z axis of the camera is the thing that tells us the direction
along which we cannot move if we want our Sprite to remain in the
same.
In the same.
X, Y plane.
Okay.
So what I did?
Is exists.
It's not what I want.
What I did is exactly what you would expect.
You can see here, I took the x axis and the y axis of the entry that I
was trying to create.
And I just assigned to those the size that we wanted, the Sprite to be
an X and I use the cameras x-axis as the access for that.
And I took the size.
We want it in y.
And I use the cameras y-axis for that and that's exactly what we want
in order to create the sort of span for the Sprite.
In camera space, basically, rather than world's face, even though we
have to express it in World space, we can do that by just using the
cameras X and Y, axes as defined in World space, right?
That's what these are.
This is the cameras, x axis defined in World space, the cameras y-axis
to find in World space.
So we use those and we get exactly what
You want, right?
And so when we use those, we get our Sprite sort of standing up
exactly like we want them to always facing the camera.
So, that's exactly what we want to do there.
The problem here is that we need a little more than that.
So if you imagine this might be, you know, and this is probably a
little bit too steep so I mean not sleep enough.
If you imagine the game wants to look roughly like this and this is
like the dude kind of coming around here.
You know, if we want the game to look roughly that perspective?
Then the question is well.
Okay, what exactly are we going to do?
If the camera is at that perspective, what are we going to do about
sorting these Sprites?
Into the world because, you know, like I said, be kind of want them to
stick sort of layer together and it might be that this is non is this
is not a sufficient amount of of standing up for the Sprites.
Now, it might be, I don't really know.
It might be enough.
But what I want to do is First add a way that we can look at how much
they are standing up.
And then if we want to and we need to, we can go in and try to figure
out a way to add some more.
Sort of puff them out further if that makes sense, the way that we
were planning on doing it before.
Only, I realized sort of after doing this, that we probably want to
start with this construction rather than this construction.
Because we do probably want them to always do X and Y axis facing like
this.
So that's sort of a separate thing.
Anyway, so ignore ignoring this part for a second and just focusing on
this part.
What I want to do here is just introduce the again, the concept of a
deep debug camera.
We've used this in the past and handmade hero, we have the about
camera, but we don't really have support for the rotation.
It now only, you know, we're sort of had it for zooming out is the is
the thing we had it for.
So, if you take a look at this, the way we have it now,
We can move the camera around, but there's only one concept of where
the camera is.
What that means is that these Sprites right are always facing the
actual camera, I'm using to view the world even though what I really
want in this, you know, ability to rotate the world around, this is
not the game, will not let you do that, right?
So, the reason I have I put this camera in is so that I can use it for
debug in order to use it for debug.
I need these Sprite cards to remain fixed at their locations and
orientations in the world, while I rotate around because my rotating
around like that.
Is the thing I'm going to use to inspect them for debugging.
So what that means is again we need that concept of to sort of
separate things.
We need the concept of a sort of the debug camera and the actual gain
camera and we need to be able to switch between those, right?
And so if you take a look at render group and we've got this sort of
notion in render group of, you know, here's some some information
about the camera and then here is the prescription.
Section Matrix, this camera information here we're using to generate
our Sprites and so what we really want to do I think is say that this
projection Matrix here maybe is going to be the thing that that the
camera that's actually using the renderer but these gear can be set
separately so they can always be set to the game's camera and the
debug camera can be something else that overrides this right.
So if we were to do something like that, you can see in here.
We sort of have this set camera transform situation and you can see
how it's getting set.
Their what I want to do here perhaps is introduced to the September
transform call and I don't know, this might be a little bit.
Sort of janky at the moment so we'll see how it goes and we'll adjust
as necessary if we need something a little bit fancier.
But if I were to go ahead here and just adjust this so that I instead
of taking a Boolean for Ortho, I have like camera transform flag idea.
And so I could do like camera is Ortho is one of them.
Maybe orthographic camera is debug.
Another one.
and so now in here, instead of taking that Ortho idea, I'm going to
take flags and then we can say well okay if it's Ortho is just if the
flags and camera is or at the graphic is set, then it'll be Ortho and
I can say that it's a debug
Camera.
If it's got his debug set and then when we come through here, I can
choose to not update certain pieces of information if it's a debug
camera, so I can say if it's debug, you know, maybe don't set these
things that I'm using for sprite generation because I want the Sprites
to be generated as if there wasn't any of that.
All right, so let's go ahead and jump into the world mode where this
is being set.
And we can see the set camera, transform call happening here and you
can see that it's going along and doing this Z rotation thing.
So, what I want,
here is I want to pass and I could, if I wanted to do a thing here,
where I do camera is perspective,
I suppose I could do something like that even though there's really
not much need for it, but if I wanted to, I could, you know, I don't
think that's necessary.
Let's just say that's just a little more information, but it's just
not necessary.
So, here we can do to set camera transforms, right?
And what I'll do is I'll do one.
That's, that's the actual camera.
And one that is debug like.
So and what I'll do is in the one where we do set camera transform,
For the regular one, I'm going to forego the debug camera orbit, debug
camera pitch stuff, right.
So, basically, what I'll do is say, okay, you know, here's the debug
one.
What camera offset, z w, World mode camera all set.
So I guess what I want to do here is say
I guess what?
I really want to do here say
That the camera off set.
in this case is actually, oops is actually
I want to add to the Z.
So I guess I could just do you know, camera offset plus D3 and just
stick this in the Z component, right?
All right.
And so here, let me go ahead and put that down here because this is
actually where we want it.
So, what I want to do here is I'm going to go ahead and set camera,
orbit and Camera pitch as opposed to debug camera orbit and debug
camera pitch, and then we'll have a camera Dolly there as well.
So we can essentially have all of this stuff set up as we want, and
then we can do this twice one with debug and one without.
So if I go up here,
And I add those in.
what I can do it for now is to set those directly because right now we
don't actually need them to be anything other than prescribed values
and
put those in there.
So if I have these as prescribed values, I don't need the the
At this point and the orbit in the pitch I probably will never use the
orbit in the actual game.
So it's really just the pitch and the pitch is going to be I guess,
probably, something like I said fairly steep.
I'm not sure exactly what it'll be.
We'll have to play with it but
Yeah, something.
Whoo.
That's not exactly what I expected to see.
I think I did something slightly wrong there.
Oh, right, I did do something slightly wrong there.
So
I should probably also have some way of switching between these now
that I think about it.
I'm not sure exactly how I should do that because I need to, I need to
be able to flip back and forth so they're effectively needs to be
something here.
Right.
And I'd like that something to be pretty quick, I guess I could use
maybe the right Mouse button for the moment or something like this and
see, I don't know.
But I will need something here.
Where it's like, use debug camera.
Yeah, and I want some way to switch really quickly between those two.
Let's take a look here.
I don't know if we have any useful Keys, really.
Yeah, not so much.
I could decide to a debug variable later, although a debug variables,
a little cumbersome to go up and set.
So I don't know that.
That's really the best choice there.
But what I can do now is just say, if input.
Input Mouse buttons for Mouse button, right?
Then we will do hold mode.
Use the video camera.
And we're good.
So this is the actual game camera here and my like rotating around
doesn't do anything.
If I switch to the right Mouse button whoops, I need I knew that to be
went down because I don't want to constantly toggle between them.
Feel like we had one, something like that was pressed.
There we go.
So if I toggle between them, now I can switch between these two.
So here's the game camera and all the Sprites are.
Facing properly towards the camera itself.
If I switch to the debug camera.
Now, when I rotate around, I can sort of see how everything is
aligned, right?
And the thing that concerns me is what I was trying to get to before
is just that if you take a look at how these guys are sort of sloped
there,
You can see how they are really kind of steeply.
Angled they cross over into the next cell boundary really early and I
just worry about that as being potentially too much.
You know, the thing is I guess and you know, I don't really know but I
guess
It's okay.
Well, I don't know I don't know that it is because for example if we
were to have something in this location here that was, you know,
sticking up straight.
Like you know, if this Cube or kind of coming up here
This would interpenetrate in.
That would be bad.
And so, I feel like from back here, which is the game camera, right?
So, from back here, I want it to look like this, but I want ways of
doing that, that will push it more up into its own square, right?
So I wanted to come closer to me,
But I need it to still retain its shape properly.
That's the trick right?
And you know I guess there's ways I could maybe do that with just
modifying what the Z coordinate actually is going to be because I do
have opportunities for doing that.
I suppose in ways that would make it so that the Z coordinate was
different but
What?
Yeah.
I don't know that I want to go that route right eye.
I guess what I'm saying is so the Z buffer is going to operate on the
information that we tell it to, right?
We are providing the Z coordinates to work with for the Z buffer and
we could choose if we wanted to to provide different information from
the z-buffer than the actual Z coordinates were using to draw the
world right?
and they would, you know, that would essentially
give us the ability to prevent things from intersecting with each
other in those in those cases.
I don't know if we want to do that or if we want to do something that
pulls these things forward in a way that preserves their perspective.
It's kind of a tough call.
But to be honest, I do think that I probably I'm I'm leaning a little
towards just using an additional value there because it does seem like
that would be much simpler if we have the world looking like this and
we simply change the Z values so that they increase much more
gradually than they would given the actual Z values here.
So that
yeah, you get, you know, different results.
I feel like that that might be the easiest solution.
Because I guess there's, you know, I can't think of any real reason to
do sort of the more advanced math.
You know, we did the math out there for doing the intersection and
bringing the, you know, figuring out a way to preserve the apparent
size of the Sprite.
But, you know, do we really want to bother doing that math?
On every Sprite all the time when we could just fake the Z coordinate
by passing down as the different Z?
Nets at the corners.
Then the actual Z coordinates were using to draw because that's one of
the things that we can do.
You know with modern programmable gpus is we don't have to confine
ourselves to just using Z as the Z that we use for rejection doesn't
have to be the Z that we use for the depth buffer we can use a
different value entirely for the depth buffer and the card doesn't
care.
It just needs to know where to get it from.
It doesn't have to be tied specifically, to where we are.
Placing the, the Sprite in the world so that does seem kind of
compelling and maybe that's a good way to go.
I kind of like that that seems pretty good to me so, so let's maybe.
Take that a little step further.
What I'd like to do now is say okay.
You know that's the Sprite cards.
Could just be the way that we do them exactly like that.
And we still have to deal with the alpha issue but otherwise the
Sprites look like they should look.
And I can play the game the way that I want to play it at the roughly,
the perspective that I want, I would also mention that this is not
private perspective that I want I wanted to be even steeper than that.
I was looking for a very steep angle in the game.
Probably something more like this, right?
Maybe even.
Maybe even more, you know, I don't know.
It's hard to say, but a very steep angle and so, you know, at that
point, you can really see to these Sprites are just our only barely
You know, only barely rising up out of their area, but this is more
what I wanted.
You know, I really didn't want very much perspective there.
You know, that was not my intent, I just needed some.
I wanted a little bit of perspective since we're going to have the
ability to do that.
I want.
Maybe just a little bit of that.
And so as you kind of move through the world,
It's just that that little tiniest bit.
We could also I suppose go for one that's
that's directly flat on.
But of course, again in that situation, we do have to think about how
we're going to stand this rights up at, maybe that answer to how we're
standing those Sprites up.
In that case would be that we would just
Again fake that that Z coordinate.
So I don't know.
The other thing is to we may find as we go a little further down that
that it does look a little nicer to have that sort of perspective be a
little bit different like it is here I'm not entirely certain that's a
good question and so you know I guess it remains to be seen because
the game is sort of played in in a tile-based fashion.
I feel like that gives us
Opportunities to maybe have a more oblique perspective like this
because it means that you're not so concerned about lining things up
precisely in 3D because the tiles, you know, kind of do that for you
and make it easier for you to do things in three dimensions that that
would ordinarily be a lot harder to do.
So I feel like that might be that might
That might be all.
We really need to do there, I don't know.
That's a good question.
The other thing though that I would point out is that, you know, we do
want to have sort of done Janee walls here so it wouldn't just be
trees.
And so like I said, we kind of need to take a look at sort of The Next
Step here, which is to to sort of get some 3D blocks in there.
All right, so let's postpone thinking about that.
Z for a little bit because we're going to need to pop over to the
opengl layer and do a bunch of stuff on that.
Maybe that'll be next weekend, but we're going to have to be able to
load shaders and be able to set what we want, our depth stuff to be
and that sort of stuff.
So we have work, we're going to have to do there, where?
Yeah, it's going to be a little bit more complicated, but
And we also need to do the multi sample anti-aliasing stuff.
So we just have a bunch of like literally nothing but opengl busy work
to do over there to just basically bring the GPU in line with the
stuff that we want to be able to do in terms of setting up.
The rendering, right?
So we do have to pop over there and do that at some point soon.
But I don't know that I want to do that quite yet because I would like
to also now start passing down some more 3D like Primitives.
And I think that for the most part will involve us having to set some
or provide some other options in our render pass.
so, the problem here,
Because we have to think a little bit about how we're submitting
things to the render in the first place.
Because we were doing things in the simple 2-D game before we really
just submitted things as Sprites because that is what we primarily
conceptualize our world to be is, you know, hey, we've got these like
2D images and they're on the screen somewhere and that's, you know,
whatever that is great.
But what I'd like to be able to do is I'd like to be able to in
addition to Sprites.
So you know I've got
Things like that tree are a rectangle.
That's drawn.
Essentially with two triangles, right?
One here and one here and that is how we're drawing individual
Sprites.
This Alpha knocks out this area.
I would also like the ability to draw basically cubes.
So I would like, for those things on the ground, you know, to
basically cubes that kind of look like this to the viewer, right?
Because they're kind of at an angle here.
So this is, you know, the top of the cube.
Looking down on.
And so the world as it stands is kind of this collection of these
cubes, you know, kind of like a, a Vox League game like a Minecraft e
sort of a thing has kind of more overtly, you know,
where you've got things that are kind of made out of these, like Cube
like pieces, you know, sort of a situation,
And I want the ability to do something like that and I need the
ability to map images onto those, right?
I want to be able to put textures on there so that you know when we
have a dungeon area whatever it can have dungeon imagery, you know
dungeon tile sets on the wall, if it's a house or something can have
wood, paneling whatever right?
Basically, whatever the artists are conceiving for what, you know, you
would want to put whatever an artist might think of that they want to
put on there, just being able to put stuff on there and we need to be
able to put different things on all the different sides of the cube.
We also need to have some way of being able to do some lighting on
here.
Meaning that like these kind of Corners, you know, we want to be able
to specify information at the corners probably.
They would allow us to do some sort of a darkening, you know.
So we can kind of in here make it get darker when we get in areas that
are like lower down and less visible or you know
Who knows any number of things?
We may want to put Lighting in there.
We may want to do all sorts of stuff like that.
So the problem with that is right that really breaks up our notion of
what we are sending down to the GPU because now not only are we
sending down this notion of these sort of textured cards that are
facing the viewer or doing whatever else.
But we also have this concept of
Of a little bit more of a structural thing.
Now, it's not a complicated structural thing.
It's not the Utah teapot or whatever.
It's just
Very simple Cubes but we're still going to need some way of
communicating that information.
And we're going to need some way.
Of efficiently specifying stuff like what image goes on each side of a
cube and where the cube is that sort of stuff.
Now, the simplest way to do this would be to just specify each Cube as
an element, as a render element, and that may be what I do first.
But,
We may find that to be an adequate going forwards and we may have to
adjust things to accommodate for it.
but,
Let's see here.
That's Ed.
I need to buy my nose.
It's going to be allergy season here.
Case anyone was wondering.
All right.
So, you know, if we want to do just the basic version of this, you
know, we've got these sort of different render types here, so maybe I
would just say like, okay we've got bitmaps and I also in addition to
bitmaps want to be able to draw cubes.
Right.
And a cube is just a thing, which specifies the data on the corners of
the cube that I need.
So maybe I've got a render entry Cube and the cube, you know, could be
specified, I guess is just like
I mean I guess I don't really want a cube per se because I want it to
be an arbitrary height.
So I need a height value for the cube but otherwise I just need like a
radius value for the cube because it's a cube and it can't really
elongate
they're supposed to be tile shaped.
So I've got a height and I've got a radius and that specifies, pretty
much everything there is to specify about the cube other than just
the, you know, the point in three dimensions, where the cube is
centered about.
And I think what I might do is say that's the like, you know,
Oops.
You know it's like the the middle of the top face of the cube just for
now I'm going to say that that's what that is so you know, that's a
cube we can specify and I don't know if we want to specify like an X
and Y axis, kind of a thing for it.
You know, it's it's do.
We want to have cubes that spin around.
I don't know for now, I'll just say no but because we can always add
that later.
And so really that's all I need other than the fact that I'm going to
need a loaded bitmap there to draw my cube right.
The texture for it basically,
and I guess I'll probably put a Primo color in there as well because
that's obviously something that's going to need just like, you know,
the
just like the bitmaps can be colorized, so you can tint whatever you
have for the color of your of your Sprite.
You can do the same thing in the case of the cube.
So, in order to do the cube, again, it's really not going to be
particularly complicated inside handmade render group, we have to do,
essentially the same thing that we were doing before know where my
pushed bitmap call is.
It is
so um inside my push bitmap call essentially I'm doing the exact same
thing and kind of see here,
We've got the the version that has the bitmap loaded in the version,
that doesn't have the bitmap loaded yet or at least doesn't know if it
at the book map, loads just using the ID, we pretty much want to have
a push Cube call that I guess is going to do roughly the same thing.
So you know we've got pretty much the same parameters.
I think for the most part, I don't know that we really need an object
transform here for any particular reason, because the object transform
kind of just has a bunch of stuff.
We don't really
Need right.
And to be honest.
We probably don't need the object transform.
For the bitmaps anymore, either.
About that separate issue.
Anyway.
so,
here we are in our first view.
Let me get rid of this for now.
We've got a group, a bitmap ID, or height.
IR p and I need the radius there.
I'll just make these in roughly the same order they come.
And and then we've got that color as well.
The alignment is not here.
We don't have any of this, that's all gone.
So we need to do the same thing we're doing before, right?
And I renders in background is not a thing that groups do anymore.
So I'm not sure that should even be there.
I'm pretty sure that's never set for anybody under any circumstances.
Yeah, I don't think it is so let's go ahead and take that out.
Here, there we go.
so, if I were to get rid of renders and background,
does anyone care?
Nope.
And because I think that was just for ground chunks so that she can go
away.
So in this case, renders in background,
Those are going away.
And in this case, I've got my push Cube call.
I'll just weld this in at the moment here.
And will separate them out only if we actually need to later.
all right, so what I want to do here is I want to push one of these
render entries
and the render entryway want is render entry Cube.
If I get one back successfully, I will push on the bitmap that I'm
expecting.
The p is going to be this p.
and then, I've got
height.
Radius.
And I'm good.
So my store color here still take sort of this lerp situation.
And so what I'd like to do is I'd like to kind of get rid of this as
well.
I feel like this T color color thing was this was only for fog and the
fog is irrelevant now because we can do the fog in the actual back
end.
So what we want to do is is I think just get rid
this entirely and make it so that this is, you know, just directly
taking what we would expect.
Here we go and doing that multiply
We go.
Let's get rid of that in this case as well.
Okay, and similarly I suppose while we're at it while we're cleaning
things up here, we can take a look at the object transform and we can
get rid of that.
Right.
And so now really nothing should happen.
I mean, all we did was add a new primitive, we just added push Cube,
and that's that's it.
So you know, we don't need anything else there for the moment.
But now, if we actually want to use the push Cube information, we need
to actually add it in here to the render.
Now, in order to motivate that I should probably actually make one of
these things because otherwise you're going to add it and nobody is
going to use it and that's not very exciting.
So what I'm going to do here is we're taking a bunch of these
rectangles to draw these traversable.
As you can see that,
Happening here, where I've got this, like, push rectangle thing that's
happening and you can kind of see to when I'm doing that.
You know, I'm I'm sort of if I remember correctly and World mode, we
were creating our standard room, it could have variance and Z, but we
turned it off.
So, you know, you could have like, sort of these, these Heights and
and
Just in in various things.
So if I wanted to, you know, I can get this this offset Z here I think
and I believe that'll just, you know, oh,
evidently not.
Well, again, that's you know what, though?
That may just be because of
Setting up where the person is in the game.
We do have a weird thing right now with when we actually create the
player.
I'm kind of interesting interested to know.
In check for joining players when we call get closest reversible.
We never really went in and looked at what was happening in here.
Let me quickly debug that because I feel like that's a problem.
Let's see here.
Because we should be able to tweak the Z by something and not have it
create a problem, right?
Okay, don't see why that would be an issue in any particular way, but
it obviously is and I do think that's because we're currently, we've
got some stuff with our way that we're doing those.
Collision things.
You can see like for reasons that we never bothered to debug our hero
starts over there.
We do not know why he started over there, right?
We were in the middle of a bunch of changes.
We never looked at what was going on there, so I want to do a quick
check.
I have a feeling that where were actually placing him is totally bogus
at the moment,
And it probably has to do with the fact that we're not placing him
anywhere in particular.
In any particular smart location.
So let me take a look here.
Because the order in which things happen when you enter the game, is a
little janky the way that we did.
It was just yeah it's not great and it is probably something that will
have to
Fix it some point.
But anyway, if we come through here, you know, the way that this works
is the first time through we call check for joining players and we do
get one, it's the player who is automatically joining.
And so the I think we actually stuff that start value in a forced way,
right?
You can see here that if one this in which we have, we basically
forced the player to be pressing the button so that they would enter
the game as if they pressed it.
So what?
Because so we don't have to start at the title screen every time.
So if we look here where we got that pressed, start that
That means that we are actually working with the same region that
we've set up here and we're not actually we don't know where the
camera is yet, right.
That's kind of the busted part about this is the first time through
the camera hasn't actually been set because the camera is not going to
get set until we hit n Sim.
Right.
And Sim is the thing that actually sets up the camera for us in terms
of figuring out where the camera should go.
And we're not even, you know, we're not really doing that.
So I think part of the problem here is, you know, the location of the
guy, you know, 000 should be right in the middle of the same region,
but it's probably not.
And so, we'll have to see what happens there.
Anyway, we look at the traversable here.
Let me actually step into that.
I want to see.
Yeah.
So here is get closest reversible because look at the closest distance
squared so the closest distance squared is 2 meters squared away.
So not actually that far away looks like
So that's interesting, but let me go ahead and check now too.
What happens if I make that change?
That I want to make before.
Like so.
So it finds the same location to stand, so that doesn't seem to
actually be the problem, so that's good.
And when we add a hero, you know, everyone's happy.
And let's take a look inside the world mode camera because I want to
know where we actually are.
So there's no offset to the camera in particular.
And these are relatively sane values.
Right.
We're at 76.
In both cases.
And that stays pretty with no offset.
And that stays pretty
pretty much the same.
Right now, let's take a look.
We all that looks pretty reasonable to me.
Yet we get nothing on the screen.
Do that.
That's a little weird.
Get two of those for some reason.
No, okay.
So I'm not sure why we end up with the nothing on the screen.
This and I want to know why that is
I was expecting it to be something with.
With the camera but I'm not sure that that's actually the case.
And there we do get more of an offset.
All right, I'm going to take a look at what.
We're what our camera is in the case, where we don't do that.
and I do not know why didn't feel the need to break their but I'd
wanted it to
All right.
So it looks like the problem is pretty simple.
Actually, it looks like the problem is just because we're not doing
the room.
Sizing stuff correctly at the moment.
Anyway,
because we're not doing that correctly, it looks
Picking a room below where we should be picking.
In fact, I suppose now with the debug camera, I should be able to
verify that though.
So here's the version where we're actually using kind of scattered
stuff for the cubes, right?
And if I
reset it to just use this one and I should get
again, a screen with nothing.
If I look up, you would think I would see, but I still don't.
It's very strange.
So yeah as far as I can tell, we're definitely getting something odd
where it's like we pick the room below.
As you can see that the Z offset was pretty substantial.
The other one.
So we have to figure out what is going on there but I'd like to pause
that for a second to finish what we were doing with the cubes and then
go from there, you can kind of see here how I've got all these
traversable 's
Rendering us, these little Jimmy.
Rendering us these little Cube shapes.
But I'm sorry rendering is the these little rectangles that are flat
but I want them to cubes.
And so what I should be able to do here.
Is change this from a push wrecked, which is what I was doing before.
Triple H Cube.
And while I'm at it.
I may get rid of the automatic outlining, we had
There we go.
So the push Cube function.
we need to pass the parameters to it that we specified from for and
those are
the group, the bitmap ID, which in this case
I guess, we'll just get.
From The Entity.
I'm not 100% certain how we were doing that.
I guess, he'd here, we had these Peace Index things.
And you can kind of see in here, we got this like piece count.
Right.
And then it looks fairly reasonable.
The question is, do we want to use the piece count in some way for
this?
If we look at the Envy visual piece, it's got a color and offset and
asset type the height and flags, it's probably more than me really
need.
So it seems like kind of Overkill in this case for something like
that.
So I don't know that we actually want that.
We probably want something a little more straightforward where we're
just specifying.
More of a an image here.
But I don't know.
So we could just say that, you know, if it's got a traversable like
this
I guess I'm just going to say, you know what, maybe we just get rid of
this and we say, sure.
Go into the Peace Index stuff that, you know, can do what it's going
to do.
We have the bitmap ID situation.
And we can then say, all right, instead of a pushpin map called
doesn't have to be pushed up that call if we want to, it can be peace
type, you know, Cube
and if it is a cube,
Then we'll just use some of this information to derive how big the
cube should be.
In this particular case we sort of have a situation where I guess
we're over specified.
You know we have this notion of the offset and maybe we can just use
the offset as the three values that we want.
And I guess we could make it so that the cube actually takes each
individual Dimension separately as well.
Since we if we are always passing that down and we don't really need
the height in this case for anything in particular.
There.
So I think we can just do
something more, like,
Well, I guess we do need the offset there.
Now that I think about it because we do we do actually need to say how
How its offset from The Entity potentially, so that's not actually
true.
So we do want that in there.
So we're going to have to figure out another way to pass that
information.
So we've got the height.
And I guess we need kind of a radius value here that we don't have,
right?
And of course color we do have
So that's a good question and I'm not sure exactly where I want to get
that information from.
It seems like that's something that just wants to be in there
separately, because you can see here, when you're passing that height
down with push bitmap, you know, that's the kind of thing that you
probably in the future want to be able to control separately, the both
of them.
So I feel like that's just something that in general, we would want
So I feel like we want something maybe more like that where that's
actually specified as a dimension.
And in this case, we could do, you know, height equals Jim one or
whatever dimmed out.
Why?
So when we do in it, when we do a bitmap, will use that.
And when we use
It in this case.
We passed it like that.
So then we're doing at peace and we specify a height like this that
would you know translate into something like this.
I don't know exactly what we want that to be, but something like this
and then if we're adding a cube, we would add it slightly differently,
right?
And we could have, you know,
This parameter could just be passed through, I suppose.
And then when people call AD piece, in this case, you know, they
would, they would pass the V2 course, there's so many people that call
that I feel like we want to keep it the way it is.
So I feel like I want one of these that does do that translation for
you.
And it's literally just a thunk.
Does nothing.
But wrap it for you.
so, I think
I think that's reasonable and that way we can have cubes that are kind
of mixed in here with everything else as part of an empty, anytime we
want.
And that seems good.
The cube render Cube call.
I do feel like maybe taking the height as the second thing makes a
little more sense there.
So we'll maybe leave it like that but otherwise I think we're good.
So we run this now and you know we took out those those perfect calls
so those are gone but now you know we can verify at least that
everything else is working just fine.
And all we need to do now is actually put in some for of the things
that have traversable is like those ground points.
We just need to give them individual pieces that they can actually
We work with.
So if I go to the world mode, where we create this,
Inside a standard room.
We've got these places where we're making these entities, right?
With floor collision and in here, they just they never have any actual
pieces to them.
So all we really need to do to finish that off, is we just need to
actually add a piece and
If we take a look at how we call this, we just need the entity.
We're trying to add the piece too.
We need the asset type.
which in this case,
There we go.
In this case.
I'm not sure what we're actually adding here, but, you know,
I guess maybe rock or stone.
We need to actually put in some real art soon because now this stuff
is going to make any sense.
Unless we do but, you know, all right, so maybe there's maybe there's
grass.
There we go.
So the asset type, in this case, we'll just put something in there
random for the moment, we need the height and the radius here.
And in this case, since we have in the entity, we kind of know what we
were doing with that before.
Just because we happen to have it here, it was 14 for the radius for
whatever reason for the height.
I don't know what we want.
Probably like, you know, three, we want these to be fairly tall.
Maybe not, maybe just one meter is fine, who knows?
and then,
We need the offset, the color, and the flags.
So the offset in this case is actually it's a little tricky because
I know I said before I was like well we'll just make it the top of the
cube.
But now that I think about it, it's like if we're going to allow this
to be sort of a general thing where entities can just have Cube pieces
to them if they want, that makes it probably a little more compelling
for us to make it be the center of the cube.
Probably.
I don't actually know that that's true.
It may actually still make more sense for it to be pivoted at the top
because, you know, if you imagine it was sort of like an appendage or
stuck to something that make more sense.
So I'm not sure that's a really tough question as to how
It should be constructed.
As to whether it should be centered or not.
And so,
I guess I'll leave it with top for now and maybe we'll live to regret
that quite a bit.
It's really hard to say.
So let's find out.
Offset in this case, we'll just be 3000.
The color can just be white for now, really do anything with that and
the flags can be like peace type Cube.
Then off you go.
So the piece type Cube situation is now in theory, in full effect, it
should get actually execute upon and so my assumption is now we'll get
in assertion in the renderer hopefully.
Yes, which tells us that.
Now we're actually getting cubes seen down in the render it.
So we just need to have the cube primitive.
Be something that actually is understood by the opengl renderer which
in this case we can do, we're not going to do anything fancy.
We're just going to do very, very basic.
And we'll base it here on.
We go.
I honor render entry bitmap.
So, okay.
We've got our render entry cubed here.
And that's really it.
And oops.
We then need to actually output this Cube.
We're going to go ahead and bind the texture.
And then we need to do essentially the same thing as we were doing up
there.
But with a little more
I guess I should say a little less fussing because we don't have to do
as much work in this particular case.
So what we want to do now is output the triangles of the cube, we
could do this with a little more finesse.
then we're about to, but
Maybe start somewhere.
So
Here's mr.
Cube
and we just need to generate some points and triangles that will
Define this Cube soap in jail can draw it, right?
And we know we've got eight vertices in a cube.
Right.
Eight corners of the cube.
And we know that every side of the cube is a face.
There are six phases and each face has 2 triangles in it, right?
Because each square has 2 triangles
So, if we want to, we can imagine creating this pretty
straightforwardly, right?
We just need to talk about these points in terms of the axes that
we're thinking of here.
And so, you know, you can imagine.
Here's my y.
Here's my X.
Here is my Z same, as we normally draw, and we've got each of these.
These are sort of the positive Z ones.
These are the negative Z one's right.
The positive y ones would be up here.
Of why ones down here.
Positive X here, Negative X over here, right?
So we can kind of think about those all of those things, all of these
Corners essentially in that way, right?
This
Corner.
Right here is negative X, right?
Positive y - Z.
I'm sorry.
Positive Z.
Right.
So in fact, if I just labeled them Negative, X positive, y, negative,
Z this is - x - y - Z, sorry positive Z.
And then why keep lying like that positive Z?
This is positive x - y positive Z.
This is positive x - y.
- Z.
This is positive.
X positive, y negative.
Z, this is negative X positive.
Y, negative Z.
This is negative X.
- y - Z.
And now we've got all the different points.
So if we want to create each of these individual faces, oops, forgot
one here.
This is positive X.
Positive, why?
- Z.
Positively rather.
So if I have all these points, now I can just think about actually
just putting in what the cubes should be, just manually.
It's pretty easy, right?
You could imagine saying, all right, I've got a bunch of points.
Let's say here in three dimensions and maybe I use like lower case for
- and uppercase for positive.
So, you know, I'd have XYZ
XYZ.
Right?
And in fact, I guess, I could do this a little more systematically may
be very easy.
Each time it's a little hard to see.
I don't know how good of an idea that actually is wish the Z's were a
little bit more clear in this font, but they're not.
So you can see here, I've got the Z lowercase.
So I've got negative, Z positive Z, then the Y goes positive, negative
Z positive Z.
Now, let's go make the X+ same thing.
And there's all my eight cases, right?
Since that's a little hard to see.
I don't know.
I think that's maybe not such a good idea.
So here's another way I could do it.
I could do like, you know, PA
Py pz and like, an X and Y and Z or something like that.
Right?
Is a little easier to see.
so, if I'm going to do it that way,
I bet - C+ Z.
And then I've got the positive y versions of those too.
And then we just make the positive X versions of all of those.
So that seems reasonable enough I suppose, right?
And so, all these are going to be is they're just bundles of the
values.
And I could literally bundle these values exactly as they are written,
right?
So it can just be
this sort of thing.
I suppose now I think about it, if I want to I could just use the
opengl immediate for this even.
Why can I not do that?
So, I can just specify the - see the positive x - x to the positive x
negative y, the positive wire the negative, to the positive Z.
And then in here,
I can just do.
This sort of thing.
All right.
So what we will see a lot is if I want to do this and in specifying a
GL triangle in order to specify the face of a cube, I'm going to have
to do something like this.
If I've got point zero, one, two, three, and I want to draw a quad.
What I have to do is I have to specify one triangle that is 012,
right?
This triangle right here.
And then I will have to spend another three vertices to specify
another triangle zero to three
rather than type that out.
I will just make a utility function for that.
I don't have one already.
I don't think I do.
Yeah.
So
You can see here, we have opengl rectangle, which is basically the
function that we want.
Problem is that the function itself has this kind of nasty habit of
specifying the begin as part of it, which we don't really want, but
this is mostly what we want.
So I can make another one, which is just like,
GL quad.
And in this case, I can go ahead and and
I can go ahead and be a little more specific here but we're specifying
in terms of
In terms of the points as well, because you can see here that it was
not actually giving me the freedom specify these points because it's
assuming The Main PX and py that sort of thing.
So I guess in a sense, this wasn't really exactly what I wanted.
But what do you do?
All right, so I'm going to have a GL quad call here.
I'm going to be able to pass it a female color.
I think what I actually want to do probably is say, you know, I've got
P0 which is you know the point out the bottom there I've got the
texture coordinates for it and I've got the color for it.
Let's say so I can pass all four of I mean all three of those in and I
just passed four of those.
So it's all of the, the actual information that I need we'll just be
over explicit there and we can always simplify it later.
so in this case now I know what I want to do is I want to specify like
field color 4fv and I'm going to pass that color zero and I'm going to
specify the texture coordinate and I'm going to specify
The point as well.
So that's an example of how to specify one point.
We just for the color, the texture coordinates and the vertex data.
And like I said I want to do 0 1, 2 and 0 to 3.
So there's 0 1 2.
And zero.
23.
And you'll notice that when I did this, I was careful to always keep
these wound the same direction so you can look and see.
I've got, I said 012 that's wound counterclockwise relative to the
facing Direction and the same is true here, 0 to 3 again wound
counterclockwise, and the reason that I wound them both in the same
direction that way.
And also both counterclockwise is just because if we ever want to use
back, face culling, right?
Backface culling is a concept that just indicates that.
Hey, if I'm looking at a closed object, right?
Like, let's say, I'm looking at this fear, I'm sorry, this fear this
Cube that we're talking.
About the one we're actually building.
Well, it's closed.
You know, there's no holes in it.
There isn't like a hole in the top.
I can use to see into the inside and what that means is that you can
only ever see the front of the faces of the cube.
Right.
You'll never see the backs of the faces of the cues because if you
turn the cube around, you'll just see the other side of a cube, you
won't see the other side of one of these faces.
You'll see the other face of the cube that's on the corresponding
opposite side.
So given that what it means is that the hardware, the gravis Hardware
can actually early out anytime it does a transform and finds that the
points for a given face are wound in the incorrect order relative to
the screen because what it knows is that if you always specify them
wound up particular way, you know, if I always specify zero one two,
And they're always around in that that counter clockwise fashion.
Then what it knows is if this Q Bert is spin around such that.
Now this face, you know,
Is my Cube again such that.
Now, this face is actually in the back here, right?
It's one of the back faces of the cube.
So it can't actually be visible because we know we can never see that.
It's a closed object would never see in there.
It's not possible.
We know we can eliminate that, that face right away.
Because look what happens.
This is zero point is now here, right?
This one point is now over here.
And this to point is up here and what you'll notice is 012, it's now
wounded the other way, right?
And that's exactly what happens as you spin something around as it
flips, as it goes from being front-facing, to you as facing you to
being back facing to you.
It flips its orientation and so I was careful to wind them that way,
so that if we want to turn something like that on, we can.
And so, you know, that was sort of a little something that was
implicit in what I do.
But that is why I did that.
It wasn't arbitrary, it was intentional.
Just so that's clear.
So, if we take a look at the cube situation here and now, and I come
Through and put in this, this GL quad situation here.
So what I can probably say is if I use this thing and now I'm back to
what I was thinking about before to where I actually do need to pack
them in.
But anyway, so if I go through my GL quad here, what I'm going to need
to do is I'm going to need to specify all the faces of this Cube here,
right?
Every last one of them.
And so, you know, I'm going to want to specify
Item in this way.
So here is one face like that.
Let's see what it is.
It's going to be a positive X, right?
Positive x - y.
Positive Z, and the next one's going to be.
Positive x - y - Z.
Next one's going to be positive, X positive, y, negative Z and the
last one is going to be all positive, positive X, positive y, positive
Z, and then the same thing is true.
For all of these.
I guess it's also now.
I think about it.
I wonder if I just want to do it.
A little simpler to say, okay, if its do 0, 1, 2 3.
So as I didn't see, it might be a little clearer.
So let's say
0 1, 2 3.
Four, five, six, seven.
Something like that.
So let's try that again because again that's I think that's going to
be a little simpler for us.
So, if we do this deal quad here and I want to do, let's say this
front face right here.
That's just 0 1, 2 3.
Then this is the entire code for that.
If I wanted to do the back face, it be four, five, six seven, right?
But again, I want it to be facing the correct direction.
So rather than four, five, six, seven, it would actually go the other
way round, right?
It be four seven six, five or seven, six five four, right?
Because it needs to be wound counterclockwise relative to somebody
looking from the back.
That makes sense.
So 76-54 is really what that should look like.
And we do have a little bit of a concern here, too.
With the texture coordinates, these are not really going to be correct
because we're going to want probably different texture, coordinates in
a lot of cases for these.
So that's a little bit harder to Envision.
In fact, for the time being, I might actually leave these as just
always this way.
And we'll play with those later, I think.
So, I'm just going to focus on just the positions instead.
So now, I've got this face, right?
I've got this front face and this back face, and I need to do these
ones around the side.
Let's do the ones the bottom and top faces next.
So the
I'm face is just 0 15 for right.
But again that would be if it was facing us, it's not, it's facing
your way.
So I need to do it the opposite direction, right?
So that's going to be for 510, right?
It's going to be wounded this way, so that when we're looking at it
from here, it'll be counterclockwise, right?
So we want it clockwise to us basically, 4510 we
Then want the top face to be wound the way we would expect.
So 2673 right, would be the correct whining for that.
And in addition to 2673 and those two, we need these final two phases
here which are these guys.
So that's the one we originally started with 1562.
And then finally, the back one again, it would be zero, four, seven
three, but we're not going in that order because it's facing the other
direction.
So it's actually going to be 7403.
And that's actually all of the faces of the cube.
So what we need to do now and I guess I probably want to leave those
in place.
There is, I want to create these actual things.
So I'm going to for the time being actually just have the color, be
the color
Although you know what to make it easier for us to see to maybe, I'll
just do this.
So that way, we'll be able to see the corners of the cubes very nicely
before we start playing around with any other information about them
for these.
I'll just set them something.
Pretty basic, and we'll leave it at that.
The other thing we can do here, if we want to is we could turn off
texturing, just for these.
So we could see them a little bit better.
I don't know if we have any particular.
I don't know if we have anything particularly useful.
For textures that we would really apply here.
so, what I might do is just say
Let's just turn that off temporarily so we can see our Cube and we'll
deal with the rest of it later.
Alright, so we have some more work to do here.
Obviously we have much of the work to do here.
I guess these just want me to hand, hold it.
So it knows how to find the text the float in there.
That's fine.
Yeah.
and so, if we take a look at this here, we've got these
These Cube points and we just need to generate what they actually are.
So in order to generate the cube points,
I'm just going to go with what we correspond in the diagram.
And so you can see zero is negative negative positive for whatever
reason.
That's what we did.
Not sure why positive negative positive is one.
Two is all positive.
And three is.
Negative positive positive.
We then did the exact same thing on the back.
So 4 is negative negative negative.
And then we did positive negative, negative and positive positive
negative.
So those are our points.
And all we really need to know.
Now is what those sort of positions, actually.
We're and so, if we take a look at how our Cuba specified, right?
We have our Cube p and obviously, the exes.
We'll start with that, which is the centered and then they're just
going to subtract or add the radius.
Oops.
And the same would be true of the, why?
so, again, just subtracting it or adding the radius
Finally, the Z is a little bit different in this case, instead of
subtracting adding anything, we were saying, we were going to have the
top, which is the most positive part.
Be at zero and then we're going to have the height.
So to get the - the minimum value, we have to do a subtraction app but
those are all of them.
So now in theory we were actually drawing cubes.
I mean, assuming that we didn't screw something up and they're not
going to be pretty right there.
Going to be real ugly and you can see that they're actually really
ugly, they're there is our Cube and everything looks good about this
except for the fact that they're all in the same place with.
So we must not be setting the offset of our Cube properly.
So I got to go double-check that but otherwise you can see our cube is
kind of what we wanted it to be.
And so,
It's good, you know, yay for our Cube.
That's all fine and dandy.
So, let's go ahead and take a look.
I think that we just when we were specifying the pieces here, right?
We specify the offset is 0.
0 0, I think we never actually in entity offset that by the
traversable position, or whatever.
It was that we were trying to do there.
I don't think we actually managed to do so in push queues.
Yeah, we just passed the piece offset and we didn't use the entity
transform at all.
So the edit transform, in this case.
We want that offset to be baked in there, right?
So now we've got all our cubes, I don't know.
Since we're subtracting the radius, I guess the rectangle was a
straight Dimension.
So the fact that we are we're using this as a radius.
Now we would have to have the value.
So our cubes are too big but otherwise our cubes are correct.
Looks like for the most part.
That looks pretty much right to me and those look like they're drawing
in the right place.
And so all of our cubes are kind of happy and that's all good.
But obviously we still have the problem that I was talking about
before which I need, well, we got a couple different problems.
One is now, we have to deal with how our stuff intersex or does
intersect as the case may be.
So we're going to have to take a look at that.
But like, you can see, for example, this tree here, and this Cube and
how they interrelate
That's going to be kind of a problem for us and we're going to have
to, you know, have a sane solution for how we're doing with that
stuff.
Like probably what we want in most cases is we want Sprites for things
like trees to, you know, always be in front if they started in front,
you know, and we don't really want to deal with the interpenetration
right.
But you can see with how these things are lying.
And again, you can see why I wanted the debug camera stuff, you can
see with how flat those are lying.
We just have this problem with how they're going to
date with each other is going to cause problems for us.
And so that's just something that we're going to have to deal with.
Oh,
It's so let's just take care of some, some house keys being here.
we have some time left in the Stream, although I don't know how much
started at 10:30.
Right.
So we'll be done at 12:30.
I think we have about 15 minutes left so we got some more stuff.
We probably want to do.
Okay, so taking a look at this.
For example, first of all, we could try to find that bug because we
know we have a bug with the way that the world rooms are working.
That might be a little bit too much to start to the with your now.
So, for the moment, I'm going to ignore that guy and we will tackle
him probably tomorrow, I think would be the best time to take a look
at that one.
To do instead, here is just say, okay, what I can do is I can reduce
the variance of some of these to produce a more reasonable set of
ground positions.
Like so, which is a little more indicative of probably what we would
be doing in the game anyway.
Here is, you know, the hero will have the hero kind of come down the
screen here.
Well, that was very strange.
I think this monitor is getting confused with, I don't think I'm
varying anything.
Maybe I am
That's very strange.
All right anyway.
So this is yeah this is more or less.
What I wanted you can tell though it's going to get pretty rough in
here.
If this is actually how we were drawing all of our cubes in this weird
psychedelic crazy way so we probably don't want to be doing that at
the moment, even just for to buy produce this.
So now that I know that are cubes are correct.
I'm going to go ahead and and switch to drawing these cubes and
Slightly more sensible, in terms of their colors.
Something that we can actually use.
So, if I come in here and set the colors to something that actually is
representative.
So, here's the cube Colour itself,
and if we set the thing to the cube color,
sorry, Primo color.
We should be able to.
Get sort of something that's that's going to be a little more stable
for us here.
So, first off, if we set a texture on it like I said, I don't know
that we have any textures.
I'll try to find one here that I can use as a starting point.
But I don't know.
It's going to work particularly well.
Let's go ahead and start that off so you can see like that's now each
face of the cube has one of those little dudes, one of those little
grasses on it.
Unfortunately, all of those were made when I thought, you know, those
are just some test textures that we threw in there that were made when
I thought we were going to do stamping and I don't really want to do
stamp anymore because the point was to make things more much more Cube
like and so we kind of need some way of making those.
We need something that's going to
be more usable there.
I don't know that we have anything at the moment.
We should probably update to the new our pack.
I guess that's something that we probably should do soon.
Just so we have the right stuff to play with here.
I'll have to go talk to an about that.
And get the latest effort / so we can do that.
But is there anywhere to go?
Here I go.
Out of here.
But otherwise that should be okay, the thing about it is again, we
probably want some way to do some lighting there which we don't have
at the moment.
We really don't have any way of distinguishing those.
So we all sort of have this problem of wanting to be able to specify
some of those Cube colors.
A little more independently so that we can have them sort of reflect
their where they are roughly and how they should be colored
differently.
So there is a little bit
That.
So, I have to think about how we want to deal with that.
Oh and here you can see, this is the case I was talking about so good.
Let's go ahead and get in there.
So this was the case that I was talking about that.
I wanted to have sort of a an answer for you.
Can see here there's this Cube and it's a little obviously difficult
because wonder if there's any what if we have anything at all?
That's an asset we could use in that location.
That would be more just want a flat lie.
Grass texture.
That doesn't have soft edges.
I just don't know if we had one in that pack.
I don't think we did.
Yeah, I really just don't think we did.
I'll try a couple things here to see if there's anything.
I could try some things and see, I don't think there is
Oh God.
Yeah.
I think we are.
SOL my friends.
so yeah, I guess I couldn't say
I guess I'm going to leave that till we have something better for it,
but all I'm trying to all I was trying to point out as you can see
here that you've got a cube and the tree is sticking directly into the
cube, right?
And so, when you view it from above, you're going to get that
artifact.
Now, that artifact is not necessarily an incorrect artifact in certain
senses.
Meaning, you know, we're again because we are still a 2-D game.
I'm just using some 3D rendering to, give us some nice effects, and
some better performance than what we would have.
If we had to do Sprites sorting and stuff like that, that I wasn't
happy with.
So it's not necessarily that that's wrong.
It's just that you know, when we're creating this world that doesn't
quite exist, right?
Because we've drawn 2D assets, but we're using them in a 3D way to
produce a 3D sort of effect.
You do have to sort of figure out how you're going to account for the
fact that sometimes you will end up with 3D problems with that 2D
fakery and you need a way around them.
And so that's what I was talking about in the
And we're because these things actually are leaning like this.
When you look at them from the side, they can interpenetrate with
relatively low stacked, things behind them, and that's bad, right?
so what we need to do there is we need to have some sort of a
A way to combat that.
And that's why I think one of the things that we probably want to do
is is have that sort of fake Z, so that things that are upright cards
get fake Z buffer values to allow them to sort differently than they
would otherwise and I don't know again like I said if that's a good or
bad idea but it seems like the right idea.
For the time being we're about out of time.
So I will go ahead and go to the Q&A for now, but that's roughly what
I wanted there.
So I think we're good.
We need to do.
Oh.
Well, you know what, in the five minutes what I can do to though, I
can also go into our Sprite code and re-enable the
Because that's really easy for us to do now.
So, you know, right now you can see our hero is not cheering or doing
any of those sort of things that you see L do.
The reason for that is because inside the render group, when we're
pushing down these axes, we're just using the camera action camera,
why directly?
And we're not ever using the x-axis y-axis that were actually getting
past here but what we can do pretty easily there is we can
Defy the code that we were placing here?
So we get our x axis Y axis, we can actually produce those axes by
doing the, by reinterpreting long, the cameras X and Y axis itself,
right?
So we know, for example, the x axis is X is talking about something
that goes along the camera x-axis, and we know that the x axis Y is
now something that goes along cameras y-axis.
So we can actually reproduce what those axes those rotated Axis or
sheared axes depending on what we got.
Last weekend just reproduce what they would have been in the camera
plane by using the cameras, two basis, vectors for that purpose and
then you can see that we re enable the shearing that we wanted exactly
like it used to be in 2D.
It's now in 3D in that plane of the camera, right?
And that's exactly what we wanted.
So again getting closer to a regular 3D version of the world here and
you know, when we go ahead and fix Alpha and get some real bitmaps in
there, we're getting very close to a proper, you know, a prepper thing
that you could actually show someone and say here is, you know, a
reasonable looking screen.
We do have quite quite a few little things to take care of before we
get there, right?
All right, so let me go ahead and go to the Q&A.
Mansfield asked any particular reason for using counterclockwise for
front faces as opposed to clockwise at?
No, not really.
So, the choice is arbitrary.
And in fact, not only is the choice arbitrary, but you can also pick
this.
So, you know, 3D apis and graphics cards.
Let you determine which faces are called in which faces are drawn,
whether you want counterclockwise faces drawn or clockwise faces
drawn.
The choice is purely arbitrary and up to the programmer in all
practical senses.
As to why it is typically used as counterclockwise in modern circles.
The reason is, you know, math.
And so I talked about the concept of right-handed coordinate system.
And a right-handed coordinate system.
Again is one where if I was to draw the coordinate system and I was to
take my hand and put my fingers so that they curl from X to y.
Right?
And I look at what direction.
My thumb sticks out.
That's my thumb.
Apparently.
My thumb sticks out along the z-axis.
Right.
So if you take a look at at just that, you know, right-handed curl,
it's a right hand.
If you take a right hand, you curl it from X to Y and their thumb
points out along Z.
That's a concept of a right-handed coordinate system for whatever
reason, the majority of math favors, right handed coordinate systems.
It favors coordinate systems where Y is up
And access to the side and Z comes out at you right comes out of the
page of the math book, if you will and that is the right handed
coordinate system.
The cross product is and geometric, algebra is typically written in
right-hand terms.
So, when you're talking about things like sheets and you have vectors
that point out of the sheets, it's usually right handed in that the
winding of these sheets is that way and the thing goes out that way.
So,
the reason that we tend to order vertices counterclockwise is just
because if you tend to be favoring right-handed, as your standard for
how you're doing math,
You think of a face?
As if you were to curl your fingers in, counterclockwise your thumb
points out in the direction, the face is facing.
And so again that's another just example of right-handedness there.
And just to be clear, this has nothing to do with actually being
left-handed or right-handed because it doesn't matter what your
dominant hand is.
Obviously you can curl either one.
So a left-handed or right-handed person.
No one is that it it wasn't like the mathematicians got together and
decided they liked it right handed people better than left-handed.
People are something for whatever reason, that's just the orientation
of the coding system.
It has nothing to do with whether you're right-handed or left-handed.
It's just saying which hand tells you the winding and the axis
Direction that's about it.
And in some sense you would think if you know I suppose there's
there's certainly more right-handed people in the world than
left-handed people.
But oddly enough if you think about it mathematically speaking this is
actually made more for left-handed people than for any other people.
Because if you are doing math you probably have a pencil in your
dominant hand and your dominant hand, in the case of a right-handed
person is their right hand, which means they cannot actually curl that
hand to check.
So it's actually a left-handed person holding a
And or a pencil doing math who can actually invoke the right hand rule
fastest, not a right-handed person.
So I don't know why they picked it.
It clearly wasn't to favor, right handed people.
If anything it's sort of favors left-handed people, I don't know if
there was a deeper reason.
Why counterclockwise is important.
It could be in that math way that like there's some weird nonsense
about like quantum physics is right.
Handed by nature or something weird like this where this the windings
are?
That way?
I have no idea, you know, sometimes stuff like that comes up and
you're like, oh no it's not arbitrary.
It's here for a reason that could be I have never heard of one though.
Like no one's ever told me.
Oh yeah, it's because of this fundamental physical principle.
So, it makes sense.
That mass should always be, you know, this way.
So, I don't know why it's that way.
That's just what it is.
The size of a debug camera pan control.
Might be a good idea.
I do agree.
That's probably true.
Probably wait till we actually need it.
But yes.
Correct tivities.
Why have everything slightly tilted?
Wouldn't it make more sense to sort the assets according to their
bottom or if you're using 3D space go for Ortho camera and using the Z
position for sorting.
So I think there's kind of two questions in there.
Because why have everything slightly tilted is is an aesthetic
question.
Right now, to programming question, whereas the second part
A programming question.
So I'm not sure if those are supposed to be related, they don't sound
like it, so I'll answer them separately.
But if they're supposed to be related, you can let me know.
So, the reason I kind of like having everything slightly tilted
potentially is it just adds a little bit more visual interest, right?
It adds a little bit more depth to the scene.
So you know if I've got the debug camera here, I can I can play
certainly with various ways of keeping this scene oriented and if I
want to let you know, I can have it be
The straight up and down the problem with having to be straight up and
down, is I would lose a little bit.
Perhaps, potentially of that sort of ability to harmonize the Sprites
with the background, right?
And what I mean by that and you'll kind of see, you can actually see
this in the way that we are doing the handmade hero art, which we
should probably.
Like I said, we need to put it in sometime.
Soon, let's go ahead and go to Molly rocket.
So if you take a look at the way that we're doing, the handmade here
are here, you can actually see that we're taking a pretty top down
perspective to it to try and keep it closer to the actual perspective
of the action.
And so part of making those Sprites be
Part of harmonizing them with the background is perhaps reflecting
that tilt a little bit in the perspective of the background so that
your is to do less work to sort of harmonize those and understand
things spatially, right?
We could have made it so that you were directly top down but then you
lose a lot of the character of the Sprites.
Because if you're directly top down, you can't really even see
someone's face.
And so there are games, you know, like Hotline Miami for example, or
something like that.
Where you take a look?
At the way they did it and it is directly top-down, right?
And so that's not necessarily because I can't actually get a bigger.
There we go.
So that's not necessarily a bad idea because you can see games that
have done it and you know, they work but it definitely it definitely
has the effect of distances saying you a certain amount from the
character of the game.
And in some cases like hot my light Hotline Miami that may be very
appropriate.
I mean this is a game about kind of a lot of, you know, Mass Slaughter
and some you know, Crazy Action sequences where everyone is dying,
including you all the time and there's blood everywhere and it's you
know, a giant sort of essentially desensitized thing.
It makes some sense to go, you know, we don't really necessarily want
this game to be about seeing the characters expressions or
Because that, you know, there's a lot of reasons why he wouldn't want
that.
But you know, in a game like handmade hero, it's a little bit
different.
Where we kind of have these characters that you did want to see their
faces.
So, you know, it's a little bit more.
Angled like that.
And so that's why I think I might like it to be, you know, it might
not be this angle but it might be a little bit.
Angled, in terms of the way in which the camera is is placed relative
in terms of tilt relative to the world.
That's just my gut feeling.
And again you know these are not that's not some kind of a
prescription or saying you have to do it that way because every game
is different and the appropriate thing to do in any particular game is
is definitely different.
So you know something like this is probably what I would be looking
for.
But I again I'm not quite sure yet exactly what I want there but
that's the basic idea as for your other questions which was
Sort of more about programming that the Aesthetics of it, I you said,
would it make more sense to sort the assets according to their bottom?
And the answer there is that you actually can't do that.
So we spent some time on him and they're looking at that and that does
not actually work for any kind of complex sort of seeing that you
might want to create.
There's a bunch of cases that don't work.
If you sort that way and there a lot of cases that we wanted, you can
go back and watch.
The episodes on sorting where we talked about this in a little more
detail.
I would also recommend you
Let's see here.
Retro City Rampage.
I would refer you to
not that one.
Is it?
It's not, right?
Is it Retro City?
What's the new?
There's a new one.
I can't remember the name of the new one.
It's not Retro City.
Rampage, it's Retro City.
Something else.
River City Ransom, that's what it is.
Sorry, I got that wrong.
So I would I would highly recommend reading this because it's laid out
in a nice concise blog format and basically
this is a case where Andrew Russell took some stuff we were talking
about and handmade hero and he was like, oh hey, I've already had to
deal with this in the game that
Working on, which is River City.
Ransom and let me tell you more about how I did it and sort of like
what we're going to do here, right?
And so, he points out some really obvious when you think about them.
But not obvious until you've actually gone through the work cases
where you need to do relatively complex things.
If you want sprite rolls to start properly and they all have to do
with the fact that perspective is kind of baked into Sprites when
artists draw them.
And you can kind of see here.
This really simple example that you wouldn't think twice about where
for example you've got this car here and that's you know all you
really needed to know, right?
Is there's a car and I got some
Writes well just sort them by the Baseline like you said, but of
course, it doesn't work at all to do that because you may find that
depending on where they are logically relative to these things, it may
be that sometimes starting by the Baseline works and sometimes from
the Baseline does not work, right?
And so what he found is that the only real way to do that particularly
well is to actually do use some logic about, he actually has some
voxel information in there.
Use logic about how the perspective is encoded in this, right?
And use that, which is pretty hardcore, right?
So, hopefully that blog entry, I don't know, the easiest way to get to
it, but let's see what the minimum Search terms are.
So River Sprite.
Sorting seems to be the quickest way to get there.
Maybe I don't know if that'll actually work or not but I would highly
recommend that blog entry as a good way to just kind of be like okay I
see why this is a little bit harder if you actually want to have some
complex cases.
Obviously you can design your whole game around avoiding these, and
then and then sort by the Baseline sir.
We, you know, you can special case stuff, and sort of hack together,
something that works.
But I was kind of more interested in something that would be a little
bit more expressive and not require a lot of special casing.
And so, this is what I felt like was the most logical thing.
In terms of your final question which was wouldn't it make more sense?
I'm sorry if you're using 3D space go for an orthogonal camera using
the Z position for sorting and the answer is I'm not sure.
I really want, orthogonal camera.
I like we've done some stuff with like room stacked on top of each
other and I kind of like having the perspective in there.
So I don't know that I really want an orthographic camera.
So we're probably going to stick with the protect the camera even if
we only
It's relatively subtle camera effects.
That's probably still going to stay that way.
And it's not particularly hard for us to deal with, really, I don't
think because like I said, the only real artifact that I'm thinking
of, is the one where we just is, the one where things are very sort
of, because they're very slanted, they interpenetrate things behind
them.
And all, I really have to do is modify the Z value for the depth
buffer.
And I think I'd probably be okay.
Are, I don't think it's gonna be too bad.
That's the old.
I noticed the camera in hand made here is defined by camera x y z and
P.
Can I get x y z kind of get x y and C from a quaternion?
Is that a good idea?
I mean, if you had quite turn Ian's on handmade hero, would you define
the camera using A quaternion and P?
The answer is yes.
If I had quaternions and handmade here right now, I would use A
quaternion and P and I would generate the XYZ axes from the
quaternion.
It's not particularly difficult because a quaternion one of the first
things that you will learn to do.
If you learn quaternions, is how to turn a quaternion into a matrix
and if you turn a quaternion to a matrix as I've sort of gone over
multiple times on handmade hero, you know how to extract the axes from
that.
So you can just look at the math for turning country into a matrix and
it's very clear just from looking at what the terms are of that
Matrix.
Exactly what the
Terms would be for the axes.
So it's very, very simple to turn a quaternion into a set of three
axes if that's what you would prefer.
And so in cases like these, when we want to be able to access those,
there's no mystery to it.
It's really no different.
It's very straightforward.
All right, let's see, the last question.
What is the X and B, 32 x and use rejects?
Those are there just to specify that I don't actually care.
If there are 32 bits, just as just that they are, as long as 32 bits
or rather can store 32 bits, but they could be 64 bits or anything
else.
I go back and forth on some of these things, one of the big problems
that you end up with.
So, so, so there's there's a lot of issues, right?
And I don't want to go down a huge Rat Hole on this because it
literally has nothing to do with.
You know, anything that we're going to have to really think about it
all here.
You know, so it's not critical to handmade hero but I'll just point it
out and that is that there's usually two things that you need to
specify in when you're when you're talking about a variable or a
member of a structure, whatever.
There's like, exactly.
You know, n Bits.
and at least,
So when you think about these cases, why do you need them?
The answer is that if I'm doing something like structured, use of
memory or reading from a file, then exactly n Bits may be important.
The reason it may be important is let's say I've got something like a
bitmap header on disk and the specification for the bitmap header is
like it's got a u16, right?
So it's got an unsigned 16 bit value.
That's like, you know, the
The width or something.
NAU 16.
That's the height.
And this is in my header.
Well, I can't very well tell the compiler.
You know, there's a width value and it's got to be at least 16 bits,
but I don't really care how big it is.
And then another one, that's a height value because I'm reading these
out of the file.
And so if I expect to read them in a block, and then look at them
right in the file, in memory, as they were in the file, their can't.
It has to be exactly 16 bits because the next value starts right there
after 16 bits worth of information.
Was the height.
So I need to be able to say, for laying out things in case, they're in
file formats.
Or in case you're getting transmitted over a network where they're
going into a data format that has to be understood by multiple
machines, that maybe have code working on different compilers of
different languages.
This has to be specified.
Exactly.
And so one thing you're doing is specifying exactly, n Bits.
And so in my parlance, I use like you 16, you 32s, 16, whatever, I use
these
For exactly.
But there's other times where you don't actually need things to be
exactly.
And in that case, I try to use a syntax, I didn't really do it on
handmade here originally and then I started doing because we're just a
force of habit so I apologize.
It's in there now.
But my intention was to skip it because I didn't really want to get
into it but I ended up doing it anyway and at least in bits is like
you 32x.
You 16 x Etc.
These are saying well I need 32 bits of space because the
Requires that much.
But if your operations are faster.
On 64 bits instead, use it because some CPUs are faster when they
don't have to downshift to smaller than their native sighs.
Sometimes it's more expensive it takes more operations for example you
know on something let I don't know probably like I think a powerpc had
this at one point certainly Intel had it I think at one point with you
16s
Can't quite remember though, where there were cases where using the
32-bit values, it's faster than using a 16-bit value.
So, forcing the compiler to the 65.
You can slow it down right, again.
Not always the case on Modern Intel CPUs, like the ones in this
computer right here, I don't know that there's any penalties of that
nature.
Well, the top of my head, I can't think of any penalties for using a
smaller type than a larger type at the moment.
But doesn't mean there aren't?
I just can't think of them but that is not always the case.
And on different platforms, you will encounter this problem.
And so I try to notate my code at least to a certain extent with that
information.
So it makes it easier for me to tune it later on platforms like that.
How much time and effort, do you spend preparing for each episode?
01 of the requirements I had for doing the series, as I wanted to
basically have to do everything on the stream with no preparation.
So there's never any preparation.
I just sit down and do the series programming.
What I would, you know, as close as possible doing what I would
normally do in whatever the programming situation is, I just try to
explain it as I go.
Oh, and Mansfield asked why be 32x and not be 1X or b8x?
That's another good question.
So you know I use B to indicate a Boolean, right?
And so the question is why not be 1X?
Because a Boolean only needs one bit.
Surely you don't need 32 bits for Boolean so isn't 32x, you know kind
of wrong.
The answer is because that's not actually what I use that syntax.
for, when I use,
A bee is just letting me know.
That.
I intend the value to be used in a billion fashion.
So 0 is false and any other value is true, that's all the be means for
me.
So what the actual size part means is what I expect it to harmonize
with because I'm going to be using those values intermixed with other
integer values.
So the answer is I pick the Boolean size based on whatever the size is
of the stuff around it, that I'm using it with typically.
But that's it.
If that makes sense.
And dude, and baseman, who is asking, can I can we do cubic spline?
Sometimes we probably will do a cubic spline on here at some point but
I would I would just point out the fact.
That that's actually up here somewhere.
Here it is.
So, if you go to this stream, this is an hour long stream.
That explains cubic spline interpolation, really explicitly, right?
You can kind of it's It's it has everything.
From start to finish on cubic splines.
So, you know,
If you want to check that out, that's everything that you we would
cover on this, if we get there.
It's already in that video.
All right, so that's about it.
I'm going to go ahead and close it down.
Alright everyone, thank you very much for joining me for another
episode of handmade here.
It's been a pleasure coding with you.
As always, if you want following series, you can always prayer to the
game on handmade hero dot-org.
It comes to the source code so you can play around with it and
experiment.
We also have a forum site.
You can go to.
If you want to ask questions, we have a patreon page, you can use to
support the video series.
We have a schedule bot, which treats the schedule at you, if you want
to know, what days and what times were going to be live?
And then you have an episode guide, you can go to if you want to catch
up on old episodes.
That's about it for this week.
I'll be back.
I'm sorry, not for this week for today.
I'll be back tomorrow when we can.
I think just we just need to do some debugging.
Now there's a couple bugs in there that we need to take care of.
And you know, I don't know, maybe go ahead and do the split sorting
for things like Shadows that are going to have.
Be drawn in a second pass so we can probably do those two things
tomorrow.
And then next weekend, we'll start on the open gel stuff that we need
to do in terms of putting in some Shader code and multi sample
anti-aliasing resolves.
So that we can clean up the artifacts that we have in there like the
sort problem and the fringy Blinky Edge stuff which needs to get taken
care of.
So I hope you'll join me for those.
That's about it until tomorrow have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.