Okay, here we go.
So, someone asked a question in the beginning of that sort of the
pre-chat here on the stream and they kind of wanted me to go back over
where, everything lives they said.
They said, like, we're destructs live and where two variables live and
stuff like that and where two functions live.
And the reason that I want to address that question specifically is
because I am very glad someone asked, we have sort of said, where
these things live, but it's hard to kind of take a lot of this stuff
in when I say it.
And I really do want people to constantly be thinking about that where
things live.
So I would like to mention again where everything lives.
Code, which is like the, you know, the things that we write here code
lives first in the executable file.
So when we compile everything and we get a DOT exe file, the code is
in there and the code is encoded.
Code is encoded.
The code is encoded in a format.
That is defined by Intel that basically says well.
And it's, there's also defined by AMD now, because I think they were
the ones who officially did the x64 spec for 64-bit Computing.
But Arc, this code is being compiled for 32-bit Computing.
So, defined by Intel and encoding in binary that basically says, what
the instructions are that the CPU supposed to do.
So, we have an executable, and the executable has that in it.
And, oh,
Wait, you know, what?
Do you guys think?
I don't know if you're feeling this.
Like I'm feeling this but I think this could be a place where we could
bring out the Gimp.
I don't know what you guys.
I don't know if you guys feel it.
You know, I don't want to, I don't want to tell you how you're
feeling.
Okay?
I want you to be in touch with your own feelings, but I feel like this
is a place where I could get out, the Wacom drawing tablet.
I got this little tab, but I've had it for a long time and I could
just go ahead and draw a diagram.
Right, let's do that.
Let's diagram this.
Let's just go crazy.
Out of this, could be a big mistake.
Like I said, Sunday, stream, Sunday, stream, anything goes.
I think you just have to say that.
That's, I mean, you know, people have standards and standards are
good.
But sometimes you just got to go nuts.
So, let's see here.
So, let's see.
Can I get a smaller pen about us about?
Oh God what has happened?
Yeah, my gimp skills are not the best game skills in the world.
Let's see here.
There we go.
That seems that seems reasonable.
So basically what happens is we have all our code.
Oh God, this is going to be awful.
Oh, man.
I
Gonna have to learn to use the Gimp better or learn how to use a Wacom
drawing tablet better, I guess.
All right.
Let's see here.
So we have code.
That we right, right?
And the compiler and the Linker.
Well.
So, the code goes into the compiler, right?
The compiler.
Spits out.
Actually what's called an obj file and we'll be looking at those in
the mainstream a little bit.
The obj files go into the Linker.
And they're joined with things called Libs.
And
Ribs are basically a bunch of obj's that have been compiled together
into a, into a group.
So there are things like the system libraries and stuff that that sort
of allows you to pay for the system.
These all go in to the Linker this time.
You know what guys?
This diagram is turning out.
Awesome.
Look at this.
This is awesome.
Tell me, you don't love this diagram.
This is amazing.
I mean, look at it already.
Look at the Majesty anyway, so the code gets goes in the compiler.
Sit down obj, file lives and obj is go into the Linker and the linkers
fix.
Us out an executable, right?
And that sits on disk.
And this is actually, this is in basically a Microsoft slat.
Well, wow, that's good.
Microsoft Intel format, and what that means is basically Microsoft
because it's Windows defined.
The format of this executable, which is basically the layout on disk
and the layout involves stuff like.
And this is not the actual layout of an egg, see because I don't even
remember the actual there that's recent years since I've looked at it,
but it's basically something that's like, you know,
Header that says, this is an executable file.
This is, this is the XE on disk.
This is on disk, right?
It's got like a fix-up table, right?
So there's a thing in here, which basically a bunch of data that says,
where we called system calls, like, where we called all the stuff that
needs to go to the opportunism, and then it's got Intel format code,
right?
It's got its got the operands for the CPU, all the stuff that's got
all the CPU code that we actually generated all bound up in here,
right?
So, then what's going to happen is 0.
And feel this.
Are you ready for this?
This is going to be insane.
You're not, you're not ready for it.
I know you're not but dig it, right.
Are you feeling that?
Insane.
Right?
You didn't think I could do it, but I did.
All right.
So what basically happens is, you know, you can, you can go look this
up there.
If you look up, Windows, executable or something on, Wikipedia, you
can go look up the actual structure of this if you're curious about it
because it's not that complicated, pretty straightforward.
But basically what happens is Windows, then comes along.
It's like, you know, in the Shell, you say, I want to run this
executable, right?
You're just like I got to run this executable.
So what it's going to do is it's going to load up this code, right?
It's going to take this code and it's going to put this code.
To memory somewhere.
So, here's the memory.
Now of the machine, right?
And it's going to take the Intel code stuff.
It's going to put it in here.
Then when it's going to do is going to look at this Fickett up this
fix-up table, which basically tells it a bunch of places in this code,
where we called system calls.
Because remember when I said one of the streams, I'm like, we don't
actually compile the whole thing together.
We, there's always a little bit of linking left to be done because any
place we call a system call.
Well, the system Windows is outside of our executable.
So, we basically have to call Windows is
Executable code somehow.
And how are we gonna do that?
We can't compile all of Windows into our thing, because then you'd
have to start Windows with our code in it somehow, right?
That doesn't make any sense.
We'd have to write the operating system for that to be true.
Wouldn't that be a nice World by the way, that's how things used to
work on like the Amiga and stuff.
Used to actually have kind of when you wrote a game.
It would boot right into the game.
No or c64 as well, but ignoring all that so many, what happens is, it
goes in here, the OS goes in this fix up table, basically, and I'm
skipping a lot of kind of minutiae, but base is going to read a fix-up
table.
That says, here's a places, they called system calls, so, go right
into the memory and patch over, like overwrite.
The the sort of blank area that's talking about the the system call
with an actual pointer to Windows, right?
Windows code.
So, you know, and I'm going to draw this a little more sanely because
this I can actually do a little more.
So, here's Windows code.
Okay, and the question is, how does Windows could get there this?
If you remember I talked about virtual memory and virtual address
spaces, right?
And I said that when you run your program you get your own virtual
address space and I'm like, it's your own address space.
It's all your own memory and windows behind the scenes.
It's kind of mapping that memory to Ram.
So this is our virtual address space basically and it doesn't
necessarily correspond to the physical memory that machine.
It just Maps it in and out as it's necessary, right?
So what happens actually, is that in your virtual?
Memory space Windows actually goes ahead and Maps.
A copy of the stuff that you need to call into your virtual address
space.
So it takes it from its space, right?
Here's the actual Windows code that's actually running in its own, you
know, address space and doing whatever.
The, you know, it wants to do and basically it goes ahead map that
into your address space then it patches up your code to point into
that code.
So any time you called like when we had our code on of still in there,
I think it is.
Yeah, so we would have this output debug string call.
Right, and we need to call Windows.
That's what was going on.
It was basically, when the code was loaded, it was finding that call
using the fix-up table that the Linker output and it was patching, a
call to the actual location of output debug string, which was
somewhere in here, right?
That's roughly, how Lincoln goes when all of that fix up is done.
Then it uses one final piece of information in.
It's not really called.
It wouldn't be called a fix-up in.
It wouldn't be in a fix of table quote-unquote, but it would be the
entry point.
Which is basically the location in this code to start running and it
just jumps right into that and then goes right.
That is how basically something gets running on an operating system.
And like I said, I skipped a lot of minutiae there and every operating
system has all kinds of crazy wacky stuff that's going on.
That's, you know, probably a little different from from this but that
is a reasonable conceptual model of what's happening when you actually
do stuff.
So when you ask where code lives, that is where code lives.
It first lives in the executable.
In here, it then gets loaded into memory and mind you.
It can often be demand, paged into memory.
So it will be virtually mapped into memory, but it may not actually
get copied into memory until you actually hit the part of the code
that you actually need to run it which case it'll load that in the
starting to look like a John Madden.
Kind of diagram, you know what I mean?
Anyway, so basically, what happens is that code, get lives in us in a
space in memory that
Windows allocated and windows map it in now against it's a Sunday
stream and we're just going all out in the Sunday stream.
I mean, look, you came to the stream on Sunday.
I get to do whatever I want on Sunday.
Okay, that's just weird.
Making a new rule.
I know we don't have rules on this this stream yet, but it's like
that's just the way things are.
Okay.
It's like it's anything goes on a Sunday stuff, just goes nuts.
So basically what happens is the virtual memory system.
You'll remember I talked about
Pages, right.
So if I have an address space, if I have a virtual memory address
space, will call that a beam as virtual memory address space, right?
And it starts at 0, and it goes up to like high number, very high
number.
Many gigabytes of memory potentially, especially on 64-bit on 32-bit.
The highest number.
You can represent is 4 billion, so it can only go up to 4 billion.
But in, you know, 64 bit and go up much higher than that, because
64-bit is huge.
Anyway, I have a virtual memory address space and it's divided up into
Pages.
These things are called Pages.
This is a
Age.
This is a page.
Right?
And these pages are typically like 4096 bytes, right?
Or sixty, four thousand bytes.
Well, 65536 64k.
It's time to 1024.
These pages are usually sizes like that.
So they're pretty granular.
But, you know, they store a fair bit, you know, 64k is a fair bit of
data in there.
There's will there's, you know, reason why stuff in there.
So the virtual memory address space is divided up into pages and those
pages.
There's basically like a table, right?
There's going to be a table in the operating system, that is, you
know, think it's usually called a page table.
I don't really know what they call it in Windows.
But anyway, there's usually a table and what that table does is that
table records like what's going on with these Pages.
Just like, okay this page, you know is actually stored on disk
somewhere because we paged it out.
So this is this page is out in disk.
So, you know, it's not actually in memory.
There's no physical memory back.
But this page right here, you know, that is in physical memory.
That's that's over here in the actual memory of the machine or
something like this.
And like I said, I don't know how they implemented this on window.
So I'm not trying to tell you anything.
Specific about how Windows works.
I'm just saying, conceptually, it's good.
Going to kind of understand the opposite of knows where these things
are.
Now, the processor, the Intel processor basically has ways it has
support for this in the hardware.
We're basically each page can have flag set on it and those flags.
I have to do with what can happen that page.
It's like, can you read this page?
Can you write this page?
Can you executive this page?
Can you execute code basically in this page?
Right?
And those flags are set on the page?
So what windows will do is it'll go, I am running low on physical
memory of the moment.
I need to make some space in the physical memory and this page is like
in the physical memory.
So what I'll do is I'll grab what's in this page.
I'll write it out to disk and then I'm going to unset the read and
write flags for this.
Page or something like this, right?
And the exact page.
I'll so I'll just it's guarded.
The page is now completely off your
Can't do anything to it.
Right?
What will then happen is when your code goes to do something on that
page, whether it's happens to be a code page.
So it's going to try to execute code, you know, and the as it's
exiting through the instructions, that eventually gets into this page
and tries to execute something, or if it's memory in your trying to
read from it, or right to it.
Like you would just variables or in there whatever and you're
accessing them.
What will happen is your process will just grind to an immediate Halt
and you'll have what's called a page fault, right?
You will basically cause a fault, they'll be an interrupt and the
operating
Some will wake back up and the Intel processor.
Basically gives the op, you know, gives the operating system, the
option to do something at that time, and what the operating system
will do is we'll go.
Oh, somebody needs this page now.
Okay, I'll go back out to disk.
I'll get it.
I'll shove it back in here.
And once it's loaded, I'll restart that process where it left off.
So basically freezes what you're doing, does the operation necessary
to put it back in there and then keeps going.
So hopefully that makes some sense and that's true of code Pages as
well as data pages and everything else.
That's what
Virtual memory system basically is, it's a system where the operating
system wakes up anytime.
Somebody needs a page.
That's not there and does something to make that work.
Now what can happen if the program is just bad.
If the program is written wrong and we'll have this happen during our
stream.
I'm sure because it's easy to have bugs in your code.
Obviously you might accidentally right to a page that's off-limits.
Like for example, you never allocated anything.
In this page.
This page is not even a thing.
You just wrote to an address some random address in memory.
You tried to
Right to it.
And you never even told the opportunism, something was there?
Because all these Pages before, the operating system, is going to
start tracking them, all the pages.
They have to actually be known to operate system.
So you have to make calls to operation.
To say, I'm going to use memory in this page now, right?
So what happens then is you get a page fault and the operating system
wakes up and goes, I don't know that page.
What, what is that page?
That doesn't make any sense?
You're obviously messed up and I'm going to stop you.
And that's when you get that little box, that's like this system has
caused an access.
Station, right?
And you've all seen this, you've all been playing the game and have
that happen.
I guarantee if you've played PC games, you've had an access violation
pop up in your like, wah, wah, wah,
Well, that's what happened.
Basically, someone had a pointer pointing somewhere.
It shouldn't they rode into it or God knows what something bad
happened and off you went.
Okay, so that's kind of a conceptual model for it.
Right?
So basically the first answer to where code code and data and all that
stuff lives is it lives in that virtual address space and basically
that virtual address space is broken up into pages.
So here are my pages.
Right?
And each page is basically stored somewhere.
It's either in the physical memory.
Right.
So each page is either in there.
Or it's on disk somewhere.
Right.
And so what will happen is for efficiency sake, when Windows goes to
load your code, which is on disk the executable, what it might choose
to do because there's no reason it can't what it might.
To do is not ever actually load the code.
It might just map the pages, right?
It'll map these pages to the spot on the drive, where your code
actually is, then it'll just start executing the code right in the
main memory, that doesn't exist, and let the page faulting bring the
code actually in.
It could decide to do that, right.
And for efficiency, maybe that's a good idea.
Because now if there's code that you don't ever really execute very
often, it never has to get loaded.
Might not be a great idea for a performance because it means when you
go to exit this piece of code, the first time it's like, oh puis hit,
you know, we got to go page out to disk that set.
Cetera, so the smarter thing would probably be to start this loading
all the pages, but you could start executing beforehand.
And that way, if you didn't beat, if the disk didn't beat the code to
the execution, it could do, blah, blah, blah.
There's all sorts of sit here.
It's good.
It's all good.
Anyway, that is some fun diagramming of where the code lives.
So,
I'm going to rearrange this here.
Now.
Let's talk about where everything else lives.
So functions.
They all live in there.
They all live in the executable.
Then they get paged into distant page, into the memory as a need to
get executed in the CPU.
Pulls them in execute them.
Now since we're being banana cakes, there's one more thing.
You should be aware of.
Here's the CPU.
This is my x86.
It's actually an x 64 in this machine, but it has an x86 has the
ability to execute x86 code.
So, typically in a CPU, you know, we've got code here and I said it
was in, you know, the Intel encoded format, right?
And I showed this, I actually showed you this encoding, right?
If you remember, I showed it to you.
We did something where I went in here and I did like, you know, I
don't know.
Something.
I don't know what we're doing.
Who knows what we were doing at the time, but I went in here and I did
go to disassembly, and there is this button here is show code bites.
Right?
And I did show code B on and off and basically what happened there was
I just turned on the ability to see what the actual encoding was the
instruction.
So this is what's actually stored in the executable and what's
actually going to run on disk.
What's actually in a run in memory when it's loaded.
This is the actual encoding.
That's what stored.
It's these bites right here.
Right here is the location in memory where the bite is stored.
And here's the B, and this is each instruction.
So, here's a function call in the function, call is encoded this way,
right?
So that stuff is in memory somewhere.
So it got loaded into memory and the CPU is trying to access it.
So the CPU comes and grabs it as it needs to.
So, as it's executing instructions.
It's going to the next instruction.
The next instruction hasn't been loaded yet.
It goes off to get it.
And what happens is it brings it into the to to the CPU but not
necessarily directly.
There's a thing typically called an eye cash, right?
And that's an called.
I cash.
I believe because it stands for instruction cache and basically what
happens is the sea.
EP, you may not.
Like to directly execute stuff out of memory because that stuff may
need to be sort of further munged for the CPU to use it.
It may need to expand some things that may need to microcode certain
think, I mean, who knows?
What does I like?
I said not a hardware designer.
I'm not going to try and pretend I know exactly why they have all
these things but point being it becomes more efficient for the CPU to
basically cash the instructions that it executes in like in its cache,
you know, it's local cache on the seat.
EU so that it can quickly access code that it's running.
So, for example, if you have a loop and that Loop is going to execute
tons of times or something, you're running all this code, it wants to
do a bunch of work on that code first and then be able to just execute
that code straight out of its cash instead of going to memory every
time to kind of pull it back in.
So, there is this thing called an eye cash and it does exist on most
CPUs.
Now that basically preps the code for use, by the CPU, in some way
that the CPU understands and it's used as a local sort of way of
storing that code.
Now, you may think
That's complete minutiae.
That's uninteresting.
And you never need to know it.
I have actually seen times on projects where the I cash was the
problem.
I think I even may have created and I cash problem one time I think on
Bink to I did a bunch of stuff with code generation that later on a
certain platform Fabi and end up having to optimize by just making the
code smaller because the I cash was actually a penalty like filling
the eye.
Cash was actually problem, don't quote me on that ask Bobby about it.
But anyway, so that's basically what happens with with code now with
data, right?
You'll remember.
So I've got these pages, right?
We keep going back to this page has thing, but I have Pages Pages
pages.
So here's my virtual memory address space and I've got all these pages
in there.
Well, what happens when I start executing my code, right?
And you know, you look back here and you got, you know, we came into
in Maine.
So we were in Maine, having a good old time and I try to declare this
local variable.
It's a projectile, right?
This big, it's a 16 byte structure or something that we've got here.
Right?
It's this thing.
I wanted to Claire and I talked about the fact that it goes on the
stack.
Well, what is the stack?
And I sort of showed, you know, I showed how you could go look at
where the memory was and that sort of stuff.
But I also said that someone has to allocate everything and so the
person who is doing that was actually the startup code.
I think it's hmm.
I think it's actually the startup code in Windows that sets up the
stack for you.
I'm pretty sure I'm about it.
I'm pretty sure that's true.
Not the C runtime library because I've compiled without the C runtime
library and didn't have to set up the stack myself.
So I think Windows actually sets up the stack for you.
And what the stack is is it's basically it Maps a page and it
basically says, okay this first page here at some address for this
particular thread of execution of your code is going to be this page.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to set a guard page right after
that page that basically says.
As soon as somebody tries to write
To this page, right assume when something gets to this page.
This page is protected.
So that will cause a fault that will actually allow me to go map a new
page in here.
So, there's basically a reserved, there's basically a step a bunch of
memory that's reserved for us to keep growing.
This thing down further and further.
So, the stack can just get bigger and bigger and bigger.
And so that every time we call a function, it gets bigger, growing the
stack.
And then whenever we return from a function, it kind of moves the
other direction.
So Stacks grow.
Do you know, they get bigger and then they shrink and then they grow
and then they shrink, and then they grow, and I talked about that
procedure.
But basically, what's happening.
There's Windows is mapping memory for us to use the stack.
And when we grow out of the size of memory that we needed for our
local variables and stuff, as we call deeper down into the, into the
functions of our program.
It's just, you know, basically allocating pages on demand as we need
them.
And then when we come back through it, we are just using less of the
stack.
So this kind of it's basically like a water level that rises and
flows.
And like I said, the reason
I can do that is because there's never a need in a program to free
something out of the middle of the stack.
It never has to free some middle page here.
Right?
It doesn't have to do that.
It's always going to free off the back because functions Nest, right?
I call a function.
I've got a function Foo, right?
It calls bar.
And then that function calls blah, right.
So I've got three functions here.
Well the top function, all of its local variables are going to have to
stay in memory.
While bar is executing and all of its are gonna have to remember while
blahs executing.
So until it returns back here.
Here, right.
You can't just free the local variables of bars, right out the middle
because you're going to return from blot to Bar.
It's going to access local variables, and all hell would break loose,
right.
So the stack always grows and shrinks from the from the top of it.
You know, it goes bigger smaller bigger.
It never has to free up the middle.
So it is not what is called the Heap, which is something that can be
freed out of the middle is not that we will talk about that later.
It is a stack and it is a very clean data structure that lets you
implement that cleanly.
So, all the rest of the stuff we talked about
So far our lives on their everything else lives on there.
That's where it lives.
So all this other stuff, projectile stack test everything, all of the
functions that are all of the stuff that's passed to our function.
Also either lives on the stack or is passed directly and CPU
registers.
That's just how that that works.
So hopefully that's a pretty complete answer to where everything lives
or at least.
Has you thinking about the complete answer and you can go research
couple of those things if you'd like to find out more about them,
okay?
Good deal.
So off we go.
And let's take a look at the twitch chat quickly just to make sure
everything's going fine.
Looks good to me.
Everything seems everyone is talking amongst themselves.
That is good.
Okay, so what I wanted to cover today and this is going to be a long
stream because we went on a long diversion and we may go on other
ones.
Like I said, Sunday stream is out of control.
It's fully fully bananas.
I wanted to talk about operators today.
So what I wanted to do is kind.
Talk to you about the stuff that you can do.
Once you actually have sort of, you know, variables and stuff like we
were declaring and you understand where they are.
But now you want to kind of do some interesting things with them.
Which obviously, you know, if you're making code, the whole point of
it is to do interesting things with a memory that you've allocated.
So I'm going to talk about operated a and I'm just going to sort of
spam some operators out there and then we're going to talk about how
they work.
So first of all, there's obviously, if I have things like this, where
I've got a bunch of variables that I've defined,
And we all know how these work.
Now they go on the stack.
So these are all living on the stack and I want to start operating on
them to do stuff.
I have basically all of the math operators that I would normally
expect to find - a few perhaps can be represented directly in C with
operators so I can basically say something like.
Okay.
I want to make X now equal to Y plus Z, right?
I can do that.
I could say that I want to be y, plus, Z Plus X.
And again, equals is not like mathematical equals.
It's an assignment operator, which means it computes this side first.
And then assigns it to this side again, that caused me no end of
consternation since I learned programming before I learned to math,
and when they started using equals to mean that both sides were
equivalent, I had no idea was going on was horrible, but hopefully,
you guys all can remember that difference easily enough.
The equals in see, always means a sign.
So it takes the right hand side, called an RH s, right hand side, and
assigned it to the left hand side.
LHS, and it does that assignment.
So after this statement is done it.
As these things and we can use all kinds of operators here.
We can do this kind of thing.
We can divide which is a /.
So it uses / because there is no convenient way to make sort of a like
actual, an actual visual like thing over another thing like you would
see in real math notation.
So they just use the slash to sort of make it look a little bit.
Like why is over Z?
We can do that sort of thing.
We can also do - obviously, we can also do what's called a unitary -
which means we can put a minus before something.
And it makes it -
Like it would in math so you can type most mathy sorts of things in
here.
Things that you can't do is power of.
So, for example, if I wanted to say x to the second power that is not
what that would mean because that is not an operation that was built
in to see.
Instead.
You have to call a function to do that.
There is a function called Powell, which will cover, maybe later
that's in the C, runtime Library if you wanted to do that.
But yeah, that's that's a separate issue.
So you can put most math operators in there and they work how you
would expect star is times.
Instead of X because X would be a variable name.
So they use star four times just like most computer things and they
use / 4 divided.
Now the thing that to that you want to remember is that much like in
mathematics in see operators have what's called a precedence, which
means that some operators happen before other operators.
Now, this is not since this is exactly like how you think of them in
math.
Really?
I'm not going to belabor that point at all or even show a demo, but
I'm simply going to say.
It works very much like you would expect multiplication binds first.
So if I
A x times Z and then I have a Plus on either side of it.
No matter what it's doing the x times e will happen before the plus
happens.
So this the Z Plus X will not magically happen MN times.
Z it will do the x times e first replace that with the quantity and
then continue to compute the pluses so much like math.
You do exactly that sort of precedents order evaluation.
So, you know divides and and times will happen first just like they do
in math.
Adds and subtracts will happen s that sort of thing.
It's not super important to remember the exact precedence rules,
because actually the best thing to do is if you're ever unsure about
them is just too, just like in math, use parentheses.
So if you wanted z+ X to happen, first, put it in parentheses and you
can always do that just like you can in math.
Now the thing you can't do in math is infer a multiplication where
there wasn't one.
So I can't write that if I want a z plus x times E.
I cannot write that it is not allowed in.
See, you must always actually specify the operator in mathematics you
can.
Just put something next to something else and it means X not the case
here.
Same thing.
I could not just use a space to say x times e, can't do that.
You have to always actually say what it is.
You actually want to do.
Now you'll notice that I've used spacing here to creatively kind of
show you what the operator precedence might be.
And I find that that's a good thing to do.
I find that?
It's usually a pretty good thing to do to leave spaces between pluses,
sometimes too kind of spaced out the equations and let it be clear to
the person reading the code.
What happens in what order or at the very least, what order you
thought they were happening in?
Because hey, maybe you had a bug in that code.
It would be nice at least to see what the person thought they were
doing and you go up.
So that's not going to work.
You know, for example, if I came into some code and I saw it looking
like this, I might be like that guy didn't realize what's going to
happen because Z times x will actually happen first, but it's pretty
clear.
He thought that this was going to happen, right?
And so, you know, all of this stuff.
Like I said, it kind of comes with practice.
It's not
Complicated, it's pretty easy to understand.
I'm not going to spend a lot of time talking about that.
I just want you to be aware of the fact that all of the stuff that's
at play and math is also at play and see, including operator
precedence.
And it's a good to kind of get yourself familiar with it.
It's really easy to look up if you want the exact rules and want to
get yourself a little more familiar with them, but that is basically
how that works.
So
Moving on to some things that are not going to be familiar to you from
math.
Those are mathematical operators, but there are also binary like
bitwise operators because since we are working with memory, we
sometimes want to do things that just have to do with the actual bits
that are actually in the variables that we are talking about.
And so if you remember we did a thing where we learned hexadecimal and
I said that one of the big reasons why you use hexadecimal.
Like, in fact, one of the only
Reasons really that I ever use hexadecimal is because it lines up with
binary.
So it's every
Every, every digit if you will in a hexadecimal number corresponds to
4 bits, which means that you can easily see how the number breaks down
that you couldn't, if you look the decimal, because any given thing,
any given digit in a decimal number doesn't line up with binary at
all.
They're all mixed together.
So, you look at the number.
You're like, I have no idea, right?
If I see 65536, I have, no, I can't break that at the six and say, oh,
that was the bottom bit or that was the bottom three bits for
something.
That's not, you know, you can't do that.
So I'm going to start to use
here, which means you're all going to have to put on your hexadecimal
hat to sort of show you a little bit more how this works.
So let's say, I make something equal to 0 XA, right?
And now, if you remember, a is the first letter after the digits in
hexadecimal so 0 through 9 and then a, so that's 10, right?
We're all on board with that.
In fact, we can can just go verify that, right?
We can look in here and the watch window and hit there and I get my 10
right and then I can see a hexadecimal.
There it is.
It's 32-bit number because I said it was an ENT and there's the a
right.
Well, what happens if I want to start sliding the a around, it sounds
like a weird thing to do, but I want to, you know, basically, I want
to move bits left or right in the variable.
I just want to shift them around.
Well, there is a shift operator, right?
And what the shift operator does is it basically says I want you to
rotate you too.
To shift the bits either to the left or the right in this number by a
certain amount that I tell you, right?
So I want to shift the B by say for which would be one hexadecimal
digit, right?
It'll move them one place to the left.
So I go in here and I have my number, right?
It's a, like we said, I'm going to shift it by 4 and boom.
They moved right?
Right to thing.
Now.
What if I want to do that a few more times, right?
What if I shift it some more?
Or we'll just shift.
It shift it shift.
It shift, it shift.
It shift it.
Let's keep on shifting.
It by 4, right?
So we'll watch it go.
There's the a right goes shifts, shifts, shifts, shifts shifts.
Now.
The question is, what happens when I shift it and it's already at the
end.
Now, the answer to this is actually that it's just sees Define
behavior.
What actually happens when you shift this because in Hardware, there's
actually a lot of different answers.
There are things called Barrel shifters, which actually can do kind of
different things.
Like, for example, they can do what's called a rotate where it comes
back on the other side.
So if I were to shift out the left side, comes back on the other side,
right?
there are things which do shift to carry which basically shifts out
and replaces what you shipped it out with zeros, but it sets a special
flag on the processor that tells you whether or not there were any
ones that got
If the doubt and stuff like that, so there's a lot of different things
but what happens in C and someone unfortunately because it's a bit
limiting, but it only has this one way.
What happens in C is it just clears?
If I shift B out, it just goes to 0, the bits that get shifted out.
They don't come back in anywhere.
And so that's just how that works and you could keep on shifting and
they ain't never going to come back in again.
They're gone.
Goodbye.
And even if I tried to shift back in like they don't go out to the
next value in memory.
It's entirely just in that one value.
So you can never
Get them back again, but I can certainly intermix my shifts obviously
with shift in the other direction, right?
You can shift by putting in the opposite version.
So I did two less than symbols is the shift.
Left 2, greater than symbols is the shift, right?
And you can see now, I can kind of do those shifts.
Shift.
You can see it wiggle back and forth, shifting back shifting back.
Now, let's shift it up a few times and then shift it back down, and
the same thing would happen.
If I shift it out the bottom, it would get clear but zeros as well.
So that's shifting.
And you may think that shifting isn't particularly interesting yet,
but you will see us do it a fair bit.
There's a number of reasons why we might do it.
I won't try to demo them today because what we've been sort of just
trying to cover the low level stuff and I won't turn it.
Try to get into the reasons why you might use it, but
Suffice to say it's more useful than you might think and you will see
us use it in the mainstream.
Furthermore, in addition to, in addition to the shifting.
Excuse me.
I gotta get it there.
No cat here.
It's delicious anyway.
So in addition to the shifting, when we're shifting these things, you
know, shifting these things all over the place.
You may ask.
Well, what does that actually do with the number?
Well, if you are a superstar which may be some of you out there are
and you only just learned binary and hexadecimal and stuff like that
from this stream, but somehow you have a gigantic brain and you think
about what happens when you shift it.
Now, what I said was every time we shift something, it basically moves
the bits down in the
That we shifted it.
So if I have say one bit set at the very bottom, so I've got a number,
right?
And it's like, 000000 it.
Let's say we, let's say it's a unsigned care.
So it's only 8 Bits long.
I've got one bit the bottom one little bit there.
What does that represent?
Well, we know that a 1 in that place represents a 1 and we know that a
bit in.
The next place would be a 2 and then a 4 and then an 8, right?
And then 16 and so on.
So if I'm to shift this bit, bit upwards, so if I go ahead and shift
that to the
At once.
What does that do to the number?
Well, it was one now.
It's too.
If I shift it up again now it's for and what I hope you can see is
basically all that's doing is it's essentially moving up in the powers
of two, what the number was.
So essentially when you shift by one to the left you are multiplying
by 2.
When you shift to the right by 1, you are dividing by 2.
So a shift is really just a multiply or divide by the power of two
that you specified.
So if I specify a one it's by 2, right?
Its I multiply by 2 or if I was going the other way, that's a divided
by 2.
Right, but if I specify to to, well, that would be shifting to places,
which is multiplying by what for right?
Because I had something here and it went right to there in one ship so
that was multiplying by 4.
Or not 2 which is 2 to the 2nd, right?
Same thing would happen.
If I shift it by three, I'd start with one but I'd get 8 which is 2 to
the 3rd.
So that is a shift by 3.
So all you're doing when you shift is just multiplying by a power of 2
and the Power of 2 is in this place, makes sense.
Hopefully it does.
Okay onto more fun things.
Although actually, let's watch it.
Let's watch it happen.
Ladies and gentlemen, we are in an IDE for a reason.
Let us see in action show.
Don't tell is the way things go.
Here on handmade hero.
Probably got a not have this bunch of numbers in the middle of the
supposedly, valid code.
Okay, we're gonna switch out a hexadecimal mode.
There you go.
You got 10.
So if you shift it up, what do we expect to get 20?
There's our 20 sets it up again.
We would select yet 40.
Got it 80.
Etc.
Right.
Just multiplying by 2 each individual time.
That's all that happens.
And that's just it's sliding up the hexadecimal.
Now if we watched it happen in the hexadecimal like we did before,
it's still the same right.
Just sliding up sliding up thing and so on and so,
Anyway, oh, well.
No, it's not.
We change it to one now, right?
So we're not going by 4.
We're going by one bit, so you can actually see the hexadecimal change
as well.
So it takes four steps to go up.
Just kind of cool, right?
You can watch it go.
It's at a right now.
It's 14:28 50 and now it's going to be back to a again as it slides in
to one hexadecimal digit over computers are great.
Really, you know, how do you not just love them anyway, so that's
basically what happens with shifting which
One of our bitwise operators, we have other bitwise operators.
I'm Missy x equal to 0 and I'm going to show you some other operators.
I'm going to use the shift that I just showed you to demonstrate these
operators.
And so, here we go.
I'm going to say shifted Up by 4 for that one.
I am going to say shifted up by, let's say eight.
But this one then I'm going to again use a shift by 4 and then I am
going to use a shift by.
Kate mmm, you know, we're not gonna do that one yet.
I'm gonna do that one in a second pass because you know what?
That one gets that one gets a
Little bit more fun and I want to savor that.
So let's do that.
Okay, here we go.
So what I have done is I have written two, more bitwise, operators or
and and and this is the sort of pipe symbol.
If you're familiar with that.
It's the vertical bar on your keyboard is how you do or and the
Ampersand is how you do.
And so I initialized X20 and you can see it here, right?
And then what I'm going to do, you know what it is?
There any way to make this be by
Binary, can I just see binary, does anyone know if that's possible?
I would love to be able to just show you the binary here instead of
the hexadecimal because it would be so much nicer.
Is there some way that I can just say Visual Studio?
Watch window binary?
Does it happen?
I don't know more stock exchange code Guru, using the watch window.
Does this actually have to do binary in it?
Of course, it
Then Google.
Why do you do this?
Binary Stock Exchange.
Do do, mmm.
Oh, come on people.
I'm not getting any satisfaction here.
All right, ladies and gentlemen, how you implement, a debugger?
That doesn't have an obvious way to show you binary.
I have no idea, but that is the way it goes.
I suspect there's some kind of common syntax maybe that I could do,
but I don't actually know.
So we'll try one more time.
Again, Sunday streamer allowed to be a Meandering.
I never have to do this anymore because I'm used to doing the
hexadecimal, but like I feel like for educational purposes, come on
people like, wouldn't you have that in there and and even
Like people who are not so familiar with it.
I don't know.
It just seems like the thing.
You would have.
Let's say, watch window comma syntax visual studio and roll the dice.
Can you say the C D and H?
4 hexadecimal?
Maybe the isn't there?
Like, you know how to watch an expression in the debugger.
Come on.
Msdn.
Hook us up here.
This is a high quality stream and we want we want your help.
Let's see.
Did you do most valid language expressions used context operators
access control?
And because I'm going to my services in here conductors, numeric
constants?
Okay.
Can we do it?
No, we can't.
You can prefix or suffix symbols represent numbers in another base,
but it looks like you can actually do it stream.
Am I right?
Let's see.
Printf percent be in value.
You can just use Pro mode and calc.
Yeah, I know I can use calc.
I want it in the actual to butter though.
That's not looking good.
Even the stream, if the stream doesn't know you probably can't do it.
So, all right.
All right, we'll have to just do it the translation ourself.
But anyway.
So what we're going to do here is we're going to try and look at this.
Just using it in.
Well, you know what?
Here's what I'll do since I, in fact, I already kind of did it.
I lined them with hexadecimal digits.
So we should just see ones appear almost as if it was binary because I
line them that way being with.
So this will this will be as good as we're gonna get.
I guess what, the or operator does which is the first operator.
I want to show you?
Is it basically sets bits in the value if either of its two operands
happen to have that bit set.
It's saying set this set, the B, if either of the two inputs are true,
so I have X, which is 0.
So, no bits are set in X and I have one shifted up for which means
there's a 1 in the fourth bit of this one.
So when I or these two together, I should just get that one bit set,
which is the one shifted up for and I step and see there.
It is.
Right.
So it's for the two of them.
Now, what I'm going to do is I'm going to or again with one shifted up
eight.
So that's a one in this place.
So I'm going to order these.
Gather it.
So, what I'm going to do is we'll keep the X, which is set.
It'll keep that bit set and it'll set the next bit as well.
Right?
And now, you can see there's two ones.
They both got set.
So, or basically is just combines all of the set B.
NE B that is set in either of its two operands, it sets in the result.
So it's just, it's a way of combining things together.
It's an or
This or this now end does sort of the the I don't know what the
correct set theory Terminus for the operation, you know, the inverse
the contrapositive of whatever it basically does a similar operation,
but instead of setting the result when either of its operands have a
bit set, it requires both of them to have that bit set.
So I've got this coming in as x 2 B that here.
But the thing I'm adding it with only has this one bit set the for a
bit set.
So when I add them together, it essentially clears out that other bit
that we set the one shifted up by 8.
That one gets knocked out by the.
And so and is often used to do what's called masking, which is to say,
I have some bit pattern and I want to remove all the other bits from
some value, and just leave the ones that were set in these positions,
right?
So you could imagine me doing something like that.
Where I said, okay, I've got some value that is full banana cakes,
right?
Let's say I set a bunch of bits in here.
Okay, so I set the three bit.
I set the 14-bit.
I set the 19 bit.
I set the 23rd bit.
I set the 30th bit.
I set the first bit and I still set the 8-Bit.
So I just said a ton of bits, right?
But now I want to know, I just want to see basically what bit whether
the bits were set in the fourth position or the third.
Those are the only B i--.
Well, that's big little bit or the 30th.
I want to see if either of those two bits per set, right?
Thank you.
Mr.
31st bit.
All right, and so I'll sign those two separate variables so we can
look at them ahead of time.
So that's our mask.
Basically, our mask is the fourth bit and the 31st bit are set in y
and then we set all these other ones 4314, 1923 30 18.
And now we just want to see what B.
They have set in common.
That is what the and operator will do for us.
So we go in here.
Look at X.
We'll look at why.
And we go through set B setting bit setting B.
Look at them all fill in.
They're all filling in our X is full of bits, ladies and gentlemen,
and now we're going to set our Mass, which is why and the, why only
has two bits that it's got that that top bit the 31st bit set the very
last bit in the value and it's got the, the fourth bit set.
So that one right there.
And now we and them together and Bam, right?
We get back, just that for bit because that was the
Only bit that they had in common.
You can see that there's the 4-bit, there's the for bit and this 31st
bit never appeared in here.
It was never set so it isn't set in the result.
Right?
So that is basically what we mean when programmers say, we're masking
we mask out of value because you sort of have a mask, what you would
put on your face.
That only shows a little bit through, right?
That makes sense.
Hopefully, that's clear.
What's happening?
There.
Or in and are the very most frequently used bitwise operators in C.
At least when I'm programming.
Those are ones.
I use most often, but there is another bitwise, operator one a
bitwise.
Yeah.
Well, there's two more actually will show you what they are.
So one more bitwise operator that's that's fairly easy to understand
is the not operator basically bitwise.
Not it's a little tilde.
It's kind of like when you put a negative in front.
Something it changes the value of that.
Something, in the expression tilde, in front of something means take
all the bits that were 0 and turn them into one and turn, all the ones
in 2008.
Inverts the value, right?
So basically, if I run in here.
Hello, what did I say?
Oh, I had a warning.
What was my warning?
Just Wyatt?
Just that something isn't used.
I like to be aware when I have mornings.
Yeah, just one reference variables.
That's fine.
I don't care if I'm nervous.
All right, so I got nothing set in x.
Yes, I do the inversion operator out.
The did not operator and all the bits are now set.
Every.
Last thing is set.
It's the maximum possible thing.
Right?
And and that is basically Works no matter what you do.
So if I make X be some combination of bits, right?
I do say a couple bits set here to do.
Oops, ladies and gentlemen, so I go in here and I set some bits, I now
have some bit set.
I do the inversion and it gives me exactly the opposite.
Everything that was set is now not set.
Damn, it is isn't and now someone brought this up in the chat.
It's a good thing to remember, too.
If you're struggling with these little bit, it is true that if you
load calc, right?
So if you go in here and you just type calc, you'll get this
calculator thing.
Basically that's built into windows inside.
There's a view that can turn to programmer mode and there's these
things that you can set hexadecimal decimal octal, binary, right?
So, if you set it to hexadecimal, I believe this will work, you can
cut and paste just
Just not the 0x part, but just the just the part that you want to see,
you can paste that in there and then it will show you the binary down
here, right?
You can sort of see 1 1 1 1 0 1 1 1 1 0 1, 1 1 right and you can see
this the inverse the exact inverse so you don't have to translate that
in your head.
You can do it here.
We you'd want to do that in the debugger.
That's where it should be.
But it for the meat, you know, it's the poor man's way of having a
debugger that actually works at all.
Okay.
Alright, so there you go.
So that is the not operated, the binary not and basically it turns B
to what they're not, hence the name, but there's one more operator.
And this one is a doozy.
I do not expect people to understand this one right away because it's
just a little confusing.
It is no different than or, and it's exactly the same conceptually,
but it's just a little bit harder for people to get because or an and
a very logical it's like is this for this set in and is like, is this
and this set it's very easy to kind of understand what those do.
It's called exclusive or and what exclusive or it does is exclusive or
if I have two variables.
So let's say I have this where I've got one shifted up for and I've
got Y is one shifted up eight.
Right?
And what I want to do is I want to do exclusive or of these two
values.
In fact, let's make this a little bit more interesting by setting a
few just a few more bits.
Do do do.
There we go.
All right.
Okay, so I've got some bits that now, you can see I've got two bits
set in x + 2, B 7 Y and only one of the bits lines up.
So if we were to do an and on this, right, we would expect to just get
the 8-Bit because both of them have 8.
So the things that they both have in common, we starting to get if we
were to do an or we were expecting to have all of these write.
The result would have the four bits set.
The 8-Bit set and the 16 bits that right.
Well, what exclusive or it does is it does something similar to the or
operation meaning that if either of the B is set?
It will the result will have it set but if both of the bits are set,
then it won't be.
So it's exactly the same as an or except for the one case which is
when both bits are set and that goes to 0.
So the reason it's called exclusive or is because it's set to or it's
exclusively and or it excludes the case where they're both set.
It's only the aura case.
It's never the and case you can't.
It when there and you could only do it when they're or and that's
exclusive or so.
When I run this, what do we expect to see right?
We expect to see that eight get cleared out, right?
And it is.
So the result has the bit set where they were where each of them had a
bit set.
But the other one didn't but the one where they both had it, set got
cleared and I realize that's just a weird thing to think of
conceptually, but it is something that happens in in programming.
It's just another tool you can use to achieve results that you want.
So it's something to be aware of and it is built into the language.
Now, the thing that's interesting about X or is that it's kind of
symmetric in a weird way.
So, for example,
If I was to do this twice, sorry, some things here.
So let's say I ex or something.
Where I xor m xor x with Y, right?
So, I get the thing that I said before, it cleared out that bit.
But now I X or x with Y again.
And what you'll notice is, I got ex back.
So one of the most common things that xor is used to do is in things
where you want to be able to invert what you did because it's an
operation that inverts properly.
If I exit.
Or something, with something in the next road.
Again, with the same thing.
I get the original value back.
Things like cryptography, tend to use this because you can X or values
together in ways that are invertible fact, really bad.
Cryptography is basically just xoring things with some key, right?
It's just like X or the the data that I'm trying to quote unquote
encrypt with some key and then when I want to decrypt it, I just X or
it with the same key again, and I believe like it was Microsoft Excel.
It's encrypted.
Stood file format for a while.
In the old days was just X or it was like we explored with something
the times have changed, we don't do that anymore, but that, that was
That was something anyway, so that's X or and that pretty much wraps
up The bitwise Operators that I wanted to cover.
So that again you have for you have and you have exclusive or and you
have not and between those you can do quite a bit of damage.
Ladies and gentlemen, that's that's quite a lot of bitwise operators
you can do and we'll be seeing those in the Stream.
You will not have to wait long to see me use those I suspect so you
will get to see how those are in.
Action basically, anyway, so let's move on to some other operators
there.
In addition to bitwise logical operators.
They're called logical because they're like, or or and like, it's
like, kind of like, logic doing logic circuitry, right?
There are, what are called straightforward, logical operators.
Just just, I think they're just called the regular logical operators.
So, there's bitwise operators and logical operators.
I think are the typical ways.
They're called one of the problems with teaching C-Class after you've
known C4.
Don't even know when I learned it.
But many multiple decades is, you forget the proper names for a lot of
things because it's, like, I don't,
It's just the thing that I use.
I've never been a particularly High falutin programmer, who reads
like, you know, Lambda the ultimate or something.
So, I'm not the kind of guy who's like all about the nomenclature.
It's like what?
You don't know.
That's the set theory.
The Third Way of representing the logical set theory, operation of
closure division, ring, / the thing produces stuff and it's like, no I
don't, I have absolutely no idea.
I would love to know but I don't know anyway, so there is also
So operators, you can use that deal with whether values are 0 or not,
and I wanted to cover these first because I was going to talk about
conditionals and conditionals are things, basically, where you can
change what code is executed based on the values of things and that is
obviously a very fundamental thing that you have to do in programming.
It is how the basis of all control flow which is the thing we're gonna
look at next.
But in order to understand how any of that works, you have to first be
able to compute something you can use for a control flow and that is
These logical operators come in.
So, if I have a value?
I'm going to talk about this.
I've defined three things here.
And what I want you to think about is each of these things.
If actually know what I'm gonna, I'm gonna get totally wild here.
Just full-on, even though I haven't talked about two's complement or
anything.
I'm going to Define for things and when we gummy - I like that, that's
right.
I did it.
I put a negative in there.
So I defined for things and when I want you to think about right now
is what each of these has as a Boolean value meaning, I'm going to
talk about a Boolean value which means is something true or false.
I need to bake things down into whether something is basically true or
false on or off.
Let's say, you know, is it set or not?
Whatever, however, you want to look at it, but it's basically I'm
going to boil things down into two categories.
And only two.
And the way that see makes this distinction for variables and we'll
see kind of why it does this in a second.
But the way that it makes this distinction is by saying, if something
is 0, it is false.
It is not true.
It is not set.
It is whatever.
However, you want to look at it.
It is the not thing and if something is 1, then it is true, right?
It is set it, is it?
It has a value.
It is.
It is the thing?
So what C defines are a set of operators that can produce these things
for you as well, that can that can use this sort of thing.
And this trueness happens for anything.
That is not 0.
It doesn't matter if the number is negative, doesn't matter.
If the number is huge.
It is simply matters that it is not zero.
So basically what happens is in see things are either zero or they are
And that is how it thinks about Boolean asst.
So when we get into things, like, if statements and conditionals,
those sorts of things, that is really the property of of, of an, if of
a true or false, is it 0 or is it not 0?
So C gives you operators that can produce these values out of things
that you want.
So for example, I may want to know for, let's say, I'm going to call
like a
I'll just do.
I'll do less stable, do less than x is less than y, right.
I'm going to compute that X is greater than y x is equal to Y.
Okay, and I'm going to put these in parentheses because I like to be
very clear about sort of how things are computed order wise, not equal
to Y.
So now we've got a bunch of comparisons here and we will see how they
work.
Okay, so obviously between x and y, x is 0, Y is 1, right.
So if I start comparing these values, if I compare them to each other,
what see will do is it will do exactly what you would have done in
math.
It'll do the mathematical comparison is greater than thing.
This is how they do equals to K naught so that you don't confuse it
with assignment.
They put 2 equals to see if values are the same and they put a knot in
n equals to see if they're not the same.
See will do the comparison between, whatever the values are, doesn't
matter what they are.
Whatever integer values they are and it will put a 0 here if it is not
true and it will put a nonzero value but not necessarily one if they
if it is true.
So we go down here and we compute less do less greater equal not equal
rights groups, not equal spelling so you can see we did the
combination of less and it gave us a 1 which is what we expected.
Because it is less.
We computed the value of Greater it gave us a 0, which is what we
expected because it is not excess, not greater.
We check for equal also, not true.
We check for not equal and it is true.
Right.
So now that's so that should be hopefully really easy to understand
it.
Basically produces zero or not zero depending on the circumstance, but
let's see what happens.
Just so we're clear on everything if we compared it, why let's say Z
and W, right?
So we put some other values in here.
You do.
Do, do, do.
There we go.
Off we go.
So now we compute less and we say Z less than W.
Well Z is much higher than W, so obviously that's zero didn't happen.
So now we say is z greater than W, right?
And it turns out that Z is in fact greater than W still write someone
in their equals, right?
They are not equal.
Not equals.
They are, in fact, not equal.
And so basically any values that you put in there, no matter what they
are, will still produce a zero or nonzero value?
Now, it is worth noting.
That the compiler at least as far as I remember, the spec is under no
particular obligation to actually produce a one there.
I think it just has to produce some nonzero value and I don't know if
that's true or not.
Check the spec.
It may even differ between C and C++ for all I know because in C++
they have an actual type called Bool and it may be that these things
are defined to produce.
You know, I don't even know.
I don't care at all about it.
All I want to do is just make you aware that the compiler may not be
required to actually produce a one there.
It's just required to produce something that is not 0.
If the thing was true, I know that for a fact but check the spec if
you want to know if it access or producer one, but anyway, we can do
that for any variables that we want to.
We can always compare them like that and then get back what we need.
And those are called The Logical operators, and that is what they look
like.
Now.
Why do we want those?
The reason that we want those is so that we can do control flow.
Which is the next thing that I want to talk about.
So control flow the way that works is basically saying, okay.
I might have some code and here is where maybe we'll bring our output
debug string back into the mix because I know everyone really loved
output.
Debug string.
I know they were a fan of output debug string.
They thought it was awesome.
And so maybe I just want to do something like print out, which one of
these is greater.
So I want to print out like Z is less than W, right?
Or I
A printout W is less than Z or I want to print out.
W is equal to Z.
Right?
I want to print those things out.
And so what I have to do, you know, obviously if I'm to run this
program, right?
I run the program and I print out all three of them and that's not
what I want.
You know, I want it only print the one of those that is true because
they can only one of them can be true.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to introduce control flow
control flow is a way.
A of preventing code from running.
Unless something is true basically and you have a lot of options to do
that in C and I'm going to show you the first and most basic one right
now.
So I am going to do this test.
I'm going to say Z is less than W.
That is z less than W.
And I'm going to say if that is true then print this out.
And so what you do is you start with the if you open a parenthesis and
close the parentheses and then you put the actual value, you want to
test in there.
Now.
Value can actually just be a variable.
So if I want to I can just I already computed it, right.
I already computed Z lesson wi can just go right on the Val variable.
It's just a value and I can put the expression in as well, that could
produce that value and it will evaluate here.
So it's all it's whatever you want.
You just have to be something that evaluates to 0 or not 0, and then
it's going to be able to do the thing in there.
Now.
If if that wasn't true now I can just leave it like that.
If I want to write I can make that be all that's going to happen,
right?
That could be the end of it.
And now, I could run that and basically, Oops.
Why I gotta get rid of my to do people test.
I want to get rid of These Warnings.
I'm sorry, that there are some warnings in here.
So this we will just sort of expand our comment out to there you go.
So, no warnings down.
So I run this and you'll notice it did not actually print out.
It did not print out this thing and why didn't print it out well
because less, as we know as we stepped in here before and saw
Less is equal to 0.
Now, if I want to, I'm going to print out this other things, so I
could, if I want to, I could also just do well.
Let's see.
Let's do greater, right?
I'm off of this editor is true.
I don't deny it.
So this is z is greater than W, run it right unsurprisingly.
We now get that because that is a value that we actually knew to be
one.
Right?
And furthermore.
I could also test for equals, right?
I could see what the equal one is.
I fight.
I can do all of these, right?
I can put them in here.
Doodoo.
and,
Done.
Right.
So that is the way to make some conditional execution.
And basically what happens is when we look at in the in the actual
debugger, you will note that any time.
The condition is not true.
It just goes ahead and full-on skips.
Everything.
That is within the curly braces.
Those curly braces are called a block.
We will talk about them in the mainstream more, but basically
everything inside the block gets executed, if the if statement
evaluates to true or not zero and everything out outside.
I'm sorry everything inside.
Skipped, if it does not.
And you can see, that's exactly what happens.
Right?
No big mystery.
They're very, very straight forward.
And what you will notice is if, for example, you already did a test on
something, it is often the case that you may want to do the opposite
thing as well.
You may want to have some code that executes when it is not the case.
And so instead of testing for not equal as well.
Well, equal is basically the same as testing for not equal because
it's just the opposite case.
So what
See also allows you to do is at the end of your if you can put an else
statement and the else statement can basically contain what to do when
the things fail.
So when this is zero, instead of one it will do it, right?
And what we get there is we get a base of the same behavior of the
program.
It's just a more concise way of writing it.
I don't have to check the separate value.
It just goes.
Okay, it wasn't true.
So execute the else Clause, right?
And that's basically why I'm just saying I'm going to execute one
either way.
Now you can stack these up.
If you would like to, as I started to write down here.
Then I figured it would be better to explain them in a slightly
different way.
You can stack these up.
So let's say I'm on here and I do if less well, I know that if
Less then it can't be anything else.
So I'm just going to put everything else in the else Clause.
I'm going to say okay, you know, well then then I'll test for if it's
greater right?
And then I'll test for if it's equal.
In here, right?
It's going to do these tests.
I'm not going to bother testing.
If it's not equal to because if it's not equal to it, it will have hit
these things.
It will hit one of those things because it'll either be greater than
or less than.
So.
We'll just do it this way for now, right?
And when I run this particular program, you will note that it does
exactly get when I thought.
It said it would do it.
Will this is not true.
So we'll evaluate these.
This is true.
So evaluate that one.
This is not true.
So it will skip it right, but if I know that these things are
All mutually exclusive.
So I only want to ever do one of them.
I can actually stack the ifs inside the else as well.
Like right on the same line and that will basically allow me to keep
cascading ifs, as long as I actually want to like as many as I want to
like this, right?
And even at the end I can have a final pass through else which is
like, I don't know what happened, something something went wrong.
What, right?
And now when we run it, basically what happens is?
It will only
Pick one of these guys.
It will test them.
Each does that one as soon as it finds when it's true?
It stops evaluating anybody else's because they're all predicated on
the fact that the previous one didn't occur.
So
That is the simplest kind of control flow.
It's basically do something, or don't do something based on the value
of a variable.
Now that value like I said can be built up out of something.
Extremely complicated, right?
We could have done a ton of math here.
We could have used all kinds of comparisons that got compared with
each other and so on.
But we may want to do is test a couple things together.
Right?
So let's say that we wanted to do and this is basically just a
glorified, not equals test.
But let's say we want to do something.
It's less.
And greater, we're both true.
Well, you know, how we had those?
Oars and Anne's that we used before, right?
That used bitwise.
We basically have the same or as Ann Ann's that we can use for
logical.
We can actually double if you just put two of the operator, you're
going to use like logical or or logical.
And like that we can actually do tests that test for multiple things
at once.
So this will do if it is less or greater, right?
So when I run to this, it's going to actually
Really look and see.
How do I get this to go?
There you go.
It's going to look and see this guy is 0.
This guy is one.
He did an or so he wants to do this case.
If either of these two things are true and that is one of them is
true.
So it goes ahead and does the case, right?
And the same thing would happen with, and right, I can double the and
and it's saying logically.
If both of these things are true.
Do what's inside, right?
So, it goes ahead and does that right?
One of them was true.
One of them wasn't, which isn't it?
In case so it skips it and continues on now.
Those are just operators like anything else.
So
Can again, do them outside.
I can make this an and operator and take this guy out right like that.
And then just test on the and does that make sense?
These are all just these are just operations.
There's nothing magical happening inside the if the, if just wants a
value.
So we do all our computation outside with it.
And there is even a logical extra.
I believe, I've almost never typed that in, but I believe you can even
do this, right?
If that makes sense.
You can say, I want to do the thing, but I don't even remember.
Member if that's true.
No, apparently it's not true.
I've said never type that in but I was like wonder if you can do a
logical X or apparently you can't.
So never mind.
Anyway, that is essentially all there is to predication and control to
and and predicated execution and see that's basically the if statement
and the else statement are all you really need for that.
Now it's worth noting that you don't actually need these little braces
here.
If you only have one thing that you're going to execute meaning, you
may have seen in other languages, you'll do.
Being like like this and then you'll have the code just right here.
Right?
And that is something you can do, but it's very misleading.
I find because there's a number of cases that include like macros and
stuff.
Where like, if for example the thing that's in here accidentally
becomes two statements somehow like you type a second one in there.
It's really going to look visually like only these are only happening
if the if is true, right?
But
Ali.
See only does the very next thing as part of the if so, this being on
the same line ends up being very misleading, because it looks like
it's going to be true.
And so I always prefer to actually just really show what is going to
happen by enclosing them in braces and making it a separate block.
So it's obvious what happens in the if and even with macro expansions
and all kinds of other crazy stuff.
This will always be a pretty solid reliable visual indication of
what's going to happen.
Same is true on the else if you want to put the code right there, but
I never do that.
I always do that and that is really just a personal preference.
But I think it's a more solid and more reliable way to keep things
from accidentally.
Spiraling out of control.
If you happen to be using macros or other things like that.
Okay.
How is everyone doing on the stream is the question.
This has been a crazy Sunday.
We've just been going.
Absolutely crazy.
It's full on.
Banana cakes, but you know, that's just how that's just how things go
sometimes.
Are we doing?
Okay?
On the stream is everyone happy.
I need to wait a little bit because the amount of time it takes before
the stream actually gets that's on there.
Did you do?
I guess that's true.
So Clemens bound, did have a good point there.
He, that was a good point.
He basically pointed out that.
Well.
Yeah, there's no, there's no.
I was saying
About X or there's no xor operator like that, but it's true.
You don't really need it because this is essentially, the xor operator
saying something is not equal to something else.
Does effectively give you the xor operator because that's what that
is.
So that's a good point.
So why bother like I mean basically this would have just been C CI
adding syntax that wasn't really necessary.
So it's probably better that.
They just didn't bother right, and you just know, well, if you wanted
X or yeah, you can't type it to look like an X or but
It is an X or that's what it is.
That would explain why I've never typed this or never even thought
that I needed it because you just kind of know like okay, I can do
that.
B for binary watch.
Okay, someone the stream has spoken.
I'm hoping this is true.
Let's see if that's true.
And okay to do, can we get a binary watch?
Let's, let's do it.
All right.
Sorry man.
I thank you for the suggestion on binary watch.
It doesn't look like it worked that maybe because we are still in
Visual Studio 2008.
Maybe, when we switch to, to the thing, it'll work.
But I don't know.
Like I said, it's maybe it might be a feature that they added.
So yeah, that's good.
All right, it's a stream going.
Okay.
Everyone's okay on the stream.
We're going to assume.
We are going to assume that it's going.
Okay.
We'll try like we'll try it on the
On the 2013, when we go to the mainstream and hopefully that'll work.
So that'll be good.
Alright, so we're going to keep going here because it's Sunday and
we're just going nuts.
We're just going to go into the remaining control flow.
Structure is just so we can show you what they are.
So sometimes, you know, before I wrote this thing out, I did a little
thing where I'm like, hey guys, you know what?
Let's set this thing equal to 0 XA.
And then let's just go ahead and shift that up by, for all the time
doo-doo-doo-doo doo-doo-doo-doo.
Right, and then I showed, you know, I went in here and I was like,
okay, you know.
We got this value.
We look at it in hexadecimal.
We can see the a we shift it up.
It's moving there.
It's going, it's like it's going crazy.
It's shifting shifting shifting and it's fun, but it is kind of
annoying that the write all this stuff.
So if there is something that I want to do repeatedly, we have things
called basically Loops, if that makes sense.
And Loops are things that allow you to go through and repeat some code
that you've written once, so that you can do it multiple times.
So if I want to do this, a bunch of times,
Times.
What I can do is, I can basically say, well, let me do this, until
something is true.
And that is called a while statement.
You can say while, and you can say something is true.
So I'm going to say well X is not equal to 0, right?
Because if x is equal to 0 that means we shifted the a all the way off
the end.
So while X is not equal to 0, I'm going to shift it.
I'm just going to keep on shifting.
It and shifting it and shifting it till it gets off the end, right?
I run this, I go into my while loop X is obviously not equal to 0 yet.
So I go in here and I shift it, and you'll notice it just keeps on
going.
Keeps on executing keeps on executing, until we finally shift it all
the way off.
And now that's not true, and Bam.
I'm out, right?
So, a while, a while, loop is really trivial.
It's just one conditional and again, that can be a variable as well.
So I could do this is the condition, right?
Right?
And then I can say, wow, condition.
Now.
It's only can execute the code in the loop.
So it's condition was set up here.
It would never reach ech.
So I would have to again set it.
I would have to test it each time after as well, right Turi.
Keep re-upping it but now you can see explicitly.
What's going on.
Hello?
Okay.
There we go.
You can see so let's see what's going on condition.
I bring it up here you can see is 1 because that is true.
I go.
And I shift it up and I reset Condition.
It's still true, still true, still true, still true as we shift and
then finally, this time through I shift and it becomes zero and now
condition becomes zero and I'm out right.
Loops are incredibly simple.
That's all they are.
The only other thing you really need to know about.
Loops is that the loop can contain an escape.
So, if I was to do this, right, basically,
Ali, if we look at this, you'll see that there is no way to ever get
out of this Loops.
Sorry, let's say well one that's just true, right?
It's just full on true.
So I had to do this and it's just going to do it and it's going to do
it forever.
And there's no way to ever get out of this Loop because one is a
constant and it's true and it's not ever changing.
So we just go and go and go, and go, and go, and go, and go, and go,
and go, and go, and go, some more, right?
So one thing that is true though, is any time we can actually just
Hand code essentially the escape from the loop by using what's called,
a break statement.
So what I can do is I can put the conditional in here and say, oh,
okay.
Well if x equals 0, right?
Which is the time that I want to stop doing this Loop, like I said, I
can just put this break statement in and what the break statement will
do is it will jump straight out of the loop immediately like right at
that time without doing anything else.
So as I go through here as I shift it up and up and up and up and up
and up and up, right when I get to the end and I'm about to shift it
off.
At the end, I get to the point where x equals 0.
I'm there, I break out.
And that's the end of the loop.
And we're out right.
There are two more kinds of Loops.
You can actually, they're there for convenience.
You can write any loop with any other loop.
There isn't like some kind of weird thing where like you have to use
one kind of loop or the other because they do something differently.
They are all basically just shorthand notation for essentially.
What is a conditional go-to.
It's basically saying when you get to the end go back to the
beginning, they're all
Shorthand for doing that in different ways.
There is a do while loop which is basically you take the while and you
put it at the end with a semicolon after it.
And then you put a do at the front and the only difference between
those two is whether it executes the loop the first time.
So, for example, if I was here and I did x equals 0, right.
So now I'm saying, only do the loop when X is equal to 0.
Well, what's going to happen.
Well, we're never going to do the loop because X is equal to a right
oxa, so
It's not equal to 0.
So now we're gonna do the loop, but maybe I wanted my Loop to, at
least always run.
Once I didn't want to check the first time.
I always want to do at least one shift, but then I just want it to
stop doing shifts.
When X finally does.
I want to stop doing shifts.
If x was not equal to 0, right.
Well, when I do this, that's exactly what happens.
It'll do the shift, right?
Once it'll get to the while and then it'll end right there.
So do is just a way of moving the test till after the first one.
So, if you want to
Always do at least one that is where to do it.
And again, it's just shorthand.
It's just the same.
I could do the exact same transformation using the while loop by
saying.
Oh, it's really just wild one and then I do the if here right and the
break that's that's all I did essentially and so, oh sorry not equal
to right.
So whatever the while condition would have been I can just test the
not of that while condition and do the break.
So basically these are all just shorthand.
There's nothing.
Really fancy to them.
They're not particularly interesting.
It's just different ways of writing the conditions.
Finally, because it is very common.
There's a thing called a for Loop and what a for Loop does.
Oops, almost wrote it.
My standard way.
What a for Loop does is a for Loop allows you to basically go ahead
and move a variables declar initialization, right?
It's test.
And its operation all in to a single concise form.
That can be pretty easily read.
And in this case, we don't even have anything to do in the body.
But this is where, you know, more stuff would happen here, right?
If you were doing a more complex for Loop, the for Loop is basically
kind of like the Uber Loop.
The thing that packs the most into a small space.
You can see what happens if I run here.
I will actually do three different things separated by semicolons.
This is the first one and this happens once at the beginning.
It has the conditional.
This is the condition for the loop.
So as long as this is true, it will keep going and then it has the
thing to do every iteration of the loop.
So every time, every time it repeats it will do this thing here,
right?
So what happens is it goes and it does oops, there's that conditional
compilation.
Don't know why it always wants to do.
It always does.
So I've got my x max equal to 0, first time through the loop.
It sets x equal to x a which is this line right here.
The next thing it does is it does the test to see whether it should
execute the loop, which is X not equal to 0 X is not equal to 0.
So then it would do the body of the loop normally, but since we have
nobody, it's just going to go ahead and do the one thing that we told
to do every iteration x equals x just add up, it does the shift right?
End of the loop keeps going testing.
Testing testing, testing testing.
Until it fails, right?
And then it goes out.
Now, it would be nice that it butter actually showed it doing the
test.
But what, it actually puts the, it puts the little green yellow arrow
here on the test.
Usually, which is kind of annoying because you'd rather see it
actually pointing here and evaluating it.
But yeah, so, anyway, to make it a little more explicit.
I'll put the output debug string that we were using.
I'll go ahead and put that there so you can see when that executes in
the grand scheme of things.
Right?
So we're going to put the a book, debug string here and say.
We are in the loop.
Okay, and here we go.
So we go through and our first time through X gets initialized to a it
tested.
It's not equal to zero.
It's not.
So now it's going to do output debug string, right?
So it does that put debug string?
And well, we don't have the, I got actually put up the output window
if you want to see this, but here we go.
Curtis.
We are in the loop it now goes and does the thing to do on each
iteration at the end which is to shift it up.
It, shifts it up it.
Now does that.
But debug string right now does the test again shift up, test, shift
up, shift up keeps going, do do do and then we're out and we end up in
of course, Windows code C, runtime Library.
All right, so that's about it for Loops.
They're not very interesting for is the hardest one to understand out
of them because it packs everything.
Here and really these things, essentially get expanded.
So if you want here is a more concise way of looking at what a for
Loop actually does a.
For Loop actually does my ntx go.
Anyway, so basically what this for Loop, exactly translates to is this
while loop down here.
It translates into this, if that makes sense.
So these two things - obviously the part here, although I can show you
where that would happen is.
Well, there you go.
Now, they're exactly equivalent.
So basically the way these work is they're just kind of they could all
be transformed into each other.
They're all exactly equivalent.
They just have different sort of shapes and stuff to them.
So basically,
What happens is a for Loop that looks like this will basically just do
you'll do this thing.
So, there it is.
It'll then do a while loop on this.
And each time to the while loop at the end of the while loop, before
it does anything else.
It'll do.
The thing that you put last year and again, it's a little hard to see
that in the de butter because it a better kind of didn't really move
the line thing to where it should have moved.
But this is conceptually.
This is what the code actually is.
So these two Loops do substantively the exact same thing.
It's just they're written in a different notation and you may find one
or the other Mark more easy to read.
Now.
The reason a lot of people prefer for Loops is because it's not really
because they're more flexible or do anything really all that
interesting over like say just
eating as a while loop like this.
Usually the reason they do it is because it makes it easier for people
reading the code to see what the main sort of reason for the loop is
because it puts out in it sort of the person who's the loop
controller, the the variable that's going to be tested and initialize
and tested and changed typically goes in here.
So it's just an easier way for people to see.
Oh, this is a loop that shifts X.
I can see, I can see that's basically what this Loop is doing.
And then I know that everything in the body of the loop is just stuff
that has to happen.
On every one of those, that's like kind of stuff that happens with the
x or whatever.
So that is why people often prefer for Loops is because they just they
give, you know, you can see that these are kind of spread out and not
really all that related in the code.
When you look at it here.
It's not that obvious.
Especially if you imagine, you know, you're typically looking at code
that has like all this other crap, sort of strewn all throughout it.
And in that particular case, it gets pretty hard to see necessarily
what the loop is.
Whereas if you know, you look at it here, the for Loops going to have
that stuff.
We all sort of mixed like this, but the x is still, it's really clear.
What's happening here, right?
So it's pretty easy to kind of kind of isolate it so it's usually like
a legibility concern and that's mostly what a forest for.
Okay, so that is pretty much it for flow control except for one that
I'm probably going to end up using it in the Stream of bunch.
So I just want to mention it.
If you're tired of writing a statements a lot.
There's a thing called a switch statement and what a switch statement
is.
Is it something that basically allows you to put many?
If together assuming that they obey a couple quick rules, so if I have
something like okay, I've got some value its X its equal to 3 and I
want to do something on like a ton of different, you know, sort of
things that X could be, right?
X could be 0, x could be 1, x could be 2, whatever, right?
So, I've got all sorts of things this editor.
I do not get along with very well.
Why are you doing these things?
Okay, so I want to test a bunch of things and basically like I kept,
Doing this and I wrote, you know, the X test over and over and over
and over and over and over again, right?
And so what a switch statement really allows you to do most of the
time these days are some other uses for it, but they're kind of a
little janky like Duff's device and these are the sorts of weird
things, but for the most part, what a switch statement is if you are
going to compare a variable to a bunch of constants.
you can put the variable or the expression, whatever something that
evaluates to a number, you can put a switch statement in and then you
can
Use what are called case labels.
And these case labels basically just have the different values that
you wanted case.
One case, two case three case for case, 5 and case 6.
All right.
So this has all the different ones, right?
That I have here.
Now, you'll notice there's actually a final thing that I could do
here.
Right?
I could put an else.
That was like, if none of these were true, it finally does this one
thing over here right now, and of course, I need to actually type the
if
Don't forget that.
Okay, so assuming you've got that set up this test them.
All right, it's going to do something here.
Here, here, here here, here here.
And I want to write this little more concisely.
I can write this as a switch statement and I can even do the the final
else.
There's a thing called a default case, which is basically the case,
when none of the things are true.
And what this basically does is the switch statement.
Basically jumps to whichever one of these case labels is true.
And if none of them are true, it jumps to the default, right?
So it's basically just a more concise way of writing this, but
It's important to remember that it only does the jump for you only the
jump.
So for example, if the thing that I was trying to do is this
Right.
This is what I've got.
I'm going to print out.
So, I basically got all the cases here.
I've got six, five, four, three, two, and one, right?
And X is equal to 3, so we would expect to do our x equals three test.
We'd expect to print that out, right?
Well.
If I go in here and do exactly the same thing with my switch
statement, right?
You can see it is definitely more concise.
But if I do this and expect it to work, I will be in for a little bit
of a surprise.
So we run this code will compile it first.
Make sure we don't got any errors.
Okay, so I jump in here.
I've got x equal to 3 test, it zero.
It's not zero.
I test it, 21.
It's not one tested to to.
It's not to adjust the 3.
It is 3.
It outputs three ifs work just
We thought they were just the way I describe them really in the
Stream.
Everybody's happy.
I come down to the switch statement X.
Of course, I can look at Exit still three right?
There it is.
And if I do my switch jump, I jump right to case 3 and I'm super
happy.
It's going to print case 3 every with everything's great.
But what happens now it prints case for it.
Prints case, 5, it creates cayde-6 and it prints the default case.
What's going on?
Well, the answer is, like I said, switch is just a jump.
It just jumps to the case that it was supposed to do.
It doesn't stop executing after it does, the jump.
So it'll just keep on keeping on.
So You Again, you've got this break statement, but I was talking about
the exits Loops break can.
Will be used to break out of a switch.
And what that does is it jumps out to after the controlling block of
the switch after the sort of the curly braces that in closed the
switch, right?
So what I want to do is I want to put a break statement in each of
these so that after it's done it will actually go out.
So now if I run my code it'll do the same in both cases.
It'll come through here.
It'll execute the case 3 and we'll jump to case three, execute.
It'll jump out.
So both of my things from case 3, which is what I
I wanted.
Okay.
So there you go.
So it's pretty simple, switch statement.
And you can even use this to your advantage if you want to.
Let's say, you want to do something in case one like, let's say, case
one actually looked like this for some reason, or actually shoots a
case 3, because that's what we're on right now.
So, let's say case, three, actually also did the stuff from case for
right?
Well, if that was the case, I could just eliminate this break and now
we're good to go often times.
People will put a comment in here so that, you know, that was
intentional, this false.
True.
Because it is kind of common for people to forget to put the break
statement in as a bug.
And so you kind of typically want to let people know, but in that
case, you get sort of the drop through for free.
So, here we go.
We present.
We do three and four.
We jump in produce, three produce for and then we break out, right?
So that's what
What?
You'd expect?
So that is the switch statement.
Okay.
Final thing.
I want to talk about on this stream, I think and this is going to be
the last dream since the main cast.
So, there's a couple things I didn't get to, I didn't really get to
dereference operator, which is we sort of kind of did a little bit but
not much and I didn't get to two's complement.
So maybe we'll try to do them in the Q&A.
I don't know.
We'll see.
But in the mainstream, I think I mean I think in this dream we're
going to wrap it up soon.
The last thing I want to talk about is I haven't
Really discussed blocks out, right?
I just kind of introduced them at the beginning and kind of showed you
them here.
We did a bunch of them with the loop bodies and stuff and you've seen
all these curly braces, but I never really outright said what goes on
with a block and the answer is a block, is basically a logical part of
the program that does have flow control implications.
Usually, if there's something preceding it, like, an, if because like
within AF, this logical block, here doesn't get executed, if the, if
isn't true.
So, oftentimes, there's an attached
Piece of control flow or like a function, right?
This is an attached piece of control that says this block only occurs
when this function is called so blocks encapsulate code.
They sort of bundle it up in a way that it only gets run.
If a particular piece of code, control flow is true, but they have
some other properties.
One is that variables, declared inside them, right?
And I'm going to go ahead and actually Vape all this right now.
Goodbye, variables declared inside them.
So if I say it, y equals 5 and then I open a block because I don't
even have to put control flow there, but I could, let's say this way.
If I can assign variables declare inside them, do not exist outside
it.
Right.
So if I do this, I will get a big old nasty War an error.
And basically what it says is X is an Undeclared.
Identifier.
Well, what do you mean?
I declared it right here.
Well, no, you didn't.
Because a block basically captures all of its variables for only
itself.
Nothing can come outside of this nested blocks blocks that are inside
can reference X just fine, right?
That's fine.
So anything that I do in an outside block will totally work, but oh
well guess I got to delete
This guy first that will totally work, and that's fine.
But things outside, if that block occurs somewhere else outside in the
program.
That is an error and that's no good.
So, yeah, so there you go.
And again, the indentation doesn't actually matter here that
indentation is just syntax syntactic.
It's not syntactic sugar.
It's just formatting.
That is C, programmers use.
So they can see what's inside but block, but it's really only the
blocks that matter.
So, for example, I could easily just write the code, like this, if I
wanted to force.
Amazing, that could just be my code.
It doesn't matter where the in, it's not like python where you have to
have indents in a certain way or anything like that.
It just it doesn't care at all.
It's fine.
So what happens with blocks?
Is there basically like the stack thing that I was talking about
before where I sang?
That's where variables live and they get pushed on the stack and then
pulled off the stack.
Well, you can basically think of blocks as sort of being having their
own sort of Stack implication when I enter a block by the time that I
get into that block and start doing stuff.
It is incumbent upon the compiler, to have pushed the space to have
made space, on the stack, for these variables that are in the block.
So, if I start doing stuff with variables in this block, by the time I
start executing
Code in there or doing whatever this stuff needs to be on the stack
and live and I can do stuff with it.
But once I get to the end it is no longer incumbent upon the compiler
or the operating system to keep those things valid.
So, as soon as you exit a block, it is entirely legal for the stuff
that you were working with to just disappear, right?
It can just be gone.
Now, oftentimes it's not actually gone because you could still access
it because it still the memory is still there and hasn't gotten like
overwritten or trash or anything yet, but the but if you were to use
it,
That would be a big source of potential bugs because the compiler is
no longer under any any restriction to keep that space used for what
you told it to be.
So it could just go use it for something else and then you got a bad
bug because you're trying to use something.
Now, you may ask me.
Well, Casey you just said that you can't refer to it.
I just saw you.
Right?
Basically do this.
Okay, and when you did it, you couldn't even compile the program.
So the question is, what are you talking about?
What do you mean?
I could reference it.
Well remember,
He allows you to do a lot of direct stuff with memory.
So maybe I Define a pointer, right?
And that pointer doesn't point to anything at first.
But in here, this pointer equals the address of X, right.
Well, now, when I get out here, I can actually do stuff with that.
Oh, and hey, this
The opportunity to talk about that dereference operator, actually, who
this is going to be good.
This is gonna be good.
This is good Sunday stream.
We'll talk about that in one second.
So, if I were to take the address of X, like, we've been doing for
this whole stream, right, to take the address where and memory X is
this pointer was declared in the outer scope.
These blocks typically are often referred to as scope.
It's like basically where you can, you know where variables are valid
to reference and where they're not is often called scope.
I don't actually know why, but it often is so, but anyway, it's in
declared in the outer.
I block this pointer is clear and the other block, which means I can
reference it anywhere in the outer block, right?
So if I want to, I can snap the address of X, I can find out what the
address of X is while.
I'm in this Scope, when I get out of the scope, when I got to the
block X goes away potentially, but I've still got its address so I can
go ahead and write to it all I want, right?
And so when I go ahead and compile this, it compiles just fine, right?
And what happens is when I go in here, you will see I will take the
address of X, right.
And now I know where X is.
I know exactly where Exodus goes, wherever it was pointed to write.
That is the actually value of x.
It was set to 6.
It's still set to 6, right?
Even though the compiler is not under any obligation to keep that
space available, can use it for something else.
I can write to it.
And Bam.
I just wrote 2x, even though it's out of the scope.
Totally not.
You should never do it.
It's just asking for disaster.
But like I said, everything in C is just happening in the memory.
It's direct their you.
Go to town on it.
And if you want to create bad bugs, waiting to happen for yourself,
you can.
So I just wanted to kind of underscore the fact that this is sort of
stuff that helps to protect you.
This sort of scoping where you were, you wrapped variables inside
Scopes and they go out of scope is to help you not make mistakes.
And when you're doing stuff like this, you're basically just asking
for trouble.
There's almost never any reason to do what I am showing you here, but
the point is, it is possible because it's all about memory.
And this got some memory at some point and that memory hasn't been
freed yet or marked as inaccessible by the operating system so we can
just keep on writing to it and it works.
So the thing that I wasn't going to cover today, it turns out that I
am because I just used it to show you something.
Super naughty is this star.
So, like I said, star is normally math.
If I do x times y, right?
That just means multiplication.
So, if I do, you know, y equals x times y, I want to do x times Y and
I want to assign it to why that's all fine, right?
The star has another meaning when it appears as just a prefix.
So when it isn't x times pointer, if it's just pointer, right?
And I can even wrap it in parentheses, to make sure that even if there
was an X out here, it wasn't going to do anything or whatever.
Right?
So I've got, you know, this thing, what that means is I'm talking
about the thing that this points to, it's a pointer.
So I want you to do the operation as if you have the thing.
It was pointing to here.
So this is pointing to X and I want to operate on X.
So,
Turns it into X essentially, it turns it into the memory location that
X was, right.
So basically if I have n star pointer and then I refer to Star
pointer, it's essentially the same as taking the Declaration of what
star pointer was removing the star from it and then, whatever that is
is what you have left.
So in this case, it's an ENT.
So star pointer is the nth at the address contained in pointer, right?
So if I took an address of an INT and stick it in pointer, which is
what I did, I took the address of X then from then on.
Star pointer refers to what's in that location, and so for example, if
I wanted to get it out, right?
So, I do this.
Right.
I want to know what was the next?
Well, I can't refer to X because it's out of the scope.
The block we left that block.
It's gone.
Well, I can still, just go ahead and get it and I can put it in y
because y.
Right is set to 5 right now but X was set to six, bam.
I just accessed it.
There's a six and so all that's doing is basically the stack.
It's just going into the stack and do a location.
That's not supposed to be used anymore.
But I know it the value still in there.
I know it's in there because the program hasn't done anything else.
Right?
So I know it's still in there.
So I just grabbed it out and I can do that.
That's totally legal.
And the dereference operator can get nuts.
If you want to write.
I could do something that's like a pointer to a pointer.
Right?
It's a pointer pointer and I can take that and make the pointer
pointer be equal to the address of the pointer.
So now I'm pointing to the pointer that's pointing to X.
Right?
And I can go ahead and get it out.
That way.
I can dereference it twice right again.
Full banana cakes for a Sunday stream.
Why not?
Bam got it out.
And so the dereference operator basically chases the pointer it says
Go to where this pointer points and I'm talking about that now.
And if I do that and I want to do it again, I can just go.
Okay, that thing you were pointing to that's a pointer.
So go find with that was pointing to and it all just works.
Right?
So you can do that.
You can have as many as you want.
You can have pointers to pointers to pointers to pointers.
You can have pointers to structure with pointers in them.
The point to other structs that more pointers in them.
You can chase them all day long.
That's how you build data structures often linked list or pointers
that point to structure that pointers that point to the next one.
The point to the next one.
That point, the next one to bite the next one.
You want to walk the list, you go through all the pointers just point.
Point point point.
Point right.
So, that syntax.
That I used in a previous stream right?
Where I had a struct and I said, oh, there was a pointer and I
referenced some member of the struct essentially that is just the same
as dereferencing.
The pointer, the way that I just showed you how to do it and then
putting the dot.
And so another way to look at that whole dot, arrow thing that I
saying is like it's kind of janky is basically like The Arrow is sort
of like saying dereference the pointer first.
Then do the dot thing.
That makes sense.
So, there you go.
Last thing when you open a new scope, you can Shadow a variable and I
snuck it in here, but I don't know if anyone caught it.
There's some eagle eyes on the stream.
So
I assume that they probably did.
But basically, what happens is if you have two variables called why
normally?
That'd be an error, right?
Normally if I did this, that's not going to compile.
It says you have redefinitions of why, but you can always Shadow a
variable by declaring a new one in a scope inside the outer scope.
So if I make a new block, inside an old block,
That block can define y again and it's a different.
Why?
What if you didn't know?
It was a different.
Why?
I just told you how you could determine that actually, right?
Let's do it.
Here is why pointer zero?
And here is why pointer one.
Let's go ahead and make y pointer zero.
Equal to the address of this Y.
And we'll make why pointer 1 equal to the address of this y.
Now, if they were the same, that means that the same why, if they're
different, their means are plenty of different memory locations.
So they're different.
Why?
Right?
Because it's all about memory, if these things are in different
places.
They're not the same.
Why?
They're just two names that point.
A different memory locations such as happen to both of you.
I well, let's see what they are.
So what do we got?
Why point is 0?
Y pointer one different.
Right?
Not the same value.
Fa e 4f a
Before, and that's how you know that they are actually in different
places.
So this made a new Y and that is the only time it is legal to do that.
Shadowing.
You have to open a new block.
Like I said, you can't Shadow a variable by declaring a new y, in the
same block as someone already declared Ally, right?
That's not allowed.
So let me look over my list.
Really briefly here.
Is there anything else I want to go over?
I think I'm going to skip, two's complement.
Sorry, guys.
Looks like looks like I got just about everything.
So I think that is it for our test streaming.
It has been very productive.
This was a crazy Sunday stream.
I am going to stop the stream now and we are going to go on to the Q&A
in a section in a session in a second here.
But first, let me say thank
You so much everyone for showing up.
We've had so many people on the stream.
We had 300 people today almost 400 at one point looked like to, that's
a lot of people watching the stream.
So thank you so much for helping me test out the streaming.
I think it'll, it's going to make a huge difference when we actually
start the proper stream on Monday having the having a me practice
doing this.
But be we've also had like a ton of people who have, you know, sort of
written in and told me things to do that.
We're really beneficial like for example, stuff that I need to set on
Twitch and how
How to you know, like making the font size bigger, all that sort of
stuff would have been stuff.
We'd have to work out in the middle of the mainstream and we've gotten
a lot of that stuff.
Sort of squared away now which makes a huge huge difference.
I think when we actually start on Monday, so thank you everyone for
all that help.
I will see you in the Q&A.
If you are interested, and if not, I will see you on Monday for the
very first actual game coding stream, which I think will be a lot of
fun.
So, thanks very much for joining us and I will see you in a second.
and,