Do you are intro to see?
Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to the fourth day of the test stream here
where we're doing a little introduction to see yesterday.
We got to do some fun stuff.
We sort of started to really see how the code and the memory actually
works together and we sort of did some some we played around a little
bit sort of showing where things are stored in the computer.
We did a bunch of things that I kind of been, you know, hoping to get
two in the first two streams.
I was kind of like building up to them and
Tonight's stream was pretty good.
That way.
I got to tie a lot of things together.
So it's pretty excited.
There was one snafu.
In the Stream and I will correct it.
Now, if you're there for the Q&A, then you already know what it is.
I'm talking about.
But what I tried to do yesterday, I wanted to show you because the,
you know, on I believe it was Thursday night.
Sorry.
Yeah, Thursday, night's dream.
We started to look at the disassembly.
So we had written some C code and we were looking at the disassembly
and I was showing you some stuff.
And I said, well this these numbers over here on the side, you know,
those numbers basically correspond to addresses in memory.
Three of where your code actually is.
Because the processor obviously, has to read the code to execute it.
It's got a read the stuff that we write.
And so it's just memory, like, everything else code is memory, just
like data is in memory.
Everything is in memory, everything you ever do is going to be in
memory somewhere.
And so I was like, you know, this was the address of where this
particular piece of code is in the actual member of the computer.
When the CPU is going to go, fetch it, execute it.
And I was like, I want to show that.
So what I did is I had showed earlier in the
The stream.
I had showed, you know, you go over here to the memory window.
You can open up this memory window.
And if you're trying to look at something, you can cut and paste an
address in there which I did and I showed you, like, here's the
memory, right?
Like we could see the memory we played with it.
It was great, it all work, great.
And then I was like, well, you can grab, you know, and the address
here and look at your code.
And when I did it, it was like unable to vote expression.
Now, I really know what was going on there because you should be able
to look at the code, but I assume that maybe it was something that had
changed recently in Windows since like, the last time I, you know,
Anything like that because it's not something you do that often.
Look at the code, the actual code segments and stuff.
So, I just assume, well, maybe for security purposes.
They turned off reading because any given page and memory.
Any virtual page in memory can be marked as readable executable
writable these sorts of things.
So I was pretty sure.
I mean I was like, well, yeah, I don't know what's going on here.
Maybe they marked it.
So you can't read those pages to avoid some kind of hacking attempt.
I don't know.
But point being I was, I was kind of confused.
I said endorsement was going on.
It turns out that was just me.
Not remembering or maybe they change it, but I'm assuming it just me
not remembering that when you put a hexadecimal address, which is what
this is in here.
You have to prefix it with zero X just like you would in code.
It's like a little notation that says the thing that's coming, next is
hexadecimal, which doesn't really make much sense when you look at it
this way because it's like, okay, but got D's in it.
Missy not decimal, must be hexadecimal, but if you had a number that
just was hexadecimal, didn't happen to use any of the letters.
You could see it.
Maybe wouldn't know which one you meant.
So putting the 0x in actually does let you look at the code and
thankfully, Someone caught that and and mentioned on the Q&A.
So we were able to do it in the Q&A, but I just wanted to correct that
for anyone who doesn't watch the Q&A?
That was what had happened.
So it's actually totally fine.
And those pages are not marked unreadable or anything like that.
And you know, it makes sense.
Anyway, it was, it was really the real one of the reasons it was so
confusing to me is because
I'm looking at it here.
I mean the debugger obviously can access that code page because you
know, if it couldn't that how is it showing us the disassembly?
How is it showing us what the code is here?
If it couldn't inspect it.
So when I asked the debugger to inspect it in here, it shouldn't be
like able to inspect it in one window and not able to expect it in the
other.
But you know, I've learned not to assume stuff like that because when
you're programming on a giant complicated operating system with a
giant complicated IDE, you never know what could be happening, right?
I mean, you never know what might be going on internally.
Could be that the person who implemented the thing that disassembles
here was using a different way of getting it to pages.
And so it worked and then the person who wrote the memory window
didn't.
So I didn't want to jump to conclusions and also during a live stream.
I mean, I'll be honest when you're live streaming, your brain is
thinking a lot about how to explain stuff and it's not thinking as
well about how to troubleshoot stuff.
So, it really does help to have people in the Stream watching out for
me, and I really appreciate that because your brains are focused on
what I'm doing and my brains focusing on explaining.
So having the two
Is actually pretty good.
It's kind of like, pair programming.
If someone can be like, no, no.
No, you just forgot the blonde.
It's like, very good.
So I really appreciate that.
Whoever that was.
Thank you very much.
I know it was Matthew vandevander, who, who actually posted it at the
end of the chat, but I think he said that it was someone else who had
said it earlier.
Like, at the time.
I don't read the chat during the stuff because it'd be too distracting
for me, but I read it at the end.
So anyway, that's just the one thing that I wanted to correct, and
it's not that big of a deal.
You will rarely be doing that with code by just wanted to show you
that it is there.
Because
Again, one of the main things that I could keep harping on through
this entire series is just so he's saying everything is in memory.
Everything is just talking about how to get things into the CPU, do
stuff on them.
Put them back out to memory.
That's the whole thing.
And so I just want to show that even the code is there.
And basically all code is is it's a bunch of in codings for these
instructions.
And I think there's a thing show code B yet.
So show code B actually put right after the address.
It actually puts you what the encoding actually was.
So this
mnemonic and this, you know, operand and this operand are actually
encoded this way.
This is how Intel encodes how the x86 and cook.
Sorry.
This is now, this is x86.
We're compiling a 32-bit mode.
So the x86 processor expects to read things that will read them like
this and know that this is what you wanted to do and the disassembler.
The things that showing us the actual Assembly Language here is
basically just reading these code B ins, you know, visual Studios
reading these code B, and then disassembling them and going, okay.
That's the mnemonic for move.
That's like that means a move instruction.
So I'm going to write move.
So it's easier for you to read.
So you don't have to sit around going.
Oh, what is 6f 445 FBF?
Because I have no idea what that is.
You'd have to go.
Look at instruction tables to know what they are.
And if you're a hardcore Assembly Language program, or you probably
know what some of them translate to but I'm so not that guy.
So I need the translation.
Anyway.
So one of the interesting things here and this is just an aside
because hey, it's a weekend stream.
We could be a little more Meandering.
One thing that's kind of interesting here.
A little side is that there's different types of processors.
I mean, I guess I should say there's different types of philosophies
in processor architecture.
And like I made abundantly clear on last week's dream.
I am not a hardware guy.
So I'm not the person to explain them to you.
But what I will say just in passing is that there's different kinds,
some kinds of processors.
The philosophy philosophy is the
Auctions are a fixed size.
So, like the number of bytes.
It takes to encode, any given instruction is fixed.
So, if you have an instruction, like, you know, move this to here, or
whatever, or add this to this or whatever, like we've got, those would
all be the same size.
It doesn't matter what the instruction is, there always the same size
and that, you know, that would be like, I believe on, for example,
powerpc.
That was true.
So, like, you know, on a powerpc, every instruction in memory as it's
encoded, when it, you know,
In the CPU, is reading it out of memory.
Those instructions are the same size.
But on Intel CPUs that they don't use that philosophy.
They have instructions that are variable length.
So basically, as the instruction is being decoded, it looks at what
the actual instruction is.
And what the actual code, you know, code, b, r to figure out how many
It should read.
So it kind of dynamically impacts it and you can actually see that
going on here, right?
You can see if we're to take this line, for example, which is one of
those move instructions.
It's
Bring the value f f into which again is 255.
That's the hexadecimal, which actually going to cover hexadecimal
today for the first time, even though it's kind of keeps poking out a
tooth.
So it's going to move that 255.
It's going to move it to this location.
The test test location, whatever the address is of test.
It's going to do that move.
That is encoded as four bytes here, c64 5f BFF, right?
And hexadecimal again, which we'll cover in a little bit.
It's each letter is basically four bits.
So if you see
two hexadecimal letters or numbers, you know that you're looking at a
bit.
So this is 32 bits right here, right?
It's 8 16, 24 32, but if we go down and look at this, add instruction
where we're just adding one to the register eax, we're taking whatever
is in that register or adding one that is encoded as only three.
So it's encoded as 83 C, 0 0 1 and there isn't a fourth, you know,
fourth B there the fourth B is actually
Actually, you know, just used for the next instruction.
So it's only three bites per instruction for these guys and I am
certainly not.
Knowledgeable enough about Hardware to tell you which one of those is
the right methodology or what, the trade-offs are between them.
I just wanted to point out that, that is the case.
And so it's interesting to kind of think about a little bit, that
there's so much of a difference there.
This can get pretty extreme because as you can see down here,
This guy only has one one bite of code push edx, which is a stack push
kind of thing.
You know, we were talking about the stack and I think the stack grows,
this grows the stack.
One could.
But anyway, so I won't that's not really super relevant to us and it's
not something that's going to come up in the series.
I don't think at all, but it's worth kind of noting the differences
between CPUs there and that there's different kind of architectures
and different sorts of things happen in them.
Because as you go, if you start to care more, as you code about what
the processor is, and how it works.
And, you know, or even if it's just fascinating to you, a lot of
things are just of interest to me.
I like learning about them, even though I'm not an expert and don't
actually need necessarily some of that knowledge.
It's just fun to learn about these
Two things like wise talking about learning about the adding circuits
fun to know how people make a CPU, add numbers together or something.
Right?
Because it's you know, it's what we use every day is kind of
interesting to learn a little bit about the other disciplines that are
involved in making a game Run that have nothing to do with maybe what
we do day to day.
So today what I'd like to do since we kind of got to the point where
we were actually thinking about memory and code and that sort of stuff
is I want to actually go over
Some I wrote actually even had some notes Here.
I want to go over sort of looking at memory in a little more detail in
terms of what see how we actually program in C to use memory
effectively.
And so the first thing I wanted to talk about was basically like
casting and indianness.
I wanted to start talking about how these values actually work.
So what we're going to do here is we're going to, we're going to get
rid of the code that we were writing.
We're going to start.
Fresh air ghost going to check.
Make sure we have the clean compile and we do.
So what I'm going to do now is I am going to go back to what we did
originally.
I'm going to make a unsigned, I'm going to make an unsigned 8-bit
value is like my cord gets caught here.
I'm going to make an unsigned 8-bit value, that we are going to start
looking at and I think I'll stick with calling it test and I am going
to assign a value to it.
I'm going to assign the value.
Let's say 500.
Now that's not going to work 200.
And since of course, it's only 8 Bits.
I can't represent 500 off to a good start today.
What I'm going to do is going to run to that line and then we are
going to execute that line and we should see.
Our value getting set to 200, and it is exactly what we expected.
Now, if you remember from last time, the Ampersand, if I want to I can
always put an ampersand in front of something to ask where in memory
that thing is, it's taking the address of that variable.
And so this tells me exactly
Where it is, and now we remember we can go to our memory window, which
I guess at this point since I'm talking about memory so much.
Maybe we should even doc, maybe we should even talk that.
So one of things they can do and visual Studios, you can kind of drag
these things around, and there's this little flower pattern thing.
If you use the little arrows that are on the flower pattern, I don't
know if you can see that on the stream, because it may not be
something that it was captured, but it comes up a little flower
pattern and there's arrows pointing up down left and right.
If you pick one, it'll doc look above to the left to the right of or
whatever, but I'm just going
To pick the middle thing that doesn't have an arrow on it, which docks
it right in place.
And so now I've got a memory window that's just kind of sitting down
here and that should be fine.
I think for our purposes and I'll move it up a little bit so that it's
not obscured too much by the by the the video of me talking to you.
So if I go here now and I look at this address that we've got four at,
you know, for test the actual address of the variable that address is
0, x 2 3, F9 17 and here we are looking
At the actual values and I'm going to switch out of hexadecimal
display again, because I don't want to talk about that quite yet.
Although, we will actually talk about today.
So I am going to go to why is it, you know, it always likes to slide
me around.
I wish it would just kind of leave that there.
There we go.
Okay.
So here we are.
And here is our 200.
We've actually, you know, done the assignment already and what I'd
like to point out to you is that we are looking at these values as
individual bytes.
So each one of these values that you see in the memory.
Window corresponds to 8 Bits of the memory, in the computer.
So, what we're going to start to address?
Now, is what happens if we ask for more than 8 Bits, right?
What happens if instead of saying unsigned car, right?
What happens if I were to say, unsigned short?
I remember an unsigned short is 16 bits.
So care is eight.
Short is 16.
So now I could do the 500, but I typed in originally,
But that will take more than 8 Bits to represent and we've asked for
16 bit.
So it shouldn't be a problem.
But the question is, since we were looking at memory there, where does
it actually go, right?
Where does it actually go?
When I, when I write that 500?
Well, so again, let's take a look.
And I'll cut, you know, get this value out here.
We'll look at the memory 33 fbe for and we're going to go ahead and
write into this location 500.
So, let's see.
What happens step.
Now.
Did you see those to change?
It was these
Right.
So what actually happened was here is the B that was actually being
pointed to right here is the location.
It wrote to that bite, it wrote 244 and then it wrote to one bite
after it.
Okay, and what I'd like you to notice about these two is that if we
actually break down the binary, as to what these two things represent,
you know, that the 244 isn't the higher part of the binary isn't the
higher part of the 16 bits.
Because what are the 16
For 500, right?
The 16 bits for 500 are this, right?
You've got, you know what, I could even make a little, I'm gonna make
a cute little diagram here.
You're Gonna Love You Gonna Love My ASCII art skills.
They're going to be awesome.
Right?
So I'm going to make a thing that shows you 16 bits here.
These are actually the bits.
So these are not hexadecimal values.
You can either be ones or zeros, right?
And so what we want to do is we want to represent 500.
So our highest bit that we want to
Do is going to be 256, right?
Which is this value here, that equals 256 is remember.
These are powers of 2.
I don't expect you to know these in your head but it goes right.
1248.
This guy right here is 16.
I don't know how to do that.
Look at me, go.
There's and gentlemen.
Can you believe it?
32 64, right 128.
256 and then they'll keep going up 512 and whatever.
We don't actually need those to represent 500 because since we know
the next bit here, this bit would be 512 right.
Read these vertically by 512.
512, 256, 128.
And it's a little hard to read since this bit would be 512 and that's
higher than the number.
We know that the first bit that we have to set is 256.
Right?
So if we subtract 500 from 256, and in fact, we can even use calc to
do this.
I don't pretend to be a math whiz so if we have five hundred and we
subtracted 56, we're left with 244, right?
And so if we if we want to do 244 we can go ahead and set 128 as well,
right?
And then we'll subtract.
It from it.
So now we've added five.
We've had a 256 and 128.
We're left with 116 which is still higher than 64 so we can set that,
right?
So we'll set that 64, we're down to 52 52 still higher than 32.
So we got to subtract 32 from it as well down to 2016.
Still there - 16 we're down to four that 1 minus 4 is 0.
So we have successfully created our number in binary by hand.
You add 4 to 16.
Into 32 to 64 to 128 to 256 and you will get 500 very exciting.
Right?
So if we actually look at these two parts, right?
I said that we were seeing in B over here.
So our B part is going to be the first 8 Bits which is this, right 1 1
1 1 0 1 0 0.
Yeah, it kind of sounds like a Flight of the Conchords song.
But the part up here is actually just one.
We only use in our second bite that we ask for the high.
terabyte is what we would call that typically because there's like
it's high and low based on basically how much power it sort of has, if
you want to add a very high number, you're going to add something in
the higher-order B because they all correspond to things that are all
higher powers of 2, then the lower order B, if you will, so, if we
take a look at this, right, the only thing that we
A higher order, byte is just one, just the one bit was set.
But in this one we actually had the 4-bit, the 16-bit 32-bit to 64-bit
and 128-bit.
Right?
Oops.
You don't need to do that at all.
So if I go back to my calc here and I see what that's actually going
to be, right?
It's going to be 4 plus 16, plus 32, plus 64, plus 128 and that's to
44, which is exactly what we got here.
So our low byte is 244 are high.
B is one, which is exactly what we expected.
But now what I want you to think about
Out is why they are in that order, right?
We have an address in memory.
These count up sequentially.
This right here is the three million four hundred and six thousand,
eight hundred and twentieth B in memory in our virtual memory space
and then this one will be the one one.
One after that.
It goes to quench turrets.
This will be one Higher.
That one will be the three million four thousand six eight hundred
twenty first byte in memory twenty second third fourth fifth going on.
Going on and on and on, but when you think about it, since we have
these bytes in memory, it's totally arbitrary.
How the CPU chooses to interpret them.
It didn't have to put the low order byte first and then the higher
order byte.
It could have chosen to do them in the opposite order.
There's no reason it's just convention, right?
The CPU is going to have a circuit in it.
That knows how to add together.
Things that are 16 bits long, but where it got each part of the 16
bits is
Avant it doesn't matter.
Right?
There isn't some hard law of physics that says that you must store the
low part first and the high part s.
So what this is called.
It is actually an arbitrary choice on the part of the CPU designer,
way back when the person first designed the x86.
What this is called is called, This is called endianness and honestly,
I don't know if it's one inner tube, you know, spelling also not my
strong suit.
So we're just going to say endian for now and adding this to the end
will be an exercise list for Google.
These are called little endian mode and big-endian mode and I believe
they come, I want to see it.
Comes from like Gulliver's Travels.
It comes from like a crazy fiction, book reference that happened a
long time before.
Like, I was born.
I don't even know.
But point being the convention in Computing is to use the term little
endian.
If the low order, byte comes first, in memory and big-endian.
If the high order comes first in memory, so what we are right?
If since we put our 254 first and our
One second.
That was low and then High we are little endian because the little
part comes first and in fact x86 processors, the standard mode used
for arm processors, although arms.
I believe the architecture is actually switchable so it but
Standard kind that you would see in like an Android or iOS.
Device, arm processors are x64, the 64-bit version of x86.
That's what sinews and most processors today, when you run stuff, like
64-bit windows and that sort of stuff or 64-bit Linux on on Intel
machines.
That's all little-endian.
So mostly, we're all in the little endian these days and it's great
because having only one, endianness makes things a lot simpler
actually, it's, it's funny.
We'll see kind of where that I'll mention a little
Cases, that, that comes up later.
But there are big Indian architectures.
And in the older times, they were a lot more prevalent than they are
today.
For example, the powerpc, which I mentioned earlier today is a big,
endian architecture.
And so things like the Xbox 360, the PlayStation 3.
Before those switched from powerpc, in their older incarnations to the
Xbox One and the PlayStation 4, which are now running x64 based
architectures.
To be power PC, like the cell processor, for example, is a powerpc
based processor, the PS3.
And so on those were big Indian, which meant that data was the other
way around, in memory.
So the one would have come first and the to 5044 would have come
second.
Now.
The reason that this is actually somewhat of concern to programmers is
because, if you are writing things that deal with memory directly,
which often times game, programmers are almost all games will have to
deal with memory directly.
Ali in a number of ways when it does, like data loading and stuff like
this, at the very least.
Once the data, you know, from getting the data from the disk where
it's stored onto the computer.
What usually turns out to be the case, is, the data stored on disk for
a program.
Like, let's say you're writing a game and you've got a lot of art
assets.
So there's textures, but on there and audio and all this sort of stuff
and all this kind of metadata about entities and all this stuff.
If you look at all that data, it's stored on disk.
You typically, just have one package for your game.
You've built all the, you've processed all the data and spend that
sort of stuff.
You may not process all that data into a different disc Pac package
for every platform.
You may want to use the same.
This package everywhere both on the PC and on the Xbox and so on.
And what that means is that data is going to be in one endian format
or another, right?
It's going to either be little-endian or big-endian because it's
stored on disk in a particular order and you know, whatever.
You wrote it out, as is what it's going to stay.
As so if you try to load data, that is big, endian on a little endian
machine, you need to do a conversion first to swap, the order of
things around, in order to make them readable proper, you know,
operable properly on the CPU.
Because like I just said, the order would be different.
The, the CPU will expect numbers that are bigger than 8, Bits to be
encoded differently in each one and where you see this rear?
Its ugly head.
Even today, when everything is like, all little endian for the most
Part is in file formats because portable file formats.
Like let's say
PSD the, for the of a Photoshop file.
You want to read in a Photoshop file, but your artist created, right?
And into a processing tool, Photoshop.
I believe is big-endian format because it was originally on Max, which
were originally Motorola and Motorola, which was sort of the earlier,
lineage of the powerpc.
Like the sixty sixty eight thousand.
What the hell was the name of thing?
68000 processor Motorola.
You know what?
My memory is so bad these days someone give me a web browser.
Motorola 68 km/h 16 s is the one I wanted.
Yes, the Motorola 68000 so macintoshes.
I believe ran on the Motorola 68k line for a while.
I don't know.
I never had a Macintosh.
So I don't really know the Amiga certainly did and I loved the Amiga
and it had 68k line in it.
Those were powerpc-based.
I'm sorry.
Those were big endian based just like the power PCS that followed them
and what that means in practice is that
File formats that were developed on those systems are often big endian
because they just wrote out the data just the way it was in memory.
They didn't do any kind of different packing just because it was on
disk.
So what you end up with is a lot of those file formats still have
their endianness of their Source architecture based baked into them.
So that's just a little, you know, a little aside that you should be
aware of and unfortunately or a rat should say perhaps fortunately we
probably won't really
I run into that too much on the on the stream because since we are in
a sort of a good World these days where everything's the same and Ian,
this we might only ever really run into it a little bit when we're
doing something like, say reading a Photoshop file, if that's what we
want to do.
But, you know, for the most part we're sort of isolated from it
because we're not probably going to have to Target any processors that
aren't already Little Indians.
So it's, you know, it's good and it's bad, it's bad because you won't
really learn it in practice, but it's it's good in that really.
It's kind of just annoying and it would be better if all processors
just stuck with little-endian.
From now on.
So no one ever had to learn it again.
Anyway, now that we've got that out of the way, hopefully, you can see
and understand now, very directly what it means to lay out things that
are bigger than one bite in memory.
Basically, all that happens is, you know, you go through and you start
stacking up each bite that you needed for the composite value into
memory.
And if we were to do this again with something that was even bigger,
right?
I could go in here and make something that's going to be 32 bits long
and maybe.
I make something that is quite large.
For example, that value there.
We will see although you know what let's make it so it won't be an
even power of to do that.
So it will get more bit set.
If we do something, that's even larger.
We will, as you would expect see that it occupies more bites.
And in this case, we would expect it to occupy for B, because we asked
for a 32-bit value.
There's me forgetting my 0x always, okay.
And you can see there at wrote 01 4853, 199 again.
This is the low order.
So, there is nothing in the low order byte.
Then.
There's the next byte, which is the next higher power 148 next higher
priority, three next higher power, 119.
And that's, that's all there is to it.
So that is how things are actually laid out in memory, when you ask
for more than 32 bits, but
In when we are actually programming for reals in the mainstream.
We do not want to constantly have to declare everything as little
parts of little bites and all these sorts of things because we would
go crazy quickly.
So what C allows us to do is it allows us to ask for things that are
actually Composites of many different types of things, all of which
might have different bit counts.
So, for example, let's say we were programming in the mainstream and
we decided that we wanted to make.
You know, something that you will see a lot of games, let's say a
projectile, right?
I want to make something that is going to shoot across the screen.
And so maybe I have something in there.
That's like an NT.
Which says, you know, let's say it's going to be is this thing, you
know, it's really not doing it quite yet.
Let's do it.
Let's do a care unsigned that is like, is this on fire?
We'll just call it that and we'll say that.
You know what?
This is going to be.
One if it's on fire and 0 if it's not this isn't probably how I would
do it in the mainstream because I'm trying to do something fairly
basic for educational purposes.
But let's just say that we felt like using 8 Bits to store something.
That is essentially only one bit of data will get into ways of not
doing that later.
But let's just say we were and then we're going to say how much damage
it does.
So maybe we have a full 32 bits just because we care about it.
We're saying to say the in the damage note.
This is how
Much damage does on impact.
And then we have like, you know, something like particles per second.
This is, you know for special effects blah blah blah.
Maybe I've got something that's like a short which is like, you know,
whatever.
You know, how many cooks there are in in the program.
In case there are too many.
Right.
So let's say we have something like this.
So
What this thing allows us to do that.
I've typed in called a struct is, it's a very simple construct in C.
But it is the backbone of most of the programming that gets done in C.
It is something that allows us to declare a layout of memory in a
prefab way that allows us to refer to it by its parts.
So we don't have to remember how we have packed these things in
memory.
We can just straight-up.
Use it so much.
Like we said down here, we said unsigned int if we wanted to.
To make test be something more complicated.
We could say, it was a projectile.
And now, what it will do is instead of it.
In one thing.
As part of test, it will actually declare all of these things for us
in pack together in memory in one place that we can refer to as that
one name.
And we will be able to do something like this this on fire equals one
because of course, we want it to be on fire.
We want the damage to be a bunch because this is super powerful
projectile.
Obvious.
Obviously, oops little typo there.
I want particles per second per second, you can
We have too many particles.
So that thing should be pretty large to, obviously tons of particles.
I mean, if the engine can't handle that many particles per second and
what good is it anyway, and then there should be maybe like 50 Cooks
because you don't want there to be too many cooks, right?
You want them to be reasonable number of cooks.
So what I have done here is I have used the C Syntax for accessing a
member, which is what the so-called right these.
Are the members for fields of this structure?
Right?
This is how I act as though, I put a period in between the name of the
one that I'm talking about the name of the particular structure that
I'm talking about and the thing inside it that I want to set I then
can use that in any place.
I would have used it if I just had declared it outside.
So if I was just declared this itself and started using it.
Me where I could use it.
We find I can use it on the other side of things too.
I could, for example, make the damage be based on whether it had fire.
So for example, I could make the damage be that so it will add one to
the damage.
If the thing was on fire, for example, right?
And these are again, this is programming.
So, their order dependent the CPU at will do these in the order in
which they appear.
And what that means is that the, this on fire will be set to one
before it gets used here.
Now, if I had done that in the opposite order, it's obviously worth
noting this would actually have been
Just whatever was in memory.
Whatever was in the part of memory that was reserved.
At the time.
It would be totally uninitialized.
And that would be pretty much probably a bug in the code because God
knows what that value would be.
But since we're doing it in this order, we know that we initialize the
first so we can use it safely and know that the value is going to be
what we set it to 0, which is 1.
All right.
So if I go ahead and run the program to this point,
We can do the same thing.
Even though this is a structure.
That's a bunch of things.
We can still use that little operator, the memory of the addressing
operator a, and we can still use that to get where the structure is.
Right?
0, X4, to FDC for is where our structure is, and what that will do is
that will give us the beginning of the structure, right?
Will give us where the first value, the first ones to find.
This is on fire, where that is, and then we can assume that the
compiler has basically.
Lee, you know, packed everything else sequentially, but what we will
notice and I think we'll even see this here because of the way that
I've typed it out, what we don't know.
How much space it might leave in between them.
So the compiler is not under any particular constraint to lay these
things out compact.
Wait.
So this is 8 Bits, right?
It's care unsigned.
So, in fact, I'll go ahead and do this.
I'll go ahead and do this math for you here.
So, if we say that, we have a care in sign, then that's one bite,
right?
So, it's one bite.
For the first thing.
We have a 32-bit value for the damage.
So that's 4 bytes.
Right?
We have a 32-bit value for the particles.
Per second, that's for B.
And we have a short which is two more bites 16 bits.
That is how many cooks are.
All right.
So this is what we've got.
So we would expect Agnes together, 4 plus 4 is 8, plus 2 is 10, plus 1
is 11.
We would expect to see something like 11 B reserved for our
projectile.
Right?
Every time we want a projectile.
We would expect the compiler to reserve 11 B.
But before I go ahead here and show you this, I think I'm actually
going to do something a little bit different, which is
Throw this this in the mix.
There is a compile-time keyword.
You can use in see, called size of which will actually tell you how
big something is.
So we can actually do size of n, t, equal size of NT.
We can do size of car, equal size of car, and we can even stick
something like unsigned in there.
So any type that you want can go in here and I'll tell you, we can do
size of in, we did that.
And then we can finally do size of tests, which is, however, big.
This thing was,
Would be, which will be the same as asking size or projectile size of
projectile.
The type is the same as size of test, the variable, because test is a
projectile, right?
So, let's see what happens if I actually go and do these things.
If I come down and do these things and I look at them in the Watchman.
Do I do sighs of car-sized event size of projectile, size of test.
We will see that.
Some things are what we expected in some things, aren't so size of car
is one, which is exactly what I said, because it always returns it in
B, and we said that Char was one bite.
It was eight bits, right?
In t, we said was 32 bits, which is 4, bytes, exactly what you said
for right?
And you know what?
I didn't do this one, but we could totally do it.
Sighs of short is too.
Which is exactly what we said.
So, you know, this, this match should be right, right.
It's one bite before, but spy for us.
But to B is 11 B.
What's wrong?
What happened?
What's weird here?
Right?
And the answer is, like, I sort of started saying before, is that the
compiler is not under any constraint to lay this structure out in
packed, as as compactly as possible.
If you will, it is not necessary.
It doesn't have to do that.
So what it can do is if it thinks it would be more efficient because
of the way the CPU accesses.
as, for example,
And the instructions it has at its disposal if it thinks it would be
more efficient, for example, to reserve 32 bits for each of these
because let's say the CPU is much slower.
Accessing an 8-bit value that is unaligned.
It's like kind of add a you know, that's that's off of a 32-bit
boundary.
Maybe the processor set up to access things at on 32-bit boundaries
very quickly, but 8-bit boundaries not so fast, right.
So it may be like, oh, you know what?
I'm I'm actually not going to pack these things tightly.
I'm going to actually reserved 32 bits for each of them because I know
I can generate faster code that way.
The compiler is allowed to do that.
So,
So what we actually see Happening Here, the sides are projectile
inside.
The test is not 11.
It's actually 16 and 16 is sort of doing exactly what I said.
If we look at this, we see that there are four elements and each of
those elements having four bytes would be 16.
So, did that happen?
I don't know.
Let's find out if I go in here and set something that makes it much
easier for us to see.
I'll just put a 1 in each one of these things, right?
Then what we would expect to see in our memory window.
If I look at the address of test is, we should be able to see as it
fill those in exactly how it decided to pack them for us.
And there's another way we can actually tell that to so we'll see.
We're going to see it in two different ways here.
But so if I go ahead and step now, you'll see it wrote the one in
there and you'll notice it didn't actually write anything else.
So it only wrote to the first bite but then when it wrote to the next
one, you will note that it skipped.
It did exactly what I suspected it would do which is it skipped three
bites.
To keep things on.
It's actually a 32-bit boundary a 4 byte boundary.
Now it wrote all of them this time and the reason that it will all
this time is because this one is declared as an end.
Since this was declared as a car on sign.
It is not incumbent upon the compiler to actually do anything with
these values.
Essentially, they were just padding.
They were there to make sure that things were aligned on particular
boundaries for the CPU, to be more efficient, which it turns out x86,
is more efficient.
I think, at a number of things in this way, so it's probably smarter
than power to do that.
But point being,
It does not actually have to write any values to these because we will
never access them.
We will only ever be reading just these 8 Bits here.
And so it was strictly doing that to maintain the alignment.
Same thing as particles per second.
It's going to write the 32 bits there and it's going to write all of
them as we expect and then too many cooks does exactly what the first
one did.
Only this one's 16 bits instead of 8 Bits, And it leaves the other two
untouched.
But we know that it reserves 16-bit B, because we asked the compiler,
how big it was, and it said 16, so it's actually using all of those.
Now, we
Also ask a different way.
We can ask where each individual memory piece is by using the address
operator.
Again.
Oops.
Is this on fire?
Not his this of fire.
I can actually ask where each individual part of this structure is in
memory and we can actually see that.
The number of the address goes up.
Exactly as we'd expect right eight to see 2024, but can we really see
that?
No, we can't because we haven't done hexadecimal yet, which brings me?
To my next topic for today, which is understanding hexadecimal.
Okay.
Now I alluded to this a bit in the Stream beforehand.
I allude to this a little bit in this dream.
I believe, I don't know, two days ago.
I'm not even sure when we've done enough screams.
Now that I remember what's on every dream.
I want to teach you, just quickly how to read hexadecimal.
Just so you'll know and you can start to practice it because like I
said, everything is kind of written in it when you're looking at
memory addresses because they get big and so it just keeps a little
more compact.
That's also if you look at this number, for example, yeah, once you do
that, you don't need to do that.
Mr.
Compiler.
There, if you look at this number, basically this people prefer this
kind of concise more concise notation to that.
To be honest with you.
I've never been a huge mr.
You know really excited about hexadecimal.
I think that, but the reason that it does also become kind of nice to
use.
At some point is just because it's binary aligned, if you think of it
that way like this number, a decimal number is not binary aligned.
So you can't
Peel off the digits as if they were powers of 2, there's nowhere, I
can stop in this number and say, that was just the first bite was that
part, right?
Because it's all mixed together since its base 10 and we're, you know,
the binary based to and base-10, they don't overlap correctly.
So basically the nice thing about hexadecimal, if I just want to talk
about what's in the bottom, B, I know.
That's just the first two characters and I can look at them
separately.
And so that's really probably where most of the use of hexadecimal
comes in, in practice.
Is just that ability to kind of say what's the low B.
What's the high B without having to try and figure it out from a
decimal, which makes it kind of hard to do.
So, the way to read hexadecimal is it just looks like this zero
through 16.
And when I get to the part where I would be rapping in base 10 to 10,
I actually switched to using.
A through F.
So basically, this is the hexadecimal conversion chart whenever you
are trying to represent the numbers from 0 to 15, you simply change
them into the numbers, 0 through the letter F, and that is
hexadecimal.
So if I have a, as a hexadecimal number, you can see, it is always
written with a 0x prefix.
That is basically just I have no idea how they picked 0x, but they
write in a with a 0x prefix to, basically say, the number that comes
next will not be decimal.
It will be hex.
Decimal, if I say 0xa.
What I really mean is 10 if I say 0xaa, right?
What I really mean is 10 for this first one, right?
Because they
They are written just like decimal the lowest value comes at the far
end and I'm going upwards and power from their plus 16 times 10,
right?
Because each one of these letters goes up by 16.
So this is really a hundred and sixty plus ten, right or 160.
Right?
So if I was in here, and I said 0xaa, yes, thank you.
I don't care about edit continue.
Just please show me.
Damn you sorry way to do math there.
Casey plus 10.
I told you I was bad at math.
I wasn't kidding.
I couldn't even add one 6210.
Awesome.
So yeah, if I put a 0 XA and there I get 170 and similarly.
It just keeps going up by 16.
So if I did 0xaa, I'm talking about 16 times, 16 times 10 plus 16
times 10.
Oops.
Right.
Plus 10 and it's the same exact thing as base 10.
If I were to tell you that I have the number, you know 444 right
that's taking 4 times.
100 plus 4 times 10 plus 4, right?
And so all we're doing is the exact same damn thing in a different
base.
We're just multiplying by 16.
Every time we go out one digit instead of x 10.
It's the easiest stupid thing in the world.
And like I said, the only even reason that I think anyone actually
cares or does it is because a little more concise and it lines up with
binary, which is all we really wanted and decimal doesn't line up.
Binary.
So it tends to not be used.
When binary is the thing that were mainly talking about.
But for the most part numbers in C will usually be decimal or they'll
be what's called floating point, which is basically like a, you know,
it's like 1.23 to or something like a fractional number will be using
mostly numbers that look like that.
So actually hexadecimal will mostly be when we're talking about bit
like specific little fiddly bit things and so you won't really have to
worry about them that much like you don't have to be some kind of
awesome.
I can translate hexadecimal in my head kind of way.
To do anything like that?
Okay, so that's actually decimal.
So let's see where we're at here for the day.
I like I said, I have no today.
Even we did end and Enos and we did hexadecimal.
We did struct.
And so the other thing that I'd like to look at then is, is casting.
I'd like to look at how casting works.
So, what I'd like to now do is point out again that one of the main
advantages of programming in something like C is that you are in
complete control, a lot of times.
And you know,
It controls wrong because Assembly Language is really the only place
where you complete control, but you're in a pretty complete control
about how things are happening with memory and how the CPU is is doing
the things that it's going to do.
And so given that that's the case.
If you look at something like this projectile struck where I asked the
compiler to lay this thing out for me.
Basically, I can do more complex stuff than just access it in this
way.
Like it's not like something like a highly.
Structured high-level programming language.
Where once you say this, you must always use.
It this way and there's no way to do anything else with it.
I don't have to do that at all.
I can do some pretty fantastically wacky.
Things if I should want to or if they should become interesting for me
to do and so I will show you a little bit of that.
Now, let's say that what I really wanted to do is look at this
structure as if it were a series of shorts, right?
So what I want to do is I want to use the pointer thing that I had
referred to in the previous.
Stream, I want to use a pointer called.
Let's say, mister pointer, man, and I want to look at test as if it
were a bunch of shorts.
So I'll do the assignments first.
I'll put these on there.
I'll actually do the the assignments, the one and you know, what, I'll
make it so that we can tell which ones, which just by MIT, you know,
assigning a different value to each of them.
Let's say and what's going to happen is I am going to ask to see, I
want to basically look at the memory.
Occupied by test as if it was just a bunch of 16-bit values.
Instead of looking at it in the way that it's laid out here by name.
Now, in order to see is a statically typed programming language is
what it's called.
That's the type of language it is and static typing means that c keeps
track of what you said things were.
If you said something was an indoor, you said something was a Karen
signed, or you said something was a projectile.
It keeps track of those and it will warn you or give you an error.
If you try.
Try to use something in a way that you didn't tell it.
so,
when I asked for the address of something like, if I were to ask for
the address of test, for example, if I was to say, projectile pointer,
you know, equals at test and I compile this, you will notice that this
line compiles, fine, but the line that I want to show you does not
compile fine, right?
It gives me an error.
It says initializing cannot convert from projectile star to short
star.
And the reason for that is because when I take the address of
something, it's assumed to be the type of the thing.
Plus the star saying it is a pointer.
It is a
Patient in memory that says, wear something like this is.
But down here since test isn't a short.
It's a projectile.
It says, hey, wait a minute.
I think you may have made a mistake.
You asked me for the pointer to a projectile.
I gave that to you and now you're trying to turn that into a point or
a short that seems like a bug now, it's very good that it did that for
me.
Even though I love low-level programming.
I love static type.
Checking.
I really like static typed languages because I they catch errors.
I make
Mistakes all the time.
You've seen me make errors in this very stream.
Maybe not tonight.
I don't know if I made errors yet.
I probably have.
But, like, in last night's dream.
For example, I made a mistake.
I made two mistakes, even I think so.
I make mistakes all the time and one of the things that you need to
be, when you write a lot of code, you need to learn how to use
language features to effectively, catch your mistakes.
And this is a great one.
This catches a ton of mistakes at compile time.
You don't have to run the
Graham knows, there's a problem.
But like I said, see you let you do pretty much anything you want with
memory.
So that error is just there to let you know.
You may have made a mistake, but you can easily tell the compiler.
It's okay, man.
I know what I'm doing.
I'm a trained professional in quotes.
So I am going to go ahead and tell you it's okay to let me do the
thing that I was about to try.
And the way that you do that was a thing called a cast.
And the way that you cast things is you basically
A just put in parentheses before the value you put in parentheses the
type, you want the thing to become.
So yes, this is a projectile star.
I would like it to become a short star, please.
And then this line will compile properly as you can see.
So now, if I run to this line, right?
I will be able to go into the watch window here and I will be able to
look at mr.
Pointer, man.
And what you can do in the Watchman.
Do this has nothing to do with C.
By the way.
This is just something that the watch window supports if you want if
you have a pointer like mr.
Pointer man, I showed you in a previous treatment, you can open this
little plus and it will show you the values that are in it, right?
It'll show you what the different values actually are.
And so if I look at mr.
Pointer, man, oops, man.
Copy that it'll show me the first value, but I know we already
I knew that I was estimating it would be 11 B.
The way the compiler actually packed.
It was actually 16 bytes, right?
So it's actually 16.
Oh, this is going to make me to compile again.
Isn't it?
Damn you edit and continue.
I need to turn it into new off.
It's ruining my flow.
So anyway, when I, when I get mr.
Appointment, I can look at the first one, but I may want to look at
more of them because it's 16.
Bytes.
That's eight shorts.
That's eight 16-bit values.
So if I want to look at all of it, I can put comma 8 after it and then
that will tell it to look at eight values.
And you can see that it shows me all eight values here, right?
And what's interesting about this is, you can actually now see, sort
of
The the structure thing in action, if you will, we looked at the
memory before and I will, I will bring it up again.
16 FC, 38, right.
We looked at the memory.
And what we have here is we asked it to interpret as shorts which
means that even though I wrote a one as the this is on fire.
It's only wrote eight bits of that and it just use the rest as
padding.
So, when I ask it to interpret as a short, it's actually going to grab
the 2004 and the one, right?
So it's going to actually use all of that to compute the actual short
value.
And I asked to be signed, you know what, since we haven't really done
signed yet.
I'm SMS which to unsigned.
Oops.
Remember the cast always has to line up and you see that caught
another.
Well, it didn't catch an error, but you can see it always warns me at
the types.
Don't align so you when you cast something, then the thing that you
put it into is going to have to be that same type.
So, anyway, if I go here and I go ahead and look at that memory 38f,
988,
I go here at hair and look, it will have grabbed these values so it
grabbed 204 and that's in the high B.
So it's 204 times 256 in the high B.
Plus the one and you can see that comes out to be the value.
That's actually they're right.
Because remember the high B start to 256.
So one in the high B is 286 to is 512 and so on, right?
So it goes up times 56.
So that's why that happened is because the garbage that was in
There beforehand doesn't get a Race.
So if we start to interpret it, we get garbage, which is exactly
expect.
This is 204 204.
So it's 2 O 4 plus 2.
6 times 20 for editing continue.
Why why must you do it?
You know what I feel like there's got to be a way to turn off edit and
continued since this is a weekend stream can be a little more
Meandering.
I am going to figure out how to turn off this this damn edit and
continue adding.
Continue.
No,
Don't don't do this.
How do I?
Okay?
No, no, no.
No.
All right.
Hold on a second.
Maybe we have to stop.
I want to set the settings and make it never ever do that again.
No, no, no.
No.
No, so view solution.
Explorer properties is s in here.
I don't even know.
No, maybe that was an options.
Tools options.
Heading to new in a no.
There we go.
Okay, that's what you want.
It's just off just don't ever do that again.
I don't ever want to hear from you again ever in the history of time,
bad at it and continue bad.
I think with that's trying to do is that's basically trying to let me
edit code.
Fly.
And then keep running, which is not something, I had any interest in
doing in this particular series.
All right, so hopefully now let's find out.
Actually.
Let me just test this first to see if I do.
Do do.
Ah, there we go.
Okay, so it'll warn me now which is fine.
I don't mind warning.
I don't need to turn that off but I just wanted it to stop hassling me
and Bruce making me restart the program.
Especially since we're in the mode where it has to rebase all the
time.
It's doing the security-based rebasing.
So I have to type the address in every time in the, in the thing.
Alright, so back to our regularly, scheduled program.
If we look in here, we can see the various values as they are getting
written out.
And they
Exactly where we expected them to be.
Everything is copacetic.
We see that the values are what we expect.
Like I was saying, it's 20 4 plus 2 to 6 times, 2 or 4 in the next
one, which is exactly what we expected to see the next one because it
was written out as an actual.
Let's see for a 40 or we go because it was written out as a 32-bit
value.
What that'll do is it's going to use this to as the next short, which
is 20, which is just to again, and then two zeros, which
Which is zero, right?
Which is 3 and 0 0, which is 0.
Then the for was written out as a short.
So we see it as a short properly, but then there's still two extra
bytes of padding and we see that number again, which is 204, 204 it
now, one thing you may be wondering, and I alluded to this in a
previous dream, but explain it now.
Is why is everything 2004?
Why is it 2004?
If this is just garbage memory that we have initialized yet and
haven't written anything to.
Why is it always to of for the answer is because 2004 in hexadecimal,
is CC do that.
So, oxc cccccc is basically 204 204, 204 204.
And what happens when you compile in debug mode in Vin?
Using visual studio.
Compiler is that you can turn on a thing and it's turned on by
default.
So when I added this, when I made this new project, is turned on the
default and debug builds.
There's the thing that basically says, clear all values, 20x CCC CCC
CCC, CCC and sees, all the way to the end, right CCs in their 2004's
the whole time, because a lot of Errors come from initial at
uninitialized values, like a lot of errors in code.
Come from you, doing something like the thing.
I alluded to before, like, saying this.
When I never initialized this, you know, test this is on fire, right?
So if things were uninitialized, they might default to zero, they
might default to some value.
That might work, they might default to some value that you might not
notice.
But 0, x cc is very blatant.
It doesn't come up that often by accident.
And so what the compiler does to try to help you in debug builds, is
it just clears the values, 20 x CC so that when you're stepping
through your code and you get the
Something like this and you look and you go.
Oh this this wasn't working.
Right, what's going on?
And I look at this is on fire.
I co X CC and I'm like, oh it's an uninitialized variable.
Right?
Whereas if it hadn't done that, maybe it might have been zero because
that's what was in there before.
0 is a common value to appear in memory.
And memory.
I think on Windows is even zeroed before you get it.
Normally, because of security concerns.
It has to erase the memory.
Hmm.
In case you were to get physical memory.
That was occupied by like a password or something.
That would be a security leak.
So,
It might well be 0 which would make you think your code was working
right up to the point where you accidentally happen to get some
memory.
That was recycled from something else and you're saying process and
it's not set to zero and now all your code is ruined and you don't
know why and you've got a really hard to find bug because it doesn't
happen all the time.
It only happens when that page gets recycled and blah blah blah, very
hard bugs to find.
So the reason that everything is 0 x cc is because this is a debug
build.
If This Were a real he's build with that feature turned off, we would
be trying to be more optimal.
The compiler would not spend its time.
Clear.
Alice to Cece because that would be inefficient and you don't want to
do that in a release build that supposed to be performance-oriented.
So there you go.
Okay, so that is casting.
We've covered endianness.
We've covered casting recovered structs.
We've covered hexadecimal.
The only other thing I wanted to cover today is I wanted to cover the
the some bitwise operators and some other things about accessing
structures.
So we're going to go for maybe about 10 more minutes and get those
things out before the Q&A.
So you may be wondering, I know that you are.
Oh and by the way, just I mean, I'm sure this is kind of starting to
be obvious by no, you know, what?
Instead of me having to say it isn't a side, I'll just do it as an
actual thing because it can lead right in.
So there's another thing you can do in C.
It is called array indexing and basically in a lot of other languages
when you hear the term array, what that means is that means a
collection of objects that are in
Next by a value, that is a number.
So for example, I may have a bunch of projectiles and so in other
languages, you may see something like this where I type in.
I want a bunch of projectiles.
I want 40 projectiles, right?
And this little bracket syntax here means that I want you to make 40
of these.
So instead of me having to do something ridiculous like this, right?
Blah blah blah blah blah.
Here's all my project.
Giles one, two three, right blah blah blah at 40.
I don't have to do that.
I can just say, give me 40 of them.
I know I need for you to just do it and furthermore when it does it,
instead of it being fine for the compiler to put them anywhere that it
wants to.
Well.
I want them to be laid out at regular intervals in memory so that I
can access them by an integer.
So that I can say projectiles for and get the fourth one, predictably,
right?
It doesn't have to be me, like, guessing words.
They are.
So if I had some if I actually had this the kind of crazy thing I was
talking about before where I have projectile zero, let's say and I
have projectile one.
Let's say I have an integer called which projectile that's going to be
set to be either 0 or 1, right?
And I want to be able to use that integer to still doing it.
You know, I'm just going to cover this right now.
I've done it too many times.
You can stick the equals right after the Declaration instead of having
to do this.
So I've done it so many times.
I just need to get it all the way, shouldn't the very first dream.
So instead of doing this, where I just declare something and then give
it a value, you can, you can always just do it on the same line.
It's fine.
Right?
So, that's all I was doing.
So, if I have a value here and I want to use that value to pick one of
these projectiles.
There's no easy way to do it.
I would have to use something that we're going to cover in the next
stream where I do something like 0, which projectile if it's equal to
one, then do the thing, you know here do do something to projectile
one.
One else do it to projectile to you know zero or something like this
you would end up in in some kind of bad.
Relation where you're doing something like this.
And again, I'll cover what these, what if statement stuff are in the
next room?
So I go into it, but I'd have to do something where I actually write
what's called, control flow code to actually get at the projectile
that I want.
And so what I'd rather do is lay them out in memory so that I can just
use arithmetic to access the one that I want, and that is what happens
when you use this syntax.
It lays them out consecutively in memory spaced by a known number
unknown size.
Usually the size of the structure itself.
And then I can use this bracket to just access one of them and I can
even access them by a variable.
So if I have, you know, which projectiles for I can do that right now.
In other languages, this is actually an abstract construct.
There's nothing you can do with it in a lot of other languages.
You're just like you got 40 of them.
You can access them with this syntax.
That's all, you know.
When see, that is not the case in see this actually creates just, it's
just about memory layout.
All it means is do that memory layout that.
I just said, which means that you can actually go ahead and do
something like take that projectile pointer that we had before us take
that projectile pointer and make the projectile pointer.
Be equal to the start of the array.
Right now, you'll notice that normally what you may have expected me
to have to do, is put the address there, because I said, when we want
to take the address of something, I need to
If you address operator, but in see one of the weird things they
decided to do is make it so that this actually is just a pointer
arrays aren't really all that different from just having a pointer to
the beginning.
So instead of bothering to make you write the syntax, which honestly,
it may have been better if they had done because there's some reasons
why it's a little bit wonky.
There's some things that there are a few things that c does wonky.
And this is one of them.
There's reasons why it's a little wonky but I won't belabor them now
because I think they're really relevant.
But point being this may have been a better decision depending on how
you want to look.
At it basically what happens when you do this is you just end up with
a pointer to the first one.
That's what you basically have.
So if you want to get a pointer to where they are, you end up with
this, so if I actually go ahead here, compile this
Oh, hey, look at this.
So, you know, I was talking about that 0 XE, C thing.
This is kind of nice.
It gave me a warning that test was uninitialized when I used it.
That this, this on fire thing was I'm going to realize.
So that's kind of doesn't have anything to what we're doing now, but
it's just it's good to know, right?
That the compiler will catch some of those for you.
That's awesome.
So that was the zeros, xcc thing, as well.
It's basically got multiple ways to help you not make that mistake.
It's got the zero X EC to prevent it and it's also got if it can tell,
if the compiler can look at the code and just obviously tell
Often times it can't because the codes too complicated and it doesn't
know where you're getting stuff from.
But in the case, where it can tell it can give you a warning, which is
awesome.
Yeah.
So those are good.
Wow, I'm going to type that.
How many times we going to take this is of Fire.
There we go.
All right.
So if I go ahead and jump down here and I take a look at what I get
with my projectiles that you can see first of all, in the watch window
I can ask for
Projectiles, which is the whole array.
And if I expand it, you can see, I've got all the ones I asked for it.
Right?
I've got all the projectiles are in here and I can look at each
individual one.
Right?
And it's made that structure for me.
And of course, they're completely uninitialized.
Crap.
At this point, right?
There's nothing, you know, I I haven't written in any of those.
So they're all oxc cccccc and debug mode.
Like I said and what you can see, they all have the same values and
it's all garbage.
Is all 0.
It's all 24 2004 as the whole way.
So because I haven't even in release mode, they would have just been
whatever, who knows whatever happened to be in that place in memory at
the time when it reserved it.
So, that's what I've got.
And when I look at the address of this zero X zero zero two, five,
right?
I can go in here if I want to again and just like everything else.
I can look at it and see course it's a giant block of 204, is that it
just initialized to when I look at projectile pointer, right
projectile.
Oh, no.
Okay, my look.
Decked Out pointer.
You can see that it's the same value.
So projectiles a projectile pointer are essentially the same.
Now.
The reason that I say that they're essentially the same and not
exactly the same is because of this little problem right here.
And this is why I say C is a little wonky, something that's good to be
aware of.
If I were to ask how big this is.
Well, how big do we expect this to be?
Right?
How big do they expect an array of 40 projectiles to be?
Well, we know that the compiler decided to reserve 16, bytes per
product.
I'll so we might expect this to be 16 times.
40.
Right?
That's what we would probably expect that to be.
So if I said size and projectiles, you know, how big is it right arm.
You know what, let me make this a little better size of projectiles,
right?
I would expect it to see that, right?
But if I ask for size of projectile pointer, right, what is the size
of projectile, pointer?
Well, I would expect to see something else now because I know what it
is.
I expect to see for because I believe pointers to be 4, bytes on the
thing that I compiling to and this is a pointer, right?
So I'm going to actually double check.
Those are both case.
So we look on here and we say size of projectiles and size of
projectile.
Projectile pointer.
Yep.
That's what we thought 16 times 40 is, in fact 640, everyone's happy,
exactly what we thought, but
I will point out that is the little bit of a snafu so I can set this
equal to this thing.
Right?
I can say that projectile pointer equals projectiles, which means that
c is and it didn't give me a warning or an error.
Anything see is agreeing with me that projectiles is just a pointer to
the first one and and that, you know, that totally worked and we saw
it work.
We know that's what it does.
But even though that's the case, see secretly understands during the,
you know.
Oh, in a place where it can see this definition, it secretly
understands.
Actually, how big it is such that when I ask, even though he knows
it's functional.
Pointer.
And I can treat it as a pointer.
I can I can do that with it.
It's not really treating it as a pointer because it actually does
remember that it's this bigger thing.
And so that's why I say it's a little wonky because really these
aren't exactly the same type.
And so this probably should just fail.
The probably should have thought of it a little differently but, you
know, see is a great language.
I'm not here to second-guess their design decisions.
Maybe there's good reasons for it.
I don't know.
But point being, it does seem like that's one of the places where C is
maybe not quite as watertight.
As one would have hoped.
So there you go.
Alright, so that's what's called array syntax.
And this is a ray accessor, which allows you to pull out individual
things.
And what I wanted to demonstrate for you was that array syntax is
really, it's complete shorthand.
It's all it is is just shorthand for messing with memory.
So if I wanted to, for example, talk about the 30th projectile, right?
And we talked about the 33 act.
Well, I'm gonna set the 30s projectile damage to
See, that's what I'm going to do.
What this actually translates into.
Okay is nothing more than the pointer to the base of it, right?
The pointer to the base of it, plus 30 times, the size of a
projectile, one projectile, right?
Dot damage.
Actually, I'm at talk about what this guy is right here in a second.
But if I wanted to, I could use this exact same syntax to access the
30th one.
And I'll talk about what this guy is saying to me.
It's another weird cc is MM.
But this is basically the same as this dot operator up here, but I'll
talk about why I couldn't use the dot in a second.
So if I wanted to do that.
Hello.
What is the problem?
Compile compile.
There we go, projectile Undeclared, identifier UPS projectiles.
There we go.
Spelling errors, always good.
Okay, so if I want to look at this, I'm going to look at the
projector.
I'm gonna get projectile, 30.
Like I said, and I'm gonna expect it to be set to 60 and Hey, look,
it's set to 60.
In fact, you know what, let's let's just double-check will make sure
that it's all going, right?
Stop.
Stop everyone.
No, don't do it.
Yes.
There we go.
Okay.
One of the thing I need.
Sorry, it's bringing out more things than I more things than I was
hoping for.
Hmm.
All right.
This is my first tip bad teaching mistake that I've made.
Well, we're going to take this in two steps.
I just realized that the thing that I wanted to do, you can't quite
show directly.
So all right.
We gotta show this, I'll show this first and then I'll show this, it's
just it's just crazy.
How much syntax I have to do to show the thing that I wanted to do.
So, okay.
Yeah.
Sorry, it's a little more.
It's a little more.
Involved, I guess I would say then then then what I had hoped for.
Okay, let's do that again.
Alright, so back to where we are and I will promise, I'll explain all
of that in a second.
I'm not trying to hand wave on you.
It's just I realized that the thing I was trying to do wouldn't
actually work the way that I wanted to show you how to do it, because
it involves more casting.
So we're gonna have to get to that second.
So we see that damage is set to 60 on the 30th projectile, which is
exactly what I was trying to do.
Now, what I wanted to show you as well, is that I can also choose to
point arithmetic, but the
Thing is see tries to be helpful.
And I kind of didn't think about this when I was going to type it in.
But, you know, when I'm actually coding, it's second nature.
You would know this.
It's just that I was trying to think teaching wise.
So I got a little ahead of myself.
But what see does when it does pointer arithmetic like this.
When I look at when I when I take a pointer to some place and memory
and I add something to it, actually uses the type that you have told
it that it was which was projectile, projectile pointer is a
projectile.
It uses the type that
Told you it was and it actually automatically does the multiplication
for you.
So I want to show you how to do this multiplication, but actually see
will do this multiplication.
It's going to automatically multiplied by the size of the projectile
when I add 30.
So this here is actually this see just inserts that multiplication for
you.
So it knows I'm trying to go by projectiles and it adds 30 times that
so when I look at this, what I'm actually looking at as 30 times 16
down from the start of projectile pointer and then
Then I set the damage equal to 100.
So, now, if we execute this line, right, you will see that it did
exactly what it said.
It would.
Do it sets it to 100, so I can actually do the point arithmetic
myself, right?
But what I want to show you what to do it entirely manually.
And in order to do that, what I have to do is first for C, using a
cast.
Just, like I said before, to treat this pointer, as if it was pointing
to only 8 Bits, which is care, right?
Then I can do the ad in individual bytes.
Then I can cast it back to a
Tactile to access the damage member of it, which will set it to 100.
Does that make sense?
And that will do exactly that.
Of course.
We already had it had to 100.
So it's just going to set it to 100 an approach to me that different
value.
So, let's take that a little bit more slowly since I had to sort of,
whip out a bunch of stuff that I kind of didn't want to have to whip
out just at that point.
But, you know, what, you going to do programming is complicated.
Sometimes you got to roll with it.
So yes, this is actually a little more straightforward.
Hopefully, this is understandable there.
The reason that I enclosed this in parentheses is because parentheses
much like they do in math help to group things together.
So, the compiler knows what order to do things.
You can imagine that if I had written this, right, it would be very
confusing for the compiler because it looks like I'm trying to access
the damage member of 30, which doesn't make any sense.
So the parentheses just allow it to know.
Okay.
I'm trying to add 32 projectile pointer, which gives me a new
projectile pointer that happens to be 30, projectiles down from where
it started.
And then I'm going to, you know, make that damage equal to 100 makes
makes reasonable sense.
Now what this catastrophic line is, right, is this is actually doing a
series of operations.
First.
It is making a bite pointer that just points to B, and it's making a
bite pointer by doing this operation, right?
Remember I said, casting turn something into a type that it wasn't
before.
It just says, Hey see, trust me.
And remember, really this is to get rid of the error.
It's not really changing what the code does.
In any particular way.
It's just to get rid of the air that I would get, right?
You see, I get an error there because this is a part or projectile and
I wanted a projector to a care.
I can't just do that without telling see hey.
Hey relax, it's cool.
I know what I'm doing.
I'm a professional programmer.
So I'm going to do the cast and it's good.
So there we go.
That's fine.
I'm creating a bite pointer.
Now.
I want to move the bike pointer forwards right by the right amount.
So that is 30 times the size of the projectile, right?
That will get me to where I want to be but you know, and I can
certainly compile this code.
You can see that it all works, but I can't now do B pointer.
Arrow damage equals 200, right?
If I were to try and try and do that, I get an error.
And the reason I got an error is because this is a point to a car and
a car is just eight bits.
Totally Anonymous.
There is no such thing as damage of those.
Right?
And so what what I have to do before I can do that is I have to turn
that pointer back into a projectile pointer, right?
I have to do projectile pointer 30, right?
And then I can cast back just like I was
Doing before by pointer like this, and now I can use that that pointer
will work right and you can see that works fine.
So
That is the crazy Shenanigans.
You have to do to do the pointer of the because C is trying to help
you out.
It's trying to help you not have to remember or not have to know at
that particular point in the code.
What you would need to add to it.
In order to get you 30 things down.
It wants you to be able to just use the 30 directly which is kind of
helpful.
Most of the time.
It is what you want.
But for purposes of this demonstration where I wanted to show you how
the memory is something that's directly controllable by you.
And you can actually go in at the byte level and poke everything.
I just wanted to show you that you can move these things around and do
the array accesses yourself.
So,
Line is nothing other than this magic sequence right here, or this
sequence right here and you can see what I did.
This is just exactly the previous thing, right?
Justin more concise in it all wrapped up in one line.
First.
I cast it to a caressed are right, that right.
There, is this right?
Then I added 30 times the size of it.
That's this right?
Then I cast it back to a projectile.
That's this.
Then I access the damage member.
So I just wrapped all that.
Up into one line, and you can always do that.
And see, you can wrap crazy amounts of stuff into one little
expression if you want to.
So, the final thing that I wanted to talk about, I guess because the
stream is about up now.
I don't know if I want to.
I think I'm going to say the other thing I'm going to talk about till
next time is this Arrow, right?
Cuz I kind of wave does.
I got the air has to be
The dart.
Whatever, what does that actually mean?
Well, in see there's a difference between a pointer and an actual
thing.
So if I say projectile test, like I did up above right, this thing
right here, right?
If I say projectile test then accessing it looks like this.
That's how acts as a test dot the thing.
But if I say projectile STAR test, so I have a pointer to a test,
right?
And I'm actually talking about the pointer itself.
I have to use the arrow syntax.
There is no difference between these two things other than
That, that is the only difference.
It is strictly.
Whether the thing you have is declared to be a pointer or whether
you're talking about.
The actual thing on the actual stack.
That is the only difference there really is, absolutely no reason for
this distinction and it's another one of the places that I think she
is a little wonky.
Really probably.
What should have happened is this should have just been considered a
pointer and it should always have just been got to access everything
or something like that.
But again, not a language designer.
I don't really want a second case.
Second-guess the C++ to be.
I'm going to see designers.
So I'm not going to say that was necessarily good or bad.
I'm just going to say it does seem to be a little bit wonky because
they don't really do anything different and there's almost even no way
to make a bug out of it.
Like it's not like it can catch a bug if I had that as a dot, it
really?
It doesn't even help that.
It's going to tell me it's wrong, right?
Like the fact that it tells me it's wrong.
There's almost nothing else.
I could have meant there other than other than Arrow, so, it's, yeah,
it's really kind of weird that it's even a thing.
It's just
Doesn't make a lot of sense.
So anyway, that's the only other thing.
I want to carrot to to mention is that the arrow syntax and the dot
syntax, you have to know whether you were dealing with a pointer or
whether you're dealing with actually a thing on the stack in order to
know which one of them to use.
But fortunately the compiler always tells you and the answer is always
just to switch it.
So if you were the person who typed this you would instantly get a
compile error, the compiler error would tell exactly where it was.
It would say must have a class structure Union type of projectile.
Did you intend to use Arrow?
It even gives you the recommendation in the answer?
Yes, I did intend to use Arrow.
So I think that is everything that I wanted to cover today.
It's basically how to do memory layout, using struts which we did and
it was sort of showed you some of the things.
There is one thing I did not mention, which I will mention very
quickly.
I don't think it's maybe something you really need to know, but there
is a thing called a pragma which we didn't cover Loops that you can
use.
Also something called an attribute, you can use depending on the
compiler, you can use
Extra like things that are outside of the scope of the language
necessarily it certainly outside scope of the original, see that you
can put, that will allow you to wrap projectile or any struct in a way
that tells the compiler that they have to be packed.
So, remember when I said, okay, we expected 11, B.
We got 16, if you really care and you know, that you need to be.
So there are ways to turn off that padding.
It's saying, hey look, I know there might be a performance penalty.
I realize, you know, I'm putting you out here mr.
Compiler.
But please, I really need you to pack these things tightly and it will
do it.
So, there are ways.
I'm not going to cover them right now, but there are ways of telling
it to pack something tightly.
When you need it pack tightly.
Just most of the time, you don't need things packed, tightly.
So you'd rather have it optimize them for.
However, whatever platform you're compiling to lay them out, in the
most sensible way for performance.
And I think that is basically everything.
I'm not going to cover a bitwise operators.
I'm going to do them next stream tomorrow, so hopefully
I'm really glad that.
I think there's a fair number of people.
There's there's us over 200 people on the stream.
That's awesome for sort of an impromptu Saturday stream.
So thank you so much.
Everyone for showing up.
It has been a another delightful coding session with all of you and I
am going to stop the recording now and I will restart it in a second
for Q&A, which will go for probably about 30 minutes.
So thanks so much for joining me and I will see you tomorrow.
If you would like to finish up, our intro to see series before we move
on.
To the full handmade hero stream on Monday.