Okay, we are back with the Q&A session for the second day of the test.
Stream, the intro to see basically this is the Q&A session for what we
talked about a little bit about basically, creating space for values,
how things are encoded as values and how Assembly Language works with
them, in order to set the stage for tomorrow, where we are going to
start looking in detail exactly how code executes on the CPU.
So let's take a look.
Alright, I am going to catch up on the chat.
Let's see doo-doo-doo-doo.
We're talking about rust here, a little.
So that's C.
2's compliment.
He's going to read our flame War about compute.
Our language is no I'm not gonna read your flame.
Are you know, what?
I will say that I really like doing this series even though I've only
done it twice.
Now, it's I love doing it.
I'm hoping to get better at
Get better at explaining things and everything, but I'm always very
positive on it and happy because I'm so enjoying doing it.
But I am just like everyone else when it comes to Flame Wars.
I am sure that if I were in the twitch chat, I would be flaming.
So I'm not going to read your flame where, but I totally, I know where
your I know where you guys are at.
I know about the flame Wars.
They happen.
What can you do?
So you said, okay, idiocracy says, Casey you mentioned earlier that
Windows requires with the line feet and a carriage return to probably
move on to the
This line and we can type this ourselves and source code with to
escape codes, back to Starbucks.
And if that's the case, how come I can use a printf statement windows
with back session without any mention of backslash R.
And the output is formatted correctly.
That is a fabulous question and it's something that I may never get to
in the mainstream because we may not need to know.
I probably will.
But so I'm going to actually answer that fully right now.
It's not.
It's not that complicated.
Okay, so what actually happens and I don't actually, you know what,
maybe?
Maybe we can even go on a little Adventure here.
I don't know.
I don't know if you guys are in the mood for an adventure, but we
could go on a little Adventure if we wanted to.
So if I type in, he was asking about printf and printf is a thing in.
See that basically is part of the standard Library.
We're going to talk about the standard library, is later.
We're going to talk about why it sucks to, but we're gonna talk about
the standard library and the standard Library Define some things that
we can do printf is a thing that prints out to a console.
So, if you're writing a console application, which we are not
I talked about that at the very beginning of the very first one of
these.
I said we're building and not a console application.
But if you were building it and you were running it from one of these
guys a command prompt when you ran, it would basically print out what
you put in here out to the command prompt.
So it's kind of like output debug string but it's actually
user-facing.
It comes out to the users command prompt.
Well I want to know is is this and
Library source.
Code installed, survey says,
Yes, it is.
Okay, so if we actually go into printf here.
And this is kind of Again, part of the emissaries always know what's
going on.
Printf is something that someone else wrote and if we want to see what
it does, we should step on in there to it.
And so we can kind of see by going through the debugger is there's a
bunch of C code in here.
We're going to open the argument list.
We're going to do some stuff with.
Oh, it's going to try to do a tricep block to try and figure out.
If anyone's going to crash in there.
It's going to do an output.
What's going on here.
I have Funk here.
We are in a crazy function.
This is
Probably the actual meat of printf, I would guess.
Is it actually going in here?
Yes, it is.
Here we go.
It's doing all of the cases.
It needs to do for printf.
Yeah, you can see.
There's all kinds of good stuff in here.
Here's the different format codes.
All right.
So this is basically the source code to printf in the Microsoft
edition of visual C++.
And what you can see in here is it's going to go through all the
string.
It's going to be tons of code to try and figure out.
What you typed in there, and I don't know if I want to actually try to
find it specifically in here because I don't actually know how it's
encoded in.
It might take a while.
I'm just doing a quick scan to see if it jumps out at me.
It's a little hard to do that while I'm talking of course because it's
code that I've never seen before bet.
Basically.
I wanted to see if it showed what happened when it got to the
backslash n.
Because that would be relevant to us.
Now.
I didn't see it there and I suspect they've been coded it separately.
Yeah.
All right.
So unfortunately I can't pinpoint the exact code for you.
But well, you know what?
Let's not give up yet.
I said we were going to go on an adventure and so you know what an
adventure takes some time sometimes why Rush The Adventure?
I was going to print out just the backslash n.
So the very first thing that happens in our print f is going to be
that.
So let's see what it does.
Shall we?
I think we shall.
Let's go on in here.
And let's see what we do.
We are going to handle locales always good case.
You're at some kind of foreign locales.
We're gonna get some stuff formatted and we have gotten ourselves into
position.
Look at that.
CH the thing that they are processing in this Loop.
I'm covered Loops yet.
But hey think we're passing in this Loop sometimes in the Q&A.
When you go on an adventure you just gotta jump.
Jump forward, you gotta jump forwards.
There's that 10.
That's the backslash n.
We were talking about.
Let's see how it handles it.
It's going into the switch statement about its current state.
Then it's going to check some things.
It's going to do a right care directly on that.
So our right care statement looks like where we need to be, what
happens in here?
It is going to call into yet another function.
Oh sweet Mercy!
Will we ever actually write a piece of code?
Let's see, written account.
I are right saying the flags.
Trying not to accidentally skip forwards as we go.
And it is going to set that if not Define Unicode.
It's going to set stream base and then
We are going to return CH and 0 now.
Okay, so I don't actually know why this is going to be a little more
complicated than I thought.
I had hoped, I might be able to point you to a very Smoking Gun there.
Which was basically like a place where it actually did the
translation, but I don't think I'm gonna be able to find it for you.
So, I'm sorry.
I want to go on an adventure.
I thought maybe we pay off but I feel like it might take a little too
long.
So I don't want to belabor that point too much.
I will simply tell you what the answer is if we continue to step.
This, we could find it actually doing where it translates out that
stream base, which, I don't know, exactly where in their code, they
actually do that because as you might imagine, I don't spend a lot of
time.
Looking at Microsoft's implementation of print out, the answer of why
you can do that is because see, tried to solve the problem for you,
the multi-platform problem.
So what I said was basically you've got Windows, you know, it wants
backslash R backslash n.
Unix operating system from Europe.
Just wants a backslash N.
I believe Mac just wants back sesh or, I don't know, Max, even
something else I think back in the old days, but nowadays, I think
since they're Unix underneath, they may, they may just adhere to the
eunuch standard now, so I said this and someone in the chat, actually,
idiocracy brought up the fact that how is he able to he programs in C
officer has tried program in C somewhat.
How is he able to put a backslash?
And when Windows wants a backslash are back session, which is what I
said.
Am I lying to you?
I would not lie to you.
It really does want to access our backsplash.
And the reason that that works is because see tried to solve this
problem for you.
It tried to basically make it so that didn't matter what problem
you're running on the same code, but still work.
So when you type this in, although it always gets translated into that
10.
The actual printf call when the stream itself is getting output to the
console under the hood in the code that you
Don't write the code that's in the C runtime Library.
That's actually the printf it will actually look for the Box.
/ ends the tens and translate them into backslash are back session.
Now, fun fact, this is why
If you go to look at and I'm just assuming that you know this because
you were asking me a question about printf.
If you go look at the signature for f, open the thing that opens a
file in the C runtime Library, you will note that it takes something
called a mode and that mode has some interesting aspects to it.
There's the thing called be that you can put on the mode, which says,
open the file in binary mode.
Hmm.
So why would I have to open a file in binary mode?
Isn't everything a computer binary with a difference between opening
and binary mode and not opening in binary mode.
Right?
Well, the answer is because see tried to solve the Line Feed problem.
And so what it did is it decided that it would actually go through and
it would translate all of those into the correct one for the platform.
So it's he's back size and it would translate it into backslash and on
Unix, just a pass-through or backs.
Us are boxed us.
And if it was on Windows, now the
With that is that if you were trying to write something in binary,
that was actually just data.
Like if you're trying to save data to a file and you tried to write it
out, the stream itself will actually translate the binary code.
So you might try to write the value 10.
You were nothing to do with the string.
Like you're trying to write out the fact that the guy has 10 hit
points and it will mess that up for you and it'll mess it up for you
in a really hard to deal with way, because it will actually insert
another character.
So now,
Your your data is all messed up.
And so what you have to do when you open a file that you want to
write, binary directly to that isn't supposed to be text and it's not
supposed to be text.
You have to tell the stream that you're writing in binary.
And so you may have encountered this bug where you accidentally forgot
the binary when you open the file that you were writing to and you
tore your hair out, you were like, I'm writing this stuff to the file
and then I try to load the file on.
It's broken.
What's going on?
Well, that's what's going on is translating for you.
And then you're like, oh, I forgot to add binary.
You had by now.
Everything works.
So that's what that is.
It's basically these functions have that built-in now output debug
string.
Also accepts backslash n.
So that's why I didn't have to put a backslash R backslash and here.
But if we were to write actual directly, if we were actually directly
writing to the console or actually directly writing to a text file on
Windows.
We would have to put the backslash R backslash n ourselves.
Hopefully, that answers that question.
Okay, let's take a look.
Here.
Is it possible to write win32 apps assuming utf-8?
Or must you?
Always use why utf-16 to be honest with you?
I don't think there's really any way to write utf-8.
You can write your app and utf-8 which a lot of people do and it's
what I would do but then you always when you talk to Windows you have
to have a little piece of code that like shimmies it out that
basically like, you know Converse the utf-8 to UTS seems really
tedious and unfortunate, but that's the way it works.
They may have added some things with like Windows 8.
Eight or stuff to do, Native utf-8 or something, but I ain't Touchin
Windows 8, so I have no idea.
I don't.
If they added that there but no, for the most part under the hood.
You actually always have to turn back to utf-16, but you probably
don't want to write your actual code that way, you probably just want
to deal with that.
At the end of the day, since Windows is the only people who do that.
So I was asking why I use dot CPP, if I write in pure C.
Is there an advantage or are you used to it?
So the reason is because I might show some C++ stuff.
I might show how to do some operator overloading.
For example, the reason that I call it programming in c is because
mostly I won't be doing much in the way of C++.
So if you were trying to learn really learn C++, I don't want to do
false advertising and tell you you're going to learn C++, because
you're not, we're not going to recover templates.
We're not going to cover inheritance for not going to cover a lot of
the things that you would do.
In C++.
We're going to stick to basic C code, but I can pile is not to be
peace because a that's what most people use even when they program in
see.
A lot of people will use dot CPS just because there's some things that
they might want to use the C++ and also because really see is easy to
compile and CPP.
Most things you can do in C are accepted by the C++ compiler.
So it's pretty easy to do so, so yeah, I really am programming this
game in C++ and we might use some C++ while we program it.
It's just that I'm not really going to be.
Be teaching much of C plus plus.
And so I didn't want to give people the expectation that they would be
learning C++ because they really won't, they're mostly learning see.
Someone asked folks frequently, right unsigned care.
In addition to care and signed our their land mines there to watch out
for the answer is, no, not really.
And so what, what what was being asked there by dr.
G's was basically that, if I were to take this unsigned here and move
it to here that is actually still totally legal.
See, it does not actually care where you put the unsigned, qualifier,
the unsigned.
It's called a CV qualifier.
No, it's not nevermind.
That's probably take notes not see cost, volatile things go after
that.
Forget.
I ever said it's not CD, qualifier.
See, Clara comes later.
It's just part of the type and the type can actually be in either
order.
I do not actually know, you know, I focus a lot on coding and what
actually works for coding and there were times in my life when I got
pretty intimate with things like the parsing of the language and
things like that and knowing stuff like where that came from
historically.
I've kind of Forgotten most of it now, so I'm actually a bad.
Person to ask for like say the historical reason why that's true at
the fact that I even said CV qualifier just been just to tell you that
I'm reaching back into part of my brain that I don't access very often
and I'll make mistake mints or say the wrong thing when I try to talk
about some of the origin stuff.
So I don't know.
The historical reason for that.
I don't know the historical reason why you can say Karen sign, I
believe you can also just say, signed care as well, instead of just
care and that works fine, too.
I think that compiled properly.
Yes.
So, yeah, so
There's a lot of ways you can write the same thing and really all that
matters.
Is that
Have signed or unsigned in there or nothing and that you have been the
type value and they all will bow down to the same thing.
So I don't think there's anything to watch out for their, it's
personal preference.
Whichever one you want.
There may be pedants out there who want to tell you.
One is right?
And what is wrong?
Or one's more convenient, or whatever.
If that's what you feel about, that's totally fine.
I couldn't care less which way they can.
Let's see.
Don't appear on your stream.
Oh, no, the tooltips don't appear.
I'm going to write that down to something to see if I can fix.
I want to kind of get maybe an outboard recording box at some point if
one exists.
So that I know that that everything I see on the screen that you can
see because it's just using OBS right now.
And I don't know if there's some things that won't work, and I don't
want to get in situations where I'm like, running the game and people
can't see the game running or things like that.
So yeah.
So, let's see.
Casey.
Do you plan to mention talk about the effect optimizations can have in
the as amount for the compiler?
Absolutely.
Boy 2 to 3.
We will absolutely be doing that.
And in fact, one of the things that I will be doing at the end of this
little interest stream, probably this weekend, the main show will be
weekdays only, but this stream is going to be this weekend as well,
because I want to really refine the stream and get really good at
doing excavations before.
The first official cast on Monday.
One of the things I'll be doing is showing you how to compile from the
command line, and I will start talking about what those options are
and what they do.
Let's see.
Print up a to do, do, do do do get the debug menu, while debugging
resource that you recommend.
Do you have resource that you'd recommend for practicing learning more
about Assembly.
Not really.
Unfortunately, I will be going through most of it on the stream and
explaining most of it, to the extent that you will need to know in
order to Be an Effective C programmer.
Now, if you want to be someone who actually programs in raw assembly,
Not just little spots of assembly.
Like, what I'll do is I'll write a few things in assembly, what?
I need them to be really fast and often times.
I can even do that by using things that the C compiler has built in.
So you don't actually really have to write assembly.
You can actually write in sort of a pseudo assembly that it will and
it will do something.
It's like register allocation for you and all this sort of thing.
So, I will be explaining what you need to know, but if you actually
want to go be a real assembly, dude, and and that, and that's not me,
right?
Like you're actually talking about
About being hardcore about Assembly Language.
Are you not know the proper references for that?
If someone out there is a hard crust.
Somebody guy if Jeff Roberts is listening or Sean Barrett old-school
guys, who do the Assembly Language Coatings, if they want to send some
resources in,
I would love to post them but I am the wrong guy to ask and I would
probably just tell you the wrong thing.
Do do.
What else did we have helped?
Learn?
Same boost.
Mac OS X is now Unix etcetera, Etc.
Sorry trying to I apologize for missing some questions here.
If you want to one thing that might be good is to put at senior ettore
before or at handmade hero one of the other before the if you have a
specific question, so I can jump to them really quickly and not miss
anything.
Let's see from scratch.
Do you mean starting with zero lines of code and making no use of any
other code other than what than a virus is provide.
Yes, that is correct.
So you're saying audio Graphics basic data structures.
Etc.
Yes.
So all of that is true.
We will not be using any libraries.
Every last thing that shows up on the screen that you hear through.
The speakers will be written by us.
And the only things that we will be using that exist out in the wild
are basically a little tiny bit of the C runtime library because the
compiler makes it very hard to get rid of it in the old days, I would
have
Actually gotten rid of it for you and showed you how to do it without
the C runtime library at all.
Even though, almost no one ever does that in practice?
I think I'm one of the only people who ever shipped a product that did
that, that's not true.
I'm sure there's tons of people who do, but in a modern error.
I was probably one of you people ever tried to do that Granny.
Could the 3D animation Library grad could compile without C runtime
library and the tools that get shipped compiled without C runtime
libraries well, but
Ignoring that we will only be using the facilities of Windows itself,
and we will only be using the most limited versions of those.
So we will not be using Windows Graphics API at all.
We will basically only being using Windows to get our B to the screen.
That's it.
So, I am with my goal with the series is teach you how to do
absolutely everything from scratch, except the operating system
basically.
And hey man, I'd love to do that part 2, but it's hard to do that on
Modern computers because there's so much left to do.
We'll see maybe on the Raspberry Pi.
I've been thinking about maybe doing it on the Raspberry Pi.
So when the series is over, it may be time for a slice of pie if you
know what I mean.
Anyway, moving on.
I think I answered the C C++ question.
You probably answer that.
But why are you using Windows .h?
So I think we covered why I'm using Windows that H, but at the risk of
spoiling something.
I will say that we are only temporarily using Windows .h Windows.
That H may go away sooner than you think, come maybe five or six days
into the stream, into the real official stream, Windows, Windows 8,
Disappear, but the reason I was using Windows that H, is because I
needed to call output debug string, which is a Windows function in the
way.
You call Windows functions.
As you include their prototypes, which are in Windows .h,
let's see.
We are going to use work.
Nah, I'll ask if we're going to .h r dot h PP.
I usually use .h, I don't know why I don't care if people use DHCP, if
they want to, that's fine too, but I always use .h,
Let's see using CP units, proceed.
If I'm participial sister Libby.
Okay, Johan.
Oh, first it probably pass that wrong.
Do you find any parts of the SQL?
Standard Library useful.
Casey like standard sort certifying the like know I love with the C++
standard Library.
It is the worst.
It is like the antithesis of how I would like code to work and I do
not.
That with a 10-foot Pole.
Now.
I admit that if you do not have your own standard library, that you
have built up over the years, that do things like sorting and stuff
like that for you.
Then I admit that it may be tempting to use it and it may actually be
more efficient to use it.
If you're just doing something really quickly and don't have time to
build something else.
It may be quicker to use a standard library because it does have a lot
of stuff in there.
But oh man, if you are serious about programming, do not touch that
thing.
It is a nightmare.
Everything.
It does just complicate your life in a number of ways whether it's
from bloating, your compile.
Time bloating.
Your executable being hard to debug, being hard to read causing tons
of extra typing that didn't need to be there.
It's just it's awful.
And it all goes hand in hand with the fact that I think C++ really
dropped the ball on metaprogramming.
The fact that they lean on templates to do.
That is just ridiculous.
And templates, are, they're just, they're designed poorly.
It's a nightmare and I'm a metaprogramming aficionado.
I don't really even write programs.
And
Handmade here is going to be one of the only programs that I right
probably ever in the future, that is not a meta program.
I do a lot of metaprogramming nowadays when I write code and it just
breaks my heart to try and program and see what C++ with the standard
library because it's just it's the worst meta programming language
I've ever seen.
Yeah, I can't stand it.
So no, I don't touch that stuff with a 10-foot pole.
I don't really want to argue about it necessarily because you know,
honestly if you can make it work, effectively for you.
Great, go for it.
I, I can't stand it and I really don't like code bases that use it.
So I really stand to stand to stay away from it, and I will constantly
be advocating against it, but that does not mean that there can't be
people who make effective use of it, and then does not mean they're
people who won't be comfortable with it.
So, you know, one of the things that's true is when I say something
sucks or when I say something that I don't like or don't use, that's
just talking about me.
Personally, what I found to be effective if you find up the opposite
to be true, then that's just a different way of programming that
you've learned.
and just be very sure that you're actually
Write about it for you.
Don't just believe something has somebody else does it?
But if you're sure that you're right about it for you, then you are
right.
What makes you effective and What Makes You efficient at coding?
Is the right thing for you to do and it's not going to be the same
even among very, very good programmers.
I have seen code from lots of different, great programmers.
In my lifetime.
I've been fortunate enough to work with great programmers and see how
they write code.
No two people write code the same way.
There are some things that seem to be true about going really great,
crook programmers.
That I've seen be like, yeah, okay, there.
Code seems to adhere to a couple things that are true, but on the
whole there's a lot of varying ways in which they work and so I
wouldn't get too hung up on anything like should use a standard
libraries, shouldn't you, whatever the principles that I'll be
teaching in handmade here as it goes, forward are more about how you
determine.
What works well, how you determine, if you should use a standard
library.
And I'm not going to tell you, whether you should use a standard
Library.
I'm going to say that.
I don't want to use it, but I'm not going to tell you, tell you not to
use it.
I'm going to tell you how to figure out that you shouldn't use it.
And then
You go through those steps that I say, and, and you look at how I say
to analyze something.
You may come to a different conclusion, you know, because it's kind of
like, you know, it's up some level.
It's a bit of an art form.
Right?
Coding is, I may say, here are the steps.
I used to come to that conclusion.
You may do the same steps and go.
No, I found that I was efficient when I did these steps.
I tried to do things and it did result in code that I could read.
Well, it did do these things and so I will harp more on the steps that
I think are true and that are Universal that you should be going
through and the
The mindset that you should have but the outcome of those is different
and each person depending on how their brain works in, depending on
how they code, is going to have a different opinion.
So, and that's fine.
And I, and as blustery as I may ever get about code things in my
heart.
I always believe that someone should be able to come to a different
conclusion than me.
And they should be able to yell at me about it, and I should be able
to yell back at them about it, but that's okay.
Takes all types.
Let's see what we've got here.
All the code and debugging.
What do you find use for graphics?
If you're out playing using libraries, such as opengl.
Do you want me to spoil the surprise Pagan heart?
Do you really want me to pose for us?
I will basically be showing you how to program by doing all of your
own rendering calling.
Absolutely, no windows whatsoever until you have done, absolutely
everything yourself, all in your own code at the very last minute.
We'll just be using Windows to basically say here is a block of memory
that we've put the graphics in that we wanted just
Just copy those colors.
Like it, literally a bitmap.
We will have in-memory copy that to the screen.
That is the only thing that windows will do for us.
The same is true for audio.
We will basically do all of the audio ourselves until we get to the
very end and then we will basically tell Windows take just that and
played out the speaker, please.
Let's see.
What type of game of this be?
What type of game will this be that I'm going to wait till the
mainstream to answer.
I will simply say that it will be a game about adventuring sort of an
action adventure game.
Let's see it's going to say the same thing fantasy.
Question is saturated addition, logically equivalent to clamp.
Well, so dr.
G.
It's yes, and no.
What I would say about saturated addition is, it is sort of, like,
clamp.
If you assume that the clamp can happen in a space that's bigger than
what you had.
So for example, if you remember here, I had to 55 and then I added 1
to it and it became zero.
So the problem there is if I were to try doing the clamp after this,
to clamp it to 55, it's too late because it already wrapped Rock back
to zero.
But if I do that computation like in the register, it was doing the
computation in a bigger space that can.
For bigger numbers.
Does the addition first then does the clamp 2255 that would work.
So it's logical equivalent in that sense, but you have to make sure
that you don't overflow the value before you do.
The clamp.
Otherwise are the same.
Paul 6.
Willie be creating a scripting language that we don't have to write
crappy C++ headers, where you want to add objects to our game Paul 6.
We will not be writing a scripting language.
We will be writing everything in C.
And the reason that we will be writing everything in C is because we
are going to try and make everything just a little bit more Dynamic
than if you were to try and do a scripting language for it, but
If we get to a point where we really need something like that, I'd be
happy to show you how to code a scripting language.
It's just there's a lot of work involved there that I don't know how
relevant it is to the actual kind of program management each.
But if we find that we need to do that or somehow this goes more
quickly.
I'm imagining it will take months to go through all these things
because I have to teach each individual thing.
So, even something that I know, would only take me a day to implement
is going to take many days to implement because I want to make sure I
explain it.
So, I would probably like to avoid doing a scripting language if I
could just because that sort of a separate thing, but, hey, maybe you
know, eventually
We get there, we could do that.
Sure.
When we get into sockets, netcode no, I'm definitely not going to do
netcode again.
I'm just going to try and cut that out.
What I want to do is focus on something.
What's the minimum set that we can do to still make a great game but
not take too much time.
And so there's a lot of great games out right now that are 2D local
co-op only or local single-player only but that are still awesome.
And so what I want to do is focus on making game, that's awesome.
But within those constraints, and the reason for that is because I'd
rather go deeper then going wider, so I don't want to
Seven years of your life to listen to this series and which I could
cover all the stuff like that Canasta or scripting languages.
For example, I don't really want to force that issue, but certainly
based on the response, if, if this series keeps being as popular as it
seems to be already,
With the number of people who are showing up to watch these, then I'll
just keep doing them ad infinitum.
I mean, I can spare an hour, a night to just keep going or two hours a
night at this point, I guess with the Q and A sessions, and so we
could just keep adding stuff to it after it's done, if we're like,
hey, yep.
We finished.
It's a good game.
Let's add that code.
I'm totally fine with that.
But I just think it'll take us so long to go through everything.
If I really do a good job explaining.
I think I'll take a so long ago through it that we need to Pare down
to just what's necessary to make a great game.
I like the old school games where, you know, there wasn't a surly
netcode in them, but they're still awesome.
We'll be creating languages.
Will you be getting a suck?
A snakehead?
We did that.
How much time to accept this anything with different as of notations?
None.
I don't think they actually spend with do much as a notation stuff.
I'll just teach you basically how to read what's going on.
So you can kind of be comfortable with it, but we won't really belabor
the point too much.
Are you going to make the music for the game?
No, I license music for the game.
I already licensed music.
The game.
Actually, the music is ready.
And I'm in the process of trying to get Art built for the game.
Unfortunately, there's no way to just license art.
Like, there is a way to license music.
So, I had to find an artist and I'm working with the artists now and
hopefully they will be interested in doing a fair bit of art for the
game, but I'm basically going to see how that goes.
Obviously, it's expensive, but I really wanted us to have art to work
with and I wanted the game to look good so that you would see that
what we were doing.
Programming is as good as the best quality stuff that there is.
We're not, you know, kind of cars.
Anything.
And part of that is having nice art.
I mean, if your art looks ugly, it's pretty hard to show off the code.
Yes, the bottom lines.
Let's see and me and her.
Can you release any information about what kind of game it is?
Make Monday Monday.
We will talk a little more about that and on that live stream at the
beginning of that live show on Monday, when I officially start the
real stream.
I will give a little explanation of what the game is going to be like
Are there any books recommend to read along with the series know?
There might be good books out there, but I don't know what they are.
I apologize.
It's been a long time since I've read a programming book.
So I don't know what the good books would be.
And I'd be afraid to recommend something in case, there's like kind of
bad ideas in it.
The game won't use the GPU Willett.
Nudists wants to say, not at first, so I want to avoid the GPU until
potentially the very end because I want to show people how to do, all
the rendering themselves.
The GPU will speed things up quite a bit from what we can do with the
only the central processor, but actually like if you look at something
like say, for example, The Binding of Isaac, the original or rebirth,
I believe, we could pretty much do cpu-based rendering.
For that.
No problem.
And those are fantastically popular games.
Nobody seem to have a problem with those in terms of the quality of
the game that they were getting.
The Flash versions too slow.
We could definitely out do that.
But I mean, you know, the rebirth one where it's actually running 60
frames a second.
I think we can get, we might not get 60.
Maybe we'll get 30 and we might have to be a little lower res, but we
can do it on the CPU.
Now, later in the series.
I probably will show how to bump it up to GPU, rendering for Speed
purposes.
But I'm hoping that we don't have to do that because I really want you
to be able to see how all the rendering works.
And as soon as you go into GPU land, there's a whole bunch of stuff
that happens behind your back.
And now, I'm behind your back.
But there's so much stuff that happens that you can't even know
because it's confidential.
You can't even know how it works.
I can't even explain to you how it works because I might not even know
because they may not ever have been something that they could tell me.
For example, I know how the internals of some stuff work but you know,
there's a whole bunch stuff that I don't know.
So I kind of have to ask like someone from Nvidia when I want to know,
a really nitty-gritty detail about something because I don't know what
happens in those chips.
And so I wanted to keep this series to all things that we could
specifically see every pixel on the screen.
We put it there and we know exactly what happened to get it.
Not sort of but exactly.
Let's see.
Why would you prefer Visual Studio compiler?
So if you see since your plan is to create a standalone library in
pure C.
Well, I'm just, I'm used to using their debugger.
I'm used to using the visual studio debugger, because that's what the
industry uses.
And I wanted people to get used to using what the industry uses at
least for now.
Because I figure people who take this class might want a job in the
game industry someday and if they want a job in the game industry,
they won't be using GCC on Windows.
They'll be using this when we are on Linux, which I will do a platform
things.
You can see I use on Linux, you'll be using llvm
Which is sort of a newer better way to do GCC compiles.
So we will be addressing.
Open-source compilers.
Just not on the Windows platform.
Let's see.
What else we got here?
Running out of time.
It's almost two hours.
Do do do.
Looking through, and I'm not seeing.
Are we recording this Q&A?
Yes, the Q&A is always recorded and posted along with the video on
YouTube.
So if you go to handmade hero dot-org, in fact, I'll just demonstrate
it for you.
So, if you go to handmade hero dot-org, you will see these buttons.
I put the buttons here at the top that are the most important buttons.
You can get to the twitch stream quickly, by doing this, and you can
get to the archive.
You can also email me a question, which will help when you get into
things yourself.
If you go to the archive, you will see that.
That actually, the Q&A from day one is already there, so you can
always get to to it this way.
So, yeah, I highly recommend that you check out the q&a's if you are
looking for a stuff because I try to answer a bunch of the questions
that I think are important.
So
Paul sex as inheritance versus composition.
We are way.
Not at that point yet.
Paul 6.
We are going to hold that till later on.
New to says, will you be the game designer?
I thought you'd given up on designed.
Yes.
And yes, actually are.
Those are both true and how can that be true?
It's a good question.
The answer is because I will be showing you how to make a game.
That is a very standard design.
I am not a very good game designer in my opinion, but I understand
games.
Well enough.
I've been playing them for so long and I understand basic game design
stuff.
So, if you want me to make
Something that's like, you know, the Legend of Zelda or something like
that.
I understand the important aspects there and I won't mess it up.
So what I'm doing here is not so much novel game design.
It's more just like make a competent action adventure game, right?
Using the things that, you know, work and action-adventure games.
I won't be branching out.
Hugely.
I won't be doing a bunch of things that no one's ever seen before.
And oh my God, it's made me cry.
And I learned about my dog that has cancer, like, none of that stuff
will be happening because I
Game designer in that sense and I don't pretend to know how to do
those things.
So, I am just going with a very standard design and I will be
obviously, also, welcoming input from my game, design friends, who are
very good game designers.
I know, plenty of people who are much better game designers than I am.
So if I have any questions, they will be.
Basically, you know, the people who sort of decide things like that.
I will just ask for help if it a design thing.
So the focus will always be on the code.
Code and the design will be very straightforward and I will you know,
basically get get people's opinions who I trust to make any decisions
that I feel like are too hard for someone like me who's a game
programmer, not a game developer.
Let's see.
So you're not having fixed answer raise from your backup, is your back
right up to a window?
Yes.
I am scared of snipers and falling through the window, Sean neck.
That is true.
You know, the thing is, the snipers should get me walking down the
street to and I can get run over by a car.
So the way I rationalize it is like of a sniper's going to get me,
they're going to get me right?
And it's some sense.
Why even bother shooting me through the window, right?
Like, I mean, it's harder to shoot through a window.
No, that's what I figure is.
So yeah, it's totally true.
It is scary but it's not as scary as as every day.
Really.
It's a dangerous world out there.
Guns are dangerous is the way we are displaying Graphics faster than
using opengl.
As far as frame rates.
No, it is actually slower than opengl.
We will be taking a speed hit so that we can do it all ourselves.
And then later, I will show you how to also do it using.
The GPU Pipeline and you can compare the speeds obviously, but we are
basically going to be doing it the old school way.
So people can learn how to render before they start using something
like opengl.
Because I think it's actually pretty important to know how to render
before you start telling opengl how to do things that you want to
render, because it really helps your understanding of even how opengl
is working.
Kendrick Beckett, how complex will the game be the game is going to be
very complex.
Actually, most of what I want to spend time doing this.
I want to show you how to write an audio engine.
I want to show you how to write a video engine, but then the majority
of the code we're going to write for most of the series is I want to
show you how to write very intricate game code and manage the
complexity that comes out of it.
So the game will be a lot more complex than most of the things you can
buy in terms of the actual game.
And that's in there.
It will not be, you know, like something like Assassin's Creed or
something or, you know, Call of Duty where there's tons of scripted
sequences.
It will not be complex in the art asset management and composition,
but in terms of like the actual complexity of what you can do in the
game, it will be vastly more complicated than something like Call of
Duty.
We're basically all I can do is shoot stuff, but they told you, you
could shoot.
So there will it is designed to be a.
The plan I have for the game is that it is designed to, to basically
Force us to mostly deal with hard item, interaction environment,
interaction, entity interaction, sorts of stuff.
So you can see how that code works because that is code that to me is
very Timeless and that are conceptually things that you have to do.
No matter what programming language, you learn in, and I want to show
how to handle those in good ways and and where the problems are and
all that sort of stuff.
Let's take a look here.
When will the game be finished a long time from now?
Because I have to explain everything.
I think it will take quite some time.
So even though it's a 2d game, which means we don't have to deal with
a lot of the 3D art pipeline stuff, which takes a lot of time.
And the art wrangling will be more straightforward because I'm
explaining everything as I go.
It's gonna take a long time.
I mean, expect expect several months before there is a interesting
game to play at all, and then expect several months after that, for us
to really
Aren't getting into all the complexity and stuff because I want to
take it slow.
Let's see.
Yes, I should change the stream title.
That's a very good point.
Thank You.
Ed's one Shah twitch title.
Okay, Andy Boy, follow up on the back to Starbucks and question your
opinion.
Was it a mistake for them to implement it in that fashion?
That is do you think they should have left it the programmer to
handle?
Okay, so you basically want to know what I think of the fact that the
C runtime Lottery, just a string translation.
Well, honestly, I think the CHC runtime layer library is kind of
crappy.
I don't think it's crappy because the people who made it didn't know
what they're doing.
I think the people who are responsible for see in general.
Are pretty awesome and I think the C runtime library was probably
actually pretty darn good for its time.
I think nowadays.
It doesn't make a whole lot of sense.
A lot of the things that they did but those are all because the
circumstances have changed and we've learned a lot more about API
design and things like this and computers are a lot faster.
So the different things matter there.
There's so many things that are there, so I really would hesitate to
criticize something about.
The way the C runtime library is designed or what they did in there,
and I don't really know the circumstances when the backslash are back
session.
Think a
In obviously, the original see didn't run on Windows because Windows
didn't exist.
So that is a later thing.
Anyway, and may not have even had anything to do with the people who
originally designed it, but I don't want to second-guess them because
they, you know, they wrote a language that has lasted for, you know,
decades and it's pretty darn good even today.
Let's see.
Hang of this bunch of doodoo.
Casey needs a mega timer.
Yes, it is time for me to end.
So I'm going to try and just blow through these last couple questions
for you.
Share some of your tricks for doing meta, pregnancy.
Probably not.
That's way out of the scope of this thing.
Which, what should I say to?
My note, open our friends who say making gaming CSA?
This is crazy.
Tell them that's fine.
Actually, if they think it's crazy.
They should not do it.
They should make it in C++.
I don't think people should use things that they don't like I would
basically say that hopefully the stream will prove that you don't
really need the best place to make a nice good clean game that runs
great reads, great and is easy to work with and so I guess if you
really want to come back at them you could say well why don't you re
Implement your own game in C++ as a live stream and we'll all watch
and see how easy that is.
I don't know.
But no, I wouldn't, you know don't argue with people.
One of the things that
I learned a long time ago.
Programming wise is arguing just makes you less viable in the job
market.
Basically, if someone else wants to program poorly, let them.
That basically means you have more job security because you're the
only person who won't be wasting all your time, typing in templates
and classes and doing inheritance.
You'll actually be writing code that actually does useful things and
you will be more valuable to the company that you work for, or you'll
be able to make a better game in less time.
So, you know, you can politely tell someone that they're probably
wrong about.
Nothing, but at the end of the day unless you're just trying to let
off steam which I do as well.
If you're unless you're just trying to let off steam, don't bother
arguing with them.
Just let them continue to programming correctly and yeah.
Easier life for you.
How much variation will be possible with?
Everyone's game is a project progresses.
I'm not sure what that means.
Sorry, maybe send me an email and I'll answer it later.
how complex require the math out of your, okay, so the math will
That complex because we're doing it in 2D and I chose that silly to
try and reduce the math load and the content load hopefully because
it's 2D not that much math, but you will need to know things like
Sines and cosines and we'll be doing some things with like ratios.
And so there will be math involved and I'll try to explain it as we
go, but it definitely will help if you understand high school math.
I probably won't bust out too much college level stuff.
Hopefully we will not have to do anything really related to two linear
algebra.
Or if accuse, and that sort of stuff.
If I already know how to program but I'm interested in the game
programming so stuff, where you're going to skip dressing that 17th or
is there some?
Okay.
So basically what he's asking is, should they start on the 17th of May
already know how to program in C?
Well enough.
And the answer is.
It depends what you want to know the Windows startup process, the
first week or two, we'll just be basically me showing you how to code
to thing in Windows that gets you into what I would call kind of the
old days, which is a place where you could just write to an audio
stream and a video surface and have them display if you care about
that.
You should watch if you don't care.
That you can skip it after that.
Yes, we will be into the game code part of code.
We will be doing stuff with rendering at various points, which you may
not care about.
If you don't care what run, if you just only want game code, but I
will try to tweet things that let you know what's going to happen and
maybe we'll try to come up with a good way of posting what's going to
happen so that you can easily jump in and out.
If you don't care about certain parts of the stream because I do
respect the fact that there are people out there who only want to see
parts of it and it's going to be a long Series, so I'll try to
facilitate that
The same could work for using Mac instead of Windows.
Yes, although not for a little while.
So basically, I the problem is I don't have a way to really stream
from Windows.
From other platforms at the moment.
I only can stream from Windows from using the OBS thing.
What I would like to do is I'm going to get a box and then I will do
the startup code to show you how to do the same startup code that
we're going to on Windows on a Mac and then all the same code will
work.
So they're basically just be a little shim that goes on each operating
system.
And so hopefully people will
The Following on the Mac eventually but not right away.
I'm sorry about that.
Let's see, last couple questions.
Looks like we are basically done with questions.
So I will wrap it up for the night.
Thank you very much.
Everyone 200 people, that's twice.
The people we had last night.
That is crazy.
Thank you so much everyone for for tuning in.
I had a great time and I hope you enjoy the stream.
If you have anything that you would like to suggest, please go ahead
and email me.
If you go to handmade hero dot-org.
There's that email button.
You can send me an email and I look forward to seeing you all.
Again tomorrow night, when we will go into a little more detail on
Assembly Language and C code and how it relates to each other.
And then we will finally be free to just code some see and take a look
at it which will get us in good shape for Monday start.
Okay.
Thanks everybody, and I will see you tomorrow.