Okay, welcome everyone.
This is the third day of the test stream here, where I am sort of
practicing to make sure everything is working properly.
And so that everyone kind of can give me feedback on how the streams
are going in preparation for Monday's, start of handmade hero.
And so what I wanted to do today, if you remember where we left off, I
was just showing you some Assembly Language and starting to talk about
what the C code was actually.
You doing today?
I hope will be a pretty exciting stream.
I am hoping that that, basically, this will kind of start to tie
things together.
Because what I've done in the past, two streams is life.
I've kind of had to throw a bunch of stuff at you and sort of give you
the general idea and hope that a lot of that stuff kind of sticks, but
I haven't been able to really get to a coherent sort of model that you
can use in your head because I needed to kind of get some things out
there.
First.
There's so many things involved.
In a program that it's kind of hard to really start from from scratch
in that sense to kind of have to give you a little bit and then go
back and go.
Okay.
Now that you've sort of seen some things, let's let's actually talk
about the holistic view.
So what I wanted to talk about today finally was memory because memory
is actually the fundamental thing that we work with in programming.
And the reason that I say that it's very fundamental is because even
though nowadays in higher
The languages we start to work with abstractions and things like this
where we're not really thinking necessarily about the memory that
we're using or what it's doing.
The important thing to remember is that a CPU itself.
The thing that we are actually programming and a GPU for that matter.
If you're working on a graphics card, those things are all about
taking in memory modifying them and putting them back out to memory.
This is true to such an extent that actually anything that you want to
do.
I don't care if it's audio or video or things that seem completely.
Leon memory.
Like they are actually all just about putting things into memory where
other things can see that memory and use it.
So, if I want to do graphics on a graphics card, and there's all this
Hardware in there, that's designed to turn things into images that go
out on, you know, even an analog, you know, old school to a CRT or
something, where there was no digital transmission, even everything
that happens up to that point is about putting the right stuff into
memory.
So that that Hardware component can read the memory
Turn it into the proper electrical signal to produce a picture on a
television or something like that.
Right?
So fundamentally programming always comes back to understanding.
What is happening with the CPU.
And the memory.
What is this EP you doing to change that memory and how and that is
the basis for all of the design of the code that you should do?
You should be thinking about that because that is what you are doing
at a core level.
That's the basis of all the optimizations.
Into the code you will do.
And it's the basis of all the debugging that you will do because
absolutely everything at the end of the day is a CPU instruction.
That changes some memory.
So nothing that you ever do.
No matter how abstract can ever really get away from the truth of the
matter that it is all about modifying memory.
And so there are definitely abstractions that help us and we will be
doing a lot of abstracting as we go where we start to think of things
at a higher level than just each individual bit and how it's being
set.
But if you lose sight in,
By early of the fact that it is all about that, you start to go very
wrong in the way that you design and Implement things.
Because you start to think of terms things in terms of their
efficiency for the abstraction.
And if you start to think of terms of things in terms of efficiency
for the distractions, that is what leads to slow code.
It's what leads to Buggy code.
It's what leads to things that I don't really consider to be very good
software.
That's why I don't like when people sort of divorce themselves from an
understanding of what happens on the computer.
Now, if someday, someone develops, a machine that can execute
You abstractions somehow then great.
We can all learn how to program abstractions, and that'll be good.
But until that day, I think it's a fundamental part of every
programmers job to understand exactly how the machine works.
And, you know, you don't have to get crazy with it.
I don't pretend to know everything that happens at Intel CPU because
oh my God, they are fantastically complicated.
So yes, just like you'll never know.
All of the things you need to know about math.
Are all of the things you need to know about anything in particular,
that's related to programming, you'll never know.
Nothing.
The point is to educate yourself enough, that you have an idea of the
things that you need to know.
You have an idea of how to drill down further into them when it's
necessary and you have enough understanding to know how deep you
should understand things for any particular purpose.
And so today.
I really want to kind of open that up and start to talk about exactly
what's happening in the memory for The Limited piece of C code that we
kind of work through the, for the past two days.
So, if you remember correctly, we had our little entry point here.
That Windows was calling.
And we had a little thing where we set a variable equal to 255 and we
added 12.
It was very exciting.
I know everyone out there with sight but I was very heartened to see
that.
Actually people were pretty excited when we opened up the Assembly
Language window when I actually ran to this line of code here.
And I went to go to disassembly here.
And I showed that here are the actual instructions that the CPU is
executing.
So I found that very heartening because I'm glad to see that people
were interested to see that because of
Honestly, I think that stuff is fascinating to and that's the sort of
stuff that I want to sort of sprinkle throughout the series so that
people get it, an idea of what's going on.
Now, before I do that, I'll notice there are some warnings in our are
compiled, their I'm going to rebuild it so I can see what they are.
Yeah, you could see.
So are compiled has some warnings and they're all about unreferenced,
local variable.
And and the reason for that is because you can see we defined a bunch
of things here because I was trying to teach you about the different
sizes that you can use for, you know, variables that you store and
since
Ever reference.
Any of them, you will notice that the compiler is sort of giving us a
little warning saying, hey, you define something here.
You said you were going to talk about a particular value, but you
never talked about it.
Was that a mistake.
So it's a warning sign an error because it can still produce the code
just fine, but it's a warning to let you know that.
So what I'm going to do here is I am going to delete this for the time
being or actually, you know, what I'll do.
I'll use a comment because I haven't taught you about if that's really
yet.
So I'm going to use a comment to get rid of that.
So that's gone.
Now, it's commented out.
And now, when I
Compile, I won't get any warning so they won't distract us from what
we're trying to do.
All right.
So the first question that I want you to ask yourselves and that I am
going to answer or hopefully try to answer for you is I told you what
this did.
I said care unsigned test was going to give us eight bits.
That were going to be treated in an unsigned fashion.
Meaning that if I was to add one to the highest value, which is 255.
It would wrap around 20.
I could not represent negative numbers.
There were no negative numbers involved so it has
Assign to it.
It's always it's always positive or zero and what I want you to ask
yourself though.
He's where is that value?
Where are those bits?
Right?
I said there were eight bits.
There were eight ones and zeros, but where are they?
And the first thing that we can actually do to figure out where they
are in some sort of, you know, rather rather topical sense is when I
come in here to the code.
In fact, you know what I'll do.
I'll just do this in code for you because I want to introduce these.
Anyway, I'm going to introduce a new thing here, which is a pointer.
And I'm going to run that here so that we can inspect the values.
So you'll note.
I've set a breakpoint.
Again.
I told you how to set breakpoints last week.
I've set a breakpoint and I've stopped on this line of code.
And what I want to show you, is this new construct that I have created
here, this new line of code.
And you know what, we won't even I'm not even go one further than
that.
Breakouts are polite because I don't want to talk about in line
decorations yet.
So there we go.
Sometimes it's easy to get
Of myself because I'm like, oh, yes, I'll just I'll just do this
thing, but it's like I have explained that yet.
Let's not go there.
So anyway, what I want to show you here is that in C.
And this is a departure from a lot of languages that people program in
these days in see, memory is a first class citizen.
So you always are able to actually find out things like the question
that I just asked, which is, where is this value?
The actual location of the value is something that is integral to see.
And is something that you can trivially, find out manipulate used to
your advantage.
And those are things called pointers in C.
Basically, you can take the address of a variable or anything else in
C.
And the address is basically a number, which tells you where in the
memory of the machine that thing is stored and you can have a thing
called a pointer which is basically something that just holds and
address.
It's like any other number.
But the number is used to reference a piece of memory and see will
allow you to use that number to do things, like go and see what's in
the memory that it's point to.
You can move them around 2.2.
Things you can increment them.
So they point to later values.
You can decrement them to point to earlier values and basically what
this means is that unlike some languages where memory is not something
you're really allowed to touch, so you can't actually go in and ask
about the actual address of something or go into an address and and
touch it change.
What's values are those sorts of things.
You always have to be using variables that are known to the compiler
and they're known what they are?
And, you know, their types are known.
That sort of stuff.
That is not true and C.
C is very fungible with memory allows you to do all the stuff that
You want to do.
And that's one of the reasons that I picked C and C++ to do this
project in first of all, it's the language that I prefer to program
in.
So that's a no-brainer but it's also because it allows me to show you
all of those low-level things.
Unlike something like that was a little higher level, you know, in PHP
or something or Java.
Probably.
Although I've never actually anything Java.
You don't have that kind of low-level access.
So there's a bunch of things that I just couldn't show you.
So the syntax this little star right here, just face.
Lee says, that the thing that I'm defining, instead of being the type
that I actually put in, like I made this beak are unsigned the exact
site.
Same type as test.
So 8 B unsigned and it's a number.
Well, when I actually did this, this right here, I didn't actually
want another 8-bit value.
What I wanted, is the ability to talk about the location in memory of
an 8-bit value.
And that is what this star does.
The star turns some type that
You've said here, when you're talking to the compiler.
It says well that type that I'm talking about.
I actually now want to talk about where a thing of that type is.
Not that the type is that and so that's what it that's really all you
have to do and anything that you put over here.
I could have put anything I could have used in like we did before, I
wanted to point to test.
So that is the reason that I use the type of test.
But oops.
Sorry, all these code changes in.
It wants to recompile obviously.
So basically what happens is once I have that I can use a new operator
in Co-operators are the things like plus that tell, you know, that
allow us to construct code.
There are things that operate on our variables.
I can use a new operator, which is the address operator.
It's this little a sand here and what it means is that every time that
I put a variable or something else and I put the Ampersand in front of
it.
What that means is I would like to know where this is in memory.
I want to know what location in memory.
You have stored this thing.
And in this case, I'm going to put it into this test pointer here that
I made.
So we can go into the watch window, which hopefully you remember how
we how we use that bum from the past.
Two days.
We can type in a name and of one of our variables or something.
And we can see the value of it.
You can see that we have not executed this line yet.
But when we execute this line, you will see that test is 255.
Just like, we thought,
It was going to be just like it was last time, but now we could also
inspect test.
Enter and test pointer.
Is actually you can see it's a hexadecimal value.
These things keep keep popping up, but we don't actually have to look
at it as hexadecimal value.
I can actually do a little black magic here.
That's a little bit further than what we want to actually get the heck
out of there, but it is just a number.
And what that number is is it is literally the number of bytes which
are 8-bit values, is the number of bytes from the bottom of memory,
the very first piece of memory all the way up to where it decided to
store test.
This is literally where in memory, we are storing this, this
particular value.
Okay, that's the memory of the computer.
That's where it is.
Now, when I say that there's a little bit of a catch to it and the
catch is actually important.
So unlike a lot of catches when I say I'll delay this and I'm going to
talk about later.
I'm actually going to talk about the, the catch right off the bat.
And the catch is that in the old days.
If I were teaching you this course in 1980 or something like that?
On a home computer.
Let's say I was teaching it in 1986 on an Amiga, which is one of my
favorite computers of all time.
If I was teaching it to their that what I just said would be literally
true.
It would literally be like a number that reference, the actual
physical memory of the machine.
But nowadays, that's no longer true.
And the reason that is no longer true is because machines today use
something called virtual memory and what virtual memory is is it's a
way to allow processes to things that you run your computer.
The
I would just sort of cooperate with each other because if you think
about it, if all of the things that you ran on your computer, in a
multitasking operating system.
And there are a lot if I bring up that process image, look at all
these things.
Look at all these things running on my computer.
I don't even know what half of these things are.
These are all these SPC.
Host Services running machine out.
Know what those are.
Here's the Wacom tablet driver.
I guess.
I don't know.
I don't even know what that is.
Pain Services, Maybe here's a networking thing.
God Only Knows Chrome is running three things.
Probably for memory.
Isolation.
I don't know.
It's it's a it's a
Free-for-all out here, right?
Look at all that stuff.
It's totally bananas.
So what you may ask is hey, if you can write all these programs that
they can just work at memory.
Like I was just showing you like, OKC, lets me poke it memory.
Lets me do these things, if that's true.
How do we avoid having these programs step on each other's memory or
like a bug in one program?
Overwrite something else or a security concern where say like one of
these programs like audio, d, g, dot exe, whatever that is decides to
read my password out of memory or something like that.
How do we stop that?
And furthermore?
How do we deal?
Deal with the fact that maybe we start running all these processes and
each process wants to use all four gigabytes of memory in the machine
wants to use them all.
Well, where does the memory that the other process was using?
Where does it go?
Where the other processes, where their memory?
Where does their memory go to the programmer?
Have to deal with that, what happens?
And the answer is that personal computers?
Probably since the late 80s and certainly in the 90s and
Words, I don't actually remember the exact chronology.
Even the Amiga got an mmu, which is a memory management unit sometime
in the 1990.
I don't even remember.
I won't I won't try to pretend that.
I can remember these things but certainly by today almost every
processor you're likely to encounter has a thing called virtual
memory, which is basically allowing a given piece of code that is
running to see what appears to be the memory of the machine.
But what is actually not the
Real memory of the machine in terms of layout.
And the way this works is that it divides memory into pages and those
pages are essentially chunks, there, a certain range say 4096 bytes
4K, if you will for KB.
Those pages exists in physical memory.
So there are some number of pages in physical memory.
But each process actually has its own concept of these pages.
And it thinks the memory is laid out in a particular way, but those
pages, that it is accessing only exists when it actually acts as them
necessarily.
The operating system is in charge of basically, shuttling, physical
memory out to say, a hard drive or something.
Like this or rearranging the layout of things using a table that is
maintained on the CPU and that the CPU does.
The translation automatically that allows each processes view of these
pages to be dynamically mapped to where they actually are in physical
memory.
And that is the virtual memory system of an operating system.
So, what happens is when I talk about a particular location in memory
in my code.
What I'm actually talking about is its address in my virtual.
Memory space.
Which looks like a real memory space to me, but really, it could be
all mapped crazy to different parts of the physical memory.
Some of it may not be in physical memory at the time because it got
swapped out to disk.
And when I go to try and actually access that memory the operating
system will actually come swap it back in to where I was trying to use
it and then it's like, oh, okay.
Now it works.
And so in order to support this, there's a bunch of stuff in the
actual Processing Unit.
There's a thing called a translation lookaside buffer.
There's these memory memory tables.
It's all sorts of things in there that allow it to basically go.
Okay.
This guy was talking about this memory location, but that's not really
where in memory that Paige is right now.
So I'm going to actually secretly change the location he asked for
when it goes out to fetch the memory and I'm going to actually give
him back the rights, the stuff that he is right as far as he's
concerned, but he'll never have to know that, that's what happened.
Okay, so hopefully that makes a little bit of sense to you and that's,
that's what virtual memory is.
But for all intents and purposes.
Is when we are coding, we can always think of our memory addresses as
being actual, physical memory addresses for the most part, but it is
important to understand that those things are happening under the hood
because we can run into a lot of problems if we don't manage things
properly.
So, for example, one of the things I
I said is that sometimes you may have to operate system, may have to
swap that memory out or something like that.
For example, if we use too much of it, or if another process comes in
and is using memory and need some memory to give some of our memory to
that process, Etc, the physical memory.
I mean, then what can happen is if we're not aware that those things
are happening under the hood.
We may run into performance problems in our code that have to do with
that swapping.
And so it's very important for us to always be aware of it and to
manage those things.
When the time comes, when we have to actually deal with things like
this.
It's important for us to understand.
That those things are going on.
So we are aware and we're not just totally confused if something like
that starts to happen.
So we'll talk about that more in the mainstream because we're
certainly not going to hit that with any of our code here.
So, anyway, now that you have a little bit of are saying about that, I
want to get back to the pointers.
So the way that these pointers work, like I said, is they basically
give you this value Here.
And Now, normally the way that they are, the way that they show up is,
As a hexadecimal value.
And I talked a little bit about the base of values, how their can
basically be octal, which is based.
Hexadecimal, which is Basics teen binary, which is based to all these
bases pointers because they tend to be relatively large numbers since
they refer to memory ranges.
In memory is huge pointers.
Actually tend to be displayed in hexadecimal by default.
So one of the reasons that I had to basically turn it into it, I had
to force the watch window to turn it into an integer to show you.
The actual number is because the even if I don't have it set to
hexadecimal display, there's a menu here that can change everything to
access also, if I want to.
But even if I don't have it set to hexadecimal display.
The see, the visual studio debugger will always actually use
hexadecimal stay for pointers.
Anyway, so like I said, it's a little bit hard to read if you're not
used to reading Basics.
Dean.
Obviously, I'm not even that great at reading base, 16, but
fortunately, you rarely actually have to read pointers and be all that
explicit about it.
You, you know, if you want to, you can do arithmetic on them to even
find out sort of if two pointers are close to each other in that sort
of stuff.
So I'll be all sorts that we can do.
So, don't sweat it too much if you can't read hexadecimal, but
eventually through programming, if you're doing it at a low level and
you're seeing them enough fuel
Probably get a little bit familiar.
So anyway, that is the actual memory location in our procedures
virtual address space which is not actually physical memory.
That is where this value is actually stored.
Now, the interesting part about that is we can actually use this
little plus here because Visual Studio will let us see what is
actually in the memory location very easily by just opening it up and
you can see there it is.
There's the value 255.
So here is the value of our variable.
Here is the value of what's pointed at and since we know that we
We made this pointer point.
At that value.
They should be the same and they are.
And when I do this line of code here and you can see that test got
incremented by 1, it got incremented.
It wrapped 20 just like we saw yesterday, but now it also wrapped here
and that is the crucial thing to understand about.
Pointers.
This pointer is pointing at the same actual memory as this thing.
So anytime we change test the stuff pointed to, by test point to where
also change because they're the same thing.
Two ways of referencing the exact same piece of memory.
Okay, so hopefully that's very clear what's going on there.
Now, you can go a little bit further.
If you'd like, to inside the debug window.
There is a Windows thing here that you can go.
And you can find memory and much like the watch window.
There are a couple different kinds of memory.
Each one is the exact same type of window, but they gave you four of
them.
So, if I go to memory window, one, I can have one of those open and if
I go to memory window to it, is a
A different view of memory, they're different, but that the same
memory that we're looking at.
It's just, they decided to give us for Windows.
So, if I am to pull out this little guy here, this is the memory of
the computer as far as our processes contrast.
This is a virtual memory, not the physical memory, the virtual memory
of the computer.
And if I want to, I can look at this location.
I can take this value.
I can copy it, I can drop it on in here, paste and I can hit return.
And now, you can see over here.
We've got the location in memory of the thing that we wanted.
Right.
Now, this is each individual bite of the memory of our computer
displayed in hexadecimal.
This is just the other stuff that's around.
It's just a stuff that's around.
Hello, their memory.
We're all having a good day today.
So what I want you to be able to see here if I actually scroll a
little bit right now, 3, C, F9, a F3 C, F9 AF right there.
I'm going to leave the cursor on it.
So we can remember where it is.
That is the location of our special value.
Right?
And so if I go in here, one of the things that's kind of cool about
this.
Watch window is I can actually sort of change values in here and the
debugger, what the debugger will actually do.
My application is Frozen right now, so it can't do anything, but the
debugger can reach in to its memory and poke at it and change the
values out from under it, which is something, we'll probably use
during your service because kind of handy when you're debugging things
to be able to poke like that if I'm to poke a new value in there,
let's say 16, right?
You will notice that the memory changed there it is, right?
And remember, its hexadecimal base.
So 16 is 10, kind of kind of confusing.
I know, but that's how it goes.
But if we want to, we can make it a little easier on ourselves by
turning off hexadecimal display.
I think, I don't know if that's actually true unsigned display.
There it is.
Hey unsigned display 9af.
Where is that again?
We gotta find our memory.
We just go ahead and have it.
Do that for Boom.
So, there is our 9af.
Just like we wanted and you can see now there is the 16 I could change
it again.
And it changes, right?
Pretty cool, but it gets even cooler than that, because this is the
thing that I really love about.
See, I can do anything I want.
It's my program.
I wrote it.
I don't need Java.
Telling me what I can and can't do.
I decide what I can?
And can't do.
And the nice thing about see, is anything that you want to do, you can
do it.
So, if I want to, I can actually just take that pointer test pointer.
It's pointing to here, right?
If I want to, in the watch window, I can type.
You know, I can't type.
Eco, but I can type some things if I want to I can move it one bite
forward, right?
It's just pointing at one bite forward now and you can see that the
value that's actually in there, right is 204 which is exactly what
we'd expect because hey, there's the next bite 204 just like we
thought I can just mess with that value to.
You know, what, I want that value.
Be something else.
I want that value to be 12, Bingo.
It's 12.
So I have free Reign Over the memory.
That's my process is using.
I can do whatever I want, and
The only thing that I can't do is I can't start poking into memory
that I haven't told the operating system.
I'm using yet.
The reason that's the case is because basically what happens is at the
outset.
Like I said, the memory that we have for a prostitute virtual it's
this sort of fake address space that the operating system sets up and
maps to virtual memory for us.
So one of the things that we'll see and I'm not going to cover this in
the beginner stream.
This is going to be covered in the main handmade the hero stream, but
I'll just give you a little quick preview.
One of the things that we need to always do before we actually use
Is we have to tell the operating system that a particular thing, a
particular location is going to start being used by US, a particular
block of memory and say, hey, operating system.
We need two megabytes of memory right now.
Can you please give them back to us and say, yes, I have reserved
Reserve this part of the virtual address space for you and then we can
start using it.
But once we have that back in the options, we can do whatever we want.
And that is just an absolutely great thing about see, love.
It, can't give it up.
Now on to even more fun stuff.
I hope this isn't too confusing for people.
I think it's pretty straightforward when you actually just look at it
directly yourself and see that there's no mystery there, right?
There's no abstraction.
We're just dealing with the hardware.
We're dealing with what the hardware does and that makes things a lot
easier.
And yeah, there's an OS in our way in this doing some things that
maybe I wish it wouldn't do because we make it easier for me to show
you things directly.
But for the most part this is what programming is to me, honestly the
base level, it's me figuring out ways in which I want to do this kind
of stuff and having that connection back to the hardware is so good
for sir.
Types of programmers.
I'm one of them and I just really like having that ability to kind of
do it at that level.
And honestly, I think you know, there's people that are way further
down that line than me even, right.
I'm not even I'm not a beachhead in that.
I'm not a I'm not a super low programmer.
I'm a medium level programmer.
But even for me it really makes it into a much more fun and
interesting experience.
So, okay.
So what I want to say before we finish this is what is this memory
here that we had?
Because I just said that stuff.
About the operating system.
Well, we wrote this whole program and you know, I mean, where did we
ask the operations for memory?
We didn't ask for any memory.
I just said, you know, you heard the words come out of my mouth that
we can't use memory, the operations and give us.
So who gave us the memory?
Who told us that 3cf 9af was some location?
We could start writing to and that would work.
That was even going to be backed by physical memory at all or that,
you know, wouldn't just be riding off into some illegal location or
God knows what else could happen.
Right?
Well, the answer is
Is that we are writing to a very special location, a very special type
of location.
And called the stack and really, it's the same memory as anything
else.
There's nothing mysterious about it at a low level, but it has a very
special.
It's a very special thing in terms of programming because in
programming the stack is something that you don't explicitly asked
for.
It is something that you get automatically and the actual Act of
asking the operating system for it is actually done for you inside the
system.
So basically you
Don't micro right?
You don't actually write the code yourself that actually gets you the
memory from the stack.
That code is actually done for you by the compiler, where necessary
and so on.
So it's just built into the actual Act of compiling something in see.
Now that would not be true.
If you were writing and completely low-level code.
If you were writing completely level assembly, you would actually have
to even get the stack yourself and you'd get it in the same way that
we're going to show how to get memory later in the mainstream, but for
all intents and purposes, it
All you have to understand that this point is that the compiler is
doing the work for asking for the memory, but after that it's exactly
the same kind of memory.
So where does that happen?
And why?
Well, the way that it happens is, since everything that you write in
code, in C is built upon the notion that things go deeper and then
shallower in a very consistent way using the function calls that we
talked about on the very first day when I enter a function and I asked
for memory by
In a way that is just declaring a variable.
That's just saying, I want a variable please.
Well, what happens there is basically, it just starts grabbing
additional memory at the bottom or the top, depending on the direction
it grows.
We'll talk about that, a little later, but it starts grabbing memory
at the end.
Let's say of this thing called the stack, and the stack grows a little
bit, and when we call a new function, when we go into that function,
when it has a variable that it needs, it grows a little more.
So it's getting bigger and bigger.
But when we get to the end of a
In it returns to the previous function and then the stack shrinks to
remove the local variables that existed there.
So, basically what happens is you're talking almost like you if you
could imagine almost like the volume bar on some kind of a of an audio
device, right?
It kind of it grows, it grows it grows it grows it grows, but then as
they get spider, it goes back down.
And then it grows.
Grows grows because I've down.
And the important thing to understand about that and what makes it a
stack is nothing ever goes away from the middle of it.
It always goes from, you know, starting at nothing to getting bigger,
getting smaller bigger smaller always as one continuous chunk.
And the reason that can work, of course, is because of that call flow
of always, We call we return.
We call call, call return return call return.
We're always doing call return.
We can never call through some functions then get rid of the local
variable sum sum function in the middle, right?
We're never going to call a bunch of functions that have a middle
function.
Go away first.
Because what would those functions?
Turn to if I actually do that, right?
If I go here.
Void bar, right?
Wow, typing skills today, too much talking not enough typing Casey.
I hear you.
If I ever make one here, if I make a function bar here and here is my
variable, right?
I call that from this guy.
So now what we're going to do, right?
We're going to go in here and we're going to say test, right?
I want to call Foo I call Foo.
I hope you can see the little arrow there.
I don't know if it comes through on the chat.
Okay, we're going into Foo, you can see bar and now we go into bar.
We return back out to Foo.
We return back out to Main and we're done with the program.
Right?
It's always like Russian nesting dolls.
Again, it goes in and it comes back out.
One thing.
Actually, you know what to?
I'm just going to, I'm gonna do lazy internet here.
If someone knows how to make this highlight this lot, the line that
I'm on really boldly when we're stepping through, so people can watch
it on Lower quality streams easier, please email me because I would
love to set that up, but I don't know Visual Studio settings that
well, and I can see this little arrow just fine, but other people
might not be able to see it.
So if someone has an idea for that, please send it to me for next
stream, I'd love to get that in there.
So anyway, so that is how a stack works.
And what's so interesting about this is we can actually just see that
in action right now.
It doesn't have
The abstract for you, basically, what happens is we go in here and
we're going to look at test pointer and we're going to see where test
pointer was now, okay.
And we're going to set that to 55 value and we can see it right here.
There is our value, right?
So now the interesting thing, well, you know what?
Let me let me back up.
Just one step.
I want to make this a lot clearer.
So I'm going to go ahead and get rid of some of these things here that
we were playing with before.
So that I can show you something a little clearer.
So we're going to make Barbie 100.
I have that variable there.
We're going to make another variable here.
You call this food variable.
We're going to make that be 200 will call this bar variable.
There we go.
And we're going to have our test, which is out here.
Right?
Makes sense.
Pretty straightforward.
Oh, you know what?
I'm doing it again.
I always do those in line declarations.
And I apologize.
We're not.
It's nothing special.
It's just actually does the assignment on the same line as the
Declaration.
We will talk about it in eventually.
It'll be fine.
But you get the idea.
There we go, separate lines.
Now.
Everyone's happy.
Okay, so I'm going to go ahead.
Run this and we get down and we stopped at our familiar location.
And I'm going to look at that address.
Going to say, please give me the address where we're going to assign
it.
We step over that line and we see the 255.
There it is.
Just like what we wanted, but now we can see a little bit more when we
step into Foo right here I go.
I'm going to set this food variable to equal to 200.
And so now what should be happening, if the stack thing that I said is
true that I just told you about, right?
I should be able to find where it's going to stick that.
You and it should be close by because all we did was kind of grow a
little bit there.
So, let's see if we can find it.
I don't know if it'll actually save it for us.
To do that is Foo variable.
It is at 79 T.
So, whereas 790, 790 would be right there.
So there it is, right.
You can actually see it right there and our previous value that we
were looking at before the test burner value was 87, F, which is right
down here.
Right?
And it's at zero because we wrapped it.
So, there is the value that we had written to in this function.
That was where it was on the stack.
And then
Here is the next location on the stack.
Now, you may notice that there is full banana cake stuff happening
here.
Like where did all this other stuff happened?
Why did it, why did put them so far apart?
If the stock is just growing in the answer to that is actually because
there's all kinds of shenanigans that actually go on with the stack,
in debug mode, when we're which is what we're compiling in here, where
you can, you know, basically the compiler has settings, which puts
stuff in there that try to help you from making a mistake.
Take it'll basically put in stack frame checking and padding regions
and all these other things to try and help you from errors where you
might be writing if you're actually doing.
So this pointer manipulation that I was doing.
So a bunch of this stuff, we don't need to worry about now, but
basically what's happening is when it pushes the stack even though it
really only needed to go a little bit to store this one, simple
integer, which is only 32 bits or whatever.
We only need to start.
That one thing.
The reason that it was actually the reason that it was actually
pushing so much stuff on is because of all that extra stuff that
happens.
So I have maybe just a little bit of time left before I go to the next
thing that I want to talk about.
So I'm just going to see if quickly and this the reason I say messy of
quick links is I don't use visual studio for compiling, hardly ever at
all like I saying before.
So it's going to be a little hard for me to find the right thing to
set here.
But if I can go in here and set to an optimized build, I may be able
to show you that stack a little more concisely.
So I'm going to see about that.
I'm going to try to compile the
And hopefully it didn't in line.
Everything here for me, but we'll see if it actually did or not.
It probably did, didn't it?
Yeah, it did.
It did.
Unfortunately which, you know, the the optimizer is going to be rather
aggressive.
Yeah.
So what I might be able to do is I might be able to turn that the just
the stack stuff off in the debug build so I can show you.
So I said I'll spend a little more time on it, but then I'm going to
move ahead because I don't want to get bogged down in that.
And I don't know where they put.
All these things in the in the GUI.
So let's take a look inside.
See passes optimizations.
Let's see if I enable intrinsic functions favor sighs sweet omit frame
pointers is there like that frame pointers is really going to do it.
I want something more than that string pulling around timeline.
Very basic runtime checks could be in there for security check.
I don't know.
I think this is going to be it's probably one of these.
I am not going to actually try it.
I think it's a little too much.
So we're going to let we're going to let that wait till a different
time when I have time to look it up ahead of time, which is where I
actually set it in there.
Just make it stop doing that.
But suffice to say, what is happening in there, is that it's pushing
extra stuff on the stock.
So that is where all our memory is coming from.
And one thing that you may have noticed, is when I ran this program,
multiple times, the memory that we looked up the last time.
Like, remember last time it was there, this time our memory is
incomplete.
A different place.
And you may wonder why that is that seems kind of odd, right?
Because I don't know aren't computers deterministic.
Why is it randomly picking memory?
The answer is because of security used to be the case that if I ran
the program multiple times, the memory would be in the same place and
this was actually very convenient for debugging and sometimes it's a
good idea to shut off the feature.
I'm about to talk about specifically because it makes me bugging
easier because all your memory will be in the same place, but what
happens nowadays?
Is that because the fixed layout of things in their virtual memory
space, when they would run allowed hackers to be able to do stuff
like, know exactly where an important thing in memory for that process
was and use code exploits to go.
Grab.
What's in that memory or reset.
What's in that memory?
Or do other things like this or to know the place to Branch to encode
to do things?
Basically, it allowed them extra flexibility that they wouldn't have
had otherwise because of that it became a thing that they do now where
they randomize where your program actually runs.
I think it's called address randomization extension at, let's take a
look.
It's got a name in Windows.
They gave it a name, address space layout randomization.
And basically, what that does is it makes sure that your code, and
your stack and your allocations and everything come back at different
locations, somewhat randomly.
I guess I'm not sure what their actual scheme for randomizing it is,
but it makes it so that it's harder for hackers to exploit that.
So that is why we get different members, excuse time.
And we may look at turning that off in the future just on the dev.
Of side of things so that we don't have to actually deal with those
in.
They'll be at the same place which will make me, make it a little
easier for me to show things.
So that is how that works.
Hopefully, you're very comfortable with this now and you've seen.
It's not that mysterious to understand these things.
It's really straightforward.
We can just look at what's happening in the memory.
We can look at how our program is working in.
I'll be honest with you, every single thing.
We do starting Monday, everything we do for the year or two, that it
takes us to make a huge awesome game.
That's going to be cool.
Every last thing we do is just that
Like that is the only thing you really have to understand is we've got
pointers to memory and we're going to fuss with the values.
I know it sounds crazy.
But that is all we will do.
And so I really want to drill these kind of fundamentals in for anyone
who's unfamiliar with them because once you get them, you're like
super powerful.
You can do anything you want and you can build your own anything you
want.
And from then on you don't have to deal with other people's
distractions.
If you want abstractions, you can make your own and you can make what
up, what the rules are.
You don't have to follow someone else's rules.
You don't have to follow what the people who design Java thought were
good.
You can follow
You think is good and that to me is very empowering and it's, it's
really great.
So the other thing that I wanted to do today, besides kind of showing
you where that's actually going, so you can understand understand what
that is, is to quickly mention that we talked before, when we went to
the to the assembly, right?
We did this.
And I went to the assembly and I said that we're going to talk about.
As I mentioned, again, a little later this number right here.
It's also a hexadecimal location in memory.
So if you want to, you can actually copy this piece of
Thing as well.
And you can go to one of those memory viewer windows that I was
talking about and you can paste in the location of the code.
So you can actually say, oh, I want to see my code now, right?
Oh, and I awesome as I say that apparently that's a total lie.
Apparently, you can't actually look at the code, presumably because
that is actually not allowed by the memory protection of this
particular thing.
All right, do I actually go unprotect the memory?
6:44.
I can't I can't do it.
Okay, so I'll simply say why you weren't able to do that.
And then maybe I'll go do that for the next for the stream tomorrow
night.
So we can actually look at it.
So I am thwarted by the virtual memory system.
Basically, what happens is if you have actual extra memory, that's
executed in the old days again and even not too long ago, maybe even
10 years ago.
Let's say five years ago.
I don't know.
I would have that would've worked.
And I've done that before.
I haven't done it recently.
From, you know, I've actually done it recently with code that but it
I worked there for a totally different reason that I won't go into.
So, basically, the reason that I can't do that now he's again, because
of security and what they often do at least I'm assuming, that's why I
have to go investigate to verify this way, but I'm assuming, that's
why what they actually do with the virtual memory system, is each of
those pages that I talked about and we'll talk about this a lot in the
mainstream actually, but each of those pages actually has things on
it.
That the CPU understands that are called flags and those Flags allow
Access Control.
They basically allow you to Mark a page as being readable by a
process.
Is writable by a process, executable by a process and what they do now
to prevent again, more hacking problems is they will Mark the pages of
your code that our executable as not being readable or writable.
So what happens is you actually take that page, you know, whatever
that page is that you're trying to exit the codon and you make it to
the process itself can even access it and that helps it to make it so
that you can't do Shenanigans where you write things into code to
change what the code is doing when you're when you're hacking.
So yeah.
Sorry, that was a little bit of
Let down.
I was kind of hoping to show you that but it's okay.
You wouldn't actually see anything except for the binary encoding of
the Assembly Language, but it would be a nice thing to see.
So maybe I'll just go ahead and write a little app sometime, not on
the stream, but just something that actually virtual and protects the
page for you so that we can go see that some of the time, anyway, wha
very disappointing, but security, I can appreciate its necessary, you
know, security is good.
Hawk, soaring is bad.
So,
now, we get to
The very special, very exciting part that I was alluding to on the
Twitter, which is that we have pictures today.
We have pictures.
So instead of just, just the code window.
I'm going to do something now which which will see if it works on the
string.
And hopefully it works on the stream.
You guys have to tell me if it does or doesn't, but we are going to
get a little bit Pulp Fiction here, and we are going to bring out the
Gimp.
Yes, it is in gentlemen, gimp the image manipulation program canoe
image manipulation program, whatever it stands for.
So I I mentioned this on the, on the, on the Twitter's on tweeting and
what I said is today's stream was going to feature the motherboard
from the trailer and one of the things I did when I was trying to, you
know, I've been I've been sort of working on this project.
Getting this project going for about a month or two.
I don't remember how long since people asked me to start doing
streams.
Basically.
I was trying to do it.
Could do for streamers, like I got a good idea.
I think, what I want to do, two for the trailer, was to kind of make
something exciting, that would sort of get across the handmade part of
things, but I couldn't really show anything in the code because the
whole point of it was we're going to write all the code from scratch
together.
So I can't start the project until after the projects already live.
And so, how do you make a trailer?
So I decided to do it by assembling hardware and of course, I love to
assemble Hardware.
I've assembled many machines.
This is one of the few machines I didn't assemble because it was a
machine from from work, from rad.
And it was built by, I guess Del it was ordered from or whatever.
But I build all the machines that I use myself and it's not hard to
do.
Probably do a little bit on that in later in the series for people who
want to build their own machines.
Super easy.
If you like order parts from new eggs and assemble them, but this is a
photograph that I took today at work of the motherboard that I used in
the trailer.
And you can see what I've done here.
Is, I've removed the heatsink from the processor.
So this is the CPU.
That's that's the actual Intel CPU.
I
Remember exactly what processor that particular motherboard had in it.
I think it was a Coke or to do quad.
I think it was a Core 2 quad.
I'm going to say that it was a core to Claude, but I don't actually
know that was Core 2 quad, but I think it was a Core 2 quad anyway,
and what you can see here, is that the thermal this, this is the stuff
in here.
Is that gray stuff is thermal grease.
It's basically something that allows the heatsink to bind to the
processor.
It fills in the little crevices, in the metal so that it can vent heat
more easily.
Get it.
Get it out because the processor
Sir, obviously gets very hot.
And so I've removed the heat sink so you can see the CPU and I put a
ruler on it.
And you might ask.
Why did you want to measure the motherboard?
Like, you can see?
How big is the motherboard?
I don't know.
It's 20 cm or something, right?
It's not.
It's not that big.
It's pretty small.
And so why did you want to measure that and what did you want to talk
about?
Well, what I want to talk about it, since now, I've introduced you,
the concept of memory.
I wanted to tell you where the memory is and why you should care where
the memory is.
So, here's a memory, these big things here.
These things that you put in.
And if anyone's out, there is built a computer themselves.
They know what they are.
There's these long kind,
Text a slot in there.
They're a sort of a commodity type of Hardware that you buy separately
and you can put in a machine and machines have some number of slots.
And basically what has to happen is every time the CPU wants to read
or write from that memory.
It has to go a long wires over to here.
It has to look in here at, you know, it has to get some bits out.
And those bits have to be sent back and they're sent back over
something called a bus, you know, not a very creative name, but a bus,
something that transfers B back and forth, right?
Right.
So that's the physical thing that actually happens in your computer is
the processor has to go out along with some wires on the bus.
It's got a use, a memory controller, which is thing that does this,
it's got to do that stuff.
Get the memory, bring it back and then it can operate on it.
Right.
Now.
What I want to get across to you here is that this is a non-trivial
problem.
Now, again, when you're working at very high levels of abstraction,
you don't necessarily think about this that much, but this is a long
way to go to get
That memory.
Okay.
That's far.
I don't know how far that is because we don't know exactly how the
routing goes on this motherboard.
Look, I don't actually know the route that it takes to get there.
But even if it just went straight from Center to Center, let's say
that's like a 10 right there on the thing and that's like an 18,
right?
So that's 8 cm that it has to go to get those bits and you're like,
eight centimeters its electricity.
It goes 8 centimeters in no time, right?
It's fast.
It's super fast.
Who cares.
Casey, you know, who?
Who cares?
And the answer is that physics cares?
Unfortunately physics cares, one time.
I got some friends at Intel and I, you know, I'll ask them.
I don't know a damn thing about Hardware, man.
I don't know anything about Hardware, right?
I don't know how to design a chip.
I don't know how they work these days.
I I watched an intro lecture from MIT course where that was taught by
game guy named I think Gill Pratt and it was like a how to build let
you know, Adder circuits and stuff.
And so I can sort of build an Adder circuit maybe if I'm
Real lucky, but I probably forgot most of it.
So so I don't know anything about modern Harbor.
They're so complicated and fantastically wild.
I certainly don't pretend to know anything about that.
But I'm just going to show you what a Layman who knows nothing about
Hardware can can know about memory and why it's a hard problem, right?
So, I don't know.
I got no special knowledge.
I'm in the same boat as you here.
I do nothing.
But let's just take the fastest thing in the world that we know about
the speed of light, right?
How fast is it?
Well, that's how fast it is.
It's 300 million meters per second right now.
Sounds pretty fast, right?
But there's a catch to that.
Even if we were the fastest thing in the world.
What is this number right here.
That is the clock speed of the CPU that's in this machine.
It is 3.2 GHz.
So what's 3.2 GHz, right.
Oops, didn't you do that?
3.2 GHz, right?
Is 3.2 x 1024.
So that would be khz x, 1024, which would be MHz times, 10.
Or so now we are actually up to gigahertz, right?
So there's the number.
So, take a look at that number for a second, right?
And now take a look at this number for a second.
It's not looking so great anymore.
And if we actually have Google do this math and I think it can
actually do it.
Directly speed of light.
/ 3.2 GHz, right.
We end up with that number nine.
Point three centimeters.
Okay.
Now just to be clear.
What a gigahertz is, is that's the smallest.
It's called a clock basically CPUs have sort of ticks where they do
their operations.
So basically inside of one clock, right?
One single tick of the CPU is the fastest that it really can do
anything.
It can't do stuff at faster than a clock.
Sometimes it can do two things in one clock cycle.
If it has started multiple of them, going
Work an issue multiple things, but they the results won't come in for,
at least one clock cycle.
So like, but between the time, whereas to start something and the time
when asked to finish, it's going to be like at least one clock
usually.
Unless there's crazy Shenanigans going on in there.
So what that means is that the CPU can actually at least possibly do
one thing or possibly a couple things depending on the circumstances.
It can do.
One thing at that speed 3.2, you know 3.2 billion times a second.
So what I'm going to look at here, when I divided the speed of light
by that speed, which is 3.2 billion.
I wanted to see how fast does light go in the amount of time that it
would take the processor to do one thing and the answer was, you know,
something like nine centimeters.
Now, I suck at how resign and I also suck at math.
So I may have typed soon wrong or whatever.
But I think that's about right people out there who are good at math.
You're welcome to correct me.
One of the things that people often say is that people who are good at
can
Programming a good at math is not true.
I suck at man.
Anyway, if we go back to our ruler here, have that 99 is like there to
there.
That's the speed of light.
It's like, can only go from here to there in that time.
It can't even get back in the time.
It takes the CPU to do something.
Okay.
So when you count up all the actual logic that has to happen in the
fact that it's not a straight line and it's got to go through stuff in
here.
Right?
And it's got to go through stuff in here.
That's crazy expensive.
Civ.
Even if it all, even if there were, it was literally a part of photon
could not make it there and back in the time, it takes the processor
to actually do something.
And the reason that I think it's important for you to understand that
is because that is why memory is such a big deal in optimization.
Now, going out and getting things from memory is a huge deal.
And what to finish the story I have friends at Intel and one of the
things that I asked one of them to time, I just said, you know, why is
memory so slow?
Still why is memory such a
I'll neck.
What's the actual hang up?
And the answer that came back was?
Wires, they were like the amount of time.
It just it's physically.
Far away is the problem and you know, no surprise.
One of the things that people are working on technologically right
now, for future Generations CPUs.
I don't know if it will happen or not.
But certainly I think you know I'm video is doing it and Intel's doing
a bunch of people working on it.
It's something called stacked D Ram, which is basically Ram that sits
on the CPU so it doesn't have to go out here to get it.
And so the question is can they get sufficient amounts of ram, you
know stuck on this right on the CPU?
So that, that, that sort of speed can can be, can be improved.
Right?
And so what, I also want to say here is, I got another picture.
This is the same motherboard, but it's a rotated at 90 degrees and
placed the, the the ruler going the other way.
So, this piece right here, that thing that is where the graphics card
sits.
You plug the graphics card into their.
All right.
So if you want to send something to the graphics card, well you got to
do it's got to go out to the men.
We first probably unless there's direct bus stuff that happens to the
graphics card, which would be you know, here to here.
Let's say or something like that.
It's got to go out to the memory and then it's good.
Got to go to the graphics card.
Probably it's going to have to do some round trips there or if it
could do some kind of weird bus Mastery.
So I don't even like I said, don't know how our design not gonna
pretend I know but basically you're dealing with something that
operates in this triangle and that's huge again speed of light again,
huge problem.
So that is why you have also huge bottlenecks in terms of the speed at
which you can
Actually get something to the graphics card in back is also a huge
problem.
There's all these sorts of things that conspire against you when
you're talking about these physical separations and it makes things
pretty hard to do.
Now the the final thing I wanted to say before I move to the next
picture we've got here is there's two things to keep in mind.
I'm going to talk about them a lot in the mainstream.
So I'll explain them more later in a lot more detail, but there's two
things, one is called latency.
Look at the handwriting and two is called throughput, right?
Also closely related bandwidth.
These are words that you want to know, and what these basically do.
The reason that I'm just sort of bringing them up.
I'm not going to Define them right now.
Really.
I'm just gonna sort of throw it out.
There is that there's two things we might want to know when we start
talking about, man.
I got it.
I'm do a lot to erase that out.
So latency and bandwidth.
The reason Earth latency and throughput.
The reason we care about this because there's two things wouldn't want
to know, when we're talking about things like getting stuff around in
this magical triangle, whatever there's how long it would take to do
it round trip and that's latency, right?
There's basically how long it
For me to start something and finish it the same thing.
But as you might imagine, let's say I sent one thing off and I'm going
off to memory and I start that thing off and maybe that thing gets to
about here so far.
It's on its way there, but then I start another thing.
So by the time, the first thing gets to hear the second thing is now
here and then in so on right, I can basically, I can I
Send more than one thing out potentially before I actually get all the
things back.
So, by the time, this thing actually gets all the way around.
I could have had maybe hundreds of things going through this triangle
before I even get the first one back and that is the throughput part.
Right?
So latency is how long it takes one thing to get all the way around.
And that is basically, if you want to know, I need to go get a
particular location in memory right now, and I'm going to wait until
it comes back.
That is what will determine how fast that can happen.
Yeah, but there's other things where it's like, I got a ton of
different things in memory.
I gotta go get, I'm going to ask for a mall and then, as they come
back and start using them, then throughput becomes a thing, which is a
measure of how fast things can go through this at Peak congestion.
Basically, at when I'm shoving as many things through it.
How many of them can I get back a second basically?
Right, would be like the measure of the bandwidth of the memory,
right?
And so typically, what happens because the because of the fact that
the physical distances here are large, is that the latency is
For to memory, but the bandwidth, the throughput can actually be quite
good because we can just send lots of things down.
So we just make sure we design our memory to be able to send back tons
of things at once, tons, tons of things, you know, in cereal.
So that basically, when we asked for tons of things, we can get back,
tons of things, much more, you know, sort of in burst, right?
So overlapping, what we do with memory ends up being a big deal in
programming specifically, because this physical distance part makes it
so that the latency is always bad.
But the throughput can go up over time and memory can get faster
throughput.
Even as the latency cannot improve because the because of the speed of
light barriers is like that because there's just nothing you can do to
speed it up, right?
And again, not a highway engineer.
It's not a great explanation.
It's just enough to allow you to think about it.
And I would highly encourage people that are interested in this sort
of stuff to go read online, do some searches search on Google and just
sort of explore yourself.
And you can probably find some good resources that go into more detail
and get the and get the specifics of this more right than I am.
About like exactly what's happening on say, a modern card last picture
for the day, and then we will go to the Q&A will close.
These guys.
This is the CPU itself.
This is a picture of What's called the dye and the dye is basically
the actual CPU, as it exists.
When Intel Fabs, the thing.
This is basically like some kind of a weird.
I don't even know, electron microscope or some kind of fancy mess up
by not.
That's not that magnified.
I don't know.
This is some low-res thing.
I downloaded off.
The Tom's Hardware basically, it's basically what an Intel chip looks
like, and that's maybe a little bit too to zoom.
This is what an Intel chip looks like nowadays.
And I want to talk to you just real quickly about what some of this
stuff is and why you care.
Now, on the chip itself.
These are basically the sections of the chip.
You can see the korres.
This is a four core machine, core core, core core.
And so, remember, I talked about the very first day.
I think I talked about the fact that a single processor can actually
have many logical pieces.
Which are actually operating as if they were separate processors in
some sense.
And that's what these cores are.
They are capable of running processes, totally in parallel, but don't
really have to wait for each other or swap things in and out.
Each one of these things can be executing stuff the time.
So each one of these cores has two things on it that are
memory-related.
It has something called an L1 cache and it has something called an L2
cache.
And those stand for level level.
One is closest.
Level 2 is a little further away and then there's this thing out here
called L3 cache which is the level 3 cache and the
and I want to bring these up just briefly before we end the stream is
because since that memory latency is so huge that time that it takes
to go out and get something back.
One of the things that processors try to do nowadays, is they try to
minimize the amount of time.
They actually have to ever talk to it and they want to be able to do a
lot of the work they do without ever actually talking the memory.
So what they've always done since for a very long time, is they've had
these caches, which are essentially sort of like, the Stacked dram
thing.
I was talking about.
They're not, they aren't stuck to beer am, but there's
Of the same thing.
They're pieces of memory that are right on the chip.
So they can be much much faster because the physical difference, the
physical distance between the core and the actual storage for the B is
much closer.
And so what can happen is when a piece of when a core needs to access
piece of memory.
It will ask this L3 cache.
Do you have it?
And if the L3 cache says yes, it just gets it from the L3 cache.
If it doesn't then it will have to go out to memory and that's what
this memory controller pieces here.
The memory controller will go ask for it and go get it out.
But a lot of times it can just fit in the L3 cache things that stay in
the L3, Cache can be much much faster because I read on the Chip And
they never have to go to the main memory.
Similarly, the L2 cache in L1 caches, which are on each individual
core are even faster than that.
And so, basically, what they are is, they're these sort of L1 cache is
pretty small.
L2, caches little bigger L3, caches bigger still.
I think it healthy caches 8 MB now on a chip.
Probably, I don't know.
Depends on the chip obviously, but there's, you know, that's a, that's
a ballpark size that it might be on a modern ship.
And so, basically, this
Cascading series of local storage that you can use in order to make it
so that you don't have to constantly pay that huge memory hit.
And so, one of the things that we're also going to have to think about
when we do the mainstream, when we do the handmade hero stream is
where constant have to be aware of, what's in the L1 cache?
What's in the L2 cache and what's in the L3 cache and there's limited
things we can do to figure out exactly what's going on there because
we don't have the ability to really inspect that much of the CPU, but
there are things like performance counters and stuff.
We can use to see how often we are working.
Going inside those caches and how often were failing in that sort of
stuff.
And we can also tell by how long our program takes to run.
A lot of times how badly it is doing utilizing those caches.
So I won't go into too much detail there.
That's really all I want to say is want to make you aware of it, but
that's basically how the memory structure works.
And so these things are not additional memory these caches for your
machine.
They are, you know, there are additional storage in that sense, but
they actually don't represent more memory.
What they represent is basically places where you can store
Copy of what is in the main memory or will be later in the main memory
in a local way that you can quickly access.
And then it later it gets dumped out to that main memory it gets
spilled out there.
And so, you know, so that's basically how memory actually works.
Is it always goes through this, this kind of caching scheme and to
some level.
You can even think of there being even bigger catching, seems you can
think of it as, as sort of this huge tear of memory.
We're basically what you're doing, you know, I might, if I may use my
Mac,
Mad gimp skills here, to expand this image.
I know this is, this is crazy.
What we're doing here?
Full crazy, but I'm going to try it.
I'm going to totally try it.
Here we go.
So what happens here is, you know, inside the core is right.
Let's say there's the L1 cache, right?
That's not, you can't see that Casey.
What are you doing?
That's the wrong color.
Let's go to here.
All right.
So there's the L1 cache in this core and there's an L2 cache in this
core and then the Z L3 cache which is here and then there's main
memory, right?
Which is here.
Main ma'am.
Okay, so the court needs to access piece of memory.
Last the L1 cache L1 cache doesn't have it as 2.
L 2 cache, L2 cache and L3 caches and have it either.
It has two main memory to get it, the main memory, right?
We'll return it back and go through these caches but there's even an
additional layer.
We could think about, I told you about the virtual memory, right?
And the physical memory.
This is physical, right?
There's another thing here, which is the hard drive, right?
There's the actual hard drive or the SD drive from the computer.
The actual Drive, the store stuff.
It could be that the operating system never actually met this thing
into physical memory.
It had a victim it for some reason, and it actually started out to the
hard drive.
And in that case, instead of the core ever, even actually going
through this process yet.
It's going to have two operating systems going to have to raise.
It will actually happen to CPU.
Will notice that the page is not even resident in memory anymore?
Through the virtual memory system.
It's the operating system will intercede using some kind of an
interrupt or something.
You know, I don't even pretend to know exactly how Windows does he
think.
So, basically, it will cause some kind of a an exception that it will
then go and the operation will take over, it will go out to the hard
drive.
It'll bring that page into main memory, right?
It'll then go back and allow your private place to keep running.
At which point you can fill the L3 cache in the L2 and L1 caches.
There's a thing called inclusivity here, which may determine which
one's those get filled and tons of other details, but you get the
idea.
I won't belabor the point that the, there's just this huge sort of
again, Russian nesting doll of memory.
That's each one's a different speed and they get slower and slower as
you go.
And if you have to spill out to the hard drive.
Well, that's a huge bad news.
So we never ever want to do that in a performance application.
If we can, if we can avoid it.
We always want to at least be going to main memory and hopefully want
to be in these caches as often as we can.
So hopefully that's given you a little taste of how your, how your CPU
works.
And we've related back here.
Hopefully, you understood the stuff.
I was showing you with the memory, how, you know, it's
All stuff.
You can inspect and that memory.
Is just the memory in your machine and the virtual address space is
something that gets mapped and translated by the CPU.
So you've seen it all today.
You've basically seen everything and everything.
I'm going to do, even in the two streams for the practice streams, for
Saturday, and Sunday.
Everything I'm going to do from now.
On is just how we manipulate that memory, every last thing,
everything.
It's all about that.
So I hope that is something that that you will keep in mind and that
will be easy for you to relate to.
As we get more comfortable with it.
It'll just be something that you just think about it.
And no, and you won't really have to worry about us.
Be part of your daily programming in and you'll be good.
So, thank you, everybody.
We've got 230 people, I guess here, which is crazy.
I even this was not the regular scheduled time because on Monday, I'm
in Friday's I think I'm going to probably move the the times around to
give people another times as a chance and also because, you know, if I
want to go out with my wife on Friday night, for example, I want to
have nights free occasionally.
So, so if that in the schedule time and all these people showed up,
that was amazing.
Thank you so much for coming.
It's been a real pleasure talking about this stuff with you.
And if you'd like to stick around for the Q&A, I'm going to do about.
I'm going to end the Q&A at 7:30, but I will be happy to do about 20
minutes of Q&A.
So I'm going to stop the recording and I'm going to start it again,
but for those of you who are on the stream of wanna stick around for
the Q&A, please.
I found that's much easier said, please go at senior ettore, just type
in at senior ettore Hoops.
See if I can actually get that somewhere.
That's easier to see on the chat.
Please do at senior ettore to
label something as a question because people like to talk to
themselves.
It makes it hard for me to scan for the questions.
So please do that.
So I will see it and we will start that right now, okay.