Okay, we are back with the Q&A for the final intro to see session the
test sessions.
We've been doing.
I think they went pretty well.
Obviously, it's hard to cram.
Everything you might want to know about, see into just 5 days, 5 hours
or something.
I don't know.
We got six hours of time.
So I strongly suspect that.
You know, if I really maybe at some point based on the response to the
handmade hero thing, which has been much much more enthusiastic than
any possible thing.
I was expecting.
I was expecting anyone to even notice the stream for months.
Basically, since there is so much interest at some point.
I probably should go through and do a real full intro to see that's
like,
You know, four weeks long or something like that so that people who
literally have no idea how to program or how to program in, C can come
to it and actually learn absolutely everything instead of kind of me
quickly going through things and showing you okay here's examples of
all the stuff that we're going to be doing and now good luck, but
hopefully it was good for some people and it's I was trying to I think
maybe it would was hopefully a little bit helpful for people who kind
of know programming already but maybe don't know all the see stuff
with like, you know pointers and how they work and where stuff goes on
the stack and executables and stuff because that's kind of stuff.
Probably that, you know, you wouldn't necessarily know if you program
in a different language that worked differently or an environment that
work differently and so on so forth.
So anyway, thanks everyone for coming to the Q&A at senior.
Ettore would be the thing to put at senior ettore in the chat window.
If you want me to see it for the questions.
And since this is a Sunday, I don't think I have to go until like 5:30
or something.
So we can do Q&A Q&A for a long time today.
If we want to we'll see how it goes.
Speaker asks, have you ever found use for a bit Fields?
The answer is, I don't know that I've ever used bit Fields myself.
Much bit fields, are basically a thing for those of you don't know,
where you basically allowed to Define, sort of struct almost, but
where the structs have a specific number of bits allocated to each
member that's less than a bite often times.
And I don't tend to use them only because I like to be more explicit
in my code.
And I don't know what the compiler is going to do.
And I do that bit Fields, the compiler is going to generate some
stuff, and I'd rather just hand code it, usually, but there, I mean, I
do do things that you could do in bit Fields.
I just usually hand code them.
So, yes, I mean, I could easily use bit Fields.
I just don't tend to, but they're useful.
So in watch the Expressions, typing X comma, B, when an input variable
X is initialized, will allow you to view the values in binary.
Does it actually?
Or is that only if you're on the newer version?
That's what we were trying to figure out earlier in the Stream.
So y comma B.
Yeah, it doesn't work.
So I think that I think they added that later.
So hopefully in the mainstream will be able to do that because I'm
going to switch to 2013 Community Edition in the mainstream, but the
problem is, I'm still, I'm using the one that was on this computer.
That was
Original one that was license for this computer because I didn't know
I needed to use some of the I want to be able to, like it's used the
register window and stuff.
So I didn't want to use express for some of the things we were doing.
But now that I know that it's actually free to just use the newer one.
I'll be using a newer one and then X comma B should hopefully work, we
hope.
Idiocracy regarding your diagram.
A virtual page is just going to physical memory.
Does the virtual memory address space itself?
Reside in physical memory.
You said that the VMA s goes out to his car to get data.
So, is there a section of physical memory set aside for the VMA, s,
and the rest of physical memory is made up of data.
Retrieved from the disk.
The diagram is a bit.
Incestuous confusing to me at the moment.
Yes, that diagram showing off the best diagram.
So, here's what I'll say.
If I remember correctly, and I may very well not so you should
probably should probably go.
Look this up if you really care.
In a Windows, the page table which basically tells it all the stuff
that thing you're asking about the thing that that understands the
virtual memory address space for processes.
I believe the page table is not itself virtual in earlier versions of
Windows even like Windows 7, I think possibly even in Windows 8.
I don't know.
So, basically the virtual memory
Map.
The thing that says we're all the pages should be and what how they're
allocating stuff.
I believe that is resides in physical memory in Windows typically, but
I believe they are now moving towards a scheme or have already moved
to this game where that itself can be virtual.
So it's like it's like two levels deep so you can paid some of it out.
And I don't know if they've done that or are doing that.
I don't pay much attention to the windows kernel advances of recent
year.
So, the answer is, I believe, it's normally in physical memory on most
versions of windows that are running.
Currently, but I think they were going to try to make that virtual
because you do run into places now with 64-bit addressing and
computers, having so much memory you do run into situations.
Now where you want more, you want to be able to not be limited by the
page table.
You don't want the page table to be this hard, constraint that starts
eating up a ton of physical memory because you can't get, you can't
move it out.
So I don't know.
So, I think that's true.
But I really don't know.
You should ask a Windows kernel expert and they would be able to tell
you.
You could also ask a Linux kernel expert, how they do theirs because
every operating system has to deal
With this problem of that.
So,
Symmetry what happened to the nice background?
I don't know what that means.
I'm sorry, if the stack lives in cash on the CPU.
What happens at the stack outgrows, the size of the cache?
Okay.
So the stack doesn't live in the cache on the CPU.
The stack lives in memory, just like anything else.
The stack is in your virtual memory space.
So when the stack grows, it's growing in regular memory.
Now the CPU since it happens to be executing code, that's using the
stack.
The stack is almost always hot in the cache.
So you usually
ER, at least the top of the stack is in the CPUs cache usually, but
it's all backed by memory.
It's not, it's not living in the cache.
The stack is the data that's actually living in memory in the virtual
memory address space of your of your running code.
Now, you may be thinking of the I cash, which I referenced and the I
cash is for code, not data.
The I cash is actually just the instructions.
The actual Assembly Language instructions, that the CPU is going to
execute that our code got compiled down to not the data.
The code that gets also back in memory.
That's all in the virtual memory address space.
It just gets pulled into the I cash when it's being executed because
the
it basically doesn't want to have to keep doing the work of like
blowing it out into Micro Ops and whatever else it needs to do.
You mentioned in the pre stream that you're crazy casting pointer with
demonstration.
Last June was undefined Behavior.
Why is this so I like I said, I usually go by what compilers do not
what the spec does because I hate the spec.
The spec is garbage and it drives me insane because I feel like they
do really bad things with a spec a lot and often times it gets worse
instead of better.
So I don't actually know that it's undefined a paper.
Someone said that it was undefined behavior and it probably is.
And the reason for that is that oftentimes technically it's undefined.
To cast things to different sizes that aren't allocated in the same
pool.
Like.
I don't think you're technically always allowed to cast something from
say, you know, a struct to a short that was randomly in it or
something.
If you don't use a short that was actually in the struck.
I don't know.
So I'm not sure.
It may be that it is actually defined but it could also be undefined.
It doesn't matter because it always works and that is really the
majority of what I usually care about is what actually works.
Works and if compiler stopped supporting that, I would not use those
compilers anymore.
Like, that's totally unacceptable to me.
There had better.
Be a switch in the compiler.
That make sure I can always get a pointer to memory and do whatever I
want and if you can't do that, that is the end of me using your
language period.
Are there system calls or something that lets you tell the OS to load
your code into physical memory?
Instead of the lazy page faulting thing.
I don't actually know.
If there's a way to tell Windows to do that in some kind of General
sense, but what I can tell you is there are ways of you doing all
kinds of shenanigans that do involve specifically telling windows.
So, you could, if you want to, let me see here.
So here, for example, is a function called virtual lock and what
virtual lock does, is virtual, lock takes a base address.
So somewhere a memory pointer and a size, which is so, some amount of
memory, and what it will do is it will just full-on lock that into
physical memory, so that it can't be swapped out anymore.
Like, I believe period.
I don't know if there's conditions where if it was really in a panic,
it could do it.
But for the most part, it means don't swap this out.
And so, you can actually go.
If you wanted to start manually, virtually locking Pages down.
If you're just like, do not ever Swap this two disc ever.
You can do that.
It's not usually.
Good idea to do that but you could so there's other things like that
to you can do if you're really trying to force the operating system to
play by your rules.
Is the C runtime Library different from the standard C library?
Well, there's the standard C++ library and then there's the standard C
library and those are different.
But yeah, the C runtime library and standard C library.
I think are just there should be two terms of the same thing.
They're just like, you know, F open and F right and stuff like that.
Are standard, C library, things stuff that C++ my library.
Like the STL that's in the C++ standard library and those are
different.
There's a difference between the CCC library in C++ standard.
But yeah, that standard Library versus runtime Library.
Think should be the same thing.
Why do you prefer knr style brackets?
Oh, so, yeah, like I was kind of saying white space is always
optional, so you can do things.
You can write code like that.
If you want, if you want your black, look at that, you can write code
that even looked, you know, it's called squash brace.
It's the weirdest thing you can do this.
I don't know if you guys have ever seen this style called squash
brace.
I always thought was funny.
Right?
It's full bananas, right?
And it looks like that.
And basically it's the weirdest style because technically the bracket
that lines up isn't the one that closes the block.
So like this goes with this, right?
But it looks like it goes with this.
It's full bananas.
So, yeah, you can write, you can indent your code.
However, you want, and you can put the braces, anywhere you want.
I use them like this because I think that's how my father did it.
I want to say, but I don't know.
I'm sorry.
I do not know.
I do that is how I've always done it and I'm just used to it.
So that's how I do it.
Are there.
Different performance characteristics?
With the different bitwise operators?
Yes!
There actually are.
So basically, the way that bit operations work is it's entirely
dependent on how the processor chose to implement them.
So there are architectures where bitwise operators are flat cost.
So basically, if I do a shift by 4, then that always cost the same as
a shift by
For shift by 30, right?
There are other architectures where the more you shift, the more it
costs.
And the reason for that is because shifting is actually, I guess kind
of annoying in the sense that where the way you have to structure the
gates so that it's actually kind of more expensive, I guess to do
shifts in that are long and sort of short.
I think I want to say that that is a bit.
Esoteric though.
I want to say that
Maybe, I don't know if the P4 had some of this stuff in it, but I
don't think so.
I want to say that for the most part, the processors that we will be
dealing with it.
Usually flat cost so or xan's shifts, I think usually are predictable
fixed amount of time and there isn't like a huge performance
difference between them.
But either way, what I will say is most of the time, those are not the
Ops you're counting.
Most code, just doesn't care how much bit Ops.
It does.
Usually the things that are costing.
You time are either floating-point Ops.
So a lot of math Ops on floating Point numbers, which we didn't.
In the Stream will be covering the mainstream.
Floating Point.
Numbers Ops your usually worried about and memory axises is really the
thing like memory.
How much memory you're sucking in.
And how many floating Ops are doing on that memory tends to be a lot
more what you're worried about.
I don't remember caring about a bit wise up, performance-wise in a
long, long time.
But, you know, correctly from our like I said, when I answer this
questions as best I can.
But, you know, honestly, my strong suit in programming tends to be.
Architecture and sort of like, code design sorts of stuff.
And I do have a lot of expertise in like animation systems and stuff
because I worked on those for a long time, but like optimization isn't
my strong suit, so, you know, if you ask me something like what's the
best way to write a blah?
I ain't going to no, like someone asked about cache, oblivious data
structures.
I don't even know what those were right, which is an example.
Like if you were a super optimizations guy.
There's probably no way you wouldn't have known what those were.
Right.
You just know that because you familiar
But I'm still mostly the type of guy who does large code.
Lots of code.
Well architected is usually what I can say.
I can give good advice on but when we're talking about like really
hardcore optimization stuff, that's something that you're almost
always going to want to want a second opinion because I'll show you
how to get it good.
But if you want it great, that's going to be somebody else.
That's going to be someone who specializes in optimizing that thing.
And there's always someone out there who specializes in optimizing
that thing, and they know more than
Someone like me who spends time doing other things because processes
are always changing and if you don't keep learning how to optimize for
the changes, you're always a little bit behind.
So I'm always going to be a little bit behind when it comes to things
like that.
Let's see here.
How much bit feeling do you do on real code, tons?
We will you will be bit, fiddling probably right out of the gate on
Monday.
I bet we'll see some bit Fielding.
It's not a ton but like it's often.
Yeah, usually do a little bit of it in everything, just a little bit.
Not a whole lot.
Will you be writing your own allocator?
Absolutely.
Absolutely, absolutely.
Couldn't you get the pointer to your variable that you want to see in
binary and look at it in the memory window, the memory window doesn't
Dubai.
Binary either.
I don't think I mean, yes, you could do that.
If the, if the thing would have laid a bunch of main braces, there you
could do that.
If it was possible to actually display binary in the memory window,
but I don't think you can, right.
I mean, yeah, it doesn't have binary.
It's only got hexadecimal.
So we'd be no better off.
We just be seeing hexadecimal again, which is, you know, it's too bad
but people seem to be suggesting relatively strenuously in the chat
that visual studio 2013, will allow us to view it in binary.
So hopefully that will be true.
We'll find out tomorrow.
Not sure if this is too big to ask, but can you show us how to open a
blank window using the win API?
That is tomorrow?
Yes, does not too big to ask.
But tomorrow, that is what we will be doing.
Clemens bound, what do you think of our aii for resource handling?
So, raii for people who don't know, I actually used to do a lot of C++
program, which is the only reason I know what raii is.
Normally, if you ask me, a C++ one of these fancy C++ isms.
I would tell you like, I don't know what that is, now care what that
is, but I do know it already is.
That's resource acquisition is initialization.
Usually, what that means, what that basically means is designing code.
Such that a, a
Logical unit.
Usually in C++ they're referring to a class which is a glorified
struct basically as soon as it has acquired any resource memory, a
file handle, a network socket, something that is a resource that has
to be acquired.
And then released Rai basically means that the class is considered
initialized once that resource.
Has been acquired and it's not supposed to do anything additional
until basically.
Basically, unless you make up a new class that does the next step.
Without trying to go in and give a full example of what that is for
everyone and showing perhaps why it is kind of silly.
I will simply say that.
The way that you want to design code in general.
Is to understand the ways in which that code can fail in practice and
designed the code.
So that it properly handles.
Those failure cases what people often advocate in C++ is trying to
write your code, such that it handles, and I'm using that in quotes.
All possible failures at all possible points.
What that means is if for some reason, my code couldn't open the file
handle that it was trying to open.
I want it to automatically through a series of exceptions and
destructors and all these other sorts of things unwind.
All the stuff that had been doing up to that point in a way that makes
it.
So that it is somehow
We cleaner.
I never find code written in that way to ever actually work in
practice very well.
I find that it's actually very brittle to failure.
And the reason that I find that it's very brittle to failure, is
because the things that people have done is they have translated, they
have, they have moved the job of thinking about the ways, the code can
actually fail into just a reflexive way of just sticking things in
Constructors and destructors.
And assuming that the unwinding of the stack will just do the right
thing.
But the answer is that usually when things fail in your program that
you expect to fail like a network socket, can't be opened or a network
socket, doesn't send the thing.
It needs to send or a file can't be opened.
Usually what you really need is custom logic that recovers from that
failure in a smart way.
And that logic is often different.
Depending on the circumstance, one file, not being able to open is
different from another file, not being open.
If I'm trying to open file a.
Maybe the thing that I want to do when it can't open is wait a few
seconds and try again, but if I'll be candid,
Be open, then.
Maybe what I want to do is just exit the damn program because
nothing's going to be able to happen and those are simple examples,
but really it's not that much more complicated that when you really
start programming a real program, really?
It's just about you need to think about the failures and you need to
write code that handles the failures.
So what I find a lot of people Soccer Plus programmers who are gung ho
but our Ira, I do that.
I don't approve of and would not recommend is they spend a ton of time
typing in code that handles failures that will never happen and then
when their code
Really does fail in the weight in the places where I would know that
that's that's legitimately going to happen on a running system.
It totally blows up and yeah, they freed the memory and close the file
handles, but that who cares?
Like you need the code to actually work.
It doesn't matter if it cleans up after itself, it needs to actually
work.
And so if you can't even get the code to work, why are you bothering
dealing with whether you close the file handle?
That is not relevant.
That is not part of the of actually the problem definition.
That is a way of making sure that your code does not leave detritus
around in leak handles, but it is not actually the primary problem
statement of what's supposed to happen.
So, like most C++ design patterns.
I find raii to be a way that people excuse themselves from doing the
hard work by doing busy work, which actually does not solve the
problem that they needed to solve.
Hope that answers that question.
Doo doo, doo doo doo.
How much would feeling would you be writing?
Your own allocator couldn't get pointer above idiocracy, asked a
question from before and yes, we will do that.
But let me just see if there's any other code questions coming down
here.
First.
I will, I will push this one onto the stack and I will not forget it.
Doo doo, doo doo, I think a four-year CS degree is a bad idea waste of
money.
I have no idea.
I have never taken one.
Are you going to use structs instead of classes?
Yes.
I never typed.
The word glass.
How will I handle the need for polymorphism polymorphism?
Is a silly idea sorry to say it like that but polymorphism is an
interesting to me.
It's just not interesting.
It's interesting.
If you actually maybe by polymorphism actually mean, full duck typing
but really like mixing is the thing that you want and C++ handles it
very poorly.
It's polymorphism using multiple inheritance, just doesn't work at
all.
So what we're actually going to do is things that are much more
powerful than inheritance.
We're basically going to implement full mix in.
Which will allow us to do things that are just far more powerful than
you can do with inheritance.
Inheritance is is useless.
It's a dumb idea.
I don't know why they put that in C++.
It's completely useless.
You can occasionally use it to do something very rudimentary.
That's basically function, pointer kinds of dispatch and even, then
it's stupid.
It doesn't work properly.
It's way less capable than a table of function pointers because you
can't modify the function pointers since the V table format is okay.
Take.
So yet inheritance in C++ is awful.
I would never ever, ever, ever use it in a program that said, there
are programmers, who I respect.
Like, John Blow, who do use it.
They use it very sparingly, usually one level inheritance at most, so
I certainly wouldn't argue with someone who decided to use it because
there are effective programmers, who do use it, but I will note that
they use it very limited.
And even John, for example is kind of Designing his own language,
because he thinks inheritance doesn't work very well.
So,
In I think even he would probably agree.
You'd have to ask him but I think he would probably agree.
That inheritance is pretty weak and lame and the only time you would
really ever use, it is for this really simple thing that it can sort
of do.
And you were almost the whole time wishing you had something better.
Will the game be C++ or C?
And any reason you did your intros at Sea in a sieve, if you file, the
game will be C in CPP because I want to use some CP features.
We will use some operator overloading, and we will use some, we may
use some Constructor Destructor pairs to do things like automatically,
cap times and blocks or something like that.
I don't know that we will but there are some little features of C++
here and there that I may use oh a function overloading is another one
too.
So I find this usually best to compile and sleepy.
P mode, even though I mostly write code that looks like, see because I
find that it's nice to be able to have the features of C++ if I want
them.
And then I just, I'm since I've had enough experience.
I know which ones to stay away from.
So I just don't use the stuff that gets you into trouble.
So it's kind of The Best of Both Worlds, to compile, your C code and
see because you can always just, you know, switch up what are the
differences between references and pointers.
There is no difference between a reference in a pointer.
Basically.
A reference is just a way of getting a free dereference in there.
So,
So, a reference.
For those of you don't know if you if you say if you declare your code
to have an ampersand in it ahead of time.
This is called a reference while I need to actually set it to
something.
That's actually
A variable, this basically gets you a pointer to why that you don't
actually have to dereference.
So instead of normally, you know, if that was a regular pointer.
I'd have to type y r f equals 6 or something to, to talk about the
value pointed to, by why ref to do a dereference a reference type.
It just means one that I don't have to do that.
I can just do it.
Directly.
I tend to not use them because I think they finally added a way to do
this and C++ in the recent spec.
But for me.
Many, many years you couldn't override them.
So you couldn't set a reference like using something, you know, update
this reference, please to point to something new, right?
You couldn't do that.
And so the reason I didn't use them as pointers.
I like to be able to set my pointer to point to new things.
And so references were kind of useless, but I think they had something
to do that now, so if you really like references, I think in the
latest latest spec you you can, you can actually swap arms.
I don't know.
Don't quote me on that.
I don't read the spec.
anymore, but
Well, let's see.
You said you were using C++, but I'll be backwards compatible with
see.
I don't think I said that this, I hope I didn't say that.
It will not really be backwards compatible.
Most things I will do.
You can compile c99 if you wanted to compile this stuff and c99 pretty
much all of handmade hero will probably compile and c99 with a few
exceptions.
That would be probably easier for you to fix.
So it will be somewhat backwards, compatible c99, but that's not a
goal.
So I don't guarantee that.
Let's see.
You might want to talk about short-circuiting.
I might talk about that the mainstream.
But okay, I'll throw it in here.
So what short-circuiting means is, if I have a lot of talking about,
like, you could sort of make these if statements that have things like
or as Ann Ann's in them.
So, okay.
Basically if you have something that looks like this, where I've got
two different things that are going to happen to evaluate my
conditional, right?
And you know what?
I don't even need to do them here.
So let's let's say we're not even talking about conditional.
I'm just Computing the values 0 1, I just want to know there's
Not zero, I just want to know if this is true or false.
Well, what happens in see is that the compiler is under no obligation
to execute any further into the line than it needs to, to actually
give you the value back.
So, for example, if it sees that Y is in fact equal to 5, right?
If y was equal to 5, it is under no obligation to actually compute Z
equals 5.
And furthermore, I believe in fact, no.
I know the specs.
Says it will not compute it.
So if you want to do something like a function call here.
Like, compute the thing one.
Right, and I'm going to make some call.
And then I'm going to say, compute the thing too.
And I want to know if either of these functions returned, you know, a
particular value.
Like I want to know if either of these returns not zero, it's under no
obligation to actually do the second thing and will not do it.
So, it means that if you're expecting compute the thing to to get
called or, you know, an easier.
One, since we haven't talked too much about function calls.
Let's say I did x equals X plus 3.
In here and Y, equals y plus 5 because C allows you to put full
Expressions, pretty much anywhere you want.
So I can actually do work and update, Y and X right in the middle
here.
If I wanted to, there's nothing wrong with that.
This one will get done.
Right but this one won't get done because it'll do this one.
It'll set x equal to X plus 3 that will be not 0 probably and so it
will never have to it knows that the value of this this or will be 1.
So it will never have to actually execute this.
So why will come out of this?
Not having the incremented by 5.
So if you were expecting it to you, will be in for a surprise that is
what circuiting is, and it is good to be aware of.
So, thank you for bringing that up.
Using Code blocks.
I can just use into Maine for my main function, what's going on with
the window stuff in Visual Studio.
It really has nothing to do with code blocks.
The entry point is determined by the C runtime library and the
operating system.
So if you're talking about code blocks on Windows, you probably just
made a project that was compiled in console mode.
And if you compile a thing in console mode, even in Visual Studio,
Is main the one you're talking about.
For example, I can even show you that if I go in here, I think I can
probably set it again.
This is always an adventure because I never know where all the
settings are in visual studio.
And I certainly takes me a while to find them usually.
So if I go in here and I want to do, let's see, can I do Linker?
Should be something in the Linker that lets me kind of say what I
want.
Okay, so this subsystem thing.
NG here, which is a subsystem Windows if I change that to substance of
console, right?
And I compiled this thing when I compile it, you'll notice that it now
won't link.
And the reason it won't think it's because it wants main, right?
It no longer is looking for win main.
So then if I go in here and say Main and use the standard notation
therefore remain, right?
Now my code starts there, right?
And that's actually where the code, this is where the code will start,
right?
So, I don't know if that answers your question.
But basically it has absolutely nothing to do with with code blocks or
Visual Studio.
It's just whether you were compiling with that as the entry point and
either way.
Windows is basically going to call into one or the other layer up
anyway, and this is something we will do in the mainstream a little
bit more, but if you look
Getting way ahead of where we probably should be at this point.
The hey, again, it's a Sunday.
If you look at something called the call stack, which is basically the
functions that have been called up to this point where we are how deep
we are.
If you back out of the call stack from where we are, and man, you'll
see that we're not actually at window.
So this thing I don't know if you can see this here.
Well, you know, you can't because of course windows.
I mean, a visual studio wants all the things to be super small van T.
So let me go and let me set the fonts to something bigger here.
So,
Let's see.
Call stack is call stack on the table, people intermediates window.
Output.
Window registers.
Watch locals Autos, Autos.
Call stack.
Hey, so, I'm going to go ahead and set the call stack to Liberation
mono and get that to be bigger.
Okay.
So, here we are in the call stack and this tells us basically who's
calling who is called in to us who the people had to call in, to us?
So if you see kernel32.dll kernel32.dll is actually where Windows
actually entered us, right?
So kernel32 is where the kernel mapped its code into our address
space.
It called into there and then that called in to us and it called in to
us here.
This is the C runtime Library.
This is code that Microsoft wrote that it linked with our executable,
which does some startup crap that allows them to implement certain
functions of the C standard runtime Library.
That called underscore underscore, teaming CRS to start up, which is
also something that supplied by Microsoft in their runtime library.
That did a bunch of initialization code, right?
You can see it happening here.
What were they doing?
They were doing some kind of a memory locked exchange.
They slept for a while.
I guess if they couldn't exchange it, they did something to check
whether they finished initializing they went.
I didn't initialise C++ Constructors that have to happen at startup
time.
I don't know.
I mean, I'm not, I'm just sort of vaguely guessing it what this is
doing.
Let's see here.
They're looking getting the command line.
They're processing.
The command line for double quotes.
It looks like skipping white space and then they finally call win
main.
If its wind main.
Otherwise, they call Main if it's main, depending on whether you'd
started console or not.
So, that's actually what's going on there.
And finally, we actually get to us after all that stuff happens.
If you were to link without the C runtime Library, you would actually
you'd be right here you would, you would be doing this and so you
wouldn't have all that stuff happen.
It would just you'd be writing you.
Mmm.
Like to know how many people bought the lesson, I'm curious at how big
the community will be.
I don't, I think the easiest way to see that is actually if you go to
just to Twitch.
So if you do twitch.tv handmade made hero, is that how you do it.
I think you can look and see how many people have subscribed because
more people subscribed by I think.
So.
How do you get subscribe?
A, how do you know what?
See, I'm too much of a twitch.
Noob.
I don't know.
I have no idea how you do, how you get, like, the stats or whatever,
but if you can, if you can go to like the the thing that says, there
you go, thirteen hundred followers.
So I assume that means like roughly 1,300 people could be watching at
maximum because presumably, unless there's people who just don't know
how to use tuition so they didn't follow it or whatever, but
presumably if you're going
Try to follow along.
Then you you did that.
Okay?
Let's see.
Short circuiting.
Will you show how to look for I cache?
Misses in the mainstream?
Probably not unless we actually run into something where we're
actually doing that.
Now, maybe I'll do a section on like performance counters from from
Intel or something, but probably not, I cache misses are super rare
thing to be optimizing for so I probably won't get to that.
But, you know, I don't know.
And again, I'm also the wrong person.
Like if you're optimizing for, I cast.
Mrs.
You're a hardcore optimization guy.
I mean, it's pretty much it if your Flex 64k alias.
I cast, mrs.
Tlb like, if you're optimizing that stuff, you're a hardcore
optimization guy and you almost never need to do that.
For Just Two to make a really good game.
If you want to push technical boundaries, you absolutely do need to
know that stuff, but we probably won't get that far.
I'm going to give people essentially the start of like, here's how we
optimize code to be good.
And here's how we are code to be good, but I'm not going to go all the
way on anything because we could Rat Hole for months on optimization,
and that's not the goal.
Like the goal is for me to give you a complete game show you how to
make all of it.
Good and to let you know what, you don't know.
So that if you're like, I really want to be if someone who spends all
my time, working on X.
You will know what x is and how to like that go further.
So I'll select in this dream.
I mention I cash so that you know that it's there, but I don't
necessarily show you everything you need to know about it.
Do you use a lot of advanced auto ship to simple ones?
Do you worry about algorithmic Owen complexity?
Yes, you always have to worry about algorithmic, 0, n complexity.
You should know the 0 n complexity of absolutely everything you do if
you don't.
That is a problem.
So, I will be mentioning that often during the stream.
Would you fight one horse-sized duck or 10?
The Legend of Zelda, swarming duck-sized horses?
That is a tough question.
I think probably horse-sized duck because I don't like horses.
I don't trust them.
I think ducks are more trustworthy.
And so I feel like a duck and I could have a fair fight.
Whereas I think 10 horses, no matter how big they were would be,
wouldn't be a fair fight.
They would try to do things to try and rig the fight against me and I
don't think that's fair.
Like, if me and the horse are going to have a fight.
I mean the duck are going to have a fight.
It's going to be a gentleman's fight.
And I feel like both of us will be able to enter it on terms that are
fair and respect each other afterwards.
No low blows, you know, nothing below the feather line and whereas if
it's going to be, for example, a horse, who knows what that thing is
going to do, that's going to be one of those things was like, look
over there and then the horse trots kick you, right?
That's like what a horse would do.
So, I think I definitely fight the one horse-sized duck.
I'm not sure if I can ask this but what operating system is your PC.
This one that were on right now is Windows 7?
Did I miss it?
Or did you not discuss functions return values passing by value
reference etcetera?
We did discuss functions.
We did discuss return values, but we have not yet discussed passing by
value versus passing by reference.
Really?
I mean, basically those are the things we'll probably get two more in
the mainstream as well as what kind of function calls you do.
Like standard Culver's is fastball.
Have you seen have an opinion on data oriented design Dodd?
Main?
I don't have not seen it.
So I do not have an opinion.
I do like code that is oriented around the data that it works with.
So I sounds like something I would like, but who knows, maybe the name
doesn't mean that?
Weird that senior trade didn't mention stack overflows at the obvious
Point, unless I missed it.
No, I did not mention stackoverflow.
Stack overflows or just what happens when you run out of guard pages
on the stack.
So you've run out of space basically for the stack.
And so, you know, you have to basically take into account the fact
that you you have limited stock size, but we will never do anything
that comes anywhere close to using the all those Stacks dies.
I don't think so that probably won't be too much of an issue.
But yeah that that's more of an advanced topic.
If you're overflowing the stack, some stuffs gone.
That's either gone wrong, or you're doing something particularly odd.
Are you going to be using opengl and DirectX?
Know we're building the engine from scratch.
We will not be using open till DirectX.
I may do eventually something that shows you how to do the renderer in
opengl.
Just so you know how to do the equivalent things.
But that would be like at the very end of the game, just to show you
how to get more performance by using a GPU basically, but but yeah,
that's it.
Royal Tom says, the comedy thing, does not work in visual studio 2013
there.
So the all the people are saying, comma, B.
Why are you saying that?
You're just, you're just trying to sow confusion.
Don't say it if you haven't tried it.
Scdf, 47 chance of me being able to follow along.
It's absolutely.
The only problem is I'm not sure exactly how I'm going to handle this.
Maybe, what I'll do is try to, I'll try to maybe try to help people.
I'm not sure, but basically, I will do the developing on Windows, but
I will show how to write the equivalent startup code on Linux and Mac.
The question is when I do that.
And so I'm trying to work out exactly how that's going to happen.
What may have to happen is I'll just write the code myself and I won't
show how to write it and it will be in the source tree.
And then later I will go and rewrite.
It it explaining how I write it on the live stream so that people can
see something like that.
I don't know.
I'm still trying to work that out, but I would like people to be able
to follow along on Linux and Mac if possible.
So, we'll see what we can do.
Cordelia night tonight to do the standard multiplication, star use B
shift to optimize itself, or does it do it in some other way?
The answer is that the compiler may take advantage of that?
Yes, if you do an integer x to the compiler, May shift if it's faster
on that platform, that's that's just one of the things that optimize
our might do, I think, usually that's called strength reduction.
In compiler parlance, it's been a while since I've talked to compiler.
But basically there's a set of optimizations that compilers can do
which turn operations that are expensive on the CPU and to ones that
are less expensive because they happen to work out.
And so one of the things that can happen is a shift by 2 or x 2 or a
shift can be kind of interchanged.
So it will do that depending on the platform if it thinks it can get
the speed win.
Let's see when you ask the chat, something keep in mind.
There's a delay.
So, make sure to wait 30.
Yes.
Yes, I do.
I do try to do that now.
Will the allocator be lock-free thread-safe?
Miss Chantix wants to know the allocator.
So it depends exactly what you're talking about.
Allocator means two different things.
There's the thing that actually gets memory from the system and that
will probably not be locked free or thread safe.
That will probably just be something that gets a memory from the
system.
The actual things that allocate out of that pool that it receives in
the operating system.
I suspect that there are maybe one place where those are locked free
and thread safe because there is one thing I do anticipate doing that
will want that, everything else will not require it and you never
write locked free thread, safe code.
If you don't need to because it is more complicated.
How much dependency injection do you use?
Dependency injection.
I'm sorry.
I do not know what you mean by dependency injection.
If enemy Mouse could tell me what they mean by that.
The simple parameter passing.
I'm sorry.
Enemy Mouse, tell me what you mean by that and I will answer that.
Let's see.
Do you feel the same way about doing raii for public?
Eyes, public apis are delicate topic and I need to see the specific
case always before I'm willing to make any kind of.
Proclamation.
I have a whole lecture that's like an hour-long.
That's on the web about API design.
You can look at if you want to that answer some of those questions,
but why will you not be using class instruct instead, like, in a bit
of detail, Maybe?
Well, first of all, I mean I should point out the fact, if it wasn't
already known to someone asking that question because I didn't cover
classes.
So if you're asking that question, you must already know, so I'm not
sure why I'm typing this in but
There is no difference between a class instruct and C++.
They are exactly the same except for one difference.
That is that a struct, has this at the beginning of it.
Implicitly and a class has this at beginning of it.
Implicitly, that's pretty much it.
So basically why am I not using a class?
Well, I could use a class if you would prefer.
There is my class.
It's great.
Right?
Do you love it?
So, yeah, there's no difference in instructing, the class.
There's no difference between those two things, literally, no
difference between those two things.
Like, what do you want to do anything?
You want to do?
You can do it.
You want to hear it from something?
Go nuts.
Right, no problem.
So there's no difference between instruction the class.
There's a C++ doesn't doesn't distinguish between those two things.
As far as I know.
They're, they're 100% equivocal equivalent.
They're 100% equivalent except for which default you use and it always
cracks me up to watch C++, programmers type.
This always I've never seen like a C++ programmer in modern times not
start their class with public.
I'm like, why didn't you just type that then you don't need?
That and you can just type private down here, but who knows?
I don't know why?
C++ programmers, do what they do.
They just, they do what they do.
You can't, you know, you gotta love them.
They like to type a lot more than they need to.
That's what that's for.
Sure.
Why will you not be using class?
Direct instead got that.
Why no classes answered?
That have no idea.
What a mixing is.
Can you elaborate a mix in is when you say that, something wants to
have a lot of stuff.
So for example,
Oil.
In a fictional language that is not exist.
I want to create a projectile like I did before but instead of having
it, specify its own layout and stuff.
I just want to say that a projectile, you know, you know.
It it is an entity.
It has flammability it, it can explode, it does.
Sort of it does do damage Etc.
And you basically lists a bunch of stuff that you want to be true
about this thing.
And then the language mixes what all of those mean together into
One thing that can do them.
All right, and C++ with multiple inheritance, tried to do this, right?
They tried to make it so that you can do those things.
Like, I am, I inherit this thing from flammable, you know, and other
things, multiple, multiple inheritance.
I inherit from multiple things that I might want to be, but it doesn't
work properly because a lot of things that you want to be able to do
in that start in, that system don't actually work the way you want mix
into work.
So what a lot of people's first farmers do is they do mix in by
Moment.
So they'll put Like A flammable thing in here, right?
And then they'll have ways of like turning a projectile, into a
flammable by returning, the interior thing out of it and blah blah
blah and it's all just a it's all just a mess.
So we will be trying to implement A system that does mix in more
cleanly for the things that we want to do and we'll just implement it
by hand.
We won't try to use any fancy language features.
We'll just do it and you'll see how it's done.
It's no big deal.
I never talked about the camera operator.
That's true.
I think it's actually technically called the sequence operator and I
am not going to talk about it because unless it actually comes up in
the Stream, which it might sometimes.
I'll probably get kind of just ignore it.
For those of you who want to know.
What a comma operator.
Is.
It just basically puts two statements next to each other.
So basically, if I do something like, you know, x equals 6, Z equals
4, it basically allows me to do two separate statements that happen.
Sequentially sort of like a semi colon operator, but
Doesn't actually have the Restriction at it, has to be grouped on a
separate thing.
Go to as well.
I'm not going to cover go to because I almost never use them.
So, there is a go to and see, but I'm not going to cover it.
I there's other.
There's a lot of things to see that I could cover.
It was not inclusive thing for sure.
I understand that I can recreate the source code at home.
But just by following your stream, but what about art and music?
Do I have to buy the game?
Download it or you provided some download links?
Yes, if you want art.
There are music.
You have to buy the game.
That's kind of what the game is.
The source code, the art the music.
So if you want that Gotta Buy it, this might have been answered.
Made you use go to and see ever know.
I don't, I'm not strictly against it.
I just haven't.
I grew up not using it and just don't use it.
Very often.
Are you been cousins?
I do not know who Ben Cousins is.
Let's see.
Why do you like?
Okay, I covered the class thing.
We'd be showing the creation of any tools like a level editor.
It's good question.
Probably will do a little bit of a little level editor, sorts of
stuff.
I want to show how to do procedurally, generated worlds.
So, I probably won't be building like, a really big level editor
because we won't be editing levels a ton, but we probably will do a
little bit of that yet.
Have you ever made anything for the demo scene or know?
Anyone who has?
I have not but Fabien who have referred to a couple times who works at
rad was part of Fab rush.
I don't actually know how to pronounce that but he is
A guy who works at rad, who is a friend of mine, and he was part of
the demo group.
There we go.
That's the one.
Let's see.
This is them, and they did a bunch of cool demos like K Kriegers,
pretty cool.
It was like some like 120k executable.
That's like a whole Quake game.
Basically.
It's pretty cool.
So yeah, I mean, I dunno, I guess that's one person who did something
don't say, I don't think I know anyone.
One else.
I don't know many people from Europe actually.
And the demo scene seems to be like way bigger there than it is here.
So like I've only, I just haven't met that many people from Europe.
So I don't know.
A lot of demo scene.
People.
I think demos are really cool.
I like the demo scene.
I think that would have been something.
I would have had fun growing up in that scene, but they didn't have
that where I lived.
Why don't use a platform independent library?
Because I want to show you how to make everything yourself after, you
know, how to make everything yourself, then by all means use a
library, if you like it.
So, what are the general plan for the game?
Get something on screen quickly possible?
Put your sugar for the whole game.
Something else.
It will be real, play it by ear.
But basically, we're going to get a simple thing up and running first.
And then, we're going to expand the parts as we go into more and more
professional quality, because that's generally how you do it.
Even, you know, when you're writing a game, that's not teaching game.
You tend to want to structure its which you push gradually outward.
So you don't have like this sort of
Huge load of crazy architecture that has to happen first where you
don't know how all the parts into relate.
So if you sort of build over time, usually works much better.
Strength reduction.
Yes, tea or water would probably be kinder to your voice than milk.
It is almond milk, but that's possibly true.
We show fractals and how to do them.
No fractals will not really be related.
Dependency injection means we used Loop to get us into a lot of
trouble and now we're using even more up to get out again, then know,
I probably won't do that.
That sounds awful.
Dia is not a common thing in C C++ be on-premise Constructors.
Otherwise, use reflective Nexus to prefilled data.
Okay.
Let's say can a struct have a Constructor?
Yes.
You're okay.
Did your teachers seriously tell you?
Okay, Lord, Julien 1992.
Did you really have a teacher?
Who told you that a struct?
Can't have a Constructor?
Because I do not know how you get a job teaching, anyone anything?
If you can't take 10 seconds to type this,
If you can't have a Constructor, how did I just type that, right?
That's all that was literally like, you know, 20 characters or
something.
I had to type in, to answer my student properly.
How did you not do that before?
You said that, that's awful?
Okay.
That's really weird.
I suppose, I shouldn't get mad.
I mean, I say wrong things on this stream.
I only know what I know.
So,
First.
Maybe I shouldn't be so hard on people.
Yeah, I guess I just never tried it.
All right, I'm gonna not be mad about that.
I think I should always try to be positive on this dream because you
know, what programming is complicated.
And so I could see someone just not knowing like maybe you just never
thought to try it.
And if you never thought to try it, then I guess you'd probably just
be like, I don't know.
I've never seen anyone do it.
So I just assumed that you couldn't and I didn't want to read the spec
because I mean I'll be honest the spec is f and giant so I could
totally see you not one green specks.
Oh nevermind.
I retract the rage rage attracted.
If you would like to tell your teacher politely that you can have
struck.
Instructs, you should do so.
Someone asked about how you started programming career.
Let's hear.
It's okay.
I think we're probably getting the point where I should answer that
question.
Let's see, it will, the will the game include old-school passwords for
saving?
We could, if you want to remind me when we're further along the game
and maybe we will, I'm going to show you how to save the game for
reals to a drive, but we could, we could do that.
It's great to see someone so excited about programming with a lot of
experience.
But do you think people interested in game design will be disappointed
in the Stream.
I person want to focus on game design first for my games and only then
implementing them it properly in C++.
It's am not in student teaching.
C++ to other people.
Just my Approach makes sense for game development.
Do you think it's faster use Python for game prototypes?
I would say that people who are primarily used on game design,
probably would be disappointing the stream because I am not a game
designer.
So if you're just interested in game design, you probably want to
watch a stream.
Someone who's a professional game designer, I would think as to
whether it's a good idea to use python, or C++ or whatever.
I have no idea what ever you are.
Most comfortable using is what you should use.
John Blow, for example, who's the best game designer?
I know he writes his prototypes and C++.
So, you know, I don't know.
I've never met a game designer who's as good as John and so obviously,
you don't need to use Python but John's also making his own language
from scratch.
So probably the reason he's not using python.
It's you think Spice Islands also bad and you probably think C++ is
just a little less bad.
And so what he probably really wants for making his games and is
prototypes as well is just a good language and that's what he's doing.
So I certainly hope he succeeds.
Maybe then the answer to that question will be much more obvious,
which is just use John Blow language to make your prototypes because
it's awesome.
How much money do game makers make?
I don't know.
That's a good question.
I have never really been a game maker.
I actually make game technology and Licensing.
Game technology was a great living.
I have always been able to make a lot of money and I'm very fortunate
to be able to do.
So, I would say that in general if you know the kinds of low-level
programming that I am focusing on in these streams where you
understand the whole process.
You do architecture.
Well, you can get down to the nitty-gritty.
You maybe aren't the best optimize.
eyes are in the world, but you understand where the
Happens and why there are a ton of high paying jobs available for you.
I basically don't know a single high-paying company out there that
isn't actually gated on Talent, not money like the primary problem.
Most of the time for projects at companies is that they cannot hire
enough.
Good engine programmers.
It is never the case that they like, have as many great engine
programmers as they need.
That never happens.
People are usually.
There are usually just implicitly job openings.
If you are a good engine style programmer.
So like if you came to me and you're like I totally powned the
handmade hero stream, like I'm awesome at this.
Now.
I know everything about this.
And you can prove to what you don't need to prove it to me because I'm
not hiring.
But you can prove that to someone that you understand all that stuff
and you're totally good at it.
I mean, that's just your instantly valuable summer because they're
just is there's a dearth of people who understand this stuff.
A lot of applicants that people get for these positions.
They only know, Java or something, right?
Because that's what they learned in school or saying that and that's
not useful and you can't put that person to work on a game engine for
a long time.
They're going to have to go through and like, learn all this stuff
and, you know, so basically game engines are places where they need
people.
They always need people.
And maybe in the future, that won't be true, but for right now,
there's always it's always hard to find enough.
Good talented, low-level programmers.
Well, the source down that include Version Control so you can back go
back versions, The Source Code control will not be version controlled.
It will rather have everyday Source in it.
So you download it.
They'll be a zip for every day and you can unzip the day that you
want.
If you have a source code control program that you like, you can just
unpack those on top of each other and check them in and have your own
source code control tree as it should be in the tool of your choice,
get or material or bizarre, or whatever you want to use.
You will see some trolls on stream.
Sometimes.
Be advised.
Yes.
There's trolls.
I know what can you do?
What do you do during the day these days?
I am working on some projects that are not announced yet.
Just working a trap provide a better salary than a senior deposition
at a game studio in the same area.
No, because it's a high-paying area.
So like, for example valve pays very well.
So like, you know, if you were working at valve or you're working at
rad, you would be getting paid very well.
There are other places in the country, where an certainly actually
also abroad, where the salaries aren't.
Hi for those positions.
And so it's really very dependent on how strong the game companies are
in your area.
Because when those game companies are making a lot of money, they are
going after that sort of hard to find engine programmers and stuff
like that.
They're paying a lot more money for them because they want the best
people and they've got the money to do.
So, but you go to an area where there's not many game companies and
they're not super wealthy, then they're not going to have that money
to sort of Chase that talent and
A comment about the our a discussion earlier.
REI does not actually mean that you have to use exceptions.
Sure, but I didn't say that.
I just was listing the things exceptions destructors and so on Rai is
just not relevant.
Like it's not, it's it is not a useful to way to look at things.
It doesn't matter how you implement it.
It's just not a useful way to look at things.
Will you use any?
I respect the game.
Know, and that brings us to the end of the question.
So now I will go back to the question that we pushed on the stack,
which was just totally not related to code at all.
But it was idiocracy is question.
Where is the question?
Where is it scrolling scrolling?
I'm sure if I knew how to search in this, we would be in good shape,
but of course, I don't because I've never
Used hex chat before and so not having used Acts chapter 4 means, I
don't really know what's going on.
So, let's see, idiocracy, idiocracy.
Idiocracy, theocracy.
Idiocracy.
Where are you?
You're gone.
You're totally gone, Bianca.
See you have scrolled.
There you are.
It's a good thing.
I am using extra though because that would have long scrolled past the
twitch chat.
I think the twitch chats not going to find that at all.
Would you talk a little
all about your background at the start of your pro in career given
that you had an early certain programming at the age of seven.
What were the circumstances in you?
Not attending college?
How have you gone about learning Source like linear algebra.
Did you crack open a textbook and learn it on your own?
Or did you just learn the bits and pieces relevant to a reviewer?
Has finally was getting it in Microsoft difficult, given your lack of
degree.
Well, so the complete story is that I grew up.
Like I said, my father was a programmer, so I learned to program
because he taught me how
And that was the only way that I learned because I didn't really have
access to any programming resources, besides him the there.
I grew up in a town that didn't even have a book store.
Let alone technical book store.
So, I pretty much had to just bend and I didn't have like a BBS dial
anything to anyone.
I have like, friends, who knew anything about programming at all.
So for most of my childhood, I just I would ask my dad and my dad
would sometimes go get books for me from like Digital Life.
Equipment Corporation or something where he worked and he would like,
give those to me and I could read those or he would teach me how to do
something and then later on like I think we would go there was a when
I kind of got a little older there was like a Borders bookstore in
Framingham, which was like 30 minutes away and we would drive there
and we look we'd sit in the section with computer books and look at
them.
Occasionally, we'd buy one, but they're expensive for kid.
And you know, I started learning some things out of books.
I think I learned
gosh, so I learned my first
3D math out of Foley and Van Dam.
I think my dad had xeroxed a page on rotation that I had learned,
stuff about that.
And then I bought the book at the borders eventually to learn stuff
like Matrix transforms.
I think that's true.
It's been so long.
I'm sorry.
I can't remember a lot of these things.
But basically, you know, in those days, there was no internet.
So it was actually pretty easy to learn a lot at home because when you
got home, there wasn't anything to do.
And if you like computers, you would just go try to do stuff.
And so it's a lot easier to learn things on your own when you're not
like on Twitter all day.
Right?
Like I imagine kids today probably have a hard time learning things
because there's just so much distraction and there's tons of games to
play and all this other stuff.
And so I played a lot of games when I was a kid too.
But like you had one game that you bought and it was expensive and you
played a lot of it.
And then when you were done, you were done right?
There wasn't just like, oh, I can go and get all these games, and
they're like, I bought a Humble Bundle.
And there's like, basically, 300 hours of gaming in there.
Right?
That's not a thing.
It was like $30 or whatever, and there was tons of game piracy to, but
even that can't keep up.
I mean, the amount of games pirated by people.
When I was a kid.
It's like smaller than the amount you could just live.
We buy nowadays on on you know, a trivial part time job that you have
as a kid, you know, you make 20 bucks a week or something and you're
going to have more games than you could even pirate from back when I
was a kid.
So yeah, I don't know.
But point being we learned a bunch of stuff myself and some friends of
mine to who used to kind of start to get into it.
None of them were as into it as I was but, you know, we learned some
stuff and wrote some stuff.
Basically, what happened from there is total luck.
If I was friends with somebody from early on like from from when I was
little and their father used to run a computer company went bankrupt
or closed in some way and he went to work as an executive for
Microsoft.
So when I was in high school, he was like you should come out here for
an internship.
Now.
I don't actually know why he wanted me to do that.
I just assumed he was just being nice.
Like I don't think there was any reason why Microsoft would care if I
went out to do an internship because I'm just some kid, but I think he
just was like, oh, you know, this was a kid who's a friend of ours
from, from back, you know, Microsoft's, obviously in Seattle, so they
moved to Seattle, but I was still in
So I'm pretty sure basically all that was was just, you know, he was
being nice to know, you know, like maybe he would like to come out and
see how we do things, and he could do an internship.
And I mean, I'm an executive here.
So if I tell them that they should have this kid as an intern, they're
going to actually know if that's true.
Maybe maybe he couldn't have done that.
I'm not positive.
But anyway, so I was in high school.
I was like, okay, so I just went out there and went
Our interview Loop for interns and I really really really lucked out
on the internet on the interview Loop is basically what it boils down
to because being so young and not really exposed to very much things.
There were only a limited set of things that I really knew how to do
well and one of the things that I really knew how to do well with
stuff like Sprite compositing because I did a bunch of programming on
the Amiga and I knew a lot of stuff about how to work with, like, bit
planes and all these sorts of other things like rectangle, Direct.
Angle copies with alpha or without or those sorts of things.
I like knew all that stuff cold because I did it all the time.
That was like, what I did because I tried to make games.
And one of the things that you do when you make games, As you move
images, around the screen.
So I super look down the interview Loop because the first very first
person on the interview Loop was a guy named Michael Edwards, I
believe, and I don't know what happened to this fellow, but isn't it
guy named Michael Edwards?
And he was actually an old-school Amiga guy too.
And so the question he happened to ask me for whatever reason was like
do a rectangle, a rectangle blitt like copy from one place to the
other and I can just write that.
Like
Even at that time, I could just write that.
And so I think he thought he enjoyed talking because we were both
naked people and he was like, oh this kid knows how to program because
he could do this thing.
This interview question that I asked him and then I had to go through
other energy or the day where I did not do nearly as well.
Like things.
I didn't know how to do very well at that time.
We're like bit operation for testing like I almost never tested bit
fields and stuff.
So like one of the questions that they asked me was something like if
you get
Back a bite.
And you want to know if there's a particular two bit value at any of
the four aligned locations in the B.
Like, what's the fastest way to do that?
And like I'm sure I answered that question.
Super poorly and another guy asked me how to draw a circle really
effectively, and he was looking for me to basically do a present ham,
Circle, sort of style thing.
And I didn't really know how to do that at all.
So, I mean, I gave them code that Drew a circle, but it was like super
slow.
By comparison, so I think mostly like, I don't know what would have
happened.
Exactly.
If I hadn't had the luck of getting someone who happened to just be
right in line with me, on the first interview because, again, it's
possible.
Like, if some Microsoft executive says that we've got this idiot kid,
from my hometown who I want to have come out here and do an
internship.
I mean, it's a political company.
Maybe I just would Dave just half the to that, you know, if maybe this
feel like great.
But luckily for me.
Me.
I actually had one interviewee who actually really did legitimately.
I think, think I was okay, probably not anything special, but at
least, okay.
And so he, they put me with him and said, you know, you can have the
you can do the internship over the summer.
You can go with this team, and I was like, awesome because, you know,
I knew when I went through the interview.
Look, I'm like, yeah, I think I probably was pretty stupid and there's
other ones, but I felt like I did a really good job here.
And I answer the question, totally correctly and that sort of stuff.
And I really like the guy.
So I was like, I could probably actually not be a total waste of time
there.
So anyway, I went out for that internship for the internship.
Over the summer, and the internship itself was a bit of a disaster.
I will say, and I
All I can say about that.
Just being completely honest is I showed up and the guy who I had
interviewed with had had in classic Microsoft fashion back.
Then, it is not Microsoft.
Now is a very milquetoast politically correct company.
When you go there, you will probably sit through hours of diversity,
training every year or something, where you watch a video that has
like one black, Persian one Asian person, you know, one Hispanic
person, one white person and like the right mix of females or
whatever, all doing things in an office.
Is that they shouldn't do and then a little, like red X comes up and
goes that was inappropriate behavior.
What you should have done, is blah, blah blah, right?
Like that is the company that they are right now and it's not their
fault.
When you get big as a company, you got to do this stuff.
There are lawsuits.
There's you know, just been incredible bulk.
That happens with a company where you're trying to manage 100,000
employees.
That's just what happens and happens to everyone.
It's happening.
The Google Now.
It happened to Microsoft back then and happens to everybody.
But at that time, which is this is back in 93 or 94 or something like
that.
I know somewhere somewhere in there, Microsoft was still kind of a
lean mean company.
They were 26, buildings total.
I think at the time and their programmers were still super gung-ho,
really sharp dudes.
If you were working at Microsoft, you were pretty good usually and I
met a lot of really good people when I was there and
They it was the era of people throwing a monitor through a wall if
stuff went down.
And so basically what had happened was there was some huge blow-up
with the guy had interviewed with that.
Had nothing to do with me.
It was about the products in the way.
He was running them and he literally just a couple days before me.
And the other interns were going to be under him.
Showed up literally just stormed out of the building and didn't come
back.
Like nobody knew where he went.
He just left.
He was so pissed about what had gone down.
I guess he just left.
So I show up.
And there's this other guy, his name, I think was Bruce Johnson and he
was a person who used to work at this sort of like he used to work at
a company that did like, defense Contracting graphic stuff.
I think he originally worked, he worked on a thing since I think he
might have worked on simnet.
I don't know if he did or not.
Anyway, it doesn't matter point, being, he's there and I'm like, who
are you?
And he's like, well,
The guy who is supposed to be your guys's manager and I'm there with
like this other guy.
I think it was Rudy celebration.
I don't remember who the other guy.
Was.
He showed up on the same day?
Might have been Rajiv.
Koyla.
I do.
Remember.
There's a couple guys there who are also entering at the same time as
me.
They were better programmers.
They were like from college, you know, so I'm the stupidest one in the
bunch for sure and I don't know what the hell's going on because I'm a
high school student.
So I don't know how to behave in a corporate setting or anything.
I'm just an idiot.
I'm complete.
Waste of time, but I'm there.
And so the other dude I'm with, you know, they set us down and they're
like look.
The two of you were supposed to be where he's gone and nobody knows
when he's coming back.
So, I'm gonna sort of be your manager for now and we're only there for
two months and this guy is out.
So it's like, all right, well fine.
And so he gives them something to do and he tells me he's like, I want
you to write a library for basically for loading.
And I files, which were the thing was some hacked up POS format that I
don't know who came up with it, but
Basically, on Windows, there was a time when you could have animated
cursors and I don't know if those are still around anymore.
But if you remember and like the original NT 351, and if you out there
who are old enough to remember this, and even going forward, I think
probably to nt4 still.
I don't know when it stopped happening.
But if you went into the mouse cursor settings, you could pick some
absolutely ridiculous stuff.
There was like a walking dinosaur, like a dinosaur that walks while
you're moving the mouse cursor.
It's
Is there, these little like things?
And so, what they had is, they had written a little file format called
an eye, which basically had a bunch of little bit map frames in it.
And I think they were only 16 color bitmap frames because this was
cursors.
We're still done with a hardware overlay at that point, on most of the
graphics cards of the day.
I want to say and so they were like 16 color only and you loaded them
in to make little cursor animations, like the walking dinosaur or like
a pointer that wiggles or
The stupid things like this.
No one cared about and what he was like.
As we want to do this thing.
We don't have a format to load animations from.
I don't think he really knew what he was doing.
So he this maybe he was just trying to make up something for me to do
and that's fine too.
But this is makes no sense.
But it was like they were try to do something with animations.
They want to do something with 3D and 2D overlay.
It seems like go right in and I loader.
So we can load and I files and it like, show them on tops of stuff.
But like, they're these little tiny.
I mean, they're like 16 by 16 or 32.
By 32, I think maximum, Maybe by 16 color.
I mean, I don't even know.
I don't know what he thought was going to happen, but he wasn't.
I think maybe thinking it through anyway, she's like, go write a
library for those.
So I did, I went wrote a library to load those.
I like Thomas back.
I don't know how it was on some server somewhere or something like
this.
He probably wanted me to it.
I wrote a library that
Of them.
And I wrote a little app, use the library but just kind of showed the,
you know, just showed the little things or whatever and then I had
nothing to do and so they were like the other guy was busy, but
working on some 3D stuff, one of the other interns who was pretty
good.
And then, you know, there was some other guys who are working on sort
of some opengl rendering who weren't interns and they were working on
this project and so they needed some 3D art.
So actually what I did for most of the rest of the internship was I
just made 3D art for them.
I
bought a copy of 3D Studio.
This is the first time I really had an experience with like exactly
how cheap money is for.
And I won't use the term these people because I am these people now
who work in this industry, but like at the time, the concept that you
would just send email and a three thousand dollar piece of software
which show up at your desk.
The next day was absurd, right.
I probably three thousand dollars would have been all the money.
I'd ever made in my lifetime and then some because I think the
Microsoft internship paid something like twenty four hundred dollars.
Or I don't know how much it made but it was more than I would have
ever made in any job at all by far.
Right.
And so prior to that three thousand dollars.
There's no way I was ever going to have my hands on three thousand
dollars.
If something got purchased for three thousand dollars that I my
parents would just have to be being extremely nice to me.
And buying me something expensive because I mean three thousand
dollars was a lot.
Or them to like it wasn't three thousand dollars, a lot of money.
But that's exactly what happened.
I was like, all right.
Well, I kind of knew how to use 3D Studio a little bit because there
is this pirate copy from this BBS guy that I knew.
So I had seen it before and I had used it before, but I didn't really
spent any serious time but it didn't really know what to do.
But I'm like, well, if we need to make 3D art, I know you can make it
in that if you can load it out of that and there were no artists at
this place.
So I'm like, if we could get a copy of that, you know, and I don't
know what to do.
I certainly can't power it something at Microsoft and
Try and call up people but can we pirate a copy of this thing?
Because it's got to be a legitimate, right?
So I don't know what to do, but they're like us, no problem.
So, someone sends a thing in and it's not one box of 3D Studio that
shows up.
It was like, at least two, it could have been like for, I don't
remember how many showed up, but it was like multiple boxes of three
thousand dollar software showed up and I'm like what the fuck?
So like that's I probably shouldn't use those that language on the
screen in case
Are children watching?
I apologize.
And I'm like, wow, that's crazy.
Like you can just send mail and like twelve thousand dollars worth of
software shows up on your desk.
That's insane.
So I made art with that for the rest of the time.
I didn't really do much programming.
They were doing some stuff in C++ and I didn't know C++.
I only knew see at the time and so I would have just gone back home
and that would have been it but we get to the meat of the story now.
Of the, the bizarre part of the story, which is I also was one of the
only people who is under 18 because almost everyone else was in
college.
I was not legally allowed to really do anything like drive a car
because a car rental company doesn't rent to you.
If you're under 18, I did find out there was a loophole to this
somewhat later, which was that?
It turns out that if you tell the people you're from Microsoft, they
just rent you the car.
This was very strange.
I at one point, A friend of mine came out to visit me while we were
there and we want it.
He was a friend of mine.
He he's like an outdoorsy guy, which I'm not really, but he was like
we should go, you know, we should go up to like Crystal Peak or
something.
We should go out to the mountains.
I'm like we can try and so like I went to a car rental place.
I don't remember how I got there.
I don't know if I took the bus or I think maybe I had somebody drive
me because again, I was friends with that, Microsoft executive guy and
their families out there, so I probably had someone maybe drop me off.
And when to the car rental place, I'm like, I want to rent a car and
I'm like, I have a valid driver's license, you know, but I'm like 16
and a half or 17 or something.
Right?
And so they're like, we can't rent you a car and I'm like, well, I
work at Microsoft.
I'm entering their for summer and like, Okay, and like gave me the car
and I'm like, alright, that's pretty amazing.
I don't know if this thing.
Microsoft's, good for it at that point or what, but they were just
like fine with it.
So we
Able to go with anyway, so so it turns out you actually came into car.
But anyway point being I'm out there and I'm living in a place that's
literally a block away from campus for the Microsoft campus.
I just walk to work every day and back and honestly, I thought it was
the greatest thing ever.
I if I had been smarter at the time a little bit smarter, I would have
just F and stayed like there's no way.
I would have gone back to high school, high school was awful and I
didn't have any interest in going to school anymore.
I hated school.
I just wanted to program computers for the most part and that's
What I got to do every day and everyone at Microsoft is smarter than
me and everyone there.
Knew more programming than me.
So it's like an and you can send mail and get three thousand dollars
worth of software delivered to your desk.
Like, why would you ever want to leave?
There's free drinks just around.
Like any sort of that you want?
Is there?
This cafeteria was subsidized.
I paid like four dollars a day to eat, right?
And for me, this is amazing.
Like this was the best thing that ever happened and I if I had any
clue at all.
I would have just like tried to be a better programmer as there.
And just said, can I just stay here?
Like, don't send me back there, don't send me back to high school
because unlike a lot of people, I guess I didn't have it.
I really liked all my friends in high school.
I actually liked the people that I went to high school with a lot of
friends of mine who are programmers.
Said, they had like bad experiences high school or like they were like
an outcast or something.
I don't even know, but I actually really like the people at high
school.
I think that's why I went back, but High School like sitting in
classes was awful.
It was the worst thing ever.
And I
Absolutely never wish that on anyone.
It was the worst thing is terrible.
So anyway, I didn't do that.
But you know, that's what I should have done the time but point being
getting back to the story, free food was a big deal or subsidized
food, I should say and there was free food, sometimes to they'd have
these in turn events that like HR would schedule and they would have
like free food for us and they would set up like volleyball and stuff.
I mean for somebody who's like spent their whole life programming.
Themselves.
And really the only thing that you get for that is people think that
you're the smart computer kid in class or whatever is really the only
thing that happens because you know, how to program going into an
environment where suddenly everyone really likes the fact that you
program and does all of these things for you is kind of amazing.
And so I think nowadays probably people take that for granted because
everyone just knows if you work a computer company is super fancy and
people Ride Scooters down the hall and you get all this free food.
It's like that was not.
Thing back then.
And so I was amazed and totally, it was totally awesome.
But when dinner chyme rolled around, there was no dinner.
I mean, everyone was gone, everyone left for the day, right?
So by 6:00 7:00, there is no one left.
And I'm just sitting there at my desk and I don't have any food and I
wasn't much of a cook and don't have a car.
So it's like this thing now.
It's like this.
It's like, how am I going to eat tonight?
You know, and I did the obvious thing.
I'd like just buy more food at lunch or I'd like buy food at lunch and
take it back with me or like a think the dude who I was rooming with
intern housing.
He like had a car.
So I just pay him.
I think and he would go to the supermarket and he would bring back
food for me too.
But eventually this is where the luck part strikes against 01 luck.
Was that someone asked me to come out to a student intern?
Am I?
Is off any at all.
That was complete luck and was not deserted.
Like I didn't do anything to have that happen other than the fact that
I had been programming computers a lot.
So it's complete luck that I got there.
And then the second thing, a complete luck.
Was the fact that I didn't know how to cook.
I didn't really know how to make dinner.
I love to cook now, but I didn't know anything there.
So, I was often at my desk late at night.
I had nothing to do, didn't have any dinner and I started to hear
noises kind of around in the building.
I'd hear people and
Walking and I see, like this weird dude with a totally messed up
African looking hat on his head and I probably using the wrong term.
I associate with an African hat because I feel like, they're there are
certain tribal cultures that use this kind of a hat.
It's like a, it's basically like a cylinder with a top and you put it
on your head.
Right?
And it's colorful they're kind of cool looking but I don't know the
culture of the various different regions of Africa.
It's a huge country and there's tons of different
Plus there.
But for some reason I associate that with with like, you know, some
kind of, some kind of a tribal decoration, tribal symbol hat or
something.
So, there's this guy walking around in that with that hat, on his
head.
And I'm like, what where is he going?
So I just kind of followed him I think and in he went into this
conference room, and there's all this food there.
There is like for chafing dishes of food and it's 8 o'clock or
something at night.
I don't even know it.
Slate, and it's all this food there.
And there's two other guys.
I think were there, at least one of the guy and I'm like, hey, you
know, what's going on?
What's all the food for it?
Turns out, the guy in the Hat is Chris Hecker.
He works there at the time.
He's working on wind G, which is like this game.
This thing to support games is like Fast bleeding on Windows machines.
You try to basically get games on Windows.
He's running a group to shift.
This wind G thing, under Mike Edwards, the guy who flamed out and left
the building and you
Came back.
He ended up coming back, two weeks later and it was this huge thing.
But he, you know, at that point they kind of had disciplined him for
this action.
It was, it was a little crazy, right?
Not important.
That's the details of his life and I don't know, the specifics, but
point being he was under Mike Edwards and I guess the flame out the
whole fight that Mike Edwards.
It had with management was over Chris's project because they weren't
supposed to be doing it or something, and he was kind of protecting
Chris's project because he thought it was a good idea and it was a
good idea by the way.
But anyway, Chris is running this project and actually
A working for Chris.
At the time I believed was was Alex st.
John, the guy who ended up running wild tangent, and who did the
DirectX evangelism if any of, you know, who that was.
He was Chris's evangelist.
Unwin G.
He was responsible for going around.
Pitching Chris's project to external game companies.
He used to evangelize printers printer drivers to people like mitt
right, your printer drivers for Windows, and he actually was working
for Chris at the time and in that room.
I think it
Chris, I want to say it was John Blossom, who is working with Chris on
Wednesday.
The project John Blossom later went on to do some indie games himself.
He also worked on Star Wars, droid works and Sim Park and stuff like
that.
I don't know.
He worked on a bunch of things.
Anyway, I was like, hey, can I like, you know, can I have some this
food?
You mind if I eat some of this food?
And I think they were like, sure, I probably getting the details
slightly wrong.
Because I'm a tell you one other thing in the second here and I'm not
sure which one of them actually happened first, but they were lecture
there because they had more food than they needed.
And basically what it was is because when G was technically in beta
shipping or something like this, Microsoft was providing food for them
and paying for it.
So, there is just free food every night now.
So, basically, every night I hung out with Chris and them and would
chat and whatever, and we got to be friends.
So I was also someone who right before then.
I had learned to play Doom.
Because we had Doom at home before.
I think that for the the internship and of course, Chris and John
often set up doom on the local network at Microsoft, because you could
play local network games of Doom multiplayer, which set up a local
network, plaything of Doom and just play it a bunch at night, when no
one else was there, right?
So, so that I don't know how much development of wengie was actually
happening at night between the food and the Doom, but I didn't care
because that was not my product.
I know.
What's going on?
So I just basically was like eating free food.
So I had some for dinner now and playing Doom at these guys and I love
doom and I've never played it multiplayer before, so that was awesome
and everything was great.
So anyway, that is really how I ended up getting into game programming
because Chris, like me well enough and he thought it would be cool if
we work together after that.
So he
Me to a bunch of his friends who were game mystery people.
And after I finished high school, I came out to Seattle to work with
Chris.
Now, the game that we worked on never shipped.
You never even really even got going, because he was starting a
company, and we kind of worked on it together, but I eventually
stopped and went and got a real programming job basically, but we
worked on it for a little while.
So, basically, I went with Chris and John Blossom guy from Benji and
another guy called John Ross, who's actually the programmer, the PC
programmer of SimCity 2000.
SimCity 2000.
The Mac side was written by by will write obviously, and the PC side
was written by this other guy.
John Ross, the four of us worked on a game together for a little
while.
It didn't pan out.
But by that time Chris had introduced me to lots of gay people.
So I could get a gut job in the game industry, which I did and I was
still an absolutely terrible program at the time.
I work for gas powered games for a little while, and did absolutely
nothing useful for them because I was allowed to programmer.
I then
To rad game tools after that and that is basically where I learned to
program for real.
Jeff Roberts.
The guy who basically runs Red game tools and has programmed every
version of Smacker and every version of Bink up too.
Big to where me and Fabien did work on it.
But basically, he had done all the work before, then.
It was just Jeff Roberts.
His wife did the accounting.
I think do the books, Mitch Sewell, who was a sales guy.
And what's his name?
I don't remember what the the receptionist name of Colin, the
receptionist and a guy named John Miles.
That was the entirety of rad at the time when I went to work there.
So I was like, it was it was basically, the only programmers were
Jeff.
John and me.
Now, John Mi is actually very, very famous game industry person.
You may not have heard of him recently because he doesn't really do
any game stuff anymore, but,
He was the guy who wrote.
I think a lot of the Ultima 5 engine Ultima 5 going way back.
He did like a lot of I think he did the texture mapper for Wing
Commander for the first one that actually had real 3D, you know, he
wrote the Mi sound system, which is what almost every game used for
audio.
At that time.
He was the tech director at digital Anvil the people who did like
starlancer and freelancer and that Chris Roberts kind of totally, I
guess I don't want to impinge any.
The ones reputation here, but like, kind of cratered and I don't think
it had much to do with John Miles.
But anyway, that was what he did before.
I guess he went off to Hollywood to make the movie of wing, Commander,
the movie or whatever.
Make no, I guess it was after that.
I don't even remember that.
You got to go look at the history of this.
I don't remember.
But John Miles point being was a was a very famous programmer for a
long time.
And then his first love was always Hardware.
So eventually he just kind of retired from software at all, and he
does Hardware now, Luke Harper design.
So anyway, I went to rad and that's where I basically spent.
And the rest of my career up until the point where I decided to leave
and do try my hand game design, one of the reasons that I say over and
over again.
I'm not doing any game design on this project.
I'm just gonna do very straightforward old-school game designers
because I am terrible game design.
I tried designing a game is called sushi bar, Samurai and the
implementation of the game went very well.
Because, hey, I know how to program.
And I also know a lot of stuff about art.
So I was able to make a bunch of art for the game.
The art looked real good.
The design of the game is terrible because I
Trying to design a new thing instead of like making an old thing that
I understood.
I try to design a new thing and I was not good enough for that.
I think I know enough design to design, you know, a traditional game
and not mess it up too badly.
And that is exactly what I want to do on this stream, but I clearly
proved to myself that designing new stuff.
If something better left to The Experts, so if you're going to design
a game that's like totally different from existing games.
I am not your guy that is, that is like John Blow territory or
genielle Bender.
Ah, GUI, I knew a lot of people who've got those skills, and I don't
have them.
So I still have that game and it's kind of cool.
Like there's some cool stuff in it and there's some cool Tech in it,
but the gameplay is awful and it just never really amounted to
anything.
So I table that and since then I've just basically worked on game
check, which I think is mostly what I'm good at is just technology for
games.
And so I worked on a project called larabee.
Which was Intel's attempt basically making a card that could do CPU
and GPU stuff.
So that you just have one processor.
That did everything essentially that, so you didn't need a separate
graphics card and it was a pretty cool project.
But it there is a number of political reasons that Intel that it
looked like it just was not going to work and so I left that project
shortly before it kind of collapsed.
I was I was more like I was kind of a rat off of a sinking ship at
some level, but it was kind of fun because I got to work on.
Low level implementation of Graphics like of DirectX basically.
That was working with like Batman binstock and Mike a Brash and Mike
Startin and later Fabien, but I he came on actually after I was off
the project to do some cleanup work with Altman because they stop sort
of working on the main line driver at that point that turned into
Intel high performance Computing.
So instead of making graphics card out of the thing, we were making,
they ended up just making a high performance Computing.
Part the facially used for crunching huge numbers and you can still
buy.
You can actually buy it.
But if you don't use it as a graphics card, basically,
After that, I worked on pink to with with Jeff and I basically did all
the like sort of research code, implementations style things if that
makes any sense, and so I essentially did stuff that like Jeff would
go.
I need these blisters or I need this thing, or I need a filter that
will do blah and I would go do those for him.
And I also made a debugging system called mustache, for that, which is
pretty cool.
If we're bored on the stream sometime.
I'll demo mustache.
It's a pretty cool thing.
And I also did after that.
I worked on the witness for a little while with John doing their
Collision detection system and upgrading the editor as well as a
couple other things, which I documented witness Wednesdays.
And that is the end.
And I'm now working on some stuff that I haven't announced yet, which
is what I do during the day and I'm doing handmade here at night and
that is pretty much everything.
I probably forgot some stuff, but that is pretty much everything.
So, hopefully that answered the question.
I'll take it.
Quick.
Look at the stream, just to see if there's anything obvious that I
left out.
See here.
How do I get down to the end?
Can I use page down?
There goes?
All right.
Let's see.
Someone said you should probably put your webcam at 100% of the screen
space during the Q&A session saw.
Yes, that would be smart.
That requires a certain level of sort of prowess here that I don't
know.
So I'm expecting I suspect my probably have to do some kind of
Some kind of like setting up multiple profiles.
So I'll take a look at that for next time because you're right if
we're going to do some kind of weird chat days, which we might want to
do at some point.
I'm going to write that down to make some way.
I can quick switch between the two quick switch.
Two full webcam.
All right, so, I don't know who stayed for that.
Ridiculous rambling, nonsense.
It looks like almost everyone.
Well.
That was Story Time with Casey.
I have to go now.
So thank you very much.
Everyone for tuning into the very last test dream.
I hope you had a good time.
I know I did, and I hope to see everyone tomorrow for the inaugural
stream of handmade hero.
And yes, I hope to see you all there.
If there's anything that you would like to ask, feel free to go to the
handmade hero website.
Where there is this little email question button if you want to know,
when we are
Broadcasting, the tweets button has a stream that basically all it
does is is send out notifications when the stream is coming every day.
So you can just quick look at that.
You don't have to subscribe to it.
If you don't want to, you can just literally just pop over here and
just look at what the what the top is and it'll tell you, and some
point, we'll try to have a countdown timer on here.
But anyway, that's it for today.
And I hope to see everyone here tomorrow.
Thanks everybody.