Okay.
Hello everyone.
And welcome to a special edition of handmade hero today.
My my very special guest is Sean McGrath who many of you already know
because he does programming streams as well.
That you've probably watched essentially what we're doing today is a
while, back on handmade hero.
And I to be honest, have completely forgotten, the reason, it
initially came up because it I think it came up even before,
potentially we did the the career story straight.
So my temptation is to say it was part of the career story stream but
in reality I think it came up before that I was talking about how the
interview process at tech companies, is not something that I
particularly agree with personally, and I was trying to explain how a
fellow named Chris Hecker, who is actually the primary developer on
game, called spy party which you may have heard of.
But he's had he's been in the industry.
A long time, he worked at Microsoft did win, G back in the day.
And he did the the animation system and the creature, morphology
system for Spore, which is pretty awesome Tech if you've never seen
it.
So he actually has an interview process that he taught me and that I
think is is really, really good.
You know, I can't say one way or another, what the perfect interview
process is but it certainly struck me as an interview process, that is
dramatically better than what, you know, people tend to use today.
When you see, how Tech interviews are conducted and how sort of, like
companies like Google, or Facebook, or this Microsoft conduct their
interviews.
And so what I wanted to sort of get across, was how that interview
process worked and on the stream.
Sean actually said, hey if you want to do it I'll just pretend to be
an interviewee and you can pretend to be the interviewer and you can
do the interview and so people can see how it's done and that's like
that sounds awesome.
Now unfortunately.
You know, I'm not Chris.
So I'm probably not as good at it as, you know, as patient zero but I
probably good enough at it, that you should be able to see how it goes
and kind of see.
Oh, okay, I get it, I get how to do this and it does require a little
bit of practice on the part of the interviewer, but that's how it
goes.
So first of all, Shawn, thanks so much for being with us, bro.
You have said you've got a sore throat today.
So I apologize for for, for
That we're putting putting extra strain on your voice, but this is,
this has been a months-long struggle, so, it's okay.
It's the wintertime, right?
That's, that's how that is in Canada, in Canada, in Canada.
How deep into Canada?
Are you Sean?
I don't know.
I've sent Toronto.
It's not that, okay?
So you're not that deep.
I remember further south than you are, but it's way colder.
Okay.
Yeah, because we've got the weird temperature inversion here, or
whatever nonsense you've got the Pacific Ocean.
Okay, well, so let me just say a quick thing about the interview and
then we'll sort of pretend to
Started.
I'm going to try and start at about 11:30.
So, the idea behind this interview is sort of to correct some of the
problems with the standard interview process that you see in Tech.
And one of the things that you typically see in Tech interviews is
programmers, are given like a programming problem of some kind, or a
tech problem of some kind, or a brain, teaser of some kind.
And you've probably seen this sort of thing, mentioned a lot,
discussed a lot online.
There are books now that you know, purport to train you or
Or, or show you the kinds of programming puzzles that you might face
if you are going to try to get a programming job.
And that's very endemic to have the programming industry at large.
Kind of does these sorts of interviews and just personally and also I
think other people probably can attest to who've gone through these
interview process has a really big problem with this is that it has
nothing to do with the act of programming.
And you know you may say well it's a programming problem.
Really has some into the act of programming.
But what I mean to say is the fundamental construct of coming into
someone's office that you've never met before being presented, a
relatively potentially depending on the, on the circumstance or
potentially tricky, programming puzzle.
And being asked to solve it on the spot is nobody's job in Tech,
right?
That is not something that you ever do day-to-day.
A programmers job is a marathon, not a Sprint.
You spend many hours programming.
The most problems of any non-trivial nature.
You will spend many hours, acquainting yourself with first becoming
comfortable with the concepts reading about what other people have
done in that area, forming opinions about what might be the right ways
to approach it experimenting with the code and whether or not a
particular programmer, can solve a puzzle in 30 minutes is kind of
irrelevant to whether they'll do a good job on a programming problem
given a week or two which is what you actually care about in the job.
And so the big
Problem with the way that programming interviews are conducted, is
they focus very much on this and it's inherently kind of an
adversarial process.
You're giving someone a puzzle you know the answer.
They don't you are forcing them in an already pressure or situation to
perform Under Pressure pressure that will not be there in their actual
job they will not have you hovering over them when they're attempting
to solve a programming problem.
They may be someone who's very nervous by nature and this may make it
very difficult for them to concentrate.
They may
may be self-conscious about their own programming ability, even though
they may be very good, they may still be self-conscious and this will
affect their ability to solve the problem in the search situation
where they feel like they're being tested.
So there's all of these things that kind of conspire to really, I
think produce unfair results in the process and that's not just a
problem.
For the person interviewing, who will get unfairly potentially
rejected from a job even though they might have been the best person
for that job.
But it also hurts the hiring side because you may be turning away.
Lots of people who would have been great at your company and very good
at what you needed them to do, simply because their personality, or
their mental state.
At the time is not up to the task of solving, these pinpoint pressure
kind of problems.
And so, what this interview is designed to do is to sort of get past
that as the Central Way at this essential turning point of a
Job interview and try to turn it into something more friendly and
comfortable.
So that the programmer isn't constantly aware of this pressure and to
maybe get them out of that head space so that they can behave more
like they would in the real work environment which is, I think a
fairer test of their ability.
So that's all I wanted to say is the preamble.
And I also, again, apologize.
If I don't do the best job on this maybe someday Chris, Hecker will
demonstrate it on History, he streams occasionally, maybe he would
stream one where he would interview somebody.
And he can correct any mistakes that I make here.
But there we go.
So,
Without further Ado, let's we're going to pretend that Sean and I
don't know each other even though we do and we're also going to
pretend that I haven't ever seen him stream code.
So I'm going to pretend I don't have any knowledge of anything that
he's done and I'm going to have to get all of that information out of
the interview myself.
Alright Sean you ready?
Let's do it.
Okay.
So, hey Sean, thanks for coming in today.
How how, how you been how's it going?
I have been great other than my sore throat.
How are you?
I'm pretty good.
I feel like for whatever reason Saturdays, I sometimes have trouble
getting up in the morning at the time that I should.
So, I've got some coffee here, I hope it's going to kick in.
If I seem a little bit Dopey, that's not representative or a company
that's representative of the earliness.
So I apologize up front for that.
Are same because I stayed up until 6:00 in the morning playing DOTA.
So, how often do you like Toda?
Oh yeah.
I mean, I assume if you stayed up till 66 playing it.
Oh, yeah.
Well, six of the morning my time that's only like, 3 or X.
So, so do you are you like a fan of online games in general or mobas
in general?
Or do you like is that?
Is that like an anomaly?
Because sometimes Dota or League of Legends like an outlier for
people.
Yeah.
I know I'm a big fan of Esports, I followed the Korean esport scene
since the late.
90s.
Oh wow.
And I've just sort of been enthralled by that but by the idea of the
sort of they're not really games at that level, like they're no longer
a breakdown, the video game part of it and become like this, almost
like mental chess with crazy reflect sort of like one-on-one
experience that I really enjoy watching.
So I've been a fan of that and I think DOTA is currently although
Starcraft.
Good work has come back, thankfully in Korea, but I think DOTA is sort
of the Pinnacle of that at the moment.
What the, what got you into Korean Esports that early because I feel
like, you know, a lot of people probably work.
Well, you know, in the late 90s, I think a lot of people probably
weren't aware of that scene at all, or, you know, kind of what even
the gaming scene was like, in Korea, if they weren't from, you know,
that country or thereabouts?
Yeah, I don't know.
I've always been a competitive person, so I
I played lots of sports when I was a kid.
And then when I was 12 or 13, I got an approach when I was 12 or 13.
I got into programming and I started making video games and that's
what sort of got me into video games.
And I just, I didn't have time for sports anymore because all I was
doing this programming.
So I had to get like something or playing games and programming.
So I had to get like some sort of competitiveness out, so I started
playing video games competitively and at the time Warcraft 2 was sort
of the most viably.
Viably competitive game and then Starcraft came out.
So I was playing that.
And then I found out about, I found out that some shoe company was
making Starcraft shoes in Korea, no way.
Like in like, 1998 or 1999 and like now that doesn't seem like a big
deal but like 20 years ago.
Yeah, video game branded shoes, that's crazy.
That would never happen here.
So I was like in Korea, there they go, crazy for this.
This is interesting, right?
So start doing a little bit of research on Korea and Esports and that
was when French
Canadian player named XDS GE GE are are moved from Quebec to Korea to
compete.
And I was like, oh my God, this is crazy.
So I was like, this is what I want to do.
So then when Warcraft 3 came out.
I played it so much that I was top 100 in u.s.
East.
Are you thirsty?
Yeah, I was yeah.
So I just, I don't know.
I've just always found.
I'm really competitive and I really like, I don't really like video
games anymore, but I used to really like video,
Games and I like programming.
So it's sort of, you know, it's a natural sort of thing.
So, tell me a little bit about that because, like, this is, this is
something that I've never for whatever reason, like, Competitive
Gaming.
I've almost never gotten into.
I don't that just because I maybe I'm just bad at it.
So I don't like, I'm not as interested in doing because I don't think
I'll be good.
I'm not sure though.
I just I've never quite done it.
So like do you generally like, is I feel like looking at your resume
here?
Like you
It doesn't look like you've ever really worked on Esports kind of
titles is that?
Because you like to keep that separate like you like to kind of have
Esports as as your recreational activity and you'd rather work on like
single player games or stuff like that.
As the as, you know, the job or is that just circumstantial?
Like it's like, hey, you know, I I never really had the opportunity to
go work on a Esports title, I was crazy about.
So I didn't and someday.
I'd really like to or like, you know what I mean?
Like, how does that fit in for you?
Yeah, I've sort of like, all the
I have video games like playing video games is basically gone for me I
don't enjoy certain to do more than I'd like to admit I suppose.
Well it's just like we would need make them for so long.
Right.
You see how the sausage is made whenever you play it?
Whenever I play game all I just see is like 100 suffering people,
right?
So it's kind of like I kind of don't get joy in playing video games
anymore, but I find that the technology and then the technology
requirements and the sort of
Of.
Programming ethos that exists in video games is the only one that I'm
interested in anymore and I still find really interesting problems
that are more or less only available in video games and like the
programming style that I like is more or less only appropriate to
video game.
So I still really enjoy the technical problems of video games and
solving those problems but actually playing them.
That's kind of that's long gone.
So what kind of technical problems are we talking about here?
When you say like the ones in video games versus you know, some other
Kind of kind of thing.
Right?
Like what's an example just so I just just to frame I mean I think I
can guess but I don't want to put words in your mouth, right?
Like I mean you probably have a very more specific idea of what you
consider.
An interesting technical problem.
Yeah, I don't know.
It's just like anything that's like, you know, where we actually care
about the resources of the system, and we want to do, take maximum
advantage of them to, to a point, right?
Like there's, there's crazy optimization stuff that I find
interesting, but I'm not
It's not like practical to do that on a wide scale basis, but like,
just generally, like, okay, we have, this is what our Hardware is.
How many triangles can be good on the screen.
How many times can we overdraw pixels on the screen?
How much transparency can we have?
What sort of things can we do in this space?
Like how should we partition our geometry?
How should we tessellate things?
All of these things?
All of these questions are how to maximize, what result we have,
whatever, we want that result to be, and it's not like, I know like
Facebook or whatever, they're going to be like, well, we can get 1%
more and of hip-hop video.
Amber whatever, right?
Or and it's like that's just not as interesting of a problem when the
solution can be just go build a Data Center and he planted up another
degree wherein wherein program where in games it's like no you have
this one x64 thing.
Make a photo realistic screen happen or make a photo realistic image
happen on the screen 90 times a second, right?
Like how do you do that?
Right.
And in that there are tons of little interesting little technical
problems that I enjoy solving.
So, which it looks like you did two major games here, dyad + + + + +.
Yeah, we're there are others that that you enjoy doing those were?
I mean, did you like those projects?
I guess, I should say like, how did you feel about them?
Yeah.
Other projects that you that you preferred to those.
That maybe I'm not aware of.
Yes.
Oh, I've done.
I did the sound effect.
System for Sound Shapes, as well for the Vita.
And the PS3, I did the backend and part of a scripting language,
implementation and rendering implementation in Flash for an MMO back
in 2005 or 2006.
So, did the entire back-end for that some of the renderer scripting
language things?
I've done that I've done contract on small contract work like, hey, we
need to make this load in less than four hours, right?
Stuff like that.
Door handle.
We split this geometry upset as faster.
I've had a little contract jobs like that on various projects but
yeah, the biggest ones are dyad.
I did everything myself.
Except the music which is a lot of work like all the design, all the
art, all about, okay.
Publishing stuff like everything and then n plus plus I just did the
programming so but only on the PS4 version not the PC version which of
those projects was your favorite or it's you did you have a clear
favorite or did you just kind of like I mean getting some perspective
on them.
Daya
I put I was so burnt out after finishing diet that I didn't play for
three years and then when I did play it, I wish I had like tears about
how much I love about how much I love the game.
It's like my favorite game.
So I love everything about it and I assumed that I was going to hate
it at the end of it because it was such a traumatic experience, right?
And then but when I played it three years later, I was like this is
the best game I've ever played in my life.
So I felt really good about that.
So did
You did you feel like that project is your favorite from a game
playing standpoint and also a technical standpoint or did you feel
like technically other projects were more interesting and dyad was
more?
Just the end product was, was your favorite?
Like which was your favorite to have done the work for versus to play?
I guess it does that excite?
Say the question?
Yeah, I think one of the so there's a couple of interesting things
that I did in both of those two games will talk about the two games.
Because the ones that was primarily it all the programming for both of
them.
Yeah.
So
Dyad it loads about 100 megabytes of text textures and about.
I can't remember 130 megabytes of sound on the PS3 with no load times.
So that was a lot of asset pre-processing and just mapping everything
out into chunks that you just mem copy.
Basically and then just set the pointers up and what refresh my memory
because well and actually, I shouldn't say refresh my memory.
I never actually ship something for the PS3.
So what
I don't actually know if the PS3, what kind of constraints were on the
load times there?
I mean that's it was this loading from a disk or downloadable it was
downloadable but like it's the harder of super super slow.
Okay.
And it was segmented memory, it will not segmented like the old ways
but it wasn't unified memory where the GPU could access CPU memory.
So there are two separate things but we ran, I ran over the budget on
the, on the CPU side of things.
So I had to chunk some of the sound onto the GPU memory and
The spu's can read to both.
So there was a lot of, but I choose you talking like eight years ago
at this point, right?
So but yeah, so there was a lot of that that was interesting, kind of
like
It's kind of dumb work.
Like it's like, oh my God, this is such a stupid constraint, how do we
solve this thing?
But at the same time it's also like this is kind of an interesting
solution.
Right.
I guess it's kind of an interesting problem of like how do we get this
thing to not have to load?
Okay, so it's a big endian machine.
So you got to put everything you have to do an asset pre-process on
everything to put it all into big endian.
What if we you know, try different texture compression things.
It's like well, what if instead of texture compressing we just used
for channels of uncompressed texture and then apply the color to eat
And also, essentially each channel is used as an alpha mask.
So that was the way I Des texture compression.
So that there was no artifacts around anything.
So, hold on a second because there's a bunch of stuff in there.
I just try to make sure I understand.
So let's starting with the with the loading stuff so basically like
you have to it sounded like you had maybe around 250 megabytes of of
asset footprint sounded like, you know, it's a little bit more and
more like 300.
Yeah.
Somebody hundred and that it has 512 Megs on the machine.
So yeah.
Is that like the uncompressed footprint doors that the footprint,
there was no compression, okay, okay.
So the uncompressed footprint is 300 megabytes.
So once the 300 megabytes is in there were good, but again, we've got
to get it off the hard drive, which is going to take probably at least
20 30 seconds.
Probably.
I don't remember what the speed of the hard drive was, but it wasn't
that long, but it was, it was over 10 seconds over 10 seconds.
So, so what was your approach to that?
Tell me like, did you just try to load everything?
With the background screaming like to get gimme.
Gimme some idea of what what the approach was.
I mean, so I know it's probably hard to remember, but just so I, yeah.
But basically, it was like, because the lovely levels were fairly
linear.
Yeah, it was.
And there was a lot of assets.
This was all done manually.
There was a lot of assets that were duplicated across multiple levels,
so they just always stayed loaded, right?
So but that was like a hundred and something MB, okay?
And then there was another 130 another 300 on top of that, okay?
So those three hundred because they were
Linear at the start of the level, or sort of the levels were linear at
the start of the levels.
You would need, you know, we could figure out what assets, you needed,
right at the start and we stuck the everything was there were two
files.
There was a GPU file to go into the GPU memory and the CPU filed ago,
in the CPU memory, and they were just ordered, like things that you
needed at the start were used at the start and then there was a thread
that was just mem, copying everything.
And hopefully, by the time, a pointer needed to be there.
The memory was there, okay?
So tell me a little
A bit more about this then.
All right.
So so I'm going into well it looks like the start of the startup of
the game needs.
I guess.
It sounds like a hundred megabytes or something of 150 megabytes of
startup data.
It sounds like you were sort of saying, how does that get in there or
is that just that happens?
Bring the save game.
Because on consoles the savegame API, I read this article about etw
being the worst API ever made, and I don't necessarily, but it's not.
Is that what you're saying?
Not its console savegame apis for the worst apis ever made.
Okay, tell me.
Tell me why I, oh, I can't just like the number of asynchronous
things, you have to keep track of and like the number of states that
can just suddenly change and the number of trc's that
Related to save games is just absolutely ridiculous.
Got it.
And you have to mount and unmount things and there's no like there's
no like file replaced, where it automatically makes a backup copy.
So you have to do that manually, okay, then it's okay it's just a it's
an absolute nightmare, right?
And just mounting a savegame like Mount point because I guess they're
chroot adore.
So I don't know how it works internally.
But like mounting a savegame mount point is like a three-second API
call.
And then on mounting it
Have to overlap it because yeah, you can't just sit there for three
seconds going.
Like, hey, do you felt here?
She's immediately?
Right.
Because I think you have like half a second or something where you
screen, doesn't refresh.
Ok.
So it's just awful right?
And there's no there's no good like the AP, the asynchronous apis at
least on the PS3 weren't good.
If I remember like the file IO apis.
Okay.
There were, there were, yeah, but I never use them.
I just made a thread and did everything manually in a separate thread,
right?
So it wasn't like,
Like those like file reading Windows where you pass it the overlap
thing and then just let the OS take care of it.
You manually did the threading.
So it was just like a bunch of dumb stuff.
You always do that at the very end, which makes things extra
frustrating.
So while that was happening, the savegame stuff was happening.
We were able to easily load the hundred Meg's that you would need for
the whole game.
So because you can save you and I, oh, like you could issue I owe for
the, for the, for the data that you needed and it would be able to
complete in
Time it took to wait for the savegame Tomato.
Laughs.
Okay.
Yeah, Steve game is like 12 bytes or something like that and it still
took, it took longer to load those 12 B than it did to load, 100
whatever was 96, or 100 Meg's or something like that.
Okay, so that comes into memory and you've just got it is what you're
saying and I guess is that partitioned as well, you kind of were
talking about the being partitioned between CPU and GPU.
Or how does that work?
It's all CPU memory.
Okay.
So partner Prince Ivan textures, but they're small.
All, but then now I go to start playing a level and I'm sort of going
through this level and you said, you've got a background thread going
and you said something about, hopefully the pointers there.
So tell me a little bit.
What is this thread do?
Like it, give me the web.
So if I remember correctly most of the most of the the data was sound
and if you're into jokes because you seemed to be having a good time,
we one of the marketing things that we did for dyad was uncompressed
audio right?
And because
Files think that he thinks that the cat.
So, all right so we'll let you were like, hey look guys.
Hey look, no compression.
No audio compression know everything digital artifacts here.
Well, I'll get to that.
All right, we didn't have audio compression only because it loaded
faster, right?
And because all of our sounds we, there were no, there's no music in
diet.
Everything was the stem of all the songs and then I wrote a dynamic
mixer, right?
So be playing like 30 or 40 Loops at a
Time and like any event that you do in the game with dynamically
change everything right?
Okay.
And so chord changes and stuff like that, we're all manual.
Like we would just swap where what sounds were playing, right?
Okay.
So it was complicated as hell but in order to do that in order to get
the decompression because there's an overhead of decompression with
Agra files when you first start it up, if I remember correctly and
then we couldn't use MP3 because we had to there was a royalty thing
at the time.
Anyway so cool.
Patent it up until like last year I think yeah.
Stop handed.
So that was a nightmare.
So we were just like screw it screw it.
We can just do it all with just raw PCM data.
So when we were marketing the game we were like hey raw PCM data.
But the sound the original samples that we used were like, 32k MP3s
like they were just terrible, right?
But like, we uncompressed them for Speed purposes and just told
everybody it was uncompressed audio, which was totally true.
So we did all of it, okay?
And people like, on forms were like, man, the audio is uncompressed.
This is so good.
And we're just like a laughing because it's like, yeah, it's Uncle.
Pressed from compressed.
Oh man.
So anyway, so what we would do is at the start of each level, there
would be like a list of, you know, 60 or 70 wav files that we would
use and the memory offset to where they were and we would line them
all up.
So that the first chunk of the memory was music that you needed at the
very start of the game, like the first.
Because like I said, like there were all the cord like we'd have,
like, seven sounds in a song and there'd be like five chords from
right as this 35.
35 sounds, but we know that we're starting on C major.
So we put C major first and then we put all the sound effects that are
for C major.
And then we, you know, maybe it goes down A fifth or something like
that.
We put that as the next chord, right?
That's just how it all worked, okay?
So we put the first score that you needed first.
And the second chord that you needed first, because the levels were
linear.
Yeah.
And then the header of the file was the B offsets to all of the all
the sounds that we needed.
Okay.
And we would just hope that by the time you got to
That part of the song that part of the level that loaded, otherwise,
you hear noise, and it never happened.
So we knew it was fast enough.
So basically you have this table that says, here are the B offsets and
we're going to jump to wherever that supposed to be and I'm going to
start playing that WAV file.
Whatever it is, now, hopefully, the thread.
The background thread has loaded that in by now but maybe it hasn't so
does the background thread loading in chunks or how is that working?
It was just a mem copy, or it was like a loop.
Them copies over, I don't remember a megabyte, like was a 96.
I don't remember exactly how it worked, but it was like a loop of mem
copies, would just keep doing it that way would update a progress
indicator of when when something was done.
So, we would know if we ever missed these, we do like mem copy because
it's coming from a hard drive, isn't it?
Yeah you just map the file and then copy.
Oh okay so it's using a memory mapped I/O not like an F, read sort of
style or right.
Right.
Okay.
And I would not, it would go MB out.
A time because I found that to be faster.
Just experimental e.
Like I do, like, do we map for MB?
We mapped the whole file.
Like, how do we do it?
And then what ended up being fastest?
If I remember correctly, was one megabyte.
But now I'm thinking, I might have been two megabytes whatever it was.
It was, I did a bunch of tests about how much we want to map.
What if we just map the whole file?
And then just do offsets, but that didn't work.
Because the OS scheduler, couldn't predict what it needed in memory
correctly.
If we were jumping around a lot.
So we just member, I just met my map.
What I needed.
I mapped a small chunk of what I need.
And then we just continuously map different parts of the file and then
mem copy it into a fixed chunk of memory.
I see, so basically your original approach was just a memory map, the
file and say, hey, we can just play right out of that, but it was too
much.
Just in time, like, you'd hit it and need it, and the OS wouldn't have
had time to go get it right.
And we, yeah, and like, the OS it's not, it doesn't solve all your
problems, right?
So it doesn't know, it didn't know what we would need it, but we
wouldn't know what we would need.
So we would be able to figure it out, got it?
Okay.
Yeah, like if I could have just memory about the file that would have
been amazing.
Would have been less work.
So.
All right.
So I guess going back to the original question there.
So technically speaking, which of the projects did you think was the
most fun, right?
Was was a diet, everything plus plus you haven't mention a Superman +
+ + + + had a lot of fun, fun things about it.
Regarding the tech that I don't really want to get into, especially on
stream.
But there was an interest, there was a couple of interesting.
There's one interesting thing about the on plus plus Tech which is how
the anti Alias or worked.
Okay.
How do we like to work?
It's a well, it's a line art game, so, because it's a line art game.
We're like, wow, there's a lot of pixels on a screen.
Let's make them as pretty as possible, right?
Because it's just lineart, okay?
But how the anti-alias our work is a little bit of a
It's a little bit insane, okay?
It's every pixel that you every line that's drawn is drawn as either.
It's signed distance field of either a circle Arc or a straight line,
right?
Everything is a circle Arc or straight line.
So we would draw.
I'm going to do a little Milton business here, good?
Yeah, be great.
All right, so what do we got screen to see?
Okay.
so basically what we were writing Shader that and what you would pass,
The Shader is, you know, P0 and P1, and there's a CPU side, I try to
Geometry Shader, don't you jump at your shaders?
I tried.
So I did this on the CPU side.
We're basically I'd say, I want to draw a line between here and here.
Okay.
And it would generate a triangle strip, you know, with points like
this or whatever.
Right.
So we generate you know your your six points I tried.
Protects indices to but it was faster to just draw six points.
So it would so you know there was a function that was like draw a line
between here and here, right?
So would draw.
So it figure out what these six points are and draw it, right?
And it would figure these out by two parameters thickness of the line,
right?
So that, you know, you thickness of your line is this, maybe right?
So you want to draw a line that's maybe this thick and everything is a
capsule, not aligned technically rights because it's the signed
distance field so we're going to get in by that to explain what you
mean by signed distance field.
So signed distance feel well at this
Field is basically a field like a 2d plane or 2D.
I guess it could be 3D surface where every point on the surface is a
function.
That is a distance to something.
So if you have to understand can I mean yeah that dried out here.
That's.
So let's do it.
We have this square, right?
This is our field will call this our field.
So you have a circle a circle in the middle, okay?
Each point on this rather than it being whatever you envision a point
to be, it is a function that is a value.
It's a function that you can evaluate each point at to be.
How far am I from this circle, right?
So you could say from this point, the value of this point here, the
value of this field is the distance from here to the the point of this
wouldn't be a circle.
Technically, we just be a point, right?
You have a point at the center so this value here is whatever this
distance here is
Right.
Okay, so this is like a mathematical function.
Yeah, it's a function.
What, where is it?
So what is the function for that?
Look like that you draw on there if you can you know what action for
this?
Yeah.
Like what's the actual function that we're talking about here?
Just so I understand call each of these points Q then we'll call the
your point P, okay?
It would be P minus q and then the length of that which is like p.x.
Askew dot X.
Squared, the Pythagorean theorem, you know, okis know why.
It's basically it's um, yeah, it's just the that's not what it is at
all.
But you know what it is?
Well guys.
I just want to make sure I get it like so so okay.
Yeah.
Can you just write out the function?
So I can see it and that way, when you're talking about the capsule,
one I can look back at it, if that makes sense and no, make the is
equal to P minus Q, which is the vector of that, okay?
And so V Dot V and then the square root of V Dot.
V is
Give you while you don't actually need the square root.
So V Dot V is going to give you the squared distance from here to here
which is the value of the function, right?
So why why don't you need the square root?
It's just an extra square root that you don't have to calculate like
why evaluate square root if you don't necessarily need it, right?
Well I just sorry I just meant like so if I've got this V Dot V and I
and I met just gives you the square so that gives you the squared
distances if you have 0 squared fall off, right?
So instead of having a linear like if you were to look at the distance
fall-off from the farthest point of the nearest point, right?
If you don't take the square, if you take the square root, you get a
linear.
If you do let's try it this way.
If you do take the square, if you don't take the square root, you get
like a function that looks like this.
So you technically do need to take the square root, okay?
Because you want to get a linear fall-off, right?
If you're doing I'm gonna explain why hold on.
Let me see if I can explain why.
So the reason why you do this, so if you were to take this and just
look at the function, right?
I'm gonna open Photoshop here.
So in Photoshop, if you were to take
Cake.
Come on, Phil.
Photoshop crashed.
Okay, that's all right.
So, if you were to take a look at, just what the function look like,
yeah, you'd get something like
Something like that.
So that's going to be what your distance field looks like.
Actually, I guess it would be inverted.
So that's going to be what your distance field looks like, right?
So out here in like so like out here, you have a distance of say one
because you're going to normalize it, over the area of the thing.
And here you're going to have a distance of zero, right?
So using the to normalize it over the area or normalize it over the
half width of the of the square, right?
So if you have a square here and it's this is 512 pixels.
You know that brawl this is going to be square root of 5 12 + 5, 12
squared.
So whatever this distance you, well we'll just use 512 for example,
right?
Because we're going to treat this as a circle, right?
So if we do that photoshop is not cooperating.
So let's just say, for example, we'll pretend that I drew the
centered.
and,
and it's stroke to it's in black and I want it in Red, so we'll do
this.
How about cornflower blue?
Well, cornflower blue and some blue here is that corn flour enough for
you?
Yeah, it's got to be corporate.
Okay, well, whatever that is, that's what it is, right?
So we're drawing a circle, we're just going to we're going to say that
for sake of argument that this is 512, this is
and 12 pixels.
This is 500.
Can I get the proper?
Button.
All right, so we're going to say this is 512 pixels, right?
Okay so you would draw a square that's exactly Jesus.
That's exactly 512 pixels.
And then at each point on the Square you compute the distance to say
the center point, right?
So right here and then you divide it by 512 so that you have a
normalized value between 0 and 1, right?
So at this point here, the farthest point on the circle is going to be
distance of 1 and your closest point is going to be a distance is
zero, right?
Doesn't make sense, okay.
Yeah, could you do that on the equation?
You had back on the other page.
They're just so I make sure we got it.
How do I operate this program?
That's a very good option.
Okay, so what are we doing?
What do you want to know?
I just want to see.
So you said, like normalize it to the thing but I wasn't sure.
I just wanted to know, like what is that?
Khloe is going on math wise here.
So I could own understanding of that.
So we draw our Square here.
Right.
Yeah.
And we're going to and then we're going to use in the pixel Shader.
We going to evaluate the distance from wherever point we are, right?
So into the pixel Shader, we pass our PC which is going to be this
point here which is our position center, okay?
And then and then
We are going to know our pixel position at each of these right?
Because this is just going to be are transformed position out of the
vertex Shader and then so we know will say that for sake of argument
that this is 1010, okay.
And we're going to say the first pixel here, we know that that's going
to be let's just say well let's switch this to 100 100.
So we're going to say that this is going to be 50 on X and we'll say
150 on why this is going to be 150.
Jesus is not.
150, 150.
This is going to be 150, 50.
And this is going to be 5050 to do that, right?
So at each one of these pixels, right.
So we know that this is a hundred across a hundred across, right?
So, we take any point at every single Pixel in the pixel Shader that
we draw.
We can take say this point here of 150.
150.
We subtract it from the center point, which we pass is like, a uniform
or something.
Yeah, it wouldn't be preferred text Data would be pretty.
Actually would be per vertex data because we will match our draw
calls.
But so we have in the in the vertex Shader, we have the center point.
So we take 50 50 - 100
100 and we get a vector, that's 50.
50.
Okay.
So which of those two points there, you've got one 50/50.
This is PC and this is p Just P PC being the center point of me being
p.
And then, so you subtract these two points and you get 50 50, okay?
And then the length of that is just the Pythagorean theorem, right?
50 well 50 squared plus 50 squared square root, right?
Okay which is twenty, five hundred twenty-five thousand square root of
five thousand some big number.
Okay?
So why did you subtract P from PC instead of the other way around?
Doesn't matter.
Okay.
Why doesn't it?
Why doesn't it matter is?
Once you once you square it, the negatives go away anyways and because
it's just a distance it's just an absolute value right?
So if you were to, if you were to take this point and this point
Point.
You're going to get the exact same distance regardless, right signs,
don't matter at that point because the square removes, the sign got
it, okay.
So now you were saying before the sort of started on this, you were
saying that you didn't need to do the square root.
So, I've got the square root here.
So okay.
Okay.
So tell me that part.
You do need a number, the square root.
Yeah.
Because so, the reason is,
So how the anti-aliasing works?
It's important for how the anti-alias.
Okay, so sorry, I interrupted you before I guess, tell me, tell me
that part then, yeah, so sometimes you need the square root, sometimes
you don't.
It depends on how much you're anti-aliasing, okay?
And how wide across your anti-aliasing.
Okay, so what we do normally is, by the way, this isn't the equations
that we used and I'm not going to remember what the equations that we
used our because I didn't derive them Krister Erickson did, they're
all in real-time Collision detection, right?
Okay.
Very simple primitive distance to Circle Arc distance triangle.
I could do it but I'll be here for hours.
Okay, yeah, yeah.
I understand, I just want to get a cursory understanding, right?
So this is, this is the to a point, right?
But you're actually doing to, you know, two points in the closest 22
points or closest to a circle Arc, which is are much more complicated.
Okay, by much more.
I mean, they're like eight lines of code but like I can't remember
them.
Exactly.
Okay, so basically, so what you would do is a very simple thing, would
be like, if this point if this here, right?
So we're going to call this going to try to draw
We're going to call this D, right?
So you compute D, which is distance, right?
And you do that at every point in the pixel Shader and you say, if D
is greater than the radius, then this pixels Alpha value is 0.
If D is less than the radius, then this pixel off of value is 1,
right?
That's going to get you.
You don't actually do the if you do step, which is an opengl function,
that just steps between a range.
And if it's higher than this it gives you a number of is lower in this
against your number, right?
Okay.
So it's like a threshold in operator.
Yes, it's exactly what it is and that will give you no anti-aliasing
and a very hard Edge, right.
And if you do that, you can just Square the distance that you want to
be and then save yourself the square root.
Now, why is that the case?
Algebra.
What do you mean?
Why is it?
Well, well because I've got this value, and if I square rooted, I'm
going to have one thing.
And if I don't square rooted, I'm gonna have another thing.
So why can I feed this?
So let's so let's say you're let's say you want your evaluation
Radius to be 10.
Okay, so you do your square root here and you get the square root of.
Yeah, this is this is square root of five thousand, right?
So that's going to be 77 or something.
So you take, you can take the square root of 56 square, root of 5, or
a 5000, and then check it versus 10.
Or you can take 5000 and check in verses 10 squared, right?
It's just algebra like are less than or equal to
The square root of will call it T minus V where a math p- be, right?
So you could do that or you could do this in this implies that.
There's a square root in here right because it's that's this formula
here.
So because this implies a square root, you can just take, you can skip
the square root and you can get PX, minus py or PX minus p.
CX squared plus p, y- p, Cy squared and then you normally have a
square root, right?
But you can take the square root off of here and then just Square the
other side of the equation.
And then you get, it's the square root which okay used to really
matter.
But now it still matters, but it's not like the end of the world.
But anyway, so you could save the square root if you don't need any
and if you don't need a linear gradient in the in the in the vector
field got it.
But now you're saying, okay, so for the anti-aliasing part which are
about to explain you're saying maybe you do still need the square
root.
It depends on how much you're anti-aliasing by, right?
Because like I said originally, when you generate the triangle strip
around the line that you want to draw your either, using your passing
two, extra parameters, the thickness of the line and some sort of fall
off, which is how blurry the line gets right, and that's what your
anti-aliasing, it's right.
Okay.
So if you pass one pixel as how thick you want the line, probably
can't tell.
But if you want the line to be, if you're on a 4K display, we're
anti-aliasing is really, really tight.
You're going to want to pixels of anti-aliasing because it looks a
little bit better.
Especially so our test for this was we took a black background which
is a white one pixel line and spun.
It very very, very slowly and and look at that and we're like, okay
where's the highest amount of artifact and then and then tweaked our
through.
Hold value for how much we wanted to blur it out based on the worst
case scenario in that situation.
And that's what we got the anti-aliasing.
Now.
Can you show a little bit of an understanding here because I'm not
sure.
I totally understand.
When you say how much anti-aliasing, you want, what, how, what do you
really mean?
Like, can you draw that good?
Maybe, yeah, yeah.
Go back to that.
Try to get to that.
Okay, sorry.
So so yeah.
Okay.
So
If you look at and I'm going to delete all this, you don't need this
anymore.
No, I've got it.
That made perfect sense.
Thank you.
Okay.
So when you draw a straight line, I'm going to do this in Photoshop
because I'm more familiar with that program and I think it does.
Okay, so when you draw a straight line in Photoshop, right?
Put on different layer for a second.
Do you draw a straight line in Photoshop?
There's absolutely no anti-aliasing on it, right?
If use the pencil tool.
So this is exactly perfect one pixel line, right?
Okay.
If you take this line, you rotate it.
I some number.
That's not nice.
Yeah,
You can get screwed, right?
Okay.
However, if you take the exact same line, right?
And then you do well, you just, you know, you can maybe the best way
of doing this.
The best way of doing this is
here.
And then we can wear it.
So if you blur the line you sort of get anti aliasing effect and then
you adjust the levels of we little bit here.
So, now what you have is you have exactly what we would have
implemented.
This is an exact to pixel fall off.
So the, the amount of anti-aliasing for this line is exactly two
pixels, right?
Also, if you look in close, you got your one solid pixel in the
middle.
And then you got some, some amount of this is all Alpha.
By the way, there's no color in this.
So you got some amount that your Alpha value, step down, one pixel
away, and some about the alphabet you step down to pixels away, right?
So now, when you take this,
This line and you put it back here and you rotate it and weird number.
It looks way better, right?
And that's because you got this amount of anti-aliasing happening,
right?
Okay.
And if you were to take, sorry, so correct me if I'm wrong here but
just from just trying to understand that part.
So in some sense you're not really talking about anti-aliasing your
more just talking about radial fall off because an anti aliased line
would only have one at most one pixel of non one alpha.
Yeah.
If you're talking about what that matrix, definition of like you're
doing triangle like FXAA or you doing Maltese amply anti-aliasing like
a moderate coverage base.
If that?
Yeah, if you don't come over, just like that.
Sort of an it.
No, it's not.
That this is a very different type of anti-aliasing.
Interesting.
Okay.
So tell me a little bit about that.
So, how did you decide or why was that the approach that was taken on
this?
As opposed to maybe the more traditional concept of anti-aliasing,
which is just to figure out how thing is touch the screen pixels,
right?
So the idea was
Does when you start moving these lines.
And if you take a line and you stretch it out, or you take a line and
then you bend it, you get it looks better in.
And when you start moving these lines, we did tests, it actually looks
better, this looks better for high.
Trust lineart.
Then simply then simply doing FXAA or something like that.
I mean, if we were to do like 16 by 16 multi sample, or something like
that, where we maybe then it would look good.
But that's just prohibitively expensive.
So I think 4x4 is what the PS4 supports natively.
I don't remember.
Whatever it is, like, I think it's for.
I think you can take 16 samples per pixel on a PS4.
Okay.
It doesn't look as good.
All right, so I guess I get it now.
So, back to the original thing, so that was what we were.
Trying to implement was this fall off?
Yes.
Okay.
And we did it through the side distance field thing.
Okay, so now go back to the thing before and just give me the the
square root versus non square root thing.
So, okay, so when you do the square root, that's fine for when you
don't want it.
When you just want a hard step it, I think, I think maybe there's too
much emphasis placed in the square root thing because I never
actually, I was just like, oh, we could say the square root but never
actually did because who cares, okay, but you know, it's worth talking
about, I guess.
So when when you do this, you have some sort of you have well do I
still have that image here?
Nope, that's something completely different.
Let's not look at that.
When you actually just look at the values of the signed distance
field, right?
You get like, I drew before
You get this right and see if to take well you get this.
So this is like this is the 120, right?
Vector.
It's just a simple Vector gradient, right?
Yeah.
So what you have to do is say, you want your circle to be, you know,
maybe this big, right?
Yeah.
So, if you want your circle to be this big, then you have to figure
out how to map from this gradient to this, right?
Oh, there's ways, you know, like I said, the first example that I gave
you was the step example, right?
Another example is there's smooth step, which is actually what we
used, which is a cubic hermite spline.
Do I need to go into that?
Yeah, cubic hermite spline.
Okay.
I don't know the actual definition of her might slide, but cubic
function is, you know, a mathematical function.
You know, Y is equal to
I guess we don't use Y in math, we go, you know, FX is what is it a
I'll use T because T is sort of the traditional F at T is equal to you
know, 80 Cube because it's cubic be t squared c t+ d, right?
So any any function that has this property has to guess the called
inflection points has to inflection points in it, where
So the curve might look like let me see if I can get the as we want
the curve to be like that.
So
You know, we'll have a curve.
This is cubic Point cubic function, right?
So you have an inflection point here and an inflection point here,
right?
And this is going to be monotonically.
Decreasing here monotonically decreasing here are monotonically
increasing here, right?
Okay.
It could be flipped.
It could be flipped, right?
Because I have three monitors up monotonic sections, right?
Okay.
With two inflection points, right?
So I believe that if a nation of a cubic hermite spline is f at T.
I don't know if this is the correct technical definition but this is
good enough.
So you're going to have F at T or sorry, not if it to you going to
have F at 0.
Crow is going to be equal to 0.
F at 1 is going to be equal to 1.
F.
The first derivative of F at 0 is going to be 0.
And the first derivative of F at 1 is also going to be 0, right?
So that just means that, you know, it's completely flat here.
It's completely flat here, right?
Okay.
Which is going to be at all inflection points, right?
But the point is that it goes from 0 to 1, right?
So at this point here, so this is f of t on the
You know, this axis here, this is 0 and then you come across here on
this axis here, this is 1, right?
Okay.
And then if you solve for all this soon as you go f at 0 so you said
all these 20 so that knocks at zero that knocks out the D parameter
because D has to be 0 and then when you do F Prime at 0, right?
So your F Prime function is going to be what is it?
380 squared plus 2 BT.
Plus C.
So if F Prime at 0 is also 0 that means that this is 0 and this is 0.
So C is also equal to zero and then you can do like a, you just set it
up as a linear systems of equations, do you know, gauss-jordan,
elimination solve it, and then I think you get minus 2T cubed plus 3T
squared, so that's your function.
Is this cubic hermite spline has essentially, no parameters.
It's, it's hard coded to be just this one little
Lump.
Yes, it's this.
This is the function.
Okay, this is not it.
So, it takes all of this and that's how it takes this normal camera
function applies, these parameters, what f is 0 what?
F Prime of 0 has to be, you fill it all in.
You get yourself systems of equations of what these two things have to
be 0 because you at this point, you only have two unknowns.
So it's got to be solvable and you get this function, I think.
Okay, pretty sure that's what it is.
All right?
That's what's that's what smooth step.
It does, right?
Okay?
So what you do is you take, that's not what we wanted, where is
Photoshop.
So basically what it does is it takes this gradient that we have here,
which is going to be a linear gradient, which is so, if you look at
the fall off, it's going to be like that.
And it takes it.
And if you put all of the parameters in it Maps it to be.
Let's use blue, it Maps it to look.
Something like that, right?
And that's going to be this part of the high C, cute.
So this here is where we do is how we determine the coverage of each
pixel.
So instead of just doing a linear fall-off where we, you know, we do a
fall off and we say if it's greater than this, if if it's greater than
this one, if it's less than this 0 by a smooth step to it, and you
sort of clamp the range and you get some sort of a gradient fall off,
where it's probably equivalent to, I don't know.
Let's see if we were to
Use Photoshop to all of its Glory.
You get something that's not really exaggerated.
Yeah, this is a really exaggerated fall off, but you get this right
that effect that you get, got it.
Okay, so I have one more question just because we're it's almost time
for me to let you go to the next interview here.
So one more question I had is just going back to something.
You said earlier, you were like, oh, the the functions we use for the
distance field, we use.
Christopher eriksson's, derivations for something and and I didn't
quite have a chance at that.
Don't ask you, sorry.
What is this something again?
What are the actual Primitives that you were talking about that?
I think you said two points or an arc or what were those what was that
second line segment?
Which is just two points and a circle Arc?
Which is a guest who to radians?
Like how far around each point of the circle?
It is.
But before, wasn't it?
Tell me the line segment once it's to show me that they're that again.
I know that you were saying that you didn't derive these two.
I'm not trying to ask that and I just meant like tell me a little bit
about that process.
So I get I kind of get that.
Part.
Okay.
So we'd have a pixel shit.
We'd have a Shader.
Actually there's another interesting part of this that I hope we have
time to get to which is double coverage pixels, which was the real,
which is the actual problem with this algorithm.
That was the, that was the hard part.
You may not have time to get to it, but we could.
But let's just to tell me this part first and then we can.
Okay, so basically you pass to a pixel Shader, you would pass two
points, P0 will call them P0 P1.
And then, instead of doing the point to like,
In the previous example, right?
We had a PC and we had all of the points in the Square.
So we would generate the same square here and instead of doing
distance to point, we did distance two line segments and then the line
segments are defined by these two points.
And in order to draw the couple hundred thousand things that we did
per frame, that we're all computed on the CPU, all of this stuff was
done in a single draw call.
So
we bash it up in a draw call.
So each vertex actually had a lot of redundant data, okay?
Because each vertex sent the P0 in the P1 because you couldn't do like
now you can inject like variables and then do weird draw call stuff
with modern opengl but you couldn't do that in on the PS4.
So basically it was a lot of redundant data built into the into the
vertebrae into the vertices.
So taking so you have to find because I understood the part about
finding the distance to a
That we were talking about before.
So if I want to talk about the distance, this line segment I suppose,
so is that something I can do with a single equation?
Or no.
So how does that work?
Kind of, I mean, to the extent that you can tell me, how does it work?
My guess is.
And I haven't looked at it, but my guess is, let's say we have this
point, okay?
We can get the distance between these two.
I don't know.
We could draw a triangle.
We can get the area of the the signed area of the triangle.
Because okay, so this is PC or PQ, I guess query Point.
Okay, so if you make two vectors V 0 PQ, this, I'm just making this
up, I hope it's correct P0.
Yeah, I mean, I'm just like when I said like, this is just, I
understand the fact that you're saying that use other ones.
So I'm not, I don't expect you to even know what I was just curious.
I'm just interested to see.
All right, so we can get these two vectors and if you take
The you know V zero x v 0, V 0, y V1, X V1 y.
You take the determinant of that which is that correct?
Yeah so it's V 0 x times V 1 y minus minus plus plus v, zero, y dot,
V1 X, that gives you the area.
One of the parallelogram half of that area, will give you the signed
distance.
So you take the determinant of that over 2 will give you the signed
distance of that and a triangles find different of what.
Sorry.
Sorry it gives you this the signed area of the triangle.
Okay, so gives you the energy of the triangle the area of the
triangle, right?
Because the determined determinant of this vector and this Vector
divided, we back into the area of the parallelogram and then over to
gives you the area of that.
And then
Yeah, formula for triangle is one half.
BH right base times height.
So if we treat this Vector here we can get the length of that pretty
easily.
We can't get the height.
So height would be our distance, right?
So we know what that area what base is so half of Base which we know
height is equal to.
Well, the determinant of V 0 V 1 over 2 we can multiply those out.
And then take the height is equal to that determinant over over or
sorry the base.
But we know what the bait, the length of the base is.
So if we take the height, is that over the base?
And we get the height, which I guess is the distance to that, but that
would only work if that is constrained within this region here.
So maybe there has to be an F to be.
Like, if that's if this, the query point is outside of that range and
I owe you, okay?
Yeah.
So wait, I think that makes some sense.
So maybe it.
Can you scroll down a little bit?
Here are it's an ethical question.
How
We do that.
So let's say we had just that line segment and we wanted to go like
okay is PQ in inside that region.
Oh God let me do that.
That's a Verona region or could be used barycentric, coordinates for
that?
I don't know.
I'd have to look it up, I don't know, I don't know.
Off the top of my head, I'm sure well, there is a Verona, I region
formula for it because we can tell, if it's in which slab, it's going
to be in.
But off the top of my head, my eyes,
Geometry knowledge would see me struggle greatly to solve this and
this is something that I would just Google.
Okay, well so that well I guess the way you do it there, right?
You've got kind of line, you sort of, you sort of make pretty.
Is that a is?
What is that?
That's perpendicular.
I guess those lines that you drew their, to the the line.
So, yeah.
So we could
because you could generate a triangle here and then
If you.this with, you can figure out which one do you do another?
Because, yeah, because you could do this generate, this triangle
figure out the winding order with the determinant to figure out if
it's inside of this side and then do it again on that side.
But there's no way that's how it works because that's way too much way
simpler.
It was wave simpler than that.
So you could like, you could, you could figure out this triangle
right?
And then figure out the winding order to tell.
If this point is here, this point is here and then you could do it
with
This triangle here and then do I have to do have to go over.
What?
No, no, I totally got actually got okay.
So yeah, so you could do that, but that's not how it was done.
It was way simpler than that and I don't remember how it was done.
All right.
Well I don't want to take up any more of your time here because we are
we are out of interview.
I got a you're going to need time to walk to the next office basically
but thanks so much for explaining all that that was that was awesome.
And yeah, it was great meeting you.
All right.
Well thank you very much.
Thank you.
All right.
That that concludes the interview process.
How did it feel?
Sean, does that with that reasonable or not?
Yeah.
I mean I don't know how my answers were.
That's what I'm sort of curious about.
Right?
Because I'm, I don't know.
Well, like it seemed fine but like, I don't know how like it seems
like the questions were all reasonable and it was sort of like just
explain this to me, but like I know that, you know, this stuff.
So I'm like, ah, fuck why is he asked me to explain this, right?
Well, that's the part that we can't get around for this.
This.
So I was going to mention that is like so normally you know just
unpacking the the interview process, right?
First of all that was perfect like that was exactly what I would have
wanted and it tells me like everything I need to know about the the
person, right?
Because, you know, you can see how basically we essentially did all
the sorts of stuff that you might expect to do in a programming
problem style interview, but it was all stuff.
You already had been familiar with
so,
You didn't have to like come in cold and you could in so much as was
possible, given that you already know me.
I'm at a bit of a disadvantage, but you get to be in the authoritative
position, which is the really important part, right?
You're telling me how this thing works, not me asking you a problem
that I know the answer to and you don't, you know what I'm saying,
right?
And, you know, yeah.
And so the problem is, you know, I know all the stuff I was playing
dumb about which makes it harder because you're
Credulous when I say stuff like why don't you need the square root?
Normally an interviewer might just think I'm that dumb right?
Like, they don't know.
Yeah, that question actually threw me off because I was like, yeah.
What do you?
What do you mean?
Of course, right.
Living in Hawaii but you know, when they're just walking in here, I
could just be some idiot.
Right?
And that's so, that's okay, you know, maybe it's not my area of
expertise.
So, right.
So, you know that is a little, that was certainly going to be harder
for you, because you knew, I knew it already, but that's how you have
to do those kinds of
Because I need to see how comfortable you are with this stuff and it's
obvious, right?
Mean you are able to explain it all and be very clear about it and
whatever is so that's exactly what you want to see but you can
understand how a lot of people.
Maybe they looked up some stuff that Krista Erickson wrote and just
typed it in and have no capability of explaining to me like what
smooth step is or why you would use it or any of that stuff, right?
And so what you're trying to do is like pull that stuff out and see to
what extent does this person really understand what they've done.
Done, right?
And it becomes very clear very quickly, right?
Either it ends up looking basically, like what you did, where you get
pretty excited about it.
And you're showing me some diagrams and you're like, see this works
like this and this is how this works and like, oh, okay, here you
didn't understand that.
Let me show you this other way of looking at it.
It quickly either goes that direction or I'm not sure like whatever I
really don't know, right.
You know what I'm saying?
Yeah.
And what I find interesting is I thought you were like I didn't know
much about what this process was beforehand so I thought you were
like, dude.
It is, I thought you were going to be like, no, right?
That linear.
Write the two equations that are needed and do and solve the linear
system of equations to get.
The termites, is that the hermite spline function?
Is that what that means?
I don't even know Matt terms, I don't know.
I have no idea.
I always read arrived on my curves every time so I have no idea what
the names for the various because you know all cubic curves are cubic
curve.
Right.
They already think.
So everyone just wanted their name attached to some so it's you know
or is it did busy I get his name on this one.
I do
No.
So I have no idea which one it is.
Yeah.
And I don't care.
All again in the interview, the only thing I cared about was that you
could show me that right?
Because then it's clear.
It's like yes, I don't, I don't even care if you solve it correctly on
the Whiteboard because I'm horrible at that kind of math.
I would probably make a mistake.
So I'm not even looking what I'm looking for.
Is your confidence in the process and what the thing is mean, and so
as long as I've got that, I just assumed that if given three hours to
solve for a her mites,
You would be able to because, you know, it's unlikely that you
couldn't open Mathematica if you needed to or something, right?
If you were that bad at solving or something and get the correct
answer or like you said, Google it, right?
So I just want to see that your brain is capable of putting all these
things together, understands the picture and knows what's going on
your ability to solve.
The math is not so interesting because again that's not something that
you do in programming that often with no assistance and especially not
in a limited amount of time, right, right.
Yeah.
And that's the other thing.
Is like, for almost all of, for almost all of the answers that I've
seen in, like this is what the Whiteboard questions are, right?
It's just like I would just use Google like yeah, right?
What data structure should I use in this situation?
I don't know.
At some sort of a tree all, I'll just Google it right?
Like the answer is almost always.
Why would I even have this information in my head?
Well, that's why again, I like this style of interview it's because
you have some process that you've gone through to do.
Ramming, right?
And you know, a lot research is an important part of programming, you
know, you don't typically want someone who's going to re-derive
everything from scratch every time without looking to see what other
people have already done.
Right.
That's, that's not right, a particularly great approach to programming
because there's a lot of smart people out there and they've looked at
this problem and you want to know what they thought.
So, one of the big reasons that I like this style is you've done that
process, whatever your process is for this problem.
Right?
And now I'm asking you to explain back to me what you figured out and
if Googling someone else's work on, it was part of the process that
doesn't matter to me.
What matters to me, is that you understood afterwards, what happened?
And how that fit into what you were doing, why?
It was the right decision or whatever, like all those sorts of things
and I can tell that when you're talking about something you've already
done when I'm giving you a problem, cold you never
Chance to go through your standard process.
So, who cares what you do at that point, you're not doing what you
would normally do, right?
Right.
So by the way, if you can see it, that's the actual form.
I actually already know how to do off the top of your head.
Yeah.
How do you know how to do it off the top of your head?
Well, so looking at it, right?
I mean, this is, the thing is, I spent all that time doing gjk and
that's the second case in gjk.
Okay, right.
Yeah.
Because I have like, no, I haven't actually implemented.
So that
the dot product of the vector of the P0 P1 Vector is pointing in the
direction.
You need to dot product against to test, which region you're in of the
three regions, okay?
You know, because it is the it is the Verona region.
So once you get that dot product, you know what region you're in, if
you're in either of the two end cap regions, you just need the
distance to the point, right?
Which we already have, it's just a fallback.
If you're inside the region, then it's just a perpendicular.
Which hey, is the cross product.
The length of the cross product is
To be the distance from the line segment out.
That's all you need 3D though.
Interval.
It's an all-day so you just do a perpendicular dot product.
YES, Prep.
.O K.
Perp out.
Okay, okay.
All right.
Well shit, they all D.
It's not in Aldie you need.
The, what is it?
The wedge product.
You need the the 4D correct.
One to go out.
But yeah, I knew how to do it but this is this again like so.
So looking at that process, right?
And kind of going back to it.
I'm packing it now for
People who are watching and again, like I said, this is this entire
stream, is it designed to instruct the interviewer, not the
interviewee, right?
The stream has nothing to do with then, like, I'm looking at the code
now with my answers dumb, this is not a good way, to determine to
determine the distance, right?
Right.
Well, so again, so it's okay.
So let's, let's unpack the whole interview if you want to talk about
the whole interview, right?
So you can see how I structured interview, right?
The first part of it was just talking to you to establish some kind of
relationship.
Or so that the person doesn't feel like they're being slapped with
tech right off the bat, right?
So, just trying to talk, you know, it was.
I thought that was really interesting to it.
Also, it was interesting personal perspective to that.
Just happened to come out.
I wasn't necessarily going for that, but it was neat.
I learned about, you know, you said you enjoyed competitive things
that you liked Esports and here's why.
And you didn't really love playing games as much anymore, which is so
I got to learn something about you, which is great to write.
If, you know, if, if the person is forthcoming about certain aspects
of that, that's a really nice thing to know, too.
Because now you just have a better connection with
That person you're going to have an easier time, interviewing them
certainly.
And you know, something about them that maybe is relevant to their
job.
Maybe not, who knows?
Right?
That's a hard thing to say, but so that part is kind of irrelevant to
the tech side.
It's just a time to get things warmed up and then from there you can
kind of see I went through about a 10-minute process and this part is
very important to get, right?
I'm a little rusty at it but hopefully I did, okay, which is trying to
get you into position to start talking with me about tech specifics.
So you saw me kind of get you down towards a specific, technical area
that I could kind of just start asking questions about and it did not
matter to me.
Where that was right.
I just needed you to be somewhere.
You felt interested in explaining something to me.
And so you saw me kind of I poked around that with the assets
dreaming, a little, it didn't seem like there was really maybe that
much there to really explain.
So I kind of I pushed around a little bit more, the diet then came up
and you start to talk about the NSA seemed like you were interested in
it.
So I was like, okay, this we can get
The I can get all the tech stuff I need out of this.
So let's just go there, right?
So then I asked you a bunch of stuff to explain to me throughout the
course of that.
And basically like I noticed that, you know, most things you felt very
comfortable, explaining the distance one.
You didn't that the two-point distance one.
You didn't want to explain, right?
You got it all because you didn't drive it, right?
So what I did is I push that one to the end because I wanted to spend
most of the time on stuff you were comfortable with because that's the
most important stuff.
And then at the end, I was just like
I'm pretty confident.
This person knows what they're doing, right?
I liked everything I heard right.
You know.
Like I was like he explained it very eloquently.
He drew diagrams that I understood he was patient with me, right?
You didn't get annoyed that I was asking these questions which again
in this circumstances even doubly good because you know, I know the
answer to a lot of these things.
So you getting impatient with me is even more on the table, right?
But you didn't you took the time to explain it which is great.
And so at the end, what I wanted
To do was just go.
Okay, let me since I'm very confident that I've gotten, you know, good
answers on a test.
Let me just see what happens if I just throw something at him that I
know he's uncomfortable with just to see where he goes.
And so that was all.
That was just was to see that.
If I had had more time at the end, I may have pushed you down to
actually trying to solve it but you know, I wasn't super interested in
that.
So I didn't prioritize that in terms of time.
Well that's a question, I would actually work.
It's just terrible.
Actually, but that's okay.
Because a lot of times, the first solution is terrible, right?
A lot of times, my first solution to any programming.
Problem is terrible and I expect yours is too.
All I wanted to see was how you were thinking about the problem.
What do your attack skills look like Etc?
Right?
And so that was it.
So if we'd had more time and it, or if I really wasn't sure because
based on all the answers you were giving me.
It seemed like you were capable of working through these things.
So I wasn't super concerned about that.
Maybe if I had been more concerned about that, we spent more time at
but I just at the end I was like let's just
To see what it looks like when he attacks the problem.
You know, that, that was all that was
It was good.
I thought you were going to go deeper like I thought I thought the
whole point of the interview originally before I knew what it was
would have been like no you have to solve this, right?
And I would have thought that for the hermite spline know you have to
because I just I knew it was minus 2T cubed plus 3T squared, right?
I just I remember that, right?
I thought you going to be like, no, dude, the take take your four
formulas, cut them all out, figure it out but I guess I mean, you
know, from my perspective
If I do that's you could cut and paste what you just told me into
Mathematica, it would produce the answer.
What I wanted to hear.
There was okay, here, I understand the concept of a cubic equation.
I understand the concept that if I constrain enough points of it, then
it will solve down to a fixed answer.
That's the important part.
I don't care if like we have computers that will solve that for you,
after, you know, that, right?
So me wasting your and my time on a
White board solving a cubic equation that's like a High School, AP
Calculus class thing at best, right?
I mean, if for some reason you couldn't do that, we could teach you to
do that on the job.
I that's like wrote skills, right?
So yeah, yeah, it's just doesn't matter.
It's not the thing that's going to determine whether you're going to
be an asset to a team.
And so I feel like interviews that focus on you doing a rope process,
that we know,
How to do.
And that computers can do just doesn't make sense.
Hearing you understand how a hermite spline comes about?
That's crucial, if you were just like, I don't know, here's the
formula and you just wrote the formula up, then I would have pushed to
go.
Okay?
How did you get that right?
But you told me, you had already told me about the time, you wrote it
out.
You'd already told me how to generate it, which is exactly what I
wanted to hear, right?
Like you told me exactly what I wanted to hear before.
I didn't even have to ask a question, right?
Okay, you see.
What I'm saying?
Yeah, there was another one where I was like, do you want me to
explain this and you were like, no, what was that?
Do you remember?
Because there's something else that I was like, this is something that
I think you'd want me to explain.
I'm not sure sorry, I don't know because again, almost all of the
questions that you often times, would go ahead and work out an
equation on the board, which may because you thought I want to or
whatever, but you'll notice, almost all the questions I asked.
Were I just wanted an explanation and
I wanted that explanation to be clear to me that you understood the
reason.
So, for example, you notice, I asked a bunch of times about Square
Root versus non square root.
Yeah.
But which threw me off because it was like a not an issue at all.
It was just like, oh, if you're only stepping, you don't need to waste
your time with the square root, right?
Right.
It's like only thing.
It was such a minor issue that you kept asking about.
I was like, what is going on, but you can see why, right?
It's because I wanted to make sure that I heard the answer like which
is which is essentially oh okay.
There is a
Insha pin signed distance field between the iso value, right?
The radius which you have therefore the thing and the equation on the
other side because all I care about is that relationship right being
equal to a particular value.
It's free for me to square both sides of this thing and I don't have
to worry but until I heard the square of the radius I couldn't be sure
that you actually have thought it all the way through, right?
Right.
So
When I when I answer that question I went through, like okay I drew
the whole equation out and I put our and I was like, you take the, did
I did you want that?
Or we could you just be like a square, the radius.
Like what do, what was it as acceptable answer for you?
Well, again it's Nick and this is crucial.
The, the whole point about this kind of interview style is it's not an
answer, it's a me.
Get making sure I've heard enough so that I know that it's 100% solid
in your head, right?
And like I said, in a lot of these cases because I already know you, I
know it's already solid in your head but right.
I potentially only know the answer, but in order to show the interview
process properly, I tried as hard as I could to go assume
Sean doesn't actually know or might not know and let me actually do
what I need to do to demonstrate to myself that he does because that's
the point of demonstrate the interview process.
Right.
Right right.
And again we have to assume that you know someone coming in the door,
doesn't necessarily know these things.
A lot of people a lot of
Hammers would fail to be able to really lucidly.
Explain a lot of the stuff you just explained.
That's just true, right?
You know, we take it for granted because a lot of times we're talking
about very good programmers.
When we talk about it, you know, like a lot of people mentioned on
these streams, you know, you or Sean or Fabi under John Blow of course
they know this stuff and of course they can explain it.
That's not the common case, right?
And when you're interviewing for these things, you know, and you're
looking to see if someone's really technically competent, it's
Not at all a given that someone's going to be able to explain those
things in that way.
So I'm not looking for an answer, right?
I'm not looking for you to say Square.
The radius I'm looking for you to say enough stuff so that I can see
that in your brain.
It's all worked out the right way and that sometimes may be as simple
as a few quick sentences.
I'm like okay, he obviously has it other times, for whatever reason,
maybe I haven't quite heard enough yet and I just want to be sure and
then that's where I need to drill down.
So it's that's all it is.
And there isn't like none of the things I asked you had.
Correct answers to me at all.
They were just let me see how this person thinks about the problem.
And once I see that it's fully formed, I can I'm satisfied, right?
Does that make sense?
Oh yeah, yeah I think I think if I ever had a job interview that would
be this would be fine.
Yeah.
And hopefully, like I said, barring the fact that a lot of things were
weird for you because you didn't understand why, I didn't understand
them or why.
I was asking you something that you knew that I already knew you put
doubt in my head.
I was like, am I explaining this like an idiot?
No, and so I apologize for that part, but that again, hopefully
wouldn't be a problem in a normal interview process because you
wouldn't know the other person was an expert on 3D or something,
right.
Weight.
And that actually, that would be, that would actually be a difficult
thing is like, if I don't know who's interviewing me, is it like an HR
person?
Because if it's an HR person like, oh my God, what am I doing?
Well, they're not going to know how to do to be able to do that you in
that way, they're not going to know how to interrogate those.
Those kind of technical problems is an HR person would be lost because
you notice my questions to you were always based on things.
You had just told me if you can't follow a technical discussion.
There's no way to conduct an interview, so it has to be a programmer
and, as to be a programmer, who's relatively good?
Ideally, the programmer does know all these things, but maybe they
don't know them.
You know, maybe they don't really know that much about signed distance
field again, that's okay because what you're trying to do as you do
assume that the interviewer is a smart technical person just because
they don't know science field that's all the more reason that that's a
good way to go about this interview because if you can't explain it to
me if I'm a relatively smart programmer and you can't explain it to
me, that's a problem, right?
Because if you understand really understand the material, you should
be able to explain it to me slowly easily.
Li as long as I'm not asking too big, right?
And so you know either way I think it works.
If the person doing the interviewing doesn't know that discipline but
is a relative smart person, that's okay because Dennis
It's literally, like, you're just my teacher, I'm just treating you as
my teacher for 30 minutes and seeing how much I feel like I really got
the understanding, the material, the end of it.
And that to me is a really good style for the interview.
Much better than programming puzzle.
Yeah.
Program puzzle.
Doesn't sound good?
This seems this seemed reasonable.
Like if I ever applied for a job which know and these days right.
It's not so relevant.
But yeah.
Yeah no, I just don't want.
Yeah.
But like if that ever happened and like I had to interview,
You like this?
I'd be like, all right this is somewhere where they at least are
trying.
Maybe I'd want to work here.
Like this is much better than then.
Like what was the one that got invert?
This tree invert like an AVL tree or something like that on a
whiteboard?
It's just like I'm just know my answer to that.
Question is no I heard it either.
Another programmer interview was design, a lock for EQ on a whiteboard
know, right?
All of those things are to me.
They tell you a lot about
What the sort of criteria is for working at that company and it, you
know, it would make me nervous about the kind of people that I might
be working with at that point.
Because if I know that the general criteria for becoming a part of
this company is there people who have to perform relatively well under
pressure like that that to me is not the criteria the filtering
criteria that I really want right II.
Don't really know who I'm going to be working with.
At that point I don't have confidence that the
I'm that I'm going to be working with has been screened in a way that
actually produces high quality people on the other side.
It's screening for something totally unrelated to that that, you know,
I don't know if it's going to be a good programming team.
You know, I have no idea at that point.
And furthermore, one of the things about this interview process, this
nice to is it means that in general, you're going to select for people
who can explain things to their co-workers.
Who don't get frustrated with people who don't understand stuff,
because they've had to go through an interview.
You process where basically, they were the expert and they were
telling someone something about what they did and that's a valuable
skill day-to-day, right?
I never thought about.
I never thought about it from that perspective and yeah, that's like
that's like the most important thing.
A programming puzzle is not a skill, you will ever use.
Again, that's not something you're going to ever do again.
In that way, right?
You're never going to be presented with a isolated high pressure,
time-limited thing.
What you are going to have to do?
Oftentimes is someone pops
Your office.
I don't understand the anti Alias or and I got to fix this bug.
Can you just tell me a little bit about how it works?
Oh, yeah.
You sure.
Casey here's like, you draw the thing up here, in up.
Like you said, I don't really remember how we did the to sign just as
feel thing.
But was Christopher eriksson's, you can go look on the web.
What you gave me was exactly what I needed to know, to go fix the anti
Alias or something was broken.
That's a real situation that will come update a day.
So right?
Also in addition to, I think it being a good interview process, it
also actually does
Are resemblance to something you will do day to day, which I think is
important.
You know, that's what the interview should be built around.
Not something you won't do, right?
Yeah, that's it.
This is definitely much better than yes.
We're going to be thanks Checker.
Thank you, Chris.
Thank you for for and I don't know, maybe he didn't come up with it.
All I know is I learned it from him.
So you'll have to tell, I don't maybe someday you can stream and say
how it came about, because I actually have no idea where it comes from
or why, why it comes from, but,
That's it.
So I guess we can probably wrap it up and you can give your voice some
much-needed.
Rest, thank you so much for for interviewing doing the mock interview.
Hopefully yes.
Thanks for explaining all the scientists feel stuff.
Everyone on the stream probably now knows well but everyone watching
don't do this.
Don't do this too but like it's important to know that the the vertex
winding thing I guess but like don't do this to figure out the
distance to a line segment go.
Get rid of.
That was one tiny little part that all the government was was, you
know, signed distance feels 101 education course which is useful to
people.
Go get, go get real-time Collision detection.
It'll answer all your questions.
All right, maybe I'll have to order a copy.
You don't have it.
I don't know you probably well, and it's just basically, I have it for
all the distance functions, it's just like, yeah, but here they are.
Yeah, here they are, he's like, okay great.
I have them now.
I never have to think about it.
Yeah.
All right, well thanks so much John I will I will hang up the Hang Ups
now.
Okay, are you streaming today?
Are you streaming when you stream in?
Next I was going to say I you know, probably in half an hour, I guess
I will.
All right, well, there you go.
So if you if you want more Sean will be streamed in half an hour.
You're not.
You're doing him in here, are you?
No, no.
That's it for today.
Okay.
What's your Twitch handle SSS McGrath?
It's SSS.
McGrath, yeah.
I always have to check the number of s's
Because sometimes I trust asses until it wasn't taken.
How come you don't do McGrath?
How come it would send that?
Do not all right?
No, I don't remember.
All right, all right, thanks so much John and thank you.
That was great.
Take it easy, man.
Okay.
Well, so if you if you want here we can takes a few quick questions if
there's any questions from people watching on the stream.
I don't know if that was a reasonable enough, sort of illustration of
the process.
I hope that it was that went what I thought very well.
That's exactly how you would like a good interview to go.
I think it for me, if I was actually interviewing Sean I feel like I
would have had all the information.
I needed but I, you know, I don't actually know.
What would have happened?
You know, he knows all that stuff and very good explaining it.
It might have been sort of thing where it would be interesting to, to
see what happens on someone who doesn't really know stuff.
But I don't want to put anyone in that position on the stream, so we
can't I don't feel comfortable demonstrating the no higher, right?
Sean's kind of an example of this is someone interviewing who you are
going to hire, right?
And so you know, demonstrating the, the obvious part of sorry, the
Counterpoint to that which is what it looks like.
When someone doesn't do well in the interview,
You and probably, you know, this is something you shouldn't hire.
I don't really feel like demonstrating that is is okay because I don't
want someone to look bad on stream, right?
And so, you'll just have to take my word for the fact that when
someone doesn't have a really tight grasp on the material, as you
drill down into it, like we did their answers will fall apart and they
can't really explain anything to you and they don't really know what's
going on and that's typically what happens.
So you know, yeah, like I said I don't feel comfortable demonstrating
that but you can sort of take my word for it.
That it does it does work.
Or you can try yourself and see how your how are your mileage is on
it, okay.
Sergio says, I believe I'm good at these kinds of interviews, but
often my main problem is just getting my foot in the door.
What advice could you give to make it more likely for me to actually
an interview?
So I think
The thing that I wanted to say there and oh, my my goodness, my head
is actually missing.
I don't know why.
I don't know why my head is missing from the stream.
That's interesting.
The webcam is supposedly there.
Right there is webcam, but you know,
I'm not visible.
I don't know why.
well, there's that
You know what?
I'm not going to try and fix that.
I'm just going to be a disembodied voice for the moment because I
don't know.
It looks like honestly, it looks like my my webcam is not even on.
Which doesn't really make any sense.
I wonder if because we were just seeing it on the Hangouts, so I
wonder if like, it got shut off for some reason.
Yeah, I don't know what happened there.
That's a that's a very good question.
Hold on one second.
I'll see if there's anything that can be done about that.
I apologize for that.
But, you know, that's, that's just some reliable Computing going on
there.
It may have been caused to Applications were trying to access the
webcam for all I know.
And I'm not sure if that's like kind of thing that they can not really
handle.
Particularly well, I wish there was some way to reinitialize, the
webcam, but I don't actually see any particular way of making that
happen, right?
Like, I kind of need to tell OBS like, hey man, can you go ahead and
Andre sort
Initialize yourself and I don't think it's going to want to do that.
Without I could probably like shut it off and turn it back on again,
but then the stream would have to go down which is less useful.
So, I don't really know any other way of getting this.
This sausage gentlemen, here to do that.
So you'll have to deal with the disembodied head for our disembodied
voice rather.
So what?
Let me go ahead and and sort of answer these questions a little bit.
Let's see here.
So Sergio, I wanted to answer your question of any advice you can give
to make it more likely to get interview.
So I just want to make clear this stream is strictly for interviewers,
right?
This dream was just a sort of demonstrate.
Hey, if you're interviewing in Tech,
here's another way to interview that I think is a lot better than the
high-pressure program puzzle.
Kind of wave interviewing, maybe consider doing it because a, I think
you get better hires out of it and be I think that it takes some of
the adversarial nature and the unpleasantness out of the interview
process that currently is going on at a lot of tech companies.
And so that was it.
I have no advice for interviewees.
I have none.
I don't know anything about that.
Process.
I do not know anything about how to increase your chances of getting
an interview or how to pass HR screens or any of that stuff.
So I have no advice to give their.
I'm I was just trying to illustrate for the other side.
Hey, here's here's how it goes, right.
Midler says, Sean was great obviously, but I think that interviewees
could also maybe do with having a bit of a plan as to which rat-holes
they'd be prepared to go down.
So to a certain degree.
Yes.
And to a certain degree, no one of the goals of this interview process
and I knew that it would be relatively easy on Sean, because he was
not familiar with the interview process.
Begin with one of the goals is to push the person into the area that
you have picked and not really let them dictate the area too much,
because yes, they may have started like rehearsing for programming.
And who's in that way you want to try as much as possible to keep them
explaining things that maybe they weren't necessarily expecting to
explain ahead of time in so much as you can.
So, you know, take that for whatever it's worth.
But
Mr.
First Dimension, I am curious how you would move forward with the
interview if someone doesn't have a lot of interesting past projects
that they are excited to talk about.
Does this just assume you're hiring experienced people?
Well, it depends what you mean by that.
So, no, it doesn't.
It doesn't assume.
You're hiring experienced people in the industry.
It does assume that you're hiring people with programming experience,
right?
If you are hiring, literally for people who don't know how to program
than, yeah, right.
It's not for that but I don't know anybody in the industry who hires
people who don't know how to program.
Maybe there are some who have like boot camps and stuff that try to
just take smart people and train them be programmers.
But assuming that you're talking about someone knows how to program.
You just don't know how to program in C.
If you haven't programmed for many many, many, many hours, right?
That's just a fact, right?
So if this person is going to be at all qualified for the job in any
way,
They have at least done a bunch of programming in school or in their
spare time or something because otherwise, they just don't not a
program yet in which case you definitely don't want them, right?
So they don't have to have done any past projects on the scale of what
Sean has done.
For example, whole games, but they must have done something.
They must have done, you know, if this person hasn't done 5,000 hours
of C programming or something, right?
Then I don't know why I would be interviewing them at all even for an
entry level position.
They're just not going to be good enough at Sea to really be part of a
team, right?
So you'd you know, under that limit where you don't have anything in
their past, that you can talk about that person is really not a
programmer yet in my mind, right?
So Sean obviously makes it look maybe a little more grandiose because
we're talking about entire projects in tired games.
He shipped and we're drilling down on those, but that thing that you
start drilling down, it could be anything.
You can be a school project, a particular class that they took that
they liked and what about it?
They liked and to explain things that they learned in it, right?
So you don't have to have the kind of breath that Sean was presenting.
You just have to have enough hours to actually be a competent
programmer.
But if that's happened, there's going to be stuff you can drill down
on and so that's really all you need there.
I think I got all the questions.
Do you think streaming yourself online?
Maybe is even helpful for interviews like you do.
um,
Possibly.
I mean, one thing that I would say is on the interviewee side.
If even taking that out of the think, it's like I said, I don't have a
lot of advice for interviewees, but one thing I would say is part of
being a good programmer on a team, if you're just programming by
yourself all the time, then this not so necessary, but part of being a
good parent of Team, like we were sort of saying at the end of the
interview, there is being able to explain what you've done to other
people in a way that they can understand.
Right?
And so doing streams, where you explain programming stuff or just
proving
Just explaining things is just a generally, good programmer skill to
have in general and the fact that it would help with an interview like
this one is just kind of a bonus on top of the fact that it's just a
good thing to know how to do.
So it is I think true that that is the sort of thing that you know you
might want to.
Practice.
And if streaming is a good way for you to practice it then that would
be good.
Yeah.
Looks like we've got everything I think.
All right.
Thank you everyone for joining me for this special edition of handmade
hero where we went over how like, how to do it Tech interviews that
are non-confrontational, or at least as non-confrontational as
possible.
Hopefully, that's something that some people out there might consider
doing instead of sort of the programming puzzle high-pressure version
of interviews, which I think are really biased towards hiring
specific, sorts of people that don't necessarily correlate at any
particular.
ocular way to people who will be good programmers for
Team.
So that's just, you know, an example of how to do it.
I tried to do it as best I could.
Again that's not my invention.
I learned it from Chris Hecker and he may watch the stream and feel
like I did a poor job of it in which case.
Yeah I do hope that if he has any interest he would demonstrate it
some time where he could kind of show maybe things that I did wrong.
Or if there's any, if there's any, like kind of finer points to it,
that I kind of missed the boat on I, like I said, I only really know
how to do it because I watched him do it and he was very good at it.
So hopefully that gives sort of, you know, puts another idea out
there, a little more broadly, in terms of how interviews can be
conducted in ways that do get down to really technical nitty-gritty,
and do force people to really demonstrate their understanding of how
things work at a deep level.
Which does not require this sort of on the spot programming puzzle.
Sort of, I guess confrontational situation that I think can cause a
lot of programmers, who are otherwise very good at programming, but
just not particularly good at that.
One situation to kind of fall down and perhaps, not get hired at a job
where they would actually be very good for that job.
So that's it.
Thank you very much for joining me tomorrow.
This, this whole weekend is basically special programming on handmade
hero.
That's just the way it worked out.
In terms of scheduling tomorrow, I had been meaning for quite some
time to try to get Charles Bloom to come and talk to us.
He could not make handmade Khan.
He was supposed to be on the panel for compression but he could not
make it.
And so he agreed to come talk to us separately.
And so tomorrow, we're going to be talking with Charles Bloom about
compression, which should be fantastic because he, he and Fabien
obviously,
Some very pioneering work in compression just recently, and it's
pretty exciting stuff.
So getting kind of like his outlook on compression how he thinks about
I think it's going to be really interesting so I'm very excited for
that.
I don't know exactly what time that will be tomorrow because we're
going to do it sort of in person, so you kind of play it by ear but of
course it will be uploaded to YouTube afterwards.
So if you can't make the stream live since we don't really necessarily
know exactly what time.
I can't tell you definitively, what time to be here for that.
You will be able to catch it on YouTube, so hopefully that should be
good.
Good and everyone can go from there.
That's about it.
Thanks for joining and we'll see, everyone tomorrow.
Until then have fun programming and see everyone on the internet.
Take it easy, everybody.