Hello everybody and welcome to a special mini handmade hero.
This is being recorded well and streamed here on July 12th which is
the day that I honestly don't know why it was specifically selected.
But it was the day that was selected for the internet at large is sort
of protest against America's fcc's decision or you know, sort of
suggestion
That they would start repealing, or messing with net neutrality.
Now, for those of you who don't know what net neutrality is, it's kind
of a difficult term because a lot of people try to make it mean
different things, but what the actual point of it is just that in the
future, what we would like to move towards because we have discovered
that the internet is a very important thing to basically, everyone's
lives at this point is eventually we'd like to see a future and I
think everyone probably would, where people
Have access to the internet and could use it as basically a utility,
right?
The same way that you think of electricity or water in a developed
country, you would think of, you know, having internet, right?
This is one of the things that is now one of the core services that
the government is expected to be able to provide or require to be
provided by private parties, in a way that's fair to everybody and
that serves the public interest as
As possible, right?
And so, in the u.s., there's obviously different models for these
sorts of things to different countries, some countries are more
socialist with the way they do their utilities.
Some companies, some countries are more privatized in the u.s.
we have kind of a mixture.
There are private companies who do you know, certain aspects of
providing utilities?
But they're typically regulated very strongly and one of the ways that
these sort of utilities can be regulated as something called common
carrier regulation and what common carrier means.
Ins in our legal system, is just that in general, you are not allowed
to discriminate based on the endpoints of what's going on.
So, for example, if you were a telephone provider and you have a call
from person a to person, b, or company a, to Company B or person a to
Company B, whatever it is, you're not allowed to give different levels
of service based on those endpoints, you have to treat what's
traveling basically a
Some kind of a constant, guaranteed service level based on whatever
these folks are paying for.
So if you pay for, you know, long distance service on a phone line,
back in the old days for internet, in this case, where you're paying
for a certain speed internet, then you have to get that speed, no
matter who you're talking to, they're not allowed to look at what
you're getting your.
You know?
Look at who you're talking to and change.
What is
You to your connection based on this.
And that's what common carrier means.
A sort of means that these rules that are in place to guarantee that
you're just providing a substrate and you're not acting above that as
some kind of an overseer or big brother or whatever else is what the
FCC decided to allow internet companies to be regulated.
Under, I believe it was last year and before that in the u.s., we
actually had a lot of problems with this sort of thing.
There actually were
Instances of isps, big powerful isps, such as Comcast messing with
internet traffic.
That was based on what you were doing.
So for example, you might get a service that claims to be a certain
speed or claims to do something particular and you're paying for it.
But then when you actually go to use that service you find that.
If you go to use BitTorrent, for example, they would cap the band with
it something lower.
Or if you go to use Netflix, maybe they tried to charge.
Flicks for that bandwidth because they would make it slower or reduce
the quality of streaming if Netflix refuse to pay, right?
All kinds of things like this that they were completely within their
rights to do because they were not regulated as a common carrier and
we're not under any legal requirement to provide Fair service, right?
And so thankfully finally and and I think that this is largely due to
the fact that there are a lot of very powerful.
Operations in the United States who want to see Fair internet traffic
rules primarily because that's how they exist, right?
Google Facebook, Twitter, you know, these are companies Amazon eBay.
They rely on a fair connection to their customers over the internet
and they don't want to see a world where they are going to be extorted
for example by Comcast or these other isps extorted in a way that
requires them to pay.
In order to get access to their customers.
And furthermore you while there's very powerful, people who want to
see that neutrality in Forest.
You can also imagine how important this is for the little people,
right?
So somebody like, Molly rocket, my company, we're nobody, right?
We're a tiny little game Studio.
We stream handmade hero, and we work on 1935 as a game, will never
have any clout.
Anywhere will never have the kind of money necessary to pay off.
Comcast or something like that when we want to connect with our
customers over the Internet, sell them a game that they can download
over the Internet, any of these sorts of things, handmade hero, right
now, when you go buy a pre-order of handmade here, when you could
download the source code, all that stuff, we are relying on the fact
that you can do that in a reasonable time using a reasonable internet
connection because we're no one special.
We're relying on just Fairplay there that you can get our stuff just
as fast as somebody who might
Have billions of dollars and ways of leveraging a contract with say
Comcast in order to get better treatment.
So it affects really everyone who uses the internet as a primary
aspect of their life.
Which at this point, is basically everybody and it affects all
businesses as well, no matter how small they are.
If you rely on the internet to connect with your customers, not having
the protection of something like net neutrality, real net neutrality
means that you can suddenly become behold.
In to extort of behavior by the isps because they could basically just
shut down your business, anytime they want by enforcing some kind of
draconian regulation at their whim, that forces you to pay for access
to your customers in ways that you maybe can't afford.
So, not only is it a huge problem for big corporations who don't want
to see a lot of their money going to this, but it's also much even
more threatening, really to small businesses because, although the,
you know, Google could probably afford to Pony up this money.
Want to, but maybe they could other businesses just can't, there's no
way they could let the, the right deals or pay.
The right amount of money.
They just don't have that kind of cloud.
So, net neutrality just makes a tremendous amount of sense, in terms
of the way, a society should function our ability to talk to each
other, should be fair, and Equitable, no matter how big or small you
are, no matter who you are, no matter what side of the political
landscape, you're on, no matter what work, what kind of work you do?
Do or how you do it.
It's just like electricity.
You shouldn't get worse electricity because you didn't strike up a
deal with the electrical company.
To give you kind of fair treatment or something like this.
You should just be able to pay the same price as everyone else for the
same service as everyone else.
And it's uniform.
This is just a good way to run utilities because it leads to the
fairest Behavior without a lot of bad like extra t''v.
For by looking at what you do and determining whether or not, they can
try to pressure you to try and get more out of you, right?
So I think there's really not a lot of arguments against it.
You do see some arguments out there that aren't particularly
compelling, of course, being made by isps, and they have to do with
things like trying to encourage them to invest more in their
infrastructure and all these sorts of things.
And to be completely honest with you, those things just sound
absolutely ridiculous to me.
I don't see how you can look at something so reliable as the
electrical service in our country.
For example, like my
Electricity almost never goes out.
It certainly goes out less than the internet goes out for example and
it's a much harder problem.
Like electricity is much much harder to deal with.
In fact, the internet companies rely on the electric companies to run
their service.
So it's kind of ridiculous to say that something that doesn't need.
To have this kind of extort of power where they think about, who is
buying their service, and who is using it?
For what to say that?
For some reason internet, service providers who have one of the
easiest jobs there is in terms of utility production.
Certainly easier than electricity certainly easier than water.
I don't know, it's probably not male may be the only one that it's
similar to in terms of cos I don't even know.
But point being they have a really easy job.
So their arguments about why it's
It's a problem for them.
Really don't hold any water and pretty much just sound like smoke
because they've never pointed to some reason, why all these other
utilities seem to be able to do a totally reasonable job?
Providing things without any of this ability, even the phone companies
were able to do this, just fine being common carriers and yet they
somehow can manage to do it.
It's just not possible for them.
They're so confused about how to put down a fiber optic cable between
Points that they just don't know how to do it without the promise of
being able to charge Netflix extra for streaming to your home or
preventing you from using BitTorrent, right?
That's just they they just can't do it because it's so darn difficult.
And so I think it's important to just keep that in perspective and
realize that while there's a lot of smoke out there, it's just a 10
second thinking about how hard their job is versus how hard other
utilities jobs are can pretty much tell.
Tell you that this is just hogwash, it's just a case of them wanting
ways to make more money and they're willing to tell you whatever it
takes for you to maybe believe them.
But I don't believe them and you shouldn't either.
So that brings me to where we're at today.
Which is that the FCC due to the way, the American system of
government works, basically, we have a legislative body, we have our
Congress and they pass laws.
But one of the things that they are allowed to do per, our
constitution is they are allowed to delegate their authority, to
institutions that they set up essentially that are then dealt with
under the executive branch of the government.
So effectively what happens is,
Our Congressional or legislative branch in this country.
Does something like say we don't want our cells, meaning our, as a
congressional body we don't want to sit around trying to micromanage
the you know, Communications infrastructure of the United States.
We simply want there to be one and we want it to follow some
reasonable guidelines.
So we're going to create a bill that creates something like the FCC
which is one of these institutions which will oversee those
Education infrastructure questions for us.
There are many of these sorts of sort of entities, in the United
States government.
And they are essentially created to do these day-to-day Services.
The SEC would
Other examples on the screws Exchange Commission that is the one that
oversees say business investing in stocks, stock markets that sort of
thing publicly traded companies.
So that's just how the government works.
And so the FCC is effectively the body that has been delegated.
The authority to enforce something, like net neutrality.
Now, to be clear Congress, still has the authority to do something
like pass, a net neutrality law and it would be really great if they
did.
Unfortunately, we've never
ever been able to get them to do that.
Now, that's something we'd still love to have them do, and there's no
question that pressure should still be applied to Congress.
Should just pass a law that says that you have to have net neutrality
because then it's out of the fcc's hands.
But for the moment because that Authority has been delegated to the
FCC and Congress has not passed a law, specifically specifying, that
the fcc's hands are tied in this matter.
It means that the discretionary power to do something like
enforcement.
Try ality is with the FCC and what the FCC has done last year.
I believe thankfully is, they have decided to assign isps as a
category to, What's called the common carrier designation that I
referred to earlier, which says that they are not allowed to
distinguish between services on their utility, they have to treat
everyone equally which is really great and it's exactly what we
wanted.
Want.
Unfortunately, it's an FCC rule.
Like I said, not a law passed by Congress.
What that means is that much as the FCC have the authority to make
that rule in the first place and to compel isps to follow it.
It also means that they can repeal it unilaterally without going
through Congress.
Because remember, Congress has never spoken on this issue, they didn't
say we had to have net neutrality, they left it up to the FCC.
So,
What we want to do now is prevent the FCC from repealing that
designation that they so wisely adopted last time thanks to an
outpouring of public support and corporate support much like the one
that we're trying to do today here on July 12.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to fill out a comment to the SEC
that is the way that you can communicate with the SEC that you think
that net neutrality has to be enforced and how it has to be enforced
name.
Through a common carrier, designation or something even more stringent
than that.
And I would encourage anyone at home who hasn't already done this, to
do, exactly the same thing.
If you have the ability to write a comment to the FCC encouraging
them, not to get rid of that common carrier designation, that would be
really great because the more people flood their server with comments,
the more it's clear.
We mean business.
And remember,
You don't want to pull any punches here.
So is, you know, a bunch of comments to the FCC.
Necessarily going to change anything, not necessarily.
But when you couple like, millions of comments to the FCC website,
plus a bunch of really powerful companies like Google and Facebook,
and Twitter, all sending their lobbyists to Congress, telling them,
that they're going to be really pissed off.
If this happens, you get a huge amount of media storm around it.
You get Representatives getting asked questions about it.
That is the kind of political pressure that can get things done and we
I know that it's true because that's how it got done in the first
place.
That's how it got added the first time.
Congress didn't tell them to do it.
They never pass a law.
It was simply public and corporate pressure on the FCC directly that
created the political climate necessary to do it.
So I think it's still possible today because if there's one thing
that's definitely true about American politics, it's that if the
people and Powerful Corporation speak together, that's kind of hard
for anyone in government to ignore, if just the people
Speak and not the corporations.
Well, maybe not so much, but in this case, that's not the only
situation, right?
We're not going into this as poor little just regular old voters
without huge pocket books.
We have a bunch of really powerful players on our side.
So now is the time to basically unload, all the barrels, just blanket
them with as much comment on this as we possibly can.
So that they know that we mean business and everyone else does too.
So if you want to know how to do that, there's a couple ways you can
do it but really Google can guide you.
If you just say, FCC comment, everyone knows what that's going to be
today and you can read a lot of different things about it.
So for example, I'm going to write one right now and you can look at
what I say but you don't have to do what I do, right?
You may have different opinions about it.
You may have other things that you want to say, you may have other
ways, you want to say it.
So there are a bunch of articles that will come up here like ARS
Technica technica's article how to write a meaningful FC.
You can't Sprint reality.
That's the one I looked at for the link and you can also look at wires
or there's all sorts of other ones out here.
You can you can do in order to find the link because it's a little bit
of a weird link as you can see but also to get some extra
instructions.
If you forget how to do it, or where to go, or what sorts of things to
say, there's write-ups about it everywhere.
So, take a look at one of those and there's also, I believe a dear FC
c-- dot org.
I want to say, did you
Go to from the Electronic Frontier Frontier Foundation.
That will also help you write a letter to the FCC as well, which you
can do.
So this is another one you can do.
That's separate.
So if you have time to as far as I know, they're actually separate.
I don't quote me on that, but I believe let's see.
Is it actually?
Or is it not?
I don't know.
They may be the same.
I just don't know whether this is a different one or not, so if you
want to just be safe, fill out both of them.
I already filled this one.
I'm going to fill this one out as well because I don't know what goes
where and I want to make
Our that every possible thing I can comment on I did because this
one's been up for a long time for a very, very long time.
So anyway, this is the one that I'm going to be filling out today
because I already filled out the other one a while back.
And the way we're going to do it is when you come to this thing, and
if you want to type it in directly, you can hear HTTP
www.fcsexcel.com.
A CFS.
/Search /.
Proceedings question.
Mark Q:.
Name: open parenthesis.
Open parenthesis 17-0.
108 closed, parentheses close parentheses.
It's quite a mouthful but there you go.
And what we're going to do is click on this plus Express button here.
And so what we're going to do is we're going to put all of the
information in here and then we're going to put in the comments now I
saw this probably not a good idea to give out all of the address
information for me on the internet at large.
So I'm just going to put in my comments and then we'll end the stream
and I'll submit it but you get the idea, right?
All you got to do is just
Put your information in here and then you put your comments in here.
Now I also don't know why I have to apologize.
I don't know whether it makes any difference if people who are from
foreign countries, fill out these forms.
I'm guessing that since the FCC is probably a very America Centric
organization.
They just don't I mean you can see here they don't even have a country
field, right?
So I don't really know but what you can see here actually, when you
look at it right is some of our sort of non-state but, you know,
related territories in one way or another are on here.
So, hey, maybe you're from one of those places just because you're not
from one of the 50 states does not mean that the FCC won't listen to
you, I guess now.
If you're from a foreign country apparently the SEC don't listen to
you because you know, they're just I don't know.
Because why would you want to listen to other countries?
It's not like the internet's Global or anything I guess.
Yeah.
What can you do?
That's that's a, that's just the way it goes sometimes.
But anyway, point being fill in this information.
I don't know if you can do it, if you're outside the country, but if
you're inside the country or territories, then you can and you've got
a drop down for you.
So definitely
Do that and then write your comments in here.
So here's what I'm going to say.
Dear FC c--.
I believe that keeping the internet free and open is one of the most
important challenges.
That I witness in my lifetime.
The internet is arguably the most important.
Look utility that.
Any municipality can have in this day in age, especially considering
it is increasingly used to access government services, as well as all
the important Services people use their day.
Daily life.
Keeping it.
Equitable and accessible to.
Everyone rich or poor.
guess I want to be more broad here, let's just say keeping it open
accessible to everyone regardless of
Their situation.
In Life or their ability.
Negotiate.
Enter into special contracts.
should say, and every
Go give me a nickel accessible to every person and every corporation,
regardless of their, their beans, for popularity.
Ability to negotiate or enter into special contracts with isps.
Or.
the amount, The Leverage political
social Bridge, they possess.
Is.
Sake.
It is absolutely crucial.
To be fair and just Society.
That we keep.
Equitable and accessible to every person and every corporation
regardless of their means should say
Here's your glasses are means or popularity ability.
Greater interests of comes with isps, or the amount of political or
social leverage.
They possess.
I guess I would say.
The internet is increasingly the.
Exclusive way in which many Americans as well.
Well, I guess I'll just focus on Americans here because I guess we've
determined that the FCC
Is America only in this form.
So let's just say Americans in this case if the internet is
increasingly exclusive way in which many Americans exercise their core
rights rights Garin paid to them by
The Constitution.
It's great spelling there.
So, I guess I would say the ability to speak publish.
Publish really the ability to access the courts and receive due
process of law.
The ability to remain informed Main, and informed and educated.
Citizen.
and,
Guess we'll leave it.
There are all now.
Inexorably tied to Equitable.
Access to the internet large.
Guess I'd say Facebook, Twitter or should say sites such as Facebook
and Twitter.
Twitter has become the new Public Square and streaming audio and
video.
Has become the new.
Wikipedia has become the standard factual reference and streaming
audio and video has become the new
It should also include.
Internet.
I should I phrase this such as Facebook and Twitter become the new
Public Square.
Wikipedia has become the standard factual reference, and most press is
now consumed digitally rather than by a print or television.
There is no longer any way to argue that the primary functions of
being an American citizen are not intimately tied, to one's ability to
access the internet.
Fairly and equitably.
Internet service.
Providers may claim that there are reasons.
Why.
Designating them as common carriers.
is harmful to their business or why it somehow will produce less
Beneficial outcomes for the public at Large.
Be important.
Regardless of the arguments here for their merits.
The important fact remains that it is irrelevant.
How they view their business and their situation, we must ensure fair
and Equitable internet access for everyone.
And if isps determine that, they cannot provide this utility in as a
common carrier, then they should be relieved of their duties to do so
and we can replace them with a standard utility model such as the one
that works.
Perfectly well for electricity water and mail.
There is no question.
That.
Services significantly.
More complex than internet service are being successfully.
Provided every day.
on a
common carrier basis.
and any
And thus, it is crucial.
It is clear that isps must meet this responsibility.
If they are.
in order to continue to,
Receive.
Publix permission to operate at all.
That's really all I have to say about that.
In closing.
I strongly urge you not to repeal.
The common carrier designation.
SPS, anything you should be expanding the degree to which
Companies that deal with and provide internet services fall under this
criteria.
All right, so what do we think here?
Yeah, I'll put this in a notepad in case we lose it.
Abner.
Coimbra says, someone said there's a possibility to choose an
international address.
ah,
there you go.
Ah, perfect.
I did.
I miss that little check box.
There you go.
Okay so cool.
You can you can fill it out so fill it out.
Even if you're not from the United States, fill it out, it can't hurt,
right?
If they don't read it, they don't read it.
But it only takes a little while to write one in and I'll make you
feel good anyway because at least you got to say your piece.
You can even stream it.
Like I did.
So other people will hear you say it or you can post it on your
Twitter feed, so everyone can read it.
And remember, it's true that they're not really probably going to read
these but you want them to receive tons of big male, right?
The idea.
This is, this is like the, you know, just the full volley.
This is, this is the like firing all of the guns, right?
We're trying to just like absolutely bombard them with tons and tons
and tons of letters that look different, right?
So they're not for male.
All right, so let's finish this.
I am writing.
Two.
Virtue as strongly as possible to continue designating isps as common.
Carriers.
This is a small type of they should be relieved of their duties.
All right.
So, there we go.
So I guess this information will be publicly available via the web so
I guess I can fill it in because it won't actually make any
difference.
Everyone will see it.
Anyway, I guess week I can use my mailing address so that's fine.
Anyway, because that's on the domain name, name of filers
KC the tree.
Kiss it.
Molly rocket.
So address is 113, Cherry Street, 706.
Seattle.
98 104.
All right, folks, here we go.
So you gotta love the fact that the FCC like they couldn't even make
the website, like, handle Carriage returns.
They're like, yeah, you know, we're qualified to make decisions about
isps but we don't know how to like have like Carriage turns in the
comments.
So you know it's I don't know.
Just just don't know how we would do it.
Friggin mystery man.
All right, so there we go, folks.
We have sent it and they have received it.
Now go do yours as well.
all right, folks, any questions
let me quit q Colin's for I head out for the evening.
Go to sleep.
All right, folks.
I'll see you this weekend.