according hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero today
is not an actual handmade hero as you
know from the schedule there is not a
handmade hero scheduled until this
weekend but well let's be honest here I
have a reason for wanting to do a stream
today mostly it's so that I am focused
and don't think about eating because I'm
sure I'm gonna get very hungry I am
scheduled to have a colonoscopy tomorrow
which is a very polite medical way of
saying that someone is going to stick a
camera up your butt and one of the
things that you have to do in that
circumstance unfortunately is you have
to be on a clear liquid diet and a clear
liquid diet means essentially you can't
have any food really of any kind you're
talking about drinking ginger ale or
eating jello so I just assume that I'm
gonna get pretty hungry today I haven't
had anything to eat today at all and so
I figured that one good way to do this
would be to stream because while I'm on
stream I have to be paying attention to
what I'm saying and doing and hopefully
that will keep me from wanting to eat
anything I'm not gonna be programming
handmade hero because like I said we
don't have a stream scheduled to this
weekend but I've got plenty of things
like in program that aren't handmade
hero obviously we've got handmade ray
and more importantly to today's thing as
you noticed that I flashed it for code
or custom party I had been waiting for
quite some time actually to make any
changes really to the custom layer that
I wrote for for coder because I got most
of what I needed when we first switch to
for coder which you'll remember I
switched from convene max to for coder
and really there weren't that many
things that I didn't have it implemented
most of the features of Emacs to this
day there's really only one feature of
Emacs that it doesn't have which is
keyboard macro recording everything else
that I ever used in Emacs it has which
is not to say that it has all the
features of UMass because Emacs has so
many random features I don't even know
what they all are there's like packaged
upon package my package so I couldn't
tell you
but in terms of the actual Emacs
features I use for could or have them
all except for two things at the time
that I stopped one was the ability to
jump anywhere into in the program using
I menus so he could jump to functions
you couldn't really jump to anything
else it was just functions but I used
that a lot and the other was keyboard
macro recording so what I said was well
I'll go back and revisit my custom layer
once Allen adds either of those two
features because then I really will need
them and in the meantime the for code or
add stuff I won't really go back and
upgrade my custom layer much even if I
should just because I'll save it in
chunks and so Allen recently added
really good jump menus and so it gave me
the opportunity to say alright it's time
to go revisit my custom layer and so
I've done a bunch of things with it now
quickly go over things that I've already
done with it I budgeted about two weeks
for it and I'm just about out of that
time so I only have like it maybe a
couple days left of edits to it and I
got what I wanted out of it but now
trying to add maybe some things that are
just more experimental and see if I can
improve editing that are just kind of
like whimsical like maybe this will be
good you know maybe it won't and I don't
know so let me first kind of show you
what the status of it is at the moment
and you'll have to ignore a little bit
of it that's the the part that's a work
in progress that we'll talk about a
little bit later so what I want you to
do is ignore sort of the bottom part of
the screen here that's got the numbers
on it and well I guess I should start
right away before I start clicking
things so the first thing I added was
this thing because again there's like
pretty robust jump lists in there now so
the first thing I did is I moved any
commands that were very special purpose
rarely executed commands into a command
Lister and I'd wanted this for a while
and this is great because now what I can
do is anytime there's like a complex
perhaps very important but just not very
often used command what I can do is put
it in here instead of wasting key
binding on it before the only way I had
to execute anything was
to use a key binding and of course
that's not very useful for things that
are rarely used so for example a toggle
full screen is something that I wouldn't
want to keep ound - it's just not
something that hardly ever happens but
once in a while I want to do it like at
startup if I forget to launch with the -
F flag or if I want to like make it a
window temporarily so that I can you
know see my four-quarter stuff at the
same time I can see other things
I'm stuff like that so that's a one good
example of thing that I've put in there
is that command Lister and that's a
great thing because now anytime we want
a comics man we can just dump it in
there and we don't have to worry about
binding it to some key and and other
stuff like that so once you've got the
command Lister that's great for those
sorts of things I then immediately also
added the idea of project switching the
reason for this is I don't really want
to have to bother closing and reopening
for a coder just to switch what I'm
working on this is not that relevant
perhaps for handmade hero where we tend
to rather exclusively work on just
handmade hero but for my daily work you
know I've got a couple different things
that are related to 1935 and our website
and all these sorts of things and all of
those things are separated into projects
which I am only building one of them at
a time I'm not building the website when
I'm working on 1935 because they just
have really no need to interrelate in
that way and so what I did is I added a
switch project function and what it does
is it reads a project a master project
file that just says where are all the
projects that you want to be able to
switch between and then it'll list them
so you can see on this machine I only
have five of them but you know on my
machine maybe I've got more and so
that's what that's for and it does
exactly what you'd think so this is
before I used to load those prj files
myself now I don't do that anymore I
just used the product switcher to switch
between them anytime I want now another
thing that I added to the project
control stuff is that in the old days
when I opened a project it just came up
with a blank screen it was like okay now
go pick up thing to edit and one of the
things I've been doing out for coder is
because I license the source code from
Allen because basically I'm like look
this is going to be my editor for the
foreseeable future unless I write my own
at some point so until then I need
access to the source code because you
know if Allen decides that he's just you
know he's had enough any good decides
he's gonna go down to Bermuda and live a
life of leisure I need some way to keep
upgrading this thing and I need it to
always be working right so I like the
source code which means I have access to
the source code which means I can make
modifications accor I've made a ton of
modifications to the core all of which
I'm submitting back to Allen hopefully
he'll mainline most if not all of them
but one of the things I added to the
core was knowledge about the state of
files on the drive in terms of what the
like Windows reports is their last right
time so one thing that I do now is if
you open a project like let's say we go
to open handmade hero on here what I
will do is I'll load whatever the last
file is that we touched right so
wherever the last file is that that got
modified we will load that file
automatically so you know company made
hero I guess we this wasn't the the
highest right time now granted I haven't
tested hardly any of the stuff so maybe
it's buggy but maybe we were in open
jail at the end I don't know so that
just is a nice little minor feature that
just says hey let's like get you started
kind of more where you left off I didn't
really want to do something where I
saved the state of for coder
I could have it's not that hard you
could have saved the two buffers that
you were looking at and your positions
in them I don't necessarily want that
because I don't it seemed like it was
one of those things that adds a fair bit
of complexity it's leaving these files
on your drive now like state files and I
don't really know that I care so I
decided not to go there just as a
judicious decision but I could totally
see doing that at some point if someone
really wanted that so I felt like this
was a way that you could sort of get
halfway to that feature without storing
any state information on the drive which
I kind of didn't I don't like I don't
like it when things leave vc2
trees and directories and all this crap
on my drive like just deal with your
stuff right minimize that I just don't
like that I like the the drive to remain
as pristine as possible it's just an OCD
kind of cleanliness thing that that you
know it's kind of the way that I I think
about things now some other things that
you'll notice about what's going on now
is you can see that we now have very
extensive syntax highlighting much more
extensive that we had in the past so for
example you can you'll note that
functions are now any anything that's a
function defined in the project not
external so a windows function wouldn't
get it and an open jail function
wouldn't get it
but anything just define in the project
meaning I can jump to it meaning you
know I've got the source that will be
highlighted now and again that was
something I modified for code or core
for and similarly things like pound of
fines they will show up in blue and same
with with types any type that's defined
in the project care is not a type that's
a keyword so that's actually a separate
thing but something like OpenGL info for
example that is a type we define and
that will get highlighted as well so I
added all that into for coder as well
and in in sort of that whole process of
adding that sort of code awareness I've
kind of taken for a color to the point
where it's actually much more
knowledgeable about the source code
right now then say Emacs was Emacs you
need to use this thing called etags
they're a piece of crap it never seemed
to work right and they were overbearing
and slow and everything right for coder
now we'll just automatically do the
right thing for my codebase anyway all
the time pretty much and so if for
example anytime we want to be able to
jump to anything in the project I just
can so for example if I wanted to jump
to that OpenGL info struct you can see
that it'll take me right there because
now it knows where it is and it knows
how to get me there and the same is true
for any function or any pound to fine I
want to go to that GL color attachment
right I can just I can go right to it
and so this is really good for code
awareness it's also pretty good
if you're working outside of your own
code base but even on handmade hero
where I've written everything and it's
not that big it's still really nice
think it's the kid just I don't have to
remember where is clear rectangle I can
just go to it right and there it is
furthermore it's a nice little handy way
to do quick searching if I want to know
what kind of functions might have the
word rectangle in them I can just do
this and actually get there it's pretty
easy right seeing everything that has
the word rectangle in it and so that's
pretty nice as well in terms of what's
going on here with software texture I'll
be completely honest with you I have no
idea why it thinks that's a pre proc it
looks or maybe that's not what it thinks
it is again none of this stuff has been
tested so a lot of it could be sort of
slightly weird I have no idea why
software texture is getting special
treatment there that's probably
something we should figure out it might
be because it thinks it's a forward
declaration of some kind color-wise I
may not be filtering out forward
declarations that's something I should
probably look at in fact let's just go
look at it now so inside the renderer
there's you know what I gotta actually
open for coder so we're gonna have to
use two versions of for coder here and
this is going to be confusing one is the
one that's in progress that we're
working on and the other is like a
stable version so I'm loading a stable
version here that we're not going to
touch because if we break it we won't be
able to edit right and so I go to for
coder here and now I've got four code or
open I can build for coder like so right
and you can notice I have many other
things I've done it's added a like
dedicated compile window here that we
can control um so when I rebuild for
coder it's rebuilding the one that I
will launch from here so then I can
relaunch this one and I can say okay
let's go back and look at that situation
in handmade hero where software what
texture was yeah you can see
it's just very strange it's like it's
got a highlight there and if you look
when you do it here it doesn't have that
so it knows it's a type but for some
reason it's getting an unusual color
there and so I think that's just a bug
and let's go track it down
so inside for coder KC render this is
where we're doing all of the syntax
highlighting and the way that I do it is
when I'm actually looking at a buffer
that's ready to be displayed at that
time I look at just what's inside the
visible region and I color anything that
matches a hash table lookup that's been
built from all of the types and stuff in
the system and so if we look at that
function which I believe is here no
that's rendering closure names here it
is mark matches so in here what we do is
you know we've got tags which are things
that are inserted into the buffer for me
for labeling things we'll talk about
those later but in here what I've got is
a thing that iterates over tokens and
looks to see whether or not they match
anything in the the index of types and
so on right and so what you can see here
is I get element by name and I pulled it
pull that out and then I asked for
whatever the color should be and what
you can see here is exactly sort of what
I suggested was a problem and let me
explain to you what the problem is so I
think I've successfully guessed what the
bug actually is if you look at what
happens with the way I build the index I
create these things called index contact
elements and they're just things that I
want to be indexed
each one of them has a color that's
associated with it those colors are
based on the type but I intentionally
made it so that each one has their own
color in case you want to do things
later where you specifically highlight
particular ones or anything like that
but what you'll notice is this can have
multiple things of the same name this is
intentional
if for example I have the you can see
right here the pound defying log F
appears multiple times in for coders
code
I want to know that I want to know all
of those places where like I want to
know that's defined multiple times I
don't want them collapse down into one
record what that means is that if I see
something twice once as one type once as
another I will have two entries each
with different types now the reason why
this is important is because some of
those things may and I'm highlighting
this one here be something that
shouldn't really have much effect on the
color unless it's the only time it
appears so in this case for a forward
declaration I don't want that to
override the color if the thing was a
function or a type defined somewhere
else right so what I want to do here is
when I'm getting the element by name I
want to search to make sure that as I go
through those elements I'm going to pick
the one that's not a forward declaration
if I can avoid it
now that's pretty easy to do I just need
some way of course sort of iterating
over them and so if we look at get
element by name you can see and here the
way that that works is it just loops
over the elements till it finds ones
that's the same right and so I can do
the same thing on the outside here I can
just say look give me all of the that's
not correct at all by the way give me
all of the ones that exist in here so
let's go through each element that I
find and what I'm going to do is I'm
going to say if this one is the only one
then you can use it but if it's a
forward declaration and you've already
got the color from some other type don't
override it
alright so the way I might do this in
fact you know what there's a slightly
easier way to do this maybe I'll do it
this way instead maybe what I'll do is
I'll preserve sort of the way it was
written before where it was looking like
this and what I'll do here is I'll say
look let me get the element if the
element is valid and the element type
happens to be a forward declaration if
that's true then what I want to do is
look to see if there's another one right
look to see if I can go one forward so
you know index content element next
equals that if they're equivalent then L
M equals next right and what I could do
here is actually do this as a while loop
so while I have an element and the type
is a forward declaration I can go
forwards right I can I can advance so
I'm gonna get the next one in the buffer
I'm gonna see whether or not it's the
same and you know like it I'm gonna
double check to see whether or not it
still matches the name that I was
looking for and if it does then I'll
move forward right so in the event that
it does not match or I don't get one so
I should also say you know let's let's
say it's valid right in fact I could
even do that a little earlier I can say
if there's a valid element and it's got
a valid next pointer and the type of the
element that I'm on is for decoration
then see if you can move
[Music]
- oh I I let it complete - that see if
you can move forward if you can then do
so and that way we won't have that
situation of forward declarations
overriding the color
so things that are forward declared will
just show up as for as specifically a
different color so you know they're not
defined in the project but things that
do have a type that just happen to get
forward declared but we're defined
somewhere in the project they will show
up differently so okay they will show up
with their correct like color by type or
whatever right so now let's switch to
handmade hero since we happen to have
that as a nice case here let's look at
the surface texture or whatever it's
called what was it called texture
something or other software texture and
there we go so we fixed that that bug
there right okay so that's good that's a
good fix let's talk about some of other
things we did or I did rather so I added
to do important note and that sort of
stuff highlighting Allen had added a
sort of makeshift little experimental
version that that would just highlight
the word to do anywhere I wanted to only
in comments and I also wanted to be able
to have many of those so to do note
study important and I don't know if I
have any of those in this code I don't
think I do but I have lots of notes for
example oh you know what I could do it
searched everywhere alright so we'll
talk about that so inside comments I
highlight those now and I also keep
track of them now when you do jump I
don't normally expose those to the jump
Lister because I only use types
functions pound defines and and the like
right for declarations so what I wanted
to do is have another way I could jump
and so I have another jumping type oh
and I have two obviously this is an
experimental one I haven't actually
pushed this to main yeah so if I did I
accidentally load hand
here oh and I closed it right so if I go
ahead and run it again here and I switch
to like handmade hero one of the things
you can see it's by jump you know
there's no notes or to do is or anything
in here but if I want a listing of those
I can actually use this other jump
blister that I made which allows you to
pick exactly the type that you want to
jump to first and it will only listing
as those type so now you can use the
ones that appear in the regular jump
list as well so I can pick on function
and now I just see a list of the
functions that are defined inside the
program right I can also ask for for
declarations and see just the things
that are forward declared which could be
any of the structs some of those trucks
may also be defined some of them may be
only forward declared but it's nice as I
can kind of see everywhere the song is
forward cleared and I can jump right to
that now similarly I can look at all my
two dudes right here's all my two dues
in a nice big list I can look at any of
them right and I can look at anything
notes that I've made in the code right
all of that stuff is now keen next like
I said way better than Emacs ever did
Emacs was lousy at letting you navigate
your source tree we're not perhaps as
good as a full compile so some of the
things that like intellisense can do
when it works which is never but let's
say it actually worked or if you just
were sane and wrote a thing that loaded
a PDB and marked up your text or
whatever um there's some things we don't
do I don't parse
structs like their contents so
autocomplete doesn't know like oh this
and I don't parse variables so it
doesn't look and go oh this variables of
this type so you probably only want to
autocomplete like the members that
should be in there that being nice to
have but I don't actually know that it's
worth the effort so I didn't bother
right
this is a premium ginger ale
it contains carbonated spring water cane
sugar citric acid natural gingers
natural flavors and natural caramel I'll
be honest this caramel use sugar that's
been heated in a pot I'm not sure how
you make natural caramel because it
seems like it has to be man-made but
maybe they found like a hot spring
somewhere with sugar that drips off of a
tree and then they pan it out of there
which explains the high price of this
premium ginger ale all right so what I
want to do now is talk about some of the
other things in there for comment
parsing I added a math parser for
comment parsing and those of you who saw
the stream on mustache I showed a little
bit of this what happens in there is if
I was to open let me say a temp file
here so I do temp test dot CPP and by
the way I don't know how to make this
stop happening if I do a test dot CPP
and I hit return it I don't know how to
say in for coder only this file and Alan
is probably not watching but I would
like something that actually had like a
give me a specific like fat like this
filing only and I should probably add
that I don't have that anyway one of the
things I do now is I pass I parse
mathematical expressions inside comments
and just give you the results because I
was tired of switching over to this
stump thing I know what this thing speed
crunch I can get rid of that now and I
didn't I don't really need it I don't
want it I just want to be able to put
math in the comments so I do now and you
can see how it works
you do like 1024 x 1024 and it produces
the results here for you it also comma
paginates it okay I don't think you guys
have ever met Molly hello Molly hey do
you want to say hi
do you wanna say hi you want to see
outside see him I would let you I don't
know if that's gonna mess up our light
let's see if we can do that how bad is
that if I let Molly have a little bit of
sense of chic and she doesn't like to be
oh there you go how you doing kid
you doing okay yeah okay she's just
gonna look out the window she's she's a
good kitten um anyway so here's the
situation it runs a really crappy parser
and it just prints the output it
paginates with commas I actually left
some code in there that you can choose
whether you want commas or periods and
stuff for a case Allan wants to merge it
into the core and switch on
internationalization I don't know if he
has that in there or not but it's set up
for that and so anyway you can do math
and see pretty quickly what's going on
which is pretty nice it also is smart
enough to go hey look if it's a whole
number don't you know print out the
whole crazy decimal but if it's not a
whole number go ahead and do it so
that's kind of nice to just just a nice
feature to have in there um so really I
like there's a bunch of other little
things that I did but I don't think
they're super relevant now to go over
obviously I tried some things with like
marking regions you can see like I I
have it so that it marks the region now
that you're on line stuff like that and
you get also it'll also highlight things
like the current token and and crap like
that but again that's not super relevant
we don't really have to talk much about
that stuff it's it's pretty boring stuff
so I think I've covered most of the mods
there's probably some things that I'm
forgetting in there but that's basically
how it goes
and so what I want to do now is focus on
some new stuff that I'd like to add and
there's some features that I still
there's some polish that still needs to
be done and so that's obviously
something that I'll look at some other
time but at least for today what I'd
like to do is is focus primarily on
implementing some new features
experimental features so let's talk
about how that is gonna go so at the
moment you can kind of see what I'm
thinking about with respect to that down
here and what you can see is I've made
these sort of numbered like bins right
I call this temporarily because it
needed a name I call this the F bar
which sounds vaguely sort of vaguely
expletive but it's not just because it
corresponds to the function keys and
you'll notice that this is the place
where the build is happening so if I
were to switch projects here and
remember this is our actual editor the
one that we're using to edit the for a
coder code this is the running for coder
test which is not but if I were to load
something up like handmade ray and do a
builds the bids build still happens down
in here and at the moment I have not
done anything to implement harmonious
coexistence of these little buttons here
with the build itself and so that in
addition to lots of other things are
what we're gonna start working on today
now what I did in prep was those things
correspond to the two things right so
first of all at any time so meaning no
matter what you're doing in the editor
the F keys are bound to what I call
executing an F bin so an F bar is a
collection of F bins F bins are the
things you see there and if I hit an F
key it will execute one of these now
that does absolutely nothing right now
and of course f12 is the hotkey for
break into the bugger
so you know hopefully someday we won't
have visual studio around or I can
unbind that key because I never want
that to be the case I'd rather have f12
available for use but ignoring that so
hitting one of those will execute that
bin now all I did at the moment is made
it so that it was clear that that's
happening right as you can see and for
those of you who don't know I my for
coder setup is modal and so the reason
that's Moodle is because one of the
things that I felt was a problem for
repetitive stress injury carpal tunnel
syndrome etc etc is the Emacs way of
having like tons of crazy button mashing
like ctrl alt this or alt bat or control
this or blah blah blah holding down keys
is just not great and especially if you
tweak your hand into a particular
position you'd have to ask Emily what
actual repetitive kind of strain
injuries you're gonna get from that sort
of thing I have no idea I don't know if
carpal tunnels likely it's probably not
because you're not pressing that hard on
the keys but just tendonitis and general
discomfort the same kind of stuff you
get from using a video game control or
too long all that sort of stuff it's
just not great and so what I did when I
switched to for coder and I had done
this on Emacs as well I was like let me
try to switch to something modal which
means like you know VI is an example of
a very modal editor right it's like
you're either in the mode where you're
entering text or in the mode where
you're operating on stuff in between
those two modes it controls whether or
not an ordinary key press like the f key
or the e key or you know D key whatever
just a regular key whether that is
effectively like hitting control that
key or whether it just inserts the key
and so it's really not that much
different and VI that's just one of the
things about VI right there's a lot of
things about VI and its philosophy that
have nothing to do with that but that
part is very different from Emacs Emacs
never really had two modes
it was always about if you wanted to do
a command you hold down the control key
and hit a key it was never about I
switch into command mode and then I just
hit the regular key does something and
so I switched over to a more VI like
thing for that and it's since I was
never a VI user it's not at all based on
VI if you were a VI user I think you
would probably try to report a bunch of
the conventions that you were used to
but I'm not so I'm not going to anyway
so when I did that modal thing you can
see that I switch between them and
you've probably seen me do that on
handmade Kuro there's actually a very
strong color indication that that's
happening when you look at the cursor
it's red if I'm in command execution
mode and that's the thing that allows me
to do stuff like you know marker region
or whatever cut and paste it do those
sorts of things or invoke the jump menu
for example that's just getting the J
key whereas if I'm in insertion mode and
it's green anything I can't just insert
the key there is no way to execute any
command except that now I am adding
these because the F keys don't have any
corresponding way to insert anything so
they're bound at all times right they're
bound to regardless of what mode you're
in now I may change my mind about that
as I go down this path a little bit more
and have the two modes do different
things when you hit the F keys but at
the moment I don't intend to now when
you are in regular mode editing things
obviously you hit the four key five key
one key it inserts that number that's
just how editing text works but if you
switch into command mode now what I've
also said is when you hit the
corresponding number key to an F key and
also I should note that the equals and
minus keys I've mapped to eleven and
twelve and the zero key I mapped to ten
so it's basically still the straight
button bar just across the top of your
keyboard right those correspond to the
bins and they will select a particular
bin right they'll just make it like the
active bin does that make sense now of
course you may be asking yourself and I
strongly suspect
that you are what is all this for who
cares
look what are you gonna do with this
well it occurs to me and has always
occurred to me for since time immemorial
that most of the things that I do in my
editor I do again right
and I believe I don't quote me on this
but I believe that VI has some sort of
support for this and Emacs had some sort
of support for this which is to say that
any time you did something complicated
such as search and replace you could
repeat that search and replace using the
mini bar in Emacs and I don't use the I
but I'm pretty sure that VI had the same
thing where you could basically say look
I did something just now I want to do
that thing again
and as long as I haven't done any other
commands in the meantime I can just do
it if I have done other commands in the
meantime again don't know about VI but
least in Emacs you could effectively say
give me a list right like show me the
last 10 searching replaces I did or
whatever and I'm gonna pick one to do
again right so one of the things that I
definitely lost on it - for coder is I
couldn't do that anymore now it wasn't
very good in Emacs support was not great
but it was nice to have and so one of
the things that I'm often thought about
is how would I fear that allowed me
access to that same sort of thing that
I'm Emacs and I'm pretty sure VI can do
how can I put that back into for coder
in a way that makes sense for me and the
way I at it can I make it better
can I improve it for my use my use case
and what I was thinking is what I'd
really like is I'd really like it to
just say look every time I do something
you
clean of goes into like a stack of
things I can do but rather than those
things being buried behind some editor
facade which is what happened like an
Emacs and certainly happens in VI
because anything in VI is always hidden
behind some crazy of Zod let's just make
it explicit so every time I do something
let's put it that's where I came up with
this idea of the F Ben and f bar anytime
I do something let's just put it down in
a bin right and if you want to do it
again you just hit the F key that
corresponds to that bin that's it right
that's all you have to do furthermore
let's standardize on the way that the
bins are organized and listed so for
example a if I jump to a particular
function then that's a command of jump
with the function name as the function
or something right as the first
parameter if I wanted to do a search
inside the buffer for the for that text
then the command be searched and the
name of that function if I want to do a
search and replace it would be search
and replace the name of that function
and the thing to replace it to and so
there's always this sort of binary op
style of what is the thing you were
trying to do what is the parameter a and
what is parameter B now why do I care
about that because then what I can do is
I can introduce operations between bins
so I can you know use this this idea of
selecting a bin and say Oh bin for has a
search in a place that's basically what
I want and I still want to keep it there
or maybe I know let's say it still has
the search place I want I just want to
edit the second parameter
I'll just have a key on the keyboard
that lets me change just a second
parameter so I don't have to start a
whole search and replace and type in the
thing to replace again right I can just
change the second parameter and go or
maybe it's the opposite maybe I just
want to change the first parameter right
similarly maybe it's got exactly what I
want in terms of the first parameter but
it's a wrong command so instead of the
command being searched in replace I just
want search well
should be able to do that really quickly
too right so what I want to do is
basically see if I can get some leverage
out of this by including locations and
files parameter names to those kinds of
functions and then a set of different
commands what can I do to make this work
pretty well and then the two big things
that I don't really know what how it
should work but it's gonna be sensitive
and I'll probably have to figure out a
good solution is every time I'm doing
something like jumping around a file or
anything like that it's gonna you know
overwrite something in the bin bar right
in the F bar and so I need some policy
for saying keep this thing around or
don't and what gets evicted probably
like least recently used gets evicted
you know or something I don't know and
so we need some way of being intelligent
about what gets removed and what doesn't
because that's gonna be the other really
important aspect of making this useful
if we assume it's useful at all so lots
of other things the active part also can
determine what like next and previous do
so one of the big problems I have in for
code are all the time right now is that
if I do a compile and then I do a search
I can't step forwards and backwards for
the for the things in the compile the
error message of the compile and the
things in the search interchangeably
it's like whatever the last one was
that's the one that it's gonna use and I
can't go back to a previous one and the
same would be true of searching I
searched once I search again I lose all
my previous search and my place in that
in those listings if I was trying to go
up and down on it right and so I also
want as part of this anytime you do the
command I want to see
the buffer so basically every F bin
would have its own like buffer backing
it and these buffers would just be
whenever I make one of these active
that's the buffer that gets displayed in
here and it's the buffer that should
have the forward and backwards motion on
it occurring so that I can just have
like 12 searches open if that's what I
want and ping-pong around them however I
want and I don't have to worry about for
coder having this kind of concept of
what the most recent one was right and
so that's what I want to try and get to
now in order to do that again I need
some way we'll get out of the experiment
for coder and back to the actual for a
coder here that we're looking at oh one
thing I meant to mention is there's also
this scope context stuff now that's
gonna get upgraded a little bit I think
in the future but basically what that is
is if you're inside of a scope work that
you can't see so like there for example
it will show you like as much
information as it can about that scope
so you can see it says this outer and
closing brace that you can't see right
here is this if statement and this outer
and closing brace that you can't see is
this for statement and this outer
enclosing braces you can't see is this
function right which is pretty awesome I
was really psyched about that feature
it's pretty neat it also if it has room
will do small else clauses as well if
you can't see the if so for example even
if you can see the clause you can see
here it'll try to put the if in there
but the problem is if it doesn't have
room so the reason is gonna probably
change from doing it this way is I think
I'm going to try and do is put it on the
closed brace here anytime it can so you
know in this case it can't there's no
closed brace so it'll continue to draw
it here but for all of these it'll just
put it after the close brace that way
you always know which close brace is
associated with which open brace
statement which is pretty handy so
that's it that's what those are people
are probably wondering what that junk is
it's showing up there
okay let me see here so f bar let's talk
about this so I haven't started this
again all I did was bind it up and make
it so that I've got the two things that
I said I wanted which was execute F in
and select F in and so what I need to do
now there's a bunch of things but first
of all I want every one of these bins to
have a backing buffer so in order to do
that I need something in here that's
like a buffer ID so every time I have a
F pin it's got a buffer and so when we
initialize the F bar here now that f bar
is gonna create buffers for everything
so I'm gonna need a thing that's like
you know in it f bar and so I pass it
the f bar and say look this is your
chance to go through and make sure
everything's kosher so this will go
through everything in the entire f bar
so like for each of these guys go ahead
and give me an f bar out of the I'm
sorry go ahead and give me an F bin out
of f bar so every time I get one of
those I then need to set in the you know
in the F in here I need to set the
buffer to be essentially an F bin buffer
that I create whose sole job it is to
like capture data right and this thing
is going to be its these F bins are
going to completely replace the for
coder notion of the build buffer and the
search buffer and stuff like that right
dead it has pulled on why what do you
think you know what here's a question
for chat let's just let's just figure
this out right
so is it gonna be a tonic water or a
ginger ale next I want to open one of
them and drink it again I have to get
100% of my calories especially through
sugar water today pretty much period so
you know we got it we got to keep it
going on here otherwise I'm just gonna
crash it's already surprising if I'll be
able to code with having had no food but
you know we'll see but give me the
verdict like tell me what we're gonna do
are we gonna do yeah are we going to do
ginger ale or are we going to do
um it looks like ginger Ale's kind of
winning all right looks like ginger ale
we're gonna drink the tonic water
eventually so that will come next all
right here comes a ginger ale oh no it
fit on me well not really on me but it's
just done my stuff thankfully nothing
did not fit on anything important like
computer hardware all right so what we
need to do here is we essentially need
to create one of these temporary buffers
but for coder often uses to you know
represent stuff that's transient like a
search result and so on now I've
actually never done that in for coder so
it's gonna be a little bit of adventure
for me because I don't really know much
about compilation and stuff like that so
you can see here this is how we're
currently doing the build and the global
compilation buffer name thing here you
can see I have defined write and I guess
although I don't really know that this
exact system command must just create
this if it doesn't exist I guess
so I don't know exit one thing I should
mention is the jump stuff does not work
for things defined in a macro that
should have been found though I wonder
why that wasn't found do we know why
that wasn't found
that seems pretty weird that none of the
functions in this file got found I
wonder if there's a parsing bug that
happens only in this file for example
you can see that it finds this function
just fine you found that function just
fine
in fact all of these are just fine until
it gets to this it looks like this API
export is somehow confusing it but I
can't think of why that would be true oh
gosh you know what I bet it's because
comments are not ignored in the parser
let's fix that
again this parser is really Genki I mean
it's the thing that I kind of hack
because here's the really super annoying
thing I think C was a pretty good
language for what it wanted to do
there's only really one thing I think
they got wrong for their time you know
and that was they made the syntax
unnecessarily hard to parse they could
have just had a function key word you
know
just-just that would have been so good
right a cast keyword just cast
appendices or something right like just
a couple little minor additions of just
one or two keywords and we could just
parse it for real right and I guess
maybe the other thing I would say is if
you had some kind of a prohibition on
the way that pound of fines could work I
mean I guess technically the
preprocessor makes it really impossible
to parse because you have to have the
entire state of the preprocessor at any
time to know so it's not quite as
straightforward as I'm making it sound
but I do think that there was a chance
there to have made something pretty easy
to parse and that's really my only
complaint for what they were trying to
do I mean we can imagine much better
languages today but that's with
incredible amounts of hindsight alright
so let's take a look here at the parsing
part of this we don't care about parsing
comment but here we are at ad buffer to
index and so that particular case is
looking at a function right and so the
way that that case works is you can see
it kind of doing this thing here where
it goes and tries to find the first
identifier in question and so the way
that this starts out is it says look if
I've got a brace then let's back up from
the brace and see if it's CPP token
parentheses close you can see exactly
what the problem is the problem is that
if it were to return comment this would
fail
and that's as Zac what's gonna happen
it's gonna find this brace it's gonna
look at the previous token in that
previous token is a comment and that's
not gonna work right so what we want to
do here instead is say something like
CPP token
you know Tompa comment pass get this
thing and then just do look let's get
this thing and while it's a comment
because we don't want those keep going
again total hack but this whole thing is
a total hack so you know not a huge not
a huge loss we're just trying to get
something that does what we want for our
code base okay and so if I were to fix
that here yeah it's fine what I would
expect now is that if I run for a coder
on itself I'm hoping that we fixed that
problem and so now in the new version if
I do do exact system command I expect to
find it and I do so that was just an
oversight there that was just like one
of the things I forget sometimes is
Allen's parser puts comments into tokens
and when I write parsers I generally do
this thing that's a two-tier so if you
say get token you will not see comments
if you say get raw token you will see
comments in white space so it you can
control like the level of token
iteration you're doing and I forget
sometimes when I'm doing a hacky parser
inside someone else's you know token
stream I sometimes forget the fact that
you know here's decisions they made here
such as I made and I guys forget stuff
like that so anyway that's all good so
we can put that to rest here but anyway
back to what we're talking about so
exact system command that takes this
buffer identify our concept now a buffer
identifier and a buffer ID are actually
different I believe don't quote me on
that but I believe that's actually true
so like for example a buffer identifier
let me
see here yeah yes so buffer identifiers
take like the string and the length and
so on oh one thing I should mention in
Alan's code the parser stuff doesn't
really work very well for stuff that's
in the public API because he does this
thing where he uses struct and caps and
of course we don't expand macros so we
would never pick that up again like I
said we're not really parsing the C so
it only works if it's code that looks
roughly like mine okay
so the buffer identifier in this case
that's outside of the sunlight I can
basically say look this is just a string
that identifies this buffer I guess if
you try to switch to it it will
automatically do that I don't actually
know
like what I don't really know is does it
just automatically create it for you I
guess
and you can see here creating one of
these things and yeah I just what I
don't really know is what that
so I guess if I'm looking at this there
isn't really a function that's just like
get me a buffer or create it but I'm
gonna make one right because that's what
I want to do so so I want this thing
effectively to do that
I guess although technically it's
startup I guess I always know that it
doesn't exist so I guess I don't really
have to do that I guess all I really
have to do is this working set a lock
always push string buffer by name in it
read-only file right now I would have
assumed that there was a function for
this
but I guess not so you know it's a
little bit weird for me to be doing this
yeah I feel like there should be just
create temporary buffer call but it
doesn't look like there is um I'm not
really sure so I'm gonna start a little
bit tenderly here and I guess what I'm
gonna say is look let's cut out the part
of this code that we think we're going
to need right which is that we need to
do this we need to do this and we need
to do this I don't think we need to look
up any of the process stuff because
that's gonna be specific just to builds
and we certainly don't need to do any of
this reporting that's a necessary as
well we don't need to clear it because
there shouldn't be anything in it but we
do need to set it as unimportant that's
a flag that lets four code or know that
we don't want to switch to it so we
don't want it to be like matched when
we're doing file switching we want to be
like listed last and stuff like that I
think that's what it means you know what
don't quote me on that I'm not sure what
that actually means so maybe that's not
true anyway uh so in terms of this stuff
here we're we're doing this bind to new
view that stuff that's probably a
separate part where we want to like
bring stuff into the view that's gonna
be part of the Select F pin sort of
thing and so that's probably going to be
really more like this code up here and
so when we're doing that it's probably
more this kind of a thing so yeah we
don't need that we really just need this
and in order to do view set file that's
an internal call so we really don't want
that per se we want a like view buffer
or something like this I'll be honest I
don't really remember what that call is
here it is so we just want to do this
right so I don't think we need any of
that
honestly it's that's just internal code
that we probably can't call so we want
to do is in here is we want to set any
time you select an F in we want the
buffer this buffer to be showing that
information so it's got the buffer ID
here right so I know that part of it I'm
going to need to receive the application
links here that's basically just the
thing that lets us do stuff with for
coder I don't know what the zero is
there and then the buffer is just the
buffer the view is not so bad because I
actually don't need to call get active
view I know which view it is at all
times because I actually that sort of f
bar bin down there at the bottom I just
have a global four so that thing is just
a global it's a hug view is what's
called I should probably call it the f
bar view from now on but so in theory at
anytime I can just get the view summary
for that I can set it to be whatever the
active F bins buffer is so if I just say
look give me
[Music]
this particular one I should then be
able to say switch to that particular
buffer now part of that and I you know
what I should really see what what is
view set buffer so when you do have you
set buffer you're sending down set
buffer flags and I don't know what the
set buffer flags actually are it looks
like there's a thing for those not in
here so here's a sip buffer flag yes up
every you were singing then when
the fast set the view will not switch to
it if some other GUI was currently up
otherwise any GUI that is up is closed
and the view switches to the file so I
don't think that's probably super
relevant to us
I don't really know so I think we can
leave that as a zero so I think this is
all we really need to do here I can also
do a thing where I say hey get active F
bin buffer or something like this where
I'm gonna say look I need to do a build
so it's gonna go into the active F bin
buffer or whatever well you know what
let's not do that yet we got to think
that through a little bit better anyway
so what we now need to do is make sure
this stuff works at all and this stuff I
don't know how we're gonna make this
work because we're doing this outside so
we have to create a buffer and do
effectively these things but we probably
can't actually call any of this stuff
right so we need a way of creating your
read-only file but we need a way of
doing it in through the for code or API
as opposed to an internal thing so
I don't know how to do that let's take a
look so here's the create buffer call
there's the working set Alec always
there's the buffer by name this
unfortunately is in it normal file
whereas we want read-only I'm not sure
how to do that so I'm going to look for
it in it read-only file so does that
mean I can't create a read-only file but
how does search do it I mean when you
create a search like here's list all
functions right and so it does this
think here it's like get buffer by name
ah ok alright ok ok ok ok so this is
what we need to do here here we go
perfect perfect perfect perfect so here
in an it f bar what I can do is I can
call the buffer set setting which
hopefully maybe possibly let's say it
might do something let's let's do that
and assume that this is good enough for
replicating what's happening there and
the unimportant thing as you can see
it's got the read-only flag it's got the
unimportant flag that seems good right
now here in the get buffer by name thing
I don't really want that
good so basically what I can do is just
skip right to this because I know that
this buffer does not exist right so
there's the decals buffer that will
create it for me
it'll set all the correct settings on it
and so now all I need is is the buffer
name right yeah that seems good so I
need a name for each of these f bar
buffers and that's fine because it's
really just going to be like f bar
percent D right so all I need to do is
prep that first so if I just say look
give me f bar and then whatever the
number of the thing is right like 1 2 3
4 5 7 8 whatever create all of those
this right here I just need to do like a
make string and in fact I'm gonna do a
mixed ring right on this because what it
needs is the size and the string so I
can just do that right and so I do make
litte string off you go
it makes the buffer of whatever this
buffer name is here right so there's
tougher name and the wrapping point is
set wrong right now which is kind of
annoying but I can fix that a little bit
later so here's the buffer that we've
created now we've done everything that
we need to do to it and so finally at
the end of all that we just need to save
what it was right so that should do that
and I think that's all we need we now
need to go like I said before we need
the application links we can't do
anything without the application links
that's the thing that allows
actually access for coders API which
means that all the stuff in here needs
to get that sent down alright um looks
like we've got an error there what is
the error right I think that should just
be make string so now I've got this
notion of switching between these f bar
buffers don't really know what's gonna
happen with it but the idea is that you
should be able to switch between them we
wouldn't really know oh well you know
what we could do so what we could do is
call append and if we call pens then we
should be able to see inside our for
coder here
well I guess it's actually buffer
replace range yeah so if in here I do a
buffer replace range that will allow me
to insert into the buffer so you know
this buffer that we've got here at the
very beginning start and string and
length so I should be able to do buffer
name dot stir and a buffer name dot size
to just stick make the contents of the
buffer just be F Ben so I can see it and
then when I switch between them and do
the selection I should be able to see
that change right now obviously none of
this is gonna work if we don't actually
emit this thing so I need to call it
when we actually start up or nothing's
gonna happen so when we actually have
the start hook case you start in here
before I do anything else I can go ahead
and and call it now default for putter
initialize I don't know if some of this
stuff should happen first probably
should I don't know so I might go ahead
and just put it down here at the bottom
so something like that where we just say
look initialize the global f bar you
know have fun I that I think should get
us to the point where we can actually
switch buffers down there
I hope it's tonic time by the way
if you want to get really excited I made
my own apple juice jello
I'm not sure when it'll be done I think
four hours so two hours on stream and if
we do a second stream later we can eat
some apple jello it's literally just
apple juice with gelatin in it
anyway so you know watch for that anyway
let's go here to nnf bar this this thing
should you know insert the stuff for us
I'm gonna see if I can make that out
like if I couldn't I don't need to do
that sorry I can do it I'm gonna see if
I can make that show me something down
at the bottom I don't know if it will
you know we'll find out but here is that
f bar I'm gonna switch to command mode
and now select yeah okay so this is kind
of nice like we can select the F bar of
our choice and we get you know those
buffers showing up exactly as we would
want now mind you I don't actually know
how to tell for coder to start the
buffer display somewhere below this
thing that is gonna be a bit of a trip I
don't want to go diving into the for
kodokor without Allen's permission on
stream because I don't know if he's okay
with me streaming edits to the core I
don't think he's watching so we can't
really ask him but I'm not going to do
that so if I had to do that I'd probably
go do that off stream but we can get
everything working just drawing wrong
and then I just need to figure out how
I'm gonna make that work because at the
moment I don't really know a way to tell
for a coder that I need a margin at the
top of the screen for some crap that I'm
drawing I don't know how you make that
happen by the time I get to the render I
think it's too late because it kind of
has this idea about where stuff is in
the buffer that's like very specific and
so I don't know I mean I could try maybe
setting the scroll position to be like
negative I don't know if for coder is
okay with that like in other words if I
told for coder that the scrolling
position was like an illegal position
something that forced it to be viewing
up from where it actually is maybe it
allows that I mean it might
and if it does I think we're okay and I
can talk about why in a second but that
might that might work okay so now what I
like to do is let's just take the simple
step of seeing if I can make like
searches and crap like that
and build let's see if I can make those
target one of the FB ins instead of the
buffers they're currently using so for
example like I've got the like global
compilation buffer name let's just go
ahead and get rid of that and see if we
can make it use an F bin instead I also
don't know what LOC jump buffer means
but my hope is that if like LOC jump
buffer is something you could just call
on any buffer and then that becomes the
new buffer that you're going to go like
up and down in when you do like error
jump to next error that sort of stuff
that would be really nice because that
would give us an easy way to do one of
the other features I want which is like
whichever one of your buffers is the
active buffer is going to be able to be
used as like you know previous and next
and all that stuff if it's as simple as
calling a lock jump buffer that would be
nice I don't know that it will be we can
look alright looks like that's simple in
the custom where
uh so
so all it's doing is storing the name of
the buffer that's like jump locked at
that time
so yeah I mean I don't really know what
to make of that
exactly cuz like for example it doesn't
seem to make a lot of sense get view for
a locked jump buffer but why would you
need a view like you should be able to
use a jump buffer just as a buffer so
who exactly calls that maybe nobody okay
so here we are in get lock jump state
which I don't know what that does in
jump direct and jumping seek jump and
that's like skip beats okay so yeah like
it's a bit of a bummer because I don't
really want to do what this is doing
right like the way that this code is set
up it's it's basically saying I need you
to actually have a view bound to this
buffer or I won't execute the jump but I
don't know that we really want that to
be a limitation I guess it's not the
worst limitation in the world it's just
not what I would have preferred because
if you switch away from the active jump
buffer to some other F bin that isn't a
jump in like it's just it's a search and
replace or something so it doesn't have
the notion I don't know it's probably
fine we can just work with it for now
and it might just never be an issue so
it's fine I don't know anyway so if I am
in select F been here and I set the
buffer I'm just gonna lock this as a
jump upper because I can and just try
and stop
right so lock jump buffer with the
buffer here I guess I literally I only
gonna have to pass the thing so I can
literally just say this is the buffer
right does it need it's a buffer summary
so I don't know why there isn't a little
bit more flexibility between but for
some reason buffer IDs but I guess
that's just how it is so let's get this
buffer summary going here so I think I
can just call that and say you know what
give me back the buffer and then we'll
lock that as the jump buffer right so
that allows me to switch between buffers
that have had jumpable stuff in it like
a search or a build and so then only
think I really need to do is anytime
that we're going to execute a build or a
search try and enforce those things to
occur on the buffer that is the
currently most likely to want that
at the moment I'm gonna do that wrong
let's do this I'm gonna do it
intentionally wrong because like I said
I don't know what our replacement
policies gonna be for these f pins so I
don't know also Jim the reason I need to
know about jump buffers is because
builds going to jump buffers
no I'm saying so yeah
also I've read the sequel what do you
mean man Alan and I are totally in it to
win it on for coder I'm like adding the
for coder as we speak anyway so let's
have a way of getting the F in here more
quickly I probably should've done this
to begin with so here we just say you
know and and I'll just make this use the
global as well so here we'll just say if
you want to get one of these things then
we do this and enough off it goes it
gets you the global f bar bins and so
maybe this stuff doesn't really need the
f bar in question and
we'll do it like this how's that so this
way you can call it either way and
everyone's happy
so now what I want to do is I want to
try using like get F been here so that
instead of the way the compilation
buffer stuff is working right now in my
code we'll just make compilations or
we'll try to make compilations work that
way
so in here where we have like
compilation I'm just gonna get rid of
that and so now everywhere that we were
previously using that will try to
redirect it towards one of these FM
things right I don't know what's going
on here
nothing good should actually be results
that should be an address of select F
then get buffer app and buffer so it's
get buffer not an actual says oh right
there's this weird access all thing all
right so now we can get back to the task
at hand which is in here we have this
buffer identifier and that this lock
jump buffer sort of thing I don't think
we need to do this anymore
oops I think that's just not necessary
and then this exact command thing that's
gonna be like I'm gonna do a get F pin
and I guess what I want to do here is
like get target F bin and that is going
to be where you call get F in on
whatever the active one is
we do it this bar bar so it still just
target whatever the active when is
eventually we got to think about what
that replacement poss can be I don't
know but we're gonna do the best we can
and so you know this will just do it
salt like so alright so global complex
buffer name is now only used there I
think that's the only place so now all
we have to do is make a buffer
identifier out of the get target F been
here and the get target F pin call will
return us an F pin and we'll just get
the buffer out of it and we'll say use
that one and I think that's all we need
so I don't really know if this will work
cuz I don't really understand the
internals of that part of for code or
well at all
but now if I'm in this mode right I can
select these bins
I can hit build and in theory it should
build right and I should be able to
build in any one of them and switch back
okay so that seems to work just fine now
the question is what if we actually had
something that actually does build and
potentially produces errors right so
let's see we loaded up handmade rain and
and hit build right okay well that's not
very good cuz that's not and in fact Oh
crumbs right so this is not as easy as
it sounds we do have one issue there and
that is that when you switch projects we
kill all of our buffers so when that
happens we have to initialize the f bar
again right everything has to get remade
because all of those buffers have been
destroyed
I don't know if this is the best way to
do this
maybe we should just prevent those
buffers from being destroyed I don't
know what to do there so there's a thing
called closed all files you can see it
happening here I want all of the buffers
to be killed but maybe what I really
want to do is kill everything that's not
an f bar buffer I guess
so maybe I'll do like is f bar buffer
don't know right so like we're gonna
kill this buffer we advanced the next
one and we say look is this one an f bar
buffer and we say here it is
so we'll just you know what I'm saying
to you something like that and so that
way we can pass the ID that we're like
about to kill and then we'll just scan
the f bar to see like is that one of
ours and if it is let's like leave it
alone please
you know so if the bin buffer equals the
ID that's passed then it's true that's
like all I can really think of as maybe
the easiest solution there it looks like
B 32 is not a thing that I defined its P
32 X
all right that's all good and so now
hopefully I can do the test that I was
trying to do before and again I say
hopefully so I run it here it is we
switched to handmade ray I asked it to
build there it goes
oops so that's good so let's suppose
that I have some errors so I'm gonna
insert some errors into handmade ray
just judiciously right and so now if I'm
on you know F bar for here and I build I
should be able to jump between these
errors right oops
oh right I changed those hotkeys
so it is jumping between the areas on
there it won't jump now if I come back
it does jump that seems like it works
that seems like it works so you know I
don't want to clear victory yet because
I don't really know if that's quite
right but that seems like it works so
that seems ok let's try something a
little harder now let's try search so in
terms of what I've got for search
obviously there's incremental search
that's not one that has to work with a
jump over so we can save looking at that
until a little later on we do want that
to interact with the F bends so we do
have to sort of deal with that but let's
just try regular to have it it's time do
we have here we got turns this so we got
about fifteen minutes so let's let's try
and get some of the search stuff working
here all right so let's suppose we take
one of the searches that I have I don't
think I've got many anymore because I
use jump blisters for a lot of stuff now
which will work a slightly different way
when we merge those into the F bin but
for things that actually dump a bunch of
gunk out into an actual buffer and then
we jump around what we need to do is
have some way of targeting those back at
the F in so let's see what my modal
commands are here so I think the only
ones you really have our list all
locations and list all substring the
locations case-insensitive so basically
K is like whole tokens and L is like
anywhere this string ever even embedded
in other stuff occurs right list all
locations of type
definition isn't really a thing anymore
because I kind of just have that it's
done so I don't know where that actually
is this all locations so list all
locations of type definition I don't
need anymore that's a thing that is
defined in for coders search so that I
that's not my call so I can make that an
unused key and we can bind it to
something useful later jump to index and
jump to definition or the good jump
Lister's I made so if those obviously
want to remain list all locations in
list all substring locations those are
probably going to get condensed into one
thing the point being those are actually
the ones we care about so list all
substring locations case-sensitive
that's really the one that I use for
just search for the string everywhere so
we really want that one to work so if I
look at lists all substring locations
case-insensitive
what I need to do is look at how that's
working and how I can target it at a
different buffer this is going to be
kind of difficult unfortunately because
the way this is going to work I don't
know if I can set the buffer that it's
going to target very easily it probably
not so we'll see
anyway query the user for a string and
list all case-insensitive things so you
can see it getting whatever the view is
that you're going to use that does list
query parameters global heat little part
true true target view so it looks like
list query parameters is actually the
thing we're talking about here so that
does a get query string which allows you
to get back what you are looking for and
then do list single parameters thing on
it which looks like what you want
because it gets past the default target
view I guess really all I have to do
though is
is change this thing so I can do this
pretty easily this is great all I have
to do is make my own function that
passes the view that is the one that
were that happens to have our F pin in
it now it's a little unfortunate I don't
understand why this takes of view
because why couldn't it just take a
buffer probably because it does a lot
jump buffer on it after so let me just
investigate a little bit further because
it would be nice if this just targeted a
buffer and not a view but we can work
around it even if it does so you know
again not the end of the world so let me
go ahead and jump to list query
parameters that calls list single
parameters so I'm gonna go ahead and do
this single parameters just takes that
target view you can see here again we're
just kind of peeling the onion and
getting down to default that perhaps
there Lisp parameters which passes
default target view so in terms of
default target view this is what I'm
curious about
yeah exactly like I thought doesn't
actually get used at all right it's just
getting the buffer so you know I would
argue that this function probably should
be broken into two parts so that that
doesn't have to happen right if we made
this function so that that it took the
buffer here then this part could be done
by somebody else and that way you're
always targeting a buffer and you're not
targeting of you which is not you know
what we want so I guess what I would say
is and you see it's doing the lit string
here so I guess right since we really
want to do is we want to basically force
this split and I'm gonna just
I'm just gonna say hey Alan let's have
that happen on an arbitrary buffers
right and so that way if we just just
cut out this code right and then we said
use that code here and then call it and
this will just be like you know list
parameters buffer and here we just say
buffer ID search buffer ID
I think that's literally all we need to
do and I'll try to keep Alan's code
style there he likes to have the brace
squash up to the previous line so if we
just did that then this call could could
happen right down here immediately after
and then that way you can call into that
part of the call chain in either place
so all the existing code will work but
then code like ours that wants to have
multiple search buffers just can and
there's nothing weird about it right so
hopefully that will work if I recompile
this I'm hoping I will just get oh right
that lock has to happen out here I'm
hoping I will just get the exact same
behavior now and there'll be no
weirdness right uh so that should work
I can also still force this like I don't
know if we want to or not I'm guessing
we don't because I'm trying to control
that now but like you could also put it
here and just pass the buffer ID cuz
lock dump buffer will split the buffer
ID out to the name if you need it to and
stuff like that so I think that's fine
okay so now that we've done that I
should be able to call this function
instead with the things that I actually
need and it should work so instead of
calling lists all substring locations
case-insensitive i need to make a new
function that will do this thing that we
actually needed to do and it'll call
this function here and it will call it
with a bunch of stuff that I don't
understand and so we're going to have to
actually sort of comb through that
custom source code to like figure out
what we actually need to do to prep this
function so that's our next job custom
commands sig here we'll just call this
Casey list I'm gonna literally call it
the same darn thing and so we'll
probably call this something like f bar
will probably move so eventually what
we're gonna do when we want these things
to store the ops that they did we're
gonna start moving all of these commands
into the F bar and the F bar will like
use the ops that happen automatically
and stuff like that you know it'll get
it'll be all mr. fancy pants up in here
and and all that but for the moment
right we're just trying to be like basic
baby steps start to put things in the
correct place so now let's go try to
recreate that function call chain one
thing at a time and so I'm first gonna
go to that list all sub screen occasions
case-insensitive and we should be able
to just do the same thing so if I come
back in here and I just paste that in
you know we need this target view and
then oh well I guess that's it so then
we're just gonna do this query
parameters now for getting the target
view again I just want the search buffer
and that true stuff so in terms of the
target new I think I do want to do this
later I might change my mind about where
that's gonna happen but for now it can
just happen in the same buffer you were
normally using for now right so we'll do
that
now then we need to go to this right
here right list query parameters and so
here we needed to do this and then here
we need to do this and then at that
point I think we can dispatch to this he
says so confidently but I think that's
it
right because then we've we've gotten
down to the place where we split so
looking at this right here's the stuff
that we know that we want substring
whole world case is sensitive so we can
actually simplify this whole rigmarole
by just welding it together we don't
need any parameterization here at the
moment because we only support one thing
now in the future we might support more
and then I'll break it out a little
differently but there we go and then of
course we also don't need to call this
thing until we actually know that we got
back a query string okay so that gets
back a quarry string and stuffs it in
that space thing or whatever that's fine
don't care and then we call this thing
what you can see here is I don't know
about the heap scratch stuff and the
strings count nonsense so I got to go
see what we did there exactly in terms
of how we were passing this stuff in so
like looking at the count the count is
just one and the strings are just the
address of this so it looks like I could
have done multiple strings that you
search for at the same time and you know
that's pretty cool
so really what I want there is like you
know string counts and strings and like
at the moment it doesn't actually work
but you know you could imagine at some
point it actually did so for right now
we'll just funk it exactly the way that
it was being flung funked before and
then later we'll figure out how we might
take advantage of that feature because
that's a pretty cool feature I like that
keep scratch let's hope those get past a
custom commands' thing I have no idea
I'm just gonna hope that they do buffer
ID is actually pretty easy for us right
that's just getting that target F in so
in here where we do get target F in I
can just have that happen whenever we
get a valid one of these whenever we get
a valid search string I can just say
look give me the bin and then that will
take care of this right I don't know if
that's gonna work we're gonna try and
hopefully not fail I think that's all we
need
so heap and scratch I don't know how to
get those so let's take a look at how
those were happening before because I'm
pretty sure list query parameters
already had them by the time we got down
here so they all must have came from the
list all locations not blah blah blah
blah blah right like the
so it's just passing the global heap in
the global partition is that that's what
it's passing right I don't really
understand why it needs those two things
but I'm guessing that the reason is
because you might want it to use a
separate off band heaps sometimes I
don't know why all right
anyway let's let's just see if that
works so if I if I launched this guy and
we try some searches let's see if they
work so the first thing we do is let's
again switch the project to handmade ray
since that's our little test thing now
what I'd like to do is say search for
everywhere the word ray appears that
should probably do it right oh and also
I guess let me switch to a particular
buffer here so we'll switch to buffer 4
and we will search for the word ray so
here's all the word ray and I should be
able to like loop through all of the
things for the word ray now and that is
happening right let's go to buffer 5 and
now search for the word Lane right so
here's all the places that Lane goes and
I can switch between them and so now for
the money
switch back to 4 oh yeah yeah awesome so
this is great just this alone will make
my life so much easier just being able
to have search buffers up this is going
to be good all right so that's great
let's take a break now it's about time
for the stream to be over does anyone
have any quick questions I'll probably
come back and do a second one because
I'm kind of psyched this is getting
close to being what I wanted now I just
need to start sucking up those opps into
the f bar and then I think we'll be in
good shape
hi Casey thanks so much Jeremy or do you
think the Rivini
benefits of programming language
resource files not based in plain text
yes I do but which are still edited in a
textual way my thought is that they
would be in a binary format optimized
for fast compile times with possibility
of embedding images and other media
files documentation is I'm more
intelligent factoring in mind the search
and replace you think that such a
language could be blah blah blah I can't
see the rest of it because it got cut
off anyway
yes to all of that I feel like we should
be moving in that direction I feel like
we should have moved in that direction a
long time ago I don't think visual
programming has to mean a disastrous
collection of crazy wiring like a seder
graph I think there's a lot of other
ways that visual programming can happen
and so I feel like you should 100%
explore that Avenue if it's something
that excites you because we we need it
and there's a hundred thousand things
you can think of that might work well
and the problem is no you're gonna have
to experiment right like the only way to
know is to experiment I already did one
right I did an experiment on that that
was the math inside comments thing right
that was an example of how do i all mint
this text file so that in addition to it
having the text that's in it I also want
you to parse a comment and if you see
something that looks like math perform
the operation right so a very simple
addition could save me a lot of time
it's nice and handy right do the same
thing for diagrams let me draw a diagram
in the comment remember it in the
comment and when you load it just parse
and show it those are some easy ways you
can get started without having to
reinvent the entire system and you know
see where it goes and you can take it
further and further and further right
and you know like you said go to a
binary file format at some point if
you've got a robust enough to latch in
that has dips and stuff the reason it's
hard to go to a binary file format right
away is because you lose all of your
standard programming tools you lose
merging tools diffing tools source code
control gets confused that sort of stuff
so sometimes it helps to start kind of
slowly when you when you want to do
incremental stuff like that when you
want to do
since Aaron when you want to do big
change like that sometimes it helps to
be more incremental pet the cat hello
Molly
how are you doing I'm sorry to wake you
Stream wanted to say hi that's good kid
okay I'll leave you alone now you're
getting good son
he's a holly rocket named after Molly or
the other way around the other way
around Anna actually named Molly Molly
after Molly rocket thanks to the
recommendation to try to make a single
head her video codec I've been having
fun thinking of all the different things
that I would want for a codec like ezel
multifarious to do encoding etc that
wouldn't have happened if I just
contributed to one of the big systems
awesome I hope you make something cool
like I said if it's a what if it's a
simple codec you can just include it
doesn't have to be that great right like
the ease of use of it would be so much
better than like mp4 or something that
you could just say ah
just throw it in there even if the files
are twice as big as mp4 and are don't
look as good or whatever you know who
know I think it would still be useful
because if if you're if you just need it
to work and you don't want to spend a
lot of effort on it then you're willing
to give some things up so it doesn't
have to be the world's grip greatest
video codec to still be useful right
because it can be optimized for just
simple keeping it simple and that's its
own that has its own value
are you worried your hop starts
customizations are plucking too hard
well I guess what I would say is it's
worth remembering that all
government-sponsored recreational back
recreational activities are clean and
efficient and so while I am somewhat
worried about that I feel like that sort
of mitigate some of the concern all
right I'm gonna wrap it up and I
probably will do another stream but
we'll take a break for I don't know how
long we'll take a break but we'll take a
break for a little while
thanks for joining me for the four coat
of customization I'm gonna come back I
think I'm interested in what we're doing
here so I kind of want to keep going
down that route so thanks for joining me
and maybe we will come back and play
with this a little bit more a little
later on alright take it easy everybody