all right hello everyone welcome to
handmade Hiro I am back for a second
stream today we're not really doing
handmade Hiro what we're doing is
working on the editor code again I'm
kind of streaming today just because I
thought it would keep my mind off the
fact I'm not letting any food and in 74
minutes I will have to start drinking
gavel ight see now for those of you who
don't know what gavel it--see is it's
not a planet it's basically just like
the medical version of a colon cleanse
so this is what it is I have no idea
what polyethylene glycol actually does
however the end effect of drinking a
bunch of gavel it--see over the course
of two hours is that you basically empty
out your entire colon which of course is
necessary for a colonoscopy
fun times from what I understand I've
never had a colonoscopy before this is
my first time from what I understand
apparently the act of drinking gavel
it--see in the amount that you have to
drink it which is a cup every 15 minutes
for two hours so basically eight ounces
every 15 minutes
apparently that activity is actually the
worst part people say that just having
to drink 8 ounces of this thing every 15
minutes is very unpleasant and I guess
it probably varies from person to person
the best they say the actual act of just
pooping continuously for a while after
it starts to work is apparently not that
bad they say the actual act of emptying
the colon like a colon cleanse is really
not that that bad it's it's not like
painful or annoying or anything like
that but the act of drinking the stuff
supposedly is so we're gonna find out
because
I'll actually stream it I'll go grab the
first two doses right eight ounces
mmm 15 minutes eight ounces I'll just
drink it
we'll see how bad it is and then you'll
know and off we go
so we still have 71 minutes of
programming to do before that kind of
excitement keeps in right so let's go
ahead and do it
and again remember I've had no food
today so I apologize if the programming
is a little slower than normal we're not
doing handmade here oh these are not for
posterity so I feel like it's okay
because we're just we're just doing for
a coder upgrades right and that's all so
where we left off was pretty cool we had
just implemented the first step of the f
pins which I was talking about before
it's just kind of a little experiment
I'm doing to see if I can't improve some
of the editor flow from like even the
old days like I said for coders pretty
much caught up with Emacs for me now in
any way that matters for the most part
and so I'm kind of looking at ways of
pushing it beyond what I had you know
because Emacs is certainly not all that
I could imagine in terms of editing so
what I did is I made it so that we could
have these sort of bins here and then
you know if I was in something like
handmade Ray and I did a search for
something we made it so that now those
bins remember what's going on so if I
have different searches I can like
ping-pong back and forth between them
and then kind of like jump around right
and that's really awesome because that
allows me to operate on sort of multiple
levels at once if I'm trying to do a
search and I'm trying to do a compile
and I want to jump around between
locations on the search and error
messages all that stuff will just work
now right because when I go to compile
it'll compile here and so I can keep
those things in bins and just switch
back and forth between them which is
great however in order to get the bins
to a place where I feel like they're
really effective and interesting there's
a bunch of things that we're
I have to do and so we need to start
kind of working towards that now we've
got the basic idea working and we need
to sort of expand it and so there's two
things I want to do first let's just fix
the drawing a little bit so it works I
don't know how I'm really gonna get for
coder to understand that it should
scroll one extra line and eventually
probably more than one extra line up to
support these mixed bins so to a certain
extent we kind of have a little bit of
an issue there and I again don't really
know how I'm going to address it we're
gonna try to figure out some way to
address it but I don't guarantee that we
necessarily can we may have to edit the
core for that but we'll certainly try
not to touch the core if we can avoid it
you know don't touch the core the other
thing that I would have preferred and I
don't know if this is possible but I
probably would say that we can implement
our own buffer switcher now that just
wouldn't list f bar buffers so we
probably want to do that eventually too
because I really don't want these fyr
buffers in here
you're never meant to switch to them in
this way if we were going to support
switching to an f bar buffer what I
would do is just have it so that you
pick the active f bar buffer here and
then just have a command that's like
switch to that would bring it up into
your main window so we'd probably also
like to eliminate f bar buffer listing I
think that's probably possible now
because since we can list buffers
ourselves using our own jump Lister it's
probably possible for us to do that
maybe we should just tackle that right
off the bat since I think that we can so
let me go ahead and jump back to our
actual stable for coder here that we're
actually using for editing so if you
look at how we're pulling up that jump
Lister in the first place that's doing
the listing for buffers that's assigned
right now when I when I do my switching
to modal B so basically if you have the
modal switch on it hit B and that's
going to interactive switch buffer now
interactive switch buffer is not
something that I implemented it's it's
actually let's see here
it's actually defined in for coder lists
and you can see what it does here is it
it's actually calling this begin
integrated Lister buffer list and that's
that's what's doing the actual work now
if I go ahead and clip that out because
I think I'm gonna maybe try to override
it we'll see if I can or if I can't we
know that that's what's normally
happening in here and so let's go in and
take a look at begin integrated Lister
buffer list it's a year there we go
so in here where we're looking at this
you can kind of see it's got kind of
another yet another line of sort of
another peel of the onion there where
I'm going to say alright let's begin the
the list that actually calls out to this
which gets these handlers here that are
going to be used for the buffer Lister
and it's called it calls into a generic
function at that point
this handlers dot refresh which is
generate all buffers list that really
looks like the money right there that
looks like what we're actually looking
for so if I come up here and take a look
at what this does you can see this thing
doing it's doing its thing here right
and inside here you can see that when it
when it loops over things it's just got
a certain way that it does does stuff
here's the part where it does the buffer
is starting with star bit there right so
first it adds all the ones that don't
have a star and then it adds the ones
that do have a star for our purposes
right we're probably going to start to
be a lot more like focused about how
we're dealing with buffers so I don't
really know that we're gonna have
buffers that have a star anymore that
concept may go away and we may just have
F bin buffers and non F bin buffers and
so what we really need to do here is we
really just need this part I think and
this part down here
just wouldn't be necessary I don't think
now the buffers that are opening views
part I guess what this is doing is it's
saying look for each of these things
here we're making a list of buffers that
are currently being viewed so we can
skip them when we build the list so that
they show up kind of at the end right
because you don't want to if you're
switching buffers you're not gonna
switch to a buffer you can already see
so we don't really need that and that's
why that's happening and then it's
getting appended kind of at the end
right
so really it's that buffer starting with
star part this is the part that we would
need to fix and I kind of wonder if
maybe this itself shouldn't kind of take
that as a kind of parameter now it can't
really take it as a parameter directly
because it's a list or call back and
this is the refresh right of that Lister
that says you know generate all the
buffers so we'd need to be parameter of
the actual Lister's the user data here
that you can see is being passed through
and it's being passed through as a zero
so there is no user data currently being
provided to this particular refresh
handler so it would have been free to
have there be some user data that had
parameters that discussed and generated
all buffers how these things were to be
filtered and so my first inclination is
really maybe this generate all buffers
list should be looking at the list or
user data and maybe it should be using
that to determine what it should be
doing in here
but to be fair I don't actually know to
what extent that actually needs to
happen for us because if we chose to
only eliminate F bin buffers that means
we would be specifically scanning for
start F bin not just our buffers and
we'd still list the other star buffers
so I'm a little bit torn as to whether
this really does what we need to do or
whether it doesn't I don't really know I
think I'm going to take the safe course
now because it seems like maybe
something that we're going to want to do
a little bit more
cific work on so I'm gonna go ahead and
pull that out in here and call this KC
generate buffers list and then what
we're gonna do is we're just gonna take
a look and see what this is doing and
simplify it down to just the things that
I actually want to have happen now you
can see the first Allen's doing here is
preparing some space I guess I don't
really understand why he does memory the
way that he does it in this it's not the
way I would have chosen to do it I would
just had a global arena here and you
just kind of push things on as you go he
does a little bit of a pre pass it looks
like he really wants to know how much
memory is gonna be used beforehand this
piece of code happens to be shareable in
either case because this is the maximum
amount of memory that you would need to
use for buffer names and so I'm gonna go
ahead and propose here that really that
should be pulled out into a separate
function which is essentially like get
max buffered name storage right and that
here would be providing back to you just
this operation right here and I don't
know if buffer count still needs to be
done here I assume that it does it
doesn't so I guess that actually that's
kind of I guess it's not the surprising
so this piece of code right here I'm
gonna argue should really be pulled out
as a separate thing which is going to
return that memory size to you so you
would just pass it one of these right
and this would get back that max buffer
name storage for you now one of the
other things that it's doing here is
adding in the buffer count times the
size of the list or node part we don't
really want that part so I'm gonna claim
that that part is sort of the same in
either case right so that's gonna happen
outside here as well right or something
like this in fact I guess I'll do it in
this code down here and then we'll deal
with it after so if we do get back to
max buffer name storage that we'll just
take a look at all of the buffers here
and add them together so it's really
just this
and then this part I guess maybe we'll
say is retained right so we'll do this
is I guess what I'm saying we'll add to
it get max but for names the original
pass the app there and so this is
actually the preamble that allows to do
that now we don't actually need this
because the get buffer count is never
used again so if we want to we can
actually just say that can be placed
here and then similarly the memory size
itself is really now just a two-term
thing so why not just make that be
something that looks like this and off
we go so you can see it happen
here I don't know what the plus three is
I that's some magic that Allen must know
does anyone have any idea what the plus
three is yeah I got I got nothing
because we're only adding as many
buffers as there actually are I would
assume
and so I don't know what the plus three
is someone should probably explain that
to me at some point but anyway so again
I'm just trying to do some compression
oriented programming here and say look I
know what needs to happen here
I have Allen's code I don't necessarily
know exactly why he's doing everything
but I can see what he's doing and so I'm
just gonna preserve what he's doing but
pull it out into some functions that
make it easy for me to reuse just that
part so when I replace the part that he
wrote with something that I wrote that
does something a little bit differently
we're still calling the same shared code
here and then I can send this back and
say hey do you want to mainline these
changes and hopefully he says yes and he
says no we just pull them out into our
own code and live with it so either way
it's really not a big deal
but especially when I see mystery
constants like this plus three showing
up in here I don't know if that's
actually valid or if that should be in
there what's going on I have literally
no idea what's happening there but since
that is happening there
like hey we want the Lister node plus
three bytes I mean I have literally no
idea what that could be for and since I
have no idea what that could be for it
makes me want to make sure that's pulled
out because in case that's something
that's actually really important I need
to make sure that everyone who's gonna
be doing weird stuff here knows about
that and calls it right so it's just one
of those things that's like kind of
mildly terrifying and if you have
something mildly terrifying you want to
make sure that everyone is doing the
mildly terrifying thing the same way
that's usually the way I look at it
right um so we're gonna do get max
lister buffer storage there we're past
that in that's the new memory size part
there so there we go we've got the new
item set thing here and we've got this
sort of code that Alan was doing here
and so what we need now is we just need
a way to that you can see here he's
building like I said an array of what
buffers are being viewed I don't know if
that's actually necessary because I is
it really that hard like the views
themselves or er that thing so it seems
like you could do that just by asking
what views are viewing the buffer so I'm
not really sure that that's necessary
but again I don't really have touched
this code so I'm gonna say what if we
just did that and that and then out in
here again this stuff is stuff we kind
of need to pull back up into this part
of the code here as we kind of work it
in to something smoother when I generate
this buffer list I'm gonna see if
there's a way to do this a little bit
more direct way
so looping over the views that are
available or that are visible at the
moment feels like it shouldn't be too
hard to do there's only two views that
exist in my for coder world so to some
extent it shouldn't be very difficult
for me to find out what those actually
are and so if you look here
this is the code that actually does that
and so if I am just going to look at
views that are that are not the F in bar
I don't know why I would need to build a
separate array that doesn't really seem
necessary unless that get view next call
is really expensive and we'll see if it
is so I'm gonna go ahead and open the
next tonic water here it's important to
remain hydrated kids alright so I'm
gonna see if that's really necessary
let's take a look like what does get
view first actually do I mean I guess
the problem I guess the problem is this
the problem is this fill view summary
right because we don't really want that
like what we want this is the whole
entirety of the code we want we just
want this panel because all we need is
the buffer ID that comes from that panel
view and presumably the panel view
itself would do it so really you know I
might say that this is probably one of
those things where the API gets in its
own way a little bit these view
summaries are like really overblown for
what we need but a lot of things just
have to go through them so I can
understand why this is happening the way
that it's happening it's not but it's
really not what we would want because it
feels like you really shouldn't need it
you know I mean but we'll keep it for
now so this is all the same stuff I
don't know why this skip thing is
happening so basically like you're
coming in here and we're saying if it's
already there we skip out but why
wouldn't you just do the opposite thing
so again I'm looping through all of the
views here right so I say here's the
buffer that I'm looking at it wants to
do it's sort of doing the little N
squared let me not insert something that
I haven't already inserted right
as we assume that we want this to go
faster and we don't care if this is
slower right we're sort of making a
decision between those two and so when I
loop over those here and I look at this
thing this tells me whether or not I
need to insert it or not right and so my
first thought is like can we just not
care about that because I know I only
ever have three views so I feel like
this is probably just better because
most of the time it would be fine right
and so I think I'd probably just leave
it at that and not really care at the
moment right that seems just more
concise for me and I know I don't care
then when we go down here and we loop
over these buffers we're saying do any
of them exist in this thing
now why don't you think about this you
know if we just had some way of tagging
buffers here's a question for you so
let's say we look at this buffer summary
what's in there
so if you were to look at this stuff
you know I would almost say that because
this is a fairly important thing it
feels like you should be able to say for
a buffer
give me the view that has this buffer
like you know I just feel like there
should be a way to quickly get from a
buffer to a view of the buffer if there
is one right like that's something that
I would just track
[Music]
oh no care about the gem plasterer
jumping let's see sorry get few yeah it
doesn't really seem to have that
[Music]
so there really is no way to get from a
view from a buffer to the view but I do
feel like that should be a thing like it
seems like that would be better than
doing it this way and it's the kind of
thing that people generally need to know
you know what I mean so I don't know
[Music]
so in here yeah we can do our filtering
we're gonna probably do exactly this
filtering and I think we're just going
to get rid of this and then the buffers
that are opening views part will just be
the same as it was before so you know
get those buffers so I guess the problem
here is so so this is why we would need
since we're using this right here this
is why we need to dedupe these so I
guess we can't really get away from D
duping them oh well I don't know that I
want to do this skipping around part of
that so I might just say that we do the
same thing we were doing here where we
do like you know this sort of thing grab
the view buffer ID if they're equivalent
and then we break out and there's a
couple different ways that I can
structure this probably if I want to
write I can probably just do this
and then I can just say look that's what
we're doing right so basically like grab
me the view buffer ID let's go through
all the ones we have so far and you know
if this thing matches the buffer ID that
we've got up here then don't store it
you know oh I want the opposite of that
so yeah and because this code is gonna
be the same pretty much every time I
kind of feel like maybe I'll just pull
it out here as well so actually am I on
the right place here I'm not I was
accidentally modifying Alan's actual
code which is not what I wanted to do
it's a problem with doing the branching
sorry about that
put that back all right so I'm gonna go
ahead and restore this code to what it
was before before I started mucking with
it all right so we this will remain the
same this happens we come down here and
we'll just take a look at this I think
if there's any other way to make that
easier I guess I could say actually
[Music]
probably just something like this right
where I just say look give me the count
and give me the array and then we'll
just do this one time that just seems a
little bit better to me because then we
don't have to keep doing it over and
over again so in here we'll just say
look here's here's the test IDE we will
do it as a for loop here and we'll loop
over
however meaning you told us there were
like so and then we'll just have a
result and in here if we ever find that
we see the one that we were looking for
we'll set the result to true and then
when we return we can we can use this
idea exists in now - kind of like
simplify all this code so basically we
can just say look if the ID doesn't
exist in our currently viewed buffer
count buffer is currently being viewed
view buffer ID right so if that's the
case then add it and that's nice
and then down here we can just do the
opposite so now we can say look if the
ID doesn't exist in this thing and some
other crap happens to be true like so on
so you can kind of see it all there
right you can get rid of the skips they
don't have to be there and then we're
just looking at the buffer buffer ID
like so and so that way this part here
where we're passing these guys down it's
a little verbose because you know see
doesn't have much support for like
closure style discussion of things but
that's fine so we could just say look if
this thing doesn't exist and these two
things are true off we go
and then finally at the end I think we
would say the same thing right
I don't know why this wasn't doing this
before that's a little confusing I feel
like you still want to check that
because I don't want to ever list those
even if they were being viewed in a view
I just don't want them so I think that's
actually not how that was supposed to go
I don't know maybe that's a bug in the
original or maybe that was intentional
not 100% sure but anyway now I think
that's more what we were looking at KCC
generate buffers list is now going to be
more of a command signified guess know
why I did this because I guess and I
think about it this kind of has to
happen like this
so I don't know why I merged those two
just wasn't thinking guess that haven't
eaten today so not great so do you mean
custom commands say now will Duke this
is interactive switch buffer this will
just be KC Interactive switch buffer and
so here we can do the same sort of stuff
we were doing before where we're gonna
do most of the other stuff and the
activates whichever part should probably
still be the same excuse me
the only difference here is that this
part here will is this code so we just
need to let kind of paste this down into
here where it belongs and eliminate this
part so there's the handlers getting
constructed here's like the user data
and target view nonsense right like this
stuff here that can just go away now and
now we have I think what we actually
need by default this will still call
Allen's Lister I'm gonna try that one
first just to make sure that it's that I
didn't totally destroy the world's but
then we'll keep going from there so
don't ask me why that's still in there
it's not supposed to be that's supposed
to look like that and then we have to
actually return this course
so there we go okay that's good and I
want to test that doing the same jump as
before so if I come in here and hit B
right I should get totally wrong stuff
right like this is not what I want
listed but it should be exactly the same
as it was before I made these changes
and it does look like that's the same
sort of it does seem a little wonky I
don't know maybe not
anyway so I'm not sure if that's exactly
right I think it is
but anyway so if I now say that generate
all buffers list is like KC generate
buffers list instead so that basically
instead of calling this thing I'm
calling my version of that thing I'm
assuming that now I will have it so
that's not listing those buffers anymore
we don't have to worry about like
polluting that list with tons of f bar
nonsense right well that worked
phenomenally parentheses did not work at
all I don't know what I did wrong there
so KC generate buffers list Oh duh we
weren't calling it that was not a fair
test before oops let's try it again
so let's switch to handmade hero I'll
switch buffers and we should see none we
should just see code and we do so that's
good
yeah that's what I want similarly when I
first start up and I switch I should see
nothing just should be an empty buffer
list and it is okay so we've got that
out of the way now what we need to do is
in that bar at the bottom there we need
to start making that bar actually you
know be some things that's we something
that we can use legitimately and it's
not gonna have like I have like trouble
seeing it and all that other sorts of
stuff so a couple things about that that
we need to address so first of all this
stuff this isn't working quite right and
the reason for that part is I kind of
want it to I wanted to go have a fixed
number of lines that would be visible
and it doesn't quite do that quite it
doesn't do that necessary correctly and
also then when you switch to this
version I want it to just be more
percentage based so it maybe takes two
thirds of the screen when you do this so
it's like four lines or two thirds of
the screen right and maybe it's not four
lines maybe it's actually five lines
will kind of see where we get to on that
so I'm not sure but you know four or
five lines probably five and so we need
to fix that
toggle as well now the way that toggle
is working is there's a function called
like set HUD line count and you call it
with the number of lines that you want
the HUD to have the problem with that is
we want to set this in two different
ways
so when we call set flood line count and
you can see if I do this where that's
being
so you can see it happening here and
here so what I want to be able to do
there is I want to be able to pass
something to this that will indicate
what it should do in both cases both the
case where I want to said to a number of
lines and the case where I want to sit
to a percentage my feeling on that so if
I look at global hood line count I'm
probably just gonna cheese out and say
something like notes if default hull
account is negative it's interpreted as
a let's say over 64 because we're being
maximally cheesy right so what I'm
seeing curious look let's get default
hood line count to be something that we
can set it to a negative and then it'll
still do a percentage so that way we can
do defaults expanded hood line count I
can say if I do want to do something
like 3/4 of the display or 1/2 of this
way let's call it half for now and I can
even make that be a thing right so if we
now go to set HUD line counts and we
change how that like
since we're not using my cool search
fins I've got to do this again
so in here we'll just say look if if
it's equal to that will pass the
expanded hood line count and that way we
don't really have to worry about it
so I think that would be okay and then
in here when we do this thing we'll say
all right assign it
you're out what's going on here and what
we'll say is what's the what's the count
set to in the case where the count is
greater than zero we'll set it this way
in the case where the count is less than
zero then we'll set it as a regular
proportion so we'll do count over and
this will be an f32
and this will be an f32 of default HUD
lime divisor right so I think that's all
I would really need to do and then now
it should be able to set it to a fixed
halfway mark no matter what your screen
resolution is which is the important
part because we you know I have
different screens of different
resolutions I run for code or on so I
can't just hard code the number of lines
here needs to be aware so now if I set
do the insert okay that was completely
useless
it just isn't working at all so that's
great we totally crushed it good job so
what's going on there when I do view set
split proportion oh yeah if it's
negative we got to account for the
negative
there we go and so now no matter what
the size of the window is right they
should both work so when it's this way
it should be about four lines and when
it's this way it should be about half no
matter what the circumstance is and
again that's a little bit tricky right
you see but you see why it used to be
that way
this needs four lines to display the the
F Bend the way I have imagined I want it
and this is just trying to show more of
what's in the F bin and so it's just
arbitrarily I want to be able to say
look use this percentage of the screen I
don't care how many lines that is per se
because I don't know how big your screen
is it just needs to be roughly that
amount right roughly that proportion of
this visual area but so that's all good
and everyone's happy and that's fine
right so let's go ahead and and push on
to the next thing uh so what I want to
do now is take a look at the way those F
bins are working and start to try and
move some of the commands into them a
little bit more properly right and so
what I want to do is I want to think
about all the things that I currently
have that are commands that could be
pushed through the F bar instead of
being pushed through the regular for
coder pathway that I have in there right
now
and start to create a structure for
storing those things right and so the
easiest way for me to do that is just to
kind of look down at the Moodle setup
that I've got here and just think about
what is actually gonna be you know
relevance so looking at the F bin H file
or the F bar H file I'm just gonna kind
of do something here like f bar commands
and then I'm just going to list the ones
that I see they're relevant so looking
at them right like set mark go to next
jump no skips KC clean and save change
active panel these are just not
that need additional explication so
they're just not appropriate for what's
going on here extended command
maybe but again those are supposedly
things that don't happen very frequently
so I think we should leave them off for
now if I just buffer find corresponding
file killed the end of lines just these
are not super important things at the
moment anyway so then looking down a
little bit further go to line doesn't
leave before people jump to index and
jump to definition those two things are
basically I would I would probably
categorize them under the operation of
jumping right so you know we have this
idea of jumping to a particular keyword
there and so those are both things that
that are probably going to be relevant
right those are going to be relevant
relevant commands and so I'm just going
to call that f bar jump for now so
that's just like saying I went somewhere
list all locations is probably also
thing so that's we're gonna have that be
a separate thing so there's a jump and
then there's also a list of locations
then we've got list all substring so
guess who says save things save and make
without asking so that's an F bar build
which is another thing we want to be
able to do we've got let's see query
replace and replace in range
those are both definitely ops so there's
like replace and there's also like
search I guess search forward and search
backward are probably different I'm not
100% sure about that let's say they're
not for now let's be Squinkie about that
undo doesn't matter switch buffer not so
much cut and paste is
kind of a whole other ball of wax let's
think about that in a second a little
bit later Interactive open redo yeah we
don't care about any of that stuff at
all moving around it's like a separate
ball wax so I think these are really the
ops that we're talking about here we
want to be able to jump to something
list all of the some things we have
builds commands replace and search
guess if I had to be honest I'm not sure
that replacement search need to be two
different things
it's possible that they should be but I
don't actually know it seems like
replace is just a superset because you
can just have like do the operation or
do the OP like the searching you let go
backwards or forwards and then there's a
thing for like replacing the thing that
you're on they kind of seem the same III
think I'm gonna like call that one thing
for now and and we'll just see what
happens
so we've got those four what I haven't
really quite thought through is what
actually happens with cut and paste I
think I do want cut and paste in there
and the question is just that's not
really a command so I guess we're just
gonna call that like f bar insert so
like if you cut something out it will go
into an F bin and then hitting the
insert button or hit that F bin will be
called an insert F bin and if you hit
that button it would paste what you had
right back into the buffer wherever you
are I don't really know to be completely
honest with you I don't really know how
we should be working with these buffers
like if you did a bunch of cut and
pastes right so I keep like I cut things
out maybe I just want to append them to
the current F bin you know what I mean
and so
I feel like that's a difficult design
decision and I think we're probably just
gonna have to play with it to see which
way I would want to go because the
problem with it is that cut and paste is
like a very frequently used operation
and if you've got these F pins and
you're trying to work with them then the
last thing you want is every time that
you do any kind of cut and paste
operation at all it mucks with your F
pin set up right and so it seems to me
like you kind of want that to be like a
sideband thing and so at any time you
can always rotate what's in an F been
using you're like using that cut and
paste history to just pull things into
or out of the F pin in question right
and so I think what we really want there
is to say say maybe that's not a thing
and maybe the f bar has like an
additional concept here which is just
like every time we do cut and paste we
have the cut and paste history that was
already a thing in for coder anyway I
think and so maybe you can just use
these F pins it's like append buffers if
you want and we'll just kind of have
that be like a special case of of what's
going on so one of the commands that you
always have is like insert the crap from
the current F pin into the end of the
buffer as a paste operation right
and I just I assume and I guess I don't
know but I assume that you don't want
that to be something that interacts
directly with F pins ever so you don't
want to just assume that the active F
pin whatever it is is the thing that's
getting all of your like like all of
your cuts and pastes but again I really
just don't know and I feel like if you
have the concept that there's an active
F pin and a target F pin so that
basically all of your operations that
you're doing go to the target F pin but
the active F pins like add everything it
gets too confusing like you need to keep
it simple enough that it's usable and
your brain isn't like spending more time
for how to use the stupid thing then
it's saving by having the additional
features so again it's just it's really
just hard to conceptualize
you know I mean it's really hard to
conceptualize and maybe the answer is no
you really just want you really you
really just want that to work I don't
know I'm really at a loss my brain is
not able to like hypothesize and it's
maybe again because I haven't had any
food all day I'm not really able to
conceptualize what the usage of this
will feel like in practice and so I
can't really do a very good job
pre-filtering you know and so I'm gonna
just have to experiment with it and see
what happens what I will say is we
probably want the ability to save more
commands than there are F bins
maybe so we probably want something like
[Music]
f bar command to be a thing and this is
f bar command type right and the F R
command type is here and then there's
like the pram to it that we've got so
like search or in place would have liked
to and you know jump would only maybe
have one and so on so yeah like
if we imagine that that's the case I
could say that every one of these things
has the command that's currently in that
F pen but then there's also like some
giant like circularbuffer of f bar
commands or some crap like this that is
just you know the F in history count and
there's just you know some ridiculously
huge number of these things sitting
around for me to like pull you know kind
of pull back you know you could do
something like that now the problem with
that is that the strings themselves have
to be memory managed to a certain extent
right especially when those things get
really large and so you know I almost
want to say maybe we could do this in a
slightly different fashion and say
rather than try to manage the things
that way what if we just assumed that
the history was just a giant buffer that
you save so if I were to say something
like this
so using Alan's model of saying there's
a start in an end position inside the
buffer and we can query for what that is
then in an fr command maybe what we
actually store is just that and then we
just have an infinitely long buffer
that's the history now there's a problem
with that and I use the term probably
sleee the problem with that is that
history buffer will eventually be
infinitely long just absolutely huge
right and you know you could imagine
wanting to remove stuff from the
beginning of the history buffer and if
you start to remove things from the
beginning of the history buffer you have
a cascading update problem where all of
a sudden all of your start and end
positions are like wrong and so I don't
really know to what extent we want to
think about or deal with that but it's a
real problem and we can't even really
rely on memory to save us because for
some reason and I'm not sure what the
reason is Allen doesn't allow 64-bit
buffers so you can't have just an
infinitely large buffer it won't work we
would hit the 2 gigabyte limit
eventually and all bets would be off
right
and that's a real bummer because other
than that one problem it'd be really
nice because it means your history would
get saved
oh man
I mean my first inclination is did you
say screw it let's do that and then the
other thing that we can do is just say
look if we use an offset because if we
wanted this thing to save and load
properly we would have to have a way of
saving what the actual indices into that
buffer were because I don't want to get
into the business of escaping them like
having escaped strings and stuff so if
we were going to save that information
in addition to the data there then we
would also have to have those integers
like for the params and stuff those
would have to be stored if we were going
to store those
then I guess there's no cost in just
storing them and storing an offset as
well and then every time you want to
remove stuff from the beginning you just
do so in other words you do this and
then you have like history first history
buffer start and so anytime you want to
pull something off the beginning you
just Inc history history of ever start
however far you wanted to go and then
the fact that all of these guys are
happened to be a you know all of these
things happen to be indices into later
in the stream is fine like it doesn't
matter that that happens right um
and so we could just do that I don't
know how good of an idea that is but you
know if you imagine something like this
we've got an f bar command here and then
you said like this was the history
buffer and that I had the f bar command
which is the history I mean I guess that
just works and you just do like and it's
just a rolling it's just a rolling index
into the thing
I this could be a really dumb idea
I am totally willing to believe that
this is like really stupid so I'm just
kind of thinking out loud and saying you
know maybe that's how it goes
once you have that history then it seems
to me like you can just make a jump
Lister that's called like load command
and it just shows you your last 4096
commands that you did and then you just
load one into the F bin that you're
currently on and that's a way to just
kind of necro old commands right back
into service right look I haven't eaten
all day I don't know what's going on so
I feel like let's just go for it I mean
what's the worst that can happen um so
let's just see that's what's gonna
happen and then these F bark commands
are basically you know some kind of you
know there's some kind of nonsense like
this and each one of the f bar things
also has a buffer backing it if it's in
the F bin so but that's not something
that we will actually keep in there
normally right and so we don't save the
whole like search results or anything we
just save the command to do the search
into the history so it doesn't get like
unreasonably large really quickly so I
feel like that would probably be okay
again the only real question here is
what to do about the cut and paste and I
don't know that part's pretty tough for
me to think through I I just don't have
an idea of where that goes
yeah look I just I just don't have a
clear thought in my head for like where
that goes for how that's happening
currently lake for paste so we're
calling Casey paste and tab right now
oops and so this function here which is
the paste function I'm not sure I'm not
sure exactly what it does so if you look
at it yeah like there is this notion of
a clipboard index and this is pretty
good right like what this does here is
it just lets you like rotate the pace
that you just did to like a previous
based right and so maybe I don't really
need to worry about paste that much and
it can just be you can just use what
Allen's already did I don't actually
know how well that works so let's just
try it so we've got Casey paste and tab
and I'm gonna shove this pace next thing
in there on e because I don't have
anything bound to e at the moment so we
can just do that and see what it does
and then we'll kind of go from there you
64 it looks like I didn't define yet
I'll make one of those cuz I'm gonna
need that probably for a bunch of stuff
so if I go ahead and do a un 6040 and
make that a u 64 then I can keep on
keeping on
if I run this and launch the thing let's
see how that actually works in practice
so if I switch projects to handmade ray
or something if I come in here and cut
that and then cut this sorry copy and
that cut and then I do like F so that's
pretty good already I just didn't have
anything bound to that because I don't
think that existed when I first did it I
think Allen added that so me me that's
just good enough and maybe we don't
really need to think too hard about cut
and paste so maybe really mostly what I
need is to just think about how can i
display those down here so that it's a
little bit more clear what they are
right so if we look at how these F bins
are set up you know you could imagine
having like some extra room on the side
for status that just shows what the
paste what the current paste setup is
you know what I mean and there's a
couple other things that I would want
that for anyway like I would want to
know what the alt tab would have been
I've wanted that for a while so that as
I'm typing it just shows me what my alt
tab would be if I hit it at any given
time so I have to guess so some things
like that that show what that is would
be nice these would be getting kind of
small at that point I don't know how
much that actually matters to be
completely honest with you but I also
don't know how many F pins I need in
practice maybe that we don't really need
12 F pins anyway like maybe 10 F pins is
fine right
so let's see what we can do with that
we'll just start slow and by the way
we're getting close right 8 minutes 50
seconds so let's see what we can do with
with how Alan's got this paste next
things set up so like the way he's got
this now is he's got this paste index
thing with the clipboard a next stuff
I'm assuming mmm so I guess I don't know
if I can just access what those things
are like
and also this is what I actually need
isn't it that's actually just the same
thing
so Casey paste and tab doesn't need to
be here anymore either
so that's cool like that took away some
of the custom stuff and it's just in for
code of proper now
so I guess what I would say is the part
that I mainly don't know right I just
I'm not quite sure I don't super
understand how I would get these so it
seems like clipboard index maybe is just
a thing that says when you do oh well
actually maybe that's actually getting
that thing I don't know let's go look at
clipboard index so is that a how is that
defined cuz it's in here here it is
so yeah it looks like that just gets us
what we want so if I just call clipboard
index repeatedly and I guess I don't
actually know how many of those there
actually are but that's probably also
explained in here because the paste
index keeps getting incremented
continuously I don't see anywhere that
it wraps that yeah so I don't really
know what I'm doing but that's okay
so let's just try this and see what what
happens so if I go into the rendering
code and I just like but stop the first
part of this buffer with my own
rendering that shows what's what's in
there let's just see what happens so in
here we'll look if we're in the global
HUD view and we do our little rectangle
dance again all this code is something
that we're gonna have to improve
substantially and that's fine but right
now we want to get everything working so
what I want to do is I do want to be
able to get this this custom variable
managed variable thing working because I
need to be able to know like where we
are in that ring so ideally I would have
something like this which is like here's
what the previous you know paste index
was just so I can get that and then I
also have this which allows me to get
like individual paste index stuff as we
go now this tells me how big it is I
think and then I need to like have some
room to grab it I guess but I don't
actually want to do that anyway because
I can only print
in this little summary view a few
characters of it anyway
so I can only really give the user like
a hint about how I about like what it is
and then I can also say how big it is I
guess I could add that as part of what
I'm printing out perhaps but you know so
let's go ahead and do a four I loop here
and let's loop over a bunch of these and
see what happens so if I say you know
board index and I just say give me I
don't know we're gonna show 16 of these
who cares so I just go over each of
these in turn and I say give me this
particular one this will tell me how big
it is and then I can also say look give
me the first 16 characters of it and I
knew that I can't tell you any more than
that then clipboard then when we do this
here what's the 0 4 by the way is that
clipboard ID so maybe there's multiple
clipboards oh ok it should always be
zero it's probably four if there's
multiple clipboards yeah all right so
we're just gonna say look go through
each of these let's find out what the
length is that's good then let's also
just get the thing right and then when
we come out of here we should have the
ability to print this thing right so I
can make a string here which is the like
this board equals make string of when
temp and now I've got that why Ellen
doesn't return strings I'll never know
he seemed really reticent to do so but I
think the string is a really useful
little thing he made here so I would
just always return them because that way
you don't have to do this all the time
anyway once I have one of those I'm just
gonna draw it
and we'll see what happens so there is
not going to deal with any of this I'm
just gonna put this at like zero zero I
guess and yeah that's it so I want to be
able to move this down each time so I'm
gonna make a wipe Ram here that I can
use for passing and so I'll start with
the wipe Ram being at the back region so
this is basically the border of the
thing I'm drawing into its gonna start
there and each time through I'll just
increment by however big one line is so
in Allen's parlance that's this thing
right and so what I can do is just this
will let me move the thing down one each
time and I'll put an X in there as well
which will just be for now the left
flush border I think that will give me
the ability to see everything in there I
think I don't actually know again you
know not my code I don't
I only know some basic stuff all right
so I don't know what scope is here to
what extent that is a thing it looks
like it's for the particular view
I don't really know so what I'm gonna do
there is say look let's get that for the
active view meaning not necessarily the
view we're drawing but let's get it for
whatever the active view is and and
we'll go from there because that's the
one we actually would care about I think
and then when we do this nonsense here
all right it's time hold on folks I will
be right back
you
hello hello there we go alright so let's
see what's gonna happen here this is 16
ounces of gavel ight see now I don't
actually know what gavel ight see is
however what I assume it is is some kind
of a preparation of water that prevents
all the water from being filtered out of
your colon too soon so that you
basically flush everything out because
I'm assuming if you just drank water it
would all get absorbed rather quickly
and end up in your bladder which is not
the thing you're trying to clear out
right I don't know not a doctor
maybe that has absolutely nothing to do
with it
we could go read about it if we cared
but we don't so again never done a
colonoscopy before have no idea how this
is going to be everyone says it's awful
I in the next half hour we'll have to
drink this whole thing I'm supposed to
drink 8 ounces every 15 minutes so right
now what we're gonna do is drink it from
the 16 ounce line down to the 8 ounce
line and then after another 15 minutes
I've set the timer again I will drink it
from the 8 ounce line down to the zero
ounce line and the stream will basically
be over once I have to go to the
bathroom and start because I'm assuming
that clearing out my colon will not be
pleasant and I won't want a stream
during it all right you ready for this
here we go and this is supposed to be
awful people say it's annoying that to
drink this much and it's disgusting or
something so I will tell you how it is
we'll see how it is
this is a weird flavor so I guess here's
what I'd say it's really not bad so I'm
assuming that well either I'm just not
particularly sensitive to it or it's
just cuz you have to drink so much of it
right by the time I get done with one
gallon of this crap well half a gallon
and then I guess I don't know it's split
into two sections
that's about right so what I would say
is I'm assuming that the problem is not
so much that's discussing because that
is not disgusting like of the stuff you
could have to drink for medical purposes
I guarantee you that is not one of the
worst
I'm sure there's stuff that tastes a lot
worse than that so I'm guessing that the
problem is just that after you know the
the fourth one of these you are pretty
unhappy with having to continue to drink
something that tastes like that because
it's certainly not delicious right so
anyway there that was it a happy
birthday colonoscopy so yeah we still
got how much time in left in the stream
you know maybe we can finish it maybe we
can't I think we still got a living in
an hour maybe I don't know I don't know
much time we got
but our timer thing probably would tell
us all right well feels weird to drink I
guess is the thing that I would say most
of us just feels odd having drank that
all right hopefully that's supposed to
happen if I if I suddenly like die on
stream someone please call the doctor
so anyway looking back at what we were
doing here a couple of things I don't
really know I don't know like where
we're supposed to get this stuff from
like the scope
I assume er let's get it from the manju
throat from the active view because what
we're trying to ask or what we're trying
to display is if I was gonna pay
something into the view I'm currently
working on what would get pasted right
so that seems like pretty
straightforward to me I would assume
okay so now we come back here we don't
really need to lend twice so I guess
what I would say is this part here that
actually gets it I'm going to do that
same trick so this length here is like
the
to a length like the total length of the
thing and then we got a string back and
the string is actually not the whole
thing
right because we are intentionally not
passing something that can actually hold
the whole thing because we're not gonna
actually do that right we're not gonna
we we don't actually need to capture the
entire thing because we don't have room
display it so I may want to know how big
it is because I may want to draw it in
that regard but other than that right
we're good so I'm gonna go ahead and say
let's do that I'm gonna call condense
white space which is a function I wrote
that basically takes a string and
removes all the white space from the
beginning the end and anywhere that
there was white space inside it
condensed it down to a single space
right and so I'm gonna try that and
we're gonna see what happens I don't
know why I did view.height this was
supposed to be wine height sorry but
again like you know not having eaten all
day
not a great not a great way to program
not a great state for your mind to be in
there's a reason that fasting monks are
not are not people who programmed most
of the things in the world it's because
you really need you want food so anyway
let's just go through here and and get
this basic part working and then we'll
see whether this worked at all what is
going on here
we have a let's see scope active view
active view IDE what's what is it
complaining about oh we already have the
active view is that true Wow awesome
so I already have the active view so I
really don't need to get it I can just
use the one that I've already got their
managed variable
alright so apparently the previous pace
index is not an in 32 so when this thing
was doing a managed variable get where
was that it was just in pace next right
so when it's doing oh I see we pass it a
thing to feed into I don't know why I
set it equal to something I guess I was
just being random so if I do previous
base lexical zero and then I get it
this has to be apparently a unit 64 that
seems fine I don't care what it is
and then the make string needs to get
Squinkie err so clipboard index is
supposed to return the length I think I
just have the order of these wrong
because yeah and the total length isn't
used that's correct
so let's get rid of that oops so in
theory that's gonna work I agree it's
not a great theory so let's see I don't
know why that says temp temp temp temp
temp temp temp did I do something stupid
I don't think so so that's just what the
clipboard is actually returning I guess
I don't know I wonder if that's a bug is
it supposed to be doing that like is it
supposed to have temp and the clipboard
the entire time I don't know let's go
ahead and see what happens if I start
using this now it's like cut and paste
that cut and paste that that's not
looking good if we're honest right I
don't know what's going on there so
we're not doing this right I don't know
what it is exactly that we're not doing
right but it's something
and so clipboard index let's go back and
look at how that's supposed to be used
so here's one question
maybe clipboard index can't handle it if
you don't pass something big enough to
fit like maybe it isn't qualified it
doesn't have the ability to truncate
maybe I don't really know but let me see
if I could find it so clipboard index
[Music]
yeah I guess I don't know let's look at
the implementation so here's where it
actually happens
interesting so it first says give me
back a pointer to an internal string
that is the one that we're talking about
right then it says if that was valid set
the size equal to that size
assuming they gave us a pointer make a
string make a string that is the you
know what I don't know what that does
make string cap off to look so it's
creating an out string that's out of the
district that's doing a copy between the
two strings so that must just be making
a string oh you know what that probably
stands for probably stands for make
string capacity and it probably says
look here's the buffer that we're using
here's the size it can accept and it
doesn't have anything in it yet then do
a copy right now the problem is it
doesn't tell us how much it actually
filled so we would have to actually do
that ourselves again this is why
returning a string would have been nice
right because we don't know how much it
actually filled so we have to actually
do the comparison ourselves to see if
the thing would have fit or if it
wouldn't have fit and that's just kind
of kind of annoying right
so in lis here we get the total length
we would know what that was coming out
of here in this case here we now need to
make a string out of the total length
this thing that it returns is not gonna
do it for us
right so instead and I guess now I think
about it we only need to call this once
as a result we can call it with the
actual truncated version and then get
the total length out this way remove
that so in here now we will have a total
length and what we
would want to do is say the well I guess
I can do that directly in here when I
make this string here's you know the
actual contents in theory and then I
need to say that the length is going to
be the total length if and only if it's
less than the array count of 10 right so
if it's less than the Iranian count of
temp then great use it if it's not oops
use the array count right I again don't
really think that's gonna fix my
problems though I mean maybe it will but
I think we've got more going wrong than
just that and yeah you could didn't you
do that kind of see that's still wrong
so what am i screwing up here folks if
the total length that comes back is less
than the array account use it otherwise
use your a count so shouldn't that I
mean that should be returning zero to me
right so the length of this thing should
be zero I think because this should be
zero and it should say if zero is less
than or a count use zero as the length
of the string
so maybe condense whitespace is broken I
don't know could be so we passed the
string to that thing
I mean I still think that should work I
don't have to step into this because
I'll be completely honest I have no idea
what's happening I don't know why we're
getting that garbage in there doesn't
seem right I probably have like a stupid
typo and it probably has something to do
with the fact that I haven't eaten today
which is not good not not where I want
to be with my life also we only have
actually you know what six five four
here we go all right so now we gotta do
this nastiness again so here is the
remaining eight ounces of gavel I see I
don't know how much of this I have to
drink total let's compute it real
quickly we can in fact even use the math
features that I added so we know that we
have two hours each hour contains what
you don't let me drink at first
each hour contains four 15-minute blocks
and we have two hours right so we know
that we've got eight total blocks of 15
minutes each one of those we have to
drink one eight ounce serving so that's
64 ounces of gavel 8c I don't know how
many Ounces are in a gallon oh why did I
do it over here I just do it over here
128 so basically what we're doing is
we're drinking a half gallon of gavel
it--see and we're drinking eight ounce
things every 15 minutes and I have a
gallon of gavel it--see and I think what
happens is tomorrow
I drink another gallon right medicine
could be worse that could be attaching
leashes to me anyway so getting back to
where we're going what we're trying to
get working here so something is not
going well for us right and I don't know
what it is because I feel like this
should be working okay and I'm not sure
where we're getting off track because I
feel like this total length call here
this should be doing what we needed to
do and it ain't so we got to figure out
why right we got to figure out why we're
getting that we got to figure out why
we're getting that that error in there
so let's go ahead and and and see what's
going down
maybe it's the condensed whitespace part
I don't know let's just try to step in
there and get a clue and what I'm gonna
do here is I'm gonna set a breakpoint on
condensed whitespace as a start and and
we'll see what happens so let's see in
fact it is that in fact exact call
that's why I picked it cuz I was like I
think the only place that'll
getting called at the moment is here so
what's happening unfortunately we're in
release mode which of course visual
studio is never able to really handle
but you know maybe we'll get lucky all
right so this board came back with a
total length it says nine and total n
here is what's in the buffer that seems
good to me
that's what we would want so I'm not
sure why we be getting an error in
drawstring for printing that
that's a work right step in there or are
we off by one here for some reason okay
we hadn't actually done nevermind that
was misleading we hadn't actually done
that yet so here we are actually
performing the call to condense
whitespace so it is possible that we
still screw this up great so let's go
ahead and do that we're copying a to
itself which seems safe so again that
looks just fine
yet color should be fine we're gonna hop
into drawstring and we're passing the
string down here is it still valid sure
seems like it
so when we actually step through the
code I don't know why we would be having
a problem with that so maybe we're
getting like an invalid font or
something or I don't know but like it
looks like we're passing a valid string
down it's just the drawing doesn't seem
to be working and you can see it reading
off as it goes I don't know I guess
maybe in translating fully process byte
is it possible that that is generating
something bad like we have the language
set up wrong or something or the font
pointers are garbage or
I mean that does look bogus there again
this is release mode build some that
100's certain it's actually has that
right but if it did it could because the
font is garbage
I don't know what to make a bat
maybe our font is not getting maybe our
font is not getting your 7o so so I
don't know like I was expecting to see
something else there I wasn't expecting
to see what I saw
so now I'm not sure where we're getting
that why we were getting that bug maybe
I ran the wrong version I know seemed
bad but let's see so here we go into
handmade here I'm gonna start cutting
and pasting things now so there we go
like now it's broken but only just now
oh so is it just when something's too
long it's just when something's too long
so it only seems to be happening if we
provide a buffer that is too small for
the copy that's coming in right so
that's very interesting so if I rebake
here that may give us some insight into
the problem
I'm gonna hop back here I'm gonna set a
breakpoint here and I'm gonna come in
and see what happens so if I say total
length its 27 that's what we expect
what's inside the temp buffer is nothing
so I'm gonna go ahead and say this is I
don't know if the word bug is
appropriate here because maybe this
isn't what's supposed to happen but it
does seem like when we jump into this
part of the code here this doesn't seem
to be copying in anything like it's
returning a science value that's
completely bogus in a sense like it's
telling us that it's this big and it's
returning that size value regardless how
much of copies in so we then have no
idea how much a copies and it doesn't
seem to copy as much as it could have
copied so what's happening inside that
copy function let's take a look but that
seems to be our problem so inside here
where we call copy how do I get how do I
get a look at that so I think that's a
string for quarter string oops and that
would be from a string to a string so
that's that's this one here so that
would call copy SS right copy checked SS
I guess
ah so yeah I mean that's gonna do it
unfortunately what I would rather it
have done there is clamped the size so
we could at least copy the rest of the
thing like is there a reason we can't
just do this
right
I mean copy as much as you can and I'll
let Alan suss that out he's probably
already got something that effectively
does that but you know basically what
we're talking about is just saying hey
copy size equals the destination size so
that's how much we're gonna copy in
right but if the copy size is or rather
I guess I want to say the other way this
is how much we would like to copy if we
would exceed this space that exists in
the buffer then we just set it to that
much so it just clamps it down right so
then we can just proceed as normal using
this copy size and then it'll just work
in all cases and if we would have
overflowed we only use like a
if it would have overflowed we just use
however much we could have used so the
return value in this case is just to
tell us whether we could or couldn't fit
the whole thing we can still retain that
behavior by basically saying look assume
that we succeed and in the case where we
have to clamp we fail right I guess
that's it so then what I would say is
hey man like give give me you know
give me the as much as you can out of
the clipboard buffer and and then we
don't have to worry about this so much
right so now I think I would probably be
able to get this going right now I hope
if I start to get larger things then fit
in the buffer it would just work so you
know if I cut that whole line all right
or not ker what did I do wrong there
is the copy size is greater than the
destination memory size the copy size
equals the destination memory size and
then befell our result the destination
string is what it is we copied that much
that all looks fine doesn't it
what's wrong with that oh I'll tell you
what's wrong with that we're not
building for coder I had commented that
out because we were only working on a
custom layer so that change wouldn't
take effect now it will have all right
so if I go ahead and run hopefully now
we can get into a better place yeah
perfect all right cool so now we've got
that satis update uh-oh we've only got
42 seconds left do we got drinking other
announces of this stuff let's turn back
off that compile because we don't really
need to be doing that most of the time I
got to go get more hold on a second
alright folks here we go
I got to be careful because I don't
drink this whole thing I just drink down
to the 8 ounce line
looks about right so how much have we
done so far so five three two six three
so yeah so we we have done by the time I
drink this one down which I will before
the end of stream by the time I drink
this one down we will have drank half of
the gavel 8c for tonight alright so
there we go
let's keep going on here so we've got
that listening working there pretty well
and so that seems fine to me and also I
wanted that auto tab thing to happen too
so let's take a look at where we get
that information from so inside my let's
see here first tab word complete so
let's look at the information when were
complete I have no idea what that does
so I guess what I would say about that
is that looks way too expensive
yeah alright so that might just be too
difficult I don't know
I mean I guess what I would say is I
think this certainly could be made to be
something that just works and we could
call on every character and it wouldn't
be a problem but I don't think I want to
tackle that so I guess we'll just we
won't have that feature that's fine so
yeah so the question then becomes I
guess what we want to know now is if I
you know have it in this view I guess I
want to leave a little bit of space for
that here and we'll just move everything
over in terms of the bins and we'll just
leave this as something separate right
like that can just be its own thing
so let me go ahead and switch over there
to the render and what we'll do is we'll
just say yeah before the bins happen
right here we'll go ahead and make that
work and one of the interesting things
about it is we couldn't just treat it as
initial bin because actually we were
kind of previously doing that like I
have been zero is intentionally not
displayed it's sort of like a phantom
bin
it's a favorite I wanted to have a null
bin potentially and so what I could do
is just say oh yeah like the thing is
going to be based on the number of bins
total and the bin goes this way I guess
and that way there'd be like one bin
just kind of like phantom sitting there
with nothing on it right and so like
this right here would be the cut and
paste
thing would go right there right and
then all the F bins happen after that
and so that way you could always see
what that was and if you zoom up you can
get more of them and we could make it so
that we just do a lot more than 16 as
well like it's got the whole
cut-and-paste history in there and then
oops that's not what I want to do so if
we actually did it that way where we
just kept going and in fact I could do
this a little bit differently so what I
could do is say look just keep going I
don't care how long you do it right just
keep going until the y-coordinate in
question passes outside of the view
right so as long as the Y is on this
side of the the of the visible area of
this sort of gutter window thing we're
making just keep going and that way
we'll just ask for as many as we
actually need to fill it rather than
saying 64 should be enough for anybody
or whatever just like look we'll do as
many as there as fit right and so if I
take a look here at ya at the plus plus
is you know what I think that I think
the the color is starting so I think
we're gonna have to call the stream we
almost made it to the next round of Java
light but not quite so I'm going to have
to go colon cleanse myself it will not
be pleasant folks but you know trust me
you're lucky you don't have to be a part
of it well and that was the end of the
stream - I guess we we timed that pretty
darn well if I do say so myself
we timed that pretty darn well well
let's verify it let's let's just close
this down and and let's verify that it
worked and then we'll say good night and
I'll talk to you after I've had someone
stick a camera
really up my butt that's like actually
what's about to happen okay so if I look
here let me see
did I recompile that I'm actually not
that resided here we go hello so a
reason that didn't build switch for
coder built oh yes there goes all right
so we're built and we ran there we go
perfect so we still got more to do maybe
we'll do some more after someone has
stuck a stuck a camera up my butt but
you know no promises I may just go
finish this stuff on my own I only
really wanted to stream it today because
I just figured it would keep my mind off
the fact that I hadn't had anything to
eat which you know I'm person who likes
to eat so that was not fun and continues
to not be fun but alright thank you so
much for joining me and I guess I will
if I don't stream anymore for our coder
streams this week then I will see you
this weekend for the return of handmade
hero which I'm looking forward to so see
you back here this weekend for that
check the handmade org slash watch page
for more info on that otherwise have fun
programming folks and I'll see you on
the Internet
take it easy everybody