okay hello everyone and welcome to a
little sort of mini tutorial on my setup
of new Emacs I want to just say
beforehand that this is not part of the
actual handmade here a stream and I am
NOT a a max advocate in any way I am NOT
trying to tell you to use Emacs I I
don't have a particular editor that I
think is great I know everyone has like
sort of this religious conviction that
the particular editor is great I have
never seen an editor that I thought was
particularly good I feel Emacs is
roughly the same as most editors it's
getting a little on in yours and it's a
bit too slow these days and a bit too
buggy but you know it's sub simply the
same as any other editor most of the
things you can do any max you can do in
other editors and most of the things you
know that it is you could do in Emacs if
you really wanted to and so on so forth
so I don't necessarily you know push
Emacs or anything like that
but I would say that you know I also if
you're going to use an editor it's not
necessarily a bad choice I don't know
that there is a good or bad choice but
what I did want to do is a lot of people
had written in and said they wanted to
try and use my eMac config and follow
along with the handmade hero stream the
way that I do it so what I'm going to do
is kind of just go over how my
configuration works and so that you can
understand what I'm doing when you see
it on the stream and if you want to use
Emacs yourself you certainly can now if
you are one of the people who have
pre-ordered handmade hero on the
handmade hero org site the source zips
all come with my Emacs config so
basically where's here there we go sorry
I've been I had to do a sync on the
witness so that's still running in the
background there okay so basically if I
go ahead and go into the handmade hero
directory so this is the place where you
would have your zip file if you follow
along at home with the source if you've
pre-ordered if you go into the misc
directory right there's a dot Emacs file
in there there's there's this guy I
don't know why there's like I should
probably get rid of it
de files or things that Emacs creates as
backups but I shut that off so I think
that only happens when there's a bug and
it can't load but point being in here
you can see that there's that dot Emacs
file and that dot Emacs file is
basically just my configuration it's all
written in list because Emacs runs on
sort of a variant of Lisp it's called
Emacs Lisp I don't actually know Lisp
hardly at all you know the only
interaction I've ever had with Lisp is
to customize going to Emacs so I really
don't know what is going on with Emacs
Lisp at all but what I do know is that
it is similar to lists but probably
different in a couple different ways
such that they call it Emacs Lisp and
not Lisp if you are a Lisp person you
probably will know the differences if
you're not you probably don't care but
there's probably a page somewhere that
summarizes them as well if you really
want to find out okay so if you want to
use this file you can actually look I've
also got an eMac stop back in here that
I use to run Emacs you can see it and
basically what you do is you pass minus
Q minus L and then the name of the file
the name of that Emacs file wherever the
path is that allows you to actually run
Emacs with my config you can also drop
it in what's called your home directory
which on Windows doesn't mean very much
I'm not sure where it defaults to but on
UNIX for example you all know what the
home directory is it's the tilde slash
shorthand whatever or you know slash
users slash KC whatever it is you can
put the dot e mixed on there and it will
automatically load but ignoring all of
that because that's neither here nor
there once you actually start up Emacs
on whatever platform you are running I
am basically going to go over all my
keyboard shortcuts and what they do now
you'll notice when it opens up by
default I have it set up into this two
pane mode so that there's like a pane on
the left and a pane on the right the
reason I do that is what I like to look
at H files and CPP files at the same
time and I tend to put my like struct
definitions in on one side and my code
on the other so I can see them it's
basically just an easy way to keep
everything up on the screen so that I
kind of have a quick reference always
when I need it so basically that is just
there's there's a bunch of commands in
Emacs that do that
sort of thing but basically they are all
in the in the dmax file let's see here
if I open that up down here split should
be some kind of that so basically that
in my Emacs file this startup windowing
line basically sort of has what's
happening there this split window
horizontally thing is the thing that
like takes the window whatever it is and
divides it down the middle and you can
keep doing that sort of thing right and
it would divide it again and that sort
of stuff so that's basically just split
window horizontally and split window
vertically does the other kind of thing
right basically those are just ways of
dividing up the screen real estate and I
don't ever do anything pretty much other
than what I've got exactly right here so
I just have that on startup and I just
use it that way okay so that is
basically what comes up when you
actually start going to Emacs using my
config now what you'll notice and I've
already done this on this thing or ready
to demonstrate this window thing is
Emacs basically has like sort of the
equivalent of a little like top level
it's got like a little way that you can
just start executing commands as if you
were running Lisp sort of it's not
really that but it's kind of like that
called the mini buffer and the mini
buffer is if you hit escape X right you
hit this not hold them down but you like
hit escape then you hit X which is
called meta X you get this little thing
down here you can see the M dash X and
you've got this little blinking cursor
and that's basically for whenever you
get into a situation where you need to
execute some commands that you don't
have set up for easy use so anytime
you're doing something out of the
ordinary you hit that meta X and you get
down there and what you can do there is
if you if you hit tab to complete things
you'll see all the commands you could
actually do and if you start typing some
of them like I typed split and hit tab
you can see that it will show me just
the things the commands that have that
involved now Emacs have so many commands
in it it's crazy I don't even know what
ten percent of those commands are like I
mean if I actually do meta X and hit the
tab and scroll through that it's just
like I don't even know I mean what is
what is quick
I have no idea you know you could type
it in and see what it does quick calc
and pair there's a wide I don't know two
plus five okay so I didn't review that
was there I never knew Emacs had that
apparently you hit medics quick calc and
it's got a calculator of course it does
cousin Emacs has everything you know
that I that would have saved me a lot of
time all these years of going with that
right but I didn't know I don't know
what is that what else can you do with
this if I'm in here MedX quick calc what
else can I do
can I do something crazy like two to the
sixth power unbelievable uh okay what
else I don't even know it's there
I'm going to start using this is it do
hexadecimal no it can't
oh it because it interpret the XS as x
all right I don't know
so so there you go this is cut this is
this is the majesty of Emacs there's so
much stuff in there so anyway if you're
down in here you tip type escape X you
get in here you can start typing stuff
you can hit tab and it'll try to
complete it for you with a can but if
you decide at any time and this is true
across all of Emacs basically if you
decide at any time that stuff has gone
horribly wrong and you didn't want to be
where you are so you don't want to be
down in the mini buffer you can hold
down control and hit G hold down control
so control G gets you out of there get
you out of the mini buffer and it'll
generally abort stuff that's going on in
the mini but if you need to get out now
suddenly when you hit that MedX thing if
there's that one if you said like let's
say you did this quick Cal thing and
you're like I don't know I want to learn
more about that it actually has some
documentation built into it so you can
type in describe function for example
and then you can type like quick calc in
there and it'll give you any
documentation that it actually has on
that thing it'll tell you where the
actual thing is implemented in the Emacs
list and you can even click on the thing
usually and go to the Lisp so this is
like the source code for it now like I
said I can't program lists partly at all
so you know I'm never really probably
going to understand most of the stuff
that's in here
like I'd have to really pay attention to
even know what was going on but if you
were a list person you could just go in
and take a look and see how things are
implemented if you cared right so
there's some other things you can do if
you type meta X help you can get this
sort of thing that sort of tells you a
bunch of keyboard shortcuts that you
could type in to get more help the most
common one is apropos which is a so if
you hit a you can then type in anything
you want like let's say we just type in
calc and hit return and that will
actually do kind of like a search for
all of the commands that have calc in it
right so you can see all the stuff that
you can do all the commands that have
calculate somewhere so yeah I mean
budget stuff you can do there I'm not
going to go into detail too much on that
stuff because you kind of get the idea
I'm just going to go ahead and talk
about all the things that I actually
have bound keys so you can tell the
stuff that I think is important and that
I use often so alt F you hold down alt
you hit F is one of the major things
that I used and that just means load a
new file and when you're in there you
can basically hit like tab to do
completion and you can hit delete will
go back like a whole directory you can
type in a thing and autocomplete it that
sort of stuff
I'm going to in the misc directory put
like an Emacs keybindings dot text right
now
Emacs sometime recently introduced a
really annoying feature which is that if
the thing that you type in is not in the
path where you're putting it so like you
see in fact I can show you for example
here I'm trying to create a new file
right I'm trying to connect create Emacs
keybindings dot text and so you know if
in this case if I hit return it'll
actually make the file and that's all
good but let's say I was in here and I
was looking for a file but did happen to
exist somewhere else like let's say that
build that bat or something right it'll
do this search for it and if it finds it
which you can see that it did it
actually then moves you to the it like
moves you right to the directory that
that thing was in and I hate this
feature I have
not gone spelunking in the list to
figure out usually there's ways to turn
these features off I have not gone
spelunking the list to figure out how to
turn that off but I hate that feature
but just be aware that it's there I
don't know if there's anything you can
do to get back to where you were I don't
know if control-j no it doesn't so I
don't actually know that that feature
drives me nuts be aware of it and it
just it's I don't even know I do not
know how to turn it off someone who's a
list guy could totally tell me and we
could put it into the dot Emacs bomb
that would be great anyway so alt F on
my Emacs is that's Alps make a little
thing here is load file in the current
window right so that's pretty important
alt s which I just did is save the file
in the current window write whatever the
file is that you're on right now
similarly alt shift F so if you just hit
shift on there then it opens that same
load file but whatever I load will load
in the other window right so I
oftentimes will do stuff like I'm in
this window working on something and I
want to open a file in the other window
I can just hit alt shift F and do it
that way right so I have alt shift F
that would go here right load file in
the other and that's you know pretty
straightforward right
so that's mostly how I get files in I
mean and I don't think I do anything
else for like file load and save I think
that's mostly it now if you already have
a file loaded you can always load a file
again so I can always hit alt shift eft
again and load something again a second
time even if it's already loaded and
that's fine it'll just make another view
of that thing and whatever the it's not
like it opens it multiple times we have
to worry about multiple copies it's
always the same file unless you
specifically ask Emacs to have two
separate versions of a file loaded which
I never want it to do so I don't have
anything
to that but you can do that it's just a
different thing so the other thing is if
you just want to switch to a buffer that
you know is already open I also have alt
B and alt shift be bound to the same
things as F so if I hit alt B it'll just
list all the buffers that are open and I
can just immediately type to one of them
and left and right arrow keys in here
while you're in the mini buffer cycle
through options obviously so I can I can
also switch buffers that way and alt
shift B switches them to them in the
other window and you can have the same
buffer open multiple times and they
synchronize right so you there's no like
I said again you can have as many views
into the same buffer as you want and
that's fine
so basically much like alt F and alt
shift F there's basically just these
which is a switch to buffer in the
current window switch to buffer in the
other window right and that's that's all
that is now similarly if you want to
just ping-pong back and forth between
the windows like I do often that is all
to W so alt W is a switch or like I know
- I'll call it switch to the other
window right I don't know these are bad
descriptions probably but you know what
I mean hopefully if you're watching this
you will understand what I mean okay
so basically that's most of how I get
around in things that are nonspecific
but if it is a specific type of file
like that I typically work with there
are some additional options so if I'm in
handmaid dot cpp for example and i would
like to get to handmade dot h because I
typically want to be able to go between
CPP's and HS I have alt C bound to that
so alt C just toggles between seeing the
H file and seeing the CPP file right so
alt C switches between H file and CPP
file or I should say toggles between H
file and CPP file in current window
right and the exact same thing as before
with the shift I tend to bind shift to
just mean do it in the other window so
that's basically what the shift does in
this case
well if I was in this window looking at
handmade EVP and I want to see the H
file in the other window I just hit alt
shift C and now I've got it in here
right make some sense hopefully that's
that's pretty clear so it's basically I
think that's everything in terms of
navigation I want to say trying to think
if I've got any other sort of stuff
that's that's about like loading files
and things but I don't think so
there might be some obscure ones but
those are most of them so okay so if you
have a buffer open and you want to get
rid of it you just don't want it open
anymore alt K will kill the buffer it
just goes away right so alt K you know
kills the buffer and it will ask to save
it first if it's modified right so it
doesn't kill it with prejudice it kills
it sort of cordially so if I type some
stuff in here and then hit alt K it'll
ask down in the you know in the mini
buffer it'll say hey did you actually
want to kill it and in this case I'll
say yes I did because I didn't want to
save those changes right pretty basic
stuff like I said nothing particularly
interesting there so let's get to actual
editing so let's say I go into a file
and I'll use a file that we didn't
haven't actually done anything in just
to kind of show you when you Oh to load
a CPP file or an H file I have Emacs
just insert this stuff directly and so
that'll happen any time you open a CPP
file or an H file that's just baked into
my DX file so you have to do anything to
make that happen that just happens so if
you're in here and you're starting to
edit code so you know you're doing you
know food on H and then you're doing boy
main int argc caressed our RV or
something like this and type stuff all
the indentations done for you
automatically usually so basically you
know I don't actually have to do
anything like hit tab or anything I just
start typing whatever it is that I want
to have happen and I don't do any
indentation it's it's syntactic
indentation but sometimes you get into
circumstances where you've done
something and it doesn't update like it
only updates the current line usually
when you do that it doesn't update
anything else so well though the
indentation is proper when you're
entering code it doesn't try to maintain
that indentation in the rest of the file
and so if I did something like enclose
the Ascend and if you can see that it
didn't actually indent eighth indent
anything over here and so one of the
things that you need to know how to do
is to do automatic indentation of a
block so in order to do that I have
first have to teach you what a block is
in Emacs so what a block is in Emacs is
basically every time you are moving the
cursor around you there's sort of an
implicit location which is wherever the
cursor is now if you want to at any time
you can sort of record where that
location is by holding down control and
hitting space and you can see down at
the bottom it says mark set so basically
control space this sets the mark right
now if the mark is set what that means
is that location wherever it is is now
like a reference point that Emacs can
use for whatever you want to do that
operates on blocks so it's basically
like a much better version of selection
because it doesn't muck up your display
at all but it silently sort of has this
opinion of where things are set so I
just go to someplace I set the mark and
then I know I can always do stuff in
reference to that mark so I can just do
ctrl ctrl tab is re indent block row tab
re and n block and so I know I set the
mark right here I can then go hit ctrl
tab and it re indents everything in the
block right now similarly I can do stuff
with that block just like you would do
with the selection and most editors
right if I have the mark set let's say I
want to get rid of this for statement
here right
and obviously home and then just go to
home and then line I don't those are not
special but I hit control space I can go
here control Q is copy right so ctrl Q
copies the block control F paste the
block control W cuts the block so
basically if I do control space control
Q I can start hitting ctrl F to insert
copies of that oh and I should also say
hmm
alt U is undo right so talk about that
one second so it's a little bit you have
to know about that okay so I can I can
also go in if I want to instead of
copying the block of control control w
kills it but I could it still goes into
the paste buffer so I can still reap a
sit-in and so on so that's just the
basic kind of text editing stuff you can
do in any editor but it all works with
at that point so that point that you
drop down is kind of handy too because
let's say you've got like a bunch of
these right I just got a bunch i got a
bigger file right and i was doing some
things up up here so i like cut this
thing out right and then i went down
here and I like pasted it in right but
now I want to go back up to where I just
did that cut I have don't ask why I do
not know I believe it's this but I have
alt shift : it pops back to previously
marked locations I don't know why it's
alt shift : I think I was running out of
keyboard assignments or something but
basically alt shift : goes back through
the history of all the places that you
ever set that mark so alt shift that so
I guess it tightly semicolon but that
would just basically alt : I guess pops
back to the previous mark and so it's
kind of handy to be able to do that
because it means you can do stuff in one
location with a code jump to another
location to go do something and then
immediately sort of Bunji back to the
location
that you previously were at and I do
that a lot on the stream it saves a lot
of like searching around for stuff so
that's kind of handy so let's say that I
also have I'll show you another thing in
terms of navigating around similar to
that mark thing let's say that these
were all like actual functions right
just different names of functions and
things that sort of stuff so I've got a
bunch of these now let's delete these so
I've got a bunch of those and let's say
that I want to jump to a particular
function in a file so all J will jump to
a function by name so if I'm just in a
file and I hit alt J I get index item
down here and I can hit tab for the
completion again and it'll just show me
what the functions are on file I can
just do G underscore main and then it
jumps me right to that so that's an easy
way for me to navigate around if I know
the function that I want to go to it's
pretty easy for me to just go ahead and
get directly to that function so it's
pretty that that's a pretty good feature
and I use it a lot so that's mostly how
the navigation and the block stuff work
undo is a little bit odd in Emacs so I
want to talk a little bit about how it
works basically it's kind of doesn't
have undo and redo it just has one giant
undo buffer that keeps getting bigger so
that's when you undo something
the act of undoing it goes on to the
undo buffer and doing something other
than undo changes the direction of the
unwinding in the undo buffer it's kind
of like get in the sense that people who
know how to use it find that it's
intuitive but if you don't know how to
use it it's completely opaque it's one
of those things where it's just like
either you're used to it or you're not
and it's completely bizarre so I don't
know but basically if you're typing
along here right and then you start
undoing this stuff without you and now
you're like oops I didn't mean to do
that
I want to reap it that stuff in well if
I hit well if I keep hitting alt u it'll
keep undoing more stuff so what I have
to do is like interrupt the undo chain
by doing something like say
just hitting the left you know the right
arrow or something like that to do
something that's non-destructive but
just do it do anything doesn't matter to
do something that isn't undo then when I
hit alt you it'll start unwinding that
undo stack right to the point where
there's nothing left to undo and then it
restarts on doing right because the undo
buffer is always growing it's just it's
very odd
I don't expect you to get used to it
right away it feels fine for me to use
but I don't think it's a good design but
it is the head of the design so you know
what are you going to do so that's
basically how undo works alright so
there's a couple of the things I'm
trying to think of all the stuff that I
tend to do from day to day that that
people might want to know about so
keyboard macros I haven't used them yet
on the stream but I do use them normally
so let's say I have I got all these sort
of functions that are like a underscore
main B underscore main C under screaming
oh I know what to do let me do this
before I get search control s is search
and it's exactly what you would expect
in any editor you just start typing and
you get it you hit ctrl s to move or
ctrl R to go backwards so basically it's
ctrl s start incremental search and then
once you're in there
ctrl s sort of moves to next next
occurrence let's say and control our
oops moves to previous occurrence just
like you would expect I also have alt o
is query replace so if I wanted to
change our GC to our count I can just
type those two in return I type the
first one return and second one return
and then it's just why your n at each
one so yes yes no yes no yes no yes yes
right something like that so if you want
to do a replace you can do that
and similarly I have the ability to do
replacement inside a paste this is kind
of handy so let's say I have this block
and I'm going to paste it a couple times
right but when I paste it
I want to be able to change the X to
something else after you do the paste
that mark is set to where you did the
paste from that's how Emacs works
Boult l does it replace inside the
marked region only so I can replace X
with Y just in that region right and
it'll work so I do it again
I'll tell X to Z do it again X 2 Q right
you can just keep on doing it so that's
kind of handy so basically that's a alt
o is query replace fault L is replaced
inside block right um I don't think
there's anything else about those is
there anything else that I do I'm
probably forgetting some things yeah I
don't know Oh one thing I should say
along with alt s alt M triggers the
compiler right so that's that's
basically I should say execute looks for
and execute a build dot bat right so
yeah that's how I was doing that if you
hit alt M it will actually do a
compilation it'll prompt you to save
things and then it'll do the compilation
to me all right
so keyboard macros keyboard macros are
pretty simple
you hit a alt Open bracket so basically
alt and then this begin recording
keyboard macro then alt close bracket is
end recording keyboard macro and then
alt uh whatever you want to cut a single
apostrophe I guess that's what that is
yeah is is replay keyboard macro now it
may not sound like keyboard macros are
particularly useful but they are in
Emacs I don't know if they are another
language in other editors as well but in
Emacs you can actually get a lot of
functionality about the out of them
so you
in bed searches and cut and paste and
all that stuff in a keyboard macro so
for example let's say we actually have
we have all these functions and they're
all like a underscore remains B
underscore main and what we want to do
is we want to turn them into something
that looks more like main underscore a
right so we want to move we want to
change where that thing is right so what
I can do is I can start recording
keyboard macro I can hit ctrl s to do a
search hit a underscore right then I can
hit basically delete to delete the the
the underscore that's kind of was in
between the main hit controls space to
mark the location hit ctrl I should talk
about these later control left arrow to
get back to the previous word ctrl W to
cut ctrl s to search for the the
parentheses go back one insert the the
underscore that I was talking about and
then paste in the new one right and if I
go ahead and do an alt bracket to finish
that one then you can see when I when I
go ahead and replay it on something
right it would do
oh well no I guess I messed that up
sorry I was talking a little bit too
much in there maybe I missed it up let's
try one more time
search for main move back one a little
thing delete that mark it W move forward
for that underscore paste should work
there we go
so then we go down and we can replace
all of those with their swizzles
equivalents so yeah that's basically it
and you can make arbitrarily complex
stuff that way it gets finicky like you
saw it didn't work the first time
because I messed something up that's
pretty common and it's typical to be a
little finicky so you only really want
to do that if you're actually doing a
lot of heavyweight edits that are
actually gonna save you a lot of time
but it works pretty well so the other
thing that I meant to say that I forgot
about was basically if I hold down the
ctrl key I can move basically by larger
increments so basically ctrl + arrow
keys
people's move cursor by larger
increments in this like word for white
space is usually what it looks for so up
and down is by white space see and let
you write or by word so that's about it
so let me take a brief look at the Emacs
file and just see if there's anything
obvious that I haven't covered yet
because I suspect there's a couple of
the things that I just haven't talked
about so we talked about the buffers we
don't need the to do thing that's a log
loading thing we talked about that we
talked about save oh I should say that
tab completes our cycles through
completions for a word so basically if
you're in somewhere editing and you want
to do main you can just hit tab and
it'll cycle through all the possible
things that's nothing quickly special
sort of like intellisense but it's just
word based it's not understanding the
code or anything
let's see those are also see fill
paragraph okay so that's probably a
little bit interesting so alt and period
is to reflow a comment you can basically
do that so for example if I'm in here
and I did some kind of comment where I
was like you know do you do this is a
long comment that starts get long-winded
and maybe the person didn't do a great
job of figuring out where the line
breaks should have gone and now it's all
messed up and so if I hit alt period
anywhere in there it'll just do it and
it that includes making more lines if it
needs to right so they can it can do it
like that and it also I believe will
automatically if you're using the other
kind of comment where you need it where
it's only one lines worth of comment I
believe it'll just yeah it just
automatically inserts more of the
comment markers for you so it's kind of
a catch-all it just does the right thing
pretty much in all circumstances
so that's where we flowing comment let's
see what else do we have we've got all
of those those are not necessary anymore
set marker pen bla bla bla
yeah yeah yeah covered all those
exchange point in mark we don't really
use ok so next in previous error those
are probably worth doing so Alt + + alt
shift + R basically go to the next error
after a compile and go to the previous
error after a compile and basically all
those are if you run that alt em thing
and then you want to go back and forth
between errors it's Alt + + Alt shift M
really pretty basic okay and there's
another good one - alt G is a go to line
number so basically if I'm on any file
and I hit alt G you can type in a line
number like 10 and it'll hop you right
to that line number which is sometimes
good if you have an external tool that's
giving you line number information you
just want to go right there that's
pretty pretty useful these are not
useful revert buffer is probably useful
so we'll put that in there for now so
alt R is revert buffer and we all
probably know what that is right it's
just a few if you make a bunch of
changes in a buffer they're just wrong
and you're like I want to go back to
what's on the disk you hit all our it'll
ask you for confirmation and then you
get back to the buffer as it stands on
disk so just like in any other editor
nothing particularly odd there so we got
the compilation stuff we covered that
we've got some variables here
that's time those are not useful and
that's it so I think this is basically
it like that's that's literally and I
should get rid of all that bogus code in
the next hand made friends we haven't um
so yeah I think that's basically it so
this is a quick reference guide for
Casey Zeman
keybindings that is basically all you
need to know that's all I'm doing on the
stream is I think basically just these
things and so like I said my needs for
an editor are relatively modest if
someone just built an editor that was
lightning fast had good syntax
highlighting good good indentation by
syntax and then supported all of these
features
I could probably that was bound to these
keys trivially with the two pane layout
I could probably just switch to it in no
time right because it's this all like
this is all I use I don't really need
anything else
so like I said I suspect I mean I don't
know for sure but I suspect if you were
using say sublime or something like that
that you could if you wanted to and I
don't know that you necessarily do want
to edit exactly the way I do but if you
did I suspect you could probably set it
up to be very close to exactly these
things because they're like I said
they're not really that complicated
there may be some things like I don't
know if it keeps a mark history and
stuff like that there maybe it's just a
few things that a particular editor just
doesn't do but for this for the most
part a pretty similar editor config
could probably be made in in most text
editors except of course window I mean a
visual studio like I tried back into k-8
to get a thing that was opponent Emacs
and there were just a number of reasons
why it didn't quite work because of the
way that they handle key bindings they
couldn't emulate these key bindings
correctly hilariously they used to have
a plugin that allowed you to but then
they like nerfed it like it didn't work
anymore and I don't know if they ever
got the plug-in working again it's just
it's classic Microsoft nonsense weird
like every time you install a new
version of one of their piece of
software you get less features than you
had in the previous version I don't know
how that ever happened but that's where
we've ended up so anyway I think that's
basically it so I'm going to call it
quits now on the Emacs thing and we'll
take a 10-minute break before starting
the regular handmade hero stream so I'm
going to go here and go ahead and turn
that off so I can have a clean recording