all right hello everyone and welcome to
the third and final part of the career
stories I guess technically there's only
really two parts for this is just the
wrap up this is that this is the coda if
you will so the sort of the the end note
to it so as anyone who's watched either
of the first two videos now would be
more than aware the idea behind this was
just to sort of get experiences from
people who have changed to software
development from some other career or at
least tried to and maybe haven't been
successful yet or maybe failed and went
back to what they're doing or maybe
succeeded and now are doing it for a
living right so anything just the
attempt was the common thread and I read
all the submissions that I got online
and there was quite a lot there right
there's I think now something like 3
plus hours of readings of folks telling
their stories and saying sort of how
things happened to them and you know
what their experience was what their
takeaways were from it and so looking
over all of that I think there is you
know kind of two two things that I'm
interested in one is like what are sort
of the the basic sort of takeaways from
it that everyone could sort of say
there's a you know the what are the
common threads here and and that sort of
thing and then the second one is like is
there anything in particular in terms of
stuff we do on handmade hero that could
be useful in terms of helping people who
want to make that that's which right and
so for the first part what I think I
heard a lot in in those sorts of stories
talking about the career move is that it
really did sort of feel to me like
there's a bit of a latent sort of
inherent draw towards this activity you
know and i think that squares well with
my experiences just personally as
someone who didn't switch crews who just
always did it
I think it is kind of true that software
development is the sort of thing that
you just sort of have a natural draw to
or you don't much like a lot of things
you might want to do like you know being
an illustrator and artist or something
like this I think that's very different
from saying like talent or not talent
right like are you going to be good at
it or not or anything like that I'm
stepping back what I'm saying I feel
like a lot of I heard a lot of people
sort of talking about the fact that just
this is the thing that they kind of are
drawn to write their kind of drawn to
the idea of doing this programming so
much so that they would do it in their
spare time or they like to tinker with
this or you know they used to do it when
they were little and then rediscovered
it again and cetera et cetera so I do
think the first step to this it does
kind of sound like if you're someone
who's thinking about this it does kind
of seem like well is that piece there
right like do you find yourself
naturally drawn to this activity not so
much as a career thing but just as
something that you find engaging right
does the mental curiosity for you hold
that appeal or does it not right and I
feel like that's kind of true just
across the board like I would say that
that's probably why I got into software
development even though I didn't do it
as a career change the reason I got in
intuitive career at all was for those
exact same reasons right it was
specifically because I felt that draw
right and I wanted to satisfy that
intellectual curiosity that was
naturally there for this activity right
so I would say you know thinking about
whether you really have that desire to
do it is probably a really good first
step because it may be that it's
something that you really don't have
that much inherent motivation to do and
if that's the case you know programming
does take a lot of work to learn you
even not particularly advanced
programming it's a foreign concept in a
lot of ways right it's it's not
extremely straightforward by any stretch
of the imagination right and so I think
that you don't want you know if you're
just looking for a career change I don't
necessarily think that you want to pick
software engineering unless you have
that inherent sort of pull towards it
because I think you're just going to be
unhappy with the decision in the end
probably you know now again that's just
total speculation though so you
shouldn't take my word for it that's
just you know again these are just kind
of the things that I took away from it
and on the flip side of that or I
shouldn't say flip side i just made a
corollary to that is I can also tell you
that the the great programmers that I've
known so people who are exceptional at
it they all have that right so if you
are interested in getting into soft
relevant because you would like to excel
at it I can certainly tell you that I've
never met a great programmer who didn't
have that right who didn't have that
inherent sort of pull towards this as an
activity and so I think that's a really
important thing to think about and just
to consider if we can make any takeaways
at all like everyone's circumstances are
obviously different and so I don't know
that there's any way to say anything
definitively but in and so much as we
can I think that that squares with my
experience and I heard it in a lot of
the stories and so I think that that's
something that we can probably draw from
and say think about that do some
thinking on that and see where you land
on that right now another sort of thing
that I feel like was sort of confirmed
for me by these but it may just be
confirmation bias on my part I don't
know but one of the questions that I get
a lot that you know i would say comes up
more frequently than then pretty much i
don't know maybe any other question
really from newer people who are
approaching this or considering this is
how much math do i need to know right
and
and I I kind of think that one of the
things that you didn't hear much in the
stories was oh I learned a lot of math
or I spent a lot of time learning math
or my math background really helped me
you know there were some people who had
sort of math in their stories there was
a little bit of math was touch upon once
or twice but you'll notice
overwhelmingly math was not involved
here right math was not a central topic
the people who were doing these
switching while they may have come from
sort of technical things often IT sorts
of stuff for that sort of thing or web
development the number of people who
came from seriously hard math stuff
wasn't actually that high it was maybe
you know it was it was less than half
even you know there was a someone who
had a math background there was someone
who had a like an architecture
background those four things surely
there was math involved in in these
sorts of things right but there were
also people talk about like oh I was
doing you know restaurant management or
I came from an art career right like
maxi on your segment from from Pixar
right so you know the fact that math is
important in in programming in a number
of ways I want to say that I think
there's a very clear distinction there
between math being important and saying
that math itself is some kind of a
predetermined or prerequisite for
getting into programming for me math
came after programming and I think for a
lot of people that can be true I have
never really felt like I faced a serious
impediment to being able to program well
because I learned math through
programming not the other way around and
I think that that there is actually I
don't want to say the word harms that
sounds though too harsh but I think
there is potential for deleterious
effects from the stereotype that people
who are good at math or naturally
gravitate towards math
are the people who will be good at
programming and naturally gravitate
towards programming I don't think that's
true I don't think that's true at all i
think they are largely unrelated in a
lot of ways right i know lots of great
programmers who were great
mathematicians I know lots of great
programmers who are horrible
mathematicians right and so I really
just don't think that those two things
are implicated or correlated in the way
that a lot of people think they are and
to give sort of a more concrete example
of this of how pervasive I think this
thinking is especially outside of maybe
programmers themselves I remember like a
year or two ago I can't remember quite
how long maybe a year and a half ago I
remember listening to a story on NPR
where they were talking about like
they're basically trying to unpack you
know why there weren't as many women
going to CS programs or graduating from
CS programs as they thought there should
be or that were traditionally the case
in the earlier days you know why was
there a kind of a fall-off in that and
so on and this has very little to do
with the story but it was the the sort
of inherent assumption in the story that
I thought was interesting when they
decided to talk to women who had fallen
out of these paths for various reasons
they were always very sure to emphasize
how good those people were at math
originally like that was some kind of
evidence about they should have been
good at programming or this was a
natural sort discipline and so I feel
like there's this cognitive sort of like
capture here maybe in the outside world
that programming in math if you were
naturally interested in math or
naturally good at math you you're going
to naturally be good or naturally
gravitated towards programming the
reason that I think that might be
deleterious is because when you want to
so for even taking that same story when
do you want to analyze something or when
you want to go figure out how do we fix
a problem like how do we convey
more people to get into programming or
to do a certain type of programming if
your mental model is I want to go start
looking at let's say the kids who are
good at math and they're going to be
good at programming right I think that
may be fundamentally misguided right I
was always much better at language arts
and like creative things than i was at
math much much better you know my grades
in English class would have been far
superior to my grades in math class
across the board right that's just the
way it was and so I think one of the
things that we run the risk of doing by
making this connection is you may end up
looking in the wrong places but or in
too narrow of places for candidates for
these things right and so to tie it back
to that story if one of the things that
you want to do was to get more women
interested in programming let's say at a
younger age and you decided to focus all
of your efforts on younger girls who
were good at math right you may be
cutting out a huge segment of the of the
eligible population there because that
may not be the right people right
programming is not the same as math and
the mindset that's necessary to be a
good programmer is not the same as the
mindset that's necessary to be good
mathematician right and so the fact that
you need math for programming is not a
the same as saying that good being good
at math or drawn to math will make you
good at programming or drawn to
programming and again to tie that back
to my personal experience I strongly
dislike math up until I left high school
actually strongly dislike math very much
did not ever want to do it for any
reason I was so much not on the math
side of things that I had an incredibly
hard time for example and I think I've
said this way back at the beginning of
handmade hero I had an incredibly hard
time
learning equations in math and the
reason is because in computers right an
equal sign in most languages means
assignment it's a temporal operator it's
the things before that happens are
different than the things that happen
after if I have a statement that says a
equals B then that does not mean that a
and B were equal for all time in
programming it means that before the
statement a was not equal to be
potentially and after the statement a is
now equal to be right I learned that
when I was seven years old I wouldn't
have calculus for another 5 i'm sorry i
wouldn't have algebra is what sorry I
didn't mean to caucus I meant algebra I
wouldn't have algebra until 7th grade is
when they started taking pre algebra
right so it was going to be another
seven years eight years I don't even
remember what the how the grades go
exactly in terms of when age wise you
took them but I new programming for so
much longer before that that when they
tried to teach me that as like I have I
don't understand what this is this makes
no sense to me how can you say this
equals line here it's like these two
things like it would have already made
this assignment up here right it was
very confusing in my head and so you
know there is a certain amount of
logical thinking that has to happen in
order to understand programming it has
to be a very because computers are so
precise you do have to understand the
concept that these things are not
flexible they are rigid right but
there's not that much of a difference
between that sort of thing and in fact I
would argue perhaps less of a difference
between that sort of a thing and the
sort of thing you would have to
understand to be a good storyteller for
example someone who understands that
things have a sequence of events and the
audience understands things based on
what you've told them so far right and
being able to keep very large worlds in
your head at once like you know I
imagine George Martin would probably be
a pretty good programmer right because
if you can conceptualize that many
characters
that many things going on at once in
many ways that to me feels more like
programming than a lot of math things do
right and so I I don't know that again
maybe just confirmation bias on my part
i don't know because i think you know
thought it was true before an hearing
these stories and not having people
mention that a lot not having said oh i
was always good at math and so right or
I really liked math and so we didn't
hear that very much in the stories or
you know in there in the stories I feel
like that kind of squares with my
opinion on it which is that I think the
sort of perspective of whether math is a
prerequisite or pre indicator for being
a good programmer outside of that sphere
of people who've actually know in and
out as professionals at in the public at
large that linkage of the two I really
do think maybe doing a lot of sort of or
maybe putting up a lot of unnecessary
impediments to people who would be going
into this career and could potentially
excel at it because they're just hearing
that math and programming thing be
really tight and so you know take the
perspective of somebody who's really
good like I said like maybe like I was
really good at writing maybe stories in
English class or something like this has
that intellectual curiosity of maybe I
would like to learn how my computer
works but is constantly hearing this
sort of oh well it's mathy it's all math
the math is the important part if you're
not good at math you're not going to
that's the wrong message to send right
and and also similar like I said if
you're looking to do sort of programs
that are trying to target people who
aren't getting into computing right now
restricting yourself hort or sort of
tailoring what you're doing towards the
math the people who have proclivities
towards math or who are currently
excelling
math related things as the sign that
they'll you know transition computing or
want to be I just I don't find that to
be a good idea I think that's probably
wrong so that's just you know again
something that I maybe am putting too
much emphasis on because I want to
confirm my hypothesis about that but
that was something that I just really
didn't notice you know in the stories is
that there wasn't that underlying thread
and I think that's that was true for me
and it sounds like it's true for these
other folks and I think it's true for a
lot of people that said I love math now
right most of the things that I do in
programming now I various some math
background to it right and I've had to
use a lot of advanced mathematics stuff
that I never would have dreamed by what
have you learned in my day to day
programming so even more strenuously
adding to this what I might suggest is
that in a lot of ways I think
programming and computers are a very
important tool for people who do not
like doing math the way math is normally
done in a school setting textbook style
math computers can really turn somebody
who never was good at math didn't like
to do math strongly disliked taking math
classes was not a strong performer in
math in school and turned them into
someone who loves math who does
day-to-day work using math who looks for
answers to things with math who explores
possibilities in math that was certainly
what happened to me and so I also see
that as yet another reason not to try
and link those two things the priests
offer you know pre-programming love of
math to a post programming love of math
I really just don't think they're
related at all you might have somebody
right now who is doing very poorly at
math
school and if you taught them to program
they would suddenly open up this whole
world of of math to them that they might
really enjoy now again I am saying all
these things data free I have no way to
back them up I don't know that we ever
really could or at least not with our
current you know level of understanding
the human brain but to give a possible
explanation for why that's true and just
to give again some more evidence
potentially or some more food for
thought there if you take what it means
to be someone who's creative right what
is creativity to a large extent well
it's sort of harnessed randomness right
you know the the ability to make
something new involves being able to
come up with new randomized ideas that
you know haven't existed before right
coming up with a new story or a new
piece of music or whatever is about
taking random ideas and random thoughts
and these sorts of things right and
constraining them down into something
that fits certain grammar or certain
form that can be shared and and
expressed and so on right and so if you
look at the kinds of people who are
going to be good at some of these
disciplines there's a lot of of
randomness in their thinking and I don't
mean that to say that they can't be
logical because I consider myself in
this camp I consider myself someone
who's in that high randomness camp
having lots of random ideas right means
that your brain enjoys seeing different
possibilities and things and permuting
and and sort of shaking up the the
marble jar right or you know pulling out
the the lottery number and seeing what
this new number is right or playing the
slot machine right in it likes this
random you know ideas sort of changing
and mutating and playing with the
possibilities math education as as it's
taught at least in this country but most
places is very much about never having
those random ideas right you are meant
to be
a computer yourself you are meant to do
the algebra yourself line after line
right and heaven forfend you make a
mistake using computers to do the math
for you using computers to verify your
results using computers to draw your
results for you all of these things take
math take the part of math that's about
not having the creativity and not having
the randomness and all those sorts of
constrained very like you know rigid
parts and they offload that job to the
computer because hey guess what it's
very good at not being creative it's
built to not be creative right we have
to add creativity to it by you know in
fact it can even generate a random
number a lot of the time right you know
it's only recently that computers had
built in ways of generating random
entropy right but anyway neither here
nor there and in so doing by offing
that's puters you open up the ability
for people's whose brains are more
scatter shot like that to harness the
power of math and to enjoy map and to
use it and to have a fun experience
because with programming you only have
to come up with the idea once you
clarify it in the computer will do it
right contrast that to map the way it's
normally done where it's like we learn
this postulate or this theorem and then
I got a crank through 30 examples where
I'm doing it myself right that is so
uncreated and so against the grain for
creative person it's really hard for
them to keep their mind on that the
whole time in order to do that job right
whereas the idea behind it whatever the
posture that was they could just go oh
okay that's interesting that's a new
piece in my brain that I can be creative
with and used for a purpose right and
now you've taken that sort of Drudge
work out of it it becomes accessible to
them because there's nothing inherently
uncreated about the act of using math or
developing new math
those things are not uncreated right and
so I think that that is kind of a kind
of a really important thing to
understand that programming is a way of
opening up mathematics to people who
wouldn't necessarily be able to excel at
it now they can potentially right now
they can make really interesting
contributions potentially to math
related things even though they may
never have been able to be good enough
at by hand math to ever have done them
right or to ever even have known they
wanted to to never even be motivated
enough to get to that point and so just
to put a final cap on that because again
i think it's like a really important
point if you go back and look at what
happened to in my life i almost
certainly would not have been a
programmer today if what had happened in
my life was that I didn't have a father
who was a programmer so I wasn't exposed
to it early I went to school you know
didn't have a computer in the home let's
say because at that time it wasn't
common wasn't that common or if it was
you might not know it was programmable
like you might have had a Commodore 64
which would have a great machine to
learn programming on you may not have
known that programming was even
something could do with it there was no
internet you may never have just
encountered that idea right so go back
in time that's not what my dad did for a
living he did something else so i don't
know i don't know about programming I go
to school I take math classes they're
awful right I hate it I don't like that
someone then says oh hey you know here's
the thing it's computer programming you
know if you like math you'll really
enjoy it I'm never gonna do that right
you know I'm never going to go do some
activity that people are telling me if I
liked math I'd like it or something
right because I don't like math right
now secretly I do I just don't know it
yet right I haven't had the experience
of a Drudge free
math so I don't know that I like it
right but just from my experience that's
what happens and so again I really just
wanna because I've never really talked
about that whole thing as a as a topic I
really want to emphasize that as
something that I think we need to
reconsider just broadly about the
messaging around programming because I
think if the messaging around
programming is always that it has a the
same sort of like people who want to do
math want to do it I think if that's
always the messaging I think we are
cutting out a large segment of the
people who might be very good at it not
to mention enjoy it which include myself
in right I include myself in that group
I conclude myself in the group of people
who would be cut out of that and and
like I don't see programming as a thing
that we're math is the primary indicator
a great historian might be a great
programmer right I see just as much
similarity to programming and history as
I do to programming and math right
reading through all kinds of texts
learning lots of different languages you
could read the source material putting
together what happened in time those
sound like the the the modus operandi of
a great debugger right a person who's
going to be great at debugging problems
math factors into it not at all right I
can't think of anything math related
that would make you be a good at
debugging right like I said language
arts being able to conceive of stories
peeing able to keep the pieces in your
head things which don't exist very large
sets of things big ideas big things
right interconnect interconnections
these sorts of things are very important
for systems architecture right very
little math or none at all involved in
systems architecture work right and so I
feel like all of these disciplines
there's a lot in common in various
programming activities and various
Princeton's there's a lot in common with
other disciplines and I think looking at
it from the lens of math is very bad
it's not to say that we don't also very
much want the people who are very good
at math because there's a ton of
programming problems that are sort of
these very focused math like things that
we need to work through in a math like
fashion where the more math thinking you
can do the better and that's where you
want the people who have been
traditionally told you know this will be
good for you but that's a very narrow
slice and there's this much wider slice
that I don't think we're looking at okay
so that's nothing so finally third thing
that I want to say about the entries
that I received and I'll kind of close
on this because I talked a lot about
sort of all that base in there the third
thing that I want to say about them was
that I feel like it's cemented for me
the fact that whatever you were doing
for your previous career you can still
get into programming right I saw just
lots of different stories from people
from very disparate circumstances in
terms of what their previous occupation
was and I didn't really hear any sort of
a common thread there may be there were
slightly more stories from people coming
from like IT ish things and that makes
sense because hey if you're around
computers all the time maybe you're more
likely to think of that and switch into
it but we are plenty of stories from
people from everything else right you
know artist architect restaurant
business you know military like there
there really wasn't this sort of
constrained narrow pool of previous
occupations that people were coming from
it felt like that was very very broad
and so the fact that it was very broad
to me suggests that yeah I don't think
you need to
worried what your previous occupation
was if you find yourself drawn towards
programming for whatever reason I think
you should consider it you should start
thinking about it because there doesn't
seem to be a hard and fast limitation
based on what you have studied in the
past what your career choice was in the
past it doesn't seem like that's really
an impediment based on what your careers
you may have harder obstacles to break
through because you know if you come
from a very well-paying career
background it may be more easier for you
to take time off and study if you work
if you have to work less hours for your
pay you can spend more time at home
learning to program so it can definitely
be easier or harder based on your career
just in terms of having the resources to
pursue a career change at all right so
that does seem true but I didn't hear in
the stories and I think it's very
important to note I really didn't hear
any sorts of reasons why previous career
choices would make it impossible for you
to switch to programming or that you
that it's too late to learn right it
seemed like at least up until about 30
years old anyway I didn't hear anything
about that the fact that we didn't have
a lot of people right in who were over
30 I don't know if that means at some
point it does become harder to learn I
don't know I suspect it probably not
it's probably just that most people
don't really consider career changes
very much at that point you know by the
time you're 35 40 maybe you're just not
considering career change much so the
reason we don't get a lot of stories you
know it just is just sampling error at
that point it may be that it still could
work just fine for you if you are 40 and
you know like like I am and want to
change their career in software
development maybe it would be fine so I
don't know that we can draw too much
from stories we haven't heard but what I
think we can draw from stories that we
have heard is that the choice of career
in the specific discipline does not seem
to be a major impediment in any
particular way journalist was another
one right so there's so many different
careers that people came from I find
that to be very encouraging because it
suggests to me that you can make that
switch and so if software engineering or
software development is something that
you think holds some attraction for you
I think the the overall takeaway is that
if you are willing to work at it it
doesn't seem like your current career
choice is an obstacle and I think that's
very positive and I'm pretty happy that
that was what we overwhelmingly I think
heard from the people who wrote in so on
that note I will conclude this video
serious and I hope that everyone has
enjoyed it I know it's a departure from
what we normally do on handmade hero but
I just wanted to take a chance on
answering question that people had
written in and asked many times that I
never had a good answer for so I'm
hoping that this video series is now
something that they can go to and at
least have an answer I don't know how
good our answer was but we tried and so
hopefully now that's something that they
can use in their decision making process
or to help them through that transition
if they do decide that it's something
they want to do so that's about it again
there will be a blog post that
accompanies these free videos and I hope
to try to put a bunch of links in there
that you can use so if you watch this
series from start to finish if you
watched all three parts and the reason
you watch them is because you're
considering such a career change please
do look for the blog entry that
accompanied these videos because that
blog entry will have links for example
to discussion forums you can use to talk
to other people about this to the
resources that we mentioned in in the
course of the stories that may have been
hard to hear the links or I may not have
been able to read the links Couture too
complicated those will be accompanying
it so if you want to get that
information definitely check out that
blog entry so that's it for today thank
you so much for joining me and we will
resume handmade hero programming
tomorrow thanks everyone and have a
great rest of you weekend