hello everyone and welcome to the second
part of the career stories stream that
we're doing here I decided to break this
up into two parts because there was well
there was a lot of people who wrote in
and I just kind of wanted to get
basically everything that people wrote
into me I wanted to read all of it
because I thought it was all pretty
valuable stuff and pretty interesting
stuff that would help folks who are
interested in this sort of thing so if
he hadn't didn't catch the first stream
I would highly recommend starting with
the first stream these make sense
together so you know these hopefully are
posted in such a way you know check the
check the notes on the video and it
should tell you how to get to the first
one if you if you're not on a page that
has them both presented together but
definitely start with the first one this
is the second part of a two-part series
on essentially career stories where I
asked people to write in and tell me
about their experiences changing careers
from one you know area of you know could
have been something close to programming
like information technology or something
like this or it could be something very
far from programming I you know
restaurant management or something like
this it did you know anything
construction work architecture whatever
it was went from a career in that or a
focus in that in their lives to actually
becoming a software developer or trying
to become a soft developer and failing
it was not just a request for success
stories it was just a request for
attempt stories and if you know it
succeeded great if you failed great you
know just tell us the story and the idea
was that people who are interested in
potentially doing this who you know or
maybe in the shoes of the people who
wrote in but just ten years ago or
something like that you know they could
sort of get something from these stories
and how did it go
what were the experiences like it was a
positive experiences a negative
experience what were the pitfalls is
there advice that could be passed along
or
just it just feels nice to know that
you're not alone in this transition that
other people have done it and here's
what they experienced and you know
sometimes it just makes a difference
just to hear other people's experiences
it doesn't necessarily mean you have to
take something from them explicitly it's
just there's sometimes something nice
implicitly about hearing about how other
people have done things and so that's
what these two streams are all about and
there was more information than I
thought could fit in one stream so last
week I read most of the sort of shorter
entries and a lot of the entries are
fairly long which is great because they
they kind of tell a complete story they
aren't just sort of isolated little
snippets of advice but you know there
was a couple that were very long and
that's like I'd like to read these two
because there's a lot of really good
information on this I thought let's just
break it up into two streams people who
are really interested in this can
therefore have you know the sort of
ability to completely take in all of the
things that people said even if they
were particularly lengthy because
sometimes the lengthy ones go into the
details that you don't get in a brief
one and that can be very valuable so
again please check out the first stream
it's got a little more explanation in it
and sort of is organized in a particular
way to kind of like give you a
perspective across a number of different
people's stories from sort of different
backgrounds and different or previous
careers this stream has I think there's
only two stories but they're
particularly long and then I'll they'll
be some just some commentary for me at
the end where I'm just gonna kind of
talk a little bit about sort of you know
what I what I took from these stories as
somebody who hasn't gone through this
and again going back to the previous
stream that was really one of the big
reasons that I asked for this
information is because I have no
personal experience to share here I've
never made a career change at all let
alone a career change of this nature and
so I didn't feel like I was in a good
position to really offer advice to
well but I often get asked to give
advice about that and I just have
nothing to say and so at the end of this
I'll sort of say here is my read on what
came in here's what I thought I learned
from what people said and you know
obviously take that with a big grain of
salt because all you know it's it was
just sort of my opinion for really I
haven't gone through it myself but I
thought I kind of tried to sort of
summarize a little bit and then talk
about a couple things related to that
which is just like if we wanted to do
some things to help people who were in
this circumstance what would they be
well you know based on what sort of I I
heard being said in multiple stories
what are the sorts of things you know
that might be useful that sort of thing
okay so let's go now to the two stories
that I wanted to read that we didn't
have a chance to read last week this
first one is from Seth batten and he
didn't provide a Twitter link or
anything but he did say he could
attribute it to him by name and he
writes in my software career started
about five years ago when I was 28 but
in my case it was not a sudden leap into
a new field for one thing I didn't have
a career before that I had a handful of
crappy office jobs unrelated to my
bachelor's which was not in computing
but more importantly I applied
programming to all my jobs leading up to
that point in all cases I was sitting in
front of a computer anyway and I needed
software to do my job there were ample
opportunities for improvement so I did
work to practice programming in spite of
not being a professional programmer I
automated data entry I found tools that
did the same job I was doing manually I
figured out how to turn nightmarish
Excel spreadsheets into recently
normalized databases so that their
upkeep took fewer years of my life my
bosses certainly didn't mind my work was
getting done faster with fewer human
errors they even let me dedicate weeks
at a time to business tool development
because it was obviously valuable my
co-workers loved that they hit their
Truscott are floated to the weird kid
with the shitty Linux laptop who liked
priming the magic before I go any
further about how I learned to do that
I want to point out that I should have
studied computer science in school my
co-workers at all crappy jobs asked me
why didn't major in it and I had no
answer programming was my hobby and
unaccredited independent study in
college and I didn't realize it
I passed my mandatory single C++ class
which is intro for non non si SE non CS
science engineers and business people ie
stupid C++ without ever opening the
textbook or even fully understanding the
problem before the lab final when
programming literacy was expected in
other engineering courses I never
struggled and before that I hacked on my
parents home computer until it broke and
then I fixed it I played video games
that required AI programming I cheated
at games by editing their content files
all of that is to say that I've always
loved programming and the only
difference is that now I live that pipe
dream of making my hobby into a job I
love software as a craft science and art
and I feel that way that way in spite of
still having to deal with the normal
business world crap now in software
engineering form I go home at night and
I still want to build programs and read
blog about engineering realities and
listen to experts of other disciplines
talk on Twitch because of that love I
think that before someone finds out how
to switch careers it's reasonable for
them to make certain that they really
want to I have a broad spectrum of
co-workers and without exception the
only ones I appreciate are those like
myself who absolutely loved the work I
have co-workers who studied computer
science because it's lucrative I have
other co-workers who realize that they
can do almost nothing and still be paid
by a large corporation and I have at
least one co-worker obviously studied
programming solely because his father
did who also works at my company
collectively these folks remind me of
someone who really loves the rock and
roll lifestyle but is unwilling to
practice anything related to music lots
of talk about architecture and local
meetup groups a fad programming
languages and participating about what
our team should do but awful at actually
doing the job because they don't like
the work I'm not trying to be negative
but to explain that a career switch may
not automatically make someone happy I
think that absolutely anyone can learn
to program and nearly everyone can
benefit from the skill like in my crappy
office job in my crappy office jobs but
that's a different topic from someone
saying everyone should start doing it
full time or even dedicate their home
hours to studying it in depth
programming's ability to be learned is
exactly the same as the ability to
change brake rotors or to apply makeup
to the face of a person before their
open casket funeral or to push a tiny
drill into a stranger's teeth in the
interest of dental health strict
possibility is not a good criterion for
career choice even if there's lots of
money to be made and the status quo is a
boring dead-end but here's why I believe
that's not a negative you don't have to
switch careers to figure out if you're
going to love it you can learn it
anytime for any reason and all it takes
is a project that you care about
likewise no need to get that bachelor's
degree you can learn everything you need
for free and if you really want a
personal trainer lots of people will
take your money for that purpose just be
aware that after a career switch you
will spend 50 percent of your work time
navigating social politics 25 percent
will be wrangling your incompetent
co-workers and managers that they don't
ruin everything your you've worked for
and if you can still enjoy the remaining
fraction of your time door golden but on
the other hand if you're free to switch
into it you're free to switch out please
take note programmers who hate the job
just another leg of a lifetime of
experimental employment now back to my
experience my career switch involved the
first day of being laid off from a
crappy job and a job ad that was unique
enough to catch my eye
programmers needed no experience
necessary
quote unquote is what it said too good
to be true but it was genuine I won't go
into detail about the awesomely terrible
project that contributed to first
footnote here and when he put first
footnote here he's actually talking
about footnotes that he included at the
bottom of this entry and I told you it
was a very long entry not kidding
so here is the first footnote which I
believe I'm getting correctly because
they're not labeled it just says first
footnote so I believe this is the first
footnote
and this is called my entry level
project footnote lots of people can't
run a computer whatsoever and lots of
community colleges recognize that and
make it part of their curriculum they
teach people how to operate Word and
Excel and PowerPoint these classes need
course material and benevolent selfless
textbook publishers provide it for a
nominal fee the most outstanding
forward-thinking publishers had the
Epiphany that courses teaching computer
usage could use interactive digital
content which might just be better than
a textbook but only in this narrow case
of course and one of those publishers
wanted students to actually run the
office programs being taught as opposed
to one of those simulations that is
tantamount to a hidden picture game that
is they didn't want students to have to
click the magic spots in the right order
and press the right key and presto the
flash based image to excel in the case
that you did the right thing
had you been interacting with the real
software this one publisher thought very
rationally that if you want to teach
someone to click on something in a menu
maybe actually letting them click on the
menu was superior but surely if you run
Excel how could you possibly evaluate
their work or prevent cheating several
companies declined to bid on this
request but one company bid and adesh
additionally submitted a proof of
concept that was the company that hired
me one deploy an online learning
management solution system something to
keep track of student IDs in enrollment
in course progress yadda yadda to deploy
a desktop application that spawns office
processes based on content downloaded
from the LMS like template documents
instructions etc 3 hire a bunch of
a-holes to write VBA scripts that check
document contents serialize those
through some esoteric net component
transmit them to the desktop app via the
LMS and submit grades based on the
scripts results they hired four of us
and absolutely no one knew what they
were doing I just happened to be really
good at not knowing what I was doing so
they gave me a salary and let me write
code for the next stupidly complicated
project that was that footnote so now
I'm gonna jump back to the place where
we were he said I won't go into detail
about the awesome utility project I
configured to first footnote here that
was a footnote but the important part
was that the work was Microsoft Office
programming and that's second footnote
here so I'm going to jump down because
like I said I felt like reading all the
stuff just so you get what people wrote
in and this was ms-office programming
footnote this could be handy for anyone
who foolishly wants to follow my method
of breaking into software if you wrangle
spreadsheets for a really for a living
you can become a programmer today all
office programs expose their files
through a document object model exactly
analogous to how the latest greatest
waiver of Xmas ECMO script which is
JavaScript exposes the hideous spec of
HTML for office it's an interface in a
language called Visual Basic for
applications and the code editor is
honestly pretty good and it's built into
every office product everything is also
reasonably well documented on MSDN and
anything that can be done through the
GUI can be done faster and better by
programming nowadays if your company has
a domain administrator who is competent
these features will be disabled
except for the most trusted computer
professionals because when code can be
freely emailed them around of a managers
and it runs automatically when a word
luck is opened that is a recipe for
virus reading it happens a lot but if
your company is not so well protected
also very common and you can find the
hidden menu option our key combination
that accra activates the macro editor
Google knows how you can learn to
program using only the standard cube
drone tools go nuts make 500 rows of
rule 30 in Excel it's great but also
clearly lame instead make a recursive 30
mais generation algorithm using cell
borders as walls if you exceed the stack
limit of 99 you will need to implement
your own stack but don't worry you have
virtually unlimited memory available in
the form of a spreadsheet
I learned this Fred sheet magic from my
physics professor who was a big fan of
doing electric field simulations in the
grid
he accidentally contributed more to a
computing career than my CFS professor
surprise surprise ok back up to the main
line all right let's see here it's hard
to jump back and forth I probably should
have done like a some kind of a in lines
them myself just a pre expansion all
right they needed macros they needed
them before the deadlines and all their
current engineers were dedicated to
finishing the project that would use
them as content and I had just spent the
previous years trying Microsoft Access
sorry tying Microsoft Access into
multiple other data sources and
producing procedural reports I wrote
scripts that populated spreadsheets for
me my work had to be usable by the 80
year old woman who did our accounting so
it was robust and reliable so I had the
right skill at the right time pure luck
however I can't end that this is that
that is true in all job searches rather
than saying step 1 learn Java step 2 get
paid to write Java the real goal is to
gradually increase software employable
experience you continuously gather
expertise and confident your ability
confidence in your ability to make
computers behave eventually a new
opportunity will pass by that allows you
to do more and learn more with software
and so a person bootstraps into becoming
a programmer it need not be a sudden
career switch at all regardless I was
very eager to career switch I had to
accept going from salary to hourly
though like I said I was laid off anyway
and I had to discuss with my spouse
about the implications of low income for
some time but obviously these are normal
job change concerns that should always
be part of a decision not something
special to software I knew that the
potential upside vastly outweighed the
temporary downside also it was such a
glowing opportunity I had to dive in I
should also note that I think it's very
important to not wait for the perfect
match opportunity to come by treat a job
as a challenge to be overcome expertise
is not required in order to be hired and
it certainly isn't required to stay
employed my co-workers that don't love
their job are perfect examples the only
requirement is that you are willing to
learn to solve the given set of problems
presented by the new job if people can
be hired after spending 12 weeks at some
ridiculous web dev bootcamp that
entailed ngi and ex nodejs
mano MongoDB and angularjs then a person
with real problem-solving skills can
certainly pick up the tech specific
stuff while on the job so never count
yourself out for lack of exact
experience
after that project they hired me onto
salary it was one of these a 16 li
trendy bespoke web project agencies as a
complete neophyte I was in heaven
every new WordPress deployment was a
chance to master some new aspect of
making Web Apps every person around me
was talented and wise and willing to
teach but best of all I was a
professional programmer I didn't set out
to become a master of the superficial
Internet and certainly and I certainly
don't think of myself that way now I am
a programmer who happens to know a lot
of minutiae about the HTTP protocol and
myriad other details that go into making
a web app I say this because I suspect
that amid the spectrum of programming
disciplines web is the most Craiglist
of them all I don't really know what he
means by that but here we go
idiots make shitty web pages and the
real programmers do X X is not a single
thing because all disciplines believe
theirs is the best or at least better
than web dev this isn't entirely untrue
programming for the web is close to the
bottom of the totem pole for a good
reason absolutely anyone can do it for a
reeving for a living
so absolutely anyone does and so lots of
poor skill can literally be found on
Craigslist for pennies on the dollar of
other software expertise so I guess
that's Craigslist in this case it's like
hireable on Craigslist I guess I was
never quite clear on that but you get
the idea but this does not mean that a
person who makes websites cannot develop
high level skills one now manager I know
was fond of describing programming in
the context of Zen in the art of
motorcycle maintenance any task can be
fulfilling if you pursue it to
excellence this is certainly true of web
dev regardless or of glory or status if
you are learning good skills it doesn't
matter what type of constraints you are
dealing with or how you arrive at good
programming fundamentals as confirmed by
experience do be sure to get diverse
ideas of what good means though isolated
study will only compound ugly solutions
into bad habits and you will develop
biases based on your environment this is
inevitable but none of that is a reason
to be picky about how to break into the
career because the specific job doesn't
set anything in stone and that cannot be
changed or overcome by effort after
about 6 months at the web project shop I
was offered the chance to make slot
machine software
I would be making games sort of mostly
in ogre 3d I haven't mentioned it until
now but I spent a lot of my spare time
making games before and after being
hired as a web dev third project
footnote so again here here's an
insertion from lower down in the text
making games footnote all the while I
was making better spreadsheets I was
also making games at home I'd become a
fan of XNA before it got to its
comically infamous state of vibrating
controllers and fart apps once that
reputation arrived I was sad because the
platform was such a beautiful dream
console games curated solely by peer
review no system like that existed
anywhere not even Android yet challenged
not even Android get challenged apples
gatekeeping of their device but you
could publish on to the 360 and no one
at Microsoft would try to keep you off
their proprietary platform absolutely
amazing
even today the most inclusive console
developer programs are still invite-only
or prohibitively expensive in my opinion
the crappiness of a lot of xbox arcade
titles was a testament to the excellence
of the framework design and it's
consequential ease of use any idiot
could and did make an Xbox game solely
by downloading a particular Visual
Studio add-on the tutorial content was
fantastic the framework itself was
opinionated just enough to trivially get
image images on the screen along with a
few other niceties like an asset
pipeline that could consume and draw a
few model formats and then he lists a
blog post here that I'll try to put up
as a reference if in the final post of
this that blog about how you can design
and a one-size-fits-all model class
spoilers you can't was written by the
lead of the project he was also a key
developer of allegro another game
framework of the past
he wrote excellent articles about how
software design works in support of
games I learned a lot from reading them
these days he leads a purely open-source
product at Microsoft which is still a
drawing library at and his writing is
still worthwhile because the framework
somehow was compatible with the Windows
Phone my one and only published mobile
title was on that platform it was pulled
three days later after copyright claim
that I couldn't afford to contest
cestlavie eventually I realized or I
guess c'est la vie I should actually use
my French pronunciation because
I did have to learn that in high school
sorry c'est la vie eventually I realized
that I didn't really want to chase the
indie success lottery or even break into
the traditional game dev discipline I'd
like to making boring old robust systems
and I was proud of software that worked
well I still occasionally bang out a
prototype confirm or deny that an idea
is fun but I don't hold on to the notion
that I might go that way professionally
I love to gather knowledge from experts
though the contrasts and similarities to
be drawn between other types of software
is really interesting and it helps me
frame my own professional efforts in a
lots of different ways which is
invaluable but in the end I don't love
video games enough anymore also getting
paid hourly for a short while was hard
with the mortgage and children this
post-mortem in particular made me
realize that starving for my art would
be impossible it was it's a link to
gamma Sutra unrest autumn August
post-mortem of the Kickstarter success
and again I'll try to post these links
into the video comments for people who
want to grab them alright so let's go
back up to the main line text which
that's okay so now we're back to talking
about the ogre 3d project this
opportunity was interesting because I
wanted to bolster my knowledge of C++ MC
I love the idea of game development and
I thought free tips trips to Las Vegas
was a cool perk so I read the ogre
manual and ace the interview I totally
sucked a C++ but they knew and but they
knew that and didn't care because I was
cheap and presumably I demonstrated
ability to learn on the job which was
all that really matters but I rejected
that offer I had a very uncomfortable
feeling that I would not learn much at
that place the lead dev half of my
interview the lead dev I guess for half
of my or the lead dev half of my
interview I guess he's talking about the
half of interview that was the lead
developer talking the lead dev half
mitred the lead dev half of my interview
didn't love programming which was just
weird to me I hadn't yet four of my
strong opinions about that quality and
being hired because of cheapness is
always dubious their office had an air
of sadness and the owner seemed like an
also they had strict policies of
not working from home
something about security concerns or
such which seemed ludicrous to me
perhaps I could have forced myself to
overcome all those obstacles but I'll
never know
instead I continued to learn to design
good database schema to transmit data
and well-defined structures and
frequently over a slothful medium and to
implement systems that could withstand
constant specification changes from
irrational customers CSS and JavaScript
for perpetual thorns in my side but I
did my best to study their best
practices and pass my reading through
the filter of software design ideals
after a time I saturated my ability to
learn while on that job and I left now I
use the last job skills to build a UI
that configures a proprietary file
system on top on top shell file server
appliance I am learning about more more
about block devices than I ever wanted
to know I can pick the brain of
developers who literally have punch card
stacks on their desks previously I
worked on the only previously I worked
on the only previously I worked on only
the trendiest of websites for seeking
out dog hotels near NASCAR tracks
programming careers are weird I
occasionally have regretted not getting
a formal education in computer science
but that education gap was almost
completely filled by the video game
lectures of Richard Buckland I'm sorry
by the video lectures of Richard
Buckland he is a faculty member at the
University of New South Wales
specializing in computer security he
also teaches a hell of a 101 series and
he gives the youtube link to that and a
102 and a 103 after the course of just
the lectures for the first-year students
not the assignments or lab work or
anything else my itch for formal
education was satisfied in addition to
being an exceptional teacher and a
thorough expert on basics he also frames
everything in terms of being happy with
your work being proud of how you spend
your life and perpetual learning he's
awesome and so then there's the
footnotes here that we already read and
then at the very end he just says abrupt
ending time to ship it that is the last
good software tip that I can think of
and he's referring of course to both
this this long story and the actual and
the actual story oh wait no did I jump
to the wrong place okay sorry I think I
jump to the wrong place I think that's
just the end actually I think that's
just the end I think
footnote actually goes with this thing
he's got separated here I think this
footnote goes with this and somehow am I
cut and paste put it in the right place
so never mind the abrupt ending part
save that for a second that's going to
come in
so the actual ending to Seth's thing is
just the that last line alright so
that's a very very lengthy story and
kind of goes into a lot of different
stuff but it definitely has sort of a
thing that I didn't hear talked about
very much in any of the other entries
which is just the idea of sort of like I
don't know what I want to want a cup of
like inch by inch in your way into
software development like basically just
saying taking any job you can that might
have some software room for doing
something with programming and keeping
broadening that definition out until you
eventually get to software development
right and most of the other entries that
I read really weren't that way they
started kind of they might have started
with a very entry-level position but
they weren't about like oh here's a job
that isn't supposed to be programming
but I figured out a way to do some
programming in it and convince my bosses
that was a good idea and I kind of like
broadened out from there that's kind of
an interesting technique and I don't
know how effective it would be you know
on a in a wider setting or you know how
oftentimes that could be made to work
but it is pretty interesting to hear
about it having worked once and it seems
like the kind of thing that could be a
potential thing that people could try as
a way of getting more programming into
their current job or taking a job where
they could do some more programming even
though it's not technically a
programming job as a way of building
that experience without needing to have
that experience first to get the job so
I thought that was pretty interesting
alright now I want to go to our last
story which is actually kind of it's I
guess I should say it's set up in a very
different way which is one of the
reasons that I wanted to do it in the
second episode as well it's set up kind
of as like a QA if that makes sense so
let me go ahead and
and read this entry this one's from jr.
Smith and he provided a Twitter handle
it's at underscore s q UI RR r LW ID e
so squirrel lied but there's underscores
beginning and 3 R's in squirrel which
normally there wouldn't be so if you
want to give a shout-out to him that's
the Twitter handle where you can do it
and he writes in though I did teach
myself a small amount of code and web
dev skills when I was younger I did not
begin life as a software developer in
earnest till I was 24 and I'm now 30 I'm
sharing my story in hopes that it can
provide some guidance to someone else
looking to make the switch if you have
further questions I can be reached at
and he gives those handles so he says
first stop briefly outlined my own
experience so that whoever reads this
can hopefully draw some parallels to
their own situation and better realize
how they can make the switch if that's
not interesting I'm posting things I
found helpful below that and so then he
just has a list here he says in middle
school in high school he taught taught
myself a little HTML CSS JavaScript
Visual Basic was not serious about it
college round one started as a CS major
wasn't sure it was what I want to do
switch to econ history joined Air Force
ROTC career in hamp
day before graduation told I was
medically disqualified for a few
delivery career no longer in hand day
after graduation
still feeling civic-minded worked worth
getting a Stafford job in the US
Congress got job one month before the
economy collapse in 2008 six months in
the first job not happy toying with
JavaScript when done with regular duties
life stuff wife then fiance started a
teaching gig I assume the role of
wedding planner that takes lots of time
post wedding much rejoicing time to get
serious about finding a job leverage
rusty web skills to get a front-end web
dev job at an agency Baltimore based
agencies stayed for a year asked for
more responsibility and more money got
neither moved on return to school
attended UMBC in the evenings starting
while at agency working ft and going to
school ft is tough but doable full-time
I think is what that means DC area based
hotel chain only programming job I
regret taking used IBM clear tools
Windows XP in 2012 and JSP pages these
are
you should run stayed less than a year
no real work was getting done seals
first Annapolis job agnostic about
Salesforce when I started turns out it's
rather dull but I did get my first
experience in what's considered the back
end of the stack which is very helpful
was let go as the newest person woodwork
dried out government contractor not
ideal but just purchased house shortly
before being let go
decided to stay here at least until
school finished and stay at a place
longer than a year site opportunities
lead capstone project for making a game
with Unreal worked with VR company
working with computer vision forestry
project doing Linux support InfoSec
startup work remote job isn't game Deb
but it's actually pretty awesome happy
to stay here while working games on my
nights and weekends and then there's
things says advice and Q&amp;A format and
that is the bulk of the entry and so
here is the QA that they wrote in
question what's the best way to start
learning answer most advice states pick
up an easy to learn language and go from
there I started by reading a C++ book
cover-to-cover to make sure I would
still find this all interesting before
making a switch don't worry about a
write language as it's almost always a
case of right tool for the job I found
it helpful to type code out of a book it
got me used to searching for typos
pasted errors whatever you do though
right actual code here's a list of
resources that I have found to be handy
interview view prep cracking the coding
interview programming questions dry
beyond belief but a good shortcut to
software engineering knowledge there's
even more painful than otherwise code
complete practical handbook I'm gonna
post the links to all these because he's
got the Amazon links about web usability
but a handful but a helpful way of
thinking about software design too for
instance you don't want to make API
difficult for co-workers or yourself a
few weeks removed to figure out and/or
to work with and he has don't make well
you know I should just read the complete
versions of these books because the
Amazon links that are cure don't
actually have the full titles and since
I don't know the full titles of some of
these books by heart I'm just going to
read them I'm just going to actually
open up the Amazon links here so I can
read the book titles as they actually
exist
on the actual covers so that people who
want to search for them who are
listening to this who maybe don't have
access to the links that will post with
them won't have trouble finding them
because there's actually quite a few of
them here okay let's take okay so like I
said the first one the interview prep
book is called cracking the coding
interview 189 programming questions and
solutions the DRI beyond belief but good
shortcuts are for engineering knowledge
that one is code complete a practical
handbook of software constructions
second edition the one about web
usability but helpful way of thinking
about software design - that one's
called don't make me think revisited a
common-sense approach to web usability
the the next one which I haven't read
yet is I haven't found a more
comprehensive game engine book and then
he lists Jason Gregory's game engine
architecture second edition jason
gregory by the way who was spoke at
handmade Comus year for those of you who
were there next ms don't become dogmatic
about patterns however it's useful to
see different ways of approaching
problems to expand your own mental tool
and then he lists game programming
patterns by robert nistrim then he said
i read the third edition but the review
suggests that this one is even better
and then he lists fundamentals of
computer graphics fourth edition by
Steve Mahre and Peter Shirley and then
he lists of nine books he says quark and
sometimes have blinders on when it comes
to the importance of top-tier schools
and startups however it tends to be
slightly better than Stack Overflow for
answering questions like what are the
strengths and weaknesses of these ten
databases or how do I learn about X or
other questions that would take a while
to pick up on your own and Cora he's
talking about course the website Cora
Adrian courage is I don't know how to
pronounce his name Co you are our eg es
does excellent breakdowns of how teams
achieve certain graphical effects this
is especially useful when you're not
even sure what to call the thing is that
you're looking at make sure to keep an
eye out for other game breakdowns from
him and that's a WEA DRI ANC
oh you are our age EES calm and this is
I'm assuming this is crowd double just
double check that I remember the name
right but yeah so this is a great
website because essentially what happens
here
is the person goes through and they
actually do like captures from the game
of like what was happening in DirectX or
OpenGL you know to look at actually what
happened for the game to produce the
rendered image that it produces and then
they go through and show all of these
sort of ripped apart pieces of the
pipeline so that you can really see how
a particular game does its rendering and
this is really great the only downside
is that there aren't that many of them
as you might imagine they take a while
but they're awesome so I would highly
recommend that looking at that side as
well anyway next questions question was
school helpful a or answer broadly
speaking yes
I wanted to make sure I had a solid CS
foundation and the only class I regret
not taking was compilers it is important
to note that some students thought their
education ended in the classroom this
could not be more wrong a degree is
useful in opening career doors ie
potential HR person looks at resume and
expects basic competency but your career
will ultimately be defined by the
challenge of the jobs you take and what
you teach yourself through products on
your own time if you're not school
inclined you can still meet your goals
but know that it will be much harder as
you will have to work much harder to
prove basic competencies but know this
after your first or maybe second job
most employers don't care where you got
your diploma or even if you have one
with the benefit of hindsight I would
say that the major benefit of a diploma
outside the education itself is the
smooth transition to a proven track
record what should I look for in my
first job answer regardless of field you
want to aim for a position that pushes
your capabilities outside of your
comfort zone if possible aim for a
smaller company on smaller teams devs
have to wear many hats you will be
forced to learn a lot more than you
would in a more specialized role for
your first position or two you really
want to aim for knowledge you really
want to aim for knowledge or salary
moreover once you have that proven
track-record salary negotiation
is much easier I'm not sure I understand
that exactly it sounds like you want to
aim for knowledge more so than salary
but maybe I'm not sure maybe I don't
really understand exactly what they're
saying but either way but everyone needs
to eat of course it's very likely that
your first job won't be your first pick
I found it helpful when making my peace
with that fact to come into a job with
sets of goals of what I wanted to
achieve then once a once a year I would
review those goals and if staying on
still made sense so this is kind of
interesting this this person is
basically saying instead of just looking
periodically to see whether I liked my
job or kind of waiting till alarm bells
went off in my head to see whether I
wanted to move they actually came up
with like what do I want from this job
as part of their taking the job and then
they would re-evaluate that periodically
which sounds pretty interesting
continuing for instance I knew I was
underpaid at my first gig but I also
knew it would be a good experience at a
way to get over that first tech job huh
once a year once a year had passed and I
wasn't seeking an increase in
responsibilities or my bottom line I
knew it was time to move on this pattern
makes sense very early in the career but
at some point you hit a salary level
where you're not going to make much more
we're not gonna make much more job
hopping that's when it becomes time to
focus on defining what you want to build
in your career but that's a good problem
to have question how did you navigate
job hunting answer my father repeated to
well two relevant things to me when I
was younger one everyone is in sales
into network network network I was
resistant to the first point but you
ultimately have to realize as I did that
a resume and interviews are ultimately
you pitching yourself to a company for
all software engineering disciplines I
suggest you follow Gale McDowell's
excellent resume advice here and this
pointer is to career cup.com so may its
CA re er CU p comm slash re s ume
formatting matters if you're sloppy on
your resume you give the impression that
you're sloppy in your work most jobs are
found through networking seventy percent
according to US News and World Cup for
my current job in some side gigs I found
all my past employment through
recruiters and that's often not ideal a
not an ideal situation for you
even good recruit
are interested more in drying ink hit up
local user groups job fairs and the like
be prepared for networking to happen in
unexpected places
as an example I found my current job
after the nicest note possible I was
hunting for jobs on Stack Overflow and
was one of the last two candidates out
of a 300 ish entry for a position we
were asked to make a quick presentation
on how we would architect a problem they
were tackling sidenote they asked that
we keep it brief so it wouldn't seem
like free work some potential employers
do this and you should avoid them they
went with the other candidate
she had one or two skills that I didn't
but my contact liked my presentation so
much that he offered to open up his
network to me which directly led to my
current gig so stay positive and
remember that rejections aren't personal
and that unknown now isn't a no forever
on a related note you'll see entry
listings asking for two to five years
experience two takeaways one this is
malarkey and usually written by clueless
people to the hidden a skier is that you
have a product to talk about that you
did of your own accord outside of a
classroom assignment two to five years
doesn't imply a salary position in terms
of scope remember that small and focused
is better question how did you handle
the stress of the transition answer this
cannot be said enough and I could stand
to be better at it myself but eat right
exercise and sleep there will be days
when this isn't possible and some days
you just need cake but you'll focus much
more easily if you're rested and don't
feel bloated and gross beyond that make
sure you plan some relaxation time my
wife and I try to get a half hour video
games in before bed this is both
relaxing and ensures we actually see
each other this may seem obvious but
make sure you spend some time with
family and friends it can be easy to
lose sight of the bigger picture when
focusing on a career transition if you
go back to school for CS as part of your
transition be kind to yourself schedule
wise I once took graphics AI operating
systems a computer architecture the same
semester while working a full time while
working full-time and buying my first
house there's always a trade-off between
getting something done faster versus a
less stressful but longer experience you
have to figure out which one works for
you but make sure you take breaks like a
weekend dedicated to not being
productive and just relaxing if you
choose the faster
option you have to do this you're also
likely to be on what to me you're also
likely going to be one of the older
students in the room it can totally feel
awkward but there's going to be other
older students I encountered other late
career switchers soldiers taking
advantage of the GI Bill and more try to
channel any awkward feelings you might
have into focusing on getting the work
done quickly and well questions how do
you handle feeling like your previous
career was a waste answer in most cases
you likely hone skills that are
absolutely transferable into your new
career this is especially true of some
of the soft skills like communicating
your ideas clearly taking feedback
experiencing taking a project to
completion and knowing when to admit
you're wrong early in my career
transition I was worried that the skills
I was developing as a front-end dev
wouldn't transfer the positions I wanted
to work at but to work towards admit at
least some of this was based off the
unfounded belief that front-end
development is somehow a less serious
discipline you will likely switch roles
a lot during career even if you like all
of those rules you should always look
for opportunities to apply previous
skills and knowledge moving forward in
my case working as a front-end dev honed
my ability to explain complex ideas
succinctly and clearly without losing
sight of the many small details
good luck working in a design heavy
field without that I have carried this
over to projects where I'm not working
on the front end and has been immensely
helpful I would say your experience is
definitely not without value even if it
wasn't in tech next question how do you
know if your career is headed in the
right direction answer I found it useful
to constantly reexamine my assumptions
and goals in my case I went back to
school determined to get a job in the
game industry my long-term goal was to
try and start my own company
my assumption was that working for a
studio would help accelerate me gaining
the knowledge I needed to go off on my
own however I kept reading post Morden's
mortems of people leaving triple-a
studios to start a small indie studio
which is affected my plan that mentioned
a few problems that caught my eye
many programs were focused in a narrow
aspect of the game so maybe my
expectation of learning a lot of
triple-a studio learning a lot at tribal
studio was not entirely correct moreover
I learned that many studios have
policies where any work you do on nights
and weekends becomes their IP while you
are their employee of course everyone
knows about this the crunch issue
however combine that with the commute
guaranteed to be over an hour and I
began to question when I would have time
to work on my own project I ultimately
was able to choose a new path to my goal
by asking what happens if I don't join
the game industry right away this was
hard for me to get over as I was pretty
attached the notion of making the
position before I turned 30 and I were
tribal but a goal nonetheless
however asking that question led to the
more important question of what do I
need to do to successfully start off on
my own I would need time to work on our
project on nights and weekends coding
experience and money saved up so that I
could finance the endeavor I decided
that I could better achieve these
requirements by not immediately
switching to the game industry to
sweeten the pot I work remote which
gives me back 10 plus hours a week
because Maryland traffic is not great I
definitely did not picture this change
in direction when I started maybe you
won't know what your long-term goals are
when you start and that's okay try out
several different kinds of projects read
up on current research watch different
GDC or SIGGRAPH or other sig conference
talks sometimes seeing what other people
are working on can help inspire some
ideas of your own question any last
thoughts answer what has helped me most
during the stressful times
was remembering that it was okay to not
like where I was at a career wise as
long as I liked where I was going and so
far it has been absolutely worth it 10
of 10 would make him noxious least
obnoxiously stressful career switch
again even if I had to face the same
challenges abrupt ending time to ship it
that is the last good software tip I can
think of and again that's from squirrel
ID underscore s q SS q UI RRR elw IDE
and that's from jr. Smith so I believe
that's all the entries that I received
I've now read all of them and you've
heard everything that I've heard that
that people wrote in and had to say and
hopefully that gave you a pretty broad
sort of you know set of experiences many
of which are have a lot of different
aspects to it most of the people who
wrote in actually came from different
disciplines which I thought was really
interesting there wasn't like one
particular way that people sort of got
into the software engineering and that
sort of thing
there wasn't one particular place that
they were all coming from there was just
a lot of different
original careers that people made the
move from so again this video along with
the previous video should hopefully give
you a wide set of different voices
different people who came from different
places and had different ways of talking
about what they did hopefully some thing
in there or the entire set taken
together will be useful to folks who are
trying to make this transition I am
going to take a quick break now and then
I'm going to do sort of basically the
third video in this series which is just
a very very brief discussion of sort of
stuff related to this that was based on
sort of my takeaways from it