okay hello everyone and welcome to the
stream I did sort of a thing we've never
done before which is I had had some
folks who had written in and this had
happened sort of multiple times
throughout the course of running
handmade here oh I've had people who
rode in and asked me a very specific
question they're several different
people asked the same exact question and
it was what advice do you have or what
is it like to change careers from what
I'm doing now to something like what you
show on handmade hero like you know I
want to go from career X to doing sort
of low-level programming or programming
in general as a career and you know I I
can only assume that the reason that
this question was asked of me is just
because it happens to be a fairly public
sort of stream for programming because
obviously I have no idea right I've been
programming for so long and I never
switched careers I don't really know the
answer to that question but I suspected
that the reason that I was getting this
question is because there weren't enough
sort of accessible materials out there
for people who wanted to go this rat so
after I'd gotten this question several
times I just like what can we do to help
give these folks an answer because I
can't answer them I have literally
nothing useful to say I'm like the worst
person to ask about this any advice I
have is probably wrong it's certainly
uneducated and not backed up by an
experience so I don't want to like
respond and say here's some advice that
and have them get steered totally down
the wrong path so what I did is I just
posted on Twitter and I said hey you
know I've been getting this question a
lot I suspect that there's a lot of
people out there who know the answer or
I mean you know the answer is probably
the wrong way to look at it right the
answer probably different from it for
everybody but who have a personal answer
who've had a personal experience with
this who have changed careers either it
went well or it went poorly they learn
thing from it - they have advice that
they'd like to pass along they you know
even just wanna to share maybe a story
that would help other people who are in
this position feel more comfortable with
their decision or give them things to
think about so I just kind of asked it
broadly and said you know anything you
want to write in you know write in and
let me know and I'll put them together
into you know sort of one big corpus
that we can put out there and that way
people who are interested in this
question can take a look and have sort
of a much better answer than I could
have given and the response was
fantastic I had many many people write
in and they wrote in sort of
impressively long stories to like really
good complete stories and so I just
figured the best thing to do at least as
a start was just to read them because I
think they're kind of great and we could
put this up as a video for reference
that people can look at when they're
thinking about this just to give them
things fuel and I could put up an audio
version if they want to listen to it as
a podcast for example but I I think it's
like it's just a lot of great
information here just for people who are
considering this sort of thing so
without further ado I would just like to
say thank you very sincerely to everyone
who took the time to write in because
none of this would be possible without
so many kind folks taking the time to
write it up I know that it's nobody's
favorite thing to take a bunch of time
to write a bunch of stuff about their
personal life I mean it takes time and
it's like you know it's reflective and
difficult and so you know a very
heartfelt thank-you goes out to everyone
who took the time to to share with us
and if anyone who watches this would
like to share similar stories we can
probably organize a good way to do that
I will try to post in the links to this
on youtube a reference where you can go
ahead and discuss this more so if you're
someone who found out about this only
after the video was already done you
could use use that contact information
to sort of get in touch and
share your stories and maybe we can kind
of keep this going as things go alright
so let's get started here the first one
I'm gonna read is actually the last one
I received and I'm gonna start off with
it because it's someone I know it's
someone I've met in person they came to
our conference both times actually
regretfully I didn't get a chance to
talk with them this time
but the first conference I did and this
comes from Andrew ah Stav and one of the
things that when people Brodie and I
said let me know if you want this to be
attributed to you or whether you'd like
to remain anonymous and so I'll be
giving the contact information for
people who wanted to be attributed and
I'll just be you know saying it on a
miss for those who didn't but this one
comes from Andrew ah stuff and he gave
his contact information
tiny construct on Twitter it's at TI NYC
o NS TR u CT give him a follower say hi
if you liked this story and he says hi
everyone my name is Andrew ah stop I'm
30 and I'll be graduating with a BS in
computer science in the fall of 2017
when I was seven or so I started
plunking around with some flavor of
basic and experimented with a few
languages and purpose-built engines as I
got older but living in rural
pre-internet Minnesota definitely
affected how much I learned my parents
knew how important computers were
becoming and we always owned a decent
machine so in many ways I was extremely
lucky on the other hand I didn't know
any programmers we didn't get dial-up
internet till I was 12 and our small
town was a two-hour drive from the
nearest bookstore and I just interject
here this is very similar to the way I
grew up I and I think one of the things
that I have always been very fortunate
to say is that my father was a
programmer so I did actually know
someone but it's important to kind of
keep in perspective here depending on
how old you are if you're like me you
maybe didn't grow up at a time when you
had access these things so anyway a nerd
continues maybe worse well I wasn't
great at math and still wouldn't say I
am during my senior year of high school
a friend basically taught our class
precalculus because a temporary teacher
didn't understand
the material and that more or less
describes how well organized our schools
math department was you're probably
beginning to see why I think internet
access and online resources are so
important to say nothing of communities
that happily accept beginners so I
stayed away from serious programming for
a few reasons and got a degree in
journalism to abbreviate that history
let's just say the era of quote-unquote
should our newspaper have a twitter
account was not the best time to go into
that field and I don't know that it's
gotten any better after four years I was
a little burnt out and was ready to move
when my now wife graduated from her
master's program with a job offer I
started digging into courses that put
all of their materials online like mi
t--'s cs50 which is mostly taught in C
I'd always enjoyed learning more about
how computers actually function so that
was great this got me thinking about
maybe going back to school or just
buying a bunch of books with the goal of
getting hired as an entry-level
programmer somewhere in Minneapolis
doing basically anything because
basically anything would be more fun and
pay better than my previous job I still
loved games but still had no perspective
on how they were made
then handmade hero started up I'd only
ever heard people describe low-level
programming as too complicated for games
which is obviously crazy and seeing
someone doing it was definitely a
wake-up call so I said hey there's
always more loans and started burning
through Khan Academy math videos after
signing up to take some intro
programming courses and calculus one
since then I've taken both great and
terrible classes but the University of
Minnesota parenthesis Twin Cities CS
program seems pretty good overall
everyone has to do C programming an
assembly reading between classes on its
operating systems and machine
architecture I've learned math that I
would have struggled with if I'd had to
teach myself and I've only had one
required class that's really hard about
modern software development it's a large
school but I have been surprised at the
number of people my age who are in the
program there's always more to learn and
I've got a long way to go but I think we
all know how getting good computers to
how getting computers to do their
freakin job can feel the expense sucks
and it's frequently humbling to be peers
to 20 year olds but every day
practicing something I enjoy instead of
pounding away at something I hate and
I'm already decent at I definitely
recommend the former best regards and
restof again he's tiny construct on
Twitter so that's a pretty good I would
say story about Pete you know about
being in the process of switching
careers which is sort of exactly the
position that I think a lot of people
are in right now I heard from some folks
who said I don't have a story to story
to share yet because I'm kind of just in
the middle of switching but I'm really
interested to hear what other people's
experiences are Andrew wrote in and gave
us kind of the Midway experience right
he's still going to university for it
and he you know obviously hopes to make
the transition I'm assuming from
university to working in either the game
industry or some other programming
industry and honestly like I feel like
he's probably going to have a lot of
success at that I've obviously I said I
know him and I've talked to him before
and I've seen him on the twitch chat a
lot of times and he seems to know what
he's doing so I think he's probably
gonna have pretty good luck at that but
that's a pretty typical story I think
also from a lot of people that I've
heard where it's like hey you know I I
kind of knew that my current career
wasn't working for me for whatever
reason and I wanted to switch so I just
like found some things to grab onto
right like you know things online that
that seemed to stick and then I just
decided to take the plunge and now I'm
you know I'm going for it
so obviously I wish him all the best of
luck and he's someone that I know
personally now so I will certainly be
keeping in touch with him and seeing how
it goes the rest of our stories are from
folks who have kind of been either
finished the transition and it went well
or finished a musician and it didn't go
well and so now we'll move in to some of
those so this this next one is actually
was submitted and honestly and it's from
someone who was in the sciences and was
it was a little younger in life so they
were in sort of university for the
sciences around 23 years old when they
decided to switch so I thought I'd start
out with this one and then there's one
that I'll pair it with afterwards so
here's that story
again this one's not attributed so my
story starts off as a biochemistry
student in Canada on track to do
medicine and it's continuing now as a
programmer working at Ubisoft
essentially there came a point in my
life around 23 years old where for the
first time I seriously sat down to
answer the question what would I truly
enjoy waking up and doing every day
video games have always been a big part
of my life and so with only one life to
live I made the commitment to make video
games for a living
this was easily the biggest and hardest
step and so they're kind of saying here
that the toughest part of this journey
if you will is just the decision to
actually do it which i think is probably
true for a lot of people because while
everything is hard work in making a
transition deciding that you really want
to do it is obviously something that
takes a lot of courage as well as
reflection I think anyway they continue
from here it's easy once you know what
you want just add work I knew where I
was I knew where I wanted to get to so I
asked the question what are the exact
things I need to do in order to get from
here to there and then I went out and
did exactly those things there's no
magic here just work every night after
my day job and every weekend so he
listed these kind of an order number one
for about two months
I read the following books cover to
cover the C programming language second
edition by Kernighan and Ritchie this is
the K NRC book for those of you don't
know it introduction to algorithms by
cormen leiserson rivest and stein or
CLRS and operating system concepts by
Silver shots Galvin and Gagne step two
for one month I trained for the coding
interview by doing every question in the
standard interview books every new grad
program are looking to get a job at
Google Facebook etc has done these it
was hugely important in gaining
confidence knowing I was on the right
track applying knowledge I had acquired
from reading too many problems and
identified my weak areas and these books
were cracking the code interview fourth
edition by Lachman elements of
programming interviews by Aziz Prakash
and Lee and then he just had a website
which is project Euler net PR oj ec t e
UL e r dotnet step three I did
coating interview with a Silicon Valley
tech exec isolated from any software
people it was so great to finally step
out of the dark and get real feedback
from someone who had interviewed many
many programmers before was hugely
important in feeling and he says feeling
I couldn't compete I'm not sure if he
means I could compete or couldn't
compete I read this entry fairly
carefully and it sounds like maybe he
did actually mean couldn't compete
because it kind of goes through you know
a failure and a success here in in a
minute so you'll have to forgive the
ambiguity there I'm not sure but anyway
step number four for two months I
applied to Google even my closest
friends don't know this I didn't get an
offer no excuses no way to sugarcoat it
failure really sucks and it is
humiliating
I kept the Google visitor pass on my
wall for over a year to constantly
remind me of that feeling I reluctantly
include this point for four reasons
first after only a few months the above
training actually does prepare you very
well for algorithm OS and computer
architecture questions next it does not
help you answer software design
questions next doing these all-day
on-site interviews is very different
than sitting at your desk thinking and
problem solving under pressure and time
constraint is hard and finally when you
fail you still wake up the next day now
I would just like to interject here that
I cannot agree more with what he just
said and I guess what I would say here
is I I have been through a similar
process sort of like I the first
experience I ever had sort of with
outside programmers was interviewing at
Microsoft for an internship and it is
very very different and very unnerving
to be put in that situation it's also
where you kind of have these problems
turn at you you're not used to this
environment you're not used to problem
solving this way under pressure like
that it's also one of the reasons that
I've very very often loudly criticized
on our stream this interview process in
particular because not only do I think
it's not a good interview process for
experienced programmers but I also think
it's particularly off-putting and
particularly difficult for novices and I
think that means you don't get a very
picture of novices actual ability now I
like I said this was an anonymous
submitted story I have no idea what this
person's qualifications were at the time
and I'm not saying that they should or
should not have gotten a job or anything
like that but I just want to underscore
the fact that these interview processes
that are very adversarial and sort of
like pressure oriented that a lot of
tech companies do these days have never
felt comfortable to me and I do not like
them and so I want to really say you
know yep
take to heart what that person said that
it's a very difficult and challenging
experience definitely try to prepare a
psychological you can for it I apologize
on behalf of our entire industry for
these it's certainly never an interview
that I would ever consent to giving but
it is unfortunately reality at a lot of
the entry-level positions that you will
have to try for if you want to get into
an industry they unfortunately do things
this way and it is very stressful and it
is humiliating it's set up to be
humiliating if you fail unfortunately
perhaps not intentionally on the part of
the companies but it really is difficult
and so yes again I am sorry for that
that's not so I really wish that was
something that this industry would
change it's not the kind of interview I
would ever be okay giving and I really
don't like the way it probably makes
people feel when they fail them or even
when they succeed to be honest you may
do very well more and you will still
feel bad it will leave a bad feeling to
you and and I wish that that was
something that we would change but
that's a topic for another day
continuing on step 5
I watched handmade hero everything I'd
learned to date was just a piece in the
orchestra OS concepts on percussion
algorithms the brass math on piano and
si played the strings I like this
analogy handmade hero however was the
maestro
it brought all these instruments
together to try and teach me how to
program watching a professional
programmer think through each step show
the process encounter problems
contemplate and rationalized solutions
all on a straightforward no BS way it
has been an irreplaceable education it
also fast tracked me down what I now
perceive to be the right way to design
software a skill I was sorely missing
I'm confident in saying watching
handmade here was a single most
important action I took
and here's the single biggest reason I
managed to realize my original goal
thank you very much for that praise I
probably don't deserve it but number six
I started my own HMH inspired projects
it's one thing watching KC work through
encountering a problem it's another when
you have to solve it yourself especially
if down the line you find out it wasn't
a good idea those lessons stick I wrote
a lot a lot of really bad code to start
perhaps my co-workers still think this
and I would say again I really agree
with everything that's in this story
basically the amount of bad code I've
written in my life is I can't even
fathom how much it is I still write bad
code today on the road to good code and
the the hope is always that you have
enough time to get to go code sometimes
you don't and the bad code ships but
there is no substitute for writing a lot
of bad code if you want to become a good
coder it's very analogous I think to
almost every other sort of trade skill
that I know of you don't get to be a
great artist without drawing a lot of
really bad drawings you don't get to be
a great musician without playing a lot
of horrible sounding notes from your
instruments and the same is true of code
you just don't get to be a good coder
without writing a lot of really bad code
it's just the nature of it and so I
think that's really good advice to take
to heart okay finishing up this story
they say that's it roughly a year after
picking up King RC I interviewed and got
a job doing gameplay programming at
Ubisoft jumping into triple-a
development on large team sizes spread
across the globe with massive massive 20
plus year old code bases is a totally
different learning experience and
frankly it has been hard the biggest
skill I've had to learn is how to sift
through and read foreign code and try to
understand different systems written by
different people at different times
potentially on different projects as a
caveat the type of programming thinking
and problems encountered at larger
companies is for my limited experience
very different than you see on handmade
hero it's less about solving the actual
problem and I agree with this
wholeheartedly on handmade hero I try to
teach very sane straightforward
programming practices a lot of times on
a lot of projects you will not have that
that fortunate experience a lot of times
things
very overcomplicated very overweight
very large and unwieldy and that is
something that I don't think really
anything can prepare you for other than
just having to do it it's unfortunate
it's not very satisfying to to have to
wade into things like that but the truth
is that no matter where you go
Ubisoft not being some kind of exception
to this but rather the rule everywhere
you go the code bases are what has been
able to work and what's been able to
manage and it is often the times that
they are not going to be perfect clean
gems of wonder they're just going to be
very large and very healty a lot of the
times and it is our job as software
engineers to figure out how to make them
better every day and that's just the
truth right so that's that's how it goes
anyway concluding currently I'm really
trying to focus on my own game and
overall trying to get better every day
have a long way to go I still study
every weekend that's the story I hope it
provides some contemplating switching
with a real example from A to Z to
reiterate what I started with the
hardest part was just committing to the
goal after that it was just keeping my
head down and putting in the work no
magic other recommended books they just
as the final thing they said linkers and
loaders by Jay Levine and linear algebra
gen right by Axler so there you go
that's a really good success story too I
suspect a lot of people would be pretty
happy to get their their first job at
some place as prominent as Ubisoft
obviously makes a lot of games
Assassin's Creed for example watchdogs
etc that are pretty famous so
congratulations on such a successful
transition and I hope you continue to
have a fulfilling career in the game
industry yeah and thanks so much for
sharing your story now let's move to
somebody who also started in the
sciences to remember that last story was
was starting in the sciences in
university let's look at a fella who
switched from the sciences at a later
time so this one comes from Eric / - on
Twitter they are e RI k PE RT tu and
there it in with this story I have
always used computers in one way or
another mostly due to me being very much
into playing
we got our first computer in our
household in the early 90s if I remember
correctly it was an Intel I 46 SX 25
megahertz with 2 or 4 megabytes of RAM
and a 120 megabyte hard drive this was
not my first computer I'm sorry this was
not the first computer we had in our
home though due to my dad's line of work
occasionally we would have a Toshiba T
3100 that he would bring home and on
that one he had Tetris most of my early
computer years was spent playing games
it was my dad who introduced me to
Wolfenstein 3d he mentioned that on the
computer at his work there was a game
where you would go around with a gun and
shoot Nazis the way he described it to
me really piqued my interest whatever
this game he was talking about was I had
to get in on that it sounded amazing
after I had played that game on his work
computer I somehow got a hold of the
shareware version of will 3d and could
play it at the computer at home I
started to subscribe to gaming magazines
and you would get a shareware disc every
month with new games on it fast forward
a couple of years at around 1994 we got
Internet which at the same time which at
the time was very early for the part of
Sweden where I grew up that's the first
time I tried online gaming which was
something new to me after high school in
the early 2000s I started studying for
my engineering degree in college looking
back now I probably should have went
with a computer science degree I looked
at that computer science programs but
they seemed to be so difficult because
of the math involved which is actually
kind of a surprising statement if I may
interject for a second I am surprised to
hear that an engineering degree has less
stringent math requirements than a
computer science degree but I never went
to university so I guess I I don't know
I always thought of engineering like you
know general mechanical engineering or
stuff like that is happening sort of
more rigorous math demands but then
again that's sort of looking more at
just what I thought University in the US
would have certainly I don't know about
what universities in Sweden would have
and also I I don't never sure because I
never went so anyway I looked at the
computer science programs but they seem
to be so difficult because the math
involved in engineering there was math
and physics but there were also a lot of
other classes that did not involve so
much logical thinking I had struggled
with math for most of my life and did
not think that I would be
able to finish all the math logical type
thinking classes that were necessary for
a computer science degree okay
first engineering job I finished college
in late 2006 and got my first
engineering job in 2007 I started
working as a development engineer for a
pharmaceutical company outside Stockholm
after about two years after around two
and a half years I was extremely fed up
with the slow process in getting
anything done due to the nature of
pharmaceuticals which if it's anything
like it is in the US I'll just interject
I can imagine how tedious that is
continuing it could take weeks and
months to get anything approved because
it had to go through several different
departments and offices this was also
around the time for the 2009 global
financial crisis so a lot of the
projects that were supposed to be done
never took off the products I was
supposed to do were put on ice and me
and my boss decided that it was probably
better if I left and started to look for
another opportunity I was not enjoying
anything at work and the things that was
hard to do were not there anymore and so
now the switch I left my engineering job
in late 2009 and started to look for a
new job due to the global financial
crisis that was in full swing by this
point there were not a whole lot of
engineering jobs for me to apply to I
was unemployed for several months but I
had friends working in the IT field in
Stockholm a couple of them were thinking
about starting up a small web company
and mentioned that if I learned
programming I could get an entry-level
position at the company they were about
to start in 2010 at 28 years old I
started to study a two-year college
course called agile web developer at a
pyrotechnic Vik goal school in Stockholm
I have no idea what a pyro Technical
School is but I truly hope that is
exactly what it sounds like
which is like a school where you learn
to light things on fire
that is the best name I've ever heard
pyrotechnical I'm sure that's not what
it means I'm sure it actually means
something like you know vocationally
oriented or something like this but the
phrase pyrotechnical sounds so cool ok
sorry anyway the frustration starts
switching careers so late was not easy
even if I had studied my fair share of
math earlier in college I was badly
prepared for the
complex thinking that is needed for
programming I had not used a whole lot
of my math logical knowledge up to that
point and it was several years ago since
I had studied the subjects that would
have helped me I remember having a very
hard time getting back into the way of
abstract thinking and it took a very
long time before I could visualize code
in my head I was also a bit jealous at
other people studying who seemed to
understand everything the first time a
new topic came up I talked to these
students and most of them had some prior
programming knowledge or had grown up in
a home where a sibling or parent was
working with programming this gave them
a huge edge they would understand
concepts in the terminology because they
had heard or seen it before but for me
it was something completely new and now
the next section they said was called
struggling with my programming
vocabulary which I've never really
thought about this too much but I can
imagine program vocabulary must be a
nightmare for people who aren't used to
it because there's so many weird terms
that we throw around that people are
just supposed to do and they're totally
forward weird they don't even
necessarily imply what they actually
mean so anyway he continues I struggled
a lot with finding words for what it was
I wanted to do in the beginning even the
simplest things were confusing to me if
I have a list and inside this list there
is another list how do I get access to
the inner list I know or at least I
think I know this can be done but what
is it called what word should I use when
I try to find information about it
online these things never seem to be a
problem for people with prior
programming knowledge they knew what
words to use and where to find this
information the tips I got from
experienced programmers at the time were
usually something along the lines of why
don't you just visit the page that
contains the manual for the language
from framework you're using that in
itself is not bad advice for me but it
really didn't help that much because I
still didn't know the word that I was
looking for I ended up having to ask
people and with my own words trying to
describe what it was I wanted to do
slowly my programming vocabulary started
to grow and I found myself getting
better and better at actually finding
what I was looking for now here's a
section on resources that helped I do
not have any specific books or websites
that I can recommend I can however give
some advice on when selecting resource
sorry I can't however give some advice
for when selecting a resource some
things you can learn from that in the
beginning everything and anything that
was related to programming because I had
no previous knowledge or experience I
really had no way of doing things that
meant that I had no preconceived notion
about what was right or what was wrong
so anything I read or learned was
something new and exciting however after
a while you start to develop your own
way of doing things you get an opinion
of what's right and what's wrong and if
you have friends at work as programmers
you will take a lot of their opinions as
facts I personally do not see that as a
problem when you are learning something
new but you will all have to start
researching a bit on your own not just
accept everything everyone says and as
soon as you do not understand a concept
or word look it up and read about it
depending on the language you are
learning there are good and bad
resources if you are learning a language
that is very popular you have to be more
careful when selecting learning
resources I made the mistake of taking
the first accepted answer on
stackoverflow.com several times at the
beginning and I feel like this is
probably a very common pitfall these
days because as a beginning programmers
sorry to interject again I feel like
people would have no idea sometimes the
answer on the top of Stack Overflow is
good sometimes it's awful and how would
you know right well you know is there
something that looks like an
authoritative resource and here it is
you don't have any way to evaluate
whether you think it might be right or
wrong and experts in the field don't
necessarily do a very good job of
policing these things not to mention the
fact that there's arguments among
experts about what is or was is not
right ways of doing things so that can
be very daunting I would imagine for
someone just trying to learn anyway
continuing and sadly I started doing
things in a bad sloppy way I later
noticed that I would also have to check
the date on the answer to see if it was
still relevant and answer from two years
ago might not be the correct waited for
you to do things today before anyone
decides to start reading a book about
programming start by checking the
reviews for the book to see if it is a
good resource there are so many books
out there today and not all of them
should be read or recommended is the
book up to date if it's about a
framework make sure it's at about the
version you will actually be using is
the book ding that your skill level
there are plenty of programming books
and they usually say what skill level
they expect you to have before you start
reading it I hope my story will I hope
my story will have given people some
information about some of the problems
of solutions
they were run into and again that's from
Eric / 2 e e RI k PE r TT you on Twitter
thanks very much for writing it now
let's move on to somebody who switched
from a totally non-technical field I
mean it I guess that's not entirely true
these days because almost every field
has technical aspects to it you know if
you are an artist or a you know musician
or a schoolteacher or anything that
might sound non-technical if it was 50
years ago honestly there's text all over
the place so to the degree to which it
is technical probably actually has a lot
to do with the particular place that
you're doing that thing or the
particular variant of that thing that
you're doing so when I say non-technical
I don't really mean that technically so
if I just mean not a field which is
specifically engineering let's say so
this comes from Christian Flores and
this is you can find them on twitter at
cfl o is AMD and they write in hello
casey here is my experience of switching
careers into software engineering later
in life my experience with going into
soft development as a professional later
in life is somewhat unique because i
started programming quite early in high
school and even got a computer science
degree in university i wanted to make
games with a hot bomb with a couple of
good friends of mine and we did one of
my friends was a good artist but we had
no one to tackle audio i had always had
an interest in music so i took it upon
myself to be the audio guy long story
short i became very excited about
writing music for games and film as a
career and so I stayed in university for
another six years to take bachelor's and
master's degrees in music the following
two years were spent trying to get jobs
of composer and sound designer for indie
films and games with mixed success one
thing that became clear as I pursued
game jobs was the importance of audio
implementation when it comes to game
audio this revelation brought me back to
my roots as a programmer and he can
perfectly honest the realization that I
had always been a better programmer than
a composer my first order of business
was picking up the audio programming
book by bulan sure and Lazzarini the
book even contained a short primer or
refresher in my case on C and I was
amazed at how fast
was able to recall so many things from
my programming days which was now about
eight years past crucial to me getting
back up to speed on programming was just
driving in and writing things in this
case it was audio plugins and I wasted
no time in writing a handful of plugins
in both VST which is for Steinberg and
au which is for Apple formats but no
less important were the many online
resources and communities that I sought
help from when I needed it including
forums on DSP plug-in development
websites blogs and published papers it
was a big boost to my confidence and
satisfaction to build projects from the
ground up that I could then release
however small they were at first
furthermore I stayed away from any
third-party framework used to build
plugins like ju c e synth edit j plug
etcetera and i firmly believe that this
is an important part of learning where
those libraries may have had a place
building all my projects from scratch
really helped me learn the fundamentals
of interacting with an sdk such as VST
and au at a lower level and sharpening
my debugging and troubleshooting skills
and i would just jump in here and
interject and say that is absolutely one
of the core principles on handmade hero
as well is that it's not so much that
libraries and frameworks and these sorts
of things are bad they may be very
useful to you and they may be important
part of your job it's more that it's
very important to learn the fundamentals
and if the fundamentals are already
always being taken care of for you by
one of these frameworks or libraries
then you never get a chance to learn
them and so I think it's really
important in any programmers career at
some point to take it upon themselves to
do some low-level work if for no other
reason than educational right it doesn't
have to be huge but just something I
think it makes a huge difference in your
skill level as a programmer to gain that
understanding all right
sorry for the interruption continuing on
I was also fortunate enough to have met
several like-minded people along the way
with ideas for building plugins and
other applications some are more
fruitful than others but I don't regret
taking on any of the opportunities that
came my way I ended up working with a
sound designer for a little over a year
building audio tools in unity for him to
use in the games he worked on unity had
notoriously bad audio support prior to
version 5 and still there audio engine
is far from acceptable in my opinion
a couple of other collaborations led to
some iOS apps which then led to my
career my current full-time professional
job as an iOS developer at a company
looking back I am very happy to have
come back around to software development
after a little detour to music I feel
much more confident in what I can do as
a programmer than I ever did as a
musician I love building things I love
the feeling of solving problems one of
the more daunting thing is I found
facing me when I got back into software
development was the sheer vastness of
resources and options so it really
helped to focus on something specific
that I enjoyed and found very
interesting and that kept me engaged
through the relearning process Cheers
Christian fluent and again that's CFL oh
is AMD on Twitter and again I apologize
to anyone for mispronouncing the name
most folks did not send into
pronunciation so I'm probably going to
get some of them wrong and I sincerely
apologize for that upfront okay now
let's go to a special treat I really
want to thank and personally from
reading and this is from somebody who I
actually know there in the Seattle area
his name's max Leon E and it's a really
special treat because this is from
somebody who is very prominent in
software development actually as you'll
find out as we go through their story
and was also very prominent in another
field and so I feel like it was really
just a really wonderful thing I know
they're very very busy all the time so
it was a really wonderful for them to
take the time to write in thank you so
much for doing so I imagine a lot of
people will obviously have just a
tremendous amount to gain from from from
what you have to say so this one's from
Max Leon E and he writes in hi Casey so
here is my story my name is max Ayane
and I worked at Pixar animation studio
as the senior lead software engineer for
render man but it was not always like
this changing career and embracing
software engineering later in life is
like changing culture or moving to a
different country I know this because I
have done both more than once actually
the change brings both positives and
negatives at the beginning you find
yourself in a different territory with
different dynamics establishments laws
and even inside jokes that you don't get
you are mature and have
lots to offer in other domains of
knowledge but you are just learning how
to write code and if there is something
that coders take very seriously it is
the code on the one hand you may find
new truths in there in the other you can
find yourself in a house of cards and
unnecessary fabricated reality that your
colors truly believe in you may buy into
it or not it is up to you just do not
underestimate the value of the different
perspective you can bring and just
interject for a second I think that's
really true one of the probably most
valuable things that a person who's
changed careers can bring to software
development is you've had a career
outside software development right and a
lot of people such as myself who are in
soft development don't know anything
else and we don't have that kind of
perspective that people from outside can
bring and that can be extraordinarily
valuable to a team or to the industry in
general when someone decides who did
something else for a living
to come in and sort of bring that
perspective so it is a truly valuable
advice I think to not let that get lost
programmers can be very abrasive
obviously we can be not the nicest
people that may just kind of go with the
territory sometimes don't let that
abrasiveness convince you not to show
your experience you know push back on us
and be like hey you know I think we
could be doing this better share that
insight and don't let people divert you
from that because that may end up being
one of the most important things you can
bring to the job is a fresh perspective
that really could change the way that
something's being done at the place that
you end up going to work and I think
that is a really really true thing
continuing with Max's story when I was a
young fellow I liked art science and
technology computers weren't ubiquitous
like today and I couldn't see a career
in software engineering my first close
encounter of computers was with the
Commodore 64
I surely punched in a few lines of basic
and played with logo but I did not see
it as a purpose later in my teen years I
had a coding class of Pascal it was easy
and natural to me but again what would I
use it for it was a bit like mathematics
in high school how many of you have
asked yourself the question what do I
need this for and I can't inject an I
would add myself to people who asked
question sometime on stream we should
talk about that because it is definitely
true
moving on in the early 90s I discovered
computer graphics I started working as a
cg artist just out of high school
computers were the tools software was
something that somebody else wrote my
life was made of techniques to define
colors and shapes while I was thinking
about composition and the psychology
behind it after a few years I got pretty
good at it up to some point when the
limitations of software I had began to
hold me as an artist
I knew that software engineering was the
mysterious thing that I glimpsed at when
I was younger I also knew that the
problems I was facing were presenting
themselves in the form of software or
the lack thereof I took a step back
bought a C++ book and read it with the
guidance of a friend if I could write
the suffering he did there was an answer
whether that is a render farm scheduler
or a new shader or subdivision services
for my favorite digital content creation
application if I learn how to code a
solution my problem I could produce
better art this in contrast to my first
encounter coding this had a clear
purpose I dusted off my math and physics
and kept studying how to write code
better codes lower level code how to
optimize it how the hardware works
certainly commercial software was
getting better and better
trumping some of my earlier solutions
but the more I progressed as an artist
the more I faced different harder
problems this duality of artists
engineer went on for over a decade I
have moved between several Studios
mostly working as an artist as a leading
artist as a supervising artist but
crossing the background was the
persistence of problems to solve and
they were getting bigger and bigger as
my level responsibilities was grilling
at some point I realized that what Beth
I had to offer was not my artistry but
my ability to understand software and
engineering from an artists perspective
or conversely how to formulate a user
need in terms of engineering during
production of the lego movie we reached
one of those crisis points that required
extreme solutions
I left my well-established artistic
career and started writing software
full-time I had to create a whole new
production path tracer renderer for the
movie as soon as that may seem that was
the only way out and I knew there was no
going back that was my departure so I
did it I knew exactly what I needed what
my users needed and I could cut through
the design process
the solution and save the production
literally and that's the kind of story
that I kind of feel like it would be
great to hear the whole story of and I
wonder maybe if max would be willing to
come on the show at some point and share
with us that story because it sounds
amazing actually but I'll simply
conclude with his final thoughts here
sometimes I miss being an artist
I miss the rhythm and energy of my
previous career but to balance that I
take satisfaction in knowing how my work
is helping many younger Me's to express
themselves through art and again that's
from Maxie Ani it's it's MaxL I a and I
on Twitter if you want to send a thank
you or follow him thank you so much
again for writing in that was that's
just a wonderful story and I I always
like to hear about people who switch who
you know liked their previous career but
still switch to software development for
some other reason because that's sort of
a separate category people of must write
a lot of people will switch career to
sufferers because they found that their
previous career they didn't like it it
wasn't for filming us for some other
reason they'll switch over and find
software to be a solution to that but
there's also lots of people who may be
very good and very satisfied at their
current job they're not feeling abrasion
there they're not feeling like they're
doing the wrong thing with their life
but for some reason they see software as
important and they're like I feel like I
need to go do this other thing
and so in Max's case it's because he
just doesn't feel like the tools are
there for what he wanted to do and that
can be a great motivating factor and I
think that's a really important thing to
embrace so thanks so much max for
sharing that now we get to I absolutely
loved this story because this was one
that I would would have hoped I would
have gotten but wouldn't have expected
to get and this is from someone who
switched careers from the public sector
into software development specifically
from the military and the reason I find
that so important is because there's a
lot of people who get into the military
in America anyway very young because
it's actually a career path for for
young people
in in the u.s. that a lot of people take
the option of doing it it's our
government isn't necessarily great at
providing work opportunities for people
it's not something we do particularly
well just as a country it's not our
strong suit unfortunately but the
military is one place that that can
happen so there are a lot of young
people who get jobs that way get their
first jobs that way but being in the
military isn't necessarily have anything
to do with programming like maybe you
might get it you know into program a
little bit if that's what you happen to
be you know designated to do but it's
probably unlikely and so I was super
psyched to have someone write in and say
that they had gone that route and came
around to software development because I
think there's a lot of people out there
who might be really interested to hear
this because they might be in the
military or might be considering going
into the military at a young age and I
feel like this story could be very very
relative to them it comes from a fellow
named Jeremy singleton and thank you so
much for writing this in because this is
a really important one I think he writes
in as requested here is a short version
of my career switching story I'm 37 I
got my first job programming at 35 I
joined the Navy back in February of 2001
I had grand dreams of becoming a Navy
SEAL and tried twice unfortunately I did
not become a Navy SEAL but I did deploy
and support spec ops as an intelligence
specialist for about eight of my 12
years in the Navy after I separated from
the Navy in 2013 I got a job working as
a contractor for a special Group within
the Special Operations Command which is
abbreviated SOCOM in fact we have a game
series called SOCOM if you're in the
game into gaming you probably played it
during one of my deployments I got fed
up with the crappy software we had to
use and decided to roll my own this
turned out to set a fire under my ass
that I couldn't put out eventually SOCOM
laid off a bunch of us in senior level
positions and I was forced to find
another job while I was waiting for my
clearance to be transferred to a job I
accepted contracting for the CIA I
received a call from a developer at
computer science corporation they were
looking for a junior developer to fill a
role at the Office of cybersecurity and
communications in Pensacola Florida
while I had no professional programming
experience they liked my enthusiasm and
offered me the job I took it without
hesitation even did the pay was less
than half of what that ping
of what the job was paying that I had
accepted previously this was extremely
stressful as I had no clue if I could
actually do it if I was actually gonna
be good at programming I knew I loved
the idea of programming and I love the
little personal products I had done but
actually working in the real world as
developer was a scary idea even though I
was able to answer the questions I was
asked during the interview I still felt
like an impostor I was leading the
comfort of SpecOps to support of specop
support to take a job programming it
turned out to be not that big of a deal
switching jobs at all the developers I
worked with at DHS understood that I was
starting from scratch and they were more
than accommodating actually having
someone jr. around motivated them to do
more training I did make sure I took
specific steps to not get in their way
and to give them reasons to trust me
with certain projects I always made sure
that I did my own research first before
asking one of them for help and when I
did ask for help I made sure to explain
the problem as I understood it and what
research had done up to that point
nothing is worst than a douchebag that
asks for help without trying to solve a
problem first that's pretty much it I'm
now working my second job in the
industry and couldn't be happier
well I could be happier if I was
creating games for a living but not
everyone gets their dream dream job
right away and so that that once again
from Jeremy singleton if you know he
would like a job in the game industry so
I will say anyone out there listening
who's got a position open if you're
interested if you need his contact
information let me know and hey if you
happen to be someone who works on like a
military shooter title it might be nice
to have somebody who was actually in
SOCOM and did intelligence support as
one of your programmers on the team
that's that's what I'd say about that
all right so thank you very much again
Jeremy for writing that one in I really
appreciate it because that's I think a
segment of sort of the career world that
I was not expecting to get any stories
from and I really was kind of hoping
that we would and the fact that you
wrote one in was awesome and I think
that's going to be really helpful for
people now let's move on to one that's
way outside tech
because I think these are kind of
interesting stories from from people who
you know sort of the ones we had before
a lot of them are kind of still inside
the tech window to a certain degree
right or had sort of brush attack and so
I kind of wanted to move on now to ones
that are very far from that as as a
starting point and kind of end up in
tech in the end so let's let's go
through some of those just to see what
they end up looking like this is I don't
know how to pronounce the names all the
time so again I apologize this is from
Curtis pop or poppy and metro to
pronounce it but on Twitter it's cjp
oppe so if you want to give a shout out
or give him a follow that's where to
look and they were in hey Casey sorry it
took a couple days to write you I wanted
to make sure I took the time to give
this the thought it deserves I'm sorry
for the novel that follows thank you for
taking the time to read these responses
and looking for experiences outside your
own that's a kindness which seems to be
rarely seen these days for the last
seven years I had worked at the same
restaurant chain and was growing
increasingly unhappy I was one of those
people who didn't know what I wanted to
do coming out of high school and after a
few unfulfilled years going to college
for a pre-med degree I dropped out I
ended up working for this restaurant
chain and like in my other careers I
advanced quickly and repeatedly
unfortunately this meant moving further
and further away from family and more
hours in a given week with no additional
compensation than I felt comfortable
with an average rook week for me for the
last two years I was there was about 40
I'm sorry about 70 hours with many
closer to 90 and at a salary designed
for 50 nonetheless I was too comfortable
my living situation to up and leave to
find something more agreeable to me and
so I enrolled in a tech school program
for web analysis programming it was one
of the few that I could find and take
fully online which was necessary to work
into my schedule
needless to say even at a few classes a
semester the time it took in addition to
my regular work schedule was quite the
investment I know it's not easy to
switch careers especially into a
specialized field like software
development I thought I would be able to
show my continued excellence in the
field I was in my ability to work
closely with the and lead a team and my
commitment and dedication toward getting
my degree even with the hours required
as evidence of my
value to an organization but I was wrong
I live in Wisconsin and as I've said a
priority for me was to move a bit closer
to my family I know it's not the next
Silicon Valley or anything but other
than a few local companies that left the
majority of my search from the Twin
Cities or you Claire Wisconsin I began
putting out applications about a year
ago at this time I probably averaged
five a week all with customized cover
letters and as much research as possible
into the values and culture of the
company to see if and where I could be a
good fit during this time I wasn't even
able to get an interview to this day I
never saw a job posting looking for
entry-level developers in my area
internships were the closest I had seen
and between having recently graduated
and not being able to take the quality
of life hit I was a hmm quality of life
hit it require I was unwilling to apply
for such positions in March I finally
decided to leave the position I was at
and dedicate myself full-time to further
building my already serviceable
portfolio and job hunting from that
point on I began putting out at least 15
resumes per week I was only called back
for two interviews and one can probably
be attributed to kind words from a
friend of a friend that one was in
person and went well it was for a small
contractor in La Crosse I was told and
heard later that I was a very strong
candidate but given they were in crunch
time they felt I lack experience and
needed someone who could hit the ground
running
the second was a phone interview and
honestly I'm pretty glad I didn't get it
I don't recall the interviewers title
but he was the leader of the software
development team and one of his first
questions was about how many lines of
code the largest program I'd written was
measuring code quality and lines is a
big red flag but I've worked on some big
projects so I didn't think it would
affect the outcome negatively when I
told him about my github profile and the
products I had on there at the time he
had never heard of git github or version
control another red flag I never heard
back every other resume or application I
turned in I either never heard back from
or received what amounted to and
automatically generated email thanking
me for applying but telling me I was
rejected because they were looking for
someone with more experience
unfortunately I don't have any
connections in the industry and in my
experience not having 3 to 5 years
experience doesn't get you in the door
in my area
the impressiveness of my portfolio my
dry personality or related experience
doesn't mean as much as whether I have a
professionally used whether I have
professionally used X language or
framework for some amount of time
outside of personal products and
volunteer projects I took a job that I'm
happier with in early October but it's
still not the one I would have wished
for I'm pleased with the company though
maybe someday a door will open for them
into their IT department and another
opportunity will come along I'm not sure
if I can think of any other information
to offer and it's a bit rambling so I
apologize for that but thank you again
for your time and I wish I could offer
you a more positive experience
sincerely Curtis Pape I would actually
say that hearing negative experiences is
actually really good I'm of course sad
to hear that you didn't end up getting
yet the job that you actually want doing
programming and I hope that someday you
actually will but I think hearing
negative experiences is actually really
important for people because I suspect
that a lot of people's first experiences
are negative I'm guessing that these
days especially like you said if you're
in an area that doesn't have a lot of
tech jobs you know if you're in Silicon
Valley there's so many tech jobs right
people have to hire for these jobs
there's just a lot more pressure to get
people in the door they may be more
willing to accept novices right but in
places where there very few tech jobs I
feel like it becomes a lot more
difficult to find those entry-level
positions they're probably much much
more difficult to come by would be my
guess I don't really know again my
experience is very out of date
I'm too old at this point to know much
about that but I shouldn't say too old
because hey if I was switching careers
right now I wouldn't be too old to be
experiencing exactly this I mean I'm too
long in the tooth in this industry to
have sort of a perspective on what it's
like to get into it because when I got
into it it was very different than it
was now so I really value hearing these
negative spaces and really I would love
to just say to everyone who wrote in who
shared something negative I that's so
valuable because I feel like other
people need to hear that it's hard you
know they may be facing the same kind of
trouble getting into the industry and I
don't think it helps anyone to feel like
they're alone right it doesn't help to
just hear a bunch of positive stories
hearing
you know stories is extremely valuable
because it lets you know that that's
happening to everyone out there and that
it's very difficult sometimes to just
get into the industry once you're in it
it's so much easier because then all
these networking opportunities open up
for you and you can change companies or
meet people and and move to other
positions that you might like better or
whatever else but getting that foot in
the door can be incredibly difficult
especially if you're in an area that
just doesn't have a lot of tech jobs
right it's just very difficult so thank
you very much Chris for writing that in
I really appreciate it I want to follow
that up with letter from Daniel Riley
that's kind of from a similar
perspective which is to say something
that was not really was not necessarily
in any kind of a tech really or
programming related industry but kind of
moved into that so this one's from
Daniel Riley on Twitter it's at D
underscore K underscore R e I ll Y so
give a follower a shout-out on Twitter
if you want to talk about this story he
writes in hi Casey
I got started fairly late in life as a
programmer I didn't learn to write code
until I was 27 I sent the majority of
the time from high school until then
moving around the country working odd
jobs
I cooked stock shelves bar attended
waiting waited tables worked in
factories did data entry inspected
electronic components and a few others
I'm sure I'm forgetting at the age of 27
I decided it was time for me to continue
my education I started taking courses at
a local Community College I took intro
to CS in programming 101 learning mostly
Java after two semesters of this I
needed to move back home and an old
friend of mine who had been working and
stuff for about ten years contacted me
he knew I had started my software
education and wanted to know if I was
interested an entry-level job to be
honest it was less than entry-level I
had a meeting with his boss and he for
reasons I still cannot fathom he offered
me a position I accepted during the
first day he sat with me and guided me
through some things at almost every
point he would say something or even
worse ask me something that I would have
no idea what he was talking about I
thought I was doing a miserable job that
would only serve to make everyone's life
their more difficult than they were
willing to abide I went home feeling
pretty down
and thought I would be let go very soon
after I shook off the dread I was
feeling I decided to work non-stop to
become the most valuable member of the
team I could possibly be I read every
book I could find took every online
course I could and asked every dumb
question Under the Sun to my
astonishment my co-workers continued to
work with me and mentor me it turns out
they just wanted someone who cared and
was willing to work hard and learn which
is something I continue to try to do to
this day it's been seven years since
then and I can't imagine what my life
would be like without this incredible
opportunity I never made it back to
college after taking that first job some
might find formal education work great
for them but I found hands-on experience
was best for me my advice to other
people in that situation is to accept
that you are learning things much later
than others and that it does not matter
ask questions after you've exhausted
other resources like Google or books if
you show that you are willing to put in
the effort it's surprising how willing
others are to help you along the way and
again that's from Danielle Riley I
apologize guys I don't know how to
pronounce these names correctly but
that's d underscore candor score Riley
on Twitter all right thank you so much
for writing that in I think that it's
also good to hear like I was saying but
from people who feel like they're not
gonna be able to do the job or that they
just don't know what they're doing when
they go in there but then it turns out
that they totally can write because that
we've actually talked about the whole
impostor syndrome thing on this handmade
hero a bunch of times and like I feel
like it's important to attract that
everyone thinks they're not good enough
right like it's very few people who are
so brash and confident that they're just
gonna be like no no I'm awesome at this
right like everyone is just like wow
this is really hard especially when
they're first starting out even if they
sound confident that may just be a front
right I know that certainly when I was
younger getting into it I always tried
to sound much more confident in fact
these days I sound a lot less confident
because I feel like I don't have to
appear more ineligible than I am I feel
like it's okay to just ask questions to
be like wait what I didn't understand
what you say they're right because I
feel like I don't have to prove myself
in that way anymore
but when you're first starting out you
know it can be really tough and you you
know that you don't know a lot of the
stuff that you need to know and you may
have a mistaken impression that everyone
else does even though they really
oftentimes don't know that much either
you know a lot of us who even who've
been working in this many many years may
not know a bunch of things that we
really should know you know it's it's a
vast field then it's difficult to
remember everything or to be aware of
all of the changes in it and and so yeah
it's really good to hear from people who
just drive home the point that like when
you start out it's gonna feel really
uncomfortable you're gonna feel like you
don't know anything that's where
everyone was and honestly it never
really goes away that much there's
always going to be people out there who
know more than you about whatever a
particular thing it is and everyone in
programming is just you know trying to
learn as much as they can to do the best
job that they can on what they're
working on that's the nature of the
beast there's it's not like a very
well-defined thing like riding a bicycle
where you just learn to do it and then
you can do it it's it's this constant
process of getting better and this
constant process of there being new
things involved so thank you so much for
writing in let's let's now move to
someone who switched over from
mathematics which I think it's pretty
interesting because it's again it's sort
of a related field but very very
different in terms of what you might be
doing for a living and this one comes
from Victoria Patriarca I'm sure I'm not
pronouncing that right either but on
Twitter it's at
Vict PA t RI AR CA so give a shout out
there for this story and here it is hi
KC I started my career after Laurent a
few months ago at 31 years old after a
Masters of Science in mathematics since
I learned C and C++ in high school more
than 15 years ago it was not a difficult
transition I knew that I like to develop
software
I like algorithms and things that have
to do with complexity and I felt that I
didn't want to continue with a PhD even
if I still adore math and doing research
moreover my twin brother is a software
developer too since I'm at the beginning
of my career I still have a lot to learn
and I like to learn in the future I plan
to search for a more research-oriented
position compared
- the one I have now but for now I am
really satisfied this transition is my
second one in fact before graduating in
mathematics I graduated in international
relations and I wanted to be a diplomat
that one was much more difficult even if
I do not regret it
there were times in which I doubted it
then I think is important to decide on
your own and try to have as much
information as possible what I mean is
that I like to play games is not a good
reason to become a software developer
moreover I think that you don't need to
change professions to learn one or more
programming languages once you have
spent enough time in front of your ID or
test editor you can decide if you really
want to become a professional software
developer I'm not the best person to ask
what you need to know but I think that
if you are not passionate about softer
them and prepared to learn from your
errors you will never have been able to
find the job you want I also do not
suggest you use computer science
curricula as a guide for your
preparation furthermore I think it's
important to focus on your abilities and
not on other person's hypothetical ones
best regards Victoria Petrarca again at
Vict PA t RI AR CA on Twitter I love
that one because I love the fact that
someone went to school to become a
diplomat and then ended up in software
engineering that's pretty awesome
I think pretty rare um I I don't really
even know what that career path must be
like in the US I think you must be like
kind of going to one of the like Ivy
League's or something like you maybe go
to something like Princeton and go to
you know one of their special schools
for politics or something like that I'm
guessing is something like this which is
really far away from software as a thing
so anyway thank you so much for writing
in and sharing that one I'm trying to
give me one quick second I want to see
where we are because I want to break
about halfway in I was going to break
into two parts so I think yeah okay so
I've got about two more to do here I'm
gonna do these two or maybe three before
stopping okay so now we're gonna hear
for someone who switched from our
texture which i think is pretty cool
because actually architecture and
software kind of seem a little similar
to me in sort of their structure even
though obviously the the nuts and bolts
are completely different pun intended I
suppose and this one's not attributed
synonymous they write in I switch to
computer science after studying
architecture realizing I was really good
at coding and enjoyed it but being put
off by some really bad advice in the 90s
when CS took off and I had four years
working in a paraprofessional field I
tried to get back into it
I did a cert qual which is sort of like
for those of you don't know in software
you can get like certified you can you
can sort of go and take tests or classes
that certify you in some particular
discipline of software usually it's for
something like you know oh this
particular framework or web development
thing or like Microsoft ecosystem you
know something like this I did a circ
well and had done some coding on my home
computer but struggled to get work went
back to uni doing nights in a call
centre while studying it was
unbelievably hard compared to the first
time I went to uni in my teens and I can
imagine how hard that must be working it
at a call centre while doing college
it's hard enough to do college yeah that
sounds rough I came out with great
grades a uni CS job and my fresh degree
but again struggled to get a job I took
one with $5,000 pay cut and a short
probation period after a month they made
up the five thousand and lifted the
probation three years later I was team
lead then I started getting pulled into
interviews and noticed a lot of sexism
in the guys after the door had closed on
candidates many women didn't even get
considered as they didn't tick all the
acronyms guys would claim that they had
for example C++ knowledge and still not
know what a pointer a reference was but
they'd get an interview anyway I began
to wonder if that was what happened to
me but I'll never know
and again that's one's keeping not
attributed for obvious reasons they
probably don't want to say bad things
about their particular employer having
sex in there whatever but you do hear
that thing
we frequently and I've never actually
been a part of the interview process at
a big company so I don't actually know
how that sort of thing works but I do
think especially in a case where you
have interview processes that are so
subjective because programming although
programming is ostensibly kind of an
objective thing and we would like it to
be it's really not it's there's a lot of
art to it and I think as a result being
objective about you know candidates in
programming is not really all that
possible and people are a lot worse as
they say so in terms of room for sexism
and racism and just in general prejudice
of any kind to creep into that process I
feel like there's a lot ton of it
because even though essentially it's
like oh dude how did this person do on
this programming problem might sound and
like an objective thing it's really not
because like I said earlier in the
stream those programming problems really
are poor ways of assessing a candidates
capabilities as a programmer they have a
lot of sort of psychological things
baked into them that may affect
different people differently and I feel
like really like they're still just a
tremendous tremendous amount of
subjectivity in these kind of interviews
which does create environments where
it's very easy for people's personal
opinions about groups of people to come
into play in ways that either they are
not aware of or are aware of and just
don't care either way so it's
unfortunate but I think it's definitely
true and I do think that it's worth
noting and which is why I think it's
really great that this person root in
it's worth noting that if you are in a
situation where that might happen that
could easily have been why you didn't
get the job right that could easily have
been why you didn't get the job and I
really hope that it doesn't discourage
people unnecessarily from contingent
pursue it because there are places
that will be fairer if you take more
chances hopefully there will be places
that are not going to be prejudiced
against people and that will give you a
chance and it's definitely a field that
needs a lot more people in terms of
diversity in it
I think there's been more than enough
information about that sort of thing
talked about in a lot of Spears so I
won't belabor the point but again thank
you very much for writing in again
unattributed but thank you so much now
we'll move on to similar to architecture
civil engineering and this one is not
rooted by name but they did want me to
give their handle on the hammering
Network forums it's just the user name
Brian on there so if you want to give a
shout out for this one that's the place
to do it
and Brian writes in I started in civil
engineering but after dropping out due
to both my health and really a lack of
interest in the field I worked as a
surveyor for a few years it started as a
co-op job for school but due to me
failing my last term and finding out
while working I simply continued working
for a while I was not enjoying the work
for there was very little ambition at my
job I wanted to go back to school I
happened to see a commercial for a video
game program at the International
Academy of Design and Technology in
Toronto and got excited for all the
wrong reasons I ended not only going to
school but also not graduated I'm sorry
I ended up not only going to school but
also graduating sorry my my reading
skills questionable timeframe this would
be July of 2004 I started class and
graduated December 2005 I'm slightly
younger than you are September 1979 so I
was turning 25 when I started the school
was okay but really it was just very
expensive and unfortunately for most of
the students who managed to get through
it most did not get jobs in industry I
can tell you more about the school if
you wish but like with everything you
got out of it what you put into it our
last project sixth and final term which
for the whole class to make a fighting
game we made a smash smash brothers type
game with barnyard animals using Ogura
3d for the main engine and rack net for
the networking
after graduating I had a really hard
time getting an interview let alone a
job I think I may I've had only a
handful of interviews before finally
getting a job Electronic Arts as a QA
tester this would have been May of 2007
I was a QA tester for a few titles speed
for speed fro Street mad in 2009 before
getting a job as a test engineer on Need
for Speed undercover
obviously I'm not an engineer but EA
needs that tends to freely give out
engineer as titles test engineers were
basically software programmers for QA
they would help out both the dev and QA
teams writing simple tools and
integrating debugging features for the
team's
over a few years I moved over to build
engineer positions on skate 3 and need
for speed to run if you're not familiar
with the position remember the drugs
work you did in episode 1 he's talking
about handmade hero setting is that
setting that up for the team or some of
my responsibilities so what he's
referring to as the build engineer it's
a position on larger teams that's
basically it's a person in charge of
making sure that projects actually can
be built and this ends up you know it's
might sound like something that's not
necessary if your only experiences with
small projects but on big projects
builds can be incredibly complicated and
Bilgin build engineer is a very common
position actually it's not that rare
because these products can get very
unwieldy very quickly and it will
require someone's full time attention to
make sure that they still build believe
me this happens a lot and it's a nun in
field position because you are dealing
with a lot of very crazy utilities
oftentimes broad class of systems it can
be a pretty tricky job position actually
and so yeah it like I said it's it's not
an uncommon position and it's a much
more complicated position than you may
think it is if your only experience has
been with small projects builds on large
things get incredibly complicated
all right in 2011 I was laid off and
managed to get another build engine
position at radical entertainment which
is now Activision I was definitely fun
it was definitely fun but unfortunately
was laid off again when the game shipped
April 2012
sadly the whole studio was laid off a
few months later on my birthday of 2012
the FIFA Server team reached out to me
in need
build engineer and I join them a few
weeks later on October 15th 2012 I state
the date for almost four years to the
date October 14 2016 was my last day
that is where you came in that was the
other email you received about inspiring
me this is an email I sent to me
privately I'm good at what I do but I
want to be better so I quit my job
having nearly 10 years experience hoping
that I could learn as much as I can
during the time off so I went back so
that when I go back to work I will be
even better my goal of my time off is
simply to learn and I have a goal of
making at least one simple game a dream
would be I am able to make money doing
that but I do not want to set myself up
for failure
anyway at 37 after 9 years working for
large video game companies I've quit my
job to be a better programmer and try
making games from scratch at the moment
I'm writing transcripts of handmade con
2015 which man that sounds like a tough
job but I think people would really love
that
but we'll move on after learning as much
as I can from you again that's from
Brian on the handmade network forums
give him a shout out if you enjoyed that
story and yeah there you go
let me see where we're at here this is
the last one all right this one comes
from Jessie Meyer and that is at Jessie
our Meyer J es ser ma ye are on Twitter
and they're at in I thought it would be
therapeutic to impact my experiences
below is my story after a decade in the
IT industry I came to realize I hadn't
the slightest clue how computers worked
I had developed a productive mental
model but an honest probing would reveal
a fundamental lack of knowledge
ethically I was making decisions that
would impact real people based on
knowledge built atop quicksand which was
unacceptable however this was generally
acceptable to my colleagues largely I
suspect because their knowledge banks
suffered from similar deficiencies an
acknowledgement of Computer Basics
ignorance was a violation of our
self-image as IT specialists so as
victims of cognitive dissidence we just
told ourselves that basics are not
necessary confirmation bias would tell
us this is fine because we've been able
to solve our problem so far problem
solved
we are problem solvers after all but I
wondered
what are these problems what if these
problems are symptomatic of ignorance
how could we detect fundamental problems
if we did not know the fundamentals have
you been living with deep problems under
our nose defying detection by
unintentional acclamation just because
we are not sensitive does that mean
they're not there something was off I
decided to address what I could myself
at age 25 the time when most that age
come rowing out with their diplomas
prime to tackle the worst problems and
confidence I was suffering from intense
self-inflicted self-doubt and not the
Honorable Descartes in kind
I felt stupid stupid for giving up
assessable career so you but for
starting over but worst of all stupid
for feeling I could make a difference
the anxiety was incapacitating panic
attacks hospital visits therapy etc
quarter life crisis my health problems
prevented me from working full time so I
picked up a part-time web development
job requiring no previous experience my
boss was excellent in accommodating for
my personal problems but also as a
teacher I was amazed at what we he came
to me I was amazed at what he knew and
how proficient he was watching a master
at play is an extremely valuable
learning environment viewers of handmade
hero will understand the job was sort of
like a programming trade school
experience I quickly picked up pragmatic
web development techniques some of which
generalized well for leader programming
tasks which was encouraging but I also
started experiencing deja vu the nature
of the problems we were facing were
uncannily similar to the ones I faced in
IT what boggled my mind were the
rationalizations used to tolerate poor
solutions in web dev they were the same
ones I heard in IT there is something
about us that is the problem the problem
I decided was education I'm 28 now I
studied computer science and mathematics
at the University of Connecticut my
academic interest is to explore
mathematical represented note helpful
metrics in varying contexts in three
years I went from virtually zero real
program experience for mathematical
know-how to one of the top performing
students in my class if that metric is
at all compelling I'm writing my own
game engine a game / engine that's
highly inspired by KC's handmade hero
his circle of friends are also highly
inspirational to me John Fabi and Shawn
etc I taught myself the physics and math
which I had always believed to be poor
at growing up which I had always
believed I was poor at growing
to implement PBR and HDR rendering
that's physically based rendering in
high dynamic range rendering in a
reasonable optimized speedy render I
wrote from scratch
I wake up motivated every day to learn
or unlearn elements of our software
operated world shifting careers has been
the most fulfilling choice of my life
but it was also the most costly
thankfully I didn't accomplish it alone
I lived with my Uncle Tom who was a
scholar he's a PhD in forestry from is a
PhD in forestry a master's in computer
science and a bachelor's in engineering
and he is a Judas at Yukons natural
resources department when he heard of my
desire to reform my foundations he took
me in as a mentee there is no doubt that
without mentorship I would not have been
able to unwind from my anxiety ridden
doubt a real case of being wrapped
around the axle as smoothly as I had
which ultimately turned into a source of
rejuvenation the very thing that caused
me anxiety is today the source of
strength I'm not married to the
challenges of my career shifting while
tending to a family will naturally take
a different path but it can be done my
twin brother has taken such a path he's
married and has a daughter from being
retort rhetorician preacher to a
historian in the classics and again
that's from Jessie mired that's Jesse R
Meyer Jes s
Twitter again thank you so much for
writing in that I will say I am very
interested in the fact that you are
dedicating academic time to studying API
design I would love to hear more about
what you find when you start researching
that I feel like API design is a
extremely important research topic that
very few people are actually tackling
and it is fascinating to hear about
someone who not only is talking about
but tackling that after switching
careers later in life that is really
inspiring and I'm really interested to
see what happens in your newly chosen
field that sounds really interesting
thank you so much for writing in now
I've come to the end of the ones that
I'm going to read on this session which
is not to say that at the end of the
ones I actually have I actually have two
others that I would like to go over but
they were very very long so what I'd
like to do is stop
for this session and next week I'd like
to do a second video with these other
ones in it and then I'll have also a
little discussion sort of as a coda to
it where I'll talk about some of the
themes in here but thank you so much for
joining me for this special edition of
the stream it's been a pleasure reading
all of these stories and hearing from so
many folks who took the time to write in
and share very personal details of their
life their successes their failures how
they were feeling I know that's a very
difficult thing to do and to put
yourself out there like that
but I feel like it was incredibly
valuable for people there are a lot of
folks who will be following in all of
your footsteps
and I think it will make a really big
difference for them to hear about how
other people fared and what their
experiences were like and how it was
emotionally I think will make a
tremendous difference for people as well
as all of the advice that was in here
lots of good things for people to think
about in terms of like what the
resources were they turn to how
important it was to have mentor is where
their first jobs were all these sorts of
things could be really valuable to
someone so again thanks to everyone who
wrote in it's been tremendously
educational for me and I think will be
very very valuable for other people to
hear these stories I will be back again
next week with a another stream where
we'll finish up the material that that
folks have written in and also sort of
have a discussion about it and I will
also probably try to create a special
forum area again that I'll link at the
bottom of these videos when we post them
that's where people can go to engage
with us more if you're someone who's
interested in switching careers into
software like the folks who have been in
these in these stories that way there'll
be somewhere to go where you can
continue the discussion or share your
story for someone who's already done it
and would like to share with other
people so again thank you so much to
everyone it's been really educational
for me hearing from everyone about this
and it's been a real pleasure thank you
so much and I wish everyone continued
success
who has found a new career in in
software development after switching and
for those of you who found it harder or
haven't had success yet I sincerely hope
that you do find success and that you
get a position that you're happy with
and where you can start to see if this
is a career that you really enjoy thanks
everyone for joining me and I will see
you guys all next week where we'll talk
about some more of these stories
thanks so much and and have a good week