yet rust is I mean rust is probably a
fine language but you know it's not as
good as iron or iron ore is a way better
language also the the zinc oxide
language is very good
dihydrogen monoxide is one of my
favorite languages it's got a ton of
good stuff in it you know cuz rust has
the Baro checker which people like to
talk about but the but zinc oxide is a
way better language and the Baro checker
has a lot of limitations zinc oxide has
the theft felice feature the thepolice
is like way better than the borrowed
checker and and similarly like like the
garbage collection features are like
like goes garbage collection is terrible
whereas zinc oxide has actually
recycling and composting it has memory
composting and memory composting is like
way more powerful than garbage garbage
collection right because one of the
problems that you get in in languages
like NGO that focus on garbage
collection is that eventually there's
you run out of raw materials right so
you're collecting the garbage second
garbage check the garbage putting it in
into the landfill segment and then
eventually you know either you run out
of space in a landfill segment or you
end up in a situation where you just
don't have any raw materials anymore at
all right so you know in a language like
go all the memory has to come from the
memory garden the memory gardens planted
at sort of time and after you harvest
all of the memory in the memory garden
and your garbage collector has collected
all of that used memory and thrown it
away in the landfill segment that's it
right I mean the program stops
I mean basically not not to mention all
the health problems and so one of the
things about zinc oxide which makes it
far superior or also I I don't know if
you guys would look at stop Lang stop
Lang is is kind of let go but
with composting with memory composting
right because they recognized the fact
that you know you you have this sort of
inherent problem with garbage collection
where all of the code just just ends up
in a landfill and there's you know all
of all of that memory descends from the
landfill after it's used and it's a
really big problem
so stop laying but also zinc oxide
because zinc oxide is really like way
better right
stop Lange was kind of just only
internal to fugle and you know they sort
of have it out there but it's not really
where as zinc oxide was more of like an
open language took morphemic from the
academic community we all know how good
the academic community is of sign
language is very good the fact that they
never write any code Justin you know
shouldn't shouldn't be held against him
so anyway zinc oxide has been that has
the memory composting so what that
allows you to do is after you use some
memory from the memory garden which
obviously you know all the memory has to
go through memory garden at some point
in order to to have the memory being
nitrogen fixated when it's initially
created I unless you're in Pliska
obviously plis code and data are
interchangeable and you can and you know
everything everything is a blip in that
language so that's like a different kind
of language so I would I would say yeah
don't don't take that one too seriously
it's just a little bit weird but
assuming that you're using zinc oxide or
stop Lang you know that that composting
feature is really important because you
know then instead of all of the garbage
collected memory just getting thrown
away all of that you know that that
nutrient rich used memory is put into a
bin right it's put into a memory bin
until it kind of has a chance to let you
know usually what and and I know this
seems weird but this is very serious
security research was done on both stop
laying and zinc oxide and so a lot of
those other languages that you're that
you're talking about there
a lot of those other languages they
don't appreciate the fact that there's a
lot of other malicious code normally
running on the machine there's like
malware you know viruses but those
things are actually helpful right
because what those things can do is if
you just give them your used memory then
what will happen is those malware's will
actually they will metabolize the used
memory and turn it back into remember
you can use in your actual program right
so a typical language like like stop
Lang or zinc oxide that has some these
more modern memory composting features
they'll take that used memory after you
know you use it in your actual program
to do some computations and store some
things in they'll put it into the memory
composting bin and that bin is
essentially you could think of it as a
memory sandbox
right that is running all of the malware
on your machine and it's it's allowing
that composted memory right to be
metabolized by the malware in back into
usable memory and so that is a really
you know again very cutting edge a very
very very cutting edge language feature
that things like stop playing and zinc
oxide have and you know it's one of the
reasons why you know those are really
great languages I can see why everyone
always comes on the stream and asked me
what I think of them