all right mmm thank you everybody for
coming by
I'm here with Casey Mira Tori of
handmade hero incorporated hello where
he makes only the finest handmade hero
so we got to get your image up again
do you want me to send you the video
feed again yeah okay you sure you up
this they might not know who you are all
right good luck
if this tanks your computer so I'm
clicking I'm doing all the know that was
pop out that was wrong okay yeah we're
fine and then I'll go back to the video
the game
oh the game is struggle blessing more
yeah of course
actually no the game is fine it's OBS is
struggle busing or whatever yeah you
need you need one of these new risin 7ap
use in your system John for extra thread
rather helps you could rip my dude most
of my CPU cores are doing nothing right
now okay let's just point that out oh
well you know multi-threading is hard
yeah it actually is hard so that that
doesn't bode well so what's up John you
you said you wanted to talk today about
water and I'd be like water is hard man
well it's hard normally fortunately well
I don't even know where to start talking
about this let me give a little bit of
an intro for the people okay so
sometimes I work on video games so one
of the games that I am working on right
now has this kind of a situation where
you walk around in a grid world and you
sort of occupy one grid square at a time
and there are puzzly things that happen
so like I could push stuff around and I
could push stuff across the water and
then this little card can go in the
river and then I can get on that thing
and I can ride it for a while I can get
off I could push this rock into the
water and it can change the course of
the water so there's like a whole game
here with you know stuff that you do
mm-hmm and it's it's a pretty well
defined game in the sense that we will
in several senses so one it's a very
kind of an abstract game that operates
on grids and so you could have the same
game for the most part with like
terrible graphics right but part of what
we're doing in this project is having
nicer graphics for several reasons I
guess one is well because it's fun to do
that it's fun to make a game with good
graphics I know there is people will
actually pay you to play your game if it
has good graphics but lastly you know
what I have discovered a long time ago
is that graphics actually really matter
they're not a separate thing from
gameplay you know like what what your
mind is doing when you play a game is in
part responding to what you see and
those responses will be different
depending on what you see right and and
so for these reasons I've always felt
that it matters what what your game
looks like right like you know early on
I don't know earlier in history and also
probably still some indie game
developers believe that like visuals
don't matter and like it just matters if
your game is a good game in terms of
some actual abstract rules or quote
mechanics unquote or whatever I hate
that word I don't hate the word but I
think it's a good word and that's I
think it's demonstrably not true and you
know some games that I work on that's
even less true than other games so for
the witness it's extremely not true like
if you just accidentally put a bug in
the shader to make the colors a little
bit different in the witness part of the
game becomes unplayable yes
yeah and so it's like so clearly these
things are coupled to some degree but
part of the reason I was doing that
stuff we did in the witnesses because it
was becoming clear that they have a lot
to do with each other always
every day well since people like
analogies to things I mean I would hope
that most people wouldn't say like well
if you know if the script for a movie is
good then you don't need cinematography
or good actors or any of that stuff
because you know the viewer will just
hear the words of the script and
understand that it's like a great film
or something but it's like but that's
not what a film is right like a film is
many things coming together to make an
overall effect so you would assume that
unless you think games are somehow
magically different than all other media
it matters how all of the pieces are
interacting and the best examples of
things in that media should be things
where every single element that that
media has are all working together for
the same end right I mean that's that's
what makes a great game as opposed to a
great game design and those are
different things and should be
considered different things yeah
absolutely and you know that doesn't
even necessarily have to do with the
budget or whatever right rearranging our
cameras and it's hard to talk well yeah
I want more of a pier situation here yes
I was I was basically subsuming you you
you were you were becoming very very
eclipsed by my very presence okay this
is about as close as I'm going to bother
to get it right now so people who are
OCD are freaking out about the
mismatched cameras so
yeah I mean I agree with that completely
and it doesn't necessarily mean in terms
of talking about games that the budget
has to be high right like there's
different types of things looking nice
right there's the you know there is the
Michael Bay it's full of explosions
right and then there's like well you can
pick a game like I don't know Monument
Valley or something where you're
objectively speaking it's not like a
trillion hours went into modeling the
levels or something right but it's like
they picked an art style and a color
scheme yeah if it's well art directed
yeah art direction goes a really really
long way and so forth yep so yeah so for
all these reasons and many more we want
the graphics in this game to look good
and you know early on I didn't worry
about that early on it was just like hey
we just make a grid it was the whole
engine was 2d actually in the very
beginning and I started implementing you
know the rules and then gradually we
bolt it up and then sometime sometime
probably before the first year was out
started going 3d and then it was just
like well we have this game with 2d
bitmap tiles the first step in making it
3d is to just put those on each face of
a cube and now we're drawing cubes right
yep so it literally started there this
whole engine so this engine is being
made in a new programming language and
so there was zero zero code in the
beginning right mhm
this wasn't there like licensed unity
and buy some stuff on the asset store
kind of a situation it's we're building
this up literally from nothing so and
part of that is also figuring out
exactly what is the game that we're
making because I sort of knew in the
beginning but then as you work on it
more and more you get more of a concrete
idea so like the river stuff that I just
showed and and you know dropping rocks
in the water and all these things like
there are a lot of nuances like in the
beginning you think well what you know
you have to be able to drop rocks in the
water but
there's a lot of nuances that have to be
decided like between between having that
high-level idea and finishing the game
right and so so at this point we're far
enough along that I think we know most
of those and we can start doing stuff
anyway so right around someone's asking
why didn't I use the witness engine
because it's in C++ and it's made for
first-person games and this is a
third-person game which looks very
different right and I mean to be fair
you you it's not like you didn't move
code over right I mean yeah no we did
that actually accelerated things a fair
bit yeah the fact that we did yeah over
I just brought the game up so you know
that the you don't have to reuse an
exact engine to still get a lot of reuse
out of stuff that you've developed yeah
I mean the editor for this game looks
very similar to the editor for the
witness because it is I mean you know
that that editor actually goes back to
yeah a happy cake right happy cake which
nobody will know what that is that's
right they can look it up it actually
goes back to a thing before happy yeah
was it gone
yeah lots of side-project people will
not know what they were okay so we can
start getting a little bit concrete at
this point after that great amount of
background I guess anyway so so around
around the end of 2018 beginning of 2019
I was like water is important in this
game there's a lot of islands in this
game right even if there weren't we want
nice-looking water in some of these
other scenes it's sort of like because
we have settings that are you know in in
watery places and well okay let's say
one more thing about about this game and
this is an idea that still has not come
to fruition but one of the high-level
ideas was like look
this game was chosen in certain ways
like the because I knew that we were
building a game from scratch right with
a new engine then I wanted to limit how
much we needed to do in certain
dimensions to have a feasible game so
for example in the witness you have like
infinite view distance we had to like
LOD all these things and like combine
meshes into clusters and like try to
paint the shadow map data into the mesh
by vertex past a certain distance and
get rid of texture data and all these
things that you do to make a
first-person game run faster with this
game part of the design was like oh this
will be a good project because the
camera is always on a localized place
like you can see here if I just pop the
game to the top for a minute the camera
there is looking down at a limited scene
and so if you decide like per square of
world what is the most dense that can be
in terms of triangles are a number of
textures or something then that puts a
cap on how much your engine ever has to
do mmm and then you know you don't have
to worry about certain things right we
could focus on building certain kinds of
capability in the engine and then worry
about other things like okay maybe
that'll happen when we do a first-person
game again right now it's not that
simple because we do have side views on
some of these levels and whatever but
for those particular levels you just
don't give yourself a problem right and
you still have a much more bounded
problem than you had before because
you're like look I still know I'm
looking at it from roughly this far away
I still know I'm only looking at it
across this angle spectrum etc etc so
yeah you have a lot more control yes
whereas first-person it's like oh dude
the player is gonna walk up all in
everything and yeah and so part of that
was wow you know so if we want to make a
game that looks really nice because we
have this very well controlled view like
it's so controlled that it doesn't even
scroll most of the time like we have
some levels that scroll but they scroll
between known positions even yeah so
it's like it's very very controlled mhm
give me one second I'm going to turn off
the air conditioning I have this modern
air conditioned
that much like computers they won't ever
do the right thing yep we have one of
those here yep we have one of those here
so I will have to turn that back on in
like probably an hour or something
mm-hmm
so one of the things I was thinking was
hey since were programming an engine for
this thing and the game has relatively
limited scenes we could go kind of over
the top when it comes to certain classes
of graphical effects right like hey
we're gonna have light beams in this
game we're gonna have a lot of water and
whatever else like crystals like all
these things we could just go kind of
insane in terms of how much like how
much pixel horsepower we spend on doing
those effects right because we sort of
have that budget that said we have to
not get into a situation where we end up
having to put in all the engineering
effort that I was just saying we were
gonna save right yeah but because you
kind of can't like yeah you have a
limited amount of engineering effort to
produce the game right yeah um but it's
always been the dream to like do that do
some really nice effects and maybe it's
kind of dumb because they're small on
the screen or whatever but maybe that
also lets us make them really nice
mm-hmm
so that is the history now we haven't
done most of those yet we do have some
limited effects that are pretty nice so
if I bring the game back up here I mean
they're not they're not like beyond
standardly nice but you know we've got
some of the basics so like there's this
crystal I'm next to and if you like
stare at it and see that it's doing you
know it's doing some refracted kind of
things yeah you know it's sampling the
frame buffer and whatever and that I did
some water stuff this week so that works
even if I drop it into the water so it's
actually like still refracting
underwater which may matter on some
levels and it's all you can't see it
that clearly
the water layers in front of it but
mm-hmm there's a nice depth fade on the
thing and all that so we're we're
starting to do some of these things but
as you can see also the water is very
basic I have these like circle like
particles moving around we'll talk in a
minute about what's going on there
mm-hmm
so about a year year and a half ago you
know I said to some people on the team
like hey it's it's probably time to get
more serious about the water and we
built up from the relatively minimal
infrastructure that we had at that time
we built up something that actually
looks nicer than what is currently here
okay so what what what you see right now
is not the best that this has ever
looked okay however you know some of the
things that we did were experiments that
were as they look better in the moment I
felt like these are not exactly on the
path to what we actually want to do okay
so what I felt we were ending up with
was we were ending up with a lot of like
I didn't have a ton of time back at that
time to like I would like send people
some emails saying here's a here's a
description of what we need to do let's
talk about what that would be just so
that I'm not very vague so okay
there are gameplay requirements like
I've just mentioned right you know you
need to do the things in the gameplay
that I just mentioned and so because
it's a puzzle game that also requires
clarity so for example on this
screenshot you see it's pretty clear
where these gameplay rivers are you know
I could make it more clear very easily
by tinting this but like so there's this
particle motion but especially the color
right now which doesn't look very fancy
like the color you know I would not
describe this as a high production value
way of coloring the rivers but it's at
least very clear right and that clarity
cannot be spoiled or it's it's something
that that we need to have control over
at all times right so fief up these
graphical effects it cannot be in a way
that makes it
like ambiguous in some levels when
you're playing where is the river and
where isn't and so one of the things we
were doing was well we have a okay so
let's talk about part of what we have
now is that we have this fluid simulator
running in the background here mm-hmm
which is where some of this stuff is
coming from so you know we seed it for
example with the flow directions of the
rivers and in this case not with
anything else so that you could maybe
vertex paint some prefered flow
directions we had some mechanisms for
that mm-hmm and let me let me pop up a
little a little Hut here where okay so
this this image in the lower left is a
shadow map which is maybe not that
relevant but that level the image just
next to it is it's a fluid sim buffer
it's a little bit minified the actual
texture I think is 2 K by 2 K and it's a
4 component thing I forget I can point
people at the paper that this is except
I don't remember which one it is it's a
4 component texture where x and y our
flow direction and then Z and W I don't
remember in what order but they're like
pressure and vorticity right so it's an
interesting like piece to have under the
hood but we were do we used to be doing
a lot more with the output of this fluid
simulation than we're doing right now so
for example we were rendering like
instead of instead of this coloring of
the rivers that we have right now that
is based on just basically sampling the
gameplay like the gameplay data of what
happens to an entity when it goes into
the square is exported via a different
texture map that we're actually not
drawing here right now and then that's
just being sampled in when we draw the
water plane currently mm-hmm and the
reason for that is because it's very
clear and we used to actually be
sampling the the fluid simulator right
and then like threshold amount is
greater than something then color it
river colored otherwise don't
and that was a little bit more organic
but it also um it wasn't very
controllable and it didn't look nice
right and so it wasn't and and you could
then try to maybe like filter that on
the back end to try to make it look more
nice but you're in the situation where
you're starting with data that doesn't
fundamentally look that nice and trying
to produce data that looks nice by
filtering it mm-hmm it's not a very good
position to be in sometimes you know
maybe it just wasn't working for me the
things that we were doing there mm-hmm
so that's actually turned off right now
there's some other stuff so there was I
guess this came from some papers or
something there used to be an element in
here that involved what do you call it
oh geez I would call what OBS is not
happy again it involved like convecting
colors around in a secondary texture map
uh-huh right
mmm so so parallel to this one on the
right here that would be another texture
gap that it was the same size it was
just like you have colored and that was
a way of like doing ocean flow and we
did that and it like it looked cool in
the abstract uh-huh but it looked like
ink spreading around yeah which is it's
always gonna look like that I mean
that's know if they can look like really
yeah and I was like this isn't this
doesn't actually look like anything we
want right so let me talk about the high
level mission statement of what do we
actually want all right so we want not
ambiguous for gameplay mm-hmm sexy video
game water right what is 60 video game
water mean well it means it responds to
lighting right in a nice way it means
it's actually kind of 3d like we did
lots of prototypes of stuff where we
were doing sort of a more 2d illustrator
II water and we had some stuff that
looked kind of cool but like it was very
2d and if you're making a 3d game where
you have like 3d lighting
and you know the player is trying to
gauge where things are in space and all
these things then the more that you do
in 2d it's both a stylistic clash and it
makes the game harder to play sometime
because it's more difficult to judge
things yep
and so there's always this balance of
gameplay and looking nice and so some of
it you see so so on the water that you
see right now you know we have this grid
in the background and it's like not the
nicest looking grid yet but it's got
some elements of what we want right it's
like it's not a perfectly it's not like
a texture map just projected down there
it's being generated by a noise function
it's like it's got some other noise
function multiplied against it so that
it's not like a constant really annoying
grid but if you want to play you can
tell where the squares are and so if you
need to know if something is 8 squares
away across the ocean or not and you can
know that and it's not a problem right
yeah and we want water that looks really
nice like you would see in like a demo
of something i high-powered high
technology water but that doesn't ruin
gameplay right so based on that
description can I ask a couple questions
sure so the first question I have is as
a game design is this the kind of game
where at some point the player is going
to be presented with a piece of water
like a pool of water with a block
blocking the mouth of the water that
they can then move and watch the water
flow out into something else there's two
versions of that right uh-huh
one is does the water level of the top
pool change like are we actually doing
volumetric transport exactly like yeah
I'm serving and the answer to that is no
okay but there's a related answer that
is yes which let me know jeez I after we
finished this piece I want to take a bit
up the windows in a little bit of a
better way here but I can go to this
other level where for example we have
this elevated pool ah thank you this is
what I was asking basically yes but it's
not the water I don't think ever drains
out of this pool but things can go from
above to below but okay so so but my
question here a little more specifically
is does that happen dynamically meaning
could there have been a block in this
thin that two-square empty spot that you
then move so that the user has to see
the water come and fill in the area even
if it doesn't drain out existing water
can they see movement of water in a 3d
way is what I'm trying to get at yeah
well okay is that something that's going
to happen in this game probably to some
degree so okay you know so what we're
doing in this game is we're starting
from on the gameplay side I'm starting
with a set of gameplay elements and then
we're exploring the way they interact
and sort of expounding on the
consequences mm-hmm and doing everything
that
well everything reasonable that those
things lead to right and so yes
otherwise known as the John blow method
of game design something like I don't
want to be typecast man not too late but
but so one of the things was you know we
had all these puzzle mechanics that were
defined in 2d and then we're extending
them to 3d right and so water was one of
the basic things and so extending water
to 3d is I wasn't gonna do it and then
we had a request from someone working on
the game to do it and it was like you
know what I like doing stuff okay let's
do all right okay but you know that so
the 3d part of it is in mid
implementation right like last week you
couldn't even have to water planes
visually right now you can and it sort
of does it correctly except like the
the flow map data between the two levels
and shared right now or like the
rendering isn't totally separate right
but for example right so you see others
this upper there's this upper plane man
you know where it goes down there's sort
of a gap but the very least that needs
to be water going down and in fact
there's two possible things that could
be because right now there's a gameplay
River that's how you kind of want to see
a gameplay River going down right but it
also could be a non flowing at the edge
but then there's still water there right
because something could like this lily
pad would be able to go off the edge
right like whether whether there was a
river there or not if it was going in
the right direction and so you kind of
still need maybe like an infinity pool
like very slight amount of water over
the edge right there's at least you know
things that could happen there but then
if there's river over the edge we have
this thing where you can disrupt rivers
right and so the river then has to be
able to stop flowing and if you have a
situation like like this where you know
let's say again this is gonna be a
little bit confusing because of the
bottom layer but let's say and say you
have a river that's being fed from an
upper level and drops down at the lower
level yeah it looks like it's in the
lower level also but that's because
again right now we just have separate
yeah yeah if you have that situation
then you sort of want to be able to
disrupt the river up here and then this
river elimination that happens flows
actually down the waterfall and down to
the bottom right that would be the thing
to do mmm-hmm so but if that is actually
erasing the whole river
yeah well it's because the level is set
up in validly low like what's actually
happening over here is not actually
valid game play state okay don't bother
it like this is how this level should be
set up to be correct you're like not
allowed to have a rock you know at the
same time so what'll happen is it'll
it'll erase it up
till it hits an obstacle I see okay
actually that's a different bug it's a
different bug when it started erasing
the whole loop I guess other side
feeding in I guess that doesn't matter
from the perspective of what we're
dealing with I was just curious what was
yeah it's that thing that last you sure
wasn't supposed to happen
I actually just fix and water bugs this
morning that had to do with again this
rewrite that I was talking about to do
multi-layer it's it's in progress right
so I would say so the term fixing water
bugs could either refer to what you were
doing or like neutering those little
things that like live on the surface of
the water well well I said I was gonna
mention what these white dots are there
yes
okay that was exactly the answer to the
question so thank you said and so I want
that stuff to happen I don't think I
want you to pull a lever and this starts
draining gosh although I mean do we do
that maybe okay like the problem is just
like okay normally if something is in
water you can't move it mm-hmm and so
you wouldn't you wouldn't normally be
able to move stuff but let me let me go
back to this level that that we were on
it's called KC MO there are some things
that you can do in water so for example
this thing this door here is in the
water and I can open and close it this
energyfield thing by standing on this
button okay okay yeah you don't think
that wery propagate ocean flow through
that if it's blocked by that but we
probably should mm-hmm
you certainly could start blocking
something with that I think so like if I
if I mess with this level where like say
this block starts out on this and then
this is like let's put it over here just
to be clear so that's going to be open
at the start of the level right if I
manipulate this so I step off the button
and close
oh that didn't actually all right so
that's not hooked up to rivers at all
but you could see that that should block
the river the same way as dropping
Estonian does mhm we just have so you
could have a level where there's one of
those at an upper level like feeding a
waterfall that turns on mm-hmm and maybe
maybe we do that or maybe we just don't
build that level yeah right or here's a
here's a more annoying situation that we
also don't totally handle right now let
me move this guy over here we have the
bard who can charm monsters and other
characters and also crystals for some
reason so like she can get this thing to
go in the water but she can also like
steer it around what sits in the water
so she can like you know keep blocking
her and cause it to read Evert and stuff
so you can imagine one of these on an
upper level that you know that is
keeping the water in that she causes it
to move out of the way and so the
question is do we build that level
mm-hmm
what just happened
did the stream crash or something people
are complaining okay I think the stream
just went down or something
all right well they're saying it's back
okay
okay um I've been having very minor
internet outages here and I don't know
what to do about that except just to
move there's a lot of reasons to do that
besides the Internet yeah we are making
a local recording so so it'll be okay
you can watch any parts that you miss
later on mm-hmm and just to clarify one
thing about that so the rocks that are
blocked like the blocker rock that
you've got charmed right now yeah so
based on the way that it's rendered
right now my guess would have been that
it wouldn't actually stop water from
flowing at all it would just stop water
from flowing like violently because it
looks like it's kind of submerged in the
water so does that mean there's kind of
two ways of blocking water in a sense as
well there's a blocking a river
quote-unquote which is a gameplay
element and then there's blocking water
which would change whether there was
water there or or not is that yeah yeah
a fair statement the property of this
rock right now is that you can step on
it but there is still water in the
square technically right but water can't
flow through it like there's water in
the square but like it doesn't do
anything right mm-hmm but you know if
you move the thing you still water right
yeah by the way your stream is now no
graphics for some reason I have no idea
yeah because I was while you were
speaking I was deciding to use that
moment to start changing the windows
around okay and then that was a disaster
we can pause for a second if you want to
try and get it back
I just do this oh okay let's just pause
and do win so what I was trying to do
was make a window capture of like you
and discord but my knees get a black
screen from window captured on this
court that's the tie quality even yeah
so like I don't and of course there's
two discord windows it says at see Mira
Tori put it up and there's like nothing
I'm trying man I'm trying my best here
it's not possible to get high quality
yeah so the problem is the only way that
I have to get you is like display I got
like I want to have you up over the game
while I'm doing the game but I can only
get you on display so just for the
record like the obvious thing that you
want is you just want discord to have a
sources button that allows you to
connect over the network to someone
else's obs
right I mean yeah now you're just asking
for wait so we should just go add that I
mean granted I'm sure like it would take
seven years just to be able to like
build or something because there's
probably like you know 17 million
libraries and 27 thousand lines of code
but 27 thousand no 27 million lines of
code but that would be a nice thing to
add anyway continue to not allow these
people to ruin our day okay so those are
things that we actually have some
latitude in deciding how high-powered we
want to make this in terms of like is it
volumetric in some way and for the
purposes of what we're talking about
today I would be satisfied if it's like
fakely volumetric like I think if you're
rendering water you want some
interesting stuff to happen so for
example you know people may not be able
to see this very well I'll I'll actually
turn off my camera again for a second
because
which that's the wrong thing I know
there's so many things so in the upper
right for example you can see that
there's sort of a very milquetoast
displacement map that's happening on on
the water like if you look up there you
can sort of see some a little bit of
specular reflection of it it's just not
turned up right now it doesn't look very
good right now you know it's one of
those things that used to look a lot
better mm-hmm
but but the point is one one very
obvious way of making this water more 3d
is to at least have like normal maps
that are flowing with all this stuff
which actually is happening it's just
the lighting is not tuned right mm-hmm
but then you actually want it like if
you really want it to feel like water
right you don't just want it like little
normal maps you want to do like
displacement map at least or possibly
geometry like scrolling by mm-hmm you
want so if I do like like so there's a
subtle issue here right which is you
want your game to feel good mm-hmm not
necessarily in an exploitative way right
so I'm not one of these Inca people who
is like I want to reward you all the
time in fact a lot of people complain
about my games because I don't reward
them all the time look what just just
hear me out for a second what if when
you push the rock into the water all
these coins came spewing out yeah they
could make the Mario coin sound yeah
that would be great but so but there is
a thing about if something actually has
gameplay circumstan
consequence and is important then there
is a dimension to a game about that
thing feeling good or not yep right
mm-hmm but part of that feeling good is
let me put it this way things that are
important in gameplay state should have
proportionate impact visually enough and
auditorily
yes and so if something is important to
gameplay but it does
have as much impact like say visually
but you spent let's say you spent a lot
of effort like I don't even know I'm
trying to pick something that doesn't
have gameplay consequence let's just
let's just say you you you took this
gray grid that I'm standing on and put a
lot of effort into making that look
really nice hmm but then you drop the
rock into the water and it like looks
like it does now which isn't as bad as
it used to like it used to just be a
grid Klunk Klunk Klunk you can still see
that happening underneath mm-hmm
underneath the particles they're kind of
hiding I'm like if that's what it is but
like it looks like the Unreal Micro
polygons demo on the ground that I'm on
right now it's like that's a that's a
fundamental mismatch you don't really
want yep okay so in cinema that's called
Hitchcock's rule and basically it says
that the importance of something to the
scene should roughly correspond to the
amount of attention it gets in the frame
and yet this of course named after Robyn
Hitchcock from The Cure absolutely not
not no relation to Alfred Hitchcock and
so I mean basically the paraphrasing of
what you've said I think is something's
audio-visual presence in the game should
roughly correspond to its importance in
the gameplay yeah you know exact yeah
rules are never really rules but they're
just like rules of thumb you feel it
when that's not the case
Yeah right player feels it when that's
not the case okay what also leads
players to create their own games
sometimes where they'll like end up
spending a ton of time with something
that is not the game at all because you
made that more fun than the actual game
right and more interesting and engaging
but yeah and so so what I imagine is for
example let's let's say if I were to do
a very straightforward thing starting
here and just extrapolating forward if I
wasn't allowed to change the core
technology that we are using at all
mm-hmm
I will I will speak in a bit about maybe
why we need more technology or there are
some things about the underlying thesis
so far of
for example using using a fluid
simulator underneath to help generate
some of this stuff then either don't
work or that we need to add more in
order to make them work mm-hmm
but that's maybe getting a little ahead
of myself I would say like if I was to
just take this forward right hmm what I
would do and and what I would I sent in
these emails originally right is like
okay for all these little white dots
that we're drawing these are actually so
so what you see in front of you right
now is actually really stupid it uses a
tremendous amount more fill rate than
then you see mostly doing nothing
because these white particles are like
my debug particles if I go I go to the
water particle render GL I can actually
show you how big these circles actually
are they're like huge
no more overlapping and the reason is
that these are supposed to be for
example like normal mapped wavelets that
constructively and destructively
interfere as they flow around right yep
and either you do a displacement map so
it's ironic that I say that nobody ever
does deferred rendering but like maybe
you just add those into a height map
scaler into a buffer and then do the
normal map and lighting computation in a
post pass right or I think I think
actually you don't need to do that
because like supposedly you can't really
add normals or gradients but but you
actually can add by vectors and like I
think if you do something slightly
correct in linear algebra aka geometric
algebra it comes out correct that you
could just evaluate normals and add
normals but I just I haven't sat down to
figure out what that is but anyway you
have all these all these wavelets like
flowing around and constructively and
destructively interfering and that gives
you something that is more water like
than what you already see and I think I
think I could get that going in like
less than a day
turn you know we actually used to have
procedurally generated like little waves
like they were just like a sort of like
a sync pulse or whatever on each of
these it was just they were looking
regular and and a little too scaled a
little too regularly like you want you
want big waves and medium waves and
small waves because you want something
noise like to happen when they mix
mm-hmm but also when you do that you
don't want it to be too noisy because
you want to be able to see the flow
going in a specific direction all right
all these things anyway so step one is
do that step two you know add that into
the Z offset of the ocean plane so that
it maybe does some stuff like occludes
at least the edges of some of these
little islands that you see here right
mm-hmm
that would also have a color component
so right now we have this very bland
background color but you actually can
can set a bitmap that will color the
whole scene right so just your standard
diffuse color thing but then we have a
few mechanisms that that are disabled
right now so both may be a background
bitmap or else vertex painted stuff so
that you don't require people to have a
bit they have a vertex paint tool in the
editor and you could go paint like well
maybe the waves are bigger over here and
smaller over here right that could be
one of the channels or although that
seems a little bit not great because I
mean it it sort of goes a little bit
against the grain of what's supposed to
be going on which is to say that it's
creating detail in the graphics where
the detail doesn't actually exist in the
gameplay like it seems like someone
should have to go put like some actual
stuff over there to change what it looks
like a little you know I'm saying to you
sort of but but also no because the
problem is the problem is you don't want
it like this is a this is a kind of
decision that has to be made correctly
for any game okay
and if you add a lot of stuff
I mean maybe like maybe we could figure
out the way to make that work but the
problem with adding stuff is that people
are always unconvinced gameplay right
like do I need to get over there or
something and if we had to do that on
every level to make the level look good
that starts to be a problem of its own
and so and so let me turn this back now
I'll make them I'll make them medium
sized dots so like I would at least like
the ability to provide a good amount of
visual visual interest on across a wide
variety of levels across hundreds of
levels without needing to do that maybe
now maybe that's the wrong assumption
and we can talk about that or maybe
other forms of visual interest like
background bitmap plus you know just
meshes on the ground under the water and
controlling the overall opacity of the
water and things like maybe that's
enough visual interest it's hard to say
mhm I feel like this would be a good
point I kind of want another drink so
why don't we do the thing
let's get questions from people do you
want to do the question curator thing
for a few minutes I mean I guess we
could but we haven't really talked about
this yet so like I I kind of feel like
the next thing to talk about is to I
have a few more things to say about the
fluid sim let me pause for a second and
start some some tea and then we can talk
about the fluid sim and then and then
maybe you can just start throwing
questions at me or whatever okay all
right so back in a minute
why don't you just chat with with the
people well I'm gonna go get some tea -
okay well people out there
I can chat with the people and we'll be
back in a minute
[Music]
[Applause]
water is not boiled yet but it's getting
there
okay is Casey back yes I am actually
all right great so here's what I thought
of to say about this issue so whereas
the visuals of things the the Robyn
Hitchcock rule that we discussed is true
mm-hmm
it is not it does not completely
determine things yes and so there are
there are aesthetic dimensions to
whatever you're talking about that are
essentially extra or that give you
freedom to make other decisions right
and so for example in a game like this I
probably want the visuals of an island
that I'm standing on to be very distinct
from the water so I don't have to squint
and say where's Island and where's water
I mean but if I make the island like
brown or like a volcanic color or you
know green grassy color or whatever
doesn't necessarily matter that's a
degree of freedom that I have right I'm
deciding what the level looks like and I
mean that's that's obvious so far I
suppose and so I would say that the goal
actually let me get I got to get the cup
for my tea sorry back in one more second
are we gonna get the swirling the
awesome like swirling chai thing one of
my favorite parts of John streams is
when you do the swirling try like and
there's the rock music playing if you do
not have a cup for it I mean you can
pour it straight in but are we getting
John are we gonna get the swirling chai
rock like hard rock thing we have no
milk right now I almost went out and got
some all right I don't
okay now that might be a bonus stream
tonight okay okay so
I would say that part of the goal is to
when we're building a water system right
is that we want to be aware that that
presents certain dimensions of aesthetic
explore ability that are a little bit
extra like the color of an island or you
know the style of whatever the grass is
or whatever all these things are right
mm-hmm
we want to both create something that
provides ample ability or ample
opportunities for that kind of
elaboration mm-hmm and also that
something that technically lets us do
those things mm-hmm you know and so so
with the fluid sim for example well okay
so so we can drive particles they the
direction about where they go could come
from the fluid sim or it could come from
somewhere else right on particular
levels like if if there's a level where
there aren't any rivers and the flow is
not going to change you could have a
statically painted flow map or an
algorithmic the painted flow map or
something and that gives you opportunity
to do certain kinds of things so you
could imagine like a lone Island in the
middle of the water where the waves kind
of like radiates around it it was sort
of like a Zen garden kind of a feeling
right or you could imagine just waves
constantly coming from you know
Southeast to Northwest like maybe maybe
the fiction of a series of levels is it
you're trying to get to the south east
like into the wind I don't know right
hmm so whatever these opportunities are
mm-hmm
we want to be able to play around with
whatever those dimensions are and so the
wave height thing was one example of
that however I will say that it often
looks weird right if you just what
awesome looks weird
sorry I meant wave wave size like
painting wave size around different
parts of the map uh-huh right yeah like
if you paint that in a way where you're
kind of being responsive to what the
islands are like
you're just saying I'm sort of painting
it where waves are big when you're a
certain distance from the islands right
then that could look more natural but if
you if you do it in a way that doesn't
correlate then it looks weird right and
so then the question is well should we
Auto generate wave size or do we prefer
sort of having the freedom or do you
want something in-between where you
generate it but let people modify it
okay you know anyway hmm
so so the last thing I want to say right
so we can control particles from fluid
soon we can control them from a
statically painted thing we could maybe
have a crossfade between those things
hmm but the idea behind a fluid sim to
begin with is that like it automatically
generates complexity for you to some
degree that responds to the things in
the level right so you can sort of see
like this Brown island on the north I I
put that there with the river flowing in
so you can sort of see that like there's
this gameplay flow causing the particles
to go in and then they sort of like flow
around to the left and go out and we
bunch up in these little pools yeah and
that's all caused by the simulator like
nobody had to hand-paint that right and
that's good just to the extent that it
produces behavior that you like yep here
it's a little bit it's a little bit
weird looking if you like sit down and
think about it because you're like wait
shouldn't the shouldn't the sum of flow
into one side be equal to the flow out
the other side and the reason it's not
is because for purposes of gameplay
clarity we cheat particle velocities
when they're inside gameplay flow so
like the the fluid simulator like in
this 2 by 3 or 2 by 4 grid that's kind
of going into the little bay there or
whatever what's it called when it's like
not a bay but it's connected on both
sides I have no idea channel it's a
channel that's kind of got bays on each
side okay um so the the actual fluid sim
has a much lower velocity for the
particles going in but were we're
amplifying it
for gameplay clarity because one thing
that happens if you don't do that is
there doesn't seem to be that big of a
difference between River and non River
because one of the things that a fluid
sim is going to do is it smooths out the
velocity field right and so even if you
color River differently from non River
then a the actual visible difference
between what you see in the river and
what you see outside the river is not
going to be very large by default if you
just say there's River here and you let
the fluid sim solve the rest and that's
actually bad probably right because then
if the idea it like why is that lilypad
not flowing but if I push it one Square
over it does flow the particles are
going just as fast in each place
approximately and so so that's like
mentally very weird all of a sudden and
that's a problem that I would like to
solve and so if you think about it like
what's a fluid sim gonna do if you just
say all the water is all the water is
still and then you have a flowing river
right here it's gonna make the stuff
right next to it almost flowing river
right
yeah and that sort of violates the
extreme discreteness of our gameplay
world yeah it's a little bit of a
contradiction in what we're asking for
yeah and now sometimes that means you
shouldn't ask for that but sometimes it
means there's an opportunity to find
something that's still systemic and
complex but that gives you what you want
and so one example like I said before
maybe we shouldn't have a fluid sim
that's one way to do it or maybe we need
more on top of the fluid sim so if you
imagined like like what would it take
actually to have a strongly flowing
river like this with the water next to
it kind of being still you would need
some kind of counter pressure right and
so like an announcer like
I mean you can't really is the answer
well I mean I haven't experimented with
it I mean obviously if you have counter
pressure it's like coming from somewhere
right III meant you can't in nature
sorry yeah I mean in nature you just
couldn't have this line of life stuff
around it not flow that's just not a
thing right yeah and so so the question
is are there things that we could feed
in mm-hmm that would make something more
like that and maybe like maybe we could
make it so that you know next to any
River like this
there's squares of water that are like
flowing into it instead of out of it or
that are twisting into it right even if
the net flow in the square isn't that
big yep and that might actually be
visually very interesting all right and
it might help with this problem and then
we cheat to bridge the rest of the way
that's one thing okay um another thing
though this is all very obviously 2d
right now right the the particles the
circular particles that I have right
here okay and let me just say I don't
think we should want or need to do like
a 3d fluid sim if we stay with fluid Sam
I think we can get by with like you know
yeah some 2d find Sims paint
I agree with you stood together huh like
it's so it's so massively more
computationally expensive to do oh yeah
to do 3d that we don't want to do that
yeah but one very easy thing that we can
do is we can have some inside the water
particles right that fill out sort of
the fill out the square so that this
river kind of area doesn't just feel
painted on top right like it it has some
depth and that could be done with
current the current system like current
technology but but I mean I it's just to
say that like whether the fluid sim is
the right thing is in question like it
does these things that are good and it
also does some things that are bad and
the things that are bad are actually
worse than the things that are good
because the things that are bad
interfere with gameplay clarity and even
not even necessarily clarity because I
could just like pump
the brightness on on the actual river
areas and and say look it's very clear
but like you you also want to sell it
like you want your brain to accept what
it's seeing yeah yeah and and so that
lilypad really should be in an area with
not that much net flow like maybe you
could imagine that it's it's maybe got a
string connecting it to a little Lily
yeah
stem connecting it somewhere and it
won't really move in a small current yet
but it will in a bigger current
something like that like we can do all
these little things put together to like
sell what's happening but of course we
have to decide what that is and then the
last thing I would say is there's a
question when I talk about I can talk
two days about this but there's a
question you know when I push when I
push this stone into the water right now
we make these very 2d particles right
and part of the reason that's so big
is to cover up the fact that we're
changing a square at a time in terms of
the coloration they're just something
that we would fix the underlying yes
happening yep but also you probably just
don't want a bunch of 2d particles right
like if you're doing sexy video game
water for the Year 2022 uh-huh 2023
we're not announced I don't know when
the games coming out 2021 january
negative 3rd 2021 yep um no that is not
it you know you would actually want
probably to see some like how does this
feel good right well there's good sounds
but there's good visuals you see like
the the wave front has like you know
some very active energetic water that's
plowing forward making the changes that
you made yep right and then so this this
rectangle that's next to where I'm
standing right now that's actually a
little bit of a mistake but there is
some entity work going underneath it
doesn't it doesn't get rendered
correctly quite yet but there's little
turbulences that get drawn so like when
the water when the water stops that this
rock there should be one here on the so
there is you just can't see it see how
like my feet or
kind of cyan color uh-huh
there's this little turbulence rectangle
here on the yep on the rock and then
there's one here on the ground and the
idea would be we would draw those into
the depth buffer or maybe some geometry
to be like oh there's water hitting
these points and splashing back right so
it would be more dynamic mm-hmm like
what what you it wouldn't just be water
smoothly flowing around a corner it
would be like waters hitting this corner
and kind of getting like violently
knocked back or mildly violently not
back uh-huh so there's been a little bit
of work in that direction but as you can
see it's like not hooked up um that's
probably enough of me just saying stuff
okay I mean I think I have everything
now yeah so I have to know get you back
on display capture okay so what is your
opinion about what should be done uh so
let me first ask a couple questions
about what you were trying to do so far
so if I understand you correctly sort of
the original concept here was you were
going to have I believe they call these
methods wave packet methods right where
you're basically like sending little
wave tracers around that rather than
being rendered as particles or level
sets they're rendered as little like
wave functions that are trying to like
have a phase that roughly gets set
relative to something that was sort of
the original basic design of what you've
got on the screen right now you just
haven't actually done that yet that's
why it's still just part of like circles
and not an actual thing yeah basically
what I'm imagining is that each one of
those particles probably has a color
component that acts in the way that you
would expect that like blends with the
other one uh-huh but then also probably
has a geometric component okay and maybe
you're adding that now the thing about
that is that's already kind of 2d look
you imagine that you were like
tessellating things down to an extreme
level maybe you would just want the test
later to make triangles there's mmm-hmm
and maybe that's better somehow okay um
but but that's the basic idea and we had
both of we've had color in the past
uh-huh and we've had we've had like
normal maps in the past yeah we haven't
had both and with the normal maps
they've always been weird they like
we're added we're yeah yeah you know and
and so and then the other question is
how much motion do you get like if
they're just like if it's if you imagine
like a sync pulse that doesn't move huh
right and that's just going through huh
you might need so many particles to do
that that it's totally unreasonable for
that to look good
yep but if you like oscillate the sync
pulse up and down so it's like actually
a standing wave that's animated you know
like like a lot of simpler wave systems
do then you probably don't need nearly
as many because you get a lot of motion
out of that and that's actually what
waves do in nature I think yes they're
sort of moving and and this body of
water is has momentum to go up and then
it's falling right now and so you can
sort of be simulating that to get I
think to drive us a little bit onto the
topic of like what are you actually
simulating yeah and so the idea here is
that I mean the idea here is at some
level every particle is simulating a
piece of water in some way like not not
it as I have a resolution as you would
need to do like anything like serious
simulation but but to get visuals out of
it and that's that's actually a stark
difference so like way back in the day a
couple years ago or whatever I had I
made a system that was much simpler but
it looks better again right um but was
limited and what that was was you know
we know the gameplay flow direction you
had all these grid points and so we'll
tessellate each square into like four
points and then we'll do like a blend of
you know normal maps like every every
pixel had like four normal Maps blended
together and and from from the neighbors
ramp and and the normal from the
neighbor was like the flow and whatever
it was me and so that was a very
relatively straightforward simple
gridded way of getting some kind of nice
you know water flow that was
controllable is just very gritted and
very not organic yep it doesn't give you
any where to go once you've done that
it's like okay great now I've got some
grids and I've got some water and it's
not as nice as I would like yep okay
it's and so this was our attempt at like
okay how do you how do you do something
different okay instead of instead of
generating your normal Maps or whatever
your waves from these fixed grid points
going into fixed directions we'll do it
just by having particles moving freely
okay so I think I've got it all so now I
will I will say what I think
off the cuff of my head with some with
some caveats so there's a couple
important caveats one is that so
so continuum dynamics is not my thing I
mean we'll start with that obviously I
don't do this for a living even a little
bit so you know my my thinking on this
topic is not going to be particularly
good and the second thing is that you
know most the time when I work on a
problem like this I do probably have a
pretty good idea when I start that's not
terrible but after I actually sit down
and really work the problem for six
months I'm at a completely different
place so I'm just guessing that whatever
I say now is also not what I would end
up with if I actually went so you know
it's the place I would start right yeah
so my high-level thinking on this is
that I actually I guess I disagree with
the second part of what you just said
which was that you had a system where
you took a grid and you did the for like
normal map lending thing and you were
like but I don't know where to go from
there so you switched to the particle
one I guess I think maybe that first
system sounds more like the right system
to me and let me go through why I think
that
so from from looking at the problem the
way you've described it I feel like the
way that I would think of it is this is
a game that wants the water to be what
the water is gonna be at each Square and
the reason I say that is because
everything else in the game is about
what's on that square so much like you
said if the lily pad is staying still
the last thing I want is the water sim
to come in here and draw some particles
clearly moving past that lily pad
because that just feels weird and it
makes the makes the player not really
understand what the heck is going on
because they look at the thing and they
go oh so I guess the water is not really
a thing I'm just supposed to look at
like the color of the water cuz that's
the thing that actually tells me and the
motion of the waters are relevant
because I can't trust it or something
right and so I feel like if you go too
far down that route you're always gonna
be fighting this sort of like cognitive
dissonance between what the water looks
like it's doing and you're always gonna
have to paper over the fact that's not
doing the right thing so for me the the
first thing I clue in on there is I want
the water to say what it's doing on each
square and I want to start there that's
just there's just what my head wants to
start with now right so that's like my
first thought is I want to start with
the gameplay and if it says this water
isn't moving then that's an important
underlying input to this system that I
should not that I should be working with
not papering over so that's thought one
thought too is I want to split the way
that I'm simulating this into two parts
so one part is creating attractive and
interesting water from that input so
that's one thing that I want to be able
to do and I think I have a pretty good
idea how to do that so we'll talk about
that in a second but the second part of
that is I probably want to tackle the
transition of water properties in a
slightly separate way and the reason I
say that is because in this game you're
not going to have most of the water
undergoing large-scale transitions most
of the time so designing a system that
can do really good effects for I pushed
a rock in front of the waterfall as the
way all of the water is being simulated
is probably going to suck down a lot
more GPU time and potentially CPU time
then I'm gonna want so in my thinking
I'm imagining that I will always want to
do a pre pass where I build rectangular
regions maybe even sometimes not exactly
rectangular regions so let's just say
disjoint set forests so some set of n
collections of contiguous squares that
are currently undergoing water
transformation and I think I would
partition my simulation into two parts
one that handles those isolated square
regions and one that handles everything
else so those are my two structural
thoughts let's start by ignoring the
transition regions first because I think
that's sort of a separate simulation
problem and then well also it's the
thing that's doing the least amount of
water at any given time so the first
question I have is have you seen we
bring it up here have you ever seen
water surface wavelets the paper by the
Nvidia paper sure do you want to take a
quick look at the video for water
surface wavelets and take a look at them
specifically the part where they show
how to paint water stuff into it
this actually might be it says SIGGRAPH
2018 aha so this could well be after I
was doing the research need to do the
thing because because when I did the
four-way grid thing that I did it was
like sort of based on mm-hmm you know
what some people some paper somewhere
yeah so jump forward to the part well
you can watch the whole thing if you
want but the part that I'm specifically
interested in is the part where they
show how to paint
uh water velocity I can't really read
the text oh wait painting is you'll be
able to see when you get there just keep
keep runnin for ya here you go
so this is just I want some waves right
and then in a second they show I want
some directional flow Suzanne yeah and
you know
I mean it's true that something like
this okay yeah so if we have a fluid sim
running in the background right mm-hmm
then wow this I don't know if this is
happening for the viewers but the video
is just super Skippy for me I think it's
just it's happening for the viewers yeah
it's okay yeah too much time guys can
your watch this video
yeah correct like it's literally
rendering frames from back in time and
then forward like it's not just yeah
it's whenever those happen to show up at
OBS like it's like that's the order you
get them in no but I mean on the screen
for me yeah yeah no I mean in the point
in the fantastic web browser there's the
future of software distribution you know
the kids like to tell me it's all mm-hmm
like I'm seeing frames out of order in
the browser mm-hmm like it's crazy okay
so something like this actually
something like you're seeing behind the
boats in this scene or like before when
they were painting the waves mhm and you
had very still water mm-hmm that
probably is the best thing honestly and
we're not really going to get that from
the fluid sim that said right mm-hmm one
thing when you said I could so if if we
say that it's a it's a fundamentally
painted driver of the visuals then we
could still use a fluid sim for
something like well here's a level that
that has it's got islands with an
interesting shape and there's just no
rivers on this level so like flow
doesn't really matter and so then we can
use that to do whatever like well we
just want we want to seed the flow maybe
with the fluid sim and like then
generate generate some paint vectors
that then we sample in like opposite
bitmap or something you know
yeah so I'm okay honestly it would be
nice to not be running a fluid sim at
runtime if we just use that as an
authoring tool sometimes but that so
just to be clear that paper is a fluid
sim
so the way that paper works is I would
say probably pretty close to the thing I
would start with for your system if I
was going to take a crack at it and what
it does is it runs a fluid sim on the
coarse mesh so kind of like the mesh
you've got out in front of you might be
the density of the fluid some like right
you wouldn't actually have a more
detailed one like it looks like when you
brought up that bitmap you were doing a
much more detailed fluid sim than the
game grid uh so this paper would do it
more like on the grid that you see in
front of you which is exactly what I
want because I'm thinking I want to
basically be able to specify some of
these values directly and then other
ones I want to just take on whatever
characters as they are and yet other
ones such as the ones like that are in
areas that are gameplay important I
might want to always zero out and say no
real motion here or almost no motion
right then what they do is they in the
so in the Tessa later on the GPU they
use the same basic idea as you get from
you know like they call those things I
think I wrote it down here so I wouldn't
forget when I was taking a quick look so
Tessa and Dorff waves they call them a
lot but they're basically like when they
do this they did the spectral analysis
of what you tend to get in water and
what the breakdown of the wave forms are
so that when you just want like when
when VFX people just want an ocean they
just like put in these parameters and
you can sample it without doing any
fluid sim it's just like it just gives
you a notion because they know what the
general waveform should be you know and
I mean kind yes so there's there's a
whole field of fluid dynamics literature
you can go read which is literally just
like we want effectively closed form
solutions to oceans and lakes and stuff
where we just sample known wave forms
and the the reason you don't just use
these always obviously is because they
don't respond to anything right they
don't they don't respond to boundaries
they don't respond to the shape of the
water if they just give you back thing
that looks like water for a given
pache and nothing else right so what the
Nvidia people did is they basically are
doing sort of that in a way that is
interpolated through the water sim so
they have the simulation vectors and
then they like basically up sample that
using what they know to be believable
waveform patterns for water right right
so that to me sounds like a really good
first step for your water thing and
here's why number one it gives you a
really good way to control the system
because you can use some water sim if
you want to by allowing the actual grid
to undergo a solve or you can just not
you can always just set those values
that that's what the painting example
sort of gives you is more of a thing
where you're like look I can just
override what that thing is telling me
because I'm gonna mostly want for all of
the places near where the player can go
to just freakin specify if this is what
it is so that feels like a really good
start and second because it's using a
wave distribution function for the up
sampling that also suggests to me that
if you had you know like I'm imagining
if I sat down or to play with this I
would gain some intuition for how those
equations were working and how I wanted
to structure them and I could probably
imagine giving artists control over
those wave functions in ways that would
allow them to shape the characteristics
of the waves to be more appropriate to
this particular game as opposed to I
want it to look like real water because
this game doesn't look like real
anything it's like a fantasy you know
world that has a certain art style to it
and you probably want your waves to be
correspondingly not like the real world
and so I feel like being able to shape
those wave functions is probably
something that could easily be done
because they're by definition being done
as a interpolation pass that doesn't
actually affect the simulation and
therefore won't like make everything
explode if the artists like does weird
things to the parameters so that's my
first thought and I think what I would
do is I would start there if it were
just me and I starting for nothing I'd
be like let's start there let's see what
we can do with interpolated
well-distributed wave some nations in
the Tessa later Bay
an underlying grid that we can paint
and/or run the sim on lightly if we
decide we need that for some reason so
you know when we have a very crisp with
gameplay grid like this mm-hmm
so one of the things that that's a job
that has to be done an aesthetic job
that has to be done regardless of the
implementation method so far because
nothing has magically solved this is you
always want to get corners to like look
good mm-hmm
so in my very original like even before
the four-way blend I had like just
scroll a normal map in one Square and
whatever and then you see the thing
going down and then going to the right
you kind of just want to round it you
know make it look nice and then the the
the the four-way blend one I forget what
it looked like but like it didn't it
didn't look great and and actually in a
lot of cases of corners or intersecting
in different ways naive blends like that
will often the kind of diet like the
blend will not be of the right magnitude
because you're adding a different number
of things or whatever or the like if you
imagine a three-way intersection
actually I don't I don't remember what
the problems were anyway there were
problems like it didn't it didn't look
that great and then the fluid sim
version of course you kind of get for I
don't even know what the fluid shape
would be right now if I turn these
articles into yeah but you can you can
already sort of see like they're not
even like evenly distributed across the
river like things tend to particles tend
to clump into the nearside flow and so
you need to maybe start addressing that
if you're even going to get a uniform
shape yeah maybe you could get it
looking good eventually but they're
problems that have to happen so I'm
wondering like so one way to control
that completely right imagine I was
generating a per pixel flow Direction
image that's at the same resolution as
the screen and then and then that's
being used by whatever back-end right
uh-huh
so an obvious thing that I can do is
just have curved tile pieces that I like
slap down for the corners or whatever
that are just like the shape that I want
right and you could add a noise function
to that or you could animate them or
something
mm-hmm but that's very controllable
mm-hm and so question one is like maybe
that's the right way to go and then
maybe I don't really want a see I guess
the thing I don't know from this paper
is if I don't want to do a sim which I'm
not necessarily sure I do like I could
think of things that I want to sim like
hey if I want this wavefront smashing
forward maybe there's just like some
little spheres bound to each other with
Springs or whatever and and I'm running
that and that's not even really a water
sim but it's just giving me something
for the front of it like yeah it's extra
right yeah um so well I mean just to be
clear like that's one of the reasons why
I thought of this paper particularly is
because it's partitioned into two halves
and you can assess each half separately
if you don't want it if you don't want
to do assume you don't then you just
don't do one right the actual rendering
part if I'm not gonna do a sim mm-hmm
like what what is the actual rendering
part do so it's it's sampling it's got
some some distributions of some
frequency distributions that it knows
yeah generate waves and it just does it
interpolate those parameters based on
surrounding grid squares and then like
yeah I mean I believe basically the the
idea behind the paper is that you have
some set of parameters that you have
computed either with the fluid sim or
just you specified what you wanted and
then the majority of the papers
contribution is let's make a Tessa later
that produces believable water from that
very low res input which I think is
exactly what you want basically right
well I'm not sure about the test later
part like if it's an Nvidia paper
they're about using GPU features in ways
that I don't well you don't you don't
necessarily what test they they're just
doing that because they want the water
to actually displace which you usually
do but you know I mean maybe you don't
in this case for some reason
but usually you want your water to have
a varying height I mean I might like I'm
agnostic about that okay but yeah you
could replace replace Tessa later with
pixel shader if you would rather right
if that's your call it doesn't matter
which one I mean or it could just be pre
tessellated to some degree like I don't
know to what degree they need to
dynamically allocate triangle density or
if I could start with like a uniform
grid I just like move those up and down
and then make up the difference with
normal man well it's it's a sample
function so you do anything you want
right if you want to you can make it
sample to tessellate if you'd rather you
can have it sample to produce pixels you
could subdivide sure if you look at the
two samples and decide that there's you
know too much variance between them you
could subdivide it I mean it's it's just
sampling functions so you know whatever
you want to do with it you could do
obviously haven't implemented the paper
myself because like I said I don't work
with this stuff but it seems like the
right place to start because it does
what you want right it takes a low res
mesh and up samples it into stuff that
looks like water which seems like a good
place to start and to see what you can
get out of that and the other reason I
say that is because since it is
fundamentally a low res a low res grid
super sampling approach to me that also
suggests that I could go in there and I
mean I don't know if I could or not
because I'm actually looked at it but
that suggests to make it probably go in
there and for lack of better term make
the interpolation worse and the reason
that I say that is because if the goal
of this game is to make things look
square II then one thing I might want to
do is change probably what they're going
to do is something like a radial basis
kind of approach where they're going to
get really nice smooth continuity cuz to
trying to look like water maybe I want
to make it look blockier with a harder
fall-off so maybe I go in there and
change it to a fairly tight smooth step
around the cube you know and things like
this the video where they were painting
that first painting part where they
showed like that seemed crisp enough
yeah yeah I agree but I don't I don't
know but it just it just I felt like
that'd be another thing I could screw
with to give the water an almost
unnatural look but one that reinforced
the gameplay in a way that might be cool
and you know maybe it might not be but
it's something
try which again usually what I'm looking
for when I look at something like this
and I have a very specific problem
statement like like you had I'm just
like how many options does this approach
give me because if the answer is I just
got to do this one thing and it comes
out the way it comes out that to me
doesn't sound very profitable because I
know that's probably not going to be
exactly what I want but this approach
was like okay there's a lot of things I
can screw with here I've got a coarse
grid and a super sampling step the super
sampling step is pretty arbitrary I
could blend it however I wanted to I
could adjust the way that was doing like
you said maybe I want to don't want to
test later maybe I just want to produce
like coloration values or normal maps
from it or whatever I could probably do
that because there's no it's not coupled
to the simulation which I really like
because the more couple days of
simulation the less flexibility gonna
have to change it without potentially
breaking everything and and all this
other crap so yeah so I felt like that
was I was like yes this is this this
feels good when I was thinking about
what you said and and remembering that
paper so anyway
well of course the problem now with this
discussion is to evaluate that paper
requires like a substantial amount of
engineering work that will not happen on
this stream that's correct so I don't
know where to take confession now
because it's sort of like well we try
that well dynamic dynamic sim is now the
question so there's the second part of
your thing which is like you know I push
push rocks in the water or I move rocks
out of the mouth of a thing yeah so
obviously that particular paper really
doesn't help us at all there I mean
maybe it helps us I mean they were they
were showing it evaluate no no I just
mean it doesn't help us because it
assumes we already have like the surface
of the water and all we're trying to do
is like up sample it to look good and
but in your case we don't actually have
that necessarily so like for example
let's the case I'm thinking of is when
you had that sort of pool sitting up
above the main level and it has this
mouth where the water can flow out right
so I'm thinking about the case where
I've got maybe one of those yellow
energy fields and so it's completely
blocked and then I remove the energy
field and now I want to see the water
come forward
like in a sort of way that creates the
resulting waterfall over time right I
don't just want to see it appear like I
want to see right and so while the
create and destroy River function that
part on the flat surfaces that part I
could see just hacking away at the
Nvidia method might produce okay results
I'm not sure it would but it might the
because you could just like make a
really turbulent parameters at the head
and tail or something right but I'm not
sure it will and then for the waterfall
case I don't see how it helps at all I
guess is what I'm saying so we still
need some idea of how that's going to be
tackled and so what I was thinking for
that is probably what I would say is I
feel like that's probably more where
your particles are gonna want to come
into play so the way I would probably
suggest tackling that the way I would
have started it is I've got a notion
both of where are the water tiles which
is what normally we're doing and let's
say we're sending them with something
like the Nvidia approach there but then
I've also got an ocean of tiles that are
becoming water so in other words they
weren't water and now because of a
gameplay state change when the gameplay
system comes in and starts tagging
things as newly water they I remember
that I had not been rendering them as
water previously so that state change
has happened in the game but the
renderer much like your animation system
is like trying to play catch-up so - is
this part of the water sim this water
Sam has now been basically given a
directive from the game hey quickly find
a way to make this look like it has
water and you're like okay and so then
what I would say is from that I would
say we probably want to now have a
particle flow like kind of a mixed
system where I'm going to be shooting
water particles from the water tile or
tiles around it into it and doing some
sort of volumetric rendering there be
because well there's only two things I
can think of to do one is that one and
then you use a level set method to
actually produce some water surfaces
until it fills up and the other one is
you know I don't know if we'd actually
work or not but it's like the only other
apps I can think of is you actually just
write something procedural which takes
the sides of water that are bordering
the cells that are newly water and you
have a way of displacing them forwards
in some procedural way that doesn't
involve shooting particles out and okay
so in terms of what we're gonna do
gameplay-wise mm-hmm like what are we
going to allow ourselves to do in terms
of level geometry yeah if you imagine so
we're talking about the case of you know
a yellow yellow force field keeping
water in and when you open it up what
happens yeah um what if there's just
like dry land below there and the water
goes down it has to go somewhere which
kind of sounds like what you're talking
about yeah I don't think we're gonna do
that okay then great I mean and and that
solves most of the problem like you
still have a problem of like you need
water traveling along this vertical
thing that somehow stylistically matches
the rest of the water but maybe that's
not that hard in theory you could
probably get away with doing something
pretty similar like so with the Nvidia
method you know their wave functions are
gonna be about upright water but you
could probably go ahead and hack those
wave functions to just be like waterfall
ask water and just use those on that
part of the water like I bet I could
make that work if you know again if I
study this for a while as a very first
approximation if you just like pretend
it's just flowing sideways yeah exactly
okay 90 degrees right exactly and then
like you know alter the higher
frequencies so that they're biased
downward or whatever so it's like yeah
things are I mean it have it's not it's
it's gonna be the kind of thing that
like you have to start
look at but I mean fundamentally
speaking it doesn't seem like an
impossibility right it's like look
there's wavefunctions
we can probably hack some together that
will produce a relatively believable
waterfall so we just apply the same
freaking technique to the water there as
we do elsewhere it just has a different
wavelength it's coated we know when we
output these in the same way that we
have the coarse mesh for everything else
we also have the coarse mesh for there
and they have specific values that say
I'm a waterfall as opposed to I'm moving
this direction that direction right yeah
and then of course you can always add
particles to taste yes you need to cover
things up mm-hmm okay well I mean I
guess that's what we're gonna try it
sounds like it makes sense to me I mean
of course I might go read the paper and
then say this is stupid
yep and more important than the paper I
would assume is just the also just going
look it's more just can we spend some
time trying to do wavefunction mixing
you know maybe the paper sucks but that
idea I think is okay so maybe just just
the broad idea could be profitable even
if the paper isn't you know yeah should
we do questions from the viewing public
now sure you feel like that's a good
time okay
KC will moderate your questions so type
the questions make sure they're the best
question that you've ever asked in your
life all the best questions and KC will
decide I will grab a snack while he's
doing that then I'll be back
how's the progress on the funnels
bearing beta Casey it's going it's a
pretty big project so it's been tough to
finish
[Music]
just a couple more minutes and I will be
ready so you know I don't usually have
food at home hmm
but way back at the start of quarantine
time I was like oh I need to get a lot
of food and then I was like all right
well I don't I don't usually eat at home
so why don't I get a lot of fun food
that I used to eat when I hit home like
when I was a kid so SpaghettiOs yeah and
at that time I invested this was a very
important investment in a box of brown
sugar cinnamon pop-tarts oh that is
serious quarantine food gotcha
and I feel that this investment has come
to maturity and it's it's time to
liquidate the investment and so I'm
doing that now so John know he left
by the way Gino's three I cannot overlay
John over his image because I don't have
a feed from John's camera his computer
can't do it unfortunately like it his
computer can't stream his webcam to me
while also capturing his screen for
twitch given so how much trouble we've
had so far
yeah like if I try to add the virtue
forget it splitter on top of all this
yeah yeah okay one sec
you know I haven't ever done the
separate streaming PC thing just because
I don't want to have more computers yeah
that might just be what I have to do I
actually highly recommend it even though
I absolutely hate computers just because
this is one case where you can just like
leave it set up and never touch it no
matter what you do to your dev machine
and that helps paper over the ridiculous
crap it's no easier to set up the first
time because it's still complete crap
and the capture card will be complete
crap and all that stuff but at least you
just like as much as possible leave it
in stasis until Windows updates itself
and ruins everything happens about every
6 months
yep ok are you ready yes ok so I guess I
would say you know no offense to the
chat but not a real not a really not a
really bumper crop today it's ok we're
gonna go through them anyway
so I'll start with the first question
which I don't I think has a pretty easy
answer so even though I don't think it's
particularly relevant necessarily it's
probably pretty easy an answer and that
is if there was way less time and budget
what sacrifices could be made to finish
this requirement faster and I have an
answer but I'll let you answer first it
doesn't really work that way like if
there were less time and budget globally
across the game you want to use the
Robyn Hitchcock from the Cure rule
mm-hmm and allocate sufficient
reasonable amounts of time to everything
to bring them all up to a particular
level right and so if you told me well
you only have a week to do water or
something I'd be like well that's gonna
put water
out of phase with everything else so
let's take some time away from something
else and put it on water however I have
another level of answer to that which is
you know so Casey you used to go to GDC
right yeah back when it didn't suck as
much yeah I used to go to GDC also and
even back then we thought it was pretty
terrible nah tonight so I what I will
say is 97 98 ish like right after it got
taken over but before they had time to
turn it to crap it was kind of amazing
like you know I remember it was a long
time ago but I remember talking to
Charles he was probably like 2000 or
2001 or something it was like I just
went to see a movie in the middle of the
day like yeah yep I know where you're
coming from okay so back when we used to
go to GDC one thing you will learn from
the wise people at GDC lecturing
incorporated mm-hmm is that you have to
scope your game
all right what you will learn from these
people is that whatever brilliant
amazing ideas you have for a game at the
outset they will tell you over and over
that you can't do all those things
mm-hmm and that 2/3 of the way through
development you'll find that you have to
dump half your game on the floor and
then Stitch the rest of it together and
rescue that in somehow ship that mm-hmm
right and then a lot of these games are
like Metacritic 65 don't even make any
money one of the reason you ship them
out the door was ostensibly to make
money and then a lot of these people the
company name on their badge when they
went to speak at GDC that company
doesn't exist anymore all right
okay still like yep I'm just saying
question the advice a little bit right
and so since I started my new way of
game design right which fortunately
we're still able to do because people
bought the witness right I have never
scoped a game where I'm making air
quotes with my finger scoping a game
means to cut it
from what you wanted to make to what you
actually can make both braid and the
witness went the other way they both got
bigger braids certainly maybe not in
terms of number of level like I didn't
know how big it was going to be in terms
of levels but in terms of like feature
set and you know how much time we spent
making it look nice and all that we did
way more right and then with the witness
it's just a massively bigger game like
we thought it would be at most you know
I figured it might be a 20-hour game
because braid was like a 5 hour game and
making a game four times as big would be
huge but it's like if you play
everything in the witness it's easily a
hundred hour game unless you're like
really fast at puzzles
it's just huge so the way I like to see
it is look if you're gonna put a lot of
effort into something anyway like it
takes it's not easy to make games right
even now with Unity game engine where
you press the make game button if you do
that you just have the same thing
everybody else has when they press the
make game button which isn't very good
right so it's hard it's hard to get to a
point where you're even able to release
something that's notable in any way
right mm-hmm
it takes you a decent amount of time and
effort to get there so why would you
then waste the opportunity that you
spent getting there by just like firing
it off a little too early and having it
not be that good right because then
it'll take you I don't know did it take
you two years to get to that point it's
gonna take you another two years or you
can get to that point again and have
another attempt at maybe being able to
make something good and so if your
response every time is I got a scope
this because it's been 2 years or
whatever then well I did I mean you you
the strategy you are undergoing has an
obvious result right and we just see
that over people's careers in the games
industry and like nobody stops to
question that
that said I'm notorious for taking a
long time doing game projects and you
don't have to take as long as we do
especially if you don't insist
building your own engine all the time
and all these things although it does
help with quality if you build your own
engine so like these are all decisions
that you can make I don't know I feel
like I've answered that question to a
reasonable degree mm-hmm so next
question is sort of a oh sorry
do you have anything to say about that
I hope the whole scoping thing and
because I know you're you're working on
your own thing that you've been working
on for a long time and I don't think you
feel like scoping it so I guess what I
would say is that I have mixed feelings
about this
here are my feelings about it so I think
scoping your life slash company is
incredibly important and scoping your
game is completely unimportant is the
guess the way I would say it because
when I try to assess like what makes
things I'm working on late it's almost
always that like I had too many other
things to do does that make sense are
you saying that work-life balance causes
you to not get work done
um no more like work work balance right
so like you know it's really hard to do
like handmade hero for example and also
work on a hard technical problem because
oftentimes like you need to be able to
go for like a month of time where your
brain is literally focused just on this
one thing right I agree
exactly engine and a game and it does
affect the quality of work like no
question yes and I think the problem is
that so okay so one thing I will say
like from what you just talked about is
I would say but you do kind of scope
your game a little bit right John
because you didn't pick
the hardest possible technical game to
do along with your compiler right and
that was a smart decision because you
could have picked a more technically
ambitious game right you easily could
have if you'd wanted to we could easily
come up with games that would have been
worse than this one now grant is as you
normally do you always go like let me
push what I can do to in this game to
the limit but you didn't go let me also
make the massively multiplayer online
first-person infinite view distance you
know a thousand people per server game
right which you could have done if you
weren't trying to say let me pick the
easiest to scope of my ideas to go with
my compiler yeah so that was a smart
decision right I would like to use a
different verb for that because I think
of those as relatively orthogonal things
okay like yeah you absolutely should be
smart at the outset about what you're
deciding to build yeah I mean that's the
the canonical newbie mistake is like kid
gets out of school and wants to get in
videogames and wants to make the super
MMO sports spaceship game or what you
know just like put everything in there
and it's like well actually it's very
difficult to do what you're talking
about
mhmmm so that is that is universal right
it's very hard to make games and you
need to respect that going in even going
back to braid though when I did braid it
was like look I have this history of not
finishing projects how do I help ensure
that I finish this one I'm gonna do a
2-d game yeah because I don't want to
deal with 3d right that was like a
foundational decision and it paid off
right it looked like that's just what
that was so that is true that is
different however then like giving up on
your dreams in the middle of development
yep sort of I mean I you could have a
hybrid of those things where it's like I
guess I'm learning now what is
practically able to be accomplished and
when I made this decision early on I
didn't really know but the people who
lecture for GE see lack
Incorporated LLC don't really have that
excuse because they've made like four
games before or whatever they should
know and they still say well you have to
scope your game every time and I'm like
no just make a better make a better
decision about what you're going to
build or work in a situation where
you're not as budget constrained right
yeah which also has implications on what
you can build right like I cannot build
a Assassin's Creed ragnerok or whatever
cuz like I just don't have that kind of
money yeah I could build an indie
version of an assassin's Creed game with
that kind of gameplay but like I just
can't build those huge Maps no you know
historically accurate things yeah but
because I don't try to do that we have
money to pay people to stay employed for
extra years beyond you know what we
originally would have scheduled or
whatever which is why we don't have to
like scope the game in the GDC lecture
sense yeah all right way too much on
this point I think ok next point and I
don't necessarily think the question
quite gets at the answer that is
actually useful but I'll ask the
question what about refractions and
seeing the seabed with some kind of
caustics i can be the answer is we
already have a very cheap basic version
of that like if i if i zoom in here I
mean maybe I'm too zoomed now as you can
sort of see if you look at those two
yellow blocks I think they're obscured
at the moment well no they're actually
not because they're taped there over
your face as well the problem is the
framerate is really low
okay so if you look at these blue Icee
okay let me I've got to lock the camera
and then all tab oh I locked it in the
wrong place
so if you look real close I mean there's
a lot of motion on the screen but you'll
see that the edges of these stones are
not solid they're actually they're
actually wavy they wave a little bit
that's because we are doing some
diffraction or refraction or whatever
that you want to call it it's not a
great deal right now but we already do
that like the shader the shader for the
ocean decides you know decides it gets
drawn after the background gets drawn
and it decides where to sample from that
background which is not a physically
correct thing to do but it is the
general hack that videogames often do to
create the impression of that and then
you know there are little geometric
tricks you can try to do to get it sort
of as close as you can to what it really
is right but again in this kind of a
game we can do that kind of a trick
heavily whereas in a game like the
witness we couldn't do that kind of a
trick we had to be physically accurate
for reasons of gameplay right so it's
actually kind of a relief to be able to
do weird hacks and stuff that said right
if we wanted to do a higher powered
version of that like I'm sure there's a
whole literature on just like how to do
5% better oh yeah I know water
refraction right so that's not like by
the time you're at a point where you're
like look I have I know what the height
of the water is per pixel and I have a
scene in the background that I know what
the depth buffer is and stuff or or I
can do some pre computed stuff just in
3d without the you know pre
rasterization or whatever like you can
do it really a lot with that and I'm not
really worried about that yeah yeah I
mean I guess what I would say to the
question is just like we're kind of
talking more right now about how do we
produce something that allows us to get
information about what the water surface
should be and how we then choose to rent
that is actually a totally separate
question that actually can be answered
in a whole variety of ways that may be
completely decoupled from how you figure
out what the surface should roughly look
like if that makes sense so you know I
mean everything from on r-tx cards we
run a ray tracer from the water surface
to actually produce the exact thing to
some kind of random hack with screen
space sampling is on the table and you
know that's usually not that hard to
decouple from the where the heck is the
water surface or what is this turbulence
at a particular point which is what we
kind of needed to know here
all right so question what about making
a prototype scene to set the stylistic
direction I have no idea what John wants
the water to look like okay that is
something that we do for most aspects of
the game however okay step one okay when
artists develop a style for a game right
partially they're working from ideas or
like sketches or something but partially
what they are doing is figuring out how
to use the tools that you give them in
the engine or in terms of what content
generation tools you have or whatever
figuring out what they can do with those
things that looks good and how to make
things look good with those things right
so if you're saying well just have them
make a concept for water it's like well
they don't have tools for water because
we haven't built the tools for water
because we don't know what those are yet
and so if they make any concept for
water well you can start doing that but
then it's not going to be constrained by
the other so like you can go into max or
Maya and like render a scene that has
cool-looking water and that could help a
little bit but it's not guided by any of
the stuff that we're talking about and
then at that point also is not guided by
you know is it real-time or not in is it
so real-time that you can throw it into
your scene and not worry about framerate
right or or even and there are other
questions like does it take a consistent
amount of time like whatever method is
being used for this water right um one
thing we did do before was you know one
person who was working on this at that
time likes Unreal Engine a lot and did a
little bit of Unreal Engine prototyping
but like it never really looked like any
like you know what water looks like in
an Unreal Engine game and it looked like
that it was like well if we want that we
know how to do that
it's just that prototyping never got
beyond that point it's possible that we
could have done that but again like part
of our job and establishing this style
of this game is to like like you want to
be a little bit new you want to just
like not copy everybody right if you
can't if you can't figure out anything
new to do then that's fine but we
already should be able to figure out new
things to do because we already have new
inputs like I don't think I've ever
played a game that has these like grid
based orthogonal River flows where you
disrupt rivers and stuff right and so
that kind of leads you to at least a
slightly different implementation than
whenever everyone else has also we're
still in a situation where technology
keeps improving over time and so just
the fact that you have better technology
than the people four years ago who made
whatever other and but by that I mean
the hardware technology right there's a
lot more transistors going the software
technology is actually worse but you
know we kind of suffer through that so
all these things mean you should be able
to do something new or different or good
and so then if you use like an old
codebase or old system to prototype
something you maybe preemptively closing
doors on ideas of how to do things you
know because because that system was
made like let's say it's old enough that
just nobody
of thought to run a high-res fluid sim
at all because maybe maybe shaders
didn't even have that ability we can go
back that far
right it's like okay well if you decide
that that looks good then you're setting
a threshold for what you're going to
accept that's you know maybe a little
too low so for all those reasons we
haven't done that yet but also though
right once we program some stuff here
and I'm like oh this is kind of good I
think this I think this is related to
what we can ship you know it'll of
course get revised a few times um only
at that point do we start figuring out
the style of the the water in the game
really because that is one of the people
on the art team take these tools and say
okay we're gonna start making stuff with
this right then we're gonna discover
like oh they want to have this ability
and they don't have it or whatever like
they should be able to do this thing or
they can do this thing and it should
look better than it does and why doesn't
it look that good or we all that kind of
thing comes out that happens but when
you're creating the technology that
happens after you create the technology
so I have a different answer that
question it's similar to what you just
said but it's a little bit broader I
guess and that is that when you're
talking about defining the look of
anything doesn't really matter what it
is when you're just doing aesthetic
experimentation it's not true that
iteration is always fastest and most
productive when given to the art team so
artistic iteration is meaning if the
thing that you're talking about is
fundamentally based on a sketching or
layering kind of process then artists
are fastest because that's their trade
it's using repetitive application of
tools to produce a result but when
you're talking about something like
water there really has never been even
in the history of all animation that I
know of including film a time when
primarily the art department produced
the water and the reefs
for that as water is far too complex for
an artist to produce with a brush pretty
much period and so what's always
happened is you have an iteration
process that involves programmers
generating tools for artists and then
the artists use those tools and it feeds
back on itself and this has happened
even since the very first time that we
had fluid dynamics in film for example
at DreamWorks on I want to say Prince of
Egypt this is exactly what happened and
it's gone from there right so in the
case of John's game specifically it
would make very little sense to ask an
artist to iterate on the water because
it's very hard for artists to produce
water effects they have to use plugins
for their favorite and I use that term
in quotes Autodesk product that sort of
produce water sometimes and oftentimes
not very well and often not very
controllable and so on and so forth it
takes a tremendous amount of artist time
to set up these simulations it's very
difficult for them to do much to them
and they take a long time to render so
the iteration time for your art staff on
water effects is usually lower than the
iteration time for your programmers and
so typically if you have programmers
with an aesthetic eye on your team you
give them the water sim first and then
you count it to your artist not the
other way around if you literally have
no programmers who understand what looks
good and what don't then you may be in a
situation where you have to head to the
art team first but normally that just
isn't the decision you would make and
it's not the decision anyone makes as
far as I know okay
so here is a question that is I guess
it's just someone wanting us to clarify
maybe when I was talking about the
Nvidia paper but the question is could
you elaborate on why you need to
multiply two noises to draw the grid
instead of using a 3d noise with dziak
as the time axis a noise multiply as a
noise part so I can probably take that
question unless you want to I mean
there are two there are multiple things
going on right there's how do you
animate it at all which like the 3d
question will answer but there's also
like you don't want a boring noise
function you want something multi scale
right and so you need to create that in
some way I would say like like we don't
you know we have very particular desires
like we don't want large portions of the
grid to be erased at one time so that
you can't see the lines over a very
broad place but if we just speckle a
bunch of little holes around through the
lines then they're gonna be pretty
consistent like there's actually a
stylistic balance right that we're
trying to achieve and I mean what yeah I
don't know okay that's all I have to say
on that so what I was gonna say is part
of that is just like when you're hacking
stuff together like you're gonna make
something that happens to look good at
the time my guess is that the grid
probably will change because once you
have the final water system in you'll
probably become a lot more obvious what
actually wants to happen there and then
at that point it'll be like yeah so the
way we do it is we sample the water soon
which tells us something about the grid
and then we use some noise on top of
that because we want to use some
displacement not related to the water
and off we go right so I'm guessing even
once the grid is like this is exactly
what we want it to be it probably will
come from multiple sources because
typically you want sources that both
capture underlying phenomena which are
coming from one system and ones that are
about an authorial input that is about
the grid only itself right so typically
it's not uncommon for wanting to apply
multiple inputs to create something
because you're trying to capture
different opinions about what should
happen oftentimes one comes from
gameplay or comes from simulation and
the other comes from tweaking that you
want to lay on top of it to maintain
certain aesthetic criteria that are
separate yeah and also
once we have more stuff like say we say
we do this other water simulator or even
say we just did the the particle one
that we have right now and just beefed
it up got it further along we would have
more material to work with
right so as long as you've got some
model of like some waves that go up and
down right then you might be like well
we can create a more visually integrated
scene by using that variation to provide
some of the some of the appearance and
disappearance for the grid lines that we
want so that we're not multiplying it by
some arbitrary external noise functions
so like for example maybe in the troughs
of waves it fades out and maybe at the
peak it doesn't fade out and maybe that
by itself isn't like enough to get you
to the style that you want but maybe
it's like half or two-thirds of it and
then you can do the rest of it with a
noise function that you layer on top of
that or something but but the more that
you have to work with that
there's just a there's a way of making
things where everything is related and
everything that can be used is used well
and so you should look for those
opportunities if you can and yeah and
and so so if you say well this is our
prototype of how the grid lines were
done early on and we don't want to
change it then you may miss those
opportunities as you improve your
implementation of the other things so
next question is there seems to be a
trade-off between visual realism and
gameplay clarity similar to the movement
system however unlike the movement
system it seems that water will look
weirder if non continuous than character
movement what do you think is a good
trade-off and what are the knobs you
could tweak to make the trade-off go one
way or the other well I will it look
weirder or really just looks vile eyes
right so okay this is gonna be weird
because we just we just redid all our
tone mapping and all this stuff so
colors are really messed up but let me
pick something like this let me get rid
of the extra so I mean here's a an
island or a set of islands it's grid
based the grading is very clear you
don't really have questions about where
you can stand on this if anything I
would say that the little ocean pattern
in the background is a little too noisy
like the bubbles pattern but you can
imagine that's part of like me breaking
all the ocean shaders and stuff right
like the water here used to look a lot
better but just you know the point that
I want to make is about the land
it's very artificially conforming to
grid squares like you don't ever expect
an island to look like this but it's
stylized and it looks coherent and the
game sells it to you so it's fine right
you can do the same thing with water
that's all I have to say about that I
think I don't know um mmm
so the only thing I would add to that is
that as far as knobs are concerned I
think we kind of already talked about
that when we were talking about like
when I was sort of pitching the like
maybe start with that Nvidia paper as an
example approach you have a lot of knobs
to turn you have what do those wave
functions look like that you're sampling
to create the wave pattern
what's the interpolation fall-off that
you're using to blend them together what
are you doing on the source coarse mesh
right so you have tons and tons and tons
of knobs and I guess the meta comment is
just one of the reasons that I went to
that first as a method to suggest was
specifically because I feel like it has
a lot of actual options which i think is
what you want in this kind of scenario
yeah so so going back to another island
example here for a second like it's not
the case that we just randomly did
someone said let's make islands that
look good and then randomly did
something and did it right it was like
we experimented we prototyped we were
like how how how square or non square do
we need these to be right if they're too
square they look weird if they're too
non square then you end up in situations
where you know it looks like you should
be able to get like cross diagonals that
you can't actually cross or you know it
just looks weird that your character is
standing on a square and is actually
like halfway in the water or a block
looks like it should fall and so we
weigh all these
given the base technology that we have
for this which is let's just so first we
could place some flat pieces down right
and then we have like some edge pieces
and there's I forget how to manipulate
it but there's like a decal layer that's
creating all this coloring so you see as
I move this piece around there's like a
decal being projected on top of it I
don't
okay there's like this and then I forget
how you there's like a little editor
where you can splat down the decals in
there so anyway we had some set of tools
for things like this right and then even
these little views it aligns in the
middle there our art direction rules
that we came up with which is like look
these can be organic and stuff that's
fine but they shouldn't they shouldn't
am big you ate the grid right so these
are sort of near the grid lines and you
look at this and you can your brain
knows where the square is and here
there's like a dark shaded bit but
you're it's in the square and your brain
knows where it is right if you come
along and use these tools to like do
this right suddenly you're making a mess
and it's not as good anymore and if I
had more time I can mess it up more and
so it's it's not like like when you look
at it at a relatively finished thing
that's had some thought into it like
this it's easy to just assume that
that's what happens when you decide to
make an island and quote make it look
nice or whatever but actually there's a
substantial thought process that goes
into very specific trade-offs and so
with water again you have those same
trade-offs and we haven't been able to
make those yet because we haven't really
implemented anything that that was ready
for production yet right so all that
comes a little later I forget I forget
how that ties in to what Casey was
saying but it totally does ok so someone
asked side note do you know if that
paper helped make the water in sea of
Thieves
I have no idea but I doubt it cuz sea of
thieves is older than that paper next
question do you have a specific approach
when implementing something out of a
paper sometimes they are quite heavy
sorry quite hand-wavy regarding
implementation details I've been burned
by papers so many times that I just
don't trust them I have a very low
opinion of of quote computer science
unquote papers that claim like if
they're about if they're about a mathy
part of computers
science I feel like I can depend on them
like if they're like you know this is
our proof that it takes oh of this many
steps to do this thing or whatever or
you know that kind of thing I think is
fine the kind that are like we got a 12%
speed up by doing the following thing
like almost all of those are garbage and
I've been very specifically I've done
jobs where even like prior to I'm
thinking of a very specific incidents
but like there had been some new papers
out I've had friends say oh yeah this is
great little did I know they didn't
actually implement them in anything
serious
I went in took a contract where I had
one month to make this thing work and I
couldn't make it work and there was no
other option that would work for the
earth you know these days with the
amount of experience that I have I could
have cobbled something together but then
I was just like I don't like I failed a
contract basically because this research
paper sucked and because I didn't know
what else to do
so yeah man I don't know like and I've
had I've had experiences like that
several times I was doing a thing in
terrain generation once where there was
a paper that claimed to be very fast and
I implemented it and I was like oh it's
not that fast actually and I wrote up a
thing about how it wasn't that fast they
could make it faster and the author of
the paper was like oh but these five
words deep deep in this paragraph out of
this five to seven page paper there's
five words that suggest something that
maybe solved this problem and I'm like
dude you didn't I can tell you didn't do
this work and you didn't publish it in
the source code and you don't know how
much this actually makes you faster or
not so like what I don't know just too
many bad experiences the incentives for
the people who publish these papers are
all wrong so so the answer is just if
I'm going in to implementing a paper
it's with extreme skepticism and an
expectation that it may not work and
that I certainly wouldn't ever do it on
a deadline anymore and then
it's with the expectation that I may
have to use the paper just as a starting
point and as a source of maybe ideas of
how to do things and then branch away
from that in terms of it actually doing
something that's good so let me take a
quick second to answer one of the
questions the that sort of popped up
that's really easy to answer really
quickly and it was so you have the
procedural method you have now more or
less and you have the baked method
provided by Nvidia couldn't you use
something similar to the way a specular
reflection map works to blend between
the two or is that we're saying already
so yeah just to be clear if if it wasn't
already the Nvidia paper is backed by a
Sim so if you want to you can just use
the simulation as your course grid or
blend the simulation between painted and
Sims however you want it's not like the
Nvidia paper is baked it's actually not
this the Nvidia paper is a sim and then
up sampling and it's the up sampling
part where you add into fine detail
waves that's that's what's going on
basically okay let's see so I think one
person said can you show the water and
the other more complete levels and talk
about what goes on there I think that's
what you kind of just have on the screen
right now right I mean all the water is
basically wrecked compared to how it
looked like this water here looked a lot
better two weeks ago you know and it's
just in part like you can see how it's
maybe if I turn off my face again you
can see how it's a little shiny in the
upper right corner and maybe looks a
little bit like somebody put effort in
at one point like it used to look a lot
more like that it's just like changing
all the the tone mapping process and
thus the calibration of all the
materials in the entire game like we
changed our dynamic range and then I
broke the water like all sorts of things
have happened so we have approximately
zero examples anymore of water
it's actually supposed to be trying to
look good which is then why this is a
good time to sort of pick it up and go
again so that we have like something you
know so this is now I think we're just
down to kind of broader questions oh
well there's one more that I guess I can
sort of answer there's a question that
says how about a detailed enough
cellular automata that represents
pressure for the water sixteen by
sixteen per tile for example so that is
what a water sim is cellular automata
and finite element analysis tomorr
basically just the same kind of idea
they are well to be a little bit more
complete so there's two ways you can
think of simulate simulations or two
main methods that you use one is called
or Larian and one's called Lagrangian or
Larian methods are ones that operate on
a fixed grid or a fixed set of points
and the grungy and methods are ones that
operate on points that move around in
space and then there are mixed models
which use a combination of the two
that's like when you get things you know
a popular method for example as a modern
method would be material point methods
which are mixed mixed methods that use
the mix of the two cellular automata is
just one word for the update step on an
oil Arian update model so if you have a
grid that has quantities represented on
the grid cellular automata is a thing
that says look I just look at the
neighbors to this grid and I have a
basically binary composite rule that
just gives me like here's the output of
the thing it doesn't involve actually
solving anything on the grid or even
attempting to solve anything on the grid
real fluid dynamics is basically
cellular automata taken up a notch right
it's you actually have equations that
you're trying to solve and you try to
structure your grid update step to
produce actual approximations to
solutions of equations on the grid that
you want to be true water in particular
this is important because water is an
incompressible fluid as opposed to say
smoke which is not what that means is
water when you push on it it comes out
the other end right
can't become more dense it has to move
if you push on one end of water it comes
out the other end that's just how water
works it's incompressible it can't be
made to occupy higher densities in some
places and lower densities and others as
opposed to say smoke or other gaseous
phenomena so as a result it's very
important that you have something that
approximates some kind of fluid
simulation if you actually want to
simulate water because it has to
simulate the effect of fairly rapidly
propagating the water across the grid so
that things when you push on one side
they need to come out the other side and
they can't just get denser in the middle
and kind of stick there which is
something this cellular automata would
generally do so I guess what I would say
is what you're talking about
is exactly what we're talking about
fluid Sims are fundamentally like the
you know the next level of cellular
automata already it's not a fair
assessment John would you say you know
it's not exactly my area of expertise
mine either
so what Casey said is fine as far as you
know okay next question is do you have
any hard and fast rules about creating
tools for team members to use things
like everything must be undoable etc
well I got mad once when somebody did
some basic stuff that wasn't like
especially when like somebody who shall
not be named right now in part because
you shouldn't ever shouldn't even be
talking about this in public at all but
something that happened that that made
me kind of upset was somebody decide
okay there's a way there's a general
system that I've been using for enemy
management going back many years right
and actually at handmade con this one
time I talked to Casey about it a little
bit because we were talking about
serialization and deserialization and
like I think I went into some details
maybe maybe I actually did a follow up
stream I think that's what happened was
I posted a follow up stream on YouTube
because we
go into as much detail as we could but
you know anyway it is just a way of
arranging how do you serialize how do
you DC realize how do you memory manage
so like if there are strings on entities
that you need to be able to type in and
change in the editor right like someone
needs to know that that's a string that
needs to get freed when the entity you
know is destroyed or whatever right and
so how does all that work well you know
sometimes people make decisions that are
really annoying so okay so for example
serialization and deserialization is how
undo work so if you want to change the
texture map on an entity right and then
you control Z that changed the entity
comes back and it looks like what it did
before because you undid the change to
the string field and then it looks up it
looks up the name of the texture like
when you undo something it there's a
little like hey reinitialize this guy
because he came out of the undo system
and whatever whatever you might need to
do to be able to get him live again do
that and so for example the name of the
texture map on the thing is in a string
field and then when you make the entity
live or whatever would you make it
active you look up that texture in the
asset list and then you put you put that
texture
well whatever now you have a pointer to
a texture instead of a string and you
can use that to render the guy right
hopefully people out there know what I'm
talking very very standard thing so in
past engines I always did that as to
very explicit separate steps there's a
string field and then you look up the
texture later because I like the clarity
of that and the lack of ambiguity now
for this engine we're doing some
experiments like well you know you have
better metadata for things maybe we can
just realize that something's a pointer
to a texture and just not store the
string field but that introduced a bunch
of difficulties but you know somebody
decided to do that change and didn't
sufficiently think about it and it
caused a lot of problems that that if it
were me doing it I like to think I would
have at least
the thought of most of those problems or
found them within the few days of
playing around with this major major
change that I would have done before
exporting into the team so for example
let's say you typo a text or name right
when you're in when you're in the editor
and what happens does it give you an alt
text or back if it gives you an alt text
or back there's no record of what you
typed because there's no string field
and now how do you correct your typos
without retyping the whole frickin thing
right if something if a texture pointer
goes into undo did you do the manual
work of pulling that back out of undo
right or did you just you know just say
oh it's fine just somebody asked to type
the text your name again if you undo it
right there was a third one that was
important
what if you type the name of a texture
field first and then you want to hot
load the texture second which was
something you could do before just fine
does that work now right so when you
make a change like that like at least
don't break things at least make sure
that everything is good especially if
the change that you're making is sort of
academic at some level like it's not
really academic it's like it's maybe a
little bit more efficient sort of or
like you don't have to have two copies
of data or something but the the team
the artists and including me the
designer at the time wants to just be
able to do stuff and not not like have
scrap breaking on us all the time and so
when you make a change like that here's
what I would say is you shouldn't make
changes to code that people use unless
you use that yourself and know what it's
gonna do and know what the failure modes
are which is a little bit easier said
than done because everybody uses tools a
little differently I use the editor in
the game all the time I use it in a
different way than the artists do
there's a lot of things they do that I
don't do there's a lot of things I do
that they don't do so it's very hard to
get complete coverage on that but like
you shouldn't be messing that stuff up
right like if you and then again an
extra part of the problem is just even
though I tell people hey bug us if
there's a problem they often won't
because they just work around it or they
know that we're all super busy and have
other stuff to do and so then you know
we go eight months to a year with like
some major stupid problem that caused
everybody a lot of headache that like
could have been fixed in you know two
hours or something a year ago and it
didn't get fixed and then the more the
more you're in an environment where
there's more of those problems happening
the more people just expect those
problems and won't notify you about them
right and so I don't know it's not easy
because at the same time if you're a
small independent developer there's a
reality on a limit to how much work you
can do so you really can't address some
of
sometimes for a while but you especially
don't want to be as an individual
engineer you don't want to be pushing
that in the wrong direction right you
want to be making that stuff worse if
you do then it's not a good scene so
next question is are there any level
design ideas that involve realistic
fluid mechanics like conservation of
mass hydraulic jumps venturi effect etc
for this game though it's just not what
the game is and then the last question I
think we had was what do you do when you
think that there is no solutions to the
problem you have
I give up cancel the game and quit the
game industry what do you think I mean
that's what all successful people do
right I don't think I've ever actually
seen a problem where I didn't think
there was some solution to it because
fundamentally speaking games are about
you know usually finding the right
approximations to problem to solutions
like you know we don't really need to
simulate water as water actually behaves
we just need to make something that we
think is aesthetically pleasing and
there's many axes you can explore to get
there
so usually you ask for an example yeah
from this questionnaire about what what
is an unsolvable problem that's a good
that's a good point
what would be an example of a problem
that has no solution
the halting problem yeah thankfully we
don't generally need that in game design
no even the halting problem right like
so all of these things have solutions a
tweet everyone agrees with that's the
best answer well I mean I knew I had
some less politically correct ones but
in terms of like actual non social
problems let's say right so like halting
problem even seems impossible right but
the way that you approach that kind of a
thing is you you step back right and you
make your universe of discourse be a
thing that contains the halting problem
that is bigger so that you know how to
like deal with the halting problem you
know where it comes up and you know how
to you know how to employ it to solve
things right so like I don't know like
like solving solving problems is not
always
the thing that makes some people a lot
better than other people at solving
problems is the ability to not just sit
there and grind on the obvious things
and to have some imagination about what
do you actually do here to to improve
this situation do we have a non joke
answer to that I don't I don't think so
cuz I mean you said because you know
sometimes when people ask that question
I have some in mind yeah they're working
on their own game and they're like man I
was trying to do this thing and it
didn't of course other times it's just
people want to ask a question right and
it doesn't doesn't make sense
I don't see a non joke answer really
well do I recall the tie I just saw a
question going but that's off topic Oh
someone asked Casey you didn't give an
answer to the implementing papers
question you seem to be fairly
up-to-date with papers so I think you
are less skeptical so I think I actually
answered this question at hand made
caught as well in the Q&amp;A session at
handmade con 2016 I actually have a
complete answer to it but for me I just
basically go and I crawl all the
research for the past 10 years or so and
I look at it all and I basically go okay
what are what is the breakdown of the
way that people are solving these
problems and usually you can luck out
and there'll be some survey papers which
you can use to like crawl rese crawl the
bibliographies for but even generic like
non papers that are just making some
random contribution in the field
typically have a giant related work
section that basically has a
bibliography that can get you most of
the way there and so I feel like
typically what happens is as you start
to read enough of these papers you get a
pretty good idea of where the actual
seminal work was and it's pretty rare
for seminal papers not to actually
explain how they frickin work it's
usually like later papers that don't
explain what the heck is going on and
they just like have a bunch of random
nom and clay chore thrown in for no
reason I think part of this is because
people who crack the problem first tend
to be the kind of thinkers who usually
can explain the
problems other people most of the time I
find so by the time I've looked through
enough of the back story I find there's
not that much that I can't grapple with
and then it's just a question of sitting
down and actually working through it on
a you know with pen and paper or code
right and it takes a little while like
you've got to sit down because
especially if fluid dynamics you're
gonna see a bunch of partial
differential equations and those aren't
my strong suit anyway so I got to sit
there and go like okay like what's this
actually saying like oh okay I see
whatever so that part is gonna be slow
no matter what you do but you know
generally I find it's fine and most of
the time I don't think of it I don't
think of that process is I'm gonna sit
down and implement this paper I think of
that process is I'm using the research
to help me decide what I'm going to
implement and what I end up implement
menteng tends to not be from any one
paper it tends to be what I think will
then solve my problem using all of the
tools that all of these people have
discovered in their attempts because now
I get it right so typically I don't look
at research papers as something to
implement anyway that's just not what I
do I tend to think of research papers as
educating me about what people have
tried so that then I can figure out what
I want to try and it saves me a
tremendous amount of time because I'm
basically getting all of their work that
I don't have to do because they
experimented with something and came up
with a thing and now I don't have to
spend the time expiring to come up with
that thing I may have to experiment to
cope with other things but not that one
because they already did it
so there's one more here it seems more
important that Stillwater remains still
in the entire still tile then flowing
water remains flowing in the entire flow
tile as long as there is some flow if
you want to sim you could pretend all
still squares are filled in and do sim
of the flowing squares only because
waves can be summed you can do an on
flowing somewhat still simulation with
all water tiles ignoring any flow they
may have add those two layers together
to get the final waves so that's again
that's not that dissimilar to what was
going on with the Nvidia paper right
it's just like a little bit better
version of that like if your constraint
was you have to use the code that's
already here and and honestly though you
might even so you know right now if I go
back to the this level um
well right now anything's real quiet
because I just started it but one of the
the KC's face on one of the things that
happens after it warms up a little bit
and by the way that's one of the
annoying things about this particular
thing is like how long do you have to
run it before it's in a steady state but
you know like so the way we sim these
particles is the particles get
accelerated way extra if they're inside
the gameplay flow and then not so much
if they're outside and of course they
have a continuous acceleration across
those boundaries because you want to see
like velocity discontinuities but they
could just be heavily heavily damped in
a way that they actually aren't right
and so that would solve so this place
where it's among the worst so if you see
this
the question then is you know you you
get something that's good
I feel like Johnson her net maybe dying
well I don't know what to say
now you're returning you have returned
John you're great you've been
resurrected I said basically everything
I think that I was gonna say there I
don't think anyone heard it okay
well it's just to say we could damp we
could damp the stuff artificially but
like there's a sense in which when you
do that you are you are implementing
things that are counter to the good
thing that you're supposedly getting out
of the system right and so then what do
you you know you have to question your
your core thesis that this is a good way
to do it if if you're then going and
subtracting a lot of that you know like
if I just ran a water Sam on the
background that might be a little better
actually than damping things because at
least then the flow directions would not
be super related but then would it just
be weird cuz it's going in a totally
weird direction I don't know so someone
had a kind of a interesting suggestion
that I think is worth mentioning sort of
broadened perhaps a little bit which is
could the riverbed play a more prominent
role and be more or less shallow and
explain why water moves or doesn't and I
kind of like that idea it's like could
the under water features be structured
in a way to help explain why the water
does what it does and the only problem I
think you'd run into there is because
the river changes course based on player
action it becomes harder if the player
couldn't do that then you could try to
construct the underwater area to
reinforce what's going on but that
becomes harder when you can
when it can change well also the thing
the thing to realize is the underwater
you know for these rivers that you can
see that are going right to left for
example if you draw what's at the bottom
of that empty square of stuff you know
it's substantially it's almost on the
next grid square you know at this angle
and so if you can see that clearly now
you start having features that seem like
coherent physical features that are in
the wrong place for you to like be
looking at them you know what I mean
so like if you look at the the yellow
stones that are there sort of like that
nook I have the water tuned right now to
be very heavily damping of them visually
you can see them if you look real close
but you know part of that is just to
make it very clear like what what square
are these in and if you start to lose
that then the question is does this
thing help you enough to make that worth
it and the answer is probably no in that
case especially because we want it you
know we want to have custom like little
visuals along the bottom that help
create the setting for any particular
level and like now do those have to be
destructible or something in case you
make an ocean go over it like I don't
even know so I I don't think that would
be high on the list of things to
entertain that said once you start going
down these routes of alternative
solutions to things sometimes you enter
a space where it's like oh I didn't
think ideas like that made sense but now
I totally see how they do so I wouldn't
totally rule it out either so I think
that's all the questions okay so that's
it we we got away much lighter this time
there's only three hours that's less
than that if you count the twenty to
twenty hours of messing with the stream
yes yes there was a lot of you trying to
not make OBS
all the frames yeah that was really
great alright alright everybody thank
you for coming by if you missed parts of
this the video will be up on YouTube
later on you can of course go to
handmade hero at twitch.tv slash
handmade underscore hero to see KC work
on really amazing water simulation
everyday or not at all or not at all
yeah you're still doing light stuff now
right where is that yeah light
propagation is really hard to do good
and fast that's true it's it's I said it
at the beginning I was like this is
going to be the worst thing we have to
do and I was right unsurprisingly
alright well if you want to do light
propagation instead of water propagation
you can go there they're pretty similar
except one has yeah well I won't even go
down that route they're that similar
alright bye everybody take it easy