hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream again just to get people
up to speed because there's been some
changes lately
handmade hero now has a discord server
you can go to use for chat it's a lot
better than the twitch chat and we do
take questions from there there's a
pound live channel that I read in during
the Q&amp;A and there's also other stuff on
there case you're interested there's a
bunch of people chatting in there it's
been pretty good so I'd highly recommend
checking that out all you have to do is
just click this button the discord
button there and it will bring you to
this page which allows you to join
that's about all you have to do and then
you are off and running now if you are
using the watch page well we've got you
covered there as well there's that
discord button right there and that
should do it looks like we need to
update this page again because it looks
like it's having trouble I think I hate
to say it but I want to say twit sent
out a notice that they changed their API
I think I'm gonna have to go update our
server code because I think they
probably changed it I don't actually
know but I think they did so we're
probably gonna have to fix that I'm not
looking forward to it but point being if
you're using the watch page there's a
discord on here as well most people
don't use the watch page obviously they
just use the episode guide or they go to
twitch but well I mean they use the
watch page to get the episode guide but
they don't necessarily use this thing
because you know it's oh this is just a
twitch bubble but anyway maybe we'll
change this to two just click on the
button I don't know as then then they'll
go to twitch or something like this I'm
not sure but I'll have to update that
because I think twitch changed your API
and probably broke our code but we'll
see anyway moving on now that we've got
that out of the way and you have two
options to push a button that says
discord and go to the Hammett hero
discord that's actually the Mali rocket
discord but obviously that covers
handmade here we will get down to
programming which if you remember
correctly we had just finished doing a
bunch of sort of optimization work on
our crafts pipeline
just light stuff - to get us running
fairly efficiently without a lot of fuss
it was surprising how much of an
improvement we got by being a little bit
careful with how we did our multi sample
resolves and then we also improved the
speed of our transmission for
transmitting dynamic vertices down in
the case of things like ground cover
where we have a lot of them and what you
get seen now is when we actually look at
the profile we're actually doing really
well we're running at about 120 frames a
second not quite which is quite well our
target is only 60 so we're like well in
advance of that now and that's good
because if you look at what we've got to
work with in terms of you know 3d stuff
how we're gonna be you know how we're
gonna be starting to stress this
pipeline more we're gonna have to move
into the land of lightning now and
lighting is gonna cost us so that's
really why I want to do this I wanted to
make sure we had a pretty good graphics
submission pipeline at at first and you
know I think we've got that pretty well
taken care of so what I want to do today
is start to actually send down lighting
information for these probes you can see
the purple color is there's little cubes
those cubes are everywhere that there is
a light probe placed currently and as
you can see right now there's two light
probes per tile we don't actually know
if that's what we're going to do in the
final game it's just sort of an
approximation and it's just the first
guess of like how we might want to do it
but that's how we're doing it at the
moment and so what we want to do now is
figure out how we're gonna actually
query these light probes in the shader
so what you can see right now is
lighting is effectively turned off it's
turned off because we have not
implemented anything that samples these
light probes and we have not actually
produced working code on the other side
for computing the lighting and the light
probes either so we now have to work on
both of those things and have them meet
in the middle what I want to do first
is I want to get the light sampling
working without actually doing any light
computation the reason for that is I'd
like to take light computation which is
going to be much harder to optimize out
of the equation first because it's the
slower of the two things and it's the
one that we probably want to do on the
CPU right now to avoid stressing the GPU
too much on lower-end of machines
obviously on our TX machines we could
just dump all the ray-tracing
directly to the card and call it a day
but for our purposes here we probably
want to do CPU tracing for most low-end
platforms and on our TX cards and so on
and so what I'd like to do now is say
let's take that out of the equation
let's pretend we've actually got
lighting already computed and so what I
want to do is first spam out lighting
that we just like pre-specified so it's
not gonna be dynamically computed I'm
just going to hard-code some answer to
the lighting question into the game that
we run every frame that just dumps some
fake lighting out into these lighting
probes we are then going to sample that
lighting in the pixel shader and see how
slow it is to sample lighting that
doesn't really cost anything for us to
produce that will give us a estimate of
how much work we're going to have to do
to do lighting this way in the final
analysis right so basically when we
actually ship the game that is how much
it will cost in the shaders to actually
run our lighting scheme and this is
important to me because I need some way
of knowing how expensive this lighting
actually is and then we can trim down
that expense before actually producing
the code that outputs lighting to this
format that to me seems like a saner
idea because if we find that it's too
expensive to sample lighting as a voxel
grid of probes we probably want to
change that scheme first before
outputting you know before actually
spending time working on an algorithm
that outputs it right so that's what
we're going to do now is get that
performance question answered and that
way we won't really have to worry as
much going into the next stage of things
because we'll already have the answer
that the format that we've chosen will
work
our runtime so that's what we're gonna
do now okay
so in order to do this we're going to
need several different things and to
start with today the thing that I'm
going to focus on he is spamming out
some prefab lighting somehow that the
graphics can actually see it and we need
two things for that the first thing that
we need for that is a way to produce
some kind of lighting that can actually
tell us that we're sampling it correctly
and then we so it's gonna it's not gonna
that's what it look like real lighting
right cuz that wouldn't help because
real lighting is very subtle and we
wouldn't be able to see subtle bugs we'd
know if we had something totally wrong
like the whole screen just comes out
black or too bright or something weird
so we'd have some idea if it was working
but we wouldn't really know if we were
getting it correct so what I'd rather do
what I want to do here is I want to
produce something that has some clear
answers to it basically structured art
so I know whether or not we're getting
an accurate or an inaccurate lighting
sample coming out and so what I'd like
to do is say look we know we're putting
in two lighting probes per tile what if
we did something like each lighting
probe had a specific color you know top
bottom left right forward back and we
pick different of those colors for each
lighting probe bright colors so when
somebody hops onto a square we can look
at the two probes say what is the color
that we're actually seeing there for
each of those probes and then when we
sample the lighting we can figure out
are we seeing the lighting correctly
correspond like as we get further up to
the top of the sprite are we properly
sampling the lighting from like the
front face of the top lighting probe
which maybe is bright red and when we
get down to the bottom of the sprite are
we maybe sampling the correct lighting
from the front face of the bottom probe
which maybe is bright blue right and
that can help us sort of that can help
us see whether our lighting samples are
producing blends that
make sense much more easily than we can
if we literally just said let's put some
real lighting in there where it's like I
don't know it looks kind of I guess it's
very easy to have subtle bugs and
lighting we've already had them we know
we'll have them again so try to
eliminate the cases where that would
happen and so what we need to do is
start down that road so the first thing
I want to do is say let's go ahead and
try to make a way of rendering these
light probes maybe that produces answers
that we can visualize so let me just
give you some perspective on that if I
go into handmade hero and I look at
where those light probes are being
rendered currently they're being
rendered as that sort of purple thing
right if I go into the entity output
that's where this is happening I'm gonna
do a search for the lighting probe
output you can see here where we do show
probes that's right here and that's
controlled I believe by a constant in
here right yeah you can see that
lighting probes right there right
and so right now we're saying show
probes is true so we're rendering these
push cubes we're giving them this purple
color I'm gonna change that now again to
just one one one one and so what we're
gonna see now is pure white probes right
as you can see there now what I want to
do I want them to be pure white why do I
want to be pure white because I want
them to actually sample the lighting now
and so what I can do is since they're
being pushed down in here I believe
lighting is still enabled for most of
these things I guess I don't actually
know that let me see how that is
actually working here so if we look at
push cube in here you can see emissions
Z by us are set to zero the usually lay
out stuff is in here it looks like
lighting enabled is just it's it's just
plain global to the to the render group
so I believe that those will just get
lit if we were lighting right so they
will flow through the lighting pipeline
so what that means is now I am
outputting a purely reflective cube to
the lighting and I'm I'm looking to see
what oops why do I have two of these I
don't know and I'm looking to see why
what I actually get when I run so I'm
gonna turn on lighting for these and
then we're gonna work on getting those
to show what's actually being what we're
actually sampling in that area then I'm
going to feed in lighting that is prefab
specific colors at each of these and
verify that they get sampled exactly
right so that's my first test is if I
place a white cube directly on the probe
what do I see as the incoming light at
each of these phases and it should be
exactly what I said the incoming light
is when I sent the probe down because I
am literally reflecting the light
exactly it is a pure white tube with a
normal facing directly in the the in the
direction of the incoming light that's
measured at that light probe we should
have no alteration of it whatsoever
right there's no cosine fall-off there's
no displacement
there's no blending it should be 100%
correct so now what we have to do is
actually start sending down this
lighting information and so when we
think about that we need to send down if
we look at what our lighting information
actually is if we take a look at what
we're sending down you can see here that
we have this notion of lighting textures
and you can see here we have all this
light data and it's basically like a
bunch of information that has to do with
points that we were sampling this is all
wrong now right because we switched to
doing your lighting probe based solution
and so we don't actually want this it's
not actually the information we would
need to do our light probe data and so
if we actually look at what information
we will need it looks a lot more like
something like this
right because what we actually want here
is to say look we've got lighting probes
and each lighting probe is going to
encode probably in some compressed
format and right now we could certainly
do it this way and basically say look
we'll pass it down a slope to begin with
but later on we're gonna switch it to
more encoding I could say this but what
we know is fundamentally speaking we are
going to pass down a series of light
probes those light probes are going to
have because until we actually like you
know adjust this for performance or any
other things that we might want these
light probes are going to have
effectively six incoming light
directions one for each face of the cube
and each of those six light directions
is going to store some RGB incoming
light value now three floats encodes how
much red how much green how much blue
light is coming in across that face but
what you have to remember is that's
super piggy we don't really want that we
could compress that down quite a bit
more we don't need a full 32-bit value
per ton all we really would need is like
you know an RGB an 8-bit RGB for how
much light was coming in on our G and B
as a percentage and then one emission
value that's like how strong the light
is and that would allow us probably a
lot more flexibility than if we just did
three u eights because then we'd have an
extra sort of power for like really
bright lights or something but it
doesn't use up the huge so it face like
an HDR encoding right it wouldn't be the
ridiculous amount of wasted space of
literally a full floating-point value
per color channel which I know we don't
need that's way more specificity than we
could possibly need for our lighting I
think our lighting just
that's you know precise right so I don't
think we need that but we do need
something like this and so we know that
we would have like I believe its
irradiance is the correct term in this
case which is basically like how much is
coming in it's it's how much is received
by that surface now it's a little bit
cheaty to use the actual term irradiance
because we're not measuring this in any
particular units but actually we could
right so I'm okay calling this light
prober radiance because actually the
code that is on either side of it could
be upgraded eventually to be physically
accurate and use an actual measure of
irradiance so really we are sort of
talking about irradiance we're talking
about a value that's related to
irradiance but maybe we're a little too
sloppy when we do our computations to
really put the certified stamp of flux
on this thing a flux per unit area but
that's basically what it is and we could
make it be that eventually if we
tightened up the code on either side
right so I'm okay with calling of that
if we store our light probe irradiance
what we would do is say look the maximum
number of light probes that we possibly
can have going here that's how many we
get right the light data width would go
in here I'm going to change this to call
to call it something else I don't even
know what like chunk count and some of
these things actually are here so we're
gonna have to start pulling out some of
the old code and actually having it be a
little bit more specific here but point
being light probe irradiance is what we
need to send down for each probe and
then we need some lookup structure that
gets us to these probes faster and what
we we need there is we're going to need
a voxel that has an actual lookup in it
now I don't think we want more than
65,000 probes active at a time so I
believe this voxel would only really be
storing 16 bits worth of data if we had
to actually simulate 65,000 light probes
I don't really think that we're gonna be
able to do that now I'm today's machines
and with what we're working on maybe on
an Archie X card that's fine but I think
we want to target things that may be a
little bit further back other than that
I'm not sure that by the time here maybe
chips even if it takes us to three more
years to do it I'm not sure everyone's
gonna have such a beef daddy platform
you know maybe maybe they do maybe they
don't
but I just I don't want to make that bet
I just don't know what's gonna happen
there I I don't have a crystal ball
right so I don't want to say that we're
gonna have like you know 16 million
light probes act at the same time I just
I don't think that's like very likely
so probably 65,000 is a much more
reasonable upper bound for the kind of
thing that we're targeting here so I
would say I'm more important thing to do
minimize that voxel footprint cuz that's
a lot of memory voxels of three
dimensional they grow quickly we really
don't want to spam out something too
much there and so if we take a look at
speed calc and we just say look let's
try to define a voxel of reasonable
dimension here maybe we say tivity six
by 256 by 256 times two how big would
that be so if we literally had a two
Beauty six by traces by tree or six
voxel it's only 32 megabytes only 30
meters which is pretty good we could
also probably tone that down quite a bit
that's probably overkill for what we
need if you think about what's going on
I mean if we flip back to what we're
looking at on the screen here I mean
come on
do we really need to be that specific
you can see even when we zoom out quite
a bit I mean you tell me how many of
those light probes are on the screen
right now it's not that many
so 2d6 I think is overkill when we're
looking at how many are across how many
are up and down honestly 64 by 64 would
probably sufficient I'm gonna go a
little higher I'm gonna say 128 by 128
but I'm thinking that this is totally
sufficient that's a 4 Meg download not
too bad per frame even if we aren't
updating it judiciously 128 by 128 by
128 screen aligned voxel seems like it
would be fine with me
that's what I would think and so what
I'd like to do is maybe look at that as
sort of more where we're going right so
125 120 voxel will try to Center it
around where the viewer is looking that
should give us enough granularity
certainly in Z I think it's enough in
X&amp;Y it should also be enough but we can
see we can always adjust it later but
that I think is a more reasonable bound
64 64 64 maybe a little bit too tight so
I don't know or loose I guess I should
say to course probably that's the right
way to say it so I don't know that we
want to go that far but you know so I'm
gonna go ahead and say light voxel dim
that's gonna be 2028 we can drop to 64
and see maybe that's fine we want the
lowest we can get away with and so here
we want to say light index voxel and
that's gonna be a light box little dim
here I'm gonna call it a cube for now
and that may be a mistake I don't know
but I'm going to call it a cube for now
and we're not going to subdivide our
dimensions differently we're just going
to put it as a cube just keep things
simple and not bias the lighting in any
particular direction so we're just gonna
leave it that way so we're gonna have a
light index voxel the indices will look
up into here the light data width
therefore we kind of know what it is
it's going to be 6 5 5 3 6 is going to
be the maximum so I'm gonna say max
light probe count goes in here and
that's just going to be this and this
light chunk count I don't really know
who is using that right now but we're
gonna probably find out pretty soon
because I'm probably gonna get rid of it
so if we actually look at how much
memories taken up by that light probe
irradiance that's gonna be 6 times 65536
as the base number which as you can see
is totally reasonably sized beats number
gonna be particularly worried about but
it's gonna get mold
by three times four because this is v3
right now that gets up to four Meg's
I'm not too worried about that again
because that will shrink I think by a
factor of three we'll be looking more
like that so our total download
bandwidth for all the lighting only
around six megabytes a frame if I'm
doing that math right I'm not sure that
I am but again nothing really to get too
concerned about on the kinds of
platforms that can run real time
lighting anyway so I think real-time
lighting kept in those bounds probably
fine
again don't quote me on that because if
we then run in it totally sucks
you're gonna come back and say well you
said it was totally fine I just saying I
think it will be to leave on but it
might not and at that point we'll have
to adjust so now if we start to compile
I don't know if we've left all that
stuff out we may or may not have you can
see it here okay so here you can see the
one place we're actually still using it
that's in the transfer we want to
basically have this push lighting
working the way that it is working we
want that so when we actually go through
and do our push lighting we do actually
want to stay here in our transfer when
we push this render element on we do
want to say here is the the light data
that we want to submit so we do actually
want that coming down the pipeline now
one of the things that we probably want
to start thinking about though is that
again this is a little bit ugly because
it's a push forward scheme we don't
really want to be pushed forward in this
way the reason we don't want to be
pushed forward is because remember we're
now trying to actually do a reasonable
job with our graphs output we don't
really want to be copying this memory
around all the time so probably what we
would rather do is have this buffer be
something that is submitted to the
graphics card at least somewhat
plausible so if we go back to the way
our platform oops if we go back to the
way our platform output for graphics is
working what we can see when we look at
the actually is this in the I think this
is actually in the renderer now though
isn't it
I think it actually is yeah so if we
take a look at where this stuff is
actually going to get output right you
can see that when we do our game render
right here is the actual primary
structure that we use to send everything
down and what you can see is we actually
have a specific thing that we give to
the game and we say this is where the
vertices go and then we say this is
where the indices go now why don't we do
it that way well the reason we do it
that way is because we actually want the
graphics card specifically or rather I
should say the graphics driver to tell
us what memory to put these things in
the reason we want the graphics card to
tell us where to put them is the grab
this card may be able to allocate those
things in such a way as to eliminate
extra work done by the CPU to put them
in a place where the graphics card can
actually get them and so we don't
typically want to just surprise the
graphics driver and say hey grab a
thriver guess what here's a place that
has all the lighting data in it it is
usually I say to us I really wish you'd
asked me first because I would have told
you to put it over here not over there
right and so probably what we want to do
is change this render end at the
tree-lighting transfer a bit and say
let's do a little more work there let's
be a little bit more specific and say
alright let's put this in here where we
say max light probe count and then we
say max light probe I'm sorry light
probe count and in here let's put the
actual lighting data where it belongs
unlike what we were doing before so
instead of having this render entry
entry lighting transfer operation or any
of that stuff we're just going to nuke
this lighting textures that's going to
go away what we're gonna say gonna do is
just output it directly where it belongs
so these things will go in here and this
information will
actually probably be something that we
just specify in in this right so maybe
here we say light voxel dim like that
right so light voxel dim we get rid of
that's that's not going to be a thing
maxilla that's not gonna think they'll
actually come through in here as run x
values and the lighting textures will
just disappear it's not going to be used
anymore and will output our stuff
directly into something that we actually
want like this and that will look like
that and you can sort of see here so
we've got light box will dim my light
box in my life lots of the Damned here
we have light probably should make this
actually right so here you can just see
me notating like this is what these are
going to be so it's basically like
whatever the MaxLite probe count is by
six right that goes in here and the
light index voxel is just gonna be the
you know three times that that dimension
right and so later we can make those
settings if we want to right now I'm
just gonna hard code them into the
render and say this is just what you get
and we can make those be settings in the
future if we want to try and make it be
more flexible but I'm not particularly
motivated that cuz I don't really see
any point to it the lighting fidelity
will just be what the lighting fidelity
is and that'll be the end of it right so
pretty straightforward okay so if I
compile this now we should get some
powers because I've gotten rid of the
lighting submission stage altogether
right so if we take a look in here and
we see push lighting like I don't even
want to talk about push lighting anymore
like I don't really want that to be
something that you ever even do because
again push
lighting is it's just not gonna it's not
gonna work the same way so we're gonna
kind of get rid of that notion all
together
that's not how lighting will work in our
system right so now what we need to do
is kind of hoops I guess we need to to
get rid of that a little bit more
stiffly there so here we do like output
lighting points right that is no longer
gonna work this way instead what that's
going to do is it's gonna output
directly into the function in question
and so when you do output lighting
points and output line tech textures
whatever I'm gonna go ahead and say like
we're gonna nuke some of these things
completely so here where we do this
where we say output loading textures I'm
just gonna do that right that's the only
one we're actually gonna have here and
then this code will be adjusted too
right into the render group directly
that's what we want to do and so here
when we come back and we look at the
loading textures and we do this push
lighting here I don't really want to do
any of this stuff the way that's being
done at all so we're not gonna do it
this way right that's not what's gonna
happen so when we do a push lighting
there you can see oh sorry
this was actually using that old code I
just deleted we don't want to do it
anymore we're just gonna assume that the
lighting gets written into the render
buffer and people who are using lighting
use the lighting and that's it
right there's nothing else to it all
right so let's go ahead and delete this
for the letting texture as part of
things I don't think we actually need
that on here at all so I'm gonna go
ahead and keep hunting for compile
errors and just try to clean this up a
little bit so now we see okay are we
gonna do update lighting we are gonna
call our lighting test here that
actually does the lighting and then you
can see us doing some stuff here where
we're doing like you know do we want to
show the letting or not and output the
lighting points and whatever we can't
really do this anymore so I'm going to
leave this for now we may reenable it
later if we actually have some way of
debugging the lighting separately the
want to use we can always rename all
that before now I just want to focus on
this
if update update lighting is enabled
then we're gonna run this lighting test
here that's gonna do it like that
and then if we want to actually put the
lighting out to the graphics card what
we're gonna do is we are going to I'm
not sure what that's actually trying to
say there so that's probably not correct
anymore but we'll leave the if in place
anyway when we do output lighting
textures that's actually a real thing
still we just don't pass it anything
right so it's actually gonna output the
lighting textures on into that render
group it will be doing that it's just
not gonna do it this way right it's just
not gonna do it by a texture call
alright um so now when we run I I don't
know we may have to go clean up some
other stuff we may get a crash or you
can kind of see so when we're actually
doing stuff if we don't call that
lighting push and I'll probably switch
now that we're gonna kind of get into
some more serious stuff here I'll
probably switch to a debug build so we
can inspect our code better as we work
through like what happens when we pull
that stuff out but what I'd like to do
now is when we actually do our lighting
test here I'm I want to make the
lighting test call just be something
that it gets past the light probe
information that we actually need and it
does it kind of all in one call now if I
bounce back to where we were talking
about the lighting I don't really care
about most of this crap to be honest
this lighting point recurse I'm gonna
leave it in there case we need it later
but but honestly a lot of this stuff
should just go but alright so coming
back here and you see what happens
during the lighting test you can see
first of all we do some nonsense with
yeah with sampling and so this all has
to get fixed me actually the lighting
because we've rebuilt our sampling table
now we can actually use it but forget
about that stuff for now when we
actually come through here and we build
our spatial partition what you'll notice
is we expected to kind of have something
here that recorded which light boxes
were actually involved right
and you can see here we actually do grab
that out of the render group here's the
light boxes here but what we saw before
was that I think without calling that
push letting call we didn't set some of
the state that we actually needed so we
need that state to be set here and so
this should crash right at that point
hopefully you can see it here and what
you can see is we're trying to get this
root box set up the reason we can't get
the root box set up is because when you
called that push lighting call initially
what it did is it output a box that we
use for our route lighting box right and
you can see that happening here where we
sort of said look here's the root box
it's box zero and so we kind of we're
expecting to always have that be built
into the system right but it wasn't
properly built into the system because
there was no box zero reserved so like
right here where we do this if the if
nobody outputted any lighting at all
right or something like that then there
would be literally no boxes so when we
ask for that root box we would actually
get nothing there would have been
nothing there right so we definitely
have a bunch of work we're gonna have to
do here to sort of make this stuff work
a little more cleany but this is work we
want to do anyway because our lighting
was not really getting sent down in a
particularly good fashion before anyway
right so let's take a look at how that
actually worked out if I go I mean one
thing you could ask is why is that even
happening to begin with to be honest
when we look at the root because root
box it's not even zero so I'm not sure
that made us because we're not setting
that array or something let's take a
look at what happens there I'm gonna
take a break point into lighting test to
see what happens sir
so here we are in lighting test
obviously you don't care about this part
this is actually about the lighting
sample so here you can see us starting
up looking at what we're getting and you
can see here this is the render group
that we're asked to do the lighting on
and you can see that it actually has no
light boxes allocated whatsoever right
there's nothing in that light box array
and so that's our first problem because
that's what we actually needed to do the
lighting on so the person responsible
for actually allocating those light
boxes didn't actually allocate the light
boxes right that's the problem
and so you know that push lighting call
was really doing it so we kind of do
need something that's gonna allocate
light boxes but my question is why are
we doing that that way anyway the light
boxes really should just be a static
thing that's inside the letting to begin
with and you don't transfer it right so
what we would rather do I think is when
we actually do an init lighting you do
the light boxes here right this is where
we actually want that to happen and we
want that to happen in such a way as to
always be correct right so when we look
at what's actually happening when we
allocate that the the light box is what
we want to do is figure out okay we're
gonna start pushing light boxes onto
this system what we want to do is
actually have those just be allocated
and you reused right I mean that's
really what we would like to do so I
think they should stay inside the
lighting system and then instead of
calling something like push lighting
what we should actually do is call
something like here is the light target
right
yeah so I think what we want to do is
more like this when we go in to update
and render world when we create the
render group that we're going to be
using for our actual assets here what I
want to do is say look that render group
that you're going to feed all this stuff
through let's go ahead and set the
lighting so we want to say something
like this let's set the lighting output
equal to whatever our lighting box array
is right and then that's where we'll
output that information now again just
trying to think about what that actually
means we have sort of two separate sets
of information here so again I want to
kind of try to think this through a
little bit better than we were thinking
it through before we want to have inner
lighting two different things probably
we want both lighting probe information
and we want light box information and
the light probe information kind of
needs to stay over time as well right so
if something is a light probe we want to
store the light probe data and we want
to update that light probe data and so
probably what we want to do here is
actually because we want this to be more
efficient long term we probably want to
sort of contemplate a few more
complicated things happening so I think
we may want to do this something like
this or like that so we kind of mark
where we again the lighting computation
and then I think we mark where we end
the letting computation right and so
when we get down to the place where we
actually do the lighting test in here I
think we would do and lighting
computation and maybe what we say here
is just like did you actually want to do
lighting or did you just want to like
throw away what was asked of you and so
on right and so I think we probably want
to do that
this and we want to get rid of all of
this and then maybe there is a thing
here which says like output lighting
textures in the case where you want to
show it or not but I think what I'd
rather do is just weld that in here so
we'd say like update the lighting
computation this way and then maybe this
flag we just get rid of for now so I
basically just look for if I if I go
look in the world mode we've got this
weird show lighting thing that's on here
so I'm just gonna say like that actually
goes away you you know you you don't get
to do that and then this output lighting
texture is part of things when we go
look at that actual call this output
lighting textures is actually not going
to be in here at all that's actually
just part of the sort of finishing of
the lighting routine and it's just
assumed that that will happen so the
test lighting call this right here this
test lighting that's actually gonna be
where that actually happens if we do it
at all there which I don't know that we
necessarily will but we're going to need
to do that at some point and so that
means that this is actually like the end
lighting computation call you pass in
here like the lighting solution that you
wanted to use you pass the render group
you pass the high priority queue and
then you pass a bull which is like you
know lighting enabled that's whether or
not we're actually gonna do the lighting
or not and then we've got a called
brackets it and that's the begin right
and that's this and that's responsible
for setting up anything that actually
needs to happen with respect to the
lighting right so again just working
this through trying to clean it up a
little bit obviously you know our
renderer keeps improving over time and
it keeps converging towards something
that's more like a real renderer which
is exactly what we want but that
requires sort of these phases of like
okay let's clean this up let's make like
now that we see what it looks like
let's make this stuff work a little
better and I also of course I'm eyeing
this as soups sorry as I'm doing it I'm
also trying to kind of imagine well I
don't want this to be too far away from
a hardware solution so that if someone
does want to implement in our TX version
of this thing that does all the ray
tracing really quickly on the GPU side
of thing and maybe like improves the
quality too right because if you have if
you can get more speed out of it by like
using an RT X card or something like
that then what you could do is crank up
the number of rays per probe and crank
down the smoothing that gives you more
responsive lighting but with the same
quality right so basically what you
could do there with our lighting
certainly as machines get better and as
ray tracing becomes more prevalent
assuming that is what happens we'll also
kind of want to be in a position where
we can choose to have a driver that
actually does this on the graphics card
over time we can transfer that work over
there as those parts become more
powerful and have special-purpose things
just for doing it so there's how we
would do sort of that setup so let's
keep going
we've got our lighting solution here and
what we need to do is do that initial
setup and so what we want to do is take
our lighting solution and probably we
want to allocate space for the lighting
boxes right in here for now and again
this stuff is going to improve over time
but we kind of want to make sure that at
least is running nominally so we don't
get too far from a working program as we
focus on each individual part so this is
not really relevant to us right now
since the light boxes are occluders and
we don't really care about occluders
right now right but we kind of need to
keep them in the mix because we are
gonna have to work on them eventually so
we're gonna push an array on here we're
going to have some kind of a maximum
light box count that we want to enforce
that will go in here and so on now the
thing is we may actually know I'm
thinking about that again we may want to
do the same thing we did before if I go
back to that
renderer platform information like we're
doing here one could argue that the
light box is actually should go in here
because again they might want to go down
to the graphics card so I may want to do
this something like this and we've got
this notion of a light box that thing is
going to change
we don't it's it's really just an
occluder now it's just a it's just a box
shaped occluder right and so I think
what we want to do here is stop talking
about any of this stuff light boxes
really I don't know where they went
lighting box sorry so if we look at this
lighting box right this is just not
something we care about anymore really
in terms of the emission texture index
stuff like that some stuff this is just
not relevant anymore because lighting
boxes are just occluders now that's all
they do and so we're gonna kind of keep
it this way but that's really what those
are going to become they are no longer
things that we actually use to
[Music]
specifically like remove I'm sorry
they're no longer things that we use to
collect light as well as block it there
are things we use strictly for blocking
light so there are only includes now and
the things that actually capture the
light are the the light irradiance
probes that are placed throughout the
environment okay so I think that's more
what we actually want to do and so when
we're out putting lighting it's gonna go
more into something like this and so
let's move towards that a little bit
more as we go when we go to the renderer
itself and we look at what's happening
in there what you can see is that our
render group you know if we just take a
look at how this is being output here if
we look at our render group these are
the things that we want to output there
and normally we get them through game
render commands you can see that the
lighting has
that stuff kind of as a separate
sideband and so what we really want to
do is now get rid of that right we want
to get rid of the light boxes we want to
get rid of the light box count all we
really want is something like this light
point index not necessary so we pretty
much pretty much want to remove all of
those things if we can right I also
don't know to what extent we need light
pounds in there but we'll talk about
that later so I'm going to nuke all of
that light box count is gone like boxes
are gone and like point index is going
we're just going to talk about light in
abled now and then when I compile I
should have a bunch of problems because
the code that was still using that stuff
is going to be in a bit of a bind right
so here we go we want to you know take a
look at this stuff where the lighting
boxes work with the entity cache over
time that we may want to do is only
right out occluders when they come into
and out of the active set right that's a
pretty easy stuff thing for us to do so
we probably want to keep that in here
probably I don't actually know I'm gonna
say at the moment since everything is
dynamic we're not probably I'll do that
because it's just really just a position
anyway and that position can change
every frame to a certain extent so I
don't know how much we really want to
compress that so I'm probably gonna get
rid of that for now but anyway so what
we're gonna look at here is we're gonna
still look at the lighting enable call
in the group because some things don't
want lighting and other things do when
we actually do a push cube we do need to
put an occluder on there because you
know these are occlusion cubes they
block light that comes through but we're
not gonna do it this way the commands is
where we will get this stuff now so what
we'll do here is we'll look at the
commands light occluder count and we'll
see if that's less than the maximum
we're allowed to do right assuming it is
will still output the light box the same
way we used to and that's to say that we
will grab out of the commands our light
boxes in this case
or I should say light occluders and we
will implement increment our light a
clear account to account for the one
that we actually used will then write it
out the same way we used to but of
course the texture information now is
well actually guess we do want that we
need to sort of fix this stuff because
what we actually wanna do here is write
the average value for this texture in
here we'll have to see what we want to
be there I don't really know what we
want to do there that's a really good
question
if we were super Squinkie we'd probably
actually keep backing sources the
textures at least at a low resolution
and actually sample them when we were
doing our lighting but man that's
getting a little bit far afield on the
GPU that is what we would do but you
know so moving on from there we take a
look here and we say if it's enable
we're gonna write out that box otherwise
there's really not much else to do here
for lighting you can see us going
through there and we then pretty much
just go through and output the cube as
quads as necessary you can see that
happening here probably optimize that
path now that we have optimized quad
output but hey that's a story for
another day if we go in here and we push
look at what the push Claude has on it
you can see that we no longer really do
anything with lighting information in
here as far as I can tell that is by
design because now that shouldn't really
be involved in here so that's great that
all looks good and so now really all we
need to do is make sure that we're
pushing lighting probes on here in some
way because at the moment we actually
aren't doing any of that at all so now
if we compile what we should get is
during lighting passes when lighting is
enabled we should actually get basically
a memory access error because people are
going to try and write to an array we
haven't initialized which is this light
occluder cheryan we're gonna do that in
a second let's finish up our compile
errors first you
you see I forgot to change that to
commands remember it's not coming out of
the group anymore so that was a bit of a
screw up I think we had another compiler
in there though let's take a look at
what it was
here's us at when we actually go to do
our and letting computation you can see
us trying to work with this stuff our
box count in our boxes what we want to
do there is try to make this thing work
out a little bit better like I said not
using the group that shouldn't be too
hard because when we hit and letting
computation here all we should really
have to do is get this stuff out of the
game commands themselves right so I
think all we really need is something
like that I don't think we really need
anything more fancy right that should do
it
it's like a computer can of course and
then when we actually go to access the
light boxes themselves it's going to be
the same thing but other than that I
think we're good and again that's just
memory that we're going to be expecting
to have provided to us by the platform
layer because the graphics card may be
the thing that wants to do it itself now
lighting is not actually the right thing
here it's think it's world mode lighting
if I remember correctly test lighting
sorry but other than that it's exactly
what we could call bear nothing
particularly weird and now we have what
I think is a more sane pipeline for that
stuff to flow through and it's shortly
gonna become something that we don't
really call tests letting anymore it's
actually gonna be fairly reasonable
lighting now we get to the part where I
said we should get a crasher because
we're gonna try the light render
we're going to try to write to an array
that doesn't have anything in it or in
this case read from an array that
doesn't have anything in it because the
solution boxes themselves don't actually
have anything there so if we look at
what that pointer is that pointer should
be 0 because it came from something that
was uninitialized just like it was
before
and so we expected that to happen and it
did here is that box as this point here
is 0 so what I want to do now
is bounced back to the platform layer
where this is actually getting
initialized and actually I guess that
would be in win32 hand meet up in jail
or is it actually in handmade or or or
the jail I'm not sure let's take a look
at that I don't actually know so when we
actually allocate those pieces of memory
right we're looking at what we're trying
to do here is when we go to start our
you know start our process we allocate
memory where this stuff gets put and so
if you look let's just go ahead and
search for because I'm not sure where it
isn't here actually if you take a look
at that renderer layout we've got things
like the vertex array and we're trying
to you know map those right so let's
take a look at where we put those you
can see we've got here like we're
creating these buffers right that stuff
here what we want to do eventually
probably is do these things exactly
analogously again alig ously so that we
can transfer them quickly we want to
have the driver be aware of them and
tell us where we want to put this stuff
but for right now we're doing basically
everything ourselves with the lighting
and we're not contemplating doing it on
the card at all so what we want to do is
just allocate this as normal so this is
inside the opengl and Nick call now
remember we also want to free these
things when we go to change the settings
I guess well I actually know we s we
don't do those we don't actually free
those we just keep those the same and so
what we should be able to do here is
just say alright when we're in OpenGL in
it and we're creating our initial stuff
we can just allocate those and and use
them as is right so what I'm gonna do
here is exactly what we did with the
other things I'm gonna say that we're
going to want the light occluders and
we're gonna allocate those I'm gonna say
that we want our light probe irradiance
and I'm gonna say that we want our light
index voxel and then what I'm going to
do is when we actually go to transfer
those so when we look at what happens
with vertex array
and when you begin a frame right and you
initialize all this stuff I'm gonna
initialize all that stuff here as well
so in here we're gonna allocate this
stuff so places where we actually need
some memory for it and what you can see
here is there's pretty much no action
there's there's no actual memory getting
allocated here that I can see right it
doesn't actually seem to be doing any
Alex just kind of a bummer for us right
yeah it doesn't actually do any Alex
here so I need some way of allocating
some memory that we're going to use here
in the handmade OpenGL driver I don't
know if we've actually got that anywhere
unfortunately I would like it if we had
some allocation somewhere but I'm not
seeing it because I'd like because
remember I want to keep this fairly
isolated I don't really want to tie this
in us we have all those sources in our
game normally but I just don't really
want to have the renderer tie-in to
anything that it shouldn't be tying into
and I so I'm just trying to figure out
if we have anything in here for
allocation that isn't GPU side
allocation so far everything we do here
is GPU side allocation right I mean you
just looking there's tons of allocation
going on in here it's all stuff we ask
the GPU for right nothing in here is
[Music]
yeah it's not
so I'm interested in that light buffer
cap variable what's happening there
yeah sadly it just doesn't look like it
so I don't know what we would do there
because we don't have we haven't ever
contemplated needing separate memory
here and that's kind of a bummer but I
guess it can't really be helped because
we just decided we didn't want to do
that there's other ways I can do it then
so I guess I'm not that worried about it
I could just not allocate the memory at
all I could say instead what we do is
these things are actually just placed
directly on to the struct here and we'll
just say all right fine if that's the
way you want it that's the way we'll do
it there's going to be a light index
voxel the light index voxel is going to
be just 128 x 128 x 128 or something
like that right and we'll define that
so that array is just exactly what you
would expect we will then have the light
probe irradiance values and those are
just going to be six times light probe
count or whatever it is right so
something like that
and that you know we'll just say is it's
this maybe I'll be a little bit more I
mean maybe that's too much right I don't
really know what we want that value to
be so we'll think about that but these
are going to be our open jail values
here and then we'll say that that light
occluder array is something as well who
knows right and then we don't have to
contemplate allocating memory it's just
part of the one allocation that we do
that stores everything the OpenGL driver
needs right pretty straightforward okay
so if we then go in here and we say okay
how are these things going to get
distributed well now we know we've got
the light probe irradiance we've got the
light index voxel we've got the light
occluders and that's the setup right
it's all good and so that's really all
we need to do now and up here we don't
actually need the OpenGL allocations
that I was contemplating because they're
just part of the array now so if we
actually look at like you know
this stuff just doesn't happen so that's
really all we we need to do and then in
here every time we restart a frame we
want to do the same stuff we were doing
before so if we look at what's happening
in the renderer when we initialize that
sort of setting down we want to make
sure that these things are all
initialized properly as well so if we
look at the MaxLite probe count right we
want to do opengl max light probe count
if we look at the light probe count
initial value that just start at zero
certainly then we've got the light voxel
dim OpenGL light index box with name
just separating inside a little bit
better maybe I'll do that right so you
can see like okay max eyebrow light poop
count here's the light probe irradiance
then we've got the voxel dim and the
light index voxel right so those get set
like so and then finally we have the max
light occluder counts which is going to
be oops it's gonna be that I don't know
why I called it the occluders I don't
normally do that and so then we have the
light occluder count which will start at
zero for every frame as well and the
light occluders so that all seems fine
to me and then we just need to actually
do this and create that value with what
I said instead of what I did so those
are our OpenGL maxes there and I need to
put those somewhere right so if we take
a look at where we've got those pound
defines in other places you know like
depth component type is one of the
Defiance looks like actually we don't
really have any honestly so I guess I
don't know but you know I think probably
they should go in here right they should
be things that are at the top of the
OpenGL header probably just so they're
kind of visible
all right and so then finally that line
index voxel dam is just something I
changed the name of it right because I
wanted that to be something that was
specified with the same name as the as
the member that it actually had so if I
go ahead and look actually and render a
dot age this right here should just be
changed so now I think we're filling all
those things out more properly so we
actually have the ability to send down
lighting information kind of the new way
that we want so let's go ahead and debug
that and find out what we've done wrong
there looks like no crash just doesn't
really mean much munch that's good it
doesn't really mean much because we're
not really doing anything right now
and also we haven't actually enabled the
lighting of so we're gonna have to sort
of do that and get that contemplated as
well so let's actually try to find out
where light enabled was actually
happening here so I'm gonna go to do a
search for that it's lighting enabled
and what he can see here is we've got to
check on it
here we've got an actual enable call
here and that's pretty much it so what
we're looking for is a call to enable
lighting we don't know who's calling
that right now or if anyone ever is and
it looks like no one actually is so what
we need to do is actually enable the
lighting somewhere no one's actually
ever turning that on and so what we need
to do if we want to start contemplating
lighting at all is we're gonna have to
actually enable it so Cana here where we
do a begin lighting computation we
actually need to enable the lighting on
this render group as well right and
maybe what we should do the way that
render group is working maybe that
should actually be how we enable it so
maybe we want to do something more like
this oops I don't know where that
lighting bounds actually was being
computed we'll have to take a look and
see it looks like in here you can see
light bounce being computed here so
actually it looks more like this stuff
wants to occur a little lower down so
once we actually compute where the
lighting bands are going to be we would
do it here
we would say here's the light bounds
right and we're gonna enable lighting on
this on this group now what I don't like
about that is you can see that it's kind
of like two calls but you'd have to make
both that doesn't seem very good to me
and so when we do begin a lighting
computation I think I might want that to
sort of be where that happens so I might
want to do something more like this
oops it's not what I actually meant to
do I might want to do something more
like this where you say okay you say big
in lending computation that actually
happens on here maybe in the future
these things weld together
but either or we've got one of our
rectangle 3s that's the light bounce you
pass that here and that's where it
actually occurs and then in here we pass
the light bounce down like this we then
say that this is the thing that gets
whether or not lighting is enabled not
the ending call so in here where you're
passing that maybe we actually pass that
up here for now something like that I'm
not sure how we actually do it but
something like that like so and then
this can actually do a thing that says
well we enable lighting or we don't
based on that
right so then in here this could
actually do the lighting or not based
instead on whether or not anyone
actually enabled the lighting right so
if this was passed as false then it just
won't do it right okay
so we're getting closer again it's
getting better it's not perfect yet but
it's not horrible and then what we can
do is run it and see if that makes any
sense to anyone in the lighting code and
we don't really know right so now we're
actually running slower and that's a
great sign because it means we're
actually doing something if you take a
look at the profile you can see that
actually we're spending time in our and
lighting computation and that's what we
want right we want to actually spend
some time in there because we're now
pushing down some actual stuff so that's
all good and now we want to do is start
to actually use these things that we
have provided space for it provided a
place for them to exist all right so
what I want to start with is we now have
a place where we're outputting the
lighting coherently every frame we're
actually filling out these things we're
not actually filling out our lighting
probes so we don't actually say anywhere
where these lighting probes are actually
getting specified and so we want to do
now is actually put that information
into letting put in the license because
we know that we do know it right hmm and
so in here where we do our RM the output
so in the entity in the end of the
output call what do you see is we you
know we sort of have we've got some
stuff we maybe need to streamline
already you know we could think about
trying to make this again keep in
keeping with the idea of trying to make
this a minimal to a hardware
implementation eventually there are some
things we might want to do to make
things easier on ourselves but I'll kind
of talk about those in a second but
we're we're outputting this stuff right
now we do know when we hit a Lennie
probe right because you can see right
here we have in is light probe call that
asks exactly that question and then we
push a cube on here to draw it so we
clearly know we could draw a lighting
probe I also don't know what we're doing
with this light probe count anything I
guess we're just specifying that
somewhere oh if I'd you can see it here
but we really don't need that right
because now we can do this this render
group here we can just output that
number right so here instead of light
probe count we can actually just do this
and if I'm sorry that will just tell us
what the light probe county is directly
right so if you look at the render
commands and what the light probe count
was on those in here you can see when we
look at everything that we've done we
actually know what the light probe count
is because that's actually something
that we now have to track so we don't
actually need to track that separately
that was just lonely we were playing
around with as something we you know
wanted to kind of know off the top of
our head so that's totally fine if we
move move move that's good if we move
down here now and we take a look at oh
you know what I forgot our draw cover is
not happening in line anymore right
draw ground cover is now happening sort
of as a separate pass that we were
timing right I think yeah that doesn't
really have to happen anymore right and
so that's probably just sort of a waste
so I probably want to get rid of that
too right we probably want that to go
away and that probably wants to come up
and be we enabled inline there there
there was no need for us to do that the
way we're doing okay so anyway moving on
so when we output this now and we do is
light probe what we really want to do is
just send down the actual light probe
right so we want to do this because
that's like a debug feature but we also
want to do a thing where we actually
push a light probe on to the light probe
stack because we're actually going to
want to use those now like we want to
actually know what's going on and if we
look at our entity
mmm-hmm when we look at what's going on
here you can see we're not really
storing the light probe information yet
right and this is where I've sort of
gotten to the point where I don't
actually know if we want to stream these
out right this is what I was saying
before the light probe position is
something that we do need to stream out
because it may move every frame we don't
know where the lighting probe positions
are actually going to be but we do need
to save like the color of the light
probes and so what will happen and what
I want to just keep an eye on is we kind
of want those things to persist on the
graphics card if we ever choose to make
them be graphics card related right
and so what I think we'd find here is
that the light probes that we have in
the system kind of need to have stable
indices and those stable indices maybe
need to go along with a stable backing
buffer right and so again I think we
need to be careful how we do this so
when I'm looking at the commands there
right maybe I was a little bit hasty on
just that one thing light probe count
may just not be a thing right what we
may actually need to do is take a look
at the world itself and look at the way
that the caching system works right and
say how many entities are cached at any
given time right so we look in here we
say max unpacked entity count and what
we do there is we're actually taking I
think of this value and using that in
some way right yeah so what you can see
here is we have a max unpacked entity
count and I believe right now our light
our entities are where the light probe
data comes from right like we'd place
entities in the world that are our the
our that are our light probes that's
what we're doing so when we actually
create this unpacked any count here
right we sort of have a problem where we
don't have a problem I guess we have an
opportunity to say we could just use the
indices that we give to each entity
transit orally while it's in the active
set as what that lighting information as
where that letting information goes
there's there's
there's a few things that I don't know
if I like about that I'm sorry for not
being particularly lucid here it's just
a little bit touching and I'm trying to
think it through I guess what I would
say is while occluders probably want to
be streamed out every time because they
have no state they're just crap in the
world that needs to intersect lights
light probes want to be averaged over
time and in order to average them over
time I need to know from one frame to
the next which light probes are which I
can't just have an unorganized
collection of light probe information
because I won't know who to blend so
what I would like to do is assign an
index to each light probe rather than it
being where it came in the order of draw
output for this frame which is not
stable I'd like it to be based on
something that from frame to frame is
always going to be identical and I think
the best way to do that would be to say
every entity when it gets unpacked
already has to be unpacked in such a way
as to have a unique identifier that
identifier will be unique to that entity
until it goes out of the active set and
so what I probably should do is when we
unpack an entity give it a spot in the
light probe based on that index now
that's piggy that's the main problem
with it it's piggy we don't actually
need that mini because there aren't that
many light probes the number of light
probes is drastically less than the
number of entities right and so the only
thing that's a little bit hairy there is
not wanting to have the indices do that
but
if we are saying that we're just gonna
incrementally update the light probes
anyway then I guess maybe the answer is
we incrementally update that array by
writing into it like a sparse texture
anyway in which case we don't care if
big blocks of it aren't used
I'm gonna go with this for now because I
can't really think of a reason not to
so here is an alternative proposal and
it does seem better if instead of doing
that we kept a separate list and that
list was just for allocating light probe
indexes so when we unpack an entity if
it's a light probe we assign it a light
probe index if it is not a light probe
we don't that would definitely be better
right because that would mean that if we
said there's only ever 10,000 light
probes active at any given time then
even though there can be way more than
10,000 entities in the uncashed set I'm
starting the cash set we wouldn't
actually need the light probe backing
store to be that big now it may be that
that extra bookkeeping just isn't worth
it because we don't have to because
maybe it's fine to sparsely update that
array on the graphics card or with the
lighting system and stuff like that
right but I'm like unconvinced right
like I feel like we may want to keep
that that set fairly tight
I really think we're gonna want that I
guess that's all I can say um so I don't
really know I'm really kind of
conflicted about that and I don't have a
particularly good idea about what's
going on there but you know if I
actually look at what goes on in the
world set and if we look at what's
actually going on you know you can see
here we've got like a used chunk space
add to freely sort of thing you can see
we've got a free list for that and then
an entities we've got a free list for
that as well right
right here where we unpacked our
entities this is where we actually
assign those entities to something
register entity where we're actually
going through and like packing and
unpacking them right like we say look if
this is if this is an entity we need we
just call this acquire unpacked slot
right and that just says let's grab the
entity the next unused entity out of
that slot right
and I guess we just do at the head end
recycle them around
so looks like we don't even really do a
free list we just keep it a compact
array yeah so I'm gonna go ahead and say
we probably just want a free list there
so all right it was a tough decision I'm
not sure if I'm making the right one but
I think this is what we want I think in
here what we want to say is look there's
a certain number of light probes that
can be active at in a given time and
that's just a limitation of the graphics
subsystem and it's gonna tell us what
that is
right or we're gonna you know come to
some agreement with the graphic system
about what that is and so what we're
gonna do is we're gonna say okay in here
we're going to assign some kind of a
lighting index set we're gonna say like
light probe slots and light probe slot
count something like this right and
maybe the way we'll do this is just
always the free list so we might
actually say something where this is
just initialized your value and then
this is the set and then we'll say first
free light probe slot right
um so yeah what I would say is we'll
just do it where when we pack stuff up
we basically free a light probe slot and
when we unpack stuff we'll use a light
probe slot and then the light probes are
really not streamed out so much as
they're just placed into the system
period right and when they're placed
into the system we just set the count to
the highest count that's actually been
used and I think that's probably all
there is to it
really
I think that's the best I can do and we
are going to have to think kind of hard
about how we want those light probe
indices to be assigned because we don't
want only things within the view frustum
to get a light probe index but we also
don't want everything outside of it to
get a light probe index automatically we
want to have a sort of region bounded
region which I guess will be our light
bounds and we'll probably want to pack
and unpack based on that more so or a
sign and on the sign based on that so my
assumption is that it's probably going
to be something we do on the pass
through the entities we're probably
going to assign the light probe indices
sort of based on that a little bit more
and we're gonna have our work cut out
for us here a little bit because we're
also gonna have to basically stream
light probe updates that have to do with
you know here's the here's what we want
to write out to the updated color values
for each of these light probe indices
right so this is gonna be nasty like
this is gonna be tricky there's there's
a lot of bookkeeping here and there's a
lot of things that could go wrong but I
think we kind of need to do something
like that because again we need these
things to be stable over time because if
we don't keep them stable over time then
we won't ever be able to do a hardware
implementation and obviously for a ray
tracer you would definitely want a
hardware implementation for higher end
graphics cards because they're they've
got silicon sitting around designed
specifically for this right and probably
will do that increasingly more so right
um so all right let's take a look at how
that would work taking this into account
so what we need to do now is say in here
where we've got the discard set we kind
of want to say in here that you get
assigned a light probe index this value
will be meaningless if this thing isn't
a light probe but if it is a light probe
it will get a valid light probe index
when it gets unpacked and it will get it
through this
so if we look at how the world's assigns
things what it needs to do here is when
we actually create the world so where is
that there it is in the create worlds
call we're going to need to do a thing
where we say the light probe slots and
light probe slot counts these have to be
assigned however we wish to assign them
and we need to put an upper bound on how
many of them we will ever choose to
assign and in order to do that we
probably need someone to tell us
honestly how many of these they want
so during create worlds what we probably
want to do here is say look you tell us
what's the max light probe count we then
create enough room to store all of that
and then we initialize the free list to
just be that everything is free right
there's nothing taken up yet so what we
say there is hmm all right
we're gonna make each of these things
free so we're going to loop over every
light probe slot we have and we're going
to say that the light probe in that slot
points to like its predecessor let's say
if we wanted to start by occupying light
probes lot 0 what I might say is that 0
should probably be an unused slot so it
should probably be the case that no one
can ever fill that slot up right so what
I would probably say is you know light
probe slot 0 is gonna be stuffed at 0
and we're never gonna let that do
anything else we're gonna say that the
first free light probes slot is going to
be 1 so we'll start filling it out there
and then here what we'll say is well
let's just go to the end right and let's
say actually you know what I could do
well no let's just go in and let's just
say that each time through here we're
gonna set it to be equal to whatever the
next one is so it's just a daisy chain
so the first 3 1 is 1 and then 1 says an
extra 1 is 2 and then 2 says next and
you know so on and so forth we then want
to get to the end of this and say look
at the actual end we get to a point
where there know like you don't get any
more right you've run out of light
probes lots to assign so so you know
game over so I think that's pretty much
what we want to do there and now we can
properly assign these as we go now what
I don't actually know is should this
live in here or not because one of the
things that we could contemplate is
since it doesn't actually matter
you know maybe we want that to be saying
that's actually external if you look at
what happens here you can see that phil
unpacked entity if we look we call out
to the game to say a we're gonna use one
now and similarly in here we kind of
when we're gonna pack an entity up we
could have called out there as well so
when we do fill unpacked entity we could
alternatively if we wanted to make a
call out to two external code that maybe
keeps the lighting information updated
separately right so I don't know the
answer to that question but I might say
that you know just looking at it it kind
of feels like maybe that is what we want
to do right and so maybe we just move
this over to world mode and say well
yeah
yeah in that voice
maybe that stuff goes in here right and
maybe what actually happens is you know
when we when we do this sort of fill
here maybe when we call those things
that's response to the world mode now
looking at it the only reason that that
looks hard to do is because you can kind
of see that we're not really getting
that information through here very
easily so if we look at the simulation
region you know it knows about the world
but it doesn't really know anything else
so it doesn't know like how to get to a
world mode and we may want to keep it
that way
right so maybe I answered my own
question there you know maybe it's just
it's not worth the extra complication to
change for those live so if we were to
go ahead and implement that in here how
would we actually make sure that these
got assigned properly
and what you can sort of see is
when we do a choir unpacked entity slot
you can see it assigning a new element
here right and so it probably has to
happen is after you fill the unpacked
entity like in here and we do register
that's probably where we would need it
to show up so when we add the entity in
the sim region right it's at that point
is where we would need it to have its
lighting index assigned as necessary so
in here we would need to like assign
indices or something like that and
that'd be something that we would just
say all right there's the world there's
the desk assign the indices please
and then like where we actually
where we actually put it away
I think that's what it would look like
right so when this thing comes into the
working set which is down here we would
assign indices to it when this thing
goes out of the working set they would
get removed and the problem I guess we
would have there is when you add an
entity so so here's where you create an
entity right when you created entity if
it's a light probe it will not get that
value assigned you know what I mean I
don't know that we actually care about
that though because when you create an
entity you're doing that at world
creation time and so you don't really
want to create light probe indices
anyway light Prebys these are things
that you really only want to assign as
necessary and we'll probably want that
to be a more tightly controlled process
that doesn't just happen when you create
an empty anyway may be my guess so if we
take a look at assign indices here and
we pass what we need to pass in here we
would say all right the light probe
index equals something now in here we
want to check to see if it is a light
probe in the first place right otherwise
we're not going to do it and similarly
when we remove the indices we're gonna
Lahti the same thing if it's not a light
probe then it doesn't participate in
this process at all and that's the whole
point of having the separate chain well
and also to be stable
so what we want to do here is assign the
light probe we want an assert that we
never blow out our limit so we want to
say here that the first free light probe
slot is not equal to zero right but then
assuming that that's okay we can just go
ahead and actually assign it and then we
say that the first free light probe slot
is going to be equal to whatever was in
that slot so you can see that popping
that off the free list there so it's
saying slot 17 right is the next one we
can use so we're gonna make this one be
slot 17 and then we're gonna go ahead
and pull whatever is in slot 17 into the
new one because it's a free list right
and then we just want to assert that we
never ran out our free list because
we're trying to make sure that we we
don't ever really want that to happen
right we want to make sure we never have
so many light probes it's not possible
to create a rule with so many light
probes in the active area that it blows
out our actual backing storm right well
I just got a notification from somebody
says you might want to ban the person
spamming twitch twitch chat sure I can
do that let me take a look
not sure what actually happens there
what I would say is I'd encourage people
not to use the twitch chat specifically
for this reason basically like it's it's
hot like there's not a lot of account
validation there and on the discord at
least I have the ability to set things
like this person has to have been a
discord member for a while and things
like that if that makes sense and so
like you know that this person who is
just like totally sucks and is spamming
our twitch chat which almost never
happens I have no idea why that happened
but like I guess what I would say is
yeah I have very limited ability to deal
with that sort of stuff on the twitch
chat because anybody they don't really
try very hard if that makes sense but
hopefully that person just looking at it
like they've violated the twitch Terms
of Service like multiple times right so
that person should have just been banned
from twitch that's really nothing to do
with our twitch chat
it's just interesting that people like
that exist in the world right human
beings they explore all random possible
things yeah and the other thing I would
say is there's four discord we can also
have a subscribers there is a
subscribers only just section already
and if we found that we were getting to
the point where we needed to be like
locked down or something we could do
that too right so anyway looks like you
guys took care of it though before I got
there anyway back to what I was doing
before we had idiots in the twitch chat
or idiot singular I guess been a while
since we've had one like a year or more
I think if we go in here and take a look
at what we're doing with our indices
when we assign indices here you can see
us doing and taking the it off the free
sort store when we remove indices
meaning to the opposite process right so
we need to be able to reclaim this value
and so what we would do there is say
alright let's assert that this is not
equal to zero right so we basically want
to say that if it was a light probe it
should have had a lighting value and so
now we need to remove those indices mmm
that's not true if was created it would
have had a zero value there that's not
actually true so we want to do is say if
it has a light probe index then we want
to deal with it right so what we want to
do there say yeah okay the light probe
index when we actually go and and see
that it has something vali assigned to
it we want to give that back to the
FreeStore in that case so we want to say
that whatever the first free light probe
slot currently is we want to take the
light probe slots themselves go to the
place where this light probe index was
right and set that equal to this one
so basically chaining on like we would a
linked list and then we say okay now we
are the next available one to use the
one that we just got rid of makes sense
now unfortunately for us we kind of do
have another nasty problem here and what
that is is we don't really have a way of
telling the graphics card or the
lighting system that we switched out
these indices right and that's the part
that's really kind of a little bit rough
and we kind of need that to happen and
what I would say is we don't really want
it to happen here where we wanted to
actually happen is for example infill
impacts entity right you can see this
code here we would probably want it to
happen more like in here so when we
actually fill in unpacked entity and we
say all right if this thing was a light
probe we probably want to send down
something that says hey this light probe
just got initialized like don't use old
values for this light probe and the
natural way to do that would we push
something into the lighting solution but
what you can see is we don't actually
have that here and that makes things
pretty tricky for us but what we can do
is do something a little bit crappy for
now and just say that our MD has some
information in it right that says in
additional light probe index that will
also just for now do a light probe clear
okay and so what we can do here is say
when we fill an unpacked entity what we
can also do is say there's a light probe
clear if this entities like probe index
is set right and then that would allow
us to clear this one when we actually
see it when we come up to actually do
whatever it is we're going to do here we
can also say like
right um and so what we can do here is
just make sure that this stuff is fairly
rigorous and we can just also say that
when we see a light probe index if we
also saw a light probe clear and what
we're trying to do here is say look
we're storing all of the lighting
information in a table you know I'm
saying basically what we want to do is
we want to make sure that the lighting
information that's in the table doesn't
pull some index and say okay there's a
light probe it went out of the active
set it had a bright light there like it
was recording a bunch of light that
really was there it goes out of the
active set so we reclaim its index now a
new light comes into the system and it
gets assigned that same index we don't
want it to think that they'll there was
that bright lighting there right it's a
bug to move the lighting from one place
to another just because we reused an
index so what we're gonna want to do
eventually is have a thing that we
allows us to say clear the lighting in
that slot like I know we've got old
information from the previous frame that
we blend in don't do it it's like a mask
to the blend that that knocks it out
right and so that's just a little
something we need to do a little bit
later okay so off we go
right and and and so on
I love how people are like spamming our
discord now unbelievable
wait how did someone fix that that
wasn't me
Wow
I don't know
that is super annoying so we may
actually require if that kind of thing
keeps up then we may actually require
people to to do some kind of a
registration right like I could do that
it's just very annoying like I'm trying
to program and people are spamming right
we almost never have that happening I'm
not sure why we had it happen today it's
a good question just pathological stuff
I suppose fortunately it's pretty easy
for me to see like with the discard
discord over on the side like it
actually works pretty well basically
like if discord is getting spammed I see
a little red number going up it's harder
for me to see if the twitch chat is
being spamed if that makes sense so
we'll see but yeah it's pretty hard -
yeah it's pretty hard pretty hard - to
deal with the twitch chat I'm not sure I
super care because twitch doesn't really
care themselves like twitch could fix
that pretty easily I mean just to give a
very simple example like that person
literally like typed the N word into our
our chat it would have been pretty
obvious for twitch you know this stream
is marked all ages so like if twitch had
any clue as soon as someone typed in a
word that was obviously not acceptable
for all ages um that person would just
be Auto banned right and I don't really
know why they don't do stuff like that
if you have a stream that's marked
adults and you want to allow free speech
on it that makes perfect sense so yeah I
mean at that point you have to have a
human who knows whether or not something
was allowed but I don't understand why
twitch still has situations where people
are typing words that are obviously not
like no one would think that that was
okay on a on a stream nah
marked for adults right I'm not sure why
you can still have those kind of
problems in a twitch chat it kind of
boggles my mind because it's if you like
if you can't air it if you can't air it
on prime-time television then it's not
okay for you know a twitch channel
marked all ages so that should be simple
I agree that it's more complicated if
you want to talk about what adults can
say because adults can kind of say
anything they want to that sort of have
free speech works but this stream isn't
marked adults I don't say those words on
the stream its marked adult right so I
don't understand why a stream for all
ages can't have the basic baseline that
anyone who types in a word on the stream
but you couldn't broadcast over a
typical government allowed air wave
would be allowed here right it just it
doesn't make a lot of sense it's
supposed to be a family friendly chat
that's different fan and all ages chat
where you can say whatever you want
right
I don't know twitch you sure don't make
it easy on streamers anyway moving on
like if we actually go back to what I
was trying to do before you know twitch
interceded if we take a look at how
we're using like how we're using our
light probe assignments what we can see
here is his light probe wasn't actually
something that was callable from the
side here so we're gonna have to just
define that as a thing that you know
operates a little bit broader and that's
fine because you know I'm lighting is a
very integral process it requires
observations I don't mind those things
being coupled a little bit more tightly
together so that's actually flying as
far as I'm concerned now when we're
actually setting up this stuff here and
we do a create world I don't know how
many lighting indices I want to signed
and so what I want to do is I want to
try
make that be like related to how many
things we have in the actual game
commands so if we take a look at our
game state right inside here we need
some way of figuring out when we begin
like a render frame or whatever that's
gonna tell us how many lighting things
we actually can use I need that
information to sort of be provided to me
in some way that's convenient
right because I need those things to be
stable and I need to pass it down here I
need to like say how many indices I want
this thing to work with right and so in
order to do that what I would need to do
is get that information out sooner like
I can't wait just until I've created a
render group I need that information to
actually be put in sumer and so if
you're looking here where we do begin to
render group we can do you see the the
red are commands kind of get passed in
right so if we look at how we're passing
those in more broadly and I look at
let's say the world mode right or at
least I tried to wrong there we go what
you can see is the render commands get
passed through here as part of update
and render world right so if we look at
where that happens there it is we're
getting these render commands sent down
to us as part of the sort of overall
process here they're getting sent down
in game update and render and if we look
at where the render commands actually
come from you can see that they're
actually passed in line to this routine
right and so we should be able to do in
here where we actually contemplate
creating the world which actually
doesn't happen in here right it happens
in world mode there it is
when we actually kind of plate creating
the world that flee world call right
that's something that we actually have
to track down and pass something to so I
wanna bubble it up like so
and I'm just gonna let the compiler like
figure out how what the call chain is
that we actually need to pass this down
through right so here is the this check
for meta input right this is the thing
that allows to actually start playing
the game here and we need to pass that
down here this is a piece of information
that this actually needs right and so I
guess I could look at this two different
ways when we look at check for a meta
input it actually does get it passed
here so I'm gonna actually just say
alright render commands gets passed in
here and then we just get it out of here
and now we're actually passing it from
the graphic system so we know that it
will at least be somewhat correct all
right so now I think we're good and what
we would like to do is we'd like to
actually go ahead and verify that
you know we're assigning these things
reasonably what you see here is it looks
like we've got a slight issue here maybe
with something where we didn't clear
something for example let's take a look
so if we look here what we can see is
the brain slot type right is what would
tell us this if we look at what's going
on to brain ID you can see that there's
no brain ID assigned this thing and you
know at the same time it's got a light
products of 1511 right and that doesn't
seem right so now we kind of have to
figure out okay what did we screw up
right so let's find out if we go into
the handmade world code and we look at
what's going on here what you can see is
we ask if it's a light probe in both
cases so in theory we should never
really be assigning that light probe
index in a case where we didn't actually
know that it was correct
and so I'm not sure exactly where that
information is
from but it could be possible that we're
doing this at the wrong time or
something else is happening right what I
would like to do is make sure that PAC
entity doesn't happen anywhere else
looks like it does I'm not sure so
looking at that that makes me wonder if
I should have really put this into PAC
entity where else does packing to be
occur yes so maybe that should just
happen there so maybe removing disease
should just be inside PAC entity and
then assign indices is a kind of
trickier one right but I think it only
wants to happen just where fill impact
entity happens and so we could do is
just do it in there and pass the world
in I don't know if that's the right idea
but I'm getting sort of a inkling that
maybe it is so maybe that it's something
that actually only happens there I'm not
sure but let's go ahead for now and just
do it like this not sure this would
really matter so I'm suspecting it
actually won't but what I'd like to do
is just start there
right and then we'll start debugging
that way I know whenever I pack identity
it's actually going through the same
code path and it can't go through two
different code paths but what we're
seeing here is when we get into one of
these things that actually had a light
probe index assigned for some reason the
thing is not saying that it's the entity
that's light probe and so that's a
little bit confusing and so I'd like to
do is find out why that happened and
more specifically I'd like to find out
if it happens all the time so like when
we come through here is this like the
first time we see this that it happens
no so actually we are assigning light
probes somewhat correctly right but then
what happens is at some point we get a
bug and somebody ends up with one that
you
maybe shouldn't have had one or
something like this right alright so we
have to figure out what's going on there
we don't really know first question I
have is are these things cleared right I
don't remember what our rule was for how
entities start out so when we create the
world do we clear that buffer and I
don't actually know
I suspect it's true looks like it's true
so when we're actually looking Jimmy
when we're actually looking there at
unpacked entities it looks like that
should roughly be working properly so
I'm not 100% sure why would we ever get
a case where the light probe index was
assigned to something but it wasn't a
light probe because it means that
someone had to have moved around or done
something or I don't really know they
had to do something Squinkie because in
general we only ever enter things that
that have to do with the light probe
index we only ever do anything with
those when we already have determined
that this thing is in fact a light probe
so in pack entity we only actually look
at that value and clear it to zero if
it's a light probe what I could do here
is say you know what a search in this
case that's the light probe in digital 0
that gives us one more layer of checking
in one more place that might catch bugs
but then in the other case where we're
actually doing our fill unpacked entity
here and we then go to do assigned
indices in that case right the assign
indices call also only does it here
right and we should always assert no
matter what that the entity that we're
getting should have a light probe index
of zero at that time and so I think
that's all good in fact this assertion
should just happen here meaning by the
time you're out of this case no matter
what happens the light probe index
should be zero right that should just be
a given so there's a few more asserts I
don't think those will help I think
we've got some other but oh no they did
that's great so here you can see us
assigning in the Knicks to somebody but
for some reason the light probe in X is
already nonzero and that should never
actually
and so that creates an interesting
question of why is that happening like
how did we get into that position right
so let's think about that let's think
about why that's actually happening
because we should have had a call to
pack entity there or something that
should have actually removed this entity
from the system right and if we do clear
uncollected entity cash I don't know if
that ever gets called okay that that
gets called when we finish the world
entirely right but when we call it clear
impact enemy cash we go through every
entity that exists in the system and we
pack them all so at the end of that
every single entity in the entire system
all of them right should have impact and
therefore should have had their
information cleared right that should
have happened so if I do an assertion
here and say light probe index well zero
now if I run I should end up in a
situation where I know that everything
started out that way at least right so
if we take a look at what's happening to
this entity now and I see like well what
light probe index does this thing have
apparently and it's got light probe
clear set to one as well so what's going
on here are we why are we assigning in
the next thing that looks like it
already had a mix assigned are we
calling assign indices too frequently
you know I guess I don't really know
right but if I look through here and I
go and I'm saying we were unpacking a
world chunk in here i acquire a new slot
and I copy in the entity data right the
packed entity data that shouldn't touch
those later values I then do a fill and
assign indices and I register the entity
that should be it right so I'm not
really sure what's going on with that
particular bug I'm tempted to end it
there because this debugging could take
a while this is a bookkeeping sort of
thing right and I don't really
know exactly where my bookie bug is so
we may want to just call it a day and
start tomorrow
on this particular bug right if I can
think of one other place I want to check
so one question would be deleted if an
entity gets deleted that's a good
argument for why it can't be and pack
entity right because there's two
separate paths that happened there
so in here we really do need this part
and these both do actually want to be
called very discreetly look very like
delicately right and so what we want to
do here is say inside pack entity if
we're gonna pack vanity then we know we
need to remove the indices that's
definitely true right so when we come in
here we just have to say all right
remove the indices from the sanity but
in the case where somebody got deleted
we also want to do that right and so
it's gonna do this path but not this
path in here so we do need two places
where a sign indices happen sort of or
rather one place where a sign indices
happen and two places we're removing two
C's happen really three because packing
this entity gets called in two places
that's fairly complicated right I don't
think that's actually gonna solve the
problem necessarily but it was a problem
so at least we got that one out of the
way all right
um because I don't think we're deleting
any entities right now so I don't think
that's really relevant so that's the
situation if we look at what kind of a
brain slot type this thing had here it's
just a zero entity so I'm not sure again
like why it was getting this assignment
is happening
I should double check if I set a
breakpoint there how often does this get
called so it gets called on every entity
when it gets unpacked as I would expect
right in here
it's kind of interesting that that's
going backwards down the ID stream but
there you go
I guess that's what you'd expect this is
in the clear probably right oh no it's
just removing them
here we are assigning new indices again
during the unpack
so we've actually done quite a bit of
reassignment here right for things that
are approved
see I couldn't tell you I'm not sure why
that's
there must be something subtle about the
way that this code was working
I'm not sure so I think it's gonna take
a while to debug so I'm gonna go ahead
and say let's just take care of that
kind of a little bit further down the
road so I'm gonna save that as a thing
for next time for now let me go ahead
and see what we've got for questions and
again you can go ahead and use hashtag
live on the discord
any questions other than why our
internet company is so bad at preventing
tons of spamming
alright looks like no questions
that keeps it simple all right we will
debug that tomorrow and then we will
move on to actually drawing the lighting
because then we will have stuff to
submit and that'll be our first that
will be our sort of first foray into the
lighting off topic how do you paralyze
hash functions you use a Merkel tree I
mean you can't you can't parallel eyes
the hash function right the point of a
hash function is that it is not
parallelizable and so what you have to
do is you have to hash your hashes and
you know usually a Merkel trees that's
done just so if you take a look here
this is just the basic idea you want to
hash all this and you need to paralyze
it you can't get a hash of all the data
because the whole point of a hash is
that the hash depends on all of the data
and the order in which the data came and
so you can't really run the same hash
function parallel because it needs to
update its state always so what you do
instead is you break it into blocks you
hash the blocks and then once you have
the hash of blocks you hash those
together right and you can imagine doing
this in a hierarchical fashion so that
each time when you hash things you then
hash the hashes and hash the hashes of
the hashes and the hashes of the hash of
the hashes right and if your hash
function itself is good and has certain
properties that you would want then you
know cryptographer people have done the
work to prove that the Merkel tree can
only be so bad on top of that meaning
the amount of hash quality that you lose
from employing a Merkel tree is not
arbitrary it's basically something that
actually you know we know um it's also
worth noting that it was patented in
1979 which
means that if you use a Merkel tree you
have the nice benefit of not being able
to be suited for patent infringement
because the patent has expired right so
if someone comes to you like you're
violating this cryptographers you're
like no I'm not I'm using the 1979
algorithm by Ralph miracle which is in
this patent which is expired thank you
right so that helps some cryptography
things are still like patent unsure
right and so sometimes it's nice to have
something in the old days that was that
indeed because then you can just go back
and go well that's the algorithm and so
I can't be liable because I'm using it
and it's fired there we go um so anyway
that's what you normally do a miracle
tree is how you would normally
parallelize the hash there's other
things maybe you might want to know
about but that was the most common thing
right
all right two more questions how does
the house function like the meow hashish
mccain development the way we typically
use it is for asset tracking so the way
that meow hash is employed typically or
other functions like it is that you want
to know when like files or intermediate
outputs are the same so you've got like
terabytes and terabytes of assets for
your game right in a big triple a game
or something and you're trying to do
stuff like fingerprint those assets and
also intermediate versions of those
assets so you know when they need to be
rebuilt or when they have changed right
so they're used for signatures on things
like assets typically piston miner asks
this is sort of off topic so beyond the
guys relative feel regard with remember
functions their namespace based on the
type whereas the free functions are all
in the same namespace unless you specify
a namespace of course with the compiler
generates is identical since you don't
use accessor see those names faces first
I know do you think this is a problem
and if so how do you work around it no I
don't think it's a problem and you can I
mean handmade hero we've I don't even
want to know how many functions we have
but we've got a lot of them and we've
never had a problem with it so it's just
not a problem
okay see I've missed the most of the
last few streams could you run the
quickest see where we're at we we run it
today just take a look back at the vaad
we've run a bunch today we ran is
beginning of today's vaad in fact
regarding the chat in the discord the
reason we don't have a subscriber only
chat is because yeah like people don't
necessarily subscribe on twitch
sometimes they buy the game and I don't
necessarily want to encourage people
specifically to subscribe on twitch
right in terms of followers only chat
hey I don't know if twitch has such a
thing as a followers only chat but even
if they did I'm not sure what that would
do because anyone can just follow you
for free and then unfollow you so if
they wanted to spam they just follow
spam you a bunch and then unfollow right
so I don't think that would actually
help cut down on the spam it might be
good for people who want to boost their
follower numbers right because hey then
that would force anyone who ever wanted
type of the chat to follow a stream or
something but I don't know that would
actually help you with spammers because
why wouldn't spammer just follow your
channel and spam you right they don't
care so I don't think that really would
help subscriber only would definitely
help cut down on spam but then again
yeah like that might be too restrictive
because a lot of people probably don't
subscribe on twitch I could force the
mr. scribe on twitch but you know I
don't know that that's really that
necessary and you know twitch doesn't
give us that much money like I'd much
rather you bought the game than
subscribed on twitch because Switzerland
gives us like half of the subscriber
value whereas the game we get the whole
thing right so it's like not even in our
best interest to try to convince you to
subscribe I put it on there mostly just
because then we get all that extra
benefits from twitch like if you have a
stream that that is a partner channel
you get a bunch of better services right
but yeah I just which even allows a
follower only chat I know they allow
subscriber only chat
since we're going off-topic I was
looking at dpi where UI and rendering it
seems annoying and win32 I'm usually
many metres behind trends so it's high
DPI render good thing to worry about
these days yes it's definitely thing to
worry about and no Windows never fix it
I don't know what goes on over there at
Microsoft these days I kind of get the
impression it's like a bunch of like
babies running around a ball pit at like
you know a McDonald's playground or
something
so they've like updated the high DPI API
calls like multiple times and they're
wrong every time they've gone through
like six in the span of like five years
and they're all wrong still totally
busted and so I just don't even know
what to say about it
it's a disaster I mean anything that's
modern is kind of a disaster because
Microsoft just doesn't even know how to
make functional api's at all anymore
it's just it's completely over and so
it's just it's a disaster it's an
absolute unmitigated disaster
all right um on that depressing note I'm
gonna go ahead and close things down
thank you for joining me for those sort
of handmade here uh sometimes recording
with you as always if you would like to
follow up stories at home you can always
go to handmade here at work and
pre-order the game it comes with a
source code so you can play around with
it at home and build it yourself maybe
you can go find out what that bug was
today before I have a chance to come
back and debug it tomorrow that'd be a
good exercise right I will be back here
tomorrow same time same place and we
will fix that bug I hope see you back
here for that until then have fun
programming everyone and I will see you
on the Internet take it easy everybody