hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are gonna be doing
some ray tracing work today we already
know what we're doing because last
weekend we stopped at a point where we
had a couple things left to implement I
would also mention our Kickstarter is
almost done you can actually see there
are like 25 hours left so by the end of
tomorrow stream it will be over and so
it's it's the last chance to get a bunch
of these different versions of the comic
over here so if you're interested in
that check it out you've got exactly one
day left let me just kind of jump back
over to what we were doing here there's
a couple different things we actually
need to do it's fairly complicated this
particular scheme in terms of the number
of steps involved but the actual routine
that does the Ray casting which is the
part we care about is very very simple
and in fact we already wrote that part
if you take a look at the raycast
routine here grid ray cast is the one in
question you can see that you've got you
know a fairly straightforward preamble
that's based on the same as the other
preamble but simpler doesn't have a
stack you can see that it just has a
walk index here it loads from a walk
table which grid nodes to do it then
looks in those grid nodes and tests all
the leaves in those grid nodes it's just
that one nested loop and that's it and
after it's done it goes through and does
the the work of producing the the hit oh
it looks like we didn't quite finish
this actually it looks like we were
still working on how exactly we were
going to do the downshift
yeah no we will avoid doing gameplay
code for as long as possible I hate
gameplay code if we can just work on
engines for the rest of our lives we'll
be very happy
gameplay code is for game designers they
do that I don't like it ideally for me
it's just like you know I can work on
the engine all the time and then there's
somebody who's a good game designer
comes along and does you know whatever
the design is that's their job
games like Cody is incredibly simple
it's much simpler than you know engine
code but design is very hard and it's
has nothing to do with programming
really I mean it does in the sense that
you have to be able to program to do it
but you can't really employ programming
skills to make good design doesn't work
that way design is a different thing
it's a different skill set it's like
being an artist right so it's different
still so good so anyway in terms of this
routine we definitely have some issues
we want to make decisions about now I
guess because we've written most of it
if I compile it here you can see there's
almost nothing left that's not done it's
just this one piece here where we try to
figure out what the normal is so we've
got a couple different ways we can do
that and just to refresh your memory so
coming out of here when we do this
collision detection or I should say ray
intersection what we're gonna have is
for Ray intersection T values so four
places the Ray intersected boxes and I'm
some of them may be nothing they might
be still at infinity so the Ray didn't
hit anything but either way we've got
four of them and when we get down to
here we want to only process the closest
one now if you take a look at this piece
of the routine here what you can see is
that actually what we do is we're taking
a we're taking this particular these
four lanes we are converting them down
into a
that we can test using a single
instruction called min Posie PU 16 which
produces whichever the smallest value is
amongst the things in the Ray like so it
of the four lanes whichever ones tiniest
and then we have a shuffler that we load
from a table that just says look if you
want to take any of the lane values that
you've got so things like the box man or
the box max we can produce a vector
quantity that now has the correct
minimum value so out of the four lanes
whichever one's the one that was the
closest hit we can spam that out to all
four and so we can do that just using a
very simple shuffle you can actually see
us doing this pea chef be here with the
shuffler this leg picks the RF or the G
or the B from the ref hit color based on
whichever one was the closest hit like
that's what that does okay so it's
pretty straightforward what we're doing
there the question is just when do you
do it right so because of the way that
the floating-point unit now works I
shouldn't call it the floating-point
unit because there's two in a sky like
chip but the way that the AL use in
skylake work with floating-point numbers
actually there's more than two depending
on how you want to look at it cuz
there's a divider and stuff but it
doesn't matter that's not a relevant
that's not relevant here the relevant
part is simply to say all of the
floating-point operations that we're
gonna do are four wide there's no way to
do a single floating-point operation
with some other thing unless you're
gonna use like the x87 legacy hardware
so really what you're doing in annex 64
if you're doing a scalar multiply is
you're still using the four-lane
multiply you're just letting it know
that if it wanted to it could like save
power by not doing that right but it's
still in the four-lane it's still using
a register that's for wide so for our
purposes we actually don't ever care if
we do four multiplies or one multiply at
the same time because they cost the same
to us the actual run
time penalty to us will be the same and
so it's our decision when we try to move
things from four wide to single because
it doesn't matter and so we want to pick
that point by whatever will give us the
the best performance right because we
can pick it however we want
we unfortunately do have to do it and
the reason is because we don't have any
way of looking up into our voxel because
that's a memory operation SSE even up
through four until you get to like
avx-512 doesn't have scatter gathers so
you can't go grab multiple memory
locations and put them into four lanes
that's not an operation we actually have
so by the time we get to voxel compute
like compute voxel irradiance at that
actual operation can only happen in
scaler so by the time we get down here
we have to have converted our four-wide
code which we came out here from into
one wide code in order to do compute
voxel irradiance so that's just a
requirement because we don't have any
way of doing memory ops for wide and so
I don't actually know when that place is
and that's what we need to do here if
you take a look at what I was sketching
out in terms of solving for probe sample
P or probe sample and what you can see
is we mostly if you look we mostly have
here a situation where we're trying to
produce a normal but all we actually
know about our hit detection is we know
where we hit the box like we know the
location where we hit the box and we
know like the min and the max of the box
in the center of the box and so on right
so we need to figure out how we're going
to produce a normal from that and one
way that I hypothesized we could do it
is by doing like a table load
right so figure out some way to you know
load out of a table based on some kind
of a mask that comes out of you know a
comparison or who knows what right and
it's yeah it's hard to say like what
would be the easiest way to do that or
what would be the best way to do that
and what we were hypothesizing here is
that we would do some kind of comparison
and produce like a sine mask or
greater-than mask and see us like doing
various things here presumably this was
an mm comp here but that's what we need
to think about now and the probe sample
p on the other hand that's not so
interesting either way because that's an
extraction and we can either do the
extraction here or we can do the
extraction here we can do it either way
and so I'm not sure either about that
one but this is like probe sample P
single so in order to do this we need to
well I guess I could do it this way we
need to extract 0 like from each of
these right and we could make something
that converts that like you know like an
extract element kind of a thing that
that that converts that I don't know if
we want to do that or not but for like
in fact if you look here you can see
we're effectively doing that right like
this this is what we're actually talking
about here so when we do this and it
looks like we've already shuffled our T
ray here so if you've already shuffled T
ray then this is going to produce result
the correct results everywhere so it
itself doesn't need to be shuffled so
probe sample P if you just extract the
individual low components from it like
so you just have your answer right
so this is probe sample piece single and
at that point we know that really it's
just probe sample n that we wouldn't
have right so you can see here that
probe sample n and this should really be
called per sample and single probably
because it's not a combined value even
though we don't really build a combined
value of that what you can see is the
only real sticking point in terms of
stuff we don't really know yet is how we
would produce this normal and so we need
some way of producing that now if these
were spheres it would be easy because
the Delta like if you just subtract the
point you hit from the center of the
sphere that's the normal you just have
to normalize it but it's the correct
direction and if you don't care about
normalization well then you're
completely done but all it's just a
normalized operation that's the only
thing you have to do unfortunately for
us that is not the case and what we end
up with here is a situation where we've
hit a box we know the location on the
box we've hit we know the center if we
subtract the two of those we actually
know that whatever value whatever the at
highest absolute value is we do know
that that is the component of the normal
that is filled because a box an axis
aligned bounding box the normal is just
plus or minus one in one channel X Y or
Z right that's it the rest of the values
of zero that's an ax line bounding box
has normals that are literally just like
one zero zero negative 1 zero zero zero
one zero zero negative one those are the
normals that's all they can be so we're
just trying to figure out which one we
have now if we were to do so you look at
what happens here we do a hit box radius
and a hit box Center what are the
interesting things about this is we
don't really need the radius I don't
think
well we do so one of the big things here
is I guess the reason we have the radius
is if we both if we scale by the radius
so so for example if I take the probe
sample P and I subtract the hitbox
center and then I scale that using the
Hadamard product here then what I end up
with is this scaled D value that now has
inside it the values that would tell me
if I took whichever one was maximum I
would know which one was the correct
normal at that point right the problem
is its absolute value maximum right so
it's not quite what I want now taking
the absolute value maximum actually
isn't particularly difficult and that's
why we kind of did this thing here so
let's actually see what would happen
let's suppose we wanted to do an
absolute value of the components of
scaled D right and so we wanted to just
start merging these together so in order
to merge these together what I would
want to do is because I now know I need
to shuffle one of these right so I want
to I want to shuffle the one of these
that's I want to shuffle the values out
of this so that I know that I'm only
working with the closest hit and again
I'm not sure in which order I should do
this like maybe the answer is I should
have shuffled these two because that's
just two shuffles and then everything
else works in scaler again it's really
hard to say I'm not sure it's one of
those confusing things the other thing
is you we probably want to repack these
slightly differently like we kind of
want them now to be such that they're
interleaved XYZ which we could actually
do probably without
much of an issue so yeah I guess maybe
after you get to this point you want to
interleave the XY and Z and you but you
would need to shuffle them down and the
question is just should you just shuffle
these two first and I think I think it's
it's better to shuffle after right
because if you have to shuffle these two
you're doing three shuffles tie plus
three shovels that's six shuffles total
and if you just shuffle the output
you're only doing three shuffles so I
think you win if you just wait right you
just wait till the end on the other hand
this does shuffled so if you shuffled
this well that doesn't shovel that's
technically an extract so hmm I think
you should uh 'fl probably at the end so
if you were to do that right the scaled
D value is just the same thing that we
did here so if I wanted to do a scale D
single it would just be something like
this and then the question is just like
okay so if I extract those three and
then I want to merge them right to do
comparisons on then I need to do two
operations to merge right
so it seems actually like maybe you
wouldn't quite do that you just do the
merge directly so I guess I guess that
tells me something I need to know we
probably would do the merge directly
here so what we would do is say all
right these are our vectors right
they're not they need to be shuffled
so that we replicate out the lines but
in addition we then want to merge them
together probably so they go X Y Z zero
would be my assumption so that we can
then do things like use them Mothe mask
on them or use the same technique we did
here to find out which one is the
minimum for example or which one is the
maximum things like this so how would we
do that the other option is again yeah
we use a comparison to compare like X Y
Z and Y Z X and then we use a table for
that so like there if we knew that like
X was less than Y and Y was less than Z
or something you know an X and Z we'd
have all three you know we'd have
comparisons on all three pairs of values
at that point XY X Z and Y Z and then we
should be able to use that that actually
seems pretty good right so yeah I think
what we would want to do maybe is this I
think what we had here was probably
right I think we want to produce like X
Y Z and Y Z X right and then what we
would want to do is just do a comp right
so
[Music]
something like this so that we can get a
comp here and we just say alright the
sign mask is just the pact XYZ the
greater mask is like the you know comp
and I guess we could do it that way and
then we just look those up in the table
as we expected seems plausible to me
[Music]
right seems plausible I mean is it the
best way probably not we can probably
get better here if we really want to and
so then what we need to do is we just
need to have some way of producing these
we know that we can just shuffle this so
if we have an X Y Z we can just shuffle
the X Y Z around so to produce a Y Z X
it would just be like a 1 to 0 right so
we don't really have to to think about
that very much we can make that out of
this so this is really the one that's a
little bit tricky because we have to
merge three values and so for that we
just need to
[Music]
so yeah again just trying to think this
through a little bit more carefully yeah
when I think about what's going on in
there I'm not sure maybe there is an
even better way to do it because the
only thing we need to do actually is to
knock out the values that are are not
the only thing we would need to do is
mask out the values that aren't the
largest so actually if we were to do a
comparison on them we probably wouldn't
actually need to use the table because
we could just knock out and normalize
so I think actually we don't really need
these
I think all we need is one mask right so
you would do this you would do like you
would take the absolute value of it
which just ends this is just a hand
right to get rid of the high bit you
would do the comparison and then you
would just load out a mask right you
just say like there'd be some clear mask
that you would do where you would do a
mauve mask on the pact on the comp and
the the clear mask table would just have
whatever the actual clearing mask is
that you actually need you would then
after loading that in you would just
hand it out so you would say all right
the pact XYZ equals the pact XYZ and the
clear mask
so now you've gotten rid of whatever the
components are that aren't the greatest
they aren't the highest component in
there and after you've finished you just
need to normalize that that one value so
in order to do that you just need to
divide by one in fact you can just do
that first so you can say pact X Y Z
equals like one overpacked X Y you know
x equals one overpacked XYZ right I
guess you don't even really need to do
that you really just need the sign bit
so I guess it's really just an or you
just say all we have the vector of all
ones right it's this so we can just say
hey it's a vector of all ones and then
we or in the signed bit from whatever
the pact thing is
and that's it right it's all ones we
know that we would clear oops
trying to think if there's a way to do
this so I'm not sure if there's another
way to do this but I'd have to think
about it we just want all ones we want
to take whatever their original sign was
which is this and or it in so that way
we preserve the sign and then we just
clear out whatever the components are we
don't want I think that's it I think
that's it you don't need this and you
don't really need this you would just
say look there's a whatever so you'd
you'd store it you'd say
so you have the probe normal single here
and it would be like a v3 but we know
there's actually four values so we want
to actually write like the whole thing
like so and then we would just take just
a one part of it I think that's it so it
still feels a little overwrought I feel
like we could do better than this if we
put our minds to it but like roughly
this is what we're talking about right
and
we can't quite do this this we need this
to be a separate value right so the ABS
pact XYZ is not the same Brent but that
is that's basically what we would do and
it just it bloats it out a little bit
much right I'm not thrilled about it
also I might want to check compute voxel
irradiance at I'm not sure what this
thing actually does here it's just
trying to produce a voxel index and a
txt why so we could again actually
extract just at the end here and I'm not
sure if that gets us anywhere
I doubt it does but we can check and in
terms of the normal the get octahedral
offset probably also can't really be
accelerated much so again I don't really
think there's much we're gonna be able
to do here this on the other hand could
easily have been done wide so that may
want to go anyway doesn't matter point
being I think we're more or less there
we just probably aren't quite great yet
this is not the world's best code for
this I I am quite sure but you know what
you gonna do so we really just have two
things to do one is we've got to figure
out what the clear mask table should be
it's just a 16 entry table
we would fill with the correct mass
values it's exactly the same as like
this thing here it's just a different
table right it's exactly the same idea
and it would just have 16 values in it
the easiest way to do this would
probably be to do it this way where we
would say that these are just masks and
they're either going to be all F's or
all zeros right and we would just have
16 of them so depending on what the
pattern of compares was you would just
have you know 16 of these and a bunch of
them would evaluate to that and a bunch
of them would evaluate to this right and
a bunch of them would evaluate to you
know this so that enough F's yes
so that's coops that's all we're talking
about here and I don't know which ones
go with which slots so we're gonna have
to actually figure that out but in terms
of which codes go where so this is like
you know in each of these slots we would
have you know a particular 16-bit value
that goes in there and this will be like
the bit pattern here right so it's like
this that's the bit pattern for the
first one it's first set we would have
the same pattern again for the next set
right and then we would have the same
pattern again for the last set it's this
whole thing repeated right in fact I can
just do this one two three four one two
three four one two three four one two
three four yeah so all we would do is we
just have to go then see which ones
correspond here and so if you look at
how the shuffling works and we do a
comparison we're doing X Y Z versus Y Z
X so X Y Z versus Y Z X means that like
and here and if it was greater right
because it's it's a greater than sign so
in here we say if X Y Z is greater than
Y Z X so the first slot right bit zero
is X greater than Y I need a comment
here
the next bit is y greater than Z and the
final bit that we actually care about is
Z greater than X and then bit three is
just going to be comparing like zero
with zero and so--but three we should be
able to guarantee that bit three is
always zero if we want to because zero
can't be greater than zero so if we want
to we could say look let's make this
table just be you know only eight long
and say this is always zero we should be
able to do that if we can't we can just
duplicate the table right so it's not
that big of a deal all right so given
that we know these things what does this
actually mean so if we have all zeros
here this means that X is not greater
than Y is y is not greater than Z and Z
is not greater than X right that's what
it's actually telling us so what we know
from I mean if we take a look at where X
is being compared against things if we I
guess is that actually enough we might
need bit three right I don't know if
that tells us everything we need cuz
let's look at what we would do like if
we were gonna write this code normally
we'd say if X is greater than Y then we
just need to know if X is greater than Z
or not right and in the other branch we
would say if Y is greater than Z or not
I think right so if X is greater than Y
and X is greater than Z then it's X
right if X was not greater than Z then
oh well I guess we need one more thing
right then we need if Y is greater than
Z because now we know that sorry
no we don't
it's just Z so that would mean that Z is
either equal to or greater than X and we
know that Y yes so it's just it's Z at
that point right if we know that Y is
actually greater than X then if Y is
greater than Z then it's Y otherwise at
Z right
am I wrong about this I feel like that's
all we would need we don't care about
tiebreakers if two things are equal we
don't care
that means you hit a corner of a box and
we wouldn't care which normal you pick
any normal would be fine I think that's
fine so yeah so if we look at what this
corresponds to X greater than Y zero it
goes into this branch right so this is
like bit zero is set and this is right
bit zero is one bit zero is zero I guess
we could do it this way right another
way to do it would just say okay look
zero I'm sorry zero one when we get in
here now we know X greater than Z so
that's actually the opposite of the last
one right that is actually important so
I think we actually want that that's
easier to produce probably I think
that's easier to for us to produce as
well that might not be true
so we may want to do it that way because
that way each vector only has two
components so they can be done with one
shuffle potentially potentially so that
may actually be better alright so in
here let's do it that way and that way
we don't have to have three values in
each one so if we do X greater than Y
so I guess another question is do I just
do this in a simpler way that no it
still seems like a probably more
instructions though because if you don't
ever make the make it packed value so
another thing I was thinking is like
well actually I mean the other thing we
could do is just do these comparisons
after the shuffling so we could do like
three shuffles to produce xxx yyy ZZZ Z
and then just do the comparisons there
because there's only three comparisons
right
gosh that's a pretty tough call because
those comparisons don't can be done
serially right so for example if you've
got these you can do like this I guess
you'd have to do the absolute value a
lot more times though so it does seem
like you'd want to pack it first I don't
know I'll sketch it out first just to
make sure I'm not wrong I mean I could
be very wrong about that but if this is
all you actually wanted to do like based
on that sort of arrangement of things
you'd say okay I need to know this many
different masks so I can figure out what
you know I'm actually going to put into
these things these would have to be
absolute values right so you'd have to
do an actual absolute value of each of
these scale D values here
so you'd need to produce this and it's
expensive right it's gonna be three
separate ands to do that so you're
looking at something like this where do
three separate shuffles three separate
absolute values and then when you get
down here you do three separate compares
right at that point you would just do
select to get your mask I guess I guess
so
the X greater than Y mask is going to be
all ones or all zeros
you
oh well Lok hey so let's think about
this for a second so if we then do the
absolute value we now know we have four
lanes one of them has the correct lane
but we don't know which one yet right so
just one of them
we haven't shuffled if we do the
comparisons we know that now we have one
lane that has the answer in it right
it's got all zeros are all ones for each
of these and we need to merge those
together to figure out which one we're
actually going to use right in terms of
whether we want the X as the wise or the
Z's so what we would then do I guess is
we do selects here so I probably
shouldn't have deleted that little guy
it was handy right
so I think that's what we're talking
about right seems good so if I do my X
is greater than Y and I do my X is
greater than Z that's the mask for X
right
so then you would also have the not uh
the X Y and not this for Z so that's one
two three four so you've got four masks
right that you need it's not great but
you know
I don't know where our other select is
it's there so yeah like you would then
do something like this which is like I
said maybe not the best thing we'll find
out so here's our masks see how this
works out
all right so now we would need to select
from one of these so we need to produce
like our x value our Y value and our Z
value that we actually care about here
so in this case we need to do like so
you know if I was to do something like
this I guess it's going to select
forward so we'll do it this way
yeah
so we need to know what the signs of
these things are so they need to have
their original sign bit board back in as
well you can see that this is probably
just a lot slower to do it this whole
way right I mean it seems like it I
don't know what what you folks think but
it seems like sketching that out this is
just the way I was saying to do it
before is just better right I mean it
just seems it seems like if you did it
this way but you're just doing a lot
more work if you don't compare
well-packed
because you don't really have to do a
lot of unpacking so I think I think this
is just worse I think it's just worse so
I would say like okay let's suppose we
want to do what we were going to do up
here where we had so the XY the XY X
thing so the only problem with that too
is that like we kind of want the X Y Z
because that's the actual thing we need
to use later you know what I mean so it
kind of seems like maybe I don't know
like like although doing it this way
seems I mean you can just do it this way
and have it be not you know have it not
be exactly the same pattern is the ifs
in here because you can just swap these
around like if if what you have is X Y Z
and Y is the X then when you actually
get to the point we need to do the X
greater than C you can just do Z greater
than X and and put the Z you know here
and the X there right so we can do it
either way and keep an X Y Z and the
reason that I'm saying that I think I
want that because it would be nice if
you're going to do two for each but we
need these packed later to do this
or presumably now maybe you don't maybe
you could do it in a slightly cleverer
way but it seems like we need that so
let's keep it this way
so when we then go to do our table this
is our clear mask table I also think
don't we do we have a sign bit we
probably have a sign bit value somewhere
here but we'll make one so if we have to
load out of our clear mask table here
what we want to do is just track what
these values are so in this case we know
that the first bit would be one in this
case the first bit would be zero when we
get in here this would be the first bit
is 1 the second bit is and I guess I'll
do it this way right the second bit is y
greater than Z so we don't know what
that is but we know that the Z greater
than X bit the other bit is also one and
then this should always be 0 like we
know that that value is always zero
right so we'll basically do this or
maybe this right and then in here we
have the opposite so that's this so we
just don't know what that middle bit is
you know what I mean it could be
anything because we don't know how Y
compares to Z so in here we have a
similar situation but it's blank blank
zero and so then what we have is for the
Y case in here we know that Y is greater
than Z so it's brank it's it's who knows
one zero in this case it's who knows
zero zero right so then if we look up
what those two correspond to here if we
look we know that blank blank one is oh
sorry one blank one is here and here
right and so one blank one has to
produce Z which would
this and the same would be true here so
any pattern that's one blank one has to
produce Z any pattern that's zero blank
one has to produce X right so zero blank
one zero blank one and those already did
produce X that just happens to be we
wrote down the table anything that
produces blank 1 0 has to be Y so blank
1 0 has to be Y
Blanc 1-0 Brent anything that ends in
ten has to be why and then finally
anything that's blank zero zero so this
and this that has to be Z alright that
is not why I wrote Y but I didn't do Y
there we go so we've got two cases for X
two cases for Y and then everything else
is Z because those are the else clauses
right if we're not sure what's going to
happen with the high bit and we want to
ensure we don't read off the table we
can just duplicate this right so we can
do this if we want to and that ensures
that no matter what happens to that
comparison we'll still get the same
values in this particular case you can
also see the effects of this so this is
16 bytes so every four of these is a
cache line right so it's also free to
duplicate the table because it doesn't
cost us anything right it's it's free we
don't care what those values are they're
never gonna get used or they are if we
don't so it's we can make the table be
this big and it doesn't cost us anything
to do so and then we want to try and
look up only into the bottom part
because that obviously saves us a cache
line to cache lines but we don't
actually need to do that so if we have a
situation where it's massively fast or
not - for some reason then we could just
avoid it right but it doesn't seem it
seems like we would really want to not
do that because we don't want to have to
look up into a second half of the tea
so we don't really need that but we can
stick it in there for now just to
eliminate a possible source of error and
then later if we make sure everything's
working correctly we should be fine
this is probably just that and now we
just have to actually pack this stuff
together properly so there's a couple
things one is that we need some way of
actually loading out the like this we
haven't written the other is we just
need to actually produce these values
here right so we need some way of doing
the shuffles and all that stuff
I thought we wrote a shuffle of one kind
or another here here's a shuffle Forex
right so I think that is just is just
all we need absolute value already
exists so absolute value is here so
there you go
and so the sign bit here right we should
probably just go and in fact you can see
it it actually does sign bit from is the
thing so we can just do sign bit from
this on the inside and then we're down
to literally just these two right so
let's start here the clear mask table
loading out a clear mask here the
problem with that is we actually need
this to load as if it were a as if it
were an mm 128 right so we need this to
be an M load UPS like so right and I
don't know
what's what is complaining about tell me
again
cannot convert from a 32x to emaan 20
wet oh sorry
is this it do we have this in here yeah
so it's that because we have our own
type there right so we can do a load I
don't know if we have a mask extract we
should we should really clean this stuff
up because we could do this all with our
own types and it would be fine but I
don't know if we actually have that it
doesn't look like we do so we probably
need to like add that like a thing to
move the mask out but whatever all right
so if we take a look at what's left
here's our load I don't know what's the
problem now
this is comped up P so really we're just
looking at a few last little things here
probed and
this is actually probe and single three
so let's just get rid of that alright so
now we just have to do the packing and
the unaligned copy right and that's just
to get this thing out into something
that the rest of the code can use so
when we want to do this packing I'm
assuming this is literally just going to
be some of these so if we do packed XYZ
we would first need to do is shuffle
where we have the scale D here and what
we would want to do I guess is say well
let's start by producing an XY vector
[Music]
we'd probably have to use the shuffler
here as well so this is probably like so
we're probably not gonna get away with
anything other than doing that if we
produce the XY vector here this would
just be like okay you know it's just so
that would be xx YY which is not really
what we want so this is probably not
right what we probably want is mm unpack
I hate these intrinsic they're so obtuse
hold on a second
well it's the instructions learn and up
twos to be fair
okay so it's unpack lo PS is what we
would want and so that'll give us X Y X
Y right
and then we just want the Z value to
come in at the end so then we would just
do like shuffle for X with the packed X
Y Z taking the bottom two as you expect
and then the Z value up on top just
comes from scale dot Z right and we
don't care what it puts in there you
know I'm saying
so that actually will have a Z value on
top of it when we do the shuffle here
let's think about this so to produce Y Z
X from X Y Z we want Y Z and then we
want to produce X and the final value
since this is Z Z if we want to do Z is
never greater than Z right what we would
want to do is take the Z again so I
think that means we can just say verify
that bit four is always zero or I should
say bit three is always zero and then
remove this half the table so I think
that's okay right and I think that gives
us everything that we need there and I
don't know that we again we don't really
have one of those so it's unfortunate
but whatever so the last thing that we
need to do is a way to actually store
this out let me just see what we've got
for that already because we probably
have a store you yeah so it's this so
it's really just that we're going to
take this value and we're gonna stick it
in
the slot that we made for it there it's
probe and single for and then I think
we're good
so again not the world's greatest
routine it's pretty ugly but if you
actually look at the number of
instructions that's not horrible could
we probably get that down by you know
even possibly get it down to about half
the instructions if we really ground on
this probably honestly we probably could
do we care probably not because it's
going to be stilled I think be quite
small compared to the other way this is
happening like this the number of ops
this has to do is probably still gonna
be quite a bit more but we don't know
that for sure so we probably should
grind on that at some point and try to
clean it up to as clean as it possibly
can be but I think we're good now in
terms of actually having grid raycast
produce reasonable values now the
problem we're gonna have now is we need
the actual tables that this uses so the
grid raycast routine needs to actually
have this stuff in it
and if we look at how this is set up we
need so in here for example these tables
like the lighting spatial grid node and
the lighting spatial grid leaf these
things all now have to actually be set
up right so we need all of these things
to get generated somehow and we don't
have a way of doing that yet so that's
one thing we have to do and then the
other thing we have to do is this walk
table here where we're going to load up
what the actual leaves are that we walk
along that's also something that we have
to do that table is a known table so
it's a table that we just have like when
we actually have our HH sphere code here
that that generates the spheres each one
of these is something that can now also
output one of these walk tables so we
will be able to get the walk table just
out of the spheres themselves and if we
look at like what HH sphere is
generating so
if we look for example in here where
it's doing these light sampling sphere
float tables this thing so when we do a
light sampling sphere in addition to the
sample Direction thing that we'll have
here it would also have a it would also
have a way of looking up the walk tables
for those directions so much the same
way as it has light sampling rate
bundles purse fear also what is this
padding for
I have no idea why there is padding in
here
I do not know what the point of that is
so that is beyond me so anyway you're
gonna load up the sample direction here
and then you also need another piece of
information which is the padding for I'm
sorry the walk table for these things so
what we probably would want to do
because like I said we're not casting
for raise at a time anymore if we do
this we would probably want to make a
separate kind of table and that table
would actually be you know a different
type of structure so in here it's like
light sample direction it would have in
it the direction the count and the
offset so you basically load these up
and they tell you like we're in the walk
table you're looking and what the actual
thing is so you'd load this would
literally be you know one 16 byte value
that has three floats for the direction
and an offset and account for the walk
this count is not going to be actual 16
bits you know it's it's more like this
right so it's hard to say exactly you
know do you need anything else in there
I'm not sure but the walk offset would
would after be 16 bits because there's
gonna be probably more than 200
centuries into this table but there you
go
so what you would actually be doing is
you'd be when you call grid raycast
you'd actually just be giving it this
instead would be my guess so rather than
any of this stuff you would probably do
something more like this
like that and then you would produce
these other values oops
you would produce these other values
synthetically by like unpacking so you
would say the radial is the sample
direction or this would actually be like
the rady
this whole thing is now the information
about the direction so the radial is
just the radii comes out of the sample
direction the walk count is just the
sample directions walk count so you're
just pulling that out and then the walk
table that you're looking in is just
whatever the sample Direction walk
offset is off of the solutions block
table right and I think that's it these
are constants actually so you don't
actually need this so that's probably
honestly just a global table that you're
walking through and I don't think you
need anything else yeah
all right so I think that's all you
would need to do the walk table here is
just a series of lookups so this would
be like a global u16 light sampling lakh
table and you just be looking up in
there and it's um who knows what this
value is right it's something we don't
know what it is and then this routine
would just operate if it had this
information I think that's what we want
looks right to me
yeah so I'm relatively happy with that I
think that's pretty good I don't
actually know I don't actually know
instinctively how well we've done here
maybe quite poor maybe not I'm not sure
this part looks very good I mean I could
be wrong about that assessment but this
part looks really good
you've got like one shuffle that's just
a shuffle so that's like one instruction
you've got another instruction another
instruction another instruction so
you're talking about four instructions
maybe latency like what like six maybe
seven cycles to downshift to no like
okay now we have something that can
produce the correct lane out of anything
we want
so that part seems pretty good I don't
know how much better you're
realistically going to ever get there I
mean seven cycles is pretty darn low so
I think mostly we're talking about this
part here as being the questionable part
and the bottom half looks fine the top
half like getting that normal just looks
really expensive you know
so here's some thoughts because I guess
I'd like to save I'd probably like to
save writing the table stuff for
tomorrow let's just think about this
normal computation a little bit more as
the tangle of cords on my desk grows
more and more absurd so if we were to go
here and I was to sort of blather on
about this particular problem what I
would say is like okay you know I know a
lot of things about this answer how many
of them can I use so if we imagine
here's our axis system
like so I what I know about this is if
you imagine whatever the raid erection
is so there's a Rea direction and it's
pointing in some way the normal is
always going to have the same sign as -
the raid erection because it can't not
right
so the normal whichever one it is when
we look here it can only be one of these
things so if the Ray is coming in at
like you know in this case what is it
it's negative z+ X right negative Y then
we know that the normal has to be the
opposite of that it has to be this sign
right so negative something could be
zero but it's negative something
positive something positive something
even if it's negative zero and that's
true right because this would be
positive X right wait how did I write
positive X this is going Wow slow
morning this is going the other way it's
going negative x negative x negative Y
negative Z so it's all positive right
and that is exactly what you see right
those are the only three normals you
could hit you can't hit these sides
because they're back facing right so we
know the sign is just whatever the
flipped bits of the raid erection were
so we can compute those directly so then
the only thing we need is to is to mask
out we just need to produce something
that masks out two of these things so we
would do if we had the value 1 1 1 we
can produce the correct signs by oaring
in the sign sorry by by oaring in the
inverse sign bit so we would not and
then or so like you know not or gives us
the sign bit
so that's two instructions for the sign
bit right but two instructions per
channel because there's XY and z
channels we could pack them I guess and
maybe we want to I don't know so we
packed those maybe we packed those first
then we do this line oh and we it's free
to pack them because we need them to be
separated well I don't know that we
actually do need them to be separated at
the moment for compute voxel we do
separate them yeah so hard to say but
something like two instructions for that
and so we're just looking for a good
cheap way to produce the mask that is
basically like then we need to do an and
here to knock out two of these right so
we need to knock out two of the normals
somehow two of the components and in
order to knock that out
in order to knock that out we really
kind of that's where we really start to
fall down because that's why we're
having to compute like the difference
between these two which is what we were
doing before and then we had to figure
out like well okay you know we we need
to normalize that by the box radius in
order to figure out which ones we should
get rid of so is there some better way
to do it
and enough
so one thing I will say is that it would
have been we could have gotten rid of
these P chef B's if it weren't for the
fact that the hitbox min and Max are not
P shift right
so here's another question are we
thinking about this at the wrong point
in the code so one of the things you can
see here is what we do is we keep the
box min in the Box max right but if we
look at what we actually determined here
one of the things that you can see is
the team in 3 and the team acts 3 that
was previously keeping so we know like
we know like we've done a comparison
here and we know we've picked a
particular T value right so we know
whether we've hit like I'm just trying
to look it through this through you can
see us loading the min and Max in right
and then we take the box min and Max and
we multiply by the inverse raid
dimension to see when we would hit the
mins and the maxes of these boxes
so maybe if we just saved some of that
instead we could extract the normal
directly
because the team in and the team
maxvalue are telling us the answer in a
sense right when we produce these two
we're saving you know when we produce
this team in in this team acts we're
producing them by comparing the X to the
Y and the Z and taking whichever one is
maximum but whichever one of those was
maximum is the answer as to who was the
normal right
and these are expensive
I mean storing this is expensive so it
seems like what maybe we could do is
just say what if we don't store this
like that's just not something we keep
and we do like a max extract a mask
extract on one of these
this feels like the right solution it's
just kind of hard in my head to
understand what's happening
but I think this will be better because
that is six selects operations right
[Music]
which by the way don't have to be done
this way anymore
we can do this in one instruction
instead of three instructions but even
so it's six instructions here and they
don't pipeline they are all on port five
fire member correctly like basically
shuffles are always port 5 or blends
right no wait you know that might not be
true let me see
nope I take it back so they do stack all
right so hard to say so those are pretty
cheap so it's only like two instructions
so I guess it would be pretty hard for
us to do unless we were really clever
it'd be pretty hard for us to do we'd
have to do it in two instructions in
order to not suck so how do we do that
how do we do that the team in 3x team in
3y team in 3z where we pick one of those
out
[Music]
yeah I don't know
I mean fundamentally we just need some
way of figuring out which one we picked
but we've filtered the values down to
get whichever one is the the actual hit
but we don't actually know which one we
picked right if we knew throughout these
operate like we're just keeping the
minimum value if we knew throughout
these operations which one we'd actually
taken that would do it but we don't
however
maybe that's not true
okay I think I've got it I think I've
got it
this may be me going totally nuts here
but hear me out previously we were
restoring six values that means if we
start any less than six values or
anywhere up to six values we haven't
taken a loss suppose we were to store
team in
well and actually also if we look here
we only take T min so T inside
we don't use so if you're inside
something casting out we ignore it right
in other words this is not used anymore
that was only for boxes that were like
container boxes so we don't need T
inside anymore so we're only taking the
T min value right so T Max is only there
as a check for collision we never record
that value we will only record team in
right we're actually loops we're
actually questioning that as well like
maybe we don't actually need that but I
don't know we'll leave that because we
don't really care about that for now
it's one to ops whatever we'll look at
that later um so what I would say is I
think we can do this since we only
record T min we can instead do a hit
like like hit team in and hit team in
X&amp;Y right so we could do this and what
we would do is just store when we had
done those comparisons just remember
what these were
right so we're just like all we're doing
there is remembering those two values
using two instructions to blend
instructions right so it's super super
super cheap we could recalculate them at
the end even if we wanted to I suppose
by just story but will mean F store the
Box know so yeah so right I mean I think
that's super cheap so we're storing way
less there we're just storing just with
the team in X and the team in Y are at
that point at the end when we get to
here we would say we don't need any of
this we don't need this we don't need
that or any of this we need none of that
all we actually have to do is just take
our hit team in and hit T max I'm sorry
hit team in X and hit team in Y and we
know that one of these X Y or Z will be
equal to the actual answer that we got
right so in other words when we found a
minimum T value we know that was either
the X the Y or the Z so at that point we
should be able to say well whatever our
T Ray was because our T ray has already
been shuffled up here we should be able
to say well figure out which one it was
because either it's going to be hit team
in X hit team in Y or neither of the two
in which case it was Z right we already
know the sign because the sign comes
from whatever the direction of the Ray
was right so if we extract the sign bit
from whatever the Ray dirrection is it's
the opposite sign of this that's all we
needed to know right it's whatever the
opposite sign of the Ray direction was
now we would need to pack the Ray
direction so we'd still need to do this
but otherwise it's it's correct and if
we wanted to keep all this wide we could
none of this is necessary now
I don't think pretty sure I don't think
we need any of this it's so we can get
the sign bit out of here and we can do
that I don't know exactly which ways we
want to do that I mean you can sort of
see it's a little bit of a mess it
depends on how you want to leave it but
you know we can either keep it wide or
we can collapse it down and I'd really
just don't know which one makes the most
sense I feel like maybe just keeping
everything wide because as soon as you
then start operating with them again
they're they need to be wired anyway and
blown out into different registers so it
may be that all of the the collapsing
down is just a fool's errand and that
you should just have compute voxel
radians at take wide in that's probably
true we'll look at that a little bit
later so let's see what goes on here
so if probe sample P is computed that's
all done already so ray D is the only
thing we would need and so let's just do
it wide we would have Radiesse right
rady y andrade easy the sign bits here
need to be knotted so they need to be
the opposite of what they are right so
you would need to take like the inverse
sign bit like from here where we're
doing sign bit from you can see here
like it's knocking out whatever the
other value was there so we also need to
do an xor with this so we would want to
do you know like inverse sign bit from
or something like that
and in here what we would do is say well
we load the mask right we and with the
mask and then we XOR with the mask to
flip it right so I think that's right
like that would like toggle a bit so
basically like you've got ones in the
high bit so anywhere there was a one
it'll become a zero anywhere it says
arabic oh my one you've got zeros
everywhere else so then everywhere that
there was zeros they would stay zero and
everywhere they were ones they would
stay ones I think that works so here we
would just say all right get the inverse
sign bit from each of these
there's our sign that's the sign of the
final result so we now know exactly what
the sign is and so now the only question
is what's the mask so you know if you
took the normal you now have basically
this I don't know how we want to produce
this but it's like written out so the
sign bit gets bored in and we just need
to know
in each case do we pick a 1 or a 0 right
so you're basically just you know you're
doing like this a select but since you
know one of the answers since you know
that you're either picking 0 or 1 we
should just be able to just do a
straight and we don't really need to do
a blend right so this is just like 1 and
mask in each case right
so okay so now we're getting somewhere
this is way way better than it was
unless I'm on total LSD trip here and
it's not actually correct so doing it
this way where we've got normals and we
just need to now know the masks the
question is what are these three masks
right so there's an X mask a Y mask and
a Z mask so we just need to figure out
what those are
well we know which ones we picked did we
right because we've got this so we can
just compare t-ray in each case so we
can say look the mat the mask for each
of these the X mask is going to be if
these things were equal right the Y mask
is going to be if these things were
equal and maybe we need to make sure
that we have not the X mask nodded off
here as well so it's a little bit hard
to say but
yeah so we just say look is it equal to
tear a in each of these cases and this
has to be piece shift by the shuffler in
order to make sure that we get the same
answer in all four lanes right if we
knew that we could never have the same
team in in both places because that
would produce a normal that kind of like
gives us the diagonal normal which is
actually right but we don't want to have
to deal with it like we don't want to
have to normalize the normal after this
like that's just wasted work for the
case where you happen to hit exactly on
the vertex you know so this is going to
be X or Y nodded right which I don't
know that we have yeah we don't so I
don't know if we have and not we do
so actually that's not true
there you go
so yeah right like holy cow is that
better way way way less instructions
than the old version way less
complicated and I think it does the
right thing we know the sign because the
sign always has to point in the opposite
direction right in theory we could even
put that into the mask maybe trying to
think I think that's fine
so I think that's just fine I think
that's just it yeah so I want to say
that's grid raycast
right I want to say that's the whole
thing now and boy is that simple
compared to what it was before right
that's like way way better and so when
we're doing compute voxel irradiance at
here how much time do I have left I
don't know how much time I have left
probably only five minutes when we're
doing compute voxel irradiance at we
just wouldn't like we would just change
this to take the non downshifted lanes
and then it would just do these ops on
f/32 sf32 for x's right
so I think that's it I'm pretty happy
about that that's like way way way
better than it was
that's probably how we should have been
doing it before and you just you
wouldn't like you wouldn't call pea chef
be in the other vert case right so this
is probably how we should have been
doing it the whole time
like that's like not a little bit better
that's like radically better that's like
so much better than the previous one
even just in terms of legibility it's
better let alone the fact that it's so
many fewer like gyrations and there's no
tables or anything so you don't even
have to worry about loads and things
happening in there it's like one two
three
[Music]
well maybe four let's say five six seven
eight nine ten eleven twelve thirteen
fourteen fifteen sixteen sixteen
instructions and that's it and you could
probably get it down a little bit more
this is probably not as clever as it
could be hmm excuse me
[Music]
like we probably could do something
slightly clever or as well but all right
all right all right all right so let's
just finish up the piping here so we
need these like when we do grid raycast
we need to pass like this thing and so
there would be four of these that would
be happening in here as well and so
right now we're just gonna pass nothings
to those and so in here rather than any
of these things we'll deal with these a
little bit later it's so it's just this
and that's what will have to be
generating in our table all right yeah
so we can also run this right now and
theoretically we shouldn't it should not
crash but it won't do anything because
there's nothing in those tables right so
it's it won't actually it won't actually
tell us anything it's meaningless but we
can run it anyway right and hey like
it's also like crazy fast because it's
not doing anything like it's not
actually testing so you're only like
what you're seeing there is the total
runtime cost for the like really
expensive diffuse blur which is actually
kind of a great thing to see now we kind
of know like it's 2.3 seconds in our
testbed for doing room to me for doing
just the for doing just the down set the
the blur the specular to diffuse all
right let's go ahead and go to cue /a
nice upgrade of the routine just wanna
let you know there's a double pea chef
in the creation of teary single oh
really
that was not my intention I've kind of
worked over this routine a few times
here so we haven't really had a chance
to go through it and make sure that
there's nothing stupid happening you are
correct sir that is not even remotely
necessary as for what it stands for it's
actually the pea doesn't stand for some
anything specific to this instruction
it's their instructions really chef B
which is shuffle bytes I believe because
it's a byte wise shuffle the pea is
actually the prefix that they they chose
when they were assigning this the SSE
instruction and mnemonics the pea just
stood for pact so what you will see if
you actually go look at the instruction
break down the way that it works is like
when you have for example like so let's
say we were just talking about the early
days so you only have like SSE MMX and
the base stuff I mean MMX would have
been the real early days in fact
actually we can probably do that with
just MMX so let's suppose you looked for
like add instructions right and I think
you could do some of this I haven't
looked a long time yet can so you have
to imagine like you're coming from x86
this is before x64 and you've got oops
you've got your add instructions that
the processor has so the x86 add
instruction it looks like this here's an
8-bit add right you add one register to
an immediate in this case right here's
an 8-bit immediate and at right to
register adds here's a you know 16-bit
memory to 16-bit register and so that's
your add instructions they're called add
right when you get to s mm x which mm x
is the first time that Intel had wide
instructions so more than one thing or
what could could happen like inside a
single register there could be more than
one value being added at once there's
boundaries in between them now you can
see that the multimedia registers here
that they're talking about like MMX
registers suddenly get a P in front of
it right and the P now stands for packed
so packed add bytes packed add keywords
doubles I don't know what the D was here
and all so I don't remember all of their
mnemonics this is saturating words
saturating bytes I believe right
saturated versus unsaturated and add an
unsaturated add is an add that wraps
around you add one to the highest value
you get the lowest value and start again
right so it wraps saturating adds they
go to the highest value and stop so if
you take the highest value and add one
to it you it remains the highest value
right and so originally in x86 there's
no such thing as a saturating add you
can look through all of the old x86
instructions there is no such thing as a
saturated wrap ads always wrap round but
in when they started doing multimedia
instructions they wanted to have it so
that like if you added two color values
together that would have overflowed
eight bits that they saturated why
because they didn't have any extra room
normally nowadays we always do
computation with Headroom so if you're
gonna do eight like bit computations you
do them in 16 bits so that you have room
and you could do something with the
values when they overflow the saturating
ads were an attempt to make it so that
you could do stuff on values we didn't
have an extra room right because this
was the early days you didn't have much
extra band we're trying to get every
last bit to count right so P chef B just
follows that naming construction if we
switch back to SSE instructions here
and we look at P Chef be what you can
see is all it's saying is it's packed
that's what the P stands for chef stands
for shuffle and B is the identifier for
8-bit values so bytes right if you were
going to shuffle something that was
different in that so if you were gonna
shuffle say 32-bit values or 16-bit
value D like chef W for like forward
which was like if they had a shop man I
don't even know if they do yeah so chef
w's are all here but since they only
work on half the value half the side of
the value usually it's high words low
words right etc hopefully that helps
hi Casey love your show lately you seem
to be having some problems with your
voice breaking coughing have you
considered visiting a speech therapist I
probably should but nowadays probably
not something I'm gonna be doing right
omit blo says the episode guide has been
updated
is this true midlow Oh interesting
oh look at that it's got all the
different sets in here now - that's kind
of cool
haha
that's cool my blue I'll have to check
out all the new additions to it that's
great
nice work ma'am
could you explain the math diagram
behind why the sign bits are the inverse
of the raised sign again I showed up
halfway through that and I think I'm
missing some context sure all right
so let's suppose I have two planes right
if you've never watched behind the curve
on Netflix you might want to check it
out it's it's about it's about the the
people who are trying to advance Flat
Earth theory as a alternative to the
scientific explanation that that the
earth is a roughly spherical shape which
is interesting because one of the odd
things about Flat Earth theory is we
don't really care what shape the earth
is anymore in that way like in the old
days when you were wondering what would
happen if you sailed too far in one
direction then what shape the earth is
is the way you're thinking about
geometry you're like ah is it does it
like wrap around or does we just do we
just hit like a wall and there's like
nothing after it or or there's a totally
different world after it like what
happens you know but like nowadays we're
struggling with things like okay so we
know topologically what happens when we
explore the earth because we did it
right and furthermore we also know what
happens observational II when we're
outside the earth looking back at it
because we did that too but what we
don't know is like what is the actual
like physical structure of the universe
right like we're we're trying we're
struggling with that we don't know but
flat or like the shape of the earth
that's not what we're trying to think
about right like they're still trying to
solve a problem whose solution doesn't
actually tell us anything mm-hmm like
it's it's
I I guess because people who are flat
earth theorists don't know about like
space-time and the other stuff like they
don't aren't able to guess to
conceptualize the kind of harder
problems that we're now facing they
think that somehow if someone was going
to have a conspiracy theory and lie
about something it would be that but
that's like so far back in the
conceptual realm that no one would
bother to lie about that right like
that's not if if the Knights Templar and
the Freemasons and everyone else got
together to like lie to society at large
about critical elements of how the
universe works the shape of the earth is
so far back on the list of things that
you wouldn't even bother lying about
that anymore
because there are so many things that we
now do that make that question
irrelevant that you'd be lying about
space-time right so it's kind of funny
to watch people construct a conspiracy
theory around something that would not
be something and all-knowing
all-powerful force would ever want to
lie about at this point because we don't
think about that anymore like we don't
use that knowledge anymore at all we use
way more advanced stuff that just that
is the thing that falls out of it so if
you were going to start doing if your
core goal at this point if you were
really actually very smart like you're
Stephen Wolfram and you're going to
develop a new kind of science you need
to start way further up and then
demonstrate that oh by the way that also
means the earth is flat but like that's
not that's you know just a thing that
falls out of the actual space-time
equations that we now are telling you to
use which which happen to end up you
know anyway so let's suppose
were let's suppose that the earth is
flat of course and the when the
Freemasons built the fake display system
that shows our heavens to us you know it
was this infinite flat plane right
that's above us and just very very large
um so let's suppose we are standing we
are the Freemasons so we're the only
peace people or the Knights in Flour
whoever else the people are that that
are the cuz the CIA so so out here in in
the place outside like you know this is
this is poor earth right oops sorry I
drew it as a sphere am i bad so earth is
in here and of course it's flat and so
there's these planes that we're keeping
earth people ignorant by displaying fake
heavens and stuff on them and then the
CIA freemasons Knights Templar whoever
else depending on how racist you are
there's probably other people in there I
don't even know but the horrible groups
that are keeping us from knowing the
truth about about things they can get
outside it right so there they can get
outside this fake thing so if they want
to then look in on this system then if
you assume that there were I mean I
don't know if the earth is flat then
theory you could maybe walk around to
the other side and see out we would need
maybe just for insurance purposes if
there's intrepid explorers we would need
you know two infinite planes one on
either side so when the CIA and their
orbital mind-control laser satellite is
out here somewhere looking in on the
system that they built then when you
think about which of these two planes
they're going to hit first what we could
say is the plane that's facing this way
versus the plane that's facing this way
so we're thinking about like all the
gears and machinery we're looking at
those right the lovely displays service
that the earth people sees on this side
um what we know is that whichever side
of this were on if we actually ever hit
this plane meaning we're not pointing
off in the opposite direction if we were
ever actually able to hit one of these
two planes we know we can only ever hit
the plane whose normal was pointing back
at us right because if we were here by
the time we got to the plane whose
normal is pointing the same direction as
us we would have hit the other plane
first right we would have hit this one
so we can't ever get to this one because
this infinite plane would have stopped
us right so how does that translate into
a box well a box is just a bunch of
infinite planes right in 2d it's two
sets of two infinite planes this set
here and this set here wherever we are
right you can see that this forms four
quadrants wherever we are in order to
get to whichever pair like of in order
to get to the one in each pair that is
first we know that we can never hit the
corresponding one first
so if I was going to hit this plane
first it's well whichever vertical plane
I'm looking at I know I'm going to be
hitting the 1 first whose normal points
back at me right whichever it is and if
I was pointing in the same direction as
that I'd never hit it I just walk off
into the distance right I will hit it
negative but of course we clamp T values
to zero in the Ray caster so you can't
ever get there same is true of this pair
I chant ever hit the one that's pointing
the same direction as me because I'll
hit the other one first will I hit this
one eventually sure will it be this the
earliest one no right so what we end up
learning is that for any given box no
matter how many dimensions
I draw it it is made up of pairs of
planes and no matter how I try to aim at
this thing if I will hit one of the
planes it will always be the one who's
pointing towards me not pointing away
from me as a result the sign of this
must always be the opposite of the sign
of this right whichever one I hit will
be pointing back towards me I'm pointing
one way it's pointing the other way in
all pairs of dimensions right or in all
dimensional pairs and that's true of any
dimensional shape right so when you are
constructing your flatter theory and I'm
sure all of you out there are because
now you know that the earth is flat and
certainly not round that would be absurd
that's just something you can take to
the bank in the n-dimensional flat earth
that we all know is true
you can tell all your flat earth friends
that the CIA Freemasons a knight Templar
when they're floating outside it will
always see the one of the two infinite
planes that they are that is has its
normal pointing back at them
not the other one because they can't
actually see through it I'm assuming
there's like a door here that the CIA
goes through or whatever that like I
don't know maybe like during an eclipse
like the CIA like goes in and out of
that door or something I'm not sure
it forms nine cop quadrants not four
quadrants oh I see you're saying you're
just talking about these other ones here
well these aren't really necessary I
mean is the way you could think about it
meaning whether or not we hit this
planar this plane is only based on
whether we're here or here right
it doesn't matter maybe to make this a
little bit more concrete suppose we're
here if we're here we can't hit one of
these planes first anyway because we'd
hit this one right so it literally
doesn't matter which one we shoot at
when we get to here probably should have
said that I'm sorry I was just thinking
about cases where you could actually hit
this part of the box right so in the
nine quadrants if you're in any of these
parts these parts are just fully
deterministic already if you are in any
of these four quadrants here or there
quadrants because there's four but
they're actually part of a octant I
guess if you're in one of these four of
the octants then you know immediately
what your normal is it's just this right
when you're in this octant any of the
four corner ones you can hit either of
these two right so when you're in a a
corner octant those are actually the
cases we are trying to handle if you
could only ever be in these four we
would have a much easier job because
then you know exactly what your normal
is just by the quadrant right because
there's no Ray the Ray that tried to hit
either of these two planes would miss
the Box entirely right
so
this doesn't have a really anything to
do with yeah with anything other than
just the fact that we know it asked me
pointing laughs direction even if this
were not access aligned you could just
transform it so it was right but the
property still holds even if you aren't
access aligned you just it's a dot
product equation now right so instead of
signs because the reason that happens is
because when you are access aligned
right sign equals dot product right so
the inner product and the sign are the
same quantity which is not true
shouldn't save quantity R this R let me
explain the whole thing if you have
access aligned vectors so I have a
vector that's like one zero zero right
if I have access aligned vectors than I
do an inner product then the sine here
right positive or negative here
translates directly into the positive or
negative of the dot product you know I'm
saying because these cannot contribute
so whatever the sign is here right
because the dot product is you know ax
BX + a YB y plus AZ BZ right if you know
a priori that you don't have two of your
terms then the sine of this is what
translates directly into the sine of
this so these two signs whatever the
sign of a ax is and BX those produce my
answer I don't need to know anything
about the other values at all right so
if I know that a is you know plus or
minus one and I know that a Y is zero
and a Z is zero then all I'm doing is
I'm saying okay
the dot product will be completely
determined by the sign and value of BX
and then I will either flip it or not
based on ax and that's the whole dot
product right so now if I say well I
want to do dot products with many of
these like I want to do a dot product
with plus or minus one zero zero zero
plus or minus one zero and zero zero
plus or minus one right so now I've got
you know all of the VEX of those are all
the vectors that are normals on this
thing right here here here here here
right so if I do dot products with all
of these vectors right then I know which
side of each of these things you're on
right I know which side of this you're
on I know which side of this you're on
notice art of this you're on and so on
right now in order to actually do the
side I need to take the vector relative
to this so I'm have to actually see what
you were relative to a point on the
plane for sure but you get the idea if I
was to construct the same algorithm but
things had to be spun so here's the axis
system but now my box is like this you
could still do similar things but you
have to actually take the dot products
right you couldn't cheat and just look
at signs anymore so one of the reasons
we like to rotate things into an access
aligned space or just construct the
algorithms in an axis line space to
begin with if we can if we look if we're
lucky which in this case we can is
because all of these dot products
degenerate down into just sines you're
just changing
you're either changing or not the sign
of a value right BX is coming in as a
real value from negative whatever to
positive whatever right that's a real
value but the only thing your dot
product is doing is plus or minus it's
just changing the sign either we flip
the sign or leave the sign the same and
so you can drastically optimize
operations that used to be whole dot
products doing
dot products of things by just using
sign flipping or sign over writing and
that's what we did here
is it faster do the matrix rotation of
the dot product though I guess there's
only one rotation and play of dot
products so if you're so if you're in a
situation like we are where all of our
boxes are access aligned anyway then
obviously it's free because now you
don't need to do a rotation if you're in
a situation where you're not that way so
you have rotated boxes and then you want
to do it then whether or not the
rotation is cheaper or not depends on
the algorithm it may be cheaper to just
constructor with the dot products it may
be cheaper to do one rotation first to
put it into an organized coordinate
system and then do it so it's really
just a case of looking at what the
algorithm does and seeing which one
makes more of the operations makes more
instructions in which one makes less all
right I think that's the end of the
queues
oh wait no there's one more if you're
curious about signed distance fields I
literally just I literally just did a QA
on signed distance fields like like
literally like two weeks ago it was a
question
to be not get this I mean here's another
one but I thought there was more
hmm hmm
might have been in the pre stream
might have been the pre stream you
missed it should have been here
alright I'm wrap it up it might still be
in the twitch vod's I don't know
those don't get annotated alright thank
you everyone for joining me for that
sort of handmade here at Sona pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow us at home you can always
go to handmade hero org and pre-order
the game it comes with the source code
so you can follow along with it
we also have a Kickstarter that it now
has probably less than 24 hours left if
you would like to get our comic now the
infinite now is the time I guess you get
23 hours left you can go check that out
it's got a cool trailer that will be
running for another 24 hours so about
time I'm back here tomorrow it will be
over well I guess it'll be during the
stream it will be over so do check that
out if you're interested that's it for
today I'll be back here tomorrow when I
will look at implementing the look-up
tables we need so that we can actually
start testing this routine which will be
a lot of debugging but hopefully we'll
end up with something significantly
faster we'll see we don't really know
that's it for today see everyone
tomorrow take it easy everybody