here we go hello everyone and welcome to
day 40 of handmade hero what is very
exciting about day 40 you may ask day 40
marks our first week of programming as
you know there the 40-hour workweek is
relatively common as a amount of time to
be working during the week and so
technically we have now done 40 hours or
so maybe we've done a little bit more
couple streams have gone longer we did
double length stream one time so we're
probably more at like 42 hours of
programming but we have basically now
done a full week's worth of programming
so if the stream started Monday morning
at 9:00 a.m. sharp we are now at Friday
one hour before 5:00 we're at 4:00 we're
at 4:00 p.m. so I think that is a pretty
good week of program that we've done and
and you know we've got a lot to show for
it things things have progressed
extremely well I would say certainly
probably better than I if you'd asked me
when we were starting if things would go
so smoothly I don't think I would have
said that they would have I think I
would have predicted us to be having a
lot more troubles than we had but
actually we've gotten to the point where
essentially we had a full freely
scrolling tilemap we've now implemented
camera support so basically the camera
is locked and when you walk off screens
you can walk back and forth between them
we've got looped loud code editing in
there we have our own win32 abstraction
layer with sound and graphics we have
alpha blended bitmap splitting so things
are things are pretty far along actually
and that that actually surprised me
after only one week of programming I
would have suspected maybe we especially
because we're doing explanations the
whole time I would have expected it to
be a little rougher than that but you
know for whatever reason it wasn't and
that's pretty awesome so here was we're
wrapping up week 40 I think or I should
say wrapping up day 40 the end of our
first working week like I said I kind of
just want to go through everything that
I've written down is to do's and just
make sure everything's
cleaned up because I want to start the
math stuff clean because I think the
next thing we need to do is start
talking about math pretty seriously so I
want to go through and just clean up
anything that we haven't that we haven't
you know sort of spent enough time just
to kind of get out of our way and then
we can kind of bring our first week of
programming to a close alright so let's
take a look here we already did last
yesterday I snuck in one of the main
things that was all to do list which is
to fix to put in a lock file for our PDB
so that our hot loading with load debug
symbols all the time it wouldn't so that
visual studio wouldn't get confused so
that was a good thing we took care also
the other thing that I had written down
was that I wanted to make sure that that
the the people who were doing work on
the people who were doing work on other
platform layers wouldn't have trouble so
we we cleaned some of that up and move
stuff into hand-made platform that would
help them so that's finished up now as
well and let's see I think the only
other stuff I have here is first of all
I believe I don't know if we ever fixed
this but I believe someone was saying
that we still had a version of T sign
sitting around yes we do um so we still
had T signs sitting in the win32 sound
out but even though we weren't using
anymore so I've wanted to get that out
of there so people aren't wondering what
that variable is doing there I wanted to
go ahead also and in our platform code
if you remember we talked about this a
little bit but people were talking about
on the forums sometimes people talk
about stuff on about the code in the
forums without having actually watched
the episode where I explain why things
are done and they were upset about this
because they didn't like the fact that I
was using pound defiance I think they
were maybe macro phobic or something
which is which is not a very good way to
be you don't really want to be macro
phobic in C or C++ because C and C++
have extremely weak text processing
ability built into them macros are
pretty much your only option I wish they
had a lot more power in the macros or a
lot more power in the language one of
the other
unfortunately they have neither of those
and so that's where you're at anyway
the reason for these guys again I'll
just restate it is that static is a
keyword in C actually means many things
and I do not like that fact
not because of readability this is
nothing to do with me being able to read
the code because I would always know
that was the / what the person was
saying on the forums they were like I
think a seaport always knows what they
are sure but that has nothing to do with
it
readability has nothing to do with it
whatsoever it's search ability you want
to be able to know where your global
variables and your local Global's are at
a moment's notice and if all of your
functions have static in front of them
then you can no longer do like automated
grepping to see whether you have any
global variables for example in your
code that's supposed to be thread safe
or in dll's that you don't want to have
any variables in them like we're doing
hot loading so we'd better not have any
Global's in them if you want to do a
grep like I want to be able to say at
any time I want to be able to say show
me all of the global variables and I
need to know that I can guarantee Lee
get that back right and so for example
this right here is a global variable now
I know what's the one global variable
that we have inside our program it's
this guy right and that's okay because
he never changes so that's a really
quick way for me to immediately know
that our dll is okay similarly I can say
do any for do any of our our what do I
call our functions have any of those in
there what's local persist look will
persist yeah
and thankfully we don't have any of
those who have to worry about that's
that's the reason you do this and you
absolutely should
it has nothing cam at ur of taste you
really want to be able to do that
searching to make sure that you don't
have serious problems that are you just
aren't going to notice until you have
some really crazy case of a
multi-threaded problem that you didn't
realize could happen because you had
global variables and something that was
getting called for multiple threads so
basically there's that but what I wanted
to do is I also wanted to define static
to know like OMG
do not compile bad bad bad right or
something like that to make sure that we
can put that somewhere where it's not
going to actually ever ever happen right
trying to think if there's somewhere we
can do this because what I want to do is
make it so that like so these are but
this macro is gonna get hmm
I'm trying to think of what I could do I
want to basically make it I was trying
to think of what I could do I've never
done this before I was trying to think
of what I could do so that static could
never be typed by itself but it's gonna
do the replacement twice in a row you
know like if I if I pound to find
internal then it's gonna replace with
static and then it's gonna apply the
other macro what I want to do is not
have it apply the other macro tryna
think if there's any way I could
actually make that happen
I wonder if this works probably not
it probably only works with well
actually let's see see you fight you can
do this I'm just macros are kind of
nasty and see all right let's let's see
let's see if we can outsmart the macro
system you know being our oops
it's no good being our wily little
selves okay
so I tried to have smart it by saying
well maybe if I can paste combine static
into a new thing maybe that will work
but I guess not
oh well new lining constant so that's
actually that's actually just because of
that so that's fine let's take a look so
no we can't I was try was thinking maybe
if I paste combined to them together you
know so that basically it would be the
results of a paste operator this this
pound pound is the paste operator in C++
is macro processor which basically takes
two inputs and welds them together and I
was thinking I wonder if maybe it
wouldn't do replacement on those but
apparently it still runs the macro
processor even on those so there's no no
refuge there for us I don't know yeah I
don't know it's unfortunate it is
unfortunate but it doesn't really seem
it doesn't really seem like there's
something I can do
oh well so that's a that's I guess just
something that will have to be left for
our own sort of our own diligence so
basically what I'll have to do which is
what I normally do is just this so I'll
have to do a check which basically says
okay what you know where did I actually
type static and let's make sure that
it's only in those particular places so
what I could do is well is basically you
know we have our build dot bat we could
also have a thing which is like static
check dot bat which does something like
statics found and then it does that
that's sort of fine stir - it does this
line of code basically oops so it does
that and and searches for all of the
things that we might want to find so
basically something
like this so we'll search for local
persist and we'll search for global
variable we'll do basically this so
statics found should be nothing
basically except for the the header file
and then Global's found will do that and
I'll put in some empty echoes here all
right
and so then I'll be able to go ahead and
run this this is the basically the poor
man's version of what I just did and
that can basically get tell me very
quickly oh and I should also do a yeah
yeah
instead of doing these there we go so
and these will have to basically be
something like that no if you can can
you do like a space no you can't really
echo a space it looks like it's just
it's just actually heck yes all right
well we will use that for now so this
way we can actually guess go ahead and
and get an easy report which is I guess
the next best thing
and this will basically tell us where we
have those statics and what they are
which which seems like good enough yeah
so we probably also only need to check I
don't know if I can assume I can do this
I I don't use fine stir except from
within
Emacs I assume I can do something like
that so that it doesn't check batch
files yeah so I could basically do
something like this which sort of checks
all of the things so I could I could set
it variable which is like you know wild
card and I can basically say all right
those are all the things that I'd like
to to check for right I don't really
want to check inside batch files or
inside binary Zoar anything like that so
let's go ahead and say it that way and
then that'll be I guess our you know
we'll call that our reasonable check
that'll be good enough so that way I can
always go out here and check
periodically if I want to to sort of say
all right here
all the stuff that we actually where we
actually type static and so we'll make
sure that essentially it's never
anything other than these three lines
right if we see anything else there we
know we've made a mistake and then
similarly here this will basically tell
us whether we have any of those Global's
it'll tell us all the ones we've got and
right now this is fine they're in the
platform layer which is what we want so
any platform layer code is totally
allowed to global variable it up but
anything in the game code is not so
basically if we see a global like this
in the game code we basically know that
it is something which has to be a
constant right it had better be
something that's never gonna be mutated
and in this case that's true and so
we're fine with that and again the
reason for that is we're doing hot
loading so we even if there was a you
know even if there was a totally
legitimate reason to use a global
variable we need to use another method
so that our hot loading would work for
any global variable that's going to be
mutated because you know if we're
changing that global variable and it was
baked into the data segment of the of
the program which is where this global
variable is going to be when it gets
reloaded it will we won't have that
change those changes that were made
right though the reload of the DLL will
clobber the changes and that will break
our hot loading so we don't want to ever
do that all right
hmm I think that's about it for that I
think that one that I had written down
here which is about the the static stuff
so get rid of that we couldn't quite do
what I had hoped maybe might be possible
but sadly was not just because of the
way the macro processor works there
might still be some trickery that you
could do so if someone else if someone
has a good tricky tricky idea about how
to make it so that you just can't type
it at all please let me know okay so
another thing I want to do is some
people we're worried about the the mouse
cursor and we kind of talked about this
a little bit but there's really no
reason for us not to just fix it for now
we haven't really you can see we got to
do here which is control cursor
visibility and so actually you know
we have a fair bit of time today I want
to kind of look at these I feel like I
feel like just looking at looking at
these here I feel like so first of all
time to get in period I feel like we did
right we did do time begin period yeah
so basically time to get in period and
sleep got done they were we haven't
really finished our timing loops because
that's gonna be for later but we did do
that so a couple things that we had here
one was also we had that the stuff that
I was working on there where we had the
sort of the the we had we had done a
little work where we could actually show
the game while we were in the editor and
I'm kind of thinking maybe that's
something that I'd like to bring back
because we've had a bunch of times where
it would have been nice to have the game
still showing in the background behind
the editor so I don't know that might be
something to talk about and then also
toggling full-screen support might be a
nice thing to do it might be nice to
start thinking about changing the
resolution of things and allowing that
to get passed down to the game because I
think that's something we want to use
for renderer tests and stuff I don't
know it's something to think about but
it looks like the rest of these are
stuff for more for for later on down the
road let's see getting a handle to our
own executable file I think we already
essentially did that as well well we
didn't quite so I guess those will be
there all right so I think we'll leave
those for now but I'm gonna go ahead and
first tackle that set cursor because we
don't do that currently and you can see
that that has one particularly odd
effect which is basically that whatever
the cursor people were wondering why
it's a spinning why it's the spinning
weight thing and the answer is it's not
actually the spinning weight thing it's
whatever the cursor was before it
entered our window because we don't
respond to the WM set cursor call and we
did not set a cursor in our wind class
what Windows does is it just does not
touch the cursor state when you move it
into our window
so what that means is you can change it
to anything you want just by like
getting it to that thing and quickly
hopping it over right I couldn't quite
get it without passing over this so it
turned into that but you know if I could
if I could get it in there yeah you can
see if I can get it in there without it
going over the the line you could make
it be the arrow and if I if I moved it
in this way it would always be the arrow
because we're passing over that thick
band same this way right you can see I
can make it be the TextEdit cursor if I
really wanted to probably can't quite
can't quite make it but you get the idea
so basically that's what's actually
happening at the moment but if you if
you look at what's actually happening in
fact we could talk about this because we
never really talked about this it's not
super important for us because we just
don't have a lot of it going on but
there is a tool in visual studio called
spy plus plus inside the tools menu if
you open it you get this sort of thing
that's like a list of windows right and
our window is one of those windows you
could find it in this list these are all
the windows that are at in the top level
in the system you can see crea has a
bunch of pop-ups that it creates and
other sorts of things like this and can
see vigil studio in there and blah blah
blah and here's our command prompt that
sort of thing there's an Emacs right
good ole max what this tool allows you
to do it's it's much more handy for
applications it's not something you
typically use for games a whole lot
because you just don't process that many
window messages at the end of the day
but just for for educational purposes
this particular tool does allow you to
do a few things where you can kind of
see what's going on in your application
as far as Windows is concerned what you
can do is you can go to find window so
you don't have to look in this width in
this list and it gives you this
hilarious little crosshairs that you
drag and move over a window right and
you can see that it's found our window
handmade here oh and there's our wind
class just like we registered it and if
I hit OK that basically will bring me
right to where it is in the list and so
you know you can you could also just
look through the list and found it but
you know it's a little quicker to do it
that way sometimes once you have it you
can go ahead and you can right click and
do highlight if you don't know where the
window is and in theory it's supposed to
blink but I didn't actually see that
happen I don't know if that's an
interaction with OBS I think it's
supposed to kind of blink the window for
you but really the thing we care
about is well you can look at properties
as well which is kind of fun you can
look at window styles are set in your
window and you can see other kind of
stuff like this the window class styles
all that all that stuff we registered is
all actually in here you can see that
there's no cursor registered no icon
registered no menu registered to a
background brush all that kind of stuff
but the more interesting thing for our
purposes now is if you right-click and
go to messages you can actually see what
are the message what the messages that
are getting dispatched by Windows to us
are right and now a lot of these we were
actually expecting to get so for example
if we go in here you can see if I hit a
key you can see that it's having key ups
and key downs get dispatched right and
so that's all good but what what's kind
of what what you can see if you look at
it normally is we're getting these nch I
hit test or ncnc hit test messages and
set cursor messages as well as mouse
move messages none of which are
responding to and it's that set cursor
message that we really want to to talk
about because that's the one that would
allow us to control what the cursor is
now like I said there's two ways you can
actually do this oh another thing that's
interesting about these I believe you
can kind of go in here and you can
actually say which ones you want yeah so
if you if you go in if you right-click
in here you can click on logging options
it's a quick way to get I think it's
also up here you can go ahead and get to
the messages that you want to see so you
can kind of like highlight you can see
all the windows messages in here and you
can clear and only select ones that you
wanted to see if you're looking for a
particular if you're looking for
particular messages and that helps cut
down on the cruft a little bit okay so
just something keep in mind anyway yeah
so that is how that works we don't
really need to use it for any particular
reason here but I just thought I'd bring
it up in case you were having troubles
where you might want to see that what I
want to do is I just want to start
processing that set cursor message and
like I said there's really two ways we
could do this one is down here when we
register our win class so one thing that
we could do
right is we could say there's a I
believe it's H cursor which is inside
the window class structure when we
register it and again this is the thing
that controls our window behaves and
it's anything that's created with this
window class but we're only creating one
window with it right what we could do
here is we can load a cursor basically
out of the default cursor set and I'll
show you what that means so this is gets
into sort of these windows minutiae
things that we really just don't care
about very much as a game developer but
once in a while you kind of brush up
against them nor you know a real
application uses all kinds of this stuff
oftentimes you know like you know an app
style application that has lots of Mouse
interaction with that isn't custom you
know sort of standard windows controls
and all that sort of stuff
so basically this load cursor function
what it's normally meant to do is
there's a thing called an RC file that
compiles into a res file which binds
into the resource fork of your
executable and all this other nonsense
that we really just don't care about for
the most part we will have to care about
a little bit when we want to actually
make an icon for our game so that when
it's sitting there in Windows you know
when you do it a double-click on it it
has an icon we'll we'll have to see how
to do that it's it's called a resource
file and we'll have to do that but we're
not doing any of that right now so we
actually don't have any resources which
are things like strings or images that
get loaded out of the out of the
executable directly basically this load
cursor function would normally allow you
to load a cursor by name using a you
know string would allow you to load that
out of your expedia Bowl one that you
had drawn and baked in there using the
resource editor which is a thing in
visual studio that would allow you to
edit cursors and save them in there
right we don't want to do that because
basically we're not gonna have a cursor
except in debug mode so all we really
want to do is say whether or not we're
in debug mode and if we are in debug
mode we would want to show the cursor
and if we're not then we wouldn't right
because either release version our game
should never show a mouse cursor of any
kind since it's not a mouse controlled
game but the thing that I was talking
about now is if you wanted to always
show a cursor what we could do is just
load cursor here right and we need to
pass our H instance which we've already
got and then we just pass a constant
which would load some of the default
stuff that you don't actually need to
bake into executable that's just in
windows proper that it can load and so
like the standard arrow is i2c arrow we
could load ID c cross for example so
here we go let's let's just put that in
there as a new that's a simple example
and now when we ran the game in theory
well you know what there's one other
thing that I guess we would have to do
actually no I feel like that should have
worked
I'm a little surprised at that that that
didn't work
oops why didn't that work that is very
odd so I guess I I look I guess I'm just
missed remembering I thought that if you
put one in there and you called F window
proc on set cursor which we do right
because we don't handle the set cursor
message so the set cursor message will
get passed through to here right I
thought that that would mean oh I know
what I did wrong this load cursor if you
use one of the things this is it's gonna
try to load it out of this executable
but I just said we don't have any of
these in our schedules so it'd be load
cursor zero if you want to load one of
the default ones from Windows you have
to pass the null two to tell it that
you're trying to load one of the windows
ones forgot about that
that's yeah let's try that again there
we go so that's what I expected to
happen
so you can see this is a little XOR
cursor kind of thing that that that
windows supplies is one of their default
cursors so now in an inside our window
it will always be that it won't just be
whatever the last thing was you won't
have that spinning anymore and that's
fine but what I'd like to do is I'd like
to be a little more explicit about it
because I'd like to be able to
I'd like to be able to have it so that
in the game can dynamically control
whether or not the cursor is visible
we're not really doing we're not we
don't have a debug overlay or anything
yet so we don't really have a reason to
use that at this time but I would like
to be able to do that and so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to go ahead and
and make it happen that way so we're
gonna leave each cursor at zero for now
and and and basically get you know get
rid of that sort of window klass one so
that won't set it for us so then I'm
gonna go ahead and get up go go up to
the the window callbacks here when we
get a WM set cursor message I can do
exactly the same thing that I was doing
before essentially right so I'm gonna
need this cursor I don't really want to
bother you I think you actually could
just call load cursor every time because
I don't think it incurs any cost
it doesn't like open a new handle to the
cursor if you're just loading one of the
default cursors but at the same time we
have a win 32 state structure that we're
able to access so in theory oh and you
know what
I wonder if set cursor can be
intercepted the way we were doing it
before well so let's let's actually look
at that as well let's take a look at
this here I'm gonna put an assert in
here and then I'm gonna go ahead and see
if it ever gets dispatched in normal
cases directly to us because again this
is for debug only so if once in a while
it didn't that would be fine but I want
to see if we can intercept this guy
basically so if we can intercept him
that would mean that we wouldn't have to
have any state there nope it looks like
it goes directly there so remember how
we did this I don't know if you recall
but basically the way that we set things
up is we have a thing that processes
messages that are that go through our
message pump our message loop properly
ones that you know we are actually just
batching to the window ourselves that
Windows puts on our queue but then we
also have our window callback which
essentially is the thing that windows
will sometimes just flat-out call and
there
nothing we can really do about that
right remember I talked about that it
firry it's always supposed to go through
the message pump but it doesn't I don't
know why they ended up in such a hybrid
scenario it's kind of bad but you know
that's just the way it is so it looks
like our set cursor will have to will
have to happen there which means we'll
have to make our cursor a global what
that's fine there's really no problem
with that so we can do a global cursor
here and we can basically say that that
the set cursor happens in there now not
a big deal I just wanted to see if it
was possible for us not to do that so
here's the global variable we have an H
cursor and this is the this is basically
the debug cursor and what we'll do is
we'll go ahead and set that inside
that's that cursor call we will use the
debug cursor in fact I guess I should
call it the global debug cursor I'm so
deep a global cursor so and then I will
call set cursor which is the function in
Windows that actually sets what the
cursor is for our window right so when
it asks us what the cursor should be we
can set what the cursor should be so
that it will know now what I would like
to know though of course is I want to
know it's been a long time since I wrote
any set cursor code so I just want to go
through and read and make sure what the
things are that Windows expects us to do
inside this message when we receive it
and let's see what it says
so the DEF when I'm up up up C sent to
the window if the mouse cursor Mouse
causes the cursor to move within a
window and mouse input is not captured
okay so basically we're just going to
get this the different or pro kleh pass
the message to window yeah it doesn't
seem like there's anything particularly
weird that we'd have to do here so
basically if we wanted to we just go in
here set cursor what do I have to pass
for set cursor do I just pass
set cursor do I not pass the window
handle oh my I don't pass the window
handle I guess that just right I guess
it's just because you could be setting
if you there's a thing you can do in
Windows where you capture the mouse
cursor and can move anywhere but it
still technically belongs to your window
so I guess it's not really a window
specific thing I guess it's just kind of
an ownership thing so I guess when we
get a set cursor we'll just go and set
it there directly and that should set it
to the debug global cursor of course the
debug global chrisser hasn't been
initialized so it's startup when we do
our win class what we would like to do
basically is also a little that cursor
so I'll do a little cursor here and
we'll do that we'll do I be C arrow
which is just the default cursor so that
way our cursor is initialized then in
theory we should be able to do something
where we actually get that set cursor to
work although we still had our wait
looks like it's working now for the most
part but yeah I've got a few oddities
there I'm not sure why it was still
looping I'm not sure why we get the the
wait arrow when we when we first come in
there it still thinks our application is
busy which is a little odd I don't know
if we're if there's some messages that
we're not responding to there
something's going on there but also it
looked like we were doing that that set
Chris are called everywhere so we didn't
actually get our sizing stuff right so I
wonder yeah I wonder what we want to do
there exactly I wonder if what we want
to do is basically just let the default
wind proc handle it
so that it'll do the sizing stuff for us
and then we will only set the cursor to
something if yeah if we need to so for
example we can do a set cursor 0 in
there and in theory I believe that would
make the course or not appear yeah so
you can see if we do a set cursor 0 we
basically get no mouse cursor at all
which is what we would want in a release
mode scenario right so maybe what we
would prefer to do is actually just do
something like
if cursor is hidden you know alright I
guess if so or like if debug show cursor
or something like this then we will
actually allow the diff when proc to
handle it otherwise not so we could do
something that looked a little like this
and then instead of having a global
cursor we just have debug global show
Chris or something like this there we go
there we go so you know what I could do
here is basically say alright we'll
actually setup the cursor in our in our
wind prog so that it'll basically allow
Windows to do whatever random stuff it
does so we don't have to go figure out
all the right stuff to do so in here
we'll still do that where we actually
specify cursor we'll load out the
default cursor IC arrow and then we'll
just have our debug global we'll
basically the debug global show cursor
and for now I guess what we can do is
basically say you know we've defined in
our handmade platform to H we've got our
definitions for for what's supposed to
be or at least I thought we did for like
handmade internal and stuff like that
and made did we did we leave those in
here no yeah so this this should
actually be this this should actually be
in handmade platform because that
actually affects everybody just want
that documentation there so basically we
said these were the things we were going
to do
so if handmade internal is is on so this
is an internal build then we probably
want that mouse cursor right we want to
see the mouse cursor and if we're
building a release build then we
wouldn't want that mouse cursor in there
right
oops and then I didn't actually change
this to a full 32 which is what I wanted
so now when we do our build in theory we
should have the mouse cursor work
properly I still don't know I do not
know why the little spinning arrow is
happening there I'm guessing we haven't
done some thing that it wants us to do
to let it know to so that it will know
that we're done loading and I don't know
let's take a look and see if we can find
out what
that is let's take a look well we want
to know when
how does Windows know your app is done
loading No
so yeah windows or win32 cursor arrow
spinning let's see here I've been the
hourglass spinning cursor display yeah
I'm not sure I might have to look this
one up on my own basically so
essentially if I remember correctly
unfortunately I remember the
circumstance but I don't actually
remember what the actual set of things
is my recollection is that when a
Windows application starts what happens
is it assumes that the application is
loading and uses the busy that arrow
with the with the spinning cursor it
uses that until you have done something
some set of things that it looks for if
you do any one of those things it
assumes that you've finished loading I
don't actually remember what any of them
are unfortunately and I'm guessing we
just aren't doing whatever that is right
so if that makes sense and I don't
really know I don't know if anyone here
has this sort of thing let's see
yeah doesn't look like these people know
I really want a Raymond Chen post let's
see here let's let's see wonder if I can
just go ahead and say Raymond Chen let's
see let's see Raymond Chen let's just
you know it doesn't look like I can
quickly get it let's see yeah I really
want a Raymond Chen Raymond Chen sight
is awesome because he answers you know
basically windows questions in a very
thorough way that's usually very
accurate but yeah so I don't know why it
thinks we're still loading it's okay I
mean it goes away after a second but
really it should have gone away right
then because there's nothing actually
that we're doing so I'm not sure why it
thinks we need to keep doing that that
cursor but I'm sure it's just a case of
something where there's there's some
call that it would prefer that we were
making that we are not making so yeah so
that's what I'm gonna assume for now I
don't actually know but but we'll we'll
leave that as it to do and I'll see if I
can find an article on it because I
remember explicitly reading about that
long ago and I've just forgotten so
we'll change this to make the right call
so Windows doesn't think we're still
loading or a bit after we actually start
so there now we can use Raymond Chen
right now because full screen support is
something that it would probably be nice
to to go ahead and put in there as well
which is that we don't really have too
much of that going on because our
renderer is kind of fixed to just
rendering that little square at the
moment but we're gonna want to start you
know getting away from that especially
when we start on the renderer
proper so one thing I did want to say
was basically fullscreen Raymond Chen
this is to give you an example since we
were talking about it
let me see if I can find one of those
here we go so I believe this is a good
article on that I don't actually know if
that's true let's see let's see here
you actually see if I can find yeah so I
guess that's the best one I don't know I
just doesn't look like the one that I
was thinking of I'm actually thinking of
a different Raymond Chen full screen
article let's find out let's see Raymond
Chen let's switch I want to show you
because this is a good blog it's a good
it's a good blog to go on I don't know
if see if the Stack Overflow has a link
to it here Google's failing me today I
guess my Google foo is not very good
here we go this is the one last thinking
of I believe yes here you go
so basically if we want to just put our
window up and cover the whole screen
which is something that we might want to
do basically this code is some probably
verifiably decent code because it comes
from Raymond who actually works on
Windows and stuff and tends to have the
right sort of answers to all of the
crazy stuff that goes on inside windows
because obviously there's just so much
stuff in Windows and it's often so crazy
spaghetti in there that the likelihood
that you'll figure out how to do
something like properly set a full
screen window without doing something
wrong in some scenario is probably
unlikely so if you can find Raymond Chen
showing you how to do something I highly
recommend that you take his advice that
said you know maybe this won't work well
we'll have to double-check you know even
Raymond Chen is wrong sometimes but I
suspect that basically if we want to
place our window at full screen this is
probably the best place to start because
essentially he
knows those internals a lot better than
anyone like outside like us is going to
know and so it's a good thing to look at
sort of what he does and so you can take
a look at this routine that he suggests
here which is basically a toggle it will
toggle between fullscreen and not and so
the way that it works is first it goes
ahead and asked what the style of the
window is currently and if the style of
the window is overlapped window which
remember is our style that we were using
which is basically a window that you
just kind of generally you know it's
it's exactly this kind of window it's
it's this kind that you can move around
and do stuff with it's not full screen
at all right if it's one of those then
he basically says let's see what the
monitor is the the monitor the primary
monitor is that we're on and let's save
where our window is currently so this
basically saves the location of the
window as it stands and this gets the
information for the primary monitor
which is I guess no I guess what it does
is I want to say I'll have to look at
what that default primary does but I
want to say it actually gets the window
the monitor that the windows currently
on and I assume default to primary would
just mean if the window like straddles
two monitors default to the primary one
or something like that I don't know but
we could check let's let's look let's
look at what that does I don't know
exactly what that flag does monitor info
get monitor info oh sorry monitor from
window is actually the actual thing
taking that monitor window there we go
so that takes the window handle right
and then you know gives us back
whichever monitor the windows on but
let's see if the windows not the set any
okay so basically if the window is not
anywhere that it can determine what the
monitor is then it will do default to
nearest default to null or default to
primary so obviously want default the
primary because we'd like to go
fullscreen on something yes that's fine
so basically that's what that does right
and then we go ahead and if assuming
that we were
able to actually execute those two
function calls we set the style to not
have any of the bits of overlapped
window in it remember overlapped window
for those of you who don't remember we
actually did this before overlapped
window is a you can jump right to window
styles look at that
thank you Google overlapped window is
actually an aggregate so you can see
it's actually overlapped caption system
in your thick frame minimized locks
maximize all the things that sort of
make a standard window a standard window
all those flags are in overlapped window
so basically what he's doing is he's
saying let's clear out all of those
they're gone now
we mask them out and then he's gonna
call set window pose to basically change
it to be the size of the full screen
right and he's passing he's saying don't
change where it is on in the Z order so
don't raise it or lower it and then give
it a notification that's what these
flags do in set window pose
give it a notification that its border
that it's it's like this part it's sort
of external to the client area has
changed and needs to be redrawn assuming
that the the thing was already full
screen which is what he's doing in this
case he does the opposite he puts those
window those overlapped window things
back in he sets the window back to
whatever the last place it was you know
was and then he goes ahead and does that
set window post to update again the set
window pose is basically a thing that
you know it's weird that there's set
window placement and then you have to
call set window pose that's just how
ridiculous Windows is basically when you
call this it doesn't actually do the
repainting necessarily for you so you
have to go ahead and do this to get your
frame to repaint properly it's windows
is full of horrible stuff like that
that's just the way it is is why you
have to look at people like Raymond Chen
to find out how to do stuff properly
because the chances that you'd figure
out these exact incantations are like
nil right so there you go so in theory
this should work I believe and so let's
go ahead and try it like I said I trust
Raymond so I think that this is probably
a good a good way to go so we'll go
ahead and do essentially exactly what he
says for for for all intents and
purposes we might you know make a slight
modification here or there but for the
most part we're going to just exactly
copy
what he does because like I said he
knows much better than we do so global
window position like this oh and he
wants it to have that size of there so
that basically would be I assumed that
the reason he's doing that is just so he
can use it even if it if it wasn't
initialized yet I'm not exactly sure why
but yes I guess when you when you call
you have to give it that size when you
get window placement probably requires
that that size is there all right so we
basically now have a thing which is like
toggle fullscreen for now and we might
make this a little more complicated
later I don't actually know why he's I
guess he was doing it in a message pump
kind of a thing but that X in that why
aren't used and neither are the key
flags so really that doesn't have to be
there really all we need to know is what
the window was right and so we're going
to go ahead and get that back get that
that style back not a big fan of
Hungarian so I'm just going to go ahead
and kind of clean this up so it doesn't
look totally out of place
and I might also while we're at it take
snap that who we got the code from right
this follows Raymond
Chen's prescription or full screen
toggling see there so that way if people
are wondering what's going on there they
can basically go oh ok let me go read
Raymond Chen's article about it and see
you know why why Casey thought that this
was the series of steps you're supposed
to do and I'm like just just following
just Rahl and Raymond man so anyway
we've got the monitor info stuff going
on here he initializes the hoops and a
half size up there okay monitor info
again we initialize it with the size
because Windows loves to have us put the
size and destructs the head of time for
no real reason I think they thought that
would increase compatibility I doubt it
ever did anyway let's go ahead and
finish up that there we need to go ahead
and put in our global window position
here like so
and we need to get our monitor info like
that then our set call should be fine
basically exactly what he was doing
style there we go and there we go H wins
top let's see
RC monitor left so these are just in the
monitor info structure keys basically
just using that monitor info to figure
out how big the screen should be which
looks like a good idea to me that will
give us the full screen and then we just
have to do the case where we want to set
it back so there we go
window oops window Wow take him very
well
window and we're gonna restore that
placement here so this is that global
again the window position and this is
just the thing that has it redo the
positioning okay so in theory that
should do our fullscreen toggle so I'm
gonna go ahead and put that down where
we do our processing our keyboard
messages let's go ahead and do that and
so really all I want to do here is I
want to call this on a particular key
message right so I want a base to be
able to toggle the full screen when I do
a particular key message and in this
case what I want to do is follow the old
since this is mostly a debugging thing
you know normally the user wouldn't be
hitting a key to toggle full screen I'm
going to use the standard the window
standard key for it which is a bit
obtuse but you know it is what it is so
I believe we handled alt f4 the standard
for this is actually if I remember
correctly it's actually alt enter right
so it's basically I don't know what the
remember what the the VK code for return
is I know if it's enter or return
but if the Alt key was down and they hit
return then I'm just going to call that
toggle full-screen function assuming
these this also I always forget to use
is down in here right
I always forget to use or wet or
basically went down
right I always forget to do to put
things in there and so these should also
be in there because we essentially only
want to ever do this stuff on key down
we don't want to do it on key up as well
because otherwise we'd trigger twice
once when it goes down once when it
comes up window is undeclared oh well
yes that's true we want to do it on the
window that that that was coming in here
what is it H wind there we go yeah I
need to get it out of the message
structure because we're not actually any
window handle and I guess I could also
say make sure that that that is valid
there we go so so let's take a look at
what we've got here looks like I'm still
doing it that's right
never never learn real ly I've done this
every time we've added a keyboard
handling I forget to do it only on the
down all right there we go so there we
go
we now go full screen just fine and so
the reason I want to do that of course
was because I feel like later on down
the road we're kind of gonna want to
have it so that we can switch to full
screen and have the renderer do
rendering a full screen even though
we'll be horribly slow in software cuz
there's too many pixels we'll want to
test you know doing that sort of stuff
so I just wanted to kind of throw that
in there it's really simple like I said
as long as you have an expert to guide
you when Raymond Chen writes about
something it takes a lot of the pain out
of Windows because you can just what he
says works like he's he just really
knows that stuff better than anyone else
and so you find someone Stack Overflow
it's probably wrong and you'll go be
super grumpy and tear your hair out
however if the Stack Overflow says
here's what Raymond Chen says just click
on the Raymond Chen link and you are
done like you can pretty much count on
that being a pretty solid answer all
right so so that's all good
I should mention a couple caveats there
they're caveats that I don't mind but
other people might so there's multiple
ways to go fullscreen and windows I'm
doing the one that I prefer but it has
downsides so the reason I prefer this
way is because I find it's a lot more
stable
and it doesn't cause weird monitor
flashing and it doesn't cause your HDMI
to lose sync and that sort of stuff but
it has some downsides one downside is
you can't change the refresh rate now
that's not a particularly big deal these
days because you really shouldn't be
changing the refresh rate on the monitor
probably whatever the users were set to
is probably the one that you want but
you know maybe they've got it set to
something wonky I don't know and you
want to try and set it to 60 if you
think the monitor can handle 60 you
could enumerate the modes and do it so
there are other things that you could be
calling right for example change display
settings I just want to point this out
change display settings is what a lot of
games will call change display settings
actually allows you to be much more
specific about what's going on and so
after you know you would you'd basically
do this first you'd call change display
settings and you would pass a bunch of
stuff like what the resolution is that
you actually wanted this to monitor to
be in right and then you would still do
probably what I just did
follow Raymond Chen's advice but you'd
first call that change display settings
and so sometimes you have to do that if
you have other concerns right look
basically we are running the game in
whatever mode the user has their
monitoring right and usually that's okay
because what you can do is you can just
have the GPU stretch you it like even if
we were only going to render at a small
resolution because we can't you know
like even let's say we only run at 1080p
even on GPUs or something and the user
is trying to run at you know some 240 by
that 2400 by something or a 3k 4k
display something like that usually what
you want to do is just stretch up to
that because the stretch split is
usually fast enough even on those large
displays to compensate but that's not
always true either sometimes on some
things like Intel integrated graphics
parts the GPU is just horribly slow
sometimes and you know it can cause you
problems and you really do want to set
that display mode so it's just worth
noting that pretty much anything that
you're gonna do can have what has has
some potential negative consequences to
the user if you really want to do fully
complete maybe you would even supply
both as possible ways of doing it and
you'd try to detect
like you'd go oh we did the switch we do
it this way and then if the frame rates
too slow we try changing the display
settings down if we detected the Blitz
too slow and maybe we can try doing this
on that stream I don't know at this
point that really shouldn't be a concern
that's more for older systems but you
never know and so it's just something to
be aware of I want to mention I don't
want people to think that there's no
downside of doing it this way it has a
lot of upsides doing it this way but
there is a potential downside or two
lurking in the shadows but anyway you
can see if the employment this way it's
much nicer because it just goes
instantly and there's no weirdness right
and so you really want to do this method
if you can get away with it and you
really only want to do the change the
slave settings if you can't that said
maybe we should eventually implement the
change display settings and I'll put it
to do to that effect adjust it and put
in a detection thing where we detect
weight our frame rates really slow and
the Blitz taking all the time let's
let's see what we can do about it right
so let's do change display settings
option if we detect slow fullscreen blip
just so we've got that in there all
right so let's see we took care of our
set cursor situation and we have our our
full screen situation going on so I
think that's good and so really all
we'll have to do eventually is decide
what we want to do render wise in terms
of who gets past what so when we get a
little bit further down the road this
will be good because now we've set
ourselves up so that when we want the
renderer to start responding to that
full screen we don't really have much
work doing the platform layer will just
kind of work all right so that's good
yeah that's that's that's good
I think that's good thing another thing
that we could do I guess real quickly I
don't know if this is what we want to do
long term probably not but in terms of
stretch di bits what we could do too is
something kind of a little wonky where
we basically do some kind of an if where
we do you know if we are in full screen
then do that stretch blit like if it
turns out that you can do a perfect 2x
do the perfect 2x and that code would be
pretty trivial right that code would be
something
that kind of looks like this let's say
we did something where we said you know
if window width equals oops I should cry
put this in the else case just showing
you kind of a simple thing here this is
not what I think I'd want to do
eventually but just to throw it out
there if the window width equals the
buffer width times two
right because we know where we were
currently doing a down sampled by two
things so this is just some hacky code
to put in here just to you know just to
show you you know an example so if we
happen to have exactly 2x display then
go ahead and go ahead and do the full on
the full on blip basically so I believe
we just want to go ahead and say offset
X offset Y is going to be zero in this
case and then the window width and the
window height so just do the full the
full lit up so if we do that then we'll
still run the way we normally run when
we're in this mode and when we're in
this mode we'll get a full screen right
and it'll basically just do an up
sampling by two which is a totally fine
up sampling and shouldn't caused any
problems so you know for the time being
that's probably fine
basically that allows us on and on 1920
by 1080 displays that allows us to to do
it in fact we could go one further which
is actually saying you know in the case
where it's greater than or equal to it
will allow it to happen by basically
saying we'll just enforce that it's
always 2x so that we basically don't
have any weird scaling because stretch
di bits doesn't do particularly good
scaling if I remember correctly so we
wouldn't really want to do that
but in this case now if it's if you're
resizing the window right and you don't
have enough room to do a perfect 2 X
scale it won't do the Proteas scale but
if you do happen to have it it'll do it
and that'll work I'm on a 1920 by 1080
monitor right now if you were on one now
that's higher than that and you went
fullscreen you just still get it up in
the corner I guess we could be even a
little bit better than that we could
even do it centered I don't know that
that necessarily matters particularly
much but you know like I said later on
you know maybe we'll flush with this a
little bit to do Kaycee centering black
bars there's that we could make this we
could spend a bunch of time making these
sorts of things better but basically
we're out of time on the stream we've
sort of done the stuff that that I had
wanted to do today there's a couple
other things that I would want to maybe
do in terms of windows cleanup but we'll
just roll them into times when we are
actually working on that part of the
code like basically there is one thing
that I want to do with the replay code
that that we didn't get a chance to do
so anyway there we go there's our little
dude he's he's you know having a good
time as you can see he is very happy and
cheery which we like and so yeah I think
that's a good place to call it for the
day because we are right about at an
hour I think I started about six or
seven minutes late and now we are six
seven minutes into the QA so I think now
would be a good time to start the Q&amp;A so
as of right now if you are to enter a
question with Q : into the stream I
would be happy to answer it for you
please try to keep the questions to
things that we've done on today's stream
or on a previous stream not about stuff
that we might do in the future because
well we'll be getting to that in the
future so you know though all of those
questions will be answered so there we
go that's a that's a I think all we
really need to do for our cleanup and on
Monday we can start on math with the
with everything kind of working
relatively smoothly okay let's take a
look at what's going on in the QA
let's see let's see
of course I gotta wait to for it to
catch up
let's see okay
you said in a stream some days ago that
you want your graphic guy to leave some
space around the object with 100% alpha
when creating bitmaps why is that I
usually tell my graphics guys to cut
empty space around the object in a BMP
to keep the files as small as possible
so well okay so there's a couple couple
things there first of all it's a
graphics girl not a graphic sky
yangshin is his female but our graphics
guy
yangshin basically I just don't want
things to go right up to the edge
necessarily but it doesn't actually
matter
I shouldn't have said that I want them
to do that it's just it's fine I don't
believe in ever using assets directly
from the artist in the game I always run
them through a processor first that's
gonna do stuff like trimming out white
space and realigning things and packing
things together and all that sorts of
stuff so I probably shouldn't have said
that that's what I want them to do it's
more that that is totally fine and and I
guess the want part of that is that when
ganc shion's working on art I don't want
her to have to think about a bunch of
engine problems right I want it to be as
fluid for her to make the art as
possible because that's when she will do
the best art and that's when she'll get
the most done right I don't want to
create obstacles to her doing good
artwork by making her think about a
stuff that I can just as well handle
automatically so instead of having her
to have this unnatural painting
experience where she's got to paint
right up to the edge of something right
or have to rely on some crazy Photoshop
export thing or whatever what I'd rather
her do is just be able to make stuff in
Photoshop save it however she wants and
then have my code go in and figure out
what needs to be exported so what I say
that's what I wanted her to do what I
want her to do is just do whatever is
easiest for her and then I will deal
with the rest of the stuff
and so yeah so that's I mean basically
I'm gonna process all the assets anyway
to put them into a blob that we can use
on handmade hero and so what I'm doing
that processing I can just click clip
that empty space sour trollee worms are
harrybo gummy bears is an important
question I guess I would say both are
good
probably harrybo gummy bears especially
if they're the mini bears the little
tiny ones those are particularly good
and fit easily in a pocket
surreptitiously we've got a fair number
of if statements that clamp values would
it makes sense to make clamp min max
range macros for these yes well so I
don't know exactly what I'm gonna want
to do with that long term but now that
we're gonna be getting into the math
part of things I will be introducing a
bunch of math functions that do clamping
sorts of stuff yeah and so so basically
yes I mean yes is the short answer
but what exactly those will look like
I'm not sure yet well when we're sort of
dealing starting to do our math library
basically what we want to start on next
week that that is the sort of thing that
we will be looking at
let's see why do you do size of a
variable and not the type for a monitor
info well because you know it's it's
can't fail right if you do it this way
so let's say that you had written it the
other way right so let's say that you
wrote this this way and then you go in
and say oh oops I forgot it's not really
a window placement right it's an H
cursor am i bad and then you go about
your day
well now you basically have introduced a
bug here right because it was taking the
size of something that was not actually
what you wanted right and so what you
want to do is you want to try and
minimize the degree to which that can
happen so it helps to basically say if
I'm trying to say that this variable
should have the size of itself in its
first member then I might as well just
do that in a way that always works no
matter what its type is right yeah it's
kind of a stupid thing anyway Windows
shouldn't have done this this way I
don't think so you should never have had
to have done this in the first place
clear to zero should have always been
the default but you know they did what
they did so we're stuck with it
do you prefer separate files for sprite
frame elements or a single sheet of them
like I said I don't care I want my
artists to do whatever is easiest for
them so I always tell any artist that I
work with the first thing we do is we
basically work together to make some PSD
format or whatever or whatever they want
that's basically here is how it's here
it's how they're going to do the art
assets and I basically let them do
whatever they want
so however they think it's gonna be
easiest for them so usually I try to say
you know if you want a multiple PS DS
for these go ahead if you want them to
be sort of different layers inside one
PSD do that the only thing I specify is
these each need to be separate layers
like I need to have these things
separate like the head the body and the
torso for example so I always say like
okay you can just make all those in one
PSD files long these are separate layers
and then I'll just extract them right so
I find that's easier for artists because
then they don't have to spend all this
time putting stuff out into different
places like it doesn't take very long to
write a PSD parser it doesn't take very
long to to process our tasks to write an
asset processor and so I just rather do
that work once and then allow the
artists to have a lot more freedom and
flexibility in their day and not have to
manhandle that because I think it slows
artists down to have to deal with that
stuff so always make life easier for
your artists because that's how you get
the best art is when artists are happy
and not spending a lot of time dealing
with your mundane engine stuff that you
should have fixed you know so I take
that pretty seriously
I've got the asserts INRI canonical I
scored that trigger quite often because
Tyrael value is about 0.7 etc is there a
quick fix for that should I just disable
the assert for now since there's a too
bad you can just disable that assert
it's really not it's it's actually not a
problem like everything will still work
just fine with those values what I just
with something we want to look at
eventually I don't know why I never get
the assert if you're getting it but you
know that's just probably slight
differences and how we're running or
something like that but yeah I wouldn't
worry about that until we get to that
part
those asserts aren't important and and
nothing breaks because of them they can
easily just not be there and it's fine I
just wanted to make sure we weren't
getting high values like I don't want to
I want to make sure the code wasn't
totally broken so if it's only just
small values then you're totally fine
anyway is it part of the plan to be able
to support different screen sizes where
the image is not scaled but instead clip
to fit the current screen no I don't
think I will ever support that because I
feel like the game has to be I feel like
that's a design issue like I don't want
to design a game that can be played at
multiple aspect ratios because I feel
like I feel like the game should be the
size that it is and it should be
designed to play right at that size
that's just kind of a personal opinion
so I would go the route of black putting
black bars if you play at the wrong
screen resolution right or you know they
don't have to be black bars they could
be some kind of a decorative element so
it doesn't necessarily look as bad as a
black bar would but you know I would
basically say the screen aspect ratio
the aspect ratio of the image is always
going to be sixteen by nine that's just
that's enforced and so the game always
plays exactly the same it doesn't play
differently when you you know have a
different screen size like four by three
although this is old can you explain how
the transient permanent storage work I'd
rather not because we actually haven't
used the transient storage yet so what
I'd say is what you hold off on that
until we actually get to the point where
we're using both of them because at that
point I will be explaining it in detail
and it'll be easier for you to
understand what's going on because right
now I just would be talking
hypotheticals because we we don't use
the transit storage at all so once I
actually am using the transient storage
then I think it'll become clearer and
I'll be explaining at that time so just
hold off on that up for a little while
when we get to the point we're using
transient storage I think it'll be
pretty obvious actually how it's working
how would you implement a vector would
you use macros metaprogramming something
else I use Mehta program for that pretty
much exclusively so anytime what you see
is not talking about a math vector that
the person who's asking the question is
talking about one of these so like a
more like an array look at you know if
you had an array type array of Foos
you know a or something like that and
the answer is always metaprogramming
yeah since we're not gonna be doing meta
programming in the stream I will just
hand code any container types that we
need but we won't probably have that
many container types so it's really not
gonna like we wouldn't need a template
for them anyway because they just won't
be that many but yeah if you're in some
kind of program that has like a metric
ton of containers or something I always
always met a program those I don't use
templates because templates are very
restrictive and and really just don't
work well for most things including that
one by the way that's a classic case of
of a place where templates don't work
well at all in my opinion
so it looks like we are basically done
with on topic questions I think yeah I
think we're basically done with on topic
questions
I don't see any more on top of questions
I only see off topic questions so maybe
I guess we will end the stream early and
I'll just start answering off-topic
questions for the last 10 minutes since
that seems as a reasonable thing to do
as any all right
so I will officially sign off here but
then when I stop recording I will just
keep streaming for 10 minutes and we can
do off-topic questions there wasn't much
of a pretty stream today so that seems
totally reasonable as well so anyway
thank you everyone for joining me for
handmade here oh it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home with the
source code you can do so at handmade
hero org you can pre-order the game and
it comes with full source please
remember to put in your correct email
when you order because the email needs
to email you with the link to download
the source so please double check that
email when you enter it we've had three
times when people have entered the wrong
emails and of course if you entered the
wrong email I can't even contact you to
get the right one so it's pretty much
like your $15 just goes up in smoke so
please make sure that you do that or if
you think that you've entered it
incorrectly you do and you don't get an
email back email me or go to the forums
and post so that we can straighten it
out because it's really important that
you get that email that's the link that
has all the downloads for you so you can
do that and then you can follow along
with the full source code and it also
has all the test assets that we've been
using so you can follow along exactly if
you want to support the video series we
do have the patreon as well you can
subscribe to and we also have a news and
forum site where there's a bunch of
resources that you can go and use to
help you learn there's an episode guide
there's coding resources page with ports
to other platforms there's a code
discussion forum you can post questions
and of course the schedule for the week
is always up there so please check that
out if you're trying to learn from the
stream it's a great place to go so thank
you everyone and we will start in on the
math which is pretty fun and pretty cool
and it will allow us to do a lot more
powerful things than what we've been
doing so far when we've had too
kind of not been using much math at all
so we'll be starting in on the math on
Monday 8 p.m. Pacific Standard Time
sharp I would love to see you there so I
hope you can join me for that and it's
gonna be I think it's gonna be a lot of
fun to go through the math again it's
been a long time since I've done that
much math honestly so I think it's gonna
be fun for me too to just to sort of get
back into it a little bit all right
thanks everyone for joining me and I
will see you on Monday