start recording okay
hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Europe
we're coming in a little bit hot today
because I just got through ranting about
people who are sort of asking about
libraries and why you don't use them and
I just kind of totally dumped on
libraries for about ten minutes so you
know there's a little bit of furor in
there there's a little bit of like fire
in the belly it's true but we are going
to channel that into coding hopefully
we'll see how it goes anyway welcome on
that note welcome to handmade hero the
show where we code a complete game live
on Twitch no libraries which is kind of
the point of the free free stream no
libraries what so ever I think the only
thing we're linking with right now is
the C runtime library which which
honestly I think eventually we'll
probably want to remove as well because
well because why not once you once
you're not linking with any libraries
you might as well not let the one
default library stand in your way from
actually be able to say you linked with
zero because it's not that much work to
remove it right but anyway
separate from that welcome to handmade
hero today we have to do some work on
something that's that's kind of the bane
of the existence of 2d games that want
to do some 3d effects which is handling
that extra Z layer and the reason for
that of course is because well the art
isn't 3d right the art is little bit
maps and you've constantly in this thing
of like how do I take little bit Maps
and turn them into something that sort
of faked some of the effects of 3d
without essentially fighting the fact
that it is bitmap art and again we could
just ignore this problem all together
and just have the game take place on a
flat plane where you can never see
anything above or below you and that is
what a lot of 2d games do but again
because this is a programming stream not
a stream about getting a game done as
soon as possible we have chosen to try
and handle Z in a number of ways just so
we can explore the complexities that
come with it and you know just so you
can watch me wrestle with them because
it's not a case where there's any
perfect solution and so I think again I
try to introduce things into the stream
that I'll have to struggle with and
weigh decisions and not just see an
immediate answer and go oh well we just
typed it in and it worked right which
you've kind of see happen like first
when we did texture mapping we just kind
of typed it in and just worked it was
like you know 15 minutes on the stream
after explaining it on the blackboard it
just works right known things like that
are pretty easy but they don't really
teach you about how to work through
difficult programming problems where
you're trying to do something that
doesn't have a necessarily right answer
and this is one of those things and so
we're in the middle of that process of
trying to work through it trying to look
at exactly what we can do to get some
amount of clean render design that still
brings out some of that z-depth to the
game so that's what we're doing today
we're gonna start some of that
exploration process because we've we
sort of set ourselves up to do that
based on what we did yesterday and today
is day 107 so if you'd like to follow
along at home and you preorder the game
on handmade hero org what you want to do
is take that source zip file you can
download and you want to unpack day 106
because that was yesterday's code that's
what we're starting with today to make
today's code alright so let's get going
let us get going here that is if I could
actually remember how to load some code
and compile it which is kind of what we
need to do so all right where we left
things off was we had sort of made just
we had like a little test world here we
were working with that actually had two
Z layers on it you can sort of see that
the way that they go here but at the
moment we have a number of things that
we're not really doing like first of all
we turned off rendering of our ground
chunks which I would like to turn back
on and what I'd like to do is start to
get a notion of those z slices in here
because we don't have that at the moment
either we can also kind of do something
where we pan up and down you can kind of
see what happens there if I move the
camera in and out a little bit but again
we haven't really done much in terms of
dealing with these these slices other
than just handling that offset right so
I think the first thing that we want to
do is is really kind of go in there and
take a look at how to get those Z slices
in there and you can see that the tree
is kind of moving at different rates
there's one ring of trees that's above
and one retreat is below but until we
put the ground
there it's gonna be hard to really
visually understand these things so
let's go ahead and do that and maybe
just start to try and get those ground
slices in place okay so what we decided
and this this change this may be a
fairly lengthy set of changes that we
want to make here because remember we've
got a lot of things in play now and
we're trying to solidify the z across
all of them right and so if you remember
we've got our sim region which is the
thing that handles basically computing
how entities update over time we have
our handmade world structure which
basically packs entities into their
locations where they are and that sort
of stuff and what I want to take a look
at here is previously we had this world
position stuff and we have the chunk Z
that's the sort of Z conceptualization
of where things are in Z and what I'd
like to do is I'd like to start getting
start talking about that Z in terms of
actual slices in the world that probably
coincide with the chunk Z so that we can
talk about them in terms of layers
because what we keep seeing when we work
through this is really we need this
concept of fixed chunks of Z because
since the bitmaps themselves can't
include really much 3d information we
need a way of sort of saying well
everything at this level we'll just
assume kind of works all together and
everything at the next level up works
all together right and we we can't
really allow things to cross between
those two to exist in both of those at
the same time because the bitmaps would
have to like shear and stuff in order to
maintain the perspective and do all
sorts of things that we really can't do
with the art style that we have and so
in order to get around that what we were
trying to do here is we're trying to
make a world that essentially exists
coherently in terms of slices and
enemies can move between the slices just
fine but in general the slices of the
world in Z should be
separate they shouldn't be trying to
have art extend between them if there's
things that need to go between them
there's art on both of the levels and we
just accept the fact that there might be
some breakage there just as part of the
way the art style works that's just how
it's gonna work
right that's what we're doing and if we
find that that breakage is too
off-putting what we'll do at the end is
instead of we can just turn off that
scaling and that will make all of our
levels line up and then we can have the
art kind of just line up with tops and
bottoms if that's what we want but I
suspect since the game is not really
about having these tall structures or
anything like that I suspect that we'll
be able to do is basically just treat
things like a series of shelves and we
really won't have any problem with it
and of course we can have lots of
entities that move between them without
really having any problems so that
should be totally fine so that's where
we're at and so I want to start thinking
about this in terms of where everything
is and try and start working through
that that chunk stuff so let's take a
look first of all how our sim region
stuff Candles unpacking entities I just
want to kind of go through this quickly
so basically what happens when we unpack
entities I don't really want to be a
move entity here I want to be in the
same region stuff that actually unpacks
which is begins Sam there it is so in
begins Sam what we do is we loop over
all of the chunks that are hit by the
camera right and we go ahead and pull
out all the entities and we add them to
our sim region and then we're we're done
right we stuff them all back in and that
is pretty agnostic about what's
happening with the chunk see and you can
see here that what generally happens is
we maintain the chunk C but we don't
become you to me we maintain the chunk C
for the camera but we never actually do
for the for the offset C we never
actually use that offset Z so you can
kind of see here we even do it we even
make sure that we preserve that
the so the camera doesn't move up and
down smoothly at the moment the camera
like hops between levels and I don't
know if that's the way we want it to do
probably that's not what we wanted to do
in the end we probably want it to kind
of move cleanly between them and so this
again also gets back to sort of the sort
of the concept of the ground and where
the ground should be but let's let's
hold off on that on that for a second so
what I want to do is I want to go back
in here and I'm going to take off out
that cam off that Z that we were playing
with a little bit there that I just kind
of threw in there for a second offset I
don't know if you remember this Z offset
I'm just gonna get rid of that real
quick so that's gone gonna get rid of
all this stuff there we go and see
offset here ground and a point with a
bat and we've got okay so I think that's
all of that so now if I run things here
we're just doing the same thing that we
were doing before everything's good and
remember we've got our sort of hidden I
guess this is because we haven't turned
our rectangle code back on so I should
probably go in here and see if I can get
our rectangle code back working because
we kind of forgot to ever re-enable that
when we were working on scaling and
stuff let's see if we can turn our
rectangle code back on as you can see
here we've got draw rectangle slowly
working in our coordinate system let's
see here draw rectangle oops there we go
draw a rectangle so if I turn that back
on I'm not sure where what the status is
of our erectile code it looks like our
rectangle code is all correct so we had
actually updated it properly we just
left it turned off and so that's fine
you can see there's room boundary is
still there in blue and that's all good
right so there's that imaginal stairwell
that we still don't have art forward you
can see as I walk up it we get to the
upper layer right and everything seems
perfectly kosher with that but we do
have that z chunk snapping right that's
a chunk snapping so what I want to do is
see if we can just turn off the zoo
chunk snapping and get us into a you
know sort of a continuous movement out
for the camera there so let's take a
look at ensign again and so here's why
that's happening right you can see that
we we take the chunk
see of the camera but we don't really
ever do anything with with the offset we
sort of preserve that offset so if we
wanted to we could probably do something
like this where we just go ahead and
leave that offset you know don't try to
restore that offset and let the offset
become set based on the camera Z and if
we do that I suspect we will have there
you go there's a continuous movement in
Z you can kind of see that working there
and that looks pretty good to me
I think that's the way we would want it
to work right where things kind of fade
in and out that top layer fades in as I
move up and down like so and so that's
all good but what we need to do now is
we need to sort of introduce that
coherent concept because what we'd like
to do again like I say is we want to
fade these I was saying this yesterday
we want to fade out that top level
because if you think about it there's
gonna be ground in here there's gonna be
like actual ground and stuff tiles so if
you know we were down here all the
ground would be obscuring our view we
wouldn't able to see anything right so
what we need to do is get rid of all of
these things that we're drawing up here
they we don't want any of those to draw
until we actually start to move up and
then when we move up they should sort of
fade in right we kind of all agree that
that's what's supposed to happen we've
talked about this on the stream you know
all the times everyone seems pretty
happy with that as a plan so the
question is how do we do that well the
first thing that we need to do is we
need to have some conception of
basically these Z slices because what I
need to do is I need to know where I am
relative to the slices and so what I
want to do is introduce that concept and
say that we have fixed Z slices in the
world and that world structure again
this this world structure here I want
this to be like a definitive reference
right I don't want everything in the
code to sort of have its willy-nilly
where's the ground what level is what
and all that sort of stuff we want to
get rid of that concept not necessarily
for collision detection like maybe we
want to have different heights of things
that you can hop on I don't know if we
want to do that or not I'm just saying
if that was sort of thing we want to do
that's a separate thing what I'm talking
about is the actual concept of where the
like ground base ground level is is
going to be in these slices
so what I want to do is have the world
structure be able to answer your
question for this point in space what is
the ground level that would be below it
or on it but if it's standing on it and
what would be the one above it and below
it right so you can kind of get this
opinion of where you are in that space
right and so I want this query that I
can basically say hey world here's what
my guy is I need you to go ahead and
tell me kind of what that strata is
right and that way we're free to modify
the way that that's working in the
future we're even free to have different
parts of the world think about it
differently if we really need to later I
don't really want to do that because I
feel like that's probably unnecessary
but if we had to like we had a special
area that needed to be treated in a sort
of a special way we could have the world
answer those queries using kind of some
kind of special stuff and everyone that
was asking would be able to still work
without having to know that there are
specials areas areas of the world that
have that sort of different stuff to
them all right by the way in case
everyone's wondering I'm drinking
strawberries Inagua fresca basically
like a strawberry agua fresca today it's
not soy milk all right let's do this so
here's my world struck and here's what I
want to do so we have that global alpha
value which I said was weak sauce but
we're going to use it just for now to
make sure that we kind of get things
working with the global alpha value and
then what we'll do is we'll pull out the
global alpha value and we'll put in a
render to to a render target thing that
will allow us to do it in in proper
fading slices like I said what we wanted
to do before okay
so what we want to do here is go all
right we've got this global alpha and so
what we want to do when we come through
here and we're rendering these entities
right what I want to do is I want to be
able to in fact I guess now that I think
about it I don't even really need the
global alpha to do this for the most
part do I because each individual entity
I'm just going to be able to see when I
when I go to render the entity I'm going
to set its alpha value to be something
sort of
- - whatsoever I'm looking for I can set
its alpha value to be based on where it
is right based on how high up it is and
in fact I guess this global alpha here
right what I could do is just move it
down so that every entity we can still
lean on that global alpha system and
what we'll do is every entity will use
its position here to kind of determine
that now we have a little bit of a Jake
eNOS and this probably gets into
something we want to talk about a little
later which is that we don't actually
know the final resting place of the
entity because we haven't simulated for
forwards yet and I think this is arguing
towards wanting to separate out the
render pass the sort of the render from
the update which was something I didn't
want to do prematurely but what kind of
we're gonna talk about that in a bit to
do Casey probably indicates we want to
separate update and render for entities
sometime soon and again so that was
something that we talked about before
and again like I said one of the reasons
that we put update and render together
as one pass architectural II speaking is
so that some things can update and
render together if it's more efficient
and other things don't have to right and
so I guess the this is sort of what your
you know what you will probably be
seeing here is I think will probably
break entities up so that they update
and render in separate stages and that's
the kind of flexibility you want to have
right so if we have other things like
particle systems maybe they update and
render together because it's more
efficient that way whereas enemies it's
because of the way that we're working
with them we need we want more
flexibility we can separate in two
passes and again that's a really
important thing I think it's good to
always have update and render be
together and then only break them apart
when you see that you have a clear
reason for doing so and then she'll get
some efficiency there or something in
return
whereas everything else you want to
leave updating and rendering together so
that you don't basically spend all this
time pulling things in in and out of the
cache for no reason just to operate on
them in two passes that didn't actually
need to happen right but anyway again
that's something we can take a look at a
little bit later on for now we don't
care we can just use one frame of lag in
terms of pinging the Alpha
doesn't matter we'll you know we can
deal with that
in a little bit so anyway we we've got
the global alpha and what I want to do
is I want to set the global alpha based
on that position so the first thing we
do is I'm just do this in line here and
then I'm gonna move it out into a query
in the world to get that that out so
that it has the properties that I was
saying we're desirable there so the way
that I'm going to do that is I'm first
gonna take a look at where the entity
actually is right and you can see that
this right here actually this this
global alpha stuff I should probably set
just just quickly in here although I
think global is automatically set to it
to 1 in there if I'm not very much
mistaken we just double check do we set
global for the 1 yes we do so we don't
need to do it up there so we want to do
is here in the sim region you can see
that we've we're gonna start off where
we're updating the entities now so what
we have is we have that entity position
what I'd like to do is figure out where
that entity is going to be right and you
can kind of see us doing it down here
where we do get get ground entity ground
point I'm gonna call that get ground
ground point function I'm gonna use that
entity ground point to determine what
the alpha value for this enemy should be
and set it here so when we call that get
him to ground point like so I'm also
gonna make sure we clear the global
alpha here you can see this little alpha
is annoying to work with so I say I
don't really want this as an actual
feature we're just kind of using it now
I don't like things that you set
globally and then after remember to
clear and all that's okay it gets a
little bit janky so you know that's kind
of why I say this is not a feature that
should stay in there we're just using it
for now so kind of keep that in the back
of your head anything you see me doing
in this mobile alpha this is just for
test code we don't want to keep this in
the render at long term I don't think
anyway so we get that ground entity
point out so we get that we'll just call
this ground P for now what I want to do
is I want to set that global alpha based
on the ground P so what I need to do is
I need to figure out how far away from
the camera it is right so when I have
that ground P and we should should know
kind of where the camera is as well
because we know that the camera is at
camera P right and so what I want to do
is I want to figure out what the
difference between those two things
actually is and I believe since the
camera is always at the center of the
sim region technically I think we can
always just assume
that right I mean is that am i am I
totally off here let me see if we've got
that or not it looks like we don't
really say where the cameras in here and
I wonder if that's a little bit of a
mistake because the sim oops sorry
that's the same entity I wonder if
that's a little bit mistaken I feel like
we should say where the camera should be
in case we want it to not be at the
origin you know you know what I mean it
seems like that's something we would
probably want to think about at least a
little bit right you see where I'm going
with that I feel like I'm gonna go ahead
and try to introduce that here I feel
like we want I'm just a camera position
like camera position relative or
something like that
that says where the camera is or
something like this right no this is the
camera position relative to the origin
of this region just so we can kind of
figure out where the camera is you know
where the camera is supposed to be
because you know maybe we've got the sim
region offset somehow from the camera in
some way we want to be able to still
know where the camera position is right
and so when we go to render we want that
camera position to be in the center
right and so what we want to do is
displace all the entities by whatever
it's negative is right so basically I'm
going to introduce this camera position
but we do begin sim right now we're
always assuming that the camera is at
the center but in the future maybe we'll
assume something else and so when we do
this here when we do all of our sim
stuff and then we go ahead and we add
entities in here right and we try to
compute their position we do get sim
space P and in here we have you know all
that stuff what I want to do is just
figure out where the camera should be
and in it for now I guess we'll just
assume that the camera is actually
nowhere right it's just I mean that is
actually just already at the center
right so the sim region oh and you know
what that'll already be done for us
actually but I'm gonna put it in here
just so we remember and I'll put it to
do KC some way of specifying what the
camera position right that should be or
something like that oh you know what
now I think about it that's actually
kind of dumb I don't know that we really
need that because only the render pass
is ever gonna care about where the
camera is probably so maybe we should
just have that happen in here right
we know that the camera position is
going to be relative to the sim region
that we opened we can just compute where
it is directly in fact we've got the
ability to do that right so we can go
ahead and say oh the camera position
that's just going to subtract wherever
the camera was from wherever the sim
region was right so it's really just
gonna be something like this world
position sim Center P like that so there
we go sim Center P and then we'll always
just say well that's the the camera
position right something like this makes
sense
oops that's game state and that way now
we know that we're actually handling it
this is just gonna produce 0 because
gonna be camera P you know subtracted
from itself it's gonna produce 0 but at
least now we would always know we have
the world here yeah at least now we'll
always know that if we want to adjust
the location of the sim center we can
and nothing will break right so that's
what I wanted to do there so what we can
do is like say okay camera relative
what's the camera relative ground P of
this thing the camera relative ground P
of this thing is going to be whatever
the ground point is - where the camera
is and then we can get that global alpha
by taking the the Z value of this that's
how high right this is off of the camera
and what we can say is well we would
like to use some kind of a function
obviously we want to clamp it between 0
and 1 we want to use some kind of a
function that will produce that that
alpha fade right and so what we can do
is we can say we've got the relative
ground P we know that if it's 0 or
negative it's below us right so
basically that's you know we don't want
to do anything there so we'd probably do
something like saying okay you know if
it's zero or negative it gets
it's fine and then what we want to do is
sort of when we have that Z value we
want to pick some distance above which
it will sort of fade out over time so
I'll maybe do it something like that so
we'll say one point five meters above
the camera something like this let's
take a look and see how that goes so
here there we go so you can kind of see
how that fades in right you can see as
we move upwards we get that nice fade in
effect and it all kind of looks
relatively relatively solid right so I
walk down the stairs the fades out I
walk up the stairs it fades in right out
and out right and so that's you know
that's relatively what we're close to
what we're going for
right and what you can see here is that
I've done this in kind of an ad hoc way
and so what I want to do is I want to
make this a little more formal just so
we can start to base it off of real
values so the first value the thing way
that I'm going to do this is I'm gonna
say okay what is the you know the how
should I say this I I want to sort of
say we've got these Z slices and the Z
slices need to fade in so what I want to
do is say where do they start fading in
and where do they stop fading in right
and so what I want to do is like fade
start Z and fade and Z right and so
obviously the fade end I want to say
mm-hmm and just to give you in fact you
know what let me do this on the on the
blackboard just so everyone's clear on
what I'm talking about here I don't want
to I don't want there to be any
confusion about what's going on what day
are we
we're day 107 so here we go day one zero
seven here we go
so what we want to do here is we want to
use me we want to parameterize this in
some way where we can go all right we've
got the camera
and at some level between the camera and
you know our magic hour fades start
let's call this everything is is fully
visible right
this is visible then at some level
between there in the range between that
start and the end this is going to fade
right and then everything up here is
invisible right make sense that's what
we want to do and furthermore we
probably also want to do something
that's like okay we've got you know
another thing here so we probably want
like fade start you know this is like
the top one and this is like fade start
bottom and fade end bottom you know I'm
Sam
so that we've kind of got in here a fade
as well and then you know everything in
here is invisible so really this visible
region actually is is this whole range
right and so what we can do there is we
can actually we could if we knew that
they were going to be the same heights
we could take the absolute value of
whatever but I don't think we want them
to be because I suspect that this is
going to be smaller than this right and
the reason for that is we may want you
know when you're looking down on
something the reason that we want to
fade out these guys is because we don't
want them to obscure your view so we
need the very first level you know if we
looked here at what the levels were you
know here's the one you know here's the
current ground but you're standing on
that the fade out start in top this is
actually where the next level would be
right here's where upstairs is right
because it should be invisible most the
time until you start walking upstairs we
shouldn't see it but we actually want
several levels of ground visible here
probably right so we probably want this
to be very different values we want this
to encompass like say this guy
right so these are not going to be the
same ranges and I think we need to sort
of appreciate that so what we need to do
is take wherever stuff is map it into
here and then produce the correct fade
values as a result right so what we want
to do is say that we've got sort of a
fade top start and a fade top end right
and I'll stack these in the way that
they actually stack so then the bottom
start Z and a fade bottom and Z like so
right that's what we want to see happen
and so what we can do here is say all
right it's gonna start fading in let's
say it's gonna start fading in a meter
above the guy or whatever and then it's
gonna stop fading at a meter and at 0.25
or something like that I don't know I'm
making this up
maybe 1.5 I don't know what did we even
say I don't even remember what we were
sort of saying is our world thing at
this point I don't even remember where
we landed on that we had set it when we
create the world when we create worlds
we had we had set the the like height
value in here somewhere I don't even
know where it is
I don't even remember this code at all
there it is initialized world so chunk
diamond meters gets passed in and so
basically somewhere in here we were
specifying it been a long time so world
Chuck dim in meters is here so typical
gamestate typical floor height right so
what we probably want to do is say okay
the fade you know that that fade ends
probably at that at that typical floor
height above right so like like the cell
right so anything that's at the floor
above us is gone you can't see it and
the fade top end is probably you know as
as it kind of starts to fade in I don't
know is some amount above that of the of
the typical floor height so it's
probably you know it's probably
something like the typical floor height
plus some percentage of the typical
floor height like a quarter of the floor
height is how long
takes to blend something in right and
then the fade bottom start you know
that's gonna be probably been negative
maybe it's two floors down something
like that everything becomes invisible
seems or starts to become invisible and
then similarly you know this would be
something and we could write this a
little you know we could accept the fact
that we're all comfortable math here and
just do that right and then down here
it's like something like this right and
so then I guess basically what we want
to do is we want to do it if here to
figure out if you're above top Z or or
below bottom Z right so we can say that
your alpha is going to be one point out
and then we'll just say all right if
your relative Z here right if your
relative Z is greater than fade top
start Z then you're fading out on the
top and otherwise if the camera relative
ground point Z is less than fade bottom
start Z then you're fading out on the
bottom okay and we're gonna set your
alpha accordingly and what I'd like to
do here is I'd like to just introduce a
function I don't think we've made one
yet right at least I don't know if we
have or not I'll be honest with you I
forget what we've done in math and what
we haven't done math this is the
consequence of doing handmade here as an
hour a day and having nothing to having
it have nothing to do with what I'm
doing at work all right so what I want
to do here is I want to introduce a
range function that we can use I want to
introduce something that's like you know
clamp map to range or something like
that and what I want to do is say
there's a min there's a T value and
there's a Max and I want you to
basically produce a value a 0 to 1 value
that's going to tell me where T falls
between min and Max it's like a berry
centric to fire right and you can see
right now we got the clamp we just don't
have the divide so essentially all we
would need to do is call clamp and then
divide by the range right so we've got
the range
it's just a max minus the min that's how
you know big the thing is and really
then all we'd have to do is say that our
result is going you know we should
probably check for zero so assuming the
range is greater than zero we'll assume
that the result is zero otherwise if the
range is greater than zero then what
we'll do is we'll go ahead and do a
clamp zero to one of whatever that key
value is divided by the range right so
that's essentially going to normalize
the T value out to being in between the
max and the of them in there right oh
and I guess I got to subtract it in
front right so this bases me around the
min as I go from the min to the max I'll
keep reducing values between min and Max
right
I'm sorry between zero and range and
divide by the range changes it into a
zero one right there we go and so now
all I have to do is like do clamp 0 1
map to range and what that allows me to
do is just specify the min the T in the
Max and we know what those are right so
we just know that we've got the top
value we've got that camera relative
Brown P V and we've got the fade top end
Z there we go and here we do the same
thing it'll start at fade bottom start Z
and it will end at fade bottom and Z I
believe that should do it now this range
goes the other way but I think that
should be okay because it just means
that the range will be negative which
will invert the sense of this divide
which I think is fine and so I think
that that should give us you know
roughly what we want there mm-hmm well
we'll find out certainly so it looks
like we set our value perhaps a little
bit too high because those aren't faded
out yet either that or I've made some
egregious error let's see so if this if
fade start Z is a typical floor height
above does that actually mean that these
things are unaligned in some way it
looks like they are left I'd love to
work on that in a second and it looks
like our fade is going the wrong way why
is that the case top start Z is the min
and this is the
oh right so I forgot though this is the
alpha so we want it to basically be
higher as it gets
we want the inverted sense of this so I
could do one - which is a little bit
more easy to read right or I can flip
these two to basically give it the
inverse sense of the mapping right I
don't know which of those is like that's
just harder to read if you do it that
way so I don't know that that's great
you know what I mean I don't I don't
know if that's if that's that's really
what we want but yeah can school got a
bug in there though why do I have a bug
in there okay no I'm wrong I can't do
that because that will produce a
negative value right which we don't
actually want nevermind so we do want it
to be this sense we want it to produce
the clamped range and then we just want
to invert it because it's alpha and so
we we want to actually know that process
yeah I have to think about that there
might be a cleaner way to write that
though anyway so let's take a look here
let me see if I can push this back up
again now that we fixed our little bug
there or I guess we want them actually
to be lower I should say so those things
are they really that's how low they are
that seems odd to me I wonder if I've
got a bug here or something like this
because there's the fade top start Z
essentially we should we should always
ah duh the fade top NZ has to end at the
floor height because otherwise it'll be
partially visible yeah okay never mind
I'm just being stupid
so that's fine so let's take a look here
so there it goes it fades away as we
come up it comes back in so we may want
that to be a little bit further up where
it starts something like that so we may
actually want this to kind of clip out
something more like that I don't
actually know something like that
probably looks a little bit better I
don't understand why we're getting it so
early though I feel like our alignment
with the typical floor height is
currently not correct or something like
this so I feel like once we go now and
do this thing where we put this into the
world as a query call it'd be nice to
start to figure out what the Z values
are of some of these entities to figure
out why it's doing that the way that it
is what I would like to do here is I
would like to potentially allow us to go
up another level so we could kind of get
a few more in here but right now we
don't really have anything that would
allow us to do that because we only ever
allow you know two things stacked on
each other I wonder if there's some way
to quickly hack our little stupid world
making stuff here I wonder if there's
some way to quickly hack that to allow
us to do door up multiple times right
you know that kind of thing so it's got
random choice door up door down and so I
guess the thing here is door up through
door down true so the problem is we
don't allow it to freely pick whether it
does draw door up or door down so I
suppose if we did right if we were to do
that then what we could do is have you
know sort of up and down be chosen
separately which I feel like would be a
good thing to do something you know like
this does this make sense to everyone
something that allows it to stack as
you know keep going up or keep going
down if you know as necessary I also
feel like at this point we should have
probably allowed it to make rooms that
kind of go that snake back on each other
but yeah so unfortunately at this point
I also don't really know we we're never
gonna necessarily get enough stacked on
each other here because it might never
create any such thing so we'd have to
kind of also do some stuff that would
would sort of create the case that we
want to test which at this point
unfortunately we're not doing so there's
a down that's good we can go down here
ooh what happened there I guess I've
ended somewhere where we don't we didn't
actually put a room on the bottom looks
like we just walked down the stairwell
into nothing that doesn't seem like a
good idea is that because we're always
assuming something about where the door
is go either way this doesn't really
help me what I need is a couple rooms
stacked on top of each other not really
sure how to do that quickly
so what happens when we create an up
stair or a down stair right when we add
a stair it does this ABS tile minus one
or AB styles thing and what do we do
here
if door direction okay so this is why we
didn't actually update the door
direction stuff right what we actually
need to do is say all right which
direction do we go in Z did we go down
or did we go up and then we need to
actually subtract whichever one it is so
if it's a door down right it's a door
down that's three and if it's door up
it's two so what we need to do is
something more like this right I believe
and so doors down do that and doors up
do this right this is some truly lousy
code here but we're not supposed to be
working on world building at the moment
and so I feel like we kind of have to
you know take the good with the bad
there the other thing I could do is you
know and I might do this the thing I
might want to do is just just make less
of these tiles right let's see here so
instead of adding wall in fact you know
what I'll do right now is I'll only add
a wall if tile Y mod 2 and tile X come
on let's take a look I want to cut down
on the number of trees just because
since we don't have an optimized
renderer it kind of helps alright so if
I walk up here of course it's hard to
tell where the hex it is but yeah
let's see here
of course this doesn't this means you
can kind of just walk through any where
you want which I hadn't thought about
beforehand but anyway all right so I can
walk through here let's go ahead out
here yeah so what I really need to do is
I need to just bias this thing so it
will build a few things on top of each
other for us I'm not sure exactly how to
do that because we need to test our are
sort of lower or below
sort of our code for things below us and
we don't seem to be it doesn't seem to
have randomly unfortunately generated
anything that had a lot of things on the
same on the same stack so let's take a
look what can I do to force that to
happen I guess what I could do is say
okay we can bias it so it just keeps
creating doors up and down or something
like that and in order to do that we
just have to have a way of adding a
stairwell that doesn't overlap the same
stairwell so that you can keep on using
them although maybe you can just make
them all be in the same place and maybe
that just works because the Z handling I
don't know let's try it it's hard to say
what I could do is say door direction is
always gonna be equal to three so it
just always goes down there's nothing
else that will ever happen that's all
that's gonna oh my god what have I done
all right well that's that's interesting
to say the least I'm a little confused
as to why there are so many levels and
what's actually it looks like they're
crossing over some threshold where we've
got a flip bug there so this it looks
like some fun something that would be
good to debug although my first question
is how are there so many entities do we
take all the entities in Z I thought we
were only doing a limited Z slice so how
did all these entities get in there
that's that's a bug like somebody's got
to fix that and then the other problem
is why are none of them fading out so
something is is is not right
all right so what's going on we've got
if you're less than fade bottom start Z
right which is which is two typical
heights down then I want to map you in
that range we're gonna be subtracted
let's see so I feel like I feel like
that should have worked so I don't
understand why that alpha isn't getting
set properly that said the more weird
thing to me is just why we're getting
such a such a strange amount we're
getting so many that it actually goes
down into nothing and and flips around
right you can see how that goes so we
only want like a couple levels here and
I feel like the sim region should never
have picked up those guys in the query
right so if we come in here and you take
a look at when it does the chunk Z min
chunky you know it doesn't it'll loop
serve the chunk Z's how are we getting
all of these entities I don't get it how
are they how are we ever finding
entities that are that low and bringing
them into the sim region so that they
get rendered right I don't get it to me
that makes no sense to me whatsoever
so I want to see what's going on there
because that's just bizarre
that's just super super super bizarre
so that's thing one to check let's let's
just check that now let's take a look at
begin sim when we come in here what does
it think the Z range actually is am i
doing something that would suggest oh
you know what else I got to do I hate to
do this because this will be super slow
because we run optimized at the moment
but let's turn off that Oh to switch so
that I can step through the code
properly okay
you made that super P all right so let's
take a look at this here stepping
through so let's take a look at our to
our our our bounds here right our min
chunk P I think we started 10 minutes
late today so we'll go ahead and go up
to them okay that's a pretty insane
range so I guess we actually did grab a
huge number of chunks these Y is our sim
region so huge is it cuz of the max
entity radius I think it must be I think
it must be so what's the end the max
entity velocity so that's the thing is
we're basically grabbing a huge chunk of
Z because of that max entity velocity so
I wonder if that's gonna have to do
that's probably got to be something that
we special case there well that was a
good thing to know cuz I did we had no
idea that that was happening so yeah so
this is a bit of a problem the updatable
bounds thing and the safety margin Z
thing right of one I think we probably
want to do a thing here where we're
we're always doing just just nothing
right there's no there's no entity
radius stuff that's happening there for
now at least we'll see if we can get
away with that but that seems more
likely not to me all right so at least
now there's a little bit less but
there's still quite a bit and so I'm
wondering if maybe something else here
is still too conservative so let's take
a look we've got the bounds we've got
the safety margin and Z which is adding
up and down which is just I don't know
if 1.0 it was a very same thing for it
but let's see Oh
update safety margin is still again yeah
oh no but we're not using that we're not
using that for Z so if we don't add
anything here and we all
we add one here then I feel like our Z
bound shouldn't be that big but let's
find out what they actually are because
maybe I'm wrong about that so what's our
initial query size let's start with that
right what is the initial size and so
let's check the bounds let's see what it
is min max right so the max Z is 15 and
the min Z is negative 15 again that just
seems crazy so what's going on here is
that something from this who is who is
making that decision sim bounds
expansion yeah so this is just this is
just totally bogus again so basically we
just never were doing anything sensible
a Z here at all like we clearly just
threw that code in just completely
ad-hoc without really thinking about
what we want to do and in terms of
symbols expansion I don't think we even
want any expansion in Z do we we just
want the level that we're at and we want
the safety margin expansions to handle
we want the sim region to handle that
expansion for us basically like we don't
want to add any anything to that I don't
think that would be my guess anyway
right of course that didn't grab
anything which is a little bit odd
so symbols expansion camera bounds and
mirrors
which we also don't know what what that
actually is just a lot of things that
were unspecified here okay so that's got
no Z so then we have the symbols
expansion which we don't really want to
do anything with although later we may
want to do do we want to simulate upper
floors etc so then we come in here we
won't add anything here we will add 1.0
on either and for the safety margin but
I don't actually know I'm just not sure
why that wouldn't why that isn't picking
anything up so I wonder if we are again
we having some kind of a stratification
problem in terms of what's included
there so let me go ahead and and and and
say that we do one the typical floor
height in either direction but
that's it right and let's see what that
gets us so that's a little more sensible
certainly right let me go ahead and we
can we can switch back to to our
optimized build now our Oh to build
still a completely unbiased compiler not
doing crazy stuff so there we go in
terms of that are fading out there is
not working properly either I think I've
got like a weird bug in my clamp map to
range I think I just wrote it poorly or
something like this I want to see I feel
like that was a that didn't work the way
I expect it to so let's take a look what
I was doing here so in clamped map to
range I figure out what the range is by
taking the max and min and then I
subtract them in from it and divide by
it I feel like that ah that's the
problem right there we can't check if
it's greater than zero because we want
to be able to support negatives so that
was why I was having a problem right you
saw how that worked right that was just
that was just me being stupid cuz I was
thinking like oh the range has to be
greater than zero but doesn't have to be
greater than zero because we want to be
able to support negative ranges so that
the set still works out right so that
code that we'd written before was
actually probably correct and then and
we were just stupid right so you
remember I thought this should work and
it didn't right always assume there's a
bug me and Chris Tucker used to say that
all the time especially we're working
with physics so there's the fade-out
working properly at the top level now
using the correct code order angle that
I thought should have worked and I
should have stuck by my guns and then
this guy wants to do starting at the
start Z and fading at the end Z which i
think is exactly what we do want him to
do so let's see if we can get that
working now properly it looks like that
still just disappears now that could
because the sim region isn't picking up
someone far enough down right and so
that I think is something we may again
may want to sort of take a look at here
so if we do that the camera but those
camera bounds that we can write where's
the camera bounds and meters what we
want to do here is say well okay
actually the min we want to look kind of
below where the camera is a little bit
so we want to do like negative 2.0 times
typical floor height right or something
like that that's we want to look maybe
two floors below possibly even three
floors below I don't know what that
number is going to be right and then we
want to look you know maybe one one four
above something like that and then we
can get rid of that that expansion thing
cuz cuz we don't really want to ever
expand probably in Z any more than we
have to
right so let's take a look here
that's oops that's gamestate and then
we've got here so that's a little more
sensible although does not look like I
did that properly somehow somehow this
is correct right camber bounds oh no
rectangle Center dim it's not a min/max
rectangle well in that case we have to
do this a little bit more gently right
but I guess I could just not do it janky
I could still do it right by just doing
it this way right I can just do it that
way when the camera bounded meters comes
back I'll just say I'll just set the
Minzy and Mac Z myself here so that I
can still set it to negative three
floors down and one floor up something
like that right and that way I don't
have to worry about setting it gym wise
so that seems fine I'm totally fine with
that all right so now that we've got
this we're fading the wrong way and so
that is again the same problem that we
had the first time I guess which is
which is again it's alpha so even though
this is the way that we would want to
write it
going from the start to the end since we
wanted inverted we would invert it this
way right and again I'm not sure that
that's the best way to braid it I feel
like we want to write it with the 1.0
but I don't know hard to say it does
introduce some extra stuff there that
doesn't actually need to happen so it's
unclear if that's what we want but
anyway now we've kind of got it working
the way that we we wanted it to work
where we can kind of fade in on either
side right but with the stairwell
stacked on top of each other they're
creating sort of that problem where the
stairwells
I'm colliding with one so I can't walk
down the other one if that makes sense
so I want to do a thing where we stagger
the stairwell location it looks like
we're just about out of time so I'm just
going to do that I'm gonna stagger that
stairwell location though here what I'm
gonna do is say if you know if AB style
Z is you know is even or odd right if AB
style is the mod 2 and this right put
the stairwell there or if AB style Z if
not AB salamati and M tile equals you
know four or something don't try this at
home kids so there you can see again
more of the kind of getting more of that
that's sort of back and forth in that we
want of course these annoying fellows
are blocking my region let's go through
here there we go
see here come down so what we can see
too is there's kind of another thing
that I haven't talked about we're not
leaving the familiars on the correct
levels either like we've got we've got a
bunch of things now that this uncovers
which is perfect because this is exactly
where I wanted to get to but you can
also see that our our scaling is not
correct which is another place I wanted
to get to and I wasn't sure when it was
gonna happen but you can kind of see it
happening now so you see how we kind of
have a weird effect where things seem to
move more quickly when they're in the
distance in terms of zooming in and out
right and that's because we haven't
actually talked about how to correctly
handle perspective in any way right and
so this uncovers a bunch of things we
want to work on which is great because I
feel like this is finally getting us
into the point where we can really nail
Z down which is something that was one
of the probably the biggest things on
our to-do list because it affects
everything so yeah so I'm pretty excited
about this this is quite good I think
this will get us into a good place so
yeah I feel like we're in good shape
here I feel like we're in good shape
here and again so what's interesting
just to head off at the pass in case no
one answers this question you notice the
familiar and the guy move with us in Z
that's because we don't do ground
handling yet remember we don't we
haven't done our ground helicopter so I
believe what's actually happening is as
we move down because the camera Z level
was considered where the ground was they
fall and as we move the ground down they
basically fall with it right so yeah but
anyway so we're in a great place to
start working on all this stuff this is
exactly where I wanted to get to very
happy about this because now we can sort
of clean up all of the Z stuff properly
I'm very very happy about that we'll get
the ground handling working this disc is
this great stuff to work on this kind of
opens up all of the problem areas we're
finally in a place where we can solidify
them out and that'll be great once we
have Z checked off I think we're in such
a great position in terms of like engine
unknowns basically so so I'm gonna go
ahead and say oh it's time for the QA
and please go ahead and prefix your
questions with
q : so I will see them and pry it please
try to keep them on topic okay
why were some of the trees upside down
so the reason some of the trees were
upside down is because we haven't really
done perspective yet and I want to kind
of avoid talking about it too much
because like basically that like I said
that's one of the things that I wanted
to actually talk about for real is how
to do that transform so we have this Z
fudge value right and this is e fudge
value which is the thing we were using
to multiply the x and y positions of
people on the screen so that they would
appear to get bigger and smaller as they
moved closer and further from the camera
but we didn't actually do any work to
make sure that it was actually doing
proper perspective computation which
means it's just basically a completely
bogus hack right so what happens as you
can see here whenever you get something
whose Z value is high enough that's
negatively high enough so like negative
what's it's negative 1 over point zero
zero one five this expression will
become negative and once it's negative
multiplying by a negative will flip
everything around you'll basically
mirror it right and so well mirror it's
the wrong word it mirrors it on two axis
but it'll flip it around right and so
basically what you're doing there is
because this is not a real perspective
if this is real perspective real
perspective thing is actually divided
right and so it can never flip because
it just as things get further and
further away this gets smaller and
smaller and smaller right but we don't
have that we have a multi multiply thing
here and so they flip so this to do
figure out exactly how Z base X Y is
place which is our work to do that to do
what we need to do is introduce a real
perspective divide there which isn't
hard to do but we have to talk about it
on the blackboard first that everyone
understands what I'm doing if that makes
sense
are the head and body entities off to
the side supposed to scale with the main
character so they are moving because the
Z so if you remember right so if you
remember how the ground stuff was we
kind of left it it was the whole reason
we went in to do the rendering stuff is
to kind of get Z straightened out so do
you see how this ground 0 nonsense is
happening at the moment right and you
kind of get this like thing where we
take a spatial partition and get where
the ground is and do this sort of other
nonsense where we try to figure out like
whether or not things were Z's aborted I
believe what's happening with those
entities is that they are actually just
being treated as you kind of move down I
believe they're being treated as if the
I believe they're being treated as if
that ground is like coming out from
under them if that makes sense I don't
actually know that that's true in fact
we could actually test this code is just
so janky and not finished that I'm not
actually sure exactly what's happening
here but I can pretty much guarantee you
it's a bug
let me see PC equals ground GPAs equals
0 do flag z supported
can overlap so I also don't know I
suspect that it's entirely because of
this ground value and the can overlap if
the region if the mover is not a region
of the reason the stairwell is true so
I'm not a hundred percent certain why
they are doing that yet but I believe
it's because they're actually moving
with the camera not which is you know
obviously not correct but it's something
that we haven't really start finish tan
dling in here so I'm not sure exactly
where that bug is per se right let's
think about this for a second because
it's kind of interesting
okay ground plus equals empty PZ minus
ground G point so that's wherever that
ground is yeah is set to Z supported
system ax equal to ground it's going to
set them back to where the ground is so
I guess what I'd like to test first as a
way of exactly what is broken in the
same region thing is that where is
ensign I want to see what happens when
you do not update the camera Z so if we
do you know this sort of thing
so if we don't update the camera Z and
instead we just move down right you can
see that it they correctly stay up where
they were right and so again the reason
why I think that's happening is because
the ground is currently based on this
weird we don't have a solid notion for
what's supposed to be happening with the
ground and I think they just basically
fall down to wherever the camera is they
land on the camera Z height except so
you could think of it as so we just need
to start we need to like button up the
Z's stuff and then we'd be fine I think
so I think that's really all that's
happening
what is Z fighting and is it something
that you have to worry about in a game
like this I can I can show you what Z
fighting is so Z fighting is a it's a
bit of a large topic but I'll try to
give you what the idea is and the short
answer is no we don't have to worry
about it but I'll explain you what it is
anyway okay so Z fighting is about depth
buffers if you don't have a depth buffer
you're probably not going to have Z
fighting you could have Z fighting in
another way which I'll touch on briefly
but I'll talk about this is the one that
you're normally going to see so I'll
talk about how you can have it without Z
depth buffers I'll talk about it without
depth buffers in a second after I give
you what the idea is first so let's talk
about with def buffers so normally if
you're doing if you're not doing a 2-d
game you're doing a 3d game and
presumably you're doing any kind of
typical 3d game which can't perfectly
figure out a draw order then what
happens is you rely on a thing called
the depth buffer to figure out what is
called hidden surface removal right in
the old days and what that means is you
can imagine if I had something like a
very simple object I just have two cubes
maybe there or you could think of them
as something more complicated like two
legs of a character right and one of
them is closer to the camera than the
other right and so when I am to draw
these cubes I always want to draw this
cube last right I want to draw this cube
first so that this region the place
where they overlap is filled by the
colors that come from this cube not this
cube right so if this is a and this is B
the correct draw order is B then a right
but the problem is in three dimensions
it's hard to know that because these
could be complex objects that you know
don't have a necessary sort or like
maybe part of this odd
is behind this object it's a curved
thing that also exists kind of behind
here so then there's no drawer it's like
draw this part of a and then this part
of a and B gum I mean I'm sorry draw
this part of a then this part of B then
this part of a or something like that to
get the drawer to right you know what
I'm saying
it gets very complicated to give you a
better maybe a better illustration
suppose that I had a doughnut right and
then something a cube inside a doughnut
right so that's the drawing thing and
we're looking at it from here so if
we're doing that we've got sort of like
a cube like shape in the middle we've
got this sort of doughnut shape coming
around it like so and then maybe the
cube sticks out the bottom a little bit
as well right and so if you think about
this the draw order if this is a and
this is B there is no draw order because
this bottom part there's re this back
part this part right of a it needs to be
this part first then this thing right
this second and then this part third
right in order to make sure that they
occlude each other properly so that you
don't see things that you shouldn't see
right
so hopefully that just gave you some
idea of it's like it's complicated if
you want to figure out a sorter so what
you typically do in 3d graphics is you
don't try to solve this problem
instead you instead of solving it per
object which is kind of what we're
talking about here which would require
you to break objects up into pieces and
sort the pieces and stuff like that you
handle it per pixel right because you
know that every pixel right for any
individual pixel we know there is one
sort order like a then B then whatever
right and furthermore at each pixel we
can do something which makes it so that
we don't have to draw them in order we
just need to know when we when we come
to a particular thing we just need to
know which whether it should replace the
thing that was there or not right and so
if you think about it let's say that we
have a draw order of B than a well if we
look at it at a pixel basis right in
fact let's go back to here so we've got
you know we've got a as our as our tube
and B is our cube thing right so we've
got a draw order of a B right if we take
a pixel that's right here right
then what's gonna happen is a is gonna
draw and it's gonna fill it in right so
you know we have what's the pixel here
right what's happening to pixel and this
is in an a/b draw order and then we have
the pixel here in the be a draw order so
whichever way the app submits them if it
draws a then B what's gonna happen is a
is gonna be there than it right then it
draws B I shouldn't I shouldn't do this
is face all right
that's no I should do I should do this
first and then second right so the first
thing this drawing is a so we look at a
and we get an A right the second thing
that's drawn is B and now what we want
to do is know that we should not replace
B we should not replace a with because B
is behind a right we want to stay with a
and then in the other draw order what we
would do is we draw B first and then
when a comes we do want to replace B
with a for this pixel right does that
make sense and the way that we do that
is with every pixel we we store a depth
information that's what a depth buffer
is and the depth of information is
basically saying how far away right was
the current occupant of the pixel right
so what we do is we draw a in here and
we say oh a was you know 1.2 meters away
from the guy or whatever right then we
draw B in here and we say well B is 3
meters away from the guy and it's like
oh well you know what we don't actually
want to do that because this is a closer
value so we keep the one that we had
whereas here we say oh it's 3 meters
away then we draw a and we go oh okay
he's 1.2 meters away that's closer so a
depth buffer is basically a thing that
remembers how far away the thing was
that filled the pixel we're on so that
we know whether to replace it with a new
pixel when it comes in and you can see
why this works now for a on top of
itself as well right if I have you know
a is a tube right but I'm looking at it
so obliquely that the tube kind of
obscures itself right well it doesn't
matter what's in here it's just it's
whatever part of a you know if there's
polygons back here
polygons up here and there drawing on
top of each other all we need to know is
what the color value would be here and
what the depth value would be here we
compare that with what exists and we
replace the color value if the depth
value is is further away right that's
all we have to do so hopefully does that
make some sense I hope that makes some
sense of people it's a very simple
scheme but just remember how far away
things are so we know whether replace it
with new things that come in okay what
z-fighting is is when this computation
is imprecise okay because it would
always work what I just said would
always work right there's no reason that
would ever not work right in conceptual
math but math is not done conceptually
in a computer it's done with floating
point values and the problem is what
happens when two surfaces are
sufficiently far from the camera such
that the floating point precision that
is representing their distance is no
longer able to distinguish between the
two right I remember we talked about
floating-point precision we talked about
it many times on the stream so okay
we've got a Z value let's say right now
we've got two things that are very close
together right they're so close together
right now but in fact there's just a
small bit of mantissa right let's say
there's like two bits or something of
mantissa that's that's actually
distinguishing between the two of these
as the camera moves further away so
these objects kind of move further back
right it becomes only one bit that's
distinguishing them and eventually it's
zero bits and when it becomes zero bits
these both these are both essentially
mapping to the same z distance from the
camera in floating point right and to be
fair does this really happen often in
floating point not so much what's
actually happening here often times is
it's not a full 32-bit floating point
value when you get z-fighting it's
oftentimes like a 16-bit approximated Z
value or something on the GPU right so
again don't think I Triple E floating
whatever the GPU is using to represent
depth which mate with which may be much
less precise than the 32-bit value for
example
okay so if that precision collapses to
zero bits what happens is you no longer
know the difference between a - between
the pixels a and B that are coming in
right and so what will happen is
whichever one of them happen to be drawn
first might actually be the one that
stays there right and you get a random
you sort of get whatever the draw order
is we'll pick who draws right and what
that would do is that would basically
show you know if we were looking at two
plates that were right on top of each
other a and B you'd basically see a if a
were drawn first or you'd see B if we
were drawn first or depending on
whatever the comparison scheme is that
if you actually lets you pick you'd see
one of the other right so that's one
form of z-fighting which is if a is
actually supposed to be both behind B
but it's drawn first it'll now start
showing up in front of B just at the
time when it moves behind right that's
one for things get much worse however
when it's slanty like this right when
it's slanted like that then what happens
is the floating-point precision may
oscillate so that it can tell that a
isn't behind B right here's a here's B
as this gets these are different Z
depths from the camera right because
these are slanted as it steps these it
may find that it can distinguish between
them at certain places because the
floating point math works out to have
one bit difference between them but on
another one it maps to 0 bits right just
because of the way it collapses in out
and out and then what you get is this
horrible stippling pattern depending on
the angle of the things where B shows
through shows in front as it should
properly but then a peeks through in
like up in a pixel e banded pattern
depending on the the sort of angle and
the iteration on the GPU right that's
the worst kind of z-fighting very bad
right and you see this nasty pixely
pattern right and so that's Z fighting
it's when the precision breaks down so
that it can no longer tell the
difference and there's a number of
places that that can come from but
hopefully I've given you some examples
of how it's kind of easy to understand
stream is over sauce
one more thing without depth buffers and
you're talking about the z-fighting
we could still have a Z fighting problem
in handmade hero even though we're not
using a depth buffer and that's because
we will be sorting our things right and
so we could still have this problem the
original problem here where is if we had
set our things that poorly such that our
our Z coordinates had gotten so large
that the mantissa could no longer
distinguish between the two of them we
might sort the two things incorrectly
all of a sudden like a supposed to be on
top of B but we drew B first right and
that's still a form of Z fighting it's
just not the same as the kind of a GPU
where since things are usually angled
and doing weird things you get a stipple
pattern because the the who is in front
who it thinks is in front is changing we
would not have that problem probably but
what we would have is we'd have the sort
order when it got up to that point where
it collapsed to 0 bits now it would sort
them differently potentially because it
would just use whoever came first or
something whereas before it was actually
doing the sort so we still at least look
it up that now we won't have that
because our Z values will never be that
large we will never have that kind of a
problem and we're doing it in full
floating point which typically GPUs at
full floating point Z buffers don't have
that problem because 32-bit is totally
fine for doing any of the Z usually that
you want to do so typically what you'll
what you'll get what you see Z fighting
wise is on modern things on modern
high-end GPUs the kind of Z fighting
that you'd see is not really the same
kind of thing that I'm talking about
it'd be more like shadow map problems
where you're doing back transforms that
lose precision because of the fact that
the they don't map 1 to 1 on the pixels
that's a whole separate thing so this
kind of Z fighting is more common in
older games than newer games
whereas newer games still have things
that you could consider to sort of be Z
fighting but they're really Z fight
they're really not the same thing there
because things are getting mapped in a
non 1 to 1 pixel way which is a separate
thing and I don't have time to talk
about that now but hopefully that's good
hopefully that is yeah
hopefully that clears that up so alright
stream is over it looks like there's
really no more questions anyway so
that's good and so hopefully everyone is
is a happy camper today everyone has has
hatun had their dose of z and alpha and
so we've got plenty of stuff this opens
up a huge set of things to work on
really excited about that tomorrow we'll
do we'll just tackle some of that maybe
look at the ground in there maybe we'll
work on the perspective transform who
knows what we'll do but we'll do
something we've got tons of a huge big
front opened up for us now so that's
good and that's what we will go do so
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it has
been a pleasure coding with you as
always always good when you could push
forward into a new problem area I think
that's kind of where we're at right now
we're getting there
so that's good thanks very much for
joining me and again if you are if
you're interested in the series you like
the series this is your first time here
we're here every every day 5 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time
here on Twitch we'd love to see you come
back it's always good to see new faces
if you want to follow along at home with
a source code we also do provide the
source code if you preorder the game you
can download the source code as well
which is a good way to play around and
just have fun with it
we also have a patreon if you want to
support the video series you want to
subscribe to the video series and just
that's just as a nice thing to do for us
it's always very appreciated you could
do that there we have a forum site you
can go to where you can ask questions
and you can also take advantage of some
stuff the community's done anti episode
guide ports to Mac &amp; Linux that sort of
stuff and we also have a tweet bot that
will tweak the schedule at you so if you
want to catch the stream live and you're
not sure what schedule is for the day or
that sort of stuff check out the tweet
bot you can do subscribe or just check
him out and see cuz it's usually got the
day's schedule on there and it doesn't
really tweet anything else except once a
night and a blue moon so so that's a
good place to check that out so thanks
again for joining me and we will see you
tomorrow for the last room of this week
for the Friday scream hope to see you
all here for some Friday fun if not have
a good weekend and I will see you on
Monday either way take it easy everyone