hello everyone and welcome hand-made
here oh sure we could a complete game
live on stream before I get started I
wanted to mention the fact that our new
comic has come out it came out Monday in
fact I don't stream during the week
these days so I didn't have a chance to
tell anyone about it but it's called me
out the infinite and it's super awesome
especially if you like cats in space
it's pretty easy to try reading you can
just go to mail the infinite calm and
there's a big old first issue button you
click on that and you can just start
reading the comic right and and off you
go so check it out if you like comics at
all
it'll be updated about once every two
months and there's you can if you want
to know when new issues are posted
anyone who signs up for the Molly Rocket
mailing list gets immediately notified
and you know if you if you ever are on
the Molly Rocket mailing list we send
out an email anytime we update one of
our projects so that's also an easy way
to know when when new issues are coming
out if you like it so give it a shot and
see what you want you can also buy the
digital deluxe edition of it if you're
really into it comes with a lot of cool
stuff like really high quality of PDFs
of all the chapters that you can you
know read online plus every time there's
one chapter we don't place online so you
can read the extra chapter like several
months earlier which is pretty awesome
there's also a big like making a book
that tons of concept art and stuff like
that and that's not wallpapers all that
good stuff
so check all that out the infinite calm
pretty easy to go to and yeah I think
it's also linked to from handmade hero
somewhere if you're on the watch page
there's there's a little like other
projects thing below it now so you can
jump to our other products pretty
quickly so it's right there at the top
anyway let's get started here we left
off last time which was not last week
because we had a for coder Jam last week
so we didn't stream but the weekend
before that we left off kind of at a
place where we sort of have some some
grunt work to do now because we did a
bunch of work to
move our asset system over to a place
where it kind of could take sort of
these text input files it said here's
all the stuff I want to pack up and how
I want to pack it up and those sorts of
things we're going to sort of replace
any kind of file naming conventions or
any of that sort of stuff that we had
been using before it's because we kind
of finally decided this was the best way
to ship it to be like this is the final
version and so doing that I would like
to you know get that system shipped and
done the problem is that we like wrote
it all and we have not really started
debugging it right so we have some
pretty unsavory work to do today which
is a we have to sort of debug the system
like we've got to actually go like
follow everything through and and get
rid of anything in there that's not
working properly which there probably is
a fair bit of because we wrote a ton of
stuff and moved a ton of stuff over the
chances that we didn't make any mistakes
very very low the other thing we have to
do is make the text preservation part of
things so at the moment what we wanted
to do in addition to you know obviously
reading these files and packing all of
our art assets from them and I think we
pretty much finished that part meaning
if there's really not I don't think
there's much of anything left to do
there other than the debugging and
polish
part of it the part that we did not do
yet is just if you want to rewrite a
file so you load handmade hero up and
you go into the edit mode and you adjust
parameters of the art so for example the
main thing right now that we edit inside
the game because it's pretty hard to
edit outside the game it's it's be able
to be really cumbersome is how sprites
are aligned like you know you want to
have a head that snaps onto a body at a
particular point or like a enemy holds a
shield and you want to like snap the
shield on at a particular point that is
something that we want to be able to
mark up in-game because it's just way
faster to be able to like drag a little
slider and see exactly what the result
is
because then we know like we got it
right and it looks right if we add it
just blindly edit some constant outside
be like blindly of the constant run the
game it's wrong blinding of the concert
really good like that's not a good
feedback loop so you want all that stuff
to be like live but the problem with
having it be live is once you edit it
you've got to preserve it right if you
don't preserve the data that you edited
live then you have no way of actually
using those edits long-term so what we
want to do is we want to be able to take
those edits which we already made all
that right that all works but we want
those edits to be saved back to
something that's not the game pack file
we even currently write them back to the
pack file so if you just wanted to like
pack everything once tweak all the art
assets and then ship the game that would
work we actually would have to do
anything because it writes it back to
HHA pack file so we're done right but I
want to have a permanent way of like it
checking into source code control the
packing list with all of those markups
in there so all of the stuff that was
like placed this this point here snap
this to this that sort of stuff should
all go in there and so that's the thing
that we don't have right now we can
parse the file we can pack from the
parse file module in fact that we have
to debug it right and so that's all fine
but we now need the way of rewriting
like sit save and rewrite that file
right so it's basically like the change
needs to get written back that's all um
so we want to do that and we you know
look we're not far from it but obviously
we have a little bit of work to do
before we get to that point so I'm gonna
go ahead and load up hand-made here out
here and we're just gonna take a look at
where we were at now remember we we
essentially have no change like we did
all this but we haven't like you know
removed our old HHA files that were
built without this system right so we're
running a debug mode here so again the
lighting is of course very slow but
otherwise you can see like everything's
fine it's loading
the assets correctly right and so it's
still using the old HHA files so we
essentially have two goals and we can
probably if we want to tackle them in
series so the first goal we could have
here is deleting the the HHA file that
has all of the current game our assets
in it and trying to get back to this
screen so looking like this with all of
the assets correctly loaded that's
something we could do to prove that we
don't have bugs in this new sort of
manifest listing style or Packer thing
right so we want to do that and that
seems like a reasonable thing to start
with especial especially since it's been
two weeks instead of one that'll just
get us reacquainted with the code right
so that we can remember what it is that
we're doing handmade here is weird like
you know we they're so long between
programming sessions normally it
wouldn't all page out of your brain so
it's worth you know taking it cautiously
like that so anyway if we take a look
back at the handmade 0 data directory
which is the thing that we care about in
this case you can see here that we've
got our data and we have like an intro
art v2 HHA we have a local HHA and then
we have some other hhas that were kind
of old things to like test these test
ones test fonts these are all hh8 the
best for ever we even made a converter
to convert the old ones forward so what
we want to do now is basically get rid
of all of these and start trying to
build a base game uhha that essentially
matches our local HHA because remember
local HHA was the thing we use to import
all the p.m. G's and so now we want to
do is make it so that when our packing
system runs it'll create a base game
that HHA that will just generate all of
that stuff all of the stuff that was
going into local hh8 will all go into
base game HHA that's our first goal our
second goal would be same thing with
intro art v2 so info art v2 data HHA was
again all of the stuff that we had had
that came from the intro cutscenes
that we also have p.m. geez of now we
want to take all of those p.m. G's and
pack those into an intro art version
right and so these two we can completely
replace this goes away so we don't care
about I'm sorry sorry these two
completely replace so they would go away
and we replaced with new ones bass game
day today would replace this one and
intro art of each day would replace this
one and then these I think basically
don't have anything we really need in
there so the only thing we would be left
with is the fact that we don't have any
way to build thoughts right now outside
of our external tool and we can decide
what we want to do about that but I
suspect what we will do is we will just
actually make a thought PNG and we will
mark the thought PNG up so I think we'll
stick with the system that we've got
right now to a certain extent and and
we'll just import it from a PNG because
we can make a PNG that just has each
character in like its own grid cell and
then we use the same import process
we've been using pretty much that just
works right um so I think we should be
okay we'll see what happens we'll give
it a shot
but that's that base we want to do and
then once we've gotten that debugged
then we can switch over to let's make
sure rewriting works and rewriting again
is just the process of taking these tags
files here that lists all the things
that should be inside and ehh eh
rewriting them basically without
mutating them at all other than
inserting any edits that we've made or
replacing lines you know that that
should have been in there or something
like that right so okay let's take a
look inside our asset system here one
thing that I think might be nice to do
at this point is there's just too much
stuff in here and so I think what I
might just start with today as a simple
thing we can do is inside handmade code
we've got the handmade
sit down H and that's EBP right I'm
gonna make a thing called handmade
import and the reason for that is we've
just got a lot of code now that does
this sort of thing and I don't really
want to have to worry about it anymore
right like I don't want it to be inside
my asset system that runs at runtime as
the actual like you know gameplay code
and all that sort of stuff all this
stuff only happens if somebody is saying
they want to do dev work on the game and
add art assets or something like that
right so there's just a huge amount of
code here that I can pull out and say
look this is going to be sort of a
separate chunk of code that only gets
used during importing right so I'd like
to keep all of this stuff separate here
just so I can see that like alright
there's a bunch of things that are like
runtime house at work but there's also a
bunch of things here that are not right
that are that are sort of things that
only are really relevant to people
editing the game and that's just kind of
a separate issue right so I'm just gonna
pull those functions out sort of slowly
here right and just make sure that I've
got enough stuff for that so like
reserved tags reserve asset that sort of
stuff like these are just not things
that matter to the runtime performance
of the game at all and so I don't really
want them in there so that I you know so
that people aren't confused about what
is and isn't actually part of the
runtime stuff so you know you can see
here now we've got sort of back to our
much more streamlined asset system and
only the things that actually matter to
the asset system proper or will be in
there and then here what I can do is
pull out also the things from the H file
so for example this import type is only
used by that asset importing there's
also stuff down here that is only used
for it like the hhd fields context the
import grids and tagged arrays all of
this stuff again only used if we are
doing that sort of import process so I'm
just moving that over now I
don't care about being this is not an
actual segregation I'm not actually
trying to draw a clean line through
these two pieces of code I don't care if
they're still still intermingled meaning
like for example inside this game asset
structure there's still things that are
only used for importing potentially
right so that's fine
right I don't mind about that at all I'm
not trying to like clearly delineate
these all I really want to do is just
have a rough separation of the two so
that I have a vague idea at least of
what I expect to be happening in import
time versus what I expect to be
happening at run time as we move forward
and I'm finished with this system way
down the line maybe I will want to do a
harder separation between the two as an
exercise to ensure that the import side
stuff is never happening in game or
doesn't have any effects on the in-game
stuff or so that you don't have to port
that stuff things like that so I don't
really know whether I want to go further
down that road or not but what I do know
is that I definitely don't want to keep
piling all the import stuff into that
file because it just makes it too
confusing as to what is happening when
I'd like to be able to keep them
separated uh so I'm gonna go ahead and
rebuild here I don't actually know
whether oops I don't actually know
whether or not I I still use the asset
memory block stuff I'm gonna just
quickly ask that question because I'm
curious yeah I don't so those were just
vestigial remains so imma get rid of
those you can see now that the in-game
editor is trying to call parts of the
asset system that we have removed and so
what I'd like to do now is I'd like to
just include the file that I created
that sort of we separated out I'm gonna
go ahead and add that back in here so
that we've got it we could make this
only in internal builds eventually if we
wanted to
but at the moment I'm not going to
bother with that again those are things
we can do a little bit further down the
line if we so choose I'm not super
concerned about them at the immediate
moment all right so here we go let's
just put those in there it's not what I
wanted I want that I think that actually
it's not acid import it's just import
and so now we should get those pieces in
there you have to excuse me like we
still haven't updated our for coder I
should really do that next week before
next week I promise I'll update for
coder all right so we got those two
things separated out now and so what I
want to do next is start by we're in
debug mode I'm gonna start by trying out
this code right
so I want to get my import changed
assets code working so that basically
what will happen is at any time if you
want to you can delete for example I
could go in here - yeah sorry I'm
already there I can go in here and
delete this base game - HHA and then
when you call like the you know the
import changed assets code it will
automatically look at the tag file it
will rebuild the HHA from that tag file
and produce a complete pack right I want
that to work that's thing one thing too
is if I change the tag file or a PNG and
I hit update it will rebuild those the
same way so basically like anytime I
want to I can just reload anything that
that I think should be reloaded and
it'll just work so that's what I'd like
to do now if that makes sense
so let's see if we can get that working
so let's just start by calling import
changed at sets step through it see how
it goes and every time we find a bug fix
it eventually hopefully we'll get to the
point where it just works and that's all
we need to do now I don't actually want
to have to click a button to do that so
what I'm gonna do is just make it so
that handmade hero just calls import
changed assets automatically because it
can and so what I'm gonna do is add a
call up here to this so that's like look
if anyone wants to call it that you can
and then in the asset system proper once
the asset system has actually loaded
everything so like in here after it gets
down to the bottom it's like alright
we're good to go we've got all of our
assets loaded and we you know we're
ready to play the game I'm just gonna
force this call here so that way when
you start up the game it will
automatically go hey let's double check
make sure everything's kosher and that
way while I'm debugging it I don't have
to like manually go click a button to
get started and this is just a general
theme that happens anytime you're
debugging things I highly encourage
thinking about how to reduce the amount
of physical steps necessary to do the
debugging because at the end of the day
the debugging time will take as long as
it takes and anything you can do to
shorten that up by reducing manual steps
your wit your winning back time for
yourself right so how they recommend you
know making sure you think about oh
could I just add some code to this thing
I'm debugging to make it much shorter to
the bug that's great right that's always
a good win there so here we go let's go
ahead and take a look and you can see
here we've finished compiling so let's
go over to our debugger and I'm going to
set a breakpoint there on that import
changed assets call right there and so
it should happen right at the beginning
I'm going to start with the nothing case
quote-unquote meaning this start with no
HHA and then later we'll try creating an
HHA and having it fail I mean sorry
creating hej and having it have
merge into it so we'll try some
different things and we'll see how it
goes so I'm gonna start running
hopefully I get a breakpoint right here
and there we are
Visual Studio does some weird things you
know it's hey I'm still waiting for a
new debugger hopefully we'll get one
sometime soon that's not Visual Studio
but you know it does some stupid stuff
like if you have an if statement I don't
know what just changed there if you have
an if a pound if statement
even though Visual Studio knows it's not
building this file because we haven't
created a project for it it's just a XE
and it knows it's not building this file
it still thinks it has the information
necessary to know whether pound ifs are
on and off it doesn't so it seems that
they're all off because of course none
of these have been set it's just really
bad right it's essentially giving you
completely false information that
especially a beginner programmer might
get really confused about what was going
on here oh well that's just you know
Microsoft me and Microsoft so if we end
up in import changed assets here and I
guess I for some reason deleted that
break point but I want it sorry leave
that on I
sohere import changed assets we're gonna
slowly step into the code you can see me
getting all of the H HTS here from the
platform layer so we want to load all of
our tag files we start out parsing the
tag file so here we go
we're gonna open up one of these tag
files here and read all of the tag file
in so we've got it entirely in memory
you can see that happening in fact I can
even just open up the tokenizer that
would have it you can see that the
pointer to the characters which is here
right yeah no is that wrong
oh I haven't started it yet there we go
so you should be able to see like once
we tokenize it all of the the data from
the file is like this is the file right
is now loaded in here so this is the
intro cutscene information and you can
see that it's just got a bunch of stuff
for the author here oh and you know what
actually let me fix one thing
we get started somebody mentioned this I
don't know if they reported it in the
github let me see here
TuneIn factor authentication ladies and
gentlemen okay so everyone now who wants
to snarf my two-factor authentication
can do it I have to
I should probably time it so that I only
enter it at the last possible second so
that anyone who is is trying to hack my
account won't have much time
all right so if I go into the bug list
let's see here here it is
there we go so in the bug list yes I was
gonna say I thought someone had reported
it and there right so if you look I
accidentally had these backwards so and
I was the person who did the title
screen and young-shin is the person who
had the who did the cut-scene stuff so
they were just backwards and so we might
as well fix that because I happen to be
looking at it and it's done now so I
think that's all good so I'm gonna close
and comment that and hopefully that that
takes care of that issue that was just a
you know mistake all right so moving on
so if we go ahead and say look we want
to get this thing loading properly let
me run back to where I was so we're
going if the intro cutscene one first so
when we load this up we're starting to
tokenize it we grab a token we look at
what the token is and it looks like the
token is an identifier and let's see
what it actually is that token is
default and actually we don't have a HHA
context and we get an error here that
error is totally correct and so the
question now
so here's something that's actually
pretty interesting about that right is
we don't actually have any way to put
these errors anywhere so like if you
look at what happens the error goes out
to an error stream and we're never gonna
see it right so it would be nice if
there was some way to like display those
errors or something but we don't really
have any way of doing that and so that's
another thing that we probably have to
look at but for now it told us the error
so we know that we've got an error in
here actually and so let's just go ahead
and fix that error right and we'll sort
of figure out how we display errors to
the user later so you can see that what
we need here is an HHA directive this
was the old way we were doing things we
decided we didn't like that because we
didn't want to have to parse we'd we
don't actually allow you to change the
HHA inside one of these we want that to
be something that you permanently sort
of state so here's a way to permanently
state that there's HHA intro cutscene
right so there's the like preprocessor
directive Ishq and of thing that we made
so that should fix that parse error
right which was correct it was an
ill-formed hht file all right let's run
it again so now we're gonna come through
here parse the hht in theory now we will
get a include directive essentially I'm
sorry an HSA directive we will try to
create that HHA by its stem and the stem
text is exactly what we think it should
be intro cutscene right so we we jump in
here and let's take a look we try to
find it and we can't find it because we
haven't loaded that yet in fact it
doesn't exist at all create if not found
is true and so we come through here
we're going to actually need to create
it so we create a path we can pass to
the platform layer here it is data intro
cutscene HHA we take a look we say
alright let's try to open that assuming
there are no errors we create a dummy
header and write it to to the file
we then initialize it and say why don't
you load this in so we kind of come
through here and try to load it in
that's us doing this here and we say all
right there are no errors that's great
so now it's it's initialized and
everyone is happy this seems broken
interesting
so if you look at this loop here we are
we may kind of have a bug in this loop
but the bug looks like it only happens
in the case where we've already got like
another bug which is that the file size
should not have been zero because we
wrote stuff to it so it should be larger
than zero that file info is getting
passed in here and so you can pretty
much see where the error is when we
create the file we don't reopen it right
so we're passing in a file info that's
not valid anymore
right and part of this is just because
our file system stuff is kind of janky
it's it's we've kind of gone through
several rounds of deciding we wanted to
do more stuff with files than we had
hoped you know what I mean and so at
this point it may be the case that we
really would rather do something a
little bit different here because it's
sort of it's sort of becoming a little
bit too cumbersome right but if you take
a look here at it for creates hhj by
stem what I'd like to do here is I would
like to have some way of refreshing this
file info right and at the moment we
don't have that what I can do instead is
literally just call it again so I could
say here like this right
so not great but we know what the
problem is and we can patch around it
for now which is fine but I'm gonna flag
that with it to do because it's not
fabulous right so you know we'll take a
look so if I jump back there to the
ghetto create oh well you know what I
should do is delete that file because I
want to run that test again and now that
thing exists so I want to delete that
and watch I want to watch that happen
again
so if I go ahead and and and and step in
there I mean let's go here no I keep
doing that okay if I go ahead and step
in there I want to take a look yeah so
that's we created I want to take a look
and see now if we get the right file
size for that so let's jump in here
let's go to the getter create so that
first directive right here if that's
gonna get or create that file we're just
looking for the file here I'm gonna set
a breakpoint when we actually go to init
it and verify that the file inflow
actually has some size now it does so
that you know should fix that problem we
come through here and we create it and
then we do the watermark retraction that
should just work because the high-water
mark should actually just be exactly the
same as it was of course visually
doesn't let me inspect file because
we've fallen out of here I don't know
why they change that horrible anyway so
once we grab the results now we've got
the file sort of ready to go and in
theory that should give us what we need
to start importing from this file so
into the context which is something that
we use for doing further importing we
have some addition
the fields here like what file index we
are going to be importing into again
that's just kind of a useful thing for
everything that we load to like shove
into the right file and we've got the
rest of stuff like the default fields
here and so on ready to be populated
right now they don't have anything in
them though so I'm going to go ahead and
start going forwards through here so
when we parse we should now get some
identifiers that we can actually process
so we come in here and now we succeed
because we've added that HHA directive
member before it was failing out on the
default block so here's the default
block what we should see happen is we
should parse this default block
hopefully our copy all up to and
including currently doesn't do anything
since I wanted to bug this you can see
this is where we got to when I ran so
that means we didn't really hit any bugs
yet we just have that not implemented
that's where we're gonna start copying
the thing from one to another I'm gonna
get rid of that right now because we're
not doing that yet so I'm just gonna say
look we're we're assuming that we wrote
something right there and we'll go we'll
go from there right so I'm gonna go
ahead and run up to there this is where
we were and keep going so first things
first we create a place to write the tag
array if we need to what's gonna happen
curious we're not gonna use that because
we've actually we're actually parsing a
default block which has no data at just
setting default fields so you can see us
pulling out those default fields let's
see if we got them right so here's the
default fields and we're about to fill
these out we wrote these into
I think just a thing called fields right
yeah so we wrote these into a thing
called fields so here's what we parsed
right all third description name is not
set which is correct because we don't
have a name set for any of this stuff
here
and so I don't know if we're gonna use
that or not ever but it's you know it's
possible anyway to do so then what we're
gonna do is say look the parsing
succeeded is it a default it is so set
the default fields equal the fields be
parsed there they are so I think that's
fine we're then going to end the
temporary memory because we're finished
parsing that block and then we can keep
going so hey the default parser works
fine that's good news
now we get to something that actually
needs to be imported and here's where
things should get significantly saucy
err so here's our parts top-level block
call here I come through the parse
top-level block call it is not a default
this time so now what I need to do is I
need to parse out where the art is
actually going to come from so here is
that file name you can see title screen
the PNG being set there and that title
screen dot PNG is where we need to grab
the art from so first we have to
construct a path thing that tells us
where it comes from you can see us doing
it with our format string function we
wrote and so here it is probably not the
best way to view it let's do it like
this so it's source intro cutscene art
title screen dot PNG did we construct it
properly we can find out let's take a
look from the starting directory which
is this is where the game runs from if
we look in source oh it's sources so no
it's already wrong that's where it
actually is so we needed an S there and
we didn't have one so we can stop right
now because we know that none of our
stuff will import properly because that
was supposed to be an S and it's not an
S so if we take a look at that sources
that's in the import here that just
needed an S at the front of it
like so and that's all we needed all
right try one more time no errors there
if I go ahead and set a breakpoint here
we should be able to jump directly to it
so here we go let's produce that again
now this time we should get a path
sources interesting art title screen
that's now what we do expect to see so
that's good now we're gonna try to get
that file and see if the OS can load it
it can let's see if it got the file size
right it looks like it did so we're good
to go now so the first thing we do is
look to see if we have a match for this
particular asset source file in this
case we we don't I don't think so we
wouldn't have seen this one before right
this isn't a if this isn't
something that we would know where it
goes so when we get back this match it
should be basically a fresh match with
nothing in it it should just have
nothing anywhere in here and I assume
like the errors stream shouldn't have
anything in it
right yet doesn't and the asset indices
should be all zeroes so it's basically
just a fresh stream with nothing in it
it doesn't have a date or the checksum
or any of that stuff set now that part
I'm not sure if that's what we want
because that should get set
[Music]
I guess the only thing that I'm a little
concerned about here is the fact that we
don't set it till afterward like we
don't set that stuff until here but I
guess that's okay because the only time
that we would have nothing set in there
is when we will absolutely get to there
because it means we've never loaded it
before so I think that's okay but it's
structured a little weird the code could
definitely be better anyway we're gonna
go into parse pieces and we're gonna
look at what this actually is I don't
actually know what it is oh it's a plate
right it's a title screen plate yeah so
the title screen plate doesn't have any
asset tags to set because it's just a
plate and plates don't have asset tags
other than the ones listed in the hht
file so it's just an import type setting
and it doesn't change the tag array so
the tag array stays now off we go so we
need a full rebuild here because we've
never seen this file before so the dates
don't match and off we go so that all
worked reasonably okay even though it's
a little convoluted we then open up the
brace for the data from this file and
we're gonna start looking at the actual
data we look through here and we see
what we get
first we see the tags so we go into the
tag part of the tag list parser this is
pulling out and just so those of you who
don't remember the files structure very
well inside here there's basically just
tags that say what these things are so
you can see here that we have this title
screen it says shot index 12 layer index
1 there's really no reason for that
other than we decided that's what it's
what it is we could tag this with just
title screen and make a new tag for that
if we want them to look it up that way
it's arbitrary right that's entirely up
to us so once we do this we just need in
here to know that that's actually going
to get parsed so let's double check that
it does we get an open paren here let's
see what the pram actually ended up
being the tag value is 12 that's what we
expect we should be good to go now and
we added the tag in there the tag ID is
what by the way shot index 12 so that's
exactly what it should be we should now
so we do have one bug once we parse out
the close paren we should have re gotten
the check so we do have an issue there
in here right after when we're actually
parsing the tag list we want to say oh
let's continue getting tokens right
because we want to we want to pick up
whatever we would have picked up after
the parenthetical so that check is
supposed to now be a semicolon or a
comma so we need to call that again so
that was just a parse bug we forgot that
we had parse something new and we want
to get that check all right so if we
continue down that let me just set a
breakpoint there that we can jump to so
here we are so now when we get it we
should be able to do the tag addition
correctly and not fall into an error
case so off we go so now let's see what
we get we get another identifier and
hopefully again we get a tag that makes
sense
later index 1 that's what it should be
so off we go
that's the semicolon that ends the tag
array so now our tag array should just
have those in it it should have two tags
in it and we saw them get parsed so
let's take a look first tag index is 15
25 one pass off thing this is 28 that
doesn't make a lot of sense because we
only parse two tags so how did we end up
with so many more tags because it should
just be 25 26
so one pass last tag index should
actually 1 2015 27 right oh no because
there is
tag which is the asset tag type and in
this case that asset tag type is tag
none interesting so I think we've got
one more bug here right which is that in
end tags the asset basic category needs
to be set in order for this tag array to
be correct or we need to stop having the
asset tag category passed in let's take
a look at how we're doing those end tags
so where are those actually getting
called right so when we do stamp assets
let's take a look when we do stamp
assets we go through and we do asset
asset type based on the import grid tags
stuff but do we ever actually set that
tag ID add tag an tag asset none so we
actually need the tags type ID to be
passed here but that's fine so that's
okay so I think maybe we're all right
the only thing we need to do is in here
don't do this if the category is asset
type none right so I think that we're
still probably okay again a little
jankier than I would like because
there's a lot going on here and we've
we've sort of we you know we sort of
re-architected this in place and so not
everything flows the way that you would
want but we can improve that over time
so I think that's correct we just won't
add the basic category tag if one is not
specified and then later when you build
one and it is specified we will add it
so I think that should do what we needed
to do all right so now when we come
through here and do asset
and we do this ad tag it'll only get
called so this time it won't get called
and we should get the right number if we
look here now you can see 25 to 26 and
27 is the end tag which is what we want
so that's all fine so that looks much
better now than it did all right so now
we've parsed what was in there that's it
so now we're ready to say look let's
let's finish up and build a file we hit
the parsing and it said no it's not time
to parse so what happened it looks like
we've got some kind of an error there
and I'm not sure what that is presumably
we hit the closed brace and left so we
must have hit an error what was the
error right so let's take a look so here
we are in error and the error is
unexpected token type how did we get it
we got it when we were parsing the
top-level block and it looks like we
required token the token we required was
a semicolon and we didn't get one so the
question is why didn't we get one well
we didn't get one because it is in fact
missing a semicolon so that's easy
enough again just a parse error and off
we go
so oh I didn't have to rebuild we didn't
change the code so let's go ahead and
run again again just kind of chipping
away at the various errors that we have
there so this time now we've actually
made it to here and I'm gonna skip the
first one because this is the default
block right this is this one so I
actually want the second one oops we got
what's
mmm we should have gotten one this time
yeah should we not have because there's
the tags and there's the clothes racing
oh well these don't have it either
that's probably not what the bug was but
we should at least make our files
correctly now it's worth noting that we
could not bother with the semicolons if
we wanted to just assume that if you see
something new it's you know it's
different but I just wanted this to kind
of look more like see so I like to
having a semicolons in there all right
so let's save that and in base game you
can see we've got all the semicolons so
this one was constructed more correctly
all right so in here let me run again
and let's see what we get
there's that require token we run again
and we're getting a required token
around the semicolon so I think this
time we're parsing it wrong because it
looks like we've got everything correct
in there and so something's up about
this so I'm gonna set a breakpoint there
and see what's going on so here's the
first time we call this and I'm just
gonna look at the tokenizer to see what
it's going to get here's the input
stream so it is going to get a semicolon
on that right it is gonna get a
semicolon on that is not gonna get a
semicolon on this though so this is
right before the default block so it
looks like we ate the semicolon on the
tag array
am i right
but the peak token call shouldn't have
done that
did we implement hoops Wow
typing problems today so it doesn't look
it doesn't look weird I will say this is
a dumb way to do this like you would
just do that right but still that
doesn't look like the problem because
that looks like that would have operated
properly so I don't think that's the
problem but clearly like why would you
copy it back in when you when you have a
duplicate one right here you might as
well just go ahead and do it right so
that's a little bit a little bit weird
so we should just do it like this
because it's just more efficient that's
it
you know compiler probably we figured
that one out for us so anyway if I take
a look a little kit more carefully now I
want to see like what is going on there
because it looks like our peak token is
is having an issue so let's see what
happens at that line of code so here we
are at the oh so hmm how do we never get
to how did we never get to that line of
code that's very strange right because
that we should have gotten to the tags I
mean how do we not get to the tags how
do we not get to that break point that I
just set when the tokenizer right if we
look at the input here's the input it is
parsed the tag array right so if it
parts the tag array what happened
aha
so yeah you can see what's going on here
right if we got to it semicolon we have
an issue because basically that that
peak token so we really need to use peak
token more is what it boils down to this
is just just too ugly right we do a peak
so can we see if we get the semicolon
the other thing we could do is roll the
semicolon parsing into the other thing
but I don't know if we really want to do
that so if you come through here you can
see we peek the token if you see a
semicolon we bail if we see an end of
fire we'd get it we need to then do this
as a peek token right so we see if the
if the thing is an open paren then we do
a get token on that too you know
retire the open paren and we can do a
sort of make sure that we didn't screw
up if we want to hear right can do it
that way we can get the open paren do
this and then peek this token right
once we peek the token we can say look
what was it we'll see which one it was
if it's a common comma we'll retire it
otherwise we'll keep going I'm sorry
otherwise we'll bail out on the Senate
go on and that way we're just only
looking to see if we're gonna settle on
if we are we'll stop right that's really
all there is to it not particularly
complicated so I think that solves a
problem we were having there and now we
won't have that weird like issue with
eating the semicolon again not the
cleanest stuff but that's I'm fine with
that
so let's take a look required token now
we should be able to get here more
reliably I think and so this is the
default one if I come back here now we
should be able to go into the non
default one we've got the match here's
the information on the death file index
it doesn't currently have one so it's
going to overwrite it right you can see
it doing that there and now that means
we definitely need a full rebuild
because going into completely different
HHA which again we already knew we need
if you throw a so it doesn't really
matter so now we're going to action
load the file right so we open up the
file and we load it all in so now we've
got the entire data there now we update
our match record so that we know that
it's there right and that's good then we
come through here and we say all right
let's take a look at the contents by
making a stream and asking the ping
parser to parse that string so hopefully
we've gotten it all in there we do so
now we're all good
then we say it was a plate import we
know that we were told that let's go
into process plate import make sure that
works we set up the width and height we
do the image extraction which is
happening here again it's in debug mode
so it's much slower than it would
normally be we look up the down sample
count we down sample and then we write
the image back to the HHA file which in
theory should just work hopefully right
so here it goes right we're writing it
back to the HHA blah blah blah blah blah
this is all code we had had running
before so all that stuff just gets set
up and we remember that we wrote this
thing in there and now big data is out
to the file happy birthday right so then
at the end if the metadata changed or
the the thing was built rebuilt in its
entirely I don't know needs metadata
change I don't know we currently just
don't set that right like we need to we
need to have some way of recording that
that has happened I don't know that we
do
so one problem that we definitely have
here is like we don't have a comparison
for these things right like we need to
compare and set the needs metadata so
like somewhere in here you know we're
running through the files we're parsing
the top level blocks every time we get
to a top level block we need to know if
we need to do a full rebuild
I think we're detecting that correctly
but if the metadata is out of date and
we need to rewrite that we're not
currently doing that
so after this parse like where all of
this stuff comes in we need to do a diff
here right that says all right do we
need like right this needs to get set
and so if we just take a look needs meta
rebuild you can see that you know it
just gets set to false and then it it
never it would never get set to true and
there definitely are cases where the hht
file we change like the tags or
something right if we've got situations
like that we want to now have some way
of differing the metadata to make sure
that we don't need to rewrite that and
so we need a function here and we can
also say like I mean you know we could
make it so that just gets defined here
but I'm not going to do that I'm gonna
say if the metadata is not already
scheduled for a rebuild right so if it
needs meta rebuild is not already
scheduled and we detect a difference so
like
so there's a magic function we haven't
written yet right snuffleupagus or into
programming
imagine we had something that did what
we wanted right
what would we pass to this thing so we
know we need to look at the assets that
currently are in there and we know we
need to sort of hand them the stuff that
we would have been shipped like handing
it right and then we would have to do
the needs mehta rebuild now looking at
that I think this can be deferred and
that's important if we're doing a full
rebuild we're doing a full rebuild so
off it goes really this thing right here
maybe is the right thing to look and see
whether we need to do it because it's
already iterating over everything to see
whether it needs to do the stamping or
not right so what I might do is say
maybe needs mehta rebuild just isn't
something that ever actually happens so
we can actually delete that and instead
what we do is we say look let's call
stamp assets and just say we always call
it right and maybe it's not even called
stamp assets maybe what it's called is
like update asset metadata right and so
in here we say we're gonna go through
everything and we're gonna make sure
that the tags are right for everything
in here and then that's the end of it
right make sense
um the way we want this to work is to
diff the things that it's about to write
and not write them if they're already
the same right so if whenever we're
seeing in the asset HHA already is fine
then we don't need to do anything so
what I'd like to do is say well alright
we've got you know asset string assets
stream here right are all happening and
we've got these tag arrays right and
those are happening so really all we
need to do here is when we do this this
tag set here week and if these two
things right so we could say like is the
tag array that already exists different
if it's not then don't change it right
so that's one thing we can do another
thing we can do is say well if the asset
type the asset site doesn't really
matter because that's just in the tag
array so that's actually not a right
back the other thing we do is say okay
if these asset strings are already the
exactly the same
we don't write those back and then
finally for the error stream we could
just say if there's no error stream then
we don't have to write that anyway so
that's a pretty simple one that could
probably be just left as it is because
it won't actually reserve any space if
there are no errors right it'll just be
like zero as always so I feel like
mostly all we need to do is make write
asset string do a diff so we could be
update asset string instead let me see
how often we call that it's only here so
if this were update asset string right
so I'm gonna say like
and in fact oops right so I'm going to
say that and then I'm going to just go
to write asset string and oops
and I'm going to put it to doing there
it's like to do don't write this if the
string is already the same so because
there's really no harm and running again
it's just wasteful like there's no need
to do this work so we can save that
information and move on so similarly the
and the error streams I'm not too
worried about because those are just
gonna get overwritten with zeros usually
and so in the case where there was no
errors no harm done if there were errors
we do need to save them so I don't
really need to compact those I think
those are fine so update assets string
is really the only thing to change there
so it's really just the tag array that
is the thing that's a little bit
complicated so the update asset metadata
call in this case really just needs to
do something smarter in this case so
when you're doing the tag builder what
we want to do is just not do this block
if the tags actually aren't different
right and so we know that we've got to
tag arrays that come together here and
then a type ID and that's basically what
we're gonna see so we just need to say
is that what's already there meaning is
is the thing that's in the file the same
already so if we looked at the H the
asset HHA first tag index as at a
Tuesday one past tag index would they
essentially be exactly the same so I can
do this
I think and
make a thing here where we check exactly
that so we can go through this set of
tags we can go through this set of tags
and then we can check this tag right and
we should be able to now do a direct
test to see whether or not these tags
are equivalent so the first thing we can
do is check the total tag count right so
in here we've got this tag array right
and then we've got this tag array and
what we can say is if the total tag
counts don't match then we don't really
need to look at the tags themselves
because obviously they're rays are
different so you know we have to rewrite
it so we can say if the total tag count
equals if the total tag count equals how
many tags are already there then we can
proceed with the diff otherwise we don't
need to proceed with the diff because we
know what's wrong and so we can just
skip right to rewriting it right so if
we say look here's how many there are in
the file at the moment for this asset
there we go here's how many are in the
file at the moment here's how many we
want there to be in the file if those
two things are the same we can dip them
if they're not then we're done right so
then we go through when we say like you
know test tag index equals
whatever that first one was right as we
loop through here all we really need to
do is say well we've got the source tag
so we can say it's like if the if the
test type index in any of these is not
equal to the source tag so basically if
the tags aren't equal then we're done
right and that's really all we need to
do anywhere in here so I think that's
pretty much it and then the final thing
is that last one the last tag so this
right this tag has to be equal to the
special tag which is the asset type and
so we need to make sort of a dummy tag
for that one if that makes sense so like
this struct here where we've got a JJ
tag this is the type tag you could say
this type tag is going to have an ID and
a value the the it's the type tag I
don't really remember what that's called
though basic category the basic category
has to be equal to whatever the basic
category was going to get set to right
so in here we would say
yeah there's that basic category and so
now we look to see if that one is
equivalent and if it is then we have to
we don't have to write it otherwise we
do right so you can see the whole thing
that does the complete tag arrayed if we
could definitely simplify this by like
making this be a routine right and maybe
we should but I don't know if we want to
or not so we do need to get tag counts
and we do needed tags are equal and so
let's just go ahead and write those two
they're not particularly difficult so if
I come up here and say okay here is get
tag count here is tags are equal what do
those look like and this is like asset
tag array I think or like you know
remember what those were called there
there are things that are import import
tag array right so this import tag array
the result of that is just going to be
the subtraction of the two right so it's
just the array one passed last
eigenvector a first tag index so really
you know nothing special there and then
the tags are equal again really pretty
basic it's just saying if I have two HHA
tags and I want to know if they're the
same I just compared their values that's
there's there's nothing more to it than
that so if you remember this this guy
here
if the IDS are equal and the values are
equal then the tags are equal because
there's nothing else in it and off you
go
so from there we can just look at what
we messed up here yeah we don't
do that oops let's try that again so
cannot import grid tag to import tag
array oh do we not have did we never fix
this stuff we probably didn't because we
were being lazy so you can see here
there's a tag this is a tag array and we
just never actually did that right this
is what we actually wanted to do and we
just didn't do it so let's just do it
now all right so this is just tags in
both of these cases and by the way we
could now make it so that this thing is
explicit because really the number of
people who actually do n tags now is not
that many and you know they could just
be explicitly adding it I don't really
know so I don't know what we want to do
there also is this part actually
necessary because the
okay so actually even the thing that I
did before was not really necessary so
the end tags call I think I think we
should just get rid of that cuz yeah
like that's not right either it's
already in there so actually I'm totally
wrong about this and it didn't actually
we didn't actually need to do that right
this was asset none and this is not
necessary there's no plus one and so I
think we should just get rid of that it
should just be an ADD tag call that gets
made that's just better so you know
that's fine
so that to do should stick and and we do
I think we probably do want to do it all
right so so now we got some easier stuff
here too instead of writing these things
these this way we can just do this which
is nice and so you know
like that and that seems really good
another way of writing it is just to say
this which is even more concise and
eventually we can probably get rid of
that entirely because that means that
now we're doing an import grid tag but
the basic category really doesn't have
to get returned there anymore as far as
I know although I guess it sort of does
so we'll see so we might leave it that
way for now we'll find out again that
basic category just a little bit
Squinkie so we'll see well we'll work it
through all right what's the problem
here these are not tag arrays but that's
fine what else we got
so looping through these it's just tags
tags which is kind of an amusing
statement but that's what it is
why is append tags a pointer and the
other one isn't it just should be a
pointer it just should be passed by
value we don't really really need that
yeah so anyway let me just quickly
change that because those are small so
we really don't need to pass them by
pointer we're probably just wasting our
time by doing that all right
every day alright so just working
through the air is now tags it's not a
member of import tag array so I guess
that was just a red herring
that's what I I just meant to do get
count cannot convert one from import
grid tag ah I see so only that one is
that makes sense this is not actually
necessary because we have the assets
here so I'm not sure why we were getting
them off with a builder probably because
we cut and pasted that code well now
paste it moved it into here from a place
that didn't have access to the assets in
another way but we do so that's all good
that means that in here too that needs
to be tags tags the words this doesn't
because tags is their different types so
again that's fine in here this is using
the Builder assets but it doesn't need
to so I'm going to get rid of that again
and then again that should be this way
in here when the age of je comes of the
combined tags that comes out has you
know the asset type in there too so I
think that's all good
update metadata doesn't need to pass the
address of that and so now I think we're
good yeah all right so let's give it one
more world here and see if we can't get
a valid import out of it I'm gonna
delete that intro cutscene dat HHA and
then I'm gonna run again we'll jump
right to the first needful rebuilds
because we pretty much know the rest of
that stuff's working now and we didn't
change it Curie's us doing our in PNG
import the plate has now been processed
and fussed with and all that other stuff
so then we go into update metadata we
take a look there's only one of these I
believe right so it's only gonna be the
first one and so like if we look at this
tags
oops
sorry I meant if we look at this tags we
should have only one place where this
occurs although actually well I guess
now I think about it we'll have none
because there is no grid so the only
tags we should have are here and the
basic asset type I guess that creates a
slight problem for us which is the basic
asset type we don't actually know what
it is right
if something is a plate if something is
a plate
what is the category it's just asset
plate right yeah so if something's gonna
be an asset plate
we need that to flow through the
pipeline better so haven't use me so
when we actually do that plate import we
do need to set one thing before we were
setting nothing but we actually do need
to set something which is in here where
we do this import plate we do want to do
one thing which is this and although
there are no other tags that would go in
place here we do need to just set the
asset category so here this is an asset
plate and we need to write this back to
something right and in our case the
something is just the zero zero element
because that's the only thing we have in
a plate is just one location right I
believe if we go look at the what is it
process multi important so if we look at
the various things here when we have
process plate import it should always do
it at zero zero so you know as long as
that zero zero is filled with the right
asset type we should be good to go so
I'm gonna call that done all right so
let's jump back to here I think we've
gotten there we go I think we've gotten
this worked out so now when we come
through here the tags type ID should be
asset plate and it is so then we can set
the asset type here because yes it type
would have been zero before so that's
good so we come through and we
we would have gotten this error by the
way we look to see whether the tags
differ so the first thing we're gonna do
is look at the count the total tag count
was three and of course before it would
just been zero so we're not gonna ever
diff the tags we're just gonna say look
they need to get written since the tag
zipper here is us building the tag array
that just depends these tag sets
together we produce the combined tag set
which should be three tags along and is
we then set that into the asset we write
out the strings and we write out the
well we don't write out the agents a
metadata yet we just mark that as dirty
or should have however I don't see us
marking it as dirty so I think that's an
mistake as well so I think we want that
HHA to be marked as dirty if any of
these things need to be written you know
I'm saying to you so that's one more
thing I think is broken there we
wouldn't touch this assets anymore right
so we'd come out here we'd be done with
that package and yeah and off we would
go so do we still have a breakpoint on
error yeah so let's run to the next
error for now we probably haven't gotten
rid of all the bugs but let's just see
if we have any more parse errors or like
obvious errors of that of that nature in
the build before we go any further with
it and and while we're at it we can sort
of look here and see you know that
should start piling things into intro
cutscene hopefully I'm not sure if it
will or not but let's take a look you
can see it does appear to be doing so
so not great
looks like we definitely have some
issues there because that's just not big
enough right it should grow
significantly beyond that so I'm not
sure what's good it should end up like
roughly that size right once
everything's piled together so I don't
know if I D but break here what ended up
happening so we're doing an image
extraction
[Music]
so it looks like hey we're just
processing a lot of big images and we're
processing the debug modes they're very
slow but nothing has gone horribly wrong
yet so we can keep it going so maybe
it's fine
these are all very large images and so
you really don't want to be in debug
mode because we we don't even really
have optimized pixel processing here
right we're just doing it in on the cpu
with floats we're not even using Cindy
so especially in debug mode it's gonna
be horriffic ly slow all right but it's
chugging along and maybe it's writing
something in there we don't really know
but hey it's getting bigger and that's
good
so that should grow eventually to a
large size and then we can also do an
HHA edit dump on it and see what we
actually got in there right so I think
that's good right
and again I guess while it's doing that
- one thing I might want to do is take a
look at where that dirty flag should go
so if you look at the HHA the the like
definition of the thing that stores
whether it needs to be written so here
it is it's called modified what we need
is a way to set modified in some way
that's reliable right and so whenever
you write asset data it'll get set and
whenever you reserve asset data it'll
get set but I don't know if that is
sufficient I don't think it is so I
think that's just really that's not
going to express enough in the in-game
editor when we set one of these it sets
that modified thing to true and that's
fine but that's not gonna cut it for
when the metadata changes happen so
inside update asset made it made a data
there we have to make sure that
everybody who might write something
actually sets that dirty flag asset
stream and up add update asset string
will because they'll call reserve data
and right asset data itself
automatically does it so basically
Reserve data's fine the only thing that
we care about here is basically here if
those tags differ then we need to set
the files modification flag to true I
think that's the only thing alright
we've hit our first error and I don't
even know what file we're on we may have
proceeded to the next file let's take a
look it looks like we did let's just
check here so file info that we're
processing at the moment is based game
so that means that actually we have
successfully in theory processed our
intro cutscene HHA now it's not very big
which is not great but I think that's
just because we haven't closed the file
handle yet so if you look here we've got
size on disk 325 right now one question
is why haven't we closed the file yet so
I wondered to be forget the file handle
closed because we probably did well I
guess not forget we leave those files
open so I guess that actually is fine
nevermind if those were supposed to be
left open for writing during during play
so what error did we hit when we were
parse when we were processing the base
game which is now different so we made
it through that other file with no
errors what did we hit here
we got an unrecognized block type when
we were parsed when we were processing a
top-level block and so the question
there would be like well what was it
right and it's called cover we don't
know what cover is yet and honestly that
sounds like a reasonable error I think
in parse pieces we just don't know what
that is right so we've got obstacles
item and in cover you can see we just
didn't set it so I think we want to set
that to to a multi tile import that just
gets ignored
and I guess again you know maybe what we
really should do is in the hht when
we're actually doing these things I
think maybe we want to just not do
anything with them we could for example
just comment them out right and so if I
go up to cover here I'm just gonna move
all of these down to the bottom and so
these are just things that we haven't we
haven't really used any of this stuff
and we will want to but we just don't
have any way to do those yet so we
should just ignore them right all right
so now let's take a look we know that
one of our files was imported okay you
can see it here intro cutscene dot h HJ
314 488 it's not as big as this one
which makes me a little bit nervous so
I'm not sure if we really got all of the
stuff in there imported the way we
should however maybe we did and maybe
the reason that smaller is because we
currently have some import size caps
that will reduce the size of things if
they're too large what could have
happened is you know this one this was
made that wasn't the case so that may
have been happening in here what I can
do is I can go back now and take a look
using HHA edit to see what's actually in
there so what I'm going to do is
remember HS 8 and it allows us to do a
minus dump so in there I can say look
take a look at this intro cutscene right
and that will dump everything that was
in it if you look at what's happened
there oh and you know what this makes
perfect sense if you look what's
happening there it had nothing in it so
why was that if not all this stuff well
again if you look at the way we
structure this routine we forgot an
obvious things that needs to happen at
some point someone needs to call write
modifications to HHA because all of
those asset tag array things that we
updated they never get written until the
end of the process right and so actually
inside handmade import at the end
this right we actually need to call that
right modifications to HH a function
otherwise it's never gonna nothing's
ever going to improve right so right
here before we finish this needs to
happen right those modifications need to
be written back now we actually need to
go through all of them so we want to
have a way of doing that for everything
and I don't know if we have that I don't
think we do so we want something that
will loop through them and anyone that's
modified it will just update it right so
we would like something that does that
essentially we want something here
that's like essentially the exact same
routine it's just it Maps over all of
them right so what we want to do is have
a for loop in here that says for every
file in the entire system if that file
was modified then rewrite it you know
time Sam
and so right amount of modifications to
HHA oops
it's basically something that's just
going to do all of that right let's just
make sure that that actually works
so if I do that it's pretty
straightforward because it happens to
just be a loop over the file indices so
we know we can just go through all of
them and for each one I can say look if
it was modified or write it that's it
it's not complicated right so that would
allow us to write all of our
modifications back and that should
really be all we need there so in this
case assets source file is not actually
the file that we're talking about here
we're actually talking about the asset
file so this was a as well that I
neglected to pick up there so there we
go
so all that should be relatively clean
now nothing weird happening so what I'd
like to do now is try a release build
and see if we get our stuff built
properly from scratch right and it
probably won't be we probably got a few
modes lurking in there but we're getting
closer
so again totally clear now nothing in
the directory I have built a release
mode version so this is the release mode
version building here and now I will run
it and see what happens right so now it
should chew through the files a lot
faster because it's at least an
optimized build so you can actually see
this number climbing much more much more
rapidly - right as the files - it that
should presumably climb to the same
number it climbed before because we
haven't changed anything so well there's
one thing they'll change it to go right
out the asset arrays so it plowed
through that
and now it's done and now it's working
on the base game so now if I want to I
should be able to look at that cutscene
one to be fair as this thing is going
through here just might as well let this
one finish as well right and hey we've
started again
now weirdly the head and stuff is
missing I am not sure why that would
have happened but I guess that may be
because we've got bugs in our import and
we've made a new asset that overrides
the asset that should have gone in that
place it could actually just be because
the alignment points are gone I don't
really know right we can actually look
at that if we want to the way that we
would do that is just say hey let's pick
one of these here let's see if we can
get the head in there somewhere
doesn't look like we can
yeah I don't see so it looks like the
head is just missing which is not good
right so I assume that's a bug like art
import did not work properly but I don't
know right because you can see like
everything else is there so doesn't look
like the head is there but not aligned
it looks like it's just busted um so
okay but we've gotten 3-1 imports so now
it's time to debug like actual errors in
the output let's take a look at the
intro cutscene stuff first oh the other
thing we could do is just see what
happens if we run the intro cutscene so
for example oh by the way this should do
like nothing essentially right yeah so
if we're only into a cutscene presumably
we'll also just not get anything here
because if we've got bugs and how we're
setting up our tags and stuff like that
we should not see the intro cutscene or
we should see like a buggy version of it
so we do see it that may although that
may also be because we're still using
the older HHA right and so we really I
guess can't judge much from that either
all right so let's start by looking a
little bit further into things let's
start by seeing what we've actually got
in there if I do a directory here I have
that intro art v2 not HHA what I'm gonna
do is make a like the two directory and
I'm gonna move intro art v2 to HHA into
the v2 directory so it's gone so now
when we load we only have intro cutscene
HHA that's all we've got
right so this is the freshly built one
if I now go to the intro cutscene the
question is what do we see do we find
any of those plates or do we not find
any of them and are they in the right
order all that stuff and now we can go
through debugging this part as we go so
you can see like nothing there right so
it cannot find those or it is finding
them but they're wrong so we like packed
the data incorrectly or something like
this alright so let's start down the
road of getting that working but I think
we're getting close now so this is nice
we're kind of getting to the end of the
road of this process where once we get
this stuff to
but we should be in good shape and have
a nice clean way to build all of our
stuff fresh all right so we find doing
HHA edit dump let's first try to get
this reporting some some stuff we can
use so I'm gonna put this into intro
cutscene text and I'm gonna run tab view
from the bonus pack on info cutscene
text if we actually look at what's going
on in here right you can see a big tiger
ready here's all our assets and when we
look at the assets we can see what's
going on let's just take a look so
looking at all this you know it actually
looks really good and that's frustrating
because you know it would be nicer if it
was obviously busted in some really
clear way you can see here that it's got
three tags a basic category of 25 which
i think is plate shot index 1 layer
index 1 right eye and so that's less
good but we can double check this basic
category stuff in a second here and
maybe there's something weird going on
there right we'll see
so all these shots look pretty good and
so I'm not really sure what to make of
that they all look like they've got
tagged properly the the bitmaps
themselves also look reasonable right
like there they've got actual data in
them that that size is even seen you
know at least somewhat plausible so I
don't really know just from looking at
this I was assuming we'd look in here
and it was just garbage I don't know
looking at this why we're not seeing
something on the screen and it's just
like I don't know maybe is the data bad
like is the bitmap that actually got
written a garbage bitmap or something
like that
and so I want to have a way of debugging
that
I want to have some like I'd like to
have some way of of looking at what a
particular bitmap was in the HHA file so
that I would know right that would be
kind of nice so here's I'm going to
propose what if we just added something
to our HHA edit so you know it's got
these commands in and create rewrite
info dump and I'll be honest I don't
really know what check hht is I think we
deleted that didn't we
that's still in there rewrite info dump
create you're right yeah that's not
really in there anymore that's just
wrong um so what I would like to do is
say look maybe we can do a thing here
where we say what if we have like a -
extract that just says if I give you
this
HHA file can you dump like a bitmap from
it so that I can look at it right and so
if I say source HHA it'll extract and
dump like all of the things I mean yeah
I mean I might as well just have it
extract all of them there doesn't seem
to be a lot of reason to extract just
one I don't think yeah I can't think of
it
so you basically say like click extract
all this stuff and extract it to this
directory right like that seems
reasonable
and so in here if we say like alright
let's have this commands where we do a
string comp here and we just say alright
extract everything from this then what I
do is I'd say get me that information
and then I would read this in and I
would just loop over all of the assets
in it and extract them out to different
directories right so this HHA a a
loading HHA has all of this information
in it so I can loop over the asset count
right I can say that there's an asset
index that goes from 1 to whatever the
asset count is and for each of those I
can output the asset index of my choice
right and I could also make it be like
there's a stem like that maybe I'll save
that so you just say like test file name
stem and so essentially what you do is
you'd pass like the first part of the
name and then I depend like the number
of the asset and the dot whatever it
should be
BMP if it's a you know a image or WAV if
it's a sound you know back how thing so
then in here what I'll do is I'll build
the asset name so I'll say like you know
desk file name and you know I'll do some
cheesery here whatever
actually are we using your standard
library oh nevermind
we're using our standard library
so I can just say alright make a test
file name here I want to have whatever
the stem is and then I want like a dot
and I want like some stuff and I'm gonna
dump a bitmap or something and so here I
want something like percent s % you
where the percent s is whatever the desk
file stem was and then the asset index
like comes after it you know and so
maybe that's
zero for as well something like that so
that will just like dump all of those
things in there and I can do the ones
that I know how to do right yeah so at
the moment what I'll do is I'll say look
we don't really handle we don't we don't
really handle anything that's not a
bitmap at the moment I'll add sounds at
some point so for right now we'll just
say look what was the type of this thing
like what kind of asset is it so when we
go into like here and there's this type
field we're just gonna look and say look
if that type is is it like an image type
then we'll we can parse it if it's not
we're just not gonna it's not gonna
happen my friend right so we just say
like okay get like if it's a bitmap off
we go if it's not then we don't and
that's the end of the bat so inside here
when we go to do the extract bitmap
accent I'm just gonna say like here's
the asset in question the loaded the
loaded HHA and here's the desk filename
that I'd like you know it to go to and
so all I need to do is just like write
this actual function I don't know if
we've got yeah
so for things that write bitmaps
we've got load BMP we have a right BMP
though too don't we I mean we definitely
do and so it's just a question of me
remembering where the heck we put it
because we have one at the very least I
thought we had but for our PNG tester
thing right where we would write out the
PNG that we loaded so like this thing
this yeah so you already have a thing
that does the writing here and I yes I
guess that's what we want maybe
I'm gonna cut and paste this for now I'm
not super sure so I'm just gonna say
look at some point we should probably
have some way of like for these
command-line utilities which we have a
couple of for various things I'm testing
really mostly it seems like we would
probably want to have some way of
sharing this code between them you know
that just seems like a good idea and I'm
also gonna let this thing not need error
streams you know if it doesn't if it
doesn't need to have them so at the
moment I might say actually where is out
F so it does do a check around the out
so this is fine so all this will be just
fine so what I really need to do here is
just call this for each asset in the
system and that should be the end of it
right so in theory this should do it for
us so we would need to know the asset oh
and this is a yeah a loaded HHA this is
an HSA asset and this is a like file
stem-vowel me actually that's a bug it's
not this fast time it's just foul name
so when we export each of these assets
what we need to do is grab this stuff
out so we know the desk file name and
that's fine and we also know the pixel
ops because those are always going to be
exactly the same so out of these right
we need to figure out which one's of
these we're going to do now invert
is what exactly it swaps rose ah so
that's if you want to flip it upside
down okay so we've got inverts which I
don't know whether we need because
bitmaps it's writing as at a top down so
ours in memory if they are top down as
well we're fine if they're actually
bottom up then we need to reverse them
right so I don't really remember which
way we did it cuz it's been so long
since we've touched that code but that's
easy enough for us to fuss with right
multiply a is whether or not we need to
do like a pre multiply alpha I assume on
there right yeah so this one I don't
think we want to multiply the alpha at
all because we've already done a are
pretty multiply if if one was gonna get
done for swap are we're writing we're
gonna be writing a windows bitmap file
so I think we do have to swap the are
because I believe we store I can't
remember again with trade store did we
do BJ we may actually start be GRE
internally though so I think swap are
doesn't actually need to be there either
replicate a just writes it as an alpha
image which again I don't think we need
so the only question is do we need to
invert it so we may just have 0 for
pixel ops but we may need to do the
inversion I'm not going to pass an air
stream
I don't care and so what we really need
to figure out is the rest of this stuff
so if we go back to the HHA file format
that should tell us what we need to know
if you look in here we've got
information from the HHA asset and it's
the bitmap part of it that we care about
because there's the dim that we that's
what we actually need to know
so inside asset we've got bitmap dot dim
and that should be our width and height
there and then we've got our pixels and
the pixels is going to be wherever the
data is supposed to be for this asset
and that was in the actual asset itself
so HHA asset data offset is where that
actually is groups right so if we look
at the loaded HHA the loaded HHA has on
everything loaded in it so this is it so
what we need to do is say well whatever
that asset was we need to take the data
store and we need to offset from the
data store wherever the asset data would
have been you know what I mean so that's
pretty straightforward as well I'm gonna
go ahead and call this pixels and I'm
gonna grab that out as a thing because
we may when we're debugging this we may
want to look at that value as well so I
think that's mostly everything that we
would need to do there in order to write
out the bitmaps I think that's mostly it
so if I go ahead and build this and look
look through here it looks like the
error stream stuff is a little borked
because we're not including that in here
so that's actually okay because I cut
and pasted it I'm just going to do this
this would be a bigger problem if I had
right so there's worth noting so where
do we actually so we're just doing a
printf to standard error for our stream
right that's how we're doing that so in
here we can just do this
and and that should solve that problem
for now that all's fine but we do have
the problem that inside the test P&amp;G
stuff I need like these utility
functions that we had that seems fine
the swap and stuff it's a swamp aren't B
and I know where that is
oh that's in that's in our utility layer
so that's all fine we could put these in
there as well just to avoid again just
duplicating things unnecessarily I'd be
fine with that
so in here if we wanted to we could just
say look those are there and that's fine
and then in test P&amp;G we just get rid of
them right so now we just have a problem
that that our bitmap header is not
defined anywhere and that's because that
was something that we've liked again
just always kind of cut and pasted so it
would be nice again if we like had some
saner way of sharing these amongst these
utilities because they don't go into
handmade here a proper and that's the
only place that we really set up a place
to share code amongst features right so
it's something to think about going
forward looking at this here we know we
don't need the stream anymore so I think
now we're good and now we just need to
see if this works at all which maybe it
does maybe it doesn't
so in here let's start by trying to dump
something from something that actually
works there's no point in trying to dump
from intro cut scene because
intercutting it's busted we're gonna use
the dump to debug it so we don't want to
start trying to get the dump working on
that because it might be busted right so
let's try dumping like the local HHA so
I'm gonna make a dump directory here and
I'm gonna say HHA edit - extract I'm
gonna say why don't you extract
I don't know test 1 v2 HHA or something
once you extract that into the dump
directory right so dump slash I don't
know
test 1 v2 go ahead and take a look so
first of all is that do anything it does
just do anything useful No
so you know close but no cigar we don't
we don't get any points we don't get to
come back next week or we don't win a
case of rice-a-roni the San Francisco
treat like nothing happens so we want to
get that dump working so that we can
look at these files so why isn't the
dump working would be question number
one what are we doing wrong there
so the bitmap dim we can look at this
how the header stuff is working we've
got the pragma pack pop bitmap header
here and presumably we're setting the
stuff correctly I don't know if we are
or not output pixel size this all seem
sane right we're just figuring out how
to line this stuff up
I mean that looks pretty reasonable to
me I'm not sure what's what would be
broken about that wait a second where is
it getting the out where is it getting
the space for output pixel size oh it's
just doing it in place
that's actually fine because we just
throw it away anyway but weird alright
so yeah that does the 2f writes and then
the F close I mean that should sort of
work right and it seems reasonable so
I'm not really sure what the problem was
there let me take a quick look and see
if there's something weird going on so
in here I'm gonna jump over to AJ edit I
think this is OK seems ok gonna take the
exact command line that we used and just
place that in here and then I'm gonna
make the working directory be handmade
slash data and we'll see if this
extraction call doesn't anything useful
so stepping in here oh and let me set it
to the debug mode so we don't have to do
fancy footwork to understand what we're
looking at in the debugger since this is
not a time critical operation shouldn't
be an issue
alright so assuming we get here which we
must because it actually was dumping
files we read the HHA and and you know
presumably that data store is just the
data store and there it is
so in here we loop through our assets
and when we get one of these bitmap
assets we create a DES file name which
that all seemed to work nicely so there
it is we then go to extract the bitmap
asset and in here we get a pixel pointer
back right which should be good
datastore plus the data offset and then
we pass in the width and height and all
that crap so let's see what that was 144
by 217 seems totally reasonable that
yields a total pixel size of 124 992
let's see if that actual value which is
this here that should equal what we
found in this HHA asset so meaning these
size should be the same and it is so
we're I mean everything looks right so
far we create a header let's
see if the header is it all reasonable
so here's the header file tight don't
really know much about what that should
be so I'm gonna assume that we got that
correct
let's hope we've got the file size which
is the header plus the pixel size that
seems good the header size is the size
the header minus 14 not sure how exactly
that works okay I know what we did wrong
see this is why we should share the code
right I bet we use the wrong bitmap
header so I'm guessing we've got two
different kinds of these although maybe
no no we don't nevermind
that is what it looks like
yeah nope I'm correct well I don't know
that I'm actually correct
so you can see in here here's the bitmap
header that the pain thing was using
right so here's the one that was doing
that right out so it was actually using
a totally different version the size of
header minus 14 part I'm not really sure
where it comes from exactly but again so
there's two different ways you can write
the bitmap and we have both versions in
our just like random crap files right
let me just see what happens now Hey
look so yeah again that's just we should
make a thing that we like something
that's like our command line utilities
stuff or maybe we just right enough in
our platform layer to make the command
line utilities use it that's the other
option it's just go full-bore right so
you can see all that stuff dumped
properly so that's great that means now
we can dump our intro 1 so if we say
like intercutting that HHA and we dump
all that stuff here we should now be
able to see what it is so this is even
more perplexing because now it's like
hey all of this stuff is accurate right
so the only thing I can think of is like
did we screw up the Alpha like why how
are we not able to see these when they
look correct like why aren't we finding
them what's going on you know what I
mean
so something's up and I'm not sure what
I might save that for tomorrow because
I'm happy with where we ended today so
at least we know like hey our whole
packing system is working pretty darn
well
but yeah so
we'll stop there I'll go to QA and we'll
pick this up tomorrow when I think we
should be all right
I should check to see how the inch are
cut scenes occurring their categories
yeah I'm just not sure what exactly is
wrong there
I'm just not sure
what's your first major gameplay
programming topic going to be we don't
we don't really have gameplay
programming topics per se you really
only do engine programming topics for
gameplay we're just gonna you know
basically just straightforwardly write
the entity code that we need for each
feature there really won't be there
won't be anything else try to stay away
from gameplay gameplay stuff cynthaiz
iasts do you use string library from CRT
I thought we wrote our own version yeah
so in our command-line utilities we
don't use our own stuff in the command
line utilities they're written on
standard libs so that anyone can compile
them hopefully on anything without
needing to change it however we could
decide not to do that later if that
makes sense so only in the game do we
call our own string your teens routines
have you ever programmed non-blocking
TCP sockets I wonder what is the cost of
directly calling rec fee and send versus
select so the answer actually is yes I
have
the only problem is I've never done it
in a super performance-critical way
where I was trying to like max out the
network performance so here's what I
will say if you're just doing it in a
game - like receive packets from the
server then calling a rec feed calling
non-blocking breakfast I would assume
would be totally fine because you're
just because the game client just
doesn't have very many connections to
service so you should be fine on a
server with a high volume of clients
like let's say you were trying to do a
lobby server with like thousands of
clients connecting and disconnecting I
don't think you would want to do that at
all because just the iteration over all
of those like saying do you have a
packet of magnitude a packet is just
really wasteful so I would say you
really want to use something like an i/o
CP or I like a Windows message something
that's like notification based so I
would just say non-blocking rect V is
fine for like one or two input streams
but if you're going to try and scale it
up to like you know tens hundreds
thousands of input streams it will I
don't think that's a very good strategy
could you improve the assert Metro such
that it prints the string IIST
expression which failed on Linux the
debugger does not always show which
assert failed where nope I can't because
there is no printf we removed all the
CRT stuff so we would have to add I mean
I could if I really cared which I don't
you could go into the win32 layer and
add the output like - to the platform
layer get an output and it would do a
printf on linux and it would do some
kind of an output on on Windows if you
just want to fix this on Linux just
change the assert macro on Linux right
I would also say men if the if on Linux
it can't tell you which is where you did
is right to zero that's kind of terrible
but of course links debuggers are
generally terrible so I don't know what
to say about that I would be shocked if
gdb didn't show you where it failed
though that what that sounds wrong you
must be using something other than gdb
what is your thought on the structure of
config files in Windows that have
sections in the close brackets do you
think it is a good structure for the
game config file I don't have a strong
opinion about it I tend to like things
to look more like C just cuz that's what
I'm used to but you know I have a
problem with it
how do you implement immediate mode desk
functionality for rendering anti-aliased
polygons
I am currently rendering n guns with a
geometry shader but I am unable to
implement anti-aliasing well so just to
be clear there's two questions that you
could be asking there and I don't know
which one you're asking if you're asking
how do you implement anti aliased
polygons if you're drawing them in the
correct order always meaning like back
to front and no intersections or
something like that then the answer is
you don't have to do anything to make
them anti aliased they just will be as
long as you use some kind of pixel
coverage for your pixel shader but if
you're asking how do you render
anti-alias polygons in an arbitrary
order you can't it's not possible so you
have to be using some actual strategy
for example you can turn on multi
sampling which is one strategy for
solving order independent anti-aliasing
of polygons you could implement def
peeling and then post blend of them like
we do in handmade Hiro that's another
strategy you could use pixel linked
lists which is yet another strategy but
yeah like the short answer of what do
you do in a geometry shader to render an
T as fuzzy as you can't you've got to
have a pixel a back-end pixel pipeline
capable of doing order independent
anti-aliasing and there are several ways
of doing that the most straightforward
one is always just to turn on multi
sampling because that's what it's made
for
but you know you've you've got a you've
got to pick something there there's no
if the fundamental problem is that if
you're drawing polygons in an arbitrary
order then
you have a problem that you don't know
which one was on top of which other one
so your coverage what it's supposed to
actually output as as a result is only
known if you know what all the samples
for that pixel were at some final time
right you can't do it any other way now
there is one method I didn't mention I
was listing for you there another one is
to change your definition of an edge
anti-aliasing to be order independence
and some people have done that but it
doesn't really do usually what you want
for high quality visuals you can look at
basically alpha functions that are not
over so the standard ALPHAN function
that we use is called over which is like
this over this and then whatever the
Alpha is it basically takes what's
underneath it and blends as much of
itself in as it needs to right and so
there are other alpha functions and that
aren't order dependent over is order
dependent and you can switch to one of
those that's yet another option but
again you you have to it's a pixel
pipeline issue not something that
happens in the geometry shader unless
I'm missing what you're trying to say
we're trying to manage entities in my
own game engine or sorry when trying I'm
just gonna rephrase this I think it's
what he sings when trying to match
others in my own game engine just me on
my own do you think the entity
components structure is worth
considering or am I just giving myself
too much work when it's just my own code
yeah generally speaking I guess what I'd
say is we've talked about NDK systems a
lot before and I would just emphasize
that I think it's just a bike shed
problem people massively over complicate
entity things and it's just um and isn't
necessary what you should do is just
write what you need the entities to do
in code and whatever falls out of that
data structure wise is fine it's really
the wrong place to focus that kind of
systemic database style thinking because
the most important thing to understand
is that anything that you impose as a
hard requirement on your entity system
is a fundamental limitation on your
gameplay right if you're just writing
your entities in C as C code then
literally anything the computer can do
can be in your game right once you start
piling systems on top of it and say the
entities have to be implemented in terms
of these systems now you have restricted
the set of possible games you can make
to those the things those systems
support in the case where you're dealing
with something incredibly specific with
hard requirements like transaction
systems for banking ATMs or whatever
where there's not a lot of crazy
functionality you're going to want but
there are a lot of hard constraints like
replicability fault tolerance
transaction logging bla bla bla that's
when it becomes important to say let's
trade flexibility for some set of you
know
things we get back by just implementing
things in this system we know we get all
this stuff so we're willing to make it
harder on ourselves to implement the
things we're actually implementing in
order to get all these things back
totally reasonable right game play is
not that way game play you want to be
able to write anything at any time you
don't want to have to stop and go oh
crap I wanted to add this gameplay
feature but I realized that the entity
component system that I wrote doesn't
support that now I've got to go rewrite
that system and then come back and write
the gameplay code and that's just it
just isn't sensible and so the most
important thing to remember is like
flexibility and gameplay code I think is
king I don't do game design really so
you know I'm not gonna sit here and tell
you exactly what you should do or what
you shouldn't do but the game designers
that I respect the most they just don't
do that kind of crap right they don't
make these like systemic things because
they know that every systemic step you
take is reducing the space of things you
can do in your game and that only makes
sense when you're intentionally trying
to carve out a space like that so I
don't know oh I see John John is here
actually John was that a reasonable
explanation of it you're really the
expert on game design systems so you
know I would I would say whatever you
say is probably the best advice on
things like this but I don't know
exactly what you would say I see you
saying don't bother with component
systems which is part of what I said but
I said something perhaps a little bit to
the side of that and I'm not sure if you
would necessarily agree with it but
also toy gang says what should I choose
ex-lover xeb I'm not enough of a Linux
expert to tell you what to do on Linux
sorry I just yeah I'm the wrong person
to ask
so Jon says yeah I haven't thought in a
while to explain the wall and yourself
in thing but that is 100% true it's like
playing go when you build a strategic
structure you are also filling in the
board and ruling out possibilities for
yourself so yeah I mean that that that I
I would think people should consider
that a much more definitive answer I
mean that's Jon makes the most like
intricate gameplay sort of thing is that
that I know of in in terms of games that
I think were great and so I just feel
like if if he's not singing the praises
of these like systemic kind of
approaches I think they're probably not
so good and it's not to say that they
might not have a place in something some
other like there's there's realms where
they might make sense you know the
example that comes to mind is like
puzzle script or something like there's
realms where you might say look the
whole point of this thing is I'm trying
to make a family of games that can only
do these things like the point is to
wall yourself in and if that's what
you're trying to do then maybe a
systemic approach makes sense but if
you're just trying to make the best game
you can for some specific game you're
writing walling yourself in just it just
seems self-defeating and if you've got
all these great benefits from it it
might make sense but you don't that's
the real problem is you're making a very
significant trade you're giving
something very valuable up and then
you're really just not getting anything
back right you get back very weak sort
of
benefits like really pretty if they're
even benefits at all you know and so in
the case of entity compliance is I think
is a pretty easy choice to say this just
doesn't really make any sense
I mean running my own game render loop
but I've been having trouble getting the
loop timing to be constant I seem to get
a stutter or skip in motion but it's not
because the render procedure takes too
long any ideas what could be the issue
sorry I know it's much not to go on but
any ideas would be helpful yeah so
there's this is first of all I guess
what I would say is you're not alone
windows in particular so you would
probably not be having this problem on
like a Playstation or something but
windows in particular and PCs in general
are very bad at doing things like
guaranteeing consistent frame timing now
there's two things that can be going on
here one is that in general if you are
not using some kind of a hard clock and
they really the only one that I know of
in the PC age you can use is the vsync
the V blank interrupts if you're not
using some kind of a hard clock tied to
the frame refresh then you're kind of
out of luck for consistent frame timing
so I'd start by VIPRE Kading into two
halves there's the type of game loop
which tries to always hit vsync and then
ask the graphics card to stall on vsync
that as far as I know is the only way to
do jitter free rendering I don't know of
any other way if that is what you're
doing and you're getting stuttering what
I would encourage you to do is try to
run your game under something like
incite and look to see what's going on
with the gravis card is it correctly
hitting those boundaries or not can you
get some information from the graphics
card about what's going on that may help
you if you're trying the other route
meaning you just flip as fast as you can
and you let it tear or you're using a
monitor that has flexible refresh rate
then the problem is usually in the
timing because the problem at that point
becomes
what you're measuring is usually not
what you need to measure for smoothness
so if you think about it the way a lot
of people do it is they present a frame
to the screen and at the time when they
made the present call they snap a clock
value then when they get to the next
time they do a present call they snap
the clock value and they use the Delta
between those two to know how far to
advance everything forward in time the
problem with that of course is it's
actually sort of a little bit too late
you're then using what the previous
frame time was to say how long this
frame should be now that can be okay if
you actually timed what you thought you
timed right and you have no frame bait
frame time-based effects such as motion
blur if you have motion blur you're done
but if you don't have motion blur you're
okay because there's no grammar that
says which frame is supposed to be which
time so you can you can still fudge it
there right but the problem is even if
you don't have motion blur you still end
up with you have time the right thing
timing the present present to present
doesn't actually tell you how long the
frame was on the screen for because you
don't know when that present actually
got committed and you don't know when
the next present will be committed so
what you really need is information back
from the graphics card on micro timing
which says here is how long these frames
are actually on the screen for as far as
I know no one actually does this
correctly and in fact Adam Ladd of app
actually I'm sorry I don't not to
pronounce his names I never heard it
pronounced the guy from Croteam
this guy right he actually was pushing
for this on the Vulcan advisory board I
remember this I don't think they ever
actually did it like he was explained
all that stuff he's like look these
things have to be timed properly in
order to get the frame updates with to
not have micro stutter in them like
little bits of wobble in the frame time
we have to know like exactly how long
the frame was on the screen for because
of the screen frame was on the screen
for all you know a few milliseconds less
than the times between the present calls
then we're actually updating the game
further than it should have been so
although the overall average frame time
is correct what were displaying to the
user has left micro stutter in it right
because we present we we updated it a
little bit too little on this frame and
a little bit too much on that frame and
the user can see this wobble right
really really perceptive of him and he's
totally right and they don't think they
ever did it unfortunately so I don't
know if that helps ideas guys says lot
of us might be the way to pronounce it
so let's say Adam Autobots also I mean
assuming that there's pronunciation
differences throughout his first name
might be pronounced differently as well
all right think we're done with
questions so I think we'll we'll all die
all right so we're getting a lot closer
and so I think we're almost done with
our asset our final asset pipeline which
is great because that'll be nice to have
that thing baked and then we can just
build the game from scratch all the time
and and it's pretty easy to have
everything yeah I don't know I'm I'm
pretty excited to have that kind of be
done and to be able to ship a thing
that's like okay here's like how we just
do packaging and you can you know dump
things and repack things and do it all
and then that's just done and it's out
there and we don't have to care anymore
so that'll be really nice and so
hopefully tomorrow we'll get a lot of
the way towards that goal there's other
things even if we get everything working
tomorrow there's other things we got to
do we got to finish sound stuff up just
to make sure those packed properly now
and load properly and we should do a
little bit with fonts so we got a couple
cleanup things you're still got to do
but we're getting pretty close and I
like it
that's about it for today I'll be back
here tomorrow to try finishing up some
of that stuff if you want to following
at home you can always go to handmade
hero org and pure to the game it comes
to the source code if you want to play
around with it maybe you can beat beat
us to the bug and try to bugging it
tonight on your own and see what you can
do also we recently really start comic
now the infinite if you're interested in
checking it out you can always read it
online if you go it's pretty easy when
you get to it if you're on handmade here
actually this this little guy here just
automatically brings us to all of our
site so you just click on meow the
infinite in the comics here first issues
up for reading check it out if you get a
chance let us know if you think I'm till
tomorrow everyone have fun programming
and I will see you on the Internet
take it easy everybody