hello everybody and welcome
to handmade hero show we could a
complete game live on stream
um we have some
sort of hanging out stuff that we were
doing um
we oh you know what i gotta turn off
that so
you know what here's the thing ryan how
did how what's the plan we need a plan
for how i can turn off battery saver at
startup
no one knows um anyway uh
what i want to do here is i want to take
a look today
at getting the tag stuff working we we
basically did all the stuff i wanted to
do but we're going to want to like
rebuild the asset files
uh and simplify the tag stuff a little
bit and then i i kind of had some
questions about it
because i was thinking just in terms of
like now that we sort of have a
you know a vague plan for what we want
to do um
in terms of cleaning up the file format
stuff
what i don't really know right is i
don't really know
i don't really know what we want to do
about tag order i was i was thinking
about this a little bit just kind of the
back of my head
and if you take a look now at the way uh
the tags
were working or whatever then you can
kind of see
like uh in here where we do the
tag hash stuff we take a bunch of tags
and we build them
into a sort of a 64-bit
identifier that packs like which you
know up to four tags and a category
together
uh and then and and to be honest with
you i'm not sure why we even bother with
the basic category anymore because that
could just be
like you could just have four tags and
the first tag is the category like these
things don't have to be
separate and so we should probably still
we should probably look at that stuff
a little bit more uh carefully later but
uh the biggest thing that i wanted to
point out is that the order of the tags
matters in this system so in other words
if you were because the hash is going to
hash these values
as one 64-bit value
um you're gonna end up in a situation
where you if you swapped the order so
like for example if i load up
one of these tags files you can see that
we have stuff like wall man-made wood
drywall or something like that
um and if you swapped that to like
man-made wall wood drywall it would be a
different
tag now i don't necessarily know if we
care
because we can just make sure we already
we always have those things
uh set up in a way that you know
uh keeps them what's the word i'm
looking for
we can always have those things set up
in a way that make sure they
uh are like we we never would tag things
in a way that doesn't go in in a strict
order
so that seems fine but there's also an
open question of whether we want the
system to support
uh doing that differently right
and the only reason
i i can't really say that i know of a
reason
not to do it one way like
you know vaguely if we just look at the
performance
uh characteristics of of how this thing
would work
like if i look uh at this hash function
that we have here you can see
how it's working is you get an aes
deck um of the seed here
and you know nominally the argument you
would make is like well you know okay so
each one of these takes four cycles
so this you know this this process here
where we do like
hash hash um into
x would be eight cycles of
cpu time to produce and so if you looked
at what you would do
if you wanted to make it so that it was
order independent
then what you would need to do is hash
each tag separately
and then like xor the results together
or something else that would be like
order independent
right um because
like xoring two things together and then
xoring a third
i believe would always it would always
swap like
they become the same right like and you
could imagine using anything that had
that property like
addition right um would like be the same
way like anything
where you like put a bunch of things
together
um and you just say like all right
we you know we know that the result will
be the same
that would make it so this would work so
the reason that this doesn't work right
now
in terms for ordered uh if you wanted to
be order independent is because the hash
is taking everything as one 64-bit chunk
and then producing a hash value that
encompasses all of that which is great
if we want it to be that way if we don't
want it to be that way
what would we do well we'd have to do
this for each chunk independently so
we'd have to like
decouple the hash into hashing each set
of
bits separately right
and the argument there would just be
the argument against that would be well
now if i had to do this four times
one for each tag that would actually
go from eight cycles right to 32 cycles
which seems like a really bad
idea but it's important to remember that
actually aes deck is
latency 4 but it's throughput one
so actually if we were to have four
independent hashes so the reason this
takes eight cycles is because
it uses the output of of the first one
as the input to the second one right so
this goes into here
so it has to wait four cycles and then
wait another four cycles before it can
extract
right because it's a serial it's a
serial dependency chain
build hash like build like munch the
bits munch the bits
extract the bits right but because you
can
actually issue one aes deck every clock
if we wanted to we could actually do all
of these
in the same at the same time
right so we could just do four aes
decks with a different hash values and
then four aes decks with different hat
with
you know for the second round of each
and all of those would overlap
so rather than going from 8 to 32
it would go like from 8 to 12. right
um
so you know it's it's really not
it wouldn't be a big deal for us to do
that said i'm just not sure
why we would do it right i don't know
what the point would be
of of actually going that far because i
can't really see
a whole lot of reason why we can't just
keep it this way
now one thing i will say is i don't
i i strongly suspect that a bunch of
these
tags are like not
necessary because things like orphan
don't do anything like um
there's there's just a bunch of things
where i'm not sure we really care but
i'm gonna leave them as they are because
there's really no
harm to it um but just to give you an
example like
you know if you have chair um and you
look at this you're like orphan man-made
chair sofa
like we don't need all those because it
just
it gets a little bit ridiculous right
and so
at some point here we're gonna have to
like deal
uh with this stuff and i don't really
know exactly how we want to but we're
gonna have to
organize the tags a little bit and at
that point we wanna think about these
like we don't need chair and sofa like
we're either gonna
put in a chair or we're gonna put in a
sofa so like you know we're
at the very least gonna do that um but
you know we just have to kind of think
these things through
and like you know and these would need
like these are
if these are both the same right they
would need like a variant here
um and and and they don't need they
probably don't need like
um
they probably don't need man-made
anymore
because it's like or or you know because
if it's the orphanage
like they're not gonna have in the
orphanage some other chair so
a lot of this stuff i feel like can just
be sort of simplified is i guess all i
mean
um like the man-made tag we probably
just don't need right because like
the orphan table the and the orphan rug
and so on
um can someone tell me like how to get
rid of that
uh also here's another thing for the
list of i have a little list of things
in four code that i want to fix
like you want to be able to just like
delete
um if you've if you've already done that
like if you were here and you go like
that you want to get rid of the comma
but you can't it like eats the whole
thing i don't know when you'd ever
actually want
that to happen
but i feel like there's probably some
way to fix that uh
i think i was using like my own version
of those before
and so like i never noticed that that
was the way that these worked or
something but i feel like there should
be
a one that actually deletes a token at a
time
and doesn't think of commas as somehow
not being a token
it looks like there's something there
that's like oh well delete
token but not you know not comma like
comma is not gonna be considered a token
or something right
um anyway so you know basically i'm just
just sort of blabbering about this but
you get the idea right so we need to
make sure all of this stuff
actually ends up meaning something that
we actually care about
um and you know i think it's roughly
sort of where it needs to be
but we'll play around with it
okay um so yeah
so moving on let's just take a look i
don't know
um where exactly we are in terms of
of actually like running stuff here but
i think what we were in the middle of
doing
at the end of last week was just looking
through all of our usage code here
and converting it to something that
makes sense
from uh the standpoint of the new tag
system
so if you take a look here you can kind
of see that we've got
two of these things here and we were
doing like an ad tag
thing oops
i've got to fix that too let's just fix
to it let's just fix that one so
because it it kills me every time um
let's go in here and just into our
bindings file so that was just because
j doesn't work everywhere
um so this
needs to work like everywhere in all
files not just code files was there
anything else that needed that
um
doesn't look like it so let me just move
that up
and put that in here
i think it would be jump or
there it is um so
also while we're in here what's the key
what's the key command for expanding the
compilation window
um because i would bind that to insert
as well
while we're at it so like something
would be insert like
flurry expand compilation
window or something
flurry toggle compilation expand
all right
um so let's go ahead and
see how that goes
and if i um
now go to here j works perfect
uh and also yeah
all right that's pretty cool um
okay so if i want to go to this add tag
function
um
so that's i don't
i don't know that we ever actually want
that anymore anyway
like add tag is probably just not a
thing we ever need to
do um
and like in here where we're doing ad
piece and that takes an asset tag hash
um i'm assuming that yeah like that
can just be nulled out
um and so i don't actually know
what happens these days let's just let
me just see
oh man so wait that actually works
how is that possible
that is so confusing that that works
like that that works
there's just okay
someone explained me this
in the land of the c plus ridiculous
nonsense
so you're telling me that if i
in here was to say
right like you know i don't know like
what's what's the highest warning level
i can ask for
w all maybe be it um
i'm not sure but like let's go ahead and
take like the most pedantic compiler in
the universe
um clang
uh and and let's let me let me just just
verify this so if i have a structure
um in here and i say like
okay like in x and then i say that i'm
going to have my square function
actually takes a foo
um so here's my new square function
so you're telling me that if i have some
other thing
over here and i say like
there's a foo right
like that and i would call the square
function on it
like so that that would work but so
would this
how is that possible because correct me
if i'm wrong
but like other stuff that would
obviously should work
if you had the ability to look up the
parameter of a function
and use its type information in your
language
wouldn't this work
i'm so confused right now
uh
what's the thing that i want to try we
went over this just the other day
it's the looking up in the space oh the
name place yeah
you
i'm so confused
yes so i i don't understand so they
have the idea that you can look up that
that
the compiler knows what type this must
have been
because the only way for it to process
this properly
was to look up and figure out what ad
piece was and then
know that the blank thing that it needed
was an asset tag hash right
so when you call something in a
namespace
how come it can't look that up in the
how come you have to do that still
right like what is the what is the point
of that
furthermore the the lookup looks works
the opposite way oops i didn't
mean to do that i meant that
you can do this because of konig lookup
right that will work
i should probably return here
like that will work it will go oh square
came from this namespace because the
parameter came through
but this doesn't
so weird
like it's the opposite one that i would
want
right like if i had to pick between
these two i'd want
i'd want um that one to work
and that one not to work just if i
thought about it for a second i'd be
like yeah if i had to pick
but that's just really strange that that
doesn't work um
but but this does like it does go look
up
like what that thing was god
c plus plus it never ceases to amaze me
like they always
manage to like half implement everything
it's so strange
like they just have no idea what they're
doing
well okay i mean i guess it's cool
though that at least we can do this now
i just always assume that you couldn't
do that because i'm like well if they
could look up by parameter then these
other things would work that i know
don't work
so i never even thought to try it but it
looks like it does now
which is great
are too bad they like they can only ever
half implement stuff
i guess
all right
yuck anyway um so
let's just go ahead and uh
go back to what we're doing and try not
to be too upset about how awful c
plus is all the time uh so we want to do
a tag hash here and you can see that
we've got like
body head item hand and whatever right
and if we look at the
um the asset stuff here you can kind of
see that there's like a thing that we
want to be able to do
and it makes me think like i probably
want so
so much the way this part here uh
allows you to sort of change or or i
shouldn't say
change to get uh the to
to get a tag hash
by using a basic category and then some
exists
existing hash i feel like we probably
want something similar
for like doing basic changes because
um well i mean i guess in this case we
it looks like we actually only need just
that one part so
yeah so i guess we don't have to worry
right now but in the future i'm thinking
we probably want one that allows us to
change targeted ones of these
uh probably in other ways i'm not sure
though so we may want something a little
fancier here
eventually for right now it looks like
it just works
um we just put like tag orphan tag hero
there
um and we leave the basic asset category
as like asset none um
and we can delete these now the that
part about it's
where we've got the um
like looking at the whether it's orphan
hero or whatever
i just want to look as i don't remember
even though we just looked at it i
wasn't paying
very close attention to that part of it
i just want to make sure it's actually
orphan hero yeah it is
so we don't really need this um we can
just get rid of that
and we can do the same thing here so we
can have
an asset tag hash that's made for
the hero and we can have an asset um
tag hash that's made for the glove
and in both cases uh we can just leave
the you know this part of it out this is
i guess glove with fingers
is what that is and so if we get rid of
that part of it
and put uh when we do this part here
we now just have to switch out what the
type of the asset is
so we can just do get asset tag um
get tag hash sorry
and just swap right so each of these
will just be a swap
on the thing on the type of thing we're
looking for but leaving the tags the
same
um so here's the like hero tags
and the glove tags oops
um and yeah
look at that look at look at how smooth
kind of stylish
all right um
you know also i should i don't want to
spoil the surprise
wait till next weekend um all right so
uh let's go ahead and
just do this for everything so
here's us creating stuff
and we're putting in a scenery tag
or a scenery asset type
and i don't know
what that would do because
anymore because when someone actually
goes to use this inanimate it's gonna
have to
set that part separately anyway
so i'm pretty sure we just don't care
about that at all right
um and so i'm assuming what we'd want to
start doing here
is passing in so in the gen crate entity
um
so in the gen create any macro here
right where it's getting this sim region
um i'm assuming what we would want to do
here is like pass
in the asset tags that we actually want
to use um
that would be my assumption and and like
uh like this crap here is
pointless and we don't need it um so i
feel like we can just kind of like fix
that
part of it um
but i don't know so let's
let's look at the calling code for this
first
and make sure that we have a reasonable
like you know sort of feel for
what we want to have happen there just
because i don't know
you know what that's what that really
looks like so presumably that's going to
be
in room gen um and
when we're adding these sorts of things
there's going to be like some kind of
call that we're going to make right
and we haven't looked at this code in a
while so i don't remember much about the
specifics but
we sort of have this idea that there's
just like a um a function
pointer um that's you know someone can
load up like what you're adding and then
you just call add on it and you don't
really have to know what you were adding
uh i think that was made to like
facilitate
use in here where we're we're doing tag
uh
we would add tags to an entity um sort
of after the fact
right so i think what largely happens
here
is this kind of code like you do in add
entity and then you add tags to the
entity
and at some point you then make a call
to actually
uh yeah like add tree tags or something
to like put the tags in that are like
what the thing was supposed to be
right um and we may still want
it to work that way i don't know uh
but we
we're changing from a system where the
entity has
a series of tags on it and then each
piece just has an asset type to having
each
piece of the entity can specify
everything itself so
i just don't know whether we need to
make something that then goes and stamps
the pieces
with those additional tags or whether
the reason we did it that way
was just a vestigial remain because
that's the way it actually happens
uh
because we want because that's actually
the good thing right
so just want to find uh where that
particular code
gets called for the callback and then
we'll look
um we'll look at that in a little bit
more detail
okay so if we look in here where we do
generate room
the create entity function itself
doesn't actually do this right so it's
going to be
like a helper function to
uh to that right that gets called and in
fact these
call add entity um
not create entity
so yeah like if you look at how this
works um
[Music]
none of these calls actually touch that
piece of it right they all
just so this would have been called like
earth at the earliest in the chain
um and that function
where's the macro here it is um
that gen create entity type
i'm gonna look for that here
all right so if we look at the gen
create entity type
you can see this function here is
yeah is like placing a record
that like you wanted to generate this
type of entity
and then presumably we just retire these
like in order
yeah okay so i mean honestly
we probably can just leave this working
exactly the way that it was
so like in here where we've got this
nonsense happening
we can just say look you get four of
these and
when you do the add tag function
we just record which ones you were
adding um
so like right here
um this code would still work the same
way
except for the fact that it wouldn't put
in this value
here right so
and where that would actually come from
i'm not sure because
we like presumably we want to still
have the like four wide
assets selector that's actually coming
from the
thing itself though so
the only thing that wouldn't work with
would be variance
so that part is a little bit
meow
so i i that's the only part i'm not 100
sure about
i want to look and see like what are all
the places where ad tag
is used for that um and i just want to
look and see
so like here's the part that's going to
be bad like
this is the part that we have to figure
out how we want to tackle
so in terms of adding like variants here
where we just want to be able to like
randomize
stuff
that part is the only part that like i'm
not sure about
so like if you imagine going back to
uh the andy gen stuff
i'm i'm sorry no in the entity code
right you remember how this stuff was
going
um
so we have like
we have this notion that like in here
when we come
into the update and render entities like
you know we process this stuff
and then we come down to this part where
we're going to do
the get best best match bitmap from
and we had this like facing direction
stuff that we were doing here yeah to
make
this match vector right
and so the thing that i'm like
the part that i'm just like not sure how
we want to do
is like how does that
how does that combine like in a sensible
way
uh with with the um
with the piece we had before
so that you know like the tag hash comes
from here and then the match vector
comes from here
and you know i'm just thinking that
through and i'm like so
so actually though don't we want the
visible piece to also have
a match vector
and this match vector is just
merged with that match vector right
because whatever that match vector is
supposed to be
like the at least the variant part
is supposed to kind of get shoved in
there
i mean at least one thing we would at
least say is that
the variant
the variant would want to be encoded in
in this entity visible piece part
if nothing else i think
i mean the other way to do it would be
to put the variant on the entity
but i'm not sure why you would bother
with that because presumably you would
like the ability to have the different
parts of an entity each be different
variants
of whatever the thing is that they are
without having them to all be the same
variant for any particular reason
but i guess i don't know
um
so that's a tough call and i don't know
the answer to that question
um and
if we look at something like variant
mapping
you know we could imagine going like
what's the total number of variants that
something has
and presumably it's you know um
presumably it's something like pretty
large right
yeah i just don't know i just don't know
so i want to think about this a little
harder
because i'm just not convinced that
particular part
is quite right um
here's the get asset from thing
um and if you
look at the match anything so like we're
going through
and we're like knocking out particular
matches so
if you look at this part of the code
like just this one part
um
you know i guess who's to say
that this actually shouldn't just have
remained
working the exact same way that it used
to
like it occurs to me that like
the best the like
the matching of the thing
by doing whatever is the closest one
maybe isn't totally stupid
because then you could just have the
variance still be
just a floating point number or
something you know
i'm just really not sure
i'm gonna i'm gonna go ahead and say
maybe we just do that
because if you think about it we've
completely gotten rid of the
entire problem we had before of these
things not being like
like they wouldn't be fast enough right
because this asset tag lookup will get
us to
a very small subset of the things that
we need
we can make the hash table as large as
we want
here and aes deck will give us a
basically perfectly scrambled
like we should have a perfect histogram
right that comes out the other end of
that
um
so i i want to say that we could just
have left this in in the interior the
same there
um i
want to say that i don't actually know
that that's true of course
um so let's see can we can we go into
github here how do you sign in
sign in we can go look at the old
code uh and uh and see what happens
where's the let's see
so if we take a look at
uh the the way this code was working
right
so in the you know in the actual
old version of the asset code if we if
we
go back a little bit right like you know
who cares
something like this uh
when we were doing sort of the look up
version
you know we use the weights and stuff
which we don't really need because
those don't have to be passed in they
can become from the asset because the
asset knows
what you would be matching on right
but if we look at the way this code used
to work i'm wondering do we just run the
same code again
um i don't actually know it's probably
in the h file isn't it
in which case this is not what we
actually want to do oh no there it was i
was like literally just there
so like if we look at this code
i wonder if we just keep this code and
get rid of the weight
i mean seems like we just can
it seems like that would just work
right and i don't know maybe i'm missing
something but
it seems like maybe we should just keep
that
it's a tough call but you know like i
said because it's sort of we're right at
that point where now we want to actually
do like the right thing here because we
have enough information to make the
decision
it seems like we might as well just
leave that and the reason i say that
is because uh the
so the usage of this
we would like the code that picks random
versions of things to not have to know
how many random versions there were
so that people can like add more over
time if they want to
and the code would still work right so
in terms of things that actually
want to have a variant value
or gradient values it seems like we'd
want those to be a thing
and then we can i don't think it would
really cost us anything to actually do
the best match because we're only
checking
like four things um
or ten things or something for that best
match
and that probably isn't too much based
on
the amount of horsepower that we have
and the low number of sprites we're
actually talking about
i wouldn't think that it would be
particularly expensive to do
and i and that could be wrong
[Music]
um
but i you know i just i don't expect
this would be that costly
i mean you know you're talking about a
pretty small number of
of actual like bitmaps on the screen at
any given time typically
and they can be baked so like when we do
like the grasses and stuff
when you generate grasses we actually
just do that
down to individual bitmap ids so at any
given time you can cache
the value if you were really worried
about the speed of it
so i might just say like let's try this
um oops
like let's just try doing it this way so
let's just say like uh hey yeah there's
like a match value that comes in here
and like there'll be a weight value
which is like the match any flags will
tell us
like what it is i guess so we'll we'll
um we can use that
feature to to like continue to do that
that checking um and so when we
when we do it we will do essentially
this
same thing here so we won't we won't do
this part obviously or any of that or
whatever
but uh we will keep this part
oops so we'll still do that
where we have a way to knock out
particular
so we will have a match any flags thing
and i guess what we'll do
in the case where we do a match any um
is and and this part we still always
want
right so we don't want to cons we don't
want to contin consider someone at all
who doesn't match the hash value if
someone matches the hash value
we then want to like sum up the
level of matching that we got right
so
we would do something like that um and
we would
keep the check index
as a result from the best match
right um and we would
want
something like this
yeah so okay
so it would just loop through the assets
in the tag hash
right um and it would look at each one
and then apply the same like matching we
were doing before
you know uh and so
the match vector e e index here
um is gonna pull that crap out the
weighted version
would not be a thing uh
and so we would get rid of that
uh and our only thing is here is this
looks like it's going
the other way around why
do we do a one minus here when we could
just take the largest value
what so what's going on there so we say
match vector and then we grab the tag
um the tags version itself
which um should be in the asset hash
right
like
so it's gonna be like
that
so we have a and b and
those are our two values that we're
trying to see like which one is closest
we look at the absolute difference
between the two
um we do like us map
we do like a periodic domain
mapping here and
again i'm not sure why we
do that because i don't know that we
really need to because we could have
just
mapped the thing properly when we
actually like we could have just f
modded the
direction properly so like this
seems stupid um
like this just seems ill advised like
that that doesn't really make a lot of
sense
but you know like okay we can leave it
that way for now
i suppose i don't know
it feels dumb um in fact
while we're doing this i i'm just gonna
go ahead and say like let's just
let's just not do that that's stupid um
so we have
these and we're gonna like
just say that's the difference value
right
so whatever the difference here is
uh we we add up all the differences
for anything where we at where we don't
match any
so this piece of code wants to actually
be negated
right like it wants to be like that
and so if this thing doesn't match
anything from this lane
then we actually add in the value here
that we that we've
got and then we do a total match um
add that distance so the match values
will get higher
as they get worse in this scheme right
um and so if the best match is lower
than the total match you know whatever
then then uh
we would take it and in order to make
that work right we want to be as close
we would want to be like as close to
zero as possible so if you look at the
way this works what we would want to do
here is just say like look just
decrease the total match value
as we go and so the largest negative
number right is what we want
um i'm sorry the
no that's not right
uh because this is still this is always
going to be the case we wouldn't get
away
with with that so what we want to do
here is say look we want the lowest
value so this would have to start out
at like the highest possible value right
um
and i think that produces what we want
so that still gives
us the the same basic idea
as we had before we switched the system
but now we get two important benefits
one is we can accelerate this part as
fast as we want so that the number of
things we're looking at is
remains hopefully quite low um but the
other thing that we can do
is now we also have exact matching on
tags which was a problem before so we
get exact match on tags first and then
the fuzzy matching
only happens which is why we can get rid
of like weight vectors
because now we know that these have to
match exactly so you start out narrowing
yourself down to just the things that
you actually care about
and then you can actually do the fuzzy
match based on
um like things like variant or whatever
and so if we then look at the asset
asset match vector types we've got in
here or face vector
variant now it makes a lot of sense so
now we're just going to set these things
to be
actual uh floating point values and off
we go so this can now return to the way
that it was
um and that will just work right
and hopefully
uh now everything will just magically
you know float around like a beautiful
morning spring
dove who has learned the beauty of
flight
you know uh so i think that's all
fine and i don't have a lot to say about
that uh tag range
i think could just go away now right
because
i think we should just fix that this is
garbage
it's not necessary um
let's see what's going on here those we
don't care about uh
going to the entity code so this stuff
is just stupid now
so facing direction the only change that
i want to make
is that it's supposed to do
um that matching we just
this part where we do importer pi
and then the one and the rap and blah
blah blah
so the the modulus side of things
um i don't know where what we've got for
modulus
do we have a modulus
[Music]
so we don't really have modulus in here
we've never actually done that but
it's not a particularly difficult
operation to do and i don't know that we
even really
need it because the facing direction
index stuff
um
i assume the output we're getting is
like
zero to two pi
i don't really know what we're setting
those two but you know let's
let's take a look so in the asset
processing
um side of things
where we do the imports uh we've got
like these tag array
nonsenses
where we set this kind of stuff
i don't really remember uh
when or why or how we did this
i just remember that we did this
so so this is is it
right and
it looks like
so it looks like if you read out the
facing direction stuff the way we're
attacking it before
it's it is literally just
the y index mod 4 times tau
so it's it's just doing that winding
so if we want this to match properly
uh i really think we can just simplify
this entire process right
so rather than what we're doing before
we had tag ranges so that we knew that
some were mapped periodically and all
this other garbage
i don't think we actually need any of
that um
i don't think any of that would be
necessary all we'd really have to do
here is just say
okay so the facing direction
is just going to be whatever the facing
direction actually is
uh and all we have to do is slide it
so that the way that it will match
against
something that ex that is uh pre like
some previously existing thing will just
map properly right so i think literally
the only
change we would actually have to make is
the end part of it so like if
the entity facing direction um
is less than uh or sorry greater than
if if you're in that last octant
so um if you're if you're
greater than a full circle
minus a quarter uh
or sorry minus a an octant right
uh define my eight
right so if you're in like the last
octant
of the circle and another way i guess we
could do that is just say
yeah like so suppose
we have an octant of a circle right so
7 8 would just be the number we're
looking for so we could just
put that in there it's not that
confusing right um so we could say if
you're in that
uh upper octant then that final one we
just want to make sure you're
gonna uh be at zero like you're gonna
map to the zero direction
region you know what i mean um
and so we can just just handle it there
and the reason that we
didn't handle it there before uh
is just because we wanted to make sure
you could
add in more of them but i i don't think
i really
care about that enough like
we don't have enough facing directions
that we're gonna have more than eight
in there anyway if that makes sense
um
i mean we're not gonna have more than
four
on the other hand i do kind of feel
stupid removing a feature that we had
before
it does feel a little dumb
you can see what we were doing here
right and so just the
the tag range for the for the facing
direction being tau 32
what it would do in here is it would
just basically with the old matching it
would make sure that the
yeah all right fine
i really i feel like we should remove
this but i'm just like
past casey wasn't wrong like that does
mean that the artist can then add more
of them
i mean they're not going to do that so i
feel dumb doing this
but it's like
it is the correct way to write that
feature right
i mean
arguably it's better
it's really hard to say like you know i
kind of feel like that should be removed
but it's like
i don't know like it's an intelligent
way to
do that thing this doesn't really cost
us anything
so like
i guess it stays i guess
i don't know so at that point i think
our choice is clear here which is just
to say that before we
load up any one of these we just say
that the match element
variant for this is whatever the piece
variant is
um so in the piece
the entity piece uh here we would just
have
a u32 for i'm sorry an f32 for the
variant
value um and i think that
that puts us right back at where we were
but with all the problems solved
i think i mean that may be a
little bit optimistic
certainly um you know i don't want to
do like an aircraft carrier mission
accomplished kind of a scene or anything
because
uh you know it's not over until
uh the fat lady runs the code but
i i feel like it's it's pretty close
um
all right so
uh yeah okay i mean sure
uh and in the original code here where
we're setting that
uh nonsense thing right uh we we
actually
don't need to do anything here
uh other than i mean i guess we could
still do it this way
there's we there are so few of these now
um that we don't have to to worry about
that anymore but um
has there any news hey ryan
you don't happen to know if allen ever
fixed the indentation do you
like are we getting a build with fixed
indentation or not
because i i i didn't actually know um
so this is not really tag range it's
like
a match vector
element right um
for e-index right so it's it's actually
it's not a tag type
um anymore and
it's actually a match element
which is a different thing uh
and so i think
oh yeah because it would be nice to know
when that was gonna get fixed if that if
that was gonna get fixed soon it would
be nice
um because it's really annoying like
there's no way to get the for loops to
look right like they go like that
which in a weird way does line something
up i assume it doesn't actually line up
yeah
so it's just for some reason it likes to
go an extra four in there
on parentheses it's always four extra on
parentheses
any anywhere you have parentheses as far
as i can tell nowadays
like if you do here you get the same
thing
right so it used to be that it lined up
dropped
with the parentheses uh which is what i
wanted and now it seems to be kind of
like
a weird like four plus thing like it's
got an extra increment
for reasons i don't i understand
all right so anyway um all right so that
match element
nonsense is is now uh in there
and everyone's happy about it they're
probably not that happy about it
uh and so i can get back to just the the
basic porting but
i think all that is now what i would
want
right that all seems good
um yeah so
what else so now we've got these things
where we're doing this ad piece call
and when we look at how entities get
added here
uh when we do
this so
the add entity call that adds it to this
region
at some point somebody probably bakes
these
tags and i think we would probably want
that to be something that kind of comes
in through here if we look at the gen
and entity uh i mean i i guess we can
still have it be
you know happen after the fact but when
you actually do this and you
you stick the entity in here
and you call this uh
um yeah okay so no one knows so we'll
see what alan says later
um so we may just want to leave this and
then we can stamp the
asset tags in later right for the pieces
as necessary that's one way to go
uh the problem with that is that it
doesn't give these functions really much
of an ability to like
kind of like fix to
to do what they would want to do here so
i'm thinking that like this call would
want to pass down
like you know here's the asset tag hash
to work with
uh like the base hash right and then
they can like
fuss with it right they can do like a
get tag hash
um and and pass the base hash there
right and that
that seems like what should be happening
um i would think
but i don't know oops i probably did
that huh
uh that to me seems like the smartest
thing to do
and we'll see like as we play with it a
little bit uh if that's actually what we
want
you know or not because i don't know uh
but we'll find out
i don't know we'll check it out
anyone here at frank zappa man
this is the central scrutinizer
so
a little uh scratchy
all right uh
so yeah i think basically now there's
really not much to this
uh at the moment because we're just
gonna
basically port all this code to the sort
of only slightly modified new way of
doing things
and then we've just got to go handle the
asset creation side
of things which will take a little bit
of work uh
but off we'll go so here when we do gen
entity at p
yeah again so this sort of stuff needs
to have an
asset tag hash
that gets passed in and
at least that's that's my argument and
i'm and i'm sticking to it
um
this code is not particularly good
anyway like we haven't really
done a whole lot of stuff with world gen
so i'm assuming we will probably do
more in the future with that
but uh so yeah
i would assume that we would want to
pass in
base hashes for like these things
because we want to be able to set like
what kind of monster it is
i i would assume but i don't really know
it might be that we weren't intending to
do that kind of stuff just yet
um and we'll see
so i think that's all good
[Music]
and
um yeah i don't think there's much else
to worry about there so here's us doing
some
stuff with like room generation and
adding pieces uh
so in this case where we're gonna we've
got like tags and stuff
that we add like later on right
so we've got like tree tags and lamp tag
and
and that sort of thing and we add
occluders here
in terms of adding this visual piece i'm
not sure
that we have to do that here so we could
in theory
change this to being something where we
like come down
and put this like over here right
um and
although actually that just those don't
actually look related so i think
actually
just this version right here where we
add them i think that's really the end
of it is
it's never really used other than to add
the cube uv layout right
so in terms of the
[Music]
the piece stuff it it really
it really doesn't matter actually so i
think that's actually the end of it and
and the really the question here is just
like
these tags uh that we have here
i don't actually know what those are
doing we got a lot of
these um
so the entity like has a bunch of tags
on it right
and and that's going to go away i think
so maybe what i want to do is delete
this
function so like that just goes away
uh and then we can
deal with the aftermath of that
uh as an easy way to have the compiler
like help us out
and so this is kind of nice right
because it gets rid of a bunch of
garbage that was there
that wasn't good um and
so now we can kind of look at this a
little bit
uh better right
so here we were looking to see whether
we were going to have like winter trees
or non-winter trees
or whatever and this kind of stuff and i
like i said we didn't we didn't really
have
uh a way of of working with these
particularly
uh usefully or not so in this case all
we really want to do is like kind of
randomly pick which one of these we
wanted now in this case we sort of were
just doing
some testing i think to say like whether
they should have uh a wintry look to
them or not
and that part of it which it's really
just like
we we only have like winter and
non-mentor trees so it's really just
like
a pit it was just a random choice do you
want to have a winter tree or do not
want to have one
these were only there to prevent picking
other trees which thankfully now
won't be a problem right
and so if we look at like the tags files
uh like this hht file right
and we look at things like where winter
was getting used here you can see it's
just like a tree winter it's like that's
the only
uh thing we actually have and the rest
of the things in there are variants so
so this part we do want
like that's a thing but tag
winter is just like either you add it or
you don't so
really all this would be is it's not an
add tag
right it's actually editing that value
of the match vector so
for add tree tags if we look at what
that's actually doing
um and again like we may
you know like we will see
but where if we actually go look at
where ad tree tags actually does stuff
you can see
like it's editing this entity here
where it just said like added the asset
scenery
we would want to pass in uh the correct
stuff for that
and where it produced variance right the
variance
i mean at some level unless you care
variance should kind of always be set to
a random unilateral value
right i mean so in some sense what we
would want to do is just say
okay like when you add a piece at all
right
so when you're in here putting one of
these in at all
presumably what we would want to do is
you would always
just generate some entropy and and you
know
and set the variant to a random value
for for almost every place that we would
ever do that like that's what we would
want to do
right and so in here the major problem
is we just don't have a source of
entropy
you know we don't we don't pass that
down and so when you have things like
this where you know it's the world
generator or whatever that would
normally be editing that
so when we do the the add piece calls
they're not really getting
uh access to the entropy now they kind
of it feels like they
they probably should have been uh in the
world generated side of things because
people don't
add pieces to things without world
generation
but you can understand why we might need
that for other things
and you you would need to make a thing
in here somewhere where you
[Music]
where you have one it needs to get a
source of energy from somewhere right
or you need to pass it in
so one thing we might consider is
expanding this notion
um and so and maybe that's what i'll do
so if we go look at like tag hash
we've got the these two things and
they're separate
so maybe what we want to do is kind of
make a combined
one of these and make something like
okay the tag hash and the mash
match vector and we combine those into
like one uniform thing
called like an asset match
you know um
i don't know something we want a struct
that has these two things
right it's got the vector and the hash
we want an easy way to like pass those
around right so it's basically 128 bits
of data it's
two floating point matching constants
and then a tag that you know can be
can be looked up on right and so we want
some way of passing those as a unit
i don't know what that should be called
um an asset
match info
bundle packet
oh yawn time it's an
asset match fun
fun matching times thing
um so i don't know what we would call
that
uh i'm just gonna call it an asset
matcher asset match
nugget asset
look up i don't know
don't care um so anyway inside here
if you know you would pass this um
this asset look up and it would be the
thing that
would be recorded and it would be like
variant and facing direction
would would both be in there um so we
could do something like that
the problem that i have with that is
it's still like fairly decoupled like
the facing direction
always comes from outside and the
variant
always comes from inside so
in a way we actually want this to be
specific
uh so we may want like an entity
piece like
asset something like that
and it's literally just this right
so that would actually be the thing
you'd pass in here
it's whatever part you would normally
have
inside uh the entity piece
itself and so uh
you know be like that
and off we go and this would be
that and
in the actual piece function here
maybe like
right
so you know
i don't know how you feel about that but
that's sort of
maybe something that makes some sense to
somebody sometimes
right and so in here we would say
[Music]
that uh we would peel those out as
necessary right so you would go
and you'd get uh out of the
asset oops
of the asset you'd get the variance um
and you would look up the oops the hash
uh like so and and that would be
you know that would be how you'd have
have uh fun
uh during the lockdown right so
i think that makes some sense and
i don't know why this is now complaining
but it is
and that's fine so if we're gonna pass
these entity piece assets in here uh
this would then
so that looks like so now it is
complaining about this for some reason
uh it doesn't know which thing to call
i guess is the problem um
out of these so it's got two of them
and i guess because they both take
the asset wait why does it not know
which one of those you would call that
seems pretty straightforward
um
how is that ambiguous i don't actually
know
um but let me just do this for one
second
and and see
fantastic
uh so anyway c plus being a gigantic
steaming pile of garbage aside uh let's
just take a look
uh at the rest of this and leave that
in its uh festering you know
pi in its festering steaming wreckage
uh so
looking at how we would do add tree tags
really what this would be
more like is like get tree tags
and it would do um you know
we haven't thought this through but you
know it would do like entity peace asset
uh as this return value and here we
would just do like get
tag hash um
and we don't care what asset type it is
because that'll get filled in by someone
else later
uh we know that we want the the winter
tag in here
um and i guess we sort of were saying we
want it sometimes
so we would either do
like that or tag none based on like a
random choice
um and i don't know like what kind of
choice that was supposed to be
uh we have a random choice function
right
yeah so you know sometimes we
we tack on the winter tags sometimes we
don't check on the winter tag i guess
is like the theory um there
and then in the variant side of things
we just
throw in a random variant as as
necessary
and that would be how we would get the
tree tags
and so then in here when we're actually
going to use that function
we just reverse the order in which this
happens
so when we call git enter to get
entity at traversable we would actually
just call like get tree tags
um to get the the tags we actually want
for trees in in this area or whatever
and presumably we don't need to actually
have the entity anymore because all we
need is the entropy source
because we're not actually editing the
end the entity at all we're just getting
the tree tags so that we can
call get end of the um
sorry gen entity at traversible
and that will now take an entity piece
asset um so the base
the base values now are always passed in
in terms of
that and these
generation calls will also be that
right um and then when
pieces are actually added to the extent
that it's necessary
um when we do these the base hash
is now actually in the like this is the
actual like
asset or base asset i guess would be
what it would be called
right and so you can get the base asset
hash if you want to um but when you do
add piece you're going to want both of
those
so i'm assuming we probably want
something
that will uh that will do this same
function
automatically for us but pass the
variant through
so here we would do something like um
you know just change asset
type or something like that
or change hash
so
we'd get the base asset we'd change the
hash as necessary but we'd pass through
the variant part
like unchanged you know what i'm saying
and i feel like that's converging on
something kind of nice now
like we're getting somewhere with that
um and this function is just a nonsense
function
it's like super simple right it's
literally just
um in
the the entity piece hash or any piece
asset thing right
you're just taking in one
and you're changing the asset type
uh like so
is it uh i can't remember in the or
sorry get tag hash i can't remember
that's a basic category is what it is
it's that
right and so all you're doing here is
saying look the result
is just whatever you passed in ex but
the hash
is going to be
modified to have
the new type right
so
whoops typing
so i think that should
solve the problem uh
and then what's our complaint here
cannot
change convert all blah blah blah to
blah blah blah
so ad piece uh is that a thing that's
like what's the problem so
it's just calling this one this change
hash is supposed
to uh
is supposed to return it into peace
asset right i mean it does it's right
there
um
base asset is base asset though
any piece asset base asset so that
should be right right because that's the
base asset is there
and that should produce the thing we
wanted right
and and add peace
is just height offset color
and then flags
although i don't know where that's
actually defined
it'd be nice if this said whether it was
a prototype or an actual function
so they're right there ahaha
so that is probably what c plus was
getting
hung up on right because of course c
plus has no idea what the functions in
your program are
unless you tell them ahead of time what
they all are
um you know heaven for fend so my
assumption is that
actually the thing where we had uh
this null asset we could now remove
right oops not that
one this one right i mean now it should
know
[Music]
yeah so
that's fine and
in here where we've got this nonsense
happening
uh now all we really would want to do
here i think
is since that
wants a variant as well
uh i would say like in much the same way
that we had that other utility function
so uh
you know
maybe we want you know do we want this
to be
you know i'm just
i'm just thinking right like i feel like
we want this to be that and
and you know shouldn't it shouldn't it
set like the variance
as well in case you had like multiple
hero over or something i mean it seems
like you would want to but
there isn't any actual
you know there isn't any actual entropy
um
flowing into that
um there really needs to be
a difference between a prototype and
a function and like and a forward
declaration needs to be listed in there
so you know which one you're jumping to
um separate issue anyway
uh so yeah like there's no entropy in
in a sim region although one might argue
there should be
because you know it makes some sense
but you know i feel almost like you
should kind of have it here now
it doesn't which is fine um
so we could just say that like if you
call this and it
and it's not doesn't have one of those
you know just gives you
it just gives you the thing back so you
know you're just like all right you know
whatever so there's a
there's one of these and it's like get
piece asset
and it's basically just the same as as
the get tag hash
um
call you know which is kind of annoying
and again it sort of the fact that
there's duplication there suggests to me
uh that perhaps we would want to
think about whether these should just be
welded into one type permanently
and i don't know
uh it's a legitimate question and i i
don't really know
um i haven't really thought about it
enough
yet uh to really i want that to not be
by made
um we need something
in uh that knows
that this is up here and
prevents anything from like
that will automatically scroll early
in this side of the window for people
who have
a webcam going right like that would be
pretty baller
um like a mode you know uh okay
so you know yeah like
something like that uh and that feels
all right to me
um
and and this would produce those entity
visible pieces
uh or entity um piece assets
that that will then go in here and these
are just change hash calls
right
so you know i'm okay with that uh that
seems fine to me
it does seem like this is this is
complaining about it
for some reason i'm not sure why we've
given it the tags it wants
right so it should be okay
but it looks like it's not oh we just
need change hash to also be forward
declared is all there is
to that um
all right so yeah
off we go um
that all looks fine
and what else what else you got
change hash already has a body i agree
with that i don't know why i duplicated
that twice
probably just because i don't know what
i'm doing
um and then we're good all right so that
seems fine
uh this is base asset
um this is
change hash
that space asset
um that is change hash
in both cases and base asset
and off we go
okay and that seems
good uh
and that's probably a good place to end
it for now
uh we can finish the rest of the sport
next weekend
uh
oh i just forgot to rename it i'm like
didn't i just do that and the answer is
i did but i forgot to type in base asset
okay so in here if we look at what's
happening on the entity where we're
adding these tags right these are tags
that are then
meant to like uh affect this
piece so i assume what we want here is
like a thing that we just say like okay
we're gonna try and like set what all
these tags are
um and
like i said i think i wanna do that next
time because this is pretty
straightforward to do but but we'd like
to do it
cleanly i don't want to get started now
and then we would just pass it to add
piece
here right so that seems pretty
straightforward and the same would be
true
um here so get like tree tags right
is is uh getting one of these uh
ndp's uh asset things and then
gen entity at traversible
um
why is that complaining that should be
correct right because it is now doing
um
although
it's out of order so
so this creator actually came
here right uh
and so that should actually work like
that and then this like tag lamp
right that would just get passed in here
so that all looks right to me now and so
i think all this will be pretty easy to
port i don't see any problems there
um yeah this should be pretty
straightforward
so i think that's converging on good i
don't necessarily know if i'm crazy
about the fact yeah this is pretty
straightforward to finish we'll do that
next weekend
i'm just not super positive
that there should really be like both
things like the tag hash not having the
variant attached to it like maybe it
just
should but i don't know
all right we'll do a brief q a and then
call it a day
can i do this yes
apparently i can
ah
uh so ryan i i told him about the bug
already though i was just curious if the
fix
was happening like i sent him
that bug last weekend so he knows about
it i just don't know if he knows
what is causing it
are asset tags used for something like
lister panels
no we don't
really use them for that we just use
them for accessing the assets
programmatically
the api you mentioned not existing
earlier for bulk sending packets
why doesn't it exist i don't know
because people don't i don't know
operating systems stopped evolving in
like 1985 or something
i guess because the api does exist on
special purpose hardware like you can
get
vendor-specific network apis
um that will do that
they just aren't you know berkeley
sockets never got updated
right and windows didn't extend it to do
it i don't know why
it seems really obvious to me that you
would want this
um and it doesn't seem like a difficult
thing
either but
[Music]
i think another problem is that people
don't seem to appreciate that like
function
calls are bad right
um i actually had this argument with
john blue the other day
um because he he doesn't think they're
bad either but i do like like if you're
gonna call a function
not only do you have to pay the overhead
of the function call which is bad
but the bigger problem is that it can't
be optimized so
if an operating system forces you to
call a function
every time you want to do something then
the number of times you can do that
thing
is inherently limited to like a very low
number right
so you're not going to do like a million
things a second by calling a function on
each one of them it's not going to
happen
right um and so
the
you want to specify data as much as
possible
and then the function call should just
be called like kickoff
right and you only call kickoff with
like bulk like you know every 256
or 1024 of the thing you're doing right
um and the application can like scale
that thing
i don't really feel like that's an
argument i feel like that's objectively
true like you can just prove it's true
just look at the code you can't do
high-volume stuff
by calling we we know this already from
graphics right
function call overhead like absolutely
destroyed
um like
batch stuff in the old date right like
the whole problem
with having to like batch up primitives
was because the function call overheads
are too high
right i mean that's the problem it's
like the doing that work whatever's
gonna happen there you want that
welded into the app side of things
because it can optimize away a lot of
the stuff that was happening right
and so you just don't code shouldn't
work that way like you don't want code
to call functions
when it could just write data you want
to minimize the number of times you
actually call a function
and just maximize the amount of time
that your code is just writing out data
because that can be like
optimized aggressively by you
or the compiler
so
thoughts on unity unreal good oh their
quality how would engine
made by you look like so that's too
broad of a question
mostly i think what i would say is like
broadly speaking
obviously i think there's some kind of
ridiculous stuff like that i've heard
like with the unreal engine taking
like a long time to build and you know
it's just very large and whatever and
you know
there's a bunch of things that are like
unwieldy and weird and all that
but on the whole if you just assume that
like the best way to assess something is
that the proof is in the pudding
it seems like unreal engine is probably
a good engine and
unity and godot probably aren't at least
not yet right
because the unity and unity and godot
have never seen like a real
like serious triple a's game
made on them ever right
so you know that while that might just
be for lack of trying
until you actually see it then you know
i'm not willing to
believe that it's really capable of
producing
uh you know a real game out of it right
like a serious
uh high stress on on the system game
whereas unreal there's been you know
countless
um aaa games shipped on it so you know
it
it does that right
um so like
i would say that's at least something
you can hang your hat on if you were
looking at an engine and going like what
am i going to use
at least you know that unreal is
capable of doing um
like a really like big
you know streaming and tons of assets
and
cutscenes and facial animation and
all that stuff you know
so
uh no orion the will of the wisp i
wouldn't consider
aaa even remotely right it's not even
like
it doesn't even it's not even really 3d
in the sense that it doesn't have to
deal with like
looking out over large horizons and so
on right
it's it's just a platformer right like
i mean that just doesn't bring in a lot
of
the more advanced problems that you
would face if you're trying to do you
know grand theft auto or something right
so
it doesn't mean you can't make good
games i've played like good games made
in unity right
like um i
i i i don't know maybe
not off the top of my head but i mean i
know that i have right like so it you
can make good games they're just not
broad expansive modern games
are not capable of doing i i've never
seen it done in unity like maybe you can
but i've never seen anyone actually do
it
and so until someone actually does i
would say that's kind of a
negative checkmark um
against that because it's like you need
that proof of concept like you want to
see
you know gears of war 17 or whatever
made in this engine so you know like
okay it can do that right like they've
worked out all of those problems
and i just haven't seen that happen in
unity or godot
so until they get to that point i would
say you know
if you're talking about picking an
engine the safer bet is probably going
to be something like unreal because you
know it
it's not going to like roll over and die
when you need to do whatever the thing
is that you're going to need to do
separately on ori and the will of the
wits i heard absolute
terrifying horror stories from the devs
on that
that like asset rebuilds were taking
like eight hours and things like
i don't even remember what like the
ridiculous things i was hearing but it's
like
anyone who's tried to make a serious
game at all
in unity i've heard really bad horror
stories from them about it
like looking at the presentation the
guys from inside did on
having to like micromanage the garbage
collector in unity to get the thing to
to like have a constant like it just
doesn't sound like a real engine to me
yet right
unity sounds like more of a thing for
like kind of like
small scale not
particularly large asset based
stuff right um
so if a game's kind of a little bit more
like has a lot less of those sorts of
things in it
um then then maybe uni's fine but i i
just wouldn't trust it
yet and they might get there someday but
it just like at the moment
i would say unreal just kind of seems
like the safer bet
that said i don't care so i don't spend
much time thinking about this because i
literally don't care
um but if you know if you had to ask me
data free like
you know you don't get to go evaluate
everything carefully but
you have to pick one right now i would
say just unreal for safety reasons
that's all
have you ever explained bit fields and
if not can you and as a solution today i
just saw that in old code
base to do the flags so you know i
i can sort of explain bit fields but
i can't really offer
much in the way of useful uh insight
there
only because i kind of got trained
out of using bit fields in the old days
because
so in in um
like in the code that you see us right
on like handmade here or whatever
you see us do basically what bit fields
were meant to do
which is like if maybe you want
a series of booleans but you don't want
to pay for them
you can pack them in as bits of a single
value so you can have like a u32 that's
32 bits and each bit can stand for a
different
boolean value rather than having bool
you know brackets 32
right for an array of 32 billions
bit fields were meant to like simplify
that process for you um
so that you can basically say like hey
here's the bit field and bit 1 is this
but 2 is this
bits 3 and 4 stand for this
and it's kind of cool but i got sort of
in the habit of not using it because in
the early days the compiler would not do
a very good job
of producing the code you actually
wanted
when you were using those so my main
reason i don't use them
is historical so
nowadays compilers might
generally always output
good quality code for bit fields
and if that was the case it's probably
dumb that i'm not using them because
they would read
um better but i don't know
and so the main reason i don't use them
is i just haven't gone and done that
work to see whether they are actually
usable
and interesting or not right
it may be that there are reasons to use
them now
it may be that there are still reasons
not to use them
um and like that's just something that
you know i haven't done and couldn't
tell you
but it's basically to get rid of like
little
like well you know what we just
literally did one in fact
um it's basically to get rid of
uh of this sort of code right
i mean you can see that this kind of
code is stupid right like there's no
reason i had to write that i could i
it's way better if i just said
here's a value that's got eight bits for
the category
um and then you know 16 bits for each
additional thing or whatever 20 what's
whatever the remaining amount is so
we might so two four so 14. so 14 bits
for these each of these and eight bits
for this
right like that would be way better
right so a bit field was meant to do
that
was meant to make it so you didn't have
to write this you could just say result
dot cat equals cat result.e0 and it
would do like the bit shuffles and
packing for you
right um
so i'm just not in the habit of doing
that because i find
uh that i like learned not to do it
long ago and then never revisited it but
so there might be reasons now
but you know
you can pack the booleans in one or two
bytes instead of taking up a byte for
each one
yeah but we already don't do that right
like we just use we just use actual ands
and ors
when we're doing bit fields right
so we don't really care about that it'd
just be different notation
um we don't really overtly use version
control
on the stream but it is updated to the
github right like the github does keep
track of the code i don't know if you
saw that today right so like every
time we finish an episode
the code goes up on the private github
um
and you know
we can look at it so if we want to know
what the code was on some day
you know we can scroll back and say like
all right on day
something something wow this is
inconvenient
wow you you couldn't list more than like
10 of these at a time
the web ladies and gentlemen we're
listing a thousand items is considered
like an impossible problem that you
would never try to solve
um so you know you can go to like one of
these things and you can say
like okay so here was the capturing the
light data day or whatever and
and we could like look at look at it or
whatever
um
so you know off you go
all right i'm gonna wrap it up um and
one last thing
is so also i would i would sort of say
separately
like in terms of like quote unquote bit
fields for networking
so if you're concerned about space for
networking um
and you're actually trying to do
something there that's about
minimizing transmission bandwidth
then actually what you what you actually
want is a compressor
so you don't want bitfields
um bitfields really have nothing to
offer what you want
is a compressor because compressors look
across
bits anyway and you'll just get a lot
better probably in most circumstances
than you know if you're gonna for like
bit fields
don't have anything really to do
with that but could explain the downside
of the json
data format well there isn't
so there's a lot of downsides to the
json data format but
it's not a bad data format like i don't
have a problem with json
in terms of the actual like structure of
json
the primary problem with json is that
it's not a very good
like i don't really think text data
formats are really that great
most of the time and so the major
problem with json
as a data format is the lack of
like the fact that it's not
binary is most of it right
like if if instead if it was based
exactly the same as it is right now but
it was binary and subtext
i would probably not have much of a
problem with it honestly
there's a couple things that they should
have done like they should have had a
way for you to pull out
repetitive types so basically like
instead of having to include in a giant
array
the name of each thing every time you
should be able to say
this is an array and the names are this
this and this and then every data member
is just the data
right so there's like rep repetition
stupidity in jstone that probably just
should have gotten rid of
um but like it's the text nature of it
that i think
is really the problem it should have
probably just been a binary format
and then if you wanted to have a text
format that you could convert that to
when you need to like edit it by hand or
something that's fine
but most of the time like text is just a
really bad idea and not just because
text tends to be bloated but actually
more because text tends to be
error-prone so there's just a lot of
stuff it's like
where people screw up the escaping of
things and you have to like
have all this weirdness in the parser to
like handle the escaping properly
um and you get all of these like
security exploits and round-trip errors
and like things that come out with weird
characters in the output and all this
garbage
because it's just because it was taxed
instead of binary right and if you just
had had it be binary none of those
things would have happened
so
why do you use 3gb bulls instead of
something smaller well we would
because usually we don't care about the
size that a boolean is because
on the stack like we probably just want
things
to work the way that they work and we
don't care so we just
think of all integers as being roughly
interchangeable
when we actually care about the size we
just make a bit vector so we just make
like a u32 that's like flags
and then we define one bit per flag when
we actually care about the size
right so the way to say it was either we
care about the size or we
don't when we don't we just leave them
32-bit because that way we don't have to
worry about whether there's weird like
okay at half
the compiler is now thinking about the
fact that this thing had to be a byte so
if it sets
a 32-bit value equal to the 8-bit value
it's got a truncate the top
which may be slower on certain blah blah
blah blah blah blah right we just say
look everything's 32-bit
so the compiler doesn't have to worry
about it and if we actually care
about the actual size of something
uh then we use a
bit like a bit vector so that we know
that bulls just take up one bit
a piece right have you heard about z
standard
developed by facebook um you know i've
heard about it a little bit
at the moment like it's pretty obvious
that rad has the best compression
technology and it's like drastically
better than things like z
standard so i don't really tend to go
look at like how
much worse is facebook's compression
than raz or something
like i might if i cared enough about it
to go look but
you know since i know it's kind of
inferior tech i haven't bothered to look
at what it actually is
all right let's wrap it up
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
throughs at home you can always go to
handmadehero.org and pre-order the game
it comes with a source code so you can
follow along
um i will be reposting the schedule and
i also
uh i noticed that yeah the embedded
episode guide while conveniently on the
front page now
that allows you to search for old
episodes and stuff like that and so on
um i know it's a little bit hard to use
because it doesn't seem
to have a full screen option in here but
i will try to add
um a button in here for you for full
screen at some point
uh so we'll take a look at that but
otherwise yeah handmadehero.org if you
need any resources if you want
to pre-order the game gas source code if
you want the schedule or if you want to
look up
stuff that happened on old episodes uh
it's all in one place now
um and i'll try to get that updated with
a button for for everyone
uh and we'll leave it at that that's it
for today
uh see you all back here probably next
weekend keep an eye on the schedule if
you want to know when uh until then have
fun programming and i'll see everyone on
the internet
take it easy everybody