hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream and honestly you
know one of the things and this is kind
of what I was lamenting just a minute
ago on the pre stream honestly one of
the things that kind of try to do and I
forget to say this a lot but it is kind
of one of the big reasons for
programming the way I program on
handmade hero is just to try to make
programming to be fun instead of a
Drudge you know a Drudge fast and i find
that for me a big part of making
programming fun is the fact that i am in
control of everything and i don't have
to worry about like what might be
happening in some library somewhere or
how something's being filtering this
stuff it's like it's all stuff that I
can go and I can fix and that kind of
helps and it also is you know it allows
me to kind of dive into stuff when I'm
interested in I can be like I'm kind of
interesting this I'm gonna go play
around with this and see what the deal
is here and that's kind of exciting and
fun and so I like that and what we've
been doing lately is kind of fun too
we've been making a debug user interface
for ourselves which is kind of just
really my excuse to show how to do some
simple user interface programming
because I know we won't really have much
of a chance to do that on the rest of
handmade hero there's really no reason
for it in the game and so what I'm doing
right now is sort of showing like okay
if you want to build some user interface
elements for your own use here's how you
would do them and so just doing kind of
the basic simple way that you could
construct some and give you a little
sort of like prime around like okay here
are some ways to think about you I stuff
and I'd like to jump back into that
because it was kind of fun and so I'd
like to explore a little bit more of
that so let's go ahead and do that if
you would like to follow along at home
of course if you've pre-ordered the game
on handmade hero org today is day 1 99
so you want to unzip day 198 source code
into a directory and that's what I'm
working with now so let's go ahead and
kind of take a little moment to refresh
here so if you look at the way this
stuff is working now it all kind of
works relatively nicely we have a
situation where we can sort of interact
with our our code and stuff here we can
make little debug variables that come
out that we can modify and we also have
the ability to insert other things like
profilers and stuff
you know in here that have kind of
special views and stuff like that and we
even have like little interactions that
we can work on Oh or maybe not looks
like we broke something looks like we
broke something at the end of the last
stream there it looks like the resized
profile thing does not always give a
valid variable there so that's kind of
interesting I'm not entirely sure why
but let's take a look here and see what
actually is the problem there so if I
take a look inside here we are in debug
interact yes and it is interacting with
this guy VAR profile what is VAR so far
is null at the moment which i assume is
just that we got into a resize profile
somehow without setting that VAR or the
VAR got cleared and i just kind of did
some stuff at the very end of last dream
and I suspect I probably broke it which
is actually kind of good to be honest
because I think I hinted at this at the
other stream there are some things clean
up why's that we want to do here and one
of the reasons that you want to do them
is so that you don't get a bug like this
or I shouldn't say so that you don't get
a bug like this because obviously you
don't really probably care if you get it
a bug like this because it's probably
not super hard to fix but more to the
point just to make it easier for you to
manage sort of the state that's
happening in here because it starts to
get a little unwieldy as you can see and
it's just it's just nicer if you can do
it but I want to go verify that we know
what the bug is first before I fix it
because I would rather not do some
changes that will potentially fix that
bug without knowing what the bug
actually is because we may just mask the
bug at that point and I don't like
having a bug that you know may have
gotten mastin and we don't really know
it it's kind of lurking in there so what
I want to do is I want to take a look at
the resize profile thing you can see
here that the only way that you could
really set it to resize profile is is if
the next hot gets set d'ivoire so I just
want to take a look and see what's going
on there why are we getting into a
situation where
next hot is not being set properly right
like why is that actually happening so
let me take a look and see if I can see
why that is the case it looks like so we
so we are presumably setting this stuff
here yeah so I mean we're setting our
debug site hot hot interaction drag
hearty so the only thing is though that
just sets the hot variable and when we
begin interaction you can see you know
what this is the problem right here when
we made this modification to the code
right and we accept a new interaction
we're not accepting the variable
potentially it looks like that we should
be accepting right because we're looking
at debug hot and that sort of stuff here
and you can see that that we in this
case set it but we don't set it in this
case so it never actually accepts that
variable in the case of the hot
interaction so really you know the other
thing we could do there is potentially
say something like you know that which
is to say if the interaction got set we
always want to set that variable so I
might just I might just go ahead and do
that and that's that's the bug that we
had there we just were a little sloppy
when we change that and that's fine so
yeah so I think we should be fine now
yeah so there we can pull those around
we also have the ability to kind of pull
off things here and drag them around and
stuff like that and so like I said we've
kind of got the the beginnings of
everything here and we've got like the
basis of stuff but it's still like kind
of janky and ugly and we don't really
have every we kind of haven't done the
refinement necessary to make this really
particularly usable like it's kind of
just got the beginnings of it there but
it's not actually what we want so what
I'd like to do is start kind of like
poking down through this a little bit
more and just start to clean up the code
a little bit and make it into something
a little more usable so the first thing
I want to do is we have this sort of
loose concept here where we've got your
this notion of like what kind of
interaction is happening and who is it
happening with but it's kind of all
implicit in all these things and we have
you know the interaction and what the
hot interaction
as men who were interacting with and
what the hot variable we could have like
a lot of stuff and what I'd like to do
is sort of take a step back there and
just figure out a good way to to
formalize that so that we we wrap it all
up into something a little more logical
and what I want to point out here is
essentially what we have is we have like
sort of a a coupling we have like we
have we have sort of like a relationship
here where the debug interaction that's
going to happen is obviously going to
happen to something so we sort of have
like an interaction and like the
parameters for that interaction and so
we want something like you know a debug
interaction params or something like
this we want to create a structure where
we can bundle these up right so we can
say what the interaction is and we can
say like what the variable is that it's
interacting with something like this and
we can even say you know in there we can
say well maybe it's happening with one
of those or maybe it's happening with
one of these right and so we can sort of
say like you know what no matter what
you might want to put in here we can
allow you to interact with that thing
whatever that thing is we can make lots
of different things so different
interactions if they want different
things can interact differently and
that's you know totally fine so if you
want to do that we just need to come up
with a name for this and not for exactly
what it would be we could call this a
debug interaction and this a debug
interaction type that's one way to do it
so we could say something like that and
then the debug interaction that we were
talking about before is really just the
type of interaction but the interaction
itself involves whatever those
parameters actually were right and so
you can kind of see those here so if we
did something like that then we can we
have the opportunity to like kind of
clean these up because then we have the
interaction and then we also have the
hot interaction and then we also have
the next hot interaction and now we
don't have all of these different things
that are happening down here they're
kind of confusing and weird right those
things can kind of go away and now we're
sort of back to something that looks a
little more sane right now we can just
kind of see we've got three things we've
got whichever the one is that kind of
when we do our
testing pass this is the thing that was
like you know the mouse was over here is
the like last one that we confirmed was
something that we want to consider being
like hot at the time and here is one if
we actually if the user actually pulls
the trigger on it so it's like three
tiers and now they're kind of really
nicely labeled and you can sort of see
exactly what's going on so I want to
start by making that simplification and
once i make thats implication i'm going
to have a bunch of compile errors and
i'm just going to kind of pile sort of
like go through those interactions I'm
sorry go through those compile errors
fixing them to work with this new
structure that's really all I'm going to
do so let's do that now so here we are
in draw a debug menu and you can see you
know what I'm also going to do I'm going
to stop this guy from blanking all the
time since he seems the screensaver of
course really really really wants to to
have them you know it's it's whole
situation occur there all right there we
go turn that off I want to be able to
see the chat if that makes make sense so
here we go we've got this is hot concept
here which is saying it just wants to
know whether this variable that we're
looking at at the moment is the one
that's being like hovered and so what I
want to do there is I'd like to again
just sort of formalize this a little bit
more we now have this concept of a debug
interaction and we know what the hot
interaction actually is right so what we
should be able to do now for is hot is
we should be able to say something like
well okay you know for this particular
item I do I know what my interaction
would be right I know which interaction
i'm talking about here in terms of the
is hot item color thing so i want to do
is basically say there's an item
interaction there's whatever interaction
there would be in the item right and
what I want to do is I want to
initialize that to be whatever it is
that this thing would normally you know
what whatever would normally happen here
and I think that's like this guy right
this is the one that sort of saying
there's no specific interaction but
here's the variable right so here's the
type of interaction it's one of those
and here is
the variable that it that's involved
just call that bar and this hierarchy so
once I've made that item interaction
then what i can do is instead of this
thing where I'm sort of doing an ad hoc
comparison here I can do something like
say you know interactions are equal and
I can just say whatever the one is that
I was talking about the one that I would
be does that match the hot one here
right because if it does then I am hot
if not then not and that also means that
i don't have this situation anymore
where i have to sort of think about what
the different you know what these sorts
of things are happening we can just sort
of let that happen in that in this sort
of predicate function right okay so yeah
let's go ahead and take that out so
we'll just assume the fat guy knows
whether or not what I'm talking about is
about to happen or not and it will
return it so it can work that way and
then in here where we've got counter
thread list we're going to do well let
me let me actually just go ahead and
implement this simple version of this
first so that we have it there like so
right and so that's just going to take
two of these guys it's just going to be
like you know a and B and the result of
that's just going to be you know if the
a type equals the V type like so and
then we're going to assume I suppose if
these are all going to be pointers for
now we can assume that we can just do
something like a test here so we don't
even have to really crack these out we
can just do something like and a dot
test equals V CAST or you know generic
something like that right
so assuming that those are true then we
assume that things are equal and let's
see so if we move down here what else we
got so in this state we have the exact
same situation right and you can kind of
see what I'm doing is I'm like moving
this stuff up so that it's more related
it's like instead of having an ad hoc
testing and then setting regimen where
we kind of go like let's test
something's ad hoc and then we'll set
something as ad hoc I'm actually making
it so that the thing that gets tested is
the same thing that gets set right so
once I test this in here what i would do
is say like oh if i'm in this rectangle
then the next hot interaction is going
to be my item interaction so that whale
again we get rid of that redundancy and
just say like okay this is the item
interaction and that is what we will set
here right and the same thing would be
true here like the next site interaction
here equals you know that item
interaction so then again you don't have
that situation where there's what kind
of multiple people doing multiple things
that may conflict or not line up so then
the only real thing we have to do now is
do that again for this guy because we
have this size box so this is like our
size interaction and the size
interaction again is pretty wrote it's
just saying the exact same thing in
terms of the variable it's going to
interact with the variable not
definitely a fused with the variable
like I guess we say interact with a
variable right so we're going to do a
resize profile think here and we're
going to have it so that so that that
interacts this way okay and then we've
got you know the standard stuff that we
were doing before what we want to do now
when we test that is hot again we want
to just do interactions or equal instead
and in fact you know what I suppose the
other thing we could do is interaction
is hot we could actually have an
interaction is hot called which actually
just takes the debug state itself and
then the item interaction and so we
don't even have to think about the fact
that there is a hot interaction we can
just say interaction is hot and expect
that it
ohs the fact that there is a debug state
and how to get the hot interaction out
of it right and so that would be
something that just thunks through to
interactions are equal bypassing debug
stayed hot interaction and and letting
it do that comparison you know so if i
do that i could say interaction is hot
right and get rid of that whole
situation that's happening there which I
don't like and now say that I just want
to say if the size interaction is the
hot interaction then I know that I'm
going to have the colors like so and
that all is pretty happy and fun again
just cleaning it up here next hot
interaction is going to become this size
interaction in that case and then i'll
go ahead and and recompile all right so
here we are this is our kind of little
hacky code i guess that we did that we
haven't really talked about much yet we
were just kind of throwing around making
sure we could move that stuff so in this
case it's the sack same thing again
right the exact exact same thing and we
can kind of see here we didn't even
bother because we were so lazy and it
was so janky to do we didn't even bother
doing a highlight for this guy but again
now it becomes a lot easier to do a
highlight and I think it will become
easier still at a second here but we can
again just call is hot interaction or
try to what is it is interaction hot
sorry whatever it is what is it I don't
even remember now hot interaction is hot
if interaction is hot and I can pass
this move interaction i guess that for
doing here if that interaction is hot
we'll go ahead and do it there was not
so there we go and I just need again to
make one of those interactions so here's
the move interaction and it's just going
to store again the stuff that we were
storing before it's just these two
things here and this time it's going to
store that hierarchy guy
slide it right like that and that's it
and then this is actually going to do
next hot interaction it's going to do
the move interaction ok so moving along
now for these guys this this all needs
to work slightly differently now right
we've got hung interaction it's hot in
debug state hot interaction type right
so assuming that that's the case then
what we want to do is we want to just
accept the whole interaction and that
gets us out of this business right here
where we had to like pick up stuff
because now the interaction type and the
thing that it's interacting with are
bundled together which is what we wanted
it's now like a logical thing that
doesn't have to be like fuss with in
that way so if the hot interaction type
is a thing then that's great if the hot
interaction type is not a thing but the
hot interaction actually does have
something to go with it in fact now that
I think about it you know if you really
at the end of the day we probably just
want to make this be something a little
bit smarter we could actually get rid of
all of this logic I think probably for
the most part you know what I'm saying
if I'm looking at this here I feel like
it's probably something we could do yeah
to be honest we don't really need I
don't think to do what we're doing here
because like where we've got this sort
of toggle value and drag value and that
sort of stuff I think probably all we
need to do there is do something like
this right we could just do something
like okay assuming that there's that the
hot interaction actually is some kind of
interaction right of some kind and I'll
just get rid of this thing here let's go
ahead and do that
and what is happening here this is if
the hot interaction type otherwise we'll
just go ahead and send to enough okay
there we go so if we want to do
something like this again just trying to
clean this up in stages if we want to do
something like this what we could say is
you know oh if the debug hot interaction
type is equal to some special thing
which is like you know an auto detect
right so if it's like you know auto auto
modify variable or something like this
so if we see that that's the type then
what we'll do is we'll switch on
whatever the hot interaction variable
type is and we'll set the hot
interactions type to be whatever it
should be in that case so it just kind
of like puts it into a more tiered
approach where basically we're saying
like okay we're assuming that someone
will tell us whether they want to be in
an auto modify state assuming that they
do want to be we'll go ahead and do that
right and similarly we'll just assume
that oh if if it is auto modify variable
then also will lift that all too i kick
in where it will go ahead and change the
tariff value if we're in that state and
then at the end it will just always
accept whatever that hot interaction
actually was right so that seems totes
totes reasonable to me and now all that
means is that when we set we're setting
none before over here right where we set
it to debugging interaction none for
variables what we actually want to do is
just set it to auto modify variable
right and that seems that seems totally
reasonable why is this get set go get
set it interact as well yeah right okay
okay so that's all good I think and
let's go ahead and fix that guy up that
looks nice
and right there we go so that's fixed
debug and interact assuming that the end
interaction type is not not then we are
going to see I guess what's actually
happening here and I suppose really this
should this should really be like a
switch I would assume where we take a
look at what's actually happening here I
feel like because this is essentially
this is the entirety of our UI code
right like this is basically it this is
what does all of the sort of the
interactions here is these three
functions and so what I'd like to do
there is just go like okay we only have
a few things that we want to do we want
toggle the pool or expand the group on
the end of it so we probably want to do
something like okay whatever the type is
you know there's there's only i guess
like two things that we care well
there's only one I guess that we care
about it's this one but we might have
more later so I just want to leave that
you know kind of a kind of thing open
right and then in here we could do
something like this we just said like
all right let's grab the bar out from
the interaction XO poops and then we can
go ahead and work on that as well right
that all seems fine and then in the
default case I guess you know we don't
really have to write in all the cases to
be honest with you I think a lot of
cases don't need to have any writing
happen but I don't know it's hard to say
we're going to leave it that way for now
we're just just because we probably
should all right so let's see we've got
interaction generic we're going to clear
this guy out dragging hierarchy doesn't
exist anymore and so that I think is all
good ok so moving on we've got our debug
interact when we're taking a look at the
interaction here again we're going to be
doing exactly the same thing as we did
before we're just going to say all right
if the interaction type is not you know
nothing
we're going to go ahead and play with it
here we don't necessarily know that we
have of our but we can pull the bar out
anyway because I guess people who use it
will know to use it people who don't
will know to not and so if we have here
like you know our move hierarchy for
example now that doesn't have to be
using some blind other function here in
fact we can also get to do this where we
pull out the debug hierarchy as well
it's variable hierarchy like so we could
say that where we have the variable
hierarchy and then in here we can do you
think we can go ahead and grab that out
as well and so now we know that we're
using the hierarchy that was actually
associated with the interaction itself
we don't have to have some kind of
mysterious extra global variable there
and that's all good so the same thing I
think would probably go for here we
would use in you know if the hierarchy
is not a thing yet then we would say
that that the debug variable hierarchy
oops the debug state interaction
hierarchy is going to be equal to this
new one that we create right like so and
then we will also set it equal here and
then this guy can just work off of that
right so that's pretty straightforward
don't think we've got much else to do
actually we're kind of giving at the end
of this porting when we add the variable
reference again that's going to be the
interacting VAR i guess so this is like
turns it originally has a VAR and this
turns it into interacting with the
hierarchy itself which is kind of
interesting actually I kind of like that
anyway I'm sorry interaction
alright so what else we got here we've
got debug state this is just this right
here is just setting the next ought to
be the hot so this is just the hot
interaction becomes the net hot
interaction that's that's really it we
don't need any of these other things now
I don't think dragging hierarchy I don't
know if that actually got said anymore I
don't think it does no it doesn't so
that's good and this stuff can all is
just like a clear right so the next hot
interaction is just going to be this is
just going to be cleared out every time
and these guys are all just now taken
care of by that one clear I think so
let's see where we're at with that like
just see if everything still works after
all that manipulation looks pretty good
right alright so we got one here that's
not good and that is that it's trying to
print out some kind of variable that
doesn't actually exist yet so that's
probably not a good thing say the least
so that looks like and let me take a
look at what actually happened there
during that ad so when we do the debug
ad variable reference we use the
interaction variable cure and I'm
assuming that after we do that ad
hierarchy it does not like that very
much although i'm not exactly sure why
so we add the hierarchy with the root
group and then we go ahead and and fuss
with that so I wonder if it doesn't
quite realize so this is this is kind of
dumb what I did here this is actually
not correct at all now that I think
about it this isn't going to work
because this is this tear value thing
actually needs to do something on the
mouse down because otherwise it's never
going to know because this is just a
shadowed variable this is the same
variables in the union right so it's not
going to work at all now that i think
about it to have both of those be to use
that in the sort of hacky way that we
were using it before so what I should
really probably do is when you do the
begin interaction that's when it should
actually occur so when you do the begin
interaction and it sees that the
interaction
right is is that type right so it'd be
something like it'd be something like
this right it'd be switch on the type
well honestly we'd probably want to
still do this part here and then after
we'd already decided what the type was
then we just say okay of the interaction
types that we've got assuming that I
want to do the tear value one then we're
going to do sort of this this thing here
right that's actually the cleaner way to
do it that actually makes a lot more
sense because that's actually doing the
thing instead of like lazily evaluating
a variable which isn't you know useful
at all so if i go to terror value then i
will create the new group that we're
tearing off i'll add the reference to it
right and enough we go but these are all
on the hot interaction at this point
although i guess you know actually may
be able to do it on the regular now so
i'll say except the interaction at that
point ma'am no you know what i like it
better on the hot I do like it better on
the hot I think it's a little bit better
that way okay so there we go so I think
that's actually what I want to do that's
that's a much nicer system there and
there we go so there I've pulled out the
renderer and I can drag it around and
all those other sorts of nice things
I've got the profile here and there we
go and I can drag that box as well and
that's all good so I think that's
reasonably better now you know things
are starting to clean up a little bit
they're not squeaky clean at all in
terms of like things that I might want
to sort of have compressed out just to
get it a little more a little more
thorough but definite looking better
than it was so at this point the other
thing that I would like to say is you
know we've got that sort of sizing
interaction and I feel like that sizing
interaction is probably something that
you would want to have in a more generic
sense as well and so one thing that I'm
wondering is like you know if we think
about it here
we could do something like this right
where the resize profile guy and in fact
I think there's going to be kind of neat
when we actually think about this year
so if this resize profile right it
doesn't really have to be called resized
profile in theory it could just be
called resize I suspect and what it
could do is it could just say instead of
losing the VAR it just uses like the v2
that's in the hierarchy if that's in the
interaction itself like this and it just
kind of goes like okay like you know I'm
just I'm just operating on some some
position right and I don't care what the
position actually is like doesn't matter
you know right i just want to write an
interaction on a position like this and
then it will just work no matter what
position it actually is that i was
working on and similarly you know like
move hierarchy for example could do
exactly the same thing it could just be
called move at some level and it could
just work on that p as well like this
you know so that seems like free
reasonable and it also seems kind of
reasonable because then you could just
get rid of terror value all together if
you wanted to and you could do something
like okay so you know let me go ahead
and make these guys so we've got resize
and move which are just generic
operators that just operate on stuff
that you know can tell me what position
it actually wants me to do there and
here i can just say like okay this is a
resize action and i'm just going to set
the position to to resize that profile
dimension right or whatever it's called
I don't remember what the actual thing
was called in there it's something like
that just do something like something
it's called dimension oh I sent why did
I spill it all the way out and we don't
spill it all the way out anywhere else
yeah who knows so anyway we can just
take the address of that right and then
we can interact with that guy and then
that's all fine right so similarly
got move hierarchy here and we could
just change that to be moved we don't
have to actually specify that the
hierarchy and then we can just say that
whatever the hierarchy is your IP is
we're just going to take the address of
that and then it will just work you know
so all I have to do to make that happen
is change these guys to like actually
pointers since now it's not an actual
thing that we're working on it's
actually just a yeah it's actually a
pointer to a v2 but I think at that
point it just works with whatever you
want to throw at it right so now I can
just do something we're like okay I'm
moving well or just won't work at all
there's also that is another nice thing
that's pretty great oh whoops that's
because that I don't know why I did that
that's still supposed to be d-mass p
folks that should not have changed so
that's pretty obvious why that does work
yeah if you had the thing to itself
turns out it's not a very good thing so
that that should be fine because that
means now like I said we can do kind of
whatever we want there let's let's get
this one working as well so now what I
have to do to make that one work since
the move already works just fine the
only thing I have to do now is terror
value doesn't have an interaction oops
doesn't have an interaction anymore so
if i go to tear value when you actually
start carrying it what we would say is
like okay the hierarchy that we add here
this hot interaction hierarchy that
thing it's uip is going to start out
being wherever the mouse is and then i'm
going to change our hot interaction
right in fact you know what you don't
even have to do this it's just debug
variable hierarchy here where we just
get the hierarchy briefly we then say to
the higher cuz you IP is wherever the
mouse started and then we say that
actually what the interaction is
actually going to be about is not going
to be a terror value interaction it's
just going to be a move interaction so
it started off as a chair it becomes a
move and the thing that it's moving you
know I'm saying is the is the
hierarchies uip that's the like that
that's the actual vector type it's
moving
right oops okay insert an errant
character there alright and so now when
we grab this you can see that it works
exactly the way it did before but now
the move is actually moot it's actually
moving generically so now anything that
we wanted to move could be moved that
way right like we don't need a specific
thing we don't need a specific one for
hierarchies versus anything else that
maybe we would want to move in the
future right which is kind of nice and
the same is true for resizing so if we
added another thing here another type
that kind of wanted to have that sort of
thing to it we could do that right and
so lets you know just just for sake of
argument I'm just going to show what i
mean by that because it may be a little
obtuse what I'm saying and so what I'd
like to do is kind of extend that notion
up look like just extend that notion 11
up so let's say it for example we had
debug variable that actually was like a
bitmap or something I and so like you
know what I'm what I'm talking about is
in here if we had a bitmap ID as one of
the variable types right because you
know we got these bitmaps and all that
sort of stuff so suppose we had like a
bitmap ID in there and one of our debug
variable types wanted to be like a
display of a bitmap or something and so
I guess you know now I think about too I
probably want to make it so that this
thing for the bitmap ID is a little bit
more expressive than that I probably
want to do like a debug you know bitmap
display or sometimes something like that
so it's got like a bitmap ID and it's
got you know like a dimension or
something or an r32 which is like size
or something like that you know what I
mean or I guess I should say of each you
it's like sighs
you know and so if I want to do that i
could go ahead and say like this guy's
in there we've got a bit map display and
you know and maybe this thing has other
stuff like you know Alfred I don't know
something like that weird like it says
whether or not to use the alpha channel
or something like this who knows what's
got in there and what we want to do is
be able to display bitmaps and so what
we do is we'd go into here where we're
displaying other things and we've got
like our profile counter or whatever
right and when we display this stuff
we'd have another one that's like the
bug variable type and it's going to be
this fit map display guy and I suppose I
probably need a type in their form as
well so you know this is like the bug
variable type fit map display and so we
throw this in here and we say we've got
a bit map display and then what we do is
we go all right whatever the like the
thing was you were doing here we're
going to do exactly the same thing and
we're just going to grab this and like
literally just stupid for now and don't
get too concerned about that it's ok
really everyone just relax we'll we'll
sort of take a look at that a little
more detail in a minute we really like
literally exactly the same thing here ok
and one thing I am going to do is I'm
going to say that if you're in the
rectangle of it it doesn't have an
interaction right now because at the
moment we don't really have a way of
interacting with bitmaps so we're just
going to leave that off for the time
being ok so game here instead of drawing
profile in like that we're not going to
do that and instead we're going to use
this bitmap thing here where we've got
bar you know bitmap what I call it
bitmap display and that that has a
dimension so it's going to use that and
I'm you know I'm not gonna I'm going to
try not to repeat past mistakes going to
make that din because that's what we
have been using so it's ginn good map
display like so and then the rest of
this stuff is pretty much the same the
only difference is here we're going to
do a push bitmap call obviously instead
of the rest of stuff that we were doing
and when we have our size interaction
the size interaction will actually say
the same it's just going to be whatever
that
map display tim was right and then
everything else pretty much stays
exactly the same so in the push bitmap
call again we kind of have to now take a
look at that render code which we
haven't really looked at in a while but
the thing that does push bitmap that's
going to take this stuff here right so
it's going to take the render group
which we have it's going to take the
bitmap ID which comes from you know
bitmaps lay whatever our bitmap ID is
here and we've got a height and that's
going to be I guess whatever our size P
is here so well I guess it's this thing
it's got the bitmap Jim why and then
we've got an offset which we don't need
I guess oh well we do need to do that we
need to place it so we need to place it
in like the center I guess of our of our
region so we have our bounds here so i
guess i just say get center of what the
bounds are that's where it would be
right and we don't really care where it
isn't Z so then we have a color we don't
need to set I think that's basically it
for the most part and yeah oops we're
off to the races so that's really it for
a bit map display and you know I I need
obviously to have some way of ever
having one of these actually occur right
so if I come in to debug variables debug
where are you debug variables and I want
to add one of these guys then what i
would do is just kind of do the exact
same thing i did here where we do debug
that variable and this time it's a
bitmap ID and you know you pass the
value and I think that's all fine
although i don't know if you can
overload on these laughs to see if you
can or not i don't remember but we'll
see and so then that just is a bit map
display it in here when it does the pic
map display stuff it's going to do
bitmap display at dot ID equals the
value will set the dimension a to I
don't know what you know normally it's a
hundred by a hundred or something or
maybe it's just like 25 by 25 minutes
tiny and we'll set the Alpha to be true
we're not actually using that alpha yet
but might as well set it so um what is
the meaning of this you're saying ID is
not a member of that guy yeah that's a
good point let's go ahead and fix that
because it shouldn't have to say bitmap
ID since we know it's a bit map alright
so I've got that now and I will go ahead
and call it so in here done at the end
as part of the test let us to debug
variable listing to add one of these
listings here and I guess the only
problem with this is I don't really know
I guess I don't really know very much
about what bitmap i would add as a
bitmap ID so I'd have to kind of look it
up in the asset system to be honest with
you I look I'd have to do like get best
match asset from so i don't know like
get best match get map run and we'd
probably do something like this you know
I don't know to try to get the head in
there something like that and in order
to do that you know we would need see
we would need to actually have the
assets which I don't know if we do I
don't know if we do at this point since
we're just kind of hacking around I will
see if maybe we do have the render group
at this point I just don't know if we
created them yet and and let's take a
look and see if we have or if we haven't
so there's that debug state coming
through or where are we here no that's
not it we need to look at where we call
debug create variables so here it is
we're in debug say so we get the assets
passed in and so we could actually do it
here in fact let's just do it out where
we actually have that so here we go so
if we were in here where we do the
profile math sort of stuff I'm going to
go ahead and do this sort of thing where
we where we go ahead and add it may be
right here in fact that seems a little
bit better to me and then we when we add
this this guy here there we go i will
see if that works so in here will do
debug got the context debug ID variable
reference this is going to be like our
test fit map here's our ID for that
bitmap and let's see how that works
let's see how that goes
entity facing direction face of
direction we don't care about at the
moment debug variable reference none of
the two overloads could convert all of
the argument types that's entirely
possible let me take a look and see d
book at variable Pittman body value so
its context name and bitmap ID that's
seems oh because it should be just debug
ad variable that's why should not be
variable reference so let's see if
that's going to work I don't know if oh
and now we are supposed to just be using
assets directly that's the whole reason
I put it there was so we didn't have to
go access something that we hadn't
actually done yet so okay so I don't
know if this will actually work I don't
know and I don't really know I guess
it's okay to keep that assert their
because just so we know when we're not
writing things out to the config file I
suppose it's better than not knowing
it's going to be a little bit of a pain
because it's going to assert every time
we add a new type even though a lot of
the times we don't actually want to
write the types out you know what I mean
so that's a little bit annoying but you
know it's fine so this is a map display
and I feel like where's the is the
profile how is the profile stuff
intercepted oh it's in debug should be
written so the way that we've decided to
do this is with debug should be written
and so I guess we'll just do it that way
right so we know that these guys are not
and what we could do in the future is
kind of segregate those into a set where
we can just do a raincheck like here's
the ones that are written there you know
this this range of values and here's the
one that aren't right so yeah so anyway
okay so anyway point being right it's
pretty easy for us to create a thing
here where we can just really trivially
still use the same resize interaction to
resize it and this is actually the
bitmap we just have one problem here
which is that the offsets the alignment
offsets and everything are still going
to be you
used because that's sort of the way that
they're defined inside the renderer
right so if you look at here you know
when it does this push bitmap call and
does all these sorts of things it's
still going to do like alignment and all
that kind of thing right it's going to
use its going to do like the get fit
mapped in thing where it does all this
sort of stuff and you know what we would
rather be able to do is be able to sort
of push one of these things a little bit
more directly so that it didn't do a lot
of that stuff where it goes through the
alignment and stuff unfortunately I
don't really I don't know what's the
best way to add that here because it's a
strictly debug function you know I could
add a flag that gets pushed on here I'm
a little reticent to do that but you
know it seems like the easiest thing to
do would be if you added something where
it was like no trust me I want you to do
this a little more specifically you know
and it would and it would do that for
you so I'm trying to think how I'd wanna
do that and it would basically be
something where you know it doesn't go
through the transform it just gives you
kind of the direct interpretation of
that particular bitmap so yeah what I
want to do that and i suppose what i
could do is make a separate function for
doing that but one which was not doing
this sort of nonsense where I you know
which which had this stuff baked a
little bit more directly right because
if this stuff part of the problem here
is when it does the get bitmap call this
sort of stuff is baked into the the push
bitmap so if i were to duplicate the
bush push him up call to have another
one I'd have to duplicate all that and I
don't want that I want that running
through the same code path and so I'm
not sure how I would want to do that
exactly because it's this is the actual
function that kind of needs to be
specified and so it's a little bit it'd
be like you'd have to have a preamble
and a post amble for it which is just a
little genki so I think
hmm I think I may not quite do it that
way so these guys will all still work
the only thing I want to get rid of is
that that Hadamard for the alignment you
know and so if we look at what's
happening with that alignment really all
it does is it modifies that offset and
so I feel like probably what I want to
have happen there is allow you to
specify some kind of a multiplier on
that alignment right like I want
something like a a coefficient you could
multiply to turn the alignment off if
you wanted to something like that yeah
this sort of thing you know I'm saying
and then what would happen in here right
is you'd have one of these as well again
I don't love it but it's the thing that
comes most of mind at the moment and so
I'll just I'm going to go with it for a
second and we'll see what happens here
and so yeah if you call push bitmap here
when you do the push again you can
specify that if you want to as an
optional parameter and that will come
through like so all right so let's see
here we've gotta get bitmap call like I
just kind of had a slight idea I haven't
have an idea that's in the wrong place
all right so all right so if i go
through cure what's this this is on the
code point stuff so these guys obviously
when they call get the map in we're
going to want to use the standard
alignment so that's all good but now in
you know in the debug code we can go
ahead and turn that off now so we could
say let's see here inside that that code
where we do
good map display we could just say like
okay when we're going to do that that
push pic map we would like you two to
nullify the alignment transform we don't
want you to do that that's like not on
the table right okay so now of course
the other thing I have to think about is
what happens when you nullify the
alignment if you notify the alignment
then the bitmap would be in the bottom
corner and so we also have to translate
our stuff so that it's at the bottom
corner I think right now I'm passing the
center because that's I don't even know
why I decided to pass the center I just
randomly did so I think we want to do to
get the min corner of our bounds I think
is the way that that routine works
pretty sure not not a hundred percent
sure and yeah that does look like it and
that's the correct size as well because
again when i export of these bitmaps I
didn't actually trim them so they are
actually it's the whole size of the guy
who just doesn't have anything down
there so that's actually correct which
is kind of cool so yeah so that's all
good that's what we wanted and we could
also draw the bounds of the guy in there
so for example I could do something like
this where where I you know put a
wrecked in there where we just say like
okay whatever the bounds of this thing
is this thing right here and there's no
hot for it it's just going to draw like
some black stuff on the background
behind a bitmap so that you can see it
there you can actually see the actual
bitmap in theory of course I also at
this point I guess have the problem if I
use the width I don't I always maintain
the aspect ratio of the bitmap which
honestly i think is probably something
that we would want to do like I feel
like that's something that is desirable
so I'm not
or what I would want to do to sort of i
don't really want them to be squishy and
so what i could do is make it so that
this actual thing when you drag it
always does actually maintain the aspect
ratio as well just by it'll take the it
would it would take sort of the the
height and always multiply it out that's
not really that hard to do believe it or
not i know it sounds a little bit tricky
but at the end of the day it's actually
not so bad because if you if you look
for example of how the the bitmap stuff
actually works in here you can actually
get the bitmap information pretty easily
yourself right you can get this used
bitmap dim and you can do sort of this
this whole process at some level so if i
wanted to i could do something like
let's see your get bit mapped in like
we're actually doing for the fonts right
and so you can kind of see it happening
here where i could just do that exact
same thing for the bitmap display and
right in line with it I could say like
okay let's let's see what the bitmap
actually is whatever that bitmap
actually is that we're going to be
looking up so I can just go like all
right whatever the bitmap display is
whatever that ID is I'm going to go
ahead and grab that so tell me what that
is and then I'm going to get the
dimensions of it back right and I don't
know what the bitmap scale and bitmap
offset things are here but I assume that
they're just going to be whatever I was
passing in for for this stuff right
there just going to be whatever when I
call push bitmap they're going to be
whatever I was passing in here so this
would be again the scale and I guess I
could sort of formalize those are going
to say the fit map scale is whatever I
was going to pass in here you know in
the and then I'll just actually pass it
here as well map scale and the bitmap
offset is going to be this stuff right
so like the X part of that
won't change so this stuff can actually
come out here because the min corner is
just the min corner we don't even have
to do the bounds part I guess because
the min corner is known so this part was
really kind of a done it I can just say
min corner and I think we're good right
so I can just say there's the min corner
I'm here there's the mid corner again
something like that and that should do
it right I think that all works now it
won't actually do anything that I just
want to test to make sure we're still
displaying properly we are and so now if
we want to make it be aspect ratio
correct all we would have to do is say
you know fix that size since we're only
using the size why just fix the size of
the variable itself to actually use the
dim that comes back in X here right that
makes sense so I think that's really all
we need to do oops I don't actually
remember what this has on it it's called
size because of course I can never I
always have to call dimensions something
different apparently that's just that's
just my thing alright so let's see if
that does it a little bit better and
there we go so now you know again we've
kind of got it locked a little bit
better and now we can see the actual
bitmap which is kind of nice as well and
so yeah I mean that's well I guess
there's not a lot more to it than that
that's kind of just the way that goes
and again so that was just kind of me
showing how you could use you could
overload the same interaction right use
that same code to just do it and you
could sort of see the other nice thing
about that was that again because of the
way that this UI code is written to be
sort of more it's designed to sort of be
more flexible and more about debug stuff
we can just add things quickly and you
don't have to spend a lot of time
fussing with giant frameworks or higher
cuz just look like that
having doing something like constraining
to an aspect ratio is as simple as just
when I'm going to display it to just
just look at the aspect ratio and fix it
right I didn't have to go like overload
a bunch of crazy code or do anything
weird you just go into the place where
it doesn't and you know you fix it and
that's the really nice thing about doing
you I this way as well especially
because you know what a debug scenario
the most important thing by far is that
you can add stuff like that easily if
you want to and so yes you can see how
that's you know 10 20 minutes to add a
display for bitmaps that works right
with directly in our system and loads
exactly the thing and all that stuff is
pretty great right and to have you know
you have resizing and all that sort of
stuff as well and again yet also you
know like Oh basil of our stuff and does
all that things so yeah so that's pretty
good and like I said that's kind of the
goal of this sort of stuff so we're
getting we're getting a little further
right we've abstracted our interactions
or instructions work pretty well where
we're not quite at yet we've got a
couple things we need to do like we're
not quite out yet is here is this stuff
is still kind of janky it's kind of all
over the place not laid out very well
and we're still doing a lot of that code
manually right you know with what's are
the size of things and that sort of
stuff and we don't even have clipping
passing through right so things can draw
over the end there which in this case I
suppose we kind of want but you know in
general we probably don't want we would
like to be able to not have that so I
think focusing next kind of now that
we've got the inter axis clean up a
little bit maybe next week eynde of
start to clean up that other part of the
you know of the whole situation now
again we do have sort of a thing that we
could decide to address here as well and
I don't know if we want to but we could
and that is that you'll notice that we
sort of have this notion that over here
they're like these parameters that are
associated with the viewing which are
maybe not so associated with the
variable and what that means is that you
know when we pull something out and
we're looking at a particular debug
value we you know we don't have the
capability to have these things we
different sizes and that's another thing
that maybe we might want to do which is
just a structural change that we could
do where the sizes could be separate on
different ones I think that might be
something we want to do because of the
very least I think why am I not grab
okay there we go at the very least one
thing that I think we would want to do
is we want to make it so that like the
collapsibility is is separated so that's
also we could do and maybe that's the
best thing to do tomorrow alright for
now I'm going to try to go to a QA but
I'll be honest with you I don't think
it's actually going to work because my
internet is not really able for some
reason to get reliable data back from
twitch it's just like right now it just
says sorry we were unable to connect to
chat reconnecting in two seconds and
that's all it says right so I really
just don't know what to do about that I
wish I did but I will try to see if I
can go to the thing ladies and gentlemen
never like actually like reinstall a
system like this basically what happens
i reinstalled linux on the system and
now like the Wi-Fi doesn't work and
everything else you know how it is all
right okay i can actually see the chat
now so maybe try to throw a cute colon
or two towards me that I can answer just
so we can have some summits of a QA and
i'll try to figure out why the wireless
doesn't work on this machine anymore
although i guess the answer is probably
just that linux doesn't work and there
you go
so yeah do we have any Q Cohen's bang a
chance make you Colin's anyone anyone of
course there may be tons of you clones
that I just can't see right now is your
the thing so that's kind of also a
lovely aspect of the whole situation
which is pretty fantastic
okay oh so I actually can see some Q
Colin's how about that maybe I'm
misunderstanding but it's a desired
behavior for the tear feature to tear
all groups below it even if they are on
the same level in the hierarchy I would
think you would only want to tear the
current group and subgroups not other
groups on the same level for example you
wouldn't want the profile group to get
torn when you tear the particles group
yeah this is why I saying like so so
right now all we're doing is we just
tear whatever the actual thing is we
just tear a reference to that thing and
so whatever that thing was doing it
would it's like it's it's not even
really a copy at all it's just a pointer
to here and so anything that you tear
your going to get the stuff below it if
you were one above right for the most
part and so that's against something
that we like I'd like to fix
structurally because I also I want to
fix the fact that they both expand
because like like I said right now we
don't actually ever run a copy and we
want to sort of actually clone the
references which is again really easy to
do but we have to actually do it so so
we should do that
if I bought a ticket for the con that I
can't use can i donate to someone I
don't see why not you could always email
me and tell me what you're like order
number was and I could change the name
to somebody else's name if you would
like can the new bit baptist lady torn
off as well yeah I don't see why not I
mean like I said the tearing stuff is a
little zygote ish at this point but it
seems like it would be able to i'm not
sure i guess right now so the only
reason we can't tear it off right now is
because there's no interaction set up
for it so so here's the deal we would
need so this part prevents it from being
the fact that this is not set up is the
thing that would prevent it so if we did
that if we actually allowed it to have
an item interaction so it knew it was an
item then I think we could just tear it
off like like so right
you know I'm saying so so that's fine
but you have to have an item interaction
because if you don't then you can't
actually do that so you know but what
you well you know what we could do
actually is we could say debug
interaction tear interaction right and
you can just say tear interaction type
equals equals not is it not where's it
auto modify available so i don't
remember exactly what we said the
criteria was the terra thing is like I
said a little bit janky alt you I so
only if it's auto modified variable is
the only kind but what I could say is
it's just like I could just say you know
it's it's tear it's always tear and so
tear interaction bar equals equals me
which is this bar and so then there
wouldn't be an interaction other than
tearing so basically just be like okay
you know yeah or maybe not huh alright
so they'll be honest I don't understand
why that didn't work I would have
thought that I would be able to tear
that value off oh not if I don't ever
actually tell it that that's the
interaction that that would do it so now
the default for bitmaps is just a tear
right that's just the interaction that
they do
so
let's see here
and so for us is it worth doing so much
do I work if the game will not feature
much you I um so I'm not sure what the
question is are you asking like if you
were on a game project and you had to
like make a decision about how much time
to spend on you I i would say in that
case the answer is probably definitely
yes because we haven't really spent any
time on you I I mean you know like if
you're going to make a debug you I you
should spend a couple weeks on it I
would think so i would think you'd spend
you know i'd probably spend you know two
three weeks at least which is something
like 90 hours of programming time
probably and so all toad will probably
have spent like 25 hours or something
like that which is actually pretty low
now if you're asking on handmade hero
should we spend time on it I would
usually say like I think we should spend
time on hammer here on anything that's
an interesting programming thing that's
worth exploring right that people should
probably know how to do usually I try to
do some of it you know and so will we
make the world's best UI system no but
we will have something relatively decent
like I said which we kind of do have now
it's not quite there yet but you know a
couple more days and I think we'll be in
pretty good shape for the stuff that we
might want you know so
thus Isaac can you add variables to
change the match vectors we could yeah
it might take a little while and there's
some things we should probably we would
want to probably think about for that
but yeah I mean obviously we could
I do not see any more q Coleman's have
we come to the q Collins I mean if you
again like if you wanted to have the
match variables be changeable in that
way then one of the things that you have
to do is that you'd have to query them
like every time you drew it so you
wouldn't be storing a bitmap ID you'd
actually store a type and a vector now
that's not necessarily a bad thing but
you know and you I guess you wouldn't
have cured everything to desecrate /
type of change I suppose but Briana gore
will there be a menu system like
pressing start and Zelda to change items
nothing fancy but just something to get
us started on how to do it no not in
this game there is not a there is not
that kind of interaction I don't really
like those very much I find them to kind
of really take you out of the game and
like basically inventory of screens I
really really don't like a lot like I
mean I think there are some ways you can
do them that maybe I don't dislike but
like those kind like specifically the
Zelda kind I really very strongly
dislike I feel like they take you really
pretty far out of the game experience in
it and I and I don't like that so
I can't remember there was a game like
like dead space or something where they
did the UI in the game or whatever and
those are a little bit better but
alright I don't see any mark you colon
so I'm going to assume that we have Q
colon doubt let's see let us see here
alrighty thank you everyone for joining
me from there sort of handmade hero to a
pleasure coating with you as always if
you would like to follow along yourself
with a source code at home you can do so
you can go to handmade here org the
source code comes with pre-orders of the
game so if you peer out of the game you
get the source code even at the moment
well we are still in the midst of
developing it so you can check that out
we also have patreon page you want
support the video series you can always
subscribe there you can also go we have
a forum site where you can go to ask
questions and watch anti devis i gotta
catch on like past videos we have a
tweet bot which of course i forgot to
update this weekend but normally almost
every weekend I I remember to update the
tweet bot so the tweet bot can always
tweet out schedule at use if you want to
get to stream live that's the easiest
way to do it that's it for today I will
be back here tomorrow at five p.m.
pacific daylight time same time same
place or we'll do a few more debug you I
things in the sort of like in the
pursuit of just getting it to a place
where we can do most the things that we
want to do and we have a few more things
we'd like to be able to do and a big one
there is being able to really easily
inspect our performance profiles and any
other profiling that we may want to add
for example if we want to add some
memory profiling in the future which is
a big one that I would like potentially
to add that would be something we'd want
to be able to show there and so we don't
really quite have the UI at the point
now where it's it's been fun you know
polished enough to be able to really do
stuff like that so that's the thing that
we really kind of want to push on so a
couple days of pushing and I think we'll
be there until then well assuming i will
see you tomorrow until then have fun
programming and i'll see you guys on the
internet take these everyone