all right we are back ends at the end of
the last stream we had just switched to
using indices to draw and the reason
that I want to do that was just because
I want to go ahead and switch to using
indices here so that we don't have to do
any primitive restarts in order to draw
lots of different separated quads and
for whatever reason quads as a first
class citizen got demoted on graphics
cards at least through Apogee L in
opengl 3.0 I want to say or somewhere
around there
quads stopped being a thing that that
you were allowed to use and we're just
down to triangle strips triangles and
fans as well as like lines and points
but in terms of actually getting
triangles on the screen this we have to
do it and if you want to do anything
else you kind of have to use your own
kind of tests later tessellation shader
geometry shaders these sorts of things
if you stick on the front end to create
your own primitives and we could do that
but I don't think that's really gonna be
necessary what I'd rather do is just use
indices they're very compact they don't
add very much space and so that will
also allow us to do other things if we
want to for example if you ever wanted
to extend this system to draw some more
arbitrary shapes like you wanted to be
able to draw a sphere Zoar you want to
be able to import some meshes and draw
them this would allow you to pretty much
do that for free and that seems like a
useful thing to have as well so that you
can kind of just have generic index
messages coming through so what I want
to do now is I want to take a look at
how we're sending those things down just
so I can show the place where this would
normally happen so if you remember
correctly when we look at our render
commands that's what actually has these
buffers in it so if you look at the game
render commands you can see that there's
stuff that gets stuck on here as vertex
array there's quad bitmaps and you know
this this white bitmap and stuff we're
streaming out our vertices into this
vertex array here and that's where we
place all the information that we
currently use for rendering all we
really want to do to make this
modification is we want to have
way of streaming out those indices as
well Jimmy so what I want to do here is
I want to have a way of having a pointer
to effectively an index array and then
when we've got this vertex count here
really what I'm going to change that to
meaning is that I III want to probably
still keep track of it so that when you
push these vertices on there we still
know if you've ever overflowed but
really the main thing we're gonna be
looking at now is that there's sort of
an index array that's happening
separately here and what I'd like to do
is I'd like to make this index array
bshorts so unsigned shorts so they're
only 16 bits long and the reason for
that is because we're trying to minimize
the amount of overhead that we take when
we use indices so when we use indices we
use indices for a number of reasons one
is so that we can refer to the same
vertex multiple times to reduce the
memory footprint of that index right
because if you think of how we were
doing it before we were specifying
vertices for each piece of a thing so if
we wanted to specify two triangles that
each shared two vertices like they do in
sort of a clod right you have two
vertices shared well rather than specify
the same vertex multiple times could be
expensive because it's a normal there's
UV there's colors all these things that
might be stuck in there rather than
doing that we'd rather do is just
specify an index multiple times that
reduces the amount of total space
necessary but in addition to that it
also reduces the amount of transforms
that the card has to do because the card
is smart enough to cache the transforms
most of the time so if we tell it to use
vertex two then a couple triangles later
we still tell it to use vertex two again
it's usually smart enough not to do the
vertex shader twice it's usually smart
enough to just cache the results of the
vertex shader and use them two times so
not only does having indices allow us to
minimize the footprint of the actual
information
self but it also allows us to to
leverage the cards ability to cash
because the card is not really smart
enough to cash and you wouldn't want it
to because we'd have to do like trace
hashes on the actual vertex data to see
that they were the same like it just
it's faster we just transform on what's
the time probably right I'm gonna have
some kind of hash lookup or nonsense
like this so so that's really important
to understand that what we're getting
out of that there's multiple things once
you want to start encoding topological
information in there indices are really
good at that we want to use them so I'm
going to break this up into two things
what I am going to do is just also point
out the fact that if we are using shorts
in this situation if we take a look at
the math for a second we know that 6 6 5
5 3 6 right Center number that's the
maximum that a you 16 can talk about
anyway
we don't have to worry about numbers
over 6 5 5 through 6
what that means is that the number of
vertices that we could possibly encode
is not gonna ever be more than that
right
so our max vertex count if we were to
look at how big a vertex is we can also
see whether we ever want to actually do
anything about that anywhere like if
this is a textured vertex we can see how
big it is it ends up being let's see 4
that's 8 9 and then another 4 so what is
that 13 set right 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12
13 well that should be really afford
yeah
I mean hard to say I guess because I'm
not sure exactly what we're going to be
doing with these per say but if we just
assume that these things are like let's
say they're gonna be under 64 bytes
because right now they are so if we were
imagining these would be 64 bytes what
you can see here is that that even if we
used every single vertex we could
possibly refer to we're only gonna have
a four megabyte vertex buffer that's the
biggest it could possibly be so one of
the things we might consider doing here
is just saying look
get rid of the deep like us ever having
to actually think about this max vertex
count and instead we'll just say that
the the match vertex count is always 6 5
5 4 6 right we could do that I'm not
sure why I do that quite yet we
definitely could do that all right so
let's move forward and have this
actually let's move forward and actually
make this work this quad bit maps will
be going away eventually so I'm gonna
kind of shoehorn it in for now
to load the bitmaps for a per block of 6
indices because we know that these are
quads but we can eliminate that entirely
when we go to the next step of this
process so let's start by just doing the
basics here what I want to do is look
for everywhere that we are sort of using
the the vertex count in the max vertex
count I want to sort of augment this now
to have the the index groups included in
there so that's what we're going to do
let's see here so in here where we do
max vertex count this render texture
group I don't know that we care about
this at all or what this even is in fact
is this what is this hold on a second
what do we what are we doing here what
are these things
these things are nothing's so these were
us just hypothesizing what we were going
to do four groups of textures we don't
need those at all so let's get rid of
that first of all because those are not
there anymore let's keep going now
all right so looking at where we're
using the max vertex count so what you
can see here is we're sort of specifying
these when they begin the frame right
we're grabbing these out here so what am
I do is I'm going to follow that lead
and just say look the OpenGL renderer is
gonna say which of those were doing and
then we're just gonna do this and what
we want to do is where we specify the
vertex array we're gonna specify an
index array as well right so really
we're just awed menteng the ability to
send down vertices we're now augmenting
that with the ability to send down
indices as well as the vertices and
really there's not a lot more to it than
that right it's that simple
so now when we do get current croisé we
pacify a quad count there what we want
to do is say look if we've got a current
club that's open we want to make sure
that that it fits right and if we can't
then we just bail now in the future I
think what we want to do here actually
when we do get current quads what we
actually want to do is just restart in
the case where we can't so I'm not sure
why we didn't write it that way to begin
with it's kind of a little bit weird but
if you think about it it's like the
vertex count that we want here is the
quad count times four and the index
count that we want here is the quad
count times six that's how much we're
gonna send down for each quad right and
so it kind of seems to me like this is
just a little bit dumb what we did here
because what we can do is say look why
don't we just look at the current quads
and see what it is and then restart if
we can't oh never mind
you know why it's because we don't
allocate any additional when we're out
so it doesn't matter anyway never mind I
think it back we don't really need to
look at that but we still do need to do
these checks so if we're doing these
checks we want to look at vertex here
and similarly I want to be able to say
look at the index count
isn't going to work then we're in
trouble here as well okay hmm so moving
on oh and I suppose that's probably it
but let me just double check for the
places these are used here's where
they're allocated yeah so this is all um
so what I'd like to do here is where we
pass in Max of vertex count there and
actually in here do we even we don't
need these anymore
right these aren't used yeah please show
me max vertex canvases right or it
should be used when we allocate the
memory correct all of this stuff is old
right
yeah so max quad count four frames
getting passed in here that's the only
thing we actually need now so all of
that was list old vestigial code that we
forgot to remove right we just have
never gotten around to deleting it so
now in cure you can see that we can do
the same thing we did before based on
the max Claude counts we can basically
based on whatever it says the max Claude
counts where we know we can use the NSE
to refer to those now here's a problem
that we would quickly run into and that
is that for the max quad count per frame
if we pass a large enough number we will
blow out the size of the indices right
we won't be able to specify enough
indices because the indices can only
represent 60 5 6 5 5 3 6 vertices and so
if we allocate more than 65536 vertices
we can't refer them anymore but that's
actually ok because we can use different
base vertices so we can slide our array
window up so we will be able to actually
reference more than 6 5 5 3 6 we just
have to keep our index count we have to
keep our indices low enough that they
don't overflow that so what we'll do is
we'll just keep building up indices
until we've pushed too many vertices on
and then we can sort of like I said just
moving in sort of batches where we kind
of slide our window forward so we don't
really need to worry about this the fact
that these will overflow the index range
because we'll be able to handle that and
I'll show you what I mean by that later
on as we go so here's our max stuff and
I'm literally just allocating a side
bandar right here for our indices like
so and there's nothing to it right this
is this is all we're talking about so
once we do that we should now have a
thing that that
that gives us exactly what we want for
streaming out these indices we're just
not using them right now and also the
other thing we have to do is just to
make sure
that are open surrender actually has the
members in it that we need so I haven't
done that yet right you know here's our
texture vertex or you know this sort of
stuff we need that index array now so
there is our index array and we also
need those those counts so once we've
got those we're good to go now and now
we've got an index array it's prepared
we're checking for it and all that good
stuff it's just no one's putting
anything in it yet so now what I'd like
to do is I'd like to go ahead and and
start by backing that number down so
basically like if we go into the win32
renderer test and we look at what we're
doing with the if we go into the
renderer test we look at what we're
doing with how many things we pass on
right we've got a maximum quad count
what I'd like to do is say look I want
this quad count to actually be really
small temporarily I want to say the
whole quad count has to fit inside one
65536 vertex batch I know this right
here is six five five three six right
that's how many quads that would be
sixty five six five five three six quads
we know that each quad is going to take
four vertices so we know that this
number is four times right the the this
total number is four times two hi so we
actually need to back it off by two
powers of two that's the maximum of
quads we could sync per frame I'm then
gonna compile and run this we should
then hit the assert it should say oh now
you you're hmm you're trying to do too
many of these primitives per frames
sorry we can't do that so I'm gonna go
ahead and run that and we should hit
that assert there's that assert right
there
so what I'm gonna do is just back off
the number of grass elements that we're
putting in there to take the pressure
off of that while we do the switch to
indices and that way we can make sure
our indices are working properly when
there's just one array and then we'll
switch to the sliding window when we've
done again this is breaking the problem
two steps you always see me do this and
the reason for that is to eliminate the
places where the bugs can be if you do
the in steps where you test each step
then you don't have to worry about bugs
that can operate across those steps
limits and focuses your ability to bug
much more specifically and it just
reduces the total time it will take you
to debug it so that's all I'm doing here
so I'm going to go ahead and change this
here this cover index to just not draw
any grasses that should eliminate any
work we were doing that goes over that
texture limit so here's the world
without any of the grass is being
rendered and that definitely gives us
what we need as far as a single buffer
workflow at work load start Network flow
okay so switching back to the OpenGL
renderer now what I want to be able to
do in here is something where these are
all these draw elements calls are
actually all just based on an index
buffer that gets passed in so rather
than the quads ever having anything to
do with sort with only telling me sort
of these vertex assets what I'd rather
do is say look we come through here you
can see us specifying this buffer data
each one of these is specifying a set of
triangles that's you know each one of
these buffer data calls is sending down
this many vertices and then you can see
me referencing those vertices here using
these arrays what I'd rather do here is
send down the array of indices as well
and then use that array right that's
what I'd like to do now I want to do
that and baby steps too so before
actually doing that what I'm gonna do
instead is I'm going to just use the
offset in here to do that
and so to do that what I need to do is
augment our renderer structure in here
just
a little bit to give us the index offset
as well so if you look at the quad
structure here what you can see is this
tells us we're in the vertex array we
are what I want to do here is I want to
say what's the index array offset as
well and this is just saying tell me
where to start
okay and so in order to have it tell me
where to start what I need to do is I
need to when I specify this index array
here rather than using this old one that
we sort of put in place for the old draw
raise what I want to do is sort of nerf
that and instead have a call to draw
elements that uses that pointer so we
know that this index RA offset so the
thing in the actual so much like here
where we were using this sort of this GL
buffer data to send down all of this
stuff and then the vertex index itself
was coming off of the entry si vertex
array offsets we're starting what I want
to do is I want to take that index
pointer and I want to actually have that
index pointer be offset by the index
array offset right and when we do that
we now know that we don't want this
index array we want the actual index
array that this would be referring into
which itself is the one that comes off
of the commands right it's the one that
the game filled out and that's the index
array that we're looking into okay so
that should give us a way to just draw
out of a prefab array that we go through
and we no longer need this vertex array
offset thing to really be encoded the
way that it is we can change that
encoding quite a bit if we would like
but we're gonna have to do that in
stages again just to avoid the
possibility of bars creeping in there
and to be more specific what I mean by
that is that if you look at how this
buffer data gets sent down we send down
all of the data here in one giant step
and then you know and and the reason
this is kind of dumb is actually this
sends it down multiple times potentially
to we only really need to send this down
once so this is just kind of dumb this
could just be sent down here in fact
what why is this happening here
this is not right at all
yeah so hold on one second
put a little pause button on everything
I said why do we still have that there
right it's a little odd are we sending
down that buffer every time for GL clods
that's super busted what we really want
to do is to do it here right I mean
that's what we actually wanted
so I don't know why we weren't doing
that probably because we weren't being
very smart about which buffers are being
used when but this is what we actually
wanted right I'm not sure what so that
change seems like it does seem like
we're getting some problems with our
depth peeling though so mm-hmm here's
what I think's happening where's our
begin screen fill yeah so you can see
the problem that we're having to have we
only have one array buffer here and the
problem with only having one array
buffer is that we need to have like for
example with this one where we're using
a different array buffer to send down
our stuff we end up in a bad situation
where we need to be able to refer to
this one buffer multiple times so the
thing about that is we OpenGL lets us do
that just fine it's just whichever
buffer we bind right so you can see here
we only have one array buffer if we just
have multiple array buffers we'd be fine
so what we want to do is have a vertex
buffer and like let's take a look here
what our other ones are so I mean you
can see actually if you just look at the
other buffer data that they're actually
all fixed buffers so if we want to we
can actually just specify each of these
buffers as one of the buffers so we've
we've got a couple different ones here
Bob there's the screen fill buffer which
is this one so let's just make that and
then we also want the sort of post I
think that's this the post processing
stretch right the composite and those
are the buffers we use since these don't
change they're the same thing right we
should be able to just create them right
off the bat so for example when we Jen
these buffers here what we'd rather do
instead of calling this bind buffer what
we'd rather do is just make these right
here right so bind the composite vertex
buffer like this and specify that data
kind of like this right and then we can
just bind that buffer here so we don't
have to send down a buffer stream we
just find a buffer and use it and the
same can be true for our screen fill
buffer this is just all this has nothing
to do with the indices this is just
better in general we should have done
this before so this was just we didn't
get to it right but this is just all
better in all cases so if you look at
the other places that we specify this
I'm not sure what is this here that's oh
that's just the one we're editing on the
other side so there's only one other
call to the buffer data that we care
about which is right here and so the
same is true for this wait this is the
same this is exactly the same
is it not that looks exactly same to me
so actually we don't need the composite
one at all we can just use a screen fill
vertex buffer in both cases and we only
need s only when we need right uh so
what we want to do now I think is if you
look at GL buffer data and you take a
look at what it actually specifies
there's sort of this this usage note and
you can see those various uses notes on
here and we don't actually need to
modify this buffer this one stays the
same so GL stream draw is like the wrong
hint we are not going to be doing it the
like none of this stuff is is as it as
it should be so we want like a GL static
draw yeah right so we want this for this
buffer because it's not changing it's
like we always use it exactly the way it
appears here so it doesn't need to go
that route okay so the screen fill
buffer is there the composite buffer is
here but we know that that's the same
one so we should be able to just do this
which means that for the rest of our
stuff what we can do here is just know
that when we submit this we will bind
our vertex buffer here and send it all
down and then whenever we go to draw in
our texture quad set whenever we go to
draw then we just find the vertex buffer
in this case here right and that should
basically do it so we want to suppose
three screen fill we want to put space
for storing this
the index that they'd open she'll give
this back we actually have to have that
in here that was just stored in here
right there so I'll just place another
one in there so now we have the so now
we have the other one okay
and when we're calling this it looks
like we need to know the point Open GL
because we don't actually know where to
get that screen fill buffer handle
otherwise but that's pretty easy okay so
now we should be able to use those
arrays sort of in a more coherent
fashion okay don't ask me why I inserted
a six right there in place of our code
and so now we look correct again right
and and and now we're not calling that
buffer transfer stuff a bunch of times
so that's good too so the other thing I
want to do there is I want to see what
effect that had on on our ability to to
have speedy rendering here because I I
realized I didn't know we were calling
that multiple times that's really bad
that means we may have forced the OpenGL
descent submit that buffer multiple
times for no reason and that's just
really stupid so okay let's just check I
want to make sure that we don't have
that we didn't just get a speed win from
that right this is what I would like to
do so now we're pushing down a ton of
cover again
and actually like it is strangely quite
a bit zippy er honestly it looks like so
I'm not sure how much of that might just
not be in shade or cost really so that
was probably a pretty big deal to be
honest with you I know we weren't really
taking any timing so that wasn't
supposed to be part of the optimization
thing but that was an important thing to
get rid of we really didn't want to have
to be doing that in that way I want to
take a look just real quickly at the Z
bias the Z bias program here I would
like to go ahead and nerf the lighting
call just temporarily so in here what I
would like to do when we're doing our
our lighting right I would like to sort
of switch this around a little bit just
temporarily I'd like to see what happens
if we just get rid of the lighting and
instead set running some to just be full
full lighting
just so I know that the shader isn't
taking an inordinate amount of time it
doesn't look like that really affected
it much right it doesn't seem to be
anyway
well I guess I don't need to live to
that I'm gonna put this back out because
I'll be switching that back back around
later on to I wonder it well actually
can I make I can probably make that
change even if root out so lighting
disabled is actually a compilation
switch we can do there too so I suppose
I could just set lighting disabled as
well so in the OpenGL renderer where
we've got the lighting disabled it's not
actually already happening let's take a
look so when we actually compile that
program let me see where we do
so that's just gonna be the
learning-disabled parameter so when we
do compile the abacus program it's like
def peel and then letting disabled so
it's just lighting disabled whether
that's turned on so what we could do to
disable lighting entirely is just make
sure that our settings are always set
that way so inside the render or test
where we set for example whether we
wanted Z Z on vsync rather we could just
say letting disabled equals true and now
we should never call the lighting at all
okay so in theory and again I don't know
but in theory we should be seeing some
slow down due to texture changes here we
would like to take some profiling about
about that if we could but I don't know
to what extent we really can what I can
tell you is if you look here at the the
speed at which is rendering at the
moment and again we actually do have a
printout of how slow it is right so if
we looked at this we could see you know
if we forced it to shrink the display
dimensions down what the difference in
speed is right just to see to what
extent it seems sensitive to that and it
doesn't really look particularly
different
to me and I'll just trying to verify
that that's actually the size that we're
getting well where's our settings have
changed
let me just set a little breakpoint
there so let's just make sure that we're
using what I think we're using in terms
of the sizes of things so we should only
be up creating buffers of that size so
for example when we go in here to create
like whatever the depth is of our frame
buffers yeah so all of this stuff should
now be pretty pretty small so I think
that just works and we are now like that
should mean that we're really not
spending much time in in that that
shading okay so let's suppose we want to
kind of move to the next stage of things
also let's make sure we're in O 2 mode
we are um so inside the renderer the
next thing that I was going to suggest
is that Jimmy I would like to now use
the indices more directly so I would
like to use an index of effort coming
from the app rather than doing one of
these every time so what I'm gonna do is
I'm just going to set up something that
takes a look at those indices and uses
them now like I said I don't want to
have all the graphs in here I don't want
to have 60 as the amount of grass I want
to do zeros the amount of grass and
start with something like this
go where I can be more specific about
always having everything in a buffer
first so we're gonna switch from doing
this stuff we're gonna switch from doing
that in a Verta in an indexed buffer
that we create right here and we're
gonna switch to one where we can just
send down the index buffer right so what
I want to do here is pretend okay let's
suppose we had an index buffer how would
this work exactly right
I believe I don't know if it's really
called that so you'll have to bear with
me for a second I look up what the
OpenGL term is for it it's this it's
this one actually element array buffer
and so if we have that so defined
doesn't look like we actually do so in
here where we define when we specify one
of these buffers I'd like to be able to
specify the element array buffer so that
we can sort of say look here's this
other array of indices I want you to use
those I don't remember if that's the
most compatible way to do it or not
[Music]
let's take a quick look here yeah so it
looks like that goes back a long ways
here's the es OpenGL ES 2.0 ducks so I
think deal element array buffer should
be fine for us so
array elements
so this is the actual identifier we need
conveniently the one right after array
buffer so we should be able to actually
bind the index buffer now and I thought
we had specified that as something that
was off of opengl index array sorry oh
no no no but we're talking about the
buffer here so we need to create one of
these for our indexes like so so we've
got a vertex buffer index buffer we need
to bind our index buffer right and we
also need to send it down so just like
we were doing before where we specify
the buffer data we need to do the same
thing for our indices so we need to do
GL array element oh sorry
element array buffer we want to specify
that in exactly the same way only this
time it's like this where we specify a
certain number of you sixteens right
otherwise everything is exactly the same
similarly where we before we're doing
our bind buffers to create the initial
versions of these things we want to do
the same thing here for that index
buffer right so that we can have a
separate handle for this buffer that
we're going to use to specify those
indices and then we can actually draw
from them later so that will set all of
our indices to be drawn but of course
unless we actually refer to that buffer
I don't believe anything will happen now
because we're still passing a pointer
although it looks like a long second
here what's the complaint I wasn't
expecting an error I was looking to just
kind of not use it but I'm not sure what
the error actually is let's take a look
the message there
encountered and out of memory error that
seems like not true so we probably
passed the wrong thing there my
assumption is that's because when we
actually were specifying the let's let's
just take a look here when we were
actually specifying the index count we
did something like like maybe you can't
say that the buffer has zero things in
it or it means that it actually was
using this thing which which I don't
know if it actually is or not let me
quickly just check that so suppose we
wanted to know if it was actually trying
to use this array well what we could do
is just make sure it doesn't by
unbinding it so now there's nothing
bound to jail element array buffer so
hopefully that'll let me focus my
debugging on the thing that's actually
the problem okay
so I guess what's happening here is the
thing that happens in OpenGL again this
is one of the reasons open jules bad is
because there's so much backwards
compatibility stuff in it because I
think a lot of the parts of OpenGL are
actually designed pretty well in some
cases if you just pick and choose
certain parts or time pretty well but
there's such a breadth and a long
history there that some things are bad
so I think what happens if I remember
correctly it's very idiosyncratic if you
bind an element array buffer then I
think what happens is this call actually
reads from that buffer but it uses this
pointer as an offset so this pointer
then becomes basically how far into the
buffer you actually wanted to start
right I'm pretty sure that's what it was
so if we wanted to make this work you
know this this goes away right we can we
can do that just by saying okay these
indices here this is actually
technically an offset so even though
we're cat
sing it to avoid start it's not a
pointer what we want to do is take that
offset so this thing and we want to
start at that offset right and then we
want to move up our indexes based on
that so really the way to think about
this would be this becomes a loop now
over the indices this is really an index
index now that sounds weird that's what
it is it's gonna go up by six that's
just what it's gonna do right and we're
gonna start at the index array offset
specified here um now what we need to do
in the quad bit maps is a little harder
but that's okay because I'm just gonna
say that for now we're gonna use all the
same quad bit map right um so
temporarily before we cuz again this is
something we want to change I'm gonna
say that in here when we grab out the
texture what I'm actually gonna do is is
just grab out some one of the random
textures in the thing just the second
texture you ever specify for some reason
right I don't know whichever one it is
it's fine with me so we're just gonna
pick a random texture here to apply
because we are gonna change how we're
specifying this and then when we go
through here I'm just gonna pass the
index array offset as whatever the index
is that we're currently on like that
right and that's how many indices in we
want to be now I think that has to be a
byte offset so I think we want that to
be like this but that's that's about it
okay so now what we need to do because I
think that's correct now what we need to
do is actually put some indices into
that buffer because what we're gonna
find is now that buffer is just filled
with garbage right oops we still get our
am i accessing off of it for some reason
oh well I don't know if that buffer is
clear so let's fill it with indices
first and then we'll don't look it
so what we need to do is every time we
push a quad in the renderer we need to
actually go into the to the index buffer
as well as every time we sort of want to
access any kind of quad like every time
we go into the push quad here we want
all of our calls to push quad to be
filling the index buffer in addition to
the vertex buffer so much like how in
here we do textured verts tar vert and
off we go
in here we also want to do the same
thing we want to do like index index
equals next count index count plus
equals six and we want to assert that we
line up okay
we've won our index out to be at that
place and then when we put these out we
want to do exactly what we did before
right
so the vertice like exactly the way we
did the vertices before we want to put
those out here so we want to like index
0 oops
1 2 3 4 5 like so right
and I suppose if we really wanted to do
this you know we could do this
I mean dividing by 6 is not a great idea
but it's okay it's temporary right
so we can do that and that still ends up
being the correct thing and we can write
that bitmap in there as well no harm no
foul so when we ran out these indices
now we need to actually write out what
these vertex indices actually are and so
we need to write out vert index relative
things so here's our vertices and now we
know that these things actually go the
other way round from how I thought they
went so they went like top down instead
of bottom up which is kind of nuts
that's what they do so if they go top
down again we want so we're going to
want 0 1 2 right and then we're going to
want 1 2 3
I think I'm not
[Music]
these of course need to be 16-bits and
be sure to sort that so this way we
would know if we ever tried to overrun
those bounds we'd get an assertion here
and that's going to be relevant in a
little bit right okay so what this looks
like interesting enough is apparently
filling the index buffer now at least
kept us within a range so so that's kind
of cool actually I wasn't necessarily
expecting that to solve that problem but
we still have to actually now get stuff
on the screen right and there's a number
of things that could be wrong here
including our our vertex indices like
including all sorts of stuff right so
our vert index here we know that that's
the base vert index off of the vertex
array so I believe that is the correct
basis here also I don't know if this
winding order is correct I got to go
right down but it doesn't matter because
if it was incorrect
we'd just be seeing the back faces
instead of the front faces so the fact
that we're seeing nothing lets us know
that that's not exactly the problem
right now let's just make a couple quick
adjustments here let's make sure we're
using a white bitmap that way we know
that we're not just picking a texture
improperly so we're not seeing anything
so that's means that that wasn't the
problem there right hmm and then finally
oh well here you go
so these are these we're saying unsigned
int for some reason we don't want them
to say unsigned and we want going to be
unsigned shorts so I don't know why that
was still saying that we just forgot to
change it
sooo now when we look it looks like
we've got one of our triangles wound
wrong still let me just so let me just
write this out now so the order of these
we determined is actually not this way
it's this way apparently apparently so
if it goes like this and we want to do
that we would do 0 1 2 for this
counterclockwise triangle and then we
would do 1 3 2 for the other one and so
that should draw all of these things
through the index buffer now and again
this isn't in except for we're passing
down from the app and that looks about
right and now if I go over to the the
actual render again and just put put
back in the cloud bitmaps
we should be good to go and that that
looks about right to me so I think
that's all good right um so now what we
can do is stop doing this entirely so
now what we can do is actually draw a
huge batch and the problem will be that
we won't know what bitmap to use but
again if I just temporarily speaking say
that the texture that I want to use is
actually going to be a nerf this
temporarily right this what I can do is
say alright let's use a texture oops
that we just Roberta pretends that it's
okay we'll just use the white bitmap
instead so we do white bitmap here
instead of the actual bitmap that we
want we're always going to use the white
bitmap if we did that then we could
actually draw this in bulk right because
now we could just say look start here
like this is where I want you to start
and this is how many I want you to draw
right but now just don't bother with a
Ferrari loop tell OpenGL to draw them
all right and that takes us from having
one draw call per sprite to having one
draw call per entire scene pass right
and so that looks like this and again
it's totally correct for everything
other than the fact that we don't have a
way to vary the textures and that's why
we want to talk about things like
texture arrays because now what we want
is some way to vary our texture I in
some way that doesn't involve having to
restart that primitive right having to
restart that loop and so let's take this
one at a time if we take a look at the
frame speed here we can see that we're
still a little slow for reasons we
really just don't know what they are and
that's the place where we'd really like
to get some profiling in here because we
just don't know where these milliseconds
are going right we
do not fundamentally know why we aren't
hitting 60 frames a second for example
we have no idea and furthermore it's a
little weird because it looks like it's
fill rate related so again it could
because of the multi sampling right it
could be because of our shader is
screwed up in some way we don't know
right so we have no idea what the reason
for the slowness is and we're gonna have
to investigate that separately but what
we can see is like when we get down to a
smaller size then all of a sudden we do
run at 60 frames a second right and
they'll be interesting to find out why
that's where we're gonna have to hope we
can get insight working relatively well
all right so if we push that process
further just to see what's going on now
the next part of this process is getting
up above the unsigned short limit
because what we're gonna hit then at
that point now that we move to that is
we're gonna see a problem where when we
do inside our inside our renderer when
we go to render we'll blow out that that
index rate really quickly so now we want
to scale up to being able to do tons of
these things so we want to be able to
put that 60 in here again and what we're
gonna find is as soon as we do that
we're gonna blow out the addressable
range for an index right that's just not
going to work
so what we see here is again we haven't
exceeded the maximum number of vertices
we have room in the buffer to put
another vertex we haven't exceeded the
maximum number of indices we've got
plenty of room in the buffer to put in
another index what we don't have is
space in a you 16 to refer to a vertex
right that's the problem so what we need
to do is find a way to get our u16s to
be able to render up into more parts of
that buffer
so what we can do here I believe and
you'll have to forgive me for not
remembering off the top of my head how
to do it because again open Jo it's kind
of a sprawl of ridiculousness at this
point but what we want to be able to do
now is pass a an offset so that we can
so that we can say look we're using
these two buffers all the vertices are
in one buffer all the indices are in the
other buffer there's no problem with
that everything fits okay so we don't
need to talk to you about multiple
buffers or anything like that
but because we're using you sixteens we
need to do this in a couple different
batches potentially where we draw 65,000
vertices at a time and then the next
65,000 vertices at a time you know and
so what you can see here is like say
this GL draw elements base vertex rate
so what you can see here is that's
almost exactly the thing that we're
looking for this call does exactly the
same thing as the other call but it
allows us to pass in a number that
shifts up all of our indices past the
numbers that they could normally hit so
now we get the ability to add a 32-bit
offset to our 16-bit index and that can
slide us anywhere inside the buffer that
we need to be right so we don't have to
do this we could use 32-bit indices but
it's pretty easy for us to not and it's
just less data that has to get
transferred right so if we wanted to do
that how would we do it well luckily we
kind of know when we call get current
quads we kind of know what's up right
what we can do is say it would this set
of quads exceed the maximum number so
would the current quads that we have
right now exceed the max per batch so
what we want to say there is look I
can't take it that it's the maximum
thing that could fit into you 16 and
maybe I'll subtract one from that just
because I don't actually want to ever
fill entirely like the space because if
we ever did want to use primitive
restart I'll just leave one so if the
maximum number we could hold in a 16-bit
integer more or less if I divide that
number by four then that's how many
different vertices I could ever
reference so I'm going to look to see
would we exceed the number that maximum
quads would we exceed that by what we're
being asked and if the answer is that we
would then I need to push a new one on
so I'm just gonna say look forget about
the old one at that point it's a it's
done it's over I'm not going to talk
about another one so don't expect me to
write then I'll go ahead and say push a
new one on start it all over again the
vertex array offset is going to be
whatever this vertex count is here right
and off we're gonna go okay so what that
allows us to do is now inside the open
gel render pass when we send these down
we know that we can now call this call
instead which is GL draw element
base vertex and what we can do is pass
that down as the base vertex so this
entry knows that all of its offsets
start at this number and then when we
actually push our quad on instead of
using this vertex count as the vertex
count that we base our indices off of
right so we not going to use this vertex
anymore this vertex in here mark we're
going to use a different base index and
it's going to be the actual quads the
number that's in the actual quads itself
right so in here where we do this entry
quad count right
it's actually going to be based off that
number so right here we're gonna say the
current clods that we're talking about
that quad count times four is going to
be the actual base index because we
don't anymore actually you know what I
don't even need to do that that's not
what I wanted I can just use this it's
really just that right um so what I can
say is hey the first vert index that
you're gonna use is this one now that
vertex RA offset is the basis so
whatever vertex index you were going to
use subtract away whatever the whatever
this quads this current quad groups
based vertex index is just subtract that
away and that's your index you know I'm
saying
okay so now we just need this function
because this is a function we don't have
so what I want to do is go ahead and
grab it
and this is what it looks like right
here so where we were doing our open gel
our you know when we basically at this
part we have a big Lemongrab where we go
through and let me grab all the api's
that we want to take here that we want
to use and so I'm just going to go ahead
and put those in here I think that's it
so I'm gonna say we want that there's
our geo elements
Jill Drummond space vertex and then what
I have to do is somewhere here
eventually I have to actually ask for it
okay now that was a lot of stuff to add
so probably we're gonna run into some
trouble here and also this that
assertion needs to be modified to
actually be correct it's not correct
anymore um so we need to sort of create
a temporary here called base index and
that's the thing we want to make sure
that we can still equal after the cast
just to make sure so that's
I mean it looks pretty darn good
actually
[Music]
and you'll notice we're actually still
running at a high frame rate hi in this
case compared to what we were running
before I don't really know about the
texture fetching there though so I I do
think when we do render up in jail here
let me just do in render or test let me
go in and make sure that whatever we're
doing is not let me just make sure that
whatever we're doing is not just because
we're using the white bitmap now I'm
gonna try using like the grass spit map
or try to find a different bitmap to use
I I don't know how to get it exactly but
I'll just I'll pick one randomly oops
this will probably be grass most of the
things we've sent down our grass so you
know um so what you can see here is that
really just getting rid of that dispatch
totally fixed our problem right um you
know there's probably a bunch of things
we're still doing wrong in terms of
frame right here because you can see we
still aren't quite as good as we
probably should be of course we can't
tell cuz Windows is still capping our
frame rate even though we asked for
vsync to be off they totally decided to
ignore us oh well but what we can see
here is that we're not getting any of
those ridiculous slowdowns we're running
basically the same frame right we were
when we weren't putting any grass in
despite the fact that now we've put in
60 grass bitmaps / 2 per tile right so
we can immediately see that the dispatch
overhead is a huge was a huge issue for
us exactly as we thought and so all we
really need now to finish things off is
a way of changing the texture every time
we swap right every time we go to a
different quad we need a way of changing
the texture and we need
texture arrays to do that or a texture
apps right those are the only two ways
we can really make that happen there is
a third way that I'm just sort of saying
that we're not gonna do and that would
be to use by endless textures and the
reason that I don't want to do that is
just because I'm afraid of that it won't
be broad enough support for it so I
think I would really just rather use the
texture race so what I would like to do
is I'd like to go ahead and set up the
texture race I don't think I have a huge
amount of time maybe 45 minutes
so it's a little tight in terms of
getting that done but really that's the
main thing that that we haven't done yet
right is a way to make this work and so
what we'd like to do here is basically
when we do this bind texture we'd like
to do just a single line texture where
you just say this is the texture we're
binding and it's over and then each of
these each of these draw calls here
would each not drunk I'll sorry each of
the vertices pulled out by the draw call
would actually contain information in it
necessary to pick so let's take a look
at what would happen there I want to
look at the vertex descriptors here we
haven't looked at these in a while
so you can see here a vert PID vert nid
vert u VI d you like this stuff right
get a triplication that sort of stuff so
what I'd like to do here is extend that
in a sense so this vert u v I'd like to
actually have a an additional thing in
here that's that allows you to get
another value which is going to be used
as a texture array index so in terms of
which texture we're selecting there the
vert light index what you could should
hopefully we'll be able to see is that
we only really use that in one program
which is right here and this is our
general like fill function right it's
this the Z bias program which does all
of our filling so what I'd like to do
here is suggest that maybe what we can
do is pass in another another value into
the front end there that will get used
here I don't know yeah so there might be
other ways that that we would want to
think about this again like I said
because we don't need it actually it
doesn't need to be specified specified
per index it can just be something
that's specified once and done it's the
same as vert light index in that in that
sense so if I just call it texture index
here then what will happen is we're
gonna talk about it being passed in this
way even though it's not super necessary
because each vertex doesn't you specify
each triangle can specify it uniquely
right so that's the part that's a little
bit wasteful here
that we're not addressing but if we take
a fried texture index in here then what
we would be able to do is use that
texture index when we're actually doing
our textile fetching so for example
right in here for text sample we could
use that to fetch into the texture right
here rather than just into a flat single
2d texture so what I'd like to do is
make it so that we can pass that
information down so basically everywhere
that we see that light index that vert
light index happening I would just I
would put in for texture index like so
so we're basically just doing the same
thing here this is still being unsigned
short because we're not gonna allow more
than 65,000 textures and I ain't gonna
happen again just grab those out just
let them grab in this right here and
there's that I'm gonna call this vert
line index area I'm sorry for it text
for index again just because I want it
to kind of line up the same way that it
was before
uh and so that's really what we're
talking about I don't really know that
we'll need anything other than that
where is that out there it is there's
texture next so now all I need to do is
actually go in there and put that
texture index into the definition of our
renderers vertex format so in here where
we do where we've got the texture vertex
where is that thing textured vertex
textured vertex textured vertex I know
you're in here somewhere there you are
so what I want to do here is have a
thing where we're like texture index
again same as this lighting and
texturing are the same they wouldn't
have to be per vertex if you wanted to
make the renderer more advanced and have
a per primitive buffer that gets read
out of that's just replicated multiple
times right so that's that's that right
and in theory if we call this now
nothing should happen
I don't think well take it back
where's our errors here parameters
vertex errors and right errors undefined
variable frag texture index you are
correct that was the wrong
capitalization
can't see I love it
not not great you know for honest about
it not fat not fabulous not sure how we
would have made that particular mistake
here
oh um not true I actually do know how we
may have made that mistake hold on one
second so in addition to those buffers
we also have these and these buffers are
so if you look at how this texture these
textured vertices are are specified here
so this is the p-value this is the light
UV this is the UV this is the color then
we have the normal light servers well so
that should be still fine right I think
that should still all be fine
are we getting any we're not getting any
errors though I'm not sure what's wrong
with that let's take a look why are we
getting that why are we getting a
problem all we did is add all we did is
advert light index right that's the I
mean I've vert texture index that's all
we did
in his route light count is that even
used anymore yeah that's not so fruit
light index and her texture index are
both just ah okay that was a mess up but
those look pretty evenly paired so I
don't know what the problem was there
exactly okay so it was just that one
typo so now we're specifying your vertex
index in the vertex shader but we're not
actually using it anywhere if we pop
over to the render and take a look at
where we would actually use this so what
would happen is inside our actual push
quad all of these would now have a
texture index set to texture index and
again we don't much like light index and
normal we don't really need as many as
are actually in here so it's kind of
messed up but you know again these are
things that we may or may not decide to
optimize later because it does cost time
to do them so if we look at light index
here and texture index is going to be
similar where we just need to figure out
what texture index it should be and so
what we can do is say well that should
just be in the render or texture that's
just going to be the value that it is
right so if I go look at the what we
have specified the render texture to be
we just want that value to be directly
usable in the shader from now on so you
see here we've got this handle
what I want to do is just take that
handle and smush it down so we're just
going to compact the handle and say
that's the value and so then what we
will do going forwards is we'll just say
oh we'll just you know make render or
textures be things that get that it's
kind of smooshed handling them and then
we're done okay uh so what can we do now
to sort of push ourselves towards that
well the first thing we have to do is we
actually have to start using texture
arrays right and in order to do that we
have to have a way of specifying
textures as part of kind of one sort of
creating a single texture handle that
refers to like a deep texture that's
multiple slices right so if we take a
look at this here what you can see is
there's sort of this notion that we're
gonna call a slightly different function
and you can see here that there's like
this notion of a layer count so what
would happen is we're still talking
about 2d textures potentially and they
still have all the same parameters that
we did have before but what we want to
do here is talk about this additional
parameter that we're gonna say allows us
to specify multiple multiple slices and
so when we call text sub image we will
also to like update images out of this
texture we would also pass in an
information about which layer we were
targeting and other things like this
right so let's take a look at those
things in more detail where's our docks
top
so when we specify this piece of
information here right I you can see
that this call is just gonna specify
like an entire cube because it's got the
width the height and the depth right and
there's nothing we can really do to
adjust it so in order to actually
specify textures differently for every
slice in separate times we need a way to
control the array the layer information
that we want to pass there right so what
you can see here is this would let us do
that right we could pass the Z offset
and the the depth could still just be
one so I'm could do one slice of it and
what you can see is the target lets us
differentiate between whether this is
supposed to be a 3d texture that's an
actual like voxel or whether this is
actually just a 2d texture with a bunch
of slices you know I'm saying so that's
really what we are looking to do is use
this function to define different slices
of our texture each to be a completely
different image all right so now GL
texts some image I don't even know if
we've got that that may be one that we
have two calls well but what would
happen is when one of these textures
gets submitted OpenGL allocate texture
so in here what we would be doing
instead of this call we would actually
be doing this call to pass that out
right now I don't like I said don't
remember if we have that we do so if we
want to do this call you can see here's
all of our things that we need to pass
me to pass the target it would be a GL
texture 2d array we have to pass the
level again we're only gonna specify
zero at the moment we want to do MIT
maps eventually but not right now
X&amp;Y offsets are always going to be the
upper corner but the depth I'm sorry the
Z offset is gonna be a certain layer
like which slice so this is the like
this is the texture index that we're
talking about the width height and depth
are always gonna be whatever the width
hype height are and one now we're gonna
have to again constrain the width and
height to be something more sensible
potentially although there's other
things we can do there as well and then
finally we need the rest of this stuff
and that's gonna be the same as it was
before right so we need this information
here read RG RG be EBA whatever right we
know the one that we're specifying is BG
RA that's always the way that we want to
pass down our information and we also
know that we've got the type field is
the same always we don't have any other
kinds of data and then that's that
standard so that's actually all we'll
really need to do at the end of the day
to get started right but the harder part
now is going to be how we deal with when
we call this allocate texture we've kind
of got a deal with another not sure how
I put this we have to deal with the idea
that we actually now allocate the
texture only once and then we're just
putting things into these slices so this
isn't that hard of a change to make
actions actually so I'm just gonna go
ahead and kind of make it but what I
want to do is I want to kind of do it
again like we were in to sort of baby
steps so the first step is I want to
change the way that we're specifying
textures to be feed-forward right and
this is the thing that I was talking
about before and basically what this
means is we're just gonna assume that
there's a certain number of textures
the renderer handles and that's the end
of the story so when we come through
here
and you know you do an initialization on
the renderer kind of like we have at the
moment where you need to say here's how
the renderer gets an issue initialized
let me see where do we define that
function here it's in win32 right so
this load render entry yeah so this is
what we're talking about so when you go
to load you pass the max quad count per
frame what we want to do is say there's
also a max texture count right and the
max texture count is just gonna say
here's how many textures you're ever
gonna talk to me about you know I'm
saying like you're never gonna tell me
about some other texture that's like you
know not within this set of textures
you're always gonna say if you told me
32 you're always gonna talk to me about
32 textures that's just what you're
gonna do right and so that's an
additional piece of initialize
information initialization information
that comes through in the initializer
then when we actually have when to do an
it up in jail what we want to do here is
when we do our initializations
we want that piece of information to be
recorded
and I actually probably want this stuff
to be recorded earlier than when these
are actually I probably want those to be
set like right off the bat right so
everybody else who might want to know
about what these maximum values are they
can always count on them being set and
that way when we call open jailing it in
here that will actually create those
textures on the initialization call and
we're good to go from there hmm excuse
me all right so temporarily like I said
though I'm not quite gonna do that I'm
gonna go ahead and do something slightly
different well actually you know I don't
even think I do need to do something
slightly different I'm just gonna just
lean on the fact that open jail already
supports this and say okay if we do an
open jail allocate texture call here
what I want to do is I want to have
those calls take a texture index I want
to assert that the texture index is less
than the max texture count I'm just
going to use it so what I'm gonna do
instead of this stuff here is I'm not
gonna say GL Gen textures I'm just gonna
use the texture index directly by saying
this I'm not going to call that and just
so we we're gonna leave zero as a non
texture for now just like I usually do
so all this stuff is going to get called
as normal and then in here where we
specify this handle I'm just essentially
writing that texture index back through
all right so this means this will never
this is not actually going to do this
anymore we're not gonna have that and in
fact what we're gonna have is a thing
where we just pass in which one of these
textures we were actually
talking about and we could call this a
renderer texture texture here and and
maybe I'll just do this something like
that okay but it doesn't return a value
so then when we do manage textures what
we want to do is say in here where we
were assigning the result texture we
actually wanted the opposite of that we
want to pass the result texture like so
and then when we go to do deletion we
don't actually really need to do
deletion anymore so I'm going to remove
this path in its entirety right this
just isn't going to be a thing
all right sue now we need Supes I just
need to put some of those things in here
that I said that I had so you know in
here there's a max texture cap hoops hmm
I think that's all fine and that's just
a bigger that was a 64-bit value this
does not return a value OpenGL allocate
texture in this case again doesn't
really have to do it this way anymore
so what we actually want to do is say
that the open gel open gel white bitmap
it's passed in here so we need open gel
white bitmap in this case to be equal to
some handle value in this case let's
just say it equals one
oh and that's a pointer in the texture
management code which we don't need it
to be anymore
so as far as handmade renderer is
concerned when we have that texture up
the texture up here can just be that and
really we could call this texture op
allocate texture update and similarly we
can just say you don't DL okay textures
anymore you just update textures that
you want to talk about and it doesn't
have a trim command potentially right so
maybe it just says hey here's a texture
op update and it's not really an
allocation anymore this doesn't really
need to be here
fact it just looks like that and we can
choose whether we eventually want other
texture ops but it may be that then this
just becomes welded together we don't
want to do anything else all right
so for the time being that's just going
to work like that
we need to pass them a texture so we
want here we don't really need very many
but I'll just say 206 textures so now we
can see this is kind of nice or too
because like I said in here now we just
say which one of these we actually
wanted so we can say hey the texture
handle that we're gonna talk about here
is this one and it doesn't have to be an
address anymore so that means that the
load bitmap function gets simpler which
is good
so just continuing down with this code
change so now in here what we need to do
is this and what we want to do here is
just assign these values to things when
we initialize them right so what I want
to do here is actually just pick these
out and what I want to do is just set
these to be equal to numbers that I
understand so I want to say like render
or texture or you know texture handle
like this and right now I'm going to
kind of cheat and say that I know which
one I know that there's one reserved for
white but what I really want to do is
move away from the renderer creating its
own white bitmap and I'd rather us just
create the white bitmap you know I'm
saying so anywhere that we were and I
don't know that actually to be honest
okay so we don't nevermind so I don't
care about that because we don't use the
white bitmap anyway okay so let me look
inside the open jail I want to look and
see if we if this uses the white bitmap
anywhere it doesn't even better so again
we can probably just get rid of that
entirely and then just inside your own
code when you're using this renderer you
will create the white bitmap if you
wanted it it's not something that the
renderer cares or knows about at all so
this is what this would look like I want
to make a little function inside the
renderer code proper that's like looks
like this
something like that
and that way those are wrapped just for
the time being while we're playing
around with it here I'd like to make
sure that we kind of know what's going
on in that in that regard right okay so
what I want to do now is inside handmade
hero when we use these these should just
be things that are assigned based on
what's available in the bitmap system
what's available in the asset system
right so what I actually want to do here
is when we do a finalized asset bitmap
I'm just gonna I we're gonna want to do
this in a better way just in general um
but this bitmap texture handle is really
just going to be something that's set
right at the outset so when we actually
do that bitmap texture handle thing
Jimmy we're gonna set that when we
actually create the bitmap so let me
just go ahead and search for that here
and hand an asset so there's one use of
it here here's the D allocation call and
again that D allocation call is now
gonna be a different thing it doesn't
actually have to deallocate it it just
has to put it on its own free list
effectively so it knows it can use that
texture handle again so we don't really
need this to be here if I guess the way
I put it so we just need to remember
which texture handles we haven't haven't
used but we're gonna be able to collapse
all this code down so I'm not even
really gonna worry about that right now
so we don't need to do that just yet
this is not necessary and let's see in a
default renderer just needs to have one
of these I'm not sure what our next
texture cap should be I don't know if we
assume that we're gonna have 512 by 512
textures that means each texture is one
megabyte so I would think we'd want to
use like a half the megabyte and a half
gigabyte of texture memory or something
it's all we would really be using for
textures would all be in this one place
I think that's probably about right so
I'm not sure let's set it to 256 first
but we need to feed that forward to the
asset system eventually as well because
those have to line up okay so now inside
handmade assets when we're looking at
creating those asset bitmaps whenever we
go to load one of those we need to
actually get one of these texture
handles here so when we would when we
would kick off a load asset when we
would create one of these
so the finalized call if you will so
when we when we would kick one of these
off what we want to do is at this time
also assign it a text a place to go
right so when we set up that texture op
Q stuff in here where we have this
bitmap the bitmap texture handle wants
to be set here right and what we need to
do is we don't want to always set it to
zero we want it to set it to something
that isn't hasn't been used yet and so
what we don't know when we do when we
start to go into this task situation
here we don't really know what textures
are or aren't available so we want to be
able to to figure that out dynamically
somehow so again I'm just going to put
it to doing here for that
or so we're going to want to do this
sort of update the asset system as a
separate pass when we go through and do
the texture race stuff because it wants
to be aware of that right but so this
texture handle here where I specify what
it is what I can do is just inside the
asset system temporarily I can just have
a monotonically increasing value and
just set that to whatever we set that to
right so I can say like
this texture or use texture handle or
next three texture handle something like
that we can just say whatever the asset
system is here we're just going to use
one of those and off we go
and the renderer by the way will assert
if that's not appropriate
right
we don't ever want this one to be zero
so we also should probably set this to
what we want when we actually start so
when we are initializing the asset
system and you know everything sort of
gets started up here I also probably
want to do start with texture handle one
right and if we want white bitmap I
could even start with texture handle two
and that's I think all we really need to
do there so let's just see where we're
at in terms of actually reconstructing
what we're trying to do here I didn't
think we had to do that we don't have to
use an unnamed generated by OpenGL do we
aren't we allowed to use the name not
generated by up in jail
I could have sworn that vut you don't
have to call Jen textures that you can
just pass whatever handle you want here
hmm
that is weird so that I'm not sure about
them did they change they maybe change
that you didn't used to have to do that
it's not a big deal because it's pretty
trivial for us to just work around that
immediately but I thought I wouldn't
even have to do that and I'm not gonna
leave this code path in so I don't
really care that doesn't support it but
I thought that was something you could
just do however it's pretty easy for us
to work around that all we have to do if
we want to is instead of and wait a
minute and didn't white bitmap not do
that yeah this call didn't have a
problem with it maybe it didn't get
there yet but it's just a little bit
weird right because it should have been
doing that anyway if we don't want to do
that that's okay so in here where we do
our open gel in it and we initialize
this stuff for the the first time what
we can do is just say alright this is
going to be some kind of an allocation
thing here where we do a GL gem textures
call and just get a bunch of these
things so temporarily I'll just do one
here right
so when we call GL gen textures here
what I want to do is say look put a
bunch of texture handles into here for
me and then what I can do is when I do
my allocate texture call I should be
able when I pass the stuff in here right
I should be able to just use the array
that that you told me right so I can
just do like okay open gel texture
handles so that should allow me to
basically set these various texture
handles to whatever I want it to be
right and you know now we've got the
renderer setting those textures and
that's what we want okay so what we now
need to do for our final step is change
from using actual texture handles to
just using slices into the texture array
so again this should be pretty
straightforward we should just be able
to do this where we say okay we don't
use texture handles anymore at all all
we really do when we allocate a texture
is just update the slice so instead of
calling any of this stuff what we're
gonna do
is just do this actually it's not handle
really anymore so what we wanted to hear
say the texture handle should be lower
than the max texture count and then here
we we just have like a we grab that
handle out it's just going to be this
texture index right so that's actually
how we're gonna update textures from now
on where we do this this handle gets its
what gets passed down okay and so when
we actually update this the other thing
too is the width and the height are kind
of irrelevant like we don't really need
to pass them anymore because they always
have to be the same thing but that's
sort of a separate thing we can talk
about a little bit later because we
actually may need to do some UV updating
kinds of stuff in order to get like
rectangular regions out of our textures
so this would actually be the way that
we would update this from Taiwan and
this vine texture here would actually
always like always in all cases bind
just our giant array texture so we would
have that and this would just be a
single texture that we allocate at the
beginning that just has all of the
slices in it
however many this says there should be
so when we actually bind that texture
and update it we should be good to go
I believe we pass to dot array 2-d there
but let me just make sure so we can so
when we bind that text sub image now
we're just updating slices of that thing
so then if we just use this instead
during startup to you know inside OpenGL
in it where before we would have been
allocating all these texture handles
instead of what we're going to do is say
well inside the OpenGL texture array we
know that we've got each of these
textures packed into this one thing so
just bind it at the start make a 3d
image out of it set the parameters that
we want and then finish up right
so what we want to make sure we do here
when we're doing this sampling too
though because there's more to it than
this right is that we need to make sure
that when we bind these textures up we
want to make sure that we set the
filtering properly because we just
wanted to stay within a slice like we
never want them to kind of like sample
outside of the slice or do anything like
that so when we actually create this
texture right here and specify the
settings for this function will have to
update in a second this is gonna be like
a zero data pointer saying we're just
gonna set the layout of it but what we
need to do is make sure that we set
these other filter parameters correctly
for it the texture arrays now have the
right texture stuff up here yeah you can
see I don't know if there's any other of
these that we would actually need
doesn't really look like it so we may
actually get away with just doing this
and not really changing anything else
yeah so we might be able to just do
something like that where we said like
okay let's look at GL tech storage we
can just call geo text or egde set up
the size that we want this thing to be
and then just call into it making
updates to the layers as we go
that seems fine so here where we specify
the 2d array the mid-level count right
now we're not going to have but
eventually I think we probably will and
you know well that's alright anyway so
in our geotech storage 3d call we need
to set the default the format for it to
be whatever our defaults right format is
and then our width in our height we knew
at the moment anyway was 512 by 512 it I
think that probably has to be something
that we pass in like what do you want
your texture size to be if that makes
sense so we'll probably have to play
with that a little bit more as we go
probably pass in texture array dimension
okay so we want to probably update that
a little bit but other than that I think
when we push these through I think we're
okay here and then that way when we're
putting pushing these down we can sort
of go from there I don't know if we have
tech storage 3d that we probably didn't
make reading probably didn't grab that
call I'm sorry that that parameter yeah
we didn't so we need to grab those out
and that but that's about it
so I can't promise I'll do bug all of
these today but this is the the basics
of it there's not really much more to do
other than debugging it and then you
know we can kind of go from there so
let's see texture stuff is there a place
we put some of that already
not really so I'll put it in here looks
like it would go Morini um so we just
need our tech storage 3d now and that's
just the thing that says look I'm not
going to tell you all of the actual
layout of this thing like all of the
contents of it I'm just going to tell
you how big it would be and then I'm
gonna fill it out incrementally as we go
that's all that's doing right so again
we'll just
and then look at text sub image 3d and
that should be all we need
alright um so when we're binding these
textures now we again have the situation
where we don't really need to worry
about binding specific textures inside
our draw elements loop so if you look at
what's going on here we can now just
make one call and the idea is that we
would just bind one texture array and
that texture array would not come out of
the there be no quad bitmaps or anything
that's just gonna be deleted entirely
and instead what we would do is say that
we're always gonna pass down our texture
array as the thing that everything grabs
you know it'll just let them grab the
texture out of there and then we just
need to actually in our shader access
that texture array using the indices
that we get passed and that's really the
only thing we need to do to make the
rest of it work and all the infinite
amount of debugging we're gonna have to
do to figure out why OpenGL isn't
working because that's obviously also
like six years of work but in general
this is all we really need to do so in
order to sample it you can see inside
the shader it should be pretty
straightforward
it depends which one we're using I don't
they don't really note it here we don't
care about the min/max because we're
actually loading it in directly so we
should actually be able to do the
correct texture fetch just in general um
I don't know yeah so we use a different
sampler type there so we should be able
to set that sampler type and go from
there so inside the Z bias shader
this one right here here's the samplers
so this texture sampler is going to be
one of these
it's gonna be the 2d array it's not
capitalized yeah that's our texture
sampler and our texture sampler is only
used just to get the one texture sample
right so we should be able to just in
that texture sampler we should be able
to just do the array sample here and so
if we look up the geocell quick
reference the call for actually getting
a texture array where the texture
sampling is no no where's our GLS so
all's here they are here they are so
those are the types where is the texture
call here it is um so right now we're
just calling texture and you can see
here that like it's got a bunch
different kinds so when we call texture
if we call sampler 2d array and we say
here's the sampler here's the vector 3p
and then the the bias we don't care
about the moment so that that number
that we were passing it the frag UV is
like insufficient it doesn't have enough
actual information there so what we want
to do is make like an array UV so we
want to say look there's an array UV and
that array UV is gonna be the frag UV I
let me do this the way that they tend to
do it just in case them fits and starts
here so we're gonna make the the frag UV
x the Frog UV Y and then this actual Z
component of the texture is gonna be the
index right it's just gonna be the frag
texture index okay
and then I just have to figure out okay
what do they want the coordinates to be
for this because I don't actually know
it's just so if it is just the layer
it's clamped so it should be just that
like that should be it and then if we
access that as an array after the array
UV that should basically do it so it's
saying take the texture go to this slice
of it and here's the actual fragment
location of the thing um so let's
actually see what we can do here invalid
texture formats invalid texture format
here are you talking about be GRE be GRA
ext I'm not sure what exact problem they
have here I need to do in debug mode to
be able to inspect all those
unfortunately so what's interesting is
we did not get a problem for allocating
earth our original so we're only having
a problem here
why is our texture array set to zero did
that not get initialized I'm gonna stop
in OpenGL in it I'm gonna switch to
debug mode and I just want to see where
we're at so there's a compile in debug
mode let's go ahead and roll forward on
that
and here is open jail allocate the
OpenGL allocation 400 duh we still call
it for this white bitmap alright so I
gotta take that out as well I don't want
to see that call in there so that's got
to go but that should have nothing to do
with it that's just because it's getting
called well it might actually because if
we haven't initialized this yet you
can't call that
so in here this is probably just
complaining about the fact that our
mipmap count needs to at least be 1/4 GL
tech storage go ahead guess in there so
it seems to like that ok
we don't really know though yet whoa all
right I was not expecting that to work
the first time out yeah that's kind of
nuts but that appears to have worked ok
well I assume we still have some
problems in there but somehow that
actually worked which is crazy and I
don't know what to make of that I was
expecting that to be a long slog alright
well here's our renderer running with
correct textures and it's running I
think actually quite fast I think that's
probably within earshot of running at 60
now you can see we've got some issues
because our textures are not always I
think for textures that are we're
sending them down and they're always
going to be blown out to the 512 by 512
size so we kind of have some more work
to do because we need to remember the
sizes of things inside those inside
those textures right so we kind of need
to do a little bit more work there but
that's pretty awesome that that just
worked I also wonder I'm curious about
what's the Geo gym it Maps call
I was curious if we could call the
generate texture map we pretty we can't
really know because when you update one
we would only want to generate the MIT
maps for one slice and I don't think it
would really allow that
yeah
so we don't really want to call this I
was gonna say we could try to reminisce
but we're gonna have to send those down
ourselves because we want to send them
down per slice and we'd want to send
those down ourselves all right so we
still have a fair bit of work here to do
we're not done but I guess we did what I
want to do day which is get the texture
is working so handmade hero obviously is
gonna have some issues which you can
kind of see um at the moment and mainly
that's just because we don't have white
bitmap yet but the real thing is just
the texture sizes so you know yeah
having the white bitmap be specified at
some point obviously necessary now let's
just go ahead and do it so if we got rid
of white bitmap let's see where that's
actually being used okay so let's
suppose we just went ahead and specified
everything here and white bitmap has to
go away um so like all this stuff it's
just got to go
also quad bitmaps is not necessary
anymore either right like all that stuff
goes away and so it's gonna have to get
that white bitmap from somewhere else
and that's the important part for our
purposes here right and so that's what
we'll be working on in a second so what
I want to do is yeah get rid of quad
bitmaps because quad bitmaps we don't
want to use anymore right that just
never wants to get set never wants to
get talked about or set or anything
anywhere and then white bitmap wants to
come from somewhere that actually is
internal to the application it's not
something that the renderer provides for
you and looking this
see it looks like that's the only other
thing that we really have to worry about
right
yeah so I think all we really need to do
is figure out where else we're gonna get
that white bitmap from and my suspicion
is the best way that we could do that is
in the renderer inside the game render
commands when you create one of these if
you want to provide a white bitmap you
can and that would just be set in here
um so all of these would just say look
you're gonna get a white texture out of
here if there is one we don't guarantee
that there is someone can set that for
you but otherwise you just won't draw
you know I'm saying so all of these can
just say look white texture like texture
oops I missed one
and it's up to your application to make
that if you want it but we're not going
to make it for you and there are other
ways we could do it wait it's not a
member of render group I thought I'd
just added it so that's just going to be
something that the app can choose to
supply on their own if they wish
otherwise you know otherwise it won't be
if that makes sense so I think that's
all I really wanted to do there and then
you know when when you create one of
these render groups if you want to
specify a white bitmap you can otherwise
you don't get one and we can make one
inside handmade hero to restore that
functionality as necessary so if we you
know look at the places in handmade here
where that's actually used
and in fact since we actually do pass in
an assets parameter for that I suppose
that's something that really should be
set separately as well probably want to
clean that up
you shouldn't have to pass this year or
that that should just be like a user
pointer or something right but just
looking at this as it goes through you
can see where these are are set what we
really want to do is have that command
be something that you kind of do in your
app and then you can set that white
texture to whatever you want if you want
to so for example inside our asset
startup is probably the right place to
do that so inside here where we set
where we go ahead and set up the assets
what I would want to do is create the
white texture here so this is something
where you know we would push on texture
out to do that so texture something like
this
so we'd say okay the texture handle for
the white texture is going to be texture
1 the the width and height of it is also
1 the actual data for that is just
whatever our white texture is so I have
to put it somewhere where we know
there's going to be a single piece of of
memory that won't go away because we
don't know when this texture off will
complete right so that just allows us to
create one of those and off we go so now
there would always be a white texture
there we also could just say look if
it's just assumed that that's texture
handle 1 all the time or maybe that's
just always texture handle 0 that seems
even better so we just assume that
texture handle 0 is always the the null
texture in that sense and then I think
we're good to go because then what we
can do is inside handmade renderer when
we do begin group that will be what it's
already always default to so is if you
want to set that texture as white you
can but you could also do something else
right okay so this won't quite work and
the reason it won't quite work is
because again it's only the it doesn't
record the sizes but you know we
probably could fix even that if we
wanted to and the way that we would fix
that is actually kind of interesting I
we can ously want to encode in our
texture handles what the width and
height actually are which I know sounds
kind of weird
but if we want to we actually can so if
you think about how this is working we
have like a 512 by 512 bit map and we're
if we want to pick like sub regions out
of that it's actually not that hard to
do
what we can do is make the renderer
texture actually embed that data with it
and then when we send down our or actual
sprites they can just bake those sizes
into there You've ease so for example in
here when we actually have a renderer
texture if we look at what this looks
like what we can do is instead say all
right let's just say there's an index a
width and a height specified for this
thing and you know I mean it can look
like this
and so then it's a 64-bit value for your
renderer texture and this is what it
encodes so then when you do texture
handle you would just say like hey what
did you want the width and height of
your texture handle to be and this
actually is now just the thing you don't
need in the texture up to have anything
else so you just do this right and I
know this seems really strange but just
trust me for a second and watch how it
works so we've got a renderer texture we
just pack into 64 bits what the index
slice is and how big we want it to be in
the thing and to be honest we could even
be fancier about that we could actually
pack an offset in here if we wanted sub
regions of the texture we could get that
fancy if we really wanted to
so this actually can be kind of flexible
in that sense and so then if we look at
the texture handle call what we can say
is like hey pass me the index then pass
me with once I do that I now have all of
the information packed into my texture
handle that I actually need and I can
just force everyone else now to act to
call it to have to actually call it if I
look at the texture ops now it's just
this it's saying like here's where I'm
gonna put that texture and so then we
can just say okay here's the index let's
let's just you know grab that index out
in fact while we're at it we could just
say let's just use it here we also know
what the width and height are so here
they are that's how we're going to
update those pieces of information and
we don't need this anymore and we can
just go from there okay so then when we
talk about this thing where we pass open
gel okay texture we can get rid of those
two this those don't exist anymore
and that's fine and they don't exist
here either I don't really know what
clear does in this case for who's
calling it
but we can still do it it's certainly
not a problem and then in here when
we're actually starting to use this
stuff this is where we start to actually
have some we actually have to do stuff
right so here's our UVs that come in on
the push quad and what we now know is
that these UVs are not necessarily
correct because the size of the thing
that we loaded in may not be the size of
the entire texture so we need to correct
for those values by inverting the value
that comes in so what we first want to
do is grab the index out this way like
so and we probably want to do this to
make sure that it doesn't ruin our day
if that makes sense but then what we
want to do is we want to come up with a
way of processing that UV information
into here we're gonna do that in just a
second but give me give me one one
little scrimp is here to make sure that
that's okay
so with this feed-forward what we do
need to do is since we don't know the
sizes of these yet
before we load them in handmade hero we
always do but we don't know the sizes of
these before we load them inside this
app what we need to do is this won't be
able to be feed-forward in that sense it
will still have to rewrite just those
pieces of it right so we would still
have to do it this way which I don't
like I'd rather do it where we can just
do a fee for it but the nice part about
that is well it's feed-forward still to
a certain degree in that although this
has to fill in the width and the height
it doesn't have to fill in the handle
the handles always correct right so that
means the multi-threaded part it's still
better than it was even though it's not
as good as it is inside the actual hand
material code base where we always know
the size of something before we load it
that make sense so anyway
that means we still do have to do this
here but that's okay because really the
only thing we're doing here is is saying
that the texture handle with well and I
could do it this way I'm gonna do a
couple things here I also want to do
like I'm gonna call us a texture
reference for now maybe or refer to
texture something like that um so I'm
gonna actually when we call this I'm
gonna rewrite this here I'm gonna say
refer to texture I want the texture
handle index and I want the width and
height baked in there now now that I
knew what they actually are like so and
then I'm gonna use that and that's the
entirety of it now everywhere that was
clung texture handle has to actually be
like refer to texture and these can kind
of do this I I maybe will make it so you
don't have to pass in a width and a
height if you don't know what the width
and the height are yet so you can if you
want to specify that but I'm gonna hold
off on that just a little bit longer
um oh you know what no no no no no I'm
doing this totally wrong
this is way better
API wise let's do it this way again this
is how we kind of wanted to do it
originally right just place this in here
and then what I'm gonna do is say okay
grass texture is one two three four five
get rid of all of those and then the
load bitmap call is actually one that
refer returns a renderer texture just
like we wanted it to originally and then
what you do here this is just like the
texture index right
that seems much better because now what
we can do is say alright the renderer
texture texture equals refer to texture
and we know the texture index because
it's been passed to us and then we can
just say that that is what we are
returning much nicer much much much much
nicer
that's definitely much better than it
was okay
conversion from s 32 that's probably
true and in fact these probably want to
all be done sort of like this where we
can sort of assert them in this way we
can just test to make sure we haven't
lost any important bits I no one should
ever be passing us anything that figure
to begin with and we'll have other
things you want to check anyway but it
just nothing all right um so now when we
do that bitmap texture handle and we
actually assign a new one to it we want
to assign the bitmap width and height at
that time as well so when we actually do
a texture handle call like this in this
case we want to pass that width and
height in so we want to do it like this
right where we know exactly what we're
doing here like so
and like I said I'm kind of I don't know
what the name of this should be but like
it's something like that so that's
everything I wanted to do there and now
when we run it we should hopefully if I
didn't screw anything up
get exactly the same thing as we did
before so that should look like exactly
like it did and this should look exactly
like it did right but now that we have
bundled with the texture what section of
the texture rewind which by the way
would would have worked for texture
atlases too if you wanted to you just
have to use an offset in there instead
of an index then what I can do is just
say look when we go to actually push out
the quad just scale the UVs that you
were gonna use scale those down to use
the width and height that we've placed
in here for you so here's all our UVs
I just need to know that you know in
width and in height value so whatever
that UV was that UV is 0 to 1 based on a
sort of an understanding of how big the
textures were but in our case we have we
know that we want to base this on a
texture size whatever these are this is
something that we need to get
information about like I said later
needs to be sort of passed into the
render but what I can do is just say
look we know what our inverse is like
our inverse U and inverse V multipliers
are so I can just take the texture width
and the texture height figure out what
percentage those are and now all of my
UV scale just works right I can just say
in fact I can just make this a v2
okay once I have that all of my UVs can
now be transformed directly so I can do
this like so and now I know exactly
that's supposed to be height and now I
know exactly what region of this larger
texture right image I'm actually trying
to fill or actually trying to use so now
you see everything gets back up to the
correct size that it was and similarly
if I come in here to to handmade Hiro
everything's right because now we're
using the right size again for our UVs
to pick out the places in the texture
array we actually wanted makes sense um
so the only thing we have left to do is
make that not be a magic constant at the
moment I'm gonna leave it a magic
constant just not a magic constant
that's hidden in the code so you'll
never find it again I'm gonna say
this is gonna be called texture or a dim
and then what I'm gonna do is say
alright that just gets stuck in here
like so and that way I will know that
the other time that I used it here and
said we should pass it in I can stop
saying that now and just say this
instead that way when we go to update
that we will instantly be able to search
for everywhere that that occurred and I
think with that we're now doing texture
arrays happy birthday
right our game still looks like poop
right now because we haven't put any
bitmaps in but man we're so ready to do
that because now we're sending down
we're sending down bulk sending down
stuff in bulk so that's kind of cool and
and our our app over here is running
quite nice so I'm going to go ahead and
go to the Q&amp;A and wrap things up
let's see are there any benefits to
using pixel buffer objects for async
texture transfers these days I've heard
that drivers copy texture data into
their internal memory anyway so the call
returns immediately in behaves very
synchronous um so half and a half hold
on one second on that and let me explain
one thing so you pixel buffer objects I
don't think you ever want to use anymore
because you can just use buffers now
generalize buffers for these sorts of
transfers and that's gonna be the better
way to do it but I just want to address
one thing so you are correct in that the
graphics card when you call a texture
transfer if you're like other transfers
this block right when you call that it
will first copy the block into its
aperture for transferring the graphics
card which is memory that has been
locked so it's not virtual memory it's
actually physically addressable memory
so the graphics card can pull it and
then it will kick off the transfer so it
is true that the jeep the CPU to GPU
transfer will always happen
asynchronously in the sense that it's
not going to sit there and wait on the
call now it's not asynchronous per se
because as soon as you use that texture
it's gonna fence I believe so I think
there's some blocking that happens there
but putting that side that said that
doesn't mean there's nothing to be saved
by using a GPU side allocated buffer I'm
sorry a driver's side allocated buffer
why the reason is because that copy from
your memory to the Jeep to the aperture
that can be used for the transfer GPU
doesn't have to happen if you allocate a
buffer primed for that kind of transfer
through OpenGL put the memory in there
to begin
and then let it go it may not have to do
the SEC that second copy so depending on
the circumstances you may be able to
save a CPU to CPU copy the CP to GPU
copy yes that always happens correctly
either way but to CPU to CPU copy you
may be able to get rid of Martin's was
saying that in core profile you still
have to generate all names it's only the
compatibility profile that lets you do
the push that's too bad I mean it's like
fine because we're not actually using it
but
what's the recommended way to deal with
windows doing an infinite window proc
loop while moving or resizing a window
just ignore the messages I mean take
them and don't actually do any work so
yeah I mean they're saying much less
active than that like I mean note we
don't have any problem with that
right here's me moving the window around
like happy birthday and it's still
animating just fine and the way we did
that is we just don't really process
paint messages we just pretend we do so
we say oh thanks for the paint message
great we finished it up it was good it's
really fun thank you right but we don't
actually do anything there and all of
our rendering happens in another thread
that's just constantly going whether
windows cares or not
so we just put our render on a different
thread not the window thread so the
window thread can lock up all day long
it doesn't really affect our game that's
just windows being windows right
and Martin says you probably would want
to replace the geotech storage duty
which is a text image ad because text or
just from up until 4.2 I'll be honest
I'm not sure how to do it though
can I just pass zero because I was gonna
do that originally but now that we have
it working I could certainly try it you
know text I yeah because I wanted to use
geo text I want to use geo text image 3d
in the first place but I didn't think I
could I thought it was mad about that
so this one is well let me leave this in
here so in here we're passing you know
the level is one the internal format
where is this which is what we're saying
the width height and depth is exactly as
it is the border is zero format and type
is this so this right here would be X B
GRA right yeah you GRA X I believe so
that's what we would call here I think
just don't know if it will work
[Music]
invalid texture format so
what would I have to tell it in order to
get it to be okay
I mean maybe this can just be something
else
I just don't know how to make it work is
the main problem like I don't know how
to get open jail to be happy with that
if you have suggestions Martin's I am
all ears because I'm just not sure how
to make it work
do you still multiply the offset in the
GL draw elements base vertex call
because I never do it and never had any
problem so I don't understand what's
going on twice do you still multiply the
offset let me just see which multiply
you're probably talking about there
while we wait for Martins to tell us the
answer of how he thinks Geo text image
could work are you talking about this
let me read the docs we may be passing
that wrong and we wouldn't know because
unless we really look and see it's
possible that we would could be wrong
about that and not know let's just look
problem here is that we're gonna have to
find docs that actually talk about how
that offset works and that's easier said
than done
uh I don't see any answers from Martin's
I guess I'm not sure yeah um so let me
go ahead and and just take a quick look
at that draw them on base vertex and
I'll look at the spec for now oops
didn't mean actually close that don't
suppose this says
here's speck so void start indices it
looks like that's the base come into the
commands if the resulting value is
larger than max to verify that type it
would behave specular through the
operation is undefined sum would be
negative we need to find the we need to
find where this would actually be talked
about probably in the element array
buffer
for Serenity's from the buffer object
whose name is bound to omen hurry before
using their indices parameters as
offsets into the buffer object in the
same fashion described as 2 9 6
[Music]
philosophers are a buffer binding is
added to the client suit ok comments to
specify the location sorry submission
for blah blah blah it's require command
copy its value array buffer binding
christening to the client state love a
lot we're entering commands do our
reason to find appears to find we're
dating when arrays first reply prod at
the pointer value of that array is used
to compute an offset in machine units so
I'm pretty sure it's time I'm it it
should be time to do 16 Oh
Martin's wants to look at the call that
fails you talk about this one it's this
one right so what happens is if we call
this then our sub image call fails so if
we call text storage 3d then our text
sub image 3d call succeeds if we call
text image 3d write select for example
if I call tech storage 3d oops if I call
text storage 3d then what happens is
everything works just fine right if I
call text image 3d like this and it
doesn't seem to matter what I'm passing
here I tried passing different things
then what happens is I get a crash on
the actual on this call so when I
attempt to actually specify a slice it
doesn't like it and it says
that the type and format combination are
not valid uh but that's on the other
call right so I'm not sure you know I'm
guessing that just these two things have
to be set differently but I'm not sure
exactly what they need to be set to
originally what we tried is having them
set to the same thing so where we
actually specify right here we tried
just saying look it's gonna be be GRE
text that's the format and yeah it just
it just doesn't like it so I don't know
if it just doesn't like I mean maybe
this just has to be something else but
I'm not really sure what makes that goro
Gnaeus because this is just the
submission this is the sprite this is
the format right here right so I'm not
sure why I'm even having to specify that
because I don't need it to so it may be
that what I need to do is tell it yeah
I'm not sure maybe I just need to tell
it something different
it needs to be Jill rgba or whatever
value does not matter because it is for
the last argument pixel data which is no
yeah but that's not true right like I
can set it to RGB and it doesn't have
any it doesn't work right now maybe if
they're both set to RGB ba which would
give us incorrect results but maybe it
would wouldn't alt the driver no that
doesn't work either right so so that's
why we were calling the storage function
it's because that was actually what
works and I would be happy not to call
it but I don't know what else we would
do yeah correct you can pass anything
you want here it doesn't care it's it's
this call that fails and I don't know
what I could possibly pass that would
get this to succeed because we've passed
both of them and it doesn't work right
makes sense so I don't know any
combination of these two that would work
um I mean obviously I can pass the same
thing to both of them like so where
they're both getting RGB a so no txt in
this case and it does not care it's the
same problem right so we didn't that I
would have assumed and would would have
is to use the term lightly here I would
have assumed that this would work only
in the sense that the immediate the
reason I immediately check for 3d is I
remember having this problem in my own
I think GL Tech's image 3d is the
failing call I don't think it is
but we can double-check so I mean it
could be that it's just delaying the
error report but it's definitely not
where it fails so I'm probably gonna
call it for now we can figure out why
that's happening some other time but
Martin's I don't think what you're
suggesting actually works right it's you
you have to do something else not sure
what but something if you don't want to
call tech storage maybe you got it
called GL text image 3d in a different
way and just to be clear this doesn't
surprise me I had the same problem in my
code base in the in the 1935 code base I
remember specifically having this
problem I should go look to see if I
ever solved it without a storage call I
might have and just forgot what the
answer was but I remember this specific
problem where it's really obtuse what
has to happen here and I don't remember
what the answer was if there was one
yeah all right I'm gonna wrap it up we
can leave this in and just say so we'll
give that shot separately and just see
you know if we can figure out what's
going on there like why it's why it's
busted all right
all right thank you for joining me for
an episode of hand made here oh it's a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade he rode up org you
don't even need the slash game you can
just type it like that and it comes with
a source code so if you want to play
around at home maybe you want to figure
out how you actually have to call GL
techs image 3d in the magical set of
fantastical OpenGL parameters most of
which are very poorly specified which
one will magically work and I know what
you're thinking
Casey invalid texture format is a
fantastic error message that tells you
everything you might ever want to know
about why it failed and you're right
we're just kind of dense for not knowing
we're gonna be on break for a little bit
so I'll be back in a couple weeks time I
will be speaking in South Korea in two
weeks at the Busan indie connect
conference in in Busan and so if you
happen to be in the asia-pacific region
and just fancy a trip to Busan or if
maybe you live in Busan already check
out that conference
it's busan indie connect and also not
just me but chris hacker will be
speaking there as well some of you may
know him
I think we've he's been mentioned before
on the stream
he's oh my god
okay websites that play music by default
don't really care for them if you want
to turn your sound off and then go look
at their website you can I've shown you
how to get there I will never be going
there again okay anyway Chris Tucker
will also be sitting there he's the what
I was trying to say before I got blasted
with music
is he's the guy who does pie party and
he's speaking there as well there's also
a couple of speakers who I don't think
there are people who I've ever purchased
personally mentioned on the stream or
anything but they obviously have other
speakers speaking there so if you want
to see me speak at the conference or a
baby wants to see Chris speak at the
conference or maybe one of the other if
you can turn off your sound and go look
at the other speakers that were speaking
might be interested to you
check out that conference it's coming up
in two weeks okay until then if you
would like to watch old episodes or
hand-made here you can always go to the
watch page it's got old episodes on
there and it really easy to search
format so you can jump around it also
has a schedule so as soon as I post
schedule for when we will be returning
that's where it'll be Wow
we also have a fun page if you want to
support projects related to the series
like like the episode guide you'll find
on the watch page that other folks do
not me check that out that fund it's a
cool place to contribute that's about it
if you want to see what else we're up to
at Molly rocket you can always click on
the handmade hero head it'll jump you
right to our other sites of the other
stuff that we're working on or you can
always sign up for our mailing address
right down at the bottom it's pretty
easy to do that's it for the next few
weeks I'll be back here once my voice
recovers and after the Busan conference
- yeah I guess we did texture rays all
right so I'll be back to do a few more
things on on the renderer and sort of
harm harmonised the asset system with
the the renderer and and then we should
be good to go we could start decorating
our world with wall textures and little
other characters and stuff like that
alright I hope everyone has a good break
and I'll see you when we return ticket
use everybody