hello everyone and welcome to handmade
heroes show recode a complete game live
on stream yesterday we moved all of our
debug control code over into using our
sort of new debug interface stuff but we
didn't get a chance to actually turn any
of that on we just kind of did all the
work of like planning it out and making
it into macros and putting it into the
debug stream and all that stuff but we
don't actually have any way of actually
testing it yet so what we're going to do
here is wire that up and this will kind
of be nice too because now we don't have
to go through a compile cycle to switch
debug switches on and off anymore they
can just be switched in real time which
is going to be nice because we just
found when we tested it going through a
compile cycle for that even though is
only a few seconds is just a little too
long kind of want it to be roughly
instantaneous you know roughly one frame
of lag instead of you know a hundred
twenty frames of lag or however many it
is when msvc gets involved so that's
what we'll be doing today today is day 2
14 so if you are following along at home
with the source code because you're one
of those folks who ordered it on a hopi
art of the game you want to unpack day
213 source code because that's what i'm
starting with today so go ahead and do
that and you will be right where i am
right now all right so where we left
things was we were compiling properly
where we had all of our d bucks which is
actually compiling out and doing the
things that they needed to do but we
want to now start to have them show up
in here and in order to do that
obviously we're going to have to have
some way of having them you know
actually wired into the system right so
what we do know so far is if you take a
look at handmade debug H what we do know
is we've done the work and I'll also
love instructions in sorry interface at
H what we do know is that when these
things if we turn off the the sort of
nullification of them because we did it
right here where we sort of had a
of turning them off like this which you
know eventually is something that would
only happen here in fact we can go ahead
and move that down here now this is the
thing that kind of turns them off so if
they are turned on what we know is that
they're going to call a thing called
initialize debug value and really our
job at this point he is to go ahead and
figure out how we're going to get things
that Hall oops this actually probably
should be that guy things that call that
initialize debug value thing we need to
get those working so that they show up
in the hierarchy soothing okay we looks
like we have a situation here where we
didn't quite fix this one debug if just
uses a path now so we can do it like
that it looks like is that correct or is
that actually wrong and antiquated I
think that's right that's that's fine
all right so yeah what we need to do now
is we need to figure out some way it
looks like there's a bug in this thing
here now which is for some reason when
it's doing the concatenation was doing
the pasting it's still getting debug
variable variable what's the I see it's
because this is supposed to be path or
even update that one so what we need to
do is actually get these guys working
and figure out some way to make sure
that they kind of get exposed in our
debug hierarchy and it looks like we
also have to bug variable have to finish
that one as well so looking at debug
variable it looks like path is getting
use somewhere perhaps where path is not
supposed to be used yep that needs to be
string eyes and it wasn't string a nice
but now I think we're good and so now
we're just at the point where
initialized debug value is going to have
to actually get fielded by our debug
code right we've got everything
compiling and doing its thing but we
need somewhere where this is actually
going to sort of cook in to the debug
system right so let's go ahead and make
that happen I feel like it should
probably actually have had as well you
know since this is kind of an entry
point I feel like this should actually
be debug initialized value or something
like that
um something like this where it's
actually got the debug prefix in front
of it just so it's clear what's going on
there may be something like this like
that okay and with something like that
now we know that any time we see one of
these debug values in the code it's
going to come in like this and really
what we need to do now is we need to
figure out a way of ligand hooking that
into our system hooking that into the
system is not going to be particularly
difficult at the moment I don't think
because all we really need to do is
create one of our little debug
hierarchies and it can be basically a
static hierarchy right because it's not
something that changes every frame it's
something that's consistent across the
entire program for the most part the
only thing that we have to worry about
is whenever the program gets reloaded
right those static values are going to
vaporize right the static values are
going to go away so if we if we want our
system to work with our dynamic code
loading we have to be a little bit more
careful with how that's going to work
exactly but other than that we should be
fine right other than that we should be
fine now there's ways we could make it
work where we don't have to worry about
that as much but I think we want to do
it the way that we're doing it so far
for a number of reasons we'll see as we
kind of go in there but basically what
that means is when we do debug
initialized value you can see here that
this gets past is sort of the the static
value that it's actually talking about
right and sort of what I'm talking about
here is when the the debug system
reloads does a reload that is going to
invalidate all of these pointers right
because if you see what happens here the
way that I've set it up is whenever you
declare one of these debug variables an
if or a regular one it creates a debug
variable that's local to the stack of
that function but persistent so it's
like a global variable but that's only
local to the scope of that function so
other people can't reference it
obviously it creates that value and then
that value is something that's going to
be twiddled with by the debug system
mean the debug system have to reach in
there and change what the value actually
is for people to do stuff like toggle
the debug switches on and off
so in order to do that what I did is I
pass the address of that persistent
value so that basically anyone in the
debug system now knows they can reach in
and poke that value and change it to
something else the problem with that is
as soon as the debug executable gets
reloaded all of that data is now gone
right those pointers are no longer valid
and so what we would want to make sure
that we did if you're trying to support
the dynamic code reloading is we want to
have a way of making like making note
effectively of the fact that those debug
values have gone away right so we could
flush them or something now for bonus
points we might want to try and make it
so that any values that we had set get
carried over to the new version and I
think there's ways we could probably do
that as well and is so we can kind of
think a little bit about that as we go I
I kind of sort of homebrewing an idea
for that it's like percolating in my
head but basically what I'm thinking is
if we wanted to do something like
dynamic code reloading but and in in
addition if we want these values to be
persistent across runs which I think we
do then I think what we want to do is
keep the concept of our config dot H
here with these global constants and
what I was thinking is when we do these
debug value initialize things what we
could do is when the debug value gets
initialized we could pass in right what
that initial value was going to be so
that when the initial value gets so so
that when you relaunch the program it
knows what the value was supposed to
because we can always rewrite this file
with the most recent values that the
person is set in the debug user
interface that's just what I'm thinking
and so basically this thing down here
which creates this this sort of global
constant thing like so what I'm
imagining there is it would sort of say
oh yeah when you create this initial
value this debug initialized value
there's going to be ways of passing
something into that so when you do this
you get those constants those constants
come out right
like so oops that's not what I wanted
not what I wanted in fact what is
happening get rid of that no bad bad
okay let's try that one more time let's
try that one more time right like that
ok so what I want to do here right if I
want to give it a way of getting what
the value should have been that can
persist across runs so I'm letting that
happen through that config thing and so
in order to do that what I mean is what
I need to do here is make sure that this
thing has a couple different types of
value potentially right some way of
making sure that this thing can can
actually initialize itself in a
meaningful way and so this is mostly the
kind of values that we're using right
you could imagine maybe these visa these
would be sort of the value types that
were happening there and so probably
what I would want to do is I would want
to make it so that this guy has a bunch
of variants right and each one of them
is basically just all it's doing is it's
doing it a type it cracks out the type
there that's really all it's meant to do
and again it's just kind of an annoying
C++ C thing you could use a template for
it perhaps if you wanted to well no you
couldn't actually use a template for it
not in this particular case but point
being you could amuse a letter language
for it anyway so what we need to do is
make sure that we have these specified
such that all of the things we might
want to pass or there I'm not sure what
the best way necessarily do that would
be maybe would this be enough to keep it
satisfied I'm not sure let's take a look
yeah so as long as we have all of these
and that's probably actually an s32
there so that is yeah so yeah so one of
the problems is you know with something
like a bool we don't really have much of
a way of stating specifically that it is
a pool or not and so that might be
something that we have to say
specifically we may have to say debug
initialize value like bull right or
something like that
where we've got the S 32s in there but
we also have one of these that's
actually specific to pool and it's like
the initialize pool or b32 like that
right and that one we would use with the
ifs and the reason that I was saying
that we have to do that is because it's
not going to be able to know the
difference between an integer and a
regular it's not gonna be leaders
because we just use our boolean type is
the same as our integer type right we
don't have two different types so it
needs kind of like one additional one
here that's going to be able to do that
bull thing do that the whole thing right
so we need one more there but anyway
that's what we're talking about here and
what we want to do is we want to turn
all these into something reasonable
right we want to turn all these into
something that just kind of does
whatever needs to do so it's like it
calls debug initialized value with sort
of the the base set of things that has
to happen right without the value that's
being set and then once it knows that
it's okay to go you know this is always
going to just return that that in
whatever the event is it's actually be
pointed to hear but once it it's done
with that it's just going to know that
it can set the value to whatever the
value was passed in and that's just a
way of like again getting that
initialization to happen automatically
for the calling code and so this is
again what this is doing you know with
these the weight of this code is being
structured again it's designed to remove
as much work as possible from the other
side of the calling fence right it's
designed as much as possible to sort of
to fix that part of the problem and yeah
so that's that's really all that's
happening there in fact you know what I
realized to you know it's too bad now
that i think about it when we do the
debug initialized value thing it's too
bad i wonder if we could use a comma
here I wonder it I wonder if we could
use a comma here to get out of this
business all entirely let's see can we
do you guys want to take a look at that
I want to I'm into it I don't know if
you're into it but I'm into it
I'm just saying hypothetically speaking
suppose we were to do something that's
not gonna actually compiler thought that
suppose you were to get rid of all this
stuff and we just said no no no no no no
no instead what we're going to do is
when we do debugging are slaves value
and we've got that type in there we're
going to call that and just let that
initialize the event but we're going to
use the sequence operator I mean I said
it we're going to use a sequence
operator to sneak in and do another
operation inside the equals right I
don't know it's a bold move is it is it
brassy is it ballsy yes am I going to go
for it yes I think that's just the way
you got to be sometimes you gotta
program you got a program dirty
sometimes you know what I mean you got
to just get up in there and you got to
do it and so that's what we're going to
do here so if I were to take this event
I know that I can construct if I have
that the type right which in this case I
know is a rule 32 right I know I could
do it this way and in here I'll know the
type as well because the types fast in
there so I'm just wondering if I can use
the sequence operator to steal away a
little bit of an assignment here right
and I don't know right I don't know if I
can do that maybe I can maybe I can't
but we'll find out and oops the event
that we're in question is actually that
right will it work I don't know nobody
knows nobody can ever know how could
they initializing connect connect four
be 32 to debug event yep put them in the
wrong order that's a little bit of a
risk with a sequence operator let's find
out if we're okay here still not good
missing before period which period debug
value path uh that's not right why did I
do that we want no that is right debug
value path why did that network do you
book value path dot it's missing a
closing quote
but why is it missing a closing quote
don't really understand they don't need
those parentheses anymore don't really
understand missing semicolon before
period it doesn't seem to like this
construction very much or at least if
I'm not mistaken it does not seem to
like that very much but of course I
might be mistaken so why does it think
I'm missing the semicolon in there what
exactly Jimmy what exactly are you
complaining about because I know debug
value pound pound path is a valid value
to look at and I feel like I should be
able to access off of it I wonder if
it's just a case of you know is it just
my sequence operator nonsense that I'm
trying to pull which admittedly is a
little bit janky is that your problem
type care unexpected yeah that does look
a little bit like I guess it does not
like my sequence operator there I feel
like that should it's probably because
it's in the initializer that it doesn't
like that would be my guess so maybe
what I can do and again this is me just
like I said I'm really kind of doing
some ridiculous things here you know
don't try this at home but what I could
do here is say oh okay maybe I use the
sequence operator inside the expression
so I do something where I try to put it
in well I can't put it in a parameter
list mm-hmm man I don't know I really
don't know I'm just trying to figure out
this any way I could get it in there in
some way that makes it so that we don't
have to deal with with the rest of it
hmm excuse me so let's try it this way
this is again completely ridiculous what
I'm doing but I'm just going to try it
does not take for up Wow
so that worked apparently okay so i
don't know if you saw what i try to do
here again it's kind of ridiculous but
basically what i wanted to do is I'm
initializing a static I don't want
anything to escape that static
initialization because I only want it to
happen once right I don't want it to
happen every time this code I only
wanted to happen once so it needs to be
on the right side of the expression that
initializes the static so i have a
function call here and what i wanted to
do was I wanted to somehow figure out a
way to get this particular piece of code
to execute in there so what I did is I
use a sequence operator right the comma
to say hey man do this first then do
this second to produce this first
argument and it is ok with that so I'm
just going to go ahead and pretend that
that was okay i'm going to pretend
nothing weird happened even though
something very weird just happened and
i'm going to do it again I'm just going
to straight up do it a second time
because that's the way we roll here so
here it is a second time and here's the
reason I was trying to do it here is
because now we only need one copy of dbh
last value because what we can do is do
the assignment right in here so here's
the value that we want to set we just
set value and then we paste on the type
and we say equals and now we've
generated all of those versions that I
was manually copying out before those
are done now so that's awesome that
saves a lot of typing lot of typing so
now we have all of our types handled and
we didn't have to duplicate functions at
all that's pretty fun sequence operator
occasionally comes in very very handy
very very handy love your sequence
operator for those of you don't know
what it does it just allows you to put
in multiple expressions and then it just
uses the value of what is the last
expression yeah it just takes the value
of whatever the last expression was so
you can just chain a bunch of unrelated
expressions together and it just execute
the last one right
well excuse all them but it evaluates to
the value of the last one all right so
we'll see if that worked that again like
I said kind of ridiculous maneuver there
but sometimes they're warranted let's go
ahead and make debug initialize value
work in some way that makes some sense
to somebody sometime somewhere inside
handmade interface debug interface we
should have that definition for the
debug event there it is right and so I'm
think assuming that well the way we
would want to do this is the clock value
would be 0 the file name would be
whatever the file name is the line
number the block name is the name you
pass in the line number would be
whatever the line number actually is so
we can maybe pass those in now we could
we could easily pass those and if we
want to sue me we've got the thread ID
I'm not sure how much we care about the
thread ID necessarily but we could even
do that if we wanted to that isn't don't
we just have a way to do get threadid
yeah and I don't know how we do get
correr index I feel like the core index
is not relevant I want to say the thread
ID isn't relative it either I don't know
I'm gonna need those initial I 200 now
because this is kind of a permanent
standing variable so I don't know what
it even means to say some of those
things about it all right so if we've
got that set up really all we would need
to do here is pass in the file name and
the line number you know and so I'm
going to go ahead and make it so that
that is what these guys expect to see
here here we are in the interface code
debug initialized value if I want to
hear I can demand those two things and
then these guys will just go ahead and
give them to me right like so
and there we go so now we've initialized
these events so the only thing that we
need to do now the only thing we need to
do in addition to that is figure out
some way to add like something into our
debug system that would allow us to
manipulate these types indirectly right
or you know that would allow them to
sort of do like a pointer to this event
right and so in order to do that we need
to add something that points into these
events and we you know we have a way of
doing that right that's that's a that's
what our sort of system is set up to do
there's like sort of the add to group
thing right we've got a dad how does
this work here we did this inside our
sort of gathering thing and data block
open data block open data block there we
go so this stuff essentially here when
we do open data block and close
datablock really what we want to do here
is we want to do this this part where we
add events to a data block what we
really want to do is just that right
what we want to do is take these things
when we get them we want to add them
just like we were adding other stuff and
then we just need some group to add them
to so if we get the debug state right in
here and i'm going to go ahead we need
there's one other thing that we're going
to need to do because this is so it's
going to fire and it's something that i
mentioned we should probably do the
other day but we didn't do so we're
going to have to do it now what we want
to do here you say ok I've got this
debug state what I'd like to do is I'd
like to add a variable to this group you
know I'd like to push it on there we do
have one sort of nasty thing here which
is that we don't necessarily know that
these calls are coming from the same
thread right so we would need some way
of making sure that when we do that when
we add things to this group we would
like to be able to make sure that only
one thread is doing that addition of the
time right so in order to do that we
need some kind of a mutex here right
we need to take some kind of a lock to
just go I need them you know I need to
access this data member which is this
group structure here I don't have lock
free versions of that code right it's
all just assuming that it can just write
the pointers if they'll be coherent at
the time and so what we need to do here
is like something that would basically
take this lock right we need something
that would go like okay you know you
know we need like an acquirer mutex you
know release mutex thing that just
allows us to modify that data member as
we go and this is the only place that
this really has to happen because most
of the time it's just not an issue there
are two ways we could do this we could
also instead push it and you know what I
just realized it's probably smarter if
we actually do the push it's probably
smarter to just let these be collated
sometime after the fact I mean if you
when you get right down to it that's
probably the case we wouldn't need to
take a mutex or anything like that we
cook what we could do is just add a vent
in here that's like hey I want to record
this permanent variable so actually
that's probably much more likely what we
should do that would also get us out of
the business of having to initialize the
debug system which I said we were going
to have to do we wouldn't have to do
that so yeah never mind that probably is
a better way to do this and we should do
that better way
now okay so yeah if we want to do that
off we go what that's going to look like
is is well this stuff here can pretty
much stay the way that it is really all
that's going to look like is inside
handmade debug interface all we would do
is say well okay when we do you know
when we do all this stuff here and we're
sort of doing these like creating these
persistent variables and we do the debug
initialize value what the debug
initialized value actually would be at
that point right is the debug
initialized value would would actually
have to be or include some some code to
push something onto the debug stream
right so we would want to be one of
these things here that does a record
debug event and record debug event would
just push the fact that this
initialization had occurred right and
yeah so pretty much I think that's
mostly all we need to do so let's look
at how record debug event works in
general looks like it works just yet
exactly what you would think right so
yeah I want to do that operation I'm
just not sure if I guess probably what
we would need to do is kind of 22 stage
that right so we'd want to do it
something like this probably and this
would be not a string so what we want to
do is like we've got debug initialized
value here and then it calls into you
know sort of the one level down version
of that so yeah it would be more like
this here is our initial call it's just
an inline function and the inline
function does a record debug event to do
that this thing and it this is basically
something that's like Mark you know Mark
debug value or something and that mark
debug value hotel where it is then it
would catch after it recorded the debug
event which is thread-safe and all that
then
call in and do this stuff although I
guess now I think about it that stuff
can just go right here as well so you
know yeah I guess this goes away
entirely so I guess this just becomes an
inline like so and this is not existing
this itself will just do what it needs
to do record debug event presumably
returns the event I'm guessing and so
the event there's actually two events
this is the like market marker event
that mark event just has to have an
event pointer that points to our event
and then it's marked right makes some
sense okay so all that has to happen for
that to work as far as I can think of in
my head and again so that makes that
totally thread safe as well which is
kind of nice is that it here we need
some way of marking these things so we
need something that's like debug type
you know Mark event remark debug value
rather and then here we need something
looks like a debug event star event and
that I think would be it right although
this should be called value debug event
to maintain consistency yeah yeah yeah
okay illegal use of this type is an
expression used 64 what are you talking
about what are you saying oh right it
works like this so I guess in this case
and that will probably define event for
us because this is a macro that expands
to something so I guess technically what
I would want to do here is debug event
this is actually like the sub event or
something right so it would be something
that looks like this
and this is valued debug event so that's
it I think seems good yeah alright so I
think that does everything we need to do
these are now in the debug stream they
can be picked up by people who are
trying to collate them and then they can
be added so I don't know again like I
said whether that's the best thing or
not but I just kind of thought of it and
it seems like it solves all the problems
that we might have had with them which
is like yeah you know we would have had
to make sure that it was thread-safe we
would have had to make sure the debug
session was the dish lifetime now we
don't care right any of that these
values just go into the stream like
everything else and then later on the
debug system if it cares will pick them
up if it doesn't care it just won't
right and so in here we'd have something
like case debug type you know mark debug
event or whatever deal with value and
here we would just do a kool-aid ad
variable to group and when we add the
variable to the group we would be adding
that sub event to some group now there's
a little bit more to it than this it's a
little bit more complicated to create
the hierarchy so that's the code will
write for the next 20 30 minutes or
whatever I guess we have 30 minutes left
for the remainder of the show will write
that code but at first let's just get it
working where all the variables kind of
just show up in a list that aren't
hierarchical and then we'll from their
kind of go into something that does a
little bit more fancy pantsy dancing
Nancy stuff to it right so there's
collate add variable to group we have
the debug state we have the event on on
this end in the middle is the problem
because these two things actually are
just fine because if we want to add it
we know it's the sub event so it's just
event value debug event that's the one
that we're trying to add we've already
marked it it's good the problem is we
don't know what group to add it to here
we have no idea so we want to do here is
we want to do something like you know
get group for a name or
thing like this or I I mean you know I
don't know we're gonna it's good that's
what's get group for name everyone loves
get group for name don't you I do I
think I'm not sure point being it's fine
don't worry about it it's just how it
goes sometimes and then it would do
collide I brought a group and and you
know honestly honestly if we're being
honest about it I almost want to say
that if we were going to be super fancy
about it if we were going to like double
up on the fanciness now with extra
fanciness I feel like we almost want to
do this in a way that's a little flyer
than that that's going to be something
more like this where we have debug
events or I guess what is collate add
variable to group returned it adds debug
very like okay so we'd have to brave the
link and we do link and we do like get a
higher you know hierarchical name or
something or get our goal link from name
you know and then in this thing we would
pass the event lock name and we say like
I want you to get me the link for this
thing right whatever it is and and when
you get me that link back what I want to
do is say whatever the link used to be
in there oh this is a tricky one
this is actually pretty tricky I'll be
honest with you it's pretty tricky so
I'm going to draw this out for you I'm
going to tell you what I was trying to
do so we're clear on it and we'll see it
will see I the thing that I wanted to do
i'm not sure if it's not as easy as I
thought it was going to be it's just a
subtlety of this of the way this code
worked oh never mind so I forgot I
already solve this problem in my head
and I even talked about the game of show
I'll tell you what I was thinking just
so you can be a part of the thought
process but what I was thinking is like
okay I'm going to create this debug
hierarchy right it's gonna be like foo
and then there's a bar in here and then
there's like a bass and the bass is
going to be some floating point value
that's like five point oh right and
we're running the game that's all good
and then we go ahead and the executable
reloads right so the executable goes
away which means that the event that
this was pointing to now goes away and
we lose the three-point oh so as
thinking before was like oh I need to be
able to like get back this one and
remember the three-point oh so I can set
it again in blah blah i forgot i just
did all that work to make sure that the
global classes through the flow through
so it's actually going to happen is when
we change these values they'll write out
to the global constant store that like
file you know a little ride out to
handmade config.h these values are going
to be written out into there eventually
which means that I don't they care about
that because the new executed will be
come pre-loaded with the right values so
that's actually kind of handy and so I
don't have to worry about the thing I
was going to do so forget all of that
nonsense that I just said because it's
all completely irrelevant goodbye
goodbye so yeah so get a group for a
name is actually a you know something
like that we could just say that that's
going to return us whatever the group is
that should be added to back to the
original thing I was saying that should
be totally sufficient
we don't have to do the preservation
thing and this again means that the only
thing we actually need to do is
implement this particular function where
it finds out what the group is for a
particular name right and here's that
name now we probably need to pass the
debug stay for that I'm guessing because
otherwise how's it going to do the
search and then the other thing we're
going to need is we're going to need
some group that these things go into
like before we kind of had this
situation where we were adding things to
to a group as the blocks got opened and
closed right and now so we're going to
have another one here that's like these
are like the values group or whatever
right the debug values group so that
group where do we do our route group
right we create one here looks like four
that's four frames we don't care about
that one so it's really in here right is
what we want yeah so we have a problem
here where we have the kool aid stuff we
again have sort of a nasty little
situation that we have and this is just
gets back to us we really need to kind
of go finish sometime soon doing the
collation stuff as more of a permanent
thing because really we want all these
guys to be permanent and then we want to
wipe them out presumably so as we kind
of move through frames we want to wipe
out data that's no longer necessary or
something like this right so we'll push
that for a second and not have to think
about that at the moment but I yeah what
we would want to do here is when we do
that kool-aid ad variable to group you
can see here that that puts it on the
collation arena and that's a problem for
us right so we kind of need to unify
those at some point soon before we get
too much further out of hand because
these are values that we don't want to
go away they're sort of permanent
standing values and so we kind of have
that dichotomy there now again the only
reason we have that the Academy is
because we haven't gone and finished
sort of how we're doing our frame by
frame processing so that means that's
probably the next thing may that's what
we should start on tomorrow either that
or we kind of have a long break so maybe
we put that off until after we come back
since it might take more than a day to
finish hard to say that maybe
doing the day hard to say but anyway so
in here when we do this we would need a
separate way of doing add kohli
parallel-group look we need something we
could say like permanent in here right
and in here where we do our part we
would have to say whether you were
trying to keep it for a while or not
right and again this is really not like
I said this is not good we don't want to
actually leave it this way this is just
like definitely a thing where we like to
do move everything to permanent because
really we don't want to actually do that
kind of flushing that was never the goal
it's just kind of how we left the system
because we hadn't actually figured out
how we were going to do frame by frame
processing yet and yeah so that'll have
to be another thing anyway so in here if
its permanent you know it would go on
the debug arena if it's not permanent it
wouldn't not very complicated right very
simple but that would have to happen and
then we do get group for hierarchical
name at the moment we can do is just say
because we just are trying to get it
working here what we can do is say
forget that we're not actually going to
do any of that at all instead what we're
going to do is just say like okay we
have the debug state values group and
everything is going to go onto the
values group right everything is you
know everything that we have is going to
go onto the value screwed so that is is
easy because we don't do any work here
variable group like so and then the
other thing that we would need to do
again is when we do collate where's the
thing that does the group kolay create
variable group right so this one right
here where we create a variable group
that as well would also need to take
that permanent thing right like so
really you know what I don't know why I
wrote it that way either since we're
just talking about this it would just be
permanent debug State kool-aid arena or
debug State keep up so I'm not sure why
I didn't do it that way both times again
probably because I was too busy to think
about the fact that we probably should
do that but yeah it's hard sometimes I'm
handmade here because you know I have to
parcel things out into like ways that
are more coherent to explain which is
not always exactly how they would do
them and most of the time I can keep it
so that they're the same but sometimes
it's like I would really go fix this now
and just take two hours to do it and it
would be done but I know that doesn't
fit inside a boundary like four episodes
and stuff and it makes it a little bit
tricky in my head but anyway so that's
relatively straightforward and that's
all done and so now we're fine and
everything is good so that should be all
we would need to do there I don't know
why we didn't call that debug state but
now these guys have to say okay this is
not permanent this guy is permanent
right this guy is not this guy's not
this guy's not and funk she does not
take one arguments that's true and
functions not take three arguments that
is also true so there we go so that's
everything but I need to initialize when
we initialize the debug system i want to
create a initial group to hold all of
these these peoples so when we call
debug start in here and this stuff kind
of gets initialized at the beginning i
want to make sure that we have
everything that we need in here so what
I want to do is is make sure that we can
do like a.m. yeah like you know whatever
the thing is values group equals like
Chloe create variable group right and
that's a pretty bad name for
because we're not actually thinking it
as a collation anymore because again
it'll presumably those names will change
again but yeah so there's our values
group so now when we run that I don't
know it should in theory pick up all
those debug variables and all we have to
do now is actually have somewhere to
display them now what we can do display
them temporarily to write is we've got
sort of our debug draw a menu so all we
have to do here in our debug draw a menu
is when we are looping over these things
we can just do a thing where we go like
okay our hacky group instead of this now
is going to actually be something else
so our hacking group is just going to be
debug state values group and this would
show us what's in that group so we can
test it and see if our stuff that picks
up these values is working at all which
I don't know if it is right okay so
let's see what's going on here so first
of all this is some weirdness here so
first of all we're sort of working in
the sense that Hey look it wired up
properly but why are we getting the same
one why are we getting you know a bunch
of calls that are the same debug value
because that local persist should have
only initialized one time so what is
that about so we got a bunch of
debugging to do but otherwise were you
know we're pretty close right we're
pretty close to what we want because it
actually did wire up properly and and we
can actually turn on the actual value in
real time now instead of a growth iqbal
do cycle so all we really need to do is
for out what's going on there with the
multiple ads and then we can proceed
right okay so let's let me start at the
beginning where we have mark debug value
we're calling kool-aid a very up to
group we get the group here and in
theory that should be fine and we're
adding in the event that's pointed to
the value debug event which should have
been that one and in fact I guess now
think about it we probably should be
using that one's name as well when we do
that we that won't matter because we're
not actually doing anything on it yet
but when we would go to do that that
would have been a problem right so now
when we call kohli add variable to group
what we want to do is to
look here inside the interface thing and
make sure that that's an actual that all
of this stuff works out properly so we
have our sub event here that we're
looking at we are pointing to that one
properly and that is the one that we're
trying to add we initialize the sub
event with the name as we should we
initialize the line number the thread ID
the core type looks right as well so all
that stuff looks for do we got about ten
minutes left on the clock edition so we
have actually 15 minutes left which is
quite a bit of time so if we can debug
this in that time so our debug ifs here
hopefully look like there would be
working relatively well to me like that
all looks pretty good and yeah I don't
see I don't really see what the problem
is here I don't understand why we would
get multiple ones and we shouldn't ever
because this is always doing you know an
initialization only once local persist
is defined to be static right I mean we
just make sure that we didn't mess that
up but presumably we don't and if it
wasn't we'd get a lot more of them so
yeah local persist attic so I feel like
that should have worked obviously it
doesn't so I'm going to just set a
breakpoint in debug initialized value so
I can see what's happening there and
figure out what's going on so here we
are getting called with this in game
update and render his ground chunks
recompute on exe change so I'm just want
to take a look here and see what we
actually got so here's our event and the
event looks about right it's got a block
name of nothing which is what we expect
because we didn't pat that's as f what
we passed it's got a line number a
threat ID that it all makes sense it's
got the type that we expect right which
is to mark the debug value and it's got
values in here that don't actually
correspond to anything quite yet right
so then we would assign it and now it's
a sign to debug value right here now of
course
debug value is completely meaningless
but that's because we have initializing
yet as we initialize it coming through
here you can see that it gets basically
what we would expect it to get here is
the name that we expect it to have
there's the line number of the thread ID
the type hmm what type is that debug be
32 so that's good and then it returns
whatever that is right so now we should
if we look at the locals here where we
don't have the locals I probably turn
them off because I very rarely use them
but now I want them if you look at the
locals here we should have yes and stuff
and we do so here is that debug value
ground chunks recompute on eggsy change
which is this one here here you can see
it is set properly as far as I could
tell although although why is it set why
is its value set to 10 because that is
what the default value is in the config
so that's again actually also totally
correct so that's even working properly
so it's got all that and then it can do
its little thing and so that's all good
everything there looks fine and I'm not
sure yeah what the problem was there ok
so
I think I know what's wrong in fact I
definitely know what's wrong yes to
things don't ask me why I thought of
this just now but sometimes the brain
works that way thing number one is it's
in the wrong place of for our processing
right this is inside the collation frame
processing which means that if we have
not had a frame marker yet we will not
record it and that is not what we want
at all right that's like a bad situation
what we want to do is record it
regardless right so what we want to do
is in here we want to actually have a
special case which is like we always
want these no matter what right so in
here where we do else processing we
would want to do a thing where we say
else if and just like we did this one
right we would want to do okay else if
this will actually it's not even else if
it would actually be up here right it's
so if eventtype equals mark debug value
oops that's no good no matter whether we
have a frame open or not we want to
capture it right so that was bug number
one because basically they were all
happening on the first frame and they
all got thrown out right we didn't
bother to prostate them so that should
solve the problem of them not showing up
if that makes sense oh wait a minute to
somehow get past this here if it up
missing in else copypasta as you guys
say okay so now we've got all these guys
right you can actually see them all here
and so now that the next question is
just how can we have so many of them
right like how come there are multiple
of these guys and the answer to that I
believe is because the statics are
probably not
being used in a thread-safe way meaning
multiple threads could probably all
enter that and start using them I guess
I don't actually know what the rules are
for that because normally that's not
something that I spend a lot of time
looking at statics like almost never use
so the in a debug systems the only time
I would ever use them and so I believe
that this is actually something to do
with that now you can see that it
actually works just fine it's just a
question of why we've got so many of
them right but I think that might be it
I feel like maybe the statics are stored
in thread-local storage or something
like this maybe I don't know to be
honest I'm not sure exact what's going
on there but I have a feeling that it
has something to do with the threading I
don't actually know you might have
nothing to do with the threading for all
I know but we're going to find out okay
so that's all working up to the point
where we're getting multiple copies but
everything else about it seems to work
okay so the question is just why are we
getting multiple values right why so the
first thing we could do is just turn off
threading and see if that's actually the
case as a test so that I know what I'm
looking for right so I know whether I'm
looking for something to do with the
threading or whether it has nothing to
do with the threading it's just a
regular old bug that doesn't have to it
doesn't have anything to do with that
right so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to reduce the number of threads
down to a different number and see if
that changes the number of duplicates
that we get right so when we have create
thread here when we do this right right
here and we have the sort of thread
count thing win32 make you I'm going to
just reduce that number right so
temporarily i'm going to say that
there's just one thread in these guys
and then i'm going to run it and let's
see see what we get so that looks to me
like we got less in the ground out in
the ground chunks out lines but
everybody else has way plenty you know
actually has tons of them right so i
would say that does not look that just
does not
look to me like it is it is a threading
thing right that looks pretty much not
like a threading thing to me all right
so if we're not looking for a threading
thing then we have to just figure out
how come we're adding these things
multiple times right look what's
happening there and I'm not exactly sure
because I feel like we shouldn't
actually call that function at all where
we do the that that initialization I
feel like that should not be getting
called multiple times what I want to do
is I want to go inspect a call site now
and see if I'm right about that or
whether the compiler is doing something
else in there entirely so let's just
take a break point here and I'm going to
go ahead and go to the disassembly
because I just want to see what is
actually happening inside this
disassembly right so here we go we're
coming through this at the first you
know the very first time we're taking a
look at this s3 location which i assume
is where the statics are stored and
we're taking a look to see whether we've
initialized it or not and it turns out
that we have not right so this jump this
jump not equal that jump would have
jumped us past right 1266 right there
you can see it goes to 86 h right 86 h
is down here somewhere there it is so it
would just skip over this code and start
doing other stuff in the event where it
was not a better didn't need to
initialize right so then we're going to
load this stuff in here here we go and
presumably like again all this stuff
like where we're actually calling to you
bug initialized value that stuff is all
happening only this one time right so
that should never happen again the
recompute on eggs you change I don't
think right here it goes we're putting
that guy in there we're pushing him on
to the t bug stack and that's just
that's just it right nothing else
happens here it just initializes the
value exact like you would expect
hmm so I don't see why that would have
also let me check one that's actually
that I can see is being so and that one
gets added multiple times as well right
so yeah not only that but it's the same
debug ID so it's like it just keeps
looping over itself as well right so I
don't understand I think we've got a
problem with our tree I don't think we
actually have a problem necessarily with
our I think we're well I don't know what
we're doing this is a bit of a puzzler
I'm not sure exactly what's happening
that's kind of bizarre that's a little
bizarre pulley add variable to group g
list insert link event is the one to add
it does not have children a cert link
event type is not equal to begin block
ok that seems pretty innocuous to me
right that doesn't seem particularly
weird let's see what happens in our in
our hockey printout thing here so
there's only braslia we're just
printing just this one tree I assume and
then we're kind of doing our traversal
here ah and again that seems pretty sane
to me I don't get it I don't get it
so it could be because we are collating
multiple times on the r yeah that's I
think still it's I think it's all just
the same thing I think about it it's all
going to be because we're collating
multiple times as well right when we do
collate debug records any time we call
restart collation it's not going to like
them it's not going to go wipe those
guys out so you know presumably if when
we did restart collation we actually did
a flush year of those guys then we would
be fine but of course we don't want to
do that because we want them to stick
around permanently right so that's a bit
of a bummer it's okay I suppose because
we could also make it so that when these
things get added we could make it so
that they if they find themselves in the
hierarchal name they don't add a new one
but I don't know so i would say
basically i think what's happening there
is when we restart collation it'll just
reread those events and add them again
and so i think really what we need to do
is just stop doing that entirely you can
see like we do this a couple times right
when the egg xia is reloaded we do it
anytime refresh collation happens right
which is any tiny press like the left
mouse button as well so I feel like that
is really what the problem is and when
the frame when the frame count right in
here we're doing it every frame yeah
well that's okay that was the next thing
we need to fix anyway so I'm just going
to say that's it for today tomorrow that
pretty much means that's what we have to
fix right and that's good anyway because
it's kind of been going on too long
having that sort of weird janky like how
do these events get retired sort of a
thing so I think probably what we would
want to do is just legitimately go in
there and be like okay let's actually
clean this out and make it so that we
process one frame at a time
and that as things pull out of the
buffer we get rid of them and stuff like
that which is going to be a little bit
of work but we'll do it right so I think
that's all good and I think probably
yeah I mean we probably should make a
pretty big dent in tomorrow I don't know
if we'll be able to finish it in time
but we could probably make a pretty big
that's in tomorrow and then that would
fix our problem with the multiple
editions so I'm going to go ahead and go
to the QA
you
just as you use says variable initiation
hack in debug if macro makes my internal
code quality kitten sad would it be
possible to move that initiation to
struct quote quote method I'm not sure
what you mean does use could you be more
specific BTW in games persisting the
debug value between live code loading is
great i didn't understand what you were
viewing but then i got it with the demo
really cool i had completed the value of
variable with the value of debug value
of debug of the variable small audition
for a huge benefit okay
any questions
you
doesn't look like it although I would
like just used to say what he thought
was the thing he wanted to have the
cleaner didn't really understand what he
was saying
uh yeah i mean he's talking about this
right here but i'm not sure
BTW names are you sad you didn't fix
collation if no more questions come in
it would be neat to see it now so you're
not sad it's going to be a pretty
involved thing right like that's our
final sort of thing for handling the
flow of data through the system so I'm
not going to fix it in like 10 minutes
right basically that's the thing where
it just kind of actually parcels it up
mr. fourth dimension will you have time
tomorrow to look at for kodir I am
trying to decide whether to prioritize
getting the new demo out tomorrow
morning i would say it depends on
whether it's closer to being switchable
to use for me which i think i think it
was completion and make inside the
program i remember what the main holdups
were uh for for coder and i don't
remember what they are but i could look
because like you added undo which is
awesome and is definitely something that
would have prevented me from being able
to switch permanently but that's not
something I need to do a for a quote of
friday on cuz like yes awesome that's
checked off the list but i don't need to
test it I trust that you have it working
right and that's undo so I'm trying to
think if there are any other things I
need to play with and it would depend
right it would depend if there's new
features that would be in that demo that
I should should see if I can move more
of my to-do list over to then we could
do it if not then I don't tend to add I
don't tend to really need to do a for
code of friday for things where it's
like this was a good feature edition but
it's not currently blocking my my dotty
max
yes that's a really long and more winded
way of doing it mr. first mentioned
gotcha I do have parameterised commands
that I'd love to hear response on sure
well you know don't forget dude you
don't have to wait for the pre stream
you could just send me the demo look it
doesn't mean email and i'll reply so
what i would say is like you know if i
have time we could do a for co2 friday
but even if we don't just send me an
email and i'll i'll look at it and send
back or apply the nighties fly why are
you awesome I just I guess you know
sometimes you just are awesome which
dojo did you train to become a code
warrior I don't know but like code
warriors bad term because there used to
be a program called codewarrior that was
like actually kind of lame it was a
integrated development environment for
the Mac
let's see here disused elaborated with
a/c muratori prefix really because I
don't see it but that may be because the
network is totally broken on my linux
laptop because linux is amazing so i
haven't seen it unfortunately i'm
looking at the raw stream and i don't i
don't see anything from disused magda
nobody i quote instead of writing debug
event name equals initiator another Bell
chiming blah blah blah make a struct
constructor debug event that initializes
the value wait why but why would I do
that what what would be the point of
doing that though like that doesn't
actually do anything different does it
and i guess i would say i actually have
a large number of problems with what
your suggest what you're suggesting
because if i add a constructor to debug
event then i can no longer actually make
one on the stack without it calling that
constructor and then i have to make
another constructor that would make it
so that it would use that one in
preference of the other one it like no
like that's making a constructor for a
debug event is definitely not on the
table so that I definitely wouldn't do
but i also am not sure what problem
you're trying to solve in the existing
code
just used so that you don't do
assignment in the function call in the
macro which makes me really sad but why
does it make you sad like what what
makes you sad about that the sequence of
operations that the CPU needs to do are
the same right so why do we care we're
there which part of the struck which
part of the line is causing them to
occur right i mean at least in this case
you can actually see what's happening
whereas in your constructor example you
wouldn't even know what was happening
you have to go look at the constructor
right so i would actually say that i
actually vastly prefer the one as
written here even though it's kind of a
typical to making constructor which i
think is probably worse on all counts
it's less understandable by a person who
is going to read it it's more likely to
create problems in other pieces of code
because now there is a constructor in
the struck which didn't have before and
so now the compiler will demand that you
call that constructor unless you add a
secondary constructor to avoid calling
it when you're going to call it right so
so yeah i would i would actually
strongly disagree with with this
suggestion that making a struct
constructor for debug event is is a
better way of writing that code i would
say it's actually strictly worse
that said I mean you know in your code
base you should do whatever you want but
in my code base I would not make that
choice also it really bothers me that
the network on this laptop is so bad
that I didn't see disused original post
like that's super oh no there it is I
did miss it there it is right there okay
I was going to be really grumpy about
that if it was like not passing me stuff
that would have been bad
and elvin i have not had any chance to
play any games recently in fact the only
time I've had the ability to play games
it was the games that i streamed the
other like two weeks ago or whatever
that was the only time I've had to play
games I wish I had more time to play
games but at the moment I just don't Sam
Martin Cohen yes elvin is alex &amp; noise
said I kept trying to pronounce his name
elsa noised or whatever but then at some
point like he just said you can just say
elvin that's what he said so now I just
say Elvin which is a lot easier to say
to say the least
how did you keep up that awesome beat
just now it's just like it's the rhythm
man the night is fly what games type
again I like all kinds of games they're
interesting I don't like games that are
like kind of very the same to like
something I've already played and just
kind of like throwing it in like I don't
like it when they do like we're gonna do
a new license movie title it's like it's
the Avengers game and it's like the same
game as like every other game only like
the little sprite that like you push the
button to like punch or whatever is now
the Hulk instead of like something else
like those games bore me so much so I
like games where there's something like
the game design is like interesting in
some way you know so
oh it's l Zen elvin that would help
because then I never knew why there was
an X in there I'm like why is there an X
elzen is easy ellison McInnes call it
Elle's in as well
alright I'm going to wind down here out
see any more programming cues so I'm
going to call it done let's save that
amusing little diagram alright so that's
it for today thank you for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero so
if pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with the
code at home you can always figure out
of the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with a source code so you can go
ahead and follow along at home we also a
forum site you can go if you want to
post questions or look at our anti
episode guide we have a patreon page
where you could support the video series
we have a tweet bot the tweets of
schedule at you so if you want to catch
the stream live which by the way the
last live stream for two weeks will be
tomorrow at five p.m. pacific daylight
time after that i am away for two weeks
so i cannot stream to you but i will
resume after that so everyone has two
weeks to catch up I expect everyone to
be caught up so yeah you know that'll be
some ketchup so yeah that's it for now
until then until tomorrow have fun
programming and I will see you guys on
the internet take it easy everyone