hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here are the show we code a complete
game live on stream we are doing some
character movement code right now and
you know I'll be honest with you I think
we pretty much finished up our simple
little example of how to make a hopping
character yesterday and so what we've
got to do today is start talking a
little bit more broadly about animation
because what we want to do now is we
want to start to tune this animation so
that it looks a lot more satisfying
right and I'll show you just real
briefly where we're at just so you can
understand what I'm saying if you don't
remember from yesterday or even if you
do just to sort of refresh your memory a
little bit here is where we are at on on
handmade heroes little dude we got if we
got to do some opengl fix it in one of
these days so we don't have that texture
down that problem so you can kind of see
what we did is we made the little body
hop along and what I said yesterday is
well now we have to do some stuff you
know we want the head to always be
connected to the body we want it to kind
of stretch to meet where the head is and
we want to add more like that's a very
in my opinion very what's dry animations
very mechanical right it's just yeah it
hops in a little parabola but you know
it's not it's not very satisfying it's
just like I'm just literally moving the
thing over and so you know remember that
like keep that in mind what that looks
like because that's you know you'll want
to sort of appreciate how we get from
where we are there to where we are going
to be after we sort of work on the
animation a little bit more so before I
go any further down there it's probably
a good time to do some black boarding so
the people who don't know very much
about animation will understand the
sorts of stuff that we're trying to do
here and have some reasonable
perspective on what is you know what is
really the way to think through these
sorts of problems and
animation in general in a game context
so I don't know how much programming
will do today it depends on how long it
takes me to get through these concepts
and how much detail I go into and then
I'm not sure how much is appropriate
given what we've already done but I feel
like we haven't really talked about it
too much so let's start by just taking
the sort of category a little bit
broadly and talk about animation in
general so what do we actually mean when
we're talking about animation well
obviously we're starting from a very
basic premise when wherever we're
talking about computer animation and
computer animation for games which is
that we know we sort of have this like
imaginary kind of film strip
you know that's kind of playing here
where we've got frame 0 frame 1 Frame 2
frame 3 right and here I'll draw in the
little perforations down the side to
make a good film strip and so obviously
you know we can't really display
anything quote-unquote animated we're
just displaying still frames and those
still frames are meant to appear to the
user as if there was motion happening
right and oftentimes we try to make it
appear sort of like what would happen if
you actually had a camera and we're
actually filming something and the
reason for that of course because that's
what people are used to seeing you're
used to watching a movie or a television
program on a monitor like the one that
we use for games and so what we expect
to see is that now what we're trying to
do when we produce these series of
frames is we're trying to capture the
effect of having something having moved
and what generally happens right if you
imagine what's going on in terms of the
sort of the process we're simulating
right there's a camera and inside the
camera this this film you know this
negative here the negative that we're
actually talking about is flowing
through this camera right it's it's you
know it's going through and it's going
into like a real right so it's kind of
like coming out here and going out of
this real and it's capturing something
on these frames and what it's actually
capturing depends quite a bit on how the
camera is set up right inside the camera
there's a little thing called a shutter
or an app
and you've all seen it right it's the
thing that like kind of looks like this
sort of a thing and it kind of spirals
in to be a small shape and then it's and
then it widens out again right it like
what it's like right it's like it can
close all the way to nothing and it
could open up to a certain state and
it's like based on how big this shutter
is more or less like it through bla bla
bla bla bla right now we're not going to
talk about depth of field or all those
other rendering things worth we might
care about with the aperture because
we're talking about animation right now
so we don't care about any of this other
than the concept of a you know exposure
time and what exposure time is is inside
a camera right you open up that aperture
to like take light into the front of the
camera and expose the film on the other
hand on the other end and for the entire
duration of that open period photons are
coming in through the camera and hitting
the film exposing it and what that means
is that a single frame of animation
right is not technically an instant in
time right it's not it's not
instantaneous what it actually is is
it's a interval of time okay and that
interval is specifically it is exactly
however long that aperture was open for
okay when the aperture closes the film
stops being exposed and advances when
the apertures open the film is getting
exposed and it's that amount of time
that we're capturing so if for example I
was using camera and I shut the set the
shutter speed to one sixtieth of a
second then I know that I've got a 16.6
repeating millisecond exposure time
which means that there is essentially
that much worth of photons coming in
okay so what that means in terms of
actually if we're really talking about
animation in its broadest sense right if
we're talking about you know animation
inside the computer in its broadest
sense what we actually want is to be
able to capture an interval of time
right so we actually aren't trying to
find out say we
and object is and only it's
instantaneous position at some point in
time we're actually talking about where
did the object if we're trying to draw
that object where did it move right
during a particular interval if that
makes sense so in the you know in the
farthest forward part of the future when
we have infinite computing power and
infinite technology and I don't know
where that you know we're in Star Trek
and everyone's got weird stuff on their
forehead because they're an alien and
you go into the holodeck because the
writers ran out of any ideas for the
actual stuff to take care take place on
the spaceship so they're gonna use
virtual reality to simulate like
Sherlock Holmes or something and before
that writer gets fired and I hope to god
they get fired basically we're talking
about their what we would actually be
doing when we're rendering imagery is
we're talking about capturing what
happens in that interval and the reason
why that's important is because if you
look at pictures you know and we talk
about two frames here's frame zero
here's frame one and I've got like a
ball it's here and then on another frame
it's over here right well if I go to see
a movie that's only happening at 24
frames a second but it still looks great
right and if the game runs at 24 frames
a second well maybe that doesn't look so
great depending on the game right looks
very staccato and part of the reason for
that is because when you're shooting a
film you get motion blur right and that
motion blur is specifically because of
what we're talking about it's cuz it's
capturing an interval so if this thing
is coming across the screen you actually
have this big long beautiful blur that's
you know showing up there and that blur
is conveying all of this motion to your
eye that makes it look a lot more rich
and so again at the limit what we're
talking about when we're talking about
animation in computer graphics we're not
actually talking about figuring out how
to draw a single frame you know and then
another single frame of time we're
talking about drawing an interval of
time and then another interval of time
and that interval is proportional to
what kind of a camera effect we were
trying to
simulate now we're not that fortunate
these days in computers so a lot of
times we can't really do that and so
sometimes we have approximate ways of
approximating motion blur but they're
not really correct and there's a bunch
of corners we cut and a lot of times we
don't try to do motion blur at all we
just try to get a high frame rate like
60 frames a second and hope that things
aren't moving so fast if they look ugly
at that rate but it certainly does lend
a certain crispness to the images you
will see in CG that's not that doesn't
have motion blur it definitely looks
different right even that's in every one
second there would be motion blur on
fast-moving things especially the kind
of things you see in games fast cars
moving around and bullets whizzing by
and all these sorts of things so that's
important to understand but assuming you
understand that now we get to what we're
actually gonna try to achieve in
handmade hero which is the simpler
problem which is just instantaneous so
if we assume that our frame rate is high
enough that we don't care too much about
motion blur or that the certain things
we might want motion blurred we will
hack right we're gonna hack those in
because you know look maybe I swing my
sword and it has this little blur trail
on it well ok we'll we'll hack that in
but we're not going to try to have
necessarily a robust solution for that
where everything is always motion
blurred correctly all the time then we
get down to the sort of thing that we're
actually doing right now and that's what
we will mostly be doing for handmade
hero which is the instantaneous problem
but it's important to understand that
this is a hack right doing thing
instantaneous is as if you had an
infinitely fast shutter so that it
opened and closed in just a you know
split-second of time and of course in
the real world you can't even do that
because there aren't enough photons in
an instant no you know photons have a
speed if something open and closing in a
literally instant of time the film
wouldn't get exposed because no photons
would go through the aperture right so
inherently there is no there isn't even
a real world analog to what this is the
closest thing I guess you could say is
imagine you had a strobe light and and
you could somehow only get the first
bounce of the strobe light and you like
shot it and like capture just those
photons I mean I don't
even know if you could strobe all the
lights in the world and get them to
arrive at yeah I don't I don't think
there's any way I can't even make up a
situation in the real world that would
actually produce a reasonable like a
real-world image like I'm looking out at
the world and that actually obeyed what
we're talking about here so this is
definitely a hack but it's a hack that's
totally fine
you know things often don't move so fast
they need much motion blur and like I
said you can always hack in some motion
blur over the top of things for things
where you find that it's important and
that's not so bad
there's also ways of using the velocity
of objects to do a post pass motion blur
for example where you can motion blur
everything and it's just not accurate it
doesn't handle like curved motion stuff
like that right things always appear to
be moving somewhat literally but again
if the frame rates high enough not so
bad so we have plenty of techniques at
our disposal we can use later if we're
too worried about that
so it's you know I don't want you to
think it's a super bad limitation that
we don't get to do this in games we have
plenty of techniques our suppose that
can compensate for some of this stuff
but on the whole is it a hack to do the
instantaneous thing absolutely and so
it's worth understanding that because
later on in your graphics career or
whatever you're doing it's important
always have that finger to mind cuz
you're morning like why can't I capture
this effect or what do I need to make
this look better and you want to
understand that that fact that in the
real world you're getting motion over
time is accumulating onto the film and
that's what you're actually gonna see
you know if you go to see a movie or
anything like that so instantaneous
animation is about being able to take
some sort of a function sample it at a
time right and we want to produce like
it's essentially a state of the world
right so we want to be able to render
the world we want to be able to render
it at a time and the way that we you
know you could imagine and we have some
function we pass in here's the time that
we want to take a look at everything it
tells us where everything in the world
is and then we're just gonna add you
know the next time around you know this
is T 0 T 1 is going to be equal to t0
plus you know our time step which is one
sixtieth of a second we move it forwards
and we
we keep going right and then we take it
at time t1 okay so that's essentially
what we're trying to do with animation
and the important thing to know here is
that usually in games we want the
flexibility to sample these functions at
arbitrary T meaning we don't just want
something that's like f of 0 is
something and F of 1 is something and F
of 2 like we don't want to have a
discrete step that was how old games
work in the old days when you had an
arcade game were something that it was
locked to 60 Hertz on the gun the CRT or
something like this
and it would literally just update one
sixtieth of a second everything was
hard-coded in what happened in that 60th
of a second and you got that you were
talking about literally a discrete thing
here and that makes sense when you don't
have floating-point when you don't have
a lot of compute power you know
computing power we have that now and so
what we'd rather do is have the ability
to adapt a little bit and the reason for
that is we run on multiple you know
multiple types of hardware okay we don't
know that our frame rate is 160 it might
be 150th in a second it might be pal
right or something it might be 130 in a
second because the users machine is too
slow it can't handle 60 frames a second
but we still want to run because it's
okay the game can be playable at 30
right maybe the users super crazy about
frame 8 they wanted it one 121-125 a
second right they 120 frames a second so
typically again we want to be able to
sample it as a tea and we want to be
able to plug in anything here so we want
to be able to advance our time step in
any kind of floating point increment we
might want okay and alternative to that
you might struck do it you could do an
alternative structure of your system
where you had some fundamental quantity
that you never went below like let's say
one thirtieth of a second is your
fundamental quantity you could then do
it in a discrete way like this and you
just say well if I want 120 frames a
second I just do four of these right so
you can there there are other ways I'm
sorry other other way around if I if I
pick 125 a second and I want one
thirtieth of a second I do four of these
right and then I could do something this
way but in general you know the trend in
games most of the time is to have that
system be flexible so you can
call it with whatever you want and you
you want to keep it within a certain
boundary so you don't call it with six
hours between frames and you don't call
it with 0.000000 one nanoseconds in
between frames because it'll fall apart
in the floating-point accuracy will just
you know explode at that point but
assuming you're within a reasonable
range 115th of a second to one six
hundredths of a second let's say you're
okay so that's really what we're talking
about here and so what that means is you
know do we have a single function that
produced this say the world well in a
sense we sort of do right we have like
game update and render but really the
actual math functional part of this the
things we're actually talking about now
what we really have is that giant you
know world function that says what's the
world look like at this point in time is
really typically composed of lots of
tiny functions right like maybe I've got
the function here that moves the hero
right and and maybe I've got the
function here that that does the head
Bob right and maybe I've got this much
so you know you've seen this in the code
when we're going to update the world we
have lots and lots of ways of creating
these functions over time some of them
are explicit like that hopping spline we
had right remember that one that was an
explicit function we actually have in
the code in fact if I go here to world
mode right here is that actual explicit
function right there's that there's a
function just written out exactly that
takes an T whatever that T value is 0 to
1 and produces out that that value that
is the location right sum over that way
other ones like move entity right they
don't have a way of producing an
absolute position what they actually do
is take one position and a delta and can
update right so they are essentially
computing only the first derivative of
the function at that time okay and so
it's important to understand there's
kind of two ways of doing there's
there's two types of functions that we
already have and this is very common
right we have functions that allow you
to do a function at time
and an output the exact position at that
time and you can plug in anything you
want here that's like our jump and then
we have other ones that require you to
tell it what was the previous position
so this is an input I need to know where
I was okay and then what they will
compute is not this this is not possible
what they will compute instead is what's
the first derivative of the function at
that point they will multiply it by the
time step and that will produce the new
P okay and this by the way we were
talking about Euler in the pre stream
this is a forward Euler step this is
basically saying I have a place I'm at I
have a derivative and I want to multiply
the derivative by the time step to get
to my new location okay this is
numerical integration it's really really
crappy numerical integration and for
most things in games it's actually fine
because if you don't have any kind of
weird physics going on you don't care
right but that's we have to do and the
reason that we have to do that is again
like I said that function there is no
function for the position of the guy
we're moving the stick around changing
is acceleration all the time he's
bumping into things so they're all these
discrete things that are changing so
there's no way to write this whereas
with that hop
well the hop we know when the hop starts
to when the hop ends it's that exact
curve we don't have to do any kind of
that updating we can evaluate directly
these are always these nice super
accurate beautiful things when you can
get away with writing an explicit thing
for an animation you're loving life it's
great but just a lot of things we want
to do in games just realistically aren't
that and even these like you saw it's
not like it's the whole guys trajectory
that's that way it's only like for one
hop and then we've got to do other
discrete business to sort of line them
up right and that brings me to the other
thing that I wanted to say which is that
the F of T notation right like this is
the F of T and this produces the world
for us well this is not really true
either typically what happens is this T
there's lots of little T's that actually
are in here there's the there's a T of
the bobbing of the head there's the T of
the hopping right and all of these are
sort of these sub little time values
we create to do these little parts of
animation which all get evaluated
separately and in our code and then they
sort of all put out some position that
gets fed up eventually into the state of
the world right so this would be you
know it'd be great if we magically had
some function for the whole world and it
was just putting the T and out pops
everything and it's all analytical and
direct great but that's not the reality
of it so typically what ends up
happening when we talk about animation
is we talk about lots of functions you
know of lots of T's right lots of
different T values and those T values
have very different ranges and all sorts
of stuff and so what we do is everything
tends to be driven off that state that's
that big delta T like this this F of T
like I said it doesn't really exist
instead what happens is we typically
take okay we know what was the time last
frame we know what the time is this
frame right we know how much time has
elapsed it's the delta T so what we do
is we feed that delta T down to
everybody and then all these little time
values all throughout the program are
all getting updated by that T and all
outputting the positions that they need
to some of them are like I said
literally doing that they're literally
taking T hop and adding delta T to it to
produce the new location of the guy they
feed that T into a an equation of it
right F hop of T hop right and that out
comes the position of the hop right so
that's happening but then other times
that delta T is used in a sort of an
Euler step where we don't know we save
the old location of the guy we know his
velocity or we try to compute it we move
him by that amount and that's his new
location again an Euler step there it's
not analytic it's not directly computed
okay and so typically
even though they're all the same kind of
unified concept at a high enough level
we typically call this physics and this
animation that's just what they
typically end up getting called when you
have a function of time that evaluates
the state of something and you can just
put in the T and outcomes the state we
typically call that animation we call
that animating a character or that's the
animation of this character right when
we put in just a delta T and we try to
solve for where this thing might have
ended up with a bunch of stuff that
happened that is what we call physics
they are both actually just animation or
they are both actually just physics
depending on what you want to call them
right they both move a physical thing in
a way in some way right according to
some rules but we tend to use those two
terms in that way in code bases and so
you know it's it's intuitive it makes
sense right because this is a thing that
seems to be doing movement kind of like
physically based or whatever and this is
the kind of thing that's like oh I had
the artist like made some key frames and
I'm moving between them right okay so
what we're talking about now when I say
animation then at that point is we're
talking about the F of T kind of thing
and we're sort of talking about well if
I want to do one of these F of T kinds
of things you know what are sort of the
techniques that are involved for for
doing these F of T's where I get gets
first to that you saw one of them which
was that parabolic arc right B splines
are very common one of these right a B
spline like you've seen many times for
our what like animation packages use for
example if I want to do an F of T equals
some like animation curve right like I
you know I want like a curve in space
somewhere right and I author these
little B spline handles that kind of go
through here you know what I mean and
then I just say as my T
goes upwards it moves along the path of
the b-splines right and that's how I
animate a dude similarly you might even
see Euler angles in their four joints
right because I want to be able to say
like oh I don't know I've got sort of
this this joint here and I've got this
this you know maybe it's let's draw the
shoulder of a guy let's say here's his
shoulder coming out here here's his head
up here and whatever and I just want to
talk about like the animating occur for
the rotation of this thing right so
maybe I make a beast line but the B
spline is talking about the angle of
this joint right blah blah blah blah
blah so B splines are kind of the
workhorse of animation very typically
and we almost did something like that
before with our with our parabola
because a parabola obviously a
second-order beasts line is a parabola
right first order is a line second order
you know this is a first order B splines
a line second orders a parabola third
order is a cubic right yeah so you're
talking about in fact let me draw these
for you okay so zeroth order just talk
about B splines for just one quick
second these are the things seen on the
you know all your animation packages
just put this little lower here's the
order of my B spline zeroth order is a
step function
it's basically teleportation right so
I'm here and then I'm instantly here I'm
here at zero I'm here at one right I'm
here also at point four I'm here also at
port four nine nine nine nine nine and
then when I'm at point five I'm over
here or something right depending on how
I want to sample it obviously but in
general I
Italy teleport from one to the other and
a zeroth-order base plan a first order B
spline is a line a first order B spline
is something that does a standard lerp
from one to the other at zero I'm here
at point five I'm here at one I'm here
at point two five I'm here point seven
five I'm here right second order B
spline is a parabola you know I've got
one more point to specify like so in
fact you know what the way if I'm
sampling these the same way you would
actually be here all the way up to point
nine nine nine
if I'm sampling them the same way I'm
sampling here it would only be once you
get to one that you go to the next
b-spline key which is here right this is
actually another key that's kind of
important to mention these are stacked
on top of each other right you know you
make these in an art package right you
kind of put one down I'll put my third
here you know they make these in our
package right you put one here you got
two handles and it kind of does this
sort of thing right and here's point
zero one two here's three here's you
know then here's four five six right and
so these are like the key frames and
these are the tangent handles
quote-unquote you know I'm saying so if
I was to do that these are the key
frames here's key frame one here's key
frame
I'm sorry here's key frame 0 hears key
frame one here's key frame - well here's
keyframes 0
and here's key frame 1 over here the
actual endpoint of the spline is going
to be over here as well right so this
guy is actually taking this as the
sample point now so in a parabola the
big difference now when we get the
second order which is why it's the first
one you tend to see in much in animation
at all is because now there's actually a
point that is not at either keyframe
right we have where we're starting and
where we're going from but we also have
an in-between point right and so what we
end up drawing doesn't ever touch that
point it's kind of like this sort of a
thing right and then finally for third
order we have cubics which means we can
specify two points which means we can
actually have a wiggle in there right so
we can have this sort of a thing it can
actually change direction twice
so anyway we'll talk about beasts lions
a little bit more completely later but I
just wanted to kind of get that out
there the different and well it well it
was kind of something that was coming up
so beef lines are very common one of
these right because they're very
versatile and you can kind of make
anything you want with some kind of a
b-spline and these to generate nice li
you can always evaluate a cubic if you
want everything your whole program could
evaluate cubics if you want to and just
by what's called not doubling which is
just repeating values multiple times
inside the same cubic you can drop it
down to any one of these so a single
animation system built strictly on
cubics can actually do parabolas lines
and step functions without any without
actually doing anything else it'll just
automatically work which is kind of nice
so that's kind of a navigator there so
anyway that's one of those very
versatile functions but just because
this is what all animation programs are
always using that's because it's a nice
general tool they can give animators and
then they can make all sorts of stuff by
tuning what the curves are and they're
fairly intuitive because people grabbing
these handles and moving the curve
around so they seem to be able to do a
reasonable job with that so great good
job everyone b-splines
but there is nothing special about
b-splines animation is literally just
that f of T it's the F of T that
produces the states that we want and
that could be formulated as a b-spline
it could be formulated as any function
we want any function at all and you saw
me do that yesterday instead of starting
with a b-spline I just said I want a
parabola here's their constraints on my
parabola let me solve for what it what
it's gonna be
and out it popped I didn't have to start
with the B spline formulation I can get
a second-order equation a different way
if I want to write so the important
thing to remember our animation Sall
stuff is just we are trying to make
functions of T we can make them any way
that we want if we don't know what to do
or were confused or we just want
something artistic yes we can just throw
a b-spline in there and that you tuned
it you know tune those handles do
whatever that will work but we can also
be more experimental we can be more
invested and we can generate any sorts
of other functions that we want as long
as they are you know feeding the T and
out comes the state that is the nature
of animation and that's where we're at
right
so let's talk about what we mean by the
state part of this now that we know what
we're kind of talking about with the F
of T because same beast slime is saying
whatever well that's just like arbitrary
scalar values in space or something like
that you know it doesn't really mean
anything until we actually talk about
what the kinds of state are that we're
trying to generate now obviously we can
generate any kind of state that we want
so we're free to every month there but
the question is in games
what kind of states are we usually
concerned with how do we tend to model
the things that we're going to be
animating and usually the way that we do
this is we have some kind of
preconceived notion like oh you people
ask me on a stream of time like we kind
of have like a you know a skeletal
animation system or stuff like this it's
like that is all just sort of like a
buzz word nonsense thing don't think
about that do not think about those
things at all though those are just like
specific instances of how things get
animated what you want to think of
instead is you want to think of just
parameter spaces and all of the other
ways that you might actually end up
doing something are all just a way of
sort of saying we're just gonna use a
parameter space that looks like this if
I say I'm going to do a skeletal
animation system it means I pre decided
that the kinds of state spaces I was
gonna handle look like this right so
let's talk about those let's talk about
you know the parameters of the state
right or the state vector I could also
throw in a physics term here for you
which is generalized coordinates Wow
handwriting not my strong suit on the
Wacom tablet okay so what we want to
think about is this F of T produces a
state and that state is something it's
anything right that we want to represent
the world in a way we can render okay
now what that means is we are free to
pick the set of parameters that make
sense to us
and it could be anything right now
you've sort of seen me do that to a
certain extent before right I already
have a situation where I talk about the
ground point of a guy and the head
height right and when I go and compute
what this is the head height of the guy
is a function of T it was f of T that
Bob value right produces the height of
the guy the ground point on the other
hand was f of T 0 plus delta T times F
of I'm sorry derivative of F at T 0
right the ground point was physically
simulated the head height was animated
and there's my guy right well actually I
think I think he didn't have that body
right he's just a head floating there
right what is this system that I've
created is it a skeletal animation
system no there's no skeleton there's no
bones there's no nothing related to
skeletal animation and if you wanted to
create this in a skeletal animation
actually you couldn't the reason that
you couldn't is because there's no such
thing as head height in a skeletal
animation system what you would have to
do instead right is you would have to
create a bone which actually has three
degrees of freedom XY and Z right or
however many it very least two and then
you would have to go ahead and animate
that Y position of the bone as if it was
the head height right now like I've said
you could certainly construct the same
effect in a stealth animation system can
you create this no because this bakes in
knowledge of the system the code knows
it does not need to simulate a bone for
the displacement of the head off of the
ground point and the reason it knows
that is because it knows it can only be
displaced upwards so it only has to
compute one scalar value right so if we
were to talk about the state vector of
this system the state vector of this
system is a four vector right it's the
ground point X the ground point Y the
ground point Z and the head height okay
so this is the state of the familiar
it's a state vector it has four
components and that's what they are our
job when we simulate the familiar right
is to take an F of T zero that's this
and produce the F of T one you know the
new one that's a new one of these and
the way that we chose to do that is by
simulating this part with forward Euler
that's how it moved around and
simulating this part with a sine
function right it was sine of T Bob or
something like that right and that is
the nature of animation code you have a
state vector the state vector is
describing the minimum potentially or it
could be it could be fatty but atom at
least it must describe the minimum
number of state variables necessary to
go from nothing to the placement of all
of the renderable objects right and
that's what this does
once I know these I can produce the
rendering output for this this guy okay
so that's what we really need and to be
honest we could talk about this you know
let me let me be more explicit with my
anomic later because I'm being a little
sloppy here that's not really what that
is this is actually the position vector
right you could say okay this is
actually the vector of that I need to
reproduce my drawing you could argue
that the state
if we're really being sort of pedantic
here he's actually the gxg yzz yes but
then t-bob that's the actual state that
I'm retaining right so you could say
I've got this is the state vector I
simulate this vector forwards then I
produce this from it right which is just
a copy in the case of these but it's
actually a sine function evaluation in
case of this right so I update my state
vector forward using my Delta time
that's a sine function I'm sorry that's
a justice an addition here it's a
simulation step here I then produce this
position vector which is a sine
evaluation here and a copy for these
guys and then I have the information I
need to do my render okay so I don't
really know like like how we want to
name these I'd have to look at the
robotics literature to de fresh my
memory but those are the in two
important concepts to have I feel like
we would probably call this our state
vector but you know we could we could
call this our generalized coordinate
vector because that's what these are
they're the coordinates that describe
this guy and then we could call this our
state you know our state vector I don't
know but I feel like I it's been 20
years since I read the robotics
literature so I don't remember I don't
remember well enough the point being
these are the two things that you need
to be concerned about in the system and
so if I was to draw it out how this
works
we have the stuff that is stored okay
and that is for example like I said it's
the GX Gy GZ of the ground point and the
t-bob we have the stuff that's stored we
have then the sort of like render we
have the like render input here and
that's again the GX Gy GZ and the T
that's re and the height head height
each head maybe I don't know what we
want to call it I probably it's probably
more like H H and mate here we have the
render input and then the render input
finally goes through one more process to
produce that our list of sparse bright
lists right and these we have one thing
which is just the head you know we just
have the head record and what actually
happens is we take these and we add this
so we take that G vector and we actually
add the head height times up basically a
fixed vector that we know which is like
0 0 1 which is like Z value upwards
right does that make sense so this is
this is how animation works you decide
what your parameters are that you're
storing that drive the animation you
have a way of generating some set of
values from them which are then used to
compute this the sort of whole state of
whatever the thing is that you're trying
to create and render so it's typically
this this multi-step process now if I
say I want a skeletal animation system
all I'm talking about is essentially
regularizing like like I'm talking about
essentially putting this this part on or
you know I guess maybe not this part we
could say this part really at a minimum
we're talking about basically taking you
know a pro Krusty's approach to this
we're basically saying from now on the
vendor in you know the actual state that
we're going to create is not gonna be
some arbitrary thing and then have a
function that we wrote that can produce
result you know the the final rendered
position of the sprites instead what
we're going to do is say that everything
always is the exact same right we're
going to say that we have a concept of a
bone and a bone has particular
information on it right it's got a
displaced
like it's got a TX @ ey mtz right it's
got a rotation in 2d that's just gonna
be you know a rotation theta it's just
gonna be one one value rotation around
the z axis you might say and then it's
going to have potentially a scale right
and we're just gonna say that everything
has these values and if you needed more
than these values you have to stick more
than one bone on there and if you needed
less than these values well tough we're
just gonna keep storing them anyway
right and that's a totally fine decision
right it's if you want to try and make
that system worse more sort of
streamlined and simple then that's
something you can do but I often find to
be overly limiting especially in 2d
because usually I want to do stuff like
use crazy functions that operate on
certain parts of this and I don't really
want to have to deal with getting at it
some backwards way like I have the way I
want this sprite can create it and I
don't want to have to worry about
fitting that into this preconceived
notion of a bone but again a bone is
just saying that well whatever this is
it's just gonna be an array of these
that's it that's all you get so you did
it better be that because that's what
it's actually gonna be right okay so
yeah so at this point I guess we've got
about 10-15 minutes later or something
so like that
I'm not sure
hmm at this point hopefully that all
makes reasonable a sense to you and
we're already doing it so hopefully you
should kind of be familiar with how
that's going at this point we now have
to kind of talk about that that step
where we actually do the rendering
because there's some stuff that we need
to do there so if we talk about our
actual handmade hero and how that's
working and how I want to work we can
sort of start to talk about how we can
improve things so for example let's say
that I've got you know that that
parabolic arc here okay and we've got
that parabolic arc
and the guy is jumping along it so here
he is he's got like a torso here and
he's got a you know he's got like a cape
and that's just moving like this so and
you know what I guess let's not come
with ring will talk about the rendering
whatever the running tomorrow let's
since I've talked all about the
functions in the breakdown of the
functions we'll talk about the running
tomorrow and maybe I'll actually go do a
little bit of code in the last 10
minutes just to sort of show how this
sort of stuff works so what I did right
is I showed you guys how to write a
function that was f of T that produces
this parabola right so we did this kind
of a thing and it looks okay right it's
not awful certainly I have played a lot
of indie games with animation that's
about that quality but we want to do a
lot better than that right we want to
look good you know we want to have we
want this to look professional quality
we don't want it just like okay it's
sort of moved in whatever and so if we
look at what's happening here I would
like there to be you know the
traditional principles of animation are
they have anticipation and
follow-through by the way I should say
it you know this is separate but every
programmer who works on it animation
should have
if you haven't read this book don't work
on animation like you should read this
book cover-to-cover before you do any
animation work whatsoever there's no
question about that so just like that
goes without saying because otherwise
you just won't understand what your even
your goals are I'm not gonna try and
cover the concepts behind how to
conceptualize actual animation because
like I said that's like this huge topic
that's about art and all that stuff but
you should at least take some time from
yourself with that if you're gonna work
on animation as a programmer to say the
least I'm just gonna say the terms and
then show how I'm going to do them I'm
not gonna try and motivate them by
saying well in 1945 they decided to do
blah and whatever or something and
that's how they figured out that this
was important animation and
follow-through are what I was going to
talk about I sort anticipation and
follow-through as well go time right
here which is that right now what
happens is there's no ease in or ease
out we just immediately go on this
parabolic arc right and when we land we
stop immediately so it's just a
perfectly like continuous linear motion
and a little bit of that is correct once
a body enters a ballistic phase it
doesn't speed up or slow down
other than the gravitational part right
so that's actually somewhat correct once
I jump in the air there's not a lot of
deceleration or acceleration that's
happening other than my gravitational
arcs but that's okay what's not okay is
how did I get this upward velocity right
well if you've ever seen someone jump
again there's the anticipation part of
the of the animation of a jump it's what
happens in real life I have to kind of
come down and compress my body like a
spring and then I leap up into the air
and I use that upward momentum to lift
me off of the ground and so if you look
at what our animation is doing right now
it doesn't look like that right it just
kind of moves in that arc and it doesn't
feel it doesn't it doesn't have any feel
of that sort of anticipation so how do
we take an F of T that produces a
parabola and produce something that has
a little bit of anticipation in it right
how would I do that
well what I want to first talk about is
how to produce
a subsection of my time step because
this is or my time window because this
is a crucial part of how you code custom
sort of animations stuff like this we
know that the F of T for our parabola
goes from T equals 0 to T equals 1 what
that means is during my jump it will
start here at T equals 0 and end here at
T equals 1 and that's all so if I want
to have more time at the beginning of
the parabolic arc to do some anticipate
or e animation of coming down and coming
back up right well I've got to do
something about this problem I've got to
do something about the fact that well at
T equals 0 I'm here at T equals anything
other than 0 I've already started my arc
I want to peg the guy at T equals 0 for
at least you know 0.1 seconds or
something or point one of the of T right
from 0 to 0.1 or something like that I
need a little bit of room there so if
I'm going to do that what I want to do
is I want to partition my my window of T
and how do I do that ok well what I do
is I do a map into range we've done this
before we've seen this before actually
and we've we actually have had that can
even have a function for it right and we
want to do a map into range normalized
ok because what we want to do is say
well we've got an entire T the T goes
from 0 to 1 and we want to start
breaking it up into discrete pieces we
want to do anticipation ballistic
and and follow-through
colloquially you know this is like this
is the launch and this is the land right
so what I need to do is have some key
values here this is T like jump and this
is T you know land or something like
that and what I want to do is now
produce three separate T values I want a
T value in here that ranges from zero to
one
I want a T value in here that ranges
from zero to one and I want to see value
in here that link ranges from zero to
one right and so what I need to do is
take a T that's on my large T timeline
right and maybe a you know in here this
is 0.3 and what I want to do is to go
from there to producing what's this
value right here which is actually
inside this T range is point you know
1/5 or something right and by the way I
want to know which of these days as I'm
in I want to know if I'm in phase zero
phase one or phase two right I want to
know which of these ones I'm in so I
want to partition my range and I want to
get out a value inside that range right
and so let's take a look at how I might
do that oh well that was good
accidentally shut off my monitor
shutting off my monitor is probably not
the best thing to do if I want to do
that because I need to be able to see my
code in order to actually make it work
all right so let's open up for read and
that's not what I wanted there we go and
I'm gonna open up world mode and I'm
gonna go ahead and and jump forward to
that part parabolic arc part so here you
can see it and if we go to our math
routines you can see that we've got a
a clamp version of this and it does the
normalization as well so like I said we
already did this we basically here's the
minimum value here's the maximum value
here's the t produce a new thing in that
range and clamp it for me right so
that's that's what we're doing I'm just
gonna coat it explicitly in the future
we may want to make an actual system
that facilitates this sort of thing but
for the moment I'm just gonna write it
out so if we are hopping I guess if I
want to do my movement T at the at the
beginning here it depends where when we
want to update this movement I may want
to update after the fact in fact I think
I probably do go ahead and clamp that
out as well so what I want to do now is
I want to test my T value as I come
through it and I want to see okay if my
T value is less than whatever my you
know mighty jump variable is which is
when I want to leave then I'm in my jump
phase okay if it's less than my teal and
then I'm in my ballistic phase and
otherwise then I'm in my my landing
phase right so we know what we're doing
in our perp in our parabola case we know
that we're just doing this I guess we
know we're also always setting the DP to
zero because we don't care about that
either but I know what I'm in my
ballistic phase that I'm doing this and
so the only thing I have to do in this
case is I have to modify my T value so I
can just say well give me my clamped T
value I want you to to map it between T
jump and T land and then I can set T
jump equal to like that and I can set T
land equal to you know that basically
point to on either side or something and
now I've done my
my windowing so now if I go and look at
the the jump off it goes
that's pretty funny although I think
that's wrong because it looks like we're
not actually that doesn't seem like it's
properly finishing the arc there which I
guess actually now I think about it is
actually correct because given the small
given how fast the person is jumping if
we're less than you know in here since
I'm not setting it when we get to here I
do have to make sure that we we actually
put ourselves down on the the final
location if that makes sense because you
know remember we're not ever evaluating
it actually peel and we skip over T land
and get into that range as we're
incrementing so we actually do need to
still I don't know why I restarted this
but so there we go right and now it's
just that windowing is happening but I'm
not doing anything inside those other
inside those other windows however if I
want to I certainly can write I can
certainly do some more interesting stuff
here and let's think about for a second
what that would be now we don't at the
moment have any concept of the the
height of the what's right I'm looking
for that that Cape there we go we don't
have any concept of how high the Cape is
off of the body right we don't actually
know what that is and so what I kind of
want to do is say well okay I'll just
use maybe the t-bob value here to
control that so what I want to do is I
want to do a clamp map to range on this
you know this initial jump phase I want
to take it there and I'm gonna say that
the t-bob is gonna kind of go I want it
to kind of come down and then back up
again right so what I want it to do is I
want it to sort of do almost a sine
pattern right I want to do like back
kind of it
and I don't really know exactly what I
want that to look like because I haven't
thought about it yet but we can sort of
play with that a little bit more so I'm
gonna say that will set the entity t-bob
and you know what I normally I guess we
want the entity t-bob in any case we'll
just cold set it up here to something
like zero and then I want that NDT Bob
to be some parameter that I can use to
drive that displacement so the T Bob in
this case I'll just say that well you
know sine if you think about what sine
does right here's our unit circle right
so cosine of 0 is 1 and sine of 0 is 0
and it goes up to 1 over this arc so if
I wanted to capture this arc of going
from 0 back to 0 as a sign right I would
just say sine of my T value but this is
PI radians right or 1/2 tau depending on
how you want to do it right so T times
pi is actually going to mean from if T
ranges from 0 to 1 that will give me
that that sort of a bob it will go from
0 to 1 to sit back to 0 so I'm gonna I'm
gonna use that I'm gonna use the fact
that we have that ability to go ahead
and set the the T Bob value to be T
times pi and then I've got that that
jump that I was looking for right that
sort of that sort of springiness so all
I have to do now is when I actually draw
this this hero body all I have to do is
actually use that T Bob now and I guess
I don't really know exactly we probably
want to go upwards so I should probably
say like oh okay you know this is
actually going to be you know entity T
Bob and it's I don't want to move it
well we'll just let that be in regular
coordinates I suppose and so when I come
up here and
I'm gonna adjust this guy we can say
that I'm moving him down right and I
probably don't want to move them down
too much we'll see how that goes
did I set the right thing I set the
wrong thing I wanted Cape yeah and the
other thing that we should probably do
is as we start to work on this I'm gonna
slow it down quite a bit so that I can
see what's happening because that'll
make it easier for us to debug it's
going so fast right now I can't even
really see what's going on which you
know mm-hmm doesn't help so here when we
do our update I'm gonna go ahead and
slow it down 6x from where it was so you
can you can already kind of see that we
got a sorted so we want the Cape on top
by the way and I should make sure that
that's happening as well so you can kind
of see it I'm almost out of time so so
here's our t-bob of this dude and yeah
at the moment do we get to pass a sort
bias into this thing I don't really
remember we shouldn't have had to the
most of the problem with this is just
that our art assets are stacked on top
of each other unfortunately and I wish
they weren't because I would rather it
be displaced upward I'll just put this
in here for now but that will come back
to bite us in a second unfortunately
so do you see how that sort of adds this
little bit of of niceness to it already
even though we haven't done anything
much at all just having that little bit
makes it look more like it's jumping now
unfortunately it's not quite what I
would want because there should be some
continuation of that motion so when I'm
in the t jump range actually what I want
to do is set this t-bob to be a little
bit I want this to be a little bit more
traffic of what I'm what I'm trying to
say here I want it to carry through so I
kind of want all of these things to sort
of be active at the same time in some
sense so what I really want to say here
is I kind of want to say if T is is you
know less than T mid or something like
this and I'm not sure what I want to
Matt to be but I really want to say is
if T is less than T made then I'm gonna
do this thing right and I want it to be
able to overlap and what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna let it I'm gonna let it come
down come back up and then come back
down again so it has a full range so I'm
gonna actually let it go for all of tau
and I'm gonna let that that jump happen
but you know what I'm not going to do
I am got to make sure this to you I came
after a tea jump and teal and so that
should clamp properly to zero which
means we should stay at movement from I
feel like that should have been right
actually I'm not sure why it wasn't a my
mapping this wrong T jump to teal and ah
right I forgot I can't overwrite my tea
like that right so this actually has to
be this sort of thing I was taking
advantage of the else miss of it all but
you can't do that right if I'm gonna
clamp these values and if I'm gonna let
them overlap I'm not allowed to do that
anymore
and so do you see how that kind of looks
a lot more like a jump now already even
though we haven't really done much to it
just having that having that happen is
just much nicer right and so similarly
what I can do now on the landing is do
exactly the same thing I can sort of
carry that through where I take the same
procedure we did here and this time
we're just going to play it from that
teal and all the way out till the end
like so and so again really really
straightforward
nothing nothing particularly crazy there
but now it just gives us like a little a
little kind of bump oh and I don't want
I only want half I don't want a full
oscillation on that one
so the other thing that we probably
would want to do is we would want to
allied this jump
so the t-bob part will probably want to
make if if you happen to be landing and
you're gonna do an immediate jump
afterwards you'd get double oscillation
in here so what we want to do is
actually alive that as well if you're
going to be doing another jump
afterwards
I'm out of time so we won't try to do
that now but that's basically you know
what we would would want to do so I'm
gonna see what happens if we speed this
back up again to a faster jump over I
gotta put an F in there I don't know why
I got to figure out why we are able to
jump outside of there I'm not really
sure why we haven't looked at that stuff
not yet but we're getting much closer to
a real sort of jump the speed at which
the jump has to happen is a little bit
is a little bit much and so what I mate
what I'll probably do too is I'll
probably move some of that animation
into the actual pre movement code so
that as you move the head it squishes
down right so like as I gets ready to
jump as I as I kind of move away and
then it jumps so I may actually not need
to do as much windowing there I may
actually move those out into the other
state but I just kind of wanted to show
you how to do that to start with right
so I'm gonna go ahead and go to the QA
now we should also do
the Cizek what's the difference between
B splines and Bezier curves so I will I
will draw it here so to start with the
difference in terms of the curves they
produce is there is no difference so a
Bezier curve and a b-spline curve are
actually the exact same curve it's just
how the knots are phrased and I'll sort
of a not in a control point you might
hear me use kind of interchangeably and
that's because they are interchangeable
when you're talking about a b-spline but
they're not as interchangeable we're
talking about bezzie a a knot or like
the t values at which your control
points occur and control points are the
positions along the curve so for example
I don't know why I drew these under
Bezier probably not so smart so if you
imagine let's say I was going to do a
curve kind of like the one I had before
so here are the points that I've
specified and here's the curve that I'm
drawing okay so what happens here is
these are control points and maybe I
shouldn't
I'll save displaying not still after I
say the b-spline thing so if I'm talking
about a Bezier curve then the number of
Bezier curves in this in this example is
actually two and the number of b-spline
curves is only one and as I can't get
this sir
and so what we're talking about when we
talk about bezier curve versus b-spline
curve is the fact that a Bezier curve is
a fixed curve with a number of points
equal to its order plus one so if I have
a third order bezzie a which is the kind
you normally have I'll put this in the
middle I guess if I have a third order
bezzie a then the number of points it
has control points is for this one this
one this one and this one are the
control points of the first Bezier curve
okay and this is it's its arc then
there's another bezier curve which is
this one this one this one and this one
right which is another four points and
this is its arc what you do with busy
occurs if you want them to chain
together is you set the control point
that's one before that like essentially
the tant the one they would call the
tangent handle the control point that's
one before the point that you end on you
set that to be exactly opposite and the
same length away as the first tangent
handle in the next Bezier curve you're
trying to line up and you set the final
point and the first point of the two
curves to be coincident right so this is
zero one two three of this first curve
and it's also zero one two three of the
second curve three and zero are the same
point here and further
in order to make this continuous curve
two and one in these cases here have to
be exactly opposed right so to state it
mathematically if this is a b c then
what i'm talking about is the fact that
a minus b which is that vector there has
to be exactly equal to c minus the B
right and then a you know another way to
state that would obviously be if I
wanted to know what this value was here
the C value it's a weight did I do that
right I did that wrong negative C minus
B right so it's a minus B equals
negative C minus B right because they
have to be pointing the opposite
directions of each other and so a minus
B equals negative C plus B right or if I
want to consolidate and I'm like I have
my a and I want and my B and I want to
know what that C value is right then
I've got a minus 2 B equals negative C
or C equals 2 B minus a okay so that's
Bezier curves and so what you're doing
with Bezier curves if you want to make a
long curve you have to keep stacking
them on top of each other stack stack
stack stack stack and if you wanted to
be continuous which you normally do you
have to always obey this and so these
handles are locked now in a drawing
program you've seen this it's called
lock tangent handles and you can unlock
them to make a bend a crease in the
curve right and so what happens when you
make a crease in the curve is when you
stop obeying that thing because at that
point because these are two totally
separate curves they will the second one
will start out in a directions totally
different from the one that the first
one ended in right
and with a third-order curve you can
actually have the directions be the same
but the accelerations are different
right and that's what would happen if I
kept these as in line but I made like
this one longer right so this one would
would you would still see a sort of
second order it wouldn't be a perfectly
true curve it would still it wouldn't
like bet it wouldn't kink but it would
like you could see that there was a
second order change all right so what's
a b-spline that's a bezier a b-spline
curve is if you pre solve for this stuff
right if you just say I'm always going
to be continuous so I'm just gonna say
hey you know what I'm gonna specify this
this this this and this right and I'm
gonna keep going and I just want my
curves to kind of come all through
together I just want them all to be
control points right so what you do
instead of at you you in the Bezier case
you end on the on one of your control
points right you start on one control
point you end on another control point
in a b-spline curve you only that's
still true for the very end but all the
the rest of the way through you actually
don't ever do that so you you would
place your control points and the curve
would never quite hit it so if I
actually had the exact same control
points I didn't modify them right if I
actually fed the exact same control
points in and didn't double this one
anymore so I isn't two anymore it's just
one control point I started out here and
I kind of like pass through these guys
you know like that kind of a thing right
if I doubled this guy again then I would
hit him but you don't want to do that
actually is that true I'm sorry no you
would not hit him you'd have to triple
him if you actually wanted to hit him I
believe because it would be a yeah I
think you definitely a triple him that's
neither here nor there so what a
b-spline does is it basically solves for
this a priori and says I'm gonna write
the
of a curve that just continues to flow
through its control points without ever
touching any of them until the very last
one right so it's as if you had a
b-spline as if you had a bezier curve
that lasted for many many many many many
many many many many control points and
the way that they do that is just by pre
solving these equations to essentially
turn around the the phrasing of the of
the curve so that you're sort of saying
well when I'm between this curve when
I'm evaluating T between here and here
right what I'm actually going to do is
evaluate this Bezier effectively when
I'm between here and here I'm going to
evaluate this Bezier so I switched up
which points I was doing before I
finished actually even tracing out what
the first busy would have been I'm
shifting to the next Bezier and then the
next one and the next one right so a
b-spline constantly moves the frame
forward through time to avoid you ever
getting to the end until you get to the
last knot they are exactly the same
curve equations though so the kinds of
curves you produced with either-or are
exactly the same and you can take a
bezzie a and fit it to a b-spline and
fit up these fine to busy and they will
be exact so it's there isn't any
difference in the actual curve the only
difference is how you are actually like
controlling that curve how you actually
what the control points actually mean
and which ones you specify is what
changes so if I have a base my looks
like this I've a Bezier looks like this
they you know the same control points
set into both of them won't produce the
same curves but there is a set of
control points that I could feed into
one that would produce the same curve as
some other set of control points in
another that makes sense
beginners perspective it seems that in
software rendering keeping milliseconds
per frame in a certain controlled
boundary as someone in the program was
controlled depending on the code quality
and orientation to her performance does
that become more difficult when going to
Hardware rendering with drivers
territory or is it the other way around
I would say it's actually hard in both
because in one case you don't know what
CPU you're running on and that's kind of
a little bit difficult but in the other
case you don't know what GP you're
running on and so it's the same
difficulty in both cases you're just
it's really hard on a PC that's why
people oftentimes enjoy program consoles
is because it's one piece of hardware so
you know you do have a lot of control
you're like we know that if we do these
things it will work right we don't have
to wonder about what will happen on this
GPU or that GPU or this CPU or that CPU
duty basement one are we going to do any
compression on the image or only
movement of the torso will we're going
to have to stretch the Cape to two to
reach the head so that that's gonna have
to happen
f SJS I'm I don't really discuss game
design stuff on the stream so I'm gonna
skip that one
is it possible to create animations like
Looney Tunes we're looking at still
frames you could see multiple heads and
limbs or features that are extremely
exaggerated distorted somehow it still
looks fine in motion smear animation is
a term I could find in 30 seconds of
googling I'm not sure exactly what
you're asking about you're talking about
just like multiple static frames and the
answer is yes you can totally do that
looks like we're out of cues
yes we're out of cues except for let's
see here
why not use Java instead of C I feel
like I've covered this lots and lots of
times
so I guess my my sort of base question
would be named the professional 3d game
engines or really named any professional
engine written in Java and the answer is
there aren't any right Frostbite not
Java unreal not Java unity not Java
destinies engine not Java and so if you
want to program in games and you're
trying to get a job programming games
and the only thing you know how to
program is Java you're not gonna get a
job on an engine team if you want to
program little toy games or whatever and
that's you know you're happy doing that
or you just you know don't care about
you know sort of advanced game engine
programming then that's fine you can use
any language you want right because it
doesn't matter you could use Python you
could use PHP if you wanted to right but
the answer is high end game engine
programming is never done in Java ever
under any circumstances most games
aren't written in Java either even if
they're not high end so you know there's
there's a minecraft witch whose
performance is abhorrent even though
they're not even doing anything in the
game hmm is written in Java but at least
I guess it works but that's like one of
the only games you can even think of
it's written in it so even most time
people don't like if a lot of games are
written in c-sharp nowadays because like
there's the XNA framework and unity
obviously is also kind of like has
c-sharp on top of it so that's kind of
more of if you were going to program in
Java I don't know why you would ever
actually program a game in Java because
it seems like c-sharp is more the the
picking kind of supported platform for
gaming you have a lot of choices for
engine stuff in whatever where's Java
you've you've really got nothing
that I know of unless you know maybe
it's like a mobile game on Android or
something since that's kind of a Java II
platform but so the you know all of that
is whatever you know do whatever you
want to do but as far as like why we
don't use Java in the stream it's
because this stream is for people to
learn how to be game engine programmers
and there are no gaming engine
programmers who like there are no game
engines that get written in Java so you
know it would be useless for me to teach
nobody wants that no one's gonna hire
you
right
Jay monkey and LW j GL are professional
open square stars are in Java just named
a couple no engines meaning game engines
those aren't game engines that anyone
actually uses like go but what game can
you buy name any game on the seat like
that's in been in the steam top 50 right
its engine is not Java right where will
you go to work at which game company
do you believe you would be working on
an engine that's written in Java there
aren't any it just doesn't happen you
know it's like it'd be like Zynga or
something would be where you would be
working if you're talking about Java
game engines they're like these little
toy things they're not the serious you
know they're just not the serious engine
and and you know maybe you could you
know you know again c-sharp is kind of
one of those things that's that's a
little more relevant because a lot of
those work but in them
a lot of those work in like in the Unity
pipeline or some people write games and
XNA like I think like Bastion was
written in XNA and Fez
hoopla probably time to just take
questions from the handmade Network IRC
uh yeah I don't actually know how to get
on that RC yet I should
in order strips the body to the head
will be the infant shearing probably not
shearing I don't know we could but I
think sharing would be would be rough
what would your ideal game programming
languages like it be very meta
programming oriented
have you seen this video on ooby's
Rayman 2d animation editor hmm hmm no I
haven't but I would like to
oh my god there is a wall of buttons
I'll have to look at that later it looks
pretty involved
so says the kid well the animation
function eventually we have that so
other entities can use them yeah
Gaston vive is it recommendable to mix
vector and raster graphics for a game I
would say that you know it depends on
the circumstances there's certainly no
reason you can't do it but you know
whether it's appropriate for your
situation is going to depend David Rosen
it will fire had a GDC talk on page or
animation have you seen it if so
thoughts yes I have seen it I thought it
was pretty good the animation in that
get in overgrowth though has some issues
to it so I'm wondering like I felt like
it should look better than it did given
sort of the way he was talking about it
I feel like there may be some weirdness
like I feel like he's maybe not using
like enough what's the word I'm looking
for I feel like he's maybe not using
enough animation for it if that makes
sense like hmm like he's not using
enough sampling would probably be my my
guess so
what he should probably do is like is is
work more with the velocities I think is
the problem because I don't know I feel
like the techniques he was describing I
feel like they would work really well
but when I looked at the animation
there's a lot of like discontinuity in
the second derivative to it so I just I
just feel like I feel like there's some
implementation problems because I feel
like the Technic techniques should have
worked better than then what they end up
looking like that's that's I don't know
so I'm not sure but that said it's not
shipped the game's not out so I don't
you know maybe they know all about that
and they're like yeah we haven't
finished you know this sort of thing
closest humanity to programming effects
in the lead of our universe how should I
know
like what do you have to say about the
researchers that claim that Java can be
faster than C++ at times I have looked
at every single time people have claimed
that and I was like yep they're wrong
like I went and looked and I was like
here's how they did it as like nope that
was just stupid cuz it can't be I mean
it's just that's it's kind of ludicrous
to even think that it can be because it
doesn't really make any sense and you
know you go to see these researchers and
they're hilarious like how bad the the
paper is and usually they don't actually
mean that it's faster than C++ what they
mean is that oh you know if you were to
create a certain program this specific
way and you use the java's construct for
it versus the c++ is construct for this
specific thing then it's faster and I'm
like okay I don't understand why that's
relevant because I could have done
exactly that thing in actual z/os us
myself if I'd wanted to so it's like not
particularly relevant now there might be
some things too where you know a Java's
maybe compiler got optimized for
something and you know you can't maybe
there's like some bad part of LLVM you
know that you can say well okay this is
slow or something like that
and Shawn no I have not seen I have I
have not seen
Oh our fellow Java aficionado here has
said that runescape which I don't think
I've ever seen is written in Java
what is runescape it's some kind of an
RPG I guess I I don't actually know
runescape
is a graphical browser game from the
client-side in Java okay that sounds
fantastic well if that's what's the kind
of thing you want to work on you know go
nuts man again not really a serious game
but okay they released the C++ client
last week oh that's great
sorry yoloswag the game you cited
actually had to replace their crappy
Java thing so bummer man I guess you
can't work there but don't worry they'll
still be a job for you it I don't know
at IBM integrating parking ticket
software for this city of you know
Pawnee
and I don't think that that minecraft
has been ported to C++ yet has it
some was suggesting that it has but I
doubted it my baby Microsoft did I don't
know but I you think that would have
been announced at some point
the wind - in addition - okay so
basically all that all the games that
we're in Java have been rewritten in C++
is that basically we're saying minecraft
got re-released in C++ and runescape got
really loose in C++
all right so I am going to wrap it up
since there are no more queues that look
relevant yeah I don't really understand
why people ever even talk about Java for
programming games because almost no
games are written in it and certainly
none that are like technically
impressive right that never has happened
pretty much ever and and it seems like
if you wanted that kind of a managed
language that's like kind of high level
it does seem kind of like you would end
up you know you'd end up doing a c-sharp
these days because you know you're
writing a Unity game or you're you know
you're using XNA or who knows what
you're using some of those things seems
like where like I've seen a lot more I
can think of a lot more games that are
that than than our Java like there's
almost none it's really really really
really rare all right thank you everyone
for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you of
course can you can pre-order the game on
I'm hammer here or gonna come to the
source code so you can play around with
it at home you can also go to the forum
site which now is hosted over on
handmade network oops I got to refresh
my page though I updated this link there
we go you can go over to the forums
where you can ask questions and and
stuff like that if you're trying to file
along with the series and you have
questions we also have a patreon page
you can support video series the
schedule pot if you want to know when
the series is gonna be live and of
course we also have our little live
button which counts down for you so if
you're curious when the shows can be on
and you want to catch another one you
can do exactly that until tomorrow I
will catch you guys on the Internet
I believe tomorrow is 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time and we will take a look at
how to do a little bit more stuff with
the animation in there take as everyone