hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream and sometimes as it happens those
of you watching out there at at home in
the comfort of your own living room or
wherever you're watching this room I
have some ideas that are better than my
ideas when you're watching stream and I
feel like that happened yesterday at the
very end of the stream I was like whom
we got to align this thing and maybe I
need to sort of figure out some way to
do an alignment update and then in the
Q&amp;A some was just like can't we just
make sure this thing is always a
multiple and I had discounted that
possibility in my head because I was
thinking about the wrong way I was
thinking like well I don't want to have
to make the world chunks be a multiple
of the lighting size and then I was like
wait a minute that's where I'm going to
think of it just make the lighting size
be a divider on the chunk size that's
what we should have done and it's okay
we didn't really spend hardly any time
on it yesterday it was only 10 minutes
or 15 minutes or something so I'm not
you know I'm not gonna lose sleep about
it but it is definitely true that that
that was a case where the chat was on
top of it and I wasn't so let's take a
look at what I'm saying for those of you
just joining us inside the lighting code
there's something I want to do which is
that if you look here at the bottom of
the sort of lighting solution work that
we're doing and this is kind of a big
old gnarly struct that this will get
sort of mushed down there's a lot of
crap in here that was just from
experiments or that isn't relevant
anymore so I realize it's a mess to look
at that's okay we're not gonna clean any
of this up until we're sure we've got
the right solution people who focus on
clean code the entire time you waste a
lot of time of your time cleaning up
code that shouldn't be cleaned up yet
and so you know just to re-emphasize
that what you're doing experimentation
get the experiments working well first
then clean up the code don't do it the
other way around because otherwise you
end up wasting a lot of time it already
wastes a ton of time well I shouldn't
waste its time well spent but it takes a
a lot of time to do experimentation when
you're exploring and trying to find a
good solution to a problem the last
thing you want to do is strap another
sort of slowdown or or you know when
you're running the marathon like that
you don't want to strap a refrigerator
to your back don't know why use that
metaphor my dad always used to say
something about strapping refrigerator
back when running a marathon I don't
know why you can't do that people can't
even move favorite Ford Raptor that's
the matter maybe one of those mini
fridges that people use in haut college
dorm rooms or hotels the mini bar
obviously without the stuff in it
because they have those weird sensors
when you pick up the thing at charges to
your hotel room in the mini bar or
whatever so if you actually strap one of
those to your back then as you were
running the jostling would probably make
it so it kept thinking that you bought
stuff from the mini bar and you would
end up with like a huge bill by the time
you got to the end of the marathon and
it seems to me that when you get to the
end of the marathon at very least you
should not have to pay because you
already did a tremendous amount of work
just to run the marathon and it's kind
of like adding insult to injury that's
like congratulations you finished the
marathon oh by the way now you have to
pay the hotel like a hundred and seventy
dollars because like the M&amp;M peanuts
like got bought 1,700 times or something
right so if you take nothing else away
from handmade hero I would say don't buy
things from the minibar it's overpriced
now back to what I was talking about we
have this idea that we're going to store
the voxel cells as a large sort of
region around where the player is and
the reason for that is just that we want
to be able to sort of cache lighting and
it may be a little inaccurate but at
least it's cached and then as the player
moves around what we'll do is we'll sort
of page in that section sort of scroll
it in inside the voxel if you will and
only in the center area of the voxel
will be actually like update the
lighting though and it's true that this
could have some negative artifacts but
with lighting we're always going to have
negative artifacts like like artifacts
that that come from the fact that we can
solve the entire lighting every frame
because there's always gonna be some lag
some lighting lag and there's nothing we
can do about that but what we're trying
to avoid here is the possibility that
something spills into view and there's
no lighting there right we would rather
have the lighting be a little bit wrong
because a light moved or turned off and
it's a little bit wrong or something now
we would rather have that than it always
be wrong where we page we scroll fast
and we end up seeing some area that
hasn't had any lighting computations in
a while
I would much rather not get there and go
okay it's just black right now and we've
have to like spend 20 30 frames getting
it back up to lit right so I would like
the ability to cache voxel results as we
move around and so I'm gonna do is have
a large voxel here that stores the
lighting information in something much
larger than what we actually transmit to
the graphics card so it is is really
just a buffer we're not computing the
lighting necessarily on this we're
literally just saying we're gonna store
a big region of the voxel cells and then
what we're gonna do is say we've got a
couple of different things we've got
wear them in in world space in
simulation space where is the minimum
corner where is the corner of the part
we're actually doing and then we have
what it's index is in the larger voxel
we have the dimensions of voxel cells
and then we have the storage for itself
and then remember the hot voxel region
so the region that is the center of this
larger voxel grid the center part
specifically that part is what gets
copied to the card and it's actually
used to render lookups we won't copy the
whole voxel because it's much larger
than we actually need to compute the
lighting it's just a cache around that
area so where we left off yesterday for
those of you who did not see yesterday's
stream is when we actually go to do the
begin lending computation you can see
here we sort of had some stuff we were
starting with this is the part that we
wanted to change instead of trying to
align on every frame we don't want to do
that we want to do this part right here
what I said should we just divided world
chunked in mirrors by some constants the
answer is yes so when we in it
lighting what I'd like to do is I'd like
to get that world chunk dim here so
basically I'm gonna demand that when we
initialize the lighting you tell me what
the world is and that way when we look
at the world so you know inside the
world struct here you can see that we've
got this chunk dim in meters so since we
know that the world will be kind of
aligned to that chunk dim in meters at
least for the the most part that for the
most part we know that world positions
anyway are aligned first of the chunk
Dumon meters with their int offsets and
then there's just a floating-point
offset on that that makes it a lot
easier for us to deal with origin P when
it comes into the system inside begin
lighting computation so here what I
would like to do is say okay we've got
world we got this like chunk Tim in
meters
situation here and the problem that we
would have with chunk diamond meters I
think is that if you look that's gonna
be here yeah so if you look what we end
up with for the world chunk Tim in
meters is you can see that it would
imply that our voxel would be
non-uniform right because if you look
you've got sort of a 17 times 1.4 a nine
times 1.4 and then the typical floor
height bit here typical floor height way
I don't really know what that's set to
at the moment but oh so it's literally
set right there I thought it was
something that was get passed in but
it's not um so the typical floor height
is like five these are like 1.4 right
and it's just like we haven't really set
ourselves up for success particularly
well here because the the the factors
don't seem to line up like these don't
have a factor of five in them and so
they wouldn't be even with this these
both have a factor of 1.4 and so in
theory what we could do is say that the
there has to be I mean we you know we
could do something like this right so
let's say it is something like that if
we took a look at what the fundamental
unit was and we said this 1.4 for
whatever reason the we could just set
the typical floor height to be like
slightly larger or slightly less large
so instead of 3.5 maybe it's just three
you know so maybe it's like three times
the fundamental unit for something like
this and if we did that then our
lighting could be represented cleanly
because each of these things divides
evenly for the fundamental unit right
it's 17 fundamental units across nine
fine fundamental units down and three
fundamental units vertically like in the
Z direction right and maybe that's fine
right like maybe that totally works or
maybe that's a like horrible idea and we
have no idea but it would let us align
our voxels to the world better and so
let's just see if that's terrible or not
if I come in here to the world mode
itself so we're looking at this game
mode world structure here and I want to
add this concept of a fundamental unit
so we sort of have the typical floor
height here I don't know why that's
stored in here but we probably had a
pretty good reason back in the day
because it needs to kind of be known
elsewhere but we got this typical floor
height so here we can also have the
fundamental unit size right and then
that way that is just something that
everything is is created from now I'm
gonna go ahead and if these out again as
well and we're gonna have a problem here
where our lighting is not actually
working right and that's gonna be an
issue because we won't be able to see
anything probably but we could do maybe
this I don't know
yeah you can see here this this wants to
take the world and so when we do our
lighting initialization we have the
create world down here and so we should
be able to do our init lighting now what
we could do though is say look it
doesn't really need to take the world it
could just take the fundamental unit and
that's actually a lot easier so in here
we would just say what's the fundamental
unit and that becomes our voxel
dimension right so here we would just
say well okay you know the cell
dimensions stuff now we know exactly
what it is the cell dimension is always
just the fundamental unit in all
directions that's 1.4 that's the size of
the voxel you know what are you gonna do
about it we can also say that maybe it
should have been three wide maybe one
point four was not enough so we could
start with twice the fundamental unit as
our box will sell them again doesn't
matter as long as an even multiple of
the fundamental unit I think we're
probably okay so we can certainly do
something like this and then we would be
out of the business of having to do this
modulus based nonsense for our voxel but
again let's just go ahead and see if
this is sensible in terms of the way
everything else works I don't know it
might horribly break everything for all
we know now the problem is we don't have
lighting in there at the moment because
I've disabled it and so we're just gonna
see a black screen which is not so much
what I would like so what I'm gonna do
is inside the OpenGL renderer just so I
can verify that we didn't break
everything horribly there I'm gonna go
into the Z bias program here and where
we set up the lighting I'm gonna turn it
off right so in here I'm just gonna say
lighting disabled equals true and we
should probably hook that up to a more
convenient debug key so I can just
toggle that on and off any time we want
but we haven't quite gotten there yet so
we're not going to worry about that at
the moment so if you look at what we've
got now here is the version of this
where we've changed the floor height a
little bit the floor Heights are now
less than they were
before and so we may have a couple
issues with our world Jen because I
don't know if we really made that floyd
parametric but it looks to me right like
there's no real harm in that
i you know big deal right
everything looks kind of fine it looks
like we have a little bit of an early
alpha issue but a lot of that's because
we're still using the height of the
player for the for the alpha fade which
i really didn't want to do like that's
kind of just a bug that's been in there
for a while and we really don't want
that we sort of want more it to be based
on the the stable height of the player
so not like the hopping height the
ground point height and so you know in
fact i might maybe let's just go fix
that right now but that's the only thing
that looks like it's a little annoying
so we may also want to change though
that threshold in addition because we
might be getting a little bit in fact
you can see it's tuned a little bit
wrong now if i remember correctly
didn't we do this you can see we've got
an alpha min alpha max there so if you
look you can kind of see this may be
hard for the folks at home to see and i
apologize for that but if you look at
what the alpha level you can see these
like the black lines of just just a very
bottom of those cubes from the ceiling
are visible that's again because the
floor height is the Alpha min alpha span
is now tuned in properly so you know you
can see if I if I adjust this value
using our real-time controls right you
can see me kind of play with that I
think we want that to be somewhere more
around to now probably or something like
that
let's just see if we can tune that value
something that we like better and then
we'll use it
so I think I like that I think I like
that maybe so a 1.6 and then the 7.5
alphys man so I'm gonna go ahead and
take a look at the Alpha min default
setting that we've got in there I think
I might go ahead and change that you can
see it's set to 275 here I'm gonna go
ahead and change that alpha min to 1.6
again you can see how nice it is when
you get those debug sliders working in
there again that's just a nice way of
making sure that you always can tune the
artistic elements of the game as
necessary to make them work better
without having to go through a lot of
trial ner it's just a nice little
simplistic aspect of that I'm seeing a
little bit of alpha there so you know
I'm I'm actually thinking maybe I was a
little bit aggressive so you know maybe
maybe 2 is actually a little bit more
required I will say it looks like that
alpha is not based on Z it looks like
it's based on camera Z no no it's not
so nevermind we did it correctly but I
guess yeah like I said I see a little
alpha coming in there so I want I don't
want any out on those bottom ones so it
maybe needs to be more like a 2 5
and that just clips out that ceiling
or just you know two to five seems
pretty safe all right so I'm gonna
switch that to two to five and then I
want to just go fix that bouncy bug cuz
it bugs me
I really hate graphics you've
you've seen me get annoyed on stream for
stuff like that and so even though I
know that's not something that's
probably that bad I just I
yeah it's not super okay with it
so anyway I'm gonna go take a look I
don't remember much about that code so I
just want to see it I'm assuming it's
probably something to do with the the
code for update camera for enemy
movement and so I don't know I'm just
gonna take a quick look at it but so you
can see the focus Minzy and Maxie are
basically like set from the the room
focus in the entity focus so if we look
at what the entity focus is I just want
to see what that that is okay so if you
look here you've got new target P - n DP
z there for the editing focus see and
the room focus Z is just whatever the
distances to the cameras are so I want
to take a look what does entity here is
it just the entity yes so entity is just
the thing that we're focusing on and so
you can see the fact that we've we're
taking this this this new target P here
and it looks like what we're saying for
entity focus Z is this is like the
difference between the thing that the
cameras focusing on and and and where
the the player is right that's that's
all that is and if we look I you know I
guess we must use that entity Z value in
a way that makes that make sense because
those are sort of measuring two
different things here
oh because that's the new target P of
the camera no that's fine that's of the
camera not of the room okay so we're
good so basically all we're saying here
is look how far is the camera from the
entity all good problem is the entity
hops around and so what I want to do is
go look and see like what do we do for
get ground point or do we even have that
like how does the entity know where it
is in terms of like hopping around and
stuff like that we need to figure that
out right we need to sort of get that
under control so if we take a look at
entity here and we just want to make
sure that we have some kind of a you
know a handle on its out of Z location I
feel like we need it really we store
this must be why we didn't do it
originally doesn't lis we really store
information about where it was on the
ground so let me take a look just inside
the entity code that little like hopping
code that we're out I just want to look
and see how that's working so if you
look here at hopping it looks like we
just set the nd P between these two
directly right so there's a twosome
space traversable yeah so I feel like we
kind of need to store a little bit of
extra data here because this is how
we're this is how we're keeping this
information it's implicit in in the
to-and-from and so we kind of need to be
able to project it back down onto that
vector if that makes sense
so I would say we need something like
you know when we're planted the entity P
just is what it is right so like you
know entity ground P equals entity P or
something like that
so this is like the the stable version
although come to think of it even this
is not quite right because as you hop
around there's sort of a you're sort of
moving at different heights as the
ground is uneven so but that's probably
okay so let's say that we do it this way
where we have a ground fee that we
update and it's just whatever the
entity's actual placement is and then
when we are doing anything where you
might actually have a hop of some kind
there what I'd like to do is set this up
so that we are properly doing that
projection so here it looks like when
we're doing movement to and movement
from right this should be pretty
straightforward yeah it is if you look
at this right all we really need to do
here is there's like the hopping like
the height displacement so it's this
right here is like the height
displacement it's the it's the Z
displacement right and so this is just a
parabola between these points and if you
look at sort of the the parabolic arc
here the B function which is just linear
between the two if we want to we can
just compute that actual linear quantity
and use that directly to update the
position so in terms of the entity like
ground P here it's actually quite simple
it's just the lerp between these two
vectors these two based on T so what do
we call this is it lerp it's just lerp
so if we want to we can just say there's
a movement from and a movement to and
we're gonna lurk those for the ground P
in that case but in that case only for a
hopping entity I think that's all we
really need right and so I think that
that's probably sufficient I don't know
that ground P needs to be saved because
it's derived from the other information
so we can probably just stick it in the
part that's only for active entities
that are in the cache seems plausible to
me anyway oh and yeah obviously we have
to we compile we're changing the layout
of a fundamental structure there so
that's not gonna fly alright so now in
theory I think we should have stable
ground projection so when we hop down
the stairs we should now see smooth
descent through the Alpha and I'm
totally wrong about that apparently oh
[Laughter]
yeah so it turns out one thing you
should do is if you go through the
trouble of computing this value you
should actually use it I don't know how
many times I've done that in a mere here
or where I'm like and so we will use
this thing and then we don't use the
thing so yet obviously I was trying to
compute a different value to use for
that expression never actually used it
in that expression so it's not a
surprise let's try that one more time
hopefully we'll get a better result now
so here is the stopping around we're
gonna go ahead and go down the stairs
here
and so let's give that a shot
and so you know we do get from the
height variance like the fact that this
is higher than that we get a little bit
of variance there so you know I don't
know if we want to try and clamp to an
actual floor level or something like
that you know we certainly could and
that's something we can think about a
little bit later we could store for
example with our interpolation points we
could store a ground p-value with those
interpolation points so that the the
actual traversable x'
right the hopping locations we could
store something that that told us about
that and then interpolate that for
stable I don't know if we want to go
that far with it that's a tough call
probably we do want to go that far with
it but at least we've gotten rid of most
of the objection artifact there so we'll
save that part for another day cuz you
know what we would do is we would just
go and say that there's a ground p-value
well you know what I'm just I'm sorry
it's these things really bugged me and
there's not much I can can do about it
but let me just take a look at what that
would look like so in the entity code
when we're doing the hopping calculation
when you get this sim spaced reversible
right you can see it doing this this
given D by ID and then it looks at
whichever traversable is on that
particular entity right which by the way
I'm not sure why we do it that way
instead of just making traversals be
their own entities probably not so what
do i do so you know what we would
probably do is in the future I think we
would probably say that these will will
be their own entities and we'll probably
just use parenting to move them around
that would be my suspicion
yeah so looking at this I think there's
a couple things you want to do and I'm
gonna make some notes up here on these
so in the entity itself I think what we
want to do is say okay I think we want
to say and the last thing is I think we
want to make these changes but I'm gonna
do that more towards the gameplay code
side of things
I think we want to do that later but I
do want to do it is awesome saying so
let's get back to the lighting code now
and yeah I think like I said setting
that fundamental unit is just seems like
the right thing because there's really
no there's really no harm in it and it
seems like everything works just fine
there's no weirdness to having the
fluorides be smaller so everything's
just just dandy I think and if you look
at this it fits nicely in there it
doesn't look like the floors are too
small if anything that's probably little
bit better than it was before
so I'm I'm totally fine with that all
righty then so coming back to the
lighting code that means that this is
now basically all correct in terms of
showing the voxel cell dimensions and
all that good stuff when we go in to
begin lighting computation here what we
want to do is we want to go ahead and
take the sort of the part we were gonna
do with the modulus before and what we
know is that the world position now that
part we don't really care about as much
right the world position is not super
important to us anymore
what we really because we know that the
the sort of numerical version of that
the go ahead and jump over here the
chunk X chunk Y in shunt Z we know those
are now correctly aligned to the light
voxel automatically so it's really only
this part that's not aligned if that
makes sense so that's the only part we
really have to worry about aligning
verses so you know we can kind of come
up with a composite offset there right
where we say if this is the origin P and
this is the offset from the chunk centre
where this world position actually is
then if we wanted to figure out where
this camera offset origin was in terms
of its relative position we would
have to use this offset manually and we
know that these parts are alive right so
we have to do now is start to get these
voxels placed in the correct way I would
like to be able to sort of draw this
region a little bit so what I want to do
here if possible is go into the world
mode and we have the sort of you have
the sort of volume outline stuff right
and what I'd like to do is draw this in
here so I want to draw two things I want
to draw the region that we're actually
going to light so I want to draw like
the large voxel and in the hot voxel
right so I want to have a large voxel
erect and a hot voxel erect and I want
to draw like the large voxel rec this
one thing and the you know the hot voxel
rect is another thing and now I want to
be able to like hop the dude around and
I want to see them move correctly
because there's a lot of stuff we can
get wrong in here it's gonna be a pretty
finicky computation so rather than try
to get it working all at once I just
want to get the visual version working
so I know it's right and then we move on
to actually using it for lighting again
always breaking the problem down as much
as I can into smaller verifiable chunks
because especially with something like
lighting where it's very hard sometimes
to tell what's going on when you look at
it you want as much as possible to break
it down into pieces that you have some
chance of getting a thumbs up or thumbs
down on clearly rather than Maya looks
kind of like it's working I don't know
you know that's not a good place to be
because small bugs can pound their right
alright so what I might want to do is
try and figure out the rest of this
information so inside the lighting comp
I'm sorry inside the lighting solution
right we do want to keep an old value
for the world for like where we're
aligning our large voxel but I'm not
going to do that yet because before we
do anything that keeps an old one we
want to do something that figures out
where the new one is and so I'm gonna go
ahead and do just that part first and
then we'll worry about updating the
voxel 4motion a little bit later on
alright so we need to come up with two
things we need a rectangle three four
large voxel erect and this needs to be
something and then we need the hotbox
erect now if we have the large voxel
erect it should be pretty easy to come
up with the hot voxel rect right because
the hot voxel rect is pretty simple it's
just gonna be well and I guess in some
sense both of these are very simple but
I guess what I mean is the Vox min
corner hot part we kind of know what it
is because it's a fixed offset away from
the larger one or alternatively if we
want to phrase it the opposite way
around we could just say once we know
where the hot one is we know where the
large one is so we really only need to
compute one or the other because they're
locked to each other and so it's it
should be a straightforward equation to
get one once we know the other one right
but computing the first one is what will
be hard because it requires that
alignment calculation okay so we know
that in order to do the the hot versus
the large these are both going to start
with whatever we compute the corners to
be up above and then we sort of got some
some ancillary information that has to
be computed here we'll go ahead and set
that up but I want to start naming these
things more appropriately because if you
look at what these are named light dim
ins light dim not helpful what we want
to say is this is the hot dim versus the
large dim so let's just make sure that
that's clear so here we say all right
we've got a hot sell count here oops
so that's how many that's how how big
the the sort of hot version is this way
so the dimension of that is going to be
the hot cell count times the voxel cell
diem
again voxel damn same between the two so
the inverse of the of that right it's
just one over it so all that stuff
remains the same and then here we're
just gonna say alright so this is the
large Jim and this is the hot-dip right
so now we're down to like okay what's
the large dim how is that specified
again pretty straightforward all we
really need to do here is figure out
what you know back here we got the light
large voxel dim we can do large cell
count like so and then we can compute
these same two values now we don't need
this one necessarily at least not at the
moment so we're not going to compute it
till we know we actually need it so we
really just have large cell count times
that voxel down so now we've got all of
that is pretty much correct right and
what you can see breaking down here is
most of this stuff is just known so all
of this is like a no-brainer right
that's just right off the bat without
doing any calculations really we can
compute all of those values just from
what are effectively constants really
right and so when you look at the the
actual hard part of the computation the
part that it's gonna be finicky is
computing one of these two corners and
again once we get one of the corners the
other one will follow suit so what I'm
gonna do is say look the hot voxel is
the one that actually matters the hot
voxel is the one that actually has to be
fit to the camera and it's gonna require
a lot of sort of funky sauce there to
make that be a reasonable equation that
always gives us you know a reasonable
expression that always gives us
something that covers the area properly
and doesn't you know because before we
were sort of doing something it's like
let's look at the camera frustum and
what's it doing we can't really do that
because we don't want this thing to
shift around so we kind of have to do is
go what's
the maximum amount we're ever gonna zoom
out and make that lighting capture that
right and then when we zoom in we need
to stay the same so we have to kind of
we have to kind of do some more
aggressive positioning here we can't
just use camera information directly so
it's gonna be a little bit of work to
make this to make this go right I think
we and I think we need one more piece of
information here too which is like the
target location like what the camera is
actually looking at right so anyway if
we want to you know keep seam down this
path let's compute this one so that
means now I think I can also down here
before we go pass it I can write an
expression that gives me the large voxel
corner from the hot voxel corner and the
reason that I think that's easy is
because we've sort of already said that
there's a fixed displacement between
these two things so the hot corner I for
example will probably just be something
we set in here it's not gonna be dynamic
it's just gonna be something that says
where does the hot voxel live inside the
larger voxel so the hot corner I is a
pretty easy thing I think for us to do
all we need to say is look what's the
actual dimensions of these various
voxels right and that will tell us where
they go in fact I can even do this
dynamically in case we do want to allow
the lighting voxel to be different
dimensions at runtime I don't know that
we ever actually want that but you can
imagine doing that because if you assume
that you have the large cell count and
the hot cell count that's more or less
all you really need to know because if
you think of what we're doing we have
the large cell count which is a bigger
number than hot cell count it's like 128
and hot cell counts like 16 right so
what we want to do is say if we have a
16 in the middle of a 128 how
we figure out where that's a line well
pretty straightforwardly we can just say
let's remove the large the hot cell
count from the large cell count right so
we would say something like this so we'd
say this is how many cells are left over
on either side right so if we divided
this by two right we would get how many
large cells there should be like on the
left of the hot cell count and how many
there should be on the right of the
count right roughly speaking so that
tells us where the hot corner should be
if we just use that offset that tells us
how far we would go to get to where if
we want a roughly center the hot cell
count inside the large cell count that's
all we really need right because that's
how many you would go to get roughly
halfway to where this thing is right and
we don't want to go the whole way
because that would push it all the way
to the end right and we want it in the
middle so we're dividing by two so that
we put the same on either side of the
hot cell count so competing the hot
corner I very simple right
so once we have the hot corner I all we
need to do then is say well from the min
corner if we just go backwards however
that much however much that is that's
all we need right so the Hadamard
product just of the of how many cells we
need to go the Hadamard product of that
like so or is this just this now I think
the Hadamard product of that with
whatever the cell dimension actually is
right is is all wheat I think right
there shouldn't really be anything else
involved so once we have all of those
computed then we're just at a point
where yeah now we need to okay so we
don't know we do have the render group I
was like we need the render group in
here there we go so once we have all
that the only thing that's missing now
you
just that anchor point where does we
just need one point in space and we've
computed everything else for our entire
voxel system from that point of space we
now need to get that point in space we
need to find that point space and that's
where we're at now let's make sure that
all of this stuff is is set up properly
as well so we should have no compiler
errors now and the only problem that we
have now with our voxel is the voxels
just not we it's not centered right so
it's always gonna be at zero the hot the
hot voxel corner is always gonna be at
zero zero zero which we know is not
correct right but if we actually look at
it you can see we've got it now right we
actually do have it there and you can
see it's sort of aligned in the middle
as well so it's exactly what we would
have wanted right it's it looks exactly
right now one thing I would say is
something seems off about the dimensions
of the voxel that looks too large
potentially well actually it might not
when you think about zooming out to that
thing maybe it's not it might be a
little bit but let's see what happens if
we change the fundamental unit scalar
there so I'm just curious let's suppose
I go into this system during unit time
and say the fundamental unit it's it's
one long instead right I'm just I'm not
sure that that might not be good but
that might now be two that might be too
small now right but that's what that
would look like and and that looks like
a little bit better bounce I'm just not
sure this might not be quite enough when
you look at what happens when we sort of
hop into let's say this other region
over here right I'm just not sure that
that's enough lighting information
necessarily it might be a little too
small and so that's the only sort of
Squinkie bit
maybe we do want it the - maybe we want
the one I really don't know I so let's
go ahead and and just try to get a
little bit of a better feel for this so
in here let's make one small change just
so we can get a more ballpark feel for
whether it's too big or too small or
whatever else if I take the Vox Minh
corner hot and I just say yeah I'm gonna
place that at I'm gonna shift its dim
sort of back a bit so I'm gonna compute
this first and I'm gonna say that it's
gonna be the negative hot Vox erect
minimum or rather dimension oh I
actually never mind I don't need that I
just need hot dick I'm just gonna go
back by half the hot dimension so I'm
basically shifting this back I'm gonna
shift it over this way just to see what
that looks like when it lines up with
the simulation center properly because
this is roughly what we actually are
trying to compute right here so if I
look at what's in the view right now you
can see that if I were to actually track
the exact target it looks like that
would be potentially enough lighting
would it not on the end though so not
quite right it's a little too small for
that zoom level you know what I'm saying
to you so it seems like you we do
actually need it to be twice the
fundamental unit and I don't know if
that means we're gonna have to make the
fundamental unit be something that's
half of that value I'm not sure we'll
see in a second let's try this again
and so that's a much cleaner
encapsulation that gets everything I
think that's what I want to use for the
lighting I think I think seeing it
centered around here it's like yeah
that's yeah that's probably right you
know I'm saying and what we can do if we
need to if that's not resolute enough
right so if that's not an acceptable
amount for the lighting what we can do
is we can go ahead and increase our
voxel resolution by two to X because we
know right now it's sixteen by sixteen
by sixteen we know we can go to 32 by 32
by 32 no worries so we can play with
that value a little bit and and make
sure that that works okay so let's check
that and then I'm gonna move forward
with this I think I think we're in the
ballpark of of where we want to be so
I'm not I'm not too worried about that
so I'm gonna switch to test light
checkerboard i'ma turn the lighting back
on and so in compile Z bias program and
get rid of that lighting disabled and
then we should see the checkerboard
light and roughly like how big that
checkerboard pattern ends up being will
give us a little bit of an indication of
how resolute the the actual lighting is
right and I said I think it's gonna be a
little bit too sparse right
in fact I'm pretty sure that's too
sparse so what I want to do there this
gives us pretty much information that we
needed what I want to do there is kind
of scale things back a little bit push
them around a little bit I'm gonna say
that we're gonna make this be a plus one
and I'm gonna say that we're gonna make
the renderer version instead of sixteen
it is going to be five so it's gonna
look like that and then we can go ahead
and back off of that scalar because now
the hot region could be one it will
actually be one fundamental unit each
time right so instead of this it will
now be that
so that just ups the resolution of the
voxel and then I think we're probably
where we want to be we'll double-check
in a second
but I think that's roughly
okay right so now let's take a look at
how the voxel aligns here's a more sort
of dense packing you can see the stripes
they seem better now why I'm not seeing
the blue stripe very well I'm not sure
probably because this is green so
there's not a lot of ability to show any
any of the stripes there but yes I'm not
not sure about why we're not getting oh
no you know what the reason is because
know what the reason is because is that
checker pattern busted hold on a second
everybody just hold your horses
I want to go in and see in test
checkerboard here it is I want to go and
see what the problem is here so
maybe something like this
so now that's more of a checkerboard and
it's an actual checkerboard pattern so
in fact I like that a lot better because
I could see it really clearly now
and furthermore you can see that areas
with lines are areas that are outside
the region which I like you can see
right on the boundary it changed from
the checkerboard to just a clamped
pattern and I like that because before
it was kind of hard to see what was
happening there but now it's not right
so now we can see the relative
resolution of the lighting in here that
looks pretty good to me I don't think
we're gonna need more than that because
again the quality of our lighting
transport is not going to be you know
like super resolute this isn't you know
Hardware ray-tracing or something so we
know we're not gonna get any kind of
spectacular levels of light transport
fidelity so we probably don't need our
voxel to be like mr. awesome voxel
because at some level it's it's not
gonna have that good of lighting
information to start with we don't need
super great interpolation on a voxel
that doesn't actually have particularly
good fidelity in the first place looking
at the vertical resolution is a little
bit hard here so I'm having a hard time
really telling like what the I'm having
a hard time telling exactly what's going
on there and you can see there's blue
and not blue but it's not it's not very
clear so I think what I would like to do
here is maybe Brian alternate some color
pattern to make it a little easier to
see maybe we'll try to alternate between
like a blue and a you know a green or
something I'm not sure I'm just trying
to see if that would make it a little
bit easier for me to see what was going
on it probably won't I mean you can sort
of see as you get up to the top of that
blue you know maybe
but then it's really hard to see the
checkerboard pattern right as well
so if we wanted to make the checkerboard
pattern be in all dimensions can you
just do this not actually sure I've
never thought about this before but if
we just wanted something like this so we
have like fulbright and then you know
dim
that did not work well
trying to think of what the right answer
is there so normally if you want to a
checkerboard you can have this first one
right so you just say if X I guess you
just want to invert the pattern as you
go up and down you know what I might
also do just so we can get this pattern
properly in the open Jill seriously I
would want to go ahead and when we
initialize that texture I'd want to set
the texture to be nonlinear so I want to
do nearest lookups so like for example
let's see here a B right right here so
here where we do the color
interpolations I would just set this to
nearest so for the checkerboard I guess
all I want to do is on the z plane
I just want to flip it so I would just
want to do like one wave it sort of an
XOR right so there's the lighting
checkerboard and that's much easier to
see right that's what I wanted so that's
pretty easy to see and then I would like
it to be that I could also see it this
way right like I'd like to be able to
see it up and down as well and I suppose
that part of the problem is this
lighting normal should also kind of be
something that can be sort of placed in
fact I couldn't do this so I want to be
able to look at least at one side of
walls so I can see them get checkerboard
as well so like for example you know you
look at this and so now what I want is I
want to be able to look at that
checkerboard I want to see how many
vertical resolutions I get as well now I
can sort of tell because I know that
this is cubic right I know that we're
not the the the voxel cells our cubes
not right rectangular prisms so I can
understand the size roughly by saying
well it's it's that big and it going
down but I would like to just see it for
myself so what I want to do here is say
well okay so we've got X mod 2 and Y mod
2 another way of saying that is just
this right like if the low bit is set
right oops
finish please
compiles take too long and release mode
so this is another way of saying that so
we should now be able to you know get
the same result here right and so if I
have X mod 1 not equal to X mod 1 that's
just an exclusive or right in other
words if I want to say I only want the
thing to be true if these are different
it's just that right that's that's the
entirety of the of the expression and so
then if I want to make it so that it
goes the opposite way depending on Z I
should be able to just X or Z in as well
right like I should be able to say
whatever Z is well just toggle it based
on that as well right
it should flip it yeah there we go so
there's our three dimensional
checkerboard and now you can really see
like where all the lighting cells are
and I guess what I would say is my only
objection is we probably want this to be
shifted because if you look well we
don't need to destroy be shifted we just
when we place our lighting probes and
our lighting grid we want the probes to
probably be placed in locations that are
not right on the edge of a grid but I
don't actually know if that even that's
true
we'll have to see but it's something to
be aware of anyway so looking at this
you can see where the active lighting
region is it nicely encapsulates
everything that could be involved when
we're zoomed in here we should now never
really see the checkerboard stop there
should always be a checkerboard
everywhere we go and I think
that should be just about it right now
looking at it the way it is now I would
almost say gosh with the lighting region
that encompassing we may be able to just
not bother with anything else yet anyway
because that's pretty much just fine
right like that just works and it's
always if it's always centered around
the simulation center we're pretty much
good to go
the only thing we have to do is make
sure we handle the simulation center
possibly having an offset there but
otherwise this really just doesn't shift
it's pretty much locked to where the
cells are and that's all I really wanted
to make sure it would do right I wanted
to make sure that wouldn't slide around
relative to that and cause artifacts so
we might be able to just leave this as
it is temporarily and and revisit it
later when we actually have a case that
you know doesn't work or something
but that seems pretty good in terms of
where the voxels are so it's kind of
where the wild things are right so I
think that's alright if we then move
forward with what we're doing and we go
ahead and set the transfer lighting
version so in here I'm gonna say a test
light transfer and you know what I could
do I could just make this easier on
myself so we just toggle which one it is
I so if we actually go ahead and set
back to the transfer version now what I
want to do is try and figure out a way
to get our sphere lighting happening
using the transfer system and I don't
remember where we left that but you can
see there's nothing on the screen right
now so our lighting is not really doing
anything so the first thing we need to
do is now get that version working and
we know that now our actual voxel values
are not garbage right they're actually
Chrisette to something right so what I
want to do is now have that something
actually create valid light legging
values by going through the large voxel
to the small voxel so here is a loop
that loops over the voxel dimension
unfortunately if you look at what's
happening here this is not correct this
is and that's against cuz we have this
kind of a Vox dim Vox ting is not good
it's ambiguous we want to start talking
about these things more concretely so
what we want to do is take a look at the
Nama clay Chur where we've got hot and
large and and make that be sort of the
the more appropriate nama clay Chur here
right
so when we set this up we go like this
now we know what the hot and the large
dims are and now we can make sure that
these two loops actually operate on
values that that are correct for the
thing that was trying to be expressed
and we can set the inverse dimension up
here for the hot version I don't know
that we actually need that later but at
least for our old test code we need it
now in here where we're doing the this
initial setup this is supposed to be
looping over the large voxel you can see
that happening here
so this is a large dim loop that's going
over the 128 by 128 voxel here we're
going over the small interior version so
that's the hot voxel like so and so in
here where we're doing these old tests
this is like the in pot dem so things
that we're operating in here that that
need to talk about dimensions there they
have to be using hot dim all right so if
we look at this indexing here this is
just saying we're inside these we're
going to be again that's gonna be hot
dimmed all the way as well so let's get
that started and then I just I think
that might be it
actually and so then we could start
working on the
the transfer code and getting that
working properly so alright so we I
think now or have the loops right but
we're gonna have to actually figure out
how to get the transfer technique so
we're gonna transfer you can see it's
just looking up the displaced version so
that's Z Y and X there the displaced
version of the hot voxel this is us
packing all the values in there
as we would expect to do and then
they're just going to get shoved into
the voxels that the voxels actually used
for lighting at hopefully the correct
location so that's all we really need
and so the problem is just probably in
here or somewhere we're doing we're not
actually stuffing these values correctly
or you know who knows what but we're
doing something wrong and so we need to
figure out like why we're screwing this
up here's us looping over the large
dimension and filling out each of the
cells you can see us using zyx
which I believe is is the way that the
transfer is working there is it doing a
zyx extraction of the sort of sub region
of the grid it's using n 0 through 3 and
C 0 to 3 so the question is are we
setting those you can see a setting two
of them anyway the the 0 C value the 0 n
value those are the two we're trying to
get happening here looking at what the
actual values that are coming through
the question is why aren't we seeing
anything at all I'm not quite sure feels
like we should be and so something's a
little bit up looking at the fall-off
here
so I don't really see anything obviously
wrong
ah yeah
so I'm not quite sure what's going on
there
I don't really see anything immediately
wrong
[Music]
so I may I may say let's let's take a
step back
let's first let's just first play with
this a little so suppose I was to nerf
this stuff temporarily and just use the
checkerboard pattern on the whole voxel
right and so we're gonna set the light
c0 here and that irradiance pack let me
just make sure I understand what a
radiance pack is doing yeah that just
takes a light though so if we were to
just say let's put a bright value in
there so we're gonna say that like our
light C is just going to be nothing in
here we'll say there are light c0 is
gonna be some bright light like you know
5 or 1 which the max light intensity so
6 times the light I don't know what the
max light intensity wants to be here but
you know what who knows I don't know
it's something you can see the
irradiance pack what it actually does it
looks at the max value and then scales
it by dividing by the max light
intensity so we can have values pretty
high here right I mean these could be
who knows what they can be quite a bit
right so who knows what we set this to
something like this maybe and I just
want to see can I make the checkerboard
like is it why are we getting nothing
right like I don't know why I'm not
seeing anything at all and so I wanted
to start by saying is the transfer that
copies from the large voxel to the
graphics output routine correct and you
know that looks like it is to a certain
extent if I go in here and set this to 5
what do I see
so I'm kind of not sure why we're
getting such a steep fall out there I
think we may have some bugs in our
irradiance code let's take a look at
this so what we're doing here is we're
creating a result value first we look at
what the highest value of any light
intensity is assuming there's any it at
all
we then scale all the light values right
such that what we're gonna multiply by
is some fraction of the maximum light
intensity value well actually so we
scale the colors so we know that the
brightest color Channel is one and
everything else is a proportion of that
right and that's what this does then we
set the intensity to be whatever this
max value was divided by the max light
intensity so that's the alpha unpack
right and then we we pack all that crap
together right that's just a BG RI pack
four by eight and I guess it's worth
noting that stuff is not gamma corrected
right so one problem that we will have
is none of that was gamma corrected so
it's actually not gonna be right when we
unpack it if it was a gamma texture
right if it was an sRGB texture so what
did we actually tell it that it was okay
so it's not it's just straight RGB right
so that seems good to me so that seems
fine let's take a look at our Z bias
program where we actually unpack the
light and see what we get there
oh right and so our max light intensity
yeah this is all just kind of wonky now
because since it's actually negative one
to one it means anything less than half
the max light intensity just wouldn't
show up right interesting so basically
like yeah we need to fix that as well
because it's a full by normal and it
should not be so that's probably that
was probably the entire problem right
now that seems bad where did our voxel
go how come I'm not seeing any oh
because it's so it does miss a line
itself sometimes there's an example of
it miss aligning itself yeah you like
it's on half alignment here it's on
whole alignment so we will need to fix
that and that's good we have a test case
now that is unaligned that is aligned
right so that's good alright so that was
probably most of our problem it's
probably just that this is not creating
enough of a of a light value and you can
you can actually yeah in fact this was
just garbage so I feel like we're gonna
have to work on our max light intensity
and coding in a second here that's gonna
have to happen because it's it's pretty
much garbage at the moment and you can
see we have it to do there for it in
fact as well so when we look at what the
light see is and it's clamping negative
one to one this is all just complete
garbage and when we actually go to do
that packing of the lighting this is not
going to be correct so we want to do
instead here probably is we probably
just want to say like all right this is
the fall-off value so the fall-off value
is like going to be something where we
just do like alert between the maximum
light intensity
and the minimum light intensity so it's
like max light intensity
you know half and whole something like
that alternatively we can just do it you
know with these two values here so
whatever the zero value basically is
yeah we give you something like that and
I don't know why we're clients lights
see yeah there's so many weird things in
this code let's clean this up this is
just ridiculous this is the light
distance right this is what this is the
light like intensity value basically
right like the this is the distance
fall-off right and so here where we do
the the light alpha value again doesn't
really make any sense the way that we're
doing this exactly because the way that
these get packed down is they're getting
packed down using the max intensity so
again all of this stuff is kind of
busted from where it probably should be
so this is not what that's this this
light alpha is totally wrong the light
alpha wants to be alert between like say
you know half the max intent light
intensity and you know seven five times
the max light intensity or something
like that based on the distance fall-off
right that's what would actually give us
usable values and then the light
actually now does have a correct color
so if we were to look at that now maybe
we would see a proper spot light and in
fact we do right so it's just a again
that was just the encoding problem so
again looks pretty good let's go ahead
and turn back on our linear and see how
we do on that what I would expect now is
a nice clean version very similar to the
one we had before and now we're set up
more to start doing our transport right
so if we go ahead and change back I
really need a hotkey for somebody's
things one of these days we have to do a
quality-of-life improvements things so
we can just toggle these really quickly
because it's really important to be able
to see these and I have to keep going
back to the code to change them I don't
want to have to go into the code to
change them I would rather just be able
to just quickly hit a key and talk about
training them without having to find any
code so there's our interpolation right
and you can in fact we could even stop
it from hopping up and down if we wanted
to by making it use the ground P now
which might be nice but anyway you can
kind of see us moving that around there
and that looks pretty nice and again we
get really really good radial again from
such a small voxel it still reconstructs
the edges perfectly because of the
signed distance field encoding which is
pretty good and then what I want to do
now is say all right let's try to start
extending this by actually doing some
casting in the voxel so what if I wanted
to say can I see the light source right
so where's that ray cast here it is so
if I was to call ray cast and say you
know give me back which what I hit just
literally that right so if I wasn't here
when we're going to do this light alpha
what if I just called ray cast on it
just just defer for purely for amusement
purposes and I guess I don't know what
does the work function do it's just a
way of having the solution here okay so
if I was to say like all right there's a
lighting work thing and I'm gonna just
like initialize that
what does that having it oops
so it's just got this so if I just want
I don't care about any of this stuff so
if I just want that and I and I want to
go ahead and do a cast on that let's try
and get that working now so we know
where the REA origin is or you know it
depends how we want to look at it but
what we could say is look the origin is
going to be its we're gonna cast away
from the voxel center we're gonna cast
it in the direction of the light and I
just want to know if we got to the light
or not like that's all I wanted to know
so if I look back at the raycast
result here right then what I want to
know is is this is the the value is the
T value basically that I would receive
is that going to be closer or further
away than then is the first thing I hit
further than the then the light that I
was trying to hit or not right and I
don't know what kit is here is that like
just a boolean value or is that actually
like I don't know I have to go look at
what we set that to so let's see when
we're actually tracking hits in here
so it looks to me like it is just a test
on t array and I'll be honest I'm not
sure why we don't just return the tier a
value but seems like we should just
return the minty ray value here but hard
to say so when we do the raycast here we
need the origin and the Ray distance
right and in this case I'm just trying
to a single ray cast I'm not trying to
do this actually quickly so what I want
to do is I want to sort of generate one
of these by lofting up one into just a
four wide version of itself which I'm
assuming we have a way of doing I don't
actually know but we would in theory
have right I'm assuming we can do
something like this so I can say like
box Center P 4 right and light in 4 and
that just does the same ray cast four
times because hey it's the same cost as
doing it once so who cares
but like normally we would want to pack
multiple things in here right and so
let's see if we can just get that
working and then we'll kind of end there
for the day and then next weekend we can
start to work on the actual light
transport code so here we have the cast
value the cast value gets back like I
said it's got this sort of hit and P
values I just want to look at one of
these so looking at the actual structure
for this thing I kind of want to extract
a single v3 from it and I'm not sure
what the easiest whoops that was not
what I wanted I'm not sure what the
easiest way to do that is because I
don't remember how we set this up
exactly so I don't know what we use for
action here here it is
so assuming I just want one of these
things I can just say look watch you
give me back the zeroth answer that's
fine with me
so I'm gonna say like here's where the
the hit P was right and I can also ask
if there actually was a hit there right
I should be able to use a mask version
and in fact I guess I can just look at
where we were calling this before and
presumably like the extraction stuff was
there and I know I look at there first
but inside compute light propagation
right we set up this light work stuff
and then here you can see us doing doing
the tests so it looks like I can just
literally do this so all I want to do is
say if we hit something then I want to
test to see how far away it actually was
right and again that's why I would have
wanted that tear a value because I would
I wanted to be able to look and see is
it longer than light dist but it's okay
I don't really need to know one way or
the other I guess so
that Caspi value that we get out here I
can just can compare that with the with
the actual light position so what I can
do is say here if the inner product I
could say if the inner product of the
thing I hit - the place I'm casting from
so that's the Vox Enter key right if the
if the inner product of that along the
direction I was casting I is less than
the distance to the actual light so in
this case I've got the light P - the Vox
Center P right and I already did that
effectively because I took the length of
that of that - acute like isn't it so
it's that so if I hit something closer
than the light source then I would just
say let's set the light C zero to its
minimum
and I can do that a little bit easier by
moving this stuff down below so where we
go here I can I can do that right and
this light D F value which we've
computed ranging from sort of a clamped
version I should oh I should clamp this
shouldn't I
this is that should have been a clamp
zero to one I lost my clamp in there
right in here what I'll do is I'll amok
with that value but first I want to make
sure that my clamp doesn't screw me up
there needed to be a clamp in there and
there wasn't so let's make sure that
works also this is just cast and 0su
then we will just see and our rigged
casting code may have been worked
because again we were mucking with it
and haven't tested it since then so I
don't necessarily SPECT this to work but
I just wanted to get this in there and
then that sets us up for a next weekend
where we can start playing with the
right caster and getting that solid
alright so in here
what I do is say all right let's just
set the light DF down to some negative
values so this is you know gonna be
where it felt the the field falls off
steeply at this point so you know deal
with it and and we'll just go from there
now I don't necessarily accept I don't
expect this necessarily work so we're
not who knows what this will do probably
nothing
looks like well that's kind of weird I
don't know what that exactly it looks
like he looks like the Ray caster is
returning hits for things out here but
not for any here or something
not quite sure what that's doing but
it's doing something around the edges
for some reason I'm not sure and again
like we haven't really looked at this
function in a while and it's probably a
little bit busty it's just a busted
busted busted function um not sure I
want to dive in here cuz probably add a
bunch of things to do but I just want to
look and see if there's anything I was
like doing it was where I was
misinterpreting what it's actually doing
that's seems reasonable
I don't see anything completely
ridiculous here it looks like I already
had that comment in here
hmm
say I don't know
I don't know what's going on there
is cast pset what does calf pset from
because I also don't really know how
we're setting that what that actually
means like where is that getting set and
why so result P equals hit P and so
that's just yeah so that's just tear a
times there rave distance so that is
literally just yet
taking tear a and moving it so this
should be roughly correct I think
[Music]
and we are only going on things that are
valid like greater than valid values
[Music]
the close enough thing might also be a
problem for us here because that is the
thing that I think lets us say that the
box is kind of like like if I were to
turn that off right so when we do t
close enough and we're checking to see
whether we can use a larger bound like a
thing that doesn't actually continue to
raycast
I'm curious if we were to look at that
is that causing a problem here
I don't think so cuz 10 meters is is
further than I think where we were
seeing that the weird sort of artifact
around the ring but in terms of saying
like is it less than close enough so in
there I wonder if I just said like look
that's gonna be a lot higher I'm
assuming that doesn't really help us
right fix the weird like I just have no
idea what's producing that result so I'm
kind of curious to be completely honest
yeah and it's not it has nothing to do
with that it looks like so so hmm I want
to end the stream but I just I hate I
always my curiosity gets the better of
me I want to know what that artifact is
and it's hard for me to not know I'm
assuming that this is the entirety of it
meaning if I remove that I would get my
perfect circle back oh no no I don't
okay so it was something else
what was the something else
right this has to go below zero and zero
is half the light intensity so that was
all yeah okay so at least now we know
that the raycasting code is not actually
producing that artifact that was gonna
drive me nuts so very good and so what
it looks like here is if we were to set
the light DF to zero in that what it
really looks like is going on the only
thing that looks like it's happening is
the raycasting code is never hitting
anything right I mean that seems like
roughly what we're seeing and to be fair
I guess I don't really know how high up
the how high up that light is but you
know like Nuria regardless of how high
up it is I think it probably should have
been hitting something and so I think
that codes just not hitting anything
would be my guess I don't know if we're
maybe we nerfed the call that builds the
bounds that might also do it but I guess
I could also look to see so if we're
like here are we kidding
are we prevented from hitting stuff
below we're not I mean we're totally
hitting it so let me just double check
that we're calling it because like I
said my curiosity always gets the better
of me I'm supposed to be ending stream
but sometimes I just don't and that's
just the way it goes so in here where we
do compute like propagation we we don't
set anything up there I don't think so
so I think the only thing that we would
have to do is when we actually call the
start of this stuff we have to build the
actual
the actual space footage but that's it
so build spatial prediction for lighting
that's the thing that acts just a okay
so we need to actually build the spatial
partition that maybe 90% of it but we
still don't know if that code is working
properly
but anyway so now the spatial partition
is actually fair right it doesn't seem
to be doing a very good job because I'm
not sure what it thinks it's hitting
there right that is freaky okay so at
least now we're getting actual like an
answer from this thing about the raycast
and so that's a that's a much bigger
improvement that's what I wanted to see
something like that cuz that's like okay
the raycast is broken and that's what we
should be seeing right not what we were
seeing before which is kind of like so
I'm gonna I'm gonna play around a little
more sorry it's just like I like where
I'm at and that's just way it goes
sometimes so you know you gotta live
with it it's it's my stream it's really
all you need to know um so anyway when
we come through here and we build this
base positioning then we're gonna do the
Ray casting what I want to do is say I
don't want to have to rely on those
p-values I just want to use the T value
here and since we already I had to do
for that anyway
what I want to do is is let the people
on the outside do the hit P detection of
Rea origin plus T ray because if you
look at that it has to actually do the
computation so there's no point in us
doing that computation that's just dumb
but we don't need that ever so if we
moved that out to where the raycast
actually happens so inside our compute
light propagation call which we're not
using right now but just to keep it so
that it is like roughly correct
it turns a sketch of code in terms of
using the positional value where we do
like ray dot P or whatever that's going
to be this so that value is going to be
Ray origin ray Direction times the TT
the ray doc T value so like T hit or
something I don't know
so whatever the T or guess T ray is what
it was called
I'm gonna call it t here so in here what
we want to do is record that value and
so instead of using the p value here
we want to actually use the the tear a
value instead so this is actually that
and bat so that we've got hit and T hit
who knows
and then we never compute that thing in
here so we just return the T value and
if you wanted to know where the position
is well you can do the add because you
can do the add this is like we do the
add there's no not harder and so we
might as well give you the maximum
amount of information there and it's
also smaller right so we we have less we
have to actually return which seems like
a plus and then plus we also have the
you know additional the ability to do
like fancy footwork like I just did
where I or or like I want to do here
where I don't have to actually use the
computation anymore right
so yeah
oh crap alright outsmarted myself so the
reason we were doing the hit p is
because we had to compute it for this I
guess
so this is because we need to compute
the normal I guess of the surface for
transports which is kind of a pain in
the butt right
yeah so it looks like it's really the
hit value that needs to change and we do
want to keep doing the P because we had
to do it I wish we didn't if I'm honest
about it I don't love it oh that's a hit
P sorry so okay and then we just we'd
get rid of that and you you can compute
that on the outside right
yeah so if you look in here then this
would be where we compute t hit and then
anyone who is using that it has to do it
this way but that's the only difference
okay and then here we don't have to do
this anymore
all of this stuff can go away and it's
just one comparison so only have to do
is say if the caste tier a dot what was
that thing that you value or whatever
it's called you thirty-two
if the tier eight or what sexually nasty
tube I guess yeah thirty-two so it's a
floating-point version or is probably an
e you know I think about it but if the
floating-point version of what we hit
the distance a way that it was is less
than the light distance then that means
we hit something before we hit the light
and that was all I really wanted to
check right so and then we just have a I
think everything now is is the way it
should be and then now we have a problem
of going back and actually implementing
our ray cast right so something is buggy
in the actual ray cast like this is not
correct you know obviously and so when
we're actually like for some reason that
light source thinks there's something in
the way trying to get to the voxel
centers but those voxel centers don't
even remotely look like there's anything
in the way to me and furthermore I'm not
sure like yeah like it's like there's
something like right here it's blocking
it but there isn't anything right so
there's something busted about that ray
cast function and who knows what it is I
have no idea so if we look I don't know
that I want to dive into this because it
probably need to draw it but what I
could do I think we still have a debug
line capability built in here which may
help so if I turned off the lighting
temporarily and just looked at the
raycast
we should be able to push a debug line
that shows where the raycast
actually happened so for example this
push debug line here this could give us
that value if I said cast from the voxel
center P out to Vox Center P plus or
well actually just get component cast up
P Zero and we draw like a I don't know
that we're going to draw we draw a
yellow line right then we should now be
able to see yellow lines going to the
light source from the cast locations and
I should turn the lighting off so we
don't have lighting in the way of that
but no why I don't see any lights here
or in a debug lines where's the debug
line drawing code is that still
happening
I guess that's like something to to ask
oh yes so this is in the wrong place
right we need to make this output the
lines after we generate them so this
just draws the debug lines there we go
and now we should be able to get them to
show up although I still don't see them
what's interesting is it like almost
works like you can see it can't seem to
really get past that outside area and
like right there you can see it sort of
is preventing me from seeing down the
hallway right so it's like only right
it's like there's these weird like bugs
where it's introducing so we definitely
just have some kind of weird like sim
debug in the raycast but it's almost
correct it's it's like Edward James
almost correct and I'm just not sure
what's going on there I would like to
see those lines and so I want to know
why I'm not seeing debug lines anymore
here's us trying to push that on going
through the debug linecount do we have
to enable that compute light propagation
so solution update debug lines is never
such anything
which seems bad
I'm not sure how that's supposed to work
I guess I'll just said it
so we're getting a assertion there so
that's like it's in release mode so it's
not showing us but you can see the
reason for that is this array count is
blown out here so if we look at how many
debug lines it supports you can see it's
4096 I'm imagining that the reason for
that is unsurprisingly there's two
million of them right and for those of
you just joining us two million lines is
actually more than 4096 lines so that's
a little bit of an issue
what I'm going to do is restrict the
casting instead of doing it over the
whole cube I'm gonna do it only in the
hot region so when we do a compute light
propagation or whatever else not it's
actually just insert sort of the light
computation and light computation what
I'm going to do there for our test in
here I'm gonna say let's go ahead and
actually only do it in the region that
we're actually gonna copy so if we look
at the solution hot corner I dot Z and
then we go from there to hot corner Z
plus hot damn right
this will only loop over the values that
we actually plan to use and that'll just
make it so we're only casting on a 32 by
32 by 32 which we can probably draw the
lines for well actually you know what I
could do we could do an even smaller
subset so maybe what I'll do is yeah
yeah yeah maybe what I'll do is I'll
only draw the line in a small subset of
them because gonna be too many lines
anyway so maybe we'll do it like if X is
greater than or equal to solution hot
corner I'd X and
why's less are greater than Eclipse
solution hot corner I'd why and the like
so right and then we also say like and
[Music]
the same thing again right so let's take
a look at something more like this where
we're gonna say I probably should have
done this as part of the cut and paste
but I didn't which was thumb so let's
say greater than equal to some kind of
an A Center like a more centered kernel
so the the hot dim over to write this
would be sort of the center area and
then what I want to do is say let's go
like eight in either direction so it's
like a so it's like the we're gonna do a
sixteen by sixteen by sixteen kind of in
the center oh that's the baby kept me a
little close let's do eight by eight by
eight right so just in the middle I'll
see if I can get some debug lines just
in that like middle region so I can see
what's happening with the raycast there
so there it is right there's our ray
cast and you can see it ray casting out
to the voxel in from from this is the
debug light that's like hovering over
the the hero's head there right and what
I want to do now is I want to like see
what does it actually think it's hitting
in in these cases where it thinks it's
hitting something right so let's filter
the lines out by only things that we
think that that that actually think they
hit right that actually think that the
distance that the Ray was able to travel
is like less than the distance that the
light is from
the voxel center of casting so I'm gonna
go in here and say just show me like
only show me rays that we actually think
hit something so that I can see why you
seem to think that it's hitting things
in places where I don't see anything
right okay so taking a look at that I
guess so so it's really confusing I
don't understand what I'm seeing because
if you look the lighting that says it's
hitting something is like over here all
of these think they hit something which
is correct because they all hit the
floor right but like why am I getting a
oh is it because of stuff that's just
under the floor I wondered if all we're
seeing is just because it's just under
the floor a little bit you think that's
possible
I mean it could be let's draw the let's
draw it the other way so let's draw it
from the light source to the cast
location so we can see if that's the
case right so let's draw it this way
instead which is not really correct it's
not showing you the Ray that was
actually cast but I just want to see
it's a more interesting connector line
for me so if we look and we go here's
the light source here's the places that
it hit right and I'm wondering if there
just look right there I guess even that
doesn't really tell me kind of what I
need to know does it so yeah I guess I
don't really know maybe this is actually
working just fine and so if you look at
what's going on here really the only
problem that I might maybe I'm having is
I'm not using the light probes yet so
we're casting from places like inside
the floor and Counting that against the
voxel right it's possible it's possible
I don't know
so maybe we just need to cast from the
voxels and if that's the case I may be
mean to cast from the light probes right
[Music]
and I really shouldn't do that now all
right all right
whatever I'm gonna call it we're gonna
go to the QA I'm gonna call it but it's
really exciting because now we're at the
point where we should be able to
actually go cast from the light probes
add the frame persistence back in and
then we're like basically at light
transport we're really close and then we
can see the main thing we've got left
that's a kind of unknown is how we're
going to encode that as assigned
distance field correctly that's gonna
take a little bit of doing right but
we're really close now all right let's
go go ahead and QA
shouldn't world Shump dim in metres use
fundamental unit yes it probably should
now that we've verified that that
actually works there's no reason not to
how about increasing the Vox gonna see
and see if that reduces acne I don't
really want to again because I I want to
now make sure that I'm casting in the
right place so what I'd rather do is go
start casting from known good locations
and then once we know we're casting from
known good locations see if it's still
there right
let's see I'm a big fan have always been
delighted with your grouchy and a good
very good sense okay I believe that this
is a very useful quality that allows you
to look at things and the role of sober
look just I still can't understand how
to develop this quality in myself can
you advise something a book production
new programming work as a web developer
if you do not mind the time these--of do
you feel answer thank you so I would say
that it's more of like just a
personality trait that you probably
either have or don't have and I don't
know but you necessarily want to develop
it if you don't have it because it leads
to it a very frustrating existence it's
the one way to say it essentially where
the where the grumpiness comes from is i
here's what I would say fundamentally
speaking your mental model of the world
as you get better at doing something
there are two ways that your natural
reaction to seeing other people do it
worse than you for what appears to be no
reason how you internalize that and
everyone kind of has to manage it to a
certain degree because as you get better
at anything even if you're never that
good at it just the fact that you're
getting better at it at all means you're
better than the person who hasn't liked
practicing it alright so you're always
gonna be better than someone a lot of
the times and you're gonna see people
doing stuff that you know how to do
better right as you get good at anything
even if you never get really good it
doesn't matter right just getting good
at all so some people internalize that
as kind of like a like an egotism or an
arrogance of the form like I'm really
awesome right and so the better they get
at something the more they think they're
awesome other people internalize that
as why is everyone else stupid right so
they don't think they continue to think
of themselves as average and they think
of other people as below average whereas
other people continue to think of other
people as average and themselves as
above average and as far as I can tell
this is just automatic it does it like
this is just what will happen to people
and one of the other two things will one
of those two things will occur and then
your natural disposition will either be
that you're a grouch which is my case
and that's when you think of other
people as being stupid because they're
not doing something as well as you think
you could do it even if the correct
answer is that that's just because you
spent the time getting good at something
and they haven't done that yet right or
you're a dick right and you're just
someone who thinks you're awesome all
the time and that everyone else is not
as good as you because you're special
right neither are great right I mean
there's a reason that people don't have
a positive opinion of people who are
grouchy or dicks all the time but I
think that's just kind of the natural
brain chemistry response goes one of
those two ways I don't know what
determines it right and so you kind of
want to develop mental techniques to
avoid that being a problem like you want
to credit try to be conscious of these
natural tendencies and then not do them
to the extent that you want to not be a
grouch all the time or you not want
don't want to be a dick all the time
right the problem is sometimes you end
up in a situation where it's just
relentless right and this is the problem
that I find the world in these days
where literally it's not just a little
bit of the world doing things that are
kind of incredibly stupid all the time
it's like all the time right everything
you use like everything you touch is
like incredibly low quality right
compared to what you think should
roughly be the case and then it just
becomes like I would like to not be
grouchy about stuff and I'd like to kind
of have a more positive framing on
things a lot of the time and I just
can't it like overwhelms me right and so
that's not a good thing and similarly I
think other people who want to think of
themselves as hotshots are awesome or
whatever would have a pretty easy time
doing that in today's world because if
you become even a slightly good
programmer everyone is way worse than
you right so if your if your jam is
feeling really good about yourself well
now's a good time to do it I guess I
would say but for those of us who just
feel bad about the world when it's doing
poorly it's not rewarding and it doesn't
really make you feel good right you get
no positive I guess all I'm trying to
say is some people will feel better
about themselves when they see other
people doing things stupid and they know
how they would do them correctly other
people just feel bad because they think
the world is crap at that point I am in
the latter category so the more I learn
about something the more I think
everyone is stupid the more I feel
scared and unhappy rather than feeling
good about myself I feel bad about the
state of the world and get scared right
so that's just what happens and you
can't change it I couldn't suddenly
decide to be a dick all the time instead
of being Grouch all the time because
your brain just I think just does one or
the other and then what you have to do
is is figure out how to not do that
thing if you want to be happy right you
have to figure out how to not be a
grouch if you're someone who feels
scared about the world when you see
people doing things stupid or if you're
an arrogant if you go the arrogant
direction and think you're awesome you
need to tone it down right you need to
figure out how to stop thinking those
thoughts and think more about how to
just like be happy and not not rub
people the wrong way because you're
being a dick right instead of rubbing
people throw away because you're being
I don't have an answer to how to solve
that problem if I did I would do it
right you're asking the opposite which
is how to become a grouch or a dick and
I'm not sure I think it's a good idea to
do that
like if you're already in the standpoint
of not having a visceral chemical
reaction to people being stupid I don't
know that you want to gain that because
there's probably ways you can get the
good part of it which is driving
yourself to be better that's the that's
the good part of thinking things are
crap is you try to work towards
improving them or vice versa right if
you're going the arrogant route or the
egotism route it's driving yourself to
be better than everybody else right and
those are both good right they both both
you thinking everything sucks and you
have to do something to fix it or you
wanting to be better than everyone so
you drive yourself to be better than
everyone right those are both good
drives because they help you get better
but the problem is they both lead to
unhappiness right in different ways
because in one way you think the world
is awful all the time and in the other
way you become insufferable right and in
both cases people don't like it most
right I mean nobody wants to sit around
listening to how awesome you are and
nobody wants to listen sit around
listening to how awful the world is so
no matter which way you go it's not
great right so what I would say about it
in general is the ideal situation like
if you could just tune your brain
chemistry perfectly what you would
probably want to do is be able to
possess the quality of looking at the
world and realizing how much it sucked
without it having an effect on you
somehow so like you could see how we're
doing all these things wrong and want to
try and fix them but without you feeling
the negative feelings that come with
that or in the opposite case which I
can't speak as much to because I usually
don't get a positive
feeling for feeling like I did something
better than other people I get the
opposite when I feel like I did
something better than someone else I
feel bad about the other people like I
have a negative feeling about them not a
positive feeling about me right so I can
talk more about that one as from a
visceral experience cuz that's what I
experience I and somebody who was more
on the egotistical side of things and
felt positive about themselves rather
than negative about other people
again same basic idea it just manifests
itself in two different attitudes right
I don't know what the best way of toning
down that is because again still bad but
it's you you end up with a different
thing you're not sitting around telling
everyone else how bad they are but you
are sitting around telling one else how
awesome you are and that's you know also
kind of insufferable right so anyway the
ideal thing if you could do it somehow
would be to have the outlook that is all
of the stuff that we're doing now can
always be better and we could be much
better than we are right now we are not
definitely not performing up to our
potential and you know that and you can
see it right it would be great if you
could develop that without having one of
those other two feelings right and I'm
not sure how to do that because if I was
trying to do that I would just do it
because you will be a happier person
just for your own good right even if you
don't care about other people at all
which I guess I probably don't just your
own just just purely selfishly right you
will be in a better mood I think most of
the time at least for the grouchy people
speaking for me if you're someone who
feels grouchy when you see people not
doing something very well you would be
happier if you didn't have those
negative emotions you don't care about
the other people at all you don't care
what they think of you you don't care
like whether they think you're a good
person or any of that stuff you just
forget it you don't care you're still
unhappy because you're sitting around
going wow the world is just
totally screwed like we can't learn
anything we're dumb we make the same
mistakes over and over again even though
there's obvious information people are
always rejecting science on every you
know every part of the political
spectrum these days just completely
rejects the scientific method and nobody
uses it right programming we don't use
it like we don't nobody actually tries
to do a good job right we're just like
screw it forget it we don't care we're
losing all of our knowledge we're losing
all our abilities and society just
bumbles forward by the fact that systems
that are actually working take a long
time to break and then eventually they
just will you know and then nobody has
power in California and everything else
right you know we're all driving around
in Mad Max mobiles like hitting each
other with long Spears from from the
back of a 4x4 right and so I don't know
how you develop that like perfect
harmony of knowing we need to do things
better actively working towards no
anything's better but not letting the
negative emotions affect you I don't
know how you do that it you know in a
world where things are at least somewhat
getting better I think it's easier to do
and what I can say is that when I was
younger things always felt really
positive to me and part of that is
obviously because I had not learned as
much so the the more naive you are the
less you see the problems in what people
are doing
so there's definitely true because as
you learn more you are more critical of
the things that you see because you have
more capacity to be but another part of
it was I in general like the industry
that I cared about which is computing
everyone really was better than me
not just at that time but possibly today
even right like the great programmers of
that time period we're very numerous
compared to the average and in a
sampling of game developers from like
1992 I would say that the me of today
would probably not be very good right
like so like I maybe am fooling myself
but I actually think that a lot of what
happened is not me getting particularly
much better at programming but rather I
think the world got a lot worse at
programming like a lot worse and so what
I perceive to have happened over the
past say 20 years or so is that I got a
little better for sure like I I'm always
improving but I never really got that
good I'm still kind of I mean I there's
a lot of things I do wrong every day and
I know what they are right and I still
make a lot of mistakes all the time it
still takes me way too long to do things
and it still takes me like sometimes
years to explore a problem and come to
the correct solution and like the whole
world just like slid past me like in a
huge way right so now I look and I go
like what the heck like I drop in to
like do some web programming stuff and
like I feel like our website is like far
and away better than like 90% of the
things that I use and I am a rank
amateur at that I have no experience
right what is going on like if if I had
dropped into some other field of
programming in 1992 and tried to do
something in six months I would be a
nobody like I couldn't I wouldn't be
able to put up anything of value really
right and like that just makes me feel
horrible
it does not make me feel like I'm good
at programming it makes me feel
terrified at like how bad the state of
things is and I just get like horrified
by it right and
I don't think you want that in your life
I really don't think you do I don't I
don't know how to say it any other way
but it's just like it's terrifying like
you don't want to feel good about your
programming in that way like I felt so
much better when everyone was better
than me and if I really thought I was a
very good programmer right now I would
be okay with the fact that I'm feeling
that way about it but I didn't get much
better like like like we have a serious
problem that's all I can say we have a
really serious problem the kinds of
people that I randomly interacted with
in programming in like the early 90s or
late 80s the the average case was so
much better than it is right now that it
is absolutely terrifying to me like it's
absolutely terrifying so I don't think
you want that feeling I really don't
think you do I mean it really feels
horrible it doesn't feel good maybe if
you're the kind of person who goes the
other way and just and and you just
become an egotistical maniac
maybe that feels great to be working to
be such a big fish in such a small pond
which I think a lot of people could
achieve these days if you put your mind
to it you can become a better programmer
than like you know 80% of the people who
work at Facebook or something probably
right like maybe go ahead and do it if
you think you're that person if you
think that's the natural because man
you'll feel so good about yourself every
day but if you think you're the kind of
person who just feels bad about the
world don't do it like don't learn that
behavior like if you don't have it in
you to have those feelings don't by
default don't gain them like don't do
that
I don't know I wish I had something
constructive to say it's an excellent
question that you asked which is how do
you develop that sort of cynicism that
allows you to say we need to do this
better because we know we can and we
need to focus on all of these flaws
because that's a fundamental engineering
mindset and I don't think you get great
engineers who can't do that like it's
obvious to me that every great engineer
I've ever met is able to focus on flaws
and say how do we move this forward but
there are times in humanity's history
where being that kind of person feels ok
and there's times when it doesn't and I
think now is the time when it really
definitely very much doesn't like it is
just a horribly miserable existence as I
guess what I would say and like don't do
it on purpose
since the Jersey did you make your
website also in C and if so is it
possible to build an entire website from
scratch and plain C using new libraries
- yes so I did build our entire website
and see it's basically an offline
content management system because I
don't put the machines on the web here
at Molly rocket I just have like one
machine that's like a crap machine
that's you know made for doing web
uploads and that's plugged into the net
and it does the streaming here and
everything else is disconnected and so I
basically have a CMS that I wrote in C
you feed data into it on one side like
images and you know markdown basically
and you know stuff stuff that you want
it's like the content for your website
there's a little animation and coding
thing right for like like this stuff
right and it just knows about a lot of
things like it knows like okay how to
you know how do these things frame and
and how do I automatically make stuff
that maintains aspect ratios you know
like that sort of stuff and it
understands all these things so you just
basically give it like here's roughly
what I want to have you know and it
takes all of that ingress and it just
spits out a static blob basically right
so it like hashes all the binary data
and figures out like which of it has to
be updated which if it doesn't and puts
those into like permanent things so they
can be marked as cache always and that
sort of stuff it it dumps all that stuff
out and it puts it into a ready to
distribute format for fastly or are
sorry for firebase fastly is the thing
that runs firebase at the CMS the CDN
level and then all I do is I just bulk
upload that whenever I want to update
the website and you know I'd love to run
our sync but of course firebase can't
use our sync it uses node
jas so updating our website despite the
fact that only like three HTML files
have changed still takes frickin five
minutes because the people who wrote
firebase don't know what our sink is
right like problem to solve since 1987
or something like that but there's the
Grouch again krub do you ever try and
measure how much of your current outlook
is affected by rose-tinted memories
there were great things about using
computers in 1992 but I remember having
to constantly do things like messed with
hi I'm that sis to try and get the most
basic things working not arguing the
current state of things isn't woeful so
yeah I guess what I would say is I don't
think there's really any rose-tinted
glasses at all and the reason I say that
is because when I think of the Haiti or
it like I think of using the like Amiga
500 or something like that and I have an
Amiga 2000 here and I occasionally boot
it up and it's like the best thing I've
ever used Hey and sure there's all kinds
of problems with it like does it have
all the features that Windows 10 has
like no of course not
right so I'm not trying to make that
comparison at all
but when you look at what they did on an
Amiga 1000 with a 68k and 512k a ram and
you look at what Microsoft is shipping
today with a PC running at 4 gigahertz
like all core with 8 cores and hyper
threading and 32 gigabytes of memory and
a graphics card with its own 4 gigabytes
of memory and and and
and and it's just it boggles the mind
how pathetic the code is today it's just
garbage and it doesn't do anything else
really the number of features I actually
interact with on Windows 10 is slightly
like a fraction more than what I did
day-to-day on my Amiga 3000 which I
don't have anymore unfortunately I've
got I've got a 2000 I grabbed from
somebody who was throwing it out I sold
my Amiga 3000 to buy a PC when the
amigas kind of went out of production
really and you couldn't really stay on
that lineage anymore I wish I had I had
if I was a rich person back then I never
would have gotten rid of it right but
you know can usually only afford one
computer back in those days I mean they
were thousands of dollars so you know
some people couldn't afford them at all
and those who could you could you know
unless you were well really wealthy you
can only afford one so anyway the I
really don't think there's any
rose-colored glasses man I mean it's
true that that adjusting like PC memory
was a pain in the butt but I mean so
like yeah there were some problems with
it when I plugged in the mouse pretty
much always worked like my Linux machine
the mouse just doesn't work sometimes
that's it right so and I have no way to
fix it ever like no chance
hi ma'am that cyst was pretty easy to
learn so only a few parameters and once
you knew him you knew him right my
machine never ran an update didn't
interrupt him me in the middle of
playing the original doom to just make a
few quick updates right there weren't
all these background services running
they don't know what they are there were
no security holes because hey guess what
nothing is running right like so it was
pretty basic at the time and if you want
get a virus on your machine you had to
actually take a floppy disk and put it
in the drive that had a virus on it
you couldn't just get one because the
thing is sitting around and Microsoft
doesn't know what they're doing right
like I don't know like it's a disaster
now I just I feel like it's a complete
mess
and it's not it's just getting worse and
worse and worse
the number of things that we've gained
is not even even close to what it should
have been right
go bond says hey meteor I feel like this
was a pretty recent shift in the
zeitgeist you I remember just five ten
years ago everyone was much more excited
about tech I don't know if five or ten
years ago is enough far back but yeah
like I mean Windows was at least until
like Vista like Windows was actually
alright to like and sometimes things
were getting better GPUs were getting
better right and we were doing stuff and
I don't know right which Windows is the
best version oh that's easy NT 351 yeah
hands down and t35 one is the best
version of Windows this ever been ever
will be in transition this about
grouchiness but when you do something
you do it qualitatively because you know
what quality is it's cool from a
programmer interview that's all I wanted
to say yeah I mean people have drives
that drive them to do things better than
they need to right and it's true that a
lot of people do that and you know like
and it's definitely a beneficial
character trait for doing better work
right like I know that I'm a much better
programmer than I would have been
because I get angry with myself when I
think something isn't right and when I
think I could do better right and I know
that getting angry with myself like that
is what makes me go further than I would
have gotten if I was just didn't have
those negative emotions if I didn't feel
badly about myself all the time I
wouldn't get better like that if I
wasn't like this was stupid you did this
dumb right and so I don't deny that's
valuable to have that character trait in
certain circumstances the problem is
when the world goes into decline it's
terrifying that's that that's the cost
right that's that's the cost and
and that's like the past 20 years let's
say 15 years maybe that that's the cost
and I and it's not good right it does
not feel good at all
brian says the city apartments Freesat
is doing some investigating the other
day and you need to use process monitor
spy and dev and random looking around I
notice a big number of events
sequentially all calling read file knows
dev am loading 180 K bike config file in
42 calls each reading four K chunks from
the file setting the offset every time
so you should be happy I feel like Devon
oftentimes loads things in one bite
chunks from files so the four K is a big
improvement Brian um I would say that
one of these days I need to do a stream
from an old machine I think I've got one
that has old Devon I would like to show
just how bad Visual Studio has gotten I
think I have a machine that still has
Visual Studio you're like five on there
and I'd like to run it and just show you
what using a debugger is like it's
instant and this is on a machine that
runs at 120th the speed of a modern
machine so this machine is 20 times
faster than the machine I'll demo on and
stepping through code in Visual Studio
is several orders of magnitude we get
here I don't know and more so because I
come from a place where I feel horrible
about those sorts of things
viscerally I don't understand why the
people making these things don't feel
horrible about themselves it's hard for
me to wrap my head around that
like I realize that it's just that's
because it's the way that my brain works
and it other people's brains don't work
that way but like how does the team that
makes Visual Studio not feel absolutely
horrible about themselves every day I I
would just be a wreck like I would just
be horrified about my own self every day
and yet they clearly don't because they
don't fix any of it right like it would
be eating at me
so much that I knew that I'd taken
something that ran in real time and made
it takes several seconds and that was my
fault like
I just feel horrible about that sort of
stuff and that's why like you know I'm
oh wait like when I release something
into the world I try to make it okay you
know I write plenty of crappy code but I
keep it internal right I try to keep
that only for my dev you know only for
my like internal process and even that I
feel bad about sometimes like like I've
said before some things that I've
written that were meant to just be for
me
like and that are pretty crappy are
things that still get used as part of
the dead process it like rad or
something right and I feel bad about
that even though I kind of don't feel
like that's my fault because someone
else just does something about that
those were supposed to be little tools
for me right to use but you know
sometimes tools that you were thought
were just a little simple something take
on a life of their own right and at that
point it's like a crap like this was
never intended to be good and now it's
actually getting used and but I don't
usually beat myself about that cuz I'm
like that's your fault man I sell you
this like you didn't pay me to do this
right this was something I had to do
quickly and in the course of some other
thing I was working on and if you want
to use it that's your decision right so
I don't feel that bad about that but if
I'm like selling something like dev
studio for a thousand bucks or whatever
the heck I license cost and I like screw
it up that badly i man I would feel
horrible right I mean I felt horrible
when I thought the boat glitch was my
fault in the witness right and it turned
out it wasn't thankfully but like even
just a little thing like that gets by me
and I feel terrible because it's my
fault right and you know I still even
felt a little bit bad because I was like
well if I had actually gone on this
project full-time which I didn't do at
the end of the witness I wasn't
full-time and I'm like I would have
caught that because I would have gone
and checked and I could have done that
right and so in a way well I didn't feel
like it was my fault cuz it wasn't my
bug I could have I could have fixed it
right because if I had been on full-time
I
have found that I bet and so you know I
still feel bad about that
what's one thing in programming your
tech that can excite you and you think
is an improvement well I mean I don't
really know of any software things at
the moment except for maybe the work
that John Blair was doing on his new
language so you know I don't know what
it will turn out to be in the end but I
just feel like it's the only language
development effort that I've seen so far
where it seems like the person has any
idea what they're doing right and that's
kind of refreshing because like
especially because John has created like
you know effectively two whole game
architectures all related like braid in
the witness herb have some similar
architectural features to them but like
that shipped incredibly impressive
things I feel like that kind of
perspective is something that most
people who develop languages just don't
have and so I'm pretty excited to see
what ends up happening with it it may
still be no good you know I mean
everything is difficult and you never
know if thing will succeed but I feel
like if I if I had to put money on it I
would say that it's the only language
probably in development right now that
I'm excited to see what happens because
I feel like it's the only one with a
person behind it who actually has done
the kinds of large-scale architecture
successfully that I think you need to
have done - or in order to actually be
able to make good language design
decisions right because a lot of other
languages are just people making
language design decisions without that
perspective they have never shipped
something on the scale of the witness
that they architected themselves right
so I'm pretty interested to see what's
gonna happen with that and I don't know
if I had to pick something other than
Jie
I mean one thing that I was excited
about recently was Charles and Fabien
making the Udo compressor I mean they
made some advances in compression
technology that are you know I don't
think anyone even thought we're
necessarily possible like I mean nobody
had really made a advancement in
compression technology for quite some
time and they come along with this thing
that just totally destroys like
everything that came before it and and
that's pretty exciting to me again
because these are just examples of where
I can like look up to somebody who's
doing something that I know is much
better than anything I would do right
like I know the util compressor is
probably something that if I wanted to
do something of that caliber it would
take years of study and I mean and I'm
and I might just not be good enough to
do it
right and it's inspiring to see that
occasionally because you almost never
see it anymore most of the things people
produce are just garbage and it's not
impressive and I don't like I'm I don't
want to make it like I don't want to be
that way right
and so when you see something that you
go like wow like the people who made
this we're just amazing and they were so
on top of it and they just absolutely
crushed it I feel like that's pretty
inspiring too because you want to be
seeing people make things that you that
are beyond your capability right you
don't want to constantly be looking
around and seeing only things that you
feel like are not even at the level you
could just sit down and do even though
it's not your area of expertise
right and so when you see people who
have specialized in something and they
go and do this thing that's just like
way better than what you would have any
idea how to do that's really inspiring
because it it's like let's you know that
there are people like pushing boundaries
in directions that are further than you
can conceive
you know what I mean and you want to
feel that way and like in terms of
software I can't think of a lot of
things like that you know like that the
Google compressors one but you know I
think I would be hard-pressed to think
of another one there probably is one out
there
I just don't know I I don't have
anything offhand but the auto compressor
is definitely one where I think like
that was just like a demonstration of
skill that I found very impressive I
think with that question I'm sorry you
didn't upset me with the question it's
it's a state of upsetness with the world
that is just lingering and it just
happens to be a question where that was
the topic of the question right you have
any advice for applying for triple-a
engineering jobs I've worked on a few
indie titles porting them to consoles
mostly uni games I think a lack of sea
boses work experience is hurting me but
it's hard to get that rig experience
without previously those less
experienced any advice not really I mean
I think you want to have some spare time
projects probably if you if you can't
get a if you cannot get a C++ job right
now I don't know how you could really
get one with no experience it probably
pretty tough entry-level C++ work is
hard to come by I think in the game
industry anyway but I don't really know
I don't apply for triple-a engineering
jobs obviously so I'm not sure how how
that market looks there may be places
for junior programmers to get into it
where there's a you know like a sort of
a bridge there but I guess I would ask
the question when you say porting a
Unity game to a console what does that
mean so cuz doesn't unity just run on
consoles
so that's not C++ expiry what does that
mean I was trying to figure out where
you're coming from exactly because then
I could kind of maybe
do you do anything specific to motivate
yourself in the world of office software
well no because you know it's not really
about motivation or not I just enjoy
programming so I do it every day pretty
much by default you know and if I go for
too many days without programming I just
get sort of for Lauren really so I never
really have to motivate myself to
program it's always just gonna happen
it's more of the feeling that you get
and a psychological tool that that takes
is the problem
not that it's demotivating it doesn't
ever demotivates me it just makes me
terrified all the time right
what I can say is that like if there was
I I do think it creates an opportunity
in the world though and you know I don't
think that opportunity is ever going to
be taken but if you were some kind of a
enterprising small country out there
somewhere right and you were like okay
we are like the government of I don't
know I'm not sure who this would ever be
in reality but you're the government of
Qatar let's say and you just decide one
day that you're gonna be like this
enlightened government and you're gonna
like try and create the next world
economy because why not before the oil
money runs out I don't know if you
actually set up a thing where it's like
okay we're gonna take a government and
we're going to say that like we
guarantee certain things like you know
we're going to create a environment
where people are 100% encouraged to be
like scientific about everything and our
entire government will be run this way
so everything has to be based on
repeatable premises and we're not going
to do any of the weird like sort of
liberal arts self-esteem complete
garbage that like the u.s. does nowadays
or that a lot of places do we're
actually gonna be like we're creating a
place primarily for people who want to
focus on excellence and never be sort of
like you know told that their primary
goal of something else
I mean I'd move there tomorrow right
like I would love to know that
everything in that society was gonna run
like on that premise right but you know
short of something like that where
someone actually creates and you know
it's not unprecedented you know there's
been plenty there's you know I mean you
look at even the founding of the u.s. or
countries that that followed suit
afterwards right there's tons of times
when there's been shifts in the way that
that people framed their societies and
how they were going to work right and so
there's nothing that says that someone
brilliant somewhere who's smarter than
me and knows how to figure this crap out
you know John Madison 2.0 or something
figures out how to structure a society
so that people are driven to always do
things well and be focused on excellence
always and everything else is not part
of your societal fabric right I feel
like it wouldn't be long before
literally all the top talent wants to be
with you right I mean I would be
trying to convince them I was good at
something so that they will let me in
because the feeling of being surrounded
by people who are all trying to be good
I mean these days I feel the opposite I
feel like I'm surrounded
pretty much entirely other than like the
small group of people who I know I feel
like I'm is surrounded by people who
could couldn't care less like everything
else is more important to them than any
quality right then then excelling then
pushing forward right and being better I
don't I don't feel like it's even on
their radar right and you can see that
manifested everywhere you go when was
the last time you saw a TED talk called
focusing on excellence like how do we
make people want to focus on excellence
I don't know is there one maybe there
was I've never there's hundred of these
things are passed around
no one ever passes that one around if
there was one right when was the last
time you saw a political debate where
they were like you know what the problem
with our country is right now no one
cares about doing things well know where
he found right not not on the table not
interesting when was the last time there
was a like a what's the word I'm looking
for
not not really incident but like
national news focused college campus
incident who knows what where the
primary flashpoint was are we focusing
on excellence are we trying to be
excellent about things when was the last
time that was a huge issue in a public
schooling debate is are we driving all
of our children to try and be excellent
of the things they do right it's like
never everything else is more important
than that
right everything else at least where I
live and probably where you live too is
not about being good we've like somehow
developed a culture where the idea is
about everything other than actually
doing a good job and I think that has
consequences in the long run if there's
ever competition and that's why I say it
creates kind of a pretty
big opportunity and it certainly creates
a big opportunity for adversaries you
know if if larger sort of competing
countries if Russia or China or you know
large industry on industrial bases got
serious about competing with the US
which you know trying to maybe is kind
of in that position to a largest then I
don't think it'd be that hard focus on
excellence in EULA be passed the u.s. in
a few decades
right because no one here cares not even
a little bit and it's never talked about
and there's no money in it and people
there are many many many many many
people all over the place whose primary
goal every day is something opposite or
at least under tangential right so
there's huge amounts of money and effort
and people spending their time trying to
get everyone to focus on things that are
not that and there's nobody like almost
nobody spending their time trying to get
people to focus on that and so what do
you think is gonna happen right
are you describing technocracy um just I
don't know if I'm describing technocracy
I'm just describing a a place where you
Center your cultural values around
excellence
that's all I'm describing right and like
I said if I knew how to do it I try to
get someone to do it right I mean I'd
I'd try to be James Madison 2.0 if I
thought that I was that good but I'm not
I don't know
right what the hell do I know I'm a
software engineer I don't know anything
about how you run a society right
I am simply talking about a symptom
right I'm talking about a symptom of a
problem which is that I'm sorry a
symptom that I can observe and it's a
symptom of something that I don't know
what it is or why it happens or how you
would prevent it right it's similar to
some kind of disease you know you see
that someone has you know hives all over
their body well you know there's hives
right but you don't know how they got
there and so that's kind of you know
what the world looks like to me I can
see that we no longer care about doing a
good job and getting better at things
that's obvious but why right I can point
to a lot of people who make it their
mission in life to distract people from
that but I don't know why they are
either right so I know that that they
are and that they don't care but I don't
know why they don't care right and I can
come up with all sorts of hypotheses but
really I'm just engaging in pop
psychology at that point and who knows
so I think unfortunates left to people
smarter and more more in tune to the way
societies function to to solve that
problem if it ever does get solved
one way to force the idea of excellences
through some form of authoritarianism
but many wouldn't like that well and
authoritarianism is is not really that
helpful because it's just as likely to
go sour right I mean this is why
dictatorships are problematic because
you know maybe you create a dictatorship
and it's great for a little while when
you're running things the way that
dictators running them because they're
really good but they die right and now
someone succeeds them and maybe they're
not so good right and so one of the
problems is that you need more than just
a way of getting people to focus on
excellence for a little while through
coercion or through some kind of a of a
dictatorial or authoritarian regime
that's not stable look maybe you'll
succeed for a little while but you won't
succeed forever and so really what
you're talking about or at least what
what I would see is the the you know the
great sort of achievement if you were
ever able to do it was how do you create
a culture where everyone feels compelled
to drive towards excellence right and I
really don't know how you do that right
I don't know
Oh Julian yet I mean that's that's a
good option right define excellence to
be whatever it's we're doing right now
and then we can kind of go oh right so
yeah I mean yeah I couldn't tell you I
don't know it's interesting to theorize
about but it's just I don't have any
answers right you know we've we've
figured out a lot of things you know if
you look at like capitalism one way of
looking at that is like oh so that was a
way of figuring out how to assign wealth
to people who accomplished something
right and that's really good because it
does drive a lot of things forward to a
certain extent but the problem is it's
still based on the wealth right so what
you end up happening what you end up
seeing happened with systems that are
like you know using capitalism is once
you have a way of generating the wealth
you no longer care about the excellence
right and that's where you end up with
having to have antitrust law and all
these sorts of things because once you
have you know monopoly you can just
extract the wealth you can bundle things
together and then some things can be
good and something's bad and now you
don't have to worry you know bla bla bla
if there's a glut or a Gold Rush
situation then there's no need for
excellence at all so you know we found
some tricks and and capitalism was a
really good one right
like I think capitalism was a great idea
as brilliant right the question is how
to get better than that and you know you
see a lot of time nowadays people saying
like socialism is good idea or something
it's like okay come on like we need to
be coming up with something better than
what we've had right like know like
figure out what's the thing after
capitalism figure it out it's not
socialism that was the thing we had
before right what's next you know give
me give me the next version there's got
to be a better way of making it so that
people
are constantly motivated to be good
right and I know there's a way to do it
right it can't be that capitalism was
the best answer we had there has to be a
better one right and you know like I
said it's not my herb SP so I don't know
what it is but it can't be it can't be
that after only ten thousand years and I
know how long we've been screwing with
this stuff it can't be that we hit the
maximum there's got to be a way to get
past it right to a place where people
are driven more towards excellence and
also driven towards excellence like one
of the really big problems that I see
with like capitalism for example is it
also doesn't have a way to account for
the problem of driving towards
excellence locally as opposed to
laterally so for example if you have
someone who is a who is the best janitor
in the world they are not making very
much money right and this creates a
problem because what it means is anyone
who's good enough to be the greatest
trainer in the world probably could have
gone and done something else and they
will because they'll get paid more right
and so you end up with this problem of
your current the industries that are
currently able to extract the most money
out of the economy those get all the
good people and everything else you have
to do it just because you love it or
something right and there's constant
pressure to not do it to do something
else because you would have gotten paid
better right and so there's also like
that kind of cross that lateral
allocation from that capitalism stock
suffers for that pretty much guarantees
that anybody who works in certain
sectors even if they are excellent at
their job either doesn't feel good about
it cuz society doesn't value them or has
no incentive to excel even if they could
have right and so there's a lot of
problems there too and that was never
really addressed with capitalism now
that's there's some good aspects of that
in capital because it means that in
theory it allocates your quote unquote
best
people to the most important place maybe
but come on now right like it has a
pretty high cost for doing that you know
what I'm saying and you end up with
ridiculous stuff like 3,000 people
working on the back end for like Twitter
or something getting huge amounts of
money when really that could have been
done by 20 people and what are we
burning all this money for we could have
paid all the janitors a lot of money and
gotten really awesome janitors
really awesome janitor right so there's
a problem with the societal value of
things and so when I think about
excellence I'm thinking everybody in
every position should be driven to be
excellent at what they do and we
definitely haven't developed a system
that makes that work we place a much
higher premium on which job you're doing
than how well you're doing it a super
crappy doctor makes way more money than
the world's best janitor and to me
that's not right to me that yields a
worse world outcome than what I would
have preferred right and so again like
and and you know obviously like
everything faction in this I it's not
just recognized system it's your
religion
it's your schooling like everything
plays a part in reinforcing the culture
of excellence we don't have it I don't
know why I don't know how to fix it it's
just sad that's all you know it's
nobody's fault just we haven't come up
with a better system
and yeah like I said capitalism versus
social number things like that they're
their small arguments they're arguments
of us eNOS if you have a small outlook
on the world it's you saying there's
nothing better than what has already
been tried right and and I don't
fundamentally believe that like I
believe we can do better than capitalism
and socialism and a combination of the
two
like I think we have to I think we can
do better than what we're doing but of
course that's my nature like right like
seeing that things are probably not as
good because you know if they were if if
they were actually optimal we would have
been living with them for hundreds of
thousands of years not not thousands
right all right I'm gonna this has been
a very long and ridiculously
philosophical stream where you know
what's the point is what I say right
like I mean I don't have any answer so I
just not sure what the point is of
talking about it it's outside my field
of expertise and I don't have anything
to suggest other than to tell you that
I'm depressed about it and I'm not sure
what good it does to let everyone know
that I'm depressed about it right unless
you all want to be depressed - all right
thank you everyone for joining me for
that sort of handmade here out so a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to pre-order the game on
handmade hair org I should say if you
would like to follow the source code you
can pare the game of hand here at org
and it comes with source code so you can
follow with it on your machine I don't
have any answer as to how you make the
world try to strive for bigger and
better accomplishments but I do have a
way for you to get the source code and
and that is it and then hey you can take
my source code and strive for bigger and
better accomplishments there is not a
single piece of handmade hero that I
don't think could be done better than
we're doing it right now and so have at
it man there is always something to
improve and pretty much everything
except the few very small very specific
pieces of things and so you know maybe
you can get a little bit of a drive to
excellence going find something in
handmade hero that currently sucks and
make it good I guarantee you there's
tons of parts you can do that with
you mentioned them all the time so you
know give it a shot
I'll be back here probably next week I
haven't put schedule yet oh wait no
that's not true I'll probably off next
week so I'll probably be back here in
two weeks when we will try to take the
ray-tracing core and start implementing
that across light probes which will then
distribute out to our lighting voxel and
I think that's kind of the last step in
the process before we're into tuning
mode really excited about that and
hopefully we can come up with good ways
of mapping those things so we can yeah
so we can have some really really really
good lighting which you know again I
want plugin to be excellent because I
want everything excellent if I can hope
see you back here for that in about two
weeks sorry I won't be here next week
I'm gonna be away for the weekend so I
can't stream but until then have fun
pouring everyone I'll see you on the
Internet trying to be as depressed as I
am about state of the world that's all I
got for you take it easy everybody