hello everyone.welcome handmade here a
show we could complete gave live on
stream I am just gonna pick up exactly
where we left off yesterday there's
really nothing particularly specific for
us to be doing today other than just
trying to get the bugs out of the new
ray caster and we made some nice little
visualizations so we kind of knew even
at the end of yesterday's stream we had
worked it out to a particular place we
are we got rid of some bugs yesterday
that we're in there as well so we kind
of already removed some but in terms of
debugging the ray caster you can see we
ended up at a place where you can
actually visualize the Ray and the bug
that I wanted to start looking at
yesterday when we stopped was the fact
that you can see these purple squares
are here right mm-hmm and these I should
say cubes these purple cubes are things
that as opposed to cyan keebz down here
may I should say magenta let's say
magenta because that's what it
technically is so these cyan cubes down
here and these magenta cubes up here you
know as soon as we pass through the
structure of the land where there
actually is something for the Ray to hit
we go from a cyan cube to a magenta cube
and even though really the main thing
that we have to focus on is why this ray
didn't hit right here because that's
where it should have hit right this ray
is marked is not hitting anything but it
should have hit whatever is right there
the weird part about this is the color
coding that I put in the algorithm for
drawing these for debug purposes is that
if there was something in the region
classified as an occluder for Ray's to
hit it was scientist magenta and if not
it was cyan so all of these are
classified as having something in them
to hit and you know while these might be
true this is definitely not true and
honestly I don't think these true should
be true either because you kind of see
in here we have not added trees to our
occlusion
currently I mean we probably should
eventually but right now we don't we
only add like these actual like square
blocks like these things are the only
things we actually bother to push down
as occluders and so when you look at
what's going on in here it's like none
of these should be like just that one
like there's just that one should be
magenta and none of these should be so
there's two possibilities one is that
our loop is just mistaken about what has
Cooter's in it and we could go check
that pretty easily the other is possibly
more likely although still a little
weird is that just our spatial index
build is wrong and it's actually
inserting things into these cubes saying
you know hey there's occluders in here
and there aren't now why inserting
occluders in here when there aren't
would cause you to miss rather than hit
I have no idea but if there's something
generically wrong with our spatial
partition build and the things we're
adding our garbage rectangles that like
are not in the right places or something
then that obviously would be a good way
to imagine this algorithm failing so you
know there's probably something there
either way and we need this
visualization to be correct because if
it's not correct we know that we've got
at least something wrong even if it's
only the visualization code and we would
want that fix as well so let's start by
just looking at what the problem is here
if we go into the debug code that
actually draws this you can see here is
where we draw the Ray and this is why we
know that we aren't hitting anything as
well even though we know we're not
because we looked in the code never hits
anything but you can see that we're
drawing a dim line a bright yellow line
would go to the intersection point and
then a dim yellow line would continue on
just we can see where the Ray will go so
we know that we're not hitting anything
and then up here this is where we're
pushing you can see the box color we say
if nodes start index equals node one
past last index that obviously means you
would never enter this loop because if
the node start index in the node one
past last index are the same you just
you'd never have this less than can
you'd never be in the loop it's a top
checked loop as for loops are so what we
want to see here is we want to see why
is this one past lassen co-starring why
is that triggering only for those things
below the level and when I look at this
code you know it's checking every time
and it's checking the node that it pulls
out here it just doesn't seem likely
that this code is broken I mean it could
be that I'm missing something when I'm
looking at it here and you know I'm just
not thinking about it right or something
but it just look likely right it doesn't
look likely so there's a couple of
things that I would like to do here one
of them is I would like to just draw
these out right so as we hit leaves that
actually have things in them I'm gonna
draw with the boxes are that we think
are in there that's because I want that
anyway but this will also let me see
what the heck these boxes are that you
know people like this thing is claiming
or in there and there's some stuff we
can do for that actually to help us
understand where these boxes are that we
can actually use as well so there's some
stuff we can do to improve this but the
first thing I do is just let's loop
through these in a separate pass only
for debugging where I draw what are the
things that are supposedly
in these grid cells that were closed I
see ants and then we're gonna do is
we'll shift with that information that
will then be able to see hopefully
something will give us some refreshment
but either way we'll shift over to the
the actual spatial partition build to
see if we've got something stupid going
on it would probably do so what we want
to do is this exact same thing we want
to do this push debug box here but what
we want to do is we want to draw the
actual leaves and what you could see is
these leaves come through as four wide
so because they're packed for sim deep
so we've got a three by four X for the
min and a three by four X for the max
again this is debug code we don't care
about how fast it runs so we're just
gonna pull those out individually and
we're just going to draw them one at a
time as debug boxes so this is like an
occluder box here and we're gonna
generate these by looping
the element index one at a time and
we're just gonna draw all four right now
not all four will actually be there
because some of these will just be
garbage like one of the things we do
when we pack these things by fours is
there aren't always four some boxes when
we have one two three right some cells
when we have one two or three and in
those cases the other values are just
filled with nothing right they don't
have anything in them and so what we
should be able to do here is we should
be able to just kind of get that
occluders out for the ones that are
there and the ones that aren't there
well we just draw garbage now we could
put an if around it but we shouldn't
need to it'll just draw like a it'll
draw a box off in the middle of nowhere
I believe and you know if it's causing
us problems we can put in if around it
because we can put into those boxes
specific values that we know won't cause
collision detection but then we can
actually take those and detect them here
so again not really concerned about that
but so what we want to do is do a rectum
and max here so we want to produce one
of our wrecks for the occluder box and
the occluder box is just going to come
from the boxman boxman we already pulled
out but we need to get specific elements
from them so what I wanted to do is get
the element
sorry component I think is what we call
it I don't know why they called it that
so we're gonna get the component of
these that corresponds to this
particular index and that's really all
we should have to do at that point we
can construct a box and pass it on
and do anything else that we want to do
with it so if I run it now I should see
something on the screen and maybe we'll
see nothing because the values are just
garbage but you know the idea would be
if we now looked we should see some
boxes of course I don't which is kind of
bizarre right I see nothing in here so
again kind of bizarre and maybe a good
thing to do now would be to step into
that code and see what those values are
look maybe those values are just
complete crap in there and then there's
like nothing that that you know that
makes any sense and that may be the case
we'll see so so that's at least
something now I can sort of see like
alright
you know something is weird going on
here and and who knows yeah and so I
don't really know when that would be the
case so again that helps us out here
because it's just adding to the number
of things that we know we're wrong in
here and we would expect to see some
boxes in here I might draw this as a
different color just so it's more
obvious like let me just draw a white
box here so that I can at least see
what's going on with with these if
there's anything if I see any white
boxes at all you know and I don't
I could also since they will occupy
exactly the same space as like you know
this cube I could also enlarge them
slightly or right like I could also just
to be doubly sure that I'm not missing
if I don't think I am I could add a
little bit here to the box just so we
can see it easier meaning I could say
look let's add sort of an enlargement
maybe to this to this box just to make
it a little bit larger so that if the
problem was it was just entirely inside
the drawn region which I don't think it
was but let's say that it might be just
as we can see it yeah and we and we
don't write like we would see it by now
if it was there so I'm pretty sure it's
just not there's not valid data in there
so I'm gonna go ahead and switch over to
probably debug build and I'll just loop
through that code and see why we're not
seeing anything because looking at the
values there will also give me some
insight into maybe what's going on wrong
in the grid build code which is exactly
the code that we need to be debugging
next so if I switch over to the lighting
code now so over in here so if I switch
over to the lighting code now and I just
jump to this part where we push it on I
can just in theory stop on the first one
and look what the values are
okay so did I do something wrong with
this code
I'm so confused so in here we know that
we're drawing at least I thought we did
we know that we're drawing in debug mode
it's really hard for me to use that
particular code path because the game
runs so slow when the lighting is put in
debug mode because it's you know not
being optimized by the compiler at all
[Music]
but let me yeah I mean so we're drawing
these in magenta right which means that
the nodes start index equals the one
past last index I'm sorry doesn't equal
which means this loop has to have
occurred I mean doesn't that piece of
code require this oh no it doesn't if
one past last index was simply less than
start index that would explain it
let's take a look shall we well there
you go so no big mystery there I thought
our code in the spatial partition build
correctly adjusted those values but
guess what it obviously doesn't because
we just watched it not so what you can
see here is in this piece of code well
there you go so yeah one of the things
that I know that a lot of people watch
John stream for I don't know if John's
here today he's probably not I haven't
seen any naysayer 88 comments but one of
the things that John often tells people
is how to succeed in the game industry I
know a lot of people want to know how to
succeed in the game industry if you want
to succeed in the game industry the
important thing to do is to make sure
that you update one pass last index
before start index so if anyone's
watching his stream at the same time
right now some says he's live you can
jump over there and tell him that one of
the one of the additional things that he
may not have mentioned yet and I'm sure
he already knows but he just may not
have mentioned it as for how to succeed
in the game industry is just make sure
you always update one pass last index
before you update start index that's
that's really how to succeed in the game
industry ok so now we should hopefully
see some kind of improvement there in
terms of at least drawing some of this
stuff but more importantly we should get
to the actual piece of code I would
think although you know apparently
that's not true right because I'm not
seeing anything so let me see what
happens here if I actually jump through
to something where that code is is
executing did I still screw it up
no I mm I don't think I did there so
that kind of looks like that means we
never had any one past lasts index so
what you can see here is that if you add
one past last index to the start index
and you know and to be honest there's
another way to Steve in the game
industry so one way is to do it this way
another way did would be to do it this
way so those are two ways to see in the
game industry one is you can update
start index first but then you have to
add it outside the divide right
another way to secede in the game
industry is to just do one past last
index first but what's interesting here
is what we're seeing is that this count
so that the you know the count for here
that actual value is coming out to zero
apparently everywhere in the entire grid
or at least everywhere that we were
looking which is not good
so this count for value here where we
have one pass last index we're rounding
it right so all this is doing is doing a
divide with a round if we add almost the
entire amount minus one and then divide
then truncation will basically become
rounding up and the reason we're always
wanting to round up is because even if
we didn't fill all of an entire bucket
of four recently to process that bucket
even if we filled only one of the bucket
before we still need to that's why we
plus three there right so we're just
trying to round up to the next highest
four count so for some reason our count
four always comes out to zero I guess
which means that if you look at what's
happening inside this piece of code when
we are actually doing these loops
somehow we're never getting any actual
counts in here which is weird and I
guess the rete well you know it's not
that weird because if we set it to zero
here to start to count and then you look
at the code in here which actually does
it it would have to increment it so
there we go
so again really pretty easy bugs to find
once we had the visualization right
because we knew immediately like what
was wrong so finding the bugs just
becomes pretty straightforward okay so
now we're in this code and we're
actually seeing something that has a
occluder in it just what we would expect
let's take a look at what the actual
values are for our occluder box just to
see if they're sensible right because I
don't you know I don't know so nothing
really weird about that that's a totally
plausible occluder box so that's good
you know I just want to make sure there
wasn't you know garbage in there which
there would have been because we're
putting these in strided so we could
have easily mixed up our shuffle when we
went from non sse2 sse3 so we can
probably switch back to release mode now
and do a little bit more checking of
what's going on but okay so already you
can pretty much see we've improved the
performance not performance that the
correctness of the code quite a bit
because now you can see we're actually
getting sensible termination right it's
terminating at the thing it actually hit
okay let's keep going a little bit more
now with the visualization side just so
we can start to see what this codes
actually doing and try to improve the
debugging of it further so here's me
running the actual code now again and
one of the things you can see is now
that we've hit something we're not
actually drawing
Raye and we we're gonna need to fix that
because obviously we just in our debug
code we're doing something stupid there
so we need to fix that what you can see
here is if you look at the white regions
because they're inflated by probably a
little bit too much it's a little bit
hard to see that's probably just a
little sliver that's on the edge of the
cube there and so I should probably go
ahead and reduce the grow amount there
let's let's see
[Music]
okay so when we draw on in here I'm
gonna say like let's maybe limit the
occluder box add radius there we'll get
rid of that temporarily let's take a
look at where we do the drawing so where
do we do that we do that in here for our
push debug line probe sample piece
single so it kind of looks like maybe
that's buggy maybe so like when we were
terminating on a cost metric which was
here the code was working when we're
terminating on an on cost metric which
is here the code was busted it's what it
looks like anyway so the production of
probe sample P by doing Rea origin plus
T ray ray D appears to be bogus or the
extraction is bogus I assume because we
know this code was working when we had
probe sample piece single just being the
terminate position right no we don't I
mean this could have been wrong on both
sides I suppose so I'm not really
willing to say that yet let's start with
something else so push debug line
solution probe sample P single to Ray
origin single the only way this code
fails is if this is wrong right because
if I come in here and say look start
from the actual origin of the Ray right
and draw it from there I'm assuming we
still see it right yeah so that's
this piece of code this piece of code is
just busted right since we know ray
origin singles at the right place
because I just looked right I mean this
wouldn't be starting at the right place
if Ray Origin single is wrong that's
exactly where we would expect it to be
then probe sample P singles the only
thing that can really be wrong you know
I'm saying
so what's going on there how are we
writing probe sample piece single and
why is it seemed to be busted by default
it'll just be a tray origin single so I
think if we fall through here without
ever updating anything for some reason
which I guess would happen if we hit the
outside so if we hit the exterior which
would be the spatial grid node
Terminator if that's what we hit then in
that case it would be fine because it
would just run nothing right it would
just yeah it would never be updated at
all but in all our cases we'll update it
and we should draw something so the
question is what's that value and why is
it busted since we have a convenient way
to break on debug I guess we can just
switch right immediately back to the
debug build and see what are the values
right so if we go here no that's
erroneous if we go here I should be able
to see what probe be single is so we can
find out what the heck like what value
even is it
so it looks like the problem are getting
here because these are all massive like
infinity style numbers they're not
actually in but they're you know
approaching and that looks like what
happened is the T value is was not
actually updated right so - like the
actual value that we picked for T is is
just erroneous and so when we look in
here like we probably came through the T
something hit path right and what we
probably saw when we because you know
the way this would be updated is we do
the P chef on the T array to get one out
here we must have been getting the wrong
one so taking a look at that
let's just see what tier a ended up
getting evaluated - you know who knows
okay so you can see here like T ray is
just kind of garbagey right it's set to
the flute maxes that it would have been
set to if we'd never hit anything so
even though I believe we did hit
something meaning something hit
apparently was actually occurring
somehow the mask value didn't correctly
update or well know you know the it's
probably the pea chef B so it probably
happened was the pea chef be like
shuffled something into place it was
erroneous right that's probably what
happened and how were we doing that so
we've got our shuffle table
and the shuffle tables gonna pick the
shuffle table is gonna pick whatever the
men pose thought it should be so this
code which was really kind of
seat-of-the-pants here it may be time to
start looking into that so what I kind
of need here is I need a debug trap that
will occur at the precise time I want to
actually debug that so I'm going to
augment that code with something
unnecessary so that I can do my debug
trap so in something hit I want to
actually stop specifically on the one
we're debugging just so I'm familiar
with what the REA is and what should
probably happen to it and in here I'm
just gonna do like a in break now equals
true don't actually care what that line
says I know in debug mode it won't get
optimized out and I'm just gonna run to
that line so when we jump down here and
we stuff okay didn't mean to have that
breakpoint still in there and that
wasn't there okay so here in break now
I'm gonna take a look at what happens
with the shuffling so the first thing we
do here is we do we do a pfb which for
some reason I don't know why mm shuffle
epi8 up here didn't turn into a pea chef
B because we made the macro to do this
I'll have to look and see why we're not
just calling PFP but so we're doing a
pea chef B here which for some reason is
called mm shuffle epi8 in the word
intrinsic world but it's a pea chef pea
the pfb is designed to take the
horizontal comparison so min posi PU 16
we're trying to use that to compare
floats which technically doesn't compare
floats but basically what we're saying
is we don't care about the bottom 16
bits of the mantissa
we just want whichever one is roughly
the lowest otherwise I don't really know
I've said this before I don't really
know that that's what we want to do it's
overly clever in fact we've got a to do
here right that's an example of me
saying look this may not be such a great
idea right but who knows we'll see
anyway what we're doing is we're taking
four floats and we're taking the high 16
bits of each float and putting it down
into the place where we would compare
them first so 2 3 that's the high of the
first float 6 7 high the second 10 11
high of the 3rd 14 15 high of the 4th
right make sense we pad the end with
just the first one and that way we know
that it can't compare favorably against
the first one because we don't want any
values higher than 4 right okay so if we
then look at what happens here so if we
take T ray P for starters and what I'll
do is we'll just take a look at what the
M 128 F 32 components are so here's what
they are we've got two bounding box hits
right and two bounding box misses like
so now it's a little bit weird because I
don't know why there are two it would
have only seemed to probably be hitting
only one and you know before I go any
further down that path I would like to
just see why that is
I'm curious if that's like wrong I'm
thinking it it probably is wrong but I
don't really know so let me just take a
look at what's going on where does this
Rea actually enter okay
and I guess I can't quite see here but
I mean it just doesn't seem plausible
right when you come through here you're
gonna hit this one and that's all you're
gonna hit right I mean you're not gonna
hit anything else so it feels a little
erroneous so I think I think we may have
a hit bug as well up here
and I'm not sure where that bug would
come from because this looks pretty good
I don't know if we screwed up the
algorithm somehow when we were modifying
it but like it doesn't look bogus you
know you can see right like here we are
checking the bounds to make sure the
team in is less than the team acts and
the team in also has to be greater than
0 which means that max Pass right we
don't care about that was for testing
inside miss which we don't care if
you're inside because the Ray Origin
just if the Ray origin was inside we
don't care about that hit so we only
care about these other hits and if you
look here you can see that you know the
the team acts and team in we've we've
gone through these and we've we've
picked the lowest I I just I just don't
know I I just don't know that doesn't
seem like it should have produced two
hits there so so one thing we'll have to
look at is just do we actually really
believe that we did those two that those
were two real hits or is this algorithm
producing erroneous results because of
something that I'm missing and that's
gonna be something we're gonna have to
to study a little bit more carefully so
let's just keep that in the back of our
heads remind me if I forget because on
streams sometimes it's hard for me to
remember all the things because my brain
is too busy like talking to you but just
keep that in mind so because I don't
base on that like limited amount of
expection that I and don't feel
comfortable that it don't think we can
write that off so I'm gonna go in here
and set a breakpoint on the break now
line and then I'm gonna look at what
happens with this shuffle so here we go
what we should be getting out of shuffle
is to write is what we should be getting
out of our arm in paws so let's just
take a look at what happens to the h
comp I'm gonna look so
in the h comp value i want to look
specifically at the u16 counters because
that's what we're actually putting into
these some I'm just gonna look at what
these are
oops it's M 128 u 16 right isn't it no
sorry it's 128 I know so when we do this
shuffle we should see these values
change here they are and what you can
see is we get these two values which are
the two which correspond to these two T
values and what you could see is they
properly correspond exactly the way that
I said that they would right so although
we're just taking the high slice of the
float we know that that includes the
sign bit in the exponent and then the
first few bits of the mantissa right so
it's like sign bit exponent in 8 bits
mantissa roughly when we do this
comparison we would then expect to find
that whatever the highest of these or
whatever the lowest of this is is though
is the closest hit unless we had two
that had the same exponent and the same
first eight bits of the mantissa right
so again this is just stupid float
tricks 101 there is no way to extract
the specific float in SSE four that I
know of if you can't check for floats
for which one's lowest that's not a
thing you can do you'd have to actually
do your own shuffle horizontal compare
basically which would take forever so
this is just two instructions to do
something that would normally take you
like six or something right so that's
all we're doing here anyway
when we then produce the midden test
value we're gonna see if this actually
correctly
bingos the float that we were actually
looking for and so if I take a look in
here at the U sixteens
that come out of this no oh I must have
caps lock on I can't see here we go
sometimes accidentally hit the caps lock
key kind of wish I could just turn that
off I just never bother to do the like
NT registry hack trick I like those
keyboards where you can just disable it
on the keyboard so it's good
so we're gonna run min pause on this and
what we would expect to find here is
that min pause should give us back first
of all what the minimum value was and
that'll go in slot zero and then what
index it was in and that'll go in slot
one right so there we go
and that answer is correct so two is the
correct answer right and so you can see
that was just me playing it fast and
loose with floats there but but it seems
to work right yeah yeah it seems like
it's the right thing so so far that
algorithm looks like it worked
shuffle index should now be two unless I
messed up the extract and I guess I did
oh my goodness
okay so extract epi16 is taking the 60
minutes so that should be one all right
if that's the only thing that we screwed
up in writing that algorithm I am pretty
happy with that cuz that was a pretty
crazy maneuver right all right so if we
jump over he or poops I should actually
continue breaking that I keep forgetting
that I only want to use this one place
right we should see that shuffle index
should now actually produce we should
should get the correct value out of this
now so let's take a look at min test
there it is and now the two is coming
out properly all right one more time
just one make sure I step through it
right because I was kind of not paying
attention there yeah so now when we pull
out the shuffle table shuffler we should
get the correct thing let's see if that
actually happens so now we should see is
this should be a broadcast this P
shuffle should basically be this P chef
should be a broadcast of lane two to all
lanes so all the lanes should become
1111 anyone anyone out there a rufus
wainwright fan come on chat rufus
wainwright anybody
anybody know seriously all right fine
well it's 11:11 and if you know rufus
wainwright then you would know that
11:11 is a song anyway so there's the
broadcast and there is that that worked
away we want so now our probe sample P
should hopefully be the correct value
because the TRA will now no longer be
garbage I don't really know much about
the normal part here we haven't really
looked at that and we're probably gonna
have to debug that code as well what we
can do here is if we want to we can
start to look at what those values
actually are but you know doesn't really
actually matter in this particular case
because we're not at that point of
debugging so I'm gonna go ahead and say
let's take a look at the diagram again
oh dear no no I don't know what that was
about
I hit something maybe that I probably
told remedy to let the program run which
then because there's a breakpoint in it
caused it to crash in Windows which
caused it to do the report I'm guessing
something like that happened don't hit
that key okay so now if we continue
running here and we take a look at what
we're what we're looking at if I look at
the raycast I can now see that hey I'm
getting getting correct result to a
certain extent right you can see that
I'm actually hitting right there which
is what I expect
I'd like to augment here just to get a
little bit better understanding of where
or the Ray is actually hitting so what I
might do here is draw this considerably
more muted and actually push a debug box
on here where I can just say rec center
dim something like that and I'll just
draw like
a small box that's just at the point
where we actually hit so this will just
give me like a little tiny like probe
point that shows like here's where we
think the Ray intersected the geometry
and so now the Ray cancer appears to be
finding the correct location like right
there it is it's hitting that cell and
you know I don't really know that
there's much else we need to prove about
it other than that seems somewhat
debugged now right I mean then actually
no certainly there could be lots of
other problems but you know it's it's a
it's closed right and so we're getting
somewhere
hopefully and we'll see now I need to
check the normal because I don't know if
that's coming out correct at all so
we're gonna have to take a look at that
and so before I go any further down the
road towards trying to make this work
well I'm just going to go ahead and see
whether or not there's yeah any
weirdness there another thing I would
say is it feels like this is the
transmission distance is too far I feel
like this value is not good like we're
allowing this thing to walk too far or
something I feel like these are opposite
you know what I mean like I feel like I
feel like this actually wants to be more
like that and this actually wants to be
more like this
because I don't think we should go very
far if we're not seeing any geometry
like we shouldn't go super far in that
case right I feel like these rays should
terminate earlier so like this is more
like what I would expect and maybe
that's a little aggressive but I feel
like we should probably stopping before
we ever get to some of these so you know
I'm gonna flip those two at least for
now because I don't think we should be
shooting quite so far as we are just
wasting time and like you know that's
plenty of grid squares to check in my
opinion for any given array we don't
need the light to propagate that far in
a single frame and you know so it
doesn't really make a whole lot of sense
um so you know looking at the
performance of this I wouldn't say that
it's particularly good yet so you know I
don't know how much of an improvement
we're actually gonna end up getting out
of the routine or not but again like
limiting those values should make a
difference meaning in theory like we can
play with the cosmetic to get some
savings there I mean I don't actually
know if we will or won't but like even
that you can kind of see it something's
a little weird about this because that
should have saved a lot of time and
doesn't really seem like it did which is
odd also not sure why that oh you know
what those tables for some reason don't
compute right on reboot I think we're
gonna have to do a thing where we forced
it to recompute the tables but it's
weird like you would expect this number
to go down more than it does which means
we may have some overhead stuff that we
need to you know clean up at this point
and I guess we'll find out as we go so
anyway I do think we want to play with
that stuff a little bit I'm gonna leave
it in for now because I want to just use
this to buggin case but I do think we
kind of want the cost metrics to be
adjusted what I'm going to do now is I'm
going to put a debug line on here that
shows the normal so I'm gonna do
a like a line coming out that shows what
we think the normal was so you know kind
of maybe a bright orange line there that
goes from the probe sample piece single
along the normal so it's probe sample
end single at that point and we probably
need to go maybe just one unit I mean
that's plenty long enough for us to see
the direction of the thing is going I
would think and I guess we'll find out
now so that's the correct normal for
this particular hit it doesn't really
tell us much about other hits we
probably need to start letting this roam
more and one thing I could do
potentially is to have some way of
changing what the debug value is so if I
go to grid raycast here
I don't know where I don't know hmm
so I don't know exactly what the best
way to do this would be I mean I kind of
want to be able to inspect arbitrary
ones of these Ray casts and I'm not sure
honestly really not actually sure how I
should do that I guess like you know it
would be nice it was just tied to like a
value so I wonder if I could just do
something like yeah there's like some
kind of like a value in here that I'll
just like edit in the debug settings or
something debug grid index I don't know
so let's just suppose that we happen to
have a debugger in index here or
something and that there was like a
debug value for this thing and then like
maybe we just have like a lighting
output of that of that value like this
is just me just making up something
because I just want to be able to like I
just want to dial in a particular value
right I mean that's all I really wanted
to do so you know I don't know if I can
do what I'm doing here but I'm gonna try
right so just say look here's a lighting
data and I want this to show up in the
lighting data and I just want it to be
something you can edit I don't know if
you can edit it I don't remember
anything about our debug system other
than it was kind of crappy but you know
I think we had the lighting in here
somewhere
yeah and so if you look at the
a lighting data here there's a it did
work I mean there's a debug grid index I
just don't know how you get this to be
editable right it looks like we I want
to say we did allow something like that
though
so like debug b32 allows you to edit a
write debug UI element I don't know how
this thing worked
it was pretty dumb um so like I have no
idea what most of these things are I
definitely don't know why this is
editable and this is not although I
would suspect it's probably has
something to do with this meaning we
probably just implemented editing for be
that did we I don't know let's take a
look so
those have nothing to thudding those do
okay so our thirty twos had a drag value
interaction but but integers didn't I
guess that was it so we finally just
make a drag value interaction for these
then I guess it would just work I mean
right which means what
like debug type u16 I mean I guess I
could use just you thirty-two because
that's probably more what I'll typically
want and we'll just make the thing our
thing in you thirty-two
I don't think I want that to be why I
think I would rather it be X maybe I'm
totally just making this up here I also
don't know if D Mouse pee I don't know
what this is going to do
so I don't really know what this is
gonna do probably nothing good and this
probably wouldn't work I mean you don't
really want to do it this way because
you want to sort of have a you want a
smoother interaction than that but oh
well
argh okay so in the actual oh you know
what I should have done actually um you
know why am I doing this there was
really no reason I had to do this this
was dumb don't do that just make the
debug value in here be I'll just make
this value be a float because then I can
have smooth dragging as well and yeah
and that's right that's the smartest
thing to do and then what we can do here
is just say look round it there that way
you can have smooth dragging and it'll
work alright so now if I take a look at
what happens I think in theory I should
be able to move this value you know why
that's so you know why that's so finicky
they're like see how kind of jitters
it's probably just again the debug
system being crappy but at least now we
can sort of move it around right like I
can sort of and I also because these are
where they are I feel like X would be a
way better drag than Y right I feel like
that would be better
I don't know why it like shakes between
those two probably just again crappy
debug code or something it doesn't
really matter it's it's the debug crap
which can stay crappy yeah it's really
weird how that behaves but so that's
pretty easy for us to change and at
least we can see that from underside
hits it tends to be about the same we
probably need some way of like entering
values in here at some point because
these will be really hard for us to to
get larger because they're going to be
quite large the number of grid squares
is some kind of way too large right but
um that's alright
so in here let's say I just do like I
don't know 10 times that although
actually let's do five times that
okay so now I'm not sure where we are in
the grid but I'm just gonna try and see
if I can fit there we go
so it looks like that's still too far
though like I don't want to be quite so
high so let's do two times that
well maybe three times that let's say I
want to be in the actual environment you
know with my tests I'm just gonna just
kind of try to find a way to to get
there I'm not seeing that
there it is okay so that's hmm
I can't quite tell where is that
actually casting from its casting from
this square looks like so that's
actually good that's in the environment
that's what I want so I'm going to move
this Square to like here maybe inside a
little bit there we go okay so let's try
maybe one up from here would be a good
casting location cuz you know looking at
this it's like it's like not clear also
this that seems to be going backwards I
think there's a lot of bugs we can get
out of picking a good spot here 14 889
I'm gonna just record that grid index in
here just as a note but then I think
what I want to do is take 14 889 as a
debug index here and then I want to add
to it the actual what I want to move
that one sheet up so I don't remember it
should be 24 by 16 I want to say is how
big the voxel is so that should give me
basically that same location but like
one up right okay and then if I run this
and we look I was hoping I would get
well so I guess I screwed up that
stepping is that oh but it's actually 24
by 17 right because it's one la ropa
sorry 26 times 18
it's actually
one larger around the whole border so
the sheets are yeah it'd be 26 by 18 per
sheet wouldn't it as I say as it totally
obviously isn't did we do different
stuff
oh we yeah I keep forgetting the spatial
partition is totally different than the
voxel it's not the same because we we're
a cast against larger areas than we do
so I don't remember what this is let's
just do it so if we actually take the
grid itself so the solution spatial grid
because I don't remember what the values
are and we just do x times y what is it
cell count that should actually work
okay
all right sorry about that yeah I could
not remember like the stuff we decide
about the spatial grid was pretty key
all right so now we're in the right
location that's the cast I wanted it's
casting off to the top which obvious
doesn't help and that's fine because now
we can move on to the next thing I
wanted to do which is I wanted to have
in the oh I know why this codes
multi-threaded that's why we were
getting the twitch the twitchiness there
that's why that makes sense yeah you
can't really do this here I guess so you
know what I could fix that by just
making this put this in the solution and
output it only at the end so why don't
we do that because hey it was really
annoying to to use that way having many
threads querying what happens there and
overwriting each other so you know what
let's I think that's probably what we
were seeing there so let's just put it
in here debug grid index and debug grey
index
put them there and then we can have this
be solution debug grid index and I'll
move this down to the single threaded
part of the code right
that seems fine okay so let's say this
is debugger in index let's say this is
debug array index these are going to be
off of the solution itself and stored
there and then these will be set
somewhere in the initializer like so and
what we will want to do here is the
debug ray index we kind of had that in
the place we recall so you can see here
when we produced the debug it was like
plus 36 um so let's actually just hard
code that into this spot instead and
then we can round this one solution
debug array index right and we need to
clamp this like we can't let it free
roam for obvious reasons because it will
fetch out of bounds here so what we
really want to do is we want to make
this correspond properly to that I could
put this in here but I'm not gonna so
what am I do instead is I'm just gonna
say all right let's bound it so the
debug ray index is less than zero well
then a equals zero and if the debug ray
index is greater or equal to or I should
say maybe just
greater than the loom than the total
which honestly I don't remember what it
was total light sample Direction counts
I guess would be the thing right so
that'll just keep us in the in the clear
so now if I actually run this there we
go
in theory I should be able to pick a ray
Direction now - right
so if we take a look here we can at
least start to look at some other things
so there's us casting array hitting a
volume it looks properly clipped
there's the bounce back right there and
that's correct as well so that's like
does look kind of correct but odd in a
certain way like having these things
right on the edge is probably not great
like we should probably clip to a
certain dimension because we don't
really care if we have a few holes in
our system so we're probably testing too
many things here but I guess that's
beside the point anyway if I look and
see what's hitting there it really does
look correct you know the problem we're
having now is the lighting is not right
it's doing a weird flood-fill thing
right but at the same time like the
raycast it looks like it's working
properly so that's a little bit
unnerving
so if we see so if we see an
intersection there I'm guessing that's
the light that's right here that we're
hitting but at the same time I should
see it so that seems buggy right like
what is happening that seems just
totally wrong I'm gonna go ahead and say
that our t terminate case is broken this
was clearly a case where we terminated
and we produced a reverse answer so
let's capture this 16 3 17 and 42 and
let's just look at that case
so that was 16 3 17 42 okay so now I
should be able to look at this case and
debug this case because it's pretty
obvious that something's busted
and I think it's the t termini we should
take a look at the compute walk table
code because this code here is actually
producing the T terminate values
and I'm wondering if they're just wrong
somehow let's take a look so here's the
code you can see that the the location
that we cast from was here and we cast
out into this direction we terminated
out here somewhere and somehow recorded
this as the hit but the the hit should
have been like like here right so super
messed up the T terminate value looks
negative and I guess I can see why it's
because we're now shifted properly to
account for going along the cell dim
yeah okay
that totally makes sense so I guess what
we really need here is probably
something more like this we probably
need to set t terminate to zero every
time we take a step we probably add T
best to it I guess
seems sort of saying as a way to do that
let's double check so there you can see
our T terminate stopping properly I
don't know that we really need it to
stop in that way probably could stop in
the middle here so you know there's
there's some of that but at least we got
rid of that that bug right because that
was obviously wrong and now of course we
can see that it's working properly now I
don't really know what I still don't
really know why that drag behavior is
going that way because now I'm not
calling multi-threaded so we don't have
that excuse anymore so yeah looking at
this I mean it just I don't know looks
like a pretty good ray tracer now that's
early outing we should probably draw
when we early out versus when we don't
but like that's like what you would
expect to see pretty much everywhere so
I'm not now sure why we're not getting
good results in terms of the actual
light because it's obviously hitting it
error case pretty quickly and you can
see the whole world floods in an odd way
but everything else you know it looks
fine so actually like the Ray caster
seems pretty good now there may be some
case we're not seeing but that seems
pretty good so does that mean that our
our actual right back is busted right or
you know is there something else that
we're doing stupid I don't know but it
seems like the Ray caster actually is
looking okay now it could mean that you
know if you take a look at this code
here's the old ray caster and you could
see like this was the part that actually
generated the right back to the spec
mask respect texels
that code has been completely changed
here so one thing that could be wrong is
this code because we have no idea we
could have just totally screwed this up
right and so if that's the case looking
at the just looking at this part of the
code and figuring out if we need to
debug this could be part of it this
should be identical unless we're passing
the wrong actual spec Texel this should
be fine
so I think it's mostly this code that
would be suspicious here so we can start
here and we'll just see if we step
through some of this code we'll just see
if we're producing plausible you know
after the like the reflect color foo
comes back does this stuff look at all
right or is it totally busted right I
think that's what we want to do okay and
so again the reason that I'm concerned
about this is because although we
haven't done our light quality pass so
our lighting is still kind of needs to
be looked at in terms of the actual
computations this should actually also
be if lighting use grid there we go so
if we look at what happens if we run the
old ray tracer we are getting like
plausible lighting with the old ray
tracer and we're not getting plausible
lighting with the new ray tracer so like
when we switch to the new ray tracer
like so
we get this sort of gradual brightening
that just ends in Fulbright right it's
very strange
so and like it just looks very odd so it
feels like even though the raycast er
seems like it's properly ray casting at
least to some extent the sampling is
maybe busted or something right because
you know the ray casters are a little
bit different but we wouldn't
necessarily expect that big of a
difference from switching between the
two ray casters we would have expected
similar sorts of results
that's not we're seeing so let's take a
look at the code that actually exits out
when we do have a hit because that's the
part that like at least I would think is
implicated the most in this case it's
especially implicated the most in my
mind because we wouldn't when the old
ray tracer hit nothing the old ray
tracer would have reported mostly sky
light results at that point if it hit
nothing this ray tracer will be should
if anything because it has earlie out in
it should be slower to report sky lights
because sky lights in this case should
only happen once you actually propagate
inward the sky light a little bit so it
should if anything be slower to go full
bright but that's not we're seeing at
all so we yeah we should probably and
you know maybe that's wrong because
maybe what happens is the sky light
propagates into the outer region and
then the diffuse blur adds energy
because like we did it wrong it does
seem like that a fusilar adds too much
energy right now for whatever reason
even though I'm not sure why
so I don't know it could just be
something like that but I think there's
still bugs in that I don't think that
would completely explain it so I'm going
to go ahead and assume that we've got a
bug in here and that we want to go
through this code like with a fine-tooth
comb at some point just so we can kind
of determine what's going on so if I go
to the grid rake astir and look at the
fallout place you know where we go okay
we hit something and we take a look at
what the results are in here as far as
we can tell we're computing the normal
correctly when we then go to extract the
probe singles we drew those and they did
appear right the emission direction in
this case is the opposite direction of
the Ray it appears that we pretty much
always do that so you know that may be
something we want to simplify later we
need the compute fox the reading set to
get a little smarter and add something
on using the emission direction I don't
think but anyway so when we come into
this reflect color of Fukase and we do
this operation we know that these two
values are right because we looked at
them and those are the two visors
actually use so we assume that reflect
our food comes back properly the reflect
fall-off is the inner product between
the sampling normal and the emission
direction so that's how much it should
be sending back at us right and like I
said I think that should probably be
done in here that's why I why I was
being passed in here in the first place
so I don't know that this is wants to be
done here but either way that's okay we
modulate by that which is what we would
expect to see we then do a
we then do a loft of the color of RGB up
to a 4x and we do hit a mission shuffle
to find out the emission level and then
we just like max those two so we we take
whichever is higher the emission or the
reflection seems plausible and then we
just extracts
so I guess what we're doing here is
we're doing a pea chef be on the hit ref
color which would be the modulation
level for reds greens and blues and then
were and then we're just multiplying by
that transmission to get the final
transmission honestly that seems fine
it's a little convoluted again I think
probably what we want to do is get
compute Fox low radiance at just taking
wide values to begin with even though it
can't really do that the rest of the
stuff it should do should probably still
stay in line so you probably want to
look at that a little bit later but you
know it looks fine
transfer PBS in this particular case
what
what's going on here folks this this is
not so I don't this is not shuffled
properly I would wager I'm not feeling
great about this like so if you take a
look at where the speck Texel stuff
happens so what you can see here is the
transfer PPS is getting sliced out as RG
b r g b r g b r g b so we're doing three
wide ads to do four pixels so that makes
sense so you can see that slicing
happening and this is the same code
right we just duplicated this code this
is how it is working in either case but
that means that the transfer PPS has to
be set up such that the transfer PPS
itself is RGB RGB RGB RGB right I don't
know what the heck this is doing but we
have to make sure that it lines up that
way and I'm not sure at the moment that
it actually does so I want to actually
verify that because I'm like huh right
so taking a look at transfer PPS to
begin with the first thing I can tell
you is that if I actually look so
transfer PPS up here is for wide and
we're only writing to one of them I
think when we like looped in this code
we just didn't do this
right so the moonlights getting written
to three channels whether we wanted it
to or not so that's just straight-up
bogus and not good right so at the very
least this would have to look like this
at the very least and at that point if
this actually is doing a full extraction
of what the hit should be for this one
hit then that does seem at least more
plausible that did not help to be at the
risk spammy erroneous but I think that's
what should have been going on there so
now we're writing to all four of the
transfer PBS channels the red the green
the blue the red the green the blue the
red the green the blue right and in this
case here this clamp wouldn't do
anything because this here will always
actually happen right so like this never
happens ever which would be bad and this
is again like we don't have a way of
getting those answers in here I guess we
sort of do in the sense that we can
force that to happen in the in the zero
out case if we wanted to
so we're gonna have to think about that
the other thing I would say is in this
case where we hit the node Terminator it
seems like this code is just broken like
who's gonna set probe piece single at
that point like nobody like nobody right
so when you miss like this has to get
updated so I think we've got some issues
I think this has to happen in a
different way I think what we actually
need is something more like that and
then this code has to be the code that
actually does the early outs so it's
like you know if the cost metric got too
low or the start index then update these
right so they're always correct that
seems like more what you want you know I
mean
and so I think now we're a little closer
to correct so now the question is why
are we getting this full braiding here
almost immediately right like what's
going on there and now I think we can
start to step through this code
investigate what's going on but I'm
pretty sure this is that was just wrong
to begin with and we need to look at
what's going on now that we're actually
creating real transfer PBS values right
yeah okay so let's take a look now what
happens there and I guess I want to
maybe pick a debug a specific debug
location I guess this one's fine because
it's gonna pick a place to sample that
doesn't have anything and that's
probably okay probably mm I don't really
know so I'm not sure what I want to do
for the next events I don't how much
time do I have left I have to - till -
so I would know when we started no one
knows when we started
so I don't know exactly I want to
proceed
and somehow the like speed is really
slow right now as well right like it's
kind of weird like something something
bad happened when I did that and I'm not
really sure what it was but it's like
really unhappy now
oh wow so actually it's not really
unhappy now it's actually quite zippy
but as soon as I turned this on like it
got much slower somehow but not now why
did it get so slow there right it was
very slow but now it's not what happened
there
can anyone see we should go back on the
replay and see it's very strange look
are we leaking some memory or something
do you see how bad that got
weird
what the heck so something is up because
here we are running it honestly like
getting very close to 60 frames second
there right we're 30 pegged for sure but
then all of a sudden we drop into
no-man's land and I don't know why look
if we took out the frame display look at
that look at that
are we having some kind of run-in with
Dean normals d normal should be turned
uh and that I don't know what could
cause that what's the what's the memory
usage let me just see isn't there some
way to get the
we're not leaking that's a stumper
really interesting so I don't have any
idea why that would be occurring my only
guess is somehow it has to do with bogus
numbers I'm totally stumped as to what
would cause such a thing to occur
because I would have thought that bogus
numbers would not be going on at the
moment meaning we would have our d
normal flush to zero and all that sort
of stuff would be gone
that's really bizarre that's really
really bizarre but it's very reliable
right and it seems like it has to do
with with the longer you run the
lighting for like something's happening
right to the values and this is the kind
of thing on the x87 that you would
immediately just go OD normals have hit
and now you're you're screwed but I
wouldn't have expected there it is right
there right I wouldn't have expected
that to be relevant to us so I'm curious
now what what on earth could we be doing
that would create such a thing let's
continue debugging further and see if we
see any signs of what's going on here
well you know what I could do too I can
maybe nerf this let's say that I do some
creative like nerfing here and just
blend in zeros periodically right so
like
um and I'm going to do this just to make
it harder for the optimizer to remove
the rest of this code so this is me sort
of forcing the transfer values to go
away right so now like you can't accrete
add a normal number anymore because I'm
not letting it do that and I'm just
curious if we still get this problem
so looking suspiciously like it does not
happen if you don't allow blending
accretion does that mean we still have d
normal numbers in play no it can't be
can it
I mean that looks rock-solid right
I mean it looks like an unusual number
like a bad numbers problem if you don't
allow it to accrete you don't seem to
have that problem and I don't know how
else you can have that occur so if we
don't do that right and I do the same
thing
well now now we're not seeing it again
oh oh there you go BAM it just hit right
so let's prove to ourselves that this is
a bad numbers problem here so I'm gonna
propose we do it in the case where we
actually hit our debug I'm gonna go
ahead and dump that cells values and so
I'm going to go like this I'm going to
come out here and I'm gonna actually
like see what there's what our values
are trending towards so I know that I
have just only one cell so it should be
fairly free for me to just like if we're
doing the 1d bug case out of this one
cell I should be able to go ahead and do
a debug block here where I just output
like what the values actually are right
that should be pretty straightforward
oops it's not what I meant to so in here
like I should be able to say like debug
this value where the value is like
whatever the spec Texel value is so like
if we look at spec Texel dot value in
this case i should be able to just
output any one of those right because
the spec Texel itself is just a v3 so
like you know that should be the four
values that are in this particular
location of the spec map and honestly we
don't need to probably need that I'll
just look at the zero with one and see I
mean if I don't find it I'll look for
more but zero should be fine
if we run it now and we open up the
lighting area we should see and we don't
so somehow I'm not seeing this hit that
should be putting forth but it is not
putting forth and I don't know why it's
not putting forth right I mean like I
should be seeing seeing that value and
I'm not is there air in here now like
that should put forth shouldn't it I
don't know why that wouldn't put forth
because debugging oh because we yeah
well you know it's okay because since we
know this is an endemic it's it persists
over frames I should be able to do it
here right so I should be able to put
forth before I turn off my debugging
because we loop multiple times over the
array right so I should have it poot
fourth it should be able to put forth a
little bit earlier than that right there
we go what the heck
so we just have complete garbage going
into these values
that would not really explain this
behavior meaning those look like actual
zeros maybe they're not maybe they're
actually tiny numbers and we're just
because we're only printing out the
first six places maybe they're getting
down towards underflow and that's what's
happening I also don't understand why is
everything Fulbright if these are all
zero right what's going on there it's
fascinating though so we're definitely
getting to the heart of the problem here
which we obviously have and just don't
understand but let's see
I assume all four are basically the same
right
like I assume we're getting the same
things in all four of these but I don't
actually know yeah
oh how interesting
how very interesting
so our mid-to are not having that
they're not flushing to zero and I'm
guessing they do at some point no we get
slow even before they do how odd all
right so we're clearly in no-man's land
here like we're we're in a place where
we don't really understand it at all
what's going on so there must be some
issues in this particular part of the
process where we're actually doing these
assigns here there should be no way to
oh well now but there should be no way
for transfer PPS to ever not get
initialized right in other words if I do
this we shouldn't be in a situation
where nope that's not true so in the
case where we did debugging we wouldn't
know we still do the loop so we
shouldn't actually if I initialize to
zero that should change nothing meaning
this is the problem we just have right
the code is broken in the interior so it
wasn't like it wasn't getting updated
this should this doesn't need to happen
it always does actually get updated
right so I guess we're at the point
where we need to start looking at why
this doesn't work so let's just step
through it that's very interesting I
think we must be having ad normal or
other unusual numbers problem I can't
think of any other way that we're
getting that slowdown it'd be nice to
verify that but I can't at the immediate
moment think of how other than maybe two
tests we could write something that
looked looped over the whole set and
looked for D normals or other unusual
numbers like is unusual we'd have like a
call that would determine that but since
we already have numbers that are
completely bogus I guess I can start
there at least and just see how we're
ending up with these transfer PPS values
the
so obviously completely messed up and
we'll see okay so if we look at the
transfer PBS values to start with even
though I didn't initialize them to 0
they are already 0 here before they're
actually getting assigned when we
actually step through and try to assign
to them here I'll you know what I can't
actually view them because we're
multi-threaded so let's turn off the
threading real quick it needs to be a
good way to step through multi-threaded
code where it only steps the one thread
be really cool if there was some way to
do that just remedy have anything like
that X 13 pixels probably isn't on right
now but is there some way in remedy you
can just step just the one thread you're
looking at on the list that would be a
pretty huge help here like visual studio
always sucked at that too like it
couldn't do it really you had to like
freeze threads man it was bad but you
could imagine a debugger having sort of
an advanced system that helped you where
you could just say look only step this
one thing and it would go freeze all the
threads for you allow you to step and
then like unfreeze them when you then
said step them all or something I don't
know like it does seem like something a
debugger could do for you it's just I'm
used to not having it because Visual
Studio didn't have it it it had this
weird like freeze system that's that was
that's super sucky anyway so all I want
to do here is say like look the lighting
cue let's turn off the multi-threading
by nerfing the ability to pass that to
lighting core so letting Q equals zero I
guess I'll just put that there
and so now we should only be stepping
through one code path okay so here's the
transfer PPS and now it's actually
non-zeros right these are the values
that we would expect because we didn't
initialize it so it should just be
garbage when we step in and see what it
is it's just the RGB is nothing at that
point so that seems fine that wouldn't
cause us a problem with it like why
would that be bad so let's go out and
look at this part of the code maybe just
to see what the heck's going on here so
if I jump to here and I look at all of
these values like it's just zero there's
nothing in transfer PPS
so what's spec Texel at that point so
here's the spec Texel and the spec Texel
value for each of these
so yeah I don't know what what's the
problem here
so the spec Texel is totally fine the
first time through anyway like when does
it get bad what's going on I mean that
looks like all zeros to me right so how
did it get how does it get to be
ridiculous
I think I I'm just too lost with what is
causing this problem I don't have a
solid idea so I feel like what I want to
do is write some augmentation code to
help me
so like remember we had is fishy or it
looks fishy
we're like a if a number just got weird
it would tell us kind of think that we
saved this for a good reason I'm just
gonna ask this thing any time we just
produced a fishy value in here I want to
know so just look at these and do an
assert on each of these so that will
just tell me like look when does this go
wrong cuz it obviously does but it's not
obvious when so maybe if we could just
catch the point in time when it starts
to look fishy we could figure out what
the heck was going on right and you know
I don't know I don't know when you could
see the first few frames there looked
good too so something's up there with
those numbers there they keep sort of
increasing very rapidly there and now
we've gotten to a fishy you know a fishy
situation so they do start well-behaved
and they just go too high and so
something about the way we're outputting
the transmission here I guess is
erroneous and boy is it so I guess that
must have something to do I guess what
I'd like to do here is let me look at
what we're producing for transfer
tons per second values for just the
debug one because that way I can look at
the manually there's way too many to
look at manually otherwise like those
values all look good right is it just a
feedback loop problem yeah it is so the
problem that we're getting is that the
lighting just keeps increasing and it
obviously increases by more and more
power each time because it's storing
more and more power very interesting so
this looks like case of just the the
diffuse blur problem you know like that
suggests that that if you just were
looking at sort of like hacking this
stuff that means if you just turned down
the transmission you would be fine
right and so we we kind of want to know
why we're getting that and if you
remember we already have this problem so
if you look at the disputes map builder
you know this is some garbage here right
and so if you imagine just doing you
know more removal like a very low
transmission value does this all of a
sudden work which again like gives us a
good clue as to what the heck is going
on so ill me take a look at what happens
in that circumstance oh I'm looking at
the wrong thing that's not what I wanted
I want this
those look like they're flattened a
little bit much but but you can see so
even with a really damped transmission
it still looks sort of feedback II at
this point I guess it's a little hard to
say you know maybe not exactly but I'm
just trying to find out if this feedback
is it's just a lighting quality issue
feedback and there's a slight difference
in the rate tracer that that would
produce it or if it's if it's a little
different let me run it quickly I think
we're in a good shape though we've we've
gotten rid of a lot of the bugs so I
think at this point we're now just down
to like looking at the actual PPS
preservation and sampling let's see what
happens when we do this quickly it in
like look at how slow that is for some
reason but we don't know why that would
be slow it's like the fact that the
numbers are low produces slowness which
suggests to me that we have a problem
with D normals I just don't understand
so you can see like even with really
gradual it's just it just transmits too
much right so something's something's
still broken there I think like look at
how that goes it just it's not
preserving the energy sure does look
kind of cool though huh but it's just
not properly preserving energy so that's
fine we're pretty close we can go ahead
and start looking at that that's so
cool-looking by the way how neat anyway
so I think we just have a few more
issues left in the way that we're
producing that transfer that's just so
weird how fascinating
so I think yeah we're just having
problems with again and so maybe now is
the time to like do the lighting quality
pass as well but it's just very strange
look at how slow that is by comparison
to what we know that it was running the
exact same algorithm doing the exact
same number of iterations it's just very
suspicious so we're kind of at an
interesting point in terms of
suspiciousness here right so anyway and
what we probably want to do right we
probably want to check for D normals I
don't know if there's some
I just don't know exactly whether we're
allowed to actually set these we want
flush to zero and do normal as zero
stuff to happen I just don't know what
those are set to I would have assumed
that they were already set I guess I
didn't know that they wouldn't be so
that's a bit weird
[Music]
so I don't know maybe I'll just try
setting these out so this can actually
be a compiler flag apparently so is this
actually an option I can set in Visual
Studio as compiler at all because this
is talking about the Intel compiler and
I don't know a Visual Studio has a
similar thing I can set them myself so
you know we could do that
and we could just see I assume these are
in the actual entrance of God they might
not be but the control word for the for
the ssee
stuff presumably can can be can be set
pretty easily I don't remember having
done this in a long time but it
shouldn't be that bad it's kind of too
many things here and I don't know
exactly what they would have called it
because I don't remember but let me just
see if I can search for control
extended control register kind of sounds
related in this case but unfortunately I
didn't actually know so this is what
we're talking about like this is the
sort of stuff we're looking at and we
just want to be able to set those and we
should probably just yeah so here's here
okay here we go this is the thing I was
looking for mm sets ESR that's the
control register so presumably I only
care about setting the exceptions and
setting the flush to zero let's see what
happened I'm just curious now let's see
what happens if I do that so if I say
you know I'm assuming that this is the
correct
mm sets ESR let's just see if I do
mm set CSR for de normals like does
someone have a nice guide to that
because someone should have said so
let's see so this is this is basically
what we want right basically it's just
roaring in the bits we actually care
about and it looks like you probably
don't actually have to do it as bits
necessarily but this is what we want so
we want to literally do exactly what
this does
and we can go double check that this is
the right bit field but that's exactly
what we want so you know at startup
right like when we're actually doing the
initial code here we probably want to to
just throw this in there as something we
do when things get started right so like
right here we would want to do mmm get
CSI which okay looks like it's an
unsigned in so this is the old control
bits here and then we get these from the
from the actual intrinsic it will return
what the floating-point unit is set to
do well unit the multiple floating-point
execution ports are set to do we can
then just pour it in like so and then we
can do an mm set CSR with the new
control bits right and what we want to
do is we want to actually go look and
see what these bits actually are because
I don't know like that you know who
knows that person is supposed to inform
they could have had a typo you know we
don't know but I'm curious to see like
to what extent we can get that to
actually do something now in this case
it looks like it didn't do anything at
all right this is still quite slow right
so let's take a look at what actually
happens in here I also don't know if we
do set CSR anywhere in the code so I
want to look and make sure that we don't
do that elsewhere okay we don't
so at startup if we set these up
properly hopefully that would be fine
now we don't actually know because
someone else could come along and set
them so another way to look at this is
maybe we should call them every time and
then let's take a look at what the
control bit should actually be so if we
go to the the control bits for this if
we look for flush to zero I want to kind
of look at I mean I guess we could look
at what these values are right but I
kind of want to look to see what these
are in the actual programming guide
right I would like to know
we had somewhere we were sticking this
stuff there it is mm-hmm
so if I look at the actual intel
architecture manual here oh you know
what didn't I do this yes so if I look
at the Intel architectural manual and I
just look at the like CSR I'm just
curious like okay well that's not very
helpful now is it that's the the wrong
State here we go here we go here we go
all right so here's a bunch of stuff
we've got d normal operation mask
we've got flushed zero under flow and
overflowed divided by zero like all this
stuff to be honest like probably we want
two sets of things we're gonna want to
knock stuff out here as well as put
stuff in and I guess we have to kind of
look so flush to zero flag provides a
means of controlling under flow
conditions on somebody floating-point
operations console ready to be loaded
from memory blah blah but 1631 are
reserved we don't really need to look at
those so if we actually look at these in
here and we look at which bits are being
set so flush 2-0 is like bit 15 right
and so you can see that that was the 8
here because here's bits 1 through 4
here's bits that's all right 0 through 3
here's bits 4 through 7 here is bits 8
through 11 in here spits 12 through 15
and 15 is set right now I would rather
do something like this
so that people know what the heck is
going on when they look at this code
right
the precision mask I don't know what
that does because I've long forgotten so
it would be nice if it were documented
so 7 through 12 we want to clear because
we don't want any exceptions to occur so
7 through 12 we want to be empty
that's this mask so that's invalid
operation de normals whatever we want
those cleared right
so do you normal stars zero we want set
which is bit six that was the four wait
but four would be wrong wouldn't it
also bit six this is the wrong way to
write this so bit six would be shifted
up five right yeah so anyway invalid
operation flag D normal flag divided by
zero flag under flip flag and I'm sorry
overflow flag and under flip flag and
precision flag these are just things get
that are set when they happen right so
this is this is just for detection so
those should all be zero and we don't
want to touch those anyway because those
are just conditioned like that just
tells you something six we want to set
seven through twelve we want clear
rounding control we probably do actually
want to set it to our rounding and then
flush to zero we want to set we should
probably set the RC as well right but
what we probably want to do here is
actually say like old control bits we
want to do like an control mask so we
want to knock out like the bits that we
want cleared and then we want to like
you know desired bits we want like
desired right
so we want like our control masks in
this case we want that to be like all
the bits we actually care about so of
all the bits we know about here let's
define them all so we want like
precision masks underflow maths overflow
mass divided by zero d normal and
invalid yeah so if we take a look at
these just in the intel bit order
we've got flush to zero we've got
rounding control and rounding controls a
little bit Squinkie because it's
actually two bits right so it's actually
two bits that are post set together and
then it starts at 13 great yeah so I
don't why don't I change the 14 that's
correct so if it was set at 1 in 0 right
if this was set to 1 it would be 1 2 3 4
5 6 all right 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
fifteen yeah so I was right I don't know
why I was thinking that because it's
already shipped in if it was 16 if you
were counting the bits then it would
have been one less but it's not here
and you normal star zero should be six
yeah right
I think I'm right there so we don't care
about 0 1 2 3 4 or 5
we care about 6 and then 7 is the
invalid op do you normal mask is 8
general opt mask rather is 8 9 10 11 12
and then we've got 13 and 14 here and 15
so then our control mask is just all of
these so this is the flush to zero a bit
the rounding control bits the precision
mask the underflow mask overflow mask
the DBZ mask the normal op mask invalid
op mask you normals are 0 that's all of
the stuff that we want to talk about so
we want to knock them all out then we
want to just put in the two we want
which are these two right now for
rounding control honestly I think we
might just not want to touch it right
now just leave it as it is
so we'll knock out everything but that
and then we'll put in the two that we
actually wanted right now I don't know
if this is gonna help we'll find out
we'll see what happens here oops oh and
also I guess well let's see so we'll run
it and we'll see if we stop I'm guessing
that maybe these mask values should
actually set to on because some mask so
it should be on if we want to stop them
from occurring right so this should
actually cause us to stop somewhere
probably I would think yeah
so that actually causes even the
standard runtime library to cause an
operation error right okay so actually
we just want our control mask and our
desired bits are actually the same in
this case because we want to set all of
them right so it just so happens that
it's the same right which is kind of
weird but that's just how it is right at
the moment so now if we run yeah in
theory we're set incorrectly so I have
no idea what this slowdown is coming
from it's fascinating
I really don't know what's causing it to
be slow it's some other thing that isn't
related to the behavior of the CPU I
guess and I don't really know like you
know I guess we could double-check that
the MCR is actually being set properly
but that's just like really weird right
it's just like really really really
weird and I have no idea why it's why
it's having that problem something super
bizarre is happening if I actually just
step in to the code here I just want to
look and see what we actually get so
here's the old control bits what we
would actually get and here's the new
control bits so it is actually the case
that that those were not what was set
like meaning this is not the exact
pattern and it looks like specifically
alike the flush to zero was not set for
example which is interesting and D
normals are zero was not set so it's
kind of a little bit weird that we
didn't get more of a change in the
program because of that so it would have
lined up with what we would have
expected to see actually believe it or
not but
for whatever reason that's not what
happened I'm gonna do something else
here a little bit strange I might put
this at the top of the lighting code
just so I can see what whether that gets
reset because that would also be if
someone else was resetting that without
our permission that would explain it too
so I just want to do it every frame to
see if that's the case
so let's actually just dump that right
here yeah where is that though
okay so what we should be able to verify
here is that we always have the same one
every time yeah so so thankfully like
now we know it's running properly we
know that no one's like interceding and
I'll double check to make sure that
didn't like make it go fast all of a
sudden but I'm pretty sure it wouldn't
because I don't think anyone would be
monkeying with our settings there don't
know but I don't imagine so yeah so you
can see like it's just really weird it's
really slow and bizarre and and I have
no idea why that would be because we
don't have things that are really
dependent on that so I don't understand
why we would be getting such a drastic
difference in speed as a result of that
but you know it could be other things we
haven't looked at it particularly
closely I am gonna go ahead and keep
this code because I do like the ability
for us to have this code available so I
am gonna put in here a thing that's like
you know set default floating or FP
behavior some you can call just to make
sure that all this stuff is set in a
particular way and we'll do that just
right at the outset and that way we've
done it to worry about it any more we
know that no matter what we're you know
how wherever we're running it'll you
know should be roughly correct and we
could be more defensive instead of every
frame if we feel like we should but at
the moment you know it's fine so that's
just so weird so I have no idea what's
going on here but you know that's a job
for next weekend we've at least got our
ray cast are working properly or at
least to a certain extent we've got it
working properly and so we should be
able to pick it up from there next time
around also question
we're still running single-threaded so
that's probably where the speed problem
was coming from not a thing that was a
slight mistake okay so actually that
that may have explained part of it right
so we still have the feedback problem
right and if I get rid of those looks
fishies here yeah yeah so let's do this
test again I bet it was to do normals
and I just forgot that I turn off the
multi-threading so let's go and look at
the code for the diffuse builds right
oops and let's look in here and say okay
so if we go back to the previous values
that we were using before where we got
the instant explosion which we know like
just kills us very quickly and we got
the performance degradation that
happened let's see if it still happens
with the normal flushing turned on now
because this is the actual test we need
a frame counter we should have a frame
counter on here so we can see at which
frame it happens and then like actually
get a more coherent understanding of
what's going on right I should put that
in here so here's us running for a while
right and we're not seeing any of the
explosion to open up there it is weird
that's just a bizarre one
I still I still have literally no idea
what the look of because of that other
than weird like values I just don't know
and I think we've said it now I mean I
think we've said it so that that's not
occurring I want to do one more thing
now I'm gonna actually call that every
frame so I'm gonna go in here and I'm
gonna call set default behavior I'm
gonna call that every frame so inside
the lighting code I just I'm just
curious
because I don't know before we do this
in the update lighting call I'm just
gonna put it in here to like reset that
right and then I'm gonna let it run
again and look at that perf cuz again
I'm just not sure I mean for all I know
some driver jumps in and sets Rd normal
flushing off for some reason and I just
don't know right so I just want to find
out if I just want to be absolutely
positive that it's not D normals or
other types of overflow underflow
problems occurring there
so it's oddly not as bad but it seems to
still have hit the problem oh you know
what I just glanced the chat and someone
pointed out each thread can have this
problem because if the MX CR is saved
per core which you would expect it to be
doing in the OS you'd have to set it for
each one of those so actually we need to
make sure that's true for everybody so
basically the MX CR should have to get
set right at the code that actually
jumps in for compute work right platform
oops
work you call back so right here we
actually need to make sure that we're
flushing de normals to actually do this
test for Fairleigh right you know what I
bet that's totally it that's a very good
catch chat
whoever caught that xx the big Fox
totally right totally right I bet I bet
that's it I bet that's it it totally
fits the behavior profile about how it
wasn't going as high that's probably as
certain cores got their MXC are set
those cores dropped off of the slow path
and back onto the fast path absolutely I
think that's totally true so excellent
catch that's almost certainly the case I
mean we'll see
maybe not but pretty sure
[Music]
yes so that's that's it
okay so thankfully that's all now very
explicable it was in fact problems with
the normals which is what we'd expect so
that's great this puts us in a fantastic
position for next weekend because now we
should be able to start working on the
lighting quality transfer part of things
and get a good solution presumably out
of the grid ray caster as well so that's
great
awesome notice someone we check the
camera out the kit but we didn't need to
do that right before like we were able
to get it to repo with just the camera
sitting in one place so the camera is
not involved here
all right cool cool excellent catch chat
excellent excellent catch all right
let's go ahead and I guess we'll go to
brief brief Q&amp;A but
so no we don't really take too much of a
look at how so the question is I'm
building my first BBH from a ray tracer
to the previous episodes where you work
on the KD tree going to how to traverse
a tree using sim D without slamming your
face into the wall nose first no because
there isn't one really so the way that
that typically gets handled in the
performance oriented literature as far
as I know is all they do is try as hard
as possible to bundle rays together
which they think will need to traverse
roughly the same part of the BBH right
so basically like if you have a bounding
volume hierarchy what you generally know
is like look if I'm shooting Ray's in
sort of similar directions they probably
have to visit roughly the same set of
nodes so that should minimize the amount
of additional visitation that I do as I
go through the tree right that tends to
be what they do now more aggressive work
in this area can do slightly different
things but that's most of it right if
you have the luxury of using scatter
gather the other thing like as a VX has
scatter gather in it if you're using a
VX - I think cascade or gatherer in its
ATX 5/12 does I don't know if - it's the
Intel chips are so confusing as to what
they haven't don't have but if you have
the luxury of using scatter gather you
can also try to do things where you go
look I'm gonna load different bounding
volumes right into my different
registers you can do stuff like that
right you can make bounding volume
hierarchies where you're like well I
scatter gather different stuff so rather
than testing against you know testing
for Ray's against one volume you test
for Ray's against for vol
all of a sudden and that so each ray is
actually in a different node of the BVH
and then you're in a better position
because then you don't really care
whether or not all your Ray's are in the
same part of the BVH you care whether
all your rays have to visit roughly the
same number of nodes in the BVH and
that's an easier thing to work on
right so
can you explain more yd normals could
cause performance to degrade no I can't
I've never looked so I have no idea why
a chip designer would be able to tell
you my understanding is that in the
actual hardware when a D normal occurs
it actually gets shunted to a literally
slower Hardware path that's that's all I
know
so I don't really know why there I don't
really know why they actually cause
performance problems at the chip level
but you know you can sort of see why
because if all of your operations if you
designed this really fast hardware
that's based around processing things as
exponent mantissa all the time and all
of a sudden you get thrown this this
value that's like not that at all I mean
it makes sense right
the it makes sense that that becomes a
thing you have to that your ship is not
optimized for right because you can't
possibly do that operation as fast as
you were doing all the other operations
so now it's gonna shut there I don't
know actually why but it you know it's
at least intuitive that that would be
the case it doesn't run contrary to what
your thought process would be if you
didn't know anything about hardware
which I don't it makes sense right it's
just it's kind of logical it's a number
formatted into bits
totally differently than it is in every
other case and if generally speaking
most of your computations occurred with
D normal numbers then you could say
well probably we should have just
designed the hardware to be fast for de
normals and they should run at the same
speeds everything else and the other
things should slow down if necessary to
like be the same speed as you normals
because this is what we should I find
ship for but most of your computations
aren't D normal so that wouldn't make
much sense right the volatile portion
consists the six doses oh yes so flush
to zero once per thread should be enough
if the Kalon convention is obeyed but
you don't know that it is right like a
driver could just set that and forget to
unset it and then you'd be screwed right
you put the code back up where you set
the bits
we should probably set the rounding
control because we might as well now
that we're setting it set it to the
thing we know it should be rather than
relying it being on the default because
why bother but we're not doing that yet
would it be worth special casing the
occurrences when a ray runs parallel to
the grid of the walk table I don't see
why we would do that I'm not sure what
that would save
do you think GPUs would have the
denormalize issue gosh I mean that's so
far afield from what I work on I guess I
don't know
so certainly GPUs in the early days
would never have addy normal issue
because they just wouldn't have support
in the hardware 40 normals at all right
so I mean I'm pretty sure that the early
at least the early GPU Hardware would
just be like screw it you give me a D
normal interest you get whatever you get
man I don't think they would detect and
process D normals at all they probably
wouldn't even throw exceptions they
would just literally just do whatever
the bits would have come out if you
didn't think about D normals at all
right you just get that answer and so
the reason that I hesitate to say that's
what would happen today is because
nowadays GPUs to a large extent are
targeting scientific computing as a main
source of high-margin revenue like
nvidia loves to sell cards to you know
government entities doing nuclear
simulation or big data mining you know
whatever the heck and d normals were
specifically in there for the purposes
of getting more precise scientific
computations I mean that's the only
reason they exist in the first place so
I guess what I would say is I'm not
prepared to say that modern GPUs
wouldn't actually handle the normals
they might I would assume and it's
purely an assumption I'm just going on
and just I have no idea I can't answer
your question but if I had to guess at
the answer my guess would be that unless
you were specifically running like a
CUDA path or some other kind of
scientific computing path that the GPU
would be automatically configured by the
affix driver not to use de normals even
if the GPU can handle D normals that
would be my expectation because graphics
drivers are all about performance and
the last thing they would want to do is
by default give developers a way to make
them slow by accidentally passing to
smaller numbers right so my assumption
would be that specifically unless you
ask a GPU to do two normal conformant
operations they won't but I actually
don't know because I've never looked all
right last question I came from dave 523
and that's oh you're talking about the
joke intro to get so I don't know what
to say about stuff like that
I think git is just a pile of crap I
mean it's you know get is is not good
sorry folks
it's terrible right now that's not the
same as saying that some of the core
ideas and get her bad because you know
using hashes to identify files is not
necessarily a bad idea especially if you
use a better hash than get used having
peer-to-peer support in your source code
control system is not a bad idea right
so it's not that some of the ideas and
get weren't good the current incarnation
of git is is absolutely terrible and I
don't actually know why any sane
programmer wouldn't agree with that they
obviously don't because tons of people
like defend it and tell you
to use it but git is absolutely horrible
it is not a good source code control
system it is dramatically over
complicated for what it does
the default things it does are usually
not what you want
it requires way too much specialized
knowledge of how it works
to be effective with it it's just very
bad so it should absolutely never have
been the standard source code control
utility but a lot of things I just said
can be said about a lot of source code
control utilities they tend to be pretty
bad so at the same time it's like it's
not like there was some amazing source
code control utility that people just
didn't use because git was there so you
could think of the standardization of
git being people picking an incredibly
bad option from a field of incredibly
bad options and at that point you know
what are you gonna say and your the
thing you say is is linus torvalds not a
good programmer as well about no linus
torvalds didn't write most of git
probably the initial simple thing that
that that leanest Torvalds wrote was
probably good because things Charles is
a good programmer in my opinion
obviously that's just a matter of
opinion but like I think he is but get
today is nothing like that there are so
many lines of code and get in a standard
distribution of get right now that
leanest our wallets hasn't even read
them let alone did he write them so git
is nothing like what he wrote originally
it's not even you know 10% leanness it's
like 0.1% leanness and 99.9% a bunch of
really crappy programmers who like piled
on top afterwards right I mean for that
matter so is the Linux kernel right like
if the Linux kernel sucks and I'm not
saying that it does but if it did it's
not
because leanest revolt is a bad
programmer that is those things do not
follow even a little bit right because
you're talking both get and the Linux
kernel are many millions of lines of
code and he didn't write them
anyway so that's my opinion on get
endless troubles who I think is very
good programmer personally I don't know
how you pronounce his name but my
understanding is it would be like Lennox
and leanness as close possibly not Linus
I feel like Linus is more of an American
pronunciation so it's more likely than
lie but I don't know any northern
European languages at all let alone
finish let's say or I don't know what
the correct pronunciation would be let's
put it that way so I guess what I would
say is go listen to him pronounce it and
that's how you pronounce it
more Swedish than finished like I said I
don't know I really don't know because
again just because someone's from a
particular country doesn't mean their
name is actually that right for example
my parents are both Italian my first
name is Irish right so the pronunciation
of Casey has nothing to do with where I
was born or who my parents were or what
their native language was or what their
ethnicity even was so you know how you
pronounce someone's name is difficult to
say I have no idea how you're supposed
to pronounce leanness I just pretty sure
it's not Linus is I guess the only thing
I can say because that's a pretty
specific pronunciation of that name that
I don't think would apply any where he's
from or where his parents were from I
just don't think you would ever say
Linus I could be wrong though
alright let's wrap it up and my goodness
I didn't realize anyone could actually
watch that video that I did about get
and not know that it wasn't fake but the
fact that you didn't know it wasn't fake
is a pretty good indication of why I
think it's pretty definitive to say that
git is not a good source to a control
system the fact that that is sort of
what it feels like to use git is just a
really good example of why this is not
really what you want and the reason that
I say that is because it's very
important to understand one very crucial
feature of source code control systems
and that is that anytime literally any
time that you spend interacting with
your source code control system is time
you aren't spending programming that
means that everything everything 100% of
the time that you spend learning a
source code control system and using a
source code control system is wasted
period so the entire job of a source
code control system author interface
designer whatever you want to call it is
to figure out how to create the most
amount of useful source code control
operations out of the simplest possible
amount of user work and education and
there's like no question that get
absolutely failed at that because not
only can it not do most things so most
of the things you would want a source
code control system to do such as for
example only store large binary older
versions on specific machines that's a
very obvious as a first thing I put in
my source code control system for
example get can't even do you have to
start using these new updates to it
called large file system awareness
there's all this crap people have added
only in the last few years to do that
it's not even part of the system right
so git has a very narrow set of things
that can actually do they mostly relate
to
basically creating lots of different in
place hash versions of things and
sending those around between different
people that's like almost all it can do
and yet the syntax and the amount of
Education you need to actually
understand what is happening in it its
output and how to fix or diagnose
problems is tremendous most people have
no idea how to use most things and get
most people can easily create errors
when they're using it and not really
understand why it's a terrible source
code control system I'm sorry it just it
is objectively on any access you want to
measure it it's really really bad the
only access you could say it succeeds on
is obviously its ability to work
distributed is good because it allowed
people to do that and that was a pretty
good improvement there was worth making
but it's not good it's not a good
implementation of that it's a bad
implementation of that right
so no and I also disagree if you say
it's not wasteful if your job is to
integrate patches from hundreds of
branches from thousand developers day in
and day out no that's false
right the job is integrating the patches
not working with the source code control
system right so the idea there is it
should have been the most you you're
trying to design a system where the
programmer does the least amount of work
to review and commit the correct set of
branches into their project right if any
work that you're doing in that system
that involves you interacting the source
code show system is wasted ideally you
wouldn't do it at all
you'd just be presented with changes and
you'd approve or deny them right that'd
be the best possible outcome it would
just be directly in your editor and
that's what would happen and you'd never
even know there was a source code
control system right you just be like
here's a change from Bob do you like
that or not and I'd be like mmm I don't
know let me build it okay and now I
don't deny right and I never even I'd
never have to learn anything right I
mean that's that's what you would want
you would want a system where you never
even knew that there was source code
control right the less you even ever
were aware that there was source code
control the better and anytime you're
thinking about source code control as
part of your job that's just a failure
of the system I mean that's pretty much
all you can say
right and it's not to say that we had
better system that's why I say like get
if you evaluate it against other source
code so it's not necessarily terrible
because there's lots of bad source code
control stems there early isn't like
some amazingly fantastic source code
control system out there but like it's
not good you know it's not it's not a
good thing that you have to spend all
this time typing in all these esoteric
git commands that's that's just not
something to be proud of right like it's
like no this is terrible we really want
something much better than this
right I mean that's just if you really
want an example of how bad get was you
know I've used it like once or twice
total I mean unless you count typing git
clone to get things occasionally right
but like you know we were at Allen's
house you me and Alan were at his place
working on for coder together right and
I wanted to do an incredibly simple
operation I just wanted I don't remember
exactly what it was it was like I just
wanted to get like the thing that Alan
had done and I wanted to transfer it
into my thing or something right and we
had even we had get experts on the
stream and they were like yeah you can't
you can't do this thing you wanted to do
it was like incredibly simple I don't
remember what it was was like super
super simple but look it can't do it you
had to go through like these oh one
thing I could have done was installed a
good extension to do it though it's
amazing right and you're just like come
on yeah this is a joke
it is not good it's it's it's really
quite poor it's it's not a good
abstraction over the set of things that
a version file system can do let's just
get over it it's not good
there'll be something ten times better
than get some day there just will be
like it's not it's not good for what it
does it's it's quite poor
which we Chester's I use a we have a
custom one at my Rockets called seamer
it's not great I kind of have plans for
a great one that you know is sort of the
next incarnation of it
see mirrors like the second incarnation
there was a see mirror one this kind of
crappy Samara 2 is actually pretty good
but I learned a lot about what is
possible with source code control in C
Mira - and I realized some really
important things about it and I was like
Oh duh there's all these things we're
not doing starts to review easily do and
I did some of them and see mirror - but
now that I know what they all are
I think see Mira 3 will be probably when
I'm capable of saying okay this is now
actually great SEMA or two is not great
it's like good but bad at some things
for no reason so I think seamer three
you know
all right
all right that's it I'm gonna call it
too many windows open hey everybody
thank you for joining me for the episode
of hand made here it's my pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along series at home you
can always head on over to hand made
here org and pier to the game it comes
to the source code so you can follow
along with it at home we're all done
with the main raycasting debug process
because I think we've kind of gotten it
working fairly well now and so now what
we have to do is actually go work on the
lighting transfer stuff which we may
have some bugs that we introduced in the
latest round but even if we don't have
bugs there we also know that we never
really did the lighting quality pass
that we needed to do so starting next
week will probably head into that where
we just start to look at really what
what are we transferring around four
fundamental quantities how are we
transferring them and how do we make
sure that they start stay properly
unbiased so we don't get fade to white
or fade to black which are the two
things that happen when you've got a
feedback loop in the lighting right
that's it for today hope see you back
here next week till then have fun
program everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet I'm gonna check to see if
John's still streaming and if he is we
will go ahead and raid so don't touch
that don't touch that dial or whatever
let's see is John still on
you see on tell me if John is streaming
mr. raid system yes he is so we're gonna
head over and and raid John's channel I
don't know what he's doing right now but
it's probably something cool so here we
go all right folks here we go