hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are going to be
continuing our lighting work today we
actually were told specifically in the
so we left on the thing where we gotta
like all right we got to debug the
lighting I cleaned up the sort of the
path that the lighting goes through so
that we weren't doing as much
unnecessary work but I didn't actually
have a chance to debug any of it or
really finish it up so that's what we
were gonna be doing this weekend we had
some bugs in there well at least one bug
in there and although we would have
tried to find that today actually on the
handmade hero github which I guess I'm
not logged into right now but I probably
should have done that we actually had
someone scriber wrote in over the week
saying hey by the way I found the bug
already in the lighting and and I fixed
it and so I'm actually tipped off to
what the bug was so I can't actually do
the work of finding it today or at least
not that book because we've already sort
of we know what it is now
so let me just show you what the problem
was when we did some of the work of
moving to like the you know when we sort
of said alright let's let's streamline
this so we're gonna actually do
everything directly in the voxel and
we're gonna do a sim D version of the
update and all that stuff when we were
computing the weights I think one of the
things and I'm not sure I can make it
happen here because you can't really see
it very well but one of the things we
noticed is that there were like parts of
the lighting that seemed like they were
always black unnecessarily like they
were supposed to not be but they were
and it turns out that the reason for
that at least assuming the bug report
was correct I never looked at the code
and unless we're on stream so I didn't
go verify it but if you remember we
create sort of this diffuse weight map
concept here and we put a bunch of
information
to it that we're going to use to look up
to do multiplies later and what we've
got is just an off by one bug in there
where we're putting in the wrong
information I should say sorry we're
putting the information into the slot
wrong because one of our lookups is
wrong and that's kind of makes sense
because we haven't polished this code
like we haven't gone through and
actually cleaned up how are things being
look we got weird constants like this -
- and all that stuff in there we
probably want to get rid of but so let
me just show you where it is if we go -
I think it's what is it called build
diffuse light Maps that's the one so if
we look in here and we look at how these
things are being updated right and then
we go to the code that actually uses
them which is down in the nope where is
it here it is I think no oh sorry right
we're doing these multi-threaded now so
it's actually in the compute light
computation call yeah we've gotten
pretty fancy haven't we so here's that
work computation it's actually being
done so it's actually out here and if we
look at where this is being done so I
believe this is it right here right and
we've got our are pulling the map out so
you can see here when we get the weights
there's a T y -1 being done here and a t
x -1 being done here and then when we
look it up we've got a T Y and a TX
minus 4 being done here so you can see
that we're actually looking this up
differently because this is the same
loop on the outside right you can see
that these are meant to line up but this
one's looking it up with T Y and this
one's looking it up with T y -1 so
everything was shifted by a row which
leads to lighting that sort of looks
sort of correct but is off a little bit
right like it's just it's rotated in our
octahedron a little bit and then just
one of the rows eventually we'll get to
garbage and that's the last row that you
see right
from top to bottom there and that's just
because again since this is picking from
T Y it starts at one whereas this one
starts at zero and it goes to the same
number so it's just going to pull one
off the end so we need to be able to
look up our diffuse weight maps with the
same thing that we were doing there and
that's that's the crucial bit so that
way you know this sort of unpacking here
where this all does it's T X minus one
nonsense and figures out where to put
everything that was all fine because
we're looking up just by TX 4
so that's all fine but we we don't
really have any way to recover from that
T Y problem so we needed to make that B
a minus 1 so let's go ahead and run it
now and we should in theory have a
slightly better version here and it
looks alright except I'm not sure why
we're not getting any lighting on the
actual character that seems a little
weird because we see it's kind of a
little bit strange right so that that
looks a little bit busted still but the
actual lighting of the world seems
correct so I'm not sure how exactly
that's happening that might just be
because of the way the random the that
could just be randomly sort of the way
that the character is because at the
moment right there's no bounce lighting
whatsoever on anything so you know
depending on exactly where the character
is relative to how you're viewing it
right you can kind of see as it goes
there so that that might be okay not
really willing to say it is or isn't the
moment but I'm really kind of only
looking at the environment and so that
looks pretty good right I mean you know
if I look at the way the lighting is
flowing again looks pretty reasonable we
do have a problem with the way the voxel
is aligned and we have to look at that
at some point so do you see like that
there that's because our voxel is not
aligned to the two like that where the
view is right it's aligned to the
simulation region and that's like very
unhelpful so do you see this box here
this box is the thing that contains our
lighting so that always has to be
centered around the view if we want to
make sure that there isn't a cutoff in
lighting but at the moment it's not and
so when you know when it does when it
switches to the simulation center like
that it's just a real issue because
sometimes the simulation center might be
at the exact center like that and
everything's fine
other times the simulation centers
shifted to the - like here now one thing
I don't know and it's probably worth
exploring is if we look at what's going
on here it's kind of an open question as
to why the simulation center got set
there because the simulation center
should be centered around the room that
we're in and for some reason the
simulation center as you can see appears
to be like over like I don't even know
what's going on with the simulation
center there but either way this is not
helpful right and so that a couple of
those things are just now in a janky
state and that's okay because it doesn't
affect our lighting computations at all
so it's not something we need to fix
immediately yeah it doesn't affect any
more any other part of the algorithm so
we can leave it to fix till later but
it's worth noting that we do have issues
with that that we want to address so I
think we're okay for now
with with like the way the lighting is
working here and I think that the next
natural step is of course to try and get
this working with some actual Bounce
lighting now
and so what we want to be able to do now
since you know this is what we're
sending down here is this diffuse map
and what we want to be able to do now is
that dis fuse map needs to get used in
our actual code path where we sample the
lighting to figure out what the lighting
is on things that we hit in the
environment right and so again just like
looking at what's happening here right
this is just a test where we spam some
light into the environment with a
specific normal and it's really it's
really just a test of the voxel
interpolation and the octahedral map
right it's just something to tell us if
we're working vaguely correctly but it's
totally wrong and doesn't actually talk
about what the light is actually doing
there much at all and also by the way
let me just run our test sphere as well
through here so that we can verify that
that's giving proper value so here's our
test sphere you can kind of see that
just doing a fall-off light on the
actual sphere you know looks fairly
reasonable because remember basically
what this is doing is anywhere that we
hit it's just basically looking to see
how much light bounces back from a
sphere that's like right here and so
it's you know it's a cosine weighting
kind of a thing now I don't again
actually know that we're totally correct
at this point because we might be
getting a little bit too much specular
I'm not sure like I'm not sure how
diffuse this should be I'd have to go
through and kind of think about exactly
what should be happening in terms of
that cosine fall-off curve because since
there is no indirect lighting it's kind
of hard for me to think about exactly
what we should be getting since we've
got two cosine falls in there one from
the actual light distribution that we
stick in there and then one from the the
actual diffuse so I'm not exactly sure
what the correct thing to see in this
case is also our clamping of lighting is
a little aggressive here and so I think
I'm going to go ahead
and get rid of a little of that clamping
just so we can like this right here no
this right where's our clamp here it is
so this right here we clamp sir one it's
not super helpful so I probably want to
clamp to something higher than one
because over brighting the light is
actually desirable in a lot of cases so
we probably don't want to clamp it in
that way like if we were gonna clamp it
we'd tone map it or do something like
that but clamping zero to one is not
it's not really good so what I'd rather
do here is say okay let's let's let this
light go a little bit higher you can see
we've got a clamp min/max here so I
think I'm just gonna say alright let's
clamp this between zero and double
bright I mean I don't know what we want
to do there in the long term we might
want to have a tone map where we map
values in some kind of way but you can
see that that adds a little bit more
character the lighting that's still not
probably enough I'd go higher than that
in terms of over brighting so that that
just looks better right because it
allows you to get a light source that
actually like whitens things up a bit
past past what their base value is so
it's actually kind of like adding in a
little bit of extra light there and that
seems reasonable to me you know yeah
not sure what the clamp tap value should
be but that seems maybe more like it and
then you know like eventually if you
want to put some tone mapping in there
we can but at the moment we would just
turn like down the brightness of a light
anyway that's looking really nice
I mean again we probably slept some bugs
in there and at some point we're gonna
have to do like a really hardcore
evaluation pass on this probably but at
the moment at least as far as I can tell
there's enough certainty that this is at
least roughly reproducing the light
field we put into it but I think we
could start to work on the indirect pass
and get that working right that way we
at least have everything working and
then we can start to do our sort of
tune-up but getting everything debugged
right all right so let's see and also
speed optimize because right now that
diffuse pass is really expensive and I
don't know we may need to do something
separable there or because there's just
too much like too many flops in that
conversion from the specular sample to
the diffuse we don't really have a way
of making that work at the moment fast
enough so although the game appears to
be running reasonably well you have to
keep in mind that this is running at
only 30 frames a second this isn't
hitting 60 right now and it's not
hitting 60 even though we're not doing
the Ray casting right so if we were to
actually turn the Ray casting on which
doesn't quite work yet because we
haven't actually gone through and gotten
the sampling in there we would we would
have an issue I'm gonna do test fear
where's my oh I'm in the wrong file so
if we were to turn these off and we
actually run the full cast path here
what's the problem lighting solution um
what am i what am I getting complaints
on what's what's full cast expect
oh it expects the lighting work that's
what it expects all right so here's
running the indirect pass and just what
you can see is like to see how that
frame rate really tanks right and so the
problem that we're gonna have also I'm
not sure what's going on I don't know
why everything is fulbright right now
that's total mystery to me so but either
way so with the full cast on you can see
the speed is just horrible right so the
problem is I don't think we are going to
have the budget for doing indirect ray
casting plus that really expensive
diffuse those two things together are
just you know either one of them is what
we can afford and not both so we need to
speed either both of them up or we need
to at least beat up the diffuse one
because the diffuse when we've looked at
quite a bit less than the Ray casting
which is already going considerably
accelerated over its base rate of just a
naive implementation and so you know I
guess I would just say this is that
that's where we're at right so we have
issues there okay
so I'm not sure why that was actually
full braiding that was kind that's kind
of a surprise to me I'm not sure what
we're actually seeing there also I'm not
sure why we're not seeing anything in
here I'm a little bit tempted to to take
a look at the well you know it might be
that we just let some debug code in
there but it sound like it did I'm a
little bit tempted to take a look at
what this texture actually is because
I'm not sure why it doesn't show up as
white or something in here
so that's a little bit strange but again
we haven't looked at this code in a
little bit so let's just go in and see
what's going on there so here's the full
cast code and basically this is the code
that we're calling if we wanted to stick
stuff into the voxel that actually gets
updated via ray casting rather than or
via distributed Red casting rather than
just
like a single cast towards the light see
if you hit it and what we get here is we
can see that we come through here we've
got our old moon light that's going to
be placed in and we can turn off the
moon light for now to avoid that being
anything that is gonna cause us a
problem you can see that the only place
that actually comes in here is when we
have light information coming down a
path where we haven't hit anything at
all right so our ray escapes the scene
entirely and we put the moon light in
there so we can get rid of that for now
and the easiest way to do that is just
the moon color here right we can turn
off so we can just say like you know
moon color equals nothing and then the
moon is turned off and we can eliminate
that from the front of you and you know
if we turn that off then I don't see a
thing different and you know what I saw
some light in there so it looks like
actually all that's happening is the
lights just building up till infinite
values probably something like that so
that's fine so here's that casting code
and what you can see here is it's going
through this thing and doing a bias
towards light version of the sampling
here where we get this light leaf I'm
not sure I really want to do that I
think I might rather just not do any
light biasing at the moment so this kind
of situation I might want to turn off at
the immediate moment and what you can
see here is that the way that that
startup works is we then start picking
at the end or at least I thought we did
maybe this is busted I thought we were
looking up ray directions here so where
does that so it looks like ray origin is
not getting updated at all so this is
just kind of garbage
oh no it's not sorry Rea directions the
only thing that needs to get updated
what am I talking about so that's the
part that we actually pick the new one
right the sampling sphere with ray
bundle index and that just goes through
and picks each one of these out and I
don't know that I actually want to do
this add padding yet so what I'm going
to do here again is just I'm not going
to bias towards the light source at the
moment I'm gonna go ahead and put this
at the top like so
oops so that we're actually not biasing
towards light sources I'll do that later
okay so here's this running without bias
towards light sources and what you
notice is it lights very quickly and so
it's already a little suspicious
oops more time I lied there we go
alright so what you can see is we're
getting still a lot of light coming in
there and I'm not really sure why we're
getting so much so that's one thing that
I want to look at if we go to the update
voxel call you can see here that what
this is doing is a slow blend each time
we do an update which is like this it's
doing a slow blend towards whatever the
lighting information is that we have
here and so one of the things that I
don't really want to do yet but that
will do eventually is make sure that our
actual light our point distribution
actually tries to get different
directions on the octahedral map each
time but that's kind of a separate issue
so the real question we want to ask now
is when we do this ray cast why are we
in a situation where the things that
come out of here are too much
represent too much light I assume that
if transfer PPS is set to nothing so
we're not trying to stuff any actual
light into this thing that it would just
remain dark right so you know there it
is if we were trying to transmit a low
amount of light so you know we're gonna
transmit some white light let's say and
we're just using a quarter light
transmission so you know not anything
particularly large then I would imagine
that we should stay at a reasonable
value right and I guess the only thing
I'm not sure about here is if that's the
transfer photons per second that we're
seeing here I'm not sure why that got so
bright right so I am a little confused
about what's going on here so we may
want to dig into that a little bit first
because I'm just just to get my head
oriented around it again it's been a
while so if I look at update voxel and
we just look at how much light is
getting thrown in there in theory right
that should always go towards this value
which means that at least in theory that
this is the expected result right and my
assumption is that the only if if that
was actually true meaning if this is
actually working properly right now and
in fact I wait but I kind of know it
isn't so look at what's happening there
do you see how it gradually gets
brighter like that so why is that
happening that's just really confusing
because if we're always blending towards
this value always something's not right
here because this lerp should always be
pushing us towards this one value but
that's not what's happening so we've got
some issue where we're I think I think
we must be doing something in the light
sea itself that we shouldn't be doing so
let's just go take a look at what's
happening there
so so where is this who's actually
touching these values so for example do
you see this here right although this
one here this is doing an update voxel
so what are we doing differently so this
update voxel right is going slowly
towards a particular value as well but
we're not getting that word bloom so let
me just let me just indulge me for a
second here if we switch to our test
case right which is this is the test
caster and I run it here's me jumping
around with my test caster right and it
seems to be working okay if we're in the
test caster and now I was to say alright
the test caster is just gonna output a
flat value now right so the same
situation I was just testing in there
right here where we go to do update
voxel instead of actually doing any kind
of lighting I'm just gonna do a gray
that is a constant value what happens to
my light okay so I thought I was doing
exactly the same thing what happens if I
do this lots of times it shouldn't do
anything different and it doesn't so you
can see that something's up like
something about the that pass is it's
like we're doing something different in
that pass such that that test code is
failing there meaning that output of
just a straightforward value is not
working and I'm not sure why that would
be so you can see that we've got some
kind of a weird bug happening here and I
don't know what it is so when we
actually do our full cast we're getting
just a much brighter value but I don't
know why and so we're gonna have to
figure out what's happening there
because that shouldn't be happening
right so when we actually do the full
cast
um the light devalue we don't use the
octahedral offset shouldn't really much
matter oh but it does so here's the
thing the fact that this is setting the
light incoming from multiple octahedral
offsets would produce this result
so having 0.25 amount of light in all of
the directions
I guess that's and then the cosine
fall-off summation that we had turns out
giving you this if you have a flat
quarter light coming in everywhere I
guess I'm still not 100% convinced of
that though but it seems like that's the
only real explanation
I don't see really any other explanation
for it so I assume that must be right
again kind of hard to say so I'm not
sure what to make of it exactly but when
you have the light coming in from all
directions yeah it's gonna sum to
something higher now I don't know does
that mean my coefficients are busted
though because it doesn't seem like that
much light should be getting in there I
wonder if my summation so if we look at
that diffuse map build is you know is
it's is that actually using incorrect
values right and I don't know so we
should probably look at what these
actually are it looks like a standard
cosine fall-off curve right and it's
clamped so it should be something that
for the most part is exactly what you
would expect so let's let me just go
into that build a few slight Maps and
take a look at what some of these light
maps actually are right because I just
want to see if those values make sense
to me because I don't I don't really
know my intuition is I'm a little
confused about why a cosine fall-off
filter on our incoming light would
produce such a bright value for a flat
known amount getting shoved in there
right that that's the thing that's
that's making me confused and it's
possible that it's correct I don't know
that it's wrong but I just don't know
that it's right either and so I want to
investigate a little so if I run this
here and and I go to the full cast so
here's where we're doing what we're
doing I just want to go to the solution
itself here there we go we got tons of
threads right now I'm gonna go to the
solution here and I just want to look
and see
for the for the diffuse map itself which
is this diffuse wait map here I just
want to look and see what kinds of
values are in here so here's a
particular entry into the diffuse map
it's zero zero right and here's like the
examples of the values this is kind of
hard to read isn't it so I mean I guess
what you can see is the fault it like
there is a lot of one values in here
like if you just look at the fall-off
it's like one point nine point six right
and that's so so yeah I mean that does
make a fair bit of sense I guess
if we're actually looking at what the
transmission should be I'm trying to
think if this is wrong or right but so
the amount of light that's bounced off
of this thing properly summed over the
hemisphere I mean is that actually
correct
I guess one way to look at it would be
if we assume that we only had one light
yeah so I think there is a fundamental
misunderstanding here perhaps by me I
think we might want to look at just let
me just work through an example for my
own edification I'm gonna get the
drawing tablet here and let me just see
because I'm not convinced that actually
I'm not convinced that we've actually
got this equation right for the
transmission and I I just want to look
because I've never looked at it quite
this way before where we're actually
doing as a filter
you
so what we've got here is if you look at
what's coming in I want to just see what
the example would be in the case where
we've got a single light source that's
getting applied to one of our diffuse
maps right so we effectively have a
specular map that we're computing so
this is like the input right and then we
have the diffuse map that we're
outputting and this is like the output
right and so if we have a single pixel
light source so you know there's a
single direction that hits this light
right then inside the diffuse map what
we're gonna have is this light if it's
directly on the diffuse map here is
gonna say well alright for any given
pixel I'm gonna sum the hemisphere area
in here which you know probably looks
like something like this right and only
one of those pixels actually has any
data in it so even if my coefficient is
one for that pixel well I know it's not
gonna get any brighter so I'm just gonna
write it in there right
so the outgoing transmitted the outgoing
transmittance for whichever pixel I was
looking at which you know in this case
would have a one-to-one correspondence
here this one will just get Fulbright
and this one will get like slightly less
right right around it right
um so in the case of a single light
source it seems correct and I guess the
interesting thing there is I think we
sort of have at least a little bit of
verification that that was true because
in the case where we were only filling
in one direction the filter worked just
fine so now the question is well what if
we actually have two so let's suppose we
have two lights one here and one here
and now we want to know what this would
be it's gonna be this one plus this one
times like 0.9 right so it's gonna be
they're gonna be pretty close and the
question is is that correct
right I mean is this what we expect to
see so what's actually happening here
well if we have a surface and this right
here this diffuse map is basically
asking how much light is leaving the
surface at this point right I'm sorry
in this direction so if we assume that
this here corresponds to this right oh
wait so there's at least there's at
least one bug here which is that we're
not using the reflection are we
so we're we're doing one thing wrong
aren't we here which is that we're
computing the transmission as if both of
these are the same and that's not right
so okay so interest okay okay okay okay
so the first things first here's our
surface normal right and if we're
talking about producing a thing that
says we want to be able to sample you
know these kind of rays from whatever
our surface normal is and then we want
the diffuse map to tell us what
direction things were going off in right
then if we're talking about these
directions it seems like we need to talk
about the transmittance function as
being actually doing the bounce right
because if we were like well you know
here's here's this direction here in
this direction here we're actually just
taking the inner product of these two
but we want to actually take the inner
product of if we're looking in this
direction we want this thing to bounce
out this way and we want to take the
inner product of the reflection right so
that's kind of a bug right but in
addition we're also not taking into
account the incoming cosine so the thing
that comes in from this angle for
example should have already been
directionally co-signed away I believe
and it's not being so we've got two bugs
I think the first bug is that the
incoming light Direction needs to get
co-signed by whatever the incidence on
the normal is and I guess I'm not sure
how to do that because we don't have a
normal in this case I mean am I wrong
with that
because since this is a light map I
guess the problem is since this is a
this is a light probe right it's a thing
that's sitting in space that's just like
sending out rays in different directions
and all it knows is it saw a particular
amount of light coming in here right so
I guess the problem unless I'm missing
something is how would you compute the
hemisphere oh but that's okay because
you're doing it now you're trying to
compute as if you had a hemisphere for
the normal so you do know what the
normal is you do know what the normal is
and so what you're doing is you're
taking the inner product of each of
these right and saying we're gonna
assume that this much light bounces out
along the normal to the surface based on
the incoming here that seems right right
am I totally wrong on that I'm not sure
but right think about that for a second
so what we're actually doing is
pretending we have a surface and we're
saying let's suppose we have a surface
that was passing through and this was
the normal and all of this stuff right
so all of this stuff is now not
considered and that's correct because
that would happen with this inner
product and all of the stuff in here is
considered and it's gonna be considered
based on how much light would bounce out
in this direction and that I guess is
the incoming light it bounces out here
and then presumably that's just the
inner product of these two for Lamberson
anyway which is what we're doing so I
guess this is so I'm I'm recently
comfortable with that right and I guess
we would just say well if all of this
light actually wasn't coming in from all
of these directions it would actually be
fairly bright probably I would assume
but that actually does look correct I
mean that that looks like what it should
be I'm not sure that there's I'm not
seeing anything weird about that right
it looks pretty good or does it
I'm gonna go with ya I mean I don't see
anything particularly weird there that
looks pretty much right to me so I don't
see a lot of error with that and then
when we're actually doing our lighting
sampling I guess that is one thing I'm
not sure about here let me just take a
look at that see bathroom I don't really
remember exactly how we process the
light once we sampled it so you can see
here where we were doing like our Texel
fetches and we you know combine them we
have a couple din ways we tried
combining them but either way you know
we're doing a fetch and we're combining
our light sources and once we actually
get that value back I guess what I would
say is you know you look at the sample
lighting here we're pulling out things
from the octahedral map so you can see
us doing that here we blend them
together and I guess once we get that
sort of back we're not accounting for
the bounce off of this surface so I do
think we're missing a cosine term here I
could be wrong about that but if you
think about what's going on in this
sampling we just have a thing that's
like how much light is would be leaving
in the direction of this you know in
this probe in this particular direction
right or I shouldn't say how much is
leaving this is how much is incident on
this hemisphere right with this
particular normal and so if we want to
know how much light bounces off of that
we would have to actually take into
account the direction we're looking
we'd have to actually modulate it by I
mean like yeah I don't know we'd have to
actually Mott we'd have to modulate it
right by by the cosine of that angle I
would think this is really tricky and
the reason is because it's hard for me
to really wrap my head around what it is
we're storing in this map right so maybe
I have to work through the entire
sampling so let's see what would we do
if let's suppose we've got an actual
surface we're trying to sample so I have
a surface here's the normal I'm looking
in this direction right so here's my eye
oh I should say eyes because yeah I mean
I've got two eyes so the eyes are
looking in this direction and then so we
want to know right we're trying to
produce like a lobe
so most lighting right would look like
something like this or something like
that right so we're producing a fair
amount of light coming from this
direction and less from other directions
and so on and so forth right so we're
trying to figure out what the light is
in this direction and so we go to our
light probe and we say oh hello mr.
probe right tell me what that same
direction is for you and we're gonna use
that value and pretend that that's how
much light is coming in here right but
if that's how much light but we have a
couple different things right that's how
much light is coming in this direction
but we also want to know all of these
other directions right so the specular
probe would have told us that but we
want kind of a summation of cosine
curves around this guy for you know the
Hemisphere as well I guess sampling you
know if we were to sample the specular
map a bunch of times with cosine
fall-off that's what we would get but
what we're trying to do here I guess is
approximate what happens
with this equation and so for diffuse
lighting I guess what we're trying to
say is well what's the average outgoing
so we are actually trying to roll that
into our precalc
right so that would mean we actually
want to roll in how much bounce is out
in a particular direction for or how
much is generally radiated out from the
surface and that radiates that radiative
transfer there is going to be based on
the actual reflection amount for each of
the incomings right so once we have that
and we want to sample that from
somewhere I mean it is generally true
that it should it should less should
exit depending on where if you're
looking flat at it you should get more
right is that actually true I mean not
really because if you assume that it's
radiating light evenly in all directions
then it's only the initial bounce that
takes the little bit of light away and
then it's just scattering in all
directions that's the point
but I also guess that in this case you
would say well as the light comes out at
you you would be losing some where's Don
Mitchell when you need him
probably researching a space program
that's usually what he's doing so yeah
I'm just not sure I'm not sure about
this this is one of those things that I
find really difficult I wish I was
better with lighting equations because I
think what we would need to do here is
actually write out the equation for what
we would be doing if we were actually
sampling the entire thing correctly and
then we need to see how we make our
diffuse map as close as possible to what
that would actually be
right and I'm just not sure I'm just not
sure what those coefficients should be
like in this in this particular piece of
code here right I just don't really know
like this is taking out that initial
amount the bounce
so the bounce footprint the fit this
part so the size of the actual like
micro surface off of which the light
bounces that's that initial cosine term
so that's like that's the cosine of the
angle here but I don't know if there's
an end we're summing all of those up so
we're taking into account for each
incoming light direction we're taking
into account the footprint the micro
surfers footprint that it bounces off of
but what I'm just not sure of is then
when we go to sample it do with an with
an actual surface do we actually need to
take into account anything about that
angle and I just don't know because it's
not really doing the right thing I mean
I'm not sure how to state this in
another way but we're taking a map that
was computed by taking a summation of
the incoming light source with the
cosine footprint for some direction and
then we've got a surface normal like
this that then bounces light and we're
then saying well okay
actually should do this exactly right so
we're taking then a view direction and
we're bouncing like we're saying okay
this direction and this direction are
the same or they're close to the same
because it's octahedral map so it's not
gonna be exact but we're interpolating
to get it and so we're gonna take all of
what that incident light was here and
assume that that is what you would be
getting right it's assuming that that's
what light was coming in here
and that's not correct oh oh
so but the only reason it's not correct
is because we're using this direction
and not this if we were actually using
this it would be correct for a Lamberson
surface so actually actually he says
maybe all we really needed to do was say
this part here actually should just be
the normal so like the r-value here
should actually just be this right so
that is what we get for diffuse lighting
which is what we were sampling from a
diffuse map it actually should be that
meaning it should look at the normal not
the reflection vector because the
reflection vector is not what the
diffuse map actually captures right the
specular map captures that let me go
ahead and change back here so that would
also mean you know let me go ahead and
let me just run the test sphere or the
test cast through here there we go so
that would also explain where we're
getting sort of some weird lookups in
there I should run the tester actually
too so if we actually look at what's
happening where's my
test cast that looks like the test cast
is still doing this nonsense there we go
so that should be more correct in terms
of diffuse lighting right and and let's
let's actually try the tester because
that's the one that actually has the
directionality to it so the test cast is
not really correct for this test we want
we want this there we go
and that's that's what we would expect
now so I think that's right and that's
all good unfortunately this gives us
really no insight into our other problem
now it's worth noting that we should
send down both maps right like we should
send down the other map as well because
the other map is it would be good for
specular sampling so we could add some
reflection in there which we probably
want to do at some point but now you can
kind of see if we're just sampling based
on the normal now it removes that
directionality which is what we would
expect so I'm not that's why I was like
uncomfortable that before it's like yeah
duh like if you're trying to sample a
diffuse map you can't use a reflection
vector because how you couldn't possibly
have computed what that should be into a
diffuse map because you would have need
to known the normal of the surface first
which we wouldn't have known so since we
know now it's like oh right we're trying
ample diffuse so you sampled by the
normal that all seems reasonable okay
unfortunately that doesn't really give
us much information about what I was
actually wondering which is is the other
thing correct where our transfer PB s
here right and again it sort of seems
like it must be I don't know like I'm
still a little nervous about it but I
guess it just means if you have that
much actual incoming light in your
environment you're okay I don't know if
that's really true I feel like it
probably means that there's like maybe
the fact that
it might be a light fall-off issue you
know would be the other possibility so
one of the things I guess I'm not sure
about is where does fall-off come in to
this right and so when we're looking at
surface-to-surface transmission the
raycasting itself kind of does fall off
in a sense because if you're looking at
how many rays could possibly hit like a
light source that is accounted for in
the Ray casting so it may be that
actually this is what you would expect
right I'm just not sure and so one thing
I let me just make sure I mean let me do
a couple of tests to make sure that it's
even plausibly right what if I I should
be able to reduce this number down to
something that doesn't get super bright
right and and that is so
so you know I don't know I don't know
what to make of that I'm also not sure I
understand why this is still showing
some reasonable amount of lighting and
yet everything in our world is dark so
that that seems a little wrong doesn't
it I mean wouldn't you say oh no you
know what that is because we clamp our
lighting down to get better an edge
interpolation so that's all right so I
guess I'm gonna go with that seems okay
honestly so let's let's assume that
that's not an error and let's try to get
this thing working so if we get rid of
this then I'm assuming our immediate
problem is just that our transfer PPS is
code is kind of garbage and you know we
end up in a in a ridiculous like we're
pumping way too much light into there we
know we turned off the moon color so in
theory we should not so there's the moon
color right we know in theory we
shouldn't be pushing any in here so
basically what we're looking at here is
this path through the code now at least
in theory when we look at what's getting
summed here so you look at the the
transfer PPS that transfer PPS is is
getting done in here so in theory anyway
if we just got rid of this I don't know
what this light fall-off is there for
probably old school code where we were
actually passing that into the voxel if
we just get rid of this we should get no
lighting right I mean in other words
we're initializing the value to zero so
we should get no lighting in the case
where we nerf that because all of the
lighting should be coming from this path
right and if we take a look at the moon
color thing and I turn that back on well
this would probably be too bright at
this point but if I turn back on the
moon color we should be able to like get
the moon color
filter it back in there at a reasonable
rate right so here's the moon color
right and let's take a look at what's
going on with that so it currently looks
busted like it looks like it's writing
to the wrong location or something I
mean you know what I'm saying
so maybe let's just start with the moon
color and figure out because that's just
coming from a direction that's not
getting sampled so let's try to pull
that together better if I go over here
and look at what's happening with the
moon color we have a moon P which is
basically saying where is the moon and
in this case you know the moon is it
looks like just straight above us just Z
up directly Z up right and so if we take
a look here what's going on we expect to
see our get octahedral offset of the
negative emission direction so the
emission direction here is this this is
the look up here so that's saying all
right here's the REA direction and it's
I guess it wants to say what's coming
back from so I hit a point I want to
know what the emission is for the light
probe in that area so that makes sense
and then we're saying well we want to
know what the negative of that was right
because we need the negative of that to
figure out where we're gonna put the the
light that we see in this direction
right because we're saying that's the
the way we were looking so that seems
correct right I may not see anything
weird about that and I guess what I
would say is this equation just kind of
looks wrong to me the emission direction
here this this is the look direction so
the emission direction I think this
needed to get negated first of all
because we're actually doing a dot with
the moon and we say moon direction we
actually have one so I think this code
is just kind of busted yeah that's more
what we would expect this code is kind
of busted and wants to look at what the
direction to the moon would be I would
think so we probably want to do is
something more like this I would say
like the moon
should have a moon direction it's a
directional light source right so I
would say we probably want to take some
direction whatever that is and maybe
that direction is you know something
like a little bit of an
over-the-shoulder kind of a feel so
let's say that it would be something
like that
maybe I don't know something like this
and then what we would want to do is say
well we know the moon direction and we
know what direction we were looking
right so what we'd like to do is take
the inner product of those two so we've
got moon direction and emission
direction and again we don't want the
emission direction we want the negative
of that because this direction we're
looking times the moon color get rid of
that to do and that would give us a more
proper use of the moon I think oops all
right probe sample P equals moon P Oh
interesting so that's how we were doing
that before that makes sense so probe
sample P is done with what that's not
even a thing that we get but we use here
so that's that should just be in here
it's like right
I get rid of these for now cuz I don't
really know what I'm gonna I can put in
my looks fishy tests if I'm trying to
look for something fishy again later but
so I'm not sure why this is so slow but
I assume it's just because we're still
running the raycasting right which I
said is expensive and then we're also
doing the diffuse so that seems right so
now if I say all right how bright is the
moonlight and the moonlight is like that
I don't know why it was times three
probably cuz we had dimmer lights before
just see what we get here so we'll just
put that right at around the ambient
floor and that seems reasonable right I
mean I don't know if we'd actually want
the moonlight to be that bright but
seems reasonable
so maybe a little darker and so that's
good that just means our lighting is at
least somewhat stable there so we can
pump and ambient into it and it's okay
now I'm not sure why we're getting like
that's a little weird right so there's a
little bit of a weird darkening that's
happening here and oh I know why it's
hitting the light source interesting and
we can see a little bit of flicker so we
know we're actually sampling the
moonlight so yeah all right you know
looks okay and so now let's see if we
can actually start to push some actual
lights through this so here's us getting
where we sample the light from here's
the normal here's our reference color
which is just whatever the surface we
were bouncing off of was and here's the
emission level of that thing and so then
we want to do some we want to see
whether or not this thing was emissive
or not right so this is the the fall-off
bit here so the 1 minus emission and
then we just go like okay take the
emission direction and the probe sample
normal that's how much of the fall-off
we're gonna have for emissive I guess
and you can see us actually using that
here so it's it's this is basically a
linear blend right between those two
well it's not really labeling but sort
of is
so I think that all just works out I
mean that seems all correct to me not
sir sample D is already the emission
direction so I'm not sure what sample D
would be used for here if I'm looking at
it it just looks all of this stuff looks
a little questionable so Rea dot and
that's correct that's where we hit
that's the normal the surface we hit
sample D is is or we already have that
right sample D is just the emission
direction so that that doesn't really
make any sense I'm not sure what yeah so
so let's think about this so we're we've
hit a surface and at that surface we
want to know what the emission direction
was from there so this actually is not
right anyway this was just supposed to
be a mission direction right because
we're supposed to say at this point with
this normal what would you have bounced
in this direction
pretty sure right and the answer in this
case would be that you would just bounce
it would it doesn't actually matter
right meaning you wouldn't care because
they're all the immersion so you would
just say you're gonna get this much no
matter what direction you're looking
right I want to say I mean am I wrong
about that is it should just be whatever
the diffuse map says at that point you
shouldn't actually need the emission
direction again this is where I'd like
Tom Mitchell Don help us oh well
you can't hear us so yeah that my only
question there is do is you know I'm
going to continue passing this down but
I don't actually know that I don't know
that there's anywhere in the equations
for what we're doing right now to
actually have that happen right so when
we do compute voxel irradiance at and we
say P and n here we want to go like
outgoing right so which direction were
actually looking at we're trying to look
at and we're pretty much not we we're
not probably going to use this so if we
take a look at what's going on here
we're gonna need to do this computation
exactly the way that would be done and
you can see us doing it here we're
looking up the voxel information we
don't actually want to do this are any
more so I'm pretty sure this is exactly
analogous to the other case where we
just want to we just want to know in the
normal direction what is that map give
us this is not what we want what we
actually want to be doing is sampling
our other map right we want to be
sampling the the actual texture map here
and and that's what we want to be
outputting so so this part is incorrect
and the weird part to me and the reason
this is a little confusing now is that
this should actually give us back this
must be wrong this code must be busted
because this should always be giving us
back a lot less light than the diffuse
map would so if all we've got is
speculative bounce around here I would
think that that would produce totally
like way less light but the opposite
appears to be true so I don't know what
to make of that
so we're gonna have to step through this
could probably figure what the heck's
going on because that doesn't really
make any sense it should be reducing low
amounts of light but instead it's
reducing super high amounts of light
right like those are all really
highlight values you know I'm saying so
what's up what is up with that
because everything I would think should
indicate that we should be getting a lot
less light into this thing
and instead we're getting a lot more
light into this thing I guess one
question would be do we ever clear this
thing properly I assume we do but it's
just weird that we're getting any light
at all we should be getting really low
amounts of light because you without the
diffused summation in there we should
only be able to get light sources if we
actually bounce directly towards them
and so there should be a lot less light
because diffuse surfaces are things that
help lightly whole environment so we
shouldn't be get at yeah so that's
pretty bizarre and I do wonder if our
compute voxel irradiance at function is
kind of busted I don't really know
so let's take these things out sort of
one by one if I go to the computer a
Tian's function and just stuff it to
produce something that's just a flat
light like so my first question would be
is a flat light going to still have
these errors because if it was then it's
not actually our light sampling it's
some other aspect right all right so I
guess I'll basically say that that is
somewhat surprising
I guess the reason for that is because
the emission interesting so we're
actually still getting the lighting
because the emission if you hit an
emitter it's going to put emission into
the system and if you hit anything else
it's gonna put Bounce lighting into the
system and so in this particular case
that turns out actually giving you some
lighting right which is real weird
and so I guess that's just giving you a
single bounce light with no movement of
the light throughout the scene looks
kind of cool though I can tell you that
hmm hmm I say so let me go ahead and
lock knock out the moon light one more
time
and just like
[Music]
yeah there we go right
interesting so that wasn't exactly what
I expected to see I was kind of
expecting to see something more related
to like like yeah that's just very
surprising but I guess that makes sense
because we do have single bounce
lighting now that's actually computing
all this lighting properly so it's like
oh you can see this light on this
surface and all that stuff and like wow
okay it's better than I thought it would
be so I moonlight back in that all looks
right and so the only question is now
why is our compute voxel irradiance
kicking back such ridiculous values or
is it just that we're overloading the
light somehow because it's specular I'm
just I'm assuming it's got to just be a
bug and it's busted but I don't really
know so let's take a look at what we're
doing here we're doing a mapping of the
sample position as you can see here
we're taking wherever the sample is
taking the corner out of it doing a off
set off set by the center oh no that's
right so we're multiplying by the
inverse dim first and then doing an
offset to get us back to the center
we're then doing a floor I'll be honest
that doesn't look right to me so the
inverse Fox will sell dim this puts us
into yeah so if we're flooring if we're
flooring I feel like that should have
been a plus let me just double-check
something Oh
double check duh that's not gonna do
nothing we're not running this path yeah
so it's a little confusing the in voxel
seldom there
something's a little a little iffy
because this is saying all right where
are we relative to the corner now which
cell are we in right and if we floored
that that would just give us which cell
that we're in but we're subtracting the
oh five to offset by the center which by
the way looks wrong there too
let me let me let me wait to see cuz
we're doing that in here right so we're
doing that in here too I assume for our
box I yeah so in here where we do our
vox uvw so to produce our vox I we just
use the floor and so I wonder if that's
actually wrong then because we've got I
wonder if that point five should
actually be in there here so the vox r
LP when we actually do the you know we
actually do this this stuff here right i
wonder if this should actually be a - i
wonder if this guy should actually have
this in here
let's see just want to see what happens
ooh
oh wait sorry
that's the Vox in total dim times the
relative P so that's actually giving you
the the full map inside so I didn't
really want to do that so I guess I
actually want it here yeah so now you
can kind of see that the light is
actually centered properly so I guess
that was actually a bug in the shader
code because remember this the light was
lit was looking like I was off to the
side a little bit so we we actually were
looking it up incorrectly there which
was a screw-up on my part right so this
is actually what it should look like and
now you can kind of see yeah now already
you know it's it's so fascinating to
write like we didn't do any work to make
moonlight not show up downstairs but the
reason it's not showing up is because
there's actually a floor above us so it
can't find the moon which is pretty cool
I don't know how we're gonna maintain
that all the time because there's places
now if you go there's nothing above it
so I don't know that that's a long-term
solution like so here the moonlight is
getting in because there's nothing above
this right and furthermore it's a little
weird because there's like shadow over
here because there is something above it
there right so we kind of need to put
ceilings on things if we wanted that to
actually happen but it's kind of cool
right and this is why simulation is
always interesting because you get
natural interesting effects out of it
and it's just pretty interesting alright
so I guess you know this was actually
correct and we just hadn't thought it
through in our actual shader so this is
right and you can see us doing it here
so we're doing the inbox seldom here and
then subtracting that so that we end up
with our actual indices so here we look
up our box index ru VW's the f
Kord - the actual read multiple
occasions of this thing which that all
seems right to me
that should come out okay then we're
actually doing a lookup of the voxel by
taking all of the different offsets same
as we were doing right and so we have
all those cell pointers now then we're
just saying are ain't let's go ahead and
get the octahedral offset lerp the
results together and off we go well this
is wrong is it or no it's nuts nuts not
so this is always between between X's so
that's fine and then this is wise and
the disease the interior so you know I
guess I'm not sure what's but what's
broken about that
let me try knocking it down a little bit
just so we can see if it's a lighting
amount problem and just so I can play
with those levels a little bit so let me
go ahead and run that here's it running
and even with it knocked down quite a
bit it still gets out of hand so it
feels like there must be something wrong
with that computation but you know I
don't I don't know obviously
so here's with it with it knocked down
dramatically
right and let me go ahead and knock it
up a little bit just to see where the
explosion point is just for my
edification so you can see it's like
really just behaving it really kind of
feeds back on itself right even at very
low levels which I would assume just
means mostly that we've forgotten some
kind of damping right like we're not
thinking about this in terms of photons
per second flowing through this thing
the way we were thinking about it before
and we're not using a diffuse map yet so
obviously that's a difference but just
where this why you would need to damp
this down all the way to like basically
at least there I might even be a little
lower than there in order to get that to
not feedback is confusing right
like that still feeds back right all the
way out so we at least know what it is
that's happening right it is the fact
that light is our lighting equation we
have this when we first did it to when
we first at our distributor we had
exactly the same problem right and you
can see like it gets these like oh I got
transferred a certain amount of light
and that light was too much or whatever
right and so we're not conceiving of the
photons per second anymore the way that
we should like we've got an issue with
how that's being looked at right and I'm
gonna have to remember kind of how we
conceptualize that to make sure that we
don't have that problem so when we talk
about how many photons per second are
flowing through something I guess the
problem is that that thing well we're
always blending towards a value though
so that's a little weird so yeah I mean
the interesting thing is we're always
blending towards a new photons per
second value right so what would cause
that value to creep upward like that
because we it should only be summing the
light probe stuff so somehow this
produces values that are like growing
which I'm not sure why it would so so
what's weirder to me still is that this
produces values that are growing when
you turn this on but the version that
actually adds the emission in does not
right so this doesn't actually do that
so let me think about what this ref
fall-off thing is here so first of all I
want to
that emission is always less than or
equal to one like I don't actually want
to ever see anything where that's not
the case
good so if a mission is always owned you
know these are all on right just to make
sure yeah so we know that the ref fall
off if the emissions on ref fall off
will be zero so it won't do anything
here and it will just add in the
emission times whatever the emitter
actually was doing so assuming that the
emission is off so assuming emission is
zero then this will not add anything and
so we're talking about only the sample n
times the emission direction so we're
talking about a fall-off curve that's
based on you know whatever the about the
the thing that we're point that's
pointing at us and what direction we
were actually trying to do an outgoing
vector of now I'm not sure that fall-off
actually is supposed to be there because
that should have already been accounted
for by the diffuse map so once we switch
to the diffuse map I'm not sure that
actually supposed to be there but if we
look at what happens with it it can only
reduce the transmission right it can
only knock it down from what it was so
then when we multiply by here that
that's never gonna add energy into the
system it can only subtract it so we
really are just taking whatever the
light sample is and multiplying it by
the sample ref color and the sample ref
color in theory should never be above
one either I guess we could assert that
too
and in fact maybe we should
so maybe I should just do this and run
it alright so I just want to make sure
there was no funny business so when we
get to compute voxel irradiance ATS the
question is how is this taking a sum of
photons per second transmission values
and getting a number that's actually
higher than any of the other photon
changes and it's not necessarily doing
that I mean it could be that the light
is bouncing around now it is doing that
because we've seen what the emission
values are and they're not that so how
is it doing that
how is it producing values that are
going above the actual emission that
we're introducing
so let's try this I'm curious to know so
let's suppose we set the emission value
to zero everywhere right so we just said
look there's no emission ever so the
moonlight is all you get right that's it
so here we are hopping around right and
we're just moonlight so we're able to
convict moonlight around now if we want
to right but that's all and so then we
go into this voxel radiance function and
I delete the damping so there's just
moonlight around what happens with just
that so all right this should give us a
way to debug this program right because
here's what's happening nothing were
ever injecting into this system ever is
now gonna be above the moon color which
is super low right it's this at maximum
point one brightness so if we're
injecting such little light into the
system how can something that only
returns the lerp of at most that value
return something greater than that value
how is that happening do you see what
I'm saying like to me that says we
definitely have a bug here right like
something really bad is happening
and I just don't know where so there's a
couple places that this could be
happening one it could be happening
inside the octahedral map by sampling
something erroneous so let's say we've
got like an off error these are some
tile bogus values I'm not sure
and we're sampling off the end of this
thing and grabbing garbage or something
like that we could have a math bug where
this lerp is not right but basically
what I want to find out is how are we
getting back values that are outside
this range so what am I try doing is I'm
going to try asserting here
that my results are is let's say less
than or equal to 0.5
and so I just want to say like look
let's just say we know that this should
never really be able to have produced
anything even close to that
so just just that should stop at some
point right
and it should return it should like halt
there because it has to right and maybe
if we just do this in debug mode then we
can go look at what the various cells
are that we were sampling see what the
actual values are and how the heck we
got a value that high right
so again just trying to figure out where
my where my mistake is by paring it down
so go ahead and run it don't want to
actually break here
and I'm just waiting for the assertion
which will be a while because this is
the super slow path oops there we go and
so now we can look at the results we see
that we've got absurdly high values in
here and so let's just see what we've
got for our cell values right so here's
our cells we've got yet here's all of
ourselves
right so here's the light color and I
guess I forgot to look at which one
we're looking at so we're looking at
five one right in here so T YT X so oops
where did that go
did I where did cells go did I delete it
somehow
how's weird so anyway inside cells let's
look here so we're looking at five one
so there's no light coming in there
maybe I should just pull these out to
something easier for me to look at but
you know what I can do it this way so
let me look up zero zero zero light c-51
so there's the light here there's the
light there so like all of this is
nothing so there must just be one of
these that's weird
all right so am I missing something like
we've got what's what the heck all right
that would do it so yeah not great so
this is garbage right here is basically
what we're looking at not our finest
hour to say the least
not sure why but let's take a look at
how this was being calculated so our
blending coefficients are complete
garbage so let's take a look at our F
chord here so our F chord is supposed to
be well let's let's start even before
that so sample P is is where we're going
like that's what we're supposed to be
looking at so here's the location in the
world that we want to look at and our
solution Vox min corner that's the basis
of the voxel right so this thing is
definitely inside the voxel well
actually I don't know how large the
voxel is so maybe not but at least point
being it's not on the let it's not on
the min side of the voxel so when we
produce our F chord we should get
something centered around this thing
times the Inbox seldom what is that in
Vox seldom by the way all right so it's
you know 0.7 is the cell dim so that's
actually gonna give us back the index
into the voxel and I don't know how big
the voxel is actually oh I see what the
problem is this thing is outside the
voxel so we just don't because our voxel
ends up getting clamped no but that
doesn't no that's wrong cuz this should
still that we don't account for that
anywhere so it's fine right because we
should still have produced in there
value here all right so let's just hold
on
bear with me for one second let's just
do this computation slightly differently
so we can look at all the parts so let's
do our like our base scored here so this
would be like the the basis there right
and this way we can say like look this
is where we're looking up and here's how
far away from the thing we're looking up
we actually are right and go ahead and
make sure that works now also we should
double-check the one in the Z bias
shader for this so if we if you look at
what happens inside the Z bias program I
just want to make sure this one's
working well is right as well so when we
floor Vox I yeah so we do a floor and
then we just do a subtract of these two
things right which is what you would
expect so actually like when you look
here
in fact when you look here at this I'm
not sure why we're even doing this this
way why is this getting multiplied out
so I think that was most of our only
problem with that was that was probably
our only pray this this is the actual
equation right we just had the length in
there for no reason but I think that's
all we actually need and let's just
verify that real quick
mm how do I get this thing - oh this is
the release mode all right wait no it's
not it's not release mode I guess this
is just having trouble with threading
run - there please what's going on there
we go
um so let me just look at the UV the w
values now so that's more what we expect
right okay so that sure seemed like our
problem why this is always at 0.5 I
don't know but probably because we have
particular Heights for off the ground
that our things are or whatever but
that's separate you so anyway
[Music]
I still think we want to look at this
code a little more carefully but I'm
gonna run it now just to see what the
result is because we are out of time for
today and tomorrow we can start looking
at it more carefully but I just want to
see what's going on here all right so
good now we're actually in a state where
things make a lot more sense that's what
I would have expected to see when we are
not injecting any emission in the system
and it's just the moonlight right and so
now if I turn the emission back on
hopefully we get something at least a
little more sane so that we can be in a
better debugging you know stronger
debugging situation starting tomorrow
okay so that's like way more sane right
I mean that looks a lot more like a
reasonable lighting computation
and the transfer is now much more stable
right okay so our biggest problem now is
just that we're not actually using a
diffuse map for sampling the lighting
for our bounced Lighting's so it's all
kind of garbage and so the biggest thing
we kind of need to do there is just make
sure we can actually get a you know an
actual emissive an actual diffuse map
for that but otherwise I think we're in
good shape now this is this is nice and
stable it's actually not that slow looks
like we've got a bug here with our cell
lookup though but I'm not sure why so
probably can't look at these values so
say we've got a bug here for lookups
where our clamped is not doing the right
thing let me just take a look
I mean that looks like it should be
fairly protected so I'm not sure why
we're getting that bug but it could be
also that maybe this the TYT x values
could be bogus as well not 100% sure
about that either way oops yeah so we're
gonna need to like let's go to briefed
QX I think that's it for today we'll
pick that up tomorrow at that point what
there we go
freak out what the heck - type
the UI is drawn at Z levels less than
negative nine nine nine
so to disable the lighting just compare
the Z to negative nine nine nine can you
quickly re-enable it so you just mean
you you want me to do in here you're
talking about this like you want a thing
inside the you want to think inside here
that's like where's our world position
I don't actually know where our world
position is role-p so you're saying
world P you want this I'm not sure if
that's what you mean
is this what we're talking about
which is fine although I'm not sure I
would want to actually do it that way in
for the in the long run right I mean I'm
gonna want to actually turn it off for
reals so that's not something I would
want to leave in there but but sure why
not
I think mostly yeah I mean if we look at
the light propagation work here so I
mean the thing that that I would want to
know you know if we were gonna play
around this I'd want to know which one
of these two passes is our actual hot
spot now so if we take a look at this
time function what I'd actually want to
do here is split this in half so in our
probably want to break it into two
blocks time to block like in here so I
would probably want to do like you know
it's timed block or you know what I
don't even really need to do that I
guess I think I can just do this mmm
well so this is hard because we'd have
to actually start at each time but all
right so maybe this this is a little
janky but we'll see behind previous
declaration oh come on
all right I'm I don't care that it hides
the previous declaration is the thing
like I don't care about that even a
little bit but yeah oh you know what I
can do here's what I can do I'll just
time full cast that's what I'll do
so if you want to look at the time I'm
assuming the reason you wanted the
profile on is because you just wanted to
see the where the time is being spent
because obviously we need to know that
for later but so if we look in here you
just
so you can kind of see like a little bit
of a breakdown here and you don't know
how accurate that really is timing wise
so it's probably not too far off from
the truth so if you take a look here you
can see that a significant amount of
time is spent in just the filtering of
the maps so you know full cast is
definitely the big loser presumably
because of the filters the sampling step
so I'm guessing and I could be wrong but
I'm guessing that this disaster here is
most of the issue I don't know for sure
but just assuming that we actually told
the optimizer like hey man don't bother
with any of that just use like one of
these things so that we weren't looking
up all that stuff I'm assuming then the
it would get a little bit more generous
or maybe not
is that really true that this is not a
particularly expensive part of the
process this is going to throw our
numbers off a lot but
seems like you can't actually do
insertions of those which makes sense
because I guess they change how the
numbering scheme goes but what just
happened
so how are we getting a error on that
why would we not be able to have a timed
function inside here oh because we call
it too many times right yeah all right
now that's fair it's just gonna we're
not even have enough room in the debug
log to store how many times they call it
cuz we call it so many times
fair enough so alright not great not
great so I'm not sure how to really get
too much information out of that other
than to just say well we can get rid of
the call to it right and see how bad
that is so we could just say here look
the light sample that comes back here is
just going to be some other thing so you
know it's like something like this so
like yeah the light sample zoe's some
stupid light in this case so if we have
the ability to switch between those like
so we could flick them on and off and
see what the optimizer produces for
those two cases so here's what we would
get if we're running with a light source
just stuffed in there so without compute
voxel irradiance at causing any problems
for us in theory and actually the
difference isn't that much so that's
pretty interesting to me because that
actually means so it's just the raycast
cost and the sampling the light is the
light if the result is not a big deal
which is interesting to me I mean if
that's the case that's actually great
because the raycast is a lot easier for
us to fix
so turning it on I mean it does get
slower but not nearly as slower as I
would have thought so I guess that's
really kind of encouraging because it
means the hardest thing to speed up
which is this is actually and we can do
it wide so that'll speed it up a little
but it means that the actual raycast
is the thing that's causing the most
pain and that's good actually because
that's the thing we probably have the
most control over to a certain extent
just in terms of like what we can speed
up and what we can't that's what I'd say
about that so yeah I guess that leaves
us in a pretty good place
I think you mentioned before that you
don't like regular expressions can you
elaborate on why yeah it's pretty simple
I just think that the syntax is so
cryptic and weird that it just doesn't
make a lot of sense to me why you would
standardize on this like the amount of
time it takes me to type in something I
want to find in my text is not a huge
deal so why not just give me a more
straightforward easy to read thing that
I can do like why do I want to remember
what like brackets dot slash three star
brackets star plus means or something
right when you could have just made it
an actual reasonable language to read
because the number of times that I type
these in is pretty low and the number of
times I have to sit there going oh wait
so what's the right way to say that I do
want a space but I don't want to this
you know just like it's just a bad it's
just bad design in my opinion you know
it's just it's just bad design I don't
think there's anything wrong with making
a subset of the parsable things that we
know we can accelerate so that part's
okay but just the syntax is just garbage
in my opinion and it should be replaced
if we have a probe in your wall and that
probe is updated with a color sample at
the wall the next frame the wall might
be brighter due to the new probe color
couldn't this spiral up to very bright
probe has to prevent this so the ideas
no absent bugs like the one that we had
there the ideas that no it wouldn't and
the reason for that is because the probe
is measuring how much light flow there
is through that probe and in theory when
it samples a wall it can only get some
convex combination of light flowing
through that from that wall right and so
at no point should we ever be able to
actually produce more flowing light than
we ever introduced into the system to
begin with right the whole point is
if we just measure the light flow how
much light is flowing through that area
it shouldn't ever be able to be more
than the maximum amount of light that we
ever have flowing that we inject right
so what we want to avoid is accumulating
light but we try not to do that by just
always measuring the amount of light
flowing right so we try not to store up
light in a way that can accumulate over
time instead we try to just blend
towards a value that is how much light
is flowing now
and so in hopefully no we don't have the
situation that you're talking about
that's the idea anyway it's post food
time the post coming she's surveying the
landscape you can't see her but she's
looking around she's decided the bowl is
safe to approach and now the food food
conching will begin
you
all right I think we're all good here
actually I guess I can leave that in
that was not really causing a problem I
guess also what's our rate bundle count
like if we change the rate bundle
countdown how many seer sample
directions are there how much does it
cost to do one just curious
so just doing one raycast is actually
fairly inexpensive right looks like and
then you really get the run time
dominated by filtering that diffuse map
so that's pretty interesting we need to
change to actually using the diffuse map
in practice but interesting it's kind of
fun you you end up like with that slow
of an update rate you end up kind of
like dropping light behind you as you go
which is kind of fun so what is that
like what about if it was for
so the game actually runs not that
poorly with you know reasonable indirect
lighting already I mean I'm pretty happy
with where this is at right I think
we're gonna be able to tighten this down
it's looking pretty cool and honestly at
this point like I think we're within
striking distance we have a lot of
finishing work to do but yeah it's it's
it's not looking too bad
so I also wonder can we now turn our
bias towards the light source back on I
don't really know that we want this I'm
still not sure if this is a good idea or
a bad idea but I'm just curious what so
what's going on here I so okay we've got
a start-up situation I'm not gonna end
for the day I want to I want to see what
that bug is so we should since we can
just start the code now I should be able
to run it in debug mode get whatever the
out-of-bounds error is here and look at
what the problem is so you know those
are not great values of T Y and T X you
know if we're gonna go ahead and be
completely honest about it so what's the
problem here so we've got all 0 R so
we're the octahedral offs that we're
asking for is R and we're getting back
garbage so what's up with that
I don't actually know how to lets
provoke this so here's get octahedral
offset and we're passing zero in here
right and so I just want to know is it
because of like the floor function is
broken or something let's find out what
we're getting
so if Durr is all zeros we're saying we
get garbage back is that correct
and neglected to actually look at the
function okay so here we are get actor
he to offset I'm cold I'm gonna cold set
this to 0 0 0 there so unfortunately
this is still multi-threaded as well so
that's a bit of an issue so I guess we
really just want to set the breakpoint
there and not there all right so Dirk
came in as zero zero zero well didn't
come in 0 we said 2 zero zero zero
what's the result
yep it's garbage so what's the UV the UV
is garbage
so it's this octahedral from unit vector
that's messed up
so if you pass all zeros to octahedral
from unit vector you get a garbage value
out so let's find out what that is so
here's the doctor he get here is
octahedral from unit vector and somehow
if this is all zeros then you get that
oh well it's cuz of that oh but actually
we yeah so how do you pass zero zero
zero to something now that I think about
it that makes perfect sense that can't
be right
because you're not allowed to actually
do that so this one norm yeah hmm
so I'm not sure how we would avoid that
but presumably what we would want to do
is avoid that earlier on right because
yeah this is not defined for that and
what we're that's coming from is if you
have to sample the light direction and
the light Direction is is ill-defined
right so let me just go take a look at
that so if we do a get octahedral offset
and we look at where that's actually
happening so the normals should never be
able to do that so we're really looking
at yeah yeah so
[Music]
this emission direction here would be
the problem and basically like this
right here would be would be an issue if
point on light and Ray origin are the
same you know I'm saying that would be
an issue and so we need some way of
avoiding that actual eventualities so I
guess we would just have to I don't know
what we would do in that case
but that would be our issue so the aprox
nas here that we're doing you know I
don't know like where we do this select
and we're selecting from the original
result value it's almost like this thing
needs to be filled with real values at
that point right
you don't want nas you want like a procs
you want like a procs normal or you know
up or something right so you want that I
think so in here you basically say like
initialize this to the up Vector or
something right and that way if you try
to normalize something and fail you hand
at the up Vector back instead of nothing
right so presumably you want something
like that now of course I don't actually
know where this particular ones coming
from so I'm going to try and find out
right
[Music]
what are we looking at here emission
direction so how are we getting when do
look well that's weird so the emission
direction here though is not zeros did I
forget to get rid of the zero or
something no so how how is that
producing an all zero value there do we
actually have a surface normal that's
zero so how are we getting a surface
normal that's zero what's up with that
so the sample end that we're passing
down here is wrong
it's a probe sample n right so we said
we hit a surface but we didn't fill in
any normal for that surface apparently
right which is total garbage so how did
that happen because that's like never
supposed to happen and I'm not sure like
I'm not sure what we did there but we
did something wrong so our raycast here
is busted at least a little bit because
the where we actually do our computation
here it looks like the hit normal for
one of the lanes that said it actually
got hit did not produce an a valid
normal right so there's something busted
there I'm not sure what but that's yeah
that's what that is in the case where we
hit something emissive it should still
give us a normal right like we should
never actually have that case and
yeah
it looks like we must have a bug in this
code somewhere in order to produce that
because we're generating this normal so
it should never actually be the case
that one of these things that did hit so
basically this hit normal this code
should always produce a valid normal if
you ever had a valid hit and it's not
doing that so this code is probably
garbage
[Music]
so if the ex mask why mask Zi mask are
not properly computed so this is an X
less than Y and X less than Z this is a
y less than X y less than Z so I mean I
guess part of the problem is if this hit
directly no one would trigger right so
probably this sort of thing has to be
like a less than or equal to for
somebody right trying to think of how
that would work but let's suppose that
all these values are zero if all these
values is zero then none of this comes
back right you know what I mean
it's like so when values are equal you
have a problem if you change them all to
great so if you have a case where yeah I
mean I guess what I'd say is what you
probably want is something like this if
X is less than or equal to Y X is less
than you go to Z so in the in the case
where all three are equal if if not all
three things are equal then one of these
things would work normally right no
that's not true
so
how about that so if all three things
are equal X will fire so it will get set
and Y will not write because this one
won't work if just two of them are equal
then there's either x and y are equal x
and z or y&amp;z if x and y are equal then
this one will trigger and this one won't
right if exit and obviously this one
won't if x and z are equal then this one
will trigger and this one won't right
and if y and z are equal then well i
guess i said that a little bit wrong so
if x and y are equal but z is not then
this should fail and this should succeed
i'm not thinking about this correctly
so in the case where X and y are equal
but Z is not then you would get a
situation here I guess which would
develop so okay so I'm just bear with me
for a second I want to see if this
corrects that particular problem yeah so
I do think I want to put in oppression
start on this today but so I'm not sure
about that one there right like I'm not
sure that really did the trick
but basically what we need to do is make
sure that this always produces a normal
that has only one one value right no
matter what
yeah so okay so this is the version that
biases towards the lights as well so the
first direction is always probing the
light source and you know I'm not sure
again like that this really makes a
difference so we may just take that out
looking at it here if I go back to the
full cast routine
the only difference right is you put
this guy up here or you don't right so
if you look at the difference between
the two
they're pretty minimal so I mean it
could be busted right as well so I don't
actually know but I'm tempted to say we
don't care about that very much so we
may just not need to do that we'll see
but yeah I don't I don't know that it
matters much right actually I guess if
it doesn't matter I'd probably leave it
this way so you just sample the right
bundle and then in here you would just
you know get rid of this
so we just do something like that and
and there we go so I'll probably just
leave it like that for now because it
doesn't seem like that's necessary and
the way that the lighting works I think
it seems like we'll be alright so we'll
see I think that biasing might not be
necessary all right so I think we're all
right so I'm gonna go ahead and close it
down I got a question how do you share
memory across functions in shared
library I know the user could allocate
memory and pass that to the library but
I was wondering how to have the library
allocate memory for internal use the
library users are having to know
anything about it
I guess what I would say is I generally
don't think that's a good idea but
that's beside the point if it's just
you're asking how do I do it you should
be able to do what you said so when you
say I tried using global that gets
initialized in the DLL main with virtual
Alec but later when I call a function
the library exports the global 0 that
sounds like there's a you have a
different problem because you should be
able to do that right that should
actually work so you probably have a
different problem happening because you
should be allowed to in DLL main do a
virtual a lock and store that and then
use it so something else is probably
happening but you should be able to do
what you're talking about
alright let's go ahead and wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me for an
episode of hand made here oh it's my
pleasure coding with you as always I
pretty excited with how that lighting is
turning out I think we've only got a
little bit more of a push before we've
got a really snazzy lighting system
looking there in this one unlike first
one we wrote
this one works for purpose of lighting
everywhere in the whole game at all
times - which is pretty great so I'm
really excited to kind of push forward
on that a little bit more as usual if
you want to follow along with the series
at home you can always pre-order the
game on handmade hero organic comes with
a source code so you can do your own
experiments with it maybe you can figure
out some ways to optimize our lighting
before I get to it tomorrow but I will
be back here tomorrow to start looking
at exactly that so hopes to you're back
here for that until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see on the
Internet take it easy everybody