hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here sure we code a complete game live
on stream we stopped yesterday just at
the point where we need to do debugging
of our import code and we also need one
other thing which is we wanted to have a
way of taking checksums of our input
files so we would know we could have a
little bit more than just the date to go
on now here's a problem I don't have a
strong opinion on what we should
implement for a checksum anything will
do but some things are significantly
better than others right like you know
the better of the hash we use the more
resilient it is to collisions the less
likely it is to do something spurious
and who knows what that would actually
end up looking like in practice
certainly it's not that hard if
something is refusing to import because
it thinks she's already changed we can
always just have a button that's like
force it to him for it this file and
it'll reemployed the file so the the
cost of a hash collision in our world is
pretty low and so it's not really very
important for us to get this right there
are cases where it's way more important
to get it right and it costs a lot if
you get it wrong code signing and those
sorts of things would be places where
you really don't want to have collisions
be easy to generate because attackers
could smooth things we don't have
attackers in this case anyone can import
a file if they want to and this is not
true this hash is not being used to
prevent anything it's actually just
being used as a minor speed-up to
prevent files from being reloaded if
they don't have to so it's a very low
weight a very low risk endeavor for us
in any hash will really do the question
is which hash should we do and I don't
know so let's take a spin around the
internet and see if I say let's get a
fast good file hash what will it say
when a good analysis extremely fashion
non credere non cryptographic hash well
that sounds pretty good but how is it in
terms of resiliency you know I don't
know let's see let's see here
well it's got a quality metric right
who knows
that seems nice it's fast all right
let's take a look at what the code looks
like here's a C++ version
it's really just a document that says
what the algorithm is by the way so it
looks like it's one that uses the some
tables which isn't necessarily a bad
thing
a lot of CRC's use tables like for
example the original crc32 stuff they
use those tables not sure if they have
them in here somewhere
a lot of the original CRC stuff CRC
stuff used tables
and it looks like they do a lot of
rotations and rounding your what wit
this must be round like a cryptographic
round not actually rounding right
what is this round like they're not in
float right so round and must be there
around like their cryptographic round I
don't know where that actually is
defined here it is
yeah so it's basically just a rotation
and then it picks the prime so it is a
cryptographic round it does a particular
rotation and then does pick that one of
the primes that it wants
is there so is there a is there just a
description of the algorithm somewhere
do we get that or is that not on the
table for some reason
I don't know why there isn't just a
thing that's out here we go well no
thought I was gonna find an article
let's take out murmur as well because
murmur I've used before and I like
better it's pretty simple it's a pretty
basic hash right
very very simple doesn't use a table and
looks like the quality at least by
whatever these benchmarks however it's
measuring it which I don't really know
how they're actually measuring these in
terms of hash qualities
it looks like the quality would be
similar we don't care too much about the
peak speed there and this the simplicity
would be nice now like I said xx hash
might have a simpler version it would be
I wish they had a simple thing here that
explained the algorithm right cuz here's
like that's here's the example it's like
here's a very simple explanation of the
algorithm so you know I don't
necessarily want something when I'm just
initially looking and trying to
understand what something's doing I
don't want to look at highly optimized
code that who knows what it's got in
there and that's you know what I mean
like I don't want to look at all that
stuff I just want a simple explanation
what's it doing so I can see you know
basically what's going on you can see
here that this is it's basically got
like a while loop that does 32 bits at a
time and you know we could just make it
so that it's always 32 bits at a time if
we wanted to we could just enforce that
so we could literally make the murmur
hash be like that big and then it just
does that final bit there right so this
is a really straightforward hash which I
think makes it may be a better choice
because I don't want something
complicated I just want something
reasonable it would be nice if we had a
64 bit murmur hash because we can store
64 bits and work with 64 bits on a 64
bit machine really easily and so
I kind of would have preferred that let
me see if there's a 64-bit murmur - yeah
so this one wasn't 64 right yeah so this
was a 32 only so basically this hash
here is a is a 64-bit version of murmur
that seems maybe like a little bit
better going here
so here you can see again very very
simple right
I like the looks of this one a lot
better they've got a lot of stuff in
here right you can see them again much
like the XX hash stuff what are the
problems with these is they always like
expand them out because they're trying
to be performant you know and so if I
just want to look at something simple
sometimes you end up in a bad situation
where you've got to wade through a bunch
of that code I don't really care about
but it's you know it's to be expected
either way that seems pretty good to me
let me go forward there I didn't know it
was no space in between those two so I
feel like that's pretty reasonable
murmur hash three might be what we want
to do and here's the like you know the
thing that I wanted which was the
description so basically it says here's
a thing like a mixer it's pretty basic
right I multiply by a constant I rotate
I multiply by another constant I take
the XOR right so this this thing that
I've this thing that I've prepared here
which is K this is not the same as H so
I've got two values I'm tracking so I
update my K with a multiplier rotation
to multiply I XOR my hash value I
assumed H as a hash value I don't really
know yet i XOR my H value with my K
which is the thing that is updating I
rotate that and then I do a multiply and
an ADD here with constants right and so
it looks like K is what I'm reading in H
is the hash value right pretty if that's
really how simple it is right I like I
just like how basic that is
and then the finalizar this is if I want
a 32-bit value this is if I want a
64-bit value right I don't know what
these values are supposed to be I don't
know if these are supposed to be 64-bit
or not let me see here yeah so those are
six so this is assuming these are 64-bit
so here's the 64-bit finalizar because
you couldn't shift something down
thirty-three bits if it wasn't right it
would just be zero so these are 64-bit
values or at least H is I don't know if
K is expected to also be 64 bits or not
so I think that's pretty easy for us to
do and I'm just gonna go ahead and do it
yeah that seems good and we could if we
want to make it easier on ourselves
again just like Pat it out but I guess
even that's something we'd probably be
pretty privileged to handle this the end
of it
pretty pretty straightforward to handle
the end of it special as well so let's
just take a look and again the reason
that I'm just going by stuff on the web
for this is that I just don't have any
cryptographic skills whatsoever so I
don't really have the ability to
evaluate cryptographic things I can't
like look at two hash functions and tell
you which one I think will be more
collision resistant I just can't so I
have to go buy other people's public
testing and attestation that's the best
I can do if I was doing something that
was really cryptographically important
which is not something I ever do I would
probably have to take the time to learn
a lot more in numerical analysis so that
I could start to have an opinion about
things like that I just don't have that
knowledge at all so I have to trust
other experts who say that things are
stronger or weaker and off you go
murmur hash is supposed to be a fast
hash that's just reasonable for files it
is not a particularly strong hash by
comparison to like a cryptogram a real
cryptographic hash like or one this
'never cryptographic views like catch
expunged or the or even like a sha not
the SI
jae-won before I destitute - or whatever
I don't think the murmur hash is meant
to compete with those it's supposed to
be more of a high-speed hash for doing
things like this just checking files
where you assume that there's no
attacker who's trying to thwart you so
I'm pretty sure murmur hash is not
something you would ever use in a
cryptographic setting a cryptography
person is welcome to correct me if there
any watching but I'm pretty sure that
that's it's not that kind of hash but
it's a fine hash for file things to the
best of my knowledge and we don't want
to waste a lot of time doing hashing so
that's why I want to go with this so if
I go into the shared code here
so this is murmur hash three in
particular that we're doing or and I say
based on here because you know I'm not
really gonna test it thoroughly or make
sure that I even comply with what they
were doing and so I don't want to say
this is a murmur hash because it might
not quite be a murmur hash it might be
our own secret nan thing that isn't
really a murmur hash all right so what I
want to do here is I want to make a hash
update like we had before and that's
just a little function that's gonna do
this right so it's going to be a K and
an H right and it's gonna it's gonna
return the H value to us because K
doesn't get stored K is read in so what
I want to do here is I want to say okay
Kate x equals c1 we got to know what ooh
that's not good
we're gonna have to find out what that
constant is oh but that's fine then we
want to do rotate left and we have if I
remember correct correct Leah rotate
left here right the problem is we don't
have a rotate left for 64-bit and so
we're gonna have to look
I don't actually know if there is one I
assume Intel put one in but even if they
didn't you can see here how we
implemented the rotate left in terms of
regular operations right ones that
didn't require a Rowell so I can do one
of these rotate left's with 64-bit if I
wanted to by just doing that right so
here where we do the the knock out of
the value we would just have to do like
okay I you know it's it's not an 31
anymore because this is 31 was there
because it's 32 minus 1 right so we
would want to do and 63 here right to
make sure that we are clipping off
whatever the sign is if there is a sign
so what we want to do here is make sure
we what we want to do here is make sure
that we can do a 64-bit one I don't
actually know if we can there may be a
rot el 64 of some kind I'm not sure so
we'll have to check that out if there
isn't then what we can do is again just
do probably the same thing here and it
should just work right because we're all
we're doing is doing two shifts to put
the things in the right position then or
them together that's all that the
rotation would be doing anyway so it
should be fine
now I think we should be able to use our
search oops
hopefully to find some of these things
if they exist so that we can just call
the compiler intrinsic if there is one
let's find out yeah remember if there
isn't
so we know oops no we know it's there
should be an underscore rod L so let's
go ahead and try to get that yes you can
see it here so let's try and find like
is there rod L 64 yep so you can see
here there's a rod L 64 so that means
that I think in theory anyway we should
be able to just stick a 64 on here and
have it I don't actually know if that's
true but hopefully it is so it looks
like it's s 64 is what it's actually I'm
sorry int is what it's actually wanting
for the amount and now I think about it
that's you know what that's actually we
don't need a 64 bit shift value right
you can only shift by up to 64 bits
anyway so this could be an 8-bit integer
for all we care about right it's just
not relevant so I don't know why I did
that I was just kind of not thinking
particularly hard about it okay so if we
want to do a rotate left as we were
instructed to do we can do that in 64
bits it's no big deal so we want to
rotate by the r1 constant which again
we're gonna have to find out what they
actually want because these constants
are important so we've got a c1 an r1 in
a c2 that's gonna affect our K then we
want to do the XOR here with whatever we
mixed up we are now going to do the XOR
that's the end of our use of K now we're
going to do further operations on the
hash value itself so this is like the
hash update step again we're rotating
left we're rotating the hash left and
we're using the same constant for the
rotation as we did with our K we then do
a multiply step so there's an m1 plus an
n1 there and then finally we return the
new H value and so this is sort of an in
fact I can probably should put this here
because it's
really this is the part that we're using
this part is just gonna read this this
part has nothing to do with the murder
hash this is just the part that's gonna
iterate over the buffer calling hash
update right so then we have the the
finalization step and the finalization
step is going to be the 64-bit one here
now I don't know why they chose to
include the constants here and not here
I'm not quite sure about that and so
we'll have to read a little bit further
on and find out what I don't really know
what that yeah I don't know why they
chose to have some of the constants and
not others so you know it's probably
because they just wanted to write this
once and they didn't want to write it
each time for 32-bit 64-bit whatever bit
right
that's probably why because they're
gonna use different constants for the
two so that's probably just wanted to
condense I'm guessing but either way
this is what we wanted to hear it's
basically just like two constants and a
bunch of XOR shifts which is fine
so murmur hash oops
murmur hash finalized so this is just
gonna take the hash value it doesn't use
any new information in fact I might put
the H at the front so it's base like you
always pass the hash value and the K is
like the new thing that you're feeding
in right so now if I want to generate
the finalization I just have to do my
this is an XOR shift and I'm doing the
same exercise right so we shift down
through three I don't remember if this
has to be you 64 but I'm gonna make sure
it is just to make sure there's no
weirdness there and then in between each
of these we need to multiply by the
constants so I'm gonna put those in here
and again those also I think have to
potentially I don't know how smart the
compiler is in terms of understanding
that these are supposed to be 64 bits
you could also do that I believe I think
not for sure but I believe that that
tells it hey look make it a 64 bit on
sign please and you can just stick that
I mean to anything when you actually
care there so I just wanted to make sure
that was operating in 64-bit and then we
will turn it so that gives us what we
need to do our murmur hash what I don't
know is where to get these classes from
because now we have to know what they
are specific to the to the particular
routine and so to find that I'm gonna
just go look at the actual code because
obviously if they improves that's the
issues if they implemented it then
they're gonna have to put the costs in
somewhere so let's take a look so here's
the murmur hash stuff I assume I can
just go in here to murmur hash 3 dot H
look and see what we've got
so we are trying to do a 64-bit one I
don't see the 64-bit one though which
isn't great hmm okay
so it looks like they have their rod el
64 right doing the same thing we were
doing
so this looks like the part that we just
implemented so there's their finalizar
for 64-bit we did not do the 32-bit
finalizar because you don't care about
it here's their 32-bit operation and you
can see they've defined the constants
for the 32-bit version so the thing that
makes you nervous tears it looks like
they don't really have a 64-bit only
version it looks like they only do 128
here right I don't know what to make of
that I'm not sure why they did that
because if you look they actually do to
64-bit mixing steps at the end so
they're they're actually mixing these
together here I'm not sure what the deal
is with that why they do to 128 that's
really strange
so you can see the way they're doing it
you've got what they're doing is they're
doing 128 bits at a time by maintaining
to 64-bit hash values right now I'm
assuming because these are 64-bit if we
want to we can't just use the constants
that for the 64-bit version it because
they're telling us what they are right
so rather than doing 2 and mixing them
together I think we can just extract the
costs we want out into it the way we're
doing it I don't see a lot of reason not
to here's the c1 value right so that's
the one here's the c2 value
so those are the two pieces we need here
try to correct this comment a little bit
so we're not gonna do to it once and mix
them because we just I just I don't even
know why that's the only other thing
they did they must have a good reason I
mean they wrote the hash in the first
place they asked you know what they're
doing but they just don't want to do
that so we can see what we want to see
here here's our here's the make this the
step right and what's particularly odd
about this step and I do not know why
they're doing this is that they're
different right so they've hashed
they're generating a hash value for K -
that's different than the way they're
for H 2 then for it that's different
from H 1 right it uses 27 or 31 uses two
different constants here and so I don't
know why they're doing that
for for subsequent blocks it must have
to do with the fact that they're going
to mix the blocks values together later
using this I guess no that's just for
the tail I don't know why so this right
the h1 plus h2 they must be doing this
because they're doing this part they're
like cross mixing the hash values right
so I don't I really just don't quite get
that which makes me a little nervous I
wish I knew why they were doing that if
we take a look at the original member
hash so here's the the basic one right
it's 15 13 and 5 for those and then it's
you know e 6 5 4 B 6 4 or whatever right
so these are completely different except
for the five five remains so these
shifts are up more which would make
sense because they're 64-bit these are
presumably picked because they're being
mixed together what I don't know is if
we just want to maintain one hash value
which of these would be better or should
there be some third as-yet-unnamed
constants that we should be using here's
okay so in murmur hash - they do have a
64-bit version so what goes on here so
this is a simpler hash actually
and I guess they decided to change it
cuz this is totally different I mean not
totally different but it's quite a bit
different
so I'm not sure what to make of that I
don't quite understand why they wouldn't
have provided a 64-bit version and I
wish there was some explanation in here
but I see nothing that even mentions
that fact and that's a little troubling
I like super fast hash dot CPP um so I
don't know what do you think we should
do maybe we should just ask dear Sirs
which constants would you use if you
were only going to produce a single
64-bit hash value and not try to hash
128 bits at once you know and and and I
don't know so I'm gonna just go with
this mixing step like I said we don't
have a lot of risk here so I'm gonna go
with this mixing step we have our c1 you
have our c2 we just need to know what I
rotate left gonna be so we'll just say
it's 31 okay and then here we've got our
other rotate is 27 so then we just need
our m1 which we know is 5 and our n1
which again this is the part that we
really just don't know
but our n1 is going to be the first
constant because I'm just purely
ignorant Li picking the first mix
because I can right that's it
now as with any of these things and this
is the downside of not knowing any
numerical analysis I have no idea how
good this is right like I have a
literally no idea I know what it's doing
right I can see how it works it's pretty
straightforward the the math that's
going on but what that math actually
accomplishes is totally opaque to me
right
like I wouldn't know if you were to
change this 2 to a 3 what would be like
does it matter right I have no idea
these constants were chosen probably
very specifically to do certain
operations to the bits and put them in
special positions and make them be
dependent on each other in a special way
I have no idea how it's working right
it's a little bit frustrating again the
reason I don't know these things is
because it never actually matters to
code that I write it's usually
sufficient to take someone who has made
a good hash that's relatively well
respected to just take their word for it
it's usually good enough because again
if you just pick something relatively
simple like this you know you can
usually put it in a relatively small
amount of space you don't think about
too much and if the cost of it being bad
isn't that high well it's okay right but
again it's a little bit nerve-racking
because you can see how if let's suppose
we actually really cared how good this
was we would have to go spend a ton of
time trying to figure out exactly how
this thing was working before we could
have any confidence that it works well
at all and of course the supremely
unsatisfying part about all of it as
with anything in cryptography we don't
really know like even the best
cryptographers really don't know how
hard something is to crack right all we
really know is that no one's cracked it
yet right or things like that and so we
don't have
ways of proving things are unbreakable
we don't have ways of proving things our
can't have collisions generated for them
we haven't gotten there yet
I mean that's like cutting-edge stuff
right and so you know it's it's kind of
a supremely unsatisfying thing in its
entirety because a lot of times even the
best people can't really tell you they
might be able to tell you well this
one's weaker than this one because we've
found this many exploits to it or we can
go through these parts of it more easily
and stuff like that but that's it's
right we don't really know much more
than that and we can also evaluate
through in practice if we just take a
bunch of random stuff and feed it
through it how often is it colliding
with small permutations and the data or
stuff like that right we can do some
testing and and that's you know maybe
that's as good as it gets right so again
it's not a very satisfying thing but
luckily for us like I say we don't have
to care we're in the envy about position
of really it doesn't matter and that's
really nice for us because it means we
can't fail too hard and that's really
what you want when you're going into
something cryptographic because if
failure is on the table oh it's it's
it's rough it's nerve-racking okay so
let's start here by creating our results
I want to note here that the seed values
are often passed in that's if we wanted
to get some additional information in
here from outside we still can do that I
don't know that we really care but if we
wanted to we could do that just by
saying something like this right where
we say look if you want to pass in a
seed value go right ahead that will be
the initial state of the hash and then
when we go through and do the hashing
we'll start from there and update as we
go now we know we're gonna have a hash
value that is that result I guess I
don't even do it that way
so what we're pretty much gonna look at
is something that does the hash
finalized at the end by taking what we
get as our last hash value and passing
it through the finalization step that
finalization step again
shifting out the low bits here you know
in a sense so shifting it over and then
xor ring so it's kind of mixing it's
it's mixing in itself through two rounds
of multiplies
I don't know why right I don't know
what's magic about those constants
that's again the thing that we maybe if
if there's a paper on rumor hash we
could go read and find out why but
basically that step it right it's we're
taking the value we're shifting it over
X soaring it in on the bottom shifting
it over X soaring and on the bottom
shifting it over X soaring it in on the
bottom so we're really mixing up those
bottom bits that way and I'm not quite
sure why I don't know if that has
something to do with the fact that we're
less sure about our bottom bits or
something you got me that's what the
numerical analysts to worry about so
anyway when we go to do our checksum
here what we want to do is we want to
read out 64-bit values so what I want to
do first is I just want to find out the
count here
so I want to say look how many 64-bit
values could I do so we know the buffer
has a count and we know that if we
divided that by eight or maybe if I'm
feeling saucy or I could just say sigh
the new 64 so however many of these
we're actually gonna do that's our count
64 and then we've got like a count
that's going to be a byte count so how
many eighths do we have right and that's
gonna be however many there are in the
buffer - the count 64 times the size of
a you 64 so what I'm doing there is
saying look how many packets of 64 bits
can I process right and then how many
eights are left over once I'm done so
that means I can go fast right I can
just say alright let's loop through all
of those
I'm just gonna loop through all of the
64-bit ones that I that I have here and
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
snap a 64-bit pointer to the data and
it's just worth noting here and I maybe
I should make this up to do so on Intel
machines they don't care very much about
alignment anymore
they really just don't I guess they
found that having the lanes move around
was not as big of a deal as it could be
I I really don't know why it used to be
a problem for them and now it doesn't
seem to be but operating on 64's that
are offset it doesn't tend to be a huge
problem anymore it used to be a much
bigger problem so at the moment I'm not
going to care about that but if in the
future we do care about that what we
would want to do there is step two the
first aligned 64-bit boundary and then
just go 64 bits along right so you can
see why that might be important
depending on the platform so we'd have
to see since this is only used in
imports we probably will never care
about it but again it's just worth
putting it to do there because we know
it could be problem mines well put it to
do so that when people are searching the
codebase they can see and maybe it heads
off some problems for them who knows
right I guess I can do this every time I
read one of these things I want to
update the murmur hash right so my
result is going to be a murmur hash
update step where I read in I pass in
the current result and I read in the
next 64-bit value from the data that
gives me a new update when I'm a poveri
end here I need to low
one final 64-bit value to suck up any of
the additional eight parts that I've got
so what I'm gonna do here is make it
residual I'm going to snap a pointer to
the residual I'm just gonna fill it
right with whatever is left so here's
the count eight that's how many bytes
are left over and I'm just gonna say
look copy from at wherever we ended copy
the residual remaining bytes put them
into my 64-bit value that I've got here
and it'll just fill them in now
technically right you might have to
think about which direction you wanted
to go do you want to fill the top bits
in or do you want to fill the bottom
bits in because since it's little endian
you know if you if you look at what
happens to grab a 64-bit value the first
thing goes into the bottom that goes up
it just so happens that doing this copy
would fill in the same order that that
grab would fill so the missing parts are
coming in in the in the right place
right the zeros will be in the right
place on a big endian machine this would
be wrong it would be the wrong round
since we don't actually care however
meaning we're just it's just however we
want to do the residual is how we do it
as long as we do the hash consistently
both times it's okay it should be fine
but it's worth noting that if we were to
run that checksum on a little any
machine and a big endian machine this
would produce potentially different
results right
so basically we don't want to support
big endian machines because I hate the
fact that endianness is still a thing
and we have all little endian machines
in consumer space right now we should
stay that way so I'm just gonna leave it
like this and everyone has a big endian
machine can eat on it so what we want to
do here is finish off that residual by
doing one final murmur half step where
we can pass in again the same format
that we have before but now we're just
going to do that residual this step
obviously only needs to be done if there
was a residual so we can just check the
count eight first and just skip all this
nonsense in the case where there wasn't
any residual this will automatically
skip itself because this first check
will fail so we don't really need to do
anything about that that should be the
entirety of the hash that should give us
back the hash code that we wanted so now
when we import things we should get that
checksum this also means that in the HHA
edit in theory when we produce that
checksum value the source file check
some stuff here we could actually
produce the synthetic checksum for the
file if we really wanted to I don't know
that we really do want to but when we do
the read hav zero and we produce that
synthetic annotation at this part here
we could actually produce the file date
and check some of the v-0 that we read I
don't think it's worth it because I
don't think we we don't really support
updating from a V 0 to V 1 file in a on
demand way so it just doesn't seem like
it would make any difference so I think
we just can leave it the way it is now
but it's nice to have that in here you
way so I think that's it I think that's
everything that we needed there and so
now we should be able to store that
annotation data into the file it should
have the check sums for the files
properly and that should be you know I
think what we want so if we go in and
and start the debugging process now we
should be able to sort of go down the
homestretch here of the art importing
process so here's the game running as it
normally would write with the with the
hero and loading the sprites in and what
I remember us doing is when we we made
his fist be something that is only comes
from imported out our tassets right and
so the question is can we now go ahead
and make the imported art assets work
again and see if we can start testing
that system so if you remember correctly
the way we did that is we said we we
don't import by default you have to
create an HHA that's suitable for
importing and if it sees that there it
will start to use it to import art
assets from the art directory so from
this directory so if I want to do that
what I can do is I can run our HHA edit
routine as you can see there's a -
create on that that - create is the
thing that tells us okay let's make a
new file here that we can use and so we
can make that local HHA and that local
HHA is what's gonna trigger all of the
dynamic loading stuff so if we create
one of those we can also take a look at
it right here's the dump it starts out
with no assets no tags no annotations
nothing right it's a version 1 file and
that's all that's in there is is
literally nothing so if I if I now run
the game we should be able to step
through
our new code and it should actually run
and do stuff and that's what we want to
see here I don't want this nonsense so
I'm gonna get rid of it so what I want
to do is I want to step into here I want
to see us get this path I want to see
this path get hit right and so the file
high watermark is 128 the idea is that
should be the header right and you can
see that it is because there's nothing
in the file so the first place we would
write is right after the header because
nothing in here right allow editing
becomes true which is good and it's our
new default append so HHA 5 is what
we're going to append through to when we
see an asset we don't know where it goes
it's going to go in here ok so then we
come through and we allocate our arrays
we're using our large arrays so we've
got tons of extra space in there to put
new assets in if we want to load them
that's exactly what we want I should
probably put an if here on whether
there's anything to append to because I
mean we don't need to do it but you know
technically even if it's an internal we
don't need space if we're not running an
append mode but you know whatever so if
we come through here now what I'm most
interested in is just this path here
this is the pet that has not been run
yet it's not going to do anything at the
moment unfortunately for uh you know I
forgots another breakpoint that was bad
well we hit an assertion anyway so
that's fine what I was gonna say is I
want to step to that code but then I
realized as soon as I had a 5 as like
wait a minute it's not going to run
because that would that part of the code
here would only run if there were any
assets in the file this is the thing
that like brings in asset information
from the existing file for importing
purposes obviously that's not going to
fly because well I mean for obvious
reasons
there is no
there there are no assets in this local
file so there's no information to pull
in in this case so all right so I can't
debug that path yet I've got to wait
till the next time we load but I can
debug the rest of the path so let's go
ahead and do that now we've got an
assertion here so we can start with this
although I would have liked to have step
through this stuff first but that's okay
we look here and we see we're supposed
to have 13 tags we wrote 208 tags is
that right so that seems bad to say the
least so I'm not sure exactly how that
ended up happening we were supposed to
write 13 tags and we wrote like an
infinity of tags so is that really what
happened there what did what did we do
so when we went to write
[Music]
so I would like to step through that a
little bit more carefully and I think I
can pretty easily so if we look at
what's going on here if I just delete
that local uhha and make a new one I
should just be able to step through that
directly which is what I want to do I
just want to watch this thing go let's
just start there all right so first
thing one knows how many assets do we
have and we want to count our tags so
let's take a look if here's our asset
that we're looping over I'm gonna set a
breakpoint here as well if this is our
asset that we're looping over you can
see inside hsj data it's got the tag
information here it is one tag per in
fact all of these are one tag per right
so the tag count is looking pretty
accurate there so we get 13 tags and 13
assets this could actually be set to a 1
here I won't actually do that well I'll
do that later because I don't want to
stop it bugging so through here I'm
gonna make 13 of everything 13 tags 14
assets 13 annotations not a lot going on
there pretty basic right so then we
create arrays for each of these things
we're gonna start by writing to the
first one here is the source asset if it
doesn't match the file index we don't
write it so we're going to want to stop
when we get to you know this is the same
loop here we're gonna want to stop when
we get to one that actually is is in the
file so if I now look in and check out
the source asset it's got one tag right
so when I come through here oh that's a
problem this is not the right loop it
should be source
right that's just wrong so again I want
to fix this here these nulls are skipped
sorry Mel asset
these are skipped this is otherwise
correct this is the problem this really
wants to use this loop those are the
tags we're trying to copy out so we do
and then you know when when we're done
here
we we should now be able to wrap that up
properly so let's go ahead and run that
should jump down there now after
importing all the pngs let's take a look
13 13 13 13 much better now we can write
out those pieces of information and then
we end so that's all good and you can
see we actually do have the art asset
there that we were interested in so now
I'm gonna close that and I mean I'm
going to bring up tab view again so I'm
gonna go into the bonus pack here I'm
gonna use tab view and I'm gonna say all
right
let's dump local HHA to local top dump
oh right and I'll never you know what we
should just go fix that I type it every
single time you know you'd think so
here's our imported file what you can
see here hopefully just want to
underscore this so this is why I spent
the time on that HHA edit utility this
is just a really nice way for us to see
what's going on
right you know it gives us this nice
debugging visualization right off the
bat I can see that this is set to
unknown should it be I don't think so so
we want to go fix that you know that's
something to do I can sort of see that
at least the checksums and the dates are
set to something right I can look at the
size of the data and see if it makes
sense it's just it gives me a way of
really testing things a little more
deeply than I ever could stepping
through and looking because it's just
hey now we now we kind of have our a
little bit more of a handle on it now
this type unknown is bad news we need to
set that to bitmap so we're still we're
not done yet we want to do a little
better here with that so let's try one
more time at initializing our system
here I'm gonna do a nature to edit
create local data HHA and then what I'd
like to do is I'd like to just go into
the code and find out where we were
supposed to be setting that so that
information if we go to the HHA file
format that information was supposed to
tell us this bitmap sound or font right
it's supposed to give us a clearer
understanding of what this thing was
it's this thing here right and so no
one's setting that right now that's not
getting labeled so what I need to do is
I need to make sure that it is so when
we find that we don't have an HHA or I
guess even when we do we have to make
sure we overwrite it if it was if it in
all cases I think so when we come
through here we need to set that value
so when we when we're creating this part
in addition the tag value so we need the
size the offset
[Music]
you know this this could use the size
too even if it was less so I think we
want to do this here we want to set that
data size down to the asset data size in
all cases we want to just say look if
the data size is greater than the asset
data size or sorry if it's less than the
asset data size then we need to reserve
a new one but then we always truncate to
that size right so I think that's
actually more we want there this one we
need to always set the type and again
that type is just it's all it's saying
is that it was a bitmap because we
wanted to make that a little bit more
explicit it's like it's a bitmap keep
that in mind
right so let's try one more time with
that fixed and let's see if we can get
this thing to look appropriate I'm gonna
go ahead and run here this is doing the
import and remember it's an optimistic
I'll so that should have done the import
and now I should be able to dump that
out and see what it what it shows up as
so if I now open one of these up we can
now see that the bitmap is is actually
correctly reported it's got the correct
size that is how big the tiles were and
[Music]
so this looks pretty good I mean that's
that's good stuff right so I'm pretty
pleased with that so now we can check
the next part of the process the next
part of the process is can we rerun the
game and furthermore if if we make it
through the reload stage will our check
for changes correctly identify that we
do not need to import these files oh and
this part again - this is good we wanted
to know this part so let's see if we get
the right source file name
hande skeleton that is the correct
source file name
we got the sprite sheets going on there
we're gonna get a create the asset index
we're gonna write in this index say
that's what's currently sitting in that
slot oh I meant to look at that my bad
okay
so yeah I think we have now correctly we
do not
well
title screen oh yeah well okay right so
I guess I just check that yeah so we do
not reach and everything seems pretty
good the only problems we have now are I
I'm not seeing the actual asset so I'm
not sure we're actually labeling it
properly so we'll see about that in a
second here
and in fact we kind of note we're
definitely not because there's no tag
these are not tagged as a hand yet right
so we've got to do that as well all
right so we're getting there let's go
ahead and and finish up if I remember
correctly we had sort of this thing
where we searched for the the basic
category right and so we need to set
that basic category where's those tags
that's kind of did sort of a hacked
thing here for temporary testing and we
might as well do that so here's yeah you
can see the tag the tag stuff here so if
we wanted to make the basic category for
these things be hand we would just put
two of them on there so we would do like
reserved tags too and we would do like
this
I don't remember what this was exactly
but it's like that I think so if we
wanted to say as a hand we could do that
we look like this when we actually go to
make the tag the tag buffers here the
difference would be that this is a plus
two so each one gets two tags now and
now if we reran that import that's what
we would get right so let's do it and I
should be able to now go look at well
and there's the there's the whatever it
the little test bitmap there and now
let's see what happens if I run a second
time it's still there so I think we're
in good shape right I mean I think
that's starting to be respectable and if
we now go look up blue angels again
today if we now go look at what's in the
file we should see yeah the basic
categories there as well as face
Direction each one of these should also
now have the information about where it
came for a minute what's a little weird
as I'm not seeing any of that oh yes I
am
there it is it's the from field I'm like
where is that go hand glove Oh - right
oh three and those are correct first
column third row uh so I think that's
all good now yeah and I think for mostly
there the next thing I want to do we've
got that weird it's we're not our ours
and our bees are flipped around we right
so we kind of need
do a Swizzle on the R&amp;B channel when we
import from the PNG so that's a little
bit annoying but we got to do that and
the other thing that we need to do is we
need to think about if we want a down
sample this is a bit annoying and let me
just let me just give you the background
of what the problem is and this is a
place where we kind of want to just say
look we'll we'll do what something
reasonable we don't want to go overboard
on it
mm-hmm so this is
okay so we now have a problem that we
have not had to confront before but we
will have to confront it soon the
problem is that the art assets are made
at 1024 by 1024 by 4 right this is the
width this is the height this is the
bits per pixel it doesn't take a math
savant to know that this is one megabyte
right 1024 x 1024 so if you take one
megabyte and you multiply it by 4 you
get 4 megabytes that means that every
sprite in our game is 4 megabytes of
data right at its source resolution the
resolution of our screen at the moment
is 1920 by 1080 that means that every
sprite in our game is made at a
resolution that would occupy roughly
this much of the screen okay way too big
does this matter for us in terms of
rendering no why doesn't it matter in
terms of rendering it doesn't matter in
terms of rendering because it would be
very simple for us to turn mipmapping
on we could down sample our sprites at
runtime very easily graphics cards can
do this on transfer almost they just do
a quick series of renderers and generate
it there's it's very easy to do all
right
and so we could down sample just in time
and then you know it would first cut it
in half and then cut it in half again
and now that's probably the right size
right so and just to be clear what I'm
talking about there is we don't want to
feed this texture and then render at
this size because the sampling will be
lousy it'll be all crackly and weird and
not properly anti-alias at all right so
we need to do filtering down to sizes
probably down to probably a 256 by 256
right is probably more in the ballpark
of what we want to start with some are
between 128 128 286 somewhere in there
so we could do that the problem we have
is the streaming streaming in four
megabytes for sprite isn't gonna fly
right let's suppose that there are 200
sprites or 300 sprites on the screen
that we need to load well 300 sprites
times 4 megabytes right equals 1.2
gigabytes am i doing that math right
right 1.2 gigabytes is way beyond the
streaming limit in any reasonable amount
of time of older series drives right now
if you're an m2 if you're an nvme like
m2 drive or MVM
PCI like a PCIe Drive no problem that
takes like one second right this is like
a second or less so no big deal
nvme X point whatever like any of these
advanced drive technologies SSD drive
technologies on the fast buses 1.2
gigabytes is not they don't even care
right it's no big deal it would only
take a second to stream that in and
you're off and running right so we'd be
able to startup go and it would just be
fine
but for older drives this is probably
gonna be too much right so if you take a
look I'm just trying to think of like
what an example would be in terms of a
minimum platform what is like HDD read
speed right now for example pop it up on
here
[Music]
so here we go
so we're talking about something like
let's say worst case is like 50
megabytes per second or even a hundred
megabytes per second so at a hundred
megabytes per second we're looking at
twelve seconds right to load in this
thing it's a little scary it's just it's
a little scary and we know we don't ever
need it to be that big we're not gonna
draw sprites at that size pretty much
ever right
the only things we'd be drawing if those
sides are not our sprites they're like
special case stuff like the title screen
you know I'm saying so I think
fundamentally speaking we want to
perhaps downsample our artwork right off
the bat like we may want to have the
size of our artwork because let's
suppose that instead of this we did
everything at 512 by 512 by 4 right
so we reduce each of these dimensions by
two well then it's one megabyte per and
if it's one megabyte per suddenly this
looks a lot better right this now looks
like three hundred Meg's which is
something like you know three seconds at
a hundred megabytes a second or six
seconds right at at fifty
so this is starting to look a lot better
especially because we're streaming so we
can bring those things in more gradually
it's not as bad furthermore if we reduce
it down again same thing right if 256 by
256 by 4 that is even better
that's 286 k right that's that's a 1/4
megabyte and it further reduces this
into a fraction of a second right at a
reasonable harddrive rate we're looking
at less than a second to stream in 300
of them
these aren't perfect measurements hard
drives have trouble with seeking so it's
worth noting that this is not really
necessarily fair the seek times can be
pretty bad depending on the the
situations SSD drives the situation gets
a lot better 550 megabytes a second and
up write 5 to 50 megabytes second is for
SSDs not on a good bus they're they're
not on like a PCIe lanes this is for
like SATA right so if we assume that it
only gets better from there and that a
lot of times people wouldn't be running
them on these then you know you can see
that to justify 26 is a really easy
sweet spot to be in we probably won't
hit any trouble I would imagine 512 by
512 is probably okay 1024 by 1024 by 4 I
just don't think it's feasible what we
would have to do is try to compress that
down run it through like a PNG style
compressor or something if we wanted
lossless or DX T texture compression if
we wanted lossy and just reduce the size
that way but what we would have to do
something right look we have to do
something
either we compress the textures someway
lossy or lossless to get it down for
from what it is or or more or we down
sample and down sampling just seems like
a good thing to start with at least a
512 by $5 for because it just doesn't
make any sense
to store things at 10 20 right 1024 now
why did I have the art done at 1024 high
temperature sorry that it never hurts to
over sample on the artwork who knows in
four years we might want to do the 8k
remaster of handmade hero and all the
drives are nvme were drives and they
read at 5 gigabytes a second and we want
all our sprites to be 1024 by 1024 by 4
because it just looks crispy er and
nicer with those beautiful pixels right
so you never want to have your artists
do the sprites at exactly the resolution
that you're gonna use you wanted to have
them do the sprites at a resolution
higher than that and downsample unless
you need them to be finicky about every
individual pixel right like if you're
doing pixel art they've got to know what
the resolution is but if you're doing
can drawn like full painted bitmap stuff
you wanna up res because you're gonna
want higher quality art assets in the
future almost certainly if you ever do a
remaster it's pretty free for the artist
to just set the bitmap size in Photoshop
to be twice as large as they were gonna
use or four times as large and with the
exception of the fact that Photoshop
tends to be way too slow because it's
extremely unoptimized other than that it
tends to be fine so that's all I want to
say so I kind of feel like we should
take our art assets here and maybe
downsample them because of that loading
pressure and like I said the only other
option would be to use some kind of some
other kind of compression I'm just not
sure I want to go that route because
again it over complicates the path at
this point we can certainly do more with
compression later on if we want to I
just don't know that now is the time for
that so I'm kind of thinking that
I just really I don't know that I wanna
I don't know that I want to dive into
compression at this point right uh so
taking a look at this what we need to do
if we wanted to make that happen is once
we identify one of these one of these
cells as having something in it when we
get to this part right and we're and
we're going to when we're going to
actually use the image what we can do is
produce a down sampled version right at
that time and there's a lot of different
ways that we can down sample I will
probably pick a box filter for now but
there are other ways of sampling and it
really depends on what you're trying to
do there's a lot of different filters I
even have my own filter that I've made
that I use for certain purposes and you
can play around with this stuff a lot
it's not worth going into too much
detail right now but I just want to
bring that up so let's go ahead and take
a look at how that would work if there's
something in the tile I want basically a
down sample and flip I know I need to
reverse the R&amp;B channels on a pinch on a
ping so what I want to do here is I want
to load in the RG and B and a I want to
down sample them and then I want to
write them out and the other thing that
I want to do and I don't really know
which way this it's a little frustrating
I don't necessarily know what the format
in ping implies I'm not quite sure
whether I should pre multiply the alpha
again or whether the Alpha whether the
PNG has the alpha pre multiplet or not
fortunately for me when we step through
in the debugger
should be obvious whether it's primo
flight or not because if we ever see a
color value higher than the Alpha value
88 premultiplied right because if it's
premultiplied it should line up directly
with the Alpha right the brightest you
can be is the Alpha Channel is that time
we always a case not necessarily it may
be that they were using some kind of
mechanic or that we didn't understand
and so the gamma curve is putting the
[Music]
the RGB above the Alpha because it's
gamma corrected after the pre-multiply I
mean I know this I could make up a
situation in which that wouldn't be true
but for the most part we should not be
seeing very high color values and very
low alpha values that's a clear telltale
sign that they are not pre multiplied if
we never see a color value higher than
an alpha value that's a pretty good
indication that they are P multiplied I
think that's the best I can give you at
the moment all right so let's take a
look we now would need we would need
when we come in here we've got a temper
Reena what I would like to do is you
know if we've got this pixel buffer here
we already do copy out into the pixel
buffer right that's what this thing's
doing and so I guess I guess we could
just push a second one of those on
that's our that's our downscale buffer
we could down sample in place if we
wanted to though and maybe we just
should
there's really no harm in it
yeah so we could just downsample in
place as well so maybe we'll just do
that so anyway when we look here and we
we take a look what's going on I'm just
gonna write a down sample in place
because why not so what if down sample
in place looks like is once we've copied
these things out into this pixel buffer
what I can do is I can just loop over
the size of the downsampled pixel buffer
right so what I would do here is say
okay my X is 0 my X is less than the
half tiled in plus plus X loop over the
rows and what you can see here is for
every tile I'm just gonna go through and
I'm gonna make a quarter sized version
of it so I'm gonna go through half of
everything I would have gone through in
the normal case okay so in the when I go
to actually produce a pixel what I want
to do here is I want to read four pixels
right and I want to filter them together
and then write them out so what I want
to do is say okay let's get my source
pixels out of here I can if I want to
actually do sort of the the row based
version here and help what that would
look like I say okay let's take
probably do it like this as well and now
I think about two if we want this thing
to be a block I would actually need it
to be compacted so now I think about it
I actually do need it to be smaller
right I need it to be like one smaller
then well no I can still write it in
place though so never mind
no I can still write it in place it
doesn't matter all right
um sue if I take the pixel buffer that's
the destination this is where the image
currently exists if I take the pixel
buffer and then I use the pixel buffer
and the pixel buffer plus one row like
right one entire X stride so this is
basically like the the tile dimension I
guess could actually do it this way so
here's the first row of the tile here's
the second row of the tile and here's
again the first row that I'm writing out
I'm writing it out so what I can do is I
can now say like you know read pixel and
I think we've got I believe actually
have a thing that's like linear like
upconvert kind of thing don't actually
know where it is
I thought we have I mean we we've got
those linear eyes but I don't know if we
have actually ones that unpack there it
is so here if I want to unpack the value
I can call rgba unpack right and that
will get me back a v4 so I can load all
my pixels in like so
so let's load in two pixels from the
first row and two pixels from the second
row so this gives me four pixels
it gives me two from the first row two
from the second row and then I can
choose to do with those what I wish so
if we assume these were stored in srgb
what I can do here is I can actually do
sort of an sRGB convert I can move them
to linear and then move them back so if
I want to do the blend in the proper
space I can choose to do that which
seems like a good idea to me looking at
what happens when I do the unpack so if
I come down here you can see the unpack
leaves them in the 255 space so let me
go to a linearize here so if I do if I
do these two operations that's my
compliment that would allow me to that
would allow me to basically do the
blending in a somewhat sRGB corrected
space remember this is approximate
because we just use square so none
squares it's not real srgb so if I want
to do these unpacks here that would
unpack my pixels I could then go ahead
and change my pixels to be linearized
just by passing them all through
and so when I do this srgb to linear one
the other thing could do is swap them I
don't know where that function is so
that's just this we could make that a
shared function let's just grab that out
and put that share
let's put it down to pack Oh and
actually but we wouldn't really need to
call it would be because we could also
use the inverse unpacking interesting
interesting so really what we could do
here is say well alright when we do RGB
a unpack right that's gonna unpack the
are the the bottom channel into our
right which is actually what we want so
we don't need to swap them because the
unpack we'll swap them for us right then
when we do the packing we just have to
make sure that we pack them back into
the correct place because right now it's
ours in the bottom channel its RGB a
right and then when we pack it back out
we just want to make sure we pack it
back out in BGR a pack so really this
probably will just work hopefully he
says not really knowing but once we
produce the color value hopefully that
works it might who knows so we unpack
linearise blend which we haven't done
yet and then pack that should give us a
downsampled and color corrected version
I'm sorry and color swapped our R&amp;B
version of what we want right so to do
that we just need a way to blend these
let's just start with the obvious the
blended color can just be all these
things added together right so all we're
doing here is saying switch them all
together divide by four is take the
average it's a simple box filter it's
the bit most basic filter you can
possibly apply it has really no
characteristics that are gonna create
spurious artifacts but it tends to blur
things maybe a little more than you
would like right
that's its property because it doesn't
look at any wider area of the image to
see whether this was a like a hard edge
or something that it should try to
preserve it just smooches down probably
will be fine for our proces we will see
here's the down sample though down
something by 2x once we do that I guess
we can do this part first actually
once we down stapled by 2x when we come
through here if the tile dim stuff is
going to be incorrect right and so
everything that was using tile dim
should be like sprite dim so I'm just
gonna say sprite dims bright dim sprite
dim so all that stuff is gonna be based
on the sprite dim so here I'm just gonna
say all right after we do that the
sprite dimension is the half tile
dimension right so now it's down
sampling what are you complaining about
that I hide the declaration of best
pixel okay I don't disagree does this
make you happy so now if I come through
and look at what's gonna happen in that
code I'm expecting to reduce the size of
these down to 512 by 512 what's more is
actually I could run this more than once
right I couldn't run this in a 4 I loop
the only downside is it welds in the
reversal of the R&amp;B and so what we could
do is move the R&amp;B up here swap which is
a little slower because it's actually
well actually it's not a little slower
and in fact maybe that's better right if
we do mmm Jimmy if we did hear a B GRA
unpack and instead did a swap did the
swap are our own beat be here right that
might be smarter because now if we want
to we can actually do this as many times
as we want right
and so this could be a four I loop that
allows us to down sample in any way that
we wish so what I could do is say
alright the sprite dim equals the tile
dim and then this right here is just a
Down sampler so we just say alright
sprite dim equals sprite come over to
something like this right so we just do
however many down samples we want if
this is one down sample it runs once if
it's two down samples it runs twice this
just continues to shrink the thing over
and over and over again right I think
that's right we got it we're I'm waving
my hands around the earth up through
entirely but I believe that would just
allow us to kind of sit there in a loop
shrink shrink shrink just keep shrinking
it down and yeah so I don't actually
know that we want to run it twice but
maybe we want to go down to 2 to 6 by 2
to 6 and if we do that would be the way
to do it so let's go ahead and try this
first things first let's make it simple
on ourselves I'm not going to run the
down sampler at all so I'm just gonna
say look let's just see if we reverse
our channels correctly right so let's
create a blank import file let's run it
and let's see if we get the correct
color channels for our our weird will
sprite there and so now I think those
are actually more correct than they were
right I think those are more proper we
don't know about the premultiplied alpha
though now I think about it that
actually still needs to be corrected so
we're gonna have to look at that in a
second I'm gonna try now down sample by
2 just to see if we can produce 56 by
let's see go local create local and run
not looking good if we're honest about
it so let's take a look first of all do
we get anything obvious wrong like is
the file even correct and what not gonna
move to the local dump there and take a
look at it alright so at least it
produced it produced the correct thing
right it's the right size it's the right
we didn't do anything obviously stupid
right so that's good but what we did do
is not actually write out the data
properly so it's still not particularly
encouraging so let's take a look at what
we did wrong here we could step through
this and see what's going on we're
assuming that we're in this pixel buffer
thing we're gonna right out here right
this best pixel buffer and that's what
we write out if I'm not mistaken right
meaning when we reserve the asset data
the thing that we actually write to the
file is the pixel buffer and we write a
set data size which is computed by just
taking the sprite dim squared times 4
which is what we want to do is by do
this by 4 right so in here when we do
our loops we're setting it up so that
we're looking at the front of the pixel
buffer when we start and writing there
oh that's our problem right there
so that actually I mean it's not our
only problem we probably have other
problems in that but that was one of our
problems so we actually want to do is
set it up to the next row and then
divide by 2 so that we're still using
the correct thing to reset our tyldum
and it gets smaller each time to me then
when we come through here we do our B
GRA unpacks and let's make sure that's
going to the right space
so that's going yeah that's correctly
going to 255 0 to 2 3 to 5 right then
we're taking esterday B 2 to 5 which is
what we're loading and we're bringing
that to linear which is what we want and
then the PAC function be Jerry pack so
not correct we want that right and off
we go
so let's try that oh you know what and
we need to we need to do the other yeah
that we're missing our d linearized 2
that would be just yeah that's
I just forgot to call the upconvert as
well we need to call this that's the
problem I shouldn't just multiply 2 to 5
I should actually do the you know we
want the square root stuff so all right
all right so we also need to look and
see whether we actually have
premultiplied alpha so that's one thing
I want to do before the end of the
stream as well let's create a locally
today and let's run but I because I
don't know if that's actually working
properly I'm concerned that it might not
be it probably isn't so I saw so we
we've got a little bit it looks like
we've got some stride issues there with
the down sampling so let's just take a
look at that
[Music]
oh yeah yeah yeah yeah so the problem
here is that source pixel is pointed to
the right place so we're gonna kind of
have to keep we're gonna have to do this
when we do the down sample and we set up
these two once we're done with a pass
we need source pixel zero and source
pixel one to move extra row down right
because source pixel one will be pointed
where source pixel zero wants to be but
source pixel one needs to be one row
below that right so we actually need at
this point to do source pixel zero plus
equals freedom source pixel one plus
equals freedom right every row they need
to advance again so that that was a mess
up there let's try that one more time
but we're almost there and like I said
they're the premultiplied alpha we got a
go look maybe I'll put in some checks
that just kind of built get some values
we can actually look at there so there's
our down sample - it looks good looking
at the edges I want to say like look at
those edges those edges look a lot to me
like it's not premultiplied you know
what I'm saying to you so I kind of feel
like that may be a pretty good
indication that it is not premultiplied
alpha I want to know though for sure and
so I want to do a little bit of us of a
scour here and just see what the values
are that we're actually getting out so
that I can have some idea of what's
going on so what I want to do is I want
to keep I'm just gonna use the blue
channel because that looked like a
fairly blue sprite
I'm just gonna use the blue channel and
I'm gonna find out okay for the max blue
alpha diff I'm gonna say it's zero
what I want to do here is say all right
when I come through here and I've got
these values when when I first import
them I'm gonna say like all right if P
zero zeros alpha value is less than Peas
or maybe both the blue value is greater
than P zero zeros alpha value right then
max blue alpha diff equals maximum max
blue alpha diff and peas or b minus p 0
0 a and so all I'm doing there is I'm
we're gonna record that maximum value so
whatever the highest difference is
between the B and the a I'm gonna record
it and the other thing I want to do is I
want to in fact you know what let me put
it like this
let's just do it like this and this will
let me store the actual pixel that it
found that that was the highest.if right
so what I want to do here is I want to
set a breakpoint on the import and I
want to see what it gets for that value
so it's gonna run through here one time
and before it hits the second time I
want to look I'm gonna look at what that
value is
okay I so let's force that to do a
refresh a reinforce and then I'm gonna
take a look at it so let's bring those
two values up max blue alpha gypsy and
max blue Jeff and run it and let's see
what the values were so I mean yeah
that's a white pixel with no alpha it is
obviously not premultiplied right so we
know that these are non premultiplied
alpha I think we sort of knew that
before because remember when we were
doing the PNG compressor and looking at
the RG and B channels there had they had
stuff in them right where there was no
sprite so we know that's not right so we
need to do the pre multiply at the end
or at the beginning I guess at the
beginning is more correct so when we
come in here what we want to do is say
look we've got a pre multiply this thing
so when we do the down sample we can do
that the problem is if we just did it
only on the down sample it's it's kind
of a problem because if
we only needed on the downsample then if
we don't downsample it doesn't it's not
gonna happen so we kind of want to do it
we kind of want to do it up in the act
and this routine
honestly unfortunately right and so I
think what we want to say here is for
each one of these pixels before we write
it out I think we're gonna actually have
to follow this and this is gonna be
slower right but I think we're just
gonna have to do it so what we want to
do is say alright we're checking to see
if there's any alpha channel if there is
an alpha channel then we're gonna use it
for boundary purposes but what we also
want to do at the same time is make sure
that we do an unpack and a repack like
so
so what we want to do here is unpack the
value do the linearization of it so it's
in the right space real in your eyes
pack right this should be a completely
neutral opera's the operation within
rounding error right should just work
shouldn't change anything other than the
swap RGB and what we do is right here we
do a multiplication of the RGB channel
by the a channel so we force the pre
multiply in the right space we did apply
we unlink your eyes it back and go right
I think that's the right place to do it
because when you unli gnear eyes you
want to be right I'm pretty sure but
with cameras always a huge mind mind
game what's wait what's happening here
why is this running anything we must
have done something wrong cuz this
should not be running anything
what was what's going on there why am I
not seeing anything
something we were just happening but I
don't know what it is
hold on one second because I wanted to
finish what I was doing first but then I
want to see what's going on there
there's my local
what did I break how could I broken
something by touching that part of the
code I'm not sure what I broke anyway
let's zoom in on that there we go so now
you can see we get those nice clean
edges and that's because you know
everything's supposed to be doing
using premultiplied alpha here and since
this was coming in with non
premultiplied alpha it was totally
breaking the renderer right it was it
was not gonna compute the right map at
all in that case and so that's importing
correctly now that that's right what's
happening if I run a second timer we
broke I don't know what broke there I
must have done something weird that I
shouldn't have done maybe I hit a key I
was not supposed to hit I don't know
what happened there let's go ahead and
and test the builds in an optimized
setting so if I if I go ahead and run
this here
so nice and zippy still so that's good
and if I if I take a look at how fast
the import works for those files on an
optimized build again just wanted to
figure out how slow the import would be
so here it is running so that's really
fast actually and that was for three
files so I feel like that's totally
acceptable because most of the time an
artist only updates one file at a time
you know cuz take some Photoshop a while
to even export it so that should be a
totally acceptable turnaround time so I
think that's everything we've got the
premultiplied alpha in there
we're on startup we're not doing
anything when we detect no changes it
looks like we can survive across runs
properly the dumps look right
also let me just here to make sure the
size is right you can see this is now
much smaller right it was previously 50
Meg's it's three now so that all looks
good and I think we're done I think
that's that's literally everything so
next week we will be clear to import at
art assets as we like which is basically
going to involve us deciding how to tag
everything and how to specify what we
want to load which is going to be a toll
a toll on thing but hey we want to get
our assets in the game we did all the
work to do it so now we actually have to
figure out how we want to specify which
ones to use not a bad problem to have
right it's like hey at some point you
got to figure out how you want to tag
things alright so I think that's it
we'll go ahead and go to the QA
at the end of the Y loop of the
downsample shouldn't it be source before
zero equal source buffer oneplus proved
in yeah you might be right huh second
let me see actually no I don't think you
are sorry I didn't mean to say you were
right in and theorem no that looks right
to me so hmm
source pixel zero and source pixel one
are both pointing at Rose they're gonna
advance all the way across to the end of
their row and now they're at the next
row that would be correct if it wasn't
for the fact that we're trying to
advance two rows at a time so they've
advanced one so this just advances them
one more row does that make sense
Martin said you add a comment for a
handling Big Ed ninis for residual value
of Calculon the hash but I feel that
it's important to mention the same
comment should apply also for dot d
resting in the loop yeah you're probably
right
[Music]
hold on I can't remember where this is
yes oh yeah so you're right because this
is gonna be it's going to use these same
shifts and constants which are going to
they're going to be the wrong way round
let's just say that because yeah the
start at will load it in in big-endian
or little-endian and at that point these
operations will go the wrong way round
everything is backwards at that point so
that's a good point Martin's I didn't
think of that when I was typing it in
and by the founder of Molly rocky yes
Molly rocket is my company
does Anna draw vector graphics initially
and would you consider raster and vector
guys in the asset system or it startup
for a game like this so actually I can
answer that in a little bit more complex
way because this is something that I
actually kind of annoys me so no Anna
uses Photoshop actually so they are not
vector graphics initially so we cannot
consider a rasterization path I would
like that because her style is very
cartoony and it could be nicely made
sort of resolution dependent the problem
is Photoshop just doesn't record
brushstrokes right so we have no ability
to make a resolution independent version
of Anna's art even though it would be
pretty straightforward if Photoshop just
recorded brushstrokes but don't not in a
way that it exports any way that I can
find and so it's it's just not really an
option your artists have to work in a
vector graphics program in order to
really have that work in the present day
and age I hope that changes in the
future but right now not so not so much
what sort of precision would we be
losing by doing the down samples and
doing s were to be linear sRGB rather
than doing the linear conversion at the
start and keeping it in linear and doing
the linear sr to be only been running
out each file um so if you mean what if
we just stored a float well okay so
there's a couple things you can't do
first of all we could just iterate over
the whole block and do the thing in
floating point right there
the answer is I you to only lose one bit
per downsample I think I can't really
think of how you would lose more because
basically like whatever you're storing
is just gonna have to round it to the
255 and but then you're gonna
immediately be blending it again so even
if you rounded wrong you'd have to round
wrong the same way on three of the four
you rounded the wrong way it would just
cancel out in the next blend so I don't
know I I don't know Neil I'd have to
think about that a little more but I
suspect the difference would be pretty
minimal for this kind of filter for more
wider filters that have uneven weighting
then you probably lose a bit every time
would be my guess a bottom bit of
precision
I don't know that you really you only
lose a bottom every surgeon every time
on this one and really it's probably
actually unlikely but I don't know I'd
have to think about that some more off
topic any suggestion or resource about
how to implement a network layer from
scratch for a massive multiplayer game
not really you're talking about like
like World of Warcraft or something you
know I guess there's one thing for you
to test out yeah
filtering is kind of a really weird sort
of topic and there's a lot of so here's
the thing we don't really know how to
analyze filtering very well audio
filtering is one thing because your ears
kind of do look at frequency domain
stuff and so analyzing them in terms of
digital filters and Fourier transforms
is not really a bad idea to a certain
extent because it actually is more
closely related to how you hear
analyzing digital filters is still kind
of something that I don't really find
super compelling a lot of the ways they
do it because it doesn't really feel
like it matches that well with how the
brain really does its own visual
filtering and so some of the stuff that
they do to analyze filters is kind of
hand-wavy to me it's like here's a
mathematical model that we're applying
analyzes filter but we've never really
justified that model as being something
you care about you know because
filtering fundamentally is about making
things that look good and if you haven't
first proven that your mathematical
model correlates well with what looks
good then it's kind of dumb to use you
know you're just using math for math
sake
and so the digital image filtering is
kind of a nasty topic and it's nasty
because I don't really feel like we've
gotten as good of a hold on it as we
really should and so some of the ways
that people analyze these filters in
terms of frequency domain stuff I think
is a little misguided so I would I would
it's an interesting thing to look into
be advised that the writing on it out
there is a little hand wavy in my
opinion just curious are there any games
that require more accurate or complex
digital filters in the image than those
of bilinear other approximations like
any sort of sharp low pass filter etc
yeah so basically you can do a lot of
different kinds of filters and they're
different and you do it real-time you do
use different ones so if you are
filtering image stuff I think a lot of
times people still do bilinear because
it's fast and it has no objection Allart
effects so I don't know to what extent
people use more complex filters in at
runtime for image to straight-up image
data but there's a lot of other kinds of
data that gets used in games now normal
Maps
light buffers like buffers that store
like lens effects and stuff like this so
depth of depth of field effects and
blurring and that sort of stuff those
often don't use bilinear filters and
they don't use but linear filters
because the kinds of things they're
trying to preserve in the filter are
better preserved with other methods
right so max filters or min filters
things like this other simple filters
are sometimes used at runtime that are
not bilinear depending on what it is
that you're trying to capture right
could you explain again the rotation to
the left in the bit pattern used well no
not really if you're not if you're
talking about the murmur hatch one
because again I don't know why they
picked these I don't know why they
decided to rotate left you know when
you're bringing these bits in they want
to mix bits so that low bits mixed with
high bits and stuff right
so it's typical to see things rotating a
lot and if you look at rotating it by 31
it's like well I want to rotate it by
like something that moves the bits in
like a marching pattern all around my
value right so 31 makes some sense 27
minute they make sense in a sort of
vague hand wavy way but no I you know I
don't know why they decided to use these
bit patterns they decided those would
mix the bits together in a resilient way
how they decided I don't know we'd have
to go read the paper and hope that it
was written in a way that explains to
people who aren't familiar with
numerical analysis why it's good right I
was thinking about a shooter but let's
think we want support multiplayer for
handmade here well I mean you know the
basics is not super complicated it's
like look you've got the in hand made
here you've already got the renderer
separated from the world sim right so
you can pull the world sim out and
you're gonna run the world sim on the
server-side and then you're gonna run
the world sim on the client-side and the
problem is that you have to now have a
way of reconciling those two things so
what's gonna happen is the server has to
send to the client what it actually
updated in the world and the clients
gonna have to fix its representation of
the world to match that right and it's
kind of nasty coding but you can make it
relatively clean if you work at it you
know
off-topic about can you give a quick
description the filter you designed I'm
fine with heavy DSP target actually no
DSP jargon necessary I will be posting
an article about it I just haven't quite
finished it it's a it's a very special
filter that's designed for a very
specific thing and it had a property
that no other filter I've I've seen has
and so I I have an article it's gonna
write about I designed it way back in
2011 it's an old filter but it just has
never been published so I have a blog
post I just have to finish it up but
you'll be able to read about it there
are no rotate left right as to see AVX
intrinsics correct not that I know of
anyway
I guess what I would say is I don't
remember if there are a BX I have 12
rotations I don't know if rotates tucked
snuck back in there it probably didn't
but I don't know
looks like it's there so I think it did
come back in in 512
I think they added rotate so so there
are if we ever end up being able to
program avx-512 which seems at this
point like a distant dream 512 got it
those look those look like rotate
intrinsic to me
my girlfriend appreciates how much you
hate on Microsoft in Windows so do i but
she said your keyboard sounds like
someone peeing in the next room and it
has ruined my life
I just need a flush now
when client updates using server and
command plates assume client simulates
locally it can create discontinuities if
simulation diverged may be an HMH it
cannot diverge that much though yeah but
that's how would this works right so the
simnet architecture which is
fundamentally the same thing that
everyone pretty much uses today right is
you have a client in a server and they
both run the simulation the client
simulation is not right because it
doesn't know what everyone else has done
it only knows what it did so it keeps
trying to run along and the server is
running the real version that has what
everyone did in it the server is sending
packets to the client to force their
simulate simulations to converge so it's
constantly sending the updates to the
client it's like hey you probably got
this wrong change it to this right so
that's exactly what the packets are
designed to do the server sends the
packets to the client that correct its
mistakes that's what it's supposed to do
right in the full simnet architecture a
server simulates every client the same
way the client would have updated it and
then it does its authenticated version
and it only sends the diffs because now
it knows exactly what the client would
have would be thinking most servers
today don't do that because it's too
much work but that was the original sim
that architecture
and that F arrow I don't know how to
press that you are correct like what
most games do is they try to smoothly
blend as much as they can
between the update of where the client
thinks something should be and where the
server tells it and you tend to kind of
try to blend between those as much as
you can sometimes it's just hugely wrong
and you can't you just got to snap it
over but you know assuming that it's a
slight correction you just try to blend
it we do need the brush strokes or with
vector graphics from a conversion tool
work well I I don't tend to like those
conversion tools they seem to produce
pretty bad results in my experience that
aren't really that useful for multi res
cuz they don't really capture what the
artist was actually doing they just sort
of capture the pixel result and I don't
know how useful that really is right
alright I'm gonna shut it on down yeah
alright thank you everyone for joining
me for the upset of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you wanted to follow along
with the series at home you can always
peer to the game on handmade hero arc it
comes with a source code so you can play
around with it I we got a bunch of other
stuff on the website check it out you
can use our watch page to watch a series
whenever we're live on Twitch it'll show
up there you can watch the stream it
also has the schedule posted at all time
so you know when the next time are going
to be live is and it's got an episode
guide that's pretty awesome
you can type stuff in there and it'll
search for episodes that have that
content for you it's it's great so check
out that page also check out the
handmade hero fun if you're interested
in supporting community projects like
have a network or that episode guide
that I just talked about it's a great
way to do it and finally you want to see
what else we're up to it Molly Rocket
just click on the handmade hero head got
all our projects here you can explore
them as well as my blog people were
asking today about that filter that'll
be posted on on here on the the blog
section as soon as I'm done with that
that's it for today hope to see you back
here next week when we will I'm out of
I'm out of delays I can't delay anymore
I'm out of things to do I've got to
start tagging things we'll figure out
how to do it well so we'll we'll roll up
our sleeves wearing short sleeves right
now but wear long sleeves next week and
we'll roll them up and we will figure
out how we want to tag these art assets
and then and then we're done we're done
with this
this whole loading for a we can bind
loading to a key or we can watch a
directory I don't know what we want to
do to trigger the reload but it looks
like it's all working so we're in we're
in good shape so we can we can have a
little party hope see you back here for
that till then have fun programming I'll
see everyone on the Internet take it
easy everybody