hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we have more or less
finished a large swath of our lighting
stuff and we're kind of down to the last
few sort of tricky bits here so what we
want to do is we want to get our sort of
ray casting system producing a stable
set of for lack of a better term inputs
to the light field interpolator and we
have a couple to do's that we wanted to
do for that in addition to just
debugging and so we're gonna start take
a look at those today there's not a lot
of mystery to most of it it's really
just turning the crank except for one
piece which is we don't really know if
we want to be able to interpolate
multiple light fields at the same time
which we have the ability to do in the
voxel subsystem we don't really know how
we would generate two light fields
exactly like we can blend one light
field so if we wanted to output
everything that we got from the lighting
solution as one single light field that
just gets interpolated like all mushed
together we can totally do that
and maybe that's fine like for all we
know that might be fine but if we want
to try and use even just two light
fields the only thing we really just
have no idea how we would do and we'd
have to sort of do some experimentation
try to work something out is how we
would break our lighting samples into
two separate light fields that each get
evaluated separately at shader time and
there are some benefits to us if we can
do that with our current way that we're
storing the light field we would only
ever get one specular highlight on
anything if we wanted it because we only
have one normal pointing towards the
like primary direction of the light
source and we're kind of implying a
applying a fog like sort of a thing to
it that will probably tweak in the
future to be even more Phong like
and if you take a look at what that does
it's going to produce a specular
highlight in that particular direction
and if we wanted to have a secondary
specular highlight somewhere we wouldn't
be able to get one but the way we're
doing light-filled currently and so
keeping the light field exactly the same
as it is now it's pretty trivial for us
to get to specular highlights at
interpolation time we just add another
light field and we already have I think
three at least going on in there and
really two would probably find anyway
the question is just how do we generate
the second one because if we just blend
everything together
we only get one light field if we want
to have two the question is what gets
blended into the first light field
versus what gets blended into the second
light field right and so it's pretty
confusing because you're like well I
don't know right it's kind of a K
clusters sort of a problem and it's not
immediately clear how we would really do
that in an incremental way normally when
you do K clusters they're not
incremental K clusters so I don't know
right and so we might have to do
something where we have some idea of
like two polar normals and they both
been really to each other or something I
mean I don't know but the point is it's
pretty confusing and we don't really
know exactly how we would do that so at
that point we have a couple different
choices one is that we figure that out
and the other is that we switch to
something that doesn't have this
property so for example if you were to
do something like I don't know circle
harmonics for example those don't have
this problem they may have other
problems they probably wouldn't give us
as good of interpolation for example for
things that we want like the sort of
sphere of light that's you know
surrounds a character or a torch that we
kind of want for our 2d look so they're
probably not a great choice for us but
one of the reasons that people choose
them is specifically because they can be
blended together in that way so you can
capture multiple pieces of light
information using spherical harmonics by
just tracking a bunch of spherical
harmonic coefficients eight in our case
would be two vox lookups and that's a
lot
right so if we wanted to do something
like spherical harmonics we could
totally do that and maybe what we end up
finding out is that that's just a more
sensible way for us to do our
interpolation I don't know that's fine
because it doesn't matter to us one way
or the other that's just a thing for
storage and reconstruction so we can
change that out relatively inexpensively
once we have everything else debugged so
it's not a huge deal if we want
experiment with stuff like that it's not
like the rest of this where it's very
structural it's really just an encoding
decoding thing and so it's just
switching out a codec stage basically
which is a nice self-contained problem
that shouldn't be too hard to deal with
right alright so I'm gonna go ahead and
and get started on that let me go ahead
and open up the game here we were
playing around with handmade ray because
Linux was a disaster but now we're back
on the main main line here so I'm gonna
go ahead and compile there we go and
open up remedy and if I run what you can
see here is this this is where we left
things again it looks actually quite
nice now
oddly enough we're not really doing any
secondary rays at all but you kind of
get a nice feel for it here this is
without interpolation so it even kind of
looks pretty nice even without
interpolation on you can see for example
the stair stepping over here it just
makes it a little easier to debug when
we don't have interpolation on so that's
why that looks the way it does
I can turn interpolation on so you can
see what that does look like if I go
into the OpenGL side of things and we
just take a look at where we're doing
computing Jimmie
aa-men all right
anyway what was I saying okay so if we
go take a look at where we're doing our
nearest filtering that should be in here
somewhere did I just scoop by it let's
see here we go oh this is weird wait so
that was actually linear filtering all
right I take it back looks like that was
because we're not filling in negative
values in that area oh and in fact you
know what that's true so it's not that
we we are actually doing in fact you can
tell you can see that's that specular
highlight there is getting a perfectly
round interpolator so never mind we are
doing linear interpolation the reason
that's happening is we're not filling in
the negative light values and I remember
exactly why that was it's because we put
it to do in there that what we want to
do is reconstruct those with the filter
right so basically what we want to do
here is say all right in the so on the
output side of things let me go ahead
and let me go ahead and go over to the
lighting to do is you can see them here
we have this right and I assume that
that is something we don't want to do
right away that was just we switched to
floats here and you can see that we
don't produce any flickering I think it
was the normals primarily that we're
producing the flickering because it
seemed like if we wanted to we were able
to actually use four colors we had
changed those two floats and it didn't
really make any difference so we don't
really know but it may be that for color
values the color and intensity it's
actually fine to use anything like you
know standard 8-bit it so it may just be
that the normals need to be encoded
better and that's really good news for
us because their normals we actually
have a lot of ways to encode those we
can do a thing where we just use like a
sign bit for Z and then like you know 15
bits each for X&amp;Y or something like that
and that would allow us to encode those
normals
probably with plenty of precision for
what we were seeing and and not have to
worry about it so I think we're in good
shape for that but that's gonna be sort
of a later to do and in fact I probably
want to move that down right like that
should be way at the end so basically
we've got two things that we really want
to work on now before we go to the
indirect light transport the first one
is this is this is the flood feeling
part that is talking about here and what
the flood feeling part is designed to do
is to make our interpolation work
properly so what happens with whenever
you're doing linear interpolation is
when you get towards edges where things
clamp to 0 so for example here's our
shadowing and this is what I'm talking
about
you will get a stair step pattern here
and the reason that you get a stair step
pattern there is just because when
something goes to 0 the interpolation
around it doesn't actually produce any
information about what happens in the
darker region of it now this looks
erroneous to me so I think we've got
another problem going on there probably
in the shader that has to do with maybe
light source clamping or something like
this and it probably it could actually
be to do with the normals as well but
the point is anything in that area that
doesn't have information once you hit
sort of the cutoff point where it gets
towards zero
you just get a flat line and what we
want to do is we want to make sure that
we fill in information in that region
that will allow us to you know anytime
we see like literally there being
nothing there we want to fill in some
information that will provide good
interpolation based on what the nearby
values actually are right and we can do
that by sampling a wider region now you
might ask why not do that in the shader
why not just sample a really wide region
and use that to reconstruct the light in
the area and the answer is because our
shader is very time intensive right it
gets run for every pixel on the screen
because we do per-pixel lighting so the
last thing we want to do oh and it's a
little it's even worse than that right
for transparent or around the edge
of things we actually run the shader
twice once for the thing inside it
what's the thing behind it and once for
the thing where it is so that we can
blend them together so it's it's even
worse if you will then every pixel on
the screen right it's actually more than
every pixel on the screen and so what we
need to be able to do is we need to have
some way of producing something that can
still be fast at that time and then when
we when we hand the fast version off
we've pre ensured that doing the fast
interpolation does the right thing and
so that's why I want to do it in this
order where instead of forcing the pixel
shader to do a large sample of multiple
voxels and reconstruct them what I want
to do is just do a filter pass over the
voxel so that the voxel that we hand to
the subsystem is just correct right so
there's a lot of ways we could do this
but that's the basic idea now what I
want to think about is where is the most
appropriate place for this to occur and
that's a pretty tricky question because
there's actually two logical places for
it and I'm not sure which one of them is
better one way to do it would be that
when we hand it off to the graphics card
we smooth it right and we could even
smooth it using the graphics card if we
want to right and that may be a very
smart thing to do because graphics cards
are very fast at doing things like
averaging you know one texture into
another texture or something right
they're set up to do that kind of
collection but what I don't know is
whether or not we want to have the sort
of for lack of a better term the fill in
the the the values that we're going to
be adding in around the border that
aren't really there but that we've
created just for interpolation what I
don't know is whether we want those to
persist over time and so what I don't
know is when we create so you know let's
say we write exactly what I'm talking
about and we go ahead and you know in in
this case here like you know we're
hopping there and we want to fill you
know these areas all get filled in with
approximate values
right what I don't know is what should
we do with those approximate values
should they only be used for this frames
reconstruction and they should not be
considered during the next frame so each
frame gets its own reconstructed version
basically is that the sensible thing to
do or is the sensible thing to do that
they get filled in in the persistent
version so that they are constantly sort
of being updated as part of the entire
system right and my thinking might my
first inclination because I don't know
that I really want to have to test both
but my first inclination is maybe we do
it well maybe we can try to do it in a
way that lets us test it for both right
to see which one we want we could write
it so that it just works over a generic
sort of array implementation and then we
could call it in two different places
and see which one produces preferable
results because I do think one thing
we've done nicely here is this is a
pretty good test case everything looks
great except at the edge right and so
what we can do is hop around and just
aesthetically speaking just make a
judgment call where does this Moo thing
look better does it look better you know
especially like that I mean that's a
really good test case right because
everything looks really nice there in my
opinion except for what happens at the
edges which we expected and know what
the problem is so how do we fix it right
so maybe we can just use the fact that
we've got a nice test case there to sort
of do that reconstruction in a couple
different ways so maybe let's try and do
that we'll see how hard it is for us to
get something that could operate at
either point in the pipeline there maybe
it has to be kind of slow but that's
okay cuz only runs once over the voxel
and and we try to make something that
will work in either case so let's go
into the lighting system and see what
that would entail and so remember we've
got two systems here you know one is we
have this light voxel cell here and this
is the giant voxel that's got everything
in it and we could certainly run
over that and anytime and then we have
another situation here where we've got
the the point where we actually output
that so we take that that information
the cells there and we push those down
to the graphics card and that's that's
this right here and so this light voxel
and light voxel see that we're looking
at here we could very easily say look we
can smooth on this or we can smooth on
this and we can see which one of those
produces a more pleasant result and
again this one this one right here is
the one that will persist so if we when
we smooth this one out it will go every
frame it will have knock-on effects for
future frames if we smooth this one out
it will not have any effects on the next
frame it'll only have the effect on just
the immediate frame or rendering because
only affecting the thing that we're
pushing to the graphics card right so
that seems reasonable to me as an option
now the way we want to do this is going
to be kind of a little bit odd and we
haven't really talked about anything
like this before
but basically what we want to do is I
think we want to pretty much leave
lighting values alone when we have them
so what we're really talking about here
is filling in lighting values where we
don't know anything right
so for places in the lighting where we
really just don't have any idea what's
going on we want to fill in those and
only those if you will now if you take a
look at what's going on here you can see
the easiest place to put this and this
is maybe the place that we'll start with
it is in the part that gets blended over
time yeah I'd really rather start with
the second one so so maybe we won't do
what I just said but anyway the point is
in here right we're producing values for
these cells based on these accumulator
pieces of accumulator information that
we got here right you know what and I
should mention there's really three
places even we could also smooth it back
in here right
the
wait line what we could do is say if on
a particular frame we got note weight
added in a particular area we could
smooth that so we could smooth only the
contribution side as well so it's really
three places we could smooth I don't
have really any idea why we would only
smooth that one but or why that would
make a difference but we could so anyway
assuming that in here we see we could
use the light C or the light n either
one but what we can do is look at those
values and if they're all zero we know
we didn't get any information in that
area right and if we didn't get any
information in that area we can then do
a collection of the things around it to
basically figure out what it might be
and the size of that window is somewhat
arbitrary but maybe I'll say that right
now it'll be sort of a three by three or
something right three by three by three
something like that because that's what
we were sort of using before right and a
three by three by three is really just
getting one sample in either direction
right and what we want to do is probably
take a look at what the gradient is in
that area now as I'm saying that we
probably actually need a five by five by
five which is you know pretty pretty
nasty but we can do this separable I
think and then maybe that's not such a
bad situation yeah anyway so if you
think about what we have to do here all
I'm really saying is look we need to be
able to look at the the region around
this point reconstruct what we think a
value would be based on derivatives of
neighboring values and you know produce
that right so how would we do that
I'm gonna go ahead and write this for
maybe the the light voxel and see stuff
here so this bit right here where we're
doing this L index so you can see the L
index here I'm gonna do it on just this
part so before we send the thing down we
will smooth it so basically right here
you know or maybe right here if you will
[Music]
mm well no okay sorry so right after we
do this I will
so I'll smooth it right here so what
we're gonna do is a second pass over
this we're gonna do the pass this way
but what you can see about this as as we
go right what you can see about this is
if we were to do it this way we would
sort of have this issue that we have to
look at a five by five by five and so
what I'd rather do is break that down
into filters that can operate sort of in
different directions right and one of
the things that we talk about this is
this is very common in filter design
I'll show you what I mean on the on the
black board here
is suppose I want to design some kind of
a filter that's going to operate over
some sample data regular space like we
have and so what am I trying to do right
well what I'm trying to do is say all
right let's suppose we took like a 1d
cross-section esteem and what I see
happening is like this sort of thing
right right
and so there's a couple different ways I
could do this if I didn't if I just did
a 3x3 one thing I could do is say well
just take whatever this value is and I
know that I'm at zero right and so just
take whatever this value is and the
Delta down to me and continue it over
here or something right yeah I'm saying
uh the problem with something like that
is we're trying to solve the problem at
us
so the reason I say we need a 5x5 right
is what I really want to do is say well
I if I'm at zero I don't really know
what the value should be so look at 2
behind me right see what their Delta is
like maybe their Delta looked like that
right see what their Delta is and assign
me that Delta again so that it like
continues to decay in roughly that
pattern right so that's why I say you
know five wide seems like the minimum we
could do I don't think we could only do
three I don't think that would really
work I mean maybe it would but I doubt
it
so I think we want to do something like
five wide and I want to do that you know
that gradient there now we don't have a
1d problem we have a 3d problem that
means that there are three such lines
passing through this point at least
right arguably more because we could
look at just the 2d version of the
problem
right here's the 2d version of the
problem I was talking about the result
that happens when we look at these
points right maybe it looks like that
but there's also what it looks like at
these points right and these points and
those and those right and so what you
would want to do in 2d for example is
look at an actual five by five or twenty
five wide grid right and we would want
to assign we would want to use all of
these sample points and weight them
together to produce the result that we
actually wanted right and then when you
get to a cube this is gonna be five more
right so it'd be also deep five deep and
you can see how this multiplies out to
just a really unfortunate value right
there's no way we want to do 25 times 5
right or 125 samples for everything we
fill in that's just a terrible thing but
the good news is if all we were going to
do is sort of like combine these values
together in a fairly direct way we may
just be able to do passes where we do
three different passes of five samples
each doing each on a line so we do like
passes that way pass that way and pass
this way right and that's three times
five instead of five times five times
five right
and what that gives us is a three versus
twenty five power right which is
dramatically faster it's you know
basically like eight times faster right
or eight times less sample so we have to
take and a factor of eight is a huge
factor right so when you're dealing with
3d problems breaking things down into a
series of 1d passes basically can be a
huge win for you because it means that
you do not actually have to you don't
actually have to compute nearly as much
stuff
now hmm it's worth noting that there are
cash implications here how big is our
light large voxel right well I believe I
don't actually remember is the
embarrassing part I don't remember what
we set it to its light look up voxel dim
there it is
so it was that plus one so I guess it's
2 to the 6th or 64 that seemed right
it's looks like it's 32 by 32 by 32 so
it'd be 64 by 64 by 64 for our larger
one is that right
Yeah right that's what it looks like to
me um so if we go ahead and imagine what
would happen if we if we figure out how
much memory footprint that would take
right
a 64 by 64 by 64 is already really large
right it doesn't fit in the cache and so
one of the problems that we would have
if we choose to do that the 32 by 32 by
32 does right it doesn't fit in the l1
cache really but it would probably fit
in the l2 because it's 32 K which is the
size the l1 cache number of entries but
each entry is you know large it's
several floats large right don't
actually remember what these look like
but yeah so it's effectively 6 times 4
or 24 right bytes long so if you imagine
this times 24 even that doesn't fit in
the l2 so even the small one doesn't
really fit in the l2 I think the l2 is
like 2 to 6 K maybe it's not let me see
what the what's the l2 these days I
never remember this stuff
it'll fit in the l2 on a Xeon I'm sure
just maybe not on my machine so here's
the info page for this chip and if you
look let's see do you have any cache
information for me here dudududu there's
the core information here it is cache
organization Oh what that's not really
that seems much larger than I was
expecting the l1 data cache to be oh oh
oh it's just deciduous multiplying out
per core that's fine
so yes see it's 32 K and 2 to 6 K so
exactly what I thought it was there just
multiplying it by this this value is the
total amount of cash like if you take
the fact that there are 4 cores on the
chip and each one gets one so that's a
little misleading if you look at these
numbers we only care about the amount
per core although I suppose in theory we
could break this up across multiple
cores and then not have to worry cuz
each one would only touch 32k of it but
well no it wouldn't cause that's to do
if we were doing the passes in that
order um so the point I'm trying to get
to with that is just that if you assume
you're gonna miss the cache every time
then it becomes also a little bit of a
trade-off it's hard to say you can see
that we will fit comfortably within the
l3 that part's not not an issue we have
the the
two megabyte size on that so all of us
all the things we just talked about will
fit inside the l3 no problem the only
issues l3 is like very slow like l3 is
much much slower l2 is usually fast
enough for you to not care it can serve
you a lot of data the l3 is a pretty big
jump down actually so it's a little bit
tough to think about what we would
necessarily want to do here in terms of
going through and doing the smoothing
because it does mean that we're gonna be
having a bit of an issue with moving
through all of that memory again and
that's not fabulous but you know I don't
really know what to make of that I'm
trying to think if there's some kind of
a way I could do this that would not
incur those kind of penalties I don't
think there really is the moment so one
thing that I guess is maybe a slight
saving grace here is that although we
missed the cache a lot we only actually
fill in values that have zeros that are
next to values that don't have zeros so
I suppose one nice thing is we only
actually have to check these values like
once like we only have to kind of mark
them down or something and then we can
maybe yeah I mean maybe okay so so
here's another proposal maybe we don't
do it this way maybe this is too
expensive and this is dumb because of
the cache effects that I don't want that
to happen
so maybe what we do instead is we do
something different and really weird and
that's just what we do on handmade here
oh so it's fine maybe what I do instead
is I say look we're only interested in
values that have no light information
next to values that do have light
information and I kind of know ahead of
time that I want to do a wide filter on
these five by five by five at least
which is extremely expensive right what
if instead we just did one pass through
on three by three by three and all we do
is we mark which ones we're going to do
which we believe because lighting the
light the field light region forms what
is effectively a three dimensional
volume in space right because lights are
volumetric so the lighting for our voxel
is basically a three dimensional blob
right that fills the space we are
talking about the surface area of that
Bob and so while the blob itself and the
voxel is volumetric it's n cubed size
the surface area will only be N squared
size meaning the number of things that
border the edge of that blob should be
significantly less so if I just remember
all of those things as sort of a stack
and then I just process the stack maybe
that will keep me out of the Pudge you
know I don't know right it's a long shot
but who knows it could work so if I just
said like I've got a temporary right
here that I'm going to call like flood
indices or something like this and I
want to be able to record like these
indexes into the voxel and I basically
know and maybe I want to write them as
this maybe I want like the three indices
or something so maybe it looks more like
that I don't know so I'm gonna record my
flood indices here and what I want to do
is I want to have a note that I can
record enough of them so if I have my
light large voxel dim here it's just
like that cubed right all right so this
would track the values and then I would
just have a flood index count we do one
pass over them to see where they are and
the kind of nice thing about this is I
could also do something where I flood
with actual like purple color as a test
to make sure we're finding all of the
places that we want to fill in do you
know what I mean so that seems good to
me I don't know so I'm gonna give this a
shot and see what happens and the other
thing out well you know what else I
could do maybe we do this as a small
voxel so it's even less right so in so
we could actually do it this way where
we take the light look up voxel dim this
thing here one thing I'm also kind of
is what if we just did
oops what if we did a thing where we
could I don't know we think of this just
seems like this is a little easier to
read doesn't it
so if I do something like that I just
know that I can now track like what
elements I think are important here and
maybe this is reasonable I don't know I
mean I guess now that I think about
why would I actually need to build the
indices so I could really just do this
the same way like do the detection first
yeah now I think about that's dumb I
don't even really need to do that
because once I do the detection not it's
free for me to fill it in at that point
right although I suppose I don't want to
yeah I'm just gonna do it without the
indices so I don't really need the
indices I can just do the pass and I can
just do it in place so it's fine
no no worries there just isn't really a
reason to do that I guess so I was
thinking that there would be a reason to
mark them but there isn't so I'm gonna
flood fill those squares with purple
first that's what I'm gonna do
and so in end lighting computation what
I want to do is when we get down here
and we are going to fill all these in
I'm gonna do that pass right here so
this is gonna be my flood fill and
what's gonna happen is for each of these
I'm gonna look and I know ahead of time
right that there's no way for me to
actually fill anything that's too far on
the edge but since if I only go through
the hot dim so like here right if I only
go through the the sort of smaller
region right you can see here we're
doing the light lookups on the voxels
this way so this is the way we look up a
cell that's that's sort of in the wider
region and if I know that I'm only
inside the hot dim then I should be able
to do the entire thing as long as the
hot dim the hot corner is gives me
enough room there and one of the
problems I guess we'll have is right now
we don't guarantee that the hot corner
has enough room I think you can kind of
be right on the edge of it in which case
this would over fetch and be bad so you
know I kind of got a
I kind of got to make sure this would
work what we could do is say all right
you know the hot corner I could check
pretty easily to make sure that the hot
corner is always like at least two in
and then at least two away from the edge
as well which would basically be like
light large voxel dim - light voxel dim
or what did we call that like look up
voxel dim so something like this and
this is not doing anything it's just
making sure that that never actually
occurs right and so if I did something
like that and just we we will hit that
assertion my assumption is we will
sometimes because right now we don't do
a very good job of placing those two
things we need to place them better so
I'm assuming we will hit that assertion
when we go down like - I feel like like
right here or something
we hit something like that it strange to
me that we didn't so maybe it always
kind of just barely skates by but we
will need to do some work I think to
avoid that and that's work we want to do
anyway it was it was the to do that was
right here this right anyway so if I
want to go ahead here and try to make
this work better than the first thing I
need to do to do my flood-fill here is
just detect whether the fill needs to
occur right and so what I want to do
there is look at sort of a DX region so
like a region around this particular
thing so it would be something like this
and I guess I'm kind of hoping that
these get unrolled because I don't
really want them to
actually have to run but something like
this so that we could look in a wider
region so it literally be just like this
although I guess I'd probably want this
the opposite way around like that so if
we were to look around here basically
what we want to do is say all right we
have our cell and then we have like a
neighbor cell right and this is just
going to be sort of looking at the
surrounding region what we want to do is
say if this cell doesn't have a value in
and the neighbor cell does then we go
into sort of the wider berth right
something like that like if this has
light and or sorry if this doesn't have
light we do the search to say if this
has light then we're good right and
again this is not very efficient and
we're not going to make it very
efficient until we verify that it
actually works so I'm going to do like
the worst possible version of this just
to get it working and then we'll think
about how we would make this actually
run in a reasonable amount of time once
we see how much time it actually does
take right so so assuming that we find
that this thing has to be filled then
what we would do is say okay let's go
ahead and do the looping over this thing
excuse me like this right and this one's
going to be over a wider loop and all
we're going to do here is we're gonna
take whatever the neighbors cell values
are and we're going to sum them into us
right so in this case we have I don't
even remember what we have here
so we want to do here is we're gonna
sort of get the L index syrup so this
part and we're gonna produce put these
values in so in here where we do the
flood-fill
we're going to do the flood fill and
then output to the actual regular voxel
so this part here so it'd look like this
and we're gonna need to create some
summation values so if we want to fill
we have to have a light and zero and a
light see zero we're gonna have to
normalize this one presumably so light
and zero is going to have to be
normalized after the fact but the light
see zero can just be some directly and
so then here what we would do is we just
sum these out right and I guess we just
get those out directly so it would just
be like literally the neighbor sell
light see and the neighbor sell light
and for the direction counts that we're
doing here which would for now we're
only summing the first one right alright
so this right here will produce just a
summation and look so the only real
thing that we need to finish this off
right is we need a coefficient bank that
tells us how much to weight each
individual value that we're placing into
the cell and I'll show you how to do
that in a second it's pretty
straightforward actually but we can
suffice to say we need to have a
coefficient bank here this is sort of
our you know our filter right this is
our our filter coefficient or I don't
know what we want to call it football
club and we know that we've got a
certain number of values here that we're
trying to add in so what we want to do
is say well we know this is a five by
five by five that we're
try and wait in here right and we need
this thing to be some set of values
right there's gonna be like you know
something like that that fills in what
this thing is supposed to be now I don't
really know necessarily how we would
want to do this it's possible that we
have to be fancier because we're only
trying we possibly only want to use
information we actually have right and
so one of the problems we're gonna have
is like if we're looking at this five by
five by five here in fact this has to be
another five this is gonna be so many
coefficients I suppose we want to
generate maybe we want to generate this
thing I don't actually filling these in
the problem that we'd have is just that
it's unclear that we want to use ones
that we don't actually have right and so
normally what I would do for a filter is
I just create the filter kernel which is
what we're looking at there and I'd you
know figure out what we want to do them
for the multiply but in this case I
guess we don't necessarily want to do
that because we don't really want to
take into account areas that don't have
any information in it we don't really
want to use so I kind of feel like we
may actually have to do this in sort of
a more in sort of a more creative way we
may want to do it as like a smaller
light pass that actually just works over
the the the five by five in sort of a
different way I'm trying to think of
like how we would do this it actually
seems kind of tricky to get right
I mean one way to look at it is we could
just look at what Delta values we have
in looking through the 5x5 and seeing
which deltas we have so whenever we see
a neighbor cell we look at the neighbor
cell that's on the other sides of it
from where we are and do that maybe I'll
try that so maybe we won't really do
this maybe we'll do this yeah and get
rid of that and this will go away oops
so maybe what we'll do instead is take
out one of those so that we're like this
right and then what we want to do is say
okay look for ones of these that do have
light and for anything here that does
have light we will try to we'll try to
make this thing be maybe more of a like
look we're just gonna look for gradients
and continue the gradients I guess I
can't really think of anything else to
do
so yeah and unless I have some other
kind of a brainstorm about what we're
gonna do this is in the wrong place that
seems like the best probably solution so
if you imagine taking this part out and
just doing something like having some
kind of a flood fill thing here so we're
gonna flood these two values and we want
to
produce these
it's a look if you think but we want to
do is say oh that's not so if we want to
flood fill those two values and we want
to pass down like alright here's where
we're starting right and then I want to
be able to sort of set these values like
I want to go you know where do I want to
go from there so maybe it's like all
right you know I'm gonna start with
those and I'm going to go only in the
direction I was already going so like I
don't know this sort of thing so I'm
going to give you a direction that I was
looking for DZ dy DX and I want you to
look it one more in that direction to
see whether or not you have any
information there you can use to produce
a gradient if you do I want you to sum
it into the flood fill right it's not a
good idea but it's an idea
um and we can sort of expand this out in
fact we could just make this be of Macra
right
so I'm gonna try that like I said it's
not good but we'll you know it's it's
the best thing I can think of at the
moment and we need to start with some we
need to start somewhere right so let's
go ahead and do this so this will give
me some way of saying well okay we since
we now don't know how many things were
summing together we're going to have to
keep track of the waiting on it because
unlike normals which can just be
normalized this cannot so this will help
us just keep track of that and make it a
little bit easier we need to figure out
whether this still has light since we're
not really sure what that's doing right
now we should probably just write that
really quickly in fact that could be
also come from a cell right and so if we
want to here we could just say all right
the and now I think about it since
that's a macro the way this is looking
here I could actually it since like was
able to fit it inside the loop this
doesn't have to be a macro so has light
on a cell can just be at the moment the
idea that the cell light n 0 dot X not
equal to 0 or see here so
yeah something like this right so that
way we can check really quickly does you
know just simply with one macro
invocation whether or not something has
light in it and if it does off we go so
here what I do is say alright we're
gonna have to do the light flood right
here so this just looks up in that I
guess in that direction so it's like
basically a knock on things so it's like
you know we'll call this cell 0 and cell
1 and so what these would be would be
like alright so we've got plus DZ plus
dy plus DX and then we have like oops we
have like two times that select going
one more in that direction you know I
mean to make this a little bit more
friendly maybe well no I think that's
what we want so we we look one more in
that direction and we see if both of
these if both have light so we know that
they're they're both valid values then
what I do is I look at the Delta between
them and I apply that to the cell that
we're currently on right now I guess the
problem I'm gonna have here is the
directionality of each is confusing
because I would have to say like how do
I get from me how do I know the whether
to apply the negative amount or the
positive amount and I suppose that could
just be a coefficient that we look up in
a table but again this is just the
annoyance of having to write this code
we know what we're trying to do it's
just a question of how to actually
compactly represent it
in a way that doesn't you know become a
complete disaster so looking at each of
these I guess what I would say is for
the negative side of things I almost
just want to make like I said make this
a macro and then just do it so I can
just be explicit I think I'm gonna do
that so I think I'm going to revert to
what I was saying before I'm gonna do it
this way
so if I was to make this the macro and
we did something like this like so and I
guess you know I don't know that I
really need to be macro could be a
function if we want it to be because I
guess there's nothing particularly
Squinkie about that so I suppose I
suppose now that we're looking at it it
could just be you just go up so I have a
second window here to edit it just put
them right here so here's the one that
checks to see if we've got light and
there's really no reason for these to be
functions it's just because C's so bad
at macros that you have to do it I mean
really what they are is local functions
so here what I need to do is pass the
lightening solution and I would need to
pass the full set of actual values so
we'd need like you know X Y Z you see
what a pain-in-the-butt this is it's
just stupid
so I can look these up pretty easily and
then I just need some way of having the
summation occur right and so this can go
away here and this probably needs to be
bundled like this and I suppose since
we're doing the flooding this way these
could maybe be just bound up in here so
you only set them once and then these
would go in here right so something like
that and this provides us with what we
need to construct this heinous function
we would get both of the values we could
now see if they both had lighting in
assuming they do we can apply this with
some kind of a coefficient right so we
can say all right if they do then what
we want to do is subtract these two so
we want to subtract cell one from cell
zero or cell zero from cell one doesn't
matter and then as long as the person
calling us knows which order we do them
in they just passes the coefficient they
want us to use which is either luck
negative or positive one right so we
multiply and then sum so we go ahead and
say all right the light weight is gonna
plus equal one here
the light and zero is gonna plus equal C
times cell 0
- so probably cell one minus cell zero I
guess I don't know which way we should
do it doesn't really matter so then
oops
gives us the summation that we wanted
and it's the pain in the butt but there
you go right so then we can just
manually write these out and we can also
see if there's a pattern if there is we
can wreak elapsed it into a for loop
right so we can sort of still see the
thing that we wanted to see so here we
would say all right there's a floodlight
here's the flood information we have an
X of Y and a Z we have a weight which is
nothing at first
we have an N zero and I see well
actually so I guess looking at this
let's just clear it and then do that so
that floods all those and then we have
like our you know dxdy disease that we
want to actually do and then our you
know our C value whatever that's going
to be so if we look at how many of these
we want to do at the very least we want
to do like you know we want to do one in
each direction right and that gives us
the cardinal direction so positive and
negative x right and maybe this is a
better way to write that so you can see
them line up a little bit better so
right like positive and negative x
positive and negative Y positive Z right
and then we probably want to do
diagonals as well I would think I mean I
don't really know that we want them but
you know those are the other ones we
probably want and so in those case you'd
be like negative x and then you'd have
every permutation of every other
coordinate set right so this is where
the like you you know this would be a
lot nicer because it's a lot less
samples but if you wanted to do
diagonals you'd have to do these right
and I think you kind of need them
probably would be my guess I mean I
don't know but so if you
take a look at what that entails it's
like okay you know it'd be something
like this so you'd have negative X you'd
have every combination of these so you
would actually also need this right I
believe and then this expanding this out
again you can kind of see you've got one
redundant one here which we already had
I mean I guess some one way to look at
it is get rid of this and just use this
table right here's all the possible
combinations that you could do right and
we know that we don't need zero zero
zero because that's not a sample but
here's all the other possible samples
right in fact I'll leave zero zero in
there so we can comment it out so if you
look at what's going to happen here when
you're looking at these values whatever
the Delta is now it's always like going
out away from the value so I wonder if
we if we can just because now we hand
code sort of the order that it happens I
wonder if we actually don't need the
coefficient maybe we don't so what
happens here if you've got this value
this value this value so you're looking
in this direction right and we're
basically saying that you know which
order do we we did one minus zero right
was how we did it for our flood line
yeah we took and oh this is zero minus 1
actually so I'm gonna change that to one
minus zero because that makes a little
bit more sense to me
but again doesn't really matter but oh
no I'm looking at the wrong thing it's
this index that we care about 1-0
oops so if we're doing 1-0 in this case
you can see here we've got the this is
the one this is the zero and this is the
one that we're actually filling this one
right here so if we subtract these two
it was it it would be saying 1-0 says
what's the derivative that goes from
zero to one right and so if we wanted to
know what the location of this guy
should be we want to add this in so we
want to say like okay what would we
expect it to be going from this guy to
this guy right and so if you look at
that we it is it is sort of the wrong
way round right because we want to take
this one and we want to produce it going
that way right so I guess what we'd
rather have here is we'd rather produce
this value a little bit more sanely what
we'd rather do is say if we were going
from 0 to 1 which is this way then we
would want to and we wouldn't need that
now I'm I'm arguing if we're going from
there to there to get to the interior 1
we'd need to apply that one more time to
whatever the current whatever the value
we would be starting on would be and
that value because that value is we know
what it is it's this one right here
right it would basically be it would
basically be saying take cell zeros
value add the Delta that you previously
added before and that's the new value
that we're going to have right for the
central differencing and what you can
see there is if you actually did this
you can sort of see that you end up just
summing light n2 twice right so it's
really just this
and then you subtract that and that
should produce the value that that we
need and I think that works all the time
because we're doubling up right so
because we're doing that I think that
would always work so it does seem like I
guess that could have been written in
line I guess I like I said I'm kind of
dumb it looks like we can so this this
is entirely parameterised bull you don't
need any special knowledge it looks like
it just works right so if we want to I
can just weld that in which is good I
could weld that in right here and do the
loop the way I had it before
so that's kind of nice I mean who knows
again this is just really ugly and
complicated so I don't really know if
we're going to be able to really get
away with this but again like I said we
got a try because we don't really know
what we need right now so we have to
start somewhere and just see where we go
with it so this now can be welded
indirectly which is great just makes it
easier for everybody the compiler can
see what's going on much more
effectively there right alright and this
is an array there we go so let's go
ahead and do bug that and see if we can
get it working looks like for this
that's some residual stuff so we really
just need that and what else you got
these now don't have to be addressed
anything else all right so a little
arduous but it looks like we more or
less got it and let me see what happens
if we actually fill those what I'd like
to do here well so it's actually already
sort of working just not very well right
you can sort of see that sometimes you
get some little angular things in there
so we're getting something and like
there for example all right it's just
not quite right the first thing I want
to do before we do anything else is I
just want to fill in where the values
are so I can get a better sense of it so
rather than doing this what I'd like to
do is when we come into this has light
part I'm just going to overwrite the
values with like bright purple
right so instead of this I'm going to
basically do this and that's just
pegging those two like purple so that we
can see where they are right so this is
like filling in those those values and
what I just want to verify right so you
can see that we are correctly at least
identifying which values don't have any
light on them sort of although that is
not really doing that so there's a
little weirdness there and I don't know
if that's because those are very small
maybe those are very very low light
values that are close to zero I don't
think so though because you can see the
interpolator is busted on those so we
have some other bug so this is good
because this is what I wanted to to
basically debug right I want to know
where those artifacts are coming from
first before I try to debug the
averaging part of things like why is
that what's happening there you see that
like what is that so I'm guessing that
something is happening with maybe in our
shader for example with erroneous
interpolation or something like that
that's messing with us before we even
really get to the point where we're
going to fill this stuff in so I want to
look at the Z bias program real quick
and find out what the deal is with that
because I don't know
all right all right well we can I think
we can sort of see what the problem is
here so if we take a look at what we
were doing before and producing these
this light floor value here the clamping
so if you look at what's happening with
the light color this is producing the
light color here but we're not clamping
it to zero and the problem is we do want
to clamp it to zero when we interpolate
it we don't want to clamp it to zero
right but we do want to clamp it to zero
once we're actually going to use it
because we don't want to apply negative
lighting in our lighting equation that
doesn't make any sense so we do want to
do something where we do like you know
so use there can we do the clamp can we
do the clamp across the entire thing I
think we can I don't really know if we
can or we can't you know I don't know if
we can over can suppose we write it out
like that so I do think we need to clamp
that there because we don't want to and
actually so I guess we know I think
about it we only want to clamp it to
zero so clamp zero one is actually not
true either because the light is allowed
to be brighter than that so it's more
like just clamped to zero which ya not
sure what the easiest way to do that
would be but this just needs to be a
very high value let me take a look at
the shader and see what the most
efficient way to tell the compiler that
is let's see what do we have here
[Music]
so it looks like they don't really
supply a clamp for that but since it's
just do it since we have min and Max
that's all we need right we can just do
a min value I'm sorry a max value on
zero and the value and that's that's the
clamp so the fact that they don't call
it a clamp doesn't matter it's still
fine right so what we can do here is if
we do clamp zero what we can do is or
clamp zero in I guess maybe is the right
way to say it what we can do there is
say look we just want the maximum value
between whatever you give us and zero so
if this value gets below zero we won't
you know we throw that out but if it's
anything else we use it right so that's
fine and so I do think that was a
problem now whether that's the whole
problem I don't know but it I think it's
a problem that we wanted to address and
so I'm glad that we did so let's see
like what we're looking at now just
trying to see and I think we're still so
we still may be getting some
you know the other thing I'm wondering
is for normal so those are those are
where the normals flip I think that's a
normal problem like an interpolation of
the normal problem I'm curious though as
to why it's a perfect why it's not
smoother right because that's just an
that's just going the normals going the
other direction but I don't quite
understand why that would be happening
in some of these places right so like
I'm not sure I understand how that I
guess I could believe that that was just
the normal interpolation but I'm not you
know I'm not really sure about it
similarly for the light normal when we
actually produce that that probably
should be normalized as well here when
we actually produce the normal and we
weren't doing that either so let's get
that in there make sure that's in the
mix but again really just not I don't
really understand what's happening like
right in here it looks like a problem
with the normal but like how how is it
flipping its I mean at that at that
point right there there's just no way
right it's some kind of degenerate
situation probably with the fact that
the normal flips at that point maybe
although I don't understand why we
wouldn't get a smoother result right I
mean you can see how smooth it is then
it hits this discontinuous point here
which just how is it doing a cubic
interpolation and producing that right
like something it's not impossible to do
that but it's a little weird and I'm not
sure why it would be doing that right
I and that's why I think there's I just
have to satisfy myself that I understand
what's going on a little bit better I'm
gonna try undoing this now I want to see
what happens here cuz like why are all
those black as well same same deal right
I don't understand like really strange
right you can see that it's sort of
doing some fill-in and sort of not again
just really not quite understanding
what's happening there and I need to be
able to understand I also should
probably look at the has light function
in case maybe that's busted again the
has light functions looking at the
normal to see what direction the normals
facing you know maybe that's a bad thing
to look at it could be that the normal
persists somehow you know we could do
this instead see if there's any light in
the area and I don't know if that would
have any effect but I doubt it yes you
can see it doesn't matter which one I
test somehow it doesn't detect the fact
that the lighting went to zero right
it's like something in here there's like
a dead zone that is coming from
something but we don't know what right
because we're detecting that there's no
light out here but we're thinking that
there's light in here another way to do
that would be to say we could flood in
the opposite direction where we look to
see like when we do where is it so when
I do that has light bit right here so
the other thing they could do is say all
right like let's actually flood this
element when we know that it
does have light and in that case set it
to yellow and then when we look here
we'll see pinks and yellows everything
should be one or the other right they
just allow this to be accessed from both
branches there so everything should be
either pink or yellow now there should
be no remaining actual light values
right so you can see that we actually
are properly touching every cell there
right like all of these then got filled
in which means that we think that they
have light right so I mean that's
actually pretty interesting so if I take
this out we think those things have
light in them right because here they
are they're yellow
when I take this out they're black so
when we're doing that test somehow we
think there's lighting information there
but what I mean
what lighting information do we do we
think we have and so that's kind of
that's that's the part I want to
investigate here right so I'd like to
know how we're getting a has light value
there because it looks like there's no
light but it thinks we did have some and
is that just because these values are
like incredibly small or is this test
busted am I looking at the wrong cell
seems unlikely
so I guess what I would say is that's
our first order of business here what's
going on with this let's add the
threshold in here to see if it's just if
those values are just small or if
there's something else weird going on
and what I'm looking for here is that
those two flood to pink so what you can
see there is that it looks like they did
have very small values right so here's
what I'm guessing this pretty much gives
me the information I need
so probably what's happening there is
because we're smoothing over time those
values are just sort of slowly
approaching zero but never quite getting
there right and that means we may want
to clamp our like flush our values down
to zero when that happens but there we
go I also don't know we can't really hit
D normals and SSE can we I god I hope
not
that would be bad we really don't want D
normals in here so anyway let's take a
look at what happens now if we re enable
the blending just to see if we get
anything more sensical now that we're
correctly identifying things as being
low light so let's go ahead and turn
this off and we'll see what happens with
the interpolation around the light
boundaries
so that seems really weird it's like
replacing those things with it looks
like I've got my it looks like my
interpolate is going the wrong way so I
think I screwed up that math that's what
it looks like to me um because I wanted
to be able to have negative values there
in the interpolator and it looks like
that's that's not at all what's
happening so hold on one second let's
take a look so what we're doing here
when we're you know summing up these
guys right I want these to have the
ability to have negative values so I'm
basically saying like take where the
take where the first one away from me is
right and add to that the Delta between
the previous one and me and that I mean
looks right right I mean that looks like
what you would do for that information
right hmm
and this should only really be able to
be negative I guess although I guess
sometimes it could be positive if it was
going the other direction I mean maybe
we always want it to be negative like
because there's no light here but I
don't know
since the light weights always positive
this won't change the sign the normal
will just be normalized so that part's
not an issue so yeah I feel like that
should be okay let me work one through
real quick just to make sure that I'm
not totally wrong about the order that
math goes so let's suppose I'm looking
at one of these actually let me do it
this way so I'm gonna look at this guy
here and you know what I'm trying to do
is just a simple you know extrapolation
so I have this guy it's zero these two
both have values so we take the Delta
between them and we want to apply it to
get this so it's just a very simple in
your linear extrapolation there's
nothing of fancy going on there at all
right so if this is a and this is B then
what I would expect to do is say look if
I started from B what I would want to do
is add from B the difference that it
took me to get to B from a right so it
would be B minus a right and that would
get me here and so that's just two B
minus a right that's the actual value
that I would expect to have and that's
where I would expect my value to be
right now
- B - a is two times like cell 0
- cell 1 and that's what we wrote right
two times cell 0
- cell 1 so it seems like that simple
extrapolation should be ok great I don't
see what the problem is there and you
know in the Z by a shader I assume we're
handling the negative values ok I don't
think there's anything in particular
weird there here's us normalizing the
normal when we actually look up the
light value we're just grabbing the
light v RGB out of that and then we
clamp to make sure we're only using the
positive portion of it right so if it
was zero we'd get min zero and that I'm
max it on that rather which would just
be either zero or if it's a positive
value we'd use the value so I don't
really have an explanation for why it's
looking the way it's looking I guess one
thing is we're not are we how are we
dealing with the light intensity here in
terms of of clamping that
so it looks like yeah when we do the
summation of the light here we're just
adding in just one irradiance and then I
assume we clamp it afterwards but maybe
we don't and that would be bad now we do
so when we call some light right we
multiply it and then we clamp it on the
way out so we don't have a problem with
it overflowing or anything like that as
far as I can tell so yeah so I'm not
sure what we're seeing there it looks
like it sort of works for a moment
almost but then it kind of doesn't right
like it sort of looks like it's working
and then it sort of settles down to a
value that that definitely isn't working
and I guess I don't have an explanation
for that we're gonna have to maybe step
to the bugger and take a look at what
some of those values actually are
and by the way this may be something
that's just not going to work it's just
a way of trying to prevent us from
having the problem where we have to
overfill every time we take a light
sample but maybe that is what we should
be doing right like maybe we should be
summing these using negative weights and
stuff like that and we'll see but yeah
that's really weird so why would we work
right up until the point where we stop
averaging and then it doesn't work
anymore why would that be the case that
doesn't really make good sense to me
what's going on there cuz there must be
some reason and I don't know what that
reason would be it could be that our
light weight Falls to zero so you know
what we could do to so we could do
something where we could do this so this
is sort of saying like hey man tell us
what the total waiting value is that you
were able to gather and if you weren't
able to gather anything mark this as as
being like the bright purple like
nonsense thing right and just so we can
see like what's going on there again
that's like super weird right like but
you can see that that's the problem it's
not able to gather any weight anymore
which doesn't really make any sense cuz
it's pretty clear that there was some
weight to be gathered there from the
other from the forward side of things
like you know it seems like you could
have easily gathered some light from at
least one of these directions you know
what I mean so I'm not sure why it would
be having such a hard time with that
with that gather right and maybe so
maybe there's like a bug in the way this
thing was going let's take a quick look
at this
so I don't see anything but circularly
weird about it I mean it looks
reasonable enough anyway hmm and in fact
even just looking here it doesn't make
much sense because if you were gonna
fill in this value right here it seems
like you would be able to fill it in
with like these two values here right
and I have no idea
by that snapping in that way either look
we've got we've got issues um let's take
a look at one thing that I would like to
take a look at here I don't really know
I don't think we should have any D
normal problems but you know maybe we do
I want to sort of add a clamp thing so
what I might want to do here is say
let's let's change this back to a zero
clamp there and when we do our averaging
so when we do our blend so ear blend V
and u and whatever right so this part
that we do just before hand what I'd
like to do here is say let's actually
make sure that these kind of blend to
actual zero so after we compute whatever
the you know this light C value is let's
go ahead and clamp these so we're doing
a normalization here and maybe that's
part of the problem I don't know but
let's take the light C value here and
make sure that that is actually clamped
as well so if we take what do we have
for clamping here for vectors so if I
want to clamp a vector so that it clamps
down to zero I guess what I want to do
is is really something like this where I
say like look if the light C 0 R value
is less than like you know some nominal
value then I want it to be clamped right
so I'm basically just saying I don't
want tiny values in here
I don't want little bits right so just
make sure that we clamp out these values
after we do the interpolation so that we
don't get anything like particularly
tiny I don't think that has anything to
do with it but I would like to just get
that out of the way right so now we can
just test for actual 0 and get what we
expect right and that's fine
again I still I have absolutely no idea
where those weird interpolation
artifacts are coming from like I have no
I don't even have the slightest idea of
why we're getting them and I also don't
understand why the interpolation is
breaking at that point that
interpolation should still have been
smooth because there's still information
in there and I guess it was all the same
value but that doesn't make any sense so
something's busted with that with the
way that that's like interpolating the
values in that area and I don't know why
that's happening either so like very
strange stuff happening here that's not
logical and I'm not sure where it's
coming from it feels to me like a
problem where we're clamping something
in like the shader or something where we
don't where we shouldn't be or not
clamping something that we should be one
or the other but I do not know how how
we would be getting that happening here
because we're only we just clamp after
the interpolation like the interpolation
happens here right so it shouldn't
really be possible to have that occur
and I don't know where that's coming
from if we turn this off entirely so we
just don't do any of this right so let's
suppose we just said all right you know
this this goes away so now we're just
letting it be back what it used to be
I mean that's the part right that I mean
that just doesn't make any sense
right it just doesn't make any sense
I don't I do not fundamentally know how
we're getting these values so we have a
bug I'm pretty positive we just have a
bug I don't think this is like an aspect
of the scheme but where is it coming
from
so thing one would be let's regularize
our normals I guess so let's just
pretend to our normals or the same
normal and see if this is the color
Channel or the normal channel because
that's like just one way I can start to
try to break this problem down so here
we have only one normal direction right
and so the question is like if we
isolate just the color channel right do
we see weird things happening and I mean
I would say pretty much no right I don't
so if I actually only have the color
channel in the mix it seems pretty good
what happens if I fill so now I am going
to include the fill right I'm going to
include the fill but I'm going to force
the normals out so we're just filling in
the color values not the normal values
right so does that get weird kind of it
still doesn't make any sense at all so
maybe we can just work
just this and figure out what's going on
there right because that's just totally
bizarre now some of it makes some sense
because as the shadow moves into place
you are changing which values you know
are present and which ones aren't but I
mean what the heck like what even is
that I don't really know if you asked me
to produce that I'm not sure I would
know how right like it's like half of
the it's inside one half of the voxels
has stuff and on the other side it
doesn't I mean I don't even know how I
would get that value especially because
now we're taking the normal out of the
equation we're hard assigning everything
to point straight up right and so all of
the color values were assigning here are
you know are specific so I don't even
know like are we even are we passing
down these values wrong even could that
be part of the mix I don't know right so
but something's really strange and so we
need to kind of make sure we know what's
going on here with that so let's let's
yeah let's let's keep pushing forward on
that so if we have light voxel n here
where we are hard setting these normals
and we hmm what would be the next ploy
here
hmm I mean one thing is like yeah it's
not a particularly good filter and I
suppose another aspect of it is yeah I
don't know I'm not sure let me take this
off for a second so if we don't run any
of this what do we actually get
so one really weird thing about that
that I guess I don't really know well
yeah well no that's alright because if
you look at where the where the thing is
actually centered you get a reasonable
result there so I guess the interesting
thing for me here is I'm wondering yeah
I mean even right there
I just I'm wondering what that is from I
just don't know is that just from a
normal interpolation problem so what if
I turn if I stuff the normal so in here
I say all right I'm I'm stuffing the
normal
what happens to this chunk right if I
take the exact same place and I stuff
the normal value to just be one right
looks like it didn't like that oh so I
just want to know what happens here is
it a normal or is it a color value right
I guess that doesn't really help me
because it's these are pointing
perpendicular anyway so let me try
making sure they point in the right
direction to reflect the light oh
actually that's the exact wrong
direction sorry so it's definitely a bug
with the normal
and I guess it's just cuz the normal
interpolates across these two and can't
properly swing I guess what happens if I
just draw the normal why don't you tell
me what you think the normal is so to do
that I'm just gonna say the result here
is actually just the light normal happy
birthday and of course I can't quite do
that I've got to maybe do something more
like this right just a
into the visible range but other than
that yeah there you go so it's the
normal go ahead and tell me what you
think the normal is just draw it that's
gonna be the new light value right I
really need to make that hot load why is
this not what happened there
work right am I missing something
there we go I know what happened there
so this is really instructive because
that should produce a visible normal at
all times if that's zero what that means
is that the normal the normal was
literally zero zero zero right so that's
like actually getting a zero zero zero
normal the reason that is so weird is
just and I guess it's because we're
doing in normal eyes is is how it's that
just must be where the thing actually
Falls to zero you get that pattern right
so I'm assuming and you know if I do
this it will be a gradual fade out right
instead of a hard line let's see
and maybe that's not true it doesn't
look true so yeah I don't understand how
that's possible that should be gradual
right because here we're just doing the
exact interpolation it should not be
possible for this to go from having some
and to not having some immediately now I
guess this clamp with the inner product
may be good but not really because again
it should gradually go to there hmm
how's this light oh so wait a minute
what is the spec see calculation here
ref see now so I there we go
so this should it really be outside I
suppose but even so I'm not sure that
explains what I was seeing but all right
so now we're not doing it inside the ax
statement there there we go so now we
can actually see the normals and they're
right there now we're okay so what we
were seeing there was specifically a
problem with this branch this light D C
greater than zero bit so it's the inner
product between the light normal which
is what's coming in here and the world
normal going to zero and I guess the
problem that we're then having is we're
having a problem that our light
attenuation is not attenuating the
entire value like it should be so like
light DC yeah I guess the problem is
light DC really needs to multiply this
whole thing
right because this if this branch is not
gonna operate when the light is behind
we can't we need this thing to fall to
zero gradually right so that tells me
exactly the part that I was missing so
that's good so what we need is this I
guess
so that we have that cosine fall-off
baked-in always because we can't not
there may be a way to write that
equation better so that we do it in a
different way but I think that maybe
what we're looking for
oops I didn't mean to leave that running
okay so let's take a look at what this
does now and see if that's better
nope still still screwed up I mean maybe
it's a little better you can see that
it's not as hard of a line but still
pretty bad right there
so what's the deal where is that coming
from
and again let's now let's move this
inside so this way we are just going to
do this or you know what let me do it
this way so if we just say light DC
times this value so I'm just going to
take whatever light DC is and I'm going
to multiply it in to see if it's
smoothly varying right so I know those
normals we looked at those before so I'm
just gonna look so basically just
multiplying by light DC gives you crap
it has hard lines in it and we have no
idea where they come from so that's good
information so now we know we have some
critical flaw with light DC where it
doesn't smoothly fall to 0 as you
interpolate these two things right I
mean that's basically what we've
determined something about it is busted
in the sense that if you just multiply
it by anything you get badness now what
I could do is say alright let's actually
take this out let's just do light DC
times white so I just want to look at
only what is is present in the light DC
channel that's all I'm doing is
rendering that right and yeah I mean so
basically that's all we need all we need
is that one value and we will get the
error light DC itself is just critically
broken right all right so how is that
possible how is it that that is not
smoothly interpolating and you know
presumably it's because our light end
value is passing through something but
again I'm not sure how it's not passing
through smoothly though because remember
we're not normal
lysing it now it's literally just
getting directly interpolated so how
could it be that steep it doesn't seem
to make a whole lot of sense does it it
should have to be smoothly passing
through those values right
and I do not know I'm gonna go into the
OpenGL code for a second here and turn
off the interpolation just to see what I
can see about that
so if I was to take the the linear blend
here and turn that off we really need to
do is I guess go inspect the actual
values and maybe I should do that in
like render dock or something right
so I can see what the actual values are
that it's interpolate in between so I
really want to do is set a break point
there and just see what the actual
values are
so here's the unincorporated values
and again I'm not really sure what the
problem is here like why those would
interpolate the way they are
mmm I'm super stumped right now I mean
this looks like a thing that's gonna
take many hours to work out right like I
probably have to go back actually like
set this up in some way that I can test
outside of the shader cuz like these are
not things you really wanted to bug
inside a shader when they get this
complicated right I need to be able to
look at them and of course you can't
debug GPU code it's not really possible
so I probably need to do this externally
and then work it through forward looking
at the lighting value here again if it's
just the clamp that should not there
should not be any way that you can
produce what we're seeing from this
equation I have no idea how that can be
possible and the reason for that is that
light n should be able to be
interpolated in this way the inner
product will take its length into
account so as it shrinks to zero you
should see a smooth blend to zero right
so how it's producing a non smooth blend
is is totally beyond me what I would
like to do I guess
is take a look at light and more
specifically here and figure out if I
actually just output that what it looks
like so for example if I just run this
where I output light and directly
I thought we saw no weird values right
so I thought what we saw here was
everything was smooth and that does
appear to be the case if I turn off
modulation so you know up here where we
do this if I just turn off the textures
so here's where we're taking like our
texture sample for example so if here
instead of a multiplication I just do in
equals right this is what the
actual normals look like we're just
putting it in there right and so what
you can see is you can see very clearly
where the zero values are right the
zeroes are right in there
but in general right I mean I don't see
anything else particularly weird so
y-you wouldn't be able to smoothly
interpolate it mean it looks smooth
right and like in here for example where
we were getting hard lines running
through the middle of this thing that
looks totally smooth now like I don't
see hard lines running running through
it
right you know everything looks gradual
and there isn't a really hard line I
mean I guess well you know I mean that's
pretty hard line I guess so maybe I
could believe that and this is sort of
in linear light space so I suppose once
we actually put those in there and
they're not encoded um I don't know I
suppose that there's some argument to be
made for maybe that is enough of
production of a hard light like maybe
that's just enough to produce a hard
line down that that side I don't feel
like it should be though
don't think it should be so another
question then I would have is suppose we
just didn't do light DC fall-off so
suppose light DC was always Phibes was
always point five let's say right so
we're just not going to use that and
we'll let let it apply the lighting
equation separately and we just won't
care about the fact that it's you know
doing sort of a weird Lac a fall off
there what do we get in that case and so
one interesting thing about that is we
still do have fairly hard lines along
the you know along this axis but you
know maybe again that's just because of
the way the interpolation breaks out but
you can see we don't have the bug
anymore so previously right you would
get it right in here as that normal to
the light source changed too
dramatically but once you take that out
of there now we're not really getting
that problem yet I mean
hmm so the inner product between the
light the direction to the light and the
world normal that is just causing us a
lot of problems and I guess we could do
something like we were doing before
where we allowed a wider berth there I
mean we could do something more like
this which was allowing sort of it to be
wider varying than it used to be I don't
feel like we should have been having to
do that but I suppose you know maybe
that makes a lot more sense and if you
look at what happens when we do allow
that you know we do get rid of a lot of
those artifacts
that's just allowing a wider angle of
incident light to a given surface so you
don't have to quite be within the 90
degree plane right and we do get a lot
better results doing that I guess I
would say for you know 6 and 1/2 dozen
of the other so I don't know I don't
know what I think about that probably
not much honestly
yeah anyway um so let's go ahead and
take a look at a couple of things first
then and then I'm gonna call it a call
it a day so if I turn back on the
flood-fill now I want to see what I end
up with but I'm not optimistic about
this just based on the problems that
we're having it looks like maybe flood
filling is not gonna cut it for us so
here's the flood fill I'll turn it back
on here's what we're looking at now
without it right get the stair-step if I
turn the flood fill back I'm assuming it
doesn't doesn't really do much for us
but I guess I don't really know so yeah
you can see that in fact the other thing
too is we got a lot brighter in areas
which we really shouldn't have been
doing so it looks like we've got a
little bit of an issue there and I'm not
sure why like this should never brighten
anything cuz it's only filling in things
that didn't exist before so I wonder if
that just is indicative that we screwed
something up like we're filling in
elements that we shouldn't be filling in
or something like that
that seems potentially like very bad
right so take a look so oh you know what
that's that's not the case that's
probably just cuz we left in one of our
normal overwrites did we yeah we did
that's just because of this let me get
rid of that so here's the flood fill
again and what you can see here is it
filled in some areas and others yeah you
can see it it just sucks right it
doesn't even make sense what it's doing
something really bizarre going on there
so I think our flood fill is also
critically broken and I guess like
taking a look at that and getting that
working again will be for next weekend
and then deciding whether we want to use
it at all as opposed to something that
maybe picks up residual values in cells
based on like again when we actually
know which light source were hitting
filling in the values there for what
those light sources would have been
if they were there right which we could
which is basically the spam box the way
we used to do
maybe we spam to some secondary piece so
we can fill those after the fact when we
detect dara'a in light there or whatever
so anyway why we're getting like why we
are not getting fills I don't know and
so looking at like there's got to be a
pretty simple bug in here but like
looking at how the fill happens why
we're not getting a fill there it
doesn't make sense right so you would
assume that this thing would fill like
more sensibly than its filling right now
because like for example right there
that should be pretty easy for this
thing to fill in you know right from
there or something it shouldn't be much
and why you're getting that snapping no
clue that's as it blends down to zero
it's snapping I guess because those
values themselves are are going to zero
so they're triggering the has light you
know call which is this stuff here right
and you know I mean that just that looks
fine I mean the other thing we could do
is try to smoothly vary this right so
you know we could do something like this
we're instead we just try to take like
how much light this thing actually has
in it or something like that
so we just take like you know so
something like that oops
which would be smoothly varying so this
way we wouldn't be having a hard cutoff
anywhere we would always just blend
things in as some kind of a function of
things right does this work
I guess not
and if we did something like that then
in here we're instead of doing something
like has light we would just use that
sort of that value as a multiplier so it
would be more like this oops maybe more
like this
so we could do something like if this
thing has too little light then we just
go through and we find out how much
light these things have something maybe
like this something like this and when
we do this blending then in here we
would just kind of take the end light
amount as like the blending weight
something like that and again I don't
really think any this is gonna work just
based on the experimentation today I
mean there could be some severe bugs in
here and maybe it works better than I
think it does because of the bug the
bugs or something but I'm not optimistic
of the flood film anyway so putting that
together right and then doing this when
we have this light amount here then we
could sort of figure out a blending that
we would use to incorporate this into
the values that are already there so
rather than just doing in equals right
we would actually do like a plus equals
and we would multiply the the light
amount or the light blend factor like
this right and the light blend factor
would be something along the lines of
light blend equals you know light amount
we know that we're taking whatever this
clamping value is so we would say well
we know that it's less than 0.1 so what
we want to do is we want to take
whatever the light amount is and
[Music]
basically invert it
so the darker the less light we have the
more we blend in our neighbor values
right again total garbage and probably
not going to do anything useful but it's
just something to look at right and so
if we do it that way what you can see is
again we get rid of a lot of those
popping artifacts right you can see how
now it's much smoother and we don't pop
in and out and again that's just because
we removed the possibility that it could
pop by always blending things smoothly
together and it looks okay but it's not
great right it's just very odd the way
that's doing it so I'm gonna go ahead
and guess that this is not that fruitful
like maybe there's bugs in there that we
can fix but I think what we're gonna
need to do is we're going to need to
actually take it seriously and produce
the like a neighborhood blending value
when we actually do the light casting
for real right I assume we're still in
this case here so I think we're still
doing test cast from probes and we're
calling the spam voxel here right so the
way this used to work is it used to spam
these voxel slices outright and I think
what we want to do now is probably say
well alright so we're probably gonna
have to do something similar to that
where we do actually do this voxel
spamming right because we know that if
we actually let me reconstitute this
here so that we know that if we do it
that way right we know we get the
correct sort of light blurring outside
of places right I should turn off the
the fill I'm at it
yeah
that's good if nine always test to see
if a block is equal to if if a value is
equal to nine then you know you can use
it all right so if I turn off the
smoothing here and just use the
full-size spamming right when we run it
we know that will produce usable values
that fill in on the outside right and
the that gets us sort of the surrounding
area and you can see that the problem
that we end up with right is that while
it fills them in we still then have the
problem one further out right and so
when we do that spamming what we could
do is just say well let's fill in the in
those regions will actually fill in sort
of negative light for what would be
there if we don't know that we can
actually hit that right I don't actually
know to what extent we can do that but
yeah so in this case where we're
actually spamming like these other voxel
slices right and I guess here yes we
have the fall-off yeah so what we want
to do here is just say yeah that
fall-off wants to be and let me just
verify that it actually will work
properly when I get outside to someplace
large enough make sure we're still
working properly on that so it seems
like we're not capturing the negative
light there properly let me just double
check what's going on there yeah so this
clamp zero to one is is the issue there
right so we want to do here when we fill
in this light is we don't want to do
that we just want this
you
oh wait I mean never actually using that
no we are so here's the light DF there
right we're doing the light a times the
light color and then adding that in to
the accumulation at that point and so we
should now be getting negative light
values the fact that we're not getting
negative light values is is a bit
strange
hmm so you see how we're not actually
getting negative light values in here
and I don't really know why see what I
mean so we should be seeing negative
light interpolation going on in there
and we're not but we should be because
that area is not in shadow it's you know
it's getting a light see accumulator
here right and that C value should now
be negative because we're letting the
light fall-off times the light distance
it should go as far as you want it to
right and so that should produce
negative values that then get placed
into the actual solution cells unless
someone else is clamping them but I
don't know who would be doing that let's
take a look
so in here after we do apply this and we
call just they don't wheat we are doing
this here Oh duh
I put the clamping in there Wow
that's pretty brilliant KC why did I do
that it doesn't make any sense right
because I was think
oh we have to make sure those values
don't go down below zero and that was
done so anyway that's still not the
problem there right I mean you can see
it's still having the same issue so
that's not the clamp in question
is anyone else clamping hey don't see
any other clamps so yeah so we're still
so we've critically broken something
about our interpolation because before
we had no trouble with interpolating
outside the range and that was because
we were using you know we were using our
sort of negative one to one system and
that was allowing us to interpolate
properly outside there but now we've
lost that ability even though we're
presumably sending down negative values
correctly we actually aren't getting
that reconstruction I don't know why so
you know again looking at this we're
clamping in the actual shader but only
once we've done the interpolation so we
shouldn't have that shouldn't be a
problem for us right and furthermore the
normals should be set properly I would
assume because we're not doing anything
weird with them but somehow we've
destroyed our ability to interpolate
this stuff is so fussy this is why I
really wish we could step through this a
little bit better than I can I'm gonna
take a quick look here and see I'm gonna
make sure we have some light values that
are negative just to be sure
so here what I'm going to do is say look
I'm going to look to see if the R value
for example is negative on the light and
if it
I'm gonna set the result to be pure red
and just is just to make sure that we
actually are seeing some I want to make
sure that we can actually see some
negative values coming through because
if we don't have any negative values
then we know we've screwed something up
on the exterior side so let's check it
out so we're definitely not yeah it's
definitely not working so this is
checking to see whether the light value
as it comes in before clamping ever
drops below zero and it doesn't right it
should so if you look at spam fox will
slice here we pass you know light
fall-off to this I guess and the light
distance you can see that all that
information there this value should
easily be able to go negative because as
the light distance goes up this will
just continue to go down and it's not
being clamped so we should be able to
get something here to go negative right
and when we add to this accumulator
we're adding a negative value so that
should drive the accumulator downward
that would be my assertion looking for
the places we actually touch that value
I mean that will leave it negative if
it's negative right and it should blend
negative value in there I mean that I
don't see any real reason why it
wouldn't yeah I don't know so why this
wouldn't provide a negative value I'm
not sure and I want to know why so we're
not going to end today till I figure
that out cuz something's really busted
this is aggravating me so if I spam
voxels slice in here what I want to do
is just assert that light DF is positive
right and so what oops and so what
should happen here is we should just get
it should you know break immediately on
any time that produces a negative value
and the fact that it's not is nuts
so I obviously am like how is that
possible right how are those things not
far enough away that we're causing this
to go so light DF is 1.0 - light
fall-off times light distance and
apparently that's not enough to make
this actually go down to negative like
you can't actually get far enough away
to make it be negative how is this
possible
[Music]
what am I missing I mean I'm not crazy
right like if I did that it would crash
immediately right so somehow this light
fall-off times light distance there
somehow that's wrong and if we look at
what we're passing there right we have
light fall-off as a value that's coming
in here and we have light position so we
have fall-off and position coming in the
light distance is just the subtraction
right to find out how far it is from the
voxel that we're spamming and that
should be an arbitrarily large value as
you get further away from the light
source the light fall-off value is just
how fast it falls off and I guess maybe
that could be too low but if it was why
are we able to get get to black right
why are we able to get to a number
that's apparently so close to one it's
almost zero but it never quite gets
above one right why would this not be
able to drive this value above one is
the question there and so presumably if
I wanted to crank the like let's suppose
like crank the light fall-off
so you know what I'm going to do here
I'm gonna let this ride
so okay so at least somebody at some
point got below zero oddly enough it
wasn't in the case that I was thinking
so what's going on we have some serious
issues I think we're probably gonna have
to rebuild this from the ground up
starting next week where I actually a
meticulously document exactly what every
value is right so what is causing that
is it possible that that's actually the
light is just not falling off steeply
enough for something like this let's go
check that out so let's look at when we
do test cast from probes maybe that's
actually it's the normal being wacky or
something I don't know so where is the
light fall-off value being passed here
so here it is right and so maybe if I
wanted it to fall off a little more
steeply I would do that okay so
basically the problem was our light
value wasn't falling off as steep as it
should be now what's a little bit
strange about that is where what was
that stair step pattern coming from is
it just the normal that that was coming
from and I guess that's part of our
disaster is that yes that actually is
like that like what's that about where
is that stair step pattern coming from
right it should
should be negative values for the light
source is it coming from the than normal
and if so why is it coming from the
normal I mean the normal shouldn't be
completely facing away from the light
source it's a little busted right but
yeah if you take a look at that then at
least now we know at least this part is
working let's go ahead and get rid of
that and so that stair step pattern was
coming presumably from the normal in
that case because it was actually
somehow the normal producing erroneous
dot product values so now if we move
along here we can see the tighter
fall-off right and the other thing we
see here is that it really isn't a very
smooth fall-off right
it feels almost like that's really kind
of going the wrong way round so like
like the the rate of fall off there like
the the light linear space is really not
working properly kind of a thing in
terms of that square it fall off so if I
actually go to the to the computation of
those voxels its fan talks will slice
and we look at what's going on here then
in terms of the light distance I don't
know if we want to try and make that
fall-off be something that's going to be
more gradual right or this light DF
value as well be something that's more
gradual and I'm trying to think of like
what exactly that would be you know what
happens if we play around with this
thing here
of course I guess I have to preserve the
sign right because squaring will get rid
of it which is a little bit of a problem
for us I suppose not that big of a deal
but so I just want to play around with
this value and see what happens if we
can produce small like a less tight
light fall-off with a couple different
like I just want to test some of that
there so they're squaring I wanted to
see what that does
and here square rooting
so that makes it even tighter right and
so the really interesting thing here
again is just that no matter what we did
to it right it doesn't really seem to
produce any kind of a smooth
interpolation it's very hard like it's a
very hard fall off on that light and
right I mean look at how dramatic that
is which again doesn't really make a lot
of sense to me and so that feels again
like you know that's part of the
encoding like the light linear versus
nonlinear in terms of maybe like what's
going on in here I don't know if we're
doing shader sim right
sim writes or not let me take a look
all right so I don't know whether we're
doing these are not at the moment
because I'm not sure how we left our
encoding z' but it looks like we're just
forcing them to true right now so we're
just using squared rights we're not
using srgb right in the frame buffer
right now although actually I guess we
can - we can turn them off if we have
allow us RGB on so let's take a look so
yeah so we're just doing the square on
the on square so like if you actually go
into the Z bias program these paths are
actually executing right so in here the
shaders sim right texts srgb that is is
happening and so on the way in we square
our textures on the way out we square
root our values that's just what we're
doing and I do wonder now so I want to
know kind of like well okay so if that's
what's happening to what extent is that
making it difficult for us in terms of
our encoding so I'm gonna go ahead and
just turn that off for a minute
and I'm not looking for what the happens
to the colors I'm looking at what
happens to that rate of that ramp
and you can see right it's a lot
smoother now do you see how much
smoother that ramp is right so I believe
what we're seeing there is that sort of
the light linear color is I think mostly
what were what we're seeing in there in
terms of how that lighting fall-off goes
so I'm not sure exactly what we want to
do to fix that problem but possibly
maybe I don't know could be that we want
to just try and go mostly realistic
since the squared space mm-hmm you know
is is at least close to somewhat gamma
correct if we did want to do this we
could in spam voxel slice we would not
take light distance as a as a Square
rooted value so instead here we would do
length squared for light distance and
that way we would get a squared fall-off
for the light because it is going down
at the more rapid rate I don't know if
that's what we want or not oh my that
looks truly bizarre and
so I guess yeah and again I think the
problem that we're gonna have here is
just that no matter what we do the
interpolation yeah okay so I'm working
this out in my head and I see the
problem is that no matter what we do
here it doesn't really matter does it
because the fall-off that we compute if
it's squared or square root it doesn't
matter because it's going to get
interpolated linearly and so what we
need is that interpolation to be in
nonlinear Hyuk
so the problem is the value coming out
of the voxel is going to interpolate
itself linearly which we actually don't
want because the fall-off is supposed to
interpolate non linearly but it won't we
could interpolate the values and then so
we would have to encode the values and
then on square them like on the way out
right in other words I'm guessing that
the only thing we could really do here
is leave it this way
so we're actually taking it and putting
it into the Square rooted space and then
when we pull it out we'd have to square
it again
I guess meaning this also and the light
see here would have to do the same thing
so like this value right here this light
see this would have to be Square rooted
as well right so so really I suppose the
thing is like you wouldn't do this you'd
square root the in code we'll talk about
that in a second but so anyway what we'd
have to do is when we pass in the light
V value here and we pull it out this
actually has to happen I don't know if
we have a square probably do nope we
don't
right so that was a really crucial thing
I didn't think about like the
interpolation of the lining values in
the voxel is the wrong way around so
we're going to have to square them and
that means when we put them in we're
going to have to square root them right
and so I think the way we would do that
is compute this correctly so we'd
complete compute it like that and then
when we actually put it in here we'd
square root the actual result right so
basically like these values here all
have to get all have to get Square
rooted when they go in and it has to be
a sign preserving square root which is
even more ridiculous again this is sort
of sounds absurd but I'm not sure how
else you would do it so when this goes
in here we would have to do a sign
preserving square root so when we do
where did that go where we do this where
we square these values we have to then
take the sign and multiply it out
properly
so like this
and I don't actually know if we have
that either but that's something we
should be able to get pretty easily
right there should be a sine function
not that kind of sine
my operators no here we go so I'm
assuming there's a sign yeah so you can
just do that so we have a sign operator
and we can just ask that for that and
that will keep it negative if we need to
be negative and this way we can
interpolate in the squared space and
things should be fine right
famous last words so if we look at that
fall-off now
oops why did that get brighter that
should not have happened is sign not
what I think it is that shouldn't have
gotten any brighter right because it's
only multiplying by the sign so it's
only gonna keep it positive or negative
so that that was hmm what happened there
that doesn't seem good
right this should not be able to change
the brightness so if we look at the
brightness here that should not be able
to change the brightness from this
and it didn't all right that's fine all
right so the question is though why oh I
see there yeah that's like why isn't it
still producing zero values and the
answer was because of that all right
okay so now our primary problem is just
that we if we actually do square these
values we have to put them in Square
rooted properly otherwise we won't fill
them right you know what I'm saying but
you can now we now can get actual smooth
fall-off on them because they would be
interpolated presumably in a space where
things are linear for them so if we
wanted to do that we need to do that
with the square root here which again is
going to be a huge pain in the butt but
we can do it so let's just just a try to
see if this actually fixes things if we
want to do this
so we actually can encode these in the
squirt sign square root space she asked
do it this way
and off we go all right so let's say we
don't have sign here
okay so yeah not pretty but again you
can kind of see right that now you can
actually get a softer fall-off if we
have it interpolate properly so now if
we widen it out again back to how far
out it used to be in the test cast from
probes part of things where we actually
specify the fall-off so now if we let it
fall off at a wider radius that maybe
that may be too wide so let's let's go
ahead and and nuke that down a little
bit I don't know what radius we actually
want that seems better so now we should
be able to get like more of a fall-off
band right by interpolating that space
and you can see we kind of do right
we kind of do it's a little wobbly right
it's not as tight as maybe we would like
it to be but it's it's not awful right
and we can get a little bit more of a
soft fall off from that as we go hmm I
don't know what the light color is
actually here but the light colors may
be a little bit bright well
soften that down but that may be
actually part of the when we put it into
the square root space depending on how
we're doing that I guess there's some
different values we could look at there
um so I don't know right we can also try
to do some encoding there and try to
keep that from from not being as bad I
don't know if that really did the trick
I don't know if I really believe that's
all that much softer compared to what we
had before trying to double check to
make sure I didn't screw anything up
there looks about right hmm
yeah
so I mean you know and again one of the
problems that you always have in this
particular circumstance too is just
you're not gonna get the exact right
answer either way because you can't
really square and screw don't distribute
over ads so you can't really quite get
exactly the result that you should get
so we're just trying to see if we can
get a result that's you know at least
closer but it's not it's not equivalent
right so I know there's no way I don't
think you can like simulated exactly
from those values right and so you're
kind of in a bit of a sticky situation
there as you as you kind of work on the
tail of that function so I don't know
that may just not be worth it it's sort
of hard to say if we were to pull that
out of there so we're not going to do if
I pull that out of there and then look
at the the corresponding result
we'll see
so yeah I mean you know looking at it
it's definitely true that you do get a
more gradual fall off with the other
with the other method right and you know
that's what you would expect I'm going
to boost this color value again but it
definitely gives us something to think
about for next week or well we'll
probably off next week but for the week
after next anyway I'm gonna change this
light color back to something brighter
and see what happens
yeah I mean so you know I'm not sure how
I want to address that really that's a
pretty tough call because you win some
you lose some with that right like
there's
there's pros and cons of doing it in the
squared space like that and again it's
not going to be exact so I'd have to
think about what we want to do there but
you can see why there's an issue with
that right is because just the rate at
which you get that fall-off is just very
abrupt and you know you have to kind of
figure out what you're gonna do about
that in terms of just the like lighting
quality and how that's going to work so
so we'll see but I'll end it there yeah
so we'll go to a brief QA but yeah
probably not too much to talk about this
time because we're going to have to
probably break things down and go much
slower through it when we come back
after the holidays because we're going
to need effectively like we're gonna
have to work this through meticulously
if we want it to work
is what it looks like to me we're not
just going to be able to throw something
in there
oh do we have a typo in the the to Z
thing there for the flood
oh yeah all right well that would
explain why we were having some of the
weird stuff happening there I knew we
must have a bug in there somewhere thank
you for that catch I don't really think
this is gonna help us much
unfortunately I mean I wish it were we
can certainly take a quick look at it
but it's I'm just gonna go ahead and
guess that this is we've got so many
problems underlying that interpolation
that I don't think there's much that
that's really gonna be able to help us
with right yeah I mean bit of a disaster
in there at the moment of course we've
done so many other changes it's hard to
say right
I'm just looking to see what's going on
in here that all seems fine yeah
that has much to do with our problem I
mean I think basically the the the flood
fill in general is probably not gonna
work right because we weren't close like
it's not close to working I think it's
just not going to work I think we're
going to have to actually fill in values
around the neighbors when we actually do
the the raycasting much like we're doing
here right to produce that that sort of
clean interpolation I don't really think
there's really anything else we can do
that's my guess anyway
yeah because it just it wasn't something
that was like close to right you know I
mean so I think it's gonna be a thing
where you can't really do it after the
fact you've got to produce the actual
function during the Ray casting using
some kind of a dead reckoning for things
that are not on a like I don't know for
things that are not really on a sample
voxel you've got to fill stuff in for
them based on what you think it might
have been when you go to write stuff
from neighbors so we'll probably have to
like basically keep a summation of what
we think it would have been in that
square by extension and then for any
square that doesn't have light coming in
on that frame we use the extended like
the guest extended version right
have no questions so we can wrap it up
all right
all right thank you everyone for joining
us today was soda handmade hero sort of
pleasure coating with you as always I
think we've pretty much hit the end of
the stuff we can do simply with the
lighting so we are going to have to do
some fairly meticulous work when we come
back it will not be a pleasant January
just just keep that in mind and we're
going to have to kind of work through
all that stuff very precisely and test
it carefully at each stage I probably
won't stream until after the holidays so
you'll have a little bit of a winter
break and you can prepare for that yeah
so that's about it as always if you want
to follow along with at home and maybe
during winter break if you want to play
around with it you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero are going to
come to the source code so you could
follow along you can always try working
through the lighting yourself you pretty
much know what we have to do right like
we've gone over everything we have basic
stuff in place for everything but now we
have to actually go through and make
sure all of those equations are tight
and we have a plausible explanation for
how each one of them is going to work
you could definitely make that a project
because all the infrastructure is in
place so it's really just working
through that math and figuring out
exactly how each individual place should
go right alright so that's it
have a happy holidays and I will see
everyone when we return take it easy
everybody