hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hear of the show we could a complete
game live on stream we have to well I
guess we'll pick up something that we
started doing on friday which I wasn't
exactly sure how I wanted it to come out
in the end but basically this week we
probably are going to be mostly dealing
with getting the the front end to the
renderer operating such that all of our
kind of Z stuff that we want to do is
shaking out nicely we implemented our
sorting algorithm so our sprites are
sorting kind of properly at this point
but we don't really have ways of doing
the layer slices that we wanted to do
because we kind of decided we want to
put things into these stacks that are
very specifically layer based and have
certain things happen to those layers
independently perhaps of other things on
the screen so we kind of have to now go
back to the thing that we were trying to
finish originally when we kind of went
off on the sorting tangent which I
suppose is not really a tangent so much
as a prerequisite and now we got to kind
of finish that that that swath of let's
try to get Z correct from the you know
from tip to toe if you will and figure
out what that looks like because we want
to now be able to you know put we have
actual stuff you know actual game stuff
happening we want all of that code now
that we start building in terms of
monster behaviors and rendering and all
those sorts of things we want all of
those to be talking the right language
right we want to basically have a nice
easy coherent way for entities to say
what they're trying to render and where
and we don't want to have a lot of cruft
there that's quite a sort of causing
these problems and you know it doesn't
sound like a huge deal but it's going to
be a lot of work so we're going to have
to do a lot of of code organization to
get this to all happen properly because
you know we have to sort of look at how
we're going to divide things into the
slices that's step one how we're going
to Pat you know how those slices are
going to flow through the render system
to the sorting and then how they're
going to get output through the back end
either the software renderer or open gel
and there's some really crucial stuff
there that decisions we have to make and
we have to have we have a lot of kind of
competing interests as well that are
happening sort of all around a very
simple example is you know we have a
choice of where we do the sorting for
example we could move the sorting into
sort of more game code right now the
sorting is kind of more happens at the
very end right you know we probably want
to move that sorting up a bit why do I
say we want to move that sorting up a
bit well if you look at what's going to
be happening in our game code sort of
goin forwards we definitely have this
this sort of this sort of idea that you
know these slices are getting prepared
and rendered separately and you know we
know in the game code what goes on each
slice and we don't necessarily need to
expose all of that kind of masa nations
to the render layer right i mean the
render layer has to be implemented both
render layer has to be sort of
implemented into places that to be
inflamed the software render in the open
chilla renderer it's also something that
kind of wants to be you know sort of
streamlined and performance-oriented at
the at the bottom level so that we don't
have a lot of weird complexity in there
that we're not sure what to do with and
blah blah blah blah so you know we don't
really even know exactly where we want
our sort to take place we're also having
to pass down these sort keys right and
we have to store those for all of the
things all the way through the pipeline
you know that is maybe kind of wasteful
and not necessarily want to do so
there's really just a lot you know it's
it's a tremendously complex thing that
we're about to kind of look into and so
I suspect it will be actually quite a
bit of thought that has to go into how
we do that correctly
so we'll start looking at that probably
tomorrow i'm guessing today what I think
we'll probably try to do is go into the
code that we were looking at on Friday
where we were just experimenting to see
what would we do you know what's the
what's the thing that we would do if we
wanted to make it so that a character or
something could have a bunch of sprites
that were in pre like a pre sorted order
and then the that sort of collection as
a whole just got sorted in rather than
having that collection be each
individually fed into the sorter and get
sorted as it normally would be using its
sort keys so I you know there's a couple
of different ways we could do that and
like I said I'm not one hundred percent
certain what the easiest way to do it is
now what I sort of slowly kind of went
down the at the end of the stream last
time and you'll have to excuse this this
was from Saturday's little a quaternion
discussion for midlo so we were talking
about this right here manual sort
override and I sort of proposed that
there were couple different things we
could do and one of the things I pointed
out was well you know we we might not
want to merge these things you know and
I was kind of going down this route of
like oh yeah if we if we merge these
things you know we end up in a situation
where we can just treat them all as one
box which is kind of nice and simple for
this order but then the question was
well you know if you get things like
this yo do you really want those to be
sorted as one single box because if they
are sorted as a single box you include a
lot of overlap that you wouldn't
normally include and you're bringing a
lot of things into the sort overlap
region potentially that that shouldn't
necessarily be there and so perhaps a
saner way I was suggesting at the very
end of last stream is that well you know
maybe we want to still keep the boxes
and just have some way of saying that
they sort together so one thing that I
was wondering is you know
so we could do something a lot simpler
that's kind of leaning on the sort key
aspect of things which is to say if we
had you know a bunch of things that look
like this and they're all supposed to
form one coherent sprite where the order
is predetermined inside the sort key we
could just give them all identical sort
keys right so basically a B and C all
have the same sort key exactly the same
sort key right but then we just use the
order they appear in the buffer to
determine who goes in front of who which
I think we already kind of do right
meaning we already Traverse we already
put things into the linked list in the
order things appear in the buffer so it
should generally be a stable sort if
everything had exactly the same sort key
in an area I think it would generally
work to just give them identical sort
keys I know it's a little bit odd but I
think that's actually the case so I
don't know that we really need to have I
don't know that we really need to have
anything else we can just say here's the
screen area they each have different
screen area but they're sort keys are
all identical right and that's something
we could do unfortunately I don't really
know but I don't really know exactly
what that sort key would be so obviously
if it's a why sprite then we know that
it's got sort of a zmax right and the
why man why max is just it's just equal
to one thing so in this case we could
just say well it's whatever the average
why of the thing is or maybe it's just
whatever the first why is week or maybe
the user just sets with the why is right
and then the zmax presumably is just
whoever have the maximum Z right so
they're the merge actually does work
pretty well
and then on the other hand if it wasn't
a wife right if it was a Z sprite then
presumably you would have to sort of do
a Wyman wimax threshold I'm not one
hundred percent sure but either way it
seems to me like that may actually be
easier than daisy chaining because then
if we don't do the Daisy training if we
yank out the days of training that I
added in there kind of i was like here's
how we would do this if we just pull
that out it seems like we could probably
get away with actually just shoving
these things into the sort normally
having them always pushed in the the
same order and then just letting the
sort deal with it from there because the
sort keys it will always return the
right value from is in front of right
whatever the tiebreaker case happens to
be it will always return that tiebreaker
case so I yeah I don't know what else to
say about that other than it seems like
it's worth a shot because it's a simple
way to get this behavior out of the
system and usually when you're talking
about relatively complicated systems
like this if you can find ways of just
condensing down the number of unique
things that has to happen usually it's a
win in the long run because even if it's
slightly slower or slightly less
efficient to do it that way sometimes
you end up getting that efficiency back
anyway just by the fact that there isn't
so much more complexity which makes your
routine smaller and simpler you can
optimize them better there's fittingly I
catch better blah blah blah blah blah
like reducing the number of things you
have to do is sometimes leads to
efficiency in and of itself in a whole
myriad of ways and so I feel like you
know what I'd like to do is try to
condense I I don't you know I i want the
Z's I want the sorting system to do what
it needs to do but I don't want it to do
it in a way that's any more complicated
than necessary it's had to be relatively
complicated to get reasonable results it
seems but that doesn't mean we want any
complexity in there that we don't need
right
so that's just my my sort of gut feeling
on that so let me go ahead and sort of
open up some code here today is day 3 11
so if you're trying to follow along at
home you want to open up day 3 10 source
code that's the source code that I'm
starting with and I believe we just have
the standard running game here let me go
ahead and just run the latest version we
go ah let's here with 22 handmade there
we go so if I'm running this right this
is what we've currently got and the idea
is to take a look at the hero sprite who
right now is actually kind of doing
sorting and probably correctly it's just
we don't want him to be sorting we don't
want his head to go behind his jacket
ever even if he does move further back
and why we just want it to always be
above and so that's like kind of just
you know the test case I guess is can we
can we go ahead and fix that right and
so if I go to let's see here if I go to
render group we started sort of you know
penciling in how this was going to work
here and let's see ya so we have this
concept of new element that we sort of
started to introduce so normally
everything gets a new element in the
sort field and so I what we need to kind
of do here is if we were going to go
with the method I was sort of suggesting
where I think it's maybe better that
they all do get their own so that they'd
sort they'd have the different screen
areas we don't really want this this
part of things anymore right so we still
want that to happen but what we do need
to do is we need to have a notion of
sort of a right back if you will for
these sort keys so that when we do like
three things we can then go over right
there sort key
is that we were that we had with actual
in with the actual aggregate sort key
that has the new information right so
what we would need to do in that case is
sort of introduce this concept here
which is sort of like what we have which
is that you know a if we if we kind of
imagine out here I don't know what the
with the most likely place for this to
go is but if we imagine it in the render
group you know we did something like
okay you know there's a there's a sort
key or something in here oops right sort
key no what is it sprite bound sorry so
if we imagine there's a sprite bound and
this is like the aggregate bound or
something like this then if we imagine
that we were going to do you know what
let's not do next offset and existing
offset or any of that stuff because
we're not going to daisy-chain these
things together all we actually want to
do and let's get up there all we
actually want to do is we want to do a
sort of you know just bookkeeping with
the aggregate bound to sort of merge in
whatever is happening for this
particular sprite right so what we want
to do here is say like all right the
existing and we kind of did that here it
looks like we've got a maximum there we
go anyway we want to have some way of
making this track what's going on so
that later we can use the aggregate
bound that we get to overwrite the
previous entries that were in whatever
this group is so we don't want to must
mess with the screen area at all we want
the screen area to be different persona
and we're leaving that here as unique
for everybody but it's just the bounds
that we might want to deal with
and so if we take the rendered group and
we say that there's an aggregate bound
that we store in there and maybe that
just gets updated here by just some
quick min max calls right so that it's
kind of getting aggregated in a
particular way at that point we may be
are in a position to help the the user
out of you know to sort of make a little
API that people who push these things on
can use to make groups that would sort
together right so let's take a look at
what happens when we do a push bitmap
call right normally when we do a push
fit BAP call we don't get anything back
and in this case I think we're going to
now have to start to return stuff right
we're going to have to actually give
something back because the user is going
to have to be able to overwrite the sort
key information that they created with
new you know they're going to basically
have to they're going to have to go sort
of romp over some existing data with
with a new sort key after they're done
right because it's not until after we
look at what the three sprites are
whatever that we would be able to
actually have that sort key have know
what the actual sort case should have
been so the question is how we actually
going to do that it's easy enough to
just keep track of this here and to
provide a reset call so basically when
you're about to push in a bunch of
things that you want to be sorted
correctly or sorted in order with each
other you just go like reset the sort
bound and then that aggregate bound at
the end after you've done all this right
so you want it to do is you know the
it's the information that you wanted is
now in the aggregate bound and it's
ready for you to use the question is
just how do you get back at the sort of
at the sort keys of the things that you
already pushed on and so what I'm going
to do here is again since I don't know
oops exactly what that should look like
I'm going to go in here to where we
actually do our push bitmap calls and
I'm every darn time I go there used to
be there
but we moved it out to entity so you can
see us kind of doing our peace index
thing where we go through each of the
pieces that's in an entity and we push a
bitmap on for it and so you know right
here would be a totally reasonable place
for us to go sort of do that that
marking that these things were supposed
to be the same sort key right but the
question is just yet how do we actually
do that and I'm not actually sure how we
should do it uh it's it's kind of tricky
right it's a it's a little bit nasty and
actually reminds me this should be
before I'd talk about the nastiness
let's go ahead
all right uh so it's a little bit nasty
because really what I want to do is I
want to be able to just have these sort
keys I I want them to just kind of work
right i I really don't I I don't really
want to be doing this book keeping and
so I'm kind of trying to think of what's
the way that a is easiest for me to work
with but be that also doesn't create a
lot of extra copying and stuff like that
because it's just you know it's going to
be a little bit messy there's just a lot
little jörg there's just a lot more sort
of nonsense to it now when we have to
kind of go back and visit it so I'm kind
of thinking in my head well you know
when these sort keys are generated you
know do we want to try and make it so
that we can generate them into a
temporary thing and then copy them in or
do I want to just keep the pointers to
the sprite bounds and so my guess is
like well you know since we know this is
highly structured data I'm thinking that
maybe what we do is we just take
advantage of that highly structured data
and just do a really simple like sort of
known right position kind of an approach
right so rather than storing the
pointers or having it returned values or
anything since I know I pushed you know
n bitmaps on here what I kind of want to
do is just say ok you know let's go
ahead and have those piece indices let's
go give each of them the correct
aggregates or key so I want to do
something like a begin aggregate sort
key where I say oh and you know what now
that i think about it we could do this
without even having user oh this is ok
this is suddenly starting to be good
suddenly the brain is starting to kick
in you know some days you feel old and
then you get a little like you're like
oh
you know I'm not not totally useless yet
so anyway I could do a beginner get sort
key here on the render group so that
lets the render group know that that's
what I'm doing and then at the end I
could say and the aggregates sort key
and that would overwrite kind of all the
things and I think I can figure out a
way to do that that's actually
relatively clean I think we actually
won't have that much trouble with that
now think about it I was thinking that
one might be kind of copy out now I
think about it really won't be it going
to be pretty simple so the only question
is how much does the user need to tell
this thing in terms of manhandling a
sort key one way to do it would be to
not have any intervention at all so
basically it would just use the min/max
whatever kind of stuff and it would do
the right thing right but it's a little
bit twiki because you know since we've
got what Z sprites why sprites remember
if i send down 3y sprites I want the
result to all be a why sprite but if I'm
just doing the minimum the maximum of
the wyman wimax or whatever it is I'm
going to end up with a Z sprite
accidentally because it's it will have
created a wide in Y sprite out of these
multiple sprites which is not what I
really want I still want the thing to be
a why sprite so the question is is that
something that we like override so do we
say like end aggregate sort key and pass
like the sort key here and we monkey
with the sort key and if so how do we
monkey with a sore key you know how do
we want to monkey with the sort key
exactly do we need information like do
we want to take our Wyman wimax from a
particular person and make that be you
know you know I don't know so that part
is a little confusing to me so I'm not
really sure what we want to do there but
what I'll say is at first let's just do
the beginning end aggregate fully
automated and then we'll try to figure
out how we're
going to make it less automated as as
things go by all right so how would we
implement this right well begin
aggregate sort key what I need to do is
I need to first initialize this
information right so my aggregate bound
needs to be initialized to something
that will allow me to store and lump
allow me to scroll there you go that
will allow me to sort of keep track of
the mins and maxes that I get so what
I'm going to do is the same trick we've
done many times on handmade hero I'm
just going to give these guys and I
suppose I don't know if we ever defined
that I'm going to initialize these guys
to the worst possible values for
whatever they are so that literally
anyone who happens to be involved will
override it right so i initialize the
max to the absolute minimum value could
possibly ever have so no matter who
comes in they will overwrite it right so
you'll always be expanding okay so you
know this would initialize that that
aggregate bound so now as you go you'll
get exactly you'll get exactly what we
wanted which is of the sprites that you
push after calling begin aggregates are
key you'll just get you'll just get all
of that that happening right um I
suppose there's another trick we could
have done here mm I don't know no all
right so I'm going to then do end our
youth sort key and you can see why this
one needs a little bit more information
what we need to do here is we need to
loop over all of the sort keys and then
we need to assign them to our we need to
overwrite them with our aggregate bound
right so our aggregate bound you know we
need something that's going to be like
sort sprite bound entry here well
actually probably going to be here
so that's going to equal something and
then we're going to want our entry sort
key to be equal to this aggregate key
that we've created right that's what we
actually want to have happen so the
question is how do we actually get this
piece of information right and we know
that we're going to have some kind of a
counter here so we can probably do
something like you know aggregate count
so it would be you know index equals
zero index you know less than either
good count plus this index or something
like this where we're looping over some
understanding of what the aggregate
count is and we just initially
initialize that aggregate count to zero
and every time we record a sprite we
would go ahead and make that aggregate
can increase right okay so when we're
doing this begin aggregate end aggregate
situation we've got that stuff happening
so then I've got you know aggregate
count or something like this in here and
so if we compile this right hopefully we
can get to the point where this is what
we don't know what sprite bound is that
true we don't know sprite poundings
apparently we don't apparently you don't
know what sprite bound is and that's a
shame so sort is there is sort not oh my
is sort not included anywhere in here
I'm confused I'm confused by that that
can't be right can it
oh right it's not know what am I talking
about it's not in sort it's in rendered
on H right yeah so render dot H would
have to actually be above render group
dot H so what it looks like which I
don't know that's going to fly but looks
like that case all right so it looks
like I jumped the gun here on putting
the word render in front of that looks
like it's actually just called group in
this function who knows why why ask why
sometimes we just named things wrong and
so yeah so let's take a look at platform
we've got our pound defiance here
where's our maximum at there it is so
I'm going to go ahead and those guys
together and so we're all compiling now
so really we just have to figure out how
do we actually get these so you know
obviously it's going to be something +
index so we just need some way of
knowing hey we're actually are these
things right and I shouldn't say plus a
nice because probably gonna be minus
index but you get the idea where
actually are these things well you can
look at what happens here right you can
see this situation where we do commands
sort entry at and we've got sort spray
bound and then we say like okay you know
for each of these it's off the push
buffer this particular location so we
know that when we start one of these
aggregates we could say well okay you
know the render group aggregate you know
first aggregate or something we know
where it is we know exactly where it is
right it's it's here
right because we know when we start the
next thing that gets pushed this is the
location that's going to get pushed at I
mean we know that so now we have a
really easy way of knowing where in the
render information this is actually
going to live so we can just snap that
pointer and say oh well you know guess
we could call it first aggregate at
probably so we now know where that is so
if we want to then you know get where
the start is we would say like oh it's
the push buffer base you know plus the
sort entry at right that's where it's
going to be that's where it would be and
that's the first one each one after that
is just going to be one before it right
so I just have to back up one each time
I want you know the one that that comes
next so I think that's like literally
alder there is to it I don't know
where's that okay commands I don't know
that really there's anything more to it
I think that's a pretty straightforward
way of implementing that that should
work right so yeah so I think now when
we do begin key NK now we have the
region who was affected we can go back
and overwrite them and we're good to go
now we just have one more problem which
is we need some way of determining what
we should actually do here right we know
we always want to increment the
aggregate count but once we are in an
aggregate we want some information about
what's going on to figure out how
whether we should expand the Y range or
average the Y range or who knows what
else right we should do I'm not sure so
you know I guess the first thing I would
say is well
you know we could do a thing where we
say you know if the group aggregate
count you know is equal to 0 then we
know that the aggregate boundary alee
just be the sort key so if it's the
first one you know just copy it then if
its subsequent ones then we just need to
know easy to Z sprite or is it a why
sprite right so we kind of want to do
here like okay if you know if and I
don't know if the render stuff has this
in there is why sprite this is in front
of ya and so you can kind of see like
this is the test right for whether
something zazzy sprite or a why sprite
on so we kind of want you know like a
thing that's like is why sprite
and I guess technically this is an izze
sprite so whatever but point being when
we pass one of these fry pans we're
gonna say like is it as East right well
it is if these two things aren't equal
to each other it's like okay so then
what we could say is well you know is it
a Z sprite this thing that we've gotten
so far and if it is as East right maybe
we assert that the thing we're getting
is also a Z sprite because if you tried
to aggregate y and z sprites together
that wouldn't work right I don't think
there's any way you could do that
because dozin actually need to be sorted
separately they can't be sorted as one
unit because there is no meaning we
don't have meaning for that so assuming
it's a Z sprite we would assert that and
assuming that it is not as East bright
than we would assert that it's not and
then we would have sort of two different
operations that we would do here so in
the case that it is a Z sprite then we
want to do I think exactly what we're
looking at here right we just want to
expand all the bounds of this thing and
move it up to the higher level right
whichever level is higher in the case
where it's a y sprite I think you know
probably we just don't do anything to
the Y pounds because it's like well you
know you just figure wherever your first
why was that's where we assume you are
now maybe later we find we want to do
something more complicated than that but
at the moment you know who knows
that's weird under why the indentation
isn't working there so in a while since
I've seen a indent bug and for cutter
matter if I did something wrong huh
weird anyway let's see is these sprites
yes the identifiers not found that is
true I gotta put that guy up in the H
file where people can see him so yeah so
that is the aggregate sorting now we got
to go through and make sure that we're
actually doing this correctly but we'll
see okay so our assert fired there oh so
here's one thing that's a slight prob
Medicare is I suppose since this is
operating all the time when we're doing
aggregation I guess I don't know we kind
of need some way to say that we're not
aggregating so that we won't do any of
this in the cases where we're not
supposed to be aggregating for lack of a
better term so I'm not sure what we want
to do there but probably just like I
guess you know if group aggregating
something like this and then when we
take a look at the render group we just
have to have in there somewhere there
has to be a like aggregating because
otherwise we're going to yet otherwise
it's going to try to aggregate all the
sprites that we ever push on right and
obviously you're going to get an
assertion in there when somebody pitches
a wife's right in disease right back to
back so what we want to do now that's
actually not a bad thing for just for
our own sanity as well because we can
say you know assert that we're not
aggregating when you try to do it begin
so we know you didn't like tied you to
begins in a row and similarly when you
do an end we can do the opposite we can
say like Oh assert that you were
aggregating one and then we turn it to
false so that seems reasonable okay so
now we've got to figure out if any of
that makes any sense and I don't know
but what I will say is first off it
doesn't look like it works properly so
that's not my favorite thing or at least
it doesn't look like it worked right off
the bat because as you can see it does
switch the order of those three who are
all on the same oh wait no they're not I
lied those are actually two separate
entities right now we're not sending
them down as aggregate so the question
is just do the does the torso in the
Cape ever change and it looks like they
don't at the moment so for all we know
this actually is working ok because and
now we just have to make sure that the
head actually gets aggregated on there
somehow right which right now we don't
have really a clean way to do but yeah
so right that actually looks that
actually looks somewhat workable so I'm
actually okay with that solution and
furthermore I think there's a certain
value to that solution as well which is
that it means it also means that you
don't have to
have like when we do that is aggregating
it gives us a nice back door because we
can also save whatever that aggregate
key is like we could add some stuff
there to save what that aggregate key
was and then you could put people into
that aggregate route just by using that
key even if you did them much later
right and that seems a lot better so i
think that means we can safely pull out
the daisy chaining stuff so i'm gonna
nuke it because it's just like i said
more complication than what I then then
I think is necessary so I think we can
say that the the entry struct doesn't
need to have that in it so where is that
guy render and tree so we just get rid
of the next field and now we just look
at everybody who was doing that and
let's see wait that was the clip wrecked
I don't want the clip wrecked I want the
render entry the render entry header
thing there it is so it's next offset
it's that guy so that guy needs to go
away and now i think the the while
header offset stuff doesn't need to be
here right because it's only going to
load one thing each time
okay and I assume that means that in
handmade rendered we didn't do that yet
but I don't actually know see it was
that just an infinite loop we had made
there yeah way to go on that glad we
never ran that that would not have
worked all right so yeah that all looks
good and now we've gotten rid of that
feature that we don't actually want so
that's good okay so now we just have a
question of well what order do we
actually put these things in and as far
as I'm concerned we'll just put them in
the order that's easiest for the render
deal with so if that's the order it's
doing with now we'll just say that we
put them we draw in whatever the
opposite order of the things come in so
like if we go to world mode and we look
at the code for creating a hero wherever
that is at peace when it does these
peace at auditions I think we just say
like okay you know that's
that's that and now those should always
be in that order and they do appear to
be okay so now we can kind of move on to
our second problem which is more a
problem for the entity system than than
it is for anybody else which is how
would we communicate something very
twiki and out of bands such as the head
should always be over the body if
they're together right it's kind of it's
kind of annoying right but you can see
the artifact that I want to get rid of
which is just as the head moves behind
where the body would be in Z you get
that that nasty little um glitch there
right where they pop and so I just I
need some way of articulating that right
and that's gonna be a little tricky now
I don't know what have I got I got 15
minutes so i think i'm even though we're
not really looking at the entity system
right now like right we're supposed to
be doing mostly sorting stuff and this
doesn't have a lot to do with the
sorting i kind of want to bounce back
there and just see where i might put
this or how i might make this happen
because again it might inform how the
api shakes out on the render group side
and so i just want to see where that
would go in the meantime i also am
wondering i think we added so like some
of these things like this is just
nonsense stuff here right these are just
I think these are literally just there
for no reason other than to try and make
the sorting work so since the sorting
actually works now I think we can just
get rid of those kind of TWiki nonsense
values that were there for no reason
other than sorting because now it just
always sorts correctly since we're
actually doing it semantically and we
know that we can just say like hey
that's gonna that's going to be that way
and off we go and so that's good so yes
so we know that that's all going to be
reasonable now the thing that i don't
know like i said is how to do the head
and the reason i don't know that is
because those two things happen
separately the head and the body are set
for entities potentially and they don't
necessarily know how to you know how to
find each other or whatever uh so I
guess my question is just well you know
is that something that I should just
hack is there a particular way that I
should be doing that cleanly and and I
don't know my guess is that the easiest
thing to do is probably is is that's why
the easier not the easiest the best
thing to do is probably to have some way
of specifying a like hey I need this
entity to be in front of this entity or
something thing that we can just put
into the into the system that's my guess
because in you know in cases where we
have all the pieces together it's
obviously much more efficient I think to
just do it the way we just did it but in
cases where we just have these weird
special case things like oh you know
maybe we want some code that says if
this guy is standing on this thing then
make sure he's in front of it or
whatever you know if we've got that kind
of one-off hacky code that we're sort of
just doing when we want to patch up
little weird to dville things that don't
make any sense any other way really I'm
not sure we want to have to do anything
beyond just the basic statement of the
facts should be true so I don't know
let's take a look so inside brain when
we do execute brain right we've got our
different brain types here and we got
the brain hero the brain hero is the
thing that that looks at you know a
bunch of stuff the probably the the head
the glove the body all this stuff and so
it knows whether the body in the head or
it it would know it would be the place
to go like oh yeah i know that you know
these two guys are together or whatever
but you know i don't know so i just
don't know how i want it to sort of
signal this piece of information
obviously I can sort of put something
into the entity structures to say like
hey you know when you go to render make
sure you do this thing but I don't know
this is a tricky one so i suppose what
will yeah so if we obsess not
functionable so if we come to the end of
the index you can see as we run through
here where we sort of do our updatable
movement mode stuff and all that
nonsense when we come to do our
rendering here you can see this is the
routine that's this is the part of the
routine that's relevant right what we
want to do here is say oh well we want
to have whatever the sort key is that
comes out of this thing we also want to
romp over the head the floating head
entity and anything that has to do with
the head we want it to get that sort key
as well
and actually now I think about we don't
even want that because since we don't
know what order of those things will be
pushed in we really do need something
that says hey this goes in front of that
or whatever so hmm
I can't say I have a particularly good
idea of how we'd want to do that the
fundamental problem that I have with it
is just that you know I'm pushing these
things down to the renderer and the
renderer is the thing that has the
sorting but I have no way of really
telling the renderer about something it
hasn't seen yet so if I'm the body and I
happen to be the thing that gets rent
you know push to the renderer first at
that point I could say hey there's a
head that's going to be coming and it
needs to go first how do i forward
reference that right that's a tricky
problem uh or similarly what if the head
already happened I then have to say oh I
have you know you saw this guy it was
the head I need to go behind him or
whatever right and so it's kind of
tricky because since we don't know what
order these things are going in and you
know I don't know that we want to start
trying to enforce the order that they're
go in because that doesn't necessarily
seem like really a good thing either I
just feel like it's a little it's a
little bit subtle
so if you think through or if you if you
look at in render dot CPP so you know
when we actually go through and build
the sprite graph which is this code
right here you can kind of see where we
do this sort of edge you know push the
push truck for the edge uh I I would
suppose that we might be able to make
something which sort of just manhandles
that edge code in a forward-looking way
so
so how about this
a manual edge specification how about
this
when we go to construct the edge graph
obviously we could do something where it
we have a side band that's some
information that's like manual edges
right and in that list of manual edges
we would have like you know here's one
and here's one to sprite these point2
like some sprite bounds and we want
these to you know say these two guys
should have the you know is in front of
edge it's like it's like this guy is in
front of this guy or something like that
right so if we were to do something like
that our problem is it's pretty easy to
choose which guy we specify this on
right because we're right in the code
and we know that the head always goes in
front of the body it's our choice we
could specify that on the body we could
specify it on the head we as programmers
it's not like harder or easier either
way to do that so we can pick which one
so since edges are flown off of the the
is in front of I believe right its edge
it's a is in front of be the its next
the same front is what it's spun off of
so you know if this is the front guy and
this is the back guy then what we would
do is say well whoever is the front guy
it's pretty easy to just make the call
at that point so when we do the is in
front of we make the call on the guy
who's the front guy not the bad guy so
then the problem becomes how do we fill
in the back who's the bad guy because we
don't know when we do that we don't
necessarily know where that guy is we
have no idea right we have no idea so
what we could do is we could use some
kind of a slotting scheme right you know
again it's kind of complicated but I
can't think of anything better what we
could say is just well there's somebody
all right there's going to be a dude and
you're gonna see a dude with tag you
know three or something and when you see
a guy with tag three that's the guy I'm
going to be in front of we count how
many of these special ones we have and
we just have a little like side band
structure at short time when we loop
through all of the nodes we just go
ahead and say oh when we see this guy
he's number three we just stick him into
the you know well well we would stick
them into bin three right then when we
process this edge list we just go and
say oh we're looking for guy three who
is guy three he's this guy off we go
right it's a little bit of extra
bookkeeping but I think it would work
and yeah I think that's my suggestion
and it we're out of time so we'll go to
the Q&amp;A
Q&amp;A begins now
hello I see no questions I guess it'll
be a quick Q&amp;A
so literally no questions
all right well if there's no questions
then I guess we're done how do I get
inst about to ask a question I don't
know how to make him do it
it's about insta BOTS kind of a national
treasure what can I say all right let's
close it down short Q&amp;A is always fine
thank you everyone for joining me from
those sort of handmade here at some
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always peer to the game on hand
made hiro de or it come to the source
code so you can follow along we also
have a forum site that you can go to ask
questions a patreon page you want
support the video series a schedule
about the tweets the schedule at you and
an episode guide that you can use to
catch up on past episodes that's about
it I'll be back tomorrow 5 p.m. pacific
daylight time until then have fun coding
and i will see you guys on the internet
take it easy everyone