hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero I you know today we're gonna have
to cover the patreon situation because
and if people who are watching this
video on demand quite a bit later you
may have forgotten about this incident
and now we're just recalling oh hey
remember that time when patreon was a
thing and then over one weekend the
entire thing collapsed and then they all
went out of business basically for those
of you who aren't aware of the situation
regarding patreon or perhaps don't even
know what patreon is patreon is a
service that allowed people to create an
account and solicit contributions for
projects they were working on and people
could go on there and pledge small money
amounts or large limits they could
pledge a thousand dollars to this person
or they could pledge one dollar to this
person didn't matter
and then the person could optionally
also offer rewards like with Kickstarter
or those kinds of project funding models
do but that's all it was right so it's
just a site where you could go and
create a essentially like it's not
really a donation cuz you're not a
charity but it's basically that it's
basically saying hey I'm working on this
project if you'd like to donate money to
it it's much appreciated you don't have
to write and occasionally depending on
the patreon it might also be that if you
donate money to it you get a bonus right
look maybe maybe this project is
creating a comic strip and if you donate
to it you will get access to our special
like you know art book PDF or something
right that you wouldn't have gotten
otherwise or I've seen people like they
give out the comic one day early from
when they post it online so you know you
get some benefits for being a donor
those sorts of things and so that is
what patreon was and handmade hero is
you know it's a commercial project it's
like half and half it's making a game
and the game in the source code still
cost fifteen dollars to buy it's
commercial project but it does have a
free side which is we give away all the
videos for free and we put up all the
programming resources for free
that we do however we created a patreon
a while back not
to long after start a series because
people were requesting a way to donate
money to the project and so we did and
we've happened for a long time and it
created it's generated quite a bit of
money cuz it's been running for like
three three years or so and it probably
collected I think somewhere around sixty
thousand dollars which is a lot of money
and what we've been doing with that
money is actually giving giving it away
most of the time I would turn around and
give away the the vast majority of the
money that came in on the patreon to
other projects that where people had
started based on handmade hero because
this seemed like the most fair way to
deal with the money and there's been a
lot of great stuff that has been
supported by this money in the past the
annotated episode guide is one of them
that's one that probably a lot of you're
familiar with and that's just it here at
handmade network slash episodes and this
is an amazing resource done by midlow
from the chat and by Asif Gartner he
made the search engine and it's
basically a thing where you can just
type in anything you want like you know
cube or something and it will tell you
anytime I did a major thing on that at
all right and this is just an amazing
resource because handmade here is not
really meant to be concise project by
default it's just me doing a bunch of
programming and showing what comes up
when you do it and so it's very hard to
access it in a random access fashion but
this resource is amazing and it's helped
so many people and that is what we gave
a significant portion of the patreon
money to over the years
similarly this entire site right which
is handmade Network this was all made by
volunteers
abner coimbra basically took it upon
himself to organize a bunch of people to
create this site and then like and
requester and I can never pronounce his
name but calamy on on the on the chat
his name is Gerren i think is how you
pronounce it but they like and a bunch
of other people I don't even know all
people who are involved built this
entire site which hosts that episode
guide not to mention all these other
wonderful products that people are
baking see handmade hero is just one of
several projects on here
that have been awesome and that are just
I mean like there's just so much great
stuff going on here
and it supports forums for them news for
them and of course stuff like that
episode guide has now has a place to
live
and so that was another thing that we
sent a bunch of money to so we tried to
let cover their hosting costs and we
would send quite a bit of money out of
our take every month to them in in
addition we also supported a number of
projects that we use on the stream we
sent money to Alan Webster's awesome for
coder project which of course is the
editor we use on stream I mean it's
literally we replace the editor we were
using buy one written by someone who was
a viewer of the series originally right
and the same was true of our drawing
program Sergio created the Milton
drawing package and that's the drawing
package that we use on streaming out to
replace mischief which is what we used
originally and so this money that came
in for the patreon even though it was
not the thing that we were using to make
money for like for Molly rocket it was
making money for a lot of people and
those people were doing amazing work so
I definitely am happy with how the
patreon thing worked out it got money
from people who wanted to donate -
project to people who did great stuff
right it did exactly what it was
supposed to do in my mind in terms of
contributors supporting volunteers on a
project right and I'll be honest
patrons kind of a janky system it didn't
make it easy to do this I basically had
to like make these pledges and pay for
the pledges first and then it would like
recover the pledges the next month and I
had to like reimburse myself or it was
even they didn't make it as easy as it
should have been but he worked right I
mean hey it got the money to the right
place eventually so that people who
wanted to to contribute money to the
project could contribute money and it
went somewhere good right and that never
would have happened without patreon so
you know I feel like they deserve some
credit for that on the other hand they
definitely have been having kind of a
streak if you will of really bad sort of
public facing issues happening and while
none of these issues have been I would
say you know really catastrophic ly
underhanded or
weird in and of themselves perhaps it is
kind of getting to the point now where
it's really not a very comfortable
platform to encourage people to support
and it's really not a platform that I
want to be associated with anymore if
for no other reason even if we take out
any of the decisions or my personal
opinions about them or any of that stuff
just the general public perception of
patreon amongst people who use the
service is rapidly declining and I don't
really want to be associated with a
platform that is that its own users are
feeling like is mistreating them right I
mean that's just not a company and it's
not a product that you want to be
associated with especially not when
you're talking about a generally a
goodwill activity right the commercial
side of handmade hero is one thing but
the volunteer side of handmade here is
quite the other and when you're talking
about people who are voluntarily for
nothing in return giving some money to
support a project it's pretty important
that that happened in a way that people
feel good about because by and large
they are doing it just because they are
trying to do a good thing right it is a
purely altruistic gesture on the airport
to try and support volunteers who are
making something that they like right
and so I feel like even more so than
with a commercial project and you know
for example the purchase of handmade
here on the source code right which goes
through send owl even more so than
something like that something that's
entirely altruistic or voluntary based
or whatever that's you know generally
based on goodwill I really don't feel
like you can afford to have sort of the
cloud of question ability you know
hanging over it that's not gonna give
people who contribute money a good
feeling about their contribution and
it's also not gonna give the people who
are just volunteering who are just
trying to get paid for hard work that
they're doing you know a good sort of
Sheen right it's not it's not painting
them with a flattering brush that
they're going through this service that
is fundamentally pissing people off I
mean let's just cut to the chase so
again taking out any sort of ideological
or
[Music]
economic disagreements you might have or
I might have with how they've been doing
things or how you specifically feel
about these things I do think that at
this point unfortunately it's gotten to
the point where regardless of anything
it's just not a great service to be a
part of so this letter here that I've
got up on the screen is something that I
wrote to everyone who has contributed to
the patreon or I guess who's still
contributing I don't know exactly how
patreon decides who gets a post to a
patrons mailing list but I believe it
just goes to anyone who's currently
subscribed and basically what I said was
you know sort of what I just said to you
here's all the great stuff that this is
enabled and hey patreon seems like
they're imploding right now and so I'm
gonna try and figure out an alternative
and that's exactly what we're doing
right now many of the projects that we
have supported have already closed their
patreon so this is rapidly becoming an
issue that we'll probably have to get
resolved this this weekend for example
for coder Allen Webster said he is
closing his patreon remedy dbg the
debugger project we were starting to
support with the handmade hero money
because we want to replacement to butter
framing here as well so we can have all
open projects running that have like
been based on essentially like the
principles of the series
I guess open isn't really the important
part it's just based on C++ low-level
coding I guess what you would say I that
one closed Abner closed the handmade
networks patreon which was a big one we
gave money to and midlow I don't think
has closed his yet and that's the
episode guide one which was another
really big one in terms of contributions
for us but he might write and so
basically patreon has has imploded with
such speed that we have not gotten a
replacement in place yet but I am going
to try and get that up this weekend so
hopefully by Monday we will have an
alternative set up that you can go to if
you are a patreon pleasure or want to
support the series and are planning on
pledging we're going to open up
something else as soon as we possibly
can and we will be closing the handmade
hero patreon very shortly
much sooner even than I thought we were
going to close it when I wrote this
letter it probably won't be weeks it'll
probably be days so I don't have an
exact update about that yet come
tomorrow's handmade hero stream I may
have a more concrete solution in place
and I can put you to it but that is what
we're working on right now and so come
Monday I suspect we will have our
patreon closed and we will have another
option in place for those people who
wanted to continue supporting these
projects so yes long story short I
apologize to everyone who is affected by
this I apologize to the people who have
been doing great work to support the
many people who learn from handmade hero
making the episode guide making the
drawing package all of these things
hosting handmade Network these things
have made a difference to many many
people and they really made a difference
to how people are able to use handmade
hero as a learning resource and I
apologize to those people who will not
be getting this money now because we
have to close the patreon I apologize to
all the patrons who have to deal with
this stuff they were just trying to
donate money to do something they liked
and now they have to worry about this
and our is their pledge being handled
properly what's happening with this
service what's going right they don't
deserve that either so I apologize to
everybody and I will try to fix patreon
disaster as soon as humanly possible in
a way that continues to allow the people
who wanted to donate money to continue
donating it so that these other projects
can continue and be funded that's really
all there is to say I don't have much to
say about patreon actual problems
because I don't think they're super
relevant suffice to say my personal take
was just after reading their
explanations of what they were doing in
this latest round I was not particularly
convinced already going into it that
they were under good leadership after
reading their latest round of
explanations for this particular problem
and given how this particular problem
came up
I would say that I have like very little
confidence in their leadership in terms
of their ability to run a site that does
what it's supposed to do and keeps
people happy so I just think there's not
a lot of future there I think they're
probably going away and so even if I
thought all of the stuff they had done
was fine I probably would still bail on
them because I don't think they're gonna
be around much longer if that makes
sense so that's it if you have any
questions people have been commenting on
this thread you can go ahead and comment
on this thread if you are a patron you
of handmade hero patreon you have gotten
this email and it does have a link to
this webpage but I mean you can see the
URL right here if you want to type it in
directly so yeah one five seven eight
six eight four seven that is the post
number so you can go here and comment on
this if you'd like to discuss it with
other patreon you can also just go to
probably a better way as he rode on a
network and here at network of course
has our forums on it there's this forums
button right here you can click on and
if you're on if you want to comment you
can comment in here anywhere you want I
don't care where you comment on it we'll
move it somewhere reasonable either way
put it under game or something and we
can talk about it there as well but
either or I suspect there's not gonna
have to be much more discussion about it
because like I said by the end of the
weekend I should have something in place
even if it's only just a mailing list
that you can put your name on so that
when we have a solution come back online
you can come back and pledge if you want
because once we close the patreon which
will happen relatively soon there will
no longer be a way for you to direct
pledges towards these projects that's
about it so anyway if you have questions
about like I said you can come comment
here I will be watching it or you can
put in the forums and I'll try to log in
there and check them out but that's
about it
and it's a lot of people like I said it
says you can see right here it's 158
people so I'm hoping that everyone got
this and everyone understands what's
going on it was more there was probably
a hundred and seventy or something
before this lots of people have already
cancelled their pledges
and understandably so so you know we
will we'll go from here and hopefully
nobody is - nobody's project is hurt too
hard by this I feel worse for probably
other people out there who were relying
on patreon more for their entire thing
like a lot of the people who do the
handmade hero stuff at least have other
irons in the fire I know there's
probably people out there who were maybe
even living on their patreon I don't
know it doesn't tend to generate a huge
amount of revenue but it generates you
know for some people it generates quite
a bit
I hope those those people's products
aren't destroyed it's a really bad
situation and I feel like you know
especially maybe some of the higher
money patrons there's people who make
like 10 20 thousand dollars a month on
patreon and run an entire business out
of it it's not many people but I know
that you know there's there's plenty of
people like Jim sterling and David Rubin
there's there's just people out there
who you know when you read about patreon
they're like hey here's some people who
basically run a studio off of this thing
and I don't know what's gonna happen to
those people I hope they're able to move
to something else because it seems like
this is going downhill quickly and it
won't have a significant effect on
handmade hero hopefully it won't have
too significant of an impact on the
handmade hero related projects but I
think there probably are some products
out there that are probably in real dire
straits because of this and I anyway my
heart goes out to those people because I
know how hard it is to be doing
something you really believe in and to
finally have it work out and then have
something like this happen and feel like
it's got to be really tough so hopefully
those people can find some other way to
get their patreon xand supporters moved
over and that not there's not too much
attrition during that process of people
just not wanting to have to bother
moving their stuff over somewhere else
or whatever so I don't know what
happened but it's really unfortunate
anyway moving off of that sad note on to
a neutral note I have been asked by none
other than midlow the maintainer of the
episode guide who I was just speaking so
highly of to please mention on stream my
chair apparently he gets a lot of people
asking about the chair or something and
he wanted to get it notated into the
episode guide and I think I've only ever
talked about the chair on the pre stream
before which of course is not kept and
is not entered into the video on-demand
archive so it cannot be notated the
chairs that we use at Mali rocket and
that I am sitting in right now is the
space seating professional eirGrid dark
back and padded black eco leather seat
two to one synchro tilt control
adjustable arms with tilt tension nylon
bass managers chair I do not know why
anyone would name a chair that I
probably would have just called it the
space eirGrid chair and then when I made
another chair I would name it something
else
but they did not decide to do that so
there you go and in case you're
wondering about whether you can afford
to forget the words space seating
professional eirGrid dark back and
padded black eco leather seat two to one
synchro tilt control adjustable arms
until attention with nylon based Madrid
chair chair you do have to because if
you accidentally get any of those words
wrong you will probably buy another
chair there are many of these chairs and
they are actually quite different so for
some reason you think you want to buy
the exact same chair that we are using
you have to actually buy this one not
one of the other ones also called a
space seating professional eirGrid chair
this is what we use I quite like them
but chairs are a matter of personal
preference so you may hate them also we
don't receive any money from eirGrid
this is a purely what we use and like
recommendation it's not a product
placement I'm just answering the
question of what we have in our
experience they're pretty cheap for
office chairs because $160 isn't free
there's definitely much cheaper office
chairs out there but there's much more
expensive office chairs out there
you can go buy a Herman Miller chair and
they can probably run you 1,400 dollars
or something like this these chairs on
the other hand I find are better than
those chairs I find them to be much more
comfortable much more supportive and
they're much cheaper so this is what we
use and we have a bunch of them here
we've been using them for several years
haven't had any problems we don't put
the arms on nobody here likes the arms
or I should say perhaps more
specifically nobody here likes having
arms on their chairs really so if
anything we either we don't mount the
arms at all most the time but other
times we mount the arms facing backwards
so there's just a place to lean back and
put your elbows if you want but when you
lean forward to work the arms are not in
your way at all because you can just
flip which the direction you can see
they're sort of tilted forwards so
that's what we use basically armless the
armless version we don't attach the arms
for this chair and hopefully that gives
me below everything he needs to notate
this for people who have questions about
the chair I think that's everything we
were supposed to cover at the beginning
of the series that's a lot of
frontmatter but hopefully it was useful
and now that we have taken up 30 minutes
with preamble let's go ahead and program
I believe if I did not reset the timer
incorrectly it is day 413 on handmade
hero I will well actually you know out
enough the episode guard has been
updated yet has it it has not let me
take a look at where we're at on the
YouTube archive we are at day 412 so day
413 is correct
oops I don't really need to get rid of
that do I just put it back there so we
are in day 413 so Dave 412 source code
if you are someone who pre-ordered the
game day 412 source code is what you
want to start with for today we are in
the middle of trying to debug our basic
lighting solution that we've been
working on so while we give Visual
Studio 17 years to start up I mean it's
a text editor after
it's gonna take a long time to load all
that important stuff let's go ahead and
run it and see where we are
I'll also build it first here just to
make sure we've got a fresh one all
right here we go so here you can see a
completely unlit level if I hit the f1
key it will run sort of our lighting
solution here and you can see our voxel
samples these are not actually the
samples of lighting they're just voxels
cells where we did compute lighting and
it just shows that I think the first or
maybe the average of the light in that
area but there's actually many lights
per voxel in the area anyway here is
what the interpolate idli ting solution
looks like as you can see it's actually
starting to get pretty good it's not
actually good yet it's just getting
pretty good because if you take a look
at what we're seeing here it's sort of
starting to look like an actual lighting
solution it's just not a good one yet
there's a lot of bugs I see in here a
lot of things that probably aren't quite
right and so our job over the next
couple sessions we already did some good
debugging we fixed the voxel
interpolation bugs that we had before
we're fetching outside the voxel would
do something stupid you already fixed
that and it made a huge difference and
now we just need to go through and check
a bunch of things
hey that we're doing reasonable lighting
calculations be that our ray casting is
actually working properly we've done no
debugging yet so far for all we know our
ray casting isn't even properly
intersecting with the boxes that we're
trying to intersect with and then we
have to also make sure that we're doing
stuff like handling our light transport
transmission properly are we over
sampling are we under sampling are we
waiting samples improperly like there's
so many things we could be drawn so
we're just gonna go through now and
start tightening up those screws and
once we have them all tightened
hopefully like I said this is already
kind of starting to look useable right
like there's some bugs in it but it's
starting to kind of look usable and if I
was walking around this game and saw a
real-time lighting doing this good of a
bouncing stuff where we had all this
sort of light play lost stuff I would be
pretty darn happy with that especially
for an indie game which honestly tends
to not have that much of that stuff in
it you know if anything they've got the
default unity screens
face nonsense going on where you got all
these weird halos all over the place and
and stuff looks weird
but anyway um so hopefully we'll be able
to get to a place that even that's much
significantly better than we're looking
at now and at that point what we'll do
is we'll move it into the GPU so that
all of the lighting is computed GPU side
after the sort of letting hierarchy is
built so we'll basically build a
Lionheart CPU drop it down let all the
letting computation happen on the GPU
side and that'll also let us do some
things like we can probably control just
how much lighting gets actually done for
example we could make a fast running
version of the game that really doesn't
have much lighting at all that we use on
platforms that don't have beefy graphics
cards right because basically what we
could do is just use all of the graphs
Clerk card horsepower which we don't
really need that much for other aspects
of the game we can just do crazy amounts
of lighting on there and then that way
we can always just dial it back and have
less good lighting in versions of the
game that are running on underpowered
systems right that aren't running on the
latest hardware which you know there's
plenty of people who might want to play
with handmade hero um so that's
basically it I would also point out I
don't know what's going on here but we
we seem to have some weird like I don't
know our our multi sample anti-aliasing
does oh is that because we're not full
screen or multi sample anti-aliasing
could look better I guess it still looks
pretty good multi sample anti-aliasing
isn't perfect I guess and we do have the
weird depth pass stuff happening so it's
still it's pretty good it's better than
nothing I guess anyway so that's our
goals and today like I said all I wanted
to really do is start drilling down into
the lighting and hunting for bugs so
that's what we're gonna do now all right
let's start by taking a look I in so
wait do that let's start by taking a
look at the shader because during the
pre streams someone was mentioning that
we forgot to clamp our direction of
lighting now normally you'll notice when
I have been doing direction lighting
I've been clamping it properly and I
guess I forgot to do that so let's take
a look yeah in fact here it is right
they're 100% right I don't know you
remember many times I've typed in this
equation where we do the inner product
here to do a directional fall-off and
you'll notice that almost every time
thereafter I did a clamp on it right and
there's no clamp here so this is
supposed to be clamped and isn't being
clamped so that was 100% correct
suggestion we want to clamp between 0
and 1 this fall off now why do I have to
clamp it there remember what we're doing
is we're taking a dot product of two
vectors to figure out what the angle
between them is and more civically what
the cosine of the angle between theirs
which is the result of the inner product
now when a vector starts going past 90
degrees its will go from you know at 90
degrees the inner product will be zero
then it will start becoming negative as
we're putting in opposite directions we
don't want to account from for any kind
of negative contribution of light once
it falls off to zero that's the end of
the possible competition that light
anything coming from behind should not
have any contribution at all it
shouldn't have a negative contribution
which is what we would be getting here
so that's a definite bug I don't know to
what extent that bug was contributing to
erroneous actual visible visible
artifacts but it certainly would have
right so it's very important to fix that
because you never want a contribution
there to be negative because you're
gonna get really nonsensical results
especially if you weren't trying to make
it be that way
so anyway here is in fact and you know
what that was a big part of it looks
like because we had much more erroneous
results down here and now we're getting
quite a bit better than we were right so
it looks like that was definitely a
problem that that now has been has been
improved dramatically and you know what
this is starting to look like I said
pretty good right I'm pretty happy with
this if we can get this running in real
time on the GPU I think that would be a
pretty nice situation like I feel like
that would look pretty darn good
again I'm just not sure yet though
whether or not we're getting reasonable
results from things like the Ray caster
now why do I say that well you know if
you take a look at what we're seeing
here light sample wise you can see that
maybe some light samples out here that
are showing that they're getting a
fairly bright light contribution but I
don't feel like that's correct the
reason I don't feel like that's correct
is because if you take a look at where
our only light source is this is our
well we it's not our only light source
we have two light sources right now one
is just an ambient skylight and one is
this light right here now I can turn off
that ambient skylight for example I can
go into the render group and we we sort
of just hacked in that when we do our
ray cast here's our ray cast what we did
is anytime we were going to return
nothing no hit we still gave back a
color that was slightly you know a
slightly gray color right and so what I
wanted to do here was just get rid of
that right eye if I just nuke that out
instead give it nothing or I guess the
shorter hand way to do that would just
be initialized to all zeros like this if
I do that instead and now rerun the
lighting solution you can see just the
contribution of just this one light and
when I see just the contribution of just
that one light I can see some things
that I don't really know how much I
believe whether they are accurate some
things look quite accurate such as this
back here this can't you know this light
source is not going to be contributing
to this here but if you look here you
can see like what is that you know where
is that light coming from because
there's really no conceivable even
erroneously sampled bounce that should
really be able to get here because in
order for something to get here
something over here would have had to
have been bright and it isn't so that
tells me that we have some bugs in our
ray caster because a lot of this looks
correct they're probably not major
glaring bugs but there's subtle bugs and
we need to fix them otherwise we're
classic gonna have these weird little
lighting artifacts right so that's you
know definitely something that Clues me
into the fact that that ray caster or
something similar to it where that
contribution is getting computed is
wrong another thing that I'm seeing here
that that makes me think that there's
you know some some issues of foot
is just that like now you know even just
just thinking about how this this
procedure was working in our in our
transmission the way that we were doing
our transmission for compute light
propagation I'm not sure whether I when
I was thinking about this this only
happens in the final gather so the
skylight part only happens in the final
gather that means our skylight wasn't
having bounced lighting before because
the skylight lit surface couldn't bounce
to another surface and that's also wrong
because if I remember correctly the way
that our light emission works you can
see here we do compute like propagation
what happens with the compute light
propagation is in here if the heat index
doesn't happen then it doesn't propagate
any light and so when it does that
raycast it's never going to sum in any
of this ambient lighting during the
initial bounces so I think what I'm
going to do here is fixin a this
particular version and say to do need a
skylight method that works with our
propagation and leave it at that
all right
if you'll excuse me for a moment okay so
that's what we're doing by the way I'm
having some delicious coffee right now I
love coffee
we bought a espresso machine for the
office because basically like if you buy
if you like to drink coffee and you buy
it from a coffee shop
it is crazy expensive like don't ever do
the math if you're someone who gets
coffee at a coffee shop don't ever do
the math but we determined that even a
relatively expensive coffee machine is
drastically cheaper than buying coffee
out and so we bought one and it's
awesome
like I just make coffee all the time now
like either decaf or regular depending
on like in the morning I make a regular
and after it's I make decaf and it's so
much cheaper it's like it turns coffee
into basically being free all of a
sudden because all you have to do is
find beans you can buy at a reasonable
price that you like and then you're done
right so yeah sorry Starbucks or other
folks who live off of the overpriced
coffee economy I gotta tell ya it's the
way to go plus you can tune it to your
own liking like you can make exactly
what you want over time which as
programmers you know we kind of like to
fixate on improvements to things it's
pretty darn good all right anyway so
yeah let's take a look here and think
about some stuff that we haven't really
addressed yet that we're probably gonna
need to address so what we're looking at
here right this is our raycast this this
is the code that does our red casting
right so we're calling this and it's
looping through all of the elements in
the system and it's skipping one person
who is generally the person that we're
looking at so if we're like okay this is
a surface we need to light and that's
the first we're looking at right now
now we want to go gather lighting we
skip intersections with that surface and
the reason that we skip intersections
with that surface is because we would
always intersect it we're on it we're
starting off on it
so floating-point precision why is we
would have to do something like offset
ourselves from the surface a little bit
to make sure that we don't hit it or
something like this and we'd really
rather not write like we'd really rather
not have to do that sort of thing so
anyway what we can see here is when we
do our intersections you'll notice that
one thing that we do is we don't hand we
don't intersect back faces and what I
mean by that is if the Ray direction is
pointing in the same direction as the
surface we don't test it and you know
what let me go ahead and bring up Milton
here it's been a while since we have
brought up Milton but I think now is the
time if I can get this cord untangled to
bring it up okay so let me go ahead and
fire up Milton here for you and then we
can discuss this aspect of it a little
bit Milton again one of those projects I
mentioned the beginning of a stream
written by viewer fan made hero who
wanted to replace the drawing package we
used ended up making something that's
actually significantly better than the
commercial project that we were using
originally which is nuts but nice job
Sergio anyway here we are on day four
thirteen Sergio by the way I think
recently said he was moving to Vancouver
I
that's pretty nearby I feel like that's
in on in just that the southwestern part
of Canada just not far from Seattle it's
like a three four-hour train ride up
there actually anyway Dave 4:13
here is our ray cast debugging in anyway
so what I've seen is you know we've got
a surface here and there's a point on
the surface we're starting to collect
lighting by casting Ray's out right or
we have an emitter here
right so this is a light and it's
shining light out and it wants to see
where it should deposit that light right
either or when we're doing this ray
casting generally what we're assuming is
that our shapes are closed right so
we're assuming we have like a solid
shape like this and that what we're
doing is when we're a cast when we're a
cast out we don't need to look at this
face
or this face for intersections and the
reason that we don't need to is because
we know we couldn't have gotten to them
without passing through one of these non
back faces or I should say non same
direction facing and say that exactly
first so if we take a look at these
normals these surface normals right if
we take a look at those what we can see
is that this plane right I will always
hit here which is a normal that's facing
backwards towards me right before I can
hit any of these ones that are facing
away from me right and that's just
because if you take a look at how this
object is divided all of its faces that
are facing toward me form a wall of what
I can see and any face that's facing
away from me is something I couldn't
have gotten to unless I pass through the
object first and that's just a property
of closed solids if you have a
completely closed solid which is any
object generally in the real world you
know there's no such thing even that
things that are open on the inside
they're actually not open right they
have a thickness and they have walls
going all around them right you can't
get to something that's on the backside
of something to you without going
through something that's on the front
side of something to you
right if you imagine just a ball or
something right I can never get to any
of this part of the ball right none of
this part of the surface without going
through this part of the surface first
right that's just a property of closed
solids so it's one way to eliminate the
number of triangles that you need to
test or in our cases quads that you need
to test you can eliminate it by a factor
of two right 50% of the surfaces to
we'll probably be back facing and 50%
will be front facing we only need to
test those 50% that our front face that
face towards us right now in case you're
wondering this is 100% exactly analogous
to the old hidden surface removal
removal algorithm or even just what we
use nowadays to speed up rendering
nowadays when we render services a lot
of times we just don't render back faces
so what happens is you know for example
if we've got a solid object in the world
right so we're drawing like a cube or
something like this there's back faces
to the cube right here's our front faces
1 2 3 and then we've got our back faces
1 2 3 right what we do when we render
typically in a raster Iser is look to
see how the polygons are wound and what
we'll say is well okay we're gonna wind
our polygons so that when we are looking
from the front side like this we're
gonna wind them so they're
counterclockwise right so here's 0 1 2 3
right that means that if you were to
imagine this cube being spun all the way
around so that now that was a back face
right so imagine this cube being spun
180 degrees so that now we've got sort
of a back face there now they wouldn't
be wound this way anymore right this
this direction is not how they'd be
wound because that's what it was when
it's facing us instead they'll be wound
this way they'll be one clockwise right
because this vertex went here so there's
zero right this vertex went here right
because it's spun around right these
were spinning around so this is one went
over here the zero went over here right
so now it's 0 1 2 3 clockwise so what we
can then do is when we go to rasterize
and we look at this quad we can go oh
it's wound the wrong way it must be back
facing just don't rasterize it at all
and so again that's a 50% save right it
saves half of the work because we never
have to rafter eyes those right so this
is the same technique that I'm using
here during the raycast is the same
thing you use in a raster eyes to save
that work it's just a good 50% savings
to realize that if you're only dealing
with closed objects during this problem
now we don't always have closed objects
in handmade hero we've got sprites right
and those sprites are just little sprite
cards right that's all they are they
don't have a solid shape and basically
what I'm electing to do is I am electing
to say when we send down the lighting
for this because remember we're gonna
send out lighting separately lighting is
based on these light quads which are not
the same as what we're drawing we don't
they're come they can be completely
separate because remember we're sampling
lighting per pixel now we don't care
what we draw we can draw completely
different scene from the one-wheel it
wouldn't make any sense
not a good idea but we could there's no
coupling in the algorithm so we can
generate a completely different lighting
model as we do for render model and this
was 100% intentional on my part because
we probably want to send down much more
simplified stuff to our lighting
solution than we do to our render
decision because we only need a course
idea of what the lighting is for this
game we don't need every last little
detail to be respected in the lighting
we're just going for our general sort of
light transmission lets us know how lit
things generally are this is not a game
that's trying to stimulate little minut
differences in the light based on little
tiny crenellations in geometry or
something like this and in fact no games
are because games can't do that yet we
don't have the horsepower but that's
neither here nor there that's more of a
tracer land if you're going down that
route but point being because of that
I'm just saying look if we want an
object to be sucking up light properly
for being in a particular area what
we're gonna do is we're just gonna send
down two things I'm either side of the
sprite card so if you imagine looking at
the game from here here's the camera and
we've got a sprite card here that's the
hero it's facing that way we're just
gonna send down to fake light things one
this way one that way so it's like a
sandwich where the hero's actual sprite
would have been in between and that way
we don't have to ever worry about dual
sided surfaces I just decided it was too
much of a pain in the butt to track them
through and probably just gonna end up
being more costly and slower to do so so
we'll just for those things that are
just flat cards we'll send down two
things anything that's a real piece of
geometry like the cubes they will just
get sent down as actual clothes geometry
and that way all
whenever we're working with these things
we can just understand the fact that we
only care about front-facing stuff right
and that should be sufficient for our
purposes so here's that code right here
and you can see that what it's doing is
just taking that inner product and going
hey look if the normal is not pointing
back towards me then I'm not going to
use it right now I don't really know why
we necessarily picked this constant I
think we've probably just picked it
randomly as something that would make
our divide not blow up because you can
kind of see that we have a divide here
by that racehorse and we have to make
sure that it doesn't blow up now why do
we have to make sure of that right there
well that's because when we do our
raycast right if we're ray casting in
this direction so here's our array
origin and here's our ray direction if
we're casting in this direction you have
to remember there are services we cannot
hit we can't hit anything that's
perpendicular for example right this ray
will just sail on by and no matter if it
went infinity or negative infinity it
doesn't matter it will never hit it
that's what this is because the inner
product of these two things will be zero
and that means racehorse n will be zero
and the math is telling us this right
the math is telling us that is not
allowed it's one of those nice places
where the math works out to tell you
things you should have known already but
even if you forgot or didn't understand
the math will then tell you and you let
go there's a divide here that means
there could be a divide by zero that
means zero is not allowed that means
almost universally when you have that in
a geometric construction that there's
some geometric scenario that literally
can't happen and it's telling you that
right and that is exactly what that is
what it's kind of cool right all right
so is so what we decided to do here was
rather than just test for an epsilon
which means hey let's see if it's close
to zero and if it's close to zero we
don't do it we actually said look we're
gonna test for an entirely one-sided
thing because again let's not bother
testing those things because you could
see if we were trying to just avoid just
just a divide by zero right we would
have something that would look more like
this
right we just want to make sure that it
was within you know or that it wasn't
within a certain range of zero but it's
say what we're doing is saying hey look
positive values we just don't want ever
right we don't want we don't care up
closes early early this is their bad and
the reason for that is again we would be
testing services we know we can't hit so
far from being a bug that's actually
good
that's what we want to see so that's
fine
so that is reasonably logical we then
take our origin here we take the Ray
origin and we we create essentially a
thing which points from the thing we're
checking the service we're checking back
towards the Ray back towards the Rays
origin right so what we're doing here is
we're just saying okay here's my Ray
Origin here is the surface we're calling
the source I think that's because we
just copied it it's just a thing we're
trying to hit and what we're doing here
is we're saying alright there's a point
on this plane we know because we made
one right and what we're gonna do is
we're gonna say alright let's create the
vector that points back in this
direction now you'll notice it's the
actually the full vector so it's not a
normal or anything it's a full vector
going all the way from here to here
right what we then do is say let's take
the dot product of the normal that we do
have from our surface and this or this
this vector going this way right so
we're taking this as a dot product right
which means it's sort of computing this
cosine here right so it's computing the
that's not right
computing the cosine that's the sign
that's the cross product right there
this is the dot product so we're taking
the cosine of this angle here and then
we're multiplying it by the length of
this vector right because remember I
said there's so many times please tell
me you know what I'm gonna say right now
please tell me you know I'm gonna say
tell me you know a transpose B equals
length of a length of B cosine theta I
if there is anyone who has been watching
handmade hero the entire way through who
doesn't know this equation I do not know
what to say to you I am going to have to
just get a white glove and slap it right
across your face because this is so
important and we've talked about so many
times again that's exactly what's
happening here we know we have one
vector that's a normal where we're
taking one thing out of the equation
right because we know one of this this
right here that's normal
the length of the normal is one so one
of these goes away that leaves us with
the cosine of theta which is this right
here times the length of B which is this
vector right here so that's exactly what
we're getting we're getting the cosine
of this angle times the length of this
vector right then what we're doing is
we're taking whatever that was we're
negating it and dividing it by this
inner product that we got back here
right and what that's doing is that's
computing a ratio right between the two
between the two directions it's creating
a ratio between this and this right and
what that's trying to do is figure out
how long it will take for something
going in this direction to cover
something that needs to go all the that
that to intersect with something that is
going in this direction right it's like
this plane depending on where you're
going to be is gonna be a different
place depending on how far you've gone
this way right and so that ratio there
is what we're competing with t-ray right
and that's gonna tell us how far along
this we have to go before we hit this
place so then we say is our a if we got
a intersection that's in front of us and
remember the reason that in front of us
is important is because when we solve
these equations we're solving these
equations it could could continuously
with regular continuous math and what
continuous math does when you know
everything that you ever did in grade
school and high school and whatever else
right probably most of college is always
in continuous math it's not in discrete
math and what that means is that when we
solve an equation right T a plus B
equals five or whatever right
we solve equations that look like these
what we end up doing is we end up
solving for a real value or potentially
even imaginary value of T right but it's
a real or imaginary value continuous it
doesn't have the notion of bounding
planes or step functions or anything
like this so what that means is when we
solve this equation it's really not
solving for array at solving for a line
right so it may produce a T value that's
representative of backwards T can be
negative right so she could equal
negative something right and we don't
want to know that if there's something
behind us that doesn't count we're
trying to look in the forward direction
only so this is the place where we clip
that out so we say all right if the
intersection is going to be in front of
us and it's closer than our closest hid
so we don't have to go as far as the
closest that we've recorded so far then
what we're going to do is we're going to
see whether or not we believe it to fall
within the legal region of this
particular hip right because remember
we're not trying to just intersect
planes we're trying to intersect squares
like little like rectangular bounds
right okay so the next thing we do is
say all right let's find out where we
actually are in the real world so we
take this Ray position computation and
we say start at the origin go out along
the normal as far as you said you what
needed to go to get to this hip we do
that
right we then look and say all right
take the inner product of this ray right
whatever this this ray position take the
inner product of that with our source
axes okay and what you'll notice here is
the relative origin part is pretty
important because the relative origin
part means we've already centered
ourselves around the source right that's
why we're using this vector this
relative origin here rather than the
original ray origin is because we want
the result of stepping along this ray to
still be in the space of this right we
want to be centered around this why
because our square is defined around
there right if this is our source P
right we've got a square that's defined
by an x-axis and a y-axis emitting from
that point and when we compute where the
Ray ends up we want it to be relative to
this we want a vector relative to this
because only if it's relative to that
can we then directly dot product it with
our axes to find out where it is so here
we go we do this we dot product with our
x-axis and our y-axis that tells us
where it is relative to them why we do
2.0 I believe is because of the way
we've stored these right so if you think
about what happens here this X check and
Y check it's is it greater than or equal
to the width greater than less less than
or equal to the width you know negative
with positive with well what happens
here is the width it would really be
half the width here so rather than
divide the width by half in both cases I
just multiply the X check by two once
right and that's it so that's all there
is to it we check to see whether it's
within those bounds and if it is within
those bounds we do consider it a hit and
off we go
right we recorded as the closest hit so
far because we know we couldn't have
gotten here unless we already determined
it was the closest set we then say which
one it was and what its emission value
was like so so that it can go back to
the calling code correctly and that's
all she wrote so to me that looks like a
pretty stable ray cast there could be a
bug lurking in there but it doesn't
there's not an obvious one so basically
I'm not super suspicious of that code
particularly however just because I'm
not supposed to have that specific code
doesn't mean we couldn't still have a
bug in the way that we're calling the
ray cast for example we don't know if
all these values are set correctly so
there could be a
looking in here we don't know and we
don't know the other thing we don't know
is is there a bug lurking in where we
set these for example could the x-axis
and whacks have been set wrong could the
width and height had been set wrong
those are things that easily could
happen which would cause a bug in what
we are doing right so there's all that
now there's another there's another
thing that we could be doing wrong here
too right so when we say which thing to
skip for example we could be saying that
wrong when we call this right we could
be calling it with the wrong information
in terms of when we're trying to
propagate that light you know are we
passing the right index here or whatever
I think we probably are pretty hard to
get that wrong I think but again there's
like all those sorts of things could be
going wrong in the trappings of this
code that would make it so even if our
raycast was rock-solid and we determined
there's no actual bugs that are really
manifesting themselves here that doesn't
mean that we don't have some kind of a
problem with how we're using the code
that is itself you know causing this
issue right similarly we also don't know
about how we generate our raycast so for
example if you take a look at this code
right here where we do compute light
propagation or the same code here in
gather final lighting this is a thing
that's supposed to distribute stuff
across the hemisphere it's a pretty
janky one right now but basically this
thing which is generating after I says
this piece of code is is trying to
generate uniform samples about a
hemisphere but it's just doing a
horrible job at it what it does it
starts up and normal and just adds a
random negative 1 to 1 value in each of
the various directions right and the
thing about that is I feel like in fact
just thinking about this this could be
completely bogus right because
there we go because let's suppose that
we have a normal right in fact let's do
yeah let's do this case so let's suppose
we have a normal now we know that this
is our normal and this is you know a
normal of length one because that's what
a normal yes and all of our normals are
normalized so what that means is this
here this length here is one but for
example right if we were to take this
axis like this right these would not be
1 right so these would be less than one
right and this right here in theory
can't be more than one though because if
this I'm sorry this right here has to be
more than one because if this we know is
one right then by just principles basic
principles of right triangles we know
that this has to be longer than one
because the hypotenuse of a triangle of
a right triangle well if any triangle
the hypotenuse you know is the longest
side that's the definition of hypotenuse
right in a right triangle we know that
neither of the two sides that are part
of the right part of the 90 degree that
connect to it those sides have to be
both shorter than the hypothenuse
hypotenuse right so we know that that's
always going to be greater the same
would be true on the other side right so
I think trying to try to guess but I
think that means that if we were to add
negative 1 in this direction or negative
1 in this direction right we would not
risk moving our normal in an arrant way
however let's suppose we added both
because there's nothing in here that
disallows that right well that would
mean is that we would be pointing
potentially negative 1 in this direction
let's say that got us here and negative
1 in this direction let's say that got
us here we would be pointing back out
the backside of the surface right
and that's simply erroneous so what will
end up happening is if we you know if we
look at something like this what will
end up happening is we're only supposed
to be casting this direction out of a
surface we might end up guessing this
direction since we're not considering
back faces which are these will sail
right through the other side of the
object and pick up light that's
transmitting through the other side the
object and hey by the way right that's
exactly what looks like it's happening
in the thing that I was complaining
about right that that is the exact kind
of thing that could be happening right
there I don't know that that's what's
happening but it would be consistent
with it so that's starting to raise my
spidey senses which I don't have because
I'm not a I'm not a spider-man of any
kind but it's starting to just make me a
little bit you know nervous so I feel
like maybe the first order of business
in this debugging process because we
know that this is crappy right when we
put it in here we knew it was crappy so
maybe the first sorta business is let's
improve this and try to make one that's
actually not gonna be super puggy right
and we don't have to improve it much we
don't need a really great lighting
solution here we're not trying to
capture perfect light or anything we
just need something that's going to do a
good hemisphere sample without totally
screwing it up which it might be doing
at the moment so I'm gonna make an
internal here and this is going to be
called like you know sample Hemisphere
and I'm just going to give it a normal
and and one of those random series and
then I'm gonna just copy this code right
here and the first I'm going to do is
again just make literally the exact
function we were already using in both
places like so and then what I'm going
to do is I'm going to take these two
places we were calling it and just
replace them with that call right so
just prepare ourselves to replace this
function at C roots that series give me
n
like so and that serious deathbed so
those should basically do exactly the
same thing so if we call it now we
should get the exact same lighting
solution we were getting before because
again remember although these are random
numbers they're pseudo random numbers
we're using the same random series every
time so we should get basically the same
results unless something weird happened
and you can see we're still getting that
weird light bleed although it looks
slightly different this time I don't
know it could be that the way these
function compiled compile them in a
different order as well so there is a
little bit of that right but either way
so if we want to improve this function
we were taking in normal and we want to
sample a hemisphere around it there's a
lot of different things we could do I'm
not sure what we want to do in terms of
improvements here but yeah like the very
first thing we could do is just reduce
the numbers that we're adding to make
sure that it can never add more than a
normalized amount right so for example
hmm a really simple way to prevent the
backwards-facing problem would be to say
something like alright we know we've got
an equation of the form x squared plus y
squared plus Z squared Square rooted
this is the length of the thing we're
adding and we know that since we've got
a unit vector in a particular direction
if we want to make sure that it can
never point in the opposite direction
ever we could just make sure that the
vector we add to it can never be more
than the amount that would get you to
like right here right so it always has
to be sort of this direction now that's
not great because it does mean as well
that we would never be able to really
get really glancing angles but that's
probably okay because we don't really
want angles in that direction very much
right because we're mostly concerned
about light that's coming in from here
because as it gets coming into here
since this is a diffuse reflectance
model this is not specular we really
don't want to count these contributions
because the cosine fall-off term will
knock them out to a largest and right
for specular that's not true
specular there's a high bounce rate at
glancing angles that's a kind of another
lighting thing we can go down at some
point but that's not for this sort of
radiosity ish kind of feeling bounces so
we know that we're basically doing this
and so if we want to make sure that this
thing can never put us back in the wrong
direction well we could say is we want
it to equal some value like you know 0.9
right so we're always we never quite get
all the way back so we could say we want
you know the length of the vector we
generate to look like this now how would
we solve this because you know we got
three unknowns and one equations not
going to go very far right the answer is
yes it is going to go very far because
we know that each of these is generated
uniformly right we're treating each of
them the same so really what we're doing
here is we're just creating three values
that each could be of a certain
magnitude so if they're all the max
magnitude let's call that M what we
would have is M squared plus M squared
plus M squared right otherwise known as
3m squared so 3m squared Square rooted
has to be you know 0.9 that would tell
us what our M could be what the maximum
range is for the thing that we're
putting in positive or negative right so
we can solve this right point-9 equals
root 3 Times root M Squared now that
simplifies pretty nicely right 0.9
equals root 3 times M and that just
means that 0.9 over root 3 equals M
right unless it's you know it's a you
know kind of a slow start today on
handmade hero so you know I don't know
maybe I'm getting too rusty there but it
seems like we could do 3 Square rooted
oops how do I commit I don't know how to
use this program at all I want to divide
point
by that well you know what I could do I
could divide this by 0.9 and then invert
it can it do that of course you can't of
course you can't do that it's Microsoft
if they don't do math there apparently
no matter how big I make this I never
get any buttons I actually want there it
is there it is right there
so it looks like around 0.5 you know I'm
saying
so let's find if that's true so let's
try 0.5 times 0.5 right and so that
would what we'd have under and if we
times that by 3 we get 0.75 right and if
we do the square root of that we get
roughly 0.9 so that's pretty close so
that that seems like basically what we
want so we know here if we were to just
set these all of these to only be able
to take a max range of 0.5 we know we
would be safe now is this great no right
this is definitely to do you know better
hemisphere sampling is this going to
stop the bad back casting situation if
this was the cause of it yes
hopefully so now let's take a letting
sample and see where we're at let's take
a look at those back surfaces and it
looks to me like there's still a little
bit of badness in there maybe it's hard
to say we didn't have much of glaring
errors necessarily we've kind of got
some in here that doesn't look good to
me although I don't know how much of
that is an interpolation error it's a
little hard to say one thing it would be
nice to do is have better visualization
here of these values
trying to think if there's any way we
could really do that because see one of
the problems that we have is this is not
a good this right here is not really
useful visualization and the reason it's
not unusual voters because this is also
getting passed through the lighting
right so we need to set the lighting
equal to all ones in order to really
make that work right
but anyway so let me move I'm gonna move
the here around a little bit or more
importantly the light source that's
attached to the hero at the moment and I
just want to see what I get
in terms of backlighting there or
lighting that that punches through and
the other thing I could do is let's try
to increase that lighting intensity as
well so if I go into the world mode and
we set that lighting there I we've got
that add piece light situation I don't
think we're actually using that there
yeah for the snake segments we're not
actually using that I believe we're just
adding a light manually me double check
that that's true yeah it's right here
so here's that that light call that's
going into the render group and you can
see hoops and you can see here where
that emission value it's that that final
one so it's this guy right here so we
can if we want to just crank that
emission value up these are unitless
right now if we don't have a particular
idea of what that unit is it's just a
light strength so you can see if I if I
Jack it up quite a bit you know it's
gonna bounce more light around from from
this particular position and so that can
help us find bugs because if I just keep
increasing that light I can really blow
out the amount of light that's going
through there and hopefully we'll see
any errors will stand out more
significantly that doesn't really look
like it increased the lighting values
all that much though that's just me
correct me if I'm wrong but that just
doesn't look that bright compared to
what it was what if we've got another
bug in there it seems like we're kind of
clamping out at a maximum brightness
there right because the brightness value
obviously is doing something like if we
compare this value here to this value
here it got brighter but it didn't get
much brighter right so that value is
definitely clamping out and I assume
that's because when we send down those
light values those must be the brightest
light values we can send that doesn't
make sense though that's definitely not
right
although now that I think about it if
our light values are always capped and
this is kind of a problem
that we would have to work out right
like if we take a look at how we're
sending these down our lighting values
that we're sampling we do have a problem
here which is that this is where our
light value is coming in right it's it's
a it's just gonna be an 8-bit value so I
feel like maybe what we would want to do
there is use that extra parameter to
encode of greater brightness amount or
something like this right I you know
maybe something that's a multiplier on
the values of the light after the fact
or something like this trying to think
of how we would do that in some way that
made sense so let's take a look at what
these values are actually saying I
assume that lighting Texel which is this
D value right here is probably gonna be
fully encoded so looking at this value
we've got RGB and a we're currently not
using a so it would kind of be like a
HDR encoding problem where it's like hey
can you is there anything really all
that useful you can do with that final
value and maybe we can like maybe we can
make that be like it's an RGB and an
exponent kind of thing I write like
that's something we could do but that
that almost certainly is the problem so
just to just to make that a little more
concrete if we take a look at what
happens in render group here when you
compute all the lighting those lighting
samples I mean there are actually
samples of lighting values right which
can be Arbor
fairly high like there's no cap on the
number of photons you know that there's
probably some physical limit on the
number of photons but it's gonna be in
the like billions and blame it's a Sun
right like you know like that's how
bright you could be that's how much so
it's certainly not like a zero to 1
clamped range like that it doesn't make
a lot of intuitive sense there and you
can see why so when we come through here
and we're like taking the incident light
you can see this clamps here at a1
that's where we're losing all that light
information right and so what we might
want to do is just figure out a way we
can get that value to be more reasonable
in terms of encoding the the information
we care about now I don't know exactly
how to do that but let's just take a
random crack at it what if instead when
we encoded this lighting value what we
said was something more like alright
let's take the incident light RGB and
we'll see how big it is right so we'll
say all right let's take the length of
the element incident light RGB right and
that will tell us how much light power
there is behind this particular light
sample then what we'll do is we'll
normalize to that right so we'll say if
light power is greater than zero because
remember there might be no light power
here at all but if light power is
greater than zero and you know we can
also say incident light equals nothing
if the light power is greater than zero
then what we'll do is say okay in that
case the incident light we won't do the
clamps are Oh to one instead what we'll
do is we'll do a clamp zero to one on
the light power like so and then we'll
use the normalized version of the light
itself so basically say like the light
color equals the incident light RGB
divided by the light power right
like that so then we can just say light
color our flight color G light color B
and then we just need to clamp only the
light power because we know that the
only the light power could really be out
of range right now we could if we wanted
to be safe we could do these anyway just
to make sure they don't get a little
over one after the normalization if
there is a little bit of error right but
otherwise you know we wouldn't really
even have to do this theoretically right
so then all we have to do is say well
this light power so now we know it could
be from zero to one is one way to
interpret it but now we could say we
want lights up to a much higher power
potentially than that right so maybe we
want lights up to a power of like 10 or
something like this I'm not sure and so
if we want lights that go up to two much
higher powers than one what we could do
here is say all right let's say that our
light power can range up to ten so when
we before we do the clamp here what
we'll say is we'll just nuke it by light
power right and we could even make this
be a thing that you could actually
specify specifically such as max light
power and you know it's ten right and in
that case if we specified it there what
we could do is say well the light power
is going to be divided by the max light
power and that's how it's going to be
encoded later on when we actually
specify these values and interpret them
in the shader what we will now get is
when we fetch the light color we now
have four values and when we actually
get that light C RGB what we need to do
here is multiply by the power first
right so that light color is now going
to be light C RGB x light color age but
back in the power x the max light power
because that's what amps that alpha
value up to its correct value right
and so in here then we would say all
right when we're actually you know
putting this information down
we need to be able to specify here you
know some of these constants right so we
also want a uniform here actually we
don't eat a uniform this can just be it
because this is fixed at compile time we
can actually just have here you know
MaxLite power equals some floating-point
value whatever that floating-point value
is and then we can just say that'll get
included right not sure why RGB isn't in
there Oh
because incident light I guess it's just
an RGB already yeah all right so you
know that's one way to encode this stuff
we got to recompile the shaders as well
so let's do a full build there instead
of leaving that open and so now if we
did that correctly
doesn't look like we did if we get this
working correctly we should be able to
have more light power involved that just
looks weird
probably because it's using it as an
actual alpha value at that point right
yeah that's because this is the the
light power is the alpha value in this
scenario right so it looks like we're
doing the colors wrong there let me see
what I messed up so if I take a look at
what's going on here I've got the light
colors RGB it's divided by the light
power which should be the length of the
incident light incoming
oh that's very simple
it's element incident light we were not
using the actual we're using the thing
that we were going to accumulate into
it's not gonna work very well so now we
can have much more powerful lights
illuminating our scene and you can see
they're the result of that is sort of
already instantly noticeable now I don't
know whether we're doing that correctly
here but hey four in a thousand light
that's probably true let's go ahead and
recompile back to a light of one and
there you can kind of see you know it
honestly it's already sort of looking
like it's a little bit better at
recording how much light was hitting
that surface although I don't know if
that's accurate or not
but now if we up the light power to two
we should be able again to sort of get a
yeah a more more light falling on that
surface and that does look like what
we're getting so that's good that allows
us to encode it and you can see that's
doing exactly what I wanted we can see
our light leaking here much more clearly
now than we used to
so now I can just blow this light out
really violent right not something we'd
ever want to happen in the actual game
but perfect for looking for our lighting
errors and we've got a lot of them you
can kind of see here right we've got a
lot of different kinds of things that
seem to be happening so you can see
light leakage here not sure why light is
able to get here so effectively right
and more
only red light so I'm not sure why this
is able to see this so well similarly
you know you can see on the undersides
of surfaces we've got a lot of light
leaking through there and what's really
interesting about that you can sort of
see like well that's kind of cool anyway
you can sort of see that you know this
may be a case of just the sampling being
bad like for these surfaces right here
you know is it just that it's picking up
the light samples that were coming from
here is that where that's coming from
you know and I don't know so a lot of
that stuff is just really kind of a
little bit confusing some of it may
actually be right like you know some of
this light made us be bounce light
coming from here which is legitimately
coming from there right so it's pretty
hard to say what's definitively a bug
that's one of the problems with lighting
is some of the effects are pretty subtle
so you don't always know that something
is actually wrong or right you have to
just kind of construct test cases and
guess right but what I'm doing now is
we're first just doing this debugging
what I'd like to do here is I'd like to
focus on some things that look very
wrong now this right here looks very
wrong to me that right there the reason
that looks very wrong to me is there
should be all kinds of zero samples here
you know I'm saying and in fact if I
look at I guess I we got to set those
let's change that light interpolations
interpretation so I can actually see
better what's going on there
okay so let's go ahead and oh you know
what else I should do while we're at it
when we are sampling that hemisphere
let's just add an assertion so we can
double check that the direction we
picked times the normal we started with
is always greater than zero because we
never wanted to go backwards right and
so that's an important thing that we
just want to make sure we never do right
and so if I run this now we should get
an assertion there if we ever head back
in the wrong direction okay so what I
wanted to say before is like okay so
when we output the debug lighting I
that's this code right here and no it's
not it's a lie if this this code right
here you can kind of see what we're
doing is we go through here and we look
at the lighting texels and we see what
we've got for colors and we just
accumulate all of the light that's in
there right one of the things we do is
we then divide by the count so we're
taking an average of the light in that
area which is fine what I would like to
do however in this case yes I'd like to
say uh you know what let's make sure
that when we do this let's interpret
that alpha value correctly so when we do
the RGB unpack here right where we do
the RGB unpack 4x8 let's just take that
unpack and before we actually do
anything to it let's actually make sure
we're undoing the power part right so
let's take a v3 color here I guess
actually we could do a v4 color
it just defaults to one alpha something
like that let's do that unpack and then
let's do the unpack RGB x equals the max
light power times unpack a right just
take that power back and just put it
back in there right so now we can see
those values a little bit better why are
we still getting alpha there that's
weird
oh because we're dividing by the count
so we need to do this part only in terms
of the RGB oops I didn't mean to
actually close it doesn't matter um so
here we can see our samples again right
so what I'd like to do is let's just
take a look at for example this area
back here but it's getting very strongly
lit for like no reason at all that would
make sense in the actual scene and let's
take a look at what those values are in
there right and what you can kind of see
is that it does look like the lighting
sample in that area is heavily red right
[Music]
but those are the front side faces these
are the back side faces right here and
there's no light in them so I guess it's
just a question of interpolating between
the two that's the issue I'm not sure
one question I do have is what would
happen if we were to increase our voxel
size our voxel resolution at this point
we had dropped it down pretty far just
because we were trying to get more
interpolation but I think we've sort of
addressed some of the reasons that we
had wanted that I wish you didn't know
if our lighting solution gets more
useful if we drop it back down right and
you know what you can see here is we got
rid of some of the artifacts that I like
those back interpolation effects look
like that is what they potentially were
I don't know about those
so Sara Lee but we get some really weird
other artifacts there right which is
these here are still seeing through to
the blue light now there are some
reasons why that could be happening
legitimately but I think those are gonna
be more excuses than anything else if
for example the lighting sample was
taken in here and up to there and that's
what was getting counted then maybe but
let's take a look at where it actually
is yeah you can kind of see that the
sample is right there and so I don't
really know what let's just do an
experiment to figure out to what extent
the placement versus what it has to go
through is affecting that ray cast
because what we can do is we can take
and make this two-sided so if Ray's
source and is on either side of this
right now we will collide against back
faces as well and so we could see what
ends up happening if we make the raycast
work in a two-sided fashion we can see
whether we still have that light leakage
and it looks like we do right
oddly enough it looks like we have
different likely light leakage though
when we do that because like there was a
very distinct blue light here before and
there isn't now so yeah it's just it's a
little strange and I'm not super
comfortable with what I'm seeing it
don't really have a handle on what's
going on what I can tell you is we
definitely have some bugs in there or
rather you know sometimes the word bug
can be ambiguous in this case sometimes
a bug means a piece of code that is not
that has an error in it which makes it
not work the way it's supposed to work
that's one kind of thing that you might
meet my bug another thing you might mean
by a bug and the one I mean this case is
anything that just produces results
that's not what you wanted right the
it could be that all of the code you
know for all we know the raycast is
working fine but just the way we're
using it is not gonna produce the right
result right like we could just be
making mistakes and how we're applying
things and so there's you know in this
case we're looking for either kind of
bug a direct bug in the system and then
also you know just a bug of the form oh
yeah you can't the light's not gonna
work if you do it that way or whatever
right like that which is a separate sort
of class of bug that isn't the same as
oh I had a negative in the wrong place
so I was doing the calculation slightly
incorrectly and you know whatever so
anyway that's really interesting to me
because I would have expected more
coherent results to that change so again
we really have some weird stuff going on
here and I'm not sure what so what I
would like to do next is I'd like to
maybe get a way where we can sort of I'd
like to have a way where we could
visualize the lighting elements more
directly again so maybe let's try to
reconstruct a path where that's gonna
happen in a more straightforward fashion
so what I want to do here is say like
okay when we do output when we do output
lighting textures and output lighting
quads and that sort of stuff is there a
way we can get just a visualization
instead of the voxel if we do output
lighting quads here right can we get a
more direct piece of information
right so here's more information about
our liquids and what I'd like to do here
is we we have this sort of double
counting problem that I mentioned before
and what the double counting problem is
is that these things are still going
through the actual lighting solution
right so what I want to do is I want to
construct a scenario whereby I can look
at the lighting solution directly
without having the lighting actually get
applied right and in order to do that I
can do one of two things either I can go
ahead and create a I can either go ahead
and create a situation where I know that
the lighting that I send down is always
neutral so there's only one light ever
being referenced by any voxel and it's
always just a uniform one one one I can
do that or I can do a mode that actually
just turns off the lighting entirely
right so we can toggle lighting by like
pushing a key or something like this I'm
leaning towards toggling lighting by
pushing a key that seems a little bit
better to me because if we were to do
that then we should be able to you know
always flip it on and off no matter what
we're looking at so I kind of feel like
that's more what I would like to do so
inside the OpenGL renderer we already
have the concept of settings that was
the thing that's that's been in there
for a while and you can kind of see in
here we've got game render settings
right and so if we look at the game
render settings you've got like
pixelization hint and our pixelation
hint and all these are those sorts of
things multi sampling debug multi
sampling hint right we can have a thing
that's this lighting disabled or
something like this right and so we can
have a thing that would toggle lighting
disabled and if the lighting was
disabled
we just wouldn't do it and so when it
comes through here what we could do is
say all right we know that the setting
is something that we want to read so we
can just come in here and say all right
pound fine
lighting disabled and put it you know
whatever the value is there and then in
here in addition to max like power we
would do is say okay when we compile the
Z bias program we also need to know that
lighting disabled value oops
because this is the only place that we
do it so it should be pretty
straightforward and so what we would do
there is we just say like our rights in
this code here we've got all of this
nonsense that's designed to help us
create some kind of lighting it's a
giant monstrosity that does all these
sorts of things instead what we'll do is
we'll say if lighting disabled else do
the lighting and then what we can say as
well service select RGB already equaled
this value let's not bother multiplying
it by the lighting at all we'll just use
the value that we already got right and
that's all we would need to do so now
the compiler will tell us that we
haven't passed that when we go to
compile this program right hello can I
jump to my error here we go so we in
here all we need to do is just take
those settings right and you can see
we've got current settings here right
all we need to do is just take those
settings and bring them on through okay
so now in theory if we run this it
should run with the lighting still
correctly because we have not set
letting disable to anything so then what
we could do is in those settings there
we can actually check the value that
we're talking about here I don't
remember where we actually typically set
those or where we set them
I have no idea I don't remember but I
think where we set them is probably in
the top of hand-made where we had a
debug switch for them yeah
so we inside the renderer here what we
can do is just put in lighting say bold
and and now it should be something that
can be set right so if I come through
here and want to toggle the lighting on
and off so you know here's it with the
lighting on in theory probably should
figure out a way to turn the lighting
off on that pass as well if I want to
set letting disabled I should be able to
set it to true or so well we're not
interesting so all the rest of the stuff
seems to be correctly recalculating but
not lighting disabled do we don't we
just do mm compare I guess we don't do
we actually manually do the mem compare
and we have to compare them all so we've
gotten our equal function I guess we
literally have yeah I'm not sure why we
don't just compare the memory directly
are there stuff in there that we don't
want to set equal to I mean we what are
we checking I guess is my question with
life tip to account debug multi sampling
hint yeah I mean we pretty much just
check everything so I don't understand
why we were doing it that way
let's do it the other way round I think
is smarter right
I think that's just better right and I
don't know if we have one of these I
don't think we do but this is just
saying hey we've got a count and to void
stars right and I just want to check
them so Wow count - - if our a + + is
not equal to star b + + return false
return true something like that right
let me just do what we'll say is alright
however much member you want to compare
give me two pointers so I'll just go to
loop through it if at any point two of
the bytes are not equal return false
otherwise we'll return true done deal
no one else cares finished right all
right so now in theory I should be able
to come through and say okay
sable the lighting and it actually
disables the lighting right don't ask me
why it clears the lighting afterwards
probably because the lighting is a
permanent texture or something like that
we should probably fix that though I'd
like to be able to toggle the lighting
and still have it be there I guess that
won't matter as much later remember not
doing single submission but yeah all
right so yeah if I was to go in here
with lighting disabled I can now see the
lighting directly right and I have to go
in and figure out the lighting power
more accurately because right now we're
not taking that into account so what I
should probably do since we have this
lighting
our concept now should probably make a
function that encodes how we're encoding
it and how we're decoding it so that we
don't have to constantly write it all
the time right so this function
basically here which is like decode
power I basically want to say like hey I
want unpacked to be equal to the decode
power of unpack and that function right
or encoded light is just this I guess we
leave the alpha value the same or we set
the alpha value to one I don't know what
we do there probably something like that
so that we can call this anywhere that
we want and have it work right so that
way whenever we're doing anything here
that involves that decode it'll be done
uniformly so for example in here when we
do front emit for example we could call
the we call the decode similarly the
encode part we could also do as a value
but I don't think we encode more than
one place so we don't really need to do
quite do that yet but this we probably
do so when we do output letting quads we
come through here and we get these
emission values for example
I guess I guess now that I think about
it when we do output lighting clods here
we're really just kind of saying these
are the light valves because that light
value is so high it's just gonna clap
clamp up to our anyway so this is not
really a light power situation I guess
so I guess we really don't have to
encode it here maybe it was a little bit
premature and that pulling that out not
that it matters it's a fine thing to
pull out anyway but yeah it looks like
that really isn't that necessary because
we won't be we actually won't be
decoding the power because we're just
reading it right out of the emitters
yeah
all right well I take it back so let's
go ahead and just take a look at the
lighting here which is what we want to
do in the first place so if I do f1 this
is the lighting solution but it's being
itself lit by its own output right so
I'm gonna hit disable here so now we can
look at it more directly so here is what
we're seeing as the lighting solution
right and in theory anyway I believe
what I could do here is if I it should
respond properly to the settings of how
intense the light is so if we went down
here and set this light down to a
reasonable level we should see a
reasonable lighting solution not a
blown-out lighting solution when I do
this right and let's see if we do so I
don't know we that still seems really
aggressive right you know it's it's less
blown out but it seems just a bit hot to
me so I'm not sure what exactly is going
on there because you look at how much
light is in the scene here there's just
not a lot of it right I mean it's it's
pretty tame
you know I don't see a lot of a lot of
brightness there really and then when I
go to disable the lighting and I look at
what that lighting solution supposedly
was I just see a lot I mean there's some
crazy bright emitters there I don't even
know how they're getting that such
bright values doesn't really make a lot
of sense that they could have such
bright values so something seems weird
about that maybe this is just related to
bugs we have to fix in our lighting but
just seems odd so don't know what I'm
seeing there and I want to know what's
going on because it doesn't feel right
it feels like there's a bug in that part
specifically so I bet you to know what
it is the output lighting quads function
doesn't do much like it just loops
through here
takes the emission color values and it
just outputs them directly right
and those emit C values are the actual
lighting that that's before the final
gather right so we could also output the
final gather color if we wanted to
and the final gather color would be if
we used incident light instead what's
interesting about this is I wonder if
our emission colors really are that
broken and it'd be interesting to know
so one thing that we could do here is we
could make the ability to set sort of a
dynamically set the config value here
for the iteration count so this lighting
iteration count here right we could make
this be something we can set dynamically
so for example and that will show up
probably I don't know if we actually
expose that in the UI let me see if we
do
should probably put these this in
lighting yeah we do so there's this
iteration cameras actually here we don't
have ways to modify you inch right now
the debug system we should but we don't
and so what we'd want to do here is is
actually set this guy equal to something
dynamically so we can see like on each
bounce how much there is right that
would be kind of useful to us so we
could kind of step through those bounces
and see what happens on each iteration
count right so I'm kind of interested in
looking at that so let's let's do that
real quick so if we take a look at the f
key pressed situation here I'm just
going to hack in a thing that's like you
know totally random so I'll make it will
be like five and six
so that we can just update that by just
pushing the F keys and set it to
whatever we want
right and then we can look at what
happens to the emitters as they go
because this will let us see on each
iteration where our light actually went
which is handy right so what I should be
able to do here oops
do that is if I just go ahead and set
the lighting off should probably set
that to disabled by default at the
moment but anyway if we set that and
then set this right so I should be able
to decrease that now right so if I have
no lighting iterations we should
literally have no light in the scene
right so when I do my f1 I should get
nothing and that is what I get so you
can see that only the things that were
set as emitters in the first place are
still emitters right so now if I
increase my light step by one now you
can see I have sent light around the
scene and you can see where I sent it
right it got sent to these guys out here
it got sent to these guys out here it
got sent to these guys here and so on
now what I don't necessarily know is
whether it should really be that bright
probably it should not because since
this is a radiative transfer if probably
sampling wise has to be taken into
account the fact that we're going
outwards from the light source and not
backwards from the surface so these
services really aren't as bright as they
appear that's probably just something we
need to go improve in the way that we're
thinking about light so from there if I
then do one more step right you can see
that now the lighting has spread you can
see where the red light is spread too
and we have some really nonsensical
results and this is this is revealing
some nice
thugs so this is great we're getting a
lot of information here it should not
have been possible for something that
was already emitting light like that to
change to emitting less this was an
emitter that had a certain amount of
straight emission and loops and what
we're seeing there is it's actually been
overwritten with a new light color
because this bounce affected it so I
think we just want to like kind of
retune the way we're doing this in the
first place these are some really this
is a really good thing to do I should've
done this a long time ago and so we can
kind of see how that light is continuing
to propagate out right so I guess what
I'd say is maybe I want to see we need
to kind of think this through because
we're getting closer to 2 goodness here
and so I kind of want to think this
through a little bit more carefully but
I think we've yep we should probably go
to the Q&amp;A we've we've done the time for
today obviously but I think we've
revealed some really good stuff to work
on now so tomorrow I think we've clearly
got a bunch of stuff we can do that will
make an immediate difference one let's
get this radiation steppin working
properly and I think we just need to
like get serious about our sampling and
how we're recording that light and
tracking it and and then step two will
be once we have that radiative transfer
working more correctly then we can start
to figure out why we're getting these
sort of cross interpolation bugs is it
just because we're putting too many
letting samples next to each other how
are we gonna spread those out properly
like blah blah blah blah blah right so
we can really start to hone in on I
think this is good I'm gonna go ahead
and go to the Q&amp;A now and I will take
questions about the patreon situation as
well because we did talk about that on
the actual stream today so even though
normally we only take programming
questions I'll take either question
because like I said on this stream we
did actually talk about that
specifically so any programming
questions you folks have or questions
about the paper
around situation I'm happy to field at
this point
ah
flying Solomon says if you updated your
fur coat to let latest version you can
now and it strings yes I noticed that
I'm pretty excited about that
I have not updated yet I tend to be a
little bit slow on for coder updates
just because I program everyday in for
coder all day and so I typically set
aside a little time for every upgrade or
do it over the weekend so I don't
interrupt my programming with that
upgrade process cuz you know something
might have changed in the config that I
have to go track down or whatever right
so I tend to always do those updates in
a very staged fashion I am looking
forward to it though for that reason
among others
could the raycasting be bouncing off the
bounds of the scene no we don't do any
bouncing off bounds right now what we
did do is we have an ambient light that
we could turn on which we did there but
we've we've turned that off for now so
that's the only thing that comes in from
the bounds of the scene speed crunch for
a great replacement of wind calc
yeah I like it
deep blue v.7 said could libera PACOM
about b replacement for patreon its
non-profit and paid for by donations to
its own liber libera pay account I'm not
sure yet so my first attempt and I'm
trying to talk to send all about this
but the people who do the payment
processing and download for the handmade
hero source code have been really great
to work with they have never done
anything like this and have always
provided a really good service that has
been very reliable and that I have
really not gotten any complaints about
the only time it ever fails is when
people miss enter their email address
when they buy the product that's about
the only problem I've ever had with it
and it's that's really not ten dolls
fault if people can't put in their
actual email address correctly that's
not much you can do right but that's the
only failure case I've really
experienced with them honestly it's been
very good so my first thing that I'm
gonna probably attempt this weekend is
to try and work out something where you
can just use send owl directly on
handmade here org to pledge a monthly or
yearly donation and then that will just
get automatically deducted and sent to
the projects that I listed in that
patreon email handmade Network the
annotations guide Milton for coder the
bugger projects right and that's the
first thing I'm gonna try and the reason
for that is because it's been around for
several years we've used it reliably we
have no have had no problems they have
not pissed anybody off yet and it's a
service we already have to maintain
anyway for the source code I kind of
been leaning towards that because I'd
rather do that then go with yet another
service that might just implode or go
out of business or anything else so I
just feel like putting our eggs in one
basket might be good because hey if send
owl went down or something bad happened
to it we would have to move the source
code purchase away from it anyway and so
I'd rather just
not have two points of failure there
like every additional one we use is
another thing I might have to deal with
when that thing goes out of business
whereas if everything just at one place
we wouldn't have to just move everything
at that point which you know is really
no more costly than moving one thing
usually whereas having it spread out it
already did exactly thing that that I
wouldn't want to do having a patreon an
to send out meant that now one of them
goes down it makes work for me if we had
had a way to do it all through send out
in the first place we would have never
had that so
just hopped into the stream are you
working on a global illumination
approach specific for 2.5 D uh sort of
and sort of not the global illumination
approach that we're using is fairly
generic and would work in any scene
however it is specifically tuned to the
fact that there's just not a lot of
polygons in the scene right that things
are giant flat cubes or flat plates and
so if this were a real game well it's a
real game if this were a real 3d game as
what I meant to say if this were a real
3d game that would not be true there
would be many many more millions of
polygons in it and you would not
necessarily be able to use this same
kind of solution now they do use
solutions like this anyway for example
and and light darn I'm not gonna
remember the name
I don't think this is the one boy where
is it it's called like oh it is
enlightened so why didn't that find it I
guess it was just too many so enlighten
is a is almost like a middleware I think
it's used in dice it's it's used in the
Frostbite engine and in the Unreal
Engine and I don't know if there's any
like demos of how it works but and I
don't really know what there I have no
idea there algorithm is but it is a
bounce light around kind of a thing
right I don't know exactly what they're
doing but it is sort of similar and I
think it works on like point clouds kind
of so there are things that are sort of
like this and that do work with to
varying degrees of accuracy with full 3d
games with lots of polygons but that's
like a whole other sort of set of things
you have to worry about for us because
we have such low scene detail in terms
of geometry because most of the
geometries in bitmaps right
most of the geometry is what the artists
drew we don't have that problem of
trying to capture radiosity on million
polygons scenes 10 million polygons
scenes 100 million polygons scenes so
while we are not doing anything specific
for 2.5 D we are doing a more
brute-force approach to global
illumination than would ever be feasible
if you were doing a non 2.5 D game so
that part is more 2.5 D hopefully that
makes sense
quick shift said I'm out of the loop
what's up with patreon patreon basically
well they've done to think too big sort
of things now that made people unhappy
one was they sort of started banning
people from the platform on ideological
grounds to a certain extent and there
was argument
definitely on whether it was ideological
or not but people definitely interpreted
it poorly and they didn't like the idea
of patreon banning people from a
platform based on non illegal activity
or something I mean I don't know what I
can't summarize why people are upset
because people are upset because they
were upset anyway they had a bad
situation with that and it ruffled some
feathers because people want to think of
patreon as a way of supporting people
they agree with not as a way of
supporting people that patreon agrees
with right and you can understand why
that ruffles some feathers that was okay
to a certain extent they definitely lost
some subscribers there but it wasn't
catastrophic literally two months later
a month later it has not been long since
that incident kind of flared up a little
bit and made some people upset then they
did something which upset almost
everybody like this was not even
ideological and wasn't really even
something that that formed really
pockets of people who agreed or disagree
with patron basically just a week or two
ago they sent out an email saying that
they're completely changing the way
pledges are counted and they tried to
make it sound like a positive change but
actually it's a very negative change for
a lot of people use the system it's
going to mean that before when they were
pledging a dollar to something and
paying a dollar for the pledge they're
now gonna have to pay a dollar 38 cents
for the pledge and things like this it's
like and the amount that the paid that
the patrons receive is not necessarily
going up depending on the circumstances
and blah blah blah so it's like it's
basically a much worse way of doing
pledges because previously what would
happen is all of your pledges would be
aggregated together and you just have a
credit card bill let's say you pledged
to 50 people and you only pledged $1 to
each of them so you're only pledging $1
to say the handmade hero patreon but you
pledge to a lot of people so it ends up
being $50 a month that $50 charge might
encourage some credit card fees but it
would be print credit card fees related
to that charts would be 2 percent or 3
percent of the 50/50 lower charge plus
whatever the 25 cents are saying you
know whatever a credit card fee is you'd
end up paying 54 55 dollars or something
for a $50 worth of pledges this made
sense to people
now what patreon is doing is they're
disaggregating all
pledges in each pledge is an individual
charge in a weird way so what ends up
happening is if you do $51 pledges each
of those pledges incurs 25 cent or a 35
cent fee plus 2% on top of that or plus
3% I don't remember what it is but
basically long and short of it is if you
do 50 one-dollar pledges you pay 50
times $1 and 38 cents roughly so you
know that ends up being something like
70 bucks or whatever right a big
difference and the creators aren't
taking home much more money in fact
they're in oftentimes taking home less
money potentially or equivalent money
but you're paying way more so the
percentage that the pay that the action
portion your plenty to actually receives
from these smaller dog donations plummet
plummets dramatically and they published
and extremely this was the thing that I
feel like I said a lot of things you
know the internet everyone's always
outraged about everything so before they
were sort of having more of that problem
where like people are upset because
people are always upset and no matter
what you do they're upset and that's one
thing this was a lot different because
this one started to get into really bad
territory of just seeming like you were
kind of trying to pull a fast one on
people and nobody likes that even people
who don't get internet outraged about
things and I'll kind of show you a
little bit of what I mean by that and
this this even to me trying to be fair
to them was really hard to see how this
happens in a realistic scenario so
here's the thing that they published you
know and this is this is like them
trying to convince you this was a good
idea right and they printed a graph and
it looks like this and what you can see
here is this is what they're saying here
was before the patreon pledge before
their change they're saying all right
creator stick tome eighty five to ninety
three percent because there's a
transaction fee of between two and ten
percent and then patreon takes their
five percent cut right now this is a
legitimate graph it doesn't make a lot
of sense to make a graph that has ranges
in it without drawing those ranges but
whatever they picked the max of this
right they took 10% stuck it here 5%
stuck it here and this was the 15% 85%
here right so that's whatever right this
is a fair diagram it probably does sort
of represent what happened although I
argue it's not it this is still not
accurate because vat moss and local
taxes get stuck on here as well so
really it's more like you know there's
another percentage in here that has to
do with country taxes and that gets
added on top of this right so there
should be another percentage on here
drawn in
that's an overage of the pledge amount
that you just had to pay because I'm
pretty sure VAT mas that mas by law has
to be tacked on so they must have been
doing that in other countries because
they're required to and they would get
sued if they didn't or not sued
prosecuted right but anyway let's take
that moss and taxes out of it for a
second this if you take taxes out of the
equation is a reasonable representation
about what was happening to your pre-tax
contribution they then showed this
diagram and if you look at this diagram
you can see that what they've done is
they've taken the previous hundred
percent that was here and said look
creators now take home ninety five
percent that's more than even the
highest percent here patreon takes five
percent that looks pretty good right but
then there's like a service fee on here
which is 2.9 percent plus BOE 0.35 cents
right now this at least starts to
correctly represent the fact that there
are charges above the pledge amount
right again this one probably should
have had it for taxes and they're not
going to represent it here but whatever
so here the same would be true there
should be taxed on here now they're also
showing that the service fee which is
previously this red bar here now don't
do not ask me why they changed which
color was which that's just again
straight-up bizarre and tells me the
people who made these charts have no
idea what they're doing but that's
separate issue right you should the
colors should be constant here this
should have been this color this should
have been this color or vice versa but
you get what's going on right so this
makes it sound like and in all of the
text here is sounds like they're doing
you a favor right but what they neglect
to mention here in the classic how to
lie with statistics sense is 35 cents is
a not a percentage so you can't put it
on a percentage graph what that means is
this bar is 100% fictitious
we have no idea how big it should
actually be until we decide how much
actual money is represented by this
graph right so what we actually have is
a situation where this black bar could
be like enormous in fact let's say a
patron plays pledged only 20 cents right
if a patron pledged only 20 cents just
the 35 cents alone would be longer than
this entire bar right on the other hand
if a patron pledged $10,000 then this 35
cent piece would be nothing it would be
invisible right and herein lies the
problem so what you end up with is a
situation where whether this is good or
not
despite the graph trying to make it
appear like it is always good is in fact
awful for anyone who makes a small
dollar pledge the smaller your pledge
the harder this a fine 35 cents kicks in
to make it so that most of what you're
paying actually goes to the service fee
right and so the problem here more so
than the service fee charge which in and
of itself was probably a bad decision
for anyone donating small amounts of
money it would not affect people
donating largemont people giving $50
$100 this graph is pretty accurate
people giving $5 $2 $1 which is a lot of
people on patreon give a small amount
right they don't have a lot of money or
they give to a lot of things so you know
maybe they're even giving $1,000 a month
but they're giving to lots and lots of
patreon right so either way you might be
you might not have very much money
you're just trying to give what you can
or you might have a lot of money but
you're giving to lots of people right
either case what happens now is your
donation amount gets clobbered by this
fee right this 35 cent fee $1 $2
donations that 35 cent fee is a huge
percentage right 35 cents at the risk of
stating the obvious is 35 percent of a
$1 pledged that's a massive amount going
to fees and they tried to slip
by everyone with graphs like this and
statements like 95% of every pledge goes
to creators right I don't know what to
say it seems very disingenuous that they
decided to present it this way I don't
understand why someone would have said
these things or drawn this graph if they
weren't intentionally trying to
manipulate public opinion to think this
change was more universally good than it
was right and I think that's what people
have really latched onto and why they're
getting angry because yes they are
probably upset the people who are giving
$1 a month to various things they're
upset that this is gonna cost them a lot
more money now and then they can't give
as much money to the people they're
trying to support I am sure that's a big
part of it but I think the real sort of
anger and out the the lashing out at
them for this and cancelling patrons
canceling pledges all that stuff is
coming from the fact that they didn't
humbly apologize for this change and say
we had no choice we have to do this
because of credit-card companies making
us do this or we felt like we had to do
this because of X Y &amp; Z they sold it
like they said this was great for
everybody they were trying to pull a
fast one on you it appears right so
whether they were or not I don't know
but that's what it came across as and
they haven't done anything to us wage
people's fears that that was the case
they've just doubled down and said no
this is better they keep insisting it's
better and they don't seem to be
listening to people say like no it
really isn't
I don't and so I don't know what to say
and so that's the patreon flameout that
appears to be happening now and like I
said unlike the last time where they
kind of had this sort of a thing I now
this seems to be a lot more dangerous
like this is this could be like a site
ending thing for them I know so many I
think just we're closing the hand-made
here a patreon on Monday at the latest I
think
but after that's closed that plus the
other people I know who have closed
their patreon 'he's you're probably
talking about three four thousand
dollars worth of contributions just from
my friends who aren't big patreon you
like I don't know anyone who's making
$10,000 off a patreon right
I know only people who are making a few
hundred dollars off the patreon right
just out of the people I know which is
four or five people or something that's
not very many six eight I don't know the
number that have closed of taking out
several thousand dollars just from that
small group and so assuming the wider
internet looks similarly there this is
gonna like cut in half their net value
or more just just this one weekend this
one mistake will literally half the size
of their thing if that's any indication
so they messed up I don't know what to
say it's in the world of the Internet
the bonus is you can become an overnight
sensation really quick I mean hey
handmade here was a good example of
something that I never thought would
have so many people watching every day
and so many people watching videos on
the mail set that's the power of the
Internet for you it happened almost
overnight just right when we started
right the Internet can do that it can
also punish you incredibly harshly
perhaps more harshly than you deserve
right that's the reality of the world we
live in
I'm sorry patreon like you know maybe
you were just trying to do a good thing
I don't know maybe you're unscrupulous I
don't know either I have no idea what
your deal is I don't know anyone at
patreon I have no idea what their morals
are ethics I don't know if they're
fundamentally trying to do good things
or if they're the types of people who
maybe started out trying to do good
things and is now like Silicon Valley VC
nastiness like you know rolling around
in in my Tesla like eating 12 dollar
toast and talking about like you know
who's in the c-suite kind of stuff like
I don't know what kind of people they
are what kind of people they've become
and generally speaking I try not to make
that kind of value judgment I sometimes
I do and I've been trying lately
cuz I've seen how horrible it is when
people do the internet but trying not to
do that I just I try to like literally
take at face value like what is this
thing doing do I like it or not let me
not try to figure out whether someone
who once worked at the company maybe
someday made a comment on Twitter that I
wouldn't have liked right I've tried to
stop doing that because it seems awful
the way people do that on the internet
now so I don't know and I don't want to
try to read behind the motives of this
change all I can say is yeah I'm
uncomfortable about it too things like
that chart make me really nervous those
look like the kinds of things people do
when either they're really really stupid
like so stupid they can't even figure
out how to make the math for a chart or
they're just kind of unscrupulous and
are trying to make things look better
than they are
right I don't know a lot of other
explanations than manipulative or
incredibly dumb either way don't really
want to be relying on a platform by
people who are either of those two
things so to me it's a good time to get
off of it it was never a source of
revenue for handmade hero anyway it was
only a way to get donations into the
project that we could then pay out to
other projects who were on volunteer
support and so I'm just gonna figure out
another way to get that done and close
down the page and point everyone some
other thing they can use hopefully a
send owl page that will just work
that's fingers crossed but that's what
I'm gonna do so there will be no
handmade hero patreon page very shortly
it will go away I already sent a message
out to all the patrons say hey stick
with it for a couple days we're gonna
try and and fix something here so so
that's what we're doing whether patreon
itself survives this incident I have no
idea I've never seen so many people
cancel their accounts that somewhere so
quickly as this I don't have an
explanation for that other than the fact
that I feel like there's a difference
between commercial and altruistic
funding model
that means you have less leeway here if
you are nice and you're selling someone
sneakers that's a fundamentally
commercial venture and if people find
out that you're using sweatshop labor
and they don't like that
there may be a slight backlash against
you and you can respond to that backlash
etc etc but it is fundamentally a
commercial transaction with different
rules and different expectations patreon
is not that kind of a service patreon is
a service that exists solely because
people are trying to feel like they're
doing a good thing
supporting projects they care about and
when you have a service I think that is
100% about goodwill like that is the
only thing that they are training on
right it is not a commercially oriented
service people are not going there for
commercial transactions primarily I
think what that means just again this is
data free this is just my gut take on it
because I don't know I think you
probably just have a lot less rope right
you're fundamentally dealing with people
with creators who want to be portraying
themselves in a positive light to the
people who are supporting them whatever
that means right and you have patrons
who want to feel like they're doing a
good thing by using the site when that
is the fundamental understanding and
there is no commercial part on top of it
right or very little I think you just
have so much less rope than a Starbucks
or a Nike or whoever who do still care
about their image because it can affect
their sales or whatever right but it's
it's a lot less of it most of the time
you're going in to Starbucks because
it's the closed coffee shop and you're
you think the coffee is fine or
whatever right you're much less
concerned about exactly how much is
going to Fairtrade coffee and exactly
how much environmentally-friendly
building materials went into there so
far whatever there are people who care
about that to certain degrees but it's
not the it's not the main reason you
went into the to the Starbucks right
it's just the things
Vox is trying to do either for them to
feel good about themselves as a company
or for you to feel better about
yourselves about buying the coffee but
that's all whereas something like
patreon I think it's just it's a lot
higher risk of something like this
because the only reason you went there
was to feel like you were doing a good
thing to support somebody was making
something you cared about that's the
only reason you showed up so I feel like
they just don't have a lot of slack and
if they're gonna make a change like this
they have to really think it through a
lot harder than they did vet it a lot
harder than they did with their patrons
and their creators because it was a
two-week thing caught everyone by
surprise right they have to take it I
think a lot more seriously because they
are not the same as a standard
commercial company that it is not a
service first positive feeling second
which I think would be how you describe
most commercial ventures right it's not
transaction first positive feeling
second it's the opposite it's positive
feeling first transaction second company
so if you do something to ruin that
positive feeling you are way more
exposed to backlash than I think anyone
else would be in the commercial sphere
for this kind of a thing right so again
not uninformed to take not a data based
analysis I have no idea of what I just
said is that all accurate but my like
kind of gut instinct is just that that
is a real problem for them and I think
what we're seeing now is an outsized
effect that this change has being as had
specifically because they are much more
susceptible I would suspect to negative
sentiment hurting their customer sort of
loyalty and engagement than what a
normal commercial adventure would hope
to experience right when they when they
have a misstep
Durov and i'm i've been having a lot of
trouble seeing motivated inspired for
new projects do you have any tips on how
to take an idea and actually bring it
fully into existence um not really
I mean I guess what I would say is
there's a couple ways you can do it
number one is you have to make sure that
you're programming every day and you're
programming for like several hours every
day and that's the first thing to look
at separately if you find that it's hard
to program every day for several hours
either a you need to do serious
behavioral work on yourself to make that
happen or you need to reassess whether
you wanted to be a programmer right not
everyone should be a programmer and not
everyone involved in software should be
a programmer right there's lots of other
things you can do there's management
there's art there's design there's all
sorts of other things that people do in
the software world that have nothing to
do with actually coding every day so you
have to assess that right do I actually
like coding every day just the act of
programming right and if the answer to
that is yes then the next step is okay
is my main problem that I constantly
switch around when I'm programming on
and I never program long enough on
something to finish it if that's really
all you're talking about there's couple
different things you can do one start
picking smaller projects sticking pick a
smaller product and work your way up
instead of picking you know I want to
make the next Call of Duty right which
is nuts and involve tons of tons and
tons and tons and tons of work how about
I want to make the next asteroids clone
right and that's it start smaller pick
smaller projects and work your way up
great way to start going gained some
confidence in shipping smaller things
before you try to ship bigger things is
a great thing to do to i spec things
specifically and only finish what you
spec right so that's not a great way to
do real projects because real products
specially gain products take refinement
they take learning from your mistakes
they take revisions but again if you're
having trouble start with sangre like
I'm gonna write down on paper
exactly what this thing is gonna do and
I'm gonna do exactly that and nothing
else is going in here no more
refinements I'm shipping that as version
one and a story right that can help cut
down on the feature creep and the
meandering and the worrying that the
thing isn't good so I can't finish it
because it's just not coming together
and I need to do stuff to fix it know
whatever is in the spec we ship it if
it's a turd it's a turd
even if I only ship it myself on github
whatever I'm finishing it so I can have
the experience of getting it done and
learning what that means right
that's not a good thing to do finally
the nuclear option get a loan take money
start a project over your head that you
will have to finish because you're
freaking out because you don't know how
to pay back the money right and that's
the way to do bigger projects having a
producer an investor or somebody
breathing down your neck and expecting
demos is a real good way to force
yourself to get work then right other
than that I don't know a lot of options
and which option is right for you or
feasible for you depends on what your
situation is what your means are what
your said what you can do what you can
afford to do what you can mentally take
for stress all that sort of stuff I
would obviously start start with the non
taking honey ones first and start to try
and get reasonably sure you can ship
things before you try to do something a
little more drastic like that but you
know I couldn't tell you that's that's
all the options I know of there's no
magic answer and you just got to find
out what works for you one other thing I
would mention is if you are always
working alone start working with
somebody else
it doesn't have to be another programmer
but somebody else who you're working
with can help you stay motivated because
if you're both working on something
that's like sort of mutually reinforcing
oftentimes find somebody else hopefully
maybe someone who's even more motivated
than you are on a typical daily basis
and hope that that will sort of bleed
over right into your motivation because
they'll be expecting deliverables from
you and that will reinforce your ability
to work did you ever get dependency to
work the new version I didn't I never
tried after that stream I just was like
well nope doesn't work and I'm out of
here
I'm fairly new to the series only on
episode 13 do you recommend coding along
with the series I personally like to
just watch and learn rather than copying
everything you type but I don't know I
would say that it depends on what you're
trying to learn from the series if
you're pretty new to program you're
pretty new to game programming I think
you may want to do some coding along
with series it doesn't have to mean that
you copy what I do but it maybe means
you should try to do some side products
or some side coding after you watch an
episode and do the same sorts of things
I'm doing just to cement that learning
in place because otherwise I feel like
it might be a little bit too ephemeral
if on the other hand you're a pretty
accomplished programmer but maybe just
haven't done programming of the sorts of
things that I'm doing here and you just
want to kind of see some new techniques
or learn some things that you're just
gonna apply like randomly on like that
sort of thing then I'd say just watching
it seems fine because you already know
what you're doing you don't need me to
show you most stuff you're just kind of
picking up odds and ends along the way
that seems like it'll just kind of sink
in just fine so I would say it depends
on what kind of learning you're trying
to do where you're at right now and only
you can really answer that question
probably have you considered applying
for a twitch partner I would subscribe
we have not done that because in the
past their contract has not allowed us
to post YouTube videos right away and we
so we had that issue with their standard
contract I might revisit it I don't
think the numbers of scrubbers we would
get would make a significant impact to
us in terms of monetary in terms of
income for the project but you know it's
something people do ask about and I
guess you'd maybe get benefits from it
I'm not sure but yeah you know I could
certainly look into it again but like I
said it's not a real high priority for
us consider getting a Bitcoin litecoin
and aetherium well it's an easy way for
people to donate it's hard to get your
money out of it though but I think it
could be worth it
descend I'll support Bitcoin
so you know I haven't really looked at
this but I I do think I can turn on
Bitcoin for purchases in Sandow I will
look at that and if so if we switch to a
send a donation system as well then
you'd be able to buy the source code
with Bitcoin or the or pledge so I will
add that to things I look at hopefully
as I get a send out system in place OCO
lumion posted a link colombian what what
does this think blog post about patron
onboarding what's in the post can you
tell me what what should I be looking
for in there I'll bring it up first of
all anyone who says like onboarding
growth I already don't like I mean
that's just a little bit of my prejudice
against Silicon Valley in general but I
mean I'll be honest if you use the term
onboarding growth I already probably
don't want to be in business with you
what can you say
yeah I mean I guess like this kind of
here like you know I suppose this year
kind of tells you what you need to know
about the way they look at paid at their
platform right they they're sort of
saying like hey unsuccessful patreon
which I guess we are probably
technically a successful patreon because
we're like eight hundred nine hundred
dollars something like that but you know
someone making fifty dollars a month I
guess they're kind of saying we don't
care about you because you're not
contributing to our viral loop and we're
you're not generating enough revenue I
don't know
you
the fundamental problem was that our
acquisition and activation funnel had a
higher ratio of people who were still
early in the process of building their
fan base meaning they were coming to the
site and not succeeding crews must have
an established online following even as
small and posted a regular frequency
online this specific figured seeking
verba creative exclusive right we were
tracking people who saw creators getting
paid and sustained in patreon and they
would misunderstand this and attribute a
reverse causality they would think that
launching a patreon page okay that seems
fine though that's true it made our
funnels our funnels useless it's great
to see other creators launch and promote
their pages and succeed financially as a
result our virality is through
visibility more than explicit
invitations we receive Dropbox for our
social network
project mondo and countering creative
growth experimentation the patron team
took a hard look at their growth levers
and realized that to make it you know it
really sucks that Silicon Valley like
95% of it seems like what they think
about all day is like how to manipulate
people into using their platform now I
can appreciate the fact that it's a
nuclear arms race right like it's kind
of like well because you know Google is
spending all of their time figuring out
how to manipulate people into you know
looking at their ads or whatever we have
to spend all day thinking about how we
manipulate people into using our
platform and you know uber the think
about all day how they manipulate people
into using their ride-sharing service
and blah blah blah like I understand
that fact but it still it still sucks
like it still it's like it's not good
just because everyone it's kind of like
nuclear weapons it's not great
that we all have them I understand why
everyone has to have them but it's not
like I'm happy about the fact that all
of these bad things are existing and I
would say that this is the kind of thing
that just leaves an awful feeling right
cuz you're just like a god like I can
tell you the amount of time we have
spent thinking about our handmade hero
purchasing funnel is exactly zero we
don't even have a funnel we just have a
web page with a button on it let's see
here
- team of oh I thought that's a 2.1
engineers in fact doesn't that say 2.1
engineers it was implemented by a team
of 2.1 engineers does that mean they
took somebody and cut him off at the
ankles and just put his feet on to the
team or what what is a point one
engineer does anyone know what that
means
maybe that's just because the program is
a patron are so bad but they only count
for point one of an engineer or
something so two point one engineers is
is actually like twenty one engineers at
a company where people know what they
were doing or something I don't know
what that means that's a I don't know
what that means at all but maybe it's a
looking Valley speak for people working
a tenth of the time on something like
one out of every one day out of every
two weeks is that a point one engineer
let's see it's called Project mondo by
the way it's like Monday dude oh here's
a diagram chain reaction the highest
leverage metric capacious growth model
is new financial Sissel creators who
trigger further creative virality as
well as help bring more patients to
countersign the service software as a
service side activation in the viral
funnel use as valuable as direct shares
okay so here's the loop I guess you guys
all got this there's a new creator that
crater launches a patreon page they
promote via multiple channels the
audience sees that page and then the the
percentage of the audience who also
creators click through enter their
credit flow so this is correct I mean
this is what happened with handmade hero
right people asked me to create a page I
did other handmade hero related projects
saw that page that was promoted by other
channels and then it create like we do
this exact loop so they're not wrong
[Music]
what if you kept the same amount of
shares but doubled your rate of
onboarding improving funnel conversion
is powerful a sharing happens out there
shank you remember product whatever um
versus radius expensive function
onboarding says affects all our metrics
ok defining friendships of creators in
order for the patreon onboarding spirit
to have a competitive effect the company
ID to be able to identify its single out
the seminar creators that have the
greatest potential to achieve financial
success so basically they're kind of
like it's a winners outs thing that
we're kind of trying to help people who
already need the least help if you will
right it's kind of like a Donald Trump
tax plan or something right it's kind of
like a we want to find people who are
already winning and help them win more
or whatever the creator for having a
five screw the creator cars driven has
absolute numbers follows around so the
team looks for quality at how much of
engagement how consistently the people
who are engaging our engagement right
okay it's like the ultimate end
quantitative criteria of a certain level
of monetary earnings because it's simple
and functional for the growth team to
optimize for that so then how do they so
how do they actually help those people
though I mean I understand how you might
go about identifying which people you
think could make more money than they
are making easily like without a lot of
work but I'm not sure how you help them
so how did they help them
because to Emil the grass will use
patreon but with a few concrete examples
they come alive and totally get it
I'm not sure what this means in Category
comparables you can't do patreon doesn't
have X featured in Greta those
complaints we're really just a
smokescreen for a more fertile fear of
having patrons expending a beggar's Bowl
the Christian only proposed sales and
asked their colleague it's easy I just
show someone on patron whom they respect
in their category and then they don't
care anymore okay so they say like look
you know such and such a famous person
who you like is using patreon to beg for
money so you should beg for money - that
makes sense
all of these seem fairly reasonable if
manipulative right
[Music]
we have creators here for the time they
meet our teams of CEO they what so what
I thought about B hmm but until we tried
we would rock through it with the fig
account to vet it does this feel
reliable is this going to make us look
amateur in front of our fans is this
something that serious careers reduce
time to some guy who took his first
guitar lesson we encountered a lot of
Opposition in the organization WYSIWYG
is the most common best rectus make it
easy make a frictionless most great
professionals efforts before some of
these people on the Internet are stupid
and improved conversions Roisin mind we
have to dumb down
the team also stands that their tool is
to fling a use case that's highly
personal and very emotional there's a
lot of vulnerability they might fail in
front of their fans people on the
internet aren't always looking for a
low-friction areas and our functioning
perfectionist
[Music]
all right that doesn't really matter
so I guess I don't know I mean other
than being kind of distasteful I'm not
really sure like like that's just like
yeah this is a Silicon Valley you know
marketing kind of nonsense right it
seems like it's roughly accurate
definitely you know double suggest that
patreon doesn't maybe care about low
dollar donations because they're not
gonna maybe comprise enough of their
income which would explain why they
don't you know maybe why they made this
fee change and thought it wouldn't be a
big deal because they're mostly thinking
about people who get $50 a month to a
project rather than people give $1 a
month maybe but I don't know it wasn't
that much stuff in here it's kind of
just a big old Silicon Valley standard
nonsense kind of a thing
okay Dragoon x6 what do you think of get
large file storage or any other get
large asset plugins over centralized
search control such as SVN or perforce
I've been taking a look and for free as
in pay solution I actually came to
mercurial with its large asset plugin
what do you recommend we use a custom
stuff it Molly so I don't have a
recommendation on if you don't have your
own source code system I don't know what
you would use exactly
I don't think particularly highly of git
it's just not really stable to me it's a
giant collection of like Python scripts
I think it is just not the kind of thing
I would trust really anything - it's
just kind of way too sprawling and it's
not concise enough for a system that's
handling like the most precious bits you
know I don't I don't so I wouldn't use
something like that but I mean I you
know I wouldn't I don't so I don't know
if you're gonna have to use something
maybe gets the best thing I don't know I
know people have used
oh sorry pearl yeah not Python Perl
scripts I don't know if mercury is
better than GUID or gets better than
mercurial I don't know if you know I
know that the witness for example would
use subversion it didn't use either of
those two and was it fabulous maybe not
did it work yes did it ever lose
anything no so you know there's
definitely products out there that are
really huge probably bigger than
whatever you're doing that used
subversion just fine so
you know
that's all that's all I could say about
that so I don't have a personal
recommendation I have worked on one
project namely the witness that did do
everything including the art assets
through subversion and it worked
it did not pose too many problems
although I do think they had to do a
little bit of work with it for certain
circumstances I think those things were
related more though to NTFS Oslo file
enumeration stuff maybe then they then
they had to actually do with subversion
so I'm not sure that I'm not sure if
they ever really had a problem with
subversion directly so I don't know but
what I can say is that you know they're
still using it as far as I know all of
John's projects still go through
subversion so he's not the kind of
person who would keep using a system if
it was completely intractable although
that said he's still using Emacs
but generally speaking no and I think if
it was causing a lot of problems he
would have done something different so I
feel like subversions probably a pretty
safe bet as well in there I don't know
if get her mercurial is like a better
choice in some way but I think
subversion would I would include that in
your list of things that maybe you would
use oh wait you did you said SVN or or
perforce not just perforce so I don't
know
alright let's go ahead and wrap it up I
think we have covered everything in the
queue colons and we talked about the
patreon fiasco as well all right thank
you everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to support the series and you
would like access to the source code or
either of those two things you can
always pre-order the game on handmade
hero org don't click the patreon link
though cuz that's going away we will
have this button removed sometime
shortly but the other buttons they'll
still be there you will still be able to
preorder the source code through send
out obviously you'll still be able to go
to the forum site and ask questions you
will still be able to use the schedule
bot to find out when we're gonna be live
and you will still be able to look at
the episode guide until tomorrow when
hopefully I'll have a little bit more
information about what we will be
replacing patreon with please have fun
programming and I will see everyone on
the Internet
take it easy everybody