hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show recode complete game live on
stream
uh we weren't originally gonna do uh
streams this weekend
but it turned out that i i did have time
available to do it
so i figure we might as well take a look
uh at where we're at and let's see here
if i just go ahead and open up
um really we we were just
replacing our collision detector because
it came time where i wanted something
fairly
robust uh that i could work with um
for the rest of the game and you know we
hadn't really looked at collision
protection
for basically the entire development
process we threw one in there at the
beginning
but we want to start doing things like
putting in little like you can see like
this little
glove in here right we want to start
putting collision detection for stuff
and so we were sort of looking at uh
how that would work and we have some
sort of
we have some reasonable ideas of how we
want that to go
and it's really just a question of
figuring out
exactly how to like what's the simplest
thing
and the most stable thing that will give
us the kind of collision detection we
want
without uh like over complicating things
right
because collision detection is actually
a very difficult problem
it's very easy to write a bad collision
detector
it's very hard to write a good one it's
probably the right way to
put it that way and collision detection
in and of itself may not really be the
right
way to phrase it what we're really
talking about is collision response so
there's one half of the problem is do
two things collide
and that's not necessarily that hard to
do
uh it's still pretty difficult to do
well so i'm not trying to say it's easy
but it's really the response part that's
the harder part making sure that
when you detect that collisions occur
resolving them in a way that always
leads to like
good results stable results for the game
that's sort of more the part uh that
that is is not great right um and so
i believe this is where we were at i'm
gonna re-enable the
um the movement routine here uh and you
can kind of see uh where we're at
so uh this was uh us
looking before and uh well that doesn't
look like it's on for some reason which
is weird
do we not i thought we left this in a
working state last time but i guess we
didn't
um you can see here that we do
a subdivision count oh you know what we
probably did
uh i think we did the like does it
accept
uh or reject thing but it looks like
yeah that that looks like it's in the
the right uh the right place though
there so i'm not sure
i guess when we when we stopped i don't
really remember but when we stopped
doing the subdivision here i guess the
move
uh entity locally thing when we were
doing the stepping
still allows it to tunnel i guess
because it's enough of
a of an enough of a step don't worry
about all this
i will explain in detail sort of where
we're at as soon as i remind myself
where we're at
um but at the moment you can see it
looks like it's just allowed to go
straight through
now uh let me re-enable the drawing as
well
um so if we go in here and we turn on
push volume outline
um and uh
we go ahead and run it here uh let's
take a look yeah so there you go so you
can see the green
is when it when it doesn't collide and
the red is when it does
and you can see there like so what
happens
is and it's hard to explain but if i
if i stop this from being able to run
larger step counts or i do something
slightly different with the desired
position stuff
uh i feel like that would
probably tell us let me just see here
results equals true if we were able to
get it
yeah that seems weird i feel like this
is i must have forgotten not trying
because it shouldn't
be doing what it's doing right now i
feel like
i'm seeing something weird like like did
we mess something up
because i feel like this is supposed to
stop it looks like
right it stops when it can't move right
it's got a result
equals false up here it tries to move
the entity
right and
assuming that it was able to move the
entity it would set the result
equal to true and if it can't it just
leaves it at the from p
location so wherever the entity was
when it started right um and so
this should and maybe it's just because
the step count
was too low or something like this
it should have stopped when it hit
things and and i don't know like it
could be that that number is just too
too low or something but it should have
stopped when it hit things
and not have been able to keep going
through but i don't actually know
um like yeah like you can see it's even
red there so i'm not sure
how it's able to to penetrate through
it looks like it doesn't care that the
collision detector said it can't go any
further
so i would have thought that would have
stopped it but for some reason it
doesn't actually seem to have
and so we'll have to look at that
because i thought we were at the place
but
either way it doesn't matter because the
point is
where we got to last time even when i go
figure out what
got messed up in here it's not
sufficient
because we didn't have a good way
of looking at how you moved through the
world
and determining that you could or
couldn't move out of a position that was
interpenetrating was
was mainly the problem um and so
yeah so i'm not sure about this so i'm
going to take a minute to just look at
this and figure out why it's not
stopping the player currently
because i want to make sure it's back to
the state that i thought it was in which
it obviously isn't
you can see here where we do the uh the
testing here
um it starts out assuming
that it's going to go to frumpy uh it
then checks to see
uh when the oh is it is it because of
how we were doing the voxel marking or
something
i don't know uh it tests to see whether
or not uh
it can be placed at each point in the
voxel and then what it does is it just
says hey for every square
in the voxel of the motion we're just
going to go
what's the one that has the closest
point to the place that we're trying to
get to
and then it moves it there and this part
here the step count thing
that was just a way of us trying to
figure out like hey
if we're going to do motion in this way
we want to make sure that we can't
tunnel so we need to make sure that the
maximum step size is fairly low
now this um
this part here was just something we ad
hoc through in just to see
what it would do and it does it's not
really something that we probably want
we want our collision section to be
fairly stable and so what we probably
want that voxel size to be
fixed we want the voxel size to be like
a
certain size that is always the same
and we probably want to make sure that
the voxel size
doesn't vary just based on the movement
right
and so
i mean the question here is do we just
go do we just keep going and go into a
subdivision kind of a thing
i think we probably want to do that um
but like i said
i don't know uh what went wrong here so
i'm just going to
just going to drill it down into this a
little bit more so here you can see what
we're doing is we have a step count
and we're basically subdividing the
motion uh
into into steps and what we do is we try
to get the player to move to along each
of the different steps with
with the understanding that you know the
distance that
has to move um is has to be capped to a
certain size
um and if we look here uh
i don't know why so what we're doing
here is we're saying here's how far
this thing wanted to move the number of
steps that will take is going to be
however long that is
minus the motion displacement size which
is the maximum
amount we want to uh allow a thing to
move
and the reason for that is that if we
want to allow
arbitrarily large movements we would
then have to make sure that our
collision detection
our collision detection prevented
tunneling
through objects of basically arbitrary
size
right and one of the things that i would
like to do
is exploit sort of efficiency gains we
could get
by having some kind of an of a known
worst case
where we're like look there is no thing
that is going there's
no point in the game where there will be
something
thin enough that it's under a particular
thinness threshold
so that we don't care if you tunnel
through something that thin
right like we're just going to say
everything in the game
is at least this minimum thickness
and once you say that then you can
exploit the fact that you never have to
look for tunneling below that threshold
whereas if you say that things can be as
thin as they want to be
you kind of put yourself in a position
where you really have to crank up
the complexity of the routine
because now you have to handle
any arbitrary little slivery thing
you're basically saying
right and so i'd like to make our job
easier by just saying look we're going
to have
some kind of a size here that we're
going to say we just don't check
for tunneling below this threshold and
the reason for that
is just purely for efficiency if we want
to make a robust collision detector
it's way easier to make an efficient
robust one
if you have some lower bound that you
can guarantee
versus no lower bound you can guarantee
so if we take a look at the total length
and we look at how
much displacement there is that's saying
here's how many steps we're going to try
and i guess when i look at this uh
i realize that that this is not um
it feels like this must not be
triggering
because it should be the case that as
soon as it tries one of these micro
steps it's basically doing micro steps
right
it's saying i'm going to try at the
various places along this line that are
however many steps there are
right i don't know why there was a
minimum step count here of
anything other than one because you
would think that that zero would be the
only invalid
step size
i so i'm not sure what this was designed
to do
um
[Music]
oh that's no no that's the minimum it's
based saying don't take
more than that step size sorry sorry so
okay
so yeah whatever uh you're basically
saying look we don't want to try
uh harder than this the problem with
something like that is
this part here has to be obeyed for the
routine to work
right so we're pretty much going to have
to do
you know to ensure that we're always at
that minimum size and that's just kind
of how it has to go
and that's fine um so when we look here
let's see here if does that change
things at all yeah so you can see that
even though
we're doing that step size it doesn't
matter right it's still able to go right
through
and so what i want to look at now is how
that's happening because
this means we're never we should never
be asking for a step
that's larger than that because we start
at the original entity p
right the place where it started at the
beginning of the frame and then we just
asked to move
little increments and we know that the
increments can't be more than this
right um unless i'm wrong about that
t step yeah because it's just it's
whatever the motion the total amount of
motion
we just take the uh percentage we are
through the steps
right which is is that and we just look
at what they are
so so that should be it should be like
right
um and so i
looking at this the question is why is
move entity locally
seeming to think that it can keep moving
it because you would think it would stop
right
so if we take a look at what happens
here uh
we start out by saying well we've got uh
well i guess we should check this
this part as well um so we go through
here and we say
look we've got uh
we've got a thing called allows motion
on collision
and that's a thing that is going to be
set on anything that's supposed to
uh that you're supposed to be able to
move through so that's like the room
um boundaries and stuff like that
but otherwise whenever something
intersects we set the occupied flag on
that part of the voxel to true
right so we march through uh
each part of the voxel we set it up so
that if something intersected
uh at that point and we just test the
two
rectangles here the thing that's moving
in the thing that's uh blocking it
we just set it to true uh so that we
know that that
that uh part of the voxel is occupied
and then we look through uh the voxel
and we just look to see
if there's any voxel cell where the
corners
were all open then we take that cell
and we allow you to move anywhere inside
that cell which again is not what we
want to do
at the end of the day but it because we
then say
that you were able to move um at that
point
if you weren't able to keep going it
should return false and it should stop
this loop and that doesn't look like
what's happening
so i feel like there's something that i
busted in here or that's wrong
and that's really the only thing that i
was saying i wanted to get to the bottom
of first
now if we look at how this
thing is working so one of the things is
as we iterate through this voxel uh we
have sort of the concept of the base of
the voxel right
um and the base of the voxel is going to
be based on this voxel bounds
here right so we do this rectum in max
and basically what we're doing is we're
saying
take the from position to position
consider those to be two corners
of the box um and we use the min max
here to just make sure that we take
whatever the enclo
the box that encloses the place we're
coming from and the place we're going to
uh it we then add what looks like a very
large
and this is probably the this is
probably the issue right here
um it looks like we then add a very
large
apron to it well no point one that's not
large what am i talking about that's
pretty small so never mind that's not
the problem
um we add an apron around that
and that gives us the voxel uh that
we're going to search
we then move through that voxel um
doing the testing like i said before uh
and we do
the cell dim which is just whatever the
voxel bounds are divided by the voxel
dimension which is exactly what you
would expect so that all looks
i don't see anything weird there i don't
know maybe other people do
um we iterate over the voc
what is this what is what is that
do we know what the heck that was
supposed to be i guess we just
forgot to delete that that's not a thing
um so we have the voxel dimension we
have the cell dimension
off we go uh and then later we iterate
over the same voxel and we start at the
front piece so in theory
and you know just to just to check the
assumptions here that i
have making uh the assumption is that if
i if i
block that out so i don't set uh i don't
run this loop
i i shouldn't see any movement right
like it like it it shouldn't
uh go anywhere nobody should be moving
okay so
so right off the bat you can tell that
this is busted for some reason
right um because there
i'm literally not updating this thing or
at least i didn't think i was
um and yet it moved right
so something's busted here and i don't
really know uh
what it is so we got to figure out
what's going on there so when i say move
entity locally
it looks like i'm passing some stuff to
this what am i passing
i'm passing the entity from p and the
entity to p
uh so so that
looks kind of weird
um but no that's okay because
no it's not so this this is what
this is would be a problem right
uh although it shouldn't it still
shouldn't have moved because
the best p should now just be always the
from p which is the entity p which so it
should
it should never change so how is it
changing
right um in here you can see
oh
what the heck is this doing here
did we just hack that in for some reason
so that whole time i was looking at this
routine it was just because we
always moved it forward
why were we doing that it must have been
something we were
playing with the last stream so that
whole thing was just probably because
somebody threw that line in there
that somebody is unfortunately me so i
can't blame somebody else
i would like to but yeah just i don't
know what that was doing there
it's fine i wanted to reacquaint myself
with all the stuff we were doing anyway
but
yeah okay so now we're back to a better
scenario which is that
um i think we're at the exact place that
i wanted to be
if i had noticed that that thing was
there uh and that is as you can see it
actually looks like
everything's working fine until you get
embedded in something right
and this is one of the things that we
really want our closed deck to handle so
it's not
a good situation but what you can see is
like for example the gameplay code
just because it doesn't care and wasn't
thinking about it it
initially creates the glove
embedded in the floor right and what you
can see
is when this thing moves around
uh you don't
i should i say this
because we only allow motion if all
of the squares of the voxel around you
are open
and we don't really search outside
of the place you're trying to move
very much you can't really
get out of things very effectively right
uh because we don't subdiv if we see
that like oh
where you are if you would have been
moved
backwards a little bit you would be out
of the thing you're in
we don't really have any way of dealing
with that kind of stuff at all
right and that's not good because one of
the things we need
is literally that
so uh we end up with a problem
that that is is a conceptual problem i'm
not sure
what the right way to change how we're
looking at the voxelization problem
is if we want to ensure that we search
for places to put the player when they
come too close
into contact with things like that or
the glove where it's embedded right
i'm really not sure how to phrase it uh
my guess
it's easy enough to detect that it
happened
because we kind of know that we didn't
find
like we know when we don't find any
place to put
the player right that's a condition we
know because we look through the voxel
cells and we don't find anything
right all of the voxel cells are
partially
occupied so when we know that
i'm wondering if that is like the thing
we
then act on and
say well we gotta widen the search area
or something like this
right um
and again i'm just not sure
when you look at like the move entity
locally routine
you know i could think of some like
hacks that sort of help
but i don't think they're really
sufficient like if you take a look at
what's happening with the apron size
here
you could imagine orienting the voxel
so that it includes a wider apron of
search
right um and
again i'm just not sure
i guess the way i would say is this
if the voxel that the person starts out
in
is considered open then you pretty much
don't have a problem
because that means that there isn't any
nearby collider
if the voxel that the person starts out
in
is so so so
the the vox the person starts out in is
not open
then that is the case that we need to
handle and so what we may want to do
is take action on that case
when we see that case
we probably need to change the idea of
what we're doing
because at that point we're saying this
thing
especially if we detect that it's
actually embedded so if all
of the voxels corners that the player
is or not the player but the entity
that's moving
if all of the voxel corners are all
colliders so they're all marked as as
closed
then you know that the player is lit or
the entity is literally embedded in
geometry and needs to be moved out
of that geometry right so we kind of
need
a strategy for that right
and i'm not sure
i'm i'm gonna say something now and it
may be totally false
but if you are in a cell
that is partially colliding
we could allow you to move toward
the part that isn't right
so that's thing a
thing b is that
if we detect that there that all of them
are colliding
then we could try to move you in a
direction
that is towards some place you can go
and
that's the part that's a little tricky
because how would we know
where that is right
how would we know where you actually can
be placed
and i guess you just have to do a very
wide search at that point so it's just
kind of like a fallback
kind of a thing um
so yeah so this is very tricky but i'm
liking where it's going
so like for example in here what you can
see is
this probably wants to be done a little
bit differently
probably what we want to do is say get
closest point in box and when we do get
closest point in box
we probably want to allow you to
in fact do we just want to allow you to
move anywhere in the box that's
towards corners that are open right
so what we could do is say uh
trying to think of the most efficient
way you could code this but like we
look at the corners of the box so we
when we get the closest point
that closest point is going to be on
like one of these
features right um
either it's inside the box itself or
it's you know it's features
we should then be able to say that
displacement
is going to it would have like
we only need to check that displacement
so so i'm thinking that it's more like
sine
[Music]
uh
it's more like sine of
didn't we have a sign or zero looks like
we don't
have a sign or zero
i thought we did for the um
octagonal the octagon thing
um but i guess we don't
so but it's sort of like i just want to
know what the sign of this thing is
right uh which direction are we going to
look
and
so yeah like i think we can just do
something like
um
so dir offset or something like a
directional offset
and we just say hey what's the direction
this thing is going
so we have the delta right and it equals
or actually we don't even need that it's
it's literally just like
um you can see what direction we would
be going
um and in fact i guess we have to do
that in here right
so we produce the test p
and the 2p right so we have the closest
point
in the box and we just see whether or
not that motion
would have been open right um
and i guess i'll do it here you might be
able to save this work because it would
be basically the same
um but so here's us doing that
computation
right and we say get the closest point
in this voxel cell
uh we then just say well we have the
test
p right and we have the from p
so we know we are coming from here okay
what that did uh we're coming from here
uh so we want to know like is the from p
less than the test px
right like like are we going
in are we going from
a lower value to a higher value of x
and if we are we want to look at the
far end of the voxel if not we want to
look at the close end of the voxel in x
and if we just do this then we know
which part of the voxel we care about
right
and so from that position it seems like
then we could tell
like do we
need to stop or not based on whether the
stuff
in that direction is positive or
negative it's kind of a long shot
but i want to see what that does so if
we try that
and i i basically say like okay let's
let's
nerf this saucy gentleman here for a
second
uh and let's just try a different if
statement
where instead of testing the entire
voxel
we're just going to test a subset of the
and that subset is specifically the part
which we just computed right uh in fact
we just only test one that seems
nuts and i can't imagine this will work
but
i don't know i'm gonna try it i guess
um i don't imagine that will do anything
good but
i just want to see like so if you allow
people to always move
towards whatever part of the vauxhall
uh is positive
what happens right and i don't know
so i'm going to test this on maybe some
of these floating heads over here
to see what they do um i have no idea
what they're going to do
but we'll see so if i if i kind of come
through here right
um or these two together
uh
[Music]
so it's not like catastrophic or
anything
right it seems to still work sort of
uh and and and those guys don't get
stuck anymore
so things that weren't stuck to begin
with don't seem to be getting stuck
in that way things that are currently
stuck
do still get stuck like the glove could
not get out
so that doesn't help um but it's at
least interesting
right uh
it's that's at least interesting
so that shows a little bit of promise uh
yeah so um
i don't know i might start i might
actually leave that in for a little
while
yeah i might leave that in for a little
while um
so that looks like no because then that
looks like they they got stuck
right see they got stuck uh
on each other at least a little bit
right
where they're trying to move crosswise
although well
actually that's i guess what you would
expect because
they are trying to move if they're both
trying to move to squares
where they're where they're actually are
pushing into each other
they don't have any ais so they're not
smart enough to know that they shouldn't
do that
why can i not move into that square
what's that about oh no
this dude is like stuck underground
that's crazy so he's occupying that
square and somehow got placed down there
not a great sign um
so i'm okay with that i might leave that
in for a little bit um
i'm at least gonna leave the code path
in there for playing around with
um but again this doesn't really help us
if uh so so
the fundamental problem of if something
starts out colliding uh we
don't have a solution for this right
so my assumption is that if something
starts out colliding what we should
probably do
is just allow the motion um
and if i remember correctly like we
couldn't do that
like this part here uh
we can't do because if we just
allow the motion
anytime uh
you can just tunnel through anything you
want right so we can't just set this to
2p
and call it a day
although
thinking through that the only reason
that's true
is because currently we don't actually
consider the placement
move to have worked if there's only
one cell
okay so actually we might
we might be able to do that
i mean i'm kind of leaning towards
actually just doing this
in the stack way like like can we just
actually have the voxel go the way the
voxel goes
like
like can we just say all right
so let's slightly change this let's
start
in the voxel so we know like we did the
from p2p
nonsense right so
what if we just actually do a thing
where we say
hey um
let's just make a stack and let's
pathfind through the voxel
for the motion
because then we could then what we could
do is say look
if you start out completely inside
we just accept the motion that you
requested
right um
because if we can't find anywhere else
to put you then we're going to let you
go
whereas if we ever find any place that
could have
that had any things that were open at
all
then we won't right we will consider
that successful
in fact we could even do that right now
in a crappy way
right you would just say this
um and then what you would do is you'd
take
this
i i should probably not quite do it that
way
so what i could do here is say all right
let's
set best p equal to 2p
in the case where there wasn't anything
open so we could do that
right away by just saying like oh okay
well um if
uh
if all of these are occupied
so basically you and them all together
like so um i could just say
like any open equals any open
or not all closed
right and now you would know like if you
found somewhere to put the player
then you prevent the move but if you
don't
then you don't right
um and so in theory that would allow
interpenetrating things to get out of
their penetration
uh fairly easily um i love the springs
the undamped springs
so uh and and you'd be fine right
uh and so the only problem there again
is that like we're gonna be allowing
things
that maybe we shouldn't allow um i'm not
sure
like i can't say for sure why is it just
because it's too small
that we end up allowing that to move
through
because i guess it's because we don't
check enough behind you but shouldn't
the place where you start
shouldn't that have been valid it seems
a little fishy to me
so something's a little off i feel like
we've got issues here
right uh i mean this this isn't great as
it is but it
shouldn't be as bad as that so i feel
like something's up
you can see here we're just saying like
if all of these are occupied
um then you can't place it there whereas
if if
uh if any of them were then then there's
an any open so that it should uh
allow uh you to place it if if any of
them were open
or if if there were no places to place
uh
the thing right um
so yeah i don't know
i don't know why that would continue
especially because you've got the apron
size
you know happening here so it should be
like looking
slightly behind um
and that just seems
it doesn't seem right um
although i suppose you know
uh with this still in there
that that may that part may be busted
but it just it doesn't quite seem
correct
uh yeah and he doesn't even need it
right it can tunnel through even without
that so it's just it seems a little bit
busted
so i'm a little bit worried and i feel
like more or less uh
at this point i don't think i'm gonna
have a lot of choice but to
have better visualization of what's
going on as we kind of explore through
here because
at any point when i'm doing this i could
just have a bug
right and without being able to see more
carefully
what's actually going on um
i won't be able to
i really won't be able to like debug
right i won't be able to know if a test
that i did
failed uh because of a
because it actually was a bad approach
or if it failed because
i just didn't have you know i i i had
some bug in there that
made it appear like it didn't work when
it should have
um so there's a couple different routes
i can go with it but you know that's
just something that was in my head at
that point
so looking at this
yeah i would say like it's weird that
part is weird
because it seems to me like any open
should always be occurring um
because wherever i placed the thing last
time should still be valid
as people are moving around it seems
like it should say oh yeah there were
places you could have been
uh it's just that they weren't they
didn't have entirely open edges so we
didn't place you there or whatever
or in the other case it's like we looked
at the at the place where you were
trying to go and we
we said that was closed so we stopped
you um
but you know it shouldn't have actually
triggered that
um that any open case
so that seems weird uh that seems weird
to me
to be completely honest um
yeah i don't know
i don't know but that seems weird that
doesn't make sense to me
it doesn't feel like that's what that
should be doing
um
so if i were to go take a look
closer i'm curious if if what we have
for visualization currently can give me
at least some clues before i have to go
further down that particular rabbit hole
um so one of the things you can see
is that like
on a particular frame i guess would be
nice if we had a little bit more of a
like
of an idea of yeah i kind of need a good
like vantage point there yeah
so you can kind of see like as it moves
it moves very slowly through there so
it's like it's like accepting the first
it looks like it's doing
it is it is literally failing
that check the any open check is
not coming back true but how can that be
because especially when you add an apron
at the beginning so you're looking
somewhat behind you
right how can it possibly be the case
that you couldn't have found a place
where at least one
of the things was unoccupied
right uh it
doesn't make a whole lot of sense now
this part uh
i suppose we should maybe think of this
more like a tetrahedron
and so like you know if if
this had actually worked and this hadn't
i have some ideas about why that would
be
the weird part is this one requires that
you
be able to move um through the entire
cube
right or it won't accept the motion
uh and so when i uh come through here
and
and we just say like okay you know i'm
still able to push through
my question is like how is that even
remotely possible
and if i turn off the any open part of
that
right so that's not happening
uh right i can't test it
i guess what i could do is move the
glove up properly
so it's not starting down in a bad
location like that
i could probably do something like that
so here in the add player call you got
you know all this nonsense
you place uh like the glove p
at whatever the position is i can say
something
uh like that and just force the glove
to not be uh interpenetrating right
so i guess you can
well but it's still allowed to go
straight through thing i i it's very
hard to tell like
this is very weird i feel like i must
have some kind of bugs
in here right because it doesn't feel
like it should be able to do that
and there's a bunch of things in there
that are still like i'm just like okay
yeah you could you could
this allows tunneling and that allows
tunneling so it's not like i'm surprised
that it's tunneling
but i am surprised that the way in which
it is tunneling currently
it's not what i would have expected it
to do right
um so that just seems really strange
it doesn't make a lot of sense to me how
that's working
um
i just i i literally have no idea i'm
i'm i i
feel like there must be some bugs in how
that's working
um can i can i tunnel the glove through
a door or only this guy
and it's it won't go through unless i
get up enough
sort of speed and i suppose
um but it definitely goes through right
i mean it certainly seems like it does
uh is there any way to get it to like
yeah
i guess i don't know maybe it doesn't i
feel like it does
i mean i guess what i can say is that
like all right so
so this case here is obviously
triggering though because
no matter what else you want to say if i
enable this case
it can tunnel trivially so that part's
obviously
busted um and so
maybe like we just first say okay figure
out why that's not working the way that
i think it should because like
why can can i just tunnel through that
guy trivially
so why is any open
when we look through here let me make
this 100 explicit
so any open is normally set to false
which means you didn't find anywhere
this code right um
i mean this code is is actually easier i
mean i don't even really need to do it
that way
um so let's just say this
any open here
right just says if these rectangles
intersect
then it's equal to true right um
and so in here we could just say like
uh
open counts equals zero um
or let's say closed count occupied count
um and we could just just count
um and so here you just do look if
there's something open
if the occupied count equals
you know vox dim cubed
or i should say it doesn't equal right
if there aren't
as many uh people occupying locations as
there are locations to occupy
then it's not opened right
[Music]
right
um and so at least now we know like okay
it there there isn't some weirdness with
the check right
and it is easy for it to tunnel through
at least that way
yeah it's pretty easy for it to tunnel
through right it's not really having
trouble going through
so that means that most of the time
it doesn't think there's anything there
are any
of them open
normally i would say that's because this
is happening in a loop so after you do
the first step of the loop while it's
open
but in here it's actually not allowed to
continue
if it doesn't find a place to to put
uh the player right or the place to put
the entity
so i'm not so that doesn't really make
sense
it's just a real puzzler how can the how
can it not have
any non-colliding
corners of the voxel
that just boggles my mind i i do not
fundamentally understand how that's
possible
um so assuming that the motion
displacement size itself
uh was the apron does that change
anything meaning if you give it
more room to search do you get worse or
better behavior
and this is just me trying to provoke
the thing right
yeah i just i fundamentally do not
understand what's going on
like i just i clearly just have no idea
i think this routine is working one way
and it is not working that way
right um
because it should not matter how
you put like you shouldn't be able to
get the two different results there
um and you clearly can
right like how is it able to push in
like that
when it's so obvious that you have a
thing behind you that
that should be occupiable right and
you're checking a whole
point one behind you for places to put
um
that that just makes no no sense at all
that that makes literally no sense at
all to me
so what are we doing wrong how are we
getting in a position
where the last frame we thought there
were plenty of places to put
both of the people uh and then on the
frame that comes
in we're like no there's nowhere to put
there's nowhere
nowhere nearby how is that possible
um
i guess because both entities are moving
and they're moving in a different way so
they each have different bounding box
sizes
i mean
but i mean this this literally requires
yeah i feel like do we just have some
kind of a bug
like with the way we're doing like
the intersection testing or something
like is this just wrong
you know or or like is there something
kind of like
because i don't i don't see it i'm not i
don't i don't understand
because the size of the voxel cell in
this case
is going to be like
or should be like quite small
you know
so i mean here's another thing let's
take this out of the equation
so you know what if we just said
look you don't you're we're not gonna um
fine uh
i don't really want that i want that
we're just gonna only do the first micro
move
right so now we know the loop so so just
in case i'm wrong
and we want to make sure the loop can't
be contributing
right i just want to know if the loop
can't be contributing yeah so we're only
taking
we're only doing the first step that
step
is only the size of one motion
displacement or lower
we are adding to it
one entire thing of that size
what am i missing guys like what am i
missing
because there's no way that should be
happening
like i cannot plausibly come up with an
argument for why that's happening
so something here
is odd i also don't know
like what is this about
yeah i was like what are those even
doing there
so like something's weird something's
very very
strange um
something is very very strange
and this code it's worth noting is
basically the same code
the only difference here is that you're
testing
you're testing what who's who is on the
grid and who is at their actual location
is different
depending on who's moving and so
you know i suppose that you know that
definitely matters
right um
yeah so i don't know i'm i'm about ready
to call it
i'm about ready to say like look i
obviously have no idea how this is
working i'm totally wrong about my
mental model
so it's time to like we have to have
debug capture
of this thing which is a big investment
right
so you don't do it unless you have to
but i think we're going to have to
um not because i think this collision
routine at the moment is very good
more just i don't feel like i'm going to
make good forward progress on it
if i don't understand why it's breaking
the way it's breaking
because it means there's something wrong
with my mental model
and while i don't want to spend you know
four hours or whatever writing something
to visualize it
i don't know that i'm gonna have a
choice right
um because without that i think we're
just dead in the water fundamentally
uh looking at what you know looking at
what we're looking at
so
i guess i'll ask you guys what do you
think
uh
do you think that we should
start the visualization process now
or do you think um
yeah what do you think oh by the way
suspect zero
um no the reason for the lag is because
uh it's it's hard to see because
it's it's difficult when you're just
looking when you're just popping into
some code like this
so do you see this code right here
um that says replace the visualization
this is actually looping
for every time we do a check on one of
those voxels
we're actually looping over uh
all two thousand entities three thousand
enemies
um so so uh
yeah yeah the the reason that you're
getting the lag
is there's no spatial partition for that
collision check
so uh i'm not worried about that right
now because the space partition part is
very easy by comparison
to the collision part and for another
reason
i kind of like the lag being in there
because having the lag in there helps me
see what this thing will do in a bad
scenario
right um if that makes sense
like it helps me go oh under
like let's suppose the game actually did
lag out
for whatever reason um
this is what's gonna happen with this
routine right so i kind of
like that normally i wouldn't like that
if i was testing like gameplay code and
how it felt and stuff i would
i would be like oh god we gotta fix this
but right now i'm like
the fact that this routine itself is
causing the lag is great
because it means i get to see what it
does under bad stress
which is exactly when collision routines
fail
and so i i will leave that in
until it's done basically and then i'm
gonna replace
this loop with a spatial partition and
we should have
no lag at all at that point um
but until then i kind of want it uh i
could add a thing to
artificially introduce lag uh but
it's if you have a natural unpredictable
bad source of lag like that already
there
why bother just use it right uh
if you don't have one though you can add
and it's a good idea to add a slider
in that you can like a debug slider that
you can
crank around um
and that's pretty cool because uh it
lets you test
your systems against lag uh which you
always should do because
you never know you know windows does
something
and your game was running at 60 frames a
second but
suddenly it's running at 10 frames a
second for five frames if you didn't
have some protection in there to make
sure that wasn't going to screw up
you're very sad right because anything
can happen
you know you know dude alt tabs to a
zoom meeting and then alt tabs back or
whatever and you get these like windows
hiccups or whatever
and then the game blows up right like so
you want to make sure that you've got
in your like defense against weird crap
like that
capping things making sure nothing
breaks just it's just a good thing
so i actually like having some lag in
this particular part of the code so we
can see what it does
um i want to check one quick thing which
is just i want to see how iterate
voxel does let's step through this code
once
we do have something that we can do by
the way so one of the problems
uh one of the things that's that's
that's rough right
uh is because lighting is so slow uh
when we switch to minus od
uh if you notice like when we run like
it's really hard to run because the
lighting
is so slow in debug mode it's like
difficult to do anything
right the lighting just eats up all the
frame time and you can't like here's the
debug build right it's
really annoying you know what i'm saying
um and so one of the problems is uh
visual studio
you can't turn on and off off the
optimizer
uh very easily with the pragma you have
to basically like
be in an optimized build and turn off
the optimizer or things like this
well it turns out apparently
that documentation was like wrong and
you actually
can or so claim someone who emailed me
they were like
i tried this
turning on optimizations in a debug
build
and it worked so you might want to try
it so we could try it
um let's take a look so if i go into the
lighting
thing and just do like a pound pragma
optimize uh and i'll have to look really
quickly
uh if you'll forgive me for a second at
what the actual switches
are they they sent me they were like
it's these
um
that they claimed worked so we can try
these and just
see um
okay so it looks like
the answer is you do
pragma optimize gt
on and it supposedly does
actually turn on optimizations even that
you didn't have on
in the flags and then you just say go
back to nothing on
and it will reset to whatever flags you
did have
right supposedly this works
i don't know if i believe it um but it's
a pretty easy thing to test
so we can test it right um
so let's take a look so i've done it uh
as they suggested and i can look and see
uh how the lighting fares uh
here doesn't look
uh particularly good
though um
let me nerf let me try some stuff
um with like the collision detector
off so if i go to
[Music]
so assuming that we don't do uh the
collision detector
so we know that it's not causing us a
problem
so we just do like hey when you try to
move an entity it doesn't move
like anybody stay where they are no code
gets run you know what i'm saying
um so i run it and what do we get
so it might be
it feels better
[Music]
than not having it um
i'm just not sure like it still seems
like the lighting is not
particularly optimized i'm wondering if
that is like uh well so there's some
other things like the light atlas
i i don't know how this pragma would
work
exactly right the other problem is like
the math code
if that's not if that doesn't have the
pragma
around it
i don't know if this really is useful
unfortunately
um like i don't
know like if you need to go in here and
and start you know
start putting optimize on that stuff
but it doesn't seem good in the light
atlas code
i don't know i could slap them in here
as well
just to see
you know if it's if it's that
uh
but but like i said i don't know
it it's better it's just not
like better enough
you know
like like it's not bad um
but but it's not good uh
so i don't really know i don't think
that's a long-term solution so i i don't
think i'm gonna bother with it
um you know maybe if we slapped it
in in enough locations you know it would
help
um but
it it just doesn't seem like it's like
if we want to solve this problem
we're probably gonna have to solve it a
different way right um
so we'll see uh anyway
uh let's keep going so
if we
uh want to take a look at this code i
just wanted to
to look at like the voxel iterator and
stuff and just make sure that stuff was
working
relatively cleanly before i do anything
fancier so here we are in the
debug build yes if the debug builds i'm
just gonna see
uh what happens in move entity
when you step into the code for
the vox stuff i'm just gonna take a
quick
like look and see um
just just to make sure the code is like
sane right
uh and and from there we'll you know
we'll go
uh further so okay uh so assuming i step
in here
uh i'm just gonna take a look and see
you know what the
uh voxel bounds
are in this case and uh
you know they look they look fine
right i mean they look like what we
would have said that you should see um
which seems fine i'm gonna look at the
voxel iterator
so here's the iterator um it's going
four four four it's starting at zero
zero zero right
uh and you know here's us going through
and and
you know what i could do to is is before
we actually get to involved in this
maybe let's change this code
uh maybe i want to pull that out
so there's like a test point that we're
going to test
the test point is here
you know um and that way i can look and
see
what we end up with for these and
you know uh that seems
easier to debug inspect right
okay um so let's try that again
i probably want the break point to be
like here here's the voxel iterator
here's the test position
uh and if we go through
and just step
i mean it looks like what we would think
right
i mean that's that's what we would
expect it to do
you know um
so that seems fine um so taking a look
here
if we take a look at like occupied count
um
so so the vox dim is is like four
right so if we look at how many things
are occupied
you know we should get in the any open
case like any open here should be one
it is um
and so like when we get down to here we
should not be doing that
and we don't um so that's good
[Music]
uh
there we go
so i mean everything seems
fine in this
code path right i mean everything looks
like what i would expect
um let's set a break point here
just for fun um
and like
i don't know i don't even know like
where's the dude
um who's
yeah the like the skull dude
um i don't even know
oh he's coming
you can see the motion caused by the
only being allowed to be
placed in the full thing yeah so anyway
if i try to force the um the thing to
tunnel through
can i switch back to the main view now
yeah if i try to force the glove
uh to get into one of those positions
can i do it
i mean we know i was able to do this
before right like i was
i was able to tunnel the thing through
right
and i i'm not able to make it happen
right now
i need to have a better repro case here
there it goes so okay
that tunneled through but it never hit
that case
right so actually
it's not because of that that it was
able to tunnel
like i've got the break point there and
like unless that
you know break points busted um
that was not the problem because it got
it got embedded into the thing
so this keeps getting weirder right
so that's really weird
yeah so that's able to go and do
interpenetration without that case so
what do you think is happening there
that's particularly weird
so it's not allowing motion if it can't
find
place that's an entirely open cell
so this is as weird as i thought it was
right
this is every bit as weird as i thought
it was so i have some questions
i have a question so
yeah it might have pushed the skeleton
up over the glove i guess that's true
um let's take a look
is that what's happening
that's kind of weird
so is this something that's only
happening because we have like
is this something that only happens yeah
when we have large time steps or
something
i mean uh small time steps
like maybe it is
actually passing underneath it is
actually passing underneath
okay all right
all right so i guess those skull things
why do they float
upwards like that anyway
and then they float downward i don't
know why they do that
but i guess that's a problem
and i have no idea why they're doing
that i guess they go
up and down they like come to rest on a
square or something
so this whole time was i actually
thinking it tunneled and it
didn't actually tunnel
hmm
all right well that's confusing
but not necessarily bad
i don't know what to make of that
so you can see the glove currently right
is trapped underneath the dude
yeah all right well so i don't know
where to what to make of that that was
interesting so maybe i should revisit
this slightly with that in mind
because maybe it's not as weird as i
thought it was and we just need to kind
of fix
so that and we can start to look at this
in a different way i'm going to
switch back to this for a moment um
because i'm not totally sure look i
don't actually know
in this case why
nobody can move
um you should be able to move
the glove should be able to move right
now and so the fact that it can't
is weird to me right it should be able
to move
in this direction and it doesn't seem to
be able to do so
and that's that seems bad
um
i guess uh
and that's not entirely what is that's
not entirely
unexpected um
because in this case if you're looking
you're going to look at a particular
corner of the voxel what you need to
kind of do is start clipping away
pieces of it so you need to say like in
the direction
of this thing are there any that i could
move towards
uh and that forms the basis that i could
move along
right so one way to look at it
is to say let's form a basis we have the
directional offset here
right and we know a couple different
things
so we know for example
um
this is going to be kind of weird but
bear with me
so what we would know here
is something that looks like this
um
in the voxel
the direction of motion which we have
here tells us
which of the points on the voxel we
would look to
to find out if we can move in that
direction
but we are fundamentally looking at
for four points right
no matter which direction we're like
aiming
there's at least i mean i guess at least
two
but more like yeah you can imagine like
a plane
and that plane is gonna clip away
at least two but possibly four
of the points of motion
so i think what we want to do is say
from our current position if you were to
look
at the position plus the movement
direction
which of these points would be in play
and
and or you know another way to look at
it be like which directions
are allowed for motion based on
uh the points of this voxel
right
i mean let's take a simple version of it
to start
so
if the uh
voxel iterator
in the z direction
so looking in the z direction
we could say like
if all the things in the z direction
well or maybe we just say if any in the
z direction
i'm i'm really i'm kind of torn as to
what
really all i'm trying to say here is the
corners of the voxel
tell us what the permissible gliding
directions
are if they're all open
or all the ones vaguely in the direction
we're trying to go or open then we can
just go
but if only some are open what we want
to do is
clip the movement vector so that you
only move in the direction
uh that those would allow right
so like when you look at this case the
problem is the glove is probably trying
to move
upward as well as out and it can't
because it can't actually go anywhere in
that direction
but if it were to have just said well
it's still i can still move
sideways which is partly that way um
that's okay right so
i'm trying to figure out what the right
way to look at the voxel pieces are
effectively i have
effectively i have like a bunch of
diagonal vectors right they're pointing
towards the corners of the cube
so now i'm starting to ask myself should
the voxel
actually be centered so that the points
so that we're actually looking at motion
[Music]
from the location we're at
this is a real brain bender
anything else
so maybe what we want to do here
is just clip the box
i love where i am
maybe what we want to do is just clip
the box
so if we said look here's
the problem with this is it might just
not be the right offsets
right you would still like so suppose
all of these are trying to go up
you know partially so the z is going to
be one up and all of those are
interpenetrating
well what we want to do is we still want
to move along the one we can so we still
want the x and y to work and we just
want to use z
zero right
um so i'm just trying to think
if we instead of doing it this way if we
basically
went through each corner of the voxel
and or or maybe as we step through the
points of the voxel we think of it more
like
this is a cube maybe the cube is around
the point
like they're just regions in space when
we say
you could have gone up to here it seems
like you want to know more about the
shape of the thing passing through it
though
right so that doesn't really seem likely
to me
so i guess what i might say is
is like within some tolerance you would
accept either point
right so
[Music]
so this is really kind of weird but
let's just
hear me out so we know that we
are moving towards a particular side of
the voxel
and the
tolerance of how we're moving would
depend on whether we would
well i guess we could just clip the
motion out in the direction that wasn't
implied so so for example
if we took you know this
one here
where we said like okay you know you've
got uh
this is the complete directional offset
um if it turns out that that
one's blocked then you try
the one without that
you try it without each of the
components so you try it without x
without
y without z um and you
clip out that movement basis
i mean i don't know man
we really should be doing this on the
light board
um all right so if we wanted to actually
see what happens here right um
so if we were literally just playing
around and we said
okay here's each of the different
uh movement patterns so this will check
uh you know all eight right two times
two times two
we would check each of the directions x
y and z
um and we could just say like that it
looks like this
right
and so for each of those we know that a
vector going in this direction from you
know wherever we're
talking about um motion in this
direction through this particular cell
uh is going to hit whatever
you know it's going to hit whatever the
occupied category is
on this thing and i don't know if we
want to consider where
the actual point would be i don't think
we do so i think we just want to kind of
carve off
uh places that would be
you know th that we kind of want to just
shrink
the box away from these things
so the problem is like we were using you
know
get closest point in box but get closest
point in box
we we don't really have a good way of
like clipping that point back
out right um
so when we
so when we go through each of these i
guess it's just like
yeah if i'm trying to think of how this
is any different from just like looking
at a box around
the thing i guess you would go i'm just
trying to get the diagonals in there
right and maybe that's pointless maybe
you just subdivide and that's stupid
yeah i don't know since we're almost out
of time
i'm just gonna say i need to sleep on
this uh i'm gonna do something slightly
different
which is just say look
um if you could stand in this cell
area then maybe we just say
that you can go anywhere
in the interior of the thing so like
if you can stand on this particular
point
then we'll let you go
no that's still not gonna work
i don't have a good idea for how to to
how to make this be
more forgiving there right
um
all right let's try it let's try one
more thing
so let's suppose that we did
something like this
so
let's suppose we want to test the
direction of motion
uh of this thing so we say all right
there's the four bases
like and i'm just going to write them
out especially we can turn them into for
loop after
so we've got the dur offset um and and
maybe i just want to call this der
so it's easier so let's say we say
in the direction of z we know there are
four
of these right um
looks like this
so in the z direction we have four
things
and maybe we just say look if there's
nowhere in the z
direction that's actually possible to go
then you can't go in the z direction
right
so if if each of these
then the displacement of the point
uh you're not allowed to go in the z
direction in this cell right
so when we're looking at the cells we
say you know
from the location of the player to this
location
um if if there isn't
uh if all of the z's are occupied in the
direction you're trying to go
then you're not allowed to go in z uh
to get there right
i mean it's pretty straight forward
thing right
so we would say like you know
test p z equals from p
z right it's this is super crappy
i'm just trying to give you an idea of
what i was thinking
and then you just do that for each of
your directions so you just
go like look if we could have gone in
that direction
um we allow it if we couldn't we don't
and that's it like it doesn't really do
anything else
you know what i'm saying
and the problem with this is we're that
is great if you're on if you're the cell
containing the actual
uh starting point if you're not it
doesn't really make any sense what i'm
doing here so this probably won't work
but i want to leave it in there as the
next thing to investigate
next time um
so yeah basically this
right so xyz is all good there
uh this one just needs to be updated for
x so the
juror comes in
here like so
um and
this would oscillate right
so i think it's just that like it
basically you look at the plane
of motion and if anybody uh
could go you let it go in that direction
if not
then you don't let it go in that
direction and you're not going to update
the motion of the player
to there um
and then you would just say look
if any of them
so if any of these
are available uh
then you go right so then we get rid of
you know we get rid of this
uh and we we essentially say something
like
you know
how many times we clip and then here we
just say oh well if the clip count is
less than three then you get to move
right uh and the other thing is
i suppose in this case what we probably
want is not
that you go that you pick the original
points
one uh
so probably what you do is more
like this
you say um
we're gonna make an attempt to place the
point right it's going to be the 2p
but uh it's gonna
we're not gonna attempt to place you
further along in the direction of travel
um if we're if we can't in this cell
right
and i don't know uh i'm really reaching
here
but i like to try weird stuff that's
that's what i do um
so you know
that's just what's gonna happen um
and nicely we still have this case live
here so when i change this
we'll see what happens probably a
disaster
um so yeah and
the direction thing here would be
like this is just the direction of like
of motion i guess
um so hey it slid out just like i
thought it would
but that may have just been because yeah
like it's just not working now
right so not great
right um but yeah so all right
so then the next question is just like
if we were to do this
per cell starting from the cell
that we're on um you know i might make a
note to myself here like
and we can test and we'll try that next
time right
oh uh we got a someone said we had a
typo here oh yeah thank you
there you go uh i don't think that will
improve matters substantively
uh probably but you know we want that
fixed
um so yeah
it's kind of weird too it looks like
it's not able to place
things like
it looks a little weird
as well like it's moving slowly oh
that's because of this nonsense though
yeah so maybe next time we start with
the voxel and we do path finding through
the voxel
and that's just what we do and we see
what happens
with this kind of a scheme
um
and yeah like we we're getting closer
though it's kind of cool that that
i don't know if you noticed it actually
pushed that guy that guy
glided along the wall you could see the
red trail
and actually went in through the door on
that really long move
so you know we're getting there um we're
far far from our goal but
we're getting you know we're making
progress um
so we'll see all right that's it
that's it for today
all right um if there's any on topic
questions i'll take them otherwise we
will wrap it up for today
and i think i know what i want to try
next time
um i think i want to try starting at the
place you're at
with the voxel cells and moving through
the voxel
as far as you can until you hit stopping
right um
and we'll see so if you have any
on topic questions i will take
them
can you explain the direction check a
bit more uh yeah i mean i can't explain
it
in a i can explain it but i can't
justify it because that's kind of just
me experimenting with some things
um so
what i kind of wanted to move towards
was saying all right we're inside
a particular cell we've tested the
corners of this cell so there's eight
corners we've tested we know whether the
the entity could position itself on
each of the eight corners so
all i want to really do here
is say if we check
the for
a particular exit direction so if i want
to leave
out of the positive z for example let's
say
this here was positive z if we wanted to
go in the positive z direction are any
of the
points in the positive z direction open
if they are then allow motion in that
direction
if they're not disallow it
right
so
i've not forgotten upload day632 i'm
just getting really tired of youtube's
garbage
um it's they keep making it harder and
harder to upload videos to youtube
and i keep not wanting to bother
um so
it's just me purely being very annoyed
but i will get to it
so it can't move backwards um well again
it's not really so it can't move
backwards
it's so it can't move in a direction
that's blocked
uh and and it's not really that
important to understand this
anyway because i'm just experimenting
with this and i was like oh well i have
a little bit of time here at the end so
let me just try it but it's not
like this is not good right so it's not
really important to understand what's
going on here because we're literally
just like trying some stuff
so it's interesting to understand what
we're trying but it's not like i've
really like i'm this is not anything
that anyone will care about
including us um right
uh no i'm not trying to prevent the
glove from moving under the skull i'm
just trying to improve the quality of
the collision detector
that's all
um when you're trapped you don't
necessarily have a vector
in right um so take for example the
starting code
where the glove was embedded in the
ground right there's no vector in it
just started out embedded
right so what i'd like to do is if you
have something like that where the game
code for whatever reason
accidentally places something inside
something else
you know ideally you want your collision
detector to just deal with it
right you don't want that to break the
whole game
it's easy to have that happen by mistake
you know imagine something's gonna spawn
an entity at some point
it's like gonna create an entity because
you did something that says that an
entity gets created here like a new
glove magically appears or who knows
what
and it accidentally is inside something
you don't want that to like break the
whole game
right so ideally you want when things
are interpenetrating
they can find their way out without
needing to know
how they got there because they may just
have appeared there
and it's hard i mean don't get me wrong
um
we're trying to do something that's
that's
on the high end of the quality
bar for sure right um
but it is what you want
right so it may be on the high end of
the quality bar but it's not
for no reason
with the live code reloading i made a
thing where global variables in the dll
can be saved and restored when you load
the dll
have you tried that before i thought
it's kind of neat um
i guess i'm not sure what you mean
do you mean like our thing we had a lot
of stuff that we did that was along
those lines but i'm not sure which kind
you mean
um
like we had one where we would just when
you changed
um when you changed
settings it would rewrite a c file that
had the settings in it so the next time
you built it would have them
we have one obviously that just like you
can change the goal of arrows and just
it would automatically recompile them we
did that at one point
like you'd click and it would recompile
the actual
constant define so that if that led to
an optimization it would happen
in the thing we had a bunch of things i
don't know if it's the one
like one like you're thinking probably
not but we have played around with a
bunch of stuff like that
all right that's the end of the on top
of questions as far as i can tell so i'm
gonna wrap it on
up uh thanks everyone for joining me for
the
set of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow the series at
home you can always pre-order the game
on handmadehero.org and it comes with
source code
so if you want to try your hand at
writing a nice
robust collision detector uh you can go
ahead and beat me to it i only program
for one or two hours every week on this
stream
on this game so you should be able to
totally totally beat me to it right
you've got all week
give it a shot uh if you do let me know
if you find something cool
i'll be back here next weekend to try to
move it forward a little bit more
until then have fun programming everyone
and i'll see you on the internet take it
everybody
you