hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show recode complete game live on
stream uh we did last weekend some
diagram collection code which basically
uh was designed to allow us to output
diagrams for debugging purposes it's not
ever meant to be something that
happens in the release version of the
game it's just for debugging purposes
and so we put uh some some collection
code that allows pieces of our
code that we want to
see visually like c augmented
information for
to dump those diagrams to a buffer
and what we need to do today is take
that buffer and display it on the screen
which you know it's not super hard but
remember we sort of have a very limited
rendering engine
uh in handmade here it's just only does
a very uh small amount of things it can
basically do
you know just the stuff that we expected
to have in the game and so we may have
to do more work you know it may be a
more complicated job than it would be if
you had
built a very complicated renderer that
did lots of things
uh so in order to do this we'll have to
see uh
you know specifically where we're at
oops that's the wrong directory all
right
i don't actually remember where we're
supposed to load this uh that looks like
the right place
okay uh so if we go in and take a look
you know the code's compiling and stuff
but it's not actually doing the drawing
right so in theory if handmade diagrams
is turned on which right now we have
forced it to be normally you know we
might turn it off or we might do
something like oh you know it's it's
only on if we set handmade internal
right to b1
something like that
uh
i mean i guess another way you could do
it is like if
uh not defined
you know
handmade
diagrams uh then handmade diagrams is
handmade internal so basically on
internal builds they're on by default
you know that kind of thing
so
assuming it's not turned off
what we do now is we create this there's
this thing called diagram group right
and what it does is it just like takes
and it fills up a buffer filled with uh
diagram
instructions
these are what the instructions look
like it's called diagram entry
uh and what we need to do now if we want
to see these on the screen is make some
way of actually drawing them
and we added a thing that was basically
like a filter because the code that you
know we actually are going to want to
diagram can sometimes get run you know
you know tens of thousands hundreds of
thousands depending on what we're trying
to diagram it may be code that runs way
too often per frame
and not only would we have a storage
issue if we did enough of them
but we would also face this problem of
the screen would just be like filled
with crap
that we don't want
so in addition to just being able to
record diagrams we also added the
ability to filter
what you are seeing
so that only diagrams that you actually
want will be drawn
and so what i thought we would do there
is it turned out uh let me launch remedy
here
let me also spell remedy correctly
uh so if we go ahead and run
handmade hero as it stands
uh what you can see is there's like
these you know there's these things i
can access with the f keys i'm hitting
the f keys right now
that are like little debug overlays
these are very common in games you see
them in basically every game there's you
know stuff like this
and if we look we had on f9 like i don't
remember exactly when we made this uh
but we made a thing that was like a time
step modifier in here and so what you
can see is like i can turn
the time step way down on the game for
looking like at things like the um
you can see like i can even turn it to
something where it doesn't get any times
at all but this way we can see like very
slow stuff right we did that um as
something
that we uh implemented a long time ago
so we can see you know stuff happening
in the collision detector you can see it
happening here uh
write stuff with the glove and all that
um and so
if we
just assume like okay we've got this
little uh
we've got this
little i don't know what you call this
uh panel
we have this little panel
uh what we could do is just say instead
of collision recorder which doesn't
really make any sense because we didn't
actually implement a collision recorder
we just kind of said maybe we should
uh instead what we could do is just make
this like the diagram panel so f9 which
is what this was
is like the diagram panel and it can
step through any diagrams right so we
don't need it to step through just uh
collision because we can make it so it
can step through any diagram and that
way we can go through here and do
something where we basically like record
or something what's happening on a frame
uh and then you know
i don't know how we'll capture it
exactly uh maybe we could use the loop
live code editing which i think still
exists i don't know if it does or not
let me see
yeah
so we still have looped live codeing and
all that stuff so we can do stuff like
this where we then um
uh
well yeah the problem is that just
re-records all of memory so
uh yeah i mean we could try to opt out
our diagram system from it but that
sounds complicated so i don't know maybe
loop live code i think won't help us
here
because it's really it's for
specifically that which is you know
editing code while you loop something in
the game
um so i don't know if that would really
help us i honestly can't quite see how
it would
um but you know at some point we need to
figure out a way
where we would figure out what diagram
to use now we have picking
right because you know if you remember
um
like this system
where we would uh pick stuff on the
screen right we can uh pick various
pieces of i don't know stuff like you
can see me picking it here
uh
right like sprites and stuff
when we have access to that we should be
able to do things like pick the hero and
have it know which sprite that was
and record diagrams for that
you know what i'm saying
um
so we should be able to do a thing where
we just go like okay
use that same picking system
uh pick a particular you know something
here
and have it show the diagrams like
filter the diagrams just to that
entity
or whatever we picked right
so i feel like what we could do
hopefully is is do that pick and i don't
know does the pic include the glove i'm
not sure if it does or doesn't but i
think it does so you know if we
are if we the glove's an easy thing to
test collision on because it just kind
of floats around and we can control
where it goes so if i pick the glove
right like that
uh i'm assuming that since it showed up
there it means that both those entities
are understood right by the system
um i like that
bug with the lighting we've gone green
apparently
nobody knows why we just have
one of these days we gotta
finish the lighting move it to the gpu
or whatever we're gonna do with it
um
yeah
uh but anyway so you know first steps
first i'm just going to go in here and
try to make this thing work so that i
can pick somebody to diagram and then
see the diagrams and there's a pretty
easy way to do that right now you can
see we just have it hard coded
that we see all these collision boxes
right uh like around the glove you can
see him going i don't know why this guy
doesn't have any he might actually have
them yeah so they're just behind him
right you can see him there
so everybody's drawing those collision
boxes that's just like everything that
is moving
uh is having those collision boxes uh
drawn oh sorry not everything's moving
everything that's floating like these
don't need them because they're just
using the occupancy like square
occupancy so they're not collision
detecting
uh on a free motion
but anything like these guys who are
free moving um or the hero who is i'm
sorry or the hero's glove that's free
moving
all of those things are going through
the collision detector uh and so they
have those little boxes drawn so what i
would suggest we do today to try and get
started on this problem of having a good
way to draw these uh things i love what
i love the frame rate independence of
that uh or dependence of that right
why you don't use proportional
derivative controllers
uh in production code that are uncapped
right if you want to fix that quickly
you can just cap its velocity but
in general you can try to make things
that are more frame rate independent but
it's pretty great because it'll just do
that forever basically
until the frame rate gets high enough
right so anytime the frame rate is low
uh you're going to get that right
anyway
um so what we want to do is just figure
out a way to make these like just those
diagrams uh pop up through the diagram
system
and you know we'll assume that this
panel here allows to pick
you know what i'm saying that that's it
so we want something very simple like
that
and so the first thing i'm going to do
is i'm going to try to move
those diagrams
into the diagram system
exclusively
right
that's the first thing we're going to do
so if we go to
uh wherever that was
like so
we can see
in here
that we set the filter to this entity
uh so that will work for us
uh and then i guess
uh
you know i don't really remember where
we were drawing this i guess
so
here's one of them
it looks like we do it
in
[Music]
four places right
uh so once inside the refinement
uh
once inside the best update so once per
iteration there
and then twice inside
uh
you know
the the move entity call on startup
basically
that i think just shows us like where
you're
uh
starting
and going kind of a thing
okay so if we take a look at what goes
on here you can see that there's like
some diagram stuff happening
in terms of control logic
you can see it here as well
and so
i don't know exactly how we want to do
this but we probably want something
like this maybe where we do
a move entity
uh you know at the top of this
um we do a diagram begin and then like
somewhere over here we do a diagram and
so that these are all enclosed
and then you know there's basically sub
diagrams so here's the refinement step
um here's whatever the collision voxel
step
right these are just various
things that we add
uh
and now what we would do is just change
those those push volume calls because
they're all now enclosed
into basically a diagram box
right
so they're going to look like that
we wouldn't need this anymore which is
great because we didn't really want that
there that we just did that so that we
could have some drawing
um and you can see us passing the box
there now we wanted to set these up with
colors
so
uh we want to do like
that
right
um
and we could make
a version of this that in fact we
probably should
as well
that just takes three parameters
you know what i'm saying
uh so there's one that would be like
because it's just a little bit easier to
type and this is just supposed to be a
simple system to use right
so if we went ahead and
just changed these into that
format
oops
i guess it was just that
if we went ahead and changed it into
that format
um
i
think that's everything
yeah
so we're just drawing two boxes there
and off we would go
when we come into this part of the
system
um there really isn't anything that's in
this function
so all the drawing that was done in this
part is done inside one of the functions
that that part calls
uh and the same is true for the bottom
here like nothing
yeah so that's really the only thing
that this was drawing
so
again this simplifies our code a bunch
which is what we kind of wanted to like
if you look here this kind of had to
keep passing
this render group around for no reason
uh which you know is just makes the code
uglier um and harder to read
so it's nice to get rid of that because
this way we have this sort of sideband
that compiles out that does everything
for you
which is the goal of debug code like you
don't want people to architect around
the debug code you want just kind of
happen automatically
off to the side
um so same thing here we can do
a oops sorry not debug diagram box so
diagram box
and you can see here that the diagram
color is set
based on this like colliding
thing um
which we can do
exactly the same way
that we were doing it
and so that takes care of that one now
will go to the diagram system instead of
to the render group which is what we
wanted
and then finally
uh there was
one other one over here somewhere wasn't
there um
there it is i'm like i know we had
another one because we looked at it
so if we take
and we
turn this one into a diagram box as well
uh then that should be the end of it
right
and now you can see here too why i kind
of want to do the system this way so you
can see that this code is keeping track
of a cell color
which is again just more architecting
around debug
which we don't want
so that's kind of why i did the system
this way
because it means instead of doing that
we can now do
this
you know
so basically we can just like push uh
the colors on there and they will be
remembered and so that way we can get
rid of that variable which again is us
architecting it's inserting code for the
diagram thing rather than just calls to
the diagram system
uh that you know so you don't have these
extra variables lying around that are
confusing about what they might be doing
like are they required for the actual
operation or are they just there to draw
the diagram now you can see that we've
eliminated just a diagram specific calls
which is more what i wanted
so if we compile this in theory uh we
should be fine
just get rid of some typos here but it
should produce a system
that puts all this stuff uh into the
correct place
for drawing later
um
just get rid of all of them
stuff that was passing that
move entity down
and i think
that's all good we do have a sort of
call
here that we added for convenience
if we want to
do this the simplest possible way
we just make this effectively you know
for all intents and purposes of macro
that really just calls this existing
color thing with the bundle of the color
so it's it's really just typing it
doesn't do anything different it's just
changing the syntax
that is allowed to be used on the
outside of the code
so now if we run this
and remove that break point
uh we should have a situation where we
no longer see any of those like debug
diagrams you can see that they're not
here anymore the glove used to like you
know show
these little squares moving around
behind it right
and it doesn't anymore so
that's exactly what we would expect it
to have happen in this particular
circumstance um and so you know yeah
exactly what we would expect is exactly
what happened so everything's good
and so now we need to do is
loft those out of there so have a way of
getting those diagrams onto the screen
and the first thing i guess we'll do is
we can um
ignore the panel part
for now because that's like the picking
thing and you know we haven't looked at
that code in a while so we're going to
page that in
ignore that part and we'll just cold set
it so what we'll do is we'll just like
go into
the
part of the code
where we start up the world or whatever
um and we'll just like set it to the
hero or set it to the glove of the hero
or something
um
right in the code so you know
we've got
a uh
an ad player call
it's gonna know which one is the hero
because in here you can see it uh doing
this ad entity
so what i can do is just force it
in the middle of
doing all of the you know initialization
for a player joining the game
i can force it to set the filter
to the glove's actual id value
right
so that will mean that now
the glove is in theory
having all of its stuff recorded because
the filter that we check which happens
in here
uh the filter that we check
will uh be for the glove which will
re-enable its diagram collection
now if i run the code again
again purely in theory
nothing will actually happen because
we're still not drawing these
what you can see however is this is this
is unfortunate and i guess i don't know
um
this has caused us a lot of problems and
i don't know what we want to do about it
so because this system pushes on a lot
of small allocations what you can see
here is we've again had this problem of
the debug bug system that just records
allocations so that we can draw them
is not really capable of handling this
very well you can see it totally
screwing up here again right
uh and so i don't know what to do about
that exactly i mean one way to do it is
you can skip it with a flag i suppose uh
but the other question here is like is
that just evidence that we've got uh an
issue happening here because you would
think that it would clear this out
frequently enough
that you wouldn't have this problem
right um
just splashed myself in the face
uh
so we're calling that diagram filter
call
right
[Music]
in here
aren't we
yeah
so we're calling that diagram filter
call
and so in theory you know the first time
through move entity that you encounter
the glove it should record all the
things and the next time through it
should filter right that's what should
happen
and
you know i assume when we diagram end
uh
i guess i don't know like when this
should get turned off
because
that's hard to say
but
it should only really have recorded the
stuff that happens inside here
which shouldn't be that many things i
mean it's a lot of things but it's not
that many it's like 10 000 or something
because remember that we're not doing
any spatial partition so it's really
it's literally going to record
all of that stuff
so i guess one way that i can
uh test this
is to just if zero this part out so
we're only drawing the things we're
drawing before and we're not going to
draw all of this
and just see what happens
um because we know it couldn't have been
that many because it was you know
feeding it to the rendering system just
fine
so without all that stuff happening
inside the
shape collide which is the n squared
part so you know it should work
um okay
so yeah it looks like that's okay i
guess um
at least for the moment so we'll we'll
address that a little bit later anyway
so nothing happens which is what we
would expect because we're not actually
drawing them but we because we hit that
uh assertion in the debug system
we now know
that this is at least working right it
did turn on and is collecting things
because the debug system wouldn't have
had an overflow condition if we weren't
dumping a ton of diagrams to it so we
know that it did turn on which it you
know is what we
wanted it to do right
um and so
i guess from hmm so i'm trying to think
now
uh oh sorry i want to reconnect
something down here that just got
unplugged
uh anyway
so what we would like to do is now start
drawing those those diagrams to restore
the same one that we had before and you
know the re render diagrams call
i don't know where we put it exactly i
don't remember
um but i imagine we would put it at the
bottom of this uh call right somewhere
you can see we put in diagram reset
i don't know that we ever actually put
in render though
um so that's a bit weird
it doesn't look like we did
so i'm assuming that if i did this
we would never actually hit it because i
don't think we ever put in the call it
looks like it doesn't look like we did
right
so
we put in the reset but we never put in
the render so i'm going to go ahead and
put in the render now
so in here
we would have the render
the render commands part is what we
would probably be passing actually not a
render group
although the diagrams want to be in that
render group so so actually i guess
that's not true
we would want to put this in some place
that had the same render group as
like the game so that the 3d transform
will be the same because the diagrams
are drawn in that transform you know
what i'm saying
so we would want to go probably to world
mode
where
you know this stuff is is all getting
drawn and you know
put it somewhere in here like you know
where we're gonna do
stuff
like whatever we're gonna do
so
yeah um
maybe there
right before we do it uh
the
the end of the right before we end
we would render the diagrams there
and so in here what we then need to do
is just write something that goes
through all of the diagrams that exist
and
show them so here's the diagram group
and in it
uh we have a first and a last so we can
in theory just do a diagram entry entry
equals group first
and off we go
so for each one of these they are typed
it's a discriminated union
and you can see in here we have uh all
of these functions
and so we we need to do a switch
on what type of thing we have
and each one of these
is going to be
its own case
and we're kind of assuming that this
code will not be particularly fast right
we're just assuming this is just going
to draw debug diagrams and we're going
to assume that we use filtering to
ensure that we never do too much right
so this is not supposed to be like a
hardcore system it's not supposed to be
particularly performance oriented it's
just supposed to be like flexible and
easy for you to dump diagrams to in a
way that you can see
right so we'll lean on the filtering
part quite a bit we'll try to make it so
that filtering um is the thing that
really
makes this work uh if that makes sense
and we can you know we can try to kind
of go from there
we can add more stuff to the filtering
part uh as we go
so in here where we have diagram begin
and end at the moment we don't really
need to do much for that but we will
because we're going to want to like
reset
colors and things like that uh
as we go in to like begins and ends
so we're probably going to want to keep
like a stack
and we're probably going to want to have
some opinion about how that works
for the moment i'm not really going to
worry about that stuff i'm just gonna
have a color
and a thickness
and i'm gonna assume that these are you
know some sensible values when you start
and
as you go through
every time you set something it's just
going to do exactly what you would
expect
so
for example in here
we would have the diagram attributes
right so this would be a trib dot color
we would just pull that out into the
sticky variable that we've got
right
um
and in here the same thing like we've
got the thickness and so on
yeah
and
in fact i guess so what we would kind of
want to do here is actually have these
default values be something that's set
right so so these are probably actually
going to look like this
right
so
we would do something like
this
right
yeah
so we would set up a sticky uh version
and then we set up a current version in
here we would set the current ones
like so
uh and the text would probably be also
part of that so
there would be like
that's never gonna be sticky so i guess
that's just a buffer
um
where we say you know what the current
text was or something
and it would start with nothing
all right uh so in here we would say all
right the text equals the text that
we're going to print
and then in stick we would just say well
whatever the current
is that becomes the new sticky one and
then here is our actual drawings our
various drawings
uh for the moment we can just do one
because we know we're only really
drawing the box right now
uh and so we'll just do the simplest
possible thing which is we'll draw the
box uh and we'll do that using the
parameters that we've got
i'm
i don't know
okay
uh so in here we would just pass the
render group which we need to get passed
in right so that's something that's just
like telling us uh
where we dump all of our actual
graphics to
so we're gonna push the volume outline
out and we're gonna push it out through
this rectangle here right
and uh
you know one interesting thing about
this
is it may be that we don't even really
have to buffer these
i wonder if it ends up such that if we
filter them properly it we can just have
this be immediate and you never needed
to buffer
yeah like it hmm
because if you think about it it's like
the reason i was buffering is i was like
well you know you want to be able to
like step through these things
i think i still want them recorded and
here's why
because i don't yet have a solution to
how i'm going to do the like okay how do
you capture one of these
we may need to implement something like
a buffer lock
so you know
when something collides
we capture that diagram and we lock that
diagram in and we don't record any new
diagrams right
because we're going to need some way of
capturing
things that happen
only like one time
on this particular frame
or whatever and then we want to look at
those right
and so just thinking it through i'm like
we may just need to say
look we're not gonna
we can't do this immediate mode
because we need to be able to store the
buffer
um i should say pure immediate mode the
interface is immediate mode regardless
right
but we're we're gonna store it and save
it
uh we can't just do it pure
because
uh we may need to just like remember
this for many frames
and draw it you know
several times
right
oh i'm tired
so i do think it's probably not a waste
of time to buffer them i was thinking
like you know is it is it not
uh
but i think it might not be
right i think it might not be
so i think we do you know i i can't say
for sure but i think we do
want the buffer there because the buffer
is kind of important
uh for other reasons
okay
um
what
oh okay
all right um so i think that's fine
since all of the renderer stuff is
actually going to take
a
uh v4 i do wonder if we want this to be
a v4
but we'll see
uh anyway
um so now we can go ahead and run this
and see if any of this stuff works uh
i'm not seeing
any of those boxes at the moment
so i don't think it did right
uh but i don't know so we're gonna have
to like step through that code uh and
see what's going on here
i assume there's nothing stupid going on
like like you know we're obviously doing
append here
uh and the box min and max does go into
zero and one
so you know it's what we would expect
here
um
so that all seems
like what you would expect
uh yeah
and at the end of every single one of
these drawing things we probably want to
do this as well um
so it resets each time
uh but i think that's basically it
right uh and and then we need some stuff
in here and you know put in the text and
points and lines and spheres and all
that stuff right so we're gonna have to
add more stuff but
seems about
about right
so let's find out why we're not seeing
those or you know what's going on there
so i'm going to go ahead and change this
to a debug build and i'm just going to
step through the diagramming
part of the code
to see what it's doing
and see if i can see what's the problem
you know what i mean
so
looks like we don't
have uh
that file open so i'll just
set a breakpoint at render diagrams
and let it take me there
so here we are uh stepping through
uh it looks like the problem here is we
didn't hit any of this
i guess
there we go so we've started recording
some now
uh and if i take a look
at this entry
we can see you know what the heck
uh we get in there
so here's an example of a box being
drawn
um
i mean
it looks fine
uh
that's not a thing
i mean that that seems fine to me
uh we've got
current color is like
pure green
seems fine thickness is 0.1 seems fine
so here's us
actually drawing
and again i mean
i don't see anything weird about those
numbers they they seem pretty good
that seems pretty good too
so i can't say off hand pun intended
uh
that
i know why that wouldn't draw
oh and it is drawing
so is it possible that we have handmade
internal turned off in release mode and
that was the only bug
was the build
no it's turned on
right i mean handmade internal the flags
are the same
even slow is turned on
right
so it's a bit weird
um
i
don't have an explanation of that did i
like not compile the code
so it seems to be working just fine now
the only thing that's a little odd is
the thickness looks wrong
so i'm guessing we actually were using o
point
like
a 0.01
for the thickness
on those so why didn't that work what
did i do wrong there i'm not sure what i
did
why that didn't work that was weird
um
but there's the diagram system in action
right so
all good
um
right seems seems fine
nothing uh nothing too
too unexpected there
and so now really i guess i just need to
be able to pick
this stuff better
uh and then we implement the other
aspects of the diagramming right we need
a way to
uh draw you know
we need slightly better filtering
because the the giant like 10 000
dispatch thing
uh is probably not gonna cut it but uh
we could do some slightly better
filtering and then we can do
um
drawing of things like the spheres and
so on
okay so lines
we already have
so it seems like that's something we
should probably just
do
i don't know what this stuff actually uh
refers to like
cf
what is cf
it's just the color what does the f
stand for
from color
function from color
face
fade
i mean i'm the only one that types in
this code base so i typed it in but
i have no idea what the f stands for
um
flat f
front
you got me
uh anyway so if we do a push line
segment here we'll get lines
right so that should be pretty
straightforward
so if we want to draw lines we can draw
lines
and to do that uh
i guess the texture part
maybe the texture part is occluded why
there's an f
i don't know we don't care what the
texture is here so we're not going to
use that
um
i don't know man
so anyway uh the from is in the entry p
the
two is in the entry p1
and then the colors right so
uh in this case the color doesn't
doesn't actually have
there's there isn't one for either
endpoint so it's just gonna be like uh
current dot color
and again you can see why i
i think i'm going to go ahead and just
change that to a v4
uh
just to make it a little bit more sane
so what i'll probably do here's my
suggestion there is this is not gonna be
a thing on the entities we're just gonna
do like v3 color
uh
maybe even v4 color
thick right
and then we'll just you know change this
around
and so now when we do this
we'll extend it to the v4 in the actual
call
so
you know it should just work
and
this
will now get it directly out of here
and then these
uh
just are larger now
and that way we don't have to constantly
mess with it uh
it's just and and if someone does want
to use alpha later we can allow we can
have a call
that would allow you to set the alpha
which we might want and that way all of
this code just works because it's
passing through the alpha now
which it might as well there's really no
reason not to all right i did that in
the wrong order oops
so now i think we get line segments as
well i don't think anyone's drawing them
so i'm not sure that matters i don't
know that we have points i think in
general we just do
uh
tiny like cubes for the points
is what we've done in the past
so so i believe all we do here is we
just do push cubes when we've wanted to
draw those and i think like we did that
for example
when we wanted to draw a
um
like a lighting sphere
i don't know if you remember but we kind
of drew
like yeah it's this thing
where the samples were like in a sphere
we just did it this way
and that to me seems like a good idea so
i'm just going to go ahead and say
that's how we're going to draw points in
here uh which is we just draw them
as cubes of the size that you specified
when you said what you wanted the
thickness to be that way you can also
control
uh that thickness
so in here we would do a radius
the radius is going to be oops
the current
thickness
three times over
the placement of the point comes from p0
the color of the point comes from the
color
and that's it for points so we're down
to just spheres and overlays and we've
got the text
uh part of this
as well so we want to do a
drawing of text and i
don't really remember much about how we
do text in this system unfortunately
um
you know i i just don't remember how any
of that stuff works
um
we're gonna have to look
so if we take a look
in the code that draws text which is
only really done for debugging um and
like editor panels and stuff like that
uh
you know i have no idea how that stuff
worked
or how we were doing it
but
you can see here like
here's us doing some stuff with that
and
it looks like text out at
is the base call
god like have a bigger stack this looks
like a java program
um
so it looks like this is our text
call
right uh we've never implemented one
so far
uh
i don't think that operates like in game
i mean this is basically it
so you you really just call
uh get bitmap for glyph
uh bitmap info and then you
you do a um
an alignment of the text here right
so it'd be pretty easy to just redo this
uh i'm just not sure
i have to think about it
so i'm not sure what we want to do here
i really don't know
um i guess we just have to play around
with it and see what makes sense
so
i think we probably just want to make a
little routine in the diagram system
that's like
takes the text and it puts it
you know centered at a position right
uh i mean i i don't really have
much of an idea you know i just figured
we probably want to be able to label
things i maybe i don't know it's unclear
whether we even really care about this
but we'll see
so i guess when it comes to spheres
these are the only things where we don't
really have a way to draw them right now
there's a lot of ways i suppose we could
draw them we could draw them using the
same kind technique we did before where
we just put points on the surface of the
sphere
we could add the ability to draw an
actual sphere
uh which would you know be something
that actually puts quads in a pattern
around the surface of a sphere i'm not
sure we really want to go that far with
it
so it's kind of hard to say what we want
to draw here uh we could put line
segments around in like a ring that just
sort of shows representationally where
the sphere would
be um
so that's another option that we could
do
and so i don't know uh it's yeah it's
really pretty
tough to say
what should happen here and i don't know
uh so anyway
moving forward with this slightly um
let's go ahead and and see if we can
the white texture thing
we have a easy way of getting just plain
white texture here right yeah
so i don't know if there's a
is there a like get white texture or
plain yeah i don't know
um so
it's that uh so we don't really have to
care about that
anyway so i don't know what we want to
do about text i'm really not sure maybe
we'll save that until next weekend when
we can have some time to think about it
for right now i just want to
uh go into the move entity stuff and see
if we can now use some of this
diagramming
to get us some information right so
let's let's see what we can do about
that
so
and we'll see if we can maybe start to
work on that panel right
so in here one of the things we know is
that if we turn this on we get problems
and the reason that we get problems is
because this is called so many times
so one thing we could do is say look
let's get this out of here uh and just
say like all right let's just show only
when they collide
um so if they haven't collided then we
won't draw this at all right we won't uh
and i guess really we probably want
the other way around
um but yeah
so what we'd like to do here is is say
if they haven't collided uh then we
don't right because that's what this is
it's like shapes collide so it's true
if they collide if they haven't collided
we won't draw anything if they have
collided then we will
um and you know we can see whether that
gives us some more of that information
right so now when this thing collides
like that we should be drawing more
stuff
and it's a little bit hard to tell
because we're already drawing so much
stuff with those like voxel occupancy
things that's hard to tell if anything
new got drawn in there now the fact that
there's some white squares in there
suggests that maybe we do
um because it's hard to say but
i
in the interest of of being clearer
about it
let's just see what happens uh
me
maybe one thing we can do is
start to put some of the filtering stuff
into
yeah like we can start to put some of
the filtering stuff into this system
so
let me think about this for a second
this is my giant stretch
um
so what i'd like to do here is i'd like
to have a
way like i said before i what i'd really
like to do is have some way of
of isolating these diagrams and that's
the part that i'm not really thinking
you know what's weird is i did this in
the witness and i actually can't
remember how i did that system
but it was a pretty good system
and
i think what it might have done is
capture many frames
and then you just like step through to
the frame you wanted
i think that may have been how it worked
so it just like it like saved you know
diagrams over multiple frames and then
you could step back through so you'd you
know you'd do something like you know
that
or or well this right
well
okay
that
so you do something like that and you
just go like okay you know i'm gonna
step through it now to see what happened
i guess one of the things one of the
nice things about this particular
situation is that's held
in a static
configuration so really
we can just you know that will just work
in the sense that we can just actually
see
you can see that we are drawing some
stuff there right those are lines
uh i believe that are being drawn right
so we are definitely drawing uh but yeah
like we want to be able to now turn
things on and off right we want to be
able to say like oh don't draw certain
certain pieces or you know turn on and
off different kinds of
of elements of this
i think the way i did that part in the
witness was i just had flag like i just
had like an enum that was like any time
you were doing a particular thing in a
diagram you just like
said which one it was you were doing and
then you could like turn them on and off
just by clicking on on like kind of like
checkboxes right
uh
and my assumption here
is
is like that would work just fine
probably uh i would suspect
um
i mean i think that would probably just
be fine so maybe we should do that like
we'll basically just have some enums and
we basically say here's a bunch of enums
that are like what parts of diagrams are
being drawn and you can just turn them
on and off or something right
now if i go and actually look
at what's being drawn there
um
you can see
putting in stuff like
spheres or whatever
um none of this stuff is being drawn in
any colors so i also don't know which
things are which
uh but you can see here that the lines
are actually only drawn in the sphere
case anyway
so we do at least know that the sphere
collision stuff is operating right
it's just not working very well like
it's not actually doing anything
um
that we would want it to
right
so if we look right at what's happening
there with the sphere you know the line
is drawn from the center of the sphere
so in the case that we expect we have
which is this one
the line is drawn from the center of the
sphere to the center of the box
right
uh
no sorry to the closest point on the box
right
so that's like the center of the sphere
is out here and the closest point in the
box is over there
um
and we have the problem where for
whatever reason the
the sphere doesn't think it can move
closer to that
right
what it's doing is it's evaluating to
see whether it can get closer to there
uh from where it is
you know
and
what's kind of weird about that is you
would assume
that it easily could just by moving out
slightly and
because it is a sphere
uh
you would think that it could
get closer to that by moving around you
know around
but it's not doing that and so i'm not
sure yeah i'm not sure what the actual
i'm not sure what the actual best way is
to look at
that
so i guess what we can do
as a game plan is we can just have a
button because like okay so at least for
this
we know we can get it into a situation
like that wasn't hard to do
where the glove gets
you know caught on something
so that it won't move
from where it is you know until we ask
it to do something different
right
and so
my assumption there is that given that
we should be able to just have a thing
on here where we just hit like
you know
capture
and then it just remembers one of those
diagrams and never clears it
right
once we have it captured then we can
step through the different parts of it
right and so yeah i mean i think that's
basically what we want i don't know how
much time i have left let me see
um
14 minutes maybe
let's say 14 minutes
so
maybe what we'll do
so we'll do that next time
maybe what we'll do this time is
one of the problems we're going to have
is we're going to want to be able to
refer to these and step through them
and at the moment they're just a linked
list which might be annoying for that
so one of the things we could do is just
say like
well
maybe they're enumerated or something or
have ids
associated with them
i suppose if you capture
it's actually fine because you just
store that pointer and like it matches
something or it doesn't you don't care
right
so that might actually be fine i guess i
don't know that that's true
uh but you can kind of see like where
i'm going with this right so in the
diagram system
uh yeah we would need a thing where like
diagram reset doesn't get called
if you've done a capture so probably
what we would need is something like in
the diagram group we would have
something like you know captured
it's like a flag that gets set
and so at some point you just do a thing
that's like diagram capture
uh
and
capture like turns that to on
you know it would need two things
it would need to to basically have a
uh
a state where you said like it's on or
it's off
um
so in here
uh we would set the captured state
of the diagram group
like that
uh and then what we do here is like
diagram is on
will always be off
uh
so if you're not captured then you can
you can be on
and then we see whether filter pass is a
separate thing right
so that way when we capture diagramming
is off permanently so no one's going to
do anything
similarly the call to reset will fail so
basically like if group captured
um
if if you haven't done a capture you can
clear if you have in a capture you
cannot clear right so once you lock in
that capture
uh it will not clear anymore
so
what we could then do is inside that
panel so in here where we had uh you
know
this this thing right
uh what we could have here is like a
lock like a
look like a toggle
i'm trying to think of should be like
two buttons or a toggle
uh
i don't really know
but
in here we could have a thing which
which basically controls that
right
so there would be like a button thing
whatever the heck this stuff is who
knows
um
where we just say all right you've got a
you know a button here
um
and you push this capture button and
when you push the capture button maybe
we actually have like a toggle
on this or something
right
where we say like diagram uh is captured
and we just say like look if it is
captured then it's like um
or something like that uh i don't know
and then in here we just say like okay
maybe remember whether the thing is
captured or not
and then in here we can set set it
so
what did i call that again
and then that's just a toggle so in here
we've got two of these we've got
like is captured
and these both have to also
kind of
have their compiled out versions so is
captured will always be zero there's
nothing you can do
and set capture will just not do
anything
at all
and that seems fine so then on here
we would have
the same thing we have
is captured
i don't know why these are not booleans
too much ref term programming where we
were just in c i guess
and uh never made one
but
that that'll do it
okay
so
i think that's good
everything seems fine there
and uh so now
you know this might actually also work
just because you know you don't really
need much for that to be working
so if i went in here and then i said
like okay like capture that diagram
um
i don't know why single stepping is like
that color but
so it doesn't look like that worked for
some reason and i don't know what the
reason actually is
like oh
i do know what that reason is you can't
change the camera
uh i mean not the camera but the basis
so you can't move out of the region so
it did work just fine but if you moved
out of the region right so it had a new
center point you'd still draw the
diagram it will just draw in a
completely different place relative to
the rest of the scene because the scene
has slid
that's fine
i don't care about that at all we just
won't do that right
so there's our diagram frozen in place
uh so that's great because that was easy
i don't know what single stepping oh so
that turns on and off
um
single stepping uh so so
that's actually we actually already kind
of had the button
i guess
uh so we don't really need this anymore
because single stepping is not
um
really a thing
in the world world mode
those don't
probably
want to
be there right uh
i'm just going to remove those because
those are going to go into the diagram
system now so i don't actually want
um
those to be there
so what does that do
if anything
suffering
[Music]
oh yeah
what's going on bean
what's going on toffee bean
what you doing
what are you doing
you just mousing around
come on up
coming up there you go
yeah
you wanna say hi
can you say hi to everybody
what are you doing
you wanna what do you wanna do you look
like you do you wanna be brushed are you
gonna do you need brushings
what's going on
tell me what's up
it looks like you want brushings you
want brushings right
okay
you want brushings
you will get
brushings for sorting
it is important to maintain optimal coat
health at all times
and brushings is an important part of
this as we know
so we know as we all know
there you go
okay
all right
looking good
looking sleek
wouldn't you say
oh yeah
okay
um
so i don't know maybe this is actually
good i don't know uh maybe i should
leave it in i didn't realize we'd
actually done it um
to be honest i thought that was just
kind of some placeholder stuff but it
looks like we actually put that in there
and if that's the case
i guess i won't take it out so so can we
use this is this still a thing that we
want what are you doing puss what are
you doing
um
like if i do
a
single stepping here
um
okay so it kind of does interesting
um so yeah i guess you know what i'll
leave that in there because you know
we we might maybe don't need the capture
stuff as much if we have that because we
can kind of step it uh maybe we'll have
to
cap the
movement amount like i
that didn't seem like a single step
to me
um
[Music]
i'm not sure
what are you doing what are you doing
booba
what are you doing
uh
so yeah i don't really know what we're
gonna do with that um
but i like it so i'm not gonna remove it
i don't know why that step was able to
move quite so far that's a bit odd uh so
maybe i'll take a look at that it could
be that we're not like clamping the
total movement amount
at all
uh
there
which we probably should
what are you doing booba
what are you doing
you just chilling
i gotta finish up the show okay we're
almost done
okay
all right
come on
go sit down for a little bit
um
so yeah like i don't know that might
just be because we're not clamping those
uh velocities at all right
um
but like if you look here in fact you
can kind of see that it's allowed to
just do like arbitrary stuff here which
is kind of nuts uh
so we must not be clamping the total
distance
or something
so maybe that's what we do next time
let's look at that and i didn't know
we'd already implemented this this is
great so we may not really need capture
much we may be able to just like get
away without really ever using it it's
nice to have it there in case we do
because it was you know free to add took
like you know two seconds to put that in
but now that we have the diagrams and
the single stepping that actually seems
pretty good because then i can just like
step through and watch each one happen
so maybe we just put a little diagram
filtering in there next time and then
hopefully you know we'd be okay
um to debug uh what's happening with
with some of that stuff
so all right let's go ahead and do q a