start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show we
code a complete game live on stream no
engines no libraries here although we
did do our one and only library stream
yesterday for the asset processor
because some people wanted to see how to
use sdb TrueType so I showed how to use
that so if you are interested in the one
and only time on handmade hero that we
will probably ever use a library that
was the day to do it so what are we
gonna do today today I'm going to show
you how to do the same thing without a
library just because why not maybe it
will make you appreciate us to be
TrueType even more so let's take a look
today is day 164 so if you want to keep
up if you want to do do if you want to
code along with me on the stream if you
will then you're gonna want to unpack
day 163 source code because that is the
source code that I'm going to be
starting with here and so if you
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
org unzip day 163 and you will be right
in line you'll be right in line with me
so let's take a look here like I said
don't allow any libraries in handmade
here a button the asset processor I'm
okay with it because that's not
something that ships on the end-users
machine so it's okay we can do that so
if you want to use this you can use this
right here s to be true type of
implementation s to be true type you
want to do that don't have a problem
with it go go for it go nuts and
and use all the libraries you want in
your asset processor and you know I
guess what I would say is even though
it's in sort of this offline asset
processor like well the reasons I don't
like using libraries I'd like to be able
to keep my code running I like to keep
it portable and I can do all sorts of
things
efficiency blah blah blah right there's
all these good reasons not to use
libraries for me in in the game and some
of those are lessened when you talk
about the asset processor because really
the asset processor doesn't have to run
on a variety of machines it doesn't have
to run 64-bit 32-bit it doesn't have to
be portable right and all these sorts of
things that doesn't necessarily have to
do because yes that processor just runs
on your machine to process the yard
assets before shipping the game and then
you're done right but even so if you
think about it you know if you want that
asset processor to be something that's
like a tool that you rely on and that
you know maybe you can work on no matter
what platform you're working out at that
time or whatever sometimes it makes
sense to apply the same sorts of rules
to your asset processor as you would
apply to to the game and so I actually
tend to even if I'm in an asset
processor if I'm gonna use a library I
still tend to only really allow
libraries that would be like SDB
TrueType where they were well engineered
by a programmer who knew what they were
doing and they're really convenient to
implement and work cross-platform and
all these are the things don't require a
build process bla bla bla just because
the asset processor eventually does
become a fairly sort of heavyweight
thing especially if you extend your game
to 3d eventually or things like this the
asset processor can be a fairly serious
endeavor and so you know as much as on
handmade here I've decided that the
asset processor is kind of the separate
thing that we're not really going to be
too concerned about you know in a real
game project it can be a fairly
formidable beasts and sort of you know
you gotta kind of think along those
lines
so I'll just say that first seven think
about but what I wanted to show today
was if you didn't want to use a library
right because I'm handmade here we don't
use any libraries in the main code base
if we didn't want to use a library how
would you have gone about extracting
these fonts would you have to written
your own TrueType font that's right
that's one thing you could do the other
thing you can do I'm not necessarily
saying it's better in fact it's probably
worse than choosing SUV trooper but
misses gonna say what you can do is you
can rely on the operating system to get
this information because every operating
system no matter what absolute you run
out you're going to have a way to
extract fonts out of that operating
system so another thing that you could
do with the asset processor is get the
fonts from windows right and so how do
you do that right well in Windows
Windows actually has a bunch of calls
for
Fonts right for example this is the text
out function the textile function is
something that can take any string and
rasterize it into an htc now we worked
with HTC's in handmade hero before
you've seen those back in the early days
when we first set up our window and
wanted to blip our you know our drawing
to it
it stands for handle to a device context
a device context is what they called
sort of the the context for drawing the
context for doing graphics work in the
graphics device interface for windows
and so what we do know is if we wanted
to start extracting fonts out of windows
we could just call this text out
function and we know that we could get
it to draw to an HDC so the question is
just could we figure out a way to get
one of these HDC s to draw into a bitmap
of our choosing right like a bitmap that
we are okay with looking at behind sort
of the back of windows if you will right
because if we could do that we can just
have windows draw the fonts and then we
can grab the fonts out of there and this
is the same principle you can follow in
just about any operating system whatever
the thing is they have that would draw
fonts we could just go ahead and and use
that thing right okay so there's
actually a couple ways we could do this
we could start by doing the absolute
slowest way I believe it's called get
pixel the absolute slowest way and
probably not a particularly good way to
go but we could try it just to make the
the sort of a note Ron called the
absolute the absolute slowest but
absolute simplest way would be this way
which would be that if we didn't want to
try and figure out how to create any
kind of a special HDC at all we could
just use a any old HDC right like no
matter any HDC we could create so we
just look at how we created any old HDC
use that and then we can call get pixel
sequentially to literally read out each
pixel in order and since this is the
asset processor we could just be fine
with that we could just be like you know
what we
kara takes a long time we're only gonna
do it once to extract the thigh and
spine right so we could do that that's
not entirely out of the question right
so maybe let's start with that
and then we could see after we're done
with that if we want to push a little
further and be a little bit more fancy
about how we do our HDC so if we have if
we have to get one of these HTC's the
way that we would want to do that is by
using a create DC call usually the way
that you would probably do that is call
and create compatible DC and we would
just use a DC that was one that we knew
about like one that was you know maybe
one that was for lack of better term
like the screen like the screen that
we're running on for example something
like this but there's a lot of ways that
we can do that right so you can take a
look in here and you can see these we
can't do a create DC call just raw here
right and you can you can pass sort of
all the different things and and sort of
speck out more explicitly what you want
to do right but that just again seems
like a lot of work because if you do
create compatible DC as long as you know
that you have a DC that roughly fits the
kind of device context that you want we
could just use that right another thing
we could do is we could also create a
window and use each DC you know blah
blah blah so there's lots of different
things that we could do there right and
I'm assuming I can't quite remember it's
been a long time but I'm assuming that
we would have to have a bitmap yeah and
it says right here before an application
can use a memory DC for drawing
operations it must select a bitmap of
the correct width and height into the DC
to select a bitmap into a DC use the
create compatible bitmap function
specifying the height width and color
organization required so we kind of know
what we would be doing we'd be creating
compatible DC we then be creating a
compatible bitmap with that DC and we
would be putting it into the HDC right
and that's that's what we would do so
let's take a look let's just do that
let's create a pound to find here which
is like use fonts from windows or
something like that
and we will define that to be one we
will then come in here and say if you
sponsor windows pound include windows
dot H right otherwise we will use STV
TrueType and so this way you can choose
whether you want to use the library or
not just kind of an example of what's
happening there and then the STB tree
type part of things we will sort of make
a version of load glyph bitmap that does
not need that does not need SD be true
type so base will say okay if you use
fonts from windows we're going to use
the windows path otherwise we're going
to use this path here okay there we go
all right
okay so if we're going to do this like I
said before we want to start with the
text out function this is the function
that we would want to call right and
this function we would want to have that
that DC so this would be our device
context right and we would want to
presumably just draw into the top of the
bitmaps we don't really need any offsets
for the text right and then when we do
the code point unfortunately we kind of
have a nasty issue here which is that
windows always wants code points always
wants utf-16 so we can just cold Cassatt
I guess but that's probably not really
the quite correct thing to do like
technically if you wanted to convert to
like a double you care T right if you
want to convert to a utf-16 character
you kind of need to do a utf-32 code
point to utf-16 conversion so we'll call
this a cheese point because it's not
really correct I don't think but it'll
be correct for any of the ANSI
characters that we were doing and
probably a lot of characters but you
know like I said not really correct so
if we did it that way
first just to get things started then
what we would do is say okay pass the
cheese point this is also gonna be text
out W right so we'd pass the cheese
point and we would say it's a one
character string that would draw the
text like so and presumably we can
actually compile that but the problem of
course will be that we don't have a
device context yet okay so we got to get
a device context here's our device
context we want to create compatible DC
right and I assume that the easiest way
to do it would be to do a create
compatible DC 0 at least that's my
assumption create compatible DC 0 I
believe is the easiest way to say like
just copy the just copy the screens you
see I don't know if we need to do a get
DC 0 I don't think we do but then again
I'm not sure so I'm gonna try that first
again with Windows it's easy to forget
this stuff I often forget this stuff but
then we want to create compatible bitmap
as well and we want to select that in
again like I don't know if
remember way back when we did window
stuff these device context you select
objects into them and those are the
objects that you are going here so for
example you thought you would select
into the thing it's kind of like saying
set the active one so this is like set
the active bitmap set the active fonts
at the active pants at the active brush
blah blah blah blah right that's how it
works so let's take a look create
compatible bitmap here this one we're
just going to use the HDC that we've
already created and we're gonna say what
the width and height is since we know
that we have a certain size size that
we're doing let's just create something
large enough that we know that we'll
always pretty much fill will always have
plenty of room for any character we're
gonna make right and that will return to
us an H bitmap right so here's our
bitmap we go ahead and grab that we
select a bitmap in now we of course want
to be able to make sure that we only do
this once right I mean we don't want to
be doing this all the time so really I
think probably what we want to be doing
is is you know something like this I
don't know what device context actually
returns and fails I assume that let's
take a look here create compatible D see
if there's so the term values the handle
and see if it is just no okay so
basically we can do device context 0 and
we can make that a static again we're in
the asset processor here so anything
goes we don't have to worry at all about
that sort of stuff so if the device
context is not initialized we will just
initialize it right we'll create it so
we'll create a bitmap with that we will
select the bitmap into our device
context like so and then we can draw our
text right so that should do it
of course I need to actually close that
block there we go
and now we're actually you know we're in
some sense we're sort of now extracting
a font but we're not extracting the
right font even because we have not
actually tried to set the font to be
Arial right was the font we were using
before
we didn't even do that hmm right and we
also don't know right we don't even know
how big that font should be we've got we
got all kinds of weird stuff going on
here right so this is this is really a
zygote of a thing it is not really fully
happening and of course we have not yet
actually tried to extract anything
either so we've got a bunch more work to
do here to say the least so let's start
by going all right we've got a couple
things we got to know first of all right
and you remember how easy it was with
Sean's thing right Sean's thing was like
this and that right that was it there's
like two things two calls and we have
the whole thing right we could just
extract everything we wanted all this
code is just our code to like basically
you know turn his bitmap into our format
that was it not not gonna be true for
Windows right windows pre tortured API
even back then it's only gotten worse
but it's pretty tortured so what we need
to do now is we need to do kind of all
the accoutrement first of all we got to
figure out how much space did that text
take up right because Sean told us right
he said here's the width here is the
height but when we draw a text in in
Windows it never did we have no idea
right we have no idea how big it is so
if we want to do that what we have to do
is we have to get some information about
it it doesn't look like they showed it
in the related here but there is a font
and text function called get text
metrics and there's also one called font
well I'm sure I'll see you in here I'm
not remembering it right off the bat but
there's there's basically functions that
will we can query sort of if you will
what the sizes of strings are and that
sort of thing so let's see get text
metrics tells us some of the stuff about
the font that's like how tall it is and
stuff like that so we probably will need
that at some point so I'm gonna just
grab that and put that in there because
we're gonna have to call that once we
get to the part in fonts where we're
actually trying to do like alignment for
the fonts and that sort of thing right
so we got cat text metrics that's gonna
have to happen device context and that
like takes one of these LP text metric
things right
we're gonna want to get that out so
we've got text metric we will ask it to
return us a filled out structure for the
text metrics and eventually we'll kind
of use we'll use that for something okay
so we nakir what else we got
we don't care about that we probably
want get text extent point 32 that does
sound like the function I was thinking
of so let's take a look
computes the width and height to the
specified string of text that's exactly
what we wanted so we're gonna need that
guy right and what this will do is when
we do our text out oops
when we do our text out we want to know
how big it's going to be so we can just
say okay get text extent point 32 here's
the device context here's our cheese
point here's the length of our cheese
point and and then we're gonna have to
actually get that that size parameter
right and that's one of these guys right
hello hello I would like to show the
people on the stream the size parameter
please thank you so this is one of those
and all it is is a structure that has
basically width and height in it that's
all it is right so it's that we would
just say fill that out please and that
would give us the width and the height
right so we can basically say okay but
width is size DX the height is size dots
- I have a party it's all good right so
now at least we would know the region
that the text occupied after we did our
text out so we know kind of what region
we want to grab right so we can start to
do the extraction of the font okay so
that gives us all the information we
need for that but we have a few more
things we kind of need to do here
obviously we're using the same device
kind of search so one thing we have to
do is clear write that region first
right because if we're going to draw the
font into it if look the fit map will be
called for every code point we want to
draw the font right
into a clean bitmap so you want to be
able to clear the background to like
black or something right and then draw a
white bitmap on top of it so that we can
see what the actual values are going to
be and not have the font the glyphs like
pile up on top of each other so we need
some way of clearing this right and I
think we've gone over this long time ago
on the window screen fill rect is the
way in Windows that you can sort of just
clear something out there's a you know
that gives you a rectangle and you can
fill it there's also another one which
is called padlet right which is a little
bit faster and doesn't use a brush right
and so I'm gonna go ahead and use padlet
and you know I shouldn't even say it's a
little bit faster it doesn't use a brush
it's not a little bit faster anymore in
the old days it would have been nowadays
this is all slow because if you want
something fast you have to go through
direct3d or something right
so you know when I say that that's kind
of me offhandedly talking about 1992 so
anyway if we go ahead here and and we
want to do our clear we know the device
counts for clearing honest States we're
drawing our fonts into we know the left
in the right are zero zero because we're
not positioning anything we know the
width and the height because we just did
it and so all we need to know is how do
we set this thing to black right how do
we get a black in there and we've got DW
Rob that's the raster op blackness
happens to be one of them we can
literally just say we want you to fill
the area with black that's one of the
raster operations it knows how to do by
default so we can just full-on clear the
thing that way and now we're just gonna
write in every time right and that's all
good that is all good
however we've still got more nonsense
coming because when we Pat lit the
blackness in there remember when we do
the text out we haven't said what color
the text should be and so the text could
very easily come out black because I
think the default vertex may even be
black so we'd end up with black text on
a black background that will not help us
extract this font in any way so we need
to do something to change that font
color and wouldn't you know it it
actually called set text color fairly
reasonably named function SEC text color
allows us to say what we want our text
color to be so we can say set text color
of the device context we can set that
color to a color F which is just white
and windows actually has a thing for
that which is it's RGB it's a little
macro which you can just say RGB to to
52525 right that's one way of quickly
specifying one of those color F
structures which is just a way of saying
I want you know ffffff to be what you
write in all the pixels where the text
is okay so that will write white text on
top of a black backdrop which means we
could now if we wanted to try doing some
extraction that code is going to look
exactly the same as it did in the case
with Shawn's right we are going to want
to allocate some memory do the little
dance of fun right we're going to want
to extract stuff but instead of
extracting it from a mono a bitmap this
time since we're going to be doing the
slow path there the dead pixel path what
we need to do is actually replace this
call where we get the Alpha we what we
need to do is replace that with the get
pixel call that I was talking about
before where we ask the device context
what the pixel is at a particular
location so we go in there and say okay
that pixel here it is you know taking a
look at it it needs the HDC the X and
the y pose right and we've got those we
know we're extracting this if x and y
right and yeah and so that's all pretty
much good right everything's fine we may
I don't remember whether this will come
in upside down or right side up so we
don't know whether we want to keep the
flipping that we were doing in Shawn's
path because I don't remember what it
will do by default what the X&amp;Y
coordinates are where they'll start in
the bottom left or the top right it's
been way too long
so I don't know but point being that get
pixel call will return us a color rest
structure and so we're gonna get back a
color ref this is the pixel and so what
we can do there is take a look at that
it's a D word right and since we're
writing white in there and we know it's
B bgg
our our we could take any one of these
three and treat that as the alphas are
all going to be the same vbg grr so we
can literally for our u8 alpha we can
just take the pixel we can end it with
echo X FF that extracts the red Channel
cast it to a u8 and that is all she
wrote right so that's all good what is
the problem cannot convert ah right
that's probably a W function yes it is
all right so let's take a look at what
we've got now
I think that's roughly the outline of
something that extracts a font we are
not setting the font yet so we're not
gonna get Arial but that is roughly
modulo bugs what we would love to have
to do create a compatible DC select a
compatible bitmap into that this is kind
of waiting around for later figure out
how big it's going to be clear it draw
it in white extract each PI pixel by
pixel and again this is very slow way to
do it because we're not reading them we
are making an operating system call
every time to get that pixel so super
slow but you know will should in theory
work pack it back up as usual and that
is the end of of the party right so
that's basically everything okay so
let's go ahead and and test that out
we'll see if that works at all remember
using the current stuff that we've got
using s DB Lib for our font extraction
this is what things should look like
right it's it's sort of sprays nothing's
all over the place and so if we wanted
to test this we should be able to
rebuild the asset library rank by going
build test asset builder right that
should rewrite all of our asset files we
can look and see that we have rewriting
them for today which is the 5th of
August right and now we can run and see
if we did anything at all
which we don't know if we did or not
right we have no idea where is our Emma
step there it is right so there we go
not great you can see that it's just
solid which is not at all what we want
to see right but it doesn't look totally
wrong in the sense that the sizes seem
right so we're not you know we're not
catastrophic ly bad we're just not good
right so now we get to try and figure
out what went wrong and maybe that first
involves me taking another drink of my
lemonade like so okay so what exactly
could be the culprits here it seems to
me like it's you know it's pretty clear
from looking at that that the Alpha is
always we're always getting white right
we're always getting back to 55 which is
not what we want to see so even though
when we call get text extent point 32 W
it looks like it's returning us the
correct size for the character for some
reason are either our patent lit to
blackness is not working right or our
set text color is not setting it to
white or something like this right
well no that can't be it because it
pretty much has to be this guy because
you know if we were to take a look at
doing nothing right I know who's at
fault here
I know exactly who's at fault here I'm
gonna run a little test
I'm gonna run tests what if we set the
text color to black mm-hmm what if what
do you guys think would happen if I set
the text color to black I'm a little
test for y'all well surprise surprise
all the letters show up and they're
inverse video what happened here well
I'll tell you what happened here that's
one of those hey I've been programming
window so long I even remember all the
bugs I used to have and this is
one of them that you always have because
you would not think that this would be
the default but it is the default when
you draw text in Windows there is like a
set text became owed or set became owed
nonsense this function right this
function determines whether or not
drawing actually leaves the background
in its original state or whether it will
fill it with the background brush when
it draws right so what we can do we have
two choices we can set VK mode to be
transparent and then this would work
fine but what was basically happening
there right was it was drawing the font
in in white but filling the whole region
around the font in white as well because
that's what it's Specter to do right
it's it's obliterating the background
behind it which was black so we could
select in a black brush as the
background color right and that would
fix it as well that seems a little
clever because then we can get rid of
Pat black right we could turn off Pat
plet select in a background brush right
and that seems kind of Supes kind of
creative right it seems kind of creative
rather than setting the mode to
transparent we could just do it that way
right I feel like that's I feel like
that's you know possibility I'm just
gonna I don't even remember how to do
background brushes I'm just gonna search
and see hey let's see windows set
background brush let's take a look let's
take look do what do you do the system
feeds the background for window organs I
don't care about any of this I don't I
want I don't want the window but I don't
want the window background I want I want
the device I want that HDC I want the
DC's background background color
set DC brush color how about that set DC
brush color set DC brush color
let's see set DC brush color function
sets the device current device contacts
each brush for the specified color value
it's advise cannot represents medical
records there's physical color let's see
when the stock DC brushless active you
see this UPS controlling one with the DC
brush color the default EC brush color
is white that is our problem we want it
to be black let's just give this a shot
ladies and gentlemen Windows GDI
let is let us just see what it does if
we full-on say the background is now
black alright will it work will it not
work we don't know but off we go
that does not look very reassuring that
is exactly where we were before
I am unimpressed I am unimpressed by
that so set Dec brush color does not see
is there a D is there a background blush
color let's take a look let's take a
look at the device context reference
this is something that if you programmed
Windows GDI
like when I used to program a gel I
would just know this so it's not like
it's that hard but anyway set DC brush
color set to see pen color sat layout
release DC get stock object I was a type
gonna play out I don't know here I'm not
sure this doesn't have set text color in
it which is a little bit weird why
doesn't it set text color it's a little
bit fishy wouldn't you say I would say
font and text functions oh it's right
there
okay set PG colorist functions the
current bar color use special color
value where's the nearest color in it so
okay blah blah blah so actually fills
the gaps between styled lines drawings
you append creating the create pen
function does not fill the gas swing
styled lines so you think this is what
the font does if the FOB arm is opaque
the back encourage you to feel gasping
style I bet this is just it's just using
this so we don't even need the brush
it's just set DK color man oh man
alright set BK color let's try it one
more time
there we go so there we go that's how
you extract the pond with Windows
and again you can choose kind of how you
want to do that on the operate system
there's different operating systems
different options different ways to do
it but you can do the same thing in
other platforms as well it's just a more
Byzantine nonsense like what I just went
through in a different way so anyway
that extracts the fonts from windows the
problem that we have right now is we are
unable to pick the font that we want and
we would like to be able to pick the
font that we want right we would like to
be able to create a font and render with
that font so there is a way to do that
it is unsurprisingly called create font
and also create font in direct there are
different ways of creating fonts and
they are really really really annoying
the reason they are annoying is because
you know and I I want to say I've never
even figured out a way to do this I
didn't try admittedly I've never tried
particularly hard but in my recollection
I don't think I ever really knew a way
to create a font from just a file on the
drive right like just hey here's a file
name man I just want to create a font
that's this file name never never
figured out a way to do that and if you
look at the font text reference it's not
it's not straightforward how to do that
right
you've kind of got these things here for
creating fonts I I don't actually
remember you know it might be add font
resource maybe is this a new thing that
this adds went from a file name right so
this looks like it I don't know if that
adds permanently or not I'm not sure any
application that as removes fonts from
the system font Oh should notify their
windows of the change when application
no longer needs a font resource that is
loaded by ad font research your move
font resource so yeah so I don't think I
ever figured out a way to just say I
want to create a font from a file I
don't want it to be loaded into Windows
I just want to draw some text with just
that font and then I'm gonna be done I'm
pretty sure the only way you can do
something approximating that
is by using ad font resource which kind
of adds it like to the whole thing right
it sort of makes it like pulls it into
Windows as a system rather than just
privately to you but I'm pretty sure
that's the only way you can actually do
it yeah people who program GDI more
these days might know of a better way
but I don't I don't think there was a
way so if we take a look at this guy
it's it's roughly what we do want though
I think and again this is this is
supported pretty much everywhere at this
point so that's fine ad font resource ax
that will be the thing that would allow
us to you know sort of give it a TTFN
that it would add into Windows and then
we could say for example private which
is that like we don't actually want you
to share this with anybody so I'm gonna
go that route I think that's probably
the easiest way to go this will get the
font into Windows so add font resource
DX right we'll pass it that filename
then we'll pass it that private flag
right if our private like so and we will
pass it the zero out there right so that
would that would add that font resource
the problem is I don't know how I get
out the font from that like meaning once
we add one how do I and how does it know
which one let's see maybe font memories
just probably uses one from font yeah it
does that's loading for memory so if I
get back one from ad font IX I'm gonna
get back an integer here and it just
tells me how many fonts were added I
don't actually know how I actually get
those fonts the font will not be present
thoughtless in the registry you install
a to location other than the window
fonts folder cannot be modified later
replaced blah blah blah but there's
nowhere to actually use that font is
there like there's just no way to
actually say I want to use I want to
create font that font right I mean am I
missing it but I don't I don't think
there is so we would also have to know
what the font that we were going to use
was actually called right we'd have to
know the name
and so let me double check ad font
resource the X example just to see if
anyone knows how to do something like
that
and it looks like they don't they just
don't know how to do it so I'm guessing
the Internet does not seem to know so
I'm guessing you just can't do it so
after you add the font resource you need
an additional piece of information right
which is the font name now SPB doesn't
need that although you might argue that
it doesn't need that if you wanted to
actually search through TTF files and
pick a specific font but in Windows we
absolutely need that because the only
way we can do it is to first add the
file name into the font set in Windows
but then we have to pull out that font
again right we have to have know what
the actual face is called not the file
name to tell it which font we're
creating here right so if we were to do
create font now at this point to make
one of these fonts right we have to
specify all this nonsense and then at
the end this is the part that's actually
the business end there the LPC - LPC
Teamster part that's the part where we
would pass the font name in to the
system right so now we've got to fill
out all this stuff but that's just kind
of a grind through the docs nothing
particularly weird happening height if
you set a negative value it's just a
little convention here greater than zero
I believe it's a match
yeah so if you use zero it uses the
default if you use greater than zero it
transforms it into device units and
matches it against the cell height
availa fonts if you use it less than
zero it transforms valuations that
matches matches its absolute value
against character height so I guess it's
like kind of saying hey if I if the
thing was upside down or something like
that I don't even know I'm not even sure
what even that's trying to say let's see
here for the M text mapping boutique use
the flying for I specify a height or a
font with a specified point size I don't
really care about that I actually wanted
to just use pixels the character a photo
also knows the am height is the
character of cell height value minus the
internal leading value the flat member
trivia suppose in the following manner
yeah so I don't know what to play with
that a little bit I feel like we may
have to do a transformation to get out
to actually figure out what value we
want to pass here to get the right pixel
size yeah cuz we don't want points we
want pixels anyway no big deal we'll
figure out the height in a second height
we'll just say for now is is I don't
even remember what we were specifying in
Jin Shawn's 1 128 or something like that
is that correct
128 yeah so I don't know we'll just say
it's 128 for now but we'll do it to do a
see you figure out how to specify pixels
properly here so in the height will just
say height the width of the font we
don't actually care because we don't
want to specify any kind of stretching
or anything like that the escapement in
fonts is just a sort of way of saying
how rotated you want the font to be like
if you're trying to do text on an angle
we don't really want any of that right
we want it to be to be 0 which is the
it's the angle between the x-axis and
the angle of the font so we want to just
run straight across the x-axis so that's
0 if that makes sense so anyway
same is true use me same is true of the
orientation which is saying how the
letters are spun the escapements like
the escapements like the running of the
actual text right but then the letters
themselves can can be sort of rotated
similarly so we don't want the letters
rotated either because we can always
rotate them ourselves in the game right
so we just want them upright standard
for the FN weight I think we don't care
we probably want normal I would say if
we have a choice that would be my guess
so let's just do normal for italic we
don't want italics right maybe I'll
label these
this is italic this is weight right
this is underlined this is strikeout
whoever uses strikeout man it's so weird
okay so character set I don't know what
we want for character set probably we
could just use an C at this point
although if we're using Unicode code
points you would think that we would be
able to say you know that we wanted that
I suppose it probably doesn't matter
because the carrots that's probably only
used if you use the ASCII function calls
that's my guess so I don't think it
matters because we're actually using the
Unicode versions when we do text out so
I feel like that's probably fine
alright so output precision how closely
the output must match the requested
fonts height width character education
segment I don't know that we care too
much about that honestly so we can just
probably do default because again I
don't think we necessarily care clip
precision I think probably also
similarly we don't care these are all
things if we were actually using this to
render our fonts like in lots of
circumstances and all that sort of stuff
but we probably want anti-aliasing on
right we don't want clear text
would say would be my guess so we
probably want because because clear text
is going to introduce that sort of thing
that's you know only appropriate for a
specific LCD panel kind of a thing and
then pitch family I think we probably
want don't care I would guess let's see
the pitch and family thought jewellery
but specify the pitch of the font could
be one of the flies default pitch fixed
pitch variable pitch so we could just do
default pitch like so default pitch and
the fight for higher bits or so the font
family can be one of the following
values decorative don't care probably
don't care you my guess so there we go
that's would create our fonts provided
that we actually had a font name right
and I think that's basically it we would
just need to say what the source font
name actually was which adds a little
complexity to our thing here right just
font name it's this additional thing
down at the bottom again it's really
annoying but that's just what happens
when you're dealing with something
that's not as good as sed s DB true type
so if we go back to the point where we
do our aerial here and we say okay I
added aerial tvf I want you to find the
font aerial unsurprisingly right then we
need our add character asset function to
have font file and face name or whatever
right or font name I should say right
and so then in here when we set that
that will set set the code point we also
set the font name to be font name and
that's really it so that's all we need
to do to actually create the fonts in
theory but just creating the font
actually isn't enough because we are not
actually using that font right we're
creating a font handle but we have not
told this d this VC to use it but we can
do that the same way we did with the
bitmap by just selecting that as an
object selecting that object into the DC
it's saying make this font the active
font and that may be everything famous
last words
we'll see there we go
and that looks that looks a lot more
Arial to me I think hard to say
you know maybe we should set it to
something a little more recognizable
like warrior you know I'm saying so if
for example we were to say you know what
don't use that use quarry or new and I
guess I don't know dirty windows fonts
courier 4.2 ETF maybe maybe courier new
so we should be able to see something
significantly different here right if we
run the asset processor now and look at
the output of its fonts right yeah so
that's definitely working it's just I
feel like the fonts are kind of thin and
anemic to some degree and I don't know
if that's just because we're generating
too large or generating them too small
so we definitely have
you know some some questions there
because let's do something else here
right let's also switch it back to using
the SDB fonts right let's let's try that
and see how that goes
we'll run the asset build and then run
the game again so you see it's just so
much nicer in the SDV library just so
much nicer there and so I think there's
a couple reasons for that one is I think
that we're the STB library is actually
getting just the text rectangle right I
think I think when we asked for the text
extent point of that letter I think it's
giving us back more than just the pixels
so so Shawn's library is actually doing
a better job of giving us back the
rectangle I would suspect we could
double check by looking at some of these
and in fact I guess one way of doing it
might be to to keep sort of the border
in there like so for example what we
could do is instead of doing the Alpha
thing in test asset builder right what
we could do is when we build our when we
when we actually use the Alpha here what
we could do is say ah you know what
that's not the one I meant in here I
should say maybe we do something like
right we do color and alpha and normally
alpha equals color but here we'll just
set it you know two to five straight up
and so you know I guess I'll do Gray's
probably better term for that so and now
you know that way I'm forcing the Alpha
to be solid so now we'll see the actual
bitmap in all of its glory here is or
not but we would have what did I do
wrong there alpha is Oh X F F that
should have been of course we've got two
of these routines yep
you should probably should try to share
a little of that source potentially you
know I'm saying great so let's do that
alpha equals 4x FF and then we'll just
say okay the rest of it's gray gray gray
gray okay we're on the asset builder
take a look at Shawn's there we go and
you can kind of see exactly what I was
saying as I suspected right like Shawn's
it's perfectly tight bounding box around
that letter there's no empty space there
right and I suspect that what we're
gonna find when we take a look at the
windows one is that is that we're not
getting that right so if I switch back
to using fonts extracted from Windows
without the STP library and I go ahead
and run test asset builder right then
yeah you can already see right you can
see how its kind of got all this empty
space on the top and the bottom and so
on right so get text extent point is
really not it's not giving us the actual
thing we wanted then I can for the
moment I can certainly also go into a
handmade hero and force those things to
be a little bit bigger right particle on
our particle system here when we push
the bitmap and I set that size I can
make those much larger temporarily like
so
right and you can kind of see how much
how much empty space there is there it's
it's pretty tight left to right but up
and down it's just plain ism
you know so it makes me think that maybe
get text extent point is is not doing
the the vertical spacing it's only doing
the horizontal spacing so yeah I guess
what I would say about that is that to
you know easily fixable by priests camp
I don't know if there's an easier way to
do it by maybe trying to convince
Windows not to do that kind of nonsense
there might be a way with some other
text extent thing let's quickly check
but then I'll just do a scan and that
would solve the problem right text
extent point let's take a look
ladies and gentlemen and see what it
says get text extent point hello no rush
here people
no rush it's not like we have to go to
Q&amp;A or anything come on there we go so
let's see it remarks remarks let's see
string with knives recomputed blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah the cafe string
that takes account they took our spacing
okay that's totally fine
the calculus room with we don't it's not
the width as a problem when this
function function returns the Texas sent
extremes of Texas for us on all the same
ways always zero that's true for both
the horizontal dimension the text it's
on the Sooners do statement so it's
basically just broken the graphics
murder is set to do GM advanced
courtesies and whose blah blah blah blah
blah blah I don't see anything that
really talks about
sort of that that other kind of width
spacing so I'm just going to scan it
making our slope get pixel loop even
slower but obviously pretty easy to do
all we need to do here is say you know
what get text extent point super super
not relevant don't care at this point so
we can just even full-on say doesn't
matter right we're not gonna do that
anymore and then we are going to set the
width and height this way okay and we
need to do a little bit more work there
if we do it so so we'll see so okay so
first of all oh you know what though I
take it back we do want to do that just
to bound the region we actually have to
search so that would be good right
so it's start with the width and height
this way and what I'll do is I'll say
okay we've got am in X right min Y and
these are going to be equal to the the
the total width so you know something
like some really huge value right these
are going to be equal to incorrect
things right something like that so as
we go through here when we do our our
loop whenever I see a pixel right if the
pixel is not equal to zero so it's not a
black pixel then I know that this is in
bounds right so what I can do here is
say you know if the Y value you know is
is less than the min Y or I should say
if the min Y is greater than the Y value
the min y equals the Y value right
if the mean x value is greater than the
x value right just this kind of nonsense
something like this right probably do X
first tend to use X first by convention
and so we'll do if the X if the max is
less than right just picking out the
maximum values and that will give me
right just by every time I take a look
here oops that will give me
the specific minimum and maximum XY
coordinates of this of this block right
that makes sense so we don't need to
record anything we actually wouldn't
need to record anything if we didn't
find any pixels that were set right so
what we can do is say if the MINIX if
min X is greater than or equal to max X
then we're good right so we found some
pixels and that's all good we can then
go through and actually do something
here right like so so if that's the case
then we can go through and do something
we need to figure out our width and
height our width and height is obviously
just going to be with equals max X minus
min X height equals max Y minus min Y
now it's not quite right because
remember the max X is the maximum x
value that's filled and the min X is the
minimum x value that's filled so let's
say there was just a pixel the fifth
pixel in was set you would get a 5 for
max x and a 5 for min X well the width
should not be zero in that case it
should be one right so we really want to
add one here to get the correct width
from that subtraction right does that
make sense that's just a little fence
posting or not a fence posting and
off-by-one kind of thing you know you've
got to make sure that you understand
width is not max minus min it's 1 past
max minus min technically okay so if we
do that now we've got the width and
height problem of course is that this is
now this is set wrong but we've actually
computed these so we can really just do
it this way now and know that we've got
the right ranges because we've kind of
computed what our min X and Max X and
min Y and max Y are and all that stuff
right so that should give us what we
want to get that bound back in there you
know so that's a good thing I don't know
why destro is in there destro should not
be in there so there we go just a quick
and dirty little bounce checker
hopefully I programmed it correctly who
knows
there we go and that does look quite a
bit better right that does look like now
we're getting kind of right up to the
edges it still looks kind of awful I
don't know if you can see that but
there's just a lot of jaggies in there I
don't know why we're not seeing any
anti-aliasing from Windows that's kind
of weird right that's just a little bit
on and I'm not sure I'm not sure why
that's happening I don't know if that's
something we're doing or something we're
not doing you know that we need to do
better right so yeah so that's all good
for the fonts of course there is one
more thing that we need to take into
account which is the fact that we
actually want a one pixel empty border
around everything because that is sort
of what's necessary for our fill
routines right and so what we'd like to
do here even maybe perhaps in a sorted
forward of forward-looking sense we'd
want to insert a border around there
which is something like you know okay we
want the MINIX to actually be one less
than it would normally be right we want
everything to be a little bit wider we
want to have that one pixel border so
that would give us our one pixel border
and that would pretty much be everything
that we would need for our for our fonts
and that should just about do it I think
that's that's pretty good for now
so why the anti-aliasing isn't working
I'm not sure I don't know if there's
something we have to do device context
anti-aliasing I'm not sure if there's
any kind of specific thing that needs to
that needs to happen there anti-aliasing
aliasing no windows
let's do text out anti-alias all right I
don't know if there's anything in
particular that we have to do for that I
don't actually know it might be okay it
might be that there's some other thing
that we have to set in there it looks
like they're setting the BK mode to
transparent I don't know if that's
actually necessary or not but you know
we're not doing that right I don't know
if we would need to do a something where
we actually create our own backing
bitmap if there's something wrong with
our backing bitmap I don't know but
that's probably something better left
for another time now it's probably a
better time to go to the Q &amp; A right all
right so yeah if you have any questions
about what we did today again that was
just showing how to not use a library to
extract fonts that's all really and I
feel like I feel like there shouldn't
have been really much mystery there
right it's just a little bit of harkens
back to the whole windows API nonsense
which of course is always a little weird
but nothing too too out of the ordinary
can the fonts have outlines you mean you
mean like if you wanted to add an
outline to the font that a font that
does not normally have an outline I'm
not I'm not
wonder-percent sure what you mean there
what did you mean by backing bitmap what
I mean by backing bitmap is that a
device context always draws into an
actual bitmap right that's well I
shouldn't say always a device context
has the notion of having a bitmap set in
it and that is the bitmap to which it
will draw that bitmap in our case we did
not really create one ourselves manually
we just said create some bitmap that
would be compatible with this device
context right and so the backing bitmap
just means like the bitmap that's you
know backing this device context it's
the one it's this one right and what I
didn't know is do we have to create one
ourselves with specific parameters in
order to get that anti-aliasing right
that's what I did that's what I don't
know right and I you know I really don't
know obviously we can do some
experiments to see we could do we could
double check to see what happens if we
do turn on padlet instead and do set VK
mode device context transparent right we
can try that first and see if that
improves if that actually leads to the
font actually being anti aliased or not
right
the other thing is maybe we're drawing
it too big it might be anti aliased and
it's just our down shrinking that makes
it not anti aliased and to do that and
you know what this would be nice too
because it was slowed down and made here
oh if I were to write this would slow
down our renderer a ton so we could see
them before easily no those really just
don't look anti aliased at all to me
that doesn't look like it has anything
to do with us that's just four on that's
just full-on garbage right there so yeah
I don't know so it doesn't look like
it's that BK mode thing so maybe it is
the problem with the backing bitmap I'm
not sure you know GDI is a mysterious
beast it's pretty random most of the
time so I don't know so I was thinking
that maybe we have to create a different
kind of backing bitmap to to make that
anti-alias properly
Cooper Caleb I love how I see trippy is
easier and arguably better than the
windows API version yeah it's not
surprising really vote on the straw poll
what is the straw poll Oh for the
handmade hero's domain name have you
guys been working on a domain name for
handmade Heroes is that is that what's
going on throw it on the straw poll what
are the names that you guys have
selected handmade heroes that are
handmade coders calm handmade dev calm
artists okay you don't want you don't
want anything that sort of has the sound
Anil in it like artisanal software is
just a bad idea
HMF set website code crafters card org I
don't know handmade dev comm handmade
coders comm both sound good I would say
maybe like are we sure these are the
best ones like should you try should we
try again for a couple another round
right or is the magic went in here so
I'm not gonna vote I'm not gonna vote
handmade heroes comm is currently
leading yeah I think the problem with
that one is people will make it get
confused they'll go to handmade hero org
and wonder why they're not seeing the
products they were trying to find it's
my guess but I could be wrong about that
does does have Windows font have
subscript and superscript support and
therefore so much over bounding also is
the anti alias only stored in the alpha
value by Windows after seeing a pro like
you struggle with this API I understand
the burden you go through with it having
seen SDB yesterday yeah so I mean like
you know I I got that done relatively
quickly because I already knew it all
but imagine coming to that as someone
who had no idea what was going on you'd
go nuts you wouldn't even know what to
look for you'd be like you'd never would
have known the opaque thing you never
would have known after step right the
the anti aliased stuff I don't remember
I think you know so like I don't even
remember what you need to do to do that
I have done that before so it's just
like it's it's really it's really pretty
rough and then
is one of Windows better api's like the
newer AP is like direct2d for example
which they introduced is ten times worse
w WPF or whatever the thing there is the
the other graphics library ten times
worse so this is the best that gets to
as you go up in years to get worse and
worse ask for superscript and subscript
I don't think they do I think normally
you just draw the font smaller do we
have the ability but it's probably just
in leaving room for the sender's and
ascenders or stuff like that it was
probably the line height like it gets
that text extent point probably always
returns the line height to clarify I do
we have the ability to create flat
bitmaps without lines on the characters
that could maybe be colored separately
well we have the ability to we could
pretty easily do that if the font had
that in it and and really all we would
need I guess you know what I don't think
stb supports that though does it I don't
know if STP supports that because you
know what I don't think TrueType
supports that to be completely honest
with you I don't think TrueType supports
that I think fonts that look like they
have outlines in TrueType are actually
just they fill the outline as a shape
and the insides actually Hollow so I
think no we really can't support that
without probably some other font file
format do you know what I mean that
would right but our system the rest of
our system doesn't care so we could you
know if you action drew individual font
characters for us they could have
outlines because they're just bitmaps in
our system so we can have full color
whatever we want right but as far as
Windows is concerned I don't think they
have it which one is worse
GDI her direct input 8 probably a
toss-up probably direct input 8 just cuz
it has comm quarter tries today a good
example of why sometimes using a
libraries okay
I don't know that today is a good
example or a bad example of that it's
more just
it's more just using a library is always
okay if you know enough about the
problem and understand enough about what
you're doing to know that the library
won't create problems for you right
usually the problem with using a library
is that people use libraries that they
don't understand and then it goes
horribly wrong
right because they don't know how to
maintain that library they don't know
what to do if the library has bugs and
if they don't know how to get the
library ported to a different platform
they don't know you know even why the
library might be slow or fast and
certain circumstance they have no idea
right and so using a library is actually
always okay as long as you know what you
are doing right so I don't think using a
library as a problem not knowing what
you're doing is the problem now the sort
of the corollary to that is when you do
know what you're doing you will pretty
rapidly find that most libraries aren't
worth using they are worse than doing it
yourself and so one of the reasons that
I don't use a lot of libraries because
there really aren't very many libraries
that are any good the STB libraries are
definitely a break in that trend FCB
libraries are so good that they usually
do legitimately save you a considerable
amount of time and they don't create
huge headaches for you down the line
when you use a less SCB library you are
often going to save total time on your
project and that is not true of most
libraries so you know if you're talking
about an s-u-v library yeah a lot of
times that ends up being a good choice
other libraries oftentimes not so much
but in either case the important thing
is to be confident enough in the domain
of the library and familiar enough with
how the library is constructed and how
it works to know that you are not making
a mistake and so that's what I would say
and on handmade hero the reason we don't
use libraries is not because there
aren't libraries we could use it would
be good because like I showed you stb
library is good the reason we don't use
libraries on them right here is because
part of the point of a Mahiro is to show
people how to code all the parts of the
game and if we just use some library to
do it
then we wouldn't know that and so that's
why I wanted to restrict the use of
libraries to only being in the asset
processor because in the game itself I
wanted to show all of it would direct
right or ClearType help out the it with
the engine the anti-icing does work
through this path I've done it before I
think you just need to do a couple other
settings ignore this if you're already
doing this but why not ship the mono
bitmap as part of the asset file instead
of the much larger RGB bitmap because do
we care like do we care about that
footprint space right that is a space
optimization and it's a space
optimization that that makes our code
more complex because now every time you
load a bitmap you have to know whether
it's a mono bitmap or regular bitmap and
you have to either then add code to our
renderer to handle mono or you have to
convert onload which takes more time and
makes your loading code slower so all of
those trade-offs you would have to go
okay am I making a good decision here
when I add this optimization for model
bitmaps and I would suggest that since
fonts are pretty much the only place
we'll probably use them there may be a
couple other like maybe particle systems
it would just be a really bad idea more
code complexity slower potential load
times or more complexity in the renderer
for what pay off slightly fault smaller
asset file size not feeling it right and
plus if we run our code through an LZ
compressor it would probably eliminate
it would shrink it down to a mono bitmap
automatically because every entry is
going to be 544 replicated values right
so the LZ compressor would eat that for
breakfast
I'm a cornbread people are liking the
idea of handmade dev yeah it sounds kind
of cool handmade dough dev seems pretty
rememberable and distinct from the main
hammy hero org site got a good name got
a good ring to it hammy dev I like it
how often do you regret using API
library and backup writing your own
implementation when you are fast paced
as you may be this sometimes is better
when your knowledge of the problem is
sufficient I basically always write
everything myself these days because my
experience in my programming career has
been that I have always regretted using
third-party
anything software tools libraries
everything I pretty much find they're
all garbage the STB libraries are like
one singular shining example of things I
have not regretted using but they are
few and far between so like you know I
pretty much regret every third-party
thing I've ever used right up until
today using like Microsoft's compiler if
I had time to read a compiler I'd
replace it right and the debugger I'd
like I'd replace la so it's just not
good enough I don't like the lying on
them and they get worse over time is the
other thing right like every time I go
and have to move to a new version for
some reason everything breaks and it's
weird and they broke something and it's
slower and all this stuff right so yeah
I have total I have total NIH but it's
not like I was born with it like I I got
it from having been so disappointed in
so many things for so long so now my
rule is basically the things that I have
right now I use I never add new things
into the mix and I'm slowly trying to
replace all of the things that I
currently have to use that a third party
with my own stuff with the possible
exception of the SDB libraries because
like I said they've been like one of the
few things where I've been pretty darn
happy about my decision to use them
what GUI toolkit do you recommend I
don't know I don't have very much
experience with them I do know that one
of the guys I can't remember I think was
from Media Molecule maybe recently
opened sourced in immediate mode
graphical user interface library that he
said was kind of following the idea that
I had put forth for how to do immediate
mode graphical user interfaces as a
thing and people seem to really like it
so you know maybe that's good but I
don't have much preference to experience
it so I couldn't say but people seem to
like it so I suppose the kid would
ClearType quality instead of anti-us
play make a difference
well ClearType quality isn't what we
want that actually plays with the color
channels like right clear type is so you
know an LCD panel so you know an LCD
panel it typically has like a little
pixel right a pixel element is actually
like looks something like maybe this or
something like RGB where it's actually
got like a bar of red a bar of green and
a bar of blue or something and this is
not really right like but there's
various ways that this is done right so
what happens is it means that when you
have two pixels together you actually
have some sub pixel precision in the
color channels meaning if I wanted to
render a font that was aligned like this
I could actually make a blue fringe here
and then fill the RG and B here and get
a font that was in that looked like it
was positioned at a greater horizontal
fidelity than the number of pixels like
so in some sense you have 3x the
resolution right horizontally
that's what ClearType does that'd be
awful for what we do because remember
we're resizing bitmaps and stuff we
don't want any
they're fringing or those will pop out
like a sore thumb so we really really
really don't want cleartype to happen
under any circumstances in our Baker
that would be like really really bad I
guess we're done I guess that's it for
the day folks that is it for the day and
you know what that's it for the week
that's all she wrote
we're off tomorrow and Friday it's a
short week on hand mahira what are you
gonna do alright everyone thank you very
much for joining me for another episode
of handmade hero hopefully that gave you
some perspective on just how good the
STD libraries are extracting fonts with
windows looks about like it probably
would look using other font libraries as
well just kind of a mess and tons of
function calls and all these other sorts
of things right STB library is always
good and of course in this situation
also they're purpose-built for what we
need so that's an even bigger bonus it
means that you know we don't have to
fuss with with sort of setting up things
like drawing context and stuff right so
there you go that's how to do it so now
you know how to extract fonts as well
and maybe on Monday I'll do some will
fix the anti-icing so it's kind of done
so you can actually switch the pass and
maybe also the font size thing we can do
just so it's it's pretty symmetric
between both paths for anyone who wants
to play with either one so that's about
it and like I said I'm off for the week
so I will see you guys back here on
Monday hopefully you will all have a
great long weekend full of coding fun I
know I have plenty of coding I will be
doing this weekend as well
so until Monday have fun with that in
the meantime if you'd like to follow
along with the series source code you
can always pre-order the game at hand
made here
it comes to the source code so you can
download it every night after I finished
coding and play around it yourself we
also have a patreon page you want
support the video series we have a forum
site we can get community ports to Mac
and Linux community annotated episode
guide and of course a forum where you
can ask questions in case you have
questions about the source code and then
we also have a tweet bot tells you when
the the show will be live before trying
to catch it live and that's pretty handy
because especially like with this week
where it's a weird schedule it's just an
easy way to kind of know what's going
down when the schedules abnormal so
check that out that's it for me I will
see you guys back here on Monday have
fun programming and until Monday I will
see you guys on the Internet take it
easy everyone