welcome to hand made here sure we could
a complete-game live on stream yesterday
so I'd want to do some camera work
yesterday but I actually ended up going
and doing something the entities this
creation system because it turns out we
had not you know our world generation
code is still pretty rudimentary right
we haven't spent a whole lot of time on
it it's something to spend more time on
as we go forward but we really just
haven't spent a lot of time in there
because we haven't been focusing on that
and so one of the things that we didn't
have was the ability to tell the world
generation look I want to place an
entity next to another entity or these
two entities have to be in this
relationship to each other like this one
asked me to the north of that one or
this one has to be above this one or
whatever so we added that yesterday and
it went pretty well and the reason that
I added that was because I wanted to
have a test for the camera system to see
if you could do things like place a
square that you hop on and it would zoom
in and then hop off and it zooms out so
for things like talking to another
character or things like that I don't
know whether we're actually going to do
this in the actual game again it's just
exploratory and this is an educational
stream so when I see opportunities to do
something in the codebase I do them
right that's generally the rule so I
don't necessarily know how much we're
going to do with this with special
cameras we may decide that they're too
distracting or they don't really work
very well from the standpoint of the
player being able to you know the player
doesn't really want to do that they
don't want to have this happen to the
camera but I want to put it into the sea
and so since I knew that we would want a
bunch of stuff in the game that had to
do with entity placement separate from
this particular problem I figured it
couldn't hurt to put this in because
we'll use the placement part even if we
don't use the camera part so I'm going
to go ahead and show you what I'm
talking about I believe at the end of
the last dream we just tested this out
by saying that we needed to have a cat
placed to the side of I'm sorry above
each of the little orphan heads we put
down
and if you see it appears to work just
fine like there's a cat above each of
these right you can see the cat each
time and and so that worked great so now
what I want to do is I want to push
forward on that and instead all right
let's create a thing that makes a place
we can have the character stand so we'll
have an orphan and we'll have them
facing downward and to the south of the
orphan we will have a square you can hop
on but zooms in okay so that's what I
want to do in the world generation code
right now so if I go into handmade prj
and I just rebuild everything so I know
we're starting from a good clean place
I'm gonna go into the world gent code
and I'm gonna go into the entity gem
code and I'm gonna see if I can make
that happen now we sort of have a mix of
code in here this is sort of the old
code that'll probably go away eventually
and this is sort of the new style code
where we basically have a callback
system where we can let's not only call
back it's more like a service system
where we basically say this is the code
you can use to create any of this type
and they're interchangeable so you can
pass a pointer to add cat at orphan and
whatever and so in here we want to add a
talk square basically like a thing that
says here is something to say and I
don't really know exactly how we're
gonna do the talking part of it because
that's really not the part that I'm
focusing on at the moment so I'm not
sure what I want in terms of the talking
but I am sure what I want in terms of
the camera and so that's the part that
I'm actually going to try and create now
if you look so this is going to be a for
lack of a better term a conversation
Square so we're just gonna call that an
add conversation and in some sense you
know maybe I should use the more the
term bark
well barks not really what it is so I am
gonna use the the term conversation for
now it's not a conversation because the
user doesn't really
responses it's not a dialogue tree but
in the end of teen it's not really
industry bark is used to refer to
something that is said out of hand by an
NPC so for example if you might be
playing a stealth suitor and a chem PC
is patrolling and you make a sound and
the NBC goes what's that or something
right or you know maybe just the NPC's
just patrolling and it goes gosh I'm
bored or I wonder what's going on over
there or things like that right just
just random stuff they say that doesn't
really have a specific part in the
narrative right it's not like something
that a scriptwriter was thinking went in
some kind of a story progression or
narrative arc it was just something that
gets recorded and can be said at any
time given a certain circumstance like
you know guard is doing this or a guard
is idle or whatever so it's not really
that either because the player is
hopping on to it so I'm gonna avoid the
term Bart for now and I'm just gonna say
look I don't know we're gonna call it
we're gonna call a conversation for now
and we'll just have to leave it there
because I don't have a better word for
it so inside room genna's well you can
see in here so we make right here you
can see me making a room camera right
and that it's just a area that says what
happens to the camera in that room right
that's all it does and it's it's how we
move the camera around in that way and
so what I want to do here is I want to
have another way of creating one of
those cameras and what do they do is I'm
gonna look at what I create here I with
respect to how the camera gets created
differently for the special camera as
for the room camera and then I'm
probably gonna do is merge those two
things together so I'm gonna like take
the camera the room cam stuff and then
the special camp stuff and I'll probably
make a utility function called create
camera volume that does all of this
stuff I and I'm gonna go from there
right
all right so if you look at what's
happening here we've got sort of a
camera for the conversation I do want to
add an entity for that I don't want to
send any flags on it because it doesn't
collide it doesn't take up space it's
not standing anywhere it's just a region
if I set the collision volume for it
what I'm going to want to do is create a
tile sized collision volume right
so whatever tile I'm on I want to create
something that occupies that entire tile
so that when people are on it it does
this operation green slot we may want to
do something with but I'm not sure right
and then when we call this function here
get camera offset Z for dim that is the
thing that tells us how far we zoom in
on rooms right and so looking at this
our minimum is like 13 that we zoom and
so I might just set that offhand right
now to 10 and furthermore I might even
do something a little bit more specific
here which is to say maybe I'll make
that a call get camera offset Z for
close-up and that way I know that when I
call that I anyone who was trying to do
something like that will call this and
then that way I know where it comes from
you know just to make it a little
clearer so there's not just a 10 sitting
around in the code and in the future we
might be able to pass parameters here to
the extent that we care about them so
we'll see right so anyway if you look at
what happens here the special brain
special brain slot for type brain room
you know what I mean that is not really
something that we want to specify here
because this isn't a room entity and so
if you look at the brain oops I hit the
caps lock key there if you look at the
types of brains that there are this may
be something that we mark and we're you
know where we maybe just want to say
like this is a
[Music]
you know some kind of camera brain thing
and the reason that I might want to do
that is because inside the simulation
system when we're updating the camera
for a particular movement of the entity
what you can see in here is normally we
just look to see whether this thing has
any kind of camera behavior set to it
and in the future we may want to just
only look at entities that have brain
type camera associated with them so
again I don't really know to what extent
I want to do that but I might want to do
that I on the other hand another thing
we could do is this where we say that
it's a conversation type so again I
really don't know what we want to do
here there's just things we could do
here at the moment I guess I will just
say hey maybe I don't really need to do
either of those things just yet I'll
just set the camera behavior to change
the offset and we'll call it a day
because at you know just looking through
that code there I just don't see much
reason to so those are the things I
considered and I guess I can't really
say that there's much reason to do them
so I think I'm gonna just avoid it for
now so if I look at how this is is
working here what I now need to do is
just get the coordinates into play and
so if we look at what's happening here
in terms of what gets passed when
entities are created what you can see
inside the world gencode what I meant to
say was really gencode what you can see
inside the room gencode is when we go in
here and create pending entities we are
gonna pass them the location and we're
also going to pass them a reference that
says this is what you're standing on and
so we can do a couple different things
here but at the moment I suppose the
easiest thing to do would really just be
to do a rectangle Center dimension where
we create a box that's just kind of
based around that p-value that we get
past so inside the MV gencode here where
you see us getting this p-value and then
the standing on value we would start
with that p-value as the center of the
box that we're gonna create excuse me
and then we create a dimension for it so
here's the dimension that we want to
make and I don't really know how big we
want these to be at the moment so I'm
just gonna create something that's small
like that I'm gonna give the dim here
and since we wanted this to be resting
on the ground P what we would do is say
we want to create a offset in Z that
happens to be whatever half of this is
so that it's basically a rectangle off
of the base right and I don't know if we
have a math for a grounded rectangle
like that so you know I'm just doing it
manually here but in the future we
should probably make some math for that
I'm guessing because that's a pretty
typical thing to want to do so if we set
the collision volume equal to this we
set the behavior equal to offset and we
set the offset equal to whatever that
close up zoom would be then when we
place the entity again in here I think
we don't really have to do that we can
just say look place the entity at the P
that it's at like this I think that's
really all we have to do and again I
don't really need to call that anything
other than entity in this case because
we're just creating that one so if we
add a conversations this will add the
close up for that conversation and it
won't do anything else though right so
it's worth noting that that's the only
thing that will do let me go ahead and
expose this series so people can call it
as necessary also don't ask me why these
aren't coming first because normally
they do so that's what that's supposed
to look like but for some reason it
didn't so anyway that's the long and
short of it now what we would need to do
is just request if that thing be added
now what I want to do before we do that
though is right now we would never see
that thing
so it'd be really hard to debug so
inside enemy I'm also gonna make it so
that we turn on drawing the bounds of
these things and so I don't really
remember what this code has to do here
but I'm pretty sure that it has changed
because for pushing volume outline we
kind of need a way to actually make this
thing to actually draw the thing at the
location it's supposed to be because the
entity transform isn't taking effect
anymore so I would need to create an
offset rectangle that like moves this
thing to the location where the entity
actually is in the world which is you
know the enemy ground pay for example
right and so just creating something
that draws those outlines first I want
to make sure I have that because
otherwise I would have no idea where
anything was in the world so I just want
to see what's going on with that and so
here you can see me drawing those
collision volumes and what you can see
from me drawing the collision volumes
right as you can see that every room has
one and the player head has one that's
just kind of a residual that's left in
there we don't use it right now but in
the future we probably will for things
like whether or not people hit you and
things like that so if you just look at
what's going on there we get exactly
what you expect and so now what I'm
looking to try and do is I want to see
when we make this change I want to see
the orphan have a collision box to its
south right that's what I'm looking for
and so I'm drawing that because I since
it's an invisible region that's just
going to control the camera maybe the
whole thing works the first time and the
camera zooms in but if it doesn't I'm in
a position where I wouldn't even know
whether the entity got created and I
don't want to start from that so I'd
like to have that code path working as
something that we have now you can also
see in here these if ones if zeros those
are things we may want to add to the HUD
eventually as well because we have live
code reloading it's free for me to just
toggle the if on and off but it's one of
those things that it's just like maybe
better in the HUD cuz it's faster you
don't have to go through
recompile to turn it on and off right so
and because it's pretty low cost to
check right okay so moving along if I
went into world gen now and we look at
when we create an orphan so in here
we've got like a place orphan call and
we're adding an orphan in here we add a
cat as a constraint and in here we say
look North I'm gonna change that to
South I'm also gonna add a tag to the
orphan and I'm gonna say that the facing
direction for the orphan is going to be
0.75 F times tau right and that's just
giving me rotation around the circle so
the thing will be facing downward
because I want the orphan facing
downward now remember tau I have a long
ramp that I've been building up about
tau and pi before I started handmade
hero and well when we got to this when
we talked about PI in tau on handmade
hero I'd really didn't have a strong a
pain about it I've been putting at PI
most of my career just used to it people
kind of made the case for tau and they
have a good case so I said well we'll
use tau on handmade hero I actually ever
ramps on pi and tau coming up it's that
both PI and tower stupid and we
shouldn't be using either of them
and so that's coming up and I will
probably post a blog post about it but
we may go through and rip those out of
handmade hero after I do that rant so
putting that aside because you don't
really need to adjust that right now I'm
just going to go ahead and set that
facing direction in here so that it's
facing right way and then in here we
have this tag I don't need to tag for
this and I'm just gonna say add
conversation and so now this should put
a conversation entity to the south of
the orphan and then I should be able to
see that entity as a collision box that
I can then go and step on right and so
that's what we're doing and so what I'm
seeing here is you can see that that
collision box looks nowhere near where
it should be right so I feel that that
is probably just highly erroneous like
I've obviously
in the wrong place where something so
let's see what's going on there and this
is exactly why I did that right this is
why I want to see it because I knew that
this would be a likely place to have
that error oh and you can see what's
going on here this is not supposed to be
p+ anything this collision volume is
relative to the entity's location so
adding the P would effectively add the P
twice so that was just a typo so let's
see if they're in the correct place now
right looks better to say the least and
so now when we hop into those I don't
actually know to what extent
we're actually triggering those properly
but now I can actually at least see that
they were placed in the correct position
and now I just want to know whether I'm
inside one or not right and I don't
actually know that I don't know whether
that case is getting triggered or
whether it isn't so the first thing I
want to do is see whether that case is
in fact being triggered or not so let's
start there I may need to recompile in
debug mode because this will be hard to
step through in fact let me just go
ahead and do that right now
if we go back here I'll put myself in a
position where I can i where the case
should trigger and so if I in here go to
the builds and I just say look give me a
debug build it should keep the state of
the game the same so we should just now
have the debug mode so this the speed of
updating should slow down dramatically
but the game is still in the exact same
position that it was so now if I go back
here and I say look tell me if we hit
this case right it should stop here
regardless because it should stop on the
room that I'm in and so the question is
just do we ever get the SPECIAL camera
showing up right and so I'm not sure I
guess I have to kind of see whether the
brain slot type equals brain slot room
or not so it loads I got to see when we
stop are we getting this happening right
and then when we are getting that I also
need to know like when we do in the
overlaps entity
I kind of need to see neither these
should be set so I need to kind of set
it to pass only I need to look at only
in pass so you can see we're never
getting here right we're not getting an
overlap of any kind right now one of the
interesting things about this and I
guess I don't I guess I should check
this a little more Sicily so when we're
doing entity and test them these so this
is the player I believe right so any
like entity is the thing that we're
passing in here right so entity this is
the players location or represents the
players location right it's this and if
you look at the collision volume what
you can see is the player doesn't
actually have one right it that there
isn't one it's just zero zero zero right
so you're testing to see whether this PE
overlaps the you know this this tests
entity in any way and what that means is
we might be in a case where we have to
enlarge this thing a little bit more in
order to actually capture the non
collision entity of the player because
it's actually a single point so looking
at this when we do this here what I
think I want to do is I want to do an ad
radius call and I just want to expand
this thing out by like a safety margin
because it's not gonna necessarily
include the ground point in its entirety
if I don't and so I just want to take
that out of the equation
I think it's that actually yeah so I
want to make sure that those boxes in
you know include that much you can see
it's much lower because we're in debug
build now so our lighting here is it's
taking all the time I should have a way
of turning the lighting off for debug
builds until we actually have it faster
and so now you can see those include the
ground a little bit right you can see
those collision volumes including the
ground a little bit and so now I want to
see if we actually can trigger that pass
case now where the players position
is on the base there so that basically
and so what you can see now is we
actually do get that right we do get
that overlap now and that was just
because again we did wait since the
player doesn't have a volume right now
and you could argue we probably should
give give the player one but because the
player doesn't have a volume right now
that test is only gonna work if the
volume actually encompasses the entire
place where the point could be and when
the player hops into it
if the player hops into it and that
point was actually a like right on the
the minimum point of the box that might
not be considered in I don't remember
how we wrote this code but for floating
point accuracy purposes we wouldn't want
to rely on that anyway so you want to
sort of capture a wider area to make
sure that no matter where that point is
floating point precision wise it's it's
always gonna actually be considered
inside so now we should get that special
camera call
happening and the special camera should
now be set if we look at what that's
actually set to for camera behaviors we
should be able to see the special camera
say that it wants an offset right so in
here there's a camera behavior yeah
right there and the offset should be set
to ten and it is right and so if we come
in and actually use that how did we jump
back up there
what okay there we go
no no what just happened there that's a
little bit weird oh wait no that I'm
sorry that's exactly what happen we
finished this loop first before we
process anything no that's all good I'm
not freaked out so when we checked such
a camera now we should do is this should
override the location and offset and it
does and so that's exactly what I wanted
to have happen right so now what we need
to do is just adjust those settings
potentially meaning that like you know
we may want to change how the zoom what
the zoom is focused on or how far in the
zoom goes but at least now we've got
that element of the camera stuff working
and so we can play around with that a
little bit more as we go so now you can
kind of see I hop in here and it zooms
in that's not enough of a zoom I wanted
a more egregious zoom so I wanted
something that was going to be really
absurd so in terms of egregious zooms
what I would really like here is
probably something just you know that's
like really really out there you know
just just just really bizarre and so let
me now try hopping on it and see what I
think of that so you know I'm gonna go
in to talk to this orphan and we get a
zoom like that yeah now you can see we
also have some problems with with the
way our camera interface is working in
terms of the that near and far plane so
when we zoom into things you can see
that the near and far planes don't keep
up properly so that's another thing
we're gonna want to make sure key you
know we're gonna want to make sure we
solve that in another in a good way but
this is what I had in mind so you know
I'm in this room doing stuff if I want
to talk to this entity it zooms in like
this and you know does some kind of
conversation nonsense here right now the
problem that I'm gonna have and one of
the things that I need this is why I
said we yesterday I alluded to this what
I really want this box to be is I want
it to sort of encompass
I want this offset to be something a
little bit more based on well you know
what here I don't really know how I want
to solve this going forward because it
depends how flexible we want to be but
let's suppose we're hard coding our
conversations to be that facing
direction then it's pretty easy to do
because the camera offset Y can just get
modified by some value so I can say
something like this and then we do that
offset right and I don't remember what
this is a plus or minus so I don't
remember which way we interpret the
offset but this would allow me to focus
on the conversation offset a little bit
more like so and that's really more the
way I want it because because you want
to see the person you're talking to and
you should kind of be at the bottom
right so that's the kind of zoom that
we're more looking for here I and once
we've got that you know we just need to
think about whether we need to
parameterize that conversation in some
other way to make it so that if you were
talking to someone to the side of you
that offset didn't you know wasn't gonna
happen that way or something so again
I'm not really sure exactly how I want
that to go but this is good enough for
now and so what will happen is when we
hop on these we'll want to have the
thing that actually puts up the line of
dialogue and we can look at doing that
but right now the important thing to
focus on is just that camera code and so
now I think I have all of the things
that I want in terms of cases for the
camera code and so now the rest of the
day we should be able to work on
improving the quality of the camera code
and again I listed kind of what all
those are but just to give a recap
I want to damp out any like unnecessary
movement of the camera like following
the hopping I don't want that I want it
to be smoother I want to try and fix the
interpolation of the Alpha clipping so
that when you zoom in on things the
Alpha clipping doesn't go ahead of you
right because that's a problem right now
and you can see that really clearly in
this case
there it was there and here it is again
here right it's that slow interpolation
of the Alpha fade distance really
doesn't work with the speed of the
camera movement so we have to get those
two things locked together better and
then yeah where you can see like it's
really bad there right and so we want
those interpolations to happen
concurrent so that you don't you know
you want to like that right what I'm
doing right now you don't want to do the
other thing so we have to fix those and
then the other thing that we want to do
is we want to we want to make sure that
we have a debug camera again and we
don't have that right now right we don't
have any way to go into debug camera
mode so those are plenty of things to
keep us busy for the rest of the day at
least on the camera and so I'm gonna
dive in on those and get working on
those right now I'm gonna tackle those
in the order that I feel like they're
actually existing right now in terms of
problems for me Oh actually there's one
other thing we have to do we also want
to have something for the camera where
we can solve for the light volume like
right now you can see the line where the
lighting stops we want something that
actually correctly takes a camera
frustum and puts all the things that are
should be lit into it and right now we
don't have that either
right so yeah so really what I need to
do is tackle these in that order and
like I said what I want to do here is I
want to focus first on that weird
interpolation problem so the first thing
we're gonna focus on is getting this to
work properly the camera looks just fine
but the the Alpha plane clipping the
Alpha value totally gets wonky
especially if you are hopping in here
for the first time from like something
where the Alpha was really far before
and then you kind of hop in here and do
a zoom quickly you can see you get a lot
of problems there so I'm gonna start
with that code and see what we can do
about that so inside the sim region we
have
the way in which the camera is getting
updated and you can see in here
for update camera for any movement which
we were just in you can see in here
where we set up the things that we want
to know we actually have like explicit
ideas about what we want the focus Minzy
and focus Maxie to be and we know where
we think the camera should be and then
we had some rather crappy interpolation
set up here where we would interpolate
those things and we just did a
proportional derivative controller for
this which i think is the only thing we
really could figure out that would was
going to work in a reasonable amount of
time that wasn't going to be a huge math
adventure and then here all we did at
the end of the stream when we were doing
that is just slapped a proportional
derivative controller on that as well
the target expected focus values and so
the question is is there some way of
measuring this so that the Z
interpolation of this and the Z
interpolation of these is more
commensurate because really what we want
to know there to a large extent is we
want to know that our Z clipping values
so our Minzy and our maxi for like the
room focus on the enemy focus right we
want to know that those values are
tracked essentially one to one with the
motion of the camera and the problem is
we can't necessarily map them directly
to the camera because we don't have the
requisite information for that at least
I don't think we do right
meaning because we don't really know
exactly what the cameras location like
we don't really know where we were
coming from because that's constantly
sort of changing in a way it's
continuous we don't know how quickly we
can set the target expected focus min
and Max to be their new values but or
rather the expected focus min and Max we
don't know how quickly we can set them
to the target because we don't know how
much the camera has to move before those
things are valid right we know how far
away we are from it but that's all we
know and so I'm not sure how to really
measure that right and so that's a
little bit tough now there are some
things that we do know so we do know for
example we do know if we wanted to make
these things be in line more
appropriately we do know that we could
eliminate some parts of the camera in
terms of updating these right so if we
were to let's say right that we were to
remove the expected focus velocities so
what if we just got rid of those
velocities because let's say that we
just don't think we're gonna be able to
quite make these to be harmonious if we
constantly have to keep matching their
speeds or something right so if we were
going to do that then the first thing
that we could say here is look if the
camera has arrived at its target right
which we know is true because you can
see these two cases are different right
so here's the one where we stop and we
lock the camera to the target if that's
the case then we want in here to have an
expected focus min and expected focus
max we want those two values to be hard
set there as well right
meaning the target and the expected
should equal each other at the time when
the camera comes to rest at the final
location right so we kind of know that
that that happens right so now the
question is kind of like well so if I
look here the question is what should I
do about updating these in the case
where we haven't done that right so in
the case where we're still updating the
cameras motion right the cameras Z Delta
or whatever else you want to talk about
that
where I'm moving the camera in Z still
potentially I want these to be in
operation right and so I kind of want
the amount that we update those to be
proportional to how far we are from the
target in a sense right meaning the
update step for the expected minimum
maximum values I want that to be
commensurate with how far we think we
have to go right to get there so what I
could do is say what is the proportion
in Z in fact you know what I think I can
do this pretty cleanly so what I'm gonna
try to do here is I'm just gonna
mathematically tie these two things
together more explicitly we know what
the Delta P value is
right and so after this is done like
after we take that step we would then
know how much of a step we took relative
to the the Z value of these two things
trying to think of exactly how I suppose
I need to actually keep that in place so
I'm gonna I guess I will leave it this
way um but basically what I want to do
here is I want to update these two based
on the ratio of their difference so
their ratio of their difference to the
reach to the step size being taken for
the length right so in here I'm going to
take these lengths so I'm gonna probably
bite the square root here so I'm gonna
say Delta P Len and I'm gonna say total
Delta P Len and so here I'm just saying
look this is the length of those two
things I can still say if the Delta P
length is less than the total then we'll
to do the step otherwise we won't right
so that's all good but then what I want
to do is in here if we're going to take
a step then what I want to do is I want
to do the Delta Minzy and the Delta max
see I want these to be computed based on
that ratio okay so there I've got the
target Minzy that's what I'm trying to
get to I've got the expected focus Minzy
so this is the range that I have to
cover to get from where I'm at from in
focus II to where I want to be right and
I can create a ratio between that and
the difference between these two right
so this is the
the length difference right maybe I'll
call this the piece ban right and so
that's just this is how far I have to
cover in terms of my total length right
and so the difference between those two
amounts of coverage I can use to figure
out and how my dress is I know that I
have a certain amount of distance to
cover to move the camera from one point
to another I also know I have a certain
amount I want to cover in terms of focus
Minzy maxi I just need to take the Delta
I'm doing in one and map it to a Delta
in the other so I know they will always
arrive at the same time does that make
sense
now all right you know what I take it
back
I over complicated that in a bad way
the focus Minzy and maxi only depend on
camera Z distance so actually we should
only be measuring the Z distance anyway
so here technically I can just do Z span
instead and what that means is if I take
the total Delta P Z that's how far I
have to go in Z that's really all I need
so then the Delta ratio here so the the
amount I'm going to go versus the amount
I have to go is just obvious right it's
just that so that tells me how to map
from a spacial motion right because it
says here is the total spatial distance
and here's the distance I'm going to go
right I can use that ratio to map things
that aren't spatial that we're in the
focus Minzy focus Maxie I can use it to
map there Delta's right does that make
sense and so setting up the map here if
I wanted to know what the if I wanted to
know how
far to go here I just need to create the
spans for each of these so this is the
Minzy span right there's the difference
there that's the direction I'm going and
that can be negative right that's
actually fine because it's allowed to be
negative since we can take steps in a
negative direction so I don't care if
there's a sign in there that's totally
fine right this will never be negative
because these are lengths so they have
to be positive right
oh well no that's not true so this
actually needs to be an absolute value
because we're checking the Z's directly
right yes problem I don't really because
that Z will also be going in the same
direction so actually I know that those
are both the same signs so it'll always
cancel that's a little nasty but you see
my point right so now what I need to do
is just from these two spans I need to
figure out how to produce one of these
that like a delta for these so I need
the Delta Minzy and the Delta maxi there
right so I just need to be able to do
that mapping so I want something in the
focus space here right I want something
in focus min space and I have a delta
which is Delta P Z I have that's the
amount that I'm actually going in space
right so this is the percentage of the
distance I'm going right I'm going this
Delta % right I mean you could think of
it as this I'm going that much so if I
just take the total amount I have to
travel in either of these and multiply
it by that value then I will get the
amount I should move to make sure that
the these two are commensurate right now
I know that's a little Squinkie but you
get my point
right
so hopefully we can tune that and to get
correct Z that updates at the same rate
the cameras updating so we don't have
that problem
right and you can see already it cleaned
up all of that lag that we were seeing
in the Alpha plane clipping now let's do
the real test let's go down the stairs
and make sure that that actually works
because that's the place where the Z
clipping really gets stressed right so
let's say I hop down here beautiful
right um and so again so all I did there
right is I just used the math to tie
those two values together and you can
you can see oh it's just it's just great
so that just removes all of that from
from the equip you can see why I
preferred that solution right by tying
the interpolations directly together I
don't have to fiddle with a bunch of
knobs to try and make sure that I got it
right and now it just can't be wrong you
know what I mean
because those Z values are locked
together so as long as they're set to
reasonable things that their start and
end point I don't have to worry about
what they do in between so much right
and so that's really yeah so that's
really great I'm really happy with that
I think that's that's very nice all
right so let's move on to other stuff
here here in the second error debug
camera probably wants to be its own day
so I'm not going to do debug camera next
well maybe whoa what did i do there
all right so to be fair maybe this has a
bad bug in it somewhere
you know what if this Z is zero this
would blow up so there is one issue here
which is that this code path really
wants to exist right
meaning if these two things if the total
Delta P Z is not at least a nominal
amount like is if this is going to be
some fraction really fractional thing
then we just hard set it right because
that's a divide there and this value
can't be 0 and it might be so we need to
take precautions when you're going to
interpolate from one place to another
and the Z's are identical we need to
just say ok we just use we pretend we're
already at the target right I think
that's all correct so looking at these
two I want to say this now that it's got
that check can also be pulled out so I
think this is also correct meaning we
can just always look at the total Delta
P and use that to make our decision
about whether we're going to do either
of the two interpolations and we don't
need to nest them and that way we don't
need to repeat this case twice so I
think that's just a little cleaner yeah
so I think that's good that seems good
up but no that was not good
Oh helps it that that goes the correct
directions basically I said if it's a
large change don't interpolate it like
okay if their way around their case
alright let's just double-check that we
don't have any issues there just try to
slide it around here a little bit
yes very good positive development
all right so this is feeling great I'm
loving this the camera feels really nice
[Music]
again there's a little wobble in there
that's the thing that I wanted to go
dress now right is that I wanted that
smoothing I don't want it to do that I
feel like the Z distance is a little
high right now so if you're on this step
I don't think you should be seeing that
so I feel like the actual clip Z
distance is not quite set correctly so
like in here right where we're setting
these I feel like the alpha distance is
is probably better set to something a
little lower you know
problem is that's really touchy with how
far that goes let me see what I think of
this
I'll play with this a little bit
so don't really like that much I think
maybe what I want to do here is say so
when you're on the ground like this the
problem is these things have a Z
variance in them and so as you go up and
down it actually is changing that alpha
clip with every height change there and
so it's a little bit tricky for me to
think about how that should really go
[Music]
I don't know
but I'm tempted to just leave it as it
is because I like the effect and if
there's occasionally things that sort of
alpha in or out we could probably do
some clamping where we where we
threshold the alpha values if need be
sorry I'm just trying to observe here I
have nothing to say at the moment
because I'm watching
yeah so I don't know I think those
values might be a little better
275 five might be more my preference
it's hard to say let me crank it up to
like 75 and see what I feel like about
that it's a little more gradual maybe
I'll leave it there so 275 75 I think
might be my my sweet spot there in terms
of like the camera alpha min alpha max
so I might change those we were using
those I'm going to use 275 and then 75
just feels a little better and they
don't get some of that ringing so I
think I'm gonna leave it there and that
feels pretty good all right so back to
our story let's talk about how we're
gonna deal with some of that damping and
some other things that potentially might
want to do so in terms of the sort of
that buoyant motion what I think we want
to do here there's a couple different
things we can do right one is we could
track the player's position separate
from the hopping but the problem with
that is it it will if we go that route
and I sort of talk I talked about this
thing a little bit in the pre stream
when someone asks this question if we
start adding additional information in
there but like things that are like
artificial things that tell the camera
what to do so you know in this case
we're we're saying this is a
conversation here's where you should
zoom that's a cinematic thing you're
trying to say I'm okay with that trying
to eliminate the hopping the bounce in
the camera for the hopping by adding
something that says here's where the
player actually is ground point is or
whatever
I like that less and the reason is
because then you constantly are creating
these special cases that we're gonna
have to
through and deal with separately such as
hopping down the stairs right we then
have to say okay do we just like
linearly move the player or what if
there's like some crazy like things that
can hop on height-wise in here or
whatever and so I just I really feel
like I don't want that I don't really
want to have this problem of having to
constantly have an out-of-band
communication channel to the camera
that's gonna be something I have to
worry about
so what I'd rather do is first and if we
have to do it I'm fine with that meaning
if we end up having to do it that's okay
if I can't solve a problem in the way
that I would like I'm okay with solving
it in the problem way that I wouldn't
like right I mean I'll do what I have to
do to get it to work okay but first I
would rather see if I can make a filter
that just only looks at the Claire's
actual position and then comes up with
the answer with nothing but that you
know what I mean so that's what I'm
gonna what I would like to try and do
now we're losing some frames here what
who's of course it's just compute light
propagation it's always just compute
light propagation we gotta we gotta come
up with the world's fastest lighting
algorithm look at that takes all our
time look at that look at this look look
at how much lighting we're doing it's
nuts we'll figure it out don't worry
don't you worry we'll figure it out uh
so anyway yeah let's go ahead and think
through this some more and and see if we
can't come up with a filter that will
just work and that way we can just be
done with it and we don't have to
constantly be feeding all these little
bread crumbs to the camera code be like
hey by the way don't really follow this
motion because it's not important and
all the other stuff so if we wanted to
look at the filt filtering that we could
do here
what I might suggest is saying well
first thing we can do is we don't really
have to update the location of the
camera if the player isn't too far from
where it would have been already right
so one thing we can do is sort of have a
camera mode like we could say what's the
camera doing right now and we could say
well if the camera is has come to rest
we just won't move the camera unless the
player has hopped outside of the unless
the target has moved sufficiently since
then right so that's one thing we could
do and that would be if we wanted to
make it so that for example let's say
you're in here you know and I'm fighting
some some bad guy and I'm like hopping
back and forth here to see how the
cameras like moving like back and forth
just kind of back and forth even though
I'm will be staying within a very small
area so one thing we might want to do
there to avoid this kind of repetitive
camera motion is just say look if I'm
not far enough away from where the
camera already is just don't worry about
it right so only kick in the camera
acceleration when we actually have come
a certain distance from where we look
where we last position of the camera
right so that's one of them and then for
the hopping that would mean that the
hopping here where we're doing this
right we can keep that state separate
meaning the X the Y and the Z states can
all be a separate state so that will
only update those states when they each
have gone a certain amount out of the
way and that would keep us from that
would keep us from moving the camera for
unnecessarily small adjustments if that
makes sense and soo what I'm gonna do
there is I'm essentially going to have a
lack of a better term a camera movement
mask might be the way to say it and the
way this is going to work is the camera
code which is this and by the way we
should probably make a camera file at
this point because it's it's own thing
could move like now that this code is
fairly real we could just pull it out
into a separate place where it does its
own thing but you know not super
motivated to do it so maybe I won't I'm
gonna have a movement mask here and that
movement mask is going to initialize to
zero zero zero and what's going to
happen is every time I go to compute a
camera DP instead of actually applying
the camera DP I'm going to mask the
camera DP by the movement mask value
right and so when I take this stuff here
and I look at like the total Delta P I'm
going to say total Delta P equals the
hat amount product of the total Delta P
times the movement mask and remember the
Hadamard product is just the
component-wise product x times X Y times
y C times Z so if the movement mask is
all zeros you will never register a
camera movement so if I run this right
now the camera just won't move right
it's not gonna go anywhere so we won't
even be able to start the game
it'll just be frozen in its tracks right
we'll just see a blank screen oh well
maybe not I guess we came to the first
one
alright I'll be honest I have no idea
how that's working
nevermind so we're not actually using
this value because reasons I guess you
can see we never use it all right this
is supposed to be in here and we didn't
do that
and so yeah I don't know what the deal
was there um so here we need total Delta
DP as well right and so this this value
also needs to get modified by that even
though it's not something that ever
equals anything other than zero at the
moment let's try that again although it
seemed like we're still getting motion
from one from zero zero III I think I'm
still missing something because we
shouldn't be able to move at all
if the total Delta P and the total Delta
DP are both zeroed out because
oh well now I think about it this will
always execute so we need to rewrite
this as well so this also needs to be
this right because if we don't do that
then we will never actually get if we
don't do that then we'll never actually
use this condition will always hit
because if these of both are both zero
we will never use the interior loop we
will always use the exterior so we need
to actually use the Delta which has been
zeroed out in this case there's other
things I could do there but that
probably is the easiest and so now we're
get what I expected to have happen which
is we don't see anything right okay so
now what I want to do is say all right
the camera movement mask is going to be
based on the difference between these
two things and so we're only going to
set these in very careful circumstances
if the camera comes to rest so if it
comes to rest in you know here then the
movement mask is going to reset to zero
zero zero so that it has no movement
right we're gonna check each element
here and we're gonna check each element
in turn for its motion and if it's large
enough we're gonna set the movement mask
up for that element so each of these and
I'm not going to bother with the floral
loop because it would be longer to right
than the actual thing basically if the
total Delta P for whatever this thing is
right it's the total Delta P for this
thing is greater
then our movement threshold for that
axis there we go
Wow spelling day if it's greater than
the threshold then the mask is one
otherwise at zero right another way to
say that oh well that's not actually
what I want I I only I don't want to set
it back to zero so I really just want to
do this meaning if the movement exceeds
our movement threshold and I'll what the
heck I'll make that be per element so we
can actually set the threshold to three
different values if you want so for
example maybe the threshold is you know
a four wide box this way but it's only a
one wide box in Z or something right
who knows how we want that done but
basically that means look if the
threshold is exceeded then we turn on
camera motion in that axis if the
threshold isn't exceeded we don't we
turn the entire camera movement off when
we arrive at our target right pretty
straightforward
so let's debug that yeah
that's not right because that has to go
there
let's try it one more time
there we go
and so now as we move from room to room
obviously we're not going to see you
know unless I screwed something up which
could have easily happened we're not
gonna see any really weird stuff
happened there because the camera was
locked per room here but we should see
stuff happen in other locations if we
you know if we did this right and I can
already tell I didn't quite do it right
because you notice that oh well there it
is so maybe I just need that region to
be larger
let's try setting this to maybe like
something like 10 that way and 8 this
way I don't know what Z should be so
that's a little bit more like it
[Music]
of course that's now a little too
permissive
[Music]
and you can see it's still doing the Bob
there and I assume that's because the Z
needs to be a larger threshold there we
go
so now it's just it lets us say stable
there it still seems like the Y is maybe
larger so why that wasn't working why is
for too little but six is not
something's a little something is a
little weird here so I think I've got
something weird
maybe that I'd not quite understanding
about the way that code ended up falling
out there because something's weird
about those settings they seem to be off
I can't quite see anything though
I don't I unfortunately I don't really
see what's off do you see how dramatic
that difference is it just seems like
that
difference should be less and that's
trigger in my my spidey sense there I
don't really have a spidey sense but
that seems wrong so I think I'm doing
something wrong but I'm not sure exactly
what it is and so that total Delta
p-value there where we subtract the
target that we're going to minus the
location that we're currently at that
doesn't seem to really be doing what I
think it should be doing and so
something is up with that code but I
don't know what and it just seems like
that threshold seems like that threshold
is weird do we have so we don't have a
just a general root debug we're gonna
have to add that because I'd like to
view this value so I would like to have
our little route back again although I
suppose for camera it's pretty easy for
me to draw that actually under the
camera stuff at the moment but yeah
whatevs so you can see the thing that
I'm having trouble with tears I want to
know why these threshold values seem to
not be behaving the way I would expect
and you can see that actually very
clearly even in the first hallway it
seems so you'll notice there's no
scrolling for all of that hopping and
now inside the threshold if I was to
change this down to 6 it should be like
if it was 8 squares before it'd be 6
squares now right
and yet I don't see any difference there
that's just so bizarre
although I guess maybe this room was
always supposed to Center anyway
so honestly what it feels like is
happening is it feels like we're setting
the movement masks to zero prematurely
which I suppose is something that could
happen maybe if the length of the total
Delta P I just I don't see it
I mean correct me if I'm wrong the
movement masks once set cannot become
unset until the camera reaches the
target right I don't see a lot of ways
that that is
yeah I I don't really see a lot of ways
that that is able to be circumvented
here and I suppose this that code is a
little Squinkie but I still think it's
correct
hmm all right so I don't have any good
ideas here I don't I can't really find
the bug by inspection so I'm gonna go
ahead and actually get these values
debugged
so you know if I look at our rendering
dump here I think I should be able to
like put some camera readout stuff in
there and just kind of get a little more
information about that I can just see
stuff is doing weird I'm obviously just
maybe I've got a typo or maybe I was
thinking this through wrong because
that's you know entirely possible so I
want to see what's going on and even
just ignoring this code down here right
I want to know why I'm getting this sort
of weird where are these thresholds
don't seem to be lining up with what I
my intuition is so what I'd like to do
is I'd like to draw the camera mask
right so I'd like to do a debug value of
the camera movement mask and I will put
that in a block under the render or just
so that we know that it goes there and
so I want to get the movement mask and I
want that Toto Delta P I want that to be
displayed here and I want to see what
the movement mask is at any given time
just just so I have some idea of what
you know what while we're at it like why
don't we just see the P and the target P
as well just so I can get some idea of
you know what those values actually end
up being so if I restart this I don't
know if I don't know if we had some
weirdness there let me see where his
renderer there we go
so just looking at those right I mean
it's already wrong but the why is wrong
it should the the total Delta P should
be trimming that I'm doing an absolute
value right so shouldn't that trigger
the movement mask to be set up to one is
there something wrong with the way I'm
doing the absolute value or something
let me get the post version of this as
well so I don't actually know how to
make a second one of these in the debug
interface I can't remember if we can
just print something out in multiple
steps that's kind of not something I
actually know about so in here where
we've got like debug value and we pass
the value it always produces this name
it looks like that name though gets
concatenate with a file on line number
so I think it's actually different so I
think I can just I think I can just do
this
furthermore I could do this I think in
which case our debug system should give
me two separate readouts one for pre and
one for post yeah and so the total Delta
P here you can see it's negative for
right
oh and I guess the threshold is 6 okay
all right Touche so let's say this was
more what I would have expected it to be
well let's say I move into like here or
something right so the total Delta P in
this case it's saying is 2.6
and that's just not enough to trigger
the motion and you know you're right
[Music]
you can kind of see - like the sense the
Z's are wrong there
it just gets cold set
so these kind of have to be more
sensitive than that which is a bummer
because it means the hopping is still a
problem
all right
so one of the things I guess I'm seeing
there is that the trigger for the motion
of the camera gosh I'm really confused
the trigger for the motion of the camera
once the camera has come to rest it
might be more that this this value
vanishes too slowly so that this here is
maybe not the right way to look at it it
may be that this Delta P needs to be
able to hit its target a little faster
so like the damping there needs to be
less or something like this so that's
kind of hard to say but I guess the
problem is that once the camera gets in
motion
sometimes it just stays in motion for a
while like in and possibly erroneously
and that may have been something sort of
what I was seeing in terms of when that
camera mass like even though that looks
like it's come to rest it hasn't
actually you can see that camera mass
doesn't get reset for a while right
watch this value here as I'm hopping
around you can see like if I do that it
takes a really long time for that to
actually come back down to being set to
zero and so I think you know we actually
want this to we want that to have a more
definitive finish point that sucks up
that small motion and so I think what
we'd want to do here is say maybe
there's like a a sort of either/or where
we're basically saying look if you're
gonna reach the target great that's one
way to stop the motion the other way to
stop the motion is if the length squared
of the Delta P is just too low right
like if it's just if it's just smaller
than some relative displacement we just
don't want it
with anymore and we could do that for
setting the camera mask separately I
don't know how we want do that I also
don't really know what's going on with
that camera position you can see it's
still interpolating I don't know right
you can notice the camera value itself
is actually interpolating
and that's super-creepy that's the the
actual p-value the the actual position
value that the camera is supposed to be
set to
and you can see here the camera movement
mask is set to one one one even though
it clearly should be set to all zeroes
right
meaning this total delta p the absolute
value of total Delta P in this case is
is clearly not above the threshold so
we're talking about whether this ever
got called and apparently it just didn't
meaning
apparently the length squared of Delta P
is not less than this
we're in la-la land so I've got a bug in
here somewhere that I'm just not seeing
because that just don't make any sense
at all right
here's Delta P let's get that in there
we're gonna have to restart because
these aren't stable yeah I mean that's
the length squared of that is definitely
I mean it's definitely set to those
values so how is that how is this not
getting triggered if the length of Delta
P is less than the length of the total
Delta or the length of Delta P is less
than this Oh again
so what we really want to do is that I
mixed up those two cases I should
probably move this up into the top case
because it's sort of the way I obviously
was thinking about it okay now let's try
to figure out what's going on here all
right so now we have to figure out what
this value should be right
oops that's not wanted so now we have to
figure out what this movement value
should be and it's basically like if the
amount that you were going to move is
just too small for us to really see and
I should probably make that be
proportional to the time step so meaning
that should vary according to the time
step and so if you were going to move
slower than something right like maybe
0.1 units per second then it's just it's
done don't move it all right
we're still getting some wonkiness of
there
you can sort of see where that hits in I
don't know if also maybe I don't know if
I really want this check per se or if I
just want to make sure that the camera
motion like I may want to instead just
say look we can keep this check we just
have to get rid of some of that damping
so maybe this value is like just too
high
so we don't really want to damp that
deceleration quite so gentle like we
want it to be pretty dramatic you know
what I mean that's a little bit too much
so I'm not sure about this it's been
pretty Squinkie and I don't love things
that feel Squinkie like that and you can
see that that's still not critically
damped like we're definitely getting
overshoot in there in that in the
proportional derivative controller which
I definitely don't want
right you see a lot of that
yes still not
still getting overshoot there too
so I don't know
that feels better
that feels pretty good now that we've
just cranked that spring a little bit so
that it doesn't quite have like that's
feeling pretty good so it may need to
spin that our spring was a little bit
was too damped so it just wouldn't ever
really get down to it wouldn't really
approach the target it was kind of like
over damped so it always had a bad curve
you can see right there like I'm getting
that bounce and the reason I'm getting
that bounce is because it still takes a
little too long so it's it's still
that's a little too damp it's not
hitting the target that's you know so
once I get into a movement zone I need
it to like stop you know
just trying to confuse it here to see
what happens
so another thing we could consider is we
could also consider having the movement
mask be signed meaning we won't start
going in a direction until you get too
far in that direction cuz right now once
I've got it going I can kind of go back
and forth like this and it will just
keep and until I actually until it
actually hits a solid state it won't
actually stop right and so that part is
a little possibly bad
sooo here's the thing that I think I
might propose thinking this through I
think this might be the wrong way to
look at this so maybe what we want to
say here is we also want to look at the
speed because that also has to match so
we may want to say look if the length
squared is wrong or that if the length
squared of the velocity
because here's this part where we've
created the new velocity and so if I'm
gonna look at the new velocity and I
want to see like what the new velocity
would be you know relative to the old
one their relative to the target I might
want to sort of get that measure it
again as well so you know if if this or
I should say that if if what we're gonna
set the velocity to and I can do that by
the camera movement mask as well if what
we're gonna set the velocity to
is less than if that difference is less
than some threshold
right and the reason I'm saying that is
because one of the problems that I'm
gonna have is that if you happen to
camera was moving pretty fast in this
direction and then the player was
hopping pretty fast in the opposite
direction
they might just happen to align and the
camera would just freeze dead in its
tracks
you know what I mean and that's not
gonna feel good so I think we also have
to check to make sure that the camera
itself is not moving too quickly
because if it is you don't want to stop
it right I never want to have that
feeling of the camera hitting a wall and
I'm still kind of getting that feeling
here occasionally let me just see I
don't know if this value might be a
little high
and so I kind of just want to try to
alleviate that wall hitting feeling so
when the cameras in motion it can stay
moving but once it stops it won't start
again until you've got a pretty good
push you know what I mean you can see
the cameras are drifting
I think I will set that cold here
so I think we can do a better job on
this than what I've done so far having
explored it I think I can do another
pass on that maybe next stream we're
close it's just that needs to be thought
through just a little bit more and you
also get some of these things where like
we kind of need to know that the camera
movement masks in certain cases like
there it's just saying well that's not
far enough for me to care about right
but that has to be so in some sense you
know you got a set when you set the
focus we may have to set the camera
movement mask up so for example like in
the case where we have a special camera
and the special camera is affecting the
X Y offset or the Z we may need to say
look in a special camera scenario you
got a one one one that you know what I
mean so the movement mask is
automatically set for something where we
know we got to zoom in right
it does not like the overlay window
so yeah I think there's I think we want
to maybe on Tang it a little bit I'm
gonna do that next stream though because
I would like to make that a little bit
it's just not quite there yet it's close
but it's not quite there yet and so I
want to just go through now that we've
got that code in there I want to go
through and give it a little bit more
polish it's very close it feels really
good it's just I can still feel a little
bit of hitches in some cases a little
bit of overshoot and stuff in there so I
think we can do better than what we've
got and so we'll we'll take a look at
that on next stream for now I think
that's good for today let's go ahead and
go to the QA
see oops that's not how you spell kiwi
neck there we go
should probably do the work to make sure
the glove floats around with you
it's kind of been annoying having it not
float around with you we haven't really
done that yet but like for some reason
we just have not done that yet I mean
I don't really want to do this at the
moment but I think it's just this
right do I need to set that I'm not sure
why that's not consistently lacing the
glove piece somewhere
there we go
all right
so not sure where that angle offset
actually gets set now I see
I'm just playing around here I should
actually look at the QA sorry this was
just bugging me all right so yeah we'll
do actual code for the fist at some
point in the future but it was just
bugging me that it wasn't floating
around with us right so I figured I'd
just make it float around with us for
now
and then we'll make it actually do it's
it's real stuff later on all right let's
see we got for Q&amp;A
so I'm not sure I understand the reason
why you don't sir the actual position
and smoothly scrolling between tiles and
the animation position doing the
bouncing the bouncing should only have
to be dealt with during render and can
be derived from the actual position so
you don't have stored anywhere am I
wrong about that uh well again wrong is
probably the wrong word
in either case because there is Lee
isn't a wrong there's just what the
consequences are of doing it various
ways so if you take what you're
suggesting to the logical conclusion you
have a lot of problems right and what
that is is anytime you want the
animation of the player to be something
more complicated than hopping from one
tile to the other what do you do so
let's suppose that the character is
hopping from one tile to the other so
you have moved their base position right
to be underneath where they were but
they're up here okay now they get hit
and they you're supposed to fly up in
the air and stay up in the air for a
little while or something like this what
where are they right you were lying to
the camera about where they actually
were so now you have to construct some
kind of interpolation rule about what
you do when you transition between your
fake position and the real position that
the player is actually at which is what
the viewer sees and so my experience is
you really don't want to do those sorts
of things and the reason is because you
will always end up producing artifacts
that you then have to go and add special
code to fix once you have more things
happening action lives than just the one
you plan for right so if instead you
just always do a filter on what the
actual thing is that the viewer looks at
it can't really be wrong because it's
what the viewer sees and so basing
things that that control the camera
movement over fake elements that the
user can't see and they're concentrating
on saying the user can see right because
the user doesn't know about your fake
camera thing then in that place where
you have to transition between the other
all hell breaks loose and so I just
don't want to deal with that I just want
to have something that will always work
for what we actually see
um and and go from there
what's the plan for lighting on the
sprites so for lighting on the sprites
we will probably depend a little bit on
how we finished up our lighting solution
but they'll probably just be adding a
Sam a synthetic sample point to the
lighting solution that just doesn't
really occlude anything or maybe it
maybe even will include we might
actually put a whole cube in there and
then we'll just light the sprite with
the result of the cube that's that's it
we won't be doing anything different
it'll still just be a cube based
lighting but there'll be a fake cube for
the sprite that you just won't render
and it's not perfect right it would be
better if we had actual 3d geometry for
all those shapes
much like what I said with the camera
you always get artifacts there it's just
those artifacts aren't gonna be that bad
because people can't pick up errors in
lighting like they can errors in
movement their eye is much more tuned to
errors and movement than it is in errors
in light so is the variance of lighting
just a side effect the random sample
yeah our lighting isn't great we need to
do a better lighting algorithm it's too
slow and we don't get good enough
results for how much time we're spending
on it we also maybe want to do it all
right we may want to do it on the
graphics card and not on the CPU so
there's a lot yeah we're about to talk
with Dino off-topic but how do you stay
motivated on projects like this I
usually would lose interest much earlier
and wonder if there are techniques hmm
so let me say two things first let me
answer your question for actual long
projects and then let me give a caveat
for handmade Europe so for long projects
I would highly recommend watching John
blows presentation on this actually gave
a presentation on not as a motivation
but just mental states right like how to
deal with mental states he talks about
some of the basics of that that you
should know and I would recommend that
he's worked on multiple very long game
projects that were very difficult the
witness in particular was like I don't
even remember how long it was seven
years very very long and it's an amazing
game at the end so it wasn't like it was
a struggle
project in a way it was like it just
really needed this much time to be done
by the number of people that we're on it
you know so I would I would reference
that people in the chat can probably
point you to the actual YouTube video
but just it's it's Jonathan plays
lecture on on like mindfulness basically
I'm managing your mental state but other
thing I'd say is I would really
encourage people to remember that Hamid
hero is not a long project handmade hero
has barely had any programming on it at
this point I mean we are talking about a
few hundred hours I don't know what it
is seven eight hundred hours of
programming that is child's play on a
project I mean I've never been on a
project that shipped that was that
little programming right you might find
one if you're using a pre-built engine
because then you're just maybe not doing
much property and all maybe you're just
like instantiating a typical
first-person shooter with the Unreal
Engine and just making art assets for it
or something so maybe then there's not
very much programming but assuming that
you're actually doing anything real
700 800 hours of programming is nothing
I mean it's a blink of an eye it's it's
like what you know twenty thirty weeks
of programming it's not even a year a
full-time work and so I would I often I
would say to people if the amount of
programming that's done on handmade hero
if you think of that as a lot that's
probably a good indication that maybe
programming isn't for you right that
should that should be a small that
should be a a very small amount of
programming and if you're early on and
you haven't had much programming
experience then that's okay but just
like if you're if you're not thinking oh
yeah I'll get up to that point
eventually and that'll be a reasonable
mount of program for me that's that's
probably a bad sign you don't really
want to be having those thoughts if
you're gonna be an engine program your
partner should not think the amount of
code on hammy or they're dumb as much
because it isn't and
there's just not that much coding work
that's gone into this project that makes
sense it's very low it stresses out over
a long period of time because I only do
a few hours a week you know but you know
that that's not hard right that's just
you know it's easy to say oh I just
spent two week hours a week on it and I
spent them you know so that doesn't
really wear you down mentally because
you're hardly putting that many hours of
work into a tree anyway how big is a
material don't we have okay
um what's it doing okay there we go
I handmade hero is 28 thousand lines of
code uh correct I mean depends on how
you want to count it you know I don't
know if you want to count comments and
stuff like that or blank lines right but
assuming you're just talking about lines
of code looks to know twenty thousand
and I think that includes handmade Ray
probably okay no it doesn't
okay so it doesn't include kami right so
it's that's a that's a fair estimate so
again like really not that big right you
know thirty thousand lines of code is
just not a lot of lines of code she's
are getting print out what does it take
for that have you noticed to change your
mental stamina it's got no there really
no if anything I think my mental state
has gotten better as I've gotten older
for better or for worse I don't know if
that's a good thing but I'll stick with
things longer now than I used to
probably I don't really get burnt out I
do get scared so I get I get really
scared about not having enough money to
finish something or stuff like that I
get I get terrified about those sorts of
things
routinely like every couple of weeks um
when I'm working on stuff that's not
like somebody else paying me a paycheck
to do a specific piece of code so I get
scared a lot but really not burnt out
you know if I was independently wealthy
if I just had like billions of dollars
or something sitting around in a bank
account
I never burn out I don't think I'd just
be happy as a clam program in a way and
I wouldn't even care if it ever shipped
I just that's just because I like the
act of programming so if I don't have to
worry about it my mental state is very
good it's when I have to worry about
actually delivering something that I get
scared and I think with good reason like
I think anyone should it's hard and it
doesn't often go well a lot of games
don't make money any more there's a lot
of reasons to be scared I think it's I
think it's totally reasonable so I don't
fault myself for that and I don't think
there's a lot you can do about that I
think it's just it's it is scary you
know it's like skydiving or something
right it just is inherently scary
it's something humans weren't meant to
do uh-huh
and so you're kind of pushing a little
bit of a emotional limit there no matter
what you do
burnout is is a different thing and I I
don't really feel like I have that very
often I definitely have some bad mental
states I get into but they're usually
fear and not exhaustion because I guess
what I would say that's just that that's
just me how long does a full rebuild
take you just saw it many many many
times every time we hit build it's a
full rebuild so I mean if you want to
see it
that's the full rebuild if the game
isn't running it might be slightly
faster I'm not sure cuz our game takes
up a lot of CPU so I don't know how that
affects it yeah so it's a faster if
you're not running the game because then
the compiler isn't fighting for time but
4.5 seconds full rebuilds that's what
the optimizations on by the way with
debug build I think that drops to 2
points something so
Tice no says motivation I could
recommend your chat about the imposter
syndrome it helped me a lot I used to
have way too high expectations of what I
can do in a day I reduce that
expectation and set myself smaller goals
for each day way easier to even start
then and I was surprised how quickly I
got way more done than I initially
wanted to do um I don't remember where
that chatty is if someone wants to post
in YouTube it must be one of the
handmade chats
yeah impostor syndrome was something
that would that that word was not really
used when I was growing up and I really
don't know how useful it is but but yeah
I think in that chat I just covered some
basic things like I just would I would
ignore that concept almost entirely and
just focus on the fact that you know
everyone is always learning and this is
a very incomplete discipline and so
hopefully in watching streams like these
you can see that it doesn't really
matter how long you've been programming
you will still make mistakes you will
still need to explore to find good
solutions you will still be stumped from
time to time you will still have to
accept imperfect solutions and that's
one of the main things I wanted to show
on the stream to begin with and so I
feel like impostor syndrome is something
that we should just banish even from
something people should worry about I
think if you're feeling like you're not
able to do the job I think you have to
remember that like this is a very hard
discipline that everyone struggles with
and that's not just you and there are
lots of concrete ways that you can get
better at things and we all are trying
to do those things and there isn't there
are no programmers out there who are
just magically awesome at everything
every day it simply is not the case I
have worked with many of the greatest
programmers in the game industry I've
worked with and they all aren't that way
right it's just it's very hard and so
rather than thinking about impostor
syndrome
I would more say realistic expectations
don't don't imagine that the people out
there who have been doing this job
longer and do it better than you or
something are doing something magical
they're only a little bit better and you
can get there if you practice right and
so yeah I mean that's one of the reasons
I think it's great that there's more
programmer streams now so that you can
watch and internalize that you can see
programmers who you may have respected
and thought never made mistakes or we're
just doing some magical thing that you
could never do you can see them like
being stupid on a stream and making us
dumb mistake and taking an hour to find
a bug that should have been obvious and
also it's like that's programming is
complicated and it's something that you
have to constantly work at and do not
set the bar unrealistically high for
yourself it's not that kind of a thing
do you ever experience having no idea on
how to approach a specific problem and
have that negatively impact how
productive you are any tip on how to
deal with it so I guess I do have a tip
on that so when you are trying to solve
a problem that you don't know how to
solve the best advice I can give is try
a lot of things what I see a lot of
programmers do that I think is bad is a
bad habit in that situation is they try
to figure out the solution before they
start typing there aren't very many hard
problems in programming that you can
figure out the solution before you start
typing now sometimes there are if it's
math oriented but then my answer just
becomes start writing right start
working the math and the reason I say
that is because if something solution or
mathematical representation is not
immediately obvious to you it probably
isn't immediately obvious period and
you're going to have to do exploration
to find it so the wrong thing to do is
to stop programming or stop writing math
and think about the problem the reason
for that is because your brain obviously
isn't good enough to jump to a solution
and that's fine use the tools you have
to explore the problem until you find a
solution make visualizations draw
everything you possibly can that relates
to the problem make simulations of the
problem collect data from those
simulations graph them right look at
everything you can if it's math work
through the math use MATLAB to graph the
math solve the math in multiple ways
right
go find math books on the topic see if
there are ideas in there that you don't
know about
right get on Google Scholar look for
research papers involved you know get
going do something right build something
and usually the solution will come out
of that the times that stumpers remain
stumpers is when you remain paralyzed
when you don't do something and so I
can't recommend highly enough
the act of active programming active
solve problem solving
whether that be writing more equations
making more graphs collecting more data
writing more code do something and that
is almost always the route to the
solution sitting there contemplating it
in your head is rarely the thing and
what you'll often find too is you may
then think of the answer the answer may
come to you in your head as if you
thought of it but that moment only comes
because you've been working the problem
right and so that that active behavior
actually stimulates your brain and
provides more context and more ideas for
it to chew on and then that idea may
can't come right
alright I'm gonna roll it up alright
thank you everyone for joining me for
notes on a handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to follow my series at home you
can always peer to the game on handmade
hero org it comes with the source code
so you can follow along with it we will
probably be on Christmas break for a
while I I will be away for Christmas
and so winter break might go till
January 10th 15 something like that so
it'll be 2 or 3 weeks before I see you
again don't let that stop you whatever
project you're working on right now our
program we're doing do some good
programming over the winter break spend
some time doing some cool stuff and
learning about programming and then when
we come back we'll have a whole bunch of
stuff we could do on handmade hero we
can play around more with the camera
code that we can get to some stuff we
even want to get to for a while I just
throwing in some nice stuff ground cover
or we could maybe look at the lighting a
little bit tie up the game look get it
looking like a real game because we're
pretty close to that actually and then I
think we can finally check that box and
say it's all game play from here on out
that'll be a bad day cuz I'm not a
designer so you know I'll do everything
I can before we get to there but at some
point we're running out of things that
are that our engine side so so we got a
few more things to do there when we're
but we're going through them pretty well
and so we'll we'll see and hopefully
when we come back to we can get the
twitch stream set up a little bit better
gets we're gonna put some imodium oh
geez and their custom emotion you know
customer to Colin's and custom badges
and stuff so now that we're twitch
partners and all that stuff we can
settle that up for you guys too so
that'll that'll be coming
when we come back from Christmas break
as well already everybody have a good
holiday season and well in regardless
have a good break even if even if it's
not winter where you are or if it's not
holidays where you are have a good
couple week break do some good program
and have some fun and I'll see everyone
when we come back thanks everybody