you
I remember you were asked what's the
best way to draw a circle at a Microsoft
job interview what's the answer so in
that way that Microsoft job interviews
at that time you know we're asking
questions that that question was I would
I would consider a particularly
knowledge-based question in that if
you're not an expert graphics programmer
you wouldn't know the answer to this
question right but the problem with that
kind of question as you might expect is
that it's highly temporal so the best
way to draw a circle back then is
absolutely not the best way to draw a
circle now and the reason for that is
because in the old days
no multi-threading right everything with
single-core for what Microsoft is
targeting no floating-point the
floating-point units were very slow at
that time and sometimes they didn't even
have a floating-point unit so it would
have been emulated and 3no wide
instructions so you know today you
wouldn't dream of trying to do something
fast
without a wide instruction right all
your instructions should be single
instruction multiple data instructions
if you're trying to do something fast
right
that's how graphics cards go fast that's
how like the CPU goes fast is lots of
cores doing wide instructions so none of
those things were true back then in fact
wide instructions were not even a thing
that were contemplated on the PC I think
they did exist in other architectures
potentially specialized architectures
and they were at least I know for a fact
they were contemplated I just don't know
if what they were shipping and
necessarily
but Intel hadn't even announced like
plans to do something like that so with
the very important caveat that it is no
longer an answer you probably should
ever be thinking about because it is
wrong now the way that they wanted to
see you do a circle was that obviously
if I give you the center of a circle and
the radius it's trivial to find one
pixel right I should probably just draw
this out but it's trivial to find one
pixel that you could consider to be on
the circle right and furthermore it's
trivial probably you know to find four
and you know rather than try to just
state it and describe it really
elaborately here I'll I'll just draw it
for you the reason for that of course is
that on a pixel grid if I say that a
circle is somewhere so we'll call this
the center of the circle right then I
know that whatever I know whatever pixel
the center is because the person had to
tell me that right so the person had to
say that this circle Center right is
like let's say CX CY right so they had
to tell me what that is and I can look
that up in the pixel grid right away
just by doing a multiplying an ad right
by you know multiplying the stride here
and then do an ad here I'm gonna get
this pixel you know I wasn't safe for
free but pretty close to free right and
then because you also have to give me
the are right the radius of the circle
that I'm trying to draw here you know I
can also find four more points for free
right because I know this point is just
gonna be like plus R in the
x-direction and I know that this point
on the circle is gonna be minus R right
and I know that the same thing would be
true
on the on the y-axis right you know I'm
saying
so from the start obviously I can get
sort of for free I can sort of get the
points that make a diamond in this you
know of what the circle would be so the
question now is how do I just draw the
the actual arc right now again just to
emphasize how not a good idea it is to
do what I'm saying now because this is
only relevant on very old hardware
hardware that literally does not exist
anywhere today except maybe in some kind
of like crazy embedded system in a very
small space or something I don't know I
don't even know if I we're like I don't
even know if there still exists hardware
where this makes sense so that's how old
this is
so in order to draw the arc what I want
to be able to do is I want to be able to
do something that does not require a
floating point and is not wide right and
it's not threaded so all of the things
you would normally do today to make a
fast routine I need to do none of those
in fact I can't do any of these and so
what ends up happening is you say well
ok in order to compute the equation for
this circle right I know that I have see
x squared plus C y squared minus R
squared equals 0 right I mean
alternatively see x squared plus C y
squared equals R squared
I mean it doesn't matter how you want to
phrase it it's up to us depending on
what we want but if we look at what's
going on here you can sort of see we've
got two things that are multiplied like
see x squared see y squared and one
thing that's a constant right so if we
move around the pixel grid this is
changing this is not right
so it's pretty free for us to compute R
squared or negative R squared and not
have to do that work anymore
but now the question is well the CX
squared plus CY squared part what are we
gonna do about that what's the easiest
way to make this work for us right
now to be honest I don't really remember
the exact answer they were looking for
but I'm just gonna do a good answer here
and I'm sure it's either as good or
better than what they were looking for
interview questions sometimes the
interviewer doesn't know the best answer
I remember there was one valve one like
that about quadtree that I later figured
out I didn't get the interview question
but the person he typically asked it had
told it to me and I was later working on
a quadtree and I figured out like just
cuz I won I was doing some stuff and I
was like oh actually that answer is not
the best answer the best answer is
actually this but that's neither here
though there all right
so anyway um looking at this what you
want to do is say how do I minimize the
cost of finding the pixels in here how
do I minimize the cost of finding which
pixels this is closest to zero because
remember in this day and age to these
things worse underpowered no one's doing
anti-aliasing or anything like that
either so we're literally just talking
about filling the pixels that make the
arc solid so we're not trying to figure
out like coverage information or
anything else that would actually
require a little bit more work than what
we're doing here we're trying to only
light up one pixel the whole way around
right all right so if you start off here
or actually let's start off on plus R
for now cuz that's just you know a
positive if you start off here you know
that see x squared plus CY squared is R
squared right because we know that this
is on the circle so that's just like a
given that has to be true and you know
that it's true because since there's no
y component the X component of the
circle is just R right and if the X
component of the circle is just R
then this is R squared minus R squared
because that term goes away so obviously
this is on the circle so what we can do
now is change it around to say if I'm
already on the circle I know that one of
my neighboring points also must be on
the circle right and furthermore I know
that those points if I only wanted to
draw the arc in one direction I know
that these points are the only candidate
points that could possibly be it because
I can never get further away from the
center of the circle then plus R right
that I know that I'm already on the
outside of the circle so I can go up or
I can go left
or I can go up and left but I certainly
couldn't go right or up and right right
these are not this is not allowed so
what I can do is rephrase the question
of which direction to go oh also by the
way I should say one more thing branches
not expensive this day why not out of
order so the processor just went in
order and retired one instruction
basically at a time I don't even think
they were superscalar I don't know what
the first superscalar x86 was but this
is like you know this is like 286 era
right a style question and so 486 is I
think we're brand new some like a fair
number of people had 386 is but the
interview questions were all from like
we're like a couple years old right so
they were all like 286 era questions so
I'm pretty sure that 286 really wasn't
superscalar so I think the 286 like had
no branch prediction I don't think I
think it just executed the branch and
then stepped to the next one
right
so I'm pretty sure although you know
it's been 30 years or whatever it's been
I don't even wanna know it's been 20 20
years 25 years um no I think it has been
30 years Jesus Christ it's been 26 years
my 727 years
so we're also talking about not caring
how much branching there is because
branches are not more expensive than
other instructions they're like the same
so normally again while you were think
about less stuff you would also not not
want tons of branches sitting around
inside your code not true anymore it's
just it's just another thing to consider
in that in back in these days it's just
another instruction so a branch that
saves you computation is probably a good
idea because branches were probably
cheaper than like an integer multiplier
or something right anyway uh so if you
look at what you're trying to do here
you're trying to pick which one of these
three is going to be the the point that
is most on the circle from our current
location right and so what we can do is
say well if I were to compute this
equation at these three points and just
pick the one that is closest to zero so
the one with the least error you know
whichever one has the least error must
be the answer so if we went ahead and
said like see X plus 1 squared plus CY
plus 1 squared minus R squared equals
you know error 0 see X plus 1 squared
plus CY squared minus R squared and lime
I don't know why I'm sexy
this entire time I've been writing see I
just mean X&amp;Y see is this it was
supposed to be the center of the circle
I'm sorry I've got carried away pretend
I didn't say that yeah this is what I
meant to say
I forgot over it is I don't know why I
was like I picked up ZX in my head and
ran with it that's why I'm bad at brain
math app um and finally x squared plus y
plus 1 squared minus R squared equals B
2 right so if you look at what these
equations come out to be you can see
that the terms are reused a ton right so
really I know that x squared plus I know
that x squared + y squared I already had
to have known because they were the
location of they were what I accepted
last round right so I know x squared + y
squared so I kind of have like two
registers I could keep which is like you
know my px and my py square I don't know
you know I don't know what you want to
call these but like I can keep these
around and just use them here so really
the only thing that I'm trying to figure
out is the new values of of these right
so I can keep those around if I want to
it depends on again the processor and
specific things is whether or not you'd
want to how many registers it has
whether you can how quickly you can
multiply an imager and all that sort of
stuff right but so what you can see here
is if I just compute these three
equations I then know three error terms
and I just have to pick whichever one is
smallest
so I compute this one I mean and more
specifically right I just compute X plus
1 and y plus 1 squared that's really all
I needed to compute I compute those two
then I add them together and subtract R
squared that's one error
add just X 1 plus the old Y squared
minus R squared that's a new one right
but I don't do we compute this because I
already computed it same down here I
just add the old x squared to the new Y
plus 1 squared that I or equids up here
subtract
squared and off we go right so then the
absolute value of each of these three
whichever one is least that's the pixel
that I need to pick right that's the
pixel that I would go to so we can get
more out of this by an ellipse
I didn't mean to change the zoom there
there we go I can get more out of this
by um do I have a space bar oops nope is
there like a key on here that is
equivalent to the space bar I should map
one okay there's like some buttons on
this pad if one was equipping the space
bar that would be pretty pretty baller
but there isn't I'm all map one maybe so
what we can do is just create a loop
that goes hey which of those three is
smaller
except that movement right now if you
want to you could also say and I think
this was part of the question perhaps so
you could say I don't want to check this
meaning I only go up or over right now
they didn't tell you any of this stuff
for the question they just said draw a
circle but I think they might have said
you don't have to do you don't have to
do single pixel diagonals so you can you
can do ones that are fat you know
because there's it's hard to say which
one you want when you think of drawing a
circle when you're talking about sloppy
pixel drawing like this it's hard to say
which one you want right so really you
can probably say that this one is not
there what that means is that when you
do this you just have one if it's like
if you know abs II 1 is less than ABS e
2 you know select this one else select
that one so you're just a loop that just
does that and goes goes goes goes right
okay so you only need to do these two to
like draw this first part of the arc
right and you can you know imagine that
going up this way now if we look at this
a little more closely we can also ask
some other questions about it if you
looked at these equations you could also
see that well we know what
this is if we explants panned it out
just using you know if I just use sort
of the math you learned in in in grade
school right X plus one times X plus one
right that's what this is if you use the
distribute you know distributive
property to expand this term you would
get x squared right on one side you
would get one squared on the other side
which of course is just one and then on
the inside you would just get 2x right
you can you can kind of see you know
what's going on there right so if you
know the old if you knew the old x
squared you could really get away with
just doing two x plus one is really what
all you need to add to it to compute the
new term does that make sense in other
words I started out in the old days I
knew what this x squared was and it
registers become a problem back in the
old days remember there's very few
registers so how that actually he didn't
have me rightness in assembly and
because I didn't know assembly at the
time really if you really wanted to talk
about this fast you'd need to write this
as assembly and I would have to start
thinking about register usage which back
then I don't even remember how many you
had you had at least four I think you
had a b c and d x ax BX CX + DX which
were I think 16-bit registers just like
they are now and I don't think you had
EAX like on the 286 I don't think they
had extended it to 32 bits yet I think
that was like the 386 that did that
maybe I don't know maybe the 286 did so
I don't know how wide these registers
were how many bits they were but I think
they were probably 16 bit
but don't don't taste that don't take my
word for it uh so anyway if you look at
what happens here you can see that in
the actual loop itself we can get a lot
of efficiency we don't actually have to
compute these equations whole cloth
because if we just store what our laxed
x squared was right so we store our old
x squared you know our old Y squared you
know I'm saying if we just store what
those are we can compute the new ones
just by adding to that right we can add
2x plus 1 and we can add 2y plus 1 to
get the new versions we test those
versions right and then just accept that
value as our new old ours our as our old
values for the next run of the loop so
that gets us out of ever actually doing
an integer multiplier because the to the
the the 2x and the 2y are actually
shifts right because if I want to do oh
wait
there's just one thing these are these
these are always yeah yeah these are
always positive numbers right because
like I said I'm gonna show you why
that's true in a second like I said I'm
starting over here right so the X&amp;Y
numbers are always positive so I don't
have to worry about any two's complement
or anything else like that I'm just
drawing in the positive quadrant of the
circle and in those days graphics always
went downward so technically you might
really if you were thinking really old
school it's actually these two pixels
we're testing and we're going this way
I'm drawing it that way because that's
how we've always drawn circles and
that's how our coordinate systems always
have worked on handmade hero so but that
doesn't matter the point is just
whichever way your graphics system
thinks is positive that's where we're
going we don't want to deal with any
two's-complement
issues we just want it to work right and
we don't wanna think about
sign-extension or anything else so if I
want to multiply something by two right
I should just be able to do that bitwise
I don't have to actually issue an
integer multiply because it's the
special case of multiplication by two
and since we're in a binary number
system right I can just move it and I
think that would work in negatives
anyway but I but before I started
talking about that I'd wanted to make
sure I would know what I was saying sure
this so we're always in positive so we
don't even have to think about that
that's not relevant so we should be able
do this entire thing without actually
doing any multipliers at all right we
can just do shift ad you know shift
increment test and go right okay so if
we even if we go one step further into
ridiculous town we can also think about
and I can't quite remember because
that's been a long time so as I looked
at this sort of thing
yeah so if you if you look at how this
is equation is being run you're always
doing a and this again just just depends
on whether you've got the registers for
it or not if you want the y squared term
if you look at what happens with with
these equations right where you do
you're always computing something in the
form x squared plus y squared minus R
squared right
and the way we're ending up computing
this entire equation is with what it
amounts to be like some Oh X you know
old x squared value oh it's probably the
wrong thing to do there
let's do previous X we're using some
previous x squared value plus right we
want to do the 2 X 2 X plus 1 right plus
some previous Y squared value because it
would be the same minus R squared right
and we want to compute well or
we're we're fundamentally doing one or
the other of this right like like that's
what we're doing makes sense because
there's there's really no there's no
other operation that we could do we're
just doing those two and then we're
testing which one of these is greater so
in here if we were to reorganize these
terms what you would see is that they're
actually the same darn equation right if
I move this py out to the headend then
what I see is this right it's the same
exact equation the only difference is
that
you know I'm saying so this right here
is actually the only difference between
these two values so what I can do
instead of all the other stuff that I
was about to do right is I can just keep
that if I want to because I only need it
that's the only value I need and then
look at what these two values do right
now it's easier said than done because
the problem is you have to update it so
you need to figure out a way that once
you change the X and the y you're going
to actually get the new value that you
would have had that was on the circle
right does that make sense so looking at
these two values here we can say well
you know the previous point that we were
at is gonna be px squared plus P us
squared plus 1 minus R squared that was
the error on the previous point we're
gonna add 2x to it or 2y to it and
that's gonna be our new error we just
want the minimum one right but assuming
we just go we'll look we're just always
trying to be as close circle as possible
we don't care what we don't really care
about knowing anything else other than
what our error is so really all we need
to store for this entire time is just
error right we just need our error value
we need our x value and our Y value and
these are just necessary for plotting
right and we'll end computation of these
two values right so we should actually
be able to get away with maybe only
three registers by storing this value
every time we go we we shift X up by two
we shift X but Y up by two we add them
right we see whichever is the lesser
error and we just write that error back
right
then we pick we take the new x value
that either the plus 1x or the plus 1y
well I think it's it's actually it's
actually - probably in both cases now I
think about it you probably you probably
want to instead of going plus going plus
both ways now that I think about it
actually implies you start here right so
maybe that's fine I don't really care it
doesn't matter just point being pick one
so that the pluses are the same so that
we don't have to compute a different
value by the way as I'm working this
through I'm thinking that actually the
interviewer didn't know half of the
things I'm saying here but that's beside
the point so we should be able to do
just the error compute it this way write
it back then we draw whichever point we
selected and continue the loop makes
sense now obviously the next question is
well at some point you're gonna have to
switch to going back down right like
you're gonna go like that and you're
gonna have to go back down and all this
other stuff right how do we do that the
final thing you need to think about in
order to make this routine fast again in
those days it is not how you would want
to do it today but if we look at what's
going on here what you can see is that
as we move around the circle it's really
eight-way symmetric if we want it to be
I mean a circle is an infinitely
symmetric shape I can draw any any line
through it
that I want right and it will be the
same after you mirror it so if I split
like straight down the middle for
example I know that every point I draw
here I could have just drawn on the
other side of the circle just fine
negating the X around the center right
so if I just always think of the X as
like plus X I could also just draw
negative X the same point right so that
means I really and I could do the same
with Y so that means I really only need
to draw one quadrant of the circle and
then I just mirror right instead of
the ex-wives I come up with I draw the
plus minus X plus minus y right so all
four combinations plus X plus y minus X
plus y plus X minus y plus oops minus X
minus y right so that gets me out of the
business of ever having to care about
going downward but if you look there's
one more symmetry you can do and I drew
it here and that's diagonal every point
on this circle that I draw XY I could
have also drawn YX right cuz it's
symmetric this way as well as that way
and that way so every point could have
been reflected about this line which
turns wise into X's and X's into Y's
right does that make sense so I can also
only draw 1/8 of the circle makes sense
so what I can do is rather than do all
of the work that you might think of for
drawing a circle I can literally do
something like while you know X is group
or I guess we're less than or equal to Y
you know do that if e1 less than e2 you
know
you know it's like this so you get the
whole drawing of your circle down to
that and then a big old honkin right
pixel right pixel right pixel right
pixel right pixel which are like memory
pokes into those addresses right make
sense so it you know essentially that is
what the interview question and you can
see like so let's say you interviewed me
today on anything related to this
because my mind already has gone through
this work I can just do it right and you
know that's the optimal result for an
interview question like this is to see
the person just like go off and like
show you all the possible things you
could have done but again it's kind of a
worthless interview question in my mind
because the this is called abrasion hand
style algorithm Brezhnev style
algorithms are algorithms that draw from
a known location based on minimizing
error as it steps along pixels you can
do them for lines as well and other
shapes pretty much anything that has an
implicit form can be drawn breast in ham
if you can find a starting point on that
shape then the brezin ham for the
algorithm is to remember what the error
is at the point that you're sitting on
and then as you draw all you do is look
at the two or three candidate points
that you want to examine and say which
one of these has the least error and you
go to that point right so really that's
that's it right that make sense
so yeah you know if you were to imagine
I don't know we're kind of in for a
penny in for a pound here should
probably upload this as a separate video
um let me just give you
so let's just say for sake of argument
right I don't know what we're gonna call
we got a test directory here I know
those are pings or something so in the
handmade Miss directory let's just say
that we've got a thing that's like like
a present ham Circle routine right so if
you imagine you're back in the old days
let's just say we have a pixel grid
right so there's a pixel grid in here
and we're just gonna make it up like the
way that it was back then where there's
just a block of memory that you write
bytes to and that's the entire thing
turn em san so basically what you want
to do is say alright live like let's say
we have a care here we have pixels and
our pixel grid is just going to be like
some kind of Sighs here that were we are
comfortable printing out like 64 by 64
right and they'll all start out equal to
0 and then what we're gonna do is we're
just gonna draw our pixel grid at the
end of the day and then exit the program
so if I were to do that what I can do is
say alright here's our output we're
gonna say that our X is 0 or X is less
than 64 right in fact I can just do this
okay so now what I want to do is just
say look if there was something in this
pixel slot like whatever it is and we'll
do X Y because that's just you know a
little bit more memory order order
friendly if there's something in that
slot then what I want to do is say like
draw something there that we know so you
know it would be something like a star
let's say oops and if there's something
there that we don't know that or rather
there was nothing there maybe we just
print a dot right so we can kind of see
what's going on every time we get to the
end we print carriage return right and
so maybe here I can also do like all
right pixels
you know 32 16 equals one okay so if I
come back here and I will go to the
build directory let's say and I just run
a CL on it so I just say CL you know
handmade misc be circle dot CPP and run
it what you can see is that it prints
out our pixel grid you know
quote-unquote right now we're super
eccentric here is the only problem like
you know this these this is not a square
font so it's gonna be like an elongated
kind of nonsense but that's just how
we'll deal with it well like what I can
do to compensate for that a little bit
is maybe make this a little bit smaller
so it's 32 by 32 and we'll plop the
middle you know middle point right so
there's our there's our nonsense and so
now we're gonna try and draw a circle
and the sword is going to be kind of an
oval because our
wrecked our coordinate system you know
is stretched right but we want to draw
our circle so we want to be able to
specify this and again no floating-point
here folks and these are really should
be shorts so you know it's really this
it's like unsigned short CX unsigned
short CY right you know we could leave
them sign too if we want doesn't really
matter because there's the pixel grids
back then we're like at best 640 by 400
or 40 so you didn't have to worry about
large numbers so you know here we've got
two short values this is going to be the
center of our circle wherever that is
and so let's say we want to draw one you
know that's centered at 10:12 and we
want the radius of our circle to be you
know six right so now I need to do my
drawing loop like I said I want to do a
drawing loop such that it starts at a
certain X&amp;Y that I know and then goes up
so that the x and y values will
basically cross at some point right and
that's how I know that I've done so I
want to do something where like my X
offset my Y offset our like our I'm not
sure to status so there's a couple
different ways I could do it one is I
can try to compute a value that are
stored that I know when my X crosses it
I've gotten over there or if I'm based
around zero I know that it's just when
the two flip so it's just like when X is
less than or Y or something right so if
I wanted to start off in that scenario
what I would first do is say well I know
that the x location that I'm starting
off at right is going to be like I
wanted that X location to be negative
right because I wanted to start on the
side where I'm always doing plus I'm
always doing a plus direction so I would
like to start off with
yeah I think that's right so I want to
start off with this as being the the
negative are right I'm gonna base it
around zero and I'm just gonna draw with
an offset so to base it around negative
R and then the Y I'm just gonna base a
zero right and then while these two well
I haven't actually crossed over yet so
while you know why and you can see that
X is gonna be negative here so it would
always be so I need to negate this in
order to do the check right meaning I
need to make sure that I as I step I
account for the fact that I'm negating
as I go now we may be able to optimize
all this stuff further as we start to
look at it more but just like for now
we're just trying to get it the basic
sketch in so then what I need to do is
say all right I need to compute my two
errors for starters and again we might
be able to simplify a lot of this but
we're just gonna start with the simple
the basic version of it and so for the
for the error if I look back at what we
were saying here right what I needed to
do is figure out if I start with the
previous error so like whatever the
previous error is over here yeah
so if I start with whatever the previous
error was right then I know that I need
to because the x squared plus y squared
minus R squared is whatever the previous
error for this thing was the plus one
plus two x is what comes out of me
computing the new value so first I need
to take my old error and I need to add
one to it to get that part of the value
right and then I need to go ahead and
and really I should probably write this
routine doing the whole computation
correctly and then do the optimized one
to show you the full thing we should
just do this whole thing some time as an
entire episode but anyway so what I want
to do here is say all right I need to
compute the updated version so I know
- the old error which I've already
committed by one plus the two X right
and then the new one is the old error
plus a2y right and now like I said I
don't actually want to do any kind of
multiply here I just want to shift right
I just want to multiply it by two by
shifting so then what I want to do is
say well I need to know which one is you
know for the absolute value whatever
that's going to be right I need to know
which one's absolute value is is is
greater right and I try to think if
there's some way we can avoid that but I
don't because it's a circle you might be
able to know that you'll always be
slightly above or equal to on a Y step
and slightly less than or equal to on an
x step so I want to say that be cut like
if you're going this way if you step
inside you're almost always gonna be
less and you step above you're always
gonna almost gonna be more so I want to
say you could do something probably like
this I want to say but we'll have to
actually analyze that a little bit more
right but I think you might be able to
get away with not actually looking at at
those values right so anyway we're gonna
do something like this and then we're
gonna record the old error as that thing
right so if in this case the old error
was if if in this case the the X step
was going to be the the better we'll
take it if in this case the Y error was
gonna be better we'll take it and when
we actually do the step here we need to
update our x and y values right I don't
know why I'm writing these in lowercase
or some of them not really how I do
things
so once we have those recorded we need
to do you know this or that and then
we're good to go
so finally we need to do a plot here and
this we will do a little bit differently
later but for right now we're just going
to do it this way so we're gonna do Y X
here to plot that particular pixel and
off we go right all right is that it
I've probably forgotten a lot of stuff
there but we're just gonna see what
happens
yeah we started out with an error of
nothing because we're assuming that
we're directly on the circle for our
definition of the circle right and this
was backwards actually meant that all
right uh sue I forgot one more thing
there we go all right um sue we are
accepting this step in the wrong
direction because this was a - right the
X is moving backwards on the actual I'm
sorry now they should be moving forward
what's why are we getting that plot oh
right because Y goes down this is
old-school Y goes down we're fine
all right so what we now need to do is
plot all the other points that I was
talking about before we need to plot you
know every single one of these so in
addition to doing this which is you know
taking each of the possible locations
into account here we also need to do
swapped versions
right so this draws every one of our
coordinates here right and now we've
sort of got our circle although it looks
like we've got one error in the oh no we
don't that's was just this right so now
we've got our circle but we don't really
have the plot of the initial pixel right
and so what we may want to do is change
us around to say let's start plotting
the thing that we were gonna plot in the
first place right and hey look there's
our circle Kanna so looking at what
happens here right you can see that we
can continue to make this even more
ridiculous as we go and reduce the
instructions even further I don't think
there were any conditional moves at that
time but if there were this becomes
branchless in a sense well not really
because you'd have to do too many of
them to probably make it worth it
because of the plus X plus y but anyway
so if you look at how simple this is
right it requires just two shifts one
negate and a check and then one equals
and one ad and that's it this part right
here is a little you know extra add to
do the ink so it's a little more cost
should be this part is incredibly
expensive so the question is what can we
do here that would is there something we
could do here that would make it less
bad right and there are a couple things
we could do certainly and one of them is
to just say well if we were to change
this pointer to just point at the center
to begin with right
we could get rid of the cyc X nonsense
right so if we did let's say we've got a
like a cursor:pointer and we make the
cursor:pointer be pointing to a specific
particularly the CX CY location then
when we drew this we would be able to we
would be able to just use x and y so if
this was a pointer to you know oh I know
what I was doing there good thing though
sore equals huh so if I do something
like that and then I say okay here's my
cursor oops oops
don't ask me what that type I was about
I want you to cast that for me well you
know what this is the step I was gonna
do next anyway so we'll just leave it at
this so let's say we've got our
cursor:pointer there right and then what
we need to do is we want to write to a
particular location in it right so I
know that I want to do this location but
I know that Y needs to move by whatever
the the stride is there right
right so each one of these Y values here
now has to be each one of those Y values
has to be multiplied by the width in
order to go the right number of pixels
right so we really need like times width
after each of these Y values and
remember these X values are effectively
Y values when they're you know in this
when they're being used in this bottom
half right because we're swapping the
two coordinates so if we drop I must
have missed somebody there I did sorry I
removed a negative right so now we're
down to cheaper but we've still got this
integer multiplied here right and the
integer multiply is not fabulous but if
you look at the structure of each of
these you can see that we actually don't
need anything other than right a Y value
times the width and an x value times the
width right because that's the only
value we're actually summing up there in
order to get our eight quadrants to come
together right so if we were to track
that value specifically rather than the
other values that we're tracking we
could simplify this even further now the
question is how do we keep that from
getting to be too many registers and
again I don't really remember how many
there are there might have been eight if
you didn't need to access the stack so
you could so if you well know you would
always need to store the no I guess if
you didn't have to access this but you
need to store where the stack is what
you can pop it so you wouldn't need that
so I think you'd at least you probably
only have seven registers at best I
don't know if it would be six or seven
how many you'd have but if you look at
how many we're using here we're using
one to store EP right and restoring two
more for x and y so we use three
registers already and then we probably
need a fourth register at least for
computing these values here probably two
registers so we probably need something
like five registers so we probably only
have two registers left to store the
pointers at best right and so the
question is what could we do here is
there any way we could make this do less
multiplies by storing two values instead
of one value for cursor right now all of
these plus X minus X plus if all of
that's pretty cheap right those ads are
not that bad and we know we have to
track x and y or do we I mean I guess we
don't necessarily but it seemed it would
seem pretty hard to not write so what we
really want to know is is there any way
we can speed up this x width here by
doing something else by tracking a value
that's like x width or something you
know like what can we do to fix this
right
and to be completely honest I don't
can't really think of it offhand
anyone got any ideas
I also I'm not sure we didn't really
check this right so you know is we may
have to do some more work here because
that is actually what we want I don't
know what that's in-game at that age
yeah looking at it though that's the
same that looks the same to me yeah so
that's this is the only part I'm not
sure about because I feel like we could
probably do this a little bit better
than we are and I guess if we were
because we would need the base value as
a problem I don't know
I don't really know how to simplify that
down to something that only takes two
slots
I mean I guess well no yeah I don't know
X fifth of five what would X shift up
five well yeah I mean assume that this
you don't know what that is right like
assume that that's that for something
right or you know this is more accurate
to what the situation really was right
so you can't use shifts anywhere
yeah the problem though is if you do it
like if we do any other kind of thing we
can't get the symmetry out of it right
if we just have the pointer that we're
using to write pixels - how do we
generate the other locations right
because it starts to become more
expensive to do that so we really it
because you really want to get the
symmetry out of it because it divides
the cost 13 by 8 right and so yeah and
someone was said store the X with an Y
with pointers you increment it currently
every run that's what I was thinking but
that's more than two registers because
you still need this value right because
you need to be able to negate the Y if
you if you stored four of them you could
do it but if you start two of them you
can't flip this thing at least not that
I can I can't think of how you do that
flip see it I'm saying so so there you
go but anyway that's something to
ruminate on that's that's the routine
right and and this this is effect this
is I think probably I don't know if it's
quite the best answer we might be able
to grind it a little a little further
than this but this was I think I ought
to be honest I think this was actually
better than the answer that the
interviewer sort of discussed at the end
of the question we're probably better
than they are at this point but that's
not surprising right it was just some
random dude at Microsoft
but that's effectively what it is right
um suppose thing I'm thinking on 68k
terms where they're a bit more ya 68k
had a lot more registers it's like twice
as many right I want to say the x86 was
really register starved that's just
you know everyone knew it nobody thought
it was good the thick were so few
freaking registers on the thing but yeah
so I don't know I I feel like this part
right here is the part we can really
improve this parts looking pretty tight
we may be able to optimize it very
slightly but it's pretty darn good right
it's it's like two shifts to adds a
compare well one add two shifts to adds
a compare to get the step and so yeah
like maybe we can get one of those out
of there but so here's a question though
here's a question we're starting to get
like way better I think than the answer
that the person gave at the time if ap
is added to each one then do we ever
actually care like this is an affine
this is an affine transform of the
equation but we don't care what the
affine transform of the equation is
because the affine transform of the
equation just moves it everything in
space over by one so in theory we should
be able to do this right and get the
same circle
I guess not
that's a different circle I guess
because of the negation here yeah that's
true it's moving it this way but we're
flipping one of them so I guess I I lied
about that so never mind I guess oh well
you know what though so if we're only
ever testing negative a zero
I suppose you could negate this
potentially you might be able to flow
that through a little bit differently
yeah I'd have to think about that but no
I guess I don't know you can't even get
rid of that so I'm not sure I'm not that
might be just about as good as it's
gonna get it's this negation that that
hurts here because otherwise you could
just clip out EP entirely because this
would let you know it's worth asking the
question can you just compare in some
other way so that you'd only have to
look at these two here and I'm not sure
about that
so there might be a little bit more
right there might be a little bit more
we can get out of that yeah George asked
the same thing can you get rid of the EP
plus equals one line and you could have
if if you didn't negate because negating
this means that the plus one actually
becomes a minus one for the e zero right
which is different than it is here
so this negation is what makes that not
possible
so yeah
so what if we changed our thinking on
this just a little bit so what if we
said look for this whole thing we're
just gonna negate the x value from what
it was right like we're just gonna we're
gonna flip the x value so if I just
negated X the whole way through it would
look like this right probably now that
that's actually still that
something like that that wrong yeah
that's totally wrong I need to do that a
little cleaner so if I wanted to gate X
here oops I know what it forgot to do
there we go so I find a gate X all the
way through then it looks like this and
I still draw the same circle right
it's that same circle yeah
and so negating Excel the way through
there does that give us any options that
we wouldn't have had otherwise I don't
really think that it does so applying
this negative here if we've wanted to
work it back through so if we said we
wanted that easy row now has to be
computed as negative right
and I guess it would have to be negated
in here though
right but we can do that if we want to
um so yeah that ends up like this I
don't that doesn't seem to really do
anything good for us though I can't see
how that would help because we still
have the negation in there the because
the its ep it still is EP plus 1 or e P
minus 1 right depending on the
circumstance
so maybe mmm yeah I just don't I don't
see it I don't see how to get rid of the
plus 1 because no matter what we do it
seems like that plus 1 right is just
it's not it's not
it's not going back in here it's always
gonna have to be like a minus one or a
plus one right like I just don't I don't
see I don't see any way we can eliminate
this line because this always wants to
be the other way round like it always
wants to change which whether you're
going plus one or minus one
based on the stepping here I mean I
guess what we could say is if we just
wanted to change the direction that X
was going just entirely though you know
with that would there be some way for us
to do that
I mean if we started oh wow so here's a
mind bender for you since we don't care
which part of the circle we compute the
X and the y on what if we reflected it
so that the x value is actually drawing
on a different part of the circle than
the Y if we say that right and we change
this to just be based on like some kind
of an R value then I think we could get
rid of it this this test knowing when
you're done does seem hard
so so that part I'm not sure about one
thing we could do and this is a real
wild shot I don't really know one thing
we could do is this I don't think that's
going to work but then we would
literally just be doing this I think so
we're actually not even ever really
drawing any we're not following a path
along the circle we're just starting X
at the origin and Y at the origin and
we're just stepping along two separate
circles seeing which step we probably
should take first I don't know I don't
know if this will work this condition I
don't know yeah cause it could it just I
don't know what condition to stop on
that's not going to require us to
compute some other value is the only
problem because at that point you kind
of need to say look while X is less than
like half of our or something you know
it would it would be like this and that
requires like another register you know
so yeah all right I screwed up something
there but you know what I mean right
like that
so let's well let me try that let's try
that and see if we get that to work
that's a real Mindbender so basically
what we're saying there is okay if if
the step on on X would produce less
error than the step on Y even though
we're stepping them on totally different
places on the circle
let me look at that equation again so if
I wanted to step x and y and I just
wanted to eliminate the plus one right
the problem there is in the absolute
value of e 1 and E 2 right otherwise we
could just do it but the absolute value
flips around which wave that plus 1 is
going now if I want to step on the
circle I feel like this should work
though I feel like we should be able to
do it this way why wasn't that why
didn't that work
I I wish I understood quite why that
didn't work
I guess that's because there needs to be
a differentiation between them otherwise
they're both doing the same thing let me
look at this one more time so here's the
original right and what we're actually
doing here when we write when we're
computing this the only difference
between these two paths is that the X
part is getting that that negation right
and the two steps have to do something
different but I guess they are because
one's X one's Y right since I should be
able to flip the x coordinate just fine
the thing that's a little confusing to
me is why I can't change it to computing
directly off of the exome directly off
of an x0 y0 right so this straight down
here here's what I'm saying so let's
suppose that we always wanted to have X
step in a way that would increase the
error on the top side of the circle and
Y so in order to do that let's say we
start the Y this way and we start the X
this way right because in both cases now
we're always going to be pushing the
error when we step right we're always
going to be pushing the error out
further as we go you know I'm Sam
and and I feel like wasn't this a minus
minus X before why is that still a plus
plus X huh I guess we inverted that at
some point I don't remember that anyway
so yeah drawing the circle this way it
feels like we should be able to say like
look take a step here if the error would
be less than taking a step here you know
what I'm saying to you but I guess it's
because the error doesn't track properly
it's a little mind-bending for me I'm
not sure how to analyze that properly
right
it just it feels like we should be able
to get those down to both going the same
direction but but somehow we don't so
now we aren't able to and I and I don't
well it well I understand maybe slightly
just in terms of wrote equation
manipulation why that's happening I
don't actually my intuition is failing
to grasp it which bothers me so like
like I want to be able to intuit why
that can't happen in a way that's a
little bit more straightforward because
right now I'm having trouble with that
if you get rid of the EP plus what
you're really asking is is X shifted
down by one I was sorry if if 2x is
different than 2 which which one is
greater 2 X or 2 y right which is
basically the same as just asking if X
or Y is greater right
yeah so I guess maybe the reason is
because since those values are based off
of the original equation you and you
need them to correctly work around 0
maybe that's the best you can do
duskie I'm sorry we decided to go with
another candidate because he went to
Harvard if if you're hiring criteria for
4cs people is that they went to Harvard
who that company is going in the tank
quick I don't know that's when to
ruminate on I think it's a fun little
puzzle right and and I don't know you
can also look up the you know this is a
if I'm spelling that right
[Music]
I was kind of hoping they would have it
minimize down to code so we could see
what they get this are e
whoa
so that seems bad like that does a bunch
of multiplies there I guess I guess it's
really just a shift by four which is
fine
I'm sorry shift by two right I don't
know what this isn't that different from
ours I suppose it looks basically the
same actually this part I'm not so sure
about so you're this this is assuming
you only ever draw one pixel on like you
can't ever draw two pixels upward which
seems weird I guess you could say that
because you if you're just doing the top
part you just assume you never do that
right so that's that seems like an
interesting way to do it
maybe like in other words that's an
optimization we didn't do but like and I
also don't know if the automation you
need to bother with but basically what
they were saying is like look either
we're gonna increment the Y or we're
gonna increment the Y and the X so they
they basically did that right which I
think we could do the same thing
probably although it might be we have to
yeah we would have to maybe do it the
opposite way around I'm not sure which
one we have our preference on yeah so if
you were to do the Y always you could do
that if you wanted to based on the way
we have it structured I don't really
know that you would care on these old
computers you would rather just do it
this way I would think but I don't know
because I think you get it better yeah I
think you get a better circle maybe this
way but maybe you don't I mean maybe you
like that one better so that's hard to
say
but we we don't really save anything by
doing that I don't think and I feel like
you need to do the update like you need
to work the update back in so that that
you count for the fact that you're doing
that every time if that makes sense
although it produces kind of an
I circle if you don't which is kind of
interesting we should make our circle a
little bit bigger just to make sure it
still looks nice to the circle but it
does seem to all right
[Music]
i'ma leave that as an exercise for the
reader to get better it will get checked
in but I feel like this part here it
would really be interesting because if
you look at how many registers it
requires you know to do this it's three
for these probably five once you can
once you do this and maybe you you could
probably do it slightly differently
maybe but I don't know but then I feel
like and then six for this I'm not sure
what else you could really do you know I
don't I don't see a lot of other stuff
there cuz this is really this is really
what's gonna kill you this part here is
now pretty free compared to this this is
just brutal right because look at all
these integer multiplies that have to
happen you really don't want those
integer well supplies in there
on these old machines right that's
really really bad so I really think this
is the most important thing to address
and I'm not sure how to best address it
you
they're just a register cow here it is
so the 386 added definitely added the
had the 32-bit stuff which we surmise I
don't know if the 286 did or not but it
it does look like we would be super
register starved so we probably would
need to do better than what we're doing
right it just let's take a look the 286
surely there is some
surely somebody lists the registers come
on Ricky chip you can do it maybe we
could chip can't do it there it is Wow
so okay there's like no data
so it looks like it's the same as the
8086 maybe
well so interestingly enough maybe we
can have four of these so maybe what we
could have done is use four registers
total by being clever and then maybe if
we really do have four address registers
we can use those for doing the four
drawings and then it would work
maybe I don't really know so I don't
know this would be an interesting
exercise to basically go rework this
routine on an actual 286 emulator right
with like actual 286 assembly code
although I guess you don't really you
know I mean there's like like DOSBox
right like you could take this right and
you could compile actual Azzam that that
actually draws like you kids you could
do mode 13 or something or any graphics
mode really or just do what I did where
you'd use the console and see to get
like a to see what you could fit in here
using only the registers available right
because that would be interesting
exercise I feel like to make work and
just see like whether or not there's
good ways of doing this stuff because
this looks brutal and like this is
definitely like
I think that's really the place all
right so this this episode of hand may
here is probably never going to actually
be an episode of hand made here oh sorry
folks we've just gotten too far off
topic this will have to be a hand made
chat instead sorry
hi Casey sorry it's pretty long and has
nothing to do with circles I'm a
mathematician trying to be a graphics
engine programmer I made some pet
projects using up until in folk in which
I was able to make the things I wanted
but since my lack of experience I had a
hard time figuring out what professional
programming is I started watching you
here in December from day one I almost
caught up going to day 5:20 thanks to
miniseries it has been in yeah and then
it got cut off well I'm very glad to
hear that I don't know if that was a
question any if there's something I can
answer for you please let me know
otherwise thanks for the kind words as
always it's always great to hear people
who can use a series to get them where
they want to be you know
I don't like so this twitch is it twitch
or hex chat who is clipping off like
something's that happen someone types in
a long question and it gets like
truncated who is doing that is that
twitch to twitch only have like a like a
Twitter like limit on the number of
characters get entered cuz like I only
end up seeing like if I look at hex chat
here I only see part of it you know what
let me look over in the twitch chat
window and see does that happen in there
as well yeah so it happens in so
twitch chat twitch chat just basically
just just poops out that is at a fairly
low counter character limit probably
because they were trying to avoid like
spam and stuff but I mean we should
probably put up like a little PSA and
it's like hey folks when you ask
questions if they're long like break
them into multiple chunks you know
because yeah I looked in twitch ad and
it was truncated there too at least on
mine
okay so there's the question jimmy
advice about sorry korean graphics
engine program for someone who has very
strong background mathematics physics
can do research perhaps can co-create
ideas wants to learn etc um I don't have
a lot of advice about that because I
don't really know what the best way to
get into this stuff is but you know the
only really thing that I've that I've
sort of said that that I can contribute
to suggestions there because again I'm
not really involved the only time I'm
ever involved in hiring people really
these days is if I if someone does
something really you know obviously
pretty impressive I try to send them
somewhere that you know can make use of
them right so I guess what I would say
is the only thing that I would do that
maybe if you're not already doing it cuz
you know I can't really give you advice
about like how to make a resume or where
to send it or stuff like that because I
don't really know how those processes
work I would recommend going and
listening to on on the on handmade
heroes channel there should be so on
here there should be a playlist for
handmade con 2016 yeah here - no no I
didn't want an ad thank you uh let's see
here just wanted to show someone where
the stuff is so this handmade controi
system technical direction at Blizzard
that's probably the best place to look
for just an overview of like how you
generically get hired at like one of
these larger companies to like start
building a resume in the game industry I
would look at that
so maybe Google for 20s handmade con
2016 technical direction at Blizzard
I would I would listen to that and just
just to it's only like an hour or
something or two hours so you just
listen to what he has to say
he's a technical director for world of
warcraft so they hire people and they
hire junior people occasionally right
and he talks about how those how that
pipeline goes so you probably listen to
that just to get that straight but the
other thing that I would suggest is if
you have time so if you are a swing time
look you watch the handmade hero series
you've got some time right there's a lot
of videos in there try to think of how
to make something that people can see
that you know what you're doing right so
you know obvious like kind of above and
beyond examples are like people who I've
sent places already like Allen Webster
did for coder right he just made an
editor and sent it to me he's like here
here's an editor it it replaces Emacs
for you anyone who can do that is just
useful right you know that if someone
can just make a whole text editor from
scratch and see right not like down we
downloaded some rich text control and
just wired it up to a menu right but
like I actually wrote the whole thing
they're obviously useful like like you
can put them on any team and any good
manager will be able to make them useful
right because they obviously have what
it takes you know to do something useful
on a team the same was true for nicks
Lifta right he wrote a full debugger I
sent him to rad because they were
working on a debugger project I'm like
here's a dude who already made a whole
debugger right the same would be true
for for George but George already has a
job he's the guy who made the debugger
we we use right now same will be true
for the for this this program here
Milton we haven't talked about in a
while but it was actually done by oh I
didn't actually know there was a
no there really isn't nevermind anyway I
sergio made milton and i don't know if
he's got i don't know if he has a pager
here anyway
you might not I guess he doesn't anyway
he made Milton and it's like an entire
drawing package that you know replaces a
commercial one that we were using before
and it's just as good right so it's like
hey this person is capable of making an
entire commercial drawing package read
themselves when you get that much
obvious stuff out like when someone
could just point was like oh this person
obviously knows they're doing it makes
it easy for someone like me or you know
any of the streamers like John blow
whatever if you have something that's
obviously you know what you're doing
then they can send you somewhere or hire
you themselves right but people who are
just like I'm pretty good but I have
nothing to point to that shows that I am
it's a lot harder right because then
you're talking about well you know no
one's gonna go out of their way to tell
some other tech director or somebody to
take a look at you because they have no
idea if you're good or not right there's
no obvious thing to look at and
furthermore like as a resume thing
there's nothing that obviously
distinguishes you from anybody else etc
so why what we said like yeah the best
thing to do if you've got some time make
something that shows me what you're
doing
make your raytracer make asteroids make
a tool that people want to use anything
that you can think of to distinguish
yourself if you can do it do that that's
the easiest way to show that you know
what you're doing is to actually
accomplish something right and so that's
the only really advice I think I could
give is if you do have the time to do
something like that
do it the other thing I would say it's
I've said a couple times its technical
blog blog about what you're doing right
and show that you are thinking through
these technical problems and that you
are able to like work your way through
them right it doesn't have to be the
kind of technical blog that's like
let me tell the world about some new
stuff they don't know about right
because you're not necessarily trying to
say hi I'm the best program in the world
or something right what you're trying to
say is I'm a good junior programmer
because that's all you need that's the
only threshold you need to cross to get
hired right because people hired you in
your programmers there's plenty places
that too so all you need to do is have a
blog that shows look I am capable of
working through these problems and I can
show that I understand them right and
that is also another way to you know to
have a concrete thing to point to that
can differentiate you from the average
candidate right so so that's you know
that's about all I can give you for
advice it's like try to do stuff that
shows you know what you're doing so you
don't just have to tell someone you're
good they can see that you're good right
and you don't have to be better than a
pro because the pros already have jobs
you just have to show that you take more
initiative and are more curious and
harder working right then the average
candidate beginner right so that's
that's I guess the best advice I could
give and whatever you can figure out to
do that that is the best thing to do and
then you know you can just show up on
one of these streams show up on drop
stream my stream or whatever just say
hey I made this thing like what do you
think if it's cool and we'll we'll look
at it right and if it is there will be
like a pool and you know we'll say oh
let me try to send you somewhere or
whatever right but otherwise it's just
showing up and singing I'm like I don't
know right like I don't know maybe
you're actually really not good and so
I'm not gonna I'm go wreck amend any to
someone to somebody if I don't have
something to point to this that makes me
think right but socho make it easy make
it easy for the person to go oh this
person is not the average person who
wants to work on games or something you
know make it the easier you make it the
more likely someone will just like
everything else when it comes to selling
something in this case you're selling
your job services right
like anything else whenever you're
trying to sell something the goal is to
just make it as easy easy as possible
for the buyer to say yes and so give
them every reason to think that you're
better than the other people who are
saying the same thing that's the best I
can offer
for what it's worth PCM has cycle exact
CPU cores if you want to be more
accurate
oh that sounds kind of cool I don't
think I've ever heard of that what's
this oh look at that well that's just
fun right there
on one of the first hand media streams
you said it was faster to work bitwise
on a you at 32 than on a you an eight
why did I really say that I'm not sure
what I would have meant by that I can
sort of say some things that could be
meant by that so probably the I mean
hopefully if I wasn't just completely
drunk that day or something probably
what I was trying to communicate was
that in in much the same way like in the
past I've said doubles are half the
speed of floats right but what I'm
trying to say there is the effective
speed of doing what you're trying to do
so on a modern x86 processor it's
actually the same speed to do bit
operations on a u8 as it is to do them
on a u-32 but doing them on a u-32 does
four bytes at a time so any bit
operation I'm trying to do if I can do
it on a full u-32 it's four times faster
than doing it on a u8 right because I'm
doing four bytes at a time instead of
one so I don't really know what the
context was that I was talking about
there so that may have nothing to do
with it but generally speaking anytime
you can like modern processors tend not
to differentiate much in terms of speed
based on width so doing something a
twined 8 bits wide versus 16 bits wide
versus 32 bits wide versus 64 bits wide
versus 120 bits wide versus 256 bits
wide well not quite that at this point
but let's say under 28 bits wide through
all the same speed right and so if you
can do your operation on a full 128 bits
at a time then that operation is just
like fundamentally going to be 16 times
faster than doing it on a u8 because you
did 16 bytes all at once now I don't
know if that's why I was talking about
or not but that's really the way to
think about it is if you have to do
things a byte at a time it's gonna be
twice
slow as if you did them short at a time
which is gonna be twice as slow as if
you did them you 32 at a time which is
gonna be twice as slow as if you did
them a 64-bit register at a time where's
gonna be twice as slow as if you have a
hundred twenty eight bit register at a
time right that's all really I'm trying
to say and the same goes for
floating-point operations it doesn't
take probably much longer I don't know
it depends we have to look at the cycle
counts but for a lot of things like
adding two floating-point numbers
together it probably takes the same
amount of time to add doubles as it does
to add floats we can look but usually
it's like roughly the same but you can
only fit two doubles into a twenty
hundred trade bit registers where you
can set four floats so even though the
add takes the same amount of time you
did twice as many ads in the same amount
of time right so it's still twice as
fast now in the future that will go even
higher it'll go up to 256 or 512 but at
the moments like on any chips that I
have anyway doing operations on 512 bit
wide registers are actually not as fast
as doing them on 128 bit wide registers
and the reason for that is actually
really complicated it's not because
they're double pumped it used to be that
used to be true and still is true on
some chips like like for example AMD
chips will like double pump eight wide
avx2
and stuff like that so it can be true
that can't be the reason but even when
they're not double pump so let's say you
have a full 512 bit wide chip or a full
Tunis it's about 56 per chip it may
still not be as fast as doing it 128 bit
wide and the reason is because the power
consumption becomes problematic so not
all chips can run as fast through the
256 and 512 paths as they can through
the hunter 8-bit path that's just
reality right so you have to be careful
making assumptions about the 256-bit
wide and the 512 bit wide cases it's not
as straightforward
128 bit wide cases right the 128 bit
wide case pretty much just runs at speed
with the right power curve and
everything's fine 26 and 512 may or may
not and you have to actually like look
at it to see and also there's weird
stuff so even on modern like core I
nines the latest core I nines I think
but but takes for the grand saw cuz you
know my chip knowledge isn't wishy-washy
but I think even on the latest core I
nines the chip powers down the 256 and
512 bit lanes when they're not in use so
there's even this extra weird penalty
for using them which is that you can't
use them sporadically if you're gonna
use them you have to use them constantly
so that it doesn't power down that part
of the chip because if you hit them the
first time there's like a massive like
you know it's like tens of thousands of
cycle penalty or something like this to
spin them up right so you can't just
like use them and then not use them and
use them and not you've got to like spin
them up and keep them spun up or some
weird nonsense like this I don't have a
lot of experience program within 20 50
to 256 to the 5th 512 wide lanes for
really hardcore optimization stuff
largely cuz most chips just don't have
that stuff so it's not an issue but you
know
any opinion of Linux way to find earlier
types with one letter like you ate I
seem well that's what I do
so in handmade hero you know obviously
I'm a fan because I that's what I do I
don't know if you've been following
along at all but we we do that so so
these are the types that we we use so I
mean if you're just looking at my pie
like it I used to use longer ones like
like I used to use them this way and I
eventually just even during handmade
here I decided I liked them even shorter
so we kind of went this week at some
point we should probably tease and just
go through and remove all but you know
it's not a big deal but yeah I do like
the short ones I don't I didn't I didn't
know that was like a Linux way of doing
it I've that's how like Jeff doesn't it
rad that's really where I got it from I
don't know the Linux part of things but
puck with a gun needs to be an enemy in
the game yeah we could I wouldn't be
averse to that someone wants to put it
in the github it wants to file a bug in
the github for a feature request for a
program for Windows only is DX the
better orb shell DX is it's just better
supported so if you're only if you're
only shipping your windows for you
definitely DX
generally speaking I'd say you probably
want to do DX on Windows these days
anyway not OpenGL cuz you wanna do like
DX on Windows and metal on Apple you
really can't do cross very well when
you're getting a college degree in
information technology should you
instead be working on hobby projects my
dad isn't wanting me to get into a post
secondary school for a long time um I
think I guess I think the the key is
just whatever makes you learn and get
better is the best thing to do I didn't
go to college of any kind so I don't
think it's necessary at all but that's
if you're the type of person who's like
very self-motivated and learns on their
own really well and if you're not then
that isn't gonna work right so I think
whether or not additional schooling
makes sense depends a lot on the person
you know and and you kind of have to
self assess right you have to figure out
like what's gonna work best for you I
don't super find that College CS stuff
is very good seems to be kind of crappy
so while it's better than nothing it's
probably not good for the working
programmer like maybe if you're someone
who wants to go in and like study
church's thesis or something like that
then College CS degrees make sense but I
will say that like the quality of actual
like coding behavior that tends to come
out of colleges seems to be pretty bad
so there's that
like there's probably some universities
where they actually teach you how to
program well but I kind of get the
feeling from my experience that most
don't probably because most college
professors don't really know how to
program very well that's not really
their job like long haul hard work
programming is just not what they do
every day right they publish papers and
like put together research these sorts
of things where the quality of the code
is not really ever gonna get tested
particularly much and that the amount of
output is very low compared to what a
hardcore commercial programmer you know
what I would expect from them or want
from them so it seems like the college
style of programming tends to be more in
line with what I see in like the 1,000
web programmers at Twitter and we don't
ever seem to get anything done kind of
programming which is like highly
theoretical a lot of nonsense process
stuff that doesn't really work not very
much output per programmer not a lot of
visible quality control like that sort
of thing just just generally taking lots
of people to do not very much not very
well right and it seems like they hire a
lot along with college degrees right and
so it seems like that kind of whole
pipeline is sort of the same general
thing up and down so I don't think
highly of that stuff
I really don't but that's not to say
that that's true everywhere right
there's probably some universities where
there are some professors who are very
serious about programming and those are
probably the kinds of places that would
churn out as a product of their
education better actual commercial
programmers but that from what I've seen
is not the norm so you know keep that
perspective maybe in the back of your
head a little bit I have done lots of
tools and see like string utility
json.parse or data visualization on
Linux using x11 vector lip and some
other tools do you think these can be
valuable for the seed
um possibly right again I would probably
say I I just give like vague advice I
mean I don't know I it's been so long
since I've tried to apply for a job in
the game industry in the traditional way
like I mean I never really did so I
can't really give good advice on that
very well all I can say is imagine you
were me or some other person with some
connections who could recommend a person
right so you're somebody who knows
people who do hiring and the question is
how do you get that you know how do you
get me to say oh this person seems to
know what they're doing right and it's
probably worth hiring me as in an
entry-level position what am I going to
go to your website and find that's gonna
make me think that right so it may well
be that some utility you've already made
could be that thing if it's true dress
it up make some posts about it make it
clear why it's interesting or what you
did on it do you know what I'm saying I
you know let's say you were like hey I
want to make a really high speed json
parser so I started with my json parser
and I profiled it and I did some back of
them of compilations to figure out how
what's memory bandwidth how close I
could get to that like do a bunch of
like blog posts on what's the fastest
possible JSON parsing I could do or
something right that's one good example
another example would be how do I make a
really good JSON parsing library here's
me analyzing the API looking how easy it
is to use try a couple different
variants looking at the usage code what
makes the smalls uses code how do I deal
with a memory properly right just seeing
is I made a JSON parser doesn't help me
right I have no context for whether or
not that person's good or bad but show
me something that shows you think
through these
you work hard at them you can solve real
things you know what the metrics are
right
give me something to latch on to and
point me at that that's the key right so
I don't know like hopefully that kind of
helps I just don't know how to how to
say it really any other way other than
if people like me are busy we're doing
stuff all the time so you know we're not
gonna spend a ton of time going and
figuring out if some other person is is
good to hire or not right but if you can
make it obvious
like if you can make it so that I want
to go read your blog because I'm gonna
learn something or it's just interesting
what you did or whatever right that gets
you in the mix for free you see I'm
saying so just I don't know like put
yourself in that headspace go how do I
make it so that someone who's busy is
not gonna spend a lot of time because
stuff gets interested in what I did
right that's the puzzle you're trying to
solve fundamentally that's the only real
way to bypass that I just send a giant
stack of CDs to everyone and hope the
random people at HR who don't know
anything about anything happened to pit
pull mine out of the like the rabbit hat
right
do you think it's enough to have a
YouTube channel instead of a webpage it
depends a YouTube channel is sometimes a
harder sell because someone has to like
actually set aside time to look at it
like keep in mind that most people read
most stuff on their phone or something
on the bus or waiting in line or while
they're commuting right and so if they
don't have their headphones on or if
they don't write you know are they
really gonna click through to a YouTube
channel how long are they gonna watch it
for right so you know I would consider I
mean how hard is it to put up something
I mean even Fabien Wright who has one of
the best technical blogs in the world um
he didn't bother making his own blog
it's just on some hosted sites like
WordPress or something right so just
just do that no one cares that Fabien
didn't make his own website um here let
me show you he just needed somewhere to
post so he did and everyone reads it
because it's really high quality right
right so it's just it's just this thing
and here's all this stuff and it's all
really good right so you know I mean
Fabien doesn't need to apply for a job
because he probably has like infinite
people who would hire him if he wasn't
already hired but the point is it's the
quality of the stuff on the site that
matters here not whether you made the
webpage so just do whatever doesn't
matter WordPress blogger I don't know go
type in some random thing like best
blogging site and just go there and put
up the content right it's the content
that matters not that you made the
webpage so you don't have to worry at
all about that
you know just if it's good enough for
Fabi and it's good enough for you for
sure right
Oh someone's asking why we're suggesting
to look at how to do it under 26 because
they were asking me about a Microsoft
job interview question that I got and
back when I interviewed as an intern and
so the question is how do you draw a
circle as quickly as possible the answer
nowadays has nothing to do with like any
of that stuff that I just showed this
basic concept of looking at x squared
plus y squared minus R squared it still
remains because hey that's the equation
for a circle but the actual way that you
solve it is nothing to do with that
right and that's because you need to
operate on wide registers now so you
need to be testing multiple things at
once more than two and so you need to do
things a little differently in order to
draw circles quickly right so I've been
using a language function polymorphism
similar I think to what John is doing
Jay I multiple dispatched especially
appetizers I recently tried out
different language types not all very
common how come not where languages have
this is it hard to implement or other
issues
um I guess to be completely honest with
you I'm gonna try not to be too overly
negative but my opinion is that most
language designers have no idea what
they're doing and that is why things
like double dispatch aren't a part of
the language right dispatch on types is
just something that you build you can
build n dimensional sparse matrices for
you should allow at least the
metaprogramming capabilities to do that
any language that doesn't have that in
2020 which is what we're coming up on
here is ridiculous obviously see the
stuff doesn't have it because as I've
said many times they have absolutely no
idea how to design a language or even
what the point of a language is so I
would say it's probably just
incompetence
right that's not to say that it's that
important of a language feature I don't
know that
dynamic dispatch across multiple types
at the same time is really that
important for most programs I think
sometimes people think it is but usually
it's actually not but that's not a
reason why your language shouldn't
support it cleanly because it's it's not
that tricky right so I don't have an
answer better than in confidence I think
it's just incompetence
I heard Jay I supposed to beta release
will you be playing around with that or
leaving it until it's matured more um if
I have time up here maybe we'll play
around unlike a stream you know at some
point when when John feels like it's
worth that you know he I would trust his
judgment
have you met the immediate programmer
like Bruce Dawson it seems they were
great programs I'm sure Bruce will be
happy to hear that yes I do know Bruce
Dawson personally amusingly enough
because he worked actually at cave dog
which was right over in Woodinville and
then after cave dog he went to Microsoft
first anyway then he ended up at valve
and now I think he's at Google so he's
always kind of been around this area
actually in in recent years I think he
might have been Canadian originally um
which is why he worked at cave dog I
think he might have known Chris maybe
that's not true I can't remember I can't
remember how he knew Chris Chris Taylor
or how he got hired that maybe knew Ron
Gilbert I don't know I don't know that
part of his backstory but yeah I love
Cigna said that was a great achievement
in text setting for sure
Bruce is a an optimization kind of kind
of person I have met him but you know I
hadn't really worked with him I don't
have a lot to say about him personally
because I don't you know I I've never
really worked with him on that stuff but
but i but I hadn't met would I have met
him uh would you sign cosign now no you
pretty much never want to use sine and
cosine for things like drawing a circle
at least not that I can think of unless
what you're trying to do is actually
compute like points on the circle right
so if you're trying to rasterize a
circle you don't really need to skip
along it so if I'm trying to produce
like points along a circle sure I'd use
sine and cosine now because that's
really the only way to do it that I can
think of but if you're trying to just
rasterize it you can still just use
implicit function evaluation for that so
you usually do are you gonna press the
circle decision to pick up
yeah it'll automatically go into the
source code control because I put it in
miss directory so it should just be
there do you ever use any scripting
language not if I can avoid it
I don't really like underpowered
languages very much is there any
computer world outside us
I'm not sure what you mean by that but
if you mean are people outside of the
United States making important
contributions to computing or running
large companies that do important
projects the answer is like absolutely
yes I mean so much so that if you look
at things like Grand Theft Auto 5 the
most profitable game in history
that's a UK development based
organization although kind of have stuff
all over the world you can look at The
Witcher developed I want to say entirely
in Poland is that correct
one of the biggest engine projects in
recent history right there's unity that
was originally developed outside the US
as well although they have us plenty of
u.s. offices now right but not not us I
don't know where most of like Ubisoft
development happens now but like
Montreal like Canada houses at least
very important parts of like the
snowflake engine studio which which does
I think I think that's I think that's
done in Montreal and I think it's what's
used for like the division and stuff
right things like this and then I know
they have they've got like offices of
France as well
there's Croteam right the people who
made both serious sam and the talus
principal there in croatia there's you
know i mean and i'm these are just off
the top of my head right and so
at least in the game industry obviously
tons of people all over the place at the
risk of stating the obvious the
PlayStation the Nintendo switch you know
these are originally Japanese companies
obviously the PlayStation 4 mostly made
in the US PlayStation 2 and prior a lot
of that stuff was Japanese based
Nintendo always in Japan for most of
their stuff although again the switch is
now mostly us because it's like an
Nvidia shield basically right but I mean
you know Super Mario 2 see breath of the
wild these are Japanese oriented
development projects obviously very
important to the latest generation of
games and there's tons of you know
Capcom the Japanese game industry is
obviously you know shouldn't need much
introduction I mean hopefully most
people are aware of what's going on in
in Japan game wise so there's a ton of
stuff happening there I'm less familiar
with like Chinese and Korean game
development but they've got a ton of it
a lot of MMO base development happens
there obviously player unknowns
battlegrounds developed in Korea there's
a bunch of MMOs that I don't really know
personally much about I can't remember
all the names of them they're like black
sea black pearl something like that was
a big one there's obviously a bunch of
web companies in China like you know
there's like Baidu line is is like the
Asian equivalent of things like Twitter
or Facebook sorts of things I think
they've got over there that we're just
totally a black desert is that it anyway
I don't know a lot of those because I
you know I don't play MMOs I'm really
ignorant about that segment of the
market and obviously since I don't speak
fluent Chinese languages or Japanese
like I can't speak Mandarin I can't
speak Japanese I can't speak Korean I
don't have a lot of experience on there
like instant message platforms or social
network sites but there
all fair right so there's tons of work
going on everywhere South America is it
seems like less influential at the
moment but gaining ground there's a lot
of game developers sort of starting to
do work in South America that's becoming
more relevant right game developers in
Argentina right like Daniel Ben Burcu a
for example who made Fidel dungeon
rescue which is a great game Argentinian
developed in Argentina uh and there's
game industry stuff developing down
there it's just I don't know of anything
big to point to like I don't think
they've necessarily had like the
crossover hit where I can point to
something you would have heard of in the
US that was developed there but I might
just be missing it but they it started
right and so I feel like you give it
time you know things take time to to get
enough talent to get enough experience
in an area to make like a breakout hit
or whatever right so I don't so that's
one obviously there's tons of
programmers in in Russia India I just
don't really know what they're working
on
I'm sure there's stuff I just don't know
what it is right I don't know of any
like big games to point to that come
came out of Russia or India but there
probably was probably a lot of contract
work happens there too on other people's
projects right like a lot of places have
like subsidiaries there that do work on
them that you may not have heard of
necessarily but right and then I'd also
point out like Israel is a great example
of a place that has tons of computer
stuff for
of all intel's israel operation was the
people who developed like a lot of the
core stuff you use Amex 64's chips
today right
like the pentium like the p3 core was
entirely them i think i i don't know how
much of the modern core is then probably
a lot they do a lot of work in israel on
the on the course obviously I think ways
was drilled from Israel like the mapping
thing which is very popular now I don't
know all the things that are developed
in Israel but there's a lot so that's
another hotbed of development both both
hardware and software um I don't know
much about the Middle East more broadly
like you know Iran Iraq Jordan Qatar
I don't know offhand of much that comes
out of there but you know there probably
would be Dubai you a lot of those places
are wealthy they probably could have a
suffrage I don't know if they do
Singapore has a large had a large push
for game developers at one point I just
don't know what came out of it I think
LucasArts might have located some people
there I don't know I would suspect
Singapore's got some I'm sorry I jumped
from the Middle East to Singapore home
sudden it's not that far I guess but
it's not really the same area um but I
know that Singapore has got a large tech
push I just don't
again know of what comes out of there
exactly some people on the chat probably
would does anyone know if Israel has a
large industry feel like most of Israel
speaks English right
I would assume that like I mean I could
be way off base here but I would assume
that Israel like it's pretty much
English as the official language and
probably also maybe has like you know
Hebrew or something as a as a cultural
language or something like this but I'm
pretty sure Israel would would be mostly
speaking English you know in any text
setting that would be my assumption I
would I would I would assume that most
Israeli tech people are are pretty much
using English most of the time they'll
be my guess um Germany I'm sure is also
another place that tipped like I can't
think about that my head but you know
they'd have a ton
Italy is harder to can't think of much
like Italy Portugal not sure about Spain
definitely they make Maxwell render for
example I think in Spain so I think they
have a fair number of like CG things
they're already hit PO and Turkey I
don't know this is turning into a giant
like world tour of game development
right it's CryEngine from Germany maybe
Oh cried Degas German okay so Crytek is
German there you go so I mean I I don't
know I'm the wrong one apps I don't keep
tabs on like the entire world of gaming
right but what I can say is that well I
don't know if everywhere in the world
has tech development now it's pretty
close like I mean you can see just those
are the things I can name off the top of
my head and I don't keep track of it so
lots and lots and lots and lots of
places have computer stuff going on
right now and some places don't have
much but they probably have a little bit
and a lot of places have a lot
increasingly I would say in game
development a lot of it the important
stuff is not happening in the u.s. I
would say you know of the engine
development that happens in the u.s.
it's probably the minority of engine
development happens in the US
so a lot of it is extra us in in my
opinion again just was thinking of the
engines right it snowflake I think it's
what's called keep I can't remember the
name the the engine name for Ubisoft but
that's for sure not us Canada
Crytek is Europe whatever the Rockstar
engine wants to be called is Europe
right I'm 99% positive that that's not
much us it might be the Rockstar San
Diego maybe they collaborate I don't
know so that it's at least it's at least
half not us let's put it that way but I
don't know their exact breakdown unity
is not majority us although again I'm
sure they have US development but it's
just not mostly frostbite Sweden we
never mentioned that one right dice in
Sweden so you know of the engines that
are developed entirely in the US I'm
trying to think what they are but like
Unreal Engine is obviously important one
but I don't know someone was saying that
Rockstar San Diego does most of the
engine if that's the case then maybe
that is a u.s. engine I don't know right
but a lot of the engines not not done in
the US they're done elsewhere you know
Europe Canada Asia more broadly
I saw some codes that use the array of
function pointers and enums to avoid
branching enums like action type move
right move left and then function
pointers associated with them do you
think it is a good idea to do that
so I guess what I would say and I'm kind
of I guess what I would say is honestly
I just don't know so the reason I don't
know is because while I know a fair bit
about what happens to branches on
skylake on modern ecstasy for Korres to
be honest I have really not studied call
much so I don't know what happens with a
dependent call instruction it may be
that a dependent call instruction is
always worse because it cannot be
predicted so it will always stall or it
may be that that's not what happens and
so it's not always worse this is
something I probably should know these
days but it just never came up
so I can't really tell you I can't
really tell you I should go read about
exactly what happens in sky like on a
call
[Music]
so let me give you some perspective on
why I'm reticent to answer that question
without actually studying it first see
if we got a diagram here all right so we
haven't really talked about any of this
stuff on handmade hero largely because
it's not the sort of thing that I work
with typically so I'm really the wrong
one to teach you but I'll do my best if
you look at a diagram for how an actual
core of a modern x64 chip is working you
know it looks like this this is the one
for the processor that we're on right
now a sky like era processor right I
think this might be a coffee like chip
or maybe it's a KB like chip I don't
what are we on right now
it's a kb lake chip which is basically a
skylight chip there there's not a whole
lot of difference between the two at
least not that we know about right so
anyway I this is what it looks like for
the chip to actually function and if you
look at how it's broken down it's broken
down into a couple discrete parts and
these parts are about different things
you do in order to produce the results
of the assembly language so you have to
remember that in the old days if you
looked at assembly language you were
more or less looking at exactly what the
processor was going to do so if you took
like the Commodore 64 or something right
or an Apple 2 if you looked at the
assembly language that was more or less
a direct mapping into like what the
hardware was actually going to do so
you didn't have to think too much about
what was going on in the chip reading
the assembly language would basically
give you the what you needed to know
most of the time about what was gonna
happen that's completely false
for modern ships and the reason it's
completely false for modern ships is
really twofold you might even say
threefold one is that they actually
don't ever execute those actual
instructions what they do is they break
those instructions into smaller things
called micro ops that then get executed
and so any given instruction may
translate into one or more micro ops and
it's the micro ops that actually tell
you what the chips going to do there's
thing one thing too is they don't have
to execute those things in any
particular way they just need to
guarantee that the results are the same
as if they did and so they get a lot of
extra speed out of doing completely
arbitrary reorderings or modifications
to the things that you tell them to do
and think three is there's a big old
memory latency sitting on top of
everything so there's all this caching
infrastructure to try and make that
memory latency go away and none of that
was true back hill days in the old days
the memory ran the same speed as the
chip right on like a c64 I'm pretty sure
that like you could access one piece of
memory every clock cycle and the
instruction could only access one piece
of memory anyway so you were like done
right and you know I was never seated
before a programmer so take that with a
grain of salt but for the most part you
know there's probably some subtlety
there still because there always is but
for the most part you just don't think
about like oh I've got all these
different caches that are happening
right it was just like now there's just
memory and the chip the memory comes
into a register does something goes back
out to memory that's it there's no
in-betweens
there's no stalls there there's no right
so because of those things it's a lot
different now the first part the entire
front end of the chip as they call it
right this whole thing is designed to do
nothing other than just figure out what
you're going to execute
there's a giant huge section of the dye
dedicated to nothing other than just
figuring out what you might actually do
right and so why do we what's all that
about well it's got to take instructions
from memory the executable lives in
memory right it's got to get it out of
there well in the old days it just read
the memory nowadays not so much because
reading memory is incredibly expensive
so first we need to have a cache for to
the code right and that's the l1
instruction cache right so first we have
to have cache control logic that pulls
pages in from the the main memory and
keeps them around second is I just said
we don't ever execute instructions we
execute my crops which are little tiny
instructions you can put together to
make larger instructions that actually
occur in their structured stream we
don't want to do the work repetitively
to turn instructions into my crops
because it's expensive so we also catch
them micro ops so not only is there a
cache of the memory that says what the
actual code is the programmer wrote but
there's also a cache of the decode of
those instructions into micro ops right
so there's this whole process here all
of this crap is designed to do nothing
other than dump micro ops into a queue
that can then be issued into the back
end for act for actual use right this
part of the of the of the chip also can
do other things so for example I want to
say
I don't know where registered names get
assigned so the register alias table is
here so if we believe this diagram which
I guess we should
this doesn't rename things so I guess
so I'm sorry I'm just trying to think
here if you let's just to give you
example what I'm thinking if you were to
do an operation like X or e ax e ax
right or XR x or r ax r ax if you XOR a
value with itself you get 0 so X ring re
x2 r ax really just says that re X is
gonna get set to 0 right that's gonna
get handled specially I just don't know
by whom so I don't know whether some of
the things that happen in here are
actually gonna get done a little bit
differently before they get through the
micro screen or whether like X or R X
are exits and sort of here and then
handled as part of the register
allocation table or who knows what right
the these are the places where that gets
handled so it looks like it gets handled
here so anyway ignore that for now it's
not germane to the question I was just
trying to think of through my head
alright so after we decode everything
into my crops then they all get sent
down to here right where they actually
start to get worked on the way this
works is this this this thing right here
rename allocate retirement this is the
buffer where all the my crops go in and
we have to retire them in order so they
go into this buffer and we can fit this
many of them but we can execute any of
them in any order we want as long as we
only ever retire them from the back
right when they go into this buffer we
actually make up names for the registers
that have nothing to do with the
registers are actually named so for
example in here you might see something
that says like add our ax + 1
right which puts a new value in our ax
and then something that says like sub r
ax 2 right that sub r ax 2 those are
actually working on different values now
like they don't they don't have to be
our ax anymore so if someone in the
future says ma VAR ax 7 to overwrite our
ax it won't have to wait for those other
two instructions it'll just give
a new name right it just it will rename
all the registers from re X to some
actual name that's based on how many
internal registers we can store so even
though like the processor has nominally
like 16 general-purpose registers that
doesn't matter what those actually are
are not registers their names for
registers that the code needs to use to
tell the processor what's going on
they're completely irrelevant for
storage because the storage actually
happens in here on way more than 16
registers right so that's what's all
going on in here finally we have a
scheduler system which is what's
actually going to determine how the UF's
go this is a nightmare apparently to
build here you see the register file 180
here 168 here
so this renaming can rename things using
up to 180 different general-purpose
registers or 168 different vector
registers like the semi registers so
again you have 16 names for registers
but you actually have at least one
hundred and sixty-eight registers right
that you can actually have in flight in
the given time this is why it doesn't
matter if you like if you have like mob
RA X something do an operation re X
write it out mob rx something those are
not gonna stall on each other just
because they both use re X it just gets
renamed and off you go
so it's as if you have like an infinite
number of those registers effectively
because by the time you actually get to
the end of it you'll probably have
you'll probably have finished any
operations that we're using the early
ones and you keep going right so then we
actually get to the Al used actually do
stuff they they do the work here based
on the scheduler determining what's
available to actually at any time and
then finally you go out to load the
store buffers which communicate to main
memory right alright so if you think
about what has to happen with branch
prediction what ends up happening in
here is when we fill when we dump stuff
down into this into this buffer where
we're saying like oh you know we need to
do these operations at some point what's
going to happen is we decided
probably based on I'm not sure how we
actually tell this thing when we missed
so again this is why I just don't know
what the calls but basically what's
gonna happen is we're gonna be filling
up things into the allocation queue
right and we're dumping them down to the
out into this buffer the reorder buffer
at some point we're gonna get to a
branch instruction and that like a jump
instruction and that jump instruction is
gonna have been predicted in the decode
to have gone one way or the other right
so we will have decoded some stream
based on the jump either not taking the
jump or taking the jump if when we get
to retiring that instruction right if
that retirement goes oh crap I'm trying
to execute this jump I have the
predicted direction of the jump taking
or not but the actual computation of the
jump that I now have done and in
retiring says to do the opposite all of
the stuff that I had pending has to be
flushed because it's all wrong so you
know I'm saying so that's why a
mispredicted branch costs you money
right costs you cost you cycles because
I already did some of the work and now
instead of just flowing nicely right
through that work and getting the peak
throughput I'm expecting I have to stop
get rid of it and tell this guy to feed
me a different instruction stream that's
the penalty right that process is the
penalty I think it's 16 cycles if you
hit the you op cache it's 20 cycles if
you miss it on sky like I think some
around there those are averages right
and obviously it probably depends on how
big fill this buffer was like how much
work you done how much work you need to
do I know there's probably dependencies
in there that's hard
what the actual penalty will be in your
code but it's something like that
all right so what I don't know because
I've never looked at it is what happens
during a call so there's two things that
could happen during a call and I don't
know which one actually happens one is
that the front end as a way of
predicting the call so if the call is to
a hard-coded address that's trivial it's
always right because it can't change if
the call is to a dependent address who
knows right it would have to have a way
of predicting what that address was in
order to do it if it doesn't have a way
of predicting it then it's just gonna
stall here until it can compute it so
it's I think just as bad as Miss
predicting a branch because nothing can
happen you're just gonna full-on install
the chip until somebody gets that number
back right so all of this buffer
everything just goes like a train with a
with a the handle pulled it just
screeches to a halt waits for everything
to retire up to the point where we've
got the actual address to jump to to
call - and then we go right so if a call
is that way then I can't really see it
being better than a branch mispredict
but maybe it is I don't know if on the
other hand a call does do prediction
then it to me it seems like it's
probably the same as a branch mispredict
right but it may be that because it's
only one misra dict and that multiple
miss predicts like a switch for it like
a switch statement might be maybe it's
easier for it to recover from that than
the other way I don't know so I just
want to give you some like some
background right like that's why I don't
know because it's subtle and you need to
go find out what actually happened you
can't just make it up like I can't just
pull something out of my butt here I
need to actually know because unless I
actually know I can't reason about it in
any way
it's it's that complicated what goes on
in here and we didn't even cover like a
lot of it right I just kind of gave you
the bare-bones version so I don't know
sky like call instruction how does this
work
so I don't know all all instruction
skylake front and decoding one of the
problems I never really know where you
look for a lot of this information
[Music]
the best way is to ask Fabien when he's
not thinking about it too much and then
he'll accidentally just tell you the
answer but you have to do it like slyly
so it doesn't annoy him if it gets
frustrated with you asking too many
questions then he might just not answer
so that's the best way if you act you
know cat you know kind of trying to
slide it in in some way that he's like
you know go go to dinner and like
mention casually oh I wonder how the
Kazi and then he'll just tell you how it
works but um you know
so let's see
maybe we can just find a place for a
reset call
well this is Adam which doesn't help us
so you know
I mean it looks to me I'm gonna go out
on a limb here this is probably wrong
we're just gonna say it it looks to me
like indirect calls are just they
attempt to predict them and they also
try to predict the RET instruction by
assuming that you didn't modify the
return location which is in most code
going to be true
so the ret is probably perfectly
predicted most of the time but the call
it sounds like is a prediction and is
probably going to be wrong so I guess
what I would say is unless you think
that the place that you are calling it
tends to call the same thing all the
time a call will still be suffering the
same penalty so the question is whether
or not expanding it out into multiple
branches would make the predictor more
or less likely to be able to do a good
job it probably depends on how many
different things there are but anyway it
seems like my intuition is least mostly
correct which is to say that a call and
a branch are basically the same thing so
the question is can you get this if you
just assume up front it's not very
predictable so my branch of my call
they're just not very predictable then
the call is definitely worse if we only
have one branch so let's say add two
things I'm going to do a or B and I can
either use an indirect call or I can use
an if I think the if is probably always
better because they're just less work to
do it's still a prediction two ifs
versus a call harder to say three ifs
that are unpredictable maybe starts to
be worse than a call that's in directed
because right so I think you probably
have to do that timing because it's
which one the overhead of a call exists
and it's mispredicted versus I just had
some if statements does that make sense
so I just don't know how to make that an
arbitrary rule I probably can't what
you're gonna have to do is is profile
both ways and see which one's faster
unless you just know that there's like
300 different possibilities so the
number of ifs we would need is just
astronomical right so obviously like to
call it's gonna win or something does
that make sense
but if it's like close I would say
[Music]
probably have to time it or assume the
ifs are faster would be the two things I
would say does that help
hopefully that helps does that answer
your question
I saw John implemented compare-and-swap
intrinsic recently for lock-free
multi-threading except for implementing
counters and stuff
what is it useful for do I understand it
correctly that it was only useful when
the thread unsafe code task is small so
compare-and-swap is actually the
building block of all asynchronous
algorithms of any complexity it's
important understand that the the
seminal paper is is this it's by Maurice
Hurley from from deck basically
everything ever invented in computing of
course came from Digital Equipment
Corporation and all or the employees
thereof who then went to work at other
companies that's not really true but
it's sort of true um this will tell you
if you actually read and internalize at
least some of this paper this will
explain why compare-and-swap
I won't really go over it here but
compare-and-swap
is actually the most important
instruction every other algorithm could
be implemented with with
compare-and-swap
but of all of the multi-threaded
algorithms all of them can be
implemented with compare-and-swap
so it is that you burp Rimet some
multi-threaded algorithms can be
implemented without compare-and-swap by
using some other thing like lock
increment or locked swap with no compare
but if you're only gonna have one thing
it's compare and swap that is that is
the one primitive you can prove can do
everything and all other things you can
prove can't do everything and this is
the paper that proves this for you
hopefully that helps and it has nothing
to do with the size of thing you're
doing or the type of album or anything
it's just a superset so compare-and-swap
does everything lock increment lock swap
lock decrement lock
and these are all worse versions of
compare-and-swap
that you can only use in certain
circumstances but sometimes they're
better in those circumstances so it's
not you don't so you want them for
optimality like speed but they can't do
as much so in terms of capability it is
always compare-and-swap that you
actually need as for whether we use it
in handy here oh I don't know we
probably don't need it in handmade hero
because we can probably get away with
locked recruitment but I don't know we
might we might use it compare-and-swap
I think we do why aren't we using analog
computing instead of bits use
frequencies there are people who propose
that the reason I think is because
that's just not what computing group out
of analog computers weren't the thing
that caught on digital computers caught
on early in like the von Neumann era
right and there were people who proposed
them back then and built them so it
remains to be seen maybe in the future
it turns out we switch to analog
computing someday I don't know but
there's something straightforward about
saying we always clamp everything to
like positive or negative right that
allows you to yet noise is a good
example it allows you to create reliable
things that that can be reproduced right
and and that's kind of a fundamental
aspect to computing so I don't know
I am 50,000 lines into a C++ Android
engine development should I rewrite it
the C way how can I change my thinking
you at some point said that one should
come to the point where OOP fails and
then and you use the non hoop but I
think I am not really there yet hope
this is a dumb question um yeah I guess
what I would say is you don't need to
change programming habits if they're not
causing you a problem now sometimes
things can be causing your problem you
don't know it that's a little bit tricky
but assuming that you're not like what I
would say is are you spending a lot of
time thinking about how your programming
and if you are that's a bad sign right
you should be mostly thinking about the
problems you're trying to solve and what
happens typically with with OOP
programming is you end up thinking about
the OOP miss stuff a lot if you see that
happening that's a good time to reassess
but if you're just not having that
problem you may not need to worry about
it right so I guess that's the way I
would think about it so let's see if you
say Fabien did one on branch prediction
is this it
okay awesome so I've not watched this
yet I will watch it but um I don't know
if this covers the call stuff but even
if it doesn't just probably everything
in here stuff you're gonna want to know
fabien like spends so much time working
on these sorts of things that like he
has a ton of knowledge about how the
chips are actually doing what they're
doing because he actually has to know
right and so probably everyone should
just watch this video this is not the
number of views that I would prefer to
see on this video like that should be
like 10 times the number there and I
won't be adding 1 to it later so I would
say like watch that video it may not
probably exact so we're talking about
but all the things that it does cover
are things you will want to know right I
don't know if there's more in here so
this one on superscalar pipes stalls
that's that probably has it maybe again
one of the problems is these may not be
super relevant to like x64 either so he
again he may not really answer your
question directly but just I'm sure
these would probably be a good thing to
get you in the mode you need to be to
like think these things through cuz
he'll be giving you the background you
need to understand why it's not a simple
question right so check out that channel
maybe someone can link to it in this
episode i know midlow often does a
really good job of building links so
maybe link to this fabien keys and
stream here like this page of the videos
and just you know watch these it's like
there's no playlist but just watch these
four videos it'll probably be a very
useful 8 hours of your time probably got
way more information density than eight
hours of handmade hero
where we're mostly just doing
programming stuff and occasionally go
through stuff but you know so I would I
would give that shot all right I'm a
wind down
thank you everybody for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero
it's a pleasure cooking with you as
always if you want to follow on home you
can always pre-order the game on Hammer
hero or it comes the source code so you
can follow along with it we did not
actually do any hand me here today so
this probably won't
I will not actually call this day 533
will call next time five three three and
this will probably go up as a handmade
chat on the on the YouTube archive so
I'll be back next week when we're just
gonna start polishing the asset system
and just plowing assets into the game
basically trying to get that we just
want to turn the crank a few times on
that get the font stuff clean get the
cover ground cover clean obstacles you
know decorate the world just try to
really start making it so that we we
need to like go through and iron out
every last little crappy thing that we
did and just improve it to the point
where it's super super smooth to just
put assets in the game we've done all
the hard work and now we just need to
like turn that crank a few times so
we'll use the excuse of like decorating
our world to just like polish all the
pieces it'll take us a couple weeks to
do because we're gonna want to really
try and do a good job of simplifying
everything down and cleaning it up and
making it nice and really easy to use
that's we'll be doing for the next few
weeks hope to see you back here for that
until then have fun programming and I
will see everyone on the Internet oh and
during this week go watch Bob Ian's
videos watch those videos and they will
help you a lot understand what's going
on in this in the modern superscalar
CPUs that do like out of order and all
that stuff all right take it easy
everybody