hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero uh we would like today
um well you know
what is our w driver it is already
um we would like to today fix
we sort of have a bit of an issue
um which is that we would like to fix
what happens in our code in our lighting
um
we'd like to fix what happens when we
have
lights that overlap probe locations
and so we've gotten to the point where
the lighting is actually working really
well i i rather like it
um i think it's really cool
but the problem that we now have to face
is that we've got this sort of bad
scenario uh that occurs right where
things are in the world uh when lights
overlap
the
the actual probe locations where we're
taking our light samples
and to show you how the that is kind of
bad you can see that as this sort of
moves around as the glove kind of moves
around you can see that the light like
uh off center
so so for example look at the wall right
the lighting on the wall responds almost
it's like perfect right it looks like
it's tracking really well
um it it looks like it should and the
light plays across the wall very
satisfying right
um and that sort of
is it's really cool right it's complete
global illumination you know we we even
have this
uh in a more dramatic sense if you want
me to uh
give a more dramatic example of what
happens here
in the entity gen if i turn off uh we've
got this thing that that sort of like
adds lights to rooms
um it'll probably have a little more
logic to it in the future right now just
kind of like add some lights to rooms if
we don't have any lights and rooms you
can kind of see what i mean more
dramatically so you can see that the
global illumination responds like
basically perfectly i mean it really
looks great
um but the actual light
directly around like like the
the
immediate location of the light source
seems to like be very intermittent right
like as it kind of goes around you see
this like sometimes it's really bright
sometimes it's not there at all like
what's going on like why is it so bad
right around the light well some of it
probably has to do with the fact that
it's never going to be exact right
um
oh
sorry
i forgot about that
apologies
apologies that was funny i always forget
to change it i'm not sure why i even ha
i can see it like i can literally look
and see it i just forget
um
anyway
uh so yeah point being it looks really
good on everywhere except right where
the light is and actually although some
of that may be sampling meaning there's
going to be some
uh you know the lighting is never
perfect and especially when we're on the
cpu side we can only cast so many rays
if we move this other gpu we may be able
to cast a lot more
and so it might improve there but if you
look at how good the the global
illumination is it really looks
fantastic except for
right over the light itself where you
can see that sometimes it looks good and
sometimes it's almost like it's not even
there right like you can see here
uh and you might ask what's going on
there well the actual problem there we
have a uh basically a thing we don't
really know how to handle or maybe we
shouldn't say that we don't know how to
handle we at least
do not handle
if we go
uh to full cast we have this um
this part of the the function here you
can see
where we uh look to see whether we're
inside
a
particular light probe
whether a particular light probe is
inside of an actual piece of geometry
and if it is it does not do the casting
right
so what ends up happening here if you
look at
uh
debug draw
so i'm not sure
how we can really show this without the
screen being filled with garbage but i'm
going to fill the screen with garbage
anyway and i guess we'll just have to
live with that
um
so
basically like
here is
you know what's happening
so what you can see here is the glove
uh like in this case for example and and
you know what maybe let me uh kind of
get
uh at a level where you can sort of see
it a little bit better
um not sure how to do this exactly but
maybe something like in here
uh so if you look at
what happens
when the glove itself is
overlapping right it it
the probe gets eclipsed
right
um what's happening when the probe gets
eclipsed is that we no longer
can really take lighting samples that
will uh hit this thing correctly right
the light itself doesn't uh
what we would like is for this probe to
represent the fact that there's a
light right here that's supposed to be
shining out in all these directions and
and so there really shouldn't be
uh what you see here which is that the
sampling from the light
is totally unable to actually gather
and i'm not sure
like let me look a little closer it's
kind of hard to see
exactly
from that angle but maybe from this
angle you can see it a little bit better
so uh what you can see here right is
like the light probe itself is
unfortunately you know inside
so it can't really do much with respect
to that light and now we are missing the
fact that there should be a really
bright light here
now if we just move the glove up so that
or made the light smaller so that it
wasn't so large uh then it wouldn't
encompass and we would get totally
different results and that's a huge
problem
because we don't want uh
like like that's a that's not at all
what we want right we don't want to have
suddenly whenever lights
like um encompass sample air points we
don't want them to suddenly get dimmer
and you can see what's happening here
now all of you know we get a proper like
this looks more like what it should look
like there's light in this locus it's
exactly what we would expect why is that
happening well it's happening because
now you can see
none of these probes
are actually
inside the light volume all of the
probes
are themselves kind of outside right
of the light volume so they all sample
at least reasonably
well that there is a light there and
they represent it with lighting which is
exactly
what you would expect
so you can see why this is important to
fix because
you know we really don't want it looking
like that splotchy kind of
it's here sometimes and it's gone other
times a kind of effect uh we do not want
this
right
the question is
what do we do
to fix it
my assumption
is that since we already do a pass to
bucket all of these uh pieces
right like you can even see that it's
happening here if you look
uh when this light
crosses a boundary so
[Music]
that's is that going to do it i'm trying
to get i don't see yeah like there's a
boundary right there
um
you can see that we already split the
light
right into two pieces because what we're
doing is we're creating a spatial
hierarchy that it's like a grid it's not
really a hierarchy it's just a spatial
grid
that we can cast through
and we already subdivide lights so that
they fit inside these cells
which means we're already doing a pass
on the you know on all the geometry to
put it into this spatial partition to
begin with
and so the question is
could we potentially just at that point
take these lights and rasterize them
into the light probes
to solve this problem
that's one thing we could do
that's like an analytical approach where
we basically say okay
let's
when we're doing our insertions of the
light
into the spatial partition we could also
do an insertion
of the light into the light probe grid
where we add the light into those probes
that it overlaps
and
the problem with that approach is it's a
little bit confusing
how you actually do it
you have to come up with an analytical
uh answer right uh
where we're just gonna basically take
the and well i guess we could sample it
as well i don't know um
it's really hard to say
but uh
we would need some way of basically
saying look uh here is for this light
probe region
here is how much of the box is
overlapping and we need to translate
that into a lighting amount
and the problem is like that light probe
can still hit
so
so i'm just not sure and there are other
ways like we could introduce noise in
terms of the sampling location
so
meaning like the placement inside of a
particular cell that we're going to
sample the lighting from could itself
also be jittered
um there's yet another
solution to this problem
i don't know if this is a great idea uh
so an alternative solution to this
problem is to say that we simply don't
allow this case to occur and i know
that's a weird thing to say but actually
it's not all that difficult
if you imagined taking the light probes
and requiring that the light probes
themselves be effectively floored to the
location of the floor and ceiling
and then you clipped light sources so
that they were never quite that high
uh that would be the end of it right so
in other words let's suppose that we
forced all light probes temporarily to
be like lower right so they're like
you know down uh closer to the floor
and you know these
maybe a little higher uh but they're
pretty high already like we wouldn't
really care if that was how high they
were that that's actually fine it's not
an issue
um
so you know
we could do something like that where
the lights have to be
not where the lights are not
allowed to really be in those locations
they're they're effectively carved out
of overlapping
there are some issues with this
like the problem is that
you know you
you want probes to be roughly where the
things are that you're lighting
and so you're gonna have this problem of
the light will always appear to sort of
be coming
from the wrong place you know what i
mean
um so that's
a little bit meh
hmm
[Music]
i really just don't know um
i wish i had something better to suggest
but to be completely honest i really
just don't
um i
i feel like i should be able to think of
something but nothing really comes to
mind that's particularly logical
um randomized sampling locations
does seem somewhat
like a thing
by the way i like the spec lighting by
the way you can kind of see the specular
lighting happening there
um you know it shouldn't be happening on
grass because at some point we need to
send down some material parameters but i
like i really like the specular lighting
as a tool for later um like where in the
future where we could play with that to
have shinier or duller surfaces
um so i'm a fan of the specular
uh the potential for the specular
lighting uh even though right now we're
not really using it right
like
you know you can see why it might be fun
to have that that kind of a wash right
you can see like it kind of plays across
the floor
um
and you know it's it's not going to be
great because our sampling is is
not dense enough
it's not going to be as good as like if
we did
some kind of screen space stuff right
but i think it does add a little bit of
character and it's free
in our current scheme basically
um it's just one extra texture sample
uh at the time that we're doing the
lighting
to
because we already computed all of the
coordinates and everything and it's just
like well that's not true we did i guess
you wouldn't need the reflection vector
so it's a little more expensive than
that but it's on the gpu side and it's
pretty cheap
so since we already have the map lying
around i do think like getting that in
there so you can see that right
hopefully
um
i feel like that's pretty good
um but yeah like so so i'm i'm pretty
happy with like everything in the
lighting except this part of it uh
because i don't really know
[Music]
i don't really know the right way to
solve that
and i don't know that unless we jitter
like
jittering our sampling locations is the
only thing i can think of that would
cleanly solve the problem but it's going
to inject a lot of noise i would think
right
because
if we randomly sample our locations
then we could just make it so that when
you hit a light source
from the inside
that counts or something right and then
i think it just kind of works
i mean maybe i'm wrong about that and
that doesn't work either but it seems
like that would probably work
um
you know don't quote me on that but i
feel like that probably works
so yeah
hmm
i mean i guess one thing i probably
should do is to try jittering the
sampling locations
because
like if i
if that doesn't add an appreciable
amount of noise
then i suppose that would probably be
the right approach because it also
improves the sampling more generally
uh
so like
you know you probably get softer fall
off you you'd get maybe less of this
sort of thing
happening here
um
god this lighting looks so freaking good
like remember there's only one light in
the scene and it's completely dynamic
and it looks so good
it's just so good
anyway
um so maybe we could try jittering the
sampling locations inside the cell um
the reason i i
feel like that's maybe a little bit
tough is just because
i
i don't know how to sample the cell
i guess you just sample now i don't know
let's just try throwing white noise into
the sampling location
and we'll see what happens
um
i think what we're doing right now
so we we have some problems we'd have to
solve too so like if you look at what
we're doing right now
we basically just if you are inside an
occluder
we don't cast
if we are
so we do allow you to cast from inside
the light source i think you just never
hit that light source which is the
problem
so i guess another thing we could do is
have it so that you can hit the thing
that you are inside of
um
so we could try that
we could try that
um
so i believe the problem that we have is
that if you look at how this
box
um
this this is a you know intersection
code for the box
and effectively what it's doing is it's
computing the
the hit
uh
and
i believe
yeah like you can see so
so the way this works is it's computing
the minimum and maximum
hit
on the box
so my assumption is the problem here is
that it will pick them
yeah
yeah okay
so
if you look at how this code works
um
you know i realize it's a little bit
hard to read because again this has been
optimized so it's you know one of the
problems when you really try to turn the
optimization crank on anything
is that it becomes harder to read the
code it's why we don't
you know that's why i say like there's
optimization and there's like
non-pessimization and you always want to
of you know do the non-pessimization
right
you always want to write code simply
clearly and do the minimum amount of
work
but actual optimization where you start
turning the crank and like rearranging
things and eliminating terms and all
this other stuff where you're
actually getting more aggressive that
does make it harder to read so this is
you know going to be harder to
understand because we've done that on
this code right
so if you look at what's happening here
you can see that it's trying to take uh
the
the t values along the ray
so how far you've gone uh along the ray
and it's trying to take whatever the
minimum and maximum of those would be
for the intersections
with each of these boxes
so
you can see here how this proceeds it's
doing that on each axis x y and z
and then it's taking and it's figuring
out what the maximum hit would be
on x y or z and the minimum hit would be
on x y or z
uh and then this t valid check is saying
if the minimum is greater than zero
uh and the and then the min and the max
you know uh they have to be spread i
believe
this term right here is the thing that
would prevent us from
casting from the inside
right
because
this
is saying that the minimum hit
has to be
forward from the origin
yeah uh
meaning the origin of the ray that's
we're casting out
we have to have gone
in the direction of the ray we cannot go
backwards along the ray
uh if the minimum hit would have been
then we're inside
now that means we're effectively already
testing for whether we're inside or not
and so what maybe is the correct thing
to do here is to change this to say
let's just remember that we were
and deal with it later
um
you know maybe that's the start to
making this work well
and again i'm i'm saying maybe right i
don't know
um but maybe that's what we should be
doing
so if that was what we're going to do
then we wouldn't bother with this
right so this would simply not occur
so we're not going to do that uh instead
uh we're
we're in in fact i guess we're just
going to clip all the way down to here
right so we're always going to cast from
inside of everything
and if we run that code then the first
problem that we're going to get and you
can see it already right is that now the
thing that this was designed to prevent
uh which is that in you know the
interior probes like probes in here are
now able to see lighting from the other
side right
now you can't really see it that well
you know and maybe you know looking at
it maybe that's just you could just
leave it that way maybe that's not a
huge deal i don't know we'd have to put
lights back in the world i'd probably
turn lights back on to make that
decision um but now we're able to hit
those uh when we're casting right
but we also now are so they're able to
cast outward but we haven't actually
done anything about the problem of this
light because the light
it's never going to gather
from
something that it cast inside of because
this code is going to prevent it
okay
um so now we have this problem of well
we would like to sample
uh
this hit this t-min hit right
we'd like to do that
and the problem is now uh we we just
need to track this so the first thing we
might say is well okay so the tmin and
tmax have to go in the right order
all right so maybe we're talking about
something like this
and this is like
t inside
yeah
you know what i mean
um
and to be honest i don't know uh about
this part here
um
but basically i think what we want is
something more like
this
you know what i'm saying
so our our test would be the t-min has
to be less than the t-max because if
it's not then it's not a valid
intersection anyway right
the t-max has to be greater than zero
because otherwise the hit is completely
behind us
completely we're not inside it it's just
behind us in the opposite ray direction
uh and we want to make sure that it is
the closer hit so if we already had a
hit that was closer than this one right
uh we we wouldn't want to use this one
as our hit
and so this now allows us to cast from
inside i would argue this term is not
used yet uh and will create problems for
us i would argue
i mean i don't know that but i believe
it will
so now we should be able to cast inside
and the light itself uh
we should be able to hit but we've got
one more problem
which is that the normal will be
pointing in the wrong direction
and i don't actually know what happens
now with the light in that regard so
whether or not this is actually testing
what i want to test i'm not sure
um
but
uh
i think it would be
i'm not i'm not entirely sure
so let's take a look
so you can see like it's it's not doing
what i want like it's it is actually
doing the cast but the cast it's
treating this as if it was an occluder
like do you see how they all went dark
um so something about the way that that
is working is broken and i'm
not sure exactly what's going on i
assume this code is working
uh
but i guess i don't actually know what i
should probably test first
is
well i guess i know it must be working
right because if it wasn't working
and you weren't hitting the light it
wouldn't go dark it would just hit
something right
so i believe this code must be working
but the question is why is it black it
should be picking up the emission
i would think
but
it doesn't appear to
so i'm not sure what's going on there
why would that be because this this hit
emission
um it should have picked up leif is
um i would have thought
hmm
interesting
so let's take a look uh no i i'm not
assuming t i must this is not used at
the moment um
i'm saving that for later
so this what i'm assuming though is if
you hit an emitter i would have assumed
that it doesn't matter what direction
the normal is facing i would have
thought that would have provided
emission to you
because something hit will be true
i
i would think
i guess i don't actually know what is
this about
oh i know this is for selecting the
normal
yeah so anyway uh if something was hit
we come down in here
and uh and we use this code we really
should rewrite this code probably to be
just ray bundles now because i think
that would be
the the more efficient way to do it
um but you know it is what it is for now
anyway uh so we come down here and we we
try to figure out like where we hit this
thing and blah blah blah we do like you
know we we do the occlusion
and we do all this stuff but i thought
like this computes the normal
right
um
and all that garbage
we
[Music]
then
when we come down here my assumption was
that we don't use any of that because
it's an emitter so my assumption would
be that it would just use the emission
level right like the emission level is
here
we do ray weight times transmission
level
um
[Music]
times the hit ref color
which yeah i mean is is just it's just
the color of the light right
so i'm pretty sure this is fine like the
right because the emission level
um is going to override the reflective
light here submission
i
so
that should just work i thought
but i'm obviously wrong and i'm not sure
why i am wrong
um
although
i i guess i can think of one it's a bit
of a long shot but i can think of one
way this could be wrong
uh off the top of my head which is that
this
um
this h-comp
uh this this nonsense here might have
something to do with it right
so basically the hcomp
is doing a min pause epu16
the
okay
if something in here were to be negative
right
that would
be the thing that
ruins it for you
right
so in here
i guess what you would have to say
is
like
if we're going to pick we've picked a
mask already at this point so
you would need something like
like that
you would need to say okay the the
minimum t value we're now gonna like
clamp it
uh so that it can't go below zero
um that would allow it to still get
picked right
um
okay
and so i guess at least i'm slightly
gratified that hey that does appear to
sort of solve the problem although uh i
mean not it doesn't solve our lighting
problem but it solves the problem of
the light not getting found when it
overlaps the probes like now you can see
that clearly worked right like it's much
brighter around the probe now it's also
kind of wrong
because like i said before now what will
have the opposite problem which is that
if the glove is not overlapping anything
it will be much less bright than if it
is because as soon as it overlaps a
probe
everything that comes out of that probe
hits that light
and then as soon as it
comes out of that
it's not right
so this is why i was saying there's no
good solution if i you know if this i
thought was going to work just doing
that i would have said oh that's the
solution so you can see why i think
there's a problem with it and it looks
like that in practice this is why i say
we might have to jitter the sampling
locations but i think it'll add too much
noise if we jitter the sampling
locations then you wouldn't get that
because you would only see sometimes
from inside
the light
right
okay so the question though is also how
much work would we have to do with t
inside to make this thing work okay
surprisingly we're not really getting
any light bleed
which is not what i would have initially
expected
what i would like to do is add lights
back to the system to see to what extent
that's actually true and to what extent
that's the artifact of that there's so
few lights that it's hard to get light
bleed because you don't have
um all that many lights to actually uh
see
cause it right
um
but you know to to my
surprise like it just looks fine
so i guess
[Music]
using t inside
doesn't actually prove necessary somehow
which
is super bizarre to me and i i have no
explanation for that um
i guess it's just because since we're
using the actual occlusion normal
test when we sample lighting because the
normal is pointing away from us we
assume it can't reflect light back so it
just works
i don't know man
um
that's not true i don't know why that
was over there
um and so here we're gonna say like
all right
so we stuck a big old comment in there
just trying to say what we're currently
thinking because that's not intuitive to
me and while i can come up an
explanation for it it's a bit surprising
it probably warrants further study
as you can see now
we don't have the problem we had anymore
but we have the opposite problem which
is that the light appears to be
extremely bright um but then uh you if
it it
it's overly bright uh because it's when
it eclipses it
100 of the light samples now have that
light as soon as it uneclipses it
100 of them don't and by the way um i
find this to be actually quite
educational uh again
just as someone doesn't work with
lighting
very often the most i've ever worked on
lighting is what you're seeing here
right like handmade hero is by far the
most i've ever done with with lighting
um that's why i'm constantly surprised
i'm like wow this looks amazing because
i didn't know that we would get it to
look this good right um
uh and it's still cpu side like we're
not even using the gpu for this lighting
which is insane um so yeah it's pretty
cool anyway
um but if you look at what's going on
here uh it's basically very educational
from the sampling standpoint again
because remember
what we've seen so far
is that we get square interpolation
artifacts when we have a discontinuity
in the function that is represented at
the sample points
right
i
and anywhere that that's not true it's
very smooth
and this is precisely that discontinuity
so when we are in between probes we have
a smooth function being sampled by those
lights
um those cast rays it's a smooth
everywhere the percentage of rays that
hits that light source is correctly
proportional to the distance
from the light source as it should be
but as soon as we eclipse one of these
with the light
then just that probe
has 100 of its rays accounted for and
all the other probes around it are fall
off based
and lo and behold the sampling that we
see
now shows a very prominent square
artifact is that why
again not a lighting expert so i'm not
prepared to say but it's just very
interesting to note that every time we
have
a known discontinuity in our system it
seems like we see it in the
interpolation very clearly
you know what i'm saying
uh so anyway looking awesome and this is
actually better than i was expecting so
i guess what i'll say is maybe we start
trying to jitter the sampling locations
and see what that does
um again i think it's a great thing
it's a great approach because it just
continues like the monte carlo style
uh
lighting integration that we're doing
but it's just like it's noisy
right it's just it's noisy so
you you know
you would expect to get exactly what i
think we're going to get which is
too much additional noise
now because our lights kind of move
horizontally mostly there is one thing
we could try which is only doing
like
like our light samples could jitter in x
and y but not really in z
um might help reduce the noise because
there's one less dimension um
[Music]
uh you know i i don't necessarily know
that that's a very compelling um
conclusion
but uh you know
now it costs us something to do this uh
the cost is this
right like um the
the sort of
way that we're doing our initial
stepping
um this
stepping initial p
uh
that has to get computed every time
because ray origin single will change
every time
so
effectively like ray origin single
uh which is used down here right
so
yeah it's just got to get propagated
down and and i don't know how much
that's going to cost us uh probably not
all that much but it's worth noting it
it's not free
so ray origin single is actually getting
computed outside and if we're sort of
saying we're just not probably gonna do
like the handling and full cast anymore
full cast starts to look pretty
pointless right so it's entirely
possible that what we actually want to
do now is just get rid of full cast
entirely
because if you imagine what this is
going to look like we don't have do we
do we have a retired directory we don't
do we yeah we do
um
so like maybe what we do here is we just
say
uh
like you know what full cast is going in
the in the bucket
um and maybe we leave it there
uh and then we're just gonna weld this
stuff into grid raycast and call it a
day right so instead of it being what it
was before we're just gonna say all
right
it's really just full cast it calls it
in here and it needs these you know
things
so let's just make those things happen
uh and and stop with all the
the fancy foot you know
just stop fancy footing around
uh this
stop just stop with all the fancy
footing you know what i'm talking about
too much fancy footing right
um
so let's
let's just weld these together
uh it's something we wanted to do for a
while
now is obviously uh our time to shine
uh it is it is our big day in the sun
uh everyone knows it but us
so let's just do it
and and
call it a day
okay uh so this stuff i saved and it's
just going away we're look we're just
not gonna do that
i
we've got this preamble which we do sort
of still want to do right like we we
would like to have this
uh raycast debugging garbage uh occur
and
[Music]
we do kind of need to remember what we
were actually using as the call
but i think other than that
we don't have to care very much so light
probe p
was getting passed down
[Music]
um
so ray origin here was not doing
anything so so
basically like
ray origin single
was was just light probe p
spec at least a few statlists were not a
thing
tile was tile
um initial grid index was solved this
way
um
and
yeah like
i guess that's just it
um
so now i my argument is that now uh
we're calling you know full full cast is
just its own function and we don't have
a sub call to grid raycast currently
right
um and and off we go uh i don't want the
debug drawing anymore because i don't
care about it
and so
um i'm going to turn that off
and now i'm going to look
at jittering the starting locations
which you know is is a little bit more
uh in-depth right
uh but it's an attempt to try and
actually measure how much of the light
is actually uh overlapping a probe
instead of just assuming that the entire
thing overlaps the probe
and
you know
um
we're
we're not expecting miracles from that i
i don't imagine it will actually work
particularly well
but
uh
we're going to do the best we can
i'm also going to make debug pick
be the thing that happens here
so that if we're doing this then debug
pick is a real thing
and
otherwise it's not
this can sort of just go directly in
line probably
so this
can probably just all be done in
one step
and
[Music]
i don't
quite see
how enabled was getting set before did i
accidentally like delete that i guess
so here this is what makes it enabled
right if if it's
this is what actually makes it be
enabled is this r equal to
so shouldn't this just set it to be that
right
i don't know
i'm not quite clear on what's happening
there
um
i'm not gonna lie
so i don't know about the debug cast we
should probably go make that um
like retest that
because i don't actually know
um that was just some sloppy nonsense
but i don't care right now because we're
not trying to debug that so what i would
like to do now
um is i would like to now uh take the
the sampling location and jitter it
right so i'd like to jitter the sampling
location
uh to see if that makes it so that this
is less uh absurdly discontinuous you
know what i'm saying
um
that's cool
uh so i'm gonna go ahead and give that a
shot and so to do the jittering of the
starting location what we would need to
do is say ray origin single
is going to kind of come down and not
actually be determined until we
pick
you know
probably the ray index so so like when
we pick the ray index like that's when
we pick reorgan single
so the things that we're getting done
like it looks like that for example the
things that we're getting done based on
ray origin single have to now like occur
later and it turns out that was almost
nothing
so that's fine although some of these
values may have gotten hoisted out so we
may lose some optimization being done by
the compiler there because we haven't
really looked at that we kind of hacked
this code and haven't really like
reoptimized it since so you know take
that with a grain of salt it may not
really be only one thing that's getting
optimized there
um but if if we take this at face value
then we can if we would like do
effectively this which is to say
um we take the ray origin single x
and
uh the ray origin single y and we can
add entropy to those
uh
probably bilaterally
right we want to displace in either
direction
and i don't know how far
like probably the whole tile dim
um
so not the spatial grenade
uh but the
but the atlas grid
um
we would want to to do that
now i'm just not even going to do that
quite yet
oops i don't know why i didn't put an
equal sign there i'm just going to let
this run at the moment which is it's
just going to be garbage but i just
wanted to make sure that this is sort of
still doing something right
um yeah okay
so with because it's one one in either
direction is gonna be roughly correct uh
it's just not quite right
so as you can see like
hey
honestly kinda works uh i don't know if
it's as good as we might want it to be
um but it's pretty good right we still
get a little bit of of uh of nastiness
there but it's it's quite close
and to be honest i'm okay with the
amount of noise that that
injected like it's not that bad
uh in my opinion right
okay so if we're only going to sample
inside the tile i i don't actually
remember how big these tiles are so i
don't know how close one actually is to
them but we don't care uh because we
should have that number with the atlas
grid in the first place so
inside the
like um
i don't remember what the heck this is
called uh
update lighting is that what it's called
so in update lighting when we
go through here we set up
this
uh voxel dim
right
uh with our atlas grid so in theory we
should be able to do like uh you know
jitter
radius
and that should just be whatever the
cell dim is of the atlas grid
uh we want to do like
0.5 of that
but we probably don't really want 0.5 of
that like we probably want to pull it
back a little bit from 0.5 but you know
for now let's just claim
that that's what we're going to do
and so we would multiply
in this case right like we would
multiply the x and the y
jitter radius by the random sample that
we get
and that would tell us how to displace
the lighting samples
right
and off we go
now i don't know how correct that's
gonna be
uh it looks a little bit wrong
um
but
you know it's hard to say because this
is a very imprecise thing that we're
doing here
um
so i don't know and and you can kind of
also see like
you see how we're getting like the
sampling right because these things can
can move around in here it's going to be
a little weird too right so you get some
weirdness there
because the lighting can now sample from
you know from further afield
so uh yeah um
and then
i don't really know where to go from
here uh
because this turned out more promising
than i was expecting
i think is the biggest thing like the
jitter did not really introduce
at nearly as much
noise as i was expecting
i wonder if that's because i did
something wrong
that could also be if we don't let it
jitter the entire
uh
volume
um
i'm curious what that does for our light
containment
you know so so some stuff is a little
weird here right like
i don't really understand why we're
getting
[Music]
i don't really understand why we're
getting
this light bleed so i think
we may have to investigate this a little
bit more because it doesn't quite look
right so i think the raycast is a little
broken which is fine because we just
said we wanted to go
make sure that the lighting um
the the debug cast was working
and and you also see there's a little
bit of a
there's a weird kind of like
disappearing act
that the light does there that doesn't
quite add up
for me
like maybe that's plausible
with this scheme but i can't quite say
for sure why it would be so i just feel
like
i feel like we're a little
i don't quite feel like this is quite
right
you know what i'm saying
foreign
like it it feels a little
like maybe i screwed something up and i
think we want to maybe draw it
uh
just to make sure
you know what i'm saying too
um as far as we know we are backface
culling actually though
uh
the occlusion this
right here
is actually what that is
but
it may not be working properly right
um
although it seemed to be before we did
the jitter location
so that's even more confusing right
um
so it's tough to say
um okay so so like
if we were to go
and draw these maybe
um
[Music]
you know
that seems good uh so let's enable grid
raycast debugging and
see what we can see
like i said we wanted to
make this
uh code work and we don't know because
we kind of just clipped it out it may
not be working now
and so
yeah we would like to
i think we we would have this is now
getting overbrighted i suspect that's
because we set the light to something
high
uh that we probably need to fix um at
some point anyway
um
so this appears to be
to be doing what we would expect
so you can see that the sampling so
let's let's move this down here
so
you can see that the sampling does
a appear
i would say
it does appear to be
you know roughly
white noise in the
you know i mean it doesn't look
obviously wrong
um i do think we're gonna need some way
of drawing like more concretely
the the
starting location so
like we need a debug box that's like
very specifically
um
drawing at the starting point so like
this for example we probably
[Music]
i um
probably i don't know do we still want
to draw that i don't know
um
but when we draw the hit here uh we
probably need to draw like where we cast
from so
you know
we probably need to do something like
this
and the color
would have to indicate like which one it
was
you know
why i stopped the program for that i
have no idea because i had it all set up
the way i wanted
but i guess that's just sometimes i
forget
that we can live edit the code in this
program
since you don't always have live code
reloading in engines sometimes it's easy
to remember that
it's easy to forget that you do
so i mean that looks correct to me
um
i i don't really see anything
particularly suspicious
um
if we look at the interior casting
again looks pretty pretty reasonable
you don't really have an x-ray mode here
but
i mean that is exactly
what i would expect
probably
although i am a little confused about
the
i guess that
like we should make this drawing a
little more space because why the
normal pointing up is being drawn out of
here
oh right okay so
that's because we're not allowing a
negative
on the location where the sample should
have been taken all right so
so that's probably worth fixing because
um
[Music]
so like
we're doing that fix in probably the
wrong place
i don't really know but like
you know it could be that that is not
actually where you want to do it
and what you would rather do is when you
do the cast ps
you would do it right before that
so the t-ray
[Music]
uh
so like
right before you do the t-ray dot p
that's where you would do it so that
nothing else actually used that value
so it's only for the horizontal compare
um
so it'd be like
t
clamped compare
like you know what i'm saying to you
you you know right
do you know
so if i change it so that the comparison
is clamped
um
i'm sorry it's not it's called t-ray
so the comparison values get clamped
before we use them but we leave the
negatives in place is that
actually going to be
more what i wanted why do i keep re
yeah
i i just cannot get it through my skull
that we don't have to restart the
program um
i do not know why i have this problem
okay
so
let's try and make this a little bit
more sensible
so
[Music]
i think that is technically correct now
as odd as that seems right like it's
basically using the far side so like if
i was going along this ray would i would
what would i have hit i would have hit
that one right
and maybe we don't want that maybe we
want to try and use
t-max as the raise team min at that
point so that we hit the side we're
casting towards
um
[Music]
i guess i don't really have a
i guess i don't really have a strong
opinion about it
um
basically i i just i don't really know
what we want there i i
uh yeah i i don't know i mean we could
do it either way and i just don't know
that there's a reason to do it
um
i really just don't know if there's a if
there's a good reason to do it that way
um
so yeah um
honestly the jittering looks okay so i
would say my current problem is just
that it doesn't seem to behave as well
as i would like
and i don't know
what that's actually from but you can
see that you kind of still get
you get that sort of
you still get a little bit of that as it
moves in between
areas you get a little bit of that
problem
right
so
so am i doing something else wrong or is
that just as good as this scheme's going
to get us
you know
uh and i'm not sure
what i will say is that all lights
beside the glove besides the glove do
look great with this scheme so i would
have no real complaints
um
[Music]
other than that one
meaning other than this i don't think
i don't think i have
an issue with what's going on but that's
not
and it's not so much that because
you know maybe there's ways we address
the you know that that being a little
too square looking
maybe that's actually something we
address a different way
so it's less that and more that do you
see that like
that lighting intensity variation that
just looks either like a bug or a
limitation of the scheme that i don't
like
right
it looks like water reflecting
oh do you mean this
like that
yeah that's uh that's the specular
so i turned that on because i thought it
was interesting um
and i wanted to remind us to do
something with it probably we didn't
have to
but basically in the shader or
we can take samples multiple samples
and so what i did is i took a specular
sample so if if we want we can turn it
off
right
if you just want pure diffuse so
basically like uh you know instead of
that you would get this
right and now there's no reflectivity
at all right so that's that's like a
purely diffuse material it's it reflects
the
light the same in like all directions
um like literally all directions
perfectly
nothing in the real world would would
really be able to do that but
here in the fake world we can
uh and then we have
uh
this which is the specular
component
right
um
and this is looks like this
uh this this you can see how shiny right
everything looks now
um
and that shininess
is
just because we're using the reflection
vector now and we're and we're not
blurring the map
so we get something that actually is
pretty cool like it actually makes the
floor look a little bit glossy
right
um and we don't need to use that like if
it turns out we don't really think the
effect
plays well enough because you know it's
sampled too sparsely or whatever
uh then we just don't use it but it was
compelling enough to me to have like i
liked the look of it and as like we
should probably do something with this
right like it's just kind of cool to
imagine hopping up to an area
and seeing this kind of like
um
that kind of light bleeding out right uh
is just kind of nice
and so so i think we're probably gonna
leave it in there and so for the moment
we just you know
we add them together
uh with no particular
rhyme or reason
but in the future what we can do
is
have a
have a parameter
uh some kind of a vertex parameter or
something
uh that we send down where we just say
oh yeah like uh how
you know specular versus how diffuse
is this material and it just gives us
another way to like use the lighting to
create visual interest which is i mean
that's what lighting is for
uh in the first place is it makes things
look a lot better
so
yeah i don't have a lot to say at this
point we more or less fix the problem
that i was talking about
with jittered sampling positions
but it's still not really the quality
of the result
although it doesn't have the bug from
before it does sort of have a separate
bug
uh which is that it still doesn't quite
look
you know i wouldn't consider it
production quality right
um
uh maybe for like a made with unity
personal learning edition kind of a
situation that's fine but i feel like
uh you know we're trying to do something
of a higher quality level here than that
and the rest of the lighting looks ten
times better than that so
you know the problem is this is gonna
bring us down right uh we only look as
good
as our worst lighting effect
right
so
we kind of want to think about what can
we do here
to
fix this problem now one thing we could
do
is see what happens with different light
sizes and that one
so i don't know what happens because if
we enlarge the light source or shrink
the light source we might see things
changes in the artifacts that help clue
us into what's going wrong because right
like i don't really know
yet
uh what the problem is
so
you know
thinking through what's going wrong here
we can do some experiments and see like
can we gain some insight into the
problem
and i have no idea if we can or not but
we're going to try
so let's suppose that the light was less
big so i shrank it
honey i shrank the light
um
that was weird
why did it like disappear
that's really bizarre isn't it kind of
so if it's that small is it like not
getting picked up by anybody is it like
it's like nobody hitting it although
that's not what's happening because i
can see it in the spec
i mean obviously it will get dimmer
because we currently don't divide by the
light size so the bigger the light the
brighter it would be
i believe
don't quote me on that
hmm
so i'm going to increase the brightness
of this light source c proportional to
how much i shrunk it of course
it's not really proportional depending
on whether this is a surface area or
volume
so i think this is giving me fairly good
information like
right at this point
the chance of you hitting the light
source appears to i guess just be too
small
when the light source is small
and maybe that is
what's causing this problem
maybe
and there's a couple ways we could get
around that like one of the things we
could do is try to target light sources
we had talked about doing that before
where we do a basically biased sampling
right now i wouldn't really call this
unbiased but it is
in that sense
it is unbiased sampling in in that sense
um
so basically what you can see is the
brightness occurs when it it is able to
eclipse at least one of the samples i
assume
to be honest yeah i don't know i feel
it's just like kind of confusing what's
going on here something seems up
maybe maybe this is fine
um
bug wise but maybe we just got a bug in
here somewhere i'm not sure but it just
seems a little odd like
it seems like it's still that the
jittered sampling locations
are
not actually
are like not actually jittered or
something
so that's
that's not
that's just not right so something
something is is off here
uh and i don't really understand what it
is
i mean what if the light source was huge
right
so now this thing is is giant and i
should probably change the power because
it's going to be too it's going to be
too strong now
um but what happens if it's super large
i mean like
it totally works right so it seems like
it's like
at some point
you dropping below like a sampling size
or something so so let's say it's at
to and we dropped down the brightness
to try to compensate for that uh we
would be even less to be like 1.25 right
it'd be like really low
uh probably even lower than that if
we're honest about it that's still a bit
too hard
um too too bright too
too much
but it looks like perfect right um like
it looks just right
so
so yeah like
we definitely have a problem here
of just the level of sampling i guess is
just not
hmm
right i mean that that looks totally
like what you would expect
um
oh
so we really just have a problem of like
if this thing
is smaller than
a certain size
we get this
unhappy
we get this like unhappy situation
um
i feel very confused
i don't have a plausible explanation for
this at all really
um
so at what point at at what like size of
the light source does this start
happening
i guess would be my other question
like
what is the actual
roughly where
do i get this blinky behavior
uh occurring and
does that tell me anything
about the problem
is it like
a nyquist sort of a
a nyquist limit where it's like okay if
the light source's radius is smaller
than the like atlas's radius
you get this problem because like now
there's still not a problem it's a bit
square
so you know the square fall off stuff
that we talked about before where it's
like okay we maybe we need to fix some
of that stuff
i mean
mind you the light source itself is
square so you know there's a little bit
of that but
um
so the question is like at that point
i don't see the bug
so but at
five we did
i want to say
so at five it's like blinky right
like it looks blinky to me now
well
i guess not really
it's a little bit blinky
so at point five it's still really not
that blinky let's try point four
it's it's pretty solid actually
that looks blinky
yeah i mean right
and so i guess it's just like at that
point
are you just seeing like that is
stationary
right
so what you're seeing there is like the
random numbers
period basically like the crappy random
number
series that we use which is probably
pretty bad
just like an xor shift or something
what you're seeing there is
that
whether it's grabbing inside or outside
over time i assume
that's my assumption anyway i could just
be making
that up but
right
um
so another question i guess i would have
is what if we stratified the sampling
i don't know
um
i'm curious what happens if we stratify
the sampling so i think that i'm going
to do it not because i think it will
help but because i want to know now
so right now we do array count of 16
uh and so what we could do there is just
say well we're going to do a rate count
of 16
um
in a four by so it's a four by four grid
and only jittered inside the grid
uh is this because it's so small the
probability of a sample rate
intersecting the emissive source starts
becoming heavily affected by the random
rays distribution and whether they
actually hit the emissive object
i mean
yeah that's what
i'm guessing at this point but we have
not proven that
right
that's what you would expect to be true
but
it doesn't necessarily mean it is true
so
i'm gonna see what happens if i stratify
the samples
uh because i can
right
so
we're looping over some
rate what the heck is sample der
is that even a thing anymore
i don't know why we have that nobody
uses that
all right
um we can also get rid of that include
file
right
um
where is that pound include hh sphere
look we don't need this anymore right
okay
so the lighting octahedral map dim
uh it has to go somewhere
i don't know where it should go
probably not there
where do we normally define that stuff
huh yeah not true anymore
so the rays protection
we don't really have anymore so i think
that probably has to
get fixed right this
total light sample direction count is
ray count but this is also wrong so the
total initiation let's just get rid of
this we're not even
doing this right anymore
um
we should just get rid of
of these stats because if we were going
to gather stats we'd have to gather
completely different stats
uh
right like they're just incorrect at
this point
okay
so
we would want to
have
have this stratified
i'm in the wrong file
yeah
uh we would want to stratify this so
that the
um
the proportion here is computed by
something else now i'm going to do this
pretty sloppy
uh
to start with because i don't care about
optimizing it until i know whether i
just want to see what it does
um so what i'm going to do is take the
ray origin single dot x
uh n dot y and i'm going to take
so let's say that the ray index we know
there's 16 rays
so let's just take and
we'll take seven
from zero to seven
uh
will be our
our x partition
uh i'm sorry
there's only 16 so it's four bits so we
only get three right
so what i'm going to do here is i'm just
going to pull out the bits of the array
index and turn them into
a stratification for the sample so
basically the x will just be the bottom
two bits and the y will be the top two
bits
um
and that'll be that
so
this produces a number
uh where we want to take the jitter
radius right and we want to basically
turn this into a bilateral so we want to
do the same thing we were doing before
um where we turn this into a bilateral
but
uh this is going to be like the number
is going to be 0 1 2 3
right
um so what we actually want is we want
it to go like negative one
point uh well
negative one
[Music]
you know
0.125 or whatever 0.125 or not
negative point three point three
one
something like this
right
um so
we
need to multiply it by some kind of
inverse
first
because if you imagine this is a well
ian actually you know what i can do this
even easier
because since we don't care about the
performance of this i can do
something more straightforward
so if we just learn between negative of
the jitter radius
um
and positive of the jitter radius
so we're just going to like
go in between
those two extremes
uh then all we have to do is turn these
numbers into something that goes from
zero to one
so we know it's zero one two three so we
would just multiply it by the inverse of
three
and
that gives us
a t value that goes from zero to one so
that's an easier way to do it
uh
and i think that's fine
but uh don't quote me on that
so um what i'd like to do is see
what happens there uh
so okay so now
in theory this is regular sampling let's
just verify that that's true but this
should be regular sampling
and so it's very strange that that's
still pulsating
right so something weird is up
i mean i could have just messed it up so
you know doesn't necessarily mean
something weird is that but
okay
so there's our sample point
and here's our uh rey index
one two three
right um
kind of hard to see why we would get
so much
pulsating there is it just because of
the ray directions randomly hitting the
light
i guess
it does seem a bit odd
uh
that that's the case
to be honest um
not sure i can really
wrap my head around that if it's not a
bug
i would vote bug
because
that just seems
totally implausible to me
i find this unlikely
so
i'm not buying it i'm going to turn off
uh the jitter uh for
you know so the random series here is
actually seated
with an offset of the sample entropy i'm
just not going to do that
so i'm going to instead
just seat it with a constant value
this will mean that now there is no
noise injection at all as far as i know
which means there should be no way to
actually produce that pulsation
it should have to be constant
so yeah so something's
majorly messed up right because now
we're casting the same rays
every frame
so there is definitely something we
don't understand
uh right there's some bug that we don't
get
which is great because that means that
we just have to find a bug not
understand some new thing
about the lighting right
but i'm pretty sure that that is what
that means because i don't see
there should be no yeah you can even see
like there's no actual noise injection
here at all
so
so where is it coming from
i'm interested in why that's blinking
why would that be blinking
so that's just the hit
it's like the hit and like there's some
kind of like z fighting
with the hit and the cast
are in the same place
i guess
um
[Music]
that
is a complete and total mystery
i have
absolutely no idea
what's happening
well
all right
i guess we now know what our project is
it's to find that bug
i do think we need to improve the
rendering of this thing
um because currently it sucks uh meaning
the the debug is
i know what all the things are like so
that's saying look this is a sample for
this light probe it's going out that
face of the octahedral map
this is the point it picked to cast out
of that's the actual array that it
selected here is the place it hit and
there's the normal
um that it's it then you know
selected for that particular hit you
know also all that's fine
you know
whatever
but
it could we should probably make that a
little bit cleaner right
um
that said
it just looks completely solid so
where the heck is the noise coming from
it should be computing like more or less
the exact same thing every frame
although to be fair that's not really
true because it is a feedback system it
does sample from the previous frame's
information
so there is
a little bit more to it than that
and i suppose it's possible that this is
setting up some kind of like an
oscillatory regime where like it's
actually just
sampling from itself it gets in this
cycle i don't see how that's possible
like i i can't even
make up an explanation for that though
you know what i'm saying
so s i i have to assume that this is a
bug that there is noise getting injected
from some look from somehow
right
um
but
where
um
i just have no idea
where would that be coming from is it
like a weird like uninitialized variable
kind of a situation
the glove doesn't bob
i mean you can see that it doesn't bob
right like it's now settled
like that's it's not moving now
that's very strange um i can turn off
the
uh temporal
like
there is a very small amount of
just sort of catch-up blend basically
like a heinz ketchup blend
uh and we can turn that off so
it's a 12 it's 12 frames
um
so if we turned that off and we just
said that the update no it's not 12
frames that's wrong um
it would take so what's that four six
it's like
five frames
it's five frames
um so if the t update blend is just one
then that means it will update
completely
on every frame
i mean
what
that's awesome
this is going to be an interesting bug
probably something to do with floating
point something
i would just like to remind everyone
that there is no code in the game right
now intentionally to make this light
blink
it is running through as far as we know
exactly the same code path
as
literally all of these other light
sources that are stable
and lighting the world normally
there is no
code
at all
here to do that that's just a straight
up bug
that somehow
somehow
was able to produce
this effect
and i have literally no idea how it's
doing that
that's pretty wild
okay
i
so we probably yeah we i i like whoever
just said about nan's uh
i assume this is something like that
where we you know we did some sloppy
modifications here
something is getting
you know
basically getting nerfed by nan just on
the edge of something i guess
all right
well
i wasn't expecting that
uh that is not what i was expecting
so
uh yeah i think we probably are gonna
want
i i have no idea what to make of that um
[Music]
i do you know what one other thing i
would like to look at because now that
we're collecting information about this
is kind of crazy
uh i would like to take a quick look and
just ask what does it look like in
completely complete darkness so
does the entire light
strobe or just
the local
like which is what's actually happening
here
so it's it's really
more or less just
it's more or less just those light
probes it looks like
everybody else only gets slightly
brighter or dimmer
you know what i mean
but they otherwise retain their sampling
fairly sanely
and in that case
where it's actually embedded so you're
not able to ever sample that light
source only the ones around it then it
does all blink
so it's only just the ones that the
light is on top of
so that suggests that it's our it's our
interior casting thing presumably
causing this problem i would guess
right
uh so my assumption would be that if we
like furthermore for testing
decided to turn that off
that we would no longer have this
problem
presumably meaning if in here we said
yeah
the like team in less than t ray part of
things
that's not
like sufficient you have to actually
be outside
right
oh still not
okay
i do wonder if i might be just too
out of food right now to tackle
something like this
this is going to be a little
nitty-gritty and i'm kind of hungry
that never goes well
um
so i don't have any particular idea
about how to approach this to be
completely honest um
turning on nan exceptions does seem like
a good idea i would agree with that
approach
but i'm also kind of confused
as to what i just saw
nan's or otherwise that didn't seem
[Music]
oh
although
um so there is one thing i would say
about that is are those directly on the
edge
because if those are directly on the
edge then actually i do have a thought
so hold on a second
leave that as max for now what is the
jitter radius
okay damn i'll say if those were
actually on the uh atlas
or the spatial grids
um
directly on the border i would have said
that would have possibly made some sense
but they're not so it doesn't matter
i assume that this cannot fix it right
meaning like so this value should not
affect it at all it should blink
no matter what
this is fascinating
so it's like only on some frames
does being inside the light
apparently work and on other frames it
doesn't
that is really weird
i'm gonna put it to do in here by the
way
all right
i got nothing
um
so we should probably get snacks and
turn on nands and step through this and
try to find
um
what the heck is going on here because i
have no idea what time is it
it's 2 20.
uh yeah i mean let's do snack you can do
some snacks
uh
oh fnarp no this this is not even
running
uh there's no accumulating is not even
ever set to anything
in fact we don't even need this if in
there at all um we could literally get
rid of accumulating as a thing
entirely
frame odd does look very suspicious
although i don't think we use it anymore
either
um
so all that stuff is is not
doesn't actually do anything
um
so
right
uh it's it's just it's doing this for
some numerical or uninitialized variable
reason
again like i said this code has been
kind of like
uh optimized a little too far just
because it's lighting it has to be very
fast because we do it so many times
uh which makes it pretty easy to have
problems like this
that are going to be like you know
oh you missed a little something because
you were doing this like aggressive
optimization very likely
so uh but i think like snacks and then
you know let's let's maybe turn on nands
or you know
try some of the things to sort of shake
out and see
if we can see something a little bit you
know
uh more
something pronounced that will kind of
fall out um i don't know
again i can't really even guess what it
would be though is the thing
so it's a bit weird but you know
we'll just say okay
um
you know something's up so whatever
whatevs
um
yeah
all right so so snack time i'm gonna
grab a snack and then we'll take a look
[Music]
foreign
me
[Music]
[Applause]
bye
food
[Music]
fun
so
[Music]
all right we're back
we're back
and we have snacks
really that's all that requires snacks
you can debug anything if you have
snacks
that was not out of the stream that was
in there the whole time
it was previously part of t valid which
was anded in but i just moved it down
right
if the ray can be negative
the ray is never negative
the ray is only positive
you can have gone backwards
and the t-min will be negative because
you start out inside so t-min can be
negative but the ray is always pointing
forwards for purposes of the analysis
right
uh the change from throb to blink was
because
i took out the temporal smoothing
there's some temporal smoothing in there
to reduce noise uh you can
um
i don't know how well you could see this
uh actually
let me try and
show you
so uh if you look
probably that's not the best um
[Music]
so if you look at the worlds with the
lighting turned back on
well
is it just me or is the lighting why is
the lighting so stable
something's we we've done something
really busted
that's the lighting with no smoothing
right now
how is that possible
oh duh um sorry
we turned off the noise
uh because we were testing so yeah yeah
sorry i can't do this uh
i can't do that demo without turning
back on the noise so
let me turn back on the noise so you can
see
so
in this
clause right here
um if i let the actual random samples be
random
then you will see the noise that i was
like what's going on it's because yeah
so
um
it's it's kind of hard to see
uh probably especially on stream but you
can sort of see hopefully how like you
get a little bit of of noise right
um and that's just because we're not
taking enough samples
uh to to really capture all of the
lighting so you know as you randomly
perturb them you get a little bit
right you get a little bit of noise
it's not much
but there is noise
right
um yes it's the blinking
um well
the flashing right the flashing in here
the flickering
not the blinking of this other this we
don't know
what that is that's what we have to
solve
um so you could leave it like this
if you want to
but
it just doesn't look very good right
like it it would be kind of annoying if
the game just looked like that all the
time that that little flickering and so
you get rid of it one of two ways either
you
do a better sampling scheme
which maybe we should do
right blue noise would have less of a
problem
some kind of stable sampling
would not have this problem but then you
get other artifacts like with when
lights move around you would get other
artifacts right
um
so
you know
you have to figure out what you're
trying to optimize for but
anyway you could leave it like that
another thing you can do
is change your sampling and finally yet
another thing to do is smooth it over
time a little bit so you just so that
noise
effectively what you're doing in that
case is is sort of
averaging over time so that you
effectively have more samples
right
because if you only take 16
samples
out of every texel per frame
[Music]
and that's not enough if you sample
average over 4 frames now you're
effectively taking 64 samples which
right it gets better
so that's why we have the temporal like
that that's why we like blend over time
there
and
you know it introduces a little bit of
lag in the lighting but otherwise you
don't really notice and it looks and you
and the flickering goes away right so
that's why we do that
we've turned it off now because
it's much easier to see this blinking
behavior um
is literally an on off uh with the
temporal smoothing it looks like a you
know a smooth curve because it's on and
it goes up and it goes down it's like
right it's like pulse code modulation
um
so we have it turned off right now
and that's
but that's why
that's why when we're not debugging we
turn it on is because we don't want that
that flickering
right
um
yeah and exactly yes the temporal
averaging is what makes the blink turn
into a throb because it's basically
doing an interpolation between full
bright and zero bright that creates a
curve like a little like you know a wave
right
it's turning a square wave
into something smoother
by using linear interpolation right
so it turns into something more like a
triangle wave
and
because it's diffusive it's more it's
it's even less like a triangle wave it's
probably more like a sine wave almost
you know
so
but all that works fine none of that is
really implicated here
that's doing that's exactly what it
should have done so that's like great
um so really the only thing we're trying
to figure out is why is it linking in
the first place because we don't really
understand and so um
and and furthermore why are none of the
other lights blinking and also why does
it not blink if it's larger it only does
this blinking if it is small right
so
in my recollection anyway
if
we were to change the size of the glove
right so the glove
at the moment
is 0.4
if we were to change the size of the
glove to like 0.5
i believe it just doesn't blink anymore
right
um
so it's like
there's definitely and you can see that
it kind of might blink if it's right at
the right location so something about
it being exactly this size
creates
like whatever the situation is that
we're seeing it creates this like
problem
uh and we'll see
oh if this is gameplay
um so mts mox was asking
if we slow the time step down
does it still blink okay so that means
that
that means that just the slight
numerical difference
of the glove
right
is enough to make this happen
whatever the this is
right
which
i mean it could be plausible that it
happens to just line up exactly
um
and moving the time step back up again
did not like
having the low time step allowed it to
get into a state where it's now no
longer doing that
which is super weird
you have to admit that's pretty weird
right
so here's a question
is it just z
like is it just because we're not
jittering in z
right
i don't think that's plausible but
let's find out
so
if i draw
everything
like
that is suspiciously
that is suspiciously at
the
just there
right
rather suspicious
hmm
i say
so
so i don't know
i don't really know what we want to do
about that
we probably don't want a full
uh jitter radius in z
but
i'm gonna go ahead and
and say
all right what if we just took the whole
took the whole situation
and said we're jittering on all three
axes
so that you can't ever pick out that
that kind of a a compass
right
um
what happens then
you still get a lot of just like weird
like sort of sampling
i don't
know it seems to be still way too
consistent
and i'm not quite sure why
like it should be very consistently
click uh flickery but it's not
sometimes it's stronger
and i don't know why
or i don't know z
get it
it's a joke
math humor
is not very good humor as it turns out
like why like what's the deal with that
i don't get it
i don't understand why it flick why it
goes in and out like that
if it's purely random something about it
must not actually be that random because
if it was
then it shouldn't have such a pronounced
difference there should it
seems weird to me
right like that that part where it just
kind of
it flickers out is that because of the z
again
maybe
but that sure was the problem in general
though like not
jittering on z was a massive mistake
right
i think the lesson we've learned today
is
don't mess with monte carlo
you know what i'm saying
monte carlo
needs to sample where it needs to sample
and don't be messing with it
but
i don't think we're quite out of the
woods yet
we're not quite there yet
we're close
but
not quite there yet
all right
oh and here's some light leaking right
so
here's an example
of of light leaking out
uh which is why i say i do think like
you know we we might have to have that t
inside remember i said like it doesn't
look like we need it
but we might we might well need it
right
uh
and you know whether we do or not
depends we haven't really looked too
closely at that but you you do get that
sort of light leaking happening there
which shouldn't be happening right
but it's not the end of the world
you could ship the game like that if you
needed to
but
while we're in here we might as well
take a look at it right
all right
okay
we've had snack time
the lighting looks really good
um i'm pretty happy with it so i'm not
you know i'm certainly not complaining
um i just think maybe we could go a
little further with it than we have uh
so i think it's possible that it could
get uh you know
still a bit better in a way that we
would care about um so we're i don't
think we're quite at the point of
diminishing returns we're almost there
uh but not quite i don't think i think
we could still get a little bit of a
bigger quality increase
um now we could i do think at this point
what we could do though is say we can
leave it for a while like it's probably
good enough now
uh that we can make the game this way so
what we might want to do instead is say
like look this is fine for now
and we'll revisit it again in a couple
of months
um
and
look at a few other lighting things
that are more important for example an
exposure curve
uh
putting in an exposure curve would be
relatively straightforward and help us
out
so an exposure curve and also a
uh
a notion of like light brightness
that allows us to do things like bloom
uh and that sort of thing
right
so so at the moment i would say like
probably improving the light transport i
do think there's another little bit of
quality to get out of here without uh
substantially doing much
so
you know maybe we should do that i don't
know
um but i do think we could also make the
decision that this is plenty good enough
for real-time global illumination
uh
maybe up until we want to take a final
pass at it before shipping
uh because it certainly creates the
character of the game just fine
uh
but what we don't have is any sort of
concept of how bright the light should
be uh or how the exposure curve should
go or or like how bloom should go right
um
so
so i don't know
so that part's harder uh to square i
don't know
what we want to do about that more
specifically
hard to say
i do think this looks really good now
though
um
like i'm pretty happy with where this is
at
uh and that's even a pretty small light
uh at this point
i don't know how small these lights can
get now but
um
it it's that's pretty good like
i'm kind of surprised honestly
of how stable that is uh
so
[Music]
that's kind of nuts that that works as
well as it does uh with no biasing
towards the light source uh it's
obviously not perfect and you do get
if you get it small enough like now
uh you do still have a fair bit of like
intensity variation that's not great
right like you know you wouldn't
you would like it to be a little bit
better than that if it could be
um
but it's still kind of
surprisingly good right
um and
there's also no real reason
uh we can't use just larger lights
um
in most of these scenarios like the the
the chances that we need the light
specifically
uh to be like that small or low
because there's not a lot of situations
where it's going to matter that the you
know what size the light is relative to
what size the light should be
um i would assume right uh so
yeah if the light oops that's a
like a non-light source
so
uh if the light is i don't know what the
light intensity should be but if the
light is like a larger light
like the 0.75 version
uh then it's pretty stable
uh and we probably just don't have to
worry about it that much right like you
know that would just work um
and be fine
right
uh and you know the the main thing that
you know maybe
i don't really want to do this but
you know if we could have had spherical
lights that would have been nice
um
because it's a little bit not as good
because the square some of the
squareness of that i think is just from
the fact that the the thing is square
it is a square light
so a square light should
probably cast a square
light on the ground
you know what i mean
um
so
i do think one of the problems we have
is like if we really want to chase the
quality
in addition to like improving that
sampling potentially
uh the other thing i think we're gonna
run into pretty quickly
is just the fact that
we probably need to add spheres
because without spheres
uh we ain't gonna get
you know
we ain't gonna get a radio looking light
source regardless of what the sampling
looks like because it ain't
radial to begin with
so um
uh you know i'd really rather not
it complicates things
uh computationally not
it's not the worst thing in the world
but it's not fantastic
um
and so you know it slows down that the
ray casting of course i don't actually
know how much of the cost is the ray
casting
and how much of the cost is the sampling
i suspect the sampling at this point is
actually our biggest cost
uh the ray
actual marching through space
doing collisions so
it's possible that we could just issue
the
intersection code for a sphere at the
same time as we do
uh the
the um
axis align bounding box and then we just
have a parameter that's like is it a
sphere or is it not you know
um
yeah i don't know
i mean i suppose maybe the argument here
is we should test it
because it's not that hard to add it
it's just hard to add it so that it's
fast
right like the the adding of a sphere
intersection code is not particularly
difficult the
determining whether we can make that run
fast enough
for it to not be an issue is a different
matter
[Music]
since
most things are aabs you could probably
also do another thing where you actually
just
put the spheres
in some other
like if you know that the only things in
the world that are spheres are light
sources
you could just do a separate pass over
those that's not
that you don't
do that for
right
um
but then again i suppose it depends on
how many lights you have
you know maybe you've got a lot of these
in the actual game like there's all
these projectiles and stuff and then you
don't really want to be doing that
i wish i had something more constructed
to say here but i really don't maybe we
just need to sleep on it
um
because i think like it eventually
you're probably gonna have so many of
these lights flying around like for
projectiles and crap
you're probably going to want them to be
you know
um
you're probably going to want them to be
bucketed just like everything else that
you're not running through giant lists
of them
um all the time so
you know
you would probably just need them to be
in the array like everything else
what happens if we create the worst case
scenario so like super bright super
small that should be like really noisy
um
would be my guess
but i don't know
find out
surprisingly it's you know it's really
not that bad but you can see the noise
right like
the
reflective noise
sort of on the periphery right you can
see that pretty pretty good and and the
specular would be very noisy right like
right
um because it's not getting filtered
like the diffuse is where it's you know
kind of going through another
um
you know another pass there right
so
i'm torn
i apologize for being indecisive here
but i really just don't know what i
should do
other than hang out with the puss
because that's always a plus regardless
um
yeah so
i should also mention something that's
probably not obvious from what we've
been doing
that i know but maybe not everyone out
there knows or hasn't thought about
so if you're wondering um what normally
happens
uh in engines here so
uh obviously most game engines don't
actually do real-time global
illumination
um
quite on this scale and the reason for
that
is actually because their geometry is
just a lot more complicated right so
we happen to be dealing with a world
that's like very simple like it's not
you know um
100 000 polygon models moving around in
like complex worlds it's just these like
it's this this like block world
so
we can do like
global illumination in real time and
it's not a huge deal um
when you want to do that in something
like
you know unreal engine or whatever they
have to use more like sparse point
sampling plus these sort of like
um transfer functions it's a long story
but point being
you know they they couldn't probably be
as aggressive as we're being here just
it's not uh plausible for them because
they it their geometry is too
complicated they have to do something
simpler
but
they also do something that we're not
doing and again it makes a difference
here so one of the things that they do
is they special case well all engines
special case light sources
we don't so in our world there's no
difference between a light source and
anything else the only difference is
that a light source emits light and
other things don't that's it
but as a result of that it means that we
they
uh
know that things are light sources and
so what they then do is they do
things like shadow mapping
or direct ray casting of just the light
source
to compute
their lighting equation for the direct
lighting
what that means is they don't care about
this what we're seeing here
right
because they would never have this they
don't care what the direct illumination
component is
of the light source from the global
illumination
what they're actually going to do is use
the global illumination only for a
secondary lighting value
that is not
the primary lightning value which is
computed directly
right
so
we are doing something fundamentally
that is not what you would normally do
and that is one of the reasons why we're
having to think about this
because you normally wouldn't think
about this you would normally split and
the system that we've written would only
be used for your indirect bounce
i hope that makes some sense what i'm
saying
so your indirect bounce lighting would
be going through a system very similar
to what i've got
uh just maybe a little less aggressive
because you would need to be using
simplified versions of your geometry or
whatever arjun just already happens to
be simpler
but you would not be using it for the
direct lighting
um because we currently are using it for
the direct lighting and maybe one could
argue that we should not be doing that
and we should just special case lights
maybe
i don't know how productive that would
be because we kind of have this problem
of like we don't really have like
there's no geometry for this guy right
like it's just
it's just two flat sprites that are
sitting there in the world that happen
to line up right so
i don't know how good direct lighting is
really gonna look when you don't have
real 3d geometry like i'm not even sure
what you would really do
um
i mean
i mean it's hard to say like we could
just if we move this to the gpu we could
just actually do it that way you could
do direct casting
uh to the light sources that are nearby
i don't know it just it seems like a
bridge too far you know
it seems like a bridge too far and so
for now the only point i'm trying to get
across here
um is that if you look at what's going
on in the system
uh we are kind of down to the last sort
of
uh issue
which is this how do we deal with the
direct lighting around a moving bright
light source which is where we're gonna
have the most
um
you know
trouble capturing the behavior
uh the reason that we're in that
position is because we're doing things a
little weird
right
um if that makes sense
uh mts mocks because they do shadow maps
from the light sources
right so so typically what you would do
is you enumerate your light sources so
you say that each like region that
you're going to render in
right
each region you're going to render in
has
some number of maximum number of lights
that it can have so let's say each one
can have eight lights 16 lights whatever
it is
you then render like 16 shadow maps
from the light source
uh the light sources
and they would probably have to be like
cube maps right or whatever you have to
actually like
you render shadow maps for the
directions of the light
and then you compute the direct lighting
using that
so the direct shadow is captured by a
shadow map or on newer like rtx cards it
might just be an actual raycast because
that's more accurate than a shadow map
so
you just do that
and then your indirect lighting
contribution that comes from a system
like this
uh i think unreal engine five calls it
lumen
um or something
i don't remember what random names they
give to these things but
basically your indirect lighting comes
from like a thing and usually much like
ours it's temporally anti-aliased pretty
heavily whereas your direct lighting
usually actually isn't like your direct
lighting is usually a shadow map that's
actually fairly accurate to that frame
like there's typically not like a huge
amount
of like lag to that uh but there could
be right
so
uh all right fnarp said crazy idea since
all your surfaces are x y x z y z planes
could you look at a circle around a
projection of the light source onto the
surface rather than spherical
intersection
i don't think i know what you're
actually suggesting concretely there
the reason that spherical intersection
is a problem for us is not because it
would be difficult to do it's just
because
when you are trying to cast multiple
things at once in cmd
you don't want like an if statement in
there so you would end up running both
intersections at the same time because
you don't know
uh what type of thing is the thing
you're intersecting against
right
um
that's that's the only reason so it just
slows you down because you have you do a
few more comp a few more
computations um
that you then blend together
so you really you would not save any you
would not
do yourself any favors by all
introducing another scheme like
that would just also make things worse
right so
hard to say
um so i don't know
i don't know
you don't have to do either all sphere
lights or all albeits you just have to
accept that you're going to get a
slowdown if you do spheres
um just to give you an example right so
just to be concrete like
if you look at what happens right we've
got these
leave
insertion things
right
and you've got an x y and a z
and
there's like a min and a max
yeah
so if you look at what happens in sign
full cast uh when we loop over those we
just do the intersection against n of
those boxes at once in this case it's
four wide so it's four boxes
at once
if you wanted some of those boxes to be
spheres then what you would do is like
there is the thing called is emission
you would have another thing that's like
um well actually probably what we do is
is emission would probably just be the
same so
we would say all lights are spherical
all occluders are boxes right so this
would be zero or one depending on
whether it's a light
and that would tell you whether it's a
sphere or a cube as well in here
this is the computation to see whether
or not this thing
uh
has hit
and what we would need to do is provide
a
another set of equations here so you
know another 10 instructions or
something
that do the intersection with a sphere
and then we would use the emission value
to select
which one of the t values the sphere
computation or the aab computation which
one we were actually going to use
if you follow me
so that's how you would have to add
spheres to the system and so it just
gets a lot more complicated because
you're you're adding a lot more
instructions to this loop where we're
testing things
and you would rather not do that
you there are other options that you can
do
um you can you could also store two
different
uh leaf arrays spheres and
cubes
um but then you have extra overhead
right like that you're doing there
there's there's all trade-offs right um
uh space naming yeah a small enough box
gives you uh spherical falloff the
problem is you're very unlikely to hit
it so the sampling gets worse
so uh and that we could change by
targeting light sources more so like i
said we there are other ways we could
try to
um
there are other ways we could try to
approach this problem
um
but you know
so it's really hard to say it's really
hard to say what we want to do here i
really don't know um it's at a point
where it's pretty nice
uh it produces great looking
environments the only thing that doesn't
look great is the dynamic lights the
highly dynamic lights
they actually look pretty good with
respect to how they affect the
environment they just don't look
particularly good where they actually
are
themselves so like the actual location
right around the light source doesn't
look fantastic right
and so it does kind of suggest that you
would want to try and
figure out how to solve that problem a
little bit better
separately from other things
but i don't really know
um
[Music]
how you do that
uh
i i really just don't quite know how you
improve that and and furthermore like i
am sort of concerned that there are
still
bugs
like if you looked
so
if you crank the sampling density up to
something that's like going to be wicked
slow right like that we can't use
because it's way too slow
um like all right so let's take 256
samples per texel right so it's yeah
it's crazy dense
sampling
just way way way way too dense
um
at that point you
you look and you go this is best case
this is if there's no right what you're
looking at on the screen now is best
case
so
it still just doesn't look that good
around the light source right
like
that just doesn't look that good it's
not horrible
but
it's not particularly great now we could
if we wanted to
um
we could make this
light source even smaller and see what
happens there but again right it's just
it's just a question of like at some
point there's that falloff and it's it's
not going to be great
so like let's suppose i did do that i
made this small enough that like maybe
now
um
we can consider it to sort of be
you know uh small enough that it should
have a fairly radial fall off
um because it's so tiny
or maybe it needs to be a little smaller
even than that
and you know like i said we'll we'll go
out somewhere uh where we can really see
the fall off and then we'll
we'll try
cranking the sample density but i'm i'm
pretty sure it still just won't look
very good right it's like like it's just
not
that part is just not going to get that
much better so here we are
um in i'll try cranking the sampling
density up you know 10 24. it's absurd
right like it's
um you know maybe a gpu could do this uh
the cpu definitely
won't
uh not this maybe a threadripper
um but
but that's about it and so now like if
we look and see what's on the screen
it's like okay
i mean
it's just not
i mean one problem here too is like it's
just not bright enough either and we
know we can't really crank the
brightness because then you get the
feedback problem so that also suggests
that we have a problem
with like how we're sampling the lights
separately
because
a 1.0 light gets dimmer as the size
goes down so it's like it's
that was that divisor problem that we
have so like the lights should be like
should have their brightness
sort of like accounted for in a way i
don't know like in other words
it's like these values have to multiply
out to one or something it's it's not
right like like right it's like a little
weird
what's going on here
um i'll try cranking this brightness up
but i don't think it's gonna necessarily
help us here
um
but you see what i'm saying right like
we we still have issues there's there's
sort of a
there's a thing
in there's sort of a thing baked into
our system
in general that makes this situation not
look very good
right and it's not
so much about
the fact that it's not so much about the
sampling it's like actually just the
system doesn't quite work right like
there's
an underlying deficiency or whatever you
want to call it um
so
you know
here's me letting it run for a little
while
um
at 10 24 samples which again like i said
is like
super ridiculously dense
and i mean uh
i'll i'll agree that it is very like
smooth fall-off
right like you don't see
the squareness of the fall-off at all
like it's perfectly radial
um
it's also just not very bright
right uh so again so i i don't know like
i just get that twinge that like
there's one more like step here that
we're like missing there's like one more
thing that like
there's there's like a
and and again like i said before
i
this is certainly because i'm just not a
lighting person so
a lot of the things that i would know if
i was like did a lot of
um work on lighting
i'm sure i would just kind of know
oh yeah like you need to to structure
the equations thus and and understand
that these units should look a
particular way and and whatever else
right like
all that is is almost certainly um
something you would
know if this is the kind of code you did
on a daily basis right but i don't so
you know it's it's me kind of like
looking
like poking around for solutions
so yeah like you know
it does
oddly enough i will say and and i guess
i don't know why
it seems weird how the power is related
here and i don't really know um
kind of confused by that to be honest
um
the glove freaking out on
time steps like would be nice to fix at
some point right
um it's just annoying
the glove code is is terrible
so like if one assumes that that is what
it should look like
roughly and then like you'd go ahead and
change this to 1024 to get like a ton of
samples
um
and it kind of converges
to like that looks kind of right
um
[Music]
you can see why i'm like weirded out a
little right uh
i guess i have an equivalent question
too which like like that just looks
right so maybe
this is this is really tricky
um
the other question i have is like okay
so suppose we go back to kind of like
the crappy one
[Music]
um that we were having a ton of problems
with before and
like it's very square
is it square at high sampling counts
because i don't know
right i'm kind of i have no idea so so
that's another question i would be
interested to hear
um
because i don't know
so here we go um
you know there's there's the square
version right
and if i crank the sampling up of that
uh to a high number
uh does it make it less square
and i have no idea
looks like no
maybe
i would i would
say that assuming that that is what it
is
so like interestingly enough like that
at that point it just doesn't change
so that again to me also says maybe
spheres would really
make a meaningful difference here
you know
um
yeah we could just disable the temp
temporal smoothing with the 1024 but i
don't think it's going to make a
difference
um so here is turning off smoothing
entirely so this is just full noise
right
and here's
turning on
a lot of samples
and like
you know it's still square
and again i wonder like is that just
because the light's shape is square
if the light shape was spherical would
we not have this problem
um
and
and i don't know
uh so i kind of want to add a sphere in
here
um
because because i almost wonder if is it
really just because the thing is square
i i don't know and if that were the case
then
it might be worth the extra computation
to fix that
i
[Music]
i don't know
um
so
like
temporal anti-listing turned off so full
full flicker
uh massively over braided light so you
can really see
um
you can really see what it looks like
if we wanted to do
these as
[Music]
as spheres
then this computation has to effectively
take
just team in
so what we would need is
like a thing here that's like
team okay
i don't know i don't know what that is
did the ime just turn on yes it did
we are not typing japanese now
so we would need a t sphere
value
and
like i think
we would have to compute those two
computation
like we have to compute those two
points
uh those two t's
and then we would do a select
so the actual t-min would be a select
using the emission flag
where we select the emission if it's an
emitter we do t min sphere
otherwise team in
uh and if it's
um
uh if it's if emissions off we we take
the aab one
right
so you know it's pretty straightforward
what i'm talking about but uh we have to
actually do this for intersection
computation here and it's going to be
ugly
um spheres
like they they kind of require like a
divide
although we can probably phrase it in
terms of invade d like we did here maybe
um
i guess i'm not
sure if i should go to the white board
for this i'm not going to be able to or
i should say the light board i'm not
going to be able to just like miracle a
sphere intersection
code out of my head
uh you know that's
that ain't going to happen
um so we should probably go to the light
board if we're gonna try and do this
this is probably too late in a stream
for this but
i guess we do it anyway hold on a second
all right
so
what are we doing
we have
a
ray origin
um and we've got array direction
[Music]
like so
uh and then we've got a sphere
with a center
and we want to know
these two points
right
so these are the two points that are
whatever the sphere radius is are
away from the sphere like center
whatever that point is maybe i'll just
call that point p because that's like
the location of the thing
and we've got the
um the radius value
for the sphere and we want to know like
if we have hit this
um and and if so where
so
the
[Music]
the ray origin here i guess we'll call
this arm we can't call uh yeah i can't
call that r so let's let's call this
this is the light probe location
um so normally i call it l maybe we'll
just call it the atlas
location so a so where we're casting
from
and we can call the direction here d
that seems fair
so we know that we have the
equation for this ray is pretty
straightforward right the equation for
the ray
is just a function of the t value along
and it's just going to be like a plus t
times d
right
um pretty straightforward
uh and the equation for the things on
the circle
uh
is
i guess
well i shouldn't say circle the thing is
on the sphere
um
is going to be
pretty much the same
right like it's just going to be
saying that anywhere in space like a
sphere is just the
is just saying anywhere in space that
you are
right
um
we are going to have the equation be
uh
x squared
plus y squared
plus z squared
right
um i i guess i should probably say that
i would like these things to be sort of
centered
probably around the sphere to get rid of
the p value because we would like these
these would normally have the center
subtracted out of them i don't really
feel like writing it quite
all out that way
so we would like to maybe say that this
here is the origin let's say so you know
we'll we'll just say this this is what
we're looking around and this
a value we can trivially just subtract
ahead of time to put it into the same
space
as the sphere but you know we can mess
the equations however we want later
so we know that this length so x squared
plus y squared plus z squared square
rooted that's the distance
we know that that distance always has to
be um
right equal to well i guess i don't
really know why i bothered uh square
rooting at half time but whatever so
that distance has to be whatever our
radius value is right so the distance
from the center just the length of that
vector
has to be equal to r and we could say
this in a easier way here right by also
just saying
like x squared
plus y squared plus z squared
minus r
right would have to be equal to zero
so so we can write that kind of uh
we can write that kind of in in
a various
various numbers of ways right
but the point is we have our
ray
and we want to know
if we have an equation for the places
that hit the sphere we want to solve for
t because we know everything else
right
so what we want to do is plug this point
in as the xyz coordinates of our
equation here
yeah
that's that's like all we're actually
doing
um
so in theory the only thing we actually
need out of this
is to say
look if we assumed we pre-transformed it
so everything's around the center of the
sphere
then if we and so we got rid of the
value p which is great because now i can
use p to actually talk about the point
along the line so everything's about the
center of the sphere
we know we have a radius value that's
the value at which we would be on the
surface of the sphere
and so if we think about the point a
plus td
um so if our if our point along the ray
is going to be equal to a plus td
then really all we're talking about with
this equation
is that the length of p
um minus r has to be equal to zero or
the length of p has to be equal to r
that's when you're on the surface right
so what we're saying is that the length
of a plus td
minus r has to equal zero um and if we
actually multiply this out uh
you know we can presumably get
um to the fact that i'm terrible at math
notwithstanding and i probably make some
mistakes in here somewhere we will
probably get
uh
something under you know something under
a square root and a plus or minus sign
which is why there will be two of them
and so on and so forth right
so if we take a look at doing that we
would just say well how do we get the
length of a plus td well like we just
said that would be
a a plus or minus right
and our minus r
equals zero so expanding out this length
well the length of something is just the
square root of each of the components
squared so it would literally be exactly
this it would be um so the
the i guess you end up in a kind of
slightly nasty situation that you would
like to avoid here which is the time
trying to think if i wrote this in the
most expedient way or not but anyway um
so anyway if you look at what these
values are actually going to be it would
be ax plus t dx right
squared
and you would then just do that for the
other two terms as well so the actual
thing we care about is this ax plus tdx
squared term
which if we multiply out is what it's
like
uh
ax plus t dx
times ax plus t dx
is just going to be
distributive rule
ax squared right
plus 2 t
t
a x dx
right because everything's positive in
here there's no
negatives um plus
t squared dx squared
do i have that right
um
so effectively
yeah we're we would end up with this is
our is our term here i suppose we don't
have to care about this root i don't
know why like i said i don't know why i
put that in there to begin with because
you could have just not done that and
left the r on the other side and squared
them so it would just be an r squared
here right and you would just have this
terms so why i didn't do that to begin
with i don't know it's because like i
said i'm bad at math
um so anyway uh if we
if we want to solve this actual equation
we would end up with these terms right
so we would these are constants
um
the ax squareds
are in the a y squares the a z squared's
those are all constant
um so they're just they're just added up
right we would just have an ax squared
plus a b x plus a a y squared plus an a
z squared
we would just add those up and then
those would just be in there and we
don't care about them
from then on right
um these we actually do care about
because they have tea in them
right
but if you look at how this is
structured again these are constants
like dx is a constant right
so if we want to just imply
let's get this out here
so if we want to just skip all of the
nonsense and go straight to the
quadratic equation
we actually just can because we can see
we've got it right here right we've got
a t squared
term
with dx squared as the coefficient right
we've got a t term here with 2 ax dx
as the coefficient there's the t right
here's the t squared here's the t
and then we have a
ax squared
as the as the constant term that doesn't
have a t value
now if we had multiplied this out all
the whole way
so that we had each one of these terms
nothing would change except for the fact
that we'd now have one of each of these
so rather than just dx squared we would
have had like you know dx
um
squared plus d y squared plus dz squared
times t squared right
so my assumption is
we literally just compute these values
for the sphere
right and they are
they're not quite computable
ahead of time because remember we have
to
[Music]
a has to be put
a a and d are like based on the ray
so we can't just like
we can't just like pre-compute them or
something
um
which is kind of annoying
i mean that seems pretty straightforward
but then now i'm just wondering
is there a smarter way to do this
because there's really not much you can
pre-compute
in this case
like that just seems like a lot of work
maybe some of these terms like cancel
out
a little bit
but
i don't really see what i've done stupid
there
i'll try it one more time
and we'll look it up after
just to see what the smartest thing is
but i don't quite see where i went wrong
there and that does seem kind of
expensive more expensive than i think
it should be
so that may just be me not having done
3d math in years
the only time i do 3d math these days is
on handmade here well that's not
entirely true occasionally i have to
hack something in like the other day i
was
writing scripts in sketchup and blender
to do some stuff for art pipelines so i
guess i still do do
i do 3d math occasionally but
um not the nitty gritty of it like i
used to
um
so you know there's that
but i'm not sure any other way to phrase
this problem right the point is
at some point you're going to get down
to
the origin of the ray plus
the ray direction times some value you
wanted to produce as your t value
um
you're going to take this and you're
going to say that the length of this
should be equal to
the radius of the sphere
you could square both sides
right and say that like
the length of this squared
equals r squared so you can remove
a root term trivially from it like we
did before
but again
i'm not sure that we really care because
we're going to be
rooting things
either way because of the
uh quadratic nature of solving a sphere
right so so the like we can only get rid
of one of those
um
we're not going to get rid of both of
them right
so anyway uh if we imagined
uh this a plus uh td in here
uh
again i don't see a lot of wiggle room
there i mean it's going to be so it's
going to be root
squared
equals r squared of
uh you know
it's just going to be ax
plus t times dx squared dot dot
and
i don't see how you get around that so
at that point you're just
you know the square and the root cancel
each other out so your dx
squared equals r squared
and you're solving this equation
of
i mean
[Music]
it seems simple enough that even i
couldn't screw it up right i mean you're
going to square this term you're going
to have one of those for each of your
components and you're going to subtract
the r squared over to the other side you
know this will eventually be
that
um and so so you're
you know like we said uh before you're
gonna end up with
ax squared plus bx squared plus cx
squared minus r squared is your c
right that's going to be your your in
your quadratic equation i need a new
marker this thing is so dull
um
you're going to end up with this as your
c term
uh your a term
is going to be the
t squareds so t it's going to be just t
squared with dx squared plus dy squared
plus dz squared and then your t term is
going to be the interior term so it's
going to be ax dx
plus a y d y plus right
and
so uh i don't know
again very rusty at this sort of stuff
so take it with a grain of salt that
might have sucked
that's just like you know trying to
summon up 15 years ago brain
it's a simple problem but you know i
probably missed some stuff but that's
basically it
uh yeah we do unfortunately
need to know the coordinates because if
we don't
um
if we don't know the coordinates of the
intersection of the sphere
then we wouldn't know whether we hit the
sphere or something else
right
because if you just find out if you've
hit the sphere
then you wouldn't actually know if there
was some other intersection that was
closer than the sphere
so
you know
so it's pretty simple but um
i just am
kind of worried about the cost
uh amusingly we've already done it on
handmade hero
uh and i don't know whether we did it
well
but we already did it for handmade rey
for those of you who watch that right
um in here somewhere
we have
a uh
a thing to to
uh raycast against the sphere right
um
here it is
and here's the code that we wrote for it
so
as i
predicted
past me did the same thing as
current me
we subtracted
the sphere's origin from the ray origin
uh which gives us a a sphere relative
ray
uh we took the inner product of the ray
direction
and itself which is just the length of
it
right
and hey guess what that's exactly what i
just said it would be it's dx squared
plus d y squared plus dz squared right
that's what the inner product is
i mean yeah it's it's the same thing i
just wrote on the board
right it's the same thing i just wrote
on the board and then here's the here's
the quadratic equation right the root
term is b times b minus four ac
i mean
what do you want
right
um
i mean it's not that bad
right
i mean i wouldn't necessarily cry about
it
but
i mean it ain't cheap
you know it it doubles the cost
uh
of of the raycast for sure of the ray
walk for sure
um
so
and right i mean you're going to use
this the
you're going to use the square root
instruction for this it's going to be
like six cycles or something
um
probably overlaps well because it's
probably on like the divider or whatever
i don't know where is it let's find out
i love how freaky the like super bright
lights look
um
i'm gonna try it
as the last thing we do today it'll
probably suck
but it's fine
i just want to test it anyway
so if we go in here to
[Music]
i
i've loaded the entirely wrong thing if
we go in here to
a web browser
and we type in ups dot info
and
um
[Music]
i open up the table
and i ask it
for
i don't know why these are checked
because i don't have one of those
if i were to ask
where the square root instruction was
what would you tell me
so
no apparently it is not on the divider
oh and that's
much
faster than i thought it
was i thought it would have been more
expensive than three cycles
all right
i mean
if it only costs three cycles
so
divide is
is way more expensive
is it not
no it's not all right so basically the
only divide that's still slow is integer
divide
i mean three cycles is still really
freaking slow
for compared to anything else
um
but that's that's sorry yeah
that's all right
um
caveat
emperor
as they say
um this
is
somewhat concerning so
it still is only on one divider right
you can see
that it's only on port zero here
so
uh you know
the multiplies are dual
ported um
so
you know
uh the latency is pretty wicked
so there's that like you ain't like you
do have to have a bunch of
this stuff in flight to get the three
um
but
so yeah
i mean
i don't know it's not that bad
it's not that bad
all right well uh so i mean here's the
code
and
oops didn't mean to actually
uh so we've already written it and we
know it at least somewhat works so
really the main problem here is just us
welding this thing
uh into
the code as it stands
so uh
we want to compute this with
you know exactly what we would expect so
we turn the ray origin into the you know
let's say the boxman
is going to hold the value for the
sphere
uh
the the center
of the sphere
just i'm just saying that
arbitrarily because i
can um
we then compute
the
a b and c values
the ray direction
is
not an issue right because the ray has
already been normalized
so like a is just one
right
because that's not even the inverse ray
direction that's just the actual ray
direction
um
right
so so we don't need a
um a a can go away
uh we
we do need b because we have no idea
like what this value is relative to the
ray direction like like we we have no
idea right um so so we do need that
and
this is
like not known until after we do
yeah i mean
uh
is that actually true though
i suspect it probably is i mean the only
reason i hesitate there is because
since the sphere relative origin is a
subtraction
and it's a subtraction between something
we don't know which is the right origin
with something we do know which is the
center of the sphere
in theory you could pre-compute the part
of this that was constant
my guess is there's no win meaning you
would still end up doing as much or more
work if you pulled out the constant part
then if you just do the subtract and
then take the dot product
but i
couldn't promise you that i
thought i'd mention it like we you would
actually want to like
write it out and make sure
you wouldn't want to do what i just did
is say like hey
um so the sphere radius
in this case is going to be like one of
the boxmans right so
like sphere r i'm sorry one of the box
maxes
like we don't care which one
um anyone will do
uh so you know that's fine
ray direction
may not be an actual thing um
yeah it's called ray d
it sounds like a cool guy named ray like
hey man what's up i'm ray d
uh
apparently we don't have times
for constants
apparently
so that has to happen
um
this
is just squaring the b term
and then subtracting this c term
same rule applies
um
and now we're not really going to go
into an if statement here right because
we we need to actually um
this this we have to add we probably
don't have one of those for
f32 x's so we'll have to add that
but then we get to the part where like
we can't afford to if around this like
that's probably not gonna happen
so
you know
we're gonna have to do something here
uh so the mask is whether or not the
root term is positive right because it
has to be over zero otherwise we didn't
intersect
so we would need to like prep the mask
value for that
which is sucks
and it's just gonna have to be
so like
it's just gonna have to be another thing
that we merge
right
like we're going to have to merge the
regular mask with a sphere mask
or knock out part of the sphere mask
it's yeah like
welcome to cindy
uh
it's actually totally fine if you have
you know a thing like a shader language
that's designed for it
so
um
the denominator
of this
uh then produces the two
t values
why are they called t p and t n o
positive and negative that's probably
what we called those
let's let's claim that's what we call
those
um and so once we have the positive
negative terms we don't really know
which one would be which
right
um
oh well no we
we sort of do right because the root
term
is a square root
so it's not like it can be negative
right the negative is like baked into
here
so we kind of know
that it's like min and max already right
like
like this is gonna be
um
like you can't add a positive value to
something and have it get smaller can
you oh well a
can a ever be yes it can
so actually that's not true
because if the denominator is negative
it will flip
so much for that
thought we were gonna get off easy there
but we didn't
right
you see why i'm saying like i don't
i don't think so
um
oh whoa whoa
no no i take it back i take it all back
it's it's b that i was looking at a
doesn't exist
no no no so i'm sorry we do luck out we
totally do
nevermind right
we're okay we're okay so the denominator
is just two
i think
right um and if the denominator is just
two then really this is just multiplying
by 0.5 which means that it can't it
wouldn't it would never flip
right
um it would never it would never flip so
i think we dodged a bullet there just in
the nick of time
um i want to say that that
is is actually
will actually compute the minimum and
maximum because
i
let me just make sure that's actually
true
because starting at negative b if you
subtract a positive value from it you
can only get smaller
and starting at negative b if you add
yes so so right
um
right that seems fine
uh so that's
cool
um
[Music]
that seems pretty good uh this is
looking better than i thought it was
going to
um this part
is
all just what we already are doing
um
so we're close
um but we've got a little bit more work
to do here uh
so so i think we're good right i think
we're good
um
if everyone is is down with that let me
see the chat's down with that
yeah
the chat is down with that
so so that's good so those are those are
simplified so let's take a look at this
other stuff up here
um and and really this is the part
that's going to be annoying because uh
we have to basically do a separate
select
because unlike the aabb
where this is sufficient
if it's a sphere we need this extra mask
term here
um so we got like yet another and
which sucks right that that's kind of
annoying because
i don't see any way out of that uh
i mean maybe what we could do is set the
t mask
set t max to zero
i don't know uh well the crossover come
to it let's just check out the rest of
it first so okay so we assume that box
max x is our radius
you know
uh we assume that that the sphere
relative origin we've got is boxman is
the center of sphere
uh we're taking our b value
is
oh wow okay so actually these can go
away sort of can't they
so so our b value is multiplied by two
right
um
you know what i'm saying
and if we just didn't do that
so let's say we
uh
we like
chat watch me here where i do this
because i probably should have done this
on the board i didn't
so if the b value did not have the two
in it
right so the two goes away
then
the in here
normally this would produce a four
so this would actually have a 4 in it
right
because we used to have a 2 and 2 times
2 here would have been 4 so this would
have been a 4 here and there would also
have been
a 2 here
right
so so there's like a 2
[Music]
in there
right
that pops out
and
if you look
this is
this is factorable now
so this
because they both have a 4
is like b squared minus c
um i think
the four can come out because it's a
product
can come out
as a two
and if it does
that means that there's a two here
which means that all of this disappears
because there's two twos
on the inside which means you can factor
it out
and if you multiplied it by 0.5 then you
just get nothing
is that right
did i do that right
watch me math people
um
so that seems good
i think we followed that through
so we're just down well you know one the
easiest thing to do
uh
right off the bat is just to add our
square root because that's kind of a
no-brainer right
um
so like in here where we've got our
other functions like like that we
actually have so we have an approximate
inverse square root so you know like
now we have an approximate i'm sorry now
we have an actual uh square root
so there squirt ps done right
um so now our only problem is that we
need an additional criteria for
intersection here that's not actually
being
[Music]
measured by the other
by the other case
so
um
so this will correctly select the
the hit that we're doing
but we also then need to add into our
mask here a sphere mask value which
itself is selected this way uh and this
is this kind of sucks
um but it's gonna be like this so
we've got a mask that says that this has
to be true
in order for this to be uh
in order for us to count this
right
um so if this thing isn't you know
isn't greater than zero
then then you can't process this
intersection but
the reason i say this gets worse
is because the sphere mask here is only
allowed to operate if
we are in the emission case
so the sphere mask itself has to be like
an
um
you know what i'm trying to say
right we need to select
based on leaf emission
um we need to select which one of these
we're going to do so do we have all ones
anywhere
um
uh if we don't this is a little harder
uh we could just invert it and use an
and not
[Music]
like
and then say like okay so it's zero
if it's emission it becomes
uh this term
right
um it's not great
uh but it's
something
uh and so now what we would need to do
is when we build the spatial partition
i mean in theory that's actually running
now i mean who the heck knows if it's
right at all
um we can try to cabin it off a little
bit so so like
i mean mostly right it's this
uh and you know you i got an idea
right
so if we turn this off
we we now have
no spheres like if i if i take this code
and i said
yeah like don't run that then we should
just get our squarey square squareness
squareness and
um
version
right
uh
whereas if i turn this on then like in
theory we're doing a sphere intersection
uh
um and and i don't really know that we
actually are it looks kind of broken so
i think it's probably not quite doing
that but it is actually doing something
different right
furthermore when we actually insert
these in we have to actually set these
correctly so at the moment
these are set wrong
so
what what i would propose is like
something like this
so we say okay if lights are spheres
then when we build the spatial partition
uh and we insert these things in
we have to actually take into account
whether or not the thing was a light
so in here where we get this kind of
thing and it's like is
um
we don't want to do this anymore for
spheres so this the spheres like don't
that's not
possible right
and this creates a potential problem for
us which which is that our our actual
tracing
is not going to be quite right because
things aren't clipped to
the
um
[Music]
they're not clipped to the volume
i
you know what i'm saying
so
this could be bad
one of the really nice things about aabs
is their clip to the volume
the spheres cannot be clipped
you would have to add code specifically
to clip them because you can't clip a
sphere uh
if you clip a sphere
to
anything
it is no longer a sphere
right it's it's now some segment section
of a sphere
an aab clipped by another aab is always
a resulting aab so
you're right
so it's it's like not great
um
it's not great
so in here we would say okay if lights
or spheres
which sometimes they are
i
if
this box is a light
then this stuff gets set differently
first of all uh the x y and z are
actually like get the center of the
thing
uh it's not the leaf box it's like the
box bounds
right the it's the
uh
it's it's
this
i i don't know what clipping region is
in fact it's not even that it's like
it's like this
um this is the
insertion rex
i guess
i don't know what you want to call that
but we want to use the original so no
matter what we did when we did this
whole thing
uh
we want to just use the center of that
now
right so the x y and z's get spammed out
in this
dumb way
uh and then the dimensions of the
insertion rect are what we care about
here and we only store one of them so
it's you know whichever one it is it is
right
um this is going to be a radius so
so like i assume we don't have a get
radius function
do we
we do
um so we just say it's going to be half
right of the dimension
of the thing and now we've inserted them
in the format that was actually supposed
to be inserted for lights right i don't
know
uh it doesn't look promising but again i
think that's probably just because it's
buggy not because uh
we have concluded that spherical light
sources don't work in this system or
something like that right
um so now
given the current setup as it is uh i'm
curious to know how squary this looks
over time
um
given that maybe this is actually kind
of buggy and not working properly it's
hard to say
but
let's give it a test so if we blur
i mean it's definitely
less squary
right
um
it's not perfect
but it's better
even without knowing if this is debugged
yet
i
it's it's probably better if we're
honest about it right
um and let me go ahead and try
uh our little trick of you know instead
of 16
um
where is that
undo happening oh it's right there
uh let's try and
and set it up to something
um actually significantly higher than
that
and see what it looks like
so it's kind of hard to say but yeah
like i don't know
it's a little bit buggy because the
sphere is like
centered wrong like this is not i don't
think this is quite right
i guess is what i would say
um
so a little bit
uh wrong but it does look a lot circular
[Music]
right
um
[Music]
so i don't know maybe this is something
we should investigate
um
it seems plausible that you would
actually want this
and
i don't know i'm not thrilled about it
but
uh if
if that's what we've got to do
that's what we've got to do and if we we
should probably go debug this code maybe
that's we'll do next weekend
uh debug this code and and see what the
quality is like because it just looks a
lot better
uh you know what i'm saying
um
so
and i'm pretty sure it's not right like
i'm pretty sure it's still got it's i'm
pretty sure it's still buggy actually
um
yeah like it's it's off in weird ways
so it's it's not quite right
um so we'll have to go do some debugging
but it might be better
um the only way we're gonna know is if
we debug it
just to make sure we're doing this right
here so the boxman x y and z is the
center x y and z
uh
the box max x
is the radius
that's what we expected
um
and here
i mean like i said we do have the
problem of this could actually
um
this could actually be
just because
we're doing the cast wrong like i said
it's gonna be it's gonna
test it it's gonna hit the sphere
sometimes when something else should
have been hit first
um
and that could have really unpredictable
results so that's a huge problem and and
maybe this that makes this a non-starter
i don't know
um but
so the tmnt max getting selected
i mean it looks fine
this cool beat
hmm
i don't see a lot wrong with that um
that all just looks
uh good let's i i just try one thing
which is
like don't break
i guess i'm not sure how you would
the way the routine is structured i'd
like to try it with letting it keep
going
so that you wouldn't s early out on
collisions um
i'm wondering if we shouldn't attach
this to the hero instead of the glove
since the glove sucks
and i don't have much
intention of actually writing controller
code
in the near future we could just say
like
yeah um
i don't know what this will do but we
can do it
so this adds like a head
light
as well um and we could just turn off
the glove light for now
so it's pretty hard to say
um
we're probably gonna have to put it off
till next time it's hard to say whether
that really is
it might be just correct
and that's just the fact that it's not
actually now it will not do the correct
first hit detection
it will hit the sphere sometimes if the
sphere happened to extend into that
um
cell
and it will record it as having hit the
sphere when it really would have hit
something else first
and so it'd be hard to know if that was
happening or not without actually
instrumenting it
um
more
right
so it's highly likely that that could
just be what's happening
what i will say is
i'm not sure it's good enough
it is better
i'm not sure it's enough better to care
why would we be having nans though
i don't think we are
why would we have that
i don't think we would
would we
um
right because so in order for the
in order for this
oh
wait this is so
this is wrong
though
why are we doing this
did we cop cut and paste this code wrong
this is supposed to happen before the
square root
this is this is supposed to test
this thing so i agree
um i agree with you but that's not
what's supposed to be happening so the
root term is supposed to be that
right and then we only actually i guess
we just copy pasted that so th this
is supposed to have the mask
right it's supposed to look like this
i'm glad you said that because yeah
that's not how that's supposed to work
right so the idea here is yes it's true
that this produces nands but they mask
out right but for some reason we were
testing
i don't know why we would do that
because you can't have that occur like
it's never going to be negative
um so that was wrong like this is what i
think you know what probably the problem
was
so
i imagine we could we probably know
exactly what the problem was
it's this
uh
no this is wrong wait no this code is
wrong
it should should right like it should be
doing
the test on this
so our old handmade ray really let us
down here
so i don't know what the heck was going
on there
um
i mean it's handmade ray which we don't
technically do like it was just a time
killer thing that we did
so okay but still
um
[Music]
that was not how that was supposed to
work uh i don't know that has anything
to do with the problems we were seeing
but it might
i like i don't know that that really
changed much but it might have right
because i don't know what exactly that
would have done it depends on how the
nan would have compared
yeah it does it actually does look like
that fixed
um at least some of the problem
right
so i would say i don't know it's
it's still kind of squary
um
let's raise the power a little bit of it
and see
what that does
hmm
so it's still a bit
[Music]
um i want to go ahead and take a
long sample here
so
that might i don't know it's hard to say
uh
because we're not really doing perfect
sphere intersection here right like it
could be that we need to actually do
this for intersections i mean the sphere
intersection computation is correct but
we're not uh
properly continuing the cast to make
sure that you actually hit the sphere so
it could still be some artifacts in
there but
at the moment anyway if that actually is
as good as it gets if that's not part of
the bug then that would mean that like
the rest of the squariness
is just in our actual reconstruction
right
so
you know
um let's see what happens if we unsphere
does that do we what's the difference
like does it look
different or not
so let's switch from spheres to not
spheres
what do we see
so it gets brighter which we would
expect because the volume is larger and
we don't currently divide the intensity
by the volume which we probably should
um
is it more square
i mean probably
it's not being clipped to the voxel why
why are you saying it's being clipped to
the voxel
it's not being clipped to the voxel
nothing's getting clipped to the voxel
um um
so i don't know um it might be worth
keeping it might not be i really
couldn't say
that's a tough
one um
it may what it may mean is we have to go
look at our at fixing our
reconstruction
a little bit better
um and if we fix our reconstruction a
little bit better
then compare the differences
uh
right
so
[Music]
yeah i mean
i don't know i think we just have to
probably just play with the
interpolation and see
uh
we could also try writing direct values
in to the instead of doing it seeing
what the interpolation reproduces like
but yeah beyond that i don't really have
a lot of ideas
beyond that i don't think i've got any
more bright ideas
so
i i think that's probably our next
week's plan then folks
is to take a look at that what time is
it
it's 4 30.
um
so yeah i mean i think it's probably
pretty good here it would be nice to get
the cool
get the speed the raycasting speed up a
little bit
um there's a little more of a trail
there than we probably want
so like you know
i think we probably want to try to get
this
up
maybe to like 20
if we could
um
you know maybe to something like this
because that's pretty locked on not a
lot of blur there but
down by 10 was a little bit worse
um so hard to say
you know
hard to say
uh but it does seem like 12 is
12 out of 60 is about as good as we can
do right now in terms of flicker free
moving it to the gpu might help a lot
but
um
[Music]
it seems like we have a frame of lag
there whether we like it or not because
of the fact that the values from the
last frame are used
for the um
for the light samples right
so that's a separate issue as well
because this is without any temporal
blur and you see you get
you still get a little right um
so
and i assume that's what that's from i
guess i don't know
you know maybe that's not what that's
from
we should probably have something that
moves
like
smoothly
that's just like a thing we should
probably create a little entity that's
just like a light
that moves around
um in like a really like consistent way
so that we can analyze some of this
stuff a little bit better
but
at the moment anyway i don't know
i don't know
we're very close to lighting that i
would say is like yes
ship it uh but it's still just not quite
there
for certain cases
and
i don't
really know
um
what approach i think we want
i mean it's probably good enough as it
is but
i don't know
so fixing the interpolation to be less
square definitely a thing that we would
like uh
whether or not that gets us all the way
there though i don't know
and i also just don't fundamentally know
whether the circles make a difference
i i'm i'm kind of guessing they sort of
don't
like it's just hey it happens to be
brighter so the effect is worse
because it's got more volume but i don't
know that it actually matters
so
so we'll see
i think that's it for today either way
um
thanks everyone for joining me
i will be back here
um
i will be back here tomorrow
is what i will do
um
no i won't i'll be back here next
weekend
i don't know fire i need to stop using
firefox
um
anyway uh i don't know what we'll do
we'll install a new web browser is what
we'll do
um
i'll be back here next weekend in the
meantime i did want to mention to anyone
who likes movies
uh anna and i are doing a new thing on
substance that you can go to if you want
to
so i thought i'd mention it
i it's just cause we didn't feel like
like we always like to discuss movies
and stuff and we didn't
feel like there was a good thing for
movie discussions so we made one uh it's
pretty easy to get to it's just molly
movie club
and so if you want to check that out
that's another thing you can check out
besides handmade hero
if you if you just need more molly
rocket stuff in your life it's over
there
i'll be back here next weekend
to
[Music]
i guess we just gotta have to make a
judgment call maybe we just look at
interpolation quality at that point
um
because maybe that's really just what
it's about i don't know i
[Music]
i
maybe we'll have some thoughts during
the week you know about what we want to
do i'm not really 100 sure
all i would say is that's where we're
headed we're almost there it looks
really good
uh but it might be able to look a little
bit better
if we
change some things around so we'll have
to take a look
that's it for today everybody thanks for
joining me i will catch you all back
here next weekend until then have fun
programming and i'll see you on the
internet
take it easy everybody