hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero sure we code a complete game
live on stream we are uh basically going
to
you know switch we're going to switch
gears a little bit
um today because i don't know if you saw
what i posted on twitter
but basically i realized that what we
were doing
was dumb and i should have thought of it
beforehand but it didn't
anyway if you take a look at where we
are we were trying to
do some work on optimizing how we were
doing ray marching
i guess it's just retracing um but if
you take a look at how we were doing it
one of the things you can see
is that we were in our
in our lighting profiling uh when we
were actually doing our grid raycast
we were trying to see if we could just
march
through the grid um
in a computational way so
like down here you know we've got code
that has the old way where we look into
a table
and then a new way where we just compute
what we're doing
and
i wanted to look at what the timing
difference would be between these two
and it turns out that the answer is it's
quite bad
right so even though we did a like sort
of pseudo-optimizing we didn't really
optimize it particularly heavily but you
know we did it's not much
right it's like you know 10 instructions
or something it's not
huge um it turns out that this is just
way too much
probably because this is very
predictable and straightforward for the
processor and this is actually a bunch
of computations and then a
you know a thing where you have to
actually depend on those computations
so this can just be fired off
immediately and this probably created
some kind of dependency chain or
something i don't know
um but it was quite a bit worse now that
doesn't actually
mean that it is worse it could be that
if we
worked on this we could get it down but
what i realized is
that may just be a waste of time because
if you take a look at what's going on in
here
i realized that there's no reason we
can't just use
the walk table and still use larger grid
sizes
so originally the problem and maybe i'll
sketch this out on the blackboard
because this was just something that i
happen to randomly think of in the
middle of the week while i was doing
something totally unrelated to handmade
hero
it just pops in your brain like i think
i just have background processes that
are like
spinning on code and they just like
complete randomly and say oh hey by the
way this was done what you did and i'm
like
yeah it was um so anyway
on day 617 here
what uh table
driven raycast
um so basically what was happening
before is like all right so we know that
the way that this thing works
and i guess you know i can use the fancy
little grid thing there we go
um is we have a lighting voxel
and we know that we're going to cast
from the center of these voxel points
to like create like our probe values
right so we're
picking like one of these right and
we're in this voxel and we're going to
send out like all these rays
right so for any given array what we
needed to do
is like go okay we need to figure out
how this ray
marches along and we would just say look
what's what geometry is in
each part of this voxel as we go and and
that's the whole thing and since we know
that we're always starting from the
center
we know that we can just for each ray
direction that we
want to cast from our table we just have
the the series of grid squares it goes
through
right
so that's really nice and convenient and
it just allows us to table drive the
search
problem is it depends on the lighting
voxel
right equaling the spatial voxel
so or you know the the the spatial
hierarchy that we use
for uh determining what occluders we
test the ray against for intersection
so previously we had to have the
lighting voxel and the spatial voxel be
coincident meaning they had to have
exactly the same size and the reason for
that was because you always had to make
sure you were starting
in somewhere that coincides with the
table so if the table was built for some
other grid
right so you know if we had just done
like oh well here's this other grid we
were doing or something
right and the walk was supposed to be
along that so it would do like here and
then here or whatever
right because then you could be casting
from
all sorts of different offsets relative
to this grid the table would never line
up with the cast anymore
so i was like oh well if what if we just
dynamically compute which grid squares
to go through
then we could use any size and i really
want to be able to use bigger
sizes because i think that would speed
us up
right now we don't get enough leverage
for grid swear
but what i realized is that's not
necessary
all you really need to do is know that
there's a correspondence between these
two things
so sure we can always do the grid
walk along this thing
if we want to but we can then
also just use that as a mapping
into our spatial occupancy table
so for example suppose we said look what
we're gonna do
is we're going to use
like three or f or four or two or
something
we're going to group these squares
together
right
like so
and so we'll basically have a low
resolution grid and a high resolution
grid
right and then we know
that there's two ways we could now
approach this problem
and i don't know which one of them will
work maybe neither of them in which case
you know we're still back to square one
but
we can do one of two things one thing we
can do
is we can just loop through
each grid square and we only need to
actually do
uh testing when we detect that we've
actually moved into a larger square so
we can just keep
whatever our coordinates were and go
from there or
we can do just something which
multiplies
out our table more so we can just say
look
we know we're always aligned we're just
aligned in one of four or eight ways
right and the problem is the table gets
bigger
right um
but the run time cost wouldn't
if that makes sense
so in that particular case
it's like well you know all right um
it's really hard to say will that be
more efficient than what we were trying
to do because it's it's in that sort of
cloudy area
of like what does the processor want to
do um
and i don't actually know but it's it
seems
worth doing to try to get the table
uh to be you know
to see if we can just make a table
that's similar in science to our
existing table but that actually just
lets
us walk directly without too much of a
problem right
so that's the thing that i would like to
take a look at now one of the things is
we could just expand the table directly
now remember the problem here is that
this is actually three dimensional
so it's not going to be four right it's
actually going to be eight
if we group these up
right it's going to be eight of these
cells
um so if we just did this directly our
table
would be like eight times the size that
it was before which is quite
uh a like it's quite a
increase right
and i don't know that there's much of a
way you can
really compress these it's a it's a good
question um
so like for example if you're always
gonna start
uh in one of these eight quadrants i
mean or eight octants um i don't
actually know
whether it i don't actually know whether
you need to store completely different
walk tables for all of those like it
could be that they're mostly the same
set of walk tables
um or that there's a way you can adjust
the values
fairly trivially to make that work i
don't know
um so there's a lot of things there that
i don't know and another
uh thing that's worth noting there is
there's the possibility
that it could be compressed um in some
way for example
let's suppose that you have two
different rays
and both rays traverse the exact same
set of cells
and the larger you make the cells
probably the more likely that's going to
be
as well right because the larger the
cells are
the less variation there's going to be
between two different rays because
there's a much wider aperture that could
catch you know
so just to give a simple example suppose
we took
a grid like this and we said well okay
we're going to take
these two rays
if we were talking about a grid that was
exactly the resolution of this
then these are not the same walk table
set because one of them
diverges and comes down here otherwise
they're the same like this four was the
same
but then these three are different right
um
but what you'll notice is that if i was
to then say well what if we had the grid
squares be this large
then all of a sudden if they're you know
two by two this is maybe the same
right um
so it's possible that that could be the
case um
but i don't really know uh right like i
don't i don't know to what extent that
would really be true
and the reason i say that is because if
you think about what happens if you move
this one down
then they are different right so
so really hard to say and i'm not sure
um
it's it's a really tough call so uh
i guess what i would say first is
maybe let's see what happens
if we just try right um and we'll see
where we get
and based on what i see we'll determine
what our next steps are going to be i
really just don't
know exactly what the right solution
here is but
so the other way to do it too was just
to say
look let's just still march on the low
red on the high res grid
and then just correspond back to the low
res grid
and that method's super simple right all
we would do there is just instead of
having an
absolute delta we would have like a
delta per channel so we'd actually track
the xyz
um in you know an actual
uh and expanded so you know maybe we'd
just do
uh like eight
you know eight eight eight uh packed
into a register
and then we'd just convert that into a
high-res grid lookup
by bit a few bit you know shuffles right
and the problem with that
because that's by far the easiest and it
doesn't change the table size table size
stays the same
and we're probably quite fast
the problem that we have with that is
that
i have no idea how we would actually
um step it
because each step in the
hi-res grid doesn't necessarily
translate into a step in the low res
grid
so you would have to have a loop like a
separate loop
that happens at the end of the main loop
to
keep stepping until you got to a new one
and that just sounds dicey that sounds
real bad
right um
uh it it could in theory be done with
like conditional moves
so that you don't have any branches and
no loops
and that's because you know you can't
take more than three grid steps
without getting to a new one right um
there's no you know there's no plausible
way you could
you could hit three grid cells and not
have the next step take you out of the
grid
i don't think um
and you know maybe it's four i'd have to
think about the fully 3d case but it's
something like this so you could you
know you could do like four conditional
moves
um and therefore not have a loop
but i just don't know um
i mean it sounds bad right
and we can try it but it sounds bad
so again pretty sure that there's
probably
there's something here we can use that's
better than computing it on the fly
like we were which even though it was
fairly concise it seemed a little too
expensive
i don't know what we can do
exactly here but it's i think it's just
worth looking at this as an alternate
method
of trying to get that grid size to be
larger
so just to be clear what i mean by that
if we take a look at our voxel
so i guess it's in the renderer that
specifies how big it is
right so you can see here that we've got
a 24 by 16 by 16 voxel
and so you could imagine doing like
a six by four by four or a twelve by
eight by eight
right
and again we leave the lighting at this
resolution
but we're just talking about the spatial
occupancy grid
um and the spatial occupancy grid would
be
smaller so
as a simple first test what i'd like to
do
is i'm just going to nerf this code here
so we're not going to
run the the branch of this code
that does
the that does the you know
the computed step version uh and i'm
going to go ahead and do
a run of the
[Music]
uh profiler and if we take a look at
the cost for our current scheme it's 4.5
ish it's been that way
for this scheme and what you can see
is here's our box count distribution and
you can see that like we just have a lot
of trouble getting high box counts we
want
more of these because we're doing like
way too much work right now on the grid
iteration i think and not enough
work in the actual box loop
it's especially true because we have
fairly sparse areas right now which
you know may not be true always so i
don't want to like try to push this
number down artificially but
you can see here we hardly ever get like
largely we'd like to be able to do like
at least
eight per cell um because otherwise
we're just spending a crap ton of time
on
loop overhead right uh and we almost
never get there
right um we almost never get there like
the number of times we have
uh stuff in the upper size of things is
really low and when we do we
we're usually wasting like some of our
lane so we really want to push this up
we want to see a lot of sevens uh maybe
even a lot of like
you know elevens and such
uh or twelves um we just wanna be
pushing up towards
the like higher capacity for the test
throughput inside a grid square
so i just want to do a little bit of
testing on this first just kind of like
push it around a little bit and so if we
take a look at
when we actually do uh the
the grid initialization um
that part where we compute the spatial
grid i want to see
to what extent i can muck with it now
the problem
is i'm not sure how much of this is
really
um you can see here we do some testing
and we we do stuff like
uh looking at the the um atlas cell
count and if the atlas cell count
differs then we do stuff like
making these grids and
so that parts i think probably a bit of
a problem
because you know we well i guess it's
not that big of a problem because i can
just
make these calls separately i suppose
um
and that would probably be fine so in
here you can see
where we do the where we do the spatial
cell count you can see it
taking the atlas cell count and just
adding a gutter
right so if we wanted to what we could
do is just
drop this right we could just drop this
down
and still do uh the part where we
actually do the spatial grid
that probably would all work so what
i'll do is i'll do that inside hh light
prof here and we'll just see what
happens
um just to see if i can you know
sort of poke it a little bit and and uh
and get a sense for it
so when we load the solution here um
what i'm going to do effectively is just
overwrite it
right and again this is just because
we're in the test code so we don't
you know we're not running the normal uh
init code because
we're not actually running inside the
game when we're doing the test
so in here where we do like vox seldim
well the
cell dim can still be the same so that's
not really
a big deal we do need to know what the
fundamental unit is but i think we kind
of know what the
fundamental unit is always because it's
always the same so i can again
hard code that just for this test you
can see that it's like 1.4 here
right um so what i could do is i could
just say look the fundamental unit is
1.4 for all of our testing so we're just
going to hard code that in while we're
just doing this hack
to see what's up and so then all i
really need to do is take this spatial
cell count here and when i do
this computation this atlas cell count
i'm just gonna divide it by two
right so we're just going to decimate it
by two um
and then we're gonna set all the rest of
stuff up this can stay the same
this can stay the same so it's it's just
this
it's just the spatial grid where we do
make voxelgrid that's the only thing
right
okay um so when we look
at uh at this we
we need to know what the atlas cell
count actually is
and i think the only real way for us to
do that here is to look inside the
solution
um and so if you take a look at the
lighting station it has the atlas
well i mean you can see here it's got
the atlas grid in it so i think we would
just do
inside that um
where's our voxel grid there it is so
inside the voxel grid you can see it's
got that cell dim there so we can just
look that up because we did
save it to the drive
all right um
oh wait it's actually cell count
sorry that's i don't know what's going
on there all right
uh so this would produce a different
spatial
uh alignment for this right it would it
would produce a different
sort of placement for it
and i think the other thing that we're
going to run into here is when we make
this voxel grid i don't know how it
figures out where the corner is
right because that's gonna be a little
bit weird so the total bounds
thing here um
i guess the answer is that that gets set
periodically probably
i would think so it's probably in here
right where we're going to call setman
corner
and so we need to take a look at the
setman corner call
and just see what's going on here
and so you can see the way that we were
doing this right so we know where the
atlas min corner is
and that's fixed in position and then
when we need to set our spatial min
corner we need that to be aligned so
we're basically saying look it's here
and what you can see is we we use this
thing called
atlas to spatial grid offset um
and i don't necessarily know why we
chose to phrase it
this way um meaning multiplied by the
cell dim instead of just
having that be the case because seldom
size doesn't change
but either way it's okay uh if we take a
look at where that's actually computed
which would presumably be in here
where's the offset yeah so if we take a
look at this
we can adjust this value as well so now
like effectively what's happening here
is since would you look at like
uh this vox cell dim value here the vox
cell dim value
always comes from the atlas it never
comes from uh
the spatial grid so in terms of setting
up where the spatial grid is we can just
say look it's gonna be
two now because we
are twice as large and that's just one
of the reasons why i was saying like i
don't
know that we really want this to be
based on the vox cell dim i mean i would
pretty much say to do
um probably just make atlas 2 spatial
grid
um a vector not
an index uh
so i don't know um i mean maybe we
don't want to do that i'm not sure uh if
we look at where
that's actually getting used um
i guess the problem we have is that that
we're trying to do
like this sort of offsetting where we we
say like here's the voxel we're in
uh and then we want to just add
something to it i think we need that to
probably be a more
complex mapping right because that's not
this is not going to be correct anymore
um
so you can see why i think like this
used to be fairly straightforward
because we knew that they were aligned
but it's gonna need a little bit more
um
trying to think of what's going on it's
gonna need a little bit more
uh flexibility so
when we're doing this and we say hey we
need to get a grid index
out of this thing for the walk
this is no longer it doesn't make sense
anymore
right for this to just be a flat offset
because it's not
ever going to be correctly indexed
the spatial grid is going to have to
have
a like a scale
value as well as an offset right
is the way to think of it and so in
addition to
mult in addition to offsetting it by one
like you can see this wants to be
you know one potentially but you know in
here we could say
all right we add these together and then
we divide by two
right that would give you the correct
index you can see we probably want that
to be
systemic like we want that to be
something that we know
where it's happening right
um but otherwise that's really all we
would need to do
and at this point i don't
actually know if that takes care of
everything but
uh it probably doesn't yeah so you can
see here like
we got some weird results there but
that's basically what we want to do so
box count
zero that doesn't really make any sense
um
what we're seeing there uh i like so we
have to go figure out what what the heck
is going on there right
um but that's basically what we want to
do
so when we make uh
yeah when we made this atlas here
voxel dim looks correct spatial cell
count is this divided by two
plus two times oh well that's actually
not correct though either right
um
so really this should just be v3s
two two two like so um
i mean again we we kind of have to
make this a little bit more systemic but
um so let's take a look at why this is
happening first
and try to start to clean that up
because i think this should be
mostly correct now we just have to go
figure out like they probably missed one
or two things in there
because this is a pretty weird thing
we're doing here
so let's switch to debug build
oops that's not the code i wanted to run
okay um so yeah so what i want to do now
is i just want to start taking a look at
what's actually happening in here
so when we do our lighting init i just
want to look and see
what's happening
um do we not call that function we in
the light prof we might not
let me get us into
this location first okay
so let's just take a look at what these
values actually are so here's solution
atlas grid solution spatial grid
here's the cell counts and
those look about right
so these values presumably won't get set
till later
um so we'll see
i'm not sure cause yeah
you need setman corner oh hmm
so you know what probably we have to
force
the setman corner to get called though
right
like now that i think about it since
we're probably just calling the yeah we
are
so the problem that we're going to have
here
is this is not going to be aligned
anymore
so that makes sense so if you take a
look at the
way this was working is you know you
have to call update lighting get these
things aligned and since we just saved
it out directly
um we were just loading it in from the
actual game scenario and and running it
um but that means we never actually do
this
call right so we need to if we're gonna
reset this thing
uh we need to to actually have some way
of setting up the spatial min corner
um the spatial min corner in this case
we would get the atlas min corner which
we can get pretty easily
because we haven't changed it and then
we need to just
set the rest of this stuff up so you can
see here like we need to figure out how
this would actually
um be aligned we know what the vox cell
dim is we could have gotten this out of
the atlas so i don't know why i bothered
with this like we could have just done
this right
um so yeah i don't know why why we
didn't do that because i'm pretty sure
these are aligned to fundamental units
anyway
uh so anyway uh yeah like if you take a
look at how this works
um when we go ahead and get the minimum
corner here
we then just need to adjust by however
much the offset is that we wanted to do
here
and um
i mean i'm pretty sure that's that's
just correct
uh all right so let's take a look
and let me just see what we get now um
for box distributions i don't know why
that's
so apparently still wrong so apparently
i'm not correct
but that i figured that would be the
main problem because
that just doesn't set any dimensions on
it right
so let's take a look at the spatial grid
here and see what it thinks so here's
the new dimensions
um for the spatial grid that you can see
here
uh oh yep i know what the other problem
is so the other problem we're going to
have here
is that this vox dim is not correct so
if this is too
wide right it's it's got to be right
it's got to be two um times the size
for the dimension because it's going to
be twice as long
each individual cell will be twice as
long right
um so yeah so in here we need to change
this up so this is going to be 2.0
right um
this is actually just going to be one at
that point
uh and this yeah
i don't really know
how we want to phrase this but this is
going to be more like that right
so it's just going to be one cell around
the outside
and that's always going to be true so we
wouldn't really need to multiply that
um that should be
fine um
and the index offset again like i don't
really know like
exactly how we want to phrase that but
you can see here the way that
that is phrased if i jump up
to sorry just gotta type that in
here when we do the flat index from
and we do this uh offsetting here
again that part is
that part is it's yeah it's not really
clear what you want to do so i think
this
one one one would still this would
actually still be fine because we could
have just done this
left it the way it was and we just put
that in
so i don't know i'm really not sure how
we want that to be phrased
but we're gonna have to look at that
separately anyway
um all right so now if we take a look at
what the box distribution is
maybe we can see a little bit more
clearly what's going on here
um so again not really sure
i understand what i'm looking at i think
we may still have uh
just a problem in here with with how
we've set this up because
just looking at the total uh box numbers
is that
oh well you know what no that could be
correct because one of the things
that you'll notice is like if we take a
look back at the original box counts you
can see
how many input box there were look how
many splits there were like this is what
this is there's only 1251 boxes but this
is how many actual splits
we ended up with right so there's way
more this would
if this is correct which it may well not
be it's much much lower right
okay
sorry i just glanced at chat everyone on
the twitch chat
who's here regularly understands what
i'm talking about
right i would assume that like
it would only be people who are just
dropping in for the first time who don't
know
because we've gone over every last
little bit of this on the stream
so people who've been watching they know
what i'm talking about
so anyway looks fine
right um and i think i was right about
this because if you just look at how
many fewer total box there are now that
could just be a premature victory lap
because it could be
the case that actually this is just
buggy um
and you know the
the binning is is just going wrong or
something right but i i if you take a
look at that
even just that doubling in size produces
just such a much better
arrangement here we are mostly up in the
higher
numbers there's very little down here
and the number of zero cells dropped
dramatically dropped by a factor of
seven because now there's like
larger empty space areas there
and so that's really important too
because we want to traverse empty space
as quickly as possible we don't want to
spend a lot of time
uh looking at empty space and going is
there anything here is there anything
here right that's not
doing anything for us we want to try and
get to the places where we might have
intersections as quickly as possible
um so we can still run like we can look
at this and say
oh yeah okay so you know we can still
run here
and and i don't to be honest i'm not
sure how we're doing the clamping
um this should have crashed
i want to say um well no because the
initial grid index wouldn't so i guess
i guess it won't crash um but uh
we're not actually doing accurate
testing here
right um we're we're doing
who knows what right so i just wanted to
see what the difference was
uh in runs and it looks like it actually
doesn't affect the runtime
very much at all it's basically the same
which is a little surprising honestly
so i'm not sure why that wouldn't have
improved our performance
uh but it's a little bit hard to say
because we're not actually
doing uh anything correctly now the walk
table is
you know completely wrong for what we're
uh for what we're asking for
so it's it's just
uh trying to think of how to say this so
it's it's
although the initial grid index is going
to be correct
um the way that this was structured the
actual uh walk would have been wrong
right okay so
i do know that the the breaking down
of the cells into two small things does
create problems for me but i don't
actually want to
to do that fix yet i want to leave that
out
and the reason for that is i want to
make sure that
in this code path here where we're doing
this sort of initial grid index stuff
what i want to do is change to passing
something that's actually
whole indices
so if we take a look at the places where
flat index from
is called so in here where we've got
a flat index from i'm just going to go
ahead and say look
uh let's nerf that call real quick and
just see where it's called
so you can see here we have flat index
from
um getting called often right
and when when you produce the flat index
from it's basically just the way of
saying look which
of these uh grid nodes are
going to uh to access
now there's a couple ways i can do this
um
but i'm going to need like this other
thing
uh i'm gonna need
voxel i don't know
what we want to call this sparse index
or something
um and i'm gonna need like a way of
saying look we wanna
pack the values into one thing so we can
still do
like addition and subtraction and crap
on it but we're gonna need some way of
doing that cleanly uh
and to be completely honest i'm not 100
sure exactly how i would want to do this
but i think
if i'm not mistaken we should
because we don't ever overflow or
underflow
on the stepping these should be
things that will um
where you can still use a single value
to update it but the actual
indices for x y and z are all kept
separate right so
if you imagine something like this
put this in the same place as the flat
index
so if we put this in here and we want to
do the same assertion presumably just to
make sure that it always actually is
inside
um and then we do something like this
you can see like i don't actually want
to do
this anymore because i want to keep
these separate so instead of getting the
cell count what i'm actually going to do
is i'm just going to order these
together
right so what i want to do is i want to
have my x my y
and my z and i want these to be
just combined into one value now if i
just ordered them directly together
obviously this wouldn't work because
uh i would basically smush them all on
top of each other so we'd be no way to
get them back out again
so what i want to do here is just spread
them out
and since i know that i'm not going to
have voxels that are
particularly big in this case what i'll
probably do is say look let's just give
each one 10 bits
so you know something like this and you
know i mean i guess if you really wanted
to you could say let's give each one 11
bits and since we know z
is less uh
you could make that particular one not
have
11 right so you have like x and y have
11 or something you can do all kinds of
stuff
um but it doesn't matter at the moment
because we know that 10 bits is way more
than we're ever going to have
um because we can't afford
we can't afford to do something
budget-wise and that's that's that dense
like right now we're talking about four
or five bits
total for the index so that's
uh twice as many bits uh
we're never gonna get there it would be
great if we could but we're never gonna
um so anyway if we take a look at the
sparse index here
uh then what we can do is we can use the
sparse index to
to do various operations right
so what we want to do um is now have a
way to use the flat index
uh to look up um into the
we want to be able to take a sparse
index and we want to be able to look up
using the sparse index into a particular
voxel grid
and so effectively what we're doing
there is producing a flat index
uh you know we're doing this operation
right
and so we want something that works
basically like this
where we can produce a flat index from
and we more or less just want the same
exact call just flat index from
and instead it's going to take a voxel
sparse index here
right and then in addition to that we're
gonna
want some way right of
like we probably want this sort of
hard-coded almost
uh because when we're doing this
indexing we
want to have some way um
of reducing the order so like in the
same way that we were doing a divide by
two so what we want to do here is say
look we're going to do
a flat index from our sparse index but
we're we know that these indices are
going to be kind of in the wrong
dimensionality or something
right
so there's again a couple ways we can do
this and
this is how we would do again i don't
know which one we want to do but this is
how we would do
uh the version where we
step in the the high-res voxel but still
use the low-res voxel
so this would allow us to step in x y
and z using an offset and then we would
just
unpack these values and uh you know
shift them by
an extra bit to divide them by two and
then do a lookup
and that would be very you know simple
for us to do and pretty efficient
so the only problem that i have is i
don't know if i want to do that
i don't know if what i'd rather do is
just table drive the thing
by generating eight different tables
depending on where
which one of the grid squares you're in
so if you're in
you know um i'm sorry
which one of the octants you're in in a
larger grid cell
and i don't have any i just don't know
so here's a thought
you know what forget this
because i here's my here's my argument
here's the argument i'm going to make
i think i can safely go with the build
the additional tables here's why
sure there's eight different ways you
can be inside a grid cell so the table
gets expanded by a factor of eight
that's a lot right
but you're going to walk
like half as far possibly
two root two as far depending on how you
know the array goes
so the table also contracts
by half so
it's really only a factor of four
expansion
which is still bad
but not as bad so i'm going to say let's
go with that first
so let's just do that first
so in order to do that again so this
initial grid
grid index now has to be something that
we preserve and pass down
because this flat index is not going to
work so
what we're going to have to pass down
here rather than any of this stuff
we're going to have to take this atlas
index
and send it down directly so i'm just
going to start by trying to do that
and what i'll do is say all right let's
look at atlas index here
where were we passing the flat index
here you can see us passing it in so i'm
going to say
it takes the whole thing right
like so
if i go up to full cast you can see it
passing it here so i'm just going to say
look this is the atlas index again
right here uh and then when that gets
passed in
you can see here it's starting to get
used and
uh it's doing a look up here into the
spatial grid
to see whether or not it's inside
something
okay
um so if we now go and say all right we
need to figure out where we actually are
in our grid so for the atlas index
we know that this would give us the
actual grid square that we're in
we would divide this by two and then add
our one
offset right um so this is actually
correct
and then we would look that up in the in
the nodes right that's that's the
correct usage
of that but this isn't and the reason
this isn't
is because in grid raycast we expect
this thing
um to
actually have different information
so what we would need here is
when we look up the walk table offset so
this this bit here
um we would need to
use the walk table offset in a different
walk table
right so this where we do light sampling
this needs to actually have like a
dimensionality to it
um and so we're going to have to do is
have like
a octant index right
that we look up here uh and so the
initial grid index
which would come in uh and
is i guess i guess to be fair it is the
correct one
like you know we we did actually get it
so this this isn't
you know fake um
and i guess i can do this in 16. um so
it's not wrong but
it just is incomplete so in addition we
need
uh the octan index um and really that's
you know even smaller that that can not
be very much of anything really
so in here where this actually looks it
up we would need
a bigger table and then in here in
addition to the grid index
we would need the auxin index too and so
when we do this actual
initial grid index here what we need to
do for the octan index is we need the
remainder
right so we're gonna have to do like a
half
index we're gonna have to say like half
atlas index
like so um and then we're going to have
to actually do the
remainder so the remainder
um from that
is the atlas index minus the half atlas
index
times two right so this is how many we
had left over
now i don't know how we want to encode
this octant index
but presumably the easiest way would
just be to say
look
we're going to take the remaining x
which is either 0 1
we're going to add it to 2 times you
know or we can even do this
so we know the remainder is always zero
or one
we divided by two you can't have any
other remainder right
um and it was a positive value so once
we have this remainder we're just going
to say okay
x goes in that bit next bit up is y
next bit up is z right
so we can pretty easily you know decode
those values
and we can make this an actual
function so that it's you know not so
mysterious
uh and so here if we say like somebody
computed a remainder
somehow right and we want an octan index
from a remainder
well here it is
and again that's just so we don't have
to like have that
you know the way we decoded that we
don't want to strew that throughout the
code we'd
because what if we change it or you know
who knows what just also for clarity
okay uh so i think that's
really all we needed there uh and so now
the problem we have is this
um and we we don't actually have
uh these tables that we would actually
need so here's the letting solution
and what you can see
here on this uh
here on this light sampling walk table
um we kind of have a problem which is
that if we change this
we will break the loading because we
just flat saved it
so we may want to do is something like
this where we just push this down
here right because this stuff doesn't
have to
you know be changed or
it doesn't doesn't really affect us
right
so we'll just put a to-do in here
but that's basically what's going on
so in the light sampling walk table um
and in fact i guess i can just leave
this at the very end i mean
whatever uh
so we can now generate this in a way
that we say look we know there are eight
octants so we can generate each
individual octant for this thing
uh and off we go but our problem now is
well we're going to have to actually
compute that somehow and so when we do
compute walk table
you know we're going to have to uh take
into account
uh all of that stuff right so
if this is eight long and i guess
another way to look at it would
do this uh if we go to compute walk
table
like so let me say this thing returns
uh now like an array of pointers instead
of whatever and i don't know
this is getting kind of annoying now so
i feel like i want to stop doing that
like i would rather this thing just
did what it's going to do so
excuse me
so what i'd rather do here is say okay
the walk table entry maybe is a thing
that you know is taken as a dest so it
doesn't
you know write out that way
oops
where did my code go
well compiler will take me there in a
moment
there we go um so anyway if we
yeah just say hey uh go ahead and build
that i also don't know
[Music]
compute walk table fast let's get rid of
this
because we're not going to be using this
anymore
all right um
all right so then i think we're good uh
and now we just have to make sure that
uh you know we don't want to call
compute walktable fast anymore it's not
a thing we use
it was just some test code and we do
want to pass that in
i wish i had some more tea but i don't
uh so i think that's the end of it
yeah okay uh and so now what we need is
we need compute walk table to actually
generate
different versions of this table right
and what we want to do here is take a
look at that max
cost per ray so max cost per ray um
i mean i guess we don't have to care at
the moment i'll put it to do on it
but
in the past we were sending down
a much higher value than we should have
so we're sending down
16 and if we have the size
of the dimension the grid that should
shrink to eight
right um because we're no longer going
to need to
visit as many grid cells to get the same
distance
so i think that's probably pretty safe
to reduce so in here i would also say
okay
where we were setting that to 16 before
um
we can probably safely set that down to
eight and
for now i'll also inside our sort of
temporary code
inside hh light prof uh i'll do that as
well
right
so all that should be fine um and we can
you know drop the the number of grid
squares that you visit down
maybe i'll do it this way because i want
to just be clear that's temporary code
because
if we re build our test data that would
get
properly slip streamed in so
i think that's all we need there and
then inside
compute walk table
i just need some way of having compute
walk table
uh actually build the different octants
so
in here we would be writing to eight of
these
so each individual octant right
and if you look at
sort of how this code is structured what
you can see is it goes per sample
direction
and uh so in here where we do like this
push array
uh what i could probably just do is is
you know
something like this right um
where we just say okay like the dust
index i guess
uh is
well it's gonna be per so i guess i
don't i don't even really want to do
that right what we want to do is for
each sample index
no that's correct so for each one of
these i just want to go through
all of the octants so like you know
something like this uh and then we just
want to do
the the routine for that octant
and as far as i can imagine the only
difference here um
actually at all uh
so like the only change would just be
this
right like everything else is exactly
the same
the only difference is like the starting
values
so in one case it was going to be half
the cell dim
now it's going to be like 2 5 the cell
dim or seven five the cell dim
er in each dimension but that's the only
that's the only difference right
um and so you know this is a fairly
clean way to do this but it's a little
obtuse i
might just do the ridiculous version of
this where we just
said all right we actually loop over
each
kind um like so
like here's the different ones of these
we want
right and when we come down here and we
do this push array we're actually going
to have like this dust table
thing and i'm just going to say look
desk table equals dest
for whatever the octan index is and the
octan index
is just something we get from compute or
get octan index or whatever it is get
octant four
uh so it's basically uh
all we would do is say the remainder
is whatever we computed it to be right
so whatever one we're on
in this iteration we get that octane out
and that's it so you know
that seems fine and so at that point
if we know what this value is all right
and i can even put that here which is uh
sort of our
sub index or something i don't want to
call this it's not the octet index
because that's the thing we're actually
uh calling some things precise but this
is basically just our oh you know what
we call this the remainder which seems
good
let's call it that so if we have the
remainder
then we know what the starting location
would be uh for each of these
right inside the cell we would just have
the starting location worked out
uh to be uh 0.25 f
times seldim plus
half of the cell dim times that
remainder
right so if we just do the remainder
times the seldem like with the hadamard
product here
then off you go so
that's pretty straightforward and then
everything is the same
so that just computes eight tables
instead of one
and each table starts with an offset in
the octant
based on the remainder and everything
else would just work
now the problem is this code is going to
be hellish to debug
and the reason for that is the same
reason i always say i've said it a
billion times
i'll say it another billion times almost
all bugs come from index problems
all the other things that people always
say bugs come from are just i don't know
why because we never have those bugs and
i don't know you actually know how many
people ever have those bugs probably if
you're just sloppy you have them or
something
um but
when you have all of these different
indexing schemes
which pretty much only happens when
you're trying to write fast code
because otherwise you just use one
the mismatch between the indices and
like you computed would use the offs a
wrong offset here
this that there that is just the thing
that always produces
your bugs and again because we have
two spatially coincident but uh
effectively disparate grids uh
that mismatch is all you know the more
coordinate systems you have the more
bugs you have it's just
maybe it's just me but in my experience
that's like where
all the time spent debugging always
comes from like
miss thinking about um
mistakes and thinking about where
indices is or for getting an offset
somewhere for getting a divide get it
right like all that stuff
and so you try to make it as systematic
as possible when you go through it but
is there's always
kind of a a difficulty expressing these
things clearly in code
and a lot of times if you try to put
more structure in place you end up
actually obscuring it even more so like
it's a hard problem because there's not
a lot of good ways to attack it
in the languages that we have
so anyway um i don't really know that
there's that much more to do
besides just when we compute the walk
table uh we now need to return on the
part where we just
you know um
set up the corners
that may be it
i mean i i don't know but i'm thinking
about it like that that might have been
the complete
that might have been it um
i don't know if there's anything else
left to do um
so i think mostly now we're just to the
point of like now we've got to go
through and find out all the things we
did wrong
uh but but i think just in terms like
conceptually speaking
that's it right so now we just have to
go take care all the bugs that
that you know um got introduced
uh so let's start we'll look at
um oh uh so well for starters here's one
bug
i forgot to put that in place
um so let's just we'll take take him in
order we'll do crash bugs first
um doesn't look like we have any
um so now we're going to have to take a
look at just like
errors first i guess like actual errors
let's take a look at what the perf is on
it since i have no idea what to expect
here
um i don't know like
again until we get it debugged we don't
even really know what this number would
mean
um where is my
there it is um so again like i hope that
box count distribution is accurate i
don't know
um but we'll see so
this 4.22 that's like better than we've
had before certainly like significantly
better um
than we've had before like 4.5 was where
we were at before
um so that's a good sign anyway but
again we don't know anything about that
we don't have any idea like this is
probably just totally wrong and if we
run
this in the game i'm assuming we'll just
have garbage
yeah so you can see like there's nothing
happening right
so we need to go through now and and
find out like
where all the problems are here with
what's going on
and you know we may
need to postpone that mostly until
tomorrow at this point i would say that
you know it may also be a good time to
kind of like
you know start to pull some of the stuff
out from the lighting code that that we
know we're not going to use anymore like
the grid raycaster is obviously much
faster
than the aab caster now um
and we've i'm pretty confident we can
continue to improve the speed so i don't
know that we still need that in there so
you know pulling out the the
a b tester and and streamlining things
more might be a good thing to do
uh i guess did we already do some of
that though i i don't actually know
uh i i don't remember like what stuff
we've actually done
i think we did that right yeah um
so we've already done that so actually i
don't even know like why is this defined
still here
yeah not sure what the point of that was
um
so anyway like hopefully we can start to
streamline some this some more too and
and just simplify it down from where it
is because it's
it's still quite complicated um
and there's probably more stuff we could
do here to make it a little bit simpler
but
uh in terms of like yeah in
just in just in terms of what actual
test code is in here
so we can also pull out some of these
other things we've got this
you know and we can all we can go look
at the the code for compute table fast
later as well
uh you know we've got it saved in the
previous versions of the code so i don't
really need that anymore
we can also get rid of some of the
things like the test sphere and stuff
like we're not using any of that stuff
anymore
and we would have to rewrite it probably
if we were going to do
any kind of real testing with it so that
stuff i think can also be kind of pulled
out of there
um which i don't know if we did that
already either
uh but like there's let's see internal
lending core build a few slide maps
the the radiance pack and and binaural
to normal those we don't use right now
but i think we will so
i'll probably leave those in there just
because we'll probably have to use them
eventually
so you can see tests here and here we
don't really
want that anymore either
looks like this is some kind of a
drawing code we left in here
just to show where things where we were
in the voxel which we don't really need
at the moment
um so that's all fine
test sphere can go
um
and that all seems fine uh
so again yeah like just slowly trying to
build
bring this code which is pr like
probably the most complicated code we
have in the entire game
right just trying to like bring it as
much in line as possible
and we'll try to do one more pass over
it after we're done
uh but anyway we we now want to know
like okay
so what is going on here why are we
getting no
uh why are we getting no output like
what's actually happening
so maybe i guess we'll just step through
um in hh light prof and we'll
see what the actual difference is
so in hh light prof if i
turn off optimizations
uh and i step into grid raycast i should
be able to take a look at some of these
things
so my first question is you know how do
these things look
uh do they make sense you know what's
going on
so let's take a look at some of these
so here's you know just some of the
entries into the
walk table let's just see what they look
like
i mean they seem pretty placid
you know those are just grid steps right
basic grid steps
exactly what you would expect um
you know i mean there's there's nothing
weird
that's that's pretty straightforward
right
so let's take a look too at some of the
other computations here so like
if you take a look at the initial grid
index
and the octan index right
as i run through here we should get like
different octants
and to be completely honest i guess
that's not exactly the pattern that i
would have expected
so i guess i can see why though so the
reason for that is because
since we're going uh in sheets
you would only get uh alternating
right because if you look at how full
cast works
i should i should say compute lighting
so you can see it steps in
z x so you'd expect to see zero one zero
one zero one zero one zero right
and then you would expect to see like
four five four five four five four five
right um and that is what we get so that
that does seem
actually that does seem correct uh so
no real complaints there
um let me take a look at the spatial
grid in general
oops
i'm just curious about some of these
values
uh that seems fair
kind of what we would expect um
again really just don't see anything
weird here
this all seems placid
right
um
so to be completely honest i'm not sure
where the trouble is coming in i
i would have liked you know for for
my ease of not having to do much work
i would have preferred to see something
more blatantly wrong
right but this looks subtle
i don't see anything obviously weird
right so we're going to look up into the
walk table
here you can see that happening and
we're just going to take a look
at you know what we end up with here in
terms of
oh all this this needs to go away by the
way like
so the raid dim index that stuff sorry
we got to get we got to pull some of
this stuff out i don't want to be
stepping through this
code also we don't need like a bunch of
these values
right so in terms of the stuff that's in
here we don't need the t
values anymore those don't have to be
here because we're not doing that
so just get them out of the way so
they're not cluttering things up
similarly none of this stuff has to be
here that's all gone
uh and i also think these don't have to
be here
like infrared pacts
uh so a bunch of that stuff just isn't
relevant anymore
um i don't know if sign ray d
needs to be here
it does all right so just pulling some
of that stuff out so i don't have to
deal with it
oops and off we go
so let's see uh
i need to step in that just ran
it ran away from me
so we are doing tests
a lot of those tests have nothing in
them but that's what we would expect
because it's a very sparse system
that's just kind of the way it is
so i guess one thing i'm not 100 sure
about is i guess we don't really know
that it's broken
[Music]
all right um so let's
i guess let's take a look at what
happens if i weld it back in
uh so if you look at how this stuff's
working here
uh again like this this is kind of ugly
and
and i don't really love it so when we do
our voxel dim here
again what i want to do is when we
create this spatial grid and we have the
spatial cell count the atlas cell count
and all this garbage
so we need this stuff to be computed
differently
so i would want to do this
for starters right and then when we do
the voxel dim i would want to do this
right so there's basically like a
multiplier ratio there on each of those
and that part's pretty straightforward
but
the
the rest of this so down here i think
this just wants to do
a subtraction for the spatial min corner
i think it just wants to do whatever the
atlas
spatial uh
whatever the spatial grids cell dim is
it just wants to be one cell because
it's always one cell all the way around
right so i think it really that is the
way that wants to be phrased because it
always has a one cell apron
so i think that always wants to be
adjusted um
that way and then when we actually
do the flat index from
part of things uh over in full cast
that part's a little squinky but when we
do this
and we do this uh atlas
to spatial grid uh index offset
um that's still gonna be one all the way
around
right so i think that's the only
patching we would need to do
to run it in the game
i think
don't quote me on that um and so
i'm not really 100 certain oh so okay so
it turns out it maybe just works
so when we actually did the patching to
line the grid up properly in the game
it just worked so maybe there wasn't
anything wrong with it
and i just thought there was gonna be
um so that's fine uh and
i think again like we don't really know
exactly if we still got bugs because
we're kind of just playing it fast and
loose as we march down the optimization
curve we're going to have to sort of go
through and do
that sort of final pass on things but
taking a look at it
in terms of our current speed again
constant forward march of progress we've
gotten
again down a little bit lower
now one of the problems here is
again i'm not really sure how far we're
approaching
so this is with the larger grid size
right i'm not sure
i'm still even not sure if that's i mean
for all we know we want to be even
bigger than that right um
and so you know you could imagine going
up uh
one more to nine you could imagine going
up to 16.
um well it's not 16 is it 64
right um so you could imagine continuing
to
make it more and more ridiculous but at
least now we can see that like
okay we have very few splits now which
is good
um and we just have a lot more that are
there's
that are you know gonna actually utilize
that loop
and that's positive thing too so that's
just
looking better right that's looking
significantly better
so what i'd like to do now is really
quickly just take a look at what happens
again if we run the testing without
doing the
the sort of uh post you know the
postcode i'm also going to take a
snapshot of this
so in the lighting code here where we've
got our little timings here
so that's down more around let's call it
4.3
ish i mean
these are not precise numbers so i don't
know why i've been placing them in there
but oh well
so the 2x facial grid size got us down
further again
um but what i would like to know
is what happens if you know we don't do
any raycrafting
right how long does this take so in the
lighting code
again if i just say look
suppose we we don't bother with any of
the stuff that you were going to do
afterward
which i guess is
so right here like let's just suppose we
just don't do this code
right so we didn't have to do any of the
casting
at all
so that's 1.02 right
um so we now know that we have a
headroom and that's better
uh which i guess i'm not really sure why
but
right because that's a little bit
different than what you take before that
could easily be within variance
right
that's not particularly variant so i
don't know we might have improved some
things who knows
right maybe this oh you know it's
probably the spatial build getting
faster
right um so it's getting better
and if we look at the difference between
those two
we've only got 3.2
uh seconds worth of delta between doing
nothing so
the the grid raycast now uh is quite a
bit faster than it was
um when we started certainly
if you took a look at the difference
between these two things
we were at 7.2 so
where's our
there we go um so we were at
7.2 seconds or 7.3 seconds
right and we know that 1.2 of those
seconds
is just the preamble stuff so if we're
talking about 6.1 seconds and now we've
got ourselves down
to 4.2
so we've doubled the speed of the
raycaster
roughly speaking and
that seems good
i don't know how long the spatial
partition build uh
takes so i might say like
build this so
if we just don't do this
right
so i guess the problem there is someone
still accesses it
i'm not sure why um
because we're not creating it oh well
you know who is
uh it's this saucy salamander
right here
right because that does actually access
it to do the testing for
whether or not you start at it out
inside the grid
oh well i was hoping i could just kind
of nerf that computation entirely
well that's okay i suppose actually let
me just back it out like this
if i want to uh not
if i want to get rid of the cost of
building the spatial partition what i
could do
is just say um
when we do these
just don't do any computations in here
so all of this code can go away
maybe that would work um so that way i
can still test it without but it still
creates something there so people won't
crash
i don't know they probably will still
so that's not accounting for anything
um maybe we're not even timing it
no we must be because it's in the
internal lighting core so i don't know
how that takes zero time but apparently
it does
unless i did that test wrong
so in theory that's just a non-issue um
which is what i would expect because it
was only done once right
um so it's you know it really shouldn't
contribute much
uh so that's fine all right so let's go
ahead and stop there and tomorrow we'll
take a look at some other things
i'll do a quick q a
that's a tough question from insobot
insabot is a rather
aggressive questioner um
you might say
can i run through how the lighting looks
now uh sure it's it's pretty
straightforward actually
um how it's actually working at the
moment um and we haven't gone into
sampling yet so we're gonna do some
different sampling things in here
to improve the quality of things but at
the moment
uh the process is pretty straightforward
now
what we do is we have a lighting voxel
that is imposed of the scene
and we step through the that casting
rays
out from the center to see what we hit
and we do a gather based on
the voxel itself so whatever the
previous frames voxel as we gather from
there
in order to speed up the ray casting we
have a second spatial grid which is half
the resolution of the voxel just because
the voxel's too
granular and we step through
uh that spatial grid looking for what
occluders exist in it and we do
the raycast against those to see what we
hit
uh and that's really it so it's it's
pretty straightforward
the problem as with anything is when you
have to go really fast
you know the code is very um dense
because you can't you know you can't
just write things the first way you have
to do them
pretty uh you know elaborate right like
this
so you get stuff that looks like that
which is kind of nonsense right but it's
just
you know it's it's not actually
complicated code it's
uh in terms of what's doing it's just we
had to write it in really obtuse ways
because that's the only way to actually
like
mostly it's because intel chips suck it
might be a right way
to say it right
if intel chips had a halfway sane
instruction set all this stuff would
look
pretty much exactly the same as it
looked before we started optimizing it
right but
sse is like one of the worst vector
instruction sets ever designed
so you know you get crap that looks like
this
yeah we'll probably do some de-noising
in a sense but
we probably won't quite do exactly
de-noising per se
we will be doing some things to make the
lighting more consistent
and then also we're going to spread it
out more but
we're probably not going to do like
literal denoising necessarily
but who knows is neon any better yes
it's way
way better
like way better
avx 512 is also way better but
nobody ships anything with it in there
so it doesn't matter
like basically the only chips with avx
512 support that you can actually use
are like
server machines so for game programming
it's useless
so avx-2 probably wouldn't help
particularly much for what we're doing
um
but
we so it's hard to say
avx2 is tough on a lot of parts it's
slow
um so you probably don't want to use it
and you don't want to mix
avx2 code because it has weird startup
penalties and stuff
on on zen it would probably be a big win
would be my guess so like if we if we
were on a horizon core i bet we'd see
some good wins on that um
but what i would say in general is
it's still just maybe a little too
aggressive at this
point so you know if you go ahead and
take a look at uh
i mean that's just rough a quarter of
the machines on steam
can't run your code that's not
i i just don't know if that's viable
right
um what i'd say about uh
oh skylake x also supports experts yeah
again skylake
x just nobody has that right
um those are server chips they don't
people with game machines don't have
that i mean here
look nobody has it
like literally nobody so
nobody has guy i don't i don't have
skylight x i don't have a single machine
in this office that's skylake x
it's just it's not a thing right it's
for server skus only at this point
and it doesn't even exist on amd
there are no avx 512 parts on amd
how is skylake x not server it's isn't
it definitely server like it's
i've only ever seen it in server skus
does anyone do desktop builds with
skylake x
maybe somebody does
because it depends on how you define
server
i mean is that
i guess that is not server maybe
i i could see i could see those i mean
that's a server
i don't know who maybe maybe like
real enthusiast gamers or something
would would put that in a
you know i mean i don't know yeah i mean
i guess like
i guess one of the things is in my mind
i
i think i probably don't have a
realistic picture of what
enthusiast gamers might actually spend
on their machine i mean i guess
i guess there are people out there who
spend a thousand dollars on a gaming cpu
um but
couldn't we do two pass one with and
without avx-2
um not really so the reason that that
doesn't
work particularly well
is that
if a cpu has avx-2 it's probably faster
than a chip that doesn't have avx-2
so it's unclear who you're optimizing
for at that point because
i mean i guess you could just say well
you turn on a higher quality setting
but typically the people we're
optimizing for are for the chips that
don't have it
right you're trying to get things fast
as fast as possible
for the machines that wouldn't have
avx-2 so this is usually the reason why
that kind of
a that kind of a dev process doesn't
make any sense
because you're just making the code even
faster on machines that already would
have run it faster
than the actual uh minimum spec you were
trying to optimize for you know
so those kind of paths only make sense
if you're trying to have an additional
quality setting
why is avx 512 so uncommon
probably number of registers
probably probably you'd have to ask
intel
and amd number number of registers and
size of register
would be my guess um
i i i don't know but that'd be my guess
abx-512 is a real bear it's 32 registers
which is way too many registers that
don't know why
it has that many um and it also adds
mask registers so it's just
it's the disaster
i want to say they do some crazy crap
like that i want to say like the mask
registers are aliased with the x87 part
or something
on modern implementations like i'm not
making that up i think that's actually
true
yeah so ice lake will have avx 512 i
think so
if they ever actually ship any of those
in quantity
it would
so all right i'm going to wrap it up
all right thank you everybody for
joining me for the episode of handmade
hero it's my pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow the
series at home you can
always pre-order the game on
handmadehero.org and it comes with a
source code so that you can play around
with it
um we'll be taking a look at some other
optimization options tomorrow
as we continue just trying to make sure
the lighting code
core stuff operates as quickly and as
cleanly as it can
that's it for today hope to be back here
tomorrow till then have fun programming
everyone
and i'll see you on the internet take it
everybody