there we go it is time ladies and
gentlemen it's time for day 66 of
handmade hero welcome and thank you for
joining me this morning it is a
beautiful morning here in sunny Seattle
Washington I don't know why it's sunny
we have a reputation for rain but it's
been very sunny this summer I don't know
global warming who knows I don't really
know not a climatologist but what I will
say is it is sunny here and I've had to
block out the light there's still some
leaking in in the back here you would
just see me in a giant halo of light
today anyway thank you for joining me
for Hammer hero this of course is the
show where we code a complete game live
on Twitch from scratch no engine no
libraries and again it's it's it's
really been a pleasure doing it it's
something I like to do it's the way I
like to code things because I just I
don't know maybe I'm a control freak is
partially the reason I like to have a
you know sort of that that entire thing
no engine and no library I like to kind
of go in there and know how every little
part works but I think it's also just
it's a great knowledge base really you
know to to go through and do all this
sort of thing I think every you know
programmer should should do it once get
that sort of understanding of the
complete pipeline and really just be
able to sort of know how everything
works even if you do end up deciding to
use engines use libraries because there
are good good stuff out there for that
it just kind of makes you so much more
well-rounded so much more able to deal
with stuff and I don't know it's just
it's a great feeling knowing you know
how to do everything even if you then
choose not to you can make better
decisions and you can also be more
powerful in terms of dealing with
problems and the stuff that you do use
and and heaven knows there's problems
and most of stuff we use these days it's
true software's complicated so let's get
started
we're on day 66 today so if you have
pre-order the game on handmade here org
you will want to unzip day 65 source
code that's something you can download
obviously tons a day 65 source code and
you'll be exactly where I am today so if
you'd like to follow along at home with
a code that is how you would do it let's
go ahead and open up the the
aforementioned handmade hero I believe
that we had just finished up updating
our code to use simulation regions which
was kind of a cool thing I
think I liked whoa don't accidentally
hit that button the guy told Windows I
wanted help don't want to see what
that's gonna do so what we've done is
we'd finished updating our code to use
simulation regions but we hadn't
actually gotten a chance to go through
and actually debug it all and there's a
couple features we need to add to it
still in order to make it be complete
and do all the things that we needed and
so today we just kind of need to go
through you know make sure that
everything's cleaned out and working
properly with our new code and we need
to add one or two small things to it to
make sure that does everything that we
need so what we have here if I remember
correctly is we have a simulation region
which does not currently have the option
of allowing entities to not essentially
exist at a location in other words there
was already concept sort of in our game
we had only just started toying around
with it but there was already a concept
that you could have something like a
sword that the hero was carrying or
could use and that that sword wasn't
anywhere in the world in particular
until they chose to use it or swing it
right and again this is not a fully
fleshed out concept yet it was just
something we were playing around with
but it seemed very potentially useful to
be able to have entities that don't have
a specific position in the world so they
can come into being and out of being as
far as rendering and stuff is concerned
that seems very useful and we could do a
lot with that
so in our simulation region what we
would like to do is support that
operation and so what we kind of want to
do is have some sort of a flag or some
kind of something where when we load
something into the simulation region to
update it we can smoothly handle the
fact that it doesn't actually exist
spatially it only exists logically and
then when we restream it out we will
keep that information so basically on
the in and out keep track of it and then
on any of the updates what we do in the
sim region understand
it's not actually participating
spatially in our simulation so how do we
do that right and that's a good question
since it's a concept we haven't really
done much with it's kind of we don't
really know much about the requirements
of it but what I would say is we do
already have this this collides concept
here and so what I wonder what I mean I
think is I do wonder if maybe now's a
good time to just kind of introduce the
concept of having flags on our entity
now we've seen flags before already
they're kind of a good catch-all for
just a simple small piece of storage
that allow us to tag our entities with
special conditions that we want them to
have and so to me and so it seems to me
that since this is kind of a special
concept that we want to make sure we can
always check about or check for it seems
like it would be a nice thing to put in
those flags right it seems like it'd be
a nice thing to be able to mark entities
specifically as being spatially
non-existent so that we can specially
check for that in code and not have to
do something we're like the Pete the the
position is set to a large value and
that's the only clue right so I think
what I might do is go ahead and just do
that I'm gonna just make a little enum
here to kind of hold our flags and again
we don't there's no particular reason to
make an enum it's kind of just a
habitual thing that I do just to group
things together where I'll put them in
an enum we could alternatively just make
a series of pound defines or if you're a
person who likes cost values you could
do them that way
basically all we need to do is define a
bunch of flags that basically say what
what the properties of entities are that
we want store in the in these flags
right so I'll go ahead and say
underneath the entity type we're just
gonna have a flag field right and then
we're gonna get rid of this collides and
I'm gonna say entity flag underscore
collides right so I'll do it this way so
there's different ways you can write
these flag fields and I usually write
them a different way I usually write
flag fields
like this where I do like you know that
and then as I go down I do two four
eight right because what we want to do
for flags is we want to have a bit field
right where each bit of a value
represents a different boolean condition
but lately I've been wondering why I do
that I've been wondering why I don't
just do it this way because this seems
like a lot easier to read where you just
kind of do like like that right where
you just shift one up by an increasing
decimal value because that's just a lot
easier to read than this so I'm gonna
try doing it this way because I feel
like I just been doing it wrong I mean
that wrong there's no wrong way to do it
as long as they come out to the right
values but I feel like this is maybe I'm
just easier slightly in my own code as
well I've been thinking I should
probably just write it like this now
ideally what we have is a thing that
makes it so that this just happened for
you automatically and I believe that
John blows language already has this
feature but unfortunately you know we
don't have Jumbo's language yet yet
someday all right so if you have
collides and then maybe we have a thing
that's like non spatial or something
like that where an entity can can sort
of just be tagged as non spatial and
then at that point we know that that
entity is not going to participate in
any spatial operations and the p-value
for it is essentially meaningless right
I might want to arrange some of these
things a little bit differently here as
well like so we have some cleanup to do
here as in here as well look we haven't
really dealt with Z's yet so that might
be something to do in the relatively
near future as well because we haven't
really thought about that much and it
would be nice to get that under control
as well as one thing we do before we go
much further with our enemy stuff maybe
put in some stairs where you go up and
down and just think about how you want
to handle that and get that going so
anyway if I have these here what I can
do now to get to kick off this change is
to just compile the program and see
where it collides was happening and then
decide how I want to handle like these
positions right and so there's a bunch
of different ways I could do this one
way I could do
this was is having calls to check each
individual flag what I think I might
want to do is basically say you know
just have something that's like flag is
set or something where I do the entity
and I pass which flag it is that I'm
looking for like this I think that might
just be an easier way to do it
so I can just say you know is or maybe
just even is set entity and then I
passed that that that flag value that I
want right that seems relatively
straightforward to me so I think that's
what I'm gonna I'm start with and that's
just an easy way of making it so that
it's clear what's going on and it's just
a you know it's a really simple function
the function is just taking one of these
same entities like so and then a flag
value like that
I can I can make it so that it this is
kind of an annoying part right in see
one of the things is kind of annoying is
what I'd like to be able to do is say I
want to take flag value here but it has
to be a one of it has to be some
combination of cementited flags that
would give me a little extra type
checking or something like that
unfortunately can't really do stuff like
that and see I can understand why it's a
little bit of a hard problem but so as a
result I'm just gonna take a unit 32
there the reason I don't take a
simonetti Flags value there is because
you wouldn't be able to or these
together like if I wanted to use a
single is set call to check for these
two things together that obviously isn't
going to be passable to a sim entity
flag taking argument because as soon as
you are it together it becomes an
integer value and so that's why I'm
using that u + 3 to flag there right
anyway so this is very simple this is
just saying there's we have you know we
know we have the entity we've got that
flag field so I'm just gonna do in
binary and with whatever the value is
whichever one of those values you've
passed in and that's gonna give me a
value that would be 0 or 1 base well 0
or the flag value right after it was
done so then I'm gonna return that value
back and that will be fine for anything
that people need to if on because as
long as it's a zero non zero that's all
that's necessary and see you don't have
to have it be
exactly zero one so that'd be the bad VD
is set call and that's totally trivial
so I'll go ahead and stash that in fact
do we have it we have an entity dot H
file I don't know if that maybe is more
appropriate to put in here we haven't
really done much with entities yet so
it's hard to say but let's go ahead and
do that so now let's see do we have any
dot CPP that should probably go I guess
in in here let's see here there we go
and so we'll do this as well these this
collisions that's a that's the same
thing this is test entity and this is
entity flag collides so we got to see if
both of the entities collide let's see
for stuff like this when we add a wall
we will want to add in that flag we
could actually do an ADD flag here
something like that where we where we
set instead of instead of doing the set
manually we go through a setting call
again don't really know if that's
necessary but I find this is more of a
notational thing this is not really a
necessary programming thing I'm not
anticipating us doing complicated things
in here
this is not me like guessing about
what's gonna happen in the code later on
and saying I think we want control over
how these are set in red I would be fine
writing the code by hand in there easily
it's not really a big deal but the
reason that I kind of want to have an
add flag in is set and that sort of
thing for these guys is more for
readability I just kind of like having
that readability so if I want to say
like add flag it's just easier for me to
see that that's what's going on right so
if I do an ADD flag here I could go
ahead and do the exact same format for
the call you pass what flag you're
trying to do and then it just takes that
entity flags and it ORS in the flag that
you give it right and so our NV flag
glides is there and
and we're all good right so that's about
it let's just finish because we've got
that same thing that we want to be able
to do here right we want to be able to
add that whoops that was wrong
collides it goes false we don't have to
do anything for because we're assuming
the flags are start at zero so you only
have to turn them on there we go this
one's gonna be a one that collides
entity flag lies so and again another
hoops another one
it's our Monstar see empty flag slides
so and the familiar also collides entity
blow sim entity flag collides alright so
that should be about it and now we just
need to deal with the sword again which
is non spatial so since the sword is non
spatial we will say add flag entity low
sim fly oops entity flag non spatial so
now we know that the sword is a non
spatial entity that's not actually
anywhere in the world at the moment so
given that that's the fact that that's
the case I suppose you know what we
actually probably don't quite need to do
that either now that I think about it
because technically I think we know when
things are spatial and non-spatial at
the moment the way that that's actually
working is when we do a change entity
location for things we're actually that
whether or not that p-value happens to
be valid we kind of already know this
right I don't know if you remember but
the way this was working is we have that
null position for the peas and non so
what we could do pretty easily is in
here just say that the way that this
works is the low entities
sym when when we change this position
the low entities sim will set it to non
spatial or spatial right so we basically
have whether there's an upir not if
there isn't a new position we'll just
oops we'll add that non spatial flag and
if there is a new position will clear
the flag and so at that point we kind of
just have this easy way of making sure
that that flag is always set based on
that value right and that seems pretty
straightforward to me now we almost
don't even need that because the low
entity stores it already but and so I
guess to some degree we could even have
this flag only be set at load time but
for now I guess I'll leave it that way
when we go and do a little bit more with
streaming entities in and out we could
do some more with that all right let's
take a look at how this is going to work
in our stream in and out let's take a
clear flag in here and so clear is
just going to do the exact same thing
clear flag will basically and with not
the flag which means it passes all other
flags through except that flag pretty
straightforward again it just gets rid
of it so if you want to remove a flag
you can do that so that should be about
it now when we're actually in the sim
region we can go ahead and start
handling these let's see what we got
here so obviously for move entity I
think we want to say yeah with move
entity we probably want to make sure
that no one's trying to move an entity
that has a non spatial flag set because
that wouldn't make any sense so probably
what I would want to do here is assert
just for now that whatever this entity
is it doesn't have the non spatial flag
set because if it did it wouldn't make
very much sense and similarly we should
probably assume that collides is
authoritative here but what we could
also do is we could say that we want
make sure that both of these things are
set right that we want we want these are
or we want so yeah this is kind of
interesting what we could do here is say
we want env flag collides and
non-spatial to not be set right so we
want is set and not is set if that makes
sense
entity flag non-spatial right we could
say that
and again like I don't really know
that's that's on both of these guys
right I don't really know if that should
be necessary we could just assert that
because maybe collides should never be
set on something that's not spatial but
I don't know so just something to think
about when we're testing entities I'll
leave it like that for now there's also
a question of whether we want to have
our own sort of collapsing for that
because the test for something and not
something else in flagged language could
be boiled down to more simply but we
could also just assume the compiler is
smart enough to do that for us or that
we just don't care we can think about
that but yeah so let's see here what
else we got we want to be able to in our
begin sim check to see if we've got that
situation going where things are non
spatial right so when we add entities in
obviously when we load something when we
do our is in rectangle check we're going
to have a situation where for any entity
that we were looking at if we have the
the low entity itself we don't really
need if it's non spatial we don't really
need to do a rectangle check on it
because it can never be inside the
rectangle if it's non spatial right so
if the entity flag non spatial is set on
this guy then we don't need to check
right so if he we only want to do things
that don't have non spatial set if non
spatial isn't set then we would go ahead
and pull
in this way when we're in our ad entity
call that's where it'll get pulled in
which is kind of a separate issue but
let's go ahead and do the enzyme first
as well so when we're in the enzyme in
the NCM we have our stored entity
reference which we've we've written back
what we want to do now is when we do our
map into chunks base we don't want to do
a map into chunks base for any entity
that isn't going to be spatial right we
want to just set them to the null
position when we map them out if he's
not spatial so what we can do there is
we can say again is if it's set the
entity that we're dealing with we can
say if that entity has the entity flag
non-spatial if it has that set then
instead of setting it to whatever the
chunk space position of that entity is
we'll just set it to the null position
right like so so that way on stream in
we don't check if it's not supposed to
be spatial and if we and when we're
streaming out we write it back correctly
based on that value right so that's one
way to do it seems reasonable for now I
don't know well you know we'll take a
look at it in more detail as we start to
use it more so the only thing that we
need to do now is take a look at entity
because identity will still add entities
by pulling them in if they're referenced
by some other entity right so load
entity reference will pull in new
entities even if they're non spatial
like if the guy is holding a sword it'll
pull in the sword and that sort of stuff
so when we do that and we do that at
entity call right that add entity call
does stuff like figuring out where
things should live in the world and so I
just want to verify that we do something
logical in that particular circumstance
right so when we're doing identity when
we add the entity and we pass it so
there's there's I believe there's
multiple ways of doing that call there's
the identity that takes a location and
there's an identity call that does not
take a location right and the get sim
space P is something that that happens
when
we don't pass that that pointer there
right and so I think let's take a look
here I think load entity reference
technically is doing it wrong at the
moment I think this is just a bug that
we just never really encountered because
we haven't done anything with the sim
region's yet but if you take a look at
low entity reference you can see that
it's actually calling this version of
identity which is one that does not
actually take a position and I think
that that's wrong so what I'm gonna do
is is I'm gonna like label that as a
call that nobody should actually be
doing oops I hit my num lock key don't
know why I did that
so I'm gonna label that as identity raw
and basically I don't want anyone to
call that call I don't think I think
what we want them to do is we want them
to call this always so that it actually
people get a position properly when they
need it and so we'll just have this this
guy call into that function where it'll
pass a zero right i mm what
that's good call it raw there we go and
that way it'll always call this get sim
space P and then all we have to do is
forget some space P now what we can do
is say well alright the v2 for the
position of this entity what we're gonna
do is we're gonna initialize that to
something and then only in the case
where we know that this entity is
something that is legitimately supposed
to be spatial so basically again we just
use that not is set entity flag non
spatial so assuming that it's not a non
spatial entity then we will go ahead and
actually figure out where it is in the
world otherwise we will set its position
to something totally random now what we
could do again is set this to some weird
value right like so so that we know that
it's it's not involved we could also in
debug mode set it to something weird
like a
nann value I don't know if we want to do
that but we could put it to do here do
we want to set this to signaling man to
make sure man in debug mode to make sure
nobody ever uses the position of a non
spatial entity and I don't know the
answer to that question there are there
are values there are floating-point
values you can set that will cause the
FPU to cause a hard exception anytime
you touch them and that might be
something we want to stick in here in
developer mode you know when we're not
in release mode so that if anyone ever
tries to use a position value that you
know that would obviously that would
break this this situation that for a non
spatial entity it would tell us right
away that might be interesting we could
do something like that all right so
anyway we cannot convert the argument
because I did not pass the pointer as I
was supposed to so that should handle
that situation right now I don't know
again where we just know that that was
one of the things that we needed to do
so I went ahead and did it but we have
other things probably that we want to be
able to do so let's go ahead and start
debugging this and see where we're at so
an update sword this is interesting so
for update sword
we never handled this as well and we've
got this need to make yeah so we
actually kind of knew that we hadn't
finished this yet I guess it looks like
I've even put an assertion in there so
let's go ahead and finish porting the
update sword routine to correctly be
non-spatial and that should be pretty
easy to do now that we actually have it
cuz before we didn't have it so when we
update sword I think there's probably
nothing really that we need to do if
it's in its non-spatial state so
basically if that non-spatial maybe
there will be in the future but for now
if that enemy flag non-spatial is is set
we don't actually need to do anything so
all we need to do is when it is actually
set and once it travels the total
distance that the sword traveled I don't
know why we don't have it to do here but
we should
to handle the fact that distance
travelled might not have enough distance
for the total entity move or the frame
we'll deal with that a little bit later
on so anyway yeah inside our update
sword call assuming that the entity
actually is spatial then we'll do the
thing where we move the sword and when
it gets to the end what we want to do
here is now make the entity not exist
anymore so we can just have a make
entity non spatial or something like
this some kind of call where we just say
make any non spatial and we pass that
entity and that will sort of delete it
from the spatial nough sub right and
that be I don't know why these are all
in line at the moment I guess probably
because we're doing them inside a switch
kind of a situation so maybe that does
make some sense but basically make enemy
non spatial is a really trivial routine
all that's gonna do is set that flag I
don't think we really need to do
anything else at the moment we could
update the sim space key to be the eval
ocation in fact I could do something
where we have a pound to find for this
you know what I'm saying like something
where essentially in this entity that H
we say pound define invalid P or
something like that and we just can make
that be whatever the value is that we're
going to do so we have our invalid P
here and we can set our invalid P here
as well so we do make entity non spatial
they'll set its p equal to that and it
will set the flag on the entity that's
to me that says that it's not spatial so
an ad flag non spatial comes in there we
go
and that's about it that's all that
should really have to do and then we
similarly have the inverse thing which
would be make entity spatial right and
to make the end of these spatial honest
amenity what you would need to do is
pass in of a position that's where you
actually want it to be and what that
would do is exactly the opposite right
it would clear that non spatial flag and
then it would set the entity's position
to the position that you asked for right
and similarly I guess we could say that
it would set
the velocity of the entity probably to
zero to clear that out as well
or maybe you pass one in we could say
that you pass in whatever it's starting
velocity should be something like that
either way it seems pretty
straightforward so let's just go ahead
and assume that we've got those guys and
that they're hanging out all right we
can deal with that later so that's what
we want to do there let's see where
we're at again just trying to figure out
exactly what's going on with all of our
stuff so in our end sim see here in our
end somwhat entity we're doing what
we're dealing with the sword here let's
let's go ahead and see why we're getting
this assertion because our sword
shouldn't have had its location changed
like that or it should have had a
location change but it shouldn't be
having an assertion problem I don't
think so I don't actually know what this
is complaining about flags equals this
oh I I do sort of see I guess what it's
complaining about here where is our
stored value P well the stored that's
that's actually fine the stored value
it's coming from an invalid chunk it
looks like is that correct
let's see stored P it's coming from
invalid chunk and it's staying an
invalid chunk so what was the assertion
what was the problem there that was
complaining about assert not old P or is
valid so it was expecting us to pass no
in in both cases where the things were
not going to be valid so that's kind of
interesting hmm I wonder if that's just
a bad idea for how it because it makes
this call kind of harder to use if that
makes sense what we'd rather be able to
do is pass the null position in here and
and have that actually be the way that
that works so I wonder if this is
actually kind of just annoying and not
really what we would want for the way
that this call works because basically
it just gonna it would make us do a
bunch of busy work here like I'd have to
go ahead and make sure I check to see
exactly whether it was spatial and now
it's not
and vice-versa and stuff and then past
nulls are not in each of these
conditions for the new P that's not such
a big deal but again for the old P it
would be I'd have to go actually start
looking at that which isn't so good and
so I wonder if maybe we just want that
code to kind of be a little more
intelligent about how it works and maybe
change up sort of how we're thinking
about these old Peas new peas and new
Peas if that makes sense
furthermore passing in the old P doesn't
really make any sense anymore because
the Lowe entity itself actually has this
information in it so this is all kind of
a little janky and kind of more about
the old way we're doing things and
doesn't really necessarily reflect what
we actually do now if that makes sense
so I wonder if yeah if this is just kind
of stupid and we shouldn't just take the
opportunity to modernize this a little
bit based on the fact that we now know
that it can always work directly on
correct values that seems like a good
idea so I'm going to go ahead and do
that so I'm gonna go ahead and say let's
get rid of this call entirely this one
right here basically and let's fold this
up into here in some kind of nice way so
instead we could just say we have a low
entity index and we have whatever maybe
when you say change and early location
you always also have to pass the entity
not just the index because it is going
to update yeah it's going to update that
call so what we could do yeah sorry I'm
just thinking this through it thickens
through what the best way to do this is
so all right I'll start with this let's
split this way I'll start with this so
what we'll do at first is we'll say okay
we have the low entity we're going to
take it a world position and the world
position for now will the new position
will always be an actual position and
you'll just pass null position if you
don't want it to set to a new position
right does that make sense because we
have the null position right and so we
can just do an is valid on something
we don't need to be able to we don't
need to pass pointers for that right so
we can say is valid new P and then we
get this right so what I could do is
make this work essentially that way
right so we've got a new P in it like
that I guess I could actually do it this
way and then we'll just have this guy do
old P world position new P like so these
will both start out being nulls which is
what this routine wanted in the first
place and then what we'll do is we'll
say if new P in it is valid right if the
new position that's pointing in that
we're getting is valid then we'll
actually set new P equal to point to it
otherwise it will remain null and for
old P what we'll do is we'll say if flow
entity if that flag is if it's not set
oops that's ass in there entity flag
non-spatial
in the case where the low entity is not
supposed to be spatial it will leave it
set to zero but in the case where it is
a spatial entity then it will go ahead
and grab that position out of out of the
low entity and use it so that would keep
it working basically the same way to do
this now and but it will you know make
it so that that we can call it in a more
sensible fashion right and so now when
you can change any location you don't
ever have to pass that you just pass
whatever the new P is going to be and
and let's take a look here so when we
add low entities in the same thing would
be true instead now when we pass that p
value here let's just go ahead and pass
real P values through for now let's take
a look we'll just pass a null position
in the cases here and again I think we
probably want to clean this up one step
further but for now this will be this
will be okay let's keep going here and
so on all right so let's see how that
gets us let's just take a look all right
well this is interesting what is going
on here
get world shunk what is our problem
chunk whoa that's weird that is just
bizarre
get world chunk chunk is returning kind
of garbagey values there what what what
has happened add low entity let's see
here so we're in we're in this call is
this the first where are we on this okay
so it's our first one so let's go ahead
and step in there that's good so we do
our ad low entity our ad low enemy it's
going to initialize that to essentially
the invalid value then we go in to add
it it's going to do the ad and then it's
gonna try and call that change location
ah well that's true so we actually have
to also check to make sure that that
isn't and valid value and that the
spatial yeah yeah so again this is a
little jakey I'm just yeah it's just a
little not quite right because you have
two things that both represent the same
value you have the fact that it's non
spatial which is a flag and then you
also have the fact that this p-value can
be set to an invalid value it's a little
janky right you see why I think that's a
little janky I don't know maybe you
don't see why I think that's a little
janky but essentially what we would have
to do here for the catch-all is say also
the p-value has to be valid right both
of those things have to be true in order
for this to be set right and that would
go this way and I just don't love that
like I just don't love that concept oops
I do that wrong because like it just
seems like
I I didn't do it wrong I just have to go
set that in here it just seems like I
don't really like that idea I never like
having state stored in two places right
it just invites errors where people said
it in one and not the other and so I'd
like to think it through how I might get
rid of that it might be sometimes you
can't avoid it and so you know if it has
to be that way it has to be that way but
it just it just makes me unhappy it's
all but yeah so all we have to do really
is initialize the P to know position and
that solves the problem that we were
having there but it's just it's just not
fantastic so yeah anyway I don't know
what exactly is going on with that guy
see here so I think that solved most of
our problems we just have a few weird
things going on now we start out
centered wrong and so I have a to do in
there to look at why now that we're
switch to stimulation reasons we're
centered wrong and then the other thing
that we have to do is I was gonna say oh
we need to update our camera code so
that it follows the guy again but again
we'll leave that low and spatial thing
for now maybe I'll put in a little note
just as something to think about is so
that we don't forget about it and when
we're looking through things in future
clean up class passes if we have a good
idea where we're like this is how we
could fix this right we'll fix it so to
do it's kind of busted that P's can be
invalid here and we store whether they
would be invalid in the flags field can
we do something better here and so you
know now might not be the best time to
tackle that it might be better to tackle
that little later on when we're doing
when we understand the structure that
active and enacted like stimulated and
nonce and and store identities are going
to look like how they're gonna look and
that's for stuff but it's just something
that's on my mind
I don't love so that's that all right so
what I want to do now is go ahead and
start cleaning up the rest of this stuff
let's find out why the camera's not
tracking the guy that would be a good
idea so when we when we add a player
we're setting the camera following index
equal to that player so I think that
should still be working but we are not
currently tracking the the movement so
let's find out why it we I thought we
copied that code in here in fact we did
it's right here so we should try to
figure out you know why isn't that
working right so the entity itself we
want to figure out why this is never
getting triggered or if it is getting
triggered why it's not taking any effect
it looks like the reason is because the
camera P never gets written back like we
update new camera P here because we used
to have a change call here and now we
don't anymore so it may be as simple as
just saying whatever the new camera P is
we could just flat-out set it to the
camera P and have that work so let's I
guess that's one way to do it let's
let's go ahead and take a look now yeah
now I guess that would be it that would
be all we'd have to do I'm not sure if
that'll work or not but let's take a
look why is my guy floating off into
space
I think his D Z never gets updated
anymore as well so we got to go take a
look at that it once he starts jumping
he never stops all right so that fix the
camera problem - let's take a look at
why our D Z is busted that's I guess
probably something that's still we never
really did anything with Z like I said
before but we might as well keep it
working so let's see here so we have the
DZ value it should be getting updated
and entities it looks like right it's
coming in through here and the DZ values
should be getting set
I'm not sure why it isn't that's kind of
odd I wonder what the problem is with
that
so if controller start ended down Kon
hero DZ equals three looks like what is
con hero con hero it looks like we never
clear it is the problem so we never
clear the con hero D requests at all and
that's obviously going to cause the
problem remember we're storing the
controller input now in anticipation for
doing some stuff later so that is pretty
straightforward that obviously makes
perfect sense yeah it's still that's a
little weird why is it moving down in
that yes so we still have some weird
bugs going on here all right so assuming
that the DZ is set to zero now I don't
remember exactly how we did this control
chair thing so we have our DZ we have
our D story our GDP seems like all of
those things probably want to be set to
zero well the D sword doesn't actually
do anything well no it does that's true
so we want to kind of zero this out I
think entirely for now we can think
about how we want to do that exactly a
little bit more in the future but we
want to zero those things out and then
when we come down here and we set those
yes so the entity DZ we only want to
update that DZ if the con hero DZ was
actually it was set to something right
yeah so we do want to actually say as
long as long as that is a it's not a
zero value then they're actually trying
to jump this is kind of janky again we
don't really care about this very much
but that restores our jump control
anyway so that's fine cuz we I don't
know we had that jump in there we -
we'll keep it for now so the last thing
I want to do is figure out why our
camera is what's going on with our
camera focus in general like what's
what's the deal with with the camera
location why are we staring at not at
the center of the room and so I'm gonna
take a look at what's going on there
because I think we've got either a bug
or just a misunderstanding
in how our code is working and so I want
to take care of that so we have done
this to do add logic to the same region
to handle um place entities we have not
done this to do yet which is what we
need to do now which is figure out why
the camera is a little wonky so let's
take a look at that we know that that's
startup we do set the camera right or at
least we were here is how we set the
camera right we said new camera PE
equals this camera tile X capital y
situation right there's there's our new
camera P and then we were adding
Monstars and familiars near there and
whatever we did all that stuff right so
is it just because we never call set
camera it is just because we never call
set camera yeah that's exactly what it
is we had those change camera calls we
deleted them I never put them back in so
basically we would want to do that right
that seems pretty obvious that maybe it
and that was it
so that's the entirety of our problem it
looks like yeah all right well that's
good so now we should restore our sword
functionality probably as well again we
started about 15 minutes late today so
to get an hour's with the programming in
I'm gonna go another 15 minutes
certainly and then we'll still do Q&amp;A so
don't worry about that but I don't want
to do less programming than we're gonna
do looks like our sim region seems to be
working pretty well no particular
problems yeah everything seems to be
restored and so now we just should
probably do our quote unquote sword
again we don't have the sword graphic
game yet so it's just a stupid little
rock but gotta start somewhere
people probably fought with rocks back
in the day the other thing we should
probably do sometime soon
is is get this sorting stuff in there
because sorting wouldn't be too hard for
us to do and that way we actually pass
in front of these entities instead of
behind them right now things are getting
drawn in whatever order they were added
to the sim right and so that's not
particularly useful we want to be able
to sort them so that things you know I
should've clued those trees not the
other way around
anyway yeah I think we just need to take
a look at what's going on with our store
because we never actually ported that
code so let's take a look at that when
we do our sword code where is that
that's going to be in our in our hero
control code right that's going to be
basically down here where we do our MD
type hero well we take a look at that D
sword what we really need to do here is
just I guess figure out what's going on
with this guy
I guess our sword the problem is is we
didn't we have to make the sword spatial
at this point right so what we want to
do is say okay if we had a sword we need
to do is make entity spatial right and
we want to pass this stuff in here we
want to pass the entity P as the
position for them and this is going to
be the DP so we already sort did the
work that we need to do here to make
that happen
so I think that's it just telling you to
make it spatial so that it participates
in the sim properly
yeah and that looks fine that looks like
what's what it should look like although
I am a little bit weirded out by why the
shadow is so toe if the shadows probably
so dark because it's probably just a
full dark well I don't know I'm a little
this that shadow looks super dark to you
why is this it looks like it's drawing
the shadow many times or maybe there's
already a shadow on the stone I don't
know but it looks wrong to me that looks
wrong so I'm gonna go ahead and set a
loop point here right I'm gonna go ahead
and and and just set a loop point so I
can fire that and just leave it kind of
firing there and then I'm gonna go in
here and take a look at what's going on
so here's my sword right and I'm gonna
go ahead and and comment out the shadow
a bit map entirely so I think that sword
that sword really feels like it's
getting drawn multiple times to me that
really does right that's what it feels
like to me so what I'm gonna do
here is I'm gonna go ahead and take I'm
just gonna see you know are we somehow
getting multiple calls is there somehow
more than one sword like getting drawn
or getting added in here I don't know
because that would be pretty easy to do
and we might may not want to add some
shucky to make sure that that since
we're creating things in the sim region
and then writing back out I wonder if
you know we should add some code there
to make sure that stuff doesn't get
loaded in and and written out twice
especially in the early times when we're
getting this in region working in might
have bugs right so alright let's take a
look here what have we got when we do
our update sword and then we do the push
bitmap what would be an easy way to do
this let's say that we took the entity
index here like so whatever the entity
index was of this of this guy let me
just go ahead and add that in to the
location the offset in pixels of that so
I might say to do 10 times the entity
index like so and I'm just gonna run
that right oh I guess that was too much
never mind
so now you'll notice that I'm only
seeing one of them alright so let's go
ahead and add a fractional value in
there there you go so we've got lots of
entity indexes that are all the sword
apparently and so that's no good
doesn't make any sense so we've clearly
done something wrong probably again we
have a bug with our sim region how our
entity's system brings in elements we're
probably not I made that hash table
specifically to prevent things from
being loaded multiple times through the
referencing system I probably have a bug
there is what I would guess although I
don't really know so point being we
should we now kind of want to go and
check to see what's going on there I
think that's that's priority number
number one so let's take a look we now
know that my suspicion was correct about
the fact that these things are broken
and so we should be able to - yeah we
should be able to figure out why so
let's go into our handmade sim region
and see we know that we're having some
kind of problem with multiple entities
we know we only ever created one sword
anyway at least we thought we did and so
I want to first do a very simple thing
which is try to add some stuff into the
sim region code to guard against having
multiple entities in the sim region that
all represent the same storage index
right and so one thing that I could do
here is for example when we do an end
sim I could do something where I try to
guard against that rewriting by doing a
check on up up and back loading
basically so what I'm going to do is I'm
gonna go in here - we already added
these flags right in our in our handmade
entity right what I'm going to do is I'm
gonna have a flag here which is like
siming or something like this right and
I'm gonna make that be a flag that's
kind of at the end here it's like a
debug flag essentially what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna say that when we load
something out right when we when we do
our begin sim and we pull something in
so when
you add in D right when we do an ad
entity call at the time that something
gets get some added in right I am going
to oh you know what and we don't really
yeah well at the time when something
gets added in I'm gonna say at that
point we mark it as having been we mark
its source entity as having been loaded
in right so we'll say that will
basically do an ad flag right sinning to
the the the source version of that in me
right so the source SIM version gets
that flag added and I also want to
assert before I add it that it was not
flat set right like so so basically will
assert here that it was not set so that
we can see if we loaded something twice
and then when we write things when we go
through and write things out again we
will go ahead and clear that flag on the
right so when we go into NCM will do the
same thing right here when we store it
out will basically do an assert that the
the place that we're storing it out to
had that sinning flag set so we'll say
okay let's assert that the store
identity had that something flat set and
then we will clear it although I guess
at this point actually this call will
clear it itself so we'll go ahead and in
assert that it's not set after that okay
so those are just again purely you know
purely debug code it's just there to
guard against bugs on our part and catch
them earlier so that we don't have to
you know sort of notice them like we did
with the sword so let's see too many
actual parameters for assert oops let's
just put the parentheses in the wrong
place there let's see what is it oh this
is supposed to be an address F so let's
see
conversion from sim entity flags to you
and 32 signed unsigned mismatched oh
please are you telling me that this is
this is always thinking itself is is
signed versus unsigned that's that's
really annoying all right
does that help anything
does this help basically this is
complaining because it's saying that
conversion percent any flags to you and
three to sign its saying that so many
flags is signed but I don't want it to
be signed I want it to be unsigned and
I'm not sure how to make it understand
that which is unfortunate we can get
around it by doing this
but that's really annoying well we'll
think about that later all right let's
see here too many actual parameters for
macro assert same thing I just cut and
paste bugged that let's go ahead and do
that there cannot news my conversion
that's just of and there we go
so now let's see if that catches our bug
I was kind of hoping that it would and
it does so that's good so when I went
ahead and and pushed the sword button we
got that assert of that siming flag
basically so let's see what's going on
here
during begin sim it's pulling something
in so it looks like what's happening if
I had to guess is our sword is getting
pulled in both by the spatial query and
by the reference and so what I'd like to
do is figure out why that's happening oh
you know what I do know why that's
happening that's actually totally what
would happen right now we're not
checking to make sure that we don't
already have the entity when we do an
identity raw which technically could
happen because basically all we did is
prevent references from bringing in
entities that were already brought in by
references but we haven't prevented
spatial queries
from bringing in entities that were
already referenced by references if that
makes sense so what we want to do is
make it so that everybody checks to make
sure that something hasn't already been
brought in through the hash table before
it does that right so what we would like
to do is much like in ludendi reference
where we check this the the hash entry
first before adding the end entry what
we want to do here is do that same check
before we do this guy right so we want
to do here is say let's make sure that
whatever that storage index is let's
make sure that that doesn't actually
exist yet before we go ahead and do this
like so right and the other thing we can
do is now map storage index to entity
map storage index to entity I think now
should collapse into the atom dere or
routine right basically this should now
be done right here because we already
have that hash entry we already know
that it's there and so we can just go
ahead and use it we don't have to look
for it again right and so that's fine so
that looks totally fine to me let's go
ahead and try that get rid of that right
and I think that should do it there we
go
and that looks much better now we're
only getting one which is what we wanted
and we're not hitting that cert at all
and so on all right so let's just clean
that up a bit
obviously we want to get rid of that
drawing change I made there we don't
want to be offsetting this by its entity
index anymore
let's go ahead and fix that and
similarly we also want to add code to
make sure that the like I don't know if
you noticed but if I hold down the key
it keeps resetting the sword we want to
make it so that if you get the key if
the swords already there it doesn't
realize the sword again pretty easy to
do now that we know whether the sword is
active or not basically all we have to
do is take it take a look and say all
right when we get it
if sword and you know
is that non-spatial then we know that
the sword is not in existence right now
and can be shot and so that's fine and
so now I can't do that anymore I have to
wait till it's done to fire again so
that's good I think now we've fixed the
two dues that we had there and we are
back into good position with the sim
regions we've got a bunch of stuff we
can do now to the sim regions are
working well and they allow us to do
references and pull things to reference
it so I think everything is in pretty
good shape we have one more thing to do
which is the apron stuff which I guess
we can do tomorrow
which is this right here so I guess
that'll be what we'll focus on tomorrow
and that may be it for upgrading our
stuff again I don't can't think of
anything else that we really had to do
in there so that's pretty good so with
that in mind maybe it's time to go to
the QA if you could go ahead and prefix
your questions with Q :
and keep them two things that we've done
on today's stream or in previous streams
if you want to ask off-topic questions
that's totally cool but not for right
now I asked those during the pre stream
come about 15 minutes before the stream
is scheduled to start and we handle
off-topic questions then so that's
totally cool but let's just do it make
sure we do it then
no question there's gonna be a quick Q&amp;A
probably it's too early in the morning
nobody has questions because they're
sleepy which I don't blame them because
I'm sleepy too does the current
Collision code support walls that are
not 90 degrees say if the wall was at 45
degrees where the collision codes still
work um
so I'm the the general part of the
collision code would work but I'm pretty
sure we don't have a a wall routine in
there at the moment for anything that's
45 degrees because we kind of just put
in place hold or collision detection
right we haven't really done the full
collision detection stuff yet so if I
remember correctly let's take a look
it's move entity yes so so the test wall
right this is the call and basically
what needs to happen is you need to
compute the intersection time of a ray
and the wall and right now we only wrote
a routine for doing that for horizontal
or vertical walls so if you wanted to do
walls at 45-degree angles or any other
angle you would just have to write this
part of the code to him you'd have to
write one of these that did that it's
very simple math to do so but we didn't
do that yet and we don't necessarily
know if we will ever do that because
what we might do is use a slightly
different way of computing collision in
the final collision protector that
doesn't quite do it this way so whether
we will do that or not
I don't know but again it's not too hard
to figure out how to do it it's the same
exact math that we were doing before
it's basically you know it's basically
just trying to figure out
the intersection time where you've got
two two rays that are going at each
other and you could you could look up
online how to do that pretty easily if
you wanted to just to the intersection
of two line segments basically or ray
versus line segment is all that needs to
go in there but the rest of this code is
it's fine I mean there is one thing to
that we want to do like this code is
fragile at the moment the reason being
because when it's it's good this code is
good in the sense that it tests to see
if you're going to hit things and it
doesn't allow you to tunnel through them
but once you actually finish the step it
doesn't handle do numerical numerical
precision properly in a safe way so if
the step happens to numerically put you
right on that edge you could end up
inside something on the next frame
because of the way the numerical stuff
works out so we do have more work to do
to make a really good collision sector
this is not one that I would ship for
that reason but but yeah but in general
the logic here of testing doesn't care
whether the walls are 45 degrees or
anything else it's just this one part
that cares and it this is the only thing
that cares even that it's a line
basically as long as you can produce the
time that team in you could test against
anything here circles or whatever right
this code doesn't care what you're
testing against really
why not set a boolean value to be
removed I assume you mean the sword it
seems like setting the position to some
arbitrary position isn't an explicit as
setting a flag to say that the entities
should be removed on the next update
frame but we do set a flag right it's
non-spatial is the flag
so we I'm not sure what you mean it's
not if we're not removing the entity the
entity is still there we're just setting
it to not be in a spatial location right
and so that that is what we're doing
essentially is is setting a pool right
we're setting it to be non spatial when
it gets removed right so making so when
we call make entity non spatial which is
in entity that's VP when we call make
entity non spatial that's what we're
doing the reason that I was setting it
speech when invalid P is just for
further debugging like I want to make
sure that people aren't still using that
P and so I want to be able to when we
look at things I want to be able to see
that it's it's in an invalid P so that
it doesn't we don't accidentally get
people who are processing it after it
becomes non spatial basically but the
entity is not getting deleted it's still
there
hi Casey the rearranging of code did did
some errors in the code I think I guess
I think it probably means like at there
were errors introduced in the in the
rearranging of code is this normal for
daily coding yes any complicated system
when you rearrange stuff you're gonna
make some mistakes and that's fine
that's totally fine I would feel
comfortable when I would run in such
errors I would feel uncomfortable when I
would run in such errors but you seem to
get the logic even better after such
encounters yeah I mean I feel like
that's that is a skill that you have to
kind of develop again hopefully I'm kind
of showing you some techniques as we go
that can help you with air like you
notice when I saw that the shadow was
busted on the entity I was like oh yeah
one thing we should probably do is put
in some checking here to guard against
multiple and like the same nd getting
pulled in in multiple ways that is a
better thing to do in my opinion right
then just debugging that one problem
because like you said whenever you're
rearranging code and whenever you're
trying to move things around you're
gonna like it's so complicated
any good game high performance and
flexibility and kind of interesting game
mechanics all those sorts of things
there's gonna be a ton of complexity
there and you want to try and develop
programming methods that allow you to
catch those things so that you don't
have to be afraid of reorganizing your
code right and like a lot of people ask
about unit testing and unfortunately
unit testing isn't really that useful in
games because it's too hard to write
unit tests that cover all the things
that could happen but that doesn't mean
that you can't put in lots of debug
checking just the same so constantly
look for places you can do not so unit
testing but ways in which you can put in
assertions and debug checks that will
validate your assumptions when you can
is still good right you want to do that
because it'll help you debug them so
that's something I did and that's an
example those assertions on the siming
flag that's an example of something
that's designed to catch those kind of
problems that
can be introduced in reorganization or
that I think are going to be common and
so that's just like yes it's it's tough
but learning how to write code that
tends to learning how to write code that
tends to fail in ways that you can
notice is very important right and so I
do try to write code that's gonna be
clear and fail in ways that we will
notice and when I think that there's
gonna be subtle failures I try to add
those assertions so that's it's a
fellated today with catching that sword
problem I was like ah this is gonna be a
subtle kind of bug so let me try and add
something to the system that's
artificial that will make the bud bug be
loud and non subtle and so bringing
those to the surface in that way is a
good way of trying to get around the
problem you're talking about which is
being uncomfortable about making those
changes because of the errors they can
introduce right do we expect most
entities to be colliding if so does it
make sense to have the flag be non
colliding instead yeah I would say that
that isn't a bad suggestion I'll put in
a Sidhu for that I don't know I haven't
really thought about exactly all the and
it - entity types we're going to have so
I don't know but I could certainly say
to do does it make more sense to have
the flag be for non colliding entities
and I don't know that's a good question
then why set null position uh where are
we talking about setting they'll
position are you talking about sending
null position in the same region here
sorry I'm still very sick
would using a tagged Union for entity
references fix issues were having with
load entity reference what issues are
you talking about I'm not sure I'm not
sure what issues you're actually
referring to if you want to be more
specific
I could elaborate do you have the whole
big picture game architecture in your
head at every point or do you have to
check what you did from time to time
usually I have the entire big picture in
my head but I don't know if that'll be
true I'm on handmade hero because like I
only do it an hour a day and I'm program
you know full time during the day as
well so my mind is mostly occupied by
stuff that I do for the main program I'm
doing during the day and so I don't know
if I'll be able to keep all of him a
hero in my head as a result but normally
I would sew on handmade hero I think I
may have to check from time to time
because I feel like I won't probably
have that same kind of situation
situational awareness they'll have when
I'm programming things every day full
time because I know that I certainly
like after I leave a project for a while
when I come back to it like if it's been
a couple months and I come back to a
project I don't remember how everything
worked and I have to look right and so I
think that might happen to me here
because it's not my main focus it's only
an hour day
no more questions looks like no more
questions I see no more questions
all right well doesn't look like we've
got any more questions so I think that
means it is time to wrap things up which
is totally fine
that actually means we're on time even
though we started the stream 15 minutes
late all right well thank you everyone
for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it is been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home with the
source code you can always go to
handmade hero org and pre-order the game
it comes with the source code which you
can download every night I upload it
after I finish coding every day on the
stream so if you'd like to do that you
can do that here you can also support
the video series by subscribing to our
patreon which you can do here which is
very much appreciated and if you would
like to be notified of the schedule we
do have a tweet bot that sits there and
tweets the schedule to you so you can
always know when we are streaming we
also have a news and forum site if you'd
like to discuss things ask questions
check out our episode guide or look at
people a community ports to Linux and
Mac that sort of thing it's not a great
stuff on there so I highly recommend
checking that out if you're interested
in the series it's a good resource to go
to so that's about it I will be here
tomorrow at our regular time 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time tomorrow so I hope
to see you all there when we will wrap
up the sim rage and stuff I think
there's really I guess there's really
nothing else on the to-do list there
except that apron thing which I wanted
to think about a little bit so I guess
we'll just kind of go through and think
about the apron thing a bit and then
we'll decide tomorrow night what it is
we're going to do next we'll just kind
of see I guess probably what we'll do is
finish our sort of combat sort of stuff
where we can have the sword hit the
monster the monster could fight back
those sorts of things I guess that's
probably the next logical thing to do so
we'll probably do that but we will see
tomorrow night hope see you there and
yeah have a good rest of your day and
rest of tomorrow and hopes to you
tomorrow night so thanks for joining me
take it easy everyone