hello everyone welcome to handmade Hero
show recode a complete game live on
stream I am in the mood stream and I had
some extra time so I figured I would
this was not an amount stream it's just
a totally unannounced day 507 and I
thought maybe what I do is just take a
break here since this wasn't an
announced stream and take a look at all
the stuff we've got on our issue list
here cuz there's a bunch of things that
are just little you know tiny stuff that
we probably will never get to if we
don't actually spend some time looking
at the issue list and fixing things so I
don't know I thought that might be a
good time to actually go in and you know
set set set aside a few an hour - for
fixing some of these things and also you
know I guess at the moment - like we
should double check to make sure sine
and cosine are the only things we
actually need for moving off the C
runtime libraries thinking we should
move off the C runtime library because
we don't need it for anything except
sine and cosine and we kind of know what
we need to do to replace those that was
another thing I was thinking of doing
although that's probably better saved
for like a weekend where we can do you
know two days of work on that because
it's it's a little involved to do that
replacement going through the math and
all that stuff anyway just looking at
some of stuff I want to go back to the
earliest things and just see what's up
you know go through these sort of issues
that have been here so some of the shots
are maybe have the wrong Z set to them
and our cutscenes let's I don't know if
that's true or not anymore but we can
certainly take a look and see if you
remember the way we do the cutscenes is
we just had a list of the plates that
were involved in the cutscene and we
just run through them and so if we jump
into this sort of for lack of a better
term blank screen where we're gonna put
a title screen someday if we let this
sit it'll go into the cutscene
that's what we're looking at here and as
far as I know
we've kept this working all throughout
all of our changes to like the renderer
in the asset system and everything so
these all work just fine but the
question is do any of them needs
modifications for Z like things that
might be set Z wrong and well you know
there's a thing that's got that's got
kind of a weird 'no stew it so you know
that's that's wrong
whatever that is going on back there
that's incorrect so that's may not have
been anything to do with what they were
talking about for that bug but we got to
fix that like right you can't see the
the old plate there what's weird about
that is a lot of these other ones still
seem correct it's kind of weird that we
only had one error there but again you
know maybe that has something to do with
the Z maybe we're just only seeing that
Z problem so maybe this bug is accurate
but just looking yeah looking through
these I'm not really seeing any other
errors other than that one this looks
fine and Santa's doing this thing here
putting it on the little little guy
looks fine too so this all looks pretty
reasonable nothing bizarre going on so
it's really just that one cutscene the
the middle one there with the that's
that second scene it looks like some of
our plates are not working properly like
they should have been oh wow
okay that's that's crazy oh you know
what though this is actually pretty good
this is presumably the texture transfer
bug that we were having that's kind of
intermittent that looks the same as the
problem we were having before so we
don't really know what's going on there
and we kind of have to figure out
whether we're getting a thread stepping
on some two threads stepping on each
other or something thinking it's done
loading when it's not done loading we
don't know what's going on there
unfortunately that's probably
intermittent it probably doesn't happen
every time so that we're still waiting
for a way to get a good repo on that one
but so so I wonder if that's what
happened in the second one as well I'm
not sure so thus far again don't I don't
know if there's any actual Z problems
here it looks like most of this is fine
so I think that maybe it's just that
that corruption bug that we're seeing
there that seems like the main thing and
that could have been the cause of the
second scenes error as well so that's
the day yeah that's that's a good
question we don't know what's causing
that we really don't so uh yeah this all
looks fine still nothing weird going on
here so that background is having it as
well you can see it looks like a
striding error is actually what it looks
like to me and you can see the way those
things are like shifted so you know
there's different ways that can happen
one way is if we're just if the stride
is just not getting set properly I mean
that's obviously a possibility as well
but another one is if you're using
memory that was written to with one
stride and then you're you know you're
not actually rewriting the thing that
you thought you were you can see there's
some problem happening up here that
could be the same problem but I'm not
100% certain so that's that one's harder
to say so I'm gonna let it run through
one more time I want to see if these
errors are the same each time or if they
vary and yeah and yeah so you can see
here we get a really different result
this time through right so there's
definitely some weird stuff going on
this seems to be able to trigger it much
more reliably probably because it's
transferring large images and we're
recycling those texture handles
frequently there's only a few special
texture handles so you can see like all
of this crazy stuff happening so let's
use this to debug that problem I don't
know that we really have any of the Z
problems that it was originally saying
we have but we do have a problem which
is the same that texture transfer
problem we were seeing in the
game as well so this is uh you know you
can see it's totally different this time
too right so let's figure out what's
going on there because we don't really
know and we needed to debug this for the
main game anyway so this is all like
really useful work okay so one thing I
would like to do is I think it would be
nice to to do this under insight maybe
at some point to see if it's got any
messages for us warnings anything that
it notices is wrong because it may be
that we're just not paying attention to
something that we should be there may be
actually the graphics card or the driver
I should say may actually be telling us
at some point hey you screwed up and we
maybe don't know so I'm not sure one way
the other if there's some other things
going on in there so we might want to
check that out first what I'm going to
do is I'm just gonna re familiarize
myself with the basic texture transfer
code and I'm just gonna try to verify
that there's nothing out of hand going
on there like nothing that I see that
jumps out at me first because before I
just start go randomly sort of look you
know investigating the code I want to do
a just a spot check so if we start one
of the nice things that we kind of know
now and we didn't necessarily know
before is if you look at where we
specify GL Tech's image and let me grab
that here because we're not there yet
here we are so where we specify GL
Tech's image you can see a specifying GL
text some image 2d and GL text image 3d
here what's interesting is we saw this
bug on both paths and I think that's
really interesting because that lets us
know that we probably don't have a
problem with like some specific use of
say our texture array if this path we're
always working properly and remember
what the difference being these two
paths is anything that can fit in our
texture array we just stick in there but
anything that's oh
oddly sized image such as one of these
big cutscene plates it uses a special
texture submission and the really
interesting thing about that is that
that means that this call can't really
itself be the problem now that doesn't
mean we don't have a problem with the
transfer we still might and the reason
that we might have a problem with the
transfer is because there's texture
there's text transfer stuff that affects
how memory is read and used so it's not
a given that it's correct from in its
entirety but what is true is we're
seeing the bug on both text image 3d and
text sub image 3d so we kind of know
that we kind of know that we're not
having a problem with a specific
internal of one of those calls it's
something that's erroneous on both write
on both paths now I'm not sure
specifically why we decided to do GL
text image 3d here for the default
sprite texture format thing I guess we
just decided that's the easier way to go
now one thing that we should probably
have been checking here is to make sure
that the max width and height of these
things comports with the size of the
textures that we allocated in the first
place
because I don't necessarily know that we
ever did that and we may have had some
textures that actually don't fit in here
our modern import path would have fixed
that by resizing them but right now we
don't go through that path for these
these are imported from old hhas
so that might actually be one of our
problems it's not our only problem
almost certainly but it definitely could
be one of them so we probably want to
take a look and see what's going on
there
so let me go ahead and check what's
going on there we have some hard-coded
constants here we just said this is our
maximum we're not going to use any earth
you know other sizes than this I can't
remember exactly where where I actually
put that it's sort of a max size
where is that go where does that go
let's take a look let's take a look so
we have the texture transfer buffer size
but where's our actual texture
dimensions you know what I can do here
let me to search for 512 since I know
what that is so you can see here there's
our texture array dimension but let's
see here so when we create these so
there's some things about this there's
actually some things here that don't
necessarily line up with what I would
expect so for starters when we're doing
special texture handles that shouldn't
be sent down that that doesn't make a
lot of sense does it
I guess we just never actually send down
one of these dimensions early on because
look at look at how we're doing this
this doesn't this doesn't make any sense
to me at all am I missing something here
so here's our path for generating our 3d
texture here right that we use for all
of our sprites and then we come down
here and we say well you know let's we
would like to make some special textures
here and so we're gonna allocate a bunch
of those but we allocate them as 2d
texture arrays for some reason which
doesn't really make any sense does it
because I thought the way that we were
rendering these is that we switch
textures every time so like I thought
and maybe this is totally wrong but I
thought those should have been regular
textures not array textures and I don't
really understand so like you can see
here we do it GL texture 2d array bond
of the texture and what's why are we
doing that what is the point of that I
guess the Oh so you know what I guess
that's so this shader works and we just
only ever specified the base well you
know I guess there's nothing wrong with
that
so I guess there's no real reason to
think that that's a problem
I suppose although I guess I don't know
that for sure that was I he's coming
back to me now when we did that we
didn't want to have to have two
different shaders so we just made it so
that we use a texture array that's only
one deep for all of these um so that all
seems fine though like again doesn't
really seem like it would be a problem
it should still work so that I don't
know I'm not seeing why any of that
would particularly problematic however
like I was saying before one of the
things that we did not do here is we
have a text transfer like there's
transfer parameters that are in effect
here where we do and that looks like we
we never actually said any of these but
if you look at how opengl works when you
call a text image any of those text
image calls like text sub image for
example like we're calling to transfer
the sprites or text image 3d like we're
calling to transfer the main one if you
look at the documentation for it when
you actually execute this transfer it
should in here oops sorry
it shouldn't here tell us this although
I don't know if it actually does that it
uses the texture transfer modes that
have been set in order to figure out how
to copy you know what I mean
and let's see yeah the pixel store mode
effects text or images state of a 1.4
blah blah blah texture memory mats and
let me see so pixel store modes and yes
you can see all see all these pixel
store modes in here all of these texture
transfer modes are relevant to us so all
of these things like pack row length and
pack image height and skip rows and skip
pixels and all that stuff this is all
going to actually affect our ability to
transfer our texture and I guess I don't
know if that can be causing us some
problems I don't the thing why the
reason I don't think that's the case is
I don't think we would be seeing it be
intermittent like it should always be
wrong if this was wrong and so I'm
assuming this isn't the problem but I
just wanted to point out that it's there
right and I I guess I'll double check to
make sure so what I don't know like what
the defaults are for some of these but
like for example it you know pack
alignment could technically hurt us
right because if it realigned rows every
time then depending on the initial
pointer alignment that could shift us
off and it would change the size as well
I don't see any others here really but
that pack alignment I'm guess I'm
curious what this value what this value
is the Geo pack alignment geo pack
alignment default oops
I'm not sure what the default is the
default is four so again can't really
see how that could really be a problem
though if it was eight
maybe but since our pixels are always
four wide I mean it doesn't seem like we
could really get that to be wrong but I
don't know um so I don't know that
that's the only basic thing I can think
of there were I'm just thinking maybe we
could have something happen weird but
yeah not not a lot else that doesn't
that's the only thing that seems
particularly like suspicious in there
but it doesn't seem likely to me
honestly we'll check it but I don't
think that's going to be it
so just based on that I would say we
probably are gonna have to start doing
some instrumentation here so the first
thing that I want to do is I want to try
and get some idea of what's actually
coming down the pipe on this and so when
I hit this GL text image 3d call what
I'd like to be able to do is figure out
whether I'm sending down bad data or not
as far as I know right so when and in
this case you know this is the one that
we normally call during the game but
we've got a good repro case here where
this one seems to fail fairly soon I
don't know how how many times I can get
that to fail or rather I don't know how
reliable the failure is but it seemed
like at least as you let it play on it
got more and more reliable as time went
on so that's something but basically
when we're watching this I'm assuming
that I'll be able to get that failure to
happen relatively soon so what I'm
wondering is can I when I come through
here can i maybe dump out the data
really quickly or do something else
along those lines where I can see
whether or not the thing I'm sending
down is corrupt or not like you see how
that's correct this time through for
example right so I have no idea what's
going on there right so another thing
that I think maybe could have some
relevance I'm not sure is I don't know
what would happen if we tried to render
with the corrupt texture with a texture
handle it hadn't been filled yet my
assumption is it would just render I
assumed it would only write a garbage
for that frame but once the texture
handle actually got filled in I would
assume that it would start working again
I don't necessarily know that that's
true
so I could believe that actually there
was something going on there weird as
well and so we should probably check
that too one of the things you can see
here is we didn't actually have we
didn't actually have that same
corruption on the second sprite so I'm
going to see what happens on Krampus now
now wait for it yeah so you can see that
all of that seems to be working
correctly and again with that sort of
suggests to me is that maybe there was a
problem with when we out you can see
some of it up there
right some bugginess up there maybe
there's just a problem with load speeds
so if you load if you're loading cold if
you're likely to be late that could
affect it I don't know
still having trouble coming up with a
reason for I'm still having trouble come
up with a good explanation it's a tough
call
hmm all right so a bunch of things to
check nothing seems particularly likely
I'm gonna go ahead and run this under
insight as well just to see whether I
get any warnings that maybe it would
give me that it wasn't gonna give me in
the other case you know and I mean so
I'm just gonna set this up to run here I
believe our working directory is not
handmade slash data anymore right our
working directory we decided was
different it's it's just handmade right
so let me go ahead and get that clipped
off and can I save this or is that not I
don't know if I can save this but you
know we'll just see what happens so
we're launching in the debugger here and
we'll just see what's up I there's
output messages here right and we can
see whether there's anything
ooh not sure why that is saying that's
log is unavailable it's not what I would
have preferred
there again
so I'm not seeing the need to texture
weirdness here
so again yeah not not really seeing
anything and don't have a really strong
idea if we're to look first so we're
gonna have to just wait a little bit
here verify that it doesn't have
anything interesting to say to us and
then we're gonna have to start going in
and instrumenting to find out what's
going wrong there and yeah like again
shouldn't be too bad it just gonna take
a little bit of code cuz we need some
way to inspect what's happening in that
actual instance where we go to do the
transfer and so we can see whether or
not something bizarre is happening it'd
be cool if you had something like an AI
debug assistant that sat there and was
like oh I see that this texture looks
weird it doesn't look like the kind of
thing you would load all right again
don't see any buggy texture Oh
maybe well not necessarily that might
actually just be where that is
I still don't see any obvious bugs there
we go
so you can see here I don't know if I
can pause this to like capture for live
analysis if we just grab this particular
frame we can also go ahead and see what
you know what's up I'm assuming though
that there's nothing particular to learn
here because I'm assuming that what
we'll see is just the textures
themselves or garbagey right at least
that's my assumption so if I go find you
know what textures are being used I'll
find that some are just kind of filled
with garbage so let's take a look at
side our texture pool here so here's all
our textures and
I guess just looking through which ones
are loaded that seems fine that these
are from the previous frame I'm not sure
which kind these are supposed to be
available revisions this looks like a
target buffer but this is presumably the
actual buffer let's step through the
drawing and see what we're actually
looking at so here's us drawing we're
gonna draw a like the depth passes on
this thing right you can see those
getting drawn in there
so I'm not sure which of these actually
produces the garbage what's interesting
about it is that at the beginning here
you can actually see that the depth
buffer is filled with garbage which
doesn't make a whole lot of sense
although I guess that's just because the
thing that wrote into it before was that
that garbage
so it looks like this is our culprit
here this is an actual texture texture
20 that's just garbage and this is what
we're using to write with so this should
have been something and it isn't and
looking at you know you can see that it
was something smaller that looks like it
got smeared out here and I'm curious to
know I don't know if this thing is able
to like view this in a different way
it's probably not but I was thinking
like you know if I could get it to use
different strides here you know like so
that I could dial in a stride to see
what this actually looks like but I
think I can make an educated guess
because if you look at what this shape
is you can see the the olive green here
you can see a little bit of like the
whites of the eyes it looks like this is
just this you know
so again if I had to guess it seems like
it seems like somehow maybe the texture
transfer memory for this guy which was
right
got reused for this guy who's a
different dimension June and I'm Santa
and so this was supposed to be some
other image but really what ended up
happening is it used this actual buffer
at when it went to reuse the texture
texture transfer and transferred a
totally erroneous thing so here's some
stuff that I you know could guess about
if we were not properly reserving our
texture transfer buffers so that more
than one person writes into a texture
transfer buffer like I say okay we need
here's the ten textures we needed to
transfer start transferring them and
like person a transfers into buffer a
person B transfers into buffer B person
C transfers into buffer a overwriting
what was supposed to be there
stuff like that right um so I want to
look at that first because it smells bad
to me like I just feel like there might
be something there and since I don't
have anything else to go on I'm just
gonna start looking at the place that I
think is the most likely culprit first
just to maximize my chances of finding
it and save the most time you know you
can only go on what you have to go on if
that makes sense all right so if I look
in here if you remember what happens in
load asset work we try to do this read
and the read targets a particular
destination buffer and then it tries to
transfer the texture which happens here
and then it does it's like end work
right and so all of that happens inside
this texture queue thing which is
actually something that lives in the
graphics card side which is like a and
up you know has some memory that it uses
for the
so you can see that here and you can see
here we've got a data pointer and this
texture app just moves it rolls through
those data pointers this transfer memory
that's here is what gets used for these
texture ops and so the thing that I'm
thinking is you know I probably just
screwed that up I mean it worked the
first time and if I remember correctly
when we did it that well first time
maybe but like right away we've probably
got some subtle bugs there that just we
haven't actually like we're not doing it
right you know what I'm saying
and so what ends up happening is we use
some memory that we didn't really have
that that was still supposed to be
committed to somebody else and that's
where the error is coming into play
right so I'm gonna go ahead and suggest
that we look there first when we
actually do those texture transfer ops
you can see here the way that we do it
when we call begin track texture
transfer I'm sorry what we call begin
texture up we look through and we say
look let's make for whatever the size is
requested let's see if we can use that
much memory continuous or wraparound
right and you know this is another good
example what if maybe like our
wraparound case is the problem you know
what I mean like what if what if one of
these cases only happens every so often
and like it set up some pointer
incorrectly or something like this right
that would be another good example right
of the kind of thing that might get
screwed up
[Music]
yeah all right so anyway let's walk
through that so when we come through
here we get an OP we say how much do we
actually need so here's the size we
actually need width times height times
four right and then we say look how much
do we have and we assume that we start
with nothing and let's try to find it
we say first we're gonna look at
whatever the you know the sort of memory
arena area we're using is we're gonna
say here's the first used byte in this
block of memory transfers and here's the
number of bytes that we're currently
using okay and so there we say if at
that point we're over the edge of the
memory then that means that we actually
start back somewhere at the beginning so
this wraps the Pointer effectively and
starts us back sort of before that first
use byte and so the size that's
available is just however much memory
there is between where we are and where
the excuse me yeah where we are and
where that first use bite was right in
the other case where the used space is
contiguous inside the region doesn't
wrap around we have to check both the
overhanging part and the beginning part
so we say all right first let's say that
we just subtract memory app from
transform account to say how much is
there between the where I am in the
buffer and the end if that's enough then
we don't need to do this case if it's
not enough then try the one that starts
at the beginning so set memory add equal
to zero it's that size available equal
to sort of that that difference between
0 and the first wife that was used once
we have that done we say is the amount
we requested gonna fit in the biggest
chunk we found right we're not saying
the biggest but we we would look for a
bigger chunk if we knew that we needed
one right so we looked for the one that
would be most likely to fit and we got
we said can we fit it if so we get an OP
out we take wherever that location was
we put that in there
we set up everything so that the last
few stuff works okay so you know one
thing I would say I would caution one
thing and that is if memory at was right
on the border is it okay here we would
subtract back so that's that's okay so
then we would say yet this is where
we're gonna write to this is how much
we're gonna write and then the place you
need to restore to is gonna be this size
requested right so that's that's how we
would move the first used forward and
that all looks pretty good and at that
point we would say oh by the way we used
that much from our memory now you know
there is something wrong with this
though and and I think I can see this
may actually just be the cause of our
bug in fact just walking through it
there I think I can sort of see the
problem actually and the problem is that
the the memory used count if we're only
increasing it by the size that we
requested then this wrap operation the
next time through will fail to produce
the actual end if the path we hit was
this one because we have failed to take
into account this additional piece of
memory right I don't know if everyone
out there gets what I'm saying
and we could go if you want let me draw
it for you just in case I don't want
anyone especially any beginners out
there who've been trying to follow along
with the series I don't want them to get
confused about what I'm talking about
here and I when I moved I failed to plug
in my welcome tablet so we're gonna just
plug it in right now and hope that it
works what could possibly go wrong you
know sure it'll be fine
go alright so if I go ahead and open up
mischief here yeah we're fine uh
good job mischief by the way I'm not
mischief this is not mischief this is
actually Milton we switched from
mischief I forgot long ago so what I'm
talking about here is we've got this
buffer and there's a couple different
cases that we're working with I'll draw
all three of them out so that you can
just think about them and then we'll
I'll show you why think there's a bug so
we record two pieces of information we
record essentially a start and a size
the start tells us we're in the buffer
to begin in terms of and and this is for
for what's used so to figure out what's
used in the buffer we record a start in
a size so the start says well this is
used and the size tells from there how
much is used so one case is this falls
inside here another case involves that
same thing and then there's a case where
it actually looks like this and of
course you can't use space off the end
of the buffer so really what it's saying
is it comes back around this way right
so it wraps okay now in the wrapping
case we don't have a problem because
there's only one way to use this chunk
of memory and it's to start here and use
as much as you can right and in the case
where the thing we're trying to fit
happens to fit in the end of the buffer
in this case we also don't have a
problem so case
totally fine case a totally fine because
the thing we got to put just fits right
in here and this is our new space that
we used and everything's fine right what
I'm suggesting is the problem becomes
when we have something where the thing
will fit at the beginning but not at the
end okay
so let's pretend that this buffer was
shorter right like it's that long or
something right so you know if something
fits at the end of that then we're good
to go right so if it fits in here that's
totally fine what we would say is we the
memory app would be here the size would
go to there and we would then record
that as the place that we would restore
ourselves to right and we would set the
used size now to be that by adding this
much to it but now in this case let's
say we had some it wasn't going to fit
we would look here and say oh it does
fit it fits over here right so then we
would set oh the last used is going to
be here the start still remains here but
then oh how much space is used well it's
gonna be this much was already used
we're adding this much there so it's
that much right but we didn't use that
much we used that much plus this much
because we skipped this part of the
buffer so in order to get back to here
we would actually need to include this
much because otherwise what will happen
is when we then go to compute how much
is used we'll miss and we'll say that we
could actually start here right so by
forgetting you know and just to draw it
one more time
we start here and we say this much is
used and I guess I need to draw that
differently we start here and we say
this much is used right now we want to
place this much in there well what we
were doing is we were saying okay the
new the amount that's used is that much
if you actually wrapped that
much you would use only that much but
we're actually starting here to place it
contiguously so we're actually using
this much because this much here was
skipped and that skip amount has to be
counted in order to get to the correct
place otherwise when we actually write
this thing in the next person will
overwrite the beginning of our buffer
you see I'm Sam I hope that makes some
sense it probably doesn't but if you
were inside my head you would know what
I meant hopefully that that just shows
you a little bit of it okay so looking
at how this is working what that means
is in here where we do a transfer memory
and we get that size you know we get
that size going I just I wonder if maybe
the correct thing to do is to not use
transfer memory last that transfer
transfer memory used count thing like
what if we just use a transfer memory
like first used and transfer memory last
used you know what I mean what if we
just did that and then every time when
we do the result we would pick we would
use that that used thing up that's one
thing we could do a different thing we
could do and you know what I think that
would simplify this code too because
remember when you actually do an end
texture op so or complete when we do
this complete drinks transfer up right
that's then gonna kick it back to the
open gel side of things and when it does
this you can see what's going on here it
modifies these two variables and when it
modifies those two variables it's
actually doing like a decrement there
and also setting this first use but
really we should be able to get away
with just doing that right we should be
able to get away with just using that
and so III think I'm encouraged to me
me do that and we can simplify this down
the size would no longer have to be
included and so inside that texture op 2
if I I went back here I think this this
could actually be removed so it would
simplify as well that part of the
process too and so then what we would
say is well in here we would do a first
used in a last used and those would just
kind of move along right so I think
that's right we could do that now
there's a reason I didn't do that
originally the reason I didn't do that
it reads originally was because I didn't
want to have to figure out how to deal
with the case where they were equal
right and the problem with that is in
the case where they were they're equal I
wouldn't know whether I that whether all
the memory was used or none of the
memory was used does that make sense but
I actually can disambiguate that and the
reason is because it just depends
whether or not there are any ops I
suppose would tell me right
if there are no ops outstanding that I
know that nothing is used and if there
are ups our ops outstanding I know that
everything has been used it might be
another way to write would be another
way to say that and so I think that
would be fine and would always work I
don't know we'll find out in a second
as I go destroy this piece of code so if
I do this and then I just clean up my
errors that will force me to you know to
write the stuff that needs to get
written to make this happen so in here
if I set that last used and first used
and then I come through here you can see
this transfer use memory count this part
this part of the logic will have to get
rewritten and that's fine this goes away
and this part will be an update of the
of the the last used code and that's
tough
but I think mostly just looking at where
this is happening
yeah we're just totally fine okay so
coming through here
we look at memory at and what I want to
do is say well memory at now I always
know where it is memory at is always
transfer memory last used right because
that is moving all the way that's always
moving forward to give me like my last
thing byte that I was using was just
before that so this memory app that's
just the value right there
I don't have to do anything to condition
it right so now what I need to know is
well okay does this thing is the using
space that's being used wrapping around
or isn't it
well it's actually pretty easy to tell
because if this pointer is before the
first used than it is right so what I
want to do here is say okay the used
space wraps around is this case all I
have to do is say if memory app which or
and you know I don't even need memory
app to be honest I could really just do
it like this if transfer memory last
used is less than transfer memory first
used so if the last pointer comes before
the first pointer then I knew I wrapped
around and so that's really all I need
to do right now memory at in this case
is again going to start here and when I
know that the space wraps around I don't
have to do this anymore because I'm not
computing on a wrapped buffer so this is
always correct now in this case and then
the size available is still gonna be
computed exactly the same way it's just
gonna be the difference between these
two
wherever I'm that last one use them it's
going to go all the way to that first
use so that's really very
straightforward right now I have to
again be careful about handling the case
where they both are equal so if they are
both equal right now what I would do is
I would fall into this case because last
year
be less than first used and so we'll
have to handle that here what we could
do also is say something like this so in
this case the size is available it's
it's really just gonna be entirely
conditioned upon whether or not there
are any ops outstanding so if there's an
OP count right now then the size
available is zero so it's only if the OP
count is equal to zero then I know that
this is the case where actually all of
the memory is now free I can use all of
it um so it makes it trivial for me to
write in the amount because it's this
entire size right I get everything so
that's an easy way district just in
bigger list of cases we know that this
case is the same and so we're really
just down to this case where the use
space doesn't wrap around that means
there's going to be two different usable
spaces this size available is still
correct right and this one is still
correct as well so I think this still
just works I don't think we need to
really change that case I think it's
still fine and so then all of this stuff
is is good it's just this now is not
what we want to update anymore what we
want to do is get that last used pointer
here and say that last used pointer is
going to equal the place where we would
have ended right so we're actually just
using that computation that we did we're
just gonna say look we just remember
what that was and so I think that's all
good and I don't think there's anything
else we really have to do there
I don't know that this
I I don't understand why this would have
to be less I it feels like that's a less
than or equal to to me and I'm just
trying to think through like what would
happen if we ended up at the very end of
the buffer and so I think if we end up
at the very end of the buffer we would
say that the used size was just zero
here right and then we would wrap to the
beginning here which is what we want so
I think that's still all okay now don't
quote me on that because well it might
be wrong and I don't want to be quoted
as having said something wrong nobody
likes that it's just very unfortunate so
let's take a look at what we have now
with our transfers and we know that this
was a pretty good case for forcing those
transfers to go erroneously let's just
hope that our luck continues and this is
going to be another case where it's
forcing those transfers to be erroneous
now I don't know if it is or not because
again we had no way of really forcing it
to happen so we just have to give it a
chance to go wrong and see
this one looks correct to me and so does
this one seems pretty good see how the
next one goes cramp is kicking through
the door seems to be a little bit of
turning point for us sometimes where we
can get some more of those errors coming
in here see how we're doing your ears
Santa such a dick
God Santa Claus is just the worst
so Krampus come in and save the day here
in a second let's see what's going on I
will see if we fixed that that sort of
corruption bug there that all looks
clean now so I don't see any more of
those artifacts we're gonna keep running
again I'm gonna go through the whole
thing and what I want to see what what
happens when we wrap around and play
again from the beginning too so that's
looking pretty good
again everything looks super clean there
yeah
yeah this all is looking good now I'm
not seeing any of those weird artifacts
so you know we can't really guarantee
that we fixed it because we're not we
don't have a reliable repro but it sure
seems like that was the bug and all of
these are replaying well so I don't also
see any problems with the Z which was
the original reason we started looking
at it as well I'm not really seeing any
issues there so this all seems pretty
good
yeah so I think we may have fixed the
bug I'm not seeing any other ones that
was definitely a bug so I mean when I
looked at that code I was like this is
not correct so we definitely fixed a bug
the question is did we fix the bug I
don't know if we did or not but the
entire the entire thing plays back
properly now so it sure seems like that
was also the bug we were seeing here
let's let it wrap once just make sure
that there wasn't some other funny
business going on there let's make sure
it can reload the first scene after you
know going around once but then I think
we're probably okay and we can move on
we can also say that there were no there
were no Z fighting problems there so I
don't think we have Z issues okay so
this is busted so when we loop around
once this is busted and this doesn't so
far there's no corrupt textures on here
so that I don't know where that's coming
from so we may want to yeah like I don't
know what's going on here right this is
all totally garbage so we're not seeing
any corruption but it's like it's using
the wrong textures so I don't know if we
have a texture recycling problem or
what's happening here but we've got to
go figure out what's going on because
this is all messed up and we don't
really have any idea why so that's
another run all right so we've got two
separate bugs one was the corruption but
looks like it's fixed I'm not seeing any
of that still even in this kind of
bizarro world that we've we're hitting
here on the second loop through so
that's these work but we all seem to
have some kind of a like picking the
incorrect texture issue and so I I
here's what I'm guessing is happening
there I'm guessing when we do evict a
special texture we don't remember that
we did because remember the asset system
doesn't have the texture handle eviction
on there so I bet that's real
all that's happening so I'm gonna go
into here and just say that I think this
is okay
let's double check just before we move
on to fixing that asset but I want to
look at this one more time
also I looks like my signature got
messed up there shot six three and four
are both 3.0 so cuz that still could be
a bug we're just not singing so let's
look at shot six and just make sure so
you don't know what he meant by shot six
I assumed it was this one but I don't
really know what I'm gonna do is since
he says both are at 3.0 F I'm just gonna
look at 3.0 F and C so yeah it looks
like these two are both of these two
here are that is the one where Krampus
is handing the kid the thing right I
don't know what these two layers are I'm
gonna run this and go to that point
probably because I don't have any better
idea about what I should be doing and
then I'll just is there any way I could
skip right to that too because I
probably can just skip right to that so
when we're doing update and render
cutscene you can see us doing the
cutscene warmup seconds that's the four
pre-caching and then we do the cutscene
T advance bit there so I think we could
just advance that time manually up by a
bit although also when does it actually
wrap that value or does it how does it
map it in there been a long time since
we've done this code so I'm not sure
yes it looks like it just kind of folds
that in to it so I think I think if I
wanted to I could just start this at you
know
a higher one one so that'd be 0 1 2 3 4
5 so 6 that be 5 right so if I wanted to
I could do that
I think am I wrong about that where I
just start directly in that one I think
see if that's true well I was one off so
yeah where's that code so this is this
st. I believe and now we're in this
scene I guess so I think that's this one
so I guess I want to set that let's try
that again
oh look at us
I see so these are actually correctly
membered so I wasn't that's why five
didn't work because it actually is a
number this way because there's a
phantom shot included there all right so
this will start directly on that one and
so what I want to do here is try
switching these layers here to give them
a difference V so I'll just do that
oops that's find out what I want and
with the C I don't know if anything will
happen okay so there is we weren't that
he was right there was some tears that
weren't in this shot before right so I
guess we did need to do that
so I think that's all good and now again
I'd like to go through and take a look
at that that recycling situation there
so I think we can call that done in the
asset system so when we talk about
special textures what you can see
happening here right is the special
texture handles they just roll around
right uh and so like I said since we
don't have any notion of when these
things actually get freed the problem
here is just gonna be when you go to use
one of these if you've already loaded it
once and this is exactly what we see
happening so I'm pretty much positive
this is the bug
if you've already loaded it once then we
don't know that we've unloaded it to
make room for something else right so
you just go on using that texture handle
thinking that the things still in it but
there isn't anything in it so what we
need is we need a way to properly
account for the fact that we have
unloaded one of these textures and so
when we unload that texture we need to
mark the fact that we have unloaded the
person who was using that texture now in
the case of the special textures we can
do that pretty easily because we can
just keep a list of which assets we're
using them I don't know how we want to
do this long term but it's not that well
you know maybe we should just talk about
how we want to do it long term because
we also have to deal with that for this
case as well so when we look for text
handles we need to free up texture
handles we could just make this whole
thing work in a so that we we do handle
them both the same way and that might be
a nicer way to do this so the problem
that we have is we have a limited number
of textures we can use because we only
have a certain amount of texture a space
on the GPU right so our goal here is to
figure out how to make sure that when we
go to allocate button to space for a new
text we're going to use how do we make
sure we put it in a place that's likely
to be the least impactful to what's
currently being drawn so we don't want
to use a texture handle that we're
likely to need again real soon so
anything that we used unlike the last
frame we don't want to do and anything
that we use maybe very recently well I
do but anything we haven't used for a
few frames seems like a good candidate
right but the question is how do we keep
track of that so the way that that you
know one way we could do this is every
time we go to use an asset we could put
it to the front of some like recently
used list right but that adds a ton of
churn and it ends up doing a bunch of
writing that it's not clear we really
ever needed to do and so you know a
better way to do it might be to say look
when we actually need to allocate
textures maybe we just go through at
that point and look at who hasn't been
used in a while and that way we just do
that sort once and we don't constantly
do rewrites right that's one way we
could do it since only one piece of code
is actually going through this route at
any given time it does mean that for the
most part we could just say well the
linked list approach does work pretty
well and it would just work here so I
don't
the other way to do it would be let's
just let's just always do that churning
so if you look at the way we did it when
we call get bitmap you can see us
marking the last used generation here
but we could just I think if we wanted
to churn do that that churn
I mean I don't really see why we
couldn't cuz nobody calls get bitmap on
multiple threads it's a single thread
function and so while you'd be
constantly hitting like these values in
memory it seems like it's probably fine
because those values are just always
there gonna be always in the cache
pretty much so I don't know that does
seem like it could be fine so the way
that that would work is inside the you
know inside the asset system here in
this instead of last used generation we
wouldn't have that in there all we would
have is an asset pointer that's like you
know next LRU and then we would just
keep a singly linked list or I guess it
would have to be a doubly linked list
right because we need to remove and
reinsert on each on each go-round right
now I'm trying to think if there's any
way we should do that differently I
think it would probably be fine so if we
did it this way then what we would need
to have is there would need to be a
sentinel at the front of the list right
but other than that I think we'd be fine
but we also could just
we also could just write it like this
like so and that way when we have the
LRU link adhere and we say look we want
to have the LRU the least recently used
list keep kept here inside the asset
system itself I could just make a thing
which says okay you know here's that LRU
sentinel it's not an entire asset it's a
fake asset right and it's the sentinel
so we don't ever have to care about that
part of it
and you can always get the asset back
from the LRU this way right now since I
want to do that casting I suppose I want
that top I'm not sure about that one way
or the other but it's probably fine so
if I want to do that I think we also had
I can't quite remember but in the shared
code we have our neighbors in hand made
that H yeah so we had some like
boilerplate for this actually right well
you could just do a d-list insert here
and be done with it right so I think
that might also be we could just reuse
that card as well if we want to now
inside here I think I may have typed
that wrong do that now I write that
typed it right
so all I would want to do here is remove
it and then reinsert it and I guess I'm
not sure why there's no remove but there
isn't
there should be this where I say Oh get
rid of this guy's so my my next previous
pointer becomes mine my previous next
pointer becomes mine and then
technically we would want to make
ourselves be circular I don't really
know that we care about that though I
don't think we do it doesn't look like
we do because in here you can see us
just does get cold set so that should be
fine so if we were to do that I could
just say look I want to do a delist
remove and then a d-list insert and we
can just insert it doesn't matter which
side we insert really we can insert as
last or we can insert as first and since
we want to call this the least recently
used list I guess I'm gonna say let's
insert it as last right and so in here
we would get rid of the last used
generation stuff and that use generation
thing would just go away in its entirety
and so this just resumes using it the
way that we were using it before so that
used generation that goes away use
generation use generation yeah
good so we find did it this way and then
all I would have to do is actually
provide the Sentinel and in this case it
you know it's the pointer to Sentinel
and I can just remove this assets
well actually remove doesn't even
require that I suppose so you know what
I guess one thing that I do want to do
there is a good reason why I would want
to keep this initialized that way
because that way you could always remove
something even if it's not in a list
removal just won't do anything right so
setting the next in previous pointers to
point to myself might be worth it
just so that I can always know that I
call that again so it's basically just
calling this init code right so this is
probably better I would say so in this
case I want to remove this asset from
you know the LRU list if it's in it and
if it's not that's fine too so I'm going
to remove the LRU link from there and
again that's this that's this struct
right here and then I want to insert it
into the lists here
and then I'll just keep those change and
that way I always know which one is the
least recently used again I worry that
it's too much work because it's
rewriting for pointers every time on
both so it's like eight pointer writes
instead of one D word right and so it's
you know it's definitely alike but you
know what though I do suppose you could
eliminate some it would only be six
right because if you know that you're
removing it to reinsert then you only
really actually need six
so I don't really know what we want to
do there long term we'll have to see but
it's entirely possible that this is
still just fine because of the that's
not an appreciable overhead so it may
just be better to do it this way because
then we don't have to have a weird
hunting process where we go through
looking to see who has the lower
generation numbers or that sort of thing
all right so if we do that then that
means it's pretty easy for us to always
get whoever the least recently used
person is and just to pop them off that
list now unfortunately we do have a bit
of a conundrum here though because we
don't necessarily know for any given
asset whether it's on the special
texture list or not right and so when we
go to do like our loading of textures
here assuming normally we call this
dimensions require special texture we
don't have any way to do that here we
would have to actually do some work now
maybe we want to actually do that work I
don't know but you can see why that adds
extra complexity there now one way we
could do it is to just say well at the
beginning we'll spin through and ask
everyone which one they're in and then
we'll put them in the proper place we
could do that but feels kind of wrong it
seems more like what we would want to do
is just check each time right
yeah and really I guess it's probably
okay because this can be alighted here's
what I will say this check can
eventually be alighted with the check
done to determine if we need to switch
to special texture mode so I think this
is okay so if I was to do this that
would let me have both of these so in
here I could have the special LRU
central or a special texture and regular
texture you know I'm saying and so that
seems good because I don't want to have
to have both and I don't want to have to
have them both together
so if we do it that way
then what we would want to do is just
say look we insert it into whichever one
we need to insert it into we know that
bitmap width and height because actually
when we return one of these here this
HHA asset bitmap bit right that's gonna
have that info in it so you know this
this right here is the same so we can
just do info gym
info gym and be done all right so I
think that would be mostly what we would
need to use there and again the big
issue there for me is that d-list remove
it just really violates the clear to
zero notice of it because that's got to
be initialized now whereas before we
wouldn't have had to have done that and
I don't know how I feel about that you
know maybe it's fine because when we
load all these assets in that has to
happen anyway but you know now you're
kind of getting into that ugly territory
of of constructor land that I hate where
everything has to have this defined
initialization point and that's just
you're asking for trouble at that point
in my opinion so again I don't love that
and I think I might say instead you know
maybe and if is just better there you
know
like maybe the better thing to do in
that case is just you know just doing if
just that you know I'm saying too and
that way you know when you remove it you
get something more like this and then we
would just clear those two that feels
better to me because now in it 2-0 works
so it's a little more confusing because
it doesn't obey the standard for for
w-league lists where you all unlinked
people point to themselves but I think I
like this better
because I really don't want to be in the
business of having to make sure all of
those links are initialized that doesn't
do it for me
so if I go from there let's see here I'm
also wondering can this stuff get moved
what do we what are what's going on with
asset locking does anyone care about
that anymore do you even have an
operation lock who calls this this is
just dead code right we like we like
pulled all this stuff out
right yeah um so my other question was
can i is there a way to just move this
code out of here can I put this
you know maybe into you know justjust
into the asset system proper here it is
does it have to it doesn't really have
to be in there like that
I'm just curious
because I would like those to not be in
the H file for any particular reason
because it don't really know yeah so
there's our prefetches oops
and I think prefetching fonts is not
really a thing but okay and this is the
same that would go into years as well so
yeah I think that was just again like we
haven't touched that code in a long time
I think we're good now I can live in
here so get bitmap is that just not was
that not exposed in here
let's take a look yeah
so these just need to be put in here
give a connect sessom and I don't think
there's an immediate for load font
anymore either so I'm pretty sure that's
just dead letter at this point I think
that's a not a real not a real thing
yeah so that should really be bad okay
yeah
sooo that keeps the list but it doesn't
actually do anything with it so we're
not quite done with that part of the
process so let's go ahead and and put
that in there as well so what we want to
do first when we actually create our
asset system here we're gonna want to
initialize those links right so I forget
what those are called here it's like
d-list in it yeah and so for the Stila
snip thing I wanna do our special
texture LRU Sentinel and our regular
text really simple I'm okay with
initializing those to point in a
circular fashion because that's free we
just do it when we initialize the asset
system it's I don't want every asset to
have to be that's just there's tons of
assets I don't want them all to have to
get touched in that way for no good
reason
so we should just hopefully run the same
as we used to run now right we shouldn't
have any any issues and then the only
question is you know how do we now use
that change to fix the loading problem
we were seeing in the cutscenes stuff
and the answer there is like okay now we
just need to use those lists to be
correct in how we apportion our textures
that's not actually that hard because
you can see here when we go to load a
bitmap you can actually see when I do
the the texture handle assignment this
was just making nonsense code right it
was just saying like alright I don't
know like do you know you give it the
next one in the sequence or whatever
right so all we really need to do is
just replace this nonsense code with
code that actually checks that LRU list
and we should be fine right so what we
want to do here is say have a
have a call for acquiring one of these
textures and I probably want like a
acquire like a choir regular texture
handle and acquire I guess I maybe I
don't care though look at it this I
suppose the code doesn't care so I
suppose in here I can really just do a
choir texture handle and it looks like
this maybe would just want to do the
check internal so like you know this
seems right and so when I call a choir
texture handle I can pass the assets and
the dimension let's say and it will just
give me back the right thing so then up
here if I have one of these guess it's a
V to you
like so I would need the assets and then
in here when it comes through to figure
out what to do about the texture handles
they could just say alright if I need a
special texture handle then I'll use one
of those if I need a regular channel
I'll use one of those but what I'm gonna
do here is instead of allowing these to
be assertions I'm gonna actually make it
be a case where it just pulls something
off the LRU so it's still gonna do this
because we do need to use new texture
handles when we haven't used them yet
right but in the case where we've run
out so we've used all the texture
handles that we have then I can do a
reuse right and so what that involves is
me taking an asset that was in use and
basically nullifying it right I want to
go in here and say this asset that was
in some state is now gonna unload it's
going to be unloaded right so I'm gonna
you know replace asset I'm gonna do
something where I do like the this asset
goes to asset State unloaded and the
texture handle for that replaced asset
becomes the result here I'm gonna call
that result so it again just getting out
of touch trails exact same way but now
what we're gonna do is when we run out
we reuse one so we just slam that guy to
unloaded so he's not loaded anymore it
can't be used and we we recycle the
texture handle right that's it pretty
basic
so same things gonna happen here what we
want to do is in here
these are should you know this should
look like the exact same piece of code
it just should should it should do this
check first right so it should it
should say if we've got any left to hand
out you know hand one out otherwise
steal it from somebody else
right and that's gonna be the exact same
thing now that we were doing before now
this code to find the replacement asset
it's going to be different because gonna
look in the LRU differently for each one
but once it does find one then that code
would actually be the same so we could
almost say something like this and then
down in here we could go okay if there's
a replace asset then we're gonna do this
this little dance right so we're
basically saying look will you know
we'll do whatever we need to do
differently for these two sets when we
figure out what's up we may set a
replacement asset with when we get down
here if we did that then you need to
like unload that guy and do whatever it
is that you're going to do and blah blah
blah right like that all has to happen
couple things
all right so first things first if this
asset doesn't have a texture handle
that's valid then we really don't want
to put it on the free list and if it
does have a texture handle that's valid
then it should be on the free list for
Zuma bleah so you probably want to do
this and you probably want to do this
know how to make a know one of these is
their clear call right like I want to
say that once you reuse it we need to
know that it's not usable anymore and so
it should look something like this
that's my story and I'm sticking to it
yeah so that seems better
and this is actually gonna get the index
out of this texture handle by the way
oops and the width and Heights are going
to be recycled right so that all seems
good bouncing I don't see any issues
with that really all right so finally to
replace an asset what we would want to
do is assert that there you know the the
list we would need to pull from has
something on it
for starters so the special texture LRU
Sentinel or the you know and actually
now I think about it
we really only need the Sentinel here so
this could actually be replaced link or
rather replace Sentinel so we can even
reuse all of this code because all we
need to do here is just say look the
Sentinel in question is this one
so we either get the regular texture you
sent or the special texture LRU Sentinel
and then we're done that's all we needed
and then all the rest of the code comes
into this block here so we say if we
need to replace the Sentinel let's make
sure that there's something in it
because otherwise well we can't get
anything and there always should be
because ha if we if we don't have any
new texture nails to give out there'd
better be somebody on the LRU right
because someone's using those texture
handles so there has to be someone there
so assuming that there is we will then
use the the d-link remove call right to
remove the first so they're replaced
sentinel next that's the first one in
the list so d-list remove would pull
that guy off you know I'm saying and
once that's pulled off then we can turn
that into an asset right because that
just is an asset pointer should do this
something like that
so that would pool and off the list we
use this texture handle and then we can
go from there
unfortunately I still use the word
texture handle there which I didn't mean
to
I meant results but other than that
we're okay I think all right so we don't
have a news empty for that so we should
probably make one of those and let's see
I could even do addy list is empty just
because hey why not and that's literally
just this
okay um I'm not sure I got the sense
right on that one by the way it's empty
if it's equal that was backwards let's
see missing before if do you just remove
that all seems fine what was it
complaining about
oh and so I think that's all I really
need to do I think that will now
properly recycle two extra handles based
on whichever one was the least recently
used and
[Music]
that's actually just to you 16 so I
guess we want to do that I guess we
don't have one of these how are you
supposed to make one of those strictly
out of curiosity yeah it looks like we
don't have one of those why not well I
Madeline
it's my codebase I can do whatever I
want right I mean how you guys stopped
me
I mean I guess you could download the
code and change it back but that still
doesn't stop me from doing it sooo yeah
in theory now we would reuse texture
handles we know in the game because we
never hit that assert we know that in
the limited amount of stuff that we're
trying out in the game here we haven't
hit that limit but it did look like we
we had that problem here in the actual
in the cutscene because when we wrap
around we had cycled through all those
textures so we know this will blow out
the special texture limit and it's
reusing texture handles in there and so
this should give us a test of that
system and it's and we should see it
either succeed or fail to reuse a
texture handle from the special texture
list we won't really know if we did the
right thing on the regular texture list
but we'll get to that point in the game
at some point to where we can get some
testing on that just you know by virtue
of using enough art assets in the game
so far it looks reasonable anyway
so I'm pretty sure by now we would have
actually blown out the number of special
textures anyway because there's not that
many of them so I think we actually are
already reusing textures I can verify
that fact by just looking in here when
we go to allocate that texture handle so
in here I mean this is gonna be in in
release mode build so you know it's a
little Squinkie to be sure but I'm
guessing we come through this path okay
apparently we come through none of this
this must have gotten welded in so it
probably got welded in here basically so
you know until someone actually tries to
acquire a texture handle here we would
and we'd have to look to see which path
that goes down by looking at the
assembly but we could try that so let's
go in here look at the disassembly and
let's see so yeah we don't have a lot to
go on here all right
so I'm guessing these are the two
texture encounter increments so I'm
guessing if we skip both of those we
have reused the texture and we did so I
believe this is the path right here
where we would be pulling it off of the
Sentinel and reusing it so I think
that's what's going on right here you
can see it doing the linked list in fact
so we are already reusing and we seem to
be reusing properly so I think that's
just all there is to it
so not only did we fixed that bug but we
also now check that item off our list
which is text your handle reuse and so
that should be fine and we're just doing
it the same way we were doing it before
when we had a more complex memory scheme
we're just keeping an LRU list can't
promise it's the best way but it works
and so yeah we can check to things off
of our list today which is pretty great
actually let me just make sure we can
wrap because we still don't really know
if we did it when I percent correctly
like this isn't very rigorous testing
here to say the least
so I would like to just verify that it
can at least wrap around because then we
know that we've hit the case where
people on the outside are trying to
reuse the texture and that's another
it's a separate issue in the code so it
could be that we didn't properly do
everything we need to do to solve that
case as well so it's worth going through
wait for it wait for it much better so
it looks like we're recycling properly
we're actually getting right like all of
those textures those all got reloaded
from disk we should also be able to see
you know if we look at our performance
we should actually see it hit the disk
to get those assets every time so each
time before the switch you can see the
preload and you know it should actually
you should actually see those spike
unfortunately it probably gets cached at
some point and so I don't know yeah like
like we're probably not if we if it's
already in the in the disk cache we're
not gonna really see it on there cuz
it's sort of a right that would just
everywhere it's a read that would just
get answered directly by the OS out of
the disk cache so there is that but yeah
if you did like a cold boot we could see
it so I think that's all good I think
that's that's just all done so we closed
out that issue
[Music]
and we just ended up doing this one too
so what else we got
we don't have much time left but we
could look and see a couple of these
other things here I guess we could look
at some of these so let's see if there's
some minor ones here let's just clean up
those so s32 from Z the industry may
pass ignored instead of at okay let me
take a look at that call
yeah so so you can see here like we're
not we're supposed to not be doing that
so we were supposed to pass this here
and I even set us up to do it but I just
as a typo and we didn't do it and so if
someone had counted on this not
advancing the app pointer it would have
broke so that's just yeah correct I mean
I think that's just strictly what it
should have been right
that way it'll it'll move ignored and
then not do it so that was definitely a
bug it just we must just not have been
using it in any way that actually ever
caused the bug to manifest but you know
it might have bitten us later so it's
good to just kind of get it out of there
where we can even though it wasn't an
issue it you know it could have become
one I look at this sign extension bug
here so this isn't the yeah oh okay I
see what you're saying here yeah
this this is this is actually fairly
subtle but it's a good point so what's
happening here is it's doing
sign-extended promotion of the 32-bit
64-bit the so this is very subtle if you
set the high bit right of a you know of
a 32-bit value then whenever that high
bit is set it's assumed that that thing
if you were doing signed arithmetic on
it or whatever it's assumed that that is
negative right that's what that means
and so any time that you have routines
that work differently based on whether
something's signed or unsigned
something's don't write some things just
work addition for example it doesn't
care whether you're adding signed or
unsigned numbers it produces the same
result because that's why we use two's
complement as a representation for
negative integers is because you don't
have to implement two different pieces
of code right all right two piece of
hardware I should say but if you set the
high bit and then you do something that
is sensitive to two signed values so
it's good to do a different thing on a
signed value you can get into trouble in
this case C is creating this value and
the C default rules create it as a
signed value so it's gonna create it as
basically negative the four billion two
billion or whatever right it's gonna
create it as like the highest negative
number or whatever that it can write
because remember all ones would be just
negative one and a sign bit with all
zeros is like the highest negative
number and so if we if we give C that
value and say compare it to a 64-bit
value it's going to up convert this from
32 bits to 64 bits and what it does that
it will do it one of two ways if it
thinks the value is on
signed it'll do an unsigned convert from
32 to 64 which will pad with zeros
that's what we've wanted so the top will
be zeros if instead it's a signed value
it will do sign extension which
replicates the high bit so if the high
but zero it'll get zeros if it's one
it'll get once that's where this is
coming from right it thinks it's sign is
replicating that high bit we didn't
really want that now it doesn't matter
because there's no actual other params
here but like Peter Forrest says here
that's who reported this if Microsoft
did add more flags in the future that
sit up in that high 64 our code would
stop working properly right and you can
see why that would be bad so we don't
want that that was just a sign extension
bug we didn't that wasn't what we
thought we were typing right we wanted
to type this as an unsigned integer so
we wanted something more like this okay
so let's see if we can verify that this
will be correct right I'm gonna go into
that code or try to anyway and you can
see there's really only one place that
we do this here but I'm going to set the
breakpoint there and I'm gonna look for
evidence of that sign extension now I
don't remember what this code is in it's
in key down so when I call key down I
get in here and if I look at the
disassembly what you can see is here's
that and it's anding with an immediate
and the immediate is this nasty bit
right here right and you can see that
sign extension going on right there
exactly as Peter suggested and so what
we'd rather do is say look this is an
unsigned value my man
don't sign extend it and so that's what
I'm going to try here and then we'll see
if I hit a key now and get back to this
code we'll see if that did the right
thing and let's see if it did uh hmm
okay well that's very interesting
so it chose to do that by making a shift
right of the value so okay
I mean it's doing what we want but that
was surprising so that's not necessarily
I guess that's just what it thought was
fascinated all right well let's watch it
work right okay so the first thing we're
gonna do is move up this is presumably
pointer in here right yeah we're gonna
do some some moving all right so we're
gonna shift RSI which is this value here
and I'm assuming that's the L / M so I'm
assuming that these are both the L
params I'm guessing I want to say
yeah of course it was mmm
I want to I want to know if that's deal
for him I'm assuming that's erm such
just assume it was we're gonna shift
them down and we're shifting them down
right like I see the heck's there we're
shifting them down
and we're gonna check them against one
so instead of ending with a mask that
would have the bit we wanted it's
actually gonna do the opposite it's
going to shift it down and then check it
there and you can see the way it chose
to do that it actually makes a lot of
sense what it's doing is it's doing a
64-bit shift to shift it down on the
main register then it's just doing the
and on the limited size register so yes
well you know although our si is a is a
and an e ax sorry RSI and our ax our 64
a bit ESI is just the bottom 32 bits of
it so it knows that it doesn't have to
worry about the rest of the stuff that
may have happened there it can just use
the bottom 32 which I guess it could
have used the larger must just not want
to do that because it's faster to encode
I guess this way so in both cases it
chose to shift it down rather than shift
one up and I assume that just produced
the shorter sequence right in an easier
comp
I guess
[Music]
and that's it so I think we fixed that
all right so that seems good and of
course the keyboard code alt works as
well so that's just something we want to
make sure of there and so we're
basically out of times there anything
else really quick I wanted to look at
what is this so I don't know where that
is
let's find out let's find out where that
so that's debug light bar vertex index
debug light vertex index yeah I don't
know what the debug light buffer Tex
index is being used for these days
yeah I don't think this is stuff we want
so I think that is correct that this
should just not be in here because
nobody ever sets that so it's not like
it's ever gonna get called so I think
that can just come out of there so
that's not really something that was
really an issue that's just I mean we
might as well remove it because why not
but yeah what's the windows open the
game
interesting we probably won't be able to
plug that one now though right so this
was a way that we could avoid open jail
for point two and I think it's fine it
was really just that we didn't realize
when we had originally written it that
we had two different ways that the the
depth or the MIT count or something the
level was specified differently
and so when we called GL tech storage
that was why and so we didn't really
want to have to call GL text orage but I
believe it's this is the problem right
usage argument values we're changing
right the levels argument which is 1
must be 0 right and so this has to
change so I think if we did this it
fails right that's why we didn't do it
and so you know if you do this you just
get nothing right it errors out and so
in theory it's just because these are
different parameters they just for some
reason open jail decided yeah might as
well make it maximally confusing and
that does seem to work so I think we can
get that out of there and that way tech
storage is an updated call so I could
remove that from the system
okay so that gets rid of GL tech storage
3d entirely which avoids
any dependencies on later versions of
OpenGL which we don't really want to do
alright I think that's it we'll go to QA
now so we got quite a few issues checked
off today at least four these are
handmade ray so we should you know we
should do another one of these maybe we
do one tomorrow but wait I thought I
marked out as closed oops
I just forgot to close it so you know I
don't that's one for a time but we're
gonna start doing sound and this might
be more of an involvement but we could
start we could look at some of these
other ones here because these
enhancements are different we don't need
to work on those those are for later and
handmade ray is for handmade ray and so
I think we would really just be doing
Linux updates check out the fullscreen
bug look at these two and go from there
alright let's go to Q&amp;A
or try to go to Q&amp;A anyway cue a
does for cooter support indenting of
shader code yet I guess I don't know uh
Alan isn't around by a chance of me so I
see what you're talking about is like
you know inside here we just had some we
just dumped some shaders like in there
and you know it for coder doesn't know
that that's a shader so it just thinks
it's a string so it doesn't indent it
right I'm not sure how I would I think I
was said to Alan maybe what you could do
is define your own in your handmade
custom to find things here where if you
use them as openings for Strings it
would continue doing indentation inside
or something like that but I I don't
know if anything like that has happened
yet
i I don't know
obviously if you copied it out to a
separate file it would just work
personally I've only used least recently
used Cash's have you ever used a LF you
and has it worked well
LF you just sounds like something you
say in chat LF you man I don't think I
know what that is or I don't know what
the acronym stands for what do you what
is LF you stand for
at least frequently used I see so you're
talking about keeping track of how many
times
something's been used so I guess what I
would say is I can't think of the reason
why I would want that for something like
textures because the problem is that
just because you use something a lot
doesn't mean you're going to use it
again and the reason for that is because
you know maybe I'm in this area and it's
the graveyard area and the player is
hopping around there for a long time so
all of these graveyard tiles are like
really frequently used but then as soon
as I leave the graveyard I'm never gonna
use those again til eat until he comes
back there right and so the fact that
they got used a lot is really not that
relevant because games tend to change
[Music]
what's in that hot set
dramatically quickly right so I feel
like a frequency based one would have to
be for a different use case maybe unless
I'm misunderstanding the idea
I just I don't feel like that really
works for gaming things as well but I
don't know but so I'm just thinking of
that just just off the top of my head it
may be that that that's not what LF use
end up doing I'm not sure I have never
used one I didn't even know that acronym
but I have certainly only ever used L
are used for replacement schemes if that
makes sense so who knows is there a good
let's see cache is divided into two
partitions called privileged and
unprivileged partitions the privileged
partition can be defined as a protected
partition if content is highly popular
is pushed in the privileged partition
replacement of the privileged partition
is done as follows lease frequently or
LF are you least frequently recently
used evict content from the unprivileged
partition pushes content from privileged
partition to unprivileged partition and
finally inserts new content into the
privileged partition in the above
procedure the LRU is used for the
privileged partition and an approximated
lfyou scheme is used for the others for
addition hence the abbreviation Allah
for you the basic idea is to filter out
the locally popular contents with a
Leffew scheme and push the popular
contents to one of the pivots version
yeah so I guess what I would say is that
might be good I would want to read up on
that more I want to see some analysis of
how that worked right in practice
because it's definitely it definitely
adds a layer of complexity so if you're
not getting something good for that
which I'm really not sure you are in the
case of the game
because I mean you have to remember
there's two different kinds of things
you might be doing here in a game it's a
little bit different than what they're
doing for like a content delivery
network so in a content delivery network
there's no such thing as like the stuff
that's that's being presented for this
frame right because a kind of delivery
network is not trying to optimize
experience for one user it's trying to
optimize experience across many many
users who are all looking at different
things in a game we know that the things
that need to be shown in this frame are
the things there's a exact set of things
so we know that the stuff at the top of
the LRU that was most recently used so
the last things on the list I guess if
they're getting added at the end we know
that those things are what was for this
frame and everything that was before
that was stuff that wasn't used on this
frame so we know it's not actually
necessary to keep that in the cache for
right now right and so I don't know that
you want this additional thing which is
like over time I also kind of want to
know that there's this set of things
that tend to come up frequently and just
because I don't need to serve them to
this user
I shouldn't have victim because the next
user probably is gonna ask for them
maybe the game wants that because
there's UI things or sounds that happen
very regularly but again I don't the
fact that it got used a lot before
doesn't mean that it's gonna get used a
lot now which is probably the case in a
CDN
I would guess so I don't know that's a
tough one it's a good question I had not
really thought about those other schemes
much
and yeah I guess what I would say is so
you're saying on there that that lfyou
has more overhead than LRU more
accounting but statistically it
supposedly converged to the same
expected values yeah that's sort of what
I was saying is like when confronted
with a new thing like that like a new
eviction scheme you kind of got a dig
into it like I can't just read it and go
is that better or worse right so that's
why I said I'd want to see more
literature on it if people have done
analyses if they hadn't I'd want to do
my own you know and just see what was up
but yeah
any more on topic questions
all right well since we have no more on
topic questions I will mention one
off-topic thing we need custom emotes
and I'm not sure what those custom
emotes should be so we're gonna make
some but we kind of need like you know
we need to do that right like we need to
we need to figure out what those assets
are gonna be and I don't remember how
many there are
let me see if I can see on here where
that is it's under like channel or
something or partner or whatever it is
yeah yeah yeah so like loyalty badges
and stuff are coming and those are just
gonna be like what you know they make
sense you're like okay these are loyal
the badge would make sense the emotes
are whatever you want right so you can
like you can define your own codes and
we can make like three of them and or
three or four of them actually four of
them I can't tell how many supposed to
be five six we can make probably more
than we can think of and so we need some
ideas about what the imodium oates
should be right like owls shame is
probably gonna be one of them
I would guess and piggy should be one of
them yeah mint spider I agree with you I
love shame and pig hat for sure
I'll make a little oops I was about to
send a mail to myself I typed on the
wrong keyboard so I just entered it into
my code instead send it to Casey there
we go
emotes so Pig hat our shame what else
good look at the handmade Network
discordant modes and john-john blows
face we would have to pay like John blow
licensing fees alright that's seen the
scene will anyway be thinking about that
if you have ideas about what you want a
Lemongrab can we do that though I don't
know if Lemongrab is is allowed I mean
that's that's Lemongrab I don't know how
like what's I don't even know what the
copyright laws on stuff like that are I
don't even know how they work there
because I think that's kind of difficult
territory I don't know if anyone sued
for using their likeness as an emote or
a cartoon character that they created as
an emote I don't know like what goes on
there at all
that's hard to say anyway I'm gonna wrap
it up oops
let's there there we go
okay thank you for joining me for this
on a handmade here it's sort of pleasure
coating with you as always if you would
like to follow along the series at home
you could always pewter the game on
handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code so you can follow along with
the series I will probably be back from
the stream I'll probably sneak another
one in there before winter break really
begins you know so so I can't promise
it's the last you'll see of me before
Christmas there might be another one
tomorrow so we'll see stay tuned until
then or till whenever we get back here
have fun coding and I'll see everyone on
the Internet take it easy everybody