hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show we coat a complete game
live on stream we I believe did all the
stuff we were gonna do yesterday one of
the bonus of these Krampus loft blitz
dreams is you get a lot of programming
timing yeah stuff done so we pretty much
finished everything up but I think all
the other thing actually works now so
the thing that we wanted to move on to
was making our UI system not look so
ugly you know we don't got to win any
awards because it's not actually really
user facing it's something only for
developers to use so you know you can
accept a lower standard of visual polish
certainly but we don't want it to be so
horrid like right now all we did was
sort of the the backbone wiry sort of
stuff and we haven't really spent any
time making it at all usable like it
needs to be cleaner looking and it also
needs to be perhaps laid out better and
and so on so so we've got some stuff we
want to do there that's just you know a
basic sort of coat of paint over the
thing so that's what we'd like to do on
this stream I'm gonna go ahead and get
started I'll show you in case you've
missed you know we've done a lot of
streams case you missed where we are on
that I'll show you where we are on that
and then just briefly explain sort of
what I wanted to do to to make it a
little bit nicer in that regard so going
to the current state of the code you can
see that if I if I use this here the UI
kind of pops up here you can see it's
totally bare-bones right it's pretty
ugly and it's just at 0-0 it's just at
the center of the screen and it just
draws it right and so that's not what we
want right we want something that's
gonna be maybe over here on the side or
something like you know what I mean like
we'd like it to be if I made it
fullscreen and we actually imagined us
adjusting some things you know we'd want
it to occupy probably over here we'd
want this line to be more legible and a
little bit easier to use
there we'd want these buttons to be laid
out a little more sensibly I would like
it to be harder for example to hit the
Save button I mentioned that before a
little harder to hit the revert button
so these are these are more serious
operations there are things that you
don't want to hit by accident undo redo
is it's probably fine but again I don't
want the size of the buttons to change
like that right so we just we've never
done any UI like work here that really
tries to make this stuff feel right and
so that's really what I want to do is
sort of try to improve the quality of
this and so that's what I'm gonna focus
on today if I have time I'd also like to
fix the positioning of these things to
be based on sort of screen agnostic
coordinates percentage based coordinates
or something similar to that because I I
don't like having to move these around
every time like that I want them to and
and that's not our that has nothing to
do with the EUI we were working on it's
just a thing that would be nice to have
in there so let's get started on that so
we're just doing sort of the visual
cleanup here and adding code to be a
little bit more sensible about how those
sorts of things should work themselves
out what I want to do is start by inside
the editor here I want to kind of make
some way of positioning this thing more
sensibly like I said so what I think
wants to happen here and I could be
wrong about that but just you know
reading the sort of limited writing
that's on the wall in this case we sort
of have this notion of sections here and
you can sort of see this begin section
idea and I think what I want to do there
is I want to have that begin section
call probably I would like that to be a
sort of a tabbed kind of a thing almost
like I think I want to do something
probably like this where we don't
we don't really go through sections and
trying to get how we wanted that maybe
you want to do it like that I'm not sure
yeah I'm not sure whether I want that
inside or out but something like this
where we can kind of have you know this
window it would list what section it was
on the top and maybe if we added more
sections
you could pick which one you were
looking at at any given time right
because again I don't want this user
interface to take up much space on the
screen so I would like to be able to if
we added if we ever added another type
of edit in here that wasn't alignment
points that was something else you know
I would want to maybe have some way of I
would want to have some way to pick
between those without having to have
like fussy debug keys like I don't want
have to remember like oh it's f7 to edit
alignment points and f9 to do this and
you know that kind of thing so you know
we'll we'll cross those bridges when we
come to them more but I do kind of want
to make it so that it looks a little bit
more like that and then I want that to
kind of be wrapped up more in a window
and understand where it's gonna be
better than zero zero obviously right so
that's kind of what we're looking for
here okay so looking at this the the
code that actually does begin section at
the moment I'm just gonna say it's
always returns true just because that's
you know and maybe I'll write it this
way instead because it doesn't really
have anything else to do but we'll you
know go ahead and make that happen
inside the code that actually calls the
renderer so when I'm actually you know
using the editor when I go to actually
draw this begin layout call this is most
of the the problem here in terms of how
things are aligning themselves what I'd
like to do with that at least for a
start is just say well you know I know
the this thing is is inside a certain
rectangles worth of stuff right I mean I
have some idea you know roughly about
about how big maybe that is so if we
look at the WI here you know we've got
this default cliprect for example and
that default cliprect is gonna tell me
the board you know the the entirety of
the screen I believe I could be wrong
about that because I don't really
remember how we chose to specify
cliprect coordinates so I don't remember
exactly what those amount to so what I'm
gonna do at first is I'm just gonna go
ahead and well you know what let's just
live dangerously I'm gonna go ahead and
try just saying like default cliprect
min X right now and just to see what
that does
right I don't know what it will do and
also don't remember yeah um so I just
want that to see if that would peg me to
the left side of screen we should look
at how that's created there to see if
that's actually gonna be the case but
anyway alright so it looks like that
cliprect
is maybe in pixels potentially I'm not
sure so because that's still giving us a
value of 0 which would not be what I
would expect right so what we need to do
here is we need to have some kind of way
of figuring out what we could pass down
here that would actually give us the
that would actually give us the leftmost
border of the screen and in order to do
that I think we may we may need to save
right because it doesn't look like we're
saving that information anywhere in
maybe it's in the render group I'll take
a look but we need some way of saying
like what that pixel position would
actually be let me take a look here so
inside the render group we've got I mean
we could always reverse-engineer it from
the game transform certainly
but again not really what I would want
to do so I think you know again it just
might make more sense to say let's save
that data inside the WI for people who
want to use it right so looking through
here what I would want to do inside the
WI is I'd want to be able to put some
information in here about where those
screen corners are and probably the
easiest thing to do would just be like
to put a rectangle in here that are the
screen dimensions right like screen
space right and inside here we'll just
specify what those are going to be so
when we create that projection this will
be something that lets us position the
way what we want so then you know we
can't use the clip right because that's
an actual pixel space or whatever we can
use this as our you know our roll I mean
it's it's really like UI space I guess
might be the way to say it so when I
actually go and make one of these Deb
you eyes what I want to do is I want to
save that information at that time
because we know what it is because we're
setting up the transform you can see
that right here and so we need to go
ahead and create something that's going
to have those balanced coordinates there
and we need to you know do some reverse
engineering to figure out what those
screen coordinates actually mapped to
you know what I mean so what I want to
do here is I want to set my UI space up
so that I can set them in and set the
max I can do that in a couple different
ways I could probably you know maybe the
best way to do it is something like this
where we do a center dim because we know
that the center is zero zero right and
we
the width is with so what we want to do
at that point is just say well we don't
know what the height is but we do know
what the screen height we do know like
how big the screen was when we said what
the window height was and so if you're
actually doing a transform that's even
the whole way through
then you should end up with exactly the
right coordinates for this to be you
know height not sure what the is it just
is it to be twos or is it for reals yeah
so my assumption would be that this if
this is at the center and that's the
total dimensions this should just give
us back the right at UI space you know
famous last words but you know so that
way it'll always be pegged to the center
line and then you know this this sort of
region of the screen you know I mean uh
so yeah like that seems fine to me that
would be easy enough to edit so you know
I can pick things over here and then in
here I can you know do whatever I want
to do seems fine so that's all well and
good I now want to do some maybe a
little bit of like background in here
I'd like to sort of make a backdrop for
this thing and maybe put the title on
there so you know like that begins
section thing maybe that sort of allows
me to draw what this this stuff has here
and maybe that section I'm just you know
sort of imagining my head maybe that
section piece is also like where I could
hide the save and revert so I'm just
thinking out loud here you know
if I have multiple sections maybe the
undo/redo and the save revert stuff you
know maybe those things can be can be
done that way and that would help put
those in a different location you know I
don't know now one of the interesting
things about undo redo right is that you
kind of want those available everywhere
so you know if I was looking at this
maybe what I would say is you know maybe
it looks a little bit more like that
and maybe we've got something more like
this going on you know I'm saying
so something where you have to actually
manually switch to like another section
of the user interface to hit one of
those other options might be better I
don't know that's just my thinking on it
I don't have a strong opinion but you
know something like this and so that way
you know the maybe the undo and redo are
always there they're in a row by
themselves and then you know the set
there's like a section that encloses
these things and there's a section that
encloses the the attach points and your
alignment points rather and you're only
ever seeing one of those at a time so
you can't really hit lever it by
accident from something from trying to
do undo redo or something save and
revert being close to each other I don't
know much about how to fix that
I mean the poor man's solution would be
like this I suppose I don't know so let
me go ahead and put some tab stuff in
there basically so that we can separate
those two things out and you know that
way you know save and revert would be
pretty pretty distant from each other I
don't know if that's a good idea or a
bad idea but that's just something about
so I'm gonna go ahead and try try making
two tabs there the begins section and
section stuff so the IDs I'm gonna want
that same process that we were doing
before where we have these like IDs that
tell you what's happening here so we're
gonna want you know the dev ID from
pointer stuff we're gonna want that and
I think you know in that case this
should be fine so making this section
that way I think would be reasonable
because now it would have a thing that
lets you you know you can use that to
uniquely identify what section you're
talking about and the same thing would
be true here so we'd have like you know
section name equals a line points and
here we just do dev ID from pointer
section name section name right and so
now we've got this notion that the
sections can actually be selected and so
what I want to do is go over to the UI
and say all right let's inside the dev
UI let's have some understanding of
which sections are active and which
sections aren't now there's an
additional I guess there's sort of an
additional issue here that when you do
begin section you're going to have to
provide and that is what is the mutual
exclusion set for the sections and I
think that part is not that hard
do the part that's a little harder is
the is just figuring out how how you
want that picking to go so
I don't really have a particularly solid
idea of how I would do that like what I
want probably is this I would probably
say here's a section picker right and
the section picker would the section
picker would like itself be a thing so
in the editor you would say I've got
this section picker that stores which
section is active so I can set it at any
time to like just to whatever I want it
to be so there'd be like WI section
picker something like that and this
would just be yeah something like that
and so when you came through here you'd
say well you know here's I want you to
let the user pick from some set of
sections and I want them to do it right
here and that's probably right like its
own row but you know we you know we
might not even want to be its own row
you know maybe it wants to be something
else right look maybe it wants to be at
the end of this row so you got undo and
redo and then you've got a picker for
what section you're in you know I don't
know and so who knows what happens there
but you'd do something like this
and then when you come down to like
saying that we're gonna have sections
those sections would just be based on
you know they would just occur whether
based on whether or not they were
selected from from from this so you
would probably say like you know every
time you did that you would just say
here's here's the section picker that
controls whether I'm
active or not you know what I mean and
you know go from there that that's about
all I can think of
seem reasonable now it's a little bit
Squinkie because you need some way of
remembering what all the options
actually were so that's a little bit
harder and
I mean the most straightforward way
would just be every time we encounter a
section we link those sections up with
the main section that's stored there and
then it knows what all the ones are to
pick from but that's a little more
stateful than possibly I would like
because you know I don't really want to
have to do a lot of heavyweight work
there for no reason so I'm trying to
think if there's a simpler way to do it
there if if you actually had each of
these sections wrapped in it's in like a
deterministic way you could do some more
clever stuff but I don't I don't see
that being really that good
so here's what I'm gonna do I'm gonna be
perhaps a little bit too clever here and
I'm gonna try something I have not tried
before when doing UI stuff it's really
kind of ridiculous but I'm gonna see if
it works cuz it's just interesting and I
like this exploring new ideas so let's
suppose I introduce a notion here called
the WI picker just like we said before
right and the only thing it stores is
the current section IAD so what it says
is if I am you know if the users
interact with this section then what you
get is remember remembers what section
is currently looked at so it makes the
begin section called trivial to
implement because we just look at what
was the dev ID you're given and what was
the current one and if they're equal you
process the section if they're not equal
you don't process the section right so
that's a pretty straightforward way to
implement that operation
then what we need is a forwards and
backwards right we need some way of you
being able to select through the
different sections for example or to
pick from a list you know this that the
other thing and so if we want something
that does that what we would need to do
is be able to say well you know the user
starts interacting saying they want to
go to like the next section or something
we don't know what that is
but we would know what that was if we
just introduced one more variable here
probably going to the next one is
actually pretty easygoing the previous
one
[Music]
it's slightly harder but again only
requires one other variable so I think
it's just this
I know it looks weird that you can
implement the whole thing with just
those two but I think you might be able
to let's take a look at that so at the
outset when we do begin section we need
to take whatever the picker was right
oops and we need to take whatever our ID
is so obviously the result now is
trivial it's just going to take a look
to see whether or not the Pickers
current section ID and the section ID
that you're trying to operate on now are
the same if they are we're done now we
just need to lotta four going forwards
and backwards and sections and I think
all we have to do to do that is say look
if the Pickers current section is
invalid then it's just I will just
assume it's me so in an uninitialized
scenario we just become whatever the
first section is that in the list so if
no one initializes us that's fine we
just picked the first section done right
if the Pickers current section ID
[Music]
equals the Pickers preception IV oh I
forgot so I did forget the variable that
I said we needed which was if we are
trying to move one forwards right so if
we're trying to we we need the control
variable that says what operation we're
trying to do if we want to go forwards
or backwards right so something like
this so then we can actually do
something where we said alright here's
here's what we're going to do we could
do something like this so we have like
the various things that you could do so
by default on startup it's going to be
this so we could just say hey if picker
move equals that well you know what I'm
gonna have one for each of those so
let's just do a switch
so if it's an init then I just said it
if it's a keep I don't need to do
anything if it's a pre I'm trying to go
to the previous one and if it's next I'm
trying to go to the next one right so if
I'm trying to go to the previous one
then all I have to do is say well if I'm
the current one oh and by the way any
time we do one of these we're done so if
I'm trying to go to if I'm trying to
initialize then I just initialize right
and I've done if I come to the previous
one then what I want to do is say well
you know if the current section ID
equals my section ID then I know that
whatever the previous section ID was is
actually the one that should be the
current section ID right so whoever came
in last is the one I want to move to and
similarly if in this case I want to go
to the next one
then if the current section ID I'm sorry
if the preception ID equals the current
section ID should should have written
this way after all then I know that the
previous person was the current section
so I need to make the current section be
me because I'm the one who comes after
them right so I'm pretty sure that's the
entire implementation
pretty simple requires two extra
variables one is the previous one and
one is what you were trying to do I
don't know what I think of that but
that's that's where we're at we could if
we want to make this even more
ridiculous I think we may you know no
just looking at it I'm thinking we may
not even really need that so if you look
at what these are actually doing here we
could have probably made those just be
interactions I don't know that I really
want to do that but you could have done
that and then this wouldn't be necessary
you just look at this oops you just look
at the interaction in question and and
you would use that so yeah pretty simple
actually I think surprisingly enough if
you actually just think it through it's
actually very very basic so I do need
this concept of a section picker though
that's like a separate kind of a thing
that we've got um but really it's it's
sort of in a way not it's it's really
like entirely implementable in almost
exact same way as this code was you know
so we certainly can here just do what
was what was the thing called again it's
a UI section picker we can just
implement it basically the same way and
the difference here would be instead of
doing the Inc or Dec and instead of ever
we don't consider these being edits or
anything so what we would do here in
these cases is we would just say well
when we go forwards and backwards for
this thing we want to set inside the
picker what the move is that the picker
was going to do so in this case it's a
primo and in this case it's a next move
and off you go now
in this setup we need to be able to get
the name that we want to print and I
think we probably just want that to be
in here that's separate from the
implementation of how you pick stuff but
we probably just want like current name
in there right and so that's pretty
simple it just means that anytime you
call begin section we just need you to
pass that name in here and you know it I
guess fine and basically anytime you
assign something in here you would want
to set the name so anytime the picker
current section ID I guess any time
result is true then you want the current
name of the picker to be equal to the
name that's given here right and I you
know what I do I just want to do that I
don't I I don't really like care stars
so now that we have a string there I'm
just going to use it you know I would
rather have it that way
so in here yeah this doesn't actually
need a label to text there and we'll
play around this a little bit more but
there we go
and I don't know that there's really
much else left to do here we just need
to be able to create a wrapped version
of that I don't remember what we called
that function I guess we called it rap Z
so go ahead and looking at what we've
got now well that was anticlimactic so
what I'd like to do is is go and debug
that see why we can't get our left and
the rights going there like when I click
on that I wanted it to execute the move
there and so you know looking at this
here when we do pick our move next I
feel like that should have worked
[Music]
question is why didn't it so hmm the
initialization part worked correctly
because this got set so that's good when
we get a picker move breathe
we're looking to see whether the current
section ID equals our section ID and so
that's basically saying if this result
would be true and if it turns out that
it is true then we move to the previous
one right which is whatever the last
person through this path would have
called and we said to keep that feels
like that should have worked so I'm not
sure why it didn't I don't know
oh because there is no other section I
didn't select anything yeah all right so
it did work just fine
um so that's good and now we can kind of
like keep ourselves from accidentally
hitting anything there that might be
untoward which is kind of a good thing
right and it allows us to you know make
sure that you know we can you can hit
undo and redo anytime we want but we
don't have to we don't have to worry too
much about accidentally hitting save and
then if I want to I can always go back
to the HHA and hit save or revert right
so that all looks good and so now I
think we're just down to the original
thing I was saying about just
straight-up beautification so trying to
clean all this up to look nicer and be
aligned and all that stuff right so just
basic typography and and CLE like you
know not really serious graphic design
of any kind but you know trying to
trying to be less disgusting so well you
know I don't really know exactly what I
want to do there but I mean the first
thing I think I would do is inside the
layout a lot of these things when you
look at how they're being drawn you know
we're passing in a thickness for the
border so there's that there's like a
thickness for the border of those right
and you know same here I think I might
want that to be somewhat parametric so
like inside the layout I think maybe
here we would actually specify in
addition to these things like you know
like the border or thickness so there's
I don't know what I don't really know
what to call that but just like the the
box thickness right and so in here we
would just say well whatever the layouts
thickness
is that's what we're gonna use and so
when we do like things like these they
all get that same thickness in basic
text element and so all of this stuff
including these buttons I want to sort
of follow that thickness rule so you
know this calls action button here and
an action button I really just want to I
want these to follow the thicknesses too
so like action button and boolean button
those both want that that as well I
don't really remember
to what extent those are used by the
debug system but again I don't care
because the debug system can set its
default thickness here to be different
as well so when we call a basic text
element here again I'm gonna say that
that like label should get that
thickness too so that all that stuff is
more systemic right so that you know
that that can all be kind of handled a
little bit so when you create one of
these dev layouts I'm gonna set it to
six by default you know when you when
you start a layout and then I'll just be
something that would do in terms of
giving things a little bit more of a
border there so that should happen on
these too now like those should be a
little thicker than they were
hopefully presumably you know I don't
really know so that's fine and then let
me go ahead and look at if that makes
this stuff look a little bit better so
you can kind of see now that that's
that's a little bit more a little bit
more readable it's not great yet you
know
it's not perfect but it's better than it
was which is sort of what we're looking
for here cuz least now these things are
aligned and so on so the next step there
is I want to be able to do a little bit
more so I think that one of the problems
I'm having is like switching between
button and label is bad because I want I
want buttons you can't push to still
look like buttons so that you know that
they would be buttons in the case where
you like undo and redo I want them to
always look like buttons I just want
them to have like a more grayed out like
you can't click this look but so that it
still looks like a button so I would
like to do that I also want again like a
backdrop in here so I want this to be
like a solid window so that you can't
like I accidentally click off this all
the time right and I don't want that
like if I miss click here I don't want
that to actually for it to think that
I'm actually clicking like like to pick
like that so I want to change that as
well so that seems pretty good
two-parent prep like the way we do
boolean buttons that can probably
improve as well there's a lot of stuff
to do here so I'm not sure where to
start let me start by
so that's an interesting case by the way
so there is one bug I just saw with the
way I was handling this so if you are on
alignment points and then you click off
you can't move to previous or next and
the reason for that is because you never
see this section so I guess you do need
one more thing which is that inside the
picker you need a thing that's like you
need some way of saying if we never like
if we never saw
like if we never see the section that
we're supposed to be looking for like if
we if the current section goes away we
need to reset to a different section
yeah and I mean and that's actually
harder so I guess the way I would do
that is this way it's a little weird but
if you think about it when you call
section picker you have the ability here
to just say well when I am doing one of
these section pick operations I know
that I could set current section exists
to false in which case when I go through
all the rest it should get set to true
by someone else eventually like so and
it's a little bit Squinkie but like yeah
basically any time anyone is able to set
the current thing so if I moved to the
previous one here right like I would
need to set it there as well
as long as someone sees that then when
we do section picker we can say that the
next time around we can just look to see
you know if picker current section
exists what we can do here is just clear
that out oops
and if I zero that out then that means
that when you have that section get
deleted it will automatically clear it
right so that way you know I've got the
agent say I can't switch because that's
the only section at the moment if I
switch here you know I can go through
those all I want and then the other
thing I can do is now if I click off of
it I should still be able to well that
should done it so I guess it didn't do
that why didn't it do that Oh cuz I set
the wrong thing
so I think that solves that problem it's
a very weird way to implement a section
picker I don't don't mind telling you
but sometimes I like to try weird stuff
so there you go so now it reverts back
right
okay so again button I wanted to be able
to have an enabled disabled on button
and so what assuming right now is it
does the enable/disable thing Action
Button I don't know who calls action
button exactly but I kind of don't know
that I really want it to be calling that
anymore so I think that's not going to
get called so I think what I'm gonna do
instead is here I'm gonna call basic
text element with the interaction and
with the the interactions here I think
what I might do is say you know if you
were gonna execute that execute it and
the enabled will set what I want the
background color to be and probably also
what this color would be so it's really
gonna be more like this and then these
colors are going to be set accordingly
so you know if you have a disabled
button it's it's you know why I started
editing the wrong case if you have a
disabled button then it's going to be
like not highlight able and and I guess
I'd keep that the bottom
it's not gonna be highlight of all and
the background color maybe also will dim
down somewhat from where it is so it'll
be like you know kind of more obvious or
you know what know maybe it's just gray
right like it's just a gray
thing to indicate that you can't really
click on it you know and that way the
enabled part just kind of works and it
won't change the button II miss of it
right so you can see now very clearly
too few buttons when they are available
and unavailable there what happened
there that was that which buggy that was
weird so it's like the enables was not
quite set right or something
what's going on we got a we got to take
a look at that but either/or so let's
suppose I just leave this as it is
and make maybe this look like this again
I'm just kind of guessing here about
what would be good yeah that's a little
bit better
so like you can see that the undo button
was supposed to light up but it didn't
and then when I click on that it still
allows me to click for some reason which
I don't want it to do so I don't know if
I think that's because the interaction
has to be set to something else so it
doesn't actually occur so maybe I do
want to do it this way and just say look
if it's not enabled then the interaction
type equals WI interaction something
so that still lets me click on an
invalid on an invalid one and I don't
understand why
right like I don't understand why that's
letting me do that
hmm
that's peculiar because if the
interaction is none here then I
shouldn't be able to interact with any
time I rendered the thing gray you
shouldn't be able to click on it because
I'm saying specifically that I don't
want there to be any way to interact
with it right so it shouldn't allow you
to click because there shouldn't be a
type unless we currently just have it so
that that type of interaction actually
works which would be weird but maybe
that is how we wrote it accidentally
so like yeah in this case I think we
want to say is this interaction
I guess that is true like it it does
actually create an interaction for a nun
but on the other hand it should never it
should never have set next to execute
though right so I'm still a little
confused like I don't really see why
that would be happening because it if
you set it to none it's not immediate
button so it shouldn't actually do
either of those two things like the next
to execute part
[Music]
what did I knock over Oh I knocked over
the poor little owl
very good
so that's strange I don't quite get that
and I may have to debug back to find out
exactly what's going on there
not sure I follow I don't follow the
logic about why something that's set to
dev UI interaction none while that can
become the active interaction it should
not like produce results because the
executing one here you know that that
result value would would never would
never come back true so I really don't
know what that's about I mean obviously
I can fix it here by not actually
filling this part in you know and that
should prevent it because now it can't
identify this one and we'll see if that
does do it or not because now I'm not
sure right because I don't follow the
logic
No
alright so clearly I just don't
understand what's going on here right
and so we should go ahead and compile
debug mode figure out how it is that
we're able to actually click on a button
that itself is not you know should not
ever be available let's go ahead and
take a look at why that's happening
because I'm stumped so I'm gonna set the
debug mode we're gonna run and here we
are in edit land I'm gonna go to the
point alignment points if I click on
this the undo button is not highlighted
so the first thing I want to do is just
find out why so if I go to handmade
in-game editor and I look at undo and
redo right what I'm expecting to see
here is undo available should be
returning true right and it's not so
what's the problem
if I look at the undo Sentinel it is
true that there's nothing on it if I
look at the in progress Sentinel there's
nothing on that either
and so it looks like it looks like that
edit got like swallowed up or something
so first thing we got to do is debug
we're that way you see here so where is
that so basically here inside this edit
a line point call so in here where we go
in here and say match you know we we
request this match we say get a create
edit in progress right and it goes and
it gets it looks for one that matches
the one we asked for and you know if we
can't find it it gets it back puts it on
the in progress lane and then later on
when we're actually doing stuff here if
the interaction is over we do a push
first here so you know maybe the first
thing to ask for is like what's going on
there right like why is that failing and
it looks like you know it's getting
called let's see what happens in the
situation where we are going to do this
that edit we're literally talking about
so I go here and I click on this so that
end interaction never got into here I
have so so the interaction isn't
actually ending when the mouse goes up
it's like this isn't happening or
something
right so we must have this wrong
like we must have got that we must have
got this wrong
so let me verify that's the case here we
are in in edit mode I click I switch we
got there that time so now I'm gonna
click on this and we got there this time
as well oh wow ok no I I get it I get it
so because this is one frame behind
meaning we will set the thing to execute
and then it has to go and execute it it
won't have happened yet by the time you
get here and that's pretty tricky right
so you will call this one edit late
always oof that's crazy so what you want
to do in this case is you want to say on
execute like when I actually executed
the thing then I move it and that's kind
of crazy I don't love that
so if we wanted to handle that the most
straightforward way we still can
it's just not fabulous but when this
happens you do know that it happened
right because you're gonna clear that
like you know inside WI right we've got
the thing here where we're like next to
execute and it clears that right so
after you've done the execute operation
you can then you know you know whether
you needed to do that that update it's
just it's a little crazy so you know in
here you would actually do this you
wouldn't be doing it this way and really
the end interaction part here is really
not doing anything so all you would add
is when you call the when you get to the
end of this right when this is done you
would say you know if you would run and
execute right so you and maybe the
better way to put that would be here
so if you've run an execute and then
you're done with it
then it's a time that you could do this
right so when you come through here
you're gonna do a bunch of things that
you may need to do where you're gonna
like set what you would executors you
know who knows what
and yeah I don't really love that so the
alternative to that is to change the way
we're doing the execution a bit instead
of having an execute we would actually
just put that as something that directly
does the Edit which is just it's it's
harder on the rest of the code because
you've got to actually then have a
switch statement that I was like which
kind of edit was happening here and so
on right and then the other way is kind
of nasty it's basically a thing that
says hey when you are done with a
particular execution pass here then you
need to do this operation and it's not
the end of the world if you want to do
that it looks kinda like in you know it
would look kind of like this inside here
we do update and render editor at the
end of it we would look and say if the
well we would do a couple things first
after we do that pass this would move
out into here so this the place where
this actually happens would be here so
it would be that the editor has the
notion of what's being executed you know
so that we would we would handle in here
and we might actually not have to do the
next end to that that might not have to
happen anymore because we're handling it
in this loop so then here what we would
say is well if there was a to execute
and now there isn't then we would do
this so basically here
if we're going from a state of executing
something to not executing something
then we're done and we should save all
of the edits that we made right I mean
it's not fabulous you know it's not my
favorite thing I've ever done in the
world but it would work
all right so let's just say we did that
as dumb as it sounds so the way that
would work is inside the in-game editor
it would now be the thing that controls
what is the what execution is occurring
right and so in here when we would be
setting the UI stuff we wouldn't
actually be setting the UI stuff we'd be
setting the editor stuff and that's all
fine that execution that occurs here we
then still need the UI system just to
know what is being executed so if we
look through here for the places where
that's happening we would just change it
so that that's part of the layout and so
when you begin one of these layouts you
would just pass it what you wanted to
execute there and so when the editor
goes to actually draw it stuff and you
make one of these layouts we would say
oh you know the like the thing you're
gonna execute is the thing that we tell
you to execute like I said not fabulous
but that's just how that goes oh and
that is deadly interaction okay so this
is probably one of these or do we not
have one of those now we did yeah so
that's ugly but UI code often is so you
know there's that let's take a look here
so I can still click on things that
aren't actually available there it looks
like you know maybe that's not what's
happening maybe that's just because I'm
clicking into empty space so we'll see
but now that that's looking a little
better
so let me go ahead and play with that a
little bit more
so I think that may just be yes so
that's not actually clickable I was
wrong about that it's just that we don't
protect you from clicking off of the
selection so I think we're we're more
reasonable now right I think we're in
good shape here okay so I think that's
all good what I'd like to do now is try
to clean up that hip apron so this is
probably what needs to happen so you
know instead of none in the case of
something that isn't clickable it would
actually be an op I think is what we
need there so that it knows that it's
not nothing it's it is something that
you could have interacted with but in
this particular case it's the
interaction is to not do anything and to
prevent you from doing anything as well
right so that you don't accidentally
click off of it
and so you know that's so there we go so
that that's much better right so I think
that's good and now I just want to make
sure there's an apron that does that
does that exact thing so that there's
basically like one blanket element that
would that would be the primary element
there now
I think all I have to do in that case is
just make like a rectangular element
that if the mouse is inside it it's just
a nun interactor so like if we look at
basic text element you can kind of see
how that's going here and this is the
code we would use for that I think right
so I can say in the in-game editor you
know where's that way out so in here you
know maybe I want to have a thing that
lets me say you know this layout is
actually a box you know
[Music]
and so what I would do there is pass a
rectangle like something that looks like
this
so inside begin layout you know which
normally does that you could have
another version here
that's a utility function that if you
say there's a rectangle now you know
looking at this you want to erect me max
has to have to actually obey rect min
max so technically it would be this
right and so this is the box in question
and when we do this layout we would call
the normal layout function as well and
the upper left corner would just be
whatever the boxes min X was and
whatever the box is max Y was and that
should do exactly the same thing but now
we're passing in the size so now when we
run this we should get the same result
but we can now include a apron there
that would prevent it from anyone from
clicking in that region so yeah so you
know we go in here and like that and I
don't know how big we want that to be
but you know we can sort of look at that
a little bit more later I guess I don't
know let's see
that's kind of weird
well maybe we'll do that later so if I
want to draw that box in there then all
I'm going to do is again take a look at
one of those like you know begin text
element I'm sorry basic text element and
the basic text element call is just
doing one of these element rectangle
operations so if I want to capture one
of those in here I should be able to I
should be able to do something like this
now when this thing does one of these
and I guess I got to move this down to a
place where it can actually call some of
this stuff right we don't want to have
to pass a dimension and have it actually
like update the size of things though
it's the only thing like we don't really
want it to do a lot of this stuff
because this is like trying to place
stuff it's trying to put things into
locations and all these other sorts of
things why there are so many push recs
here I have no idea
it's like drawing a black or what wood
is not for
does anyone know what this is supposed
to do like what is that code
oh that's four that's four if it's
sizable I see so that's if you want to
be able to size it what so it draws the
border around the element okay all right
okay sure I'll give you that
so again just looking at all this stuff
I don't think you know in this case we
would just do this stuff directly so if
we call begin layout box we're gonna
automatically set our you eyes next hot
interaction type to be
if the mouse is inside the rectangle
that we have we're gonna automatically
say that the next interactions type is
going to be no op because we don't want
anything to happen unless you're
actually over a UI element we want to
block any click through so we need to
like if the element bounds now and so
figuring out what the element bounds are
you can see here it does this
calculation which is doing all kinds of
nuts to move it around we already have
that stuff I think so I believe it's
literally just the box right and then we
would like to draw that area so we would
like to do a push rect so in here where
we're doing this sort of thing we want
to be able to drop that back behind the
whole thing so would be this and I guess
this doesn't need to happen here so it's
really just that's the entirety of the
code I think and this probably should be
a parameter that you can set in case you
want different colors there I'm gonna
say it's just a translucent like you
know dark backdrop and that's all there
is
[Music]
let's see what happens here so there we
go it's really interesting what happens
in this mode it's like the scaling is
off I don't know what's going on there
it's a good question so looking at this
I would like the area here to be a
little bit more compressed we'll take a
look at that in a second
but otherwise I think we're good so I
would like to a couple things first of
all this should probably be a little bit
darker 0.5 is not really was not doing
it for me there and I would like the
upper corner here to have maybe the
thickness respected sort of an a
duplicate sense maybe so it's sort of
like something to happen in here I'm not
sure what the value should be maybe it
shouldn't be the thickness maybe it
should but I'm just gonna have a border
inset there probably just to make things
a little bit easier to see
all right
so it's seems good you can notice I
can't click on anything in here which is
the goal so that seems pretty good what
I will say is the it would be nice maybe
if this was a little smaller so we might
want to try and condense how this is
being drawn so it doesn't take up so
much space changing the size and percent
Peas would be probably a good start so
you know
something like that and then this could
be knocked over a bit right so instead
of zero zero it could be like whatever
the MINIX is you know could be more like
that
so I think all that's good I might put
the delete here the parent stuff I may
just make that a toggle this doesn't
really even need to be there so I think
that label can go away so I'm gonna put
that here I'm gonna take that out of
here entirely and this for editable
boolean's I might change the way those
work
what I probably want to do there inside
the WI is I'd like the Edit of a billion
to not do this
I think I just want it to be a button
that has different colors depending on
the circumstance you know so it's it's
maybe something more like this
I mean it would be nice to use the
button code so I wonder if maybe I could
just have those B parameters to it
default parameters to it that you could
specify actually because it would be
nice if you could just do this right
it's a lot simpler if that's the case
so if I was to call through to this one
and you know I just wanted a different
highlight or something I don't know
don't have a good idea for this one I
mean I guess one thing we could do here
is say you know take take what was going
on and it just merge them together into
a single button piece of text so that
the way that this is working it's just
like and I guess we could even have that
be based on the veldt you know the
person could pass that those in has the
values to I don't I don't know I'm I'm
not thinking of anything here sorry
yeah weird the rest of the stuff go
though what what did I do
how come none of these came through
there so was it just because I got rid
of that string like what happened to
editable type
let's try that
yeah so that's reasonable
and I might make the color of that
change too
I don't know so inside here it would be
nice if if the if it stayed the same
size so that's a little bit annoying but
you know I don't like the fact that it
shifts in here when we call button I may
say look you can set the backdrop color
if you want to and that'll let you set
this here and for this one here it'll
just if you're disabled it'll always go
to gray for the moment anyway so then
when we do an editable boolean you could
set the background color based on the
value so like at the end of this we can
say well you know it can be this or this
[Music]
so maybe we'll do like okay you know
it's it's it's green if you if you have
it set and it's red if you haven't or
something so you kind of know like green
means go red means stop or something
in both cases I'd want it to be full'
Alfred don't want to be see-through
I don't know why I keep closing the apt
to ash but I just leave the app running
it does seem like maybe they're a little
too dark there to like the text I just
mean so yeah it seems like maybe this
should be more like a seven-five
I do think for the because our our live
code reloading does have that string
rebasing problem that's kind of annoying
I wonder if we should like just not do
that anymore so when we unload the game
code here because it's just annoying to
have to constantly deal with that so if
we just never unload the library then we
wouldn't have that problem and then we
don't have to worry about it as much
right all right so it's a little bit
hard to read against that backdrop still
I think so I kind of want to make maybe
the backdrop be a little bit dimmer so I
the I'm just kind of looking at the Debu
i code here so like the default maybe on
this you know it should just be a little
darker so maybe it's you know more like
more like that just not so bright you
know what I mean actually do it
that doesn't actually seem to be looking
so that doesn't really seem to be doing
the reload what did I do wrong there
is there a reason why we cannot we
cannot get code reloading anymore cuz
not freeing the library should still be
fine right like it should be able to
still do its reload like it normally
would like it can still go through here
and reload the file yeah
oh no it can't
interesting so if we want to be fancier
there we actually have to move it to
different temples every time that's
interesting
so here where we do this temp game code
DLL flow path we would actually have to
have a way of cycling those
yeah so that's definitely trickier and
and so I think what we'd want to do
there is keep trying to move it to a new
file name until we couldn't anymore but
I think that's worth doing right so if
you look at how this works here we would
need some way of like adding to that
like making that file name be able it's
a sort of increment and go forward so it
can you know go up by one or pick a
random number that it sticks on the end
of that right because we want to be able
to say look if you if the current dll
still in use that's okay we'll just keep
on using it and copy the newly built dll
to a new location and run that right so
if you look at how this is going the cat
string this part of things here right we
need to be able to stick a number at the
end of that or something it's just some
monotonically increasing thing I and
this I don't know if this has the
ability to call shares does it let's
find out
yet does so we could convert this to
using format string now and that would
make this a lot more powerful so we
could just have an incrementing number
there and we wouldn't need to use cat
strings anymore for example right so in
here where we're calling this we would
just say you know where we've got these
source and stuff and we would get the to
do desk bounds checking would be done as
well because format strings does that so
if we were to say look we want a format
string that's like this and that and we
are then saying that the things that
we're passing are these that's actually
pretty easy to do
in fact yeah so like if we just get rid
of this entirely and then we call format
string and we say here's the death count
here's the dest we've got two things we
want you to compat on there a and B and
so here's all we need you to do with
that so the file name part that's just a
rap Z this other part here is not a rap
Z that's actually something where we
want to you know do whatever this
nonsense is right something like this so
then that can concatenate those together
for us and what that means is we should
be able to what's the question here oh
for crying out loud
so that should work just fine I would
think and now we have the ability to
optionally Inc you know tack on a like a
variable there that if we want to have
something that just keeps trying to move
to another location it just will
it'll get slower as it goes potentially
but that's okay but we could actually
keep the you int there so it might not
and so what I think we could do here is
just say alright this situation here
we're not gonna actually do that the way
that we were doing it there so instead
you know we're gonna do something like
[Music]
we're gonna do something like let's save
this and then what we're gonna do is say
if unique equals zero we don't print
anything
and if unique equals anything else
we're gonna call right tack that on I
mean I think that should be fine
well you know what though it's not it's
not that great I guess because file name
can't be there but that's probably okay
we can probably just do it this way you
and I mean so we're probably okay there
let me take a look yeah so what we want
to do here is say this temp temp game
code DLL full path nonsense stuff right
that thing is is uh is not gonna happen
no more right so that's out of the
that's out of the mix
so this when we go to actually do this
load instead of having the temp DLL name
come in there it's gonna come in here
and we're gonna need to pass a state in
here that would allow us to actually
access the stuff we need but otherwise
this bit of nonsense it's gonna let us
pass a variable name and then what we're
gonna do is inside here we're gonna keep
trying to copy until we can't copy
anymore so we're gonna do something like
this
if you load if you're hot reload more
than ten and twenty four times you're
gonna have to stop you have to restart
so yeah you go through the temp dll's
you ask for each one in series if this
succeeds you stop if it fails you Inc
the number so you're just gonna keep
trying like to see if you can actually
copy the darn file and if you can then
you're good to go right
so inside the state wherever that saucy
gentleman is so inside here right we're
gonna have a thing called temp DLL
number and then when you do went through
to build eggsy path filename blah blah
blah right you're gonna be able to pass
the unique there and then we're gonna
have one that's like if you don't want
to do that then then we just pass zero
right which will upend nothing so by
default it just works exactly the way
that it used to and nothing actually
changes but if you are trying to use it
with that why is this all messed up okay
there we go then it just works we need
to pass the win32 state here so because
that wasn't getting that before but now
it will have to and so let me go down
and just look here at how that's working
the global wintered state yet so I
assume the win32 state is actually
cleared by default in fact we're not
going through mr. so yeah it definitely
is um so all we really need to do now is
when we go to call that function it
needs to actually get past the state
information
I assume that's just state and then
maybe that just works or maybe we delete
our entire file address file all of our
files and our hard drive crashes who
knows let's take a look so what we would
expect to see now is in the build
directory right here's the pill
directory and all the garbage that's in
there what you can see is there's a
handmade temp DLL and so now what I
would expect to see is if I make a
change now right like I'm doing the
editor or whatever like I said and if I
make a change now to one of these things
I would expect it to like update and the
handmade DLL will not get over Tammy
10th Avila will not get overwritten it
will actually just create another one
which has a different number appended to
the end it should be a beginning so it
means like zero one underscore right so
yeah that's all we're talking about here
so let's see if that actually works so
inside here like if I want to still tone
that down
little bit which I may want to write
like maybe I changed this to something
like that I should see that color change
eventually here hopefully it looks like
it did and and then in here I should see
yep there it is okay
I all right so I think we've mostly
accomplished everything we wanted and I
think we're good to go
look I think we can now just actually go
focus on implementation stuff I think
that's as good as I might want to move
the the variably sized one here over to
the over to the end and I also might
want those edit editable type things I
might want those to sort of be together
right probably maybe so it's more like
that so I think that's really all I want
to do for other stuff they're like yeah
so that and then that's probably good
enough like you know we don't need
anything too fancy so probably we're
good to go here
and maybe that unused will just be add
yeah like that the other thing is maybe
in the editor you know this thing
shouldn't be proportional the window
size maybe it's just a fixed size
because it kind of is just a fixed size
sort of thing so you know maybe this is
like UI space men X plus however many
pixels this thing is right like because
it's not scalable it's just a fixed size
and it doesn't matter how big the window
is it has to be that size to fit the
junk in there that's in there you know
what I mean
and so not sure how many pixels that
should actually be it should probably be
another looks like 200 maybe but that
make more sense because then it's just
taking up however much space it actually
needs to fill itself up and then you
know then you're good to go
so you select one of these and that's
the correct size there and then you know
you do that and it's fine right so that
seems good
right
this should really be a little bit
longer though
I'm gonna go ahead and call that for now
and we will go to QA
recently so the QT is not that good what
you just liked about it pretty much
everything I mean I don't even know
where to start if you compare the sort
of the notion of what you would want to
understand in other words I want to make
a user interface right and you know
you've never used qt before so you're
you're coming to it and you know the
first thing that you obviously want to
think about in terms of any API design
is literally everything the person has
to learn to use the API is wasted time
right because the goal of using QT or
any other UI library for that matter is
not to learn QT QT is worthless as a
thing of itself it's just a UI that it
produces that you wanted so any
information you had to ingest or
anything that you had to learn to use
that thing is cognitive overhead that
you could have been spending somewhere
else so someone comes to a system and
they're like I want to use this UI
library it's just from the outset the
goal is they know what the user
interface they're trying to make looks
like like they're like alright I want
you know list box here and I want to put
some stuff in that list box and the
users going to click on it and whichever
when they click on there I'm going to
make a box over here that shows you know
a different UI based on which one they
clicked on and that they know you know
they don't have to learn that they know
what what they want it to be and so then
what you want to look at is what is the
process through which a a person learns
how to represent those ideas that they
have in their head in QT and that is a
nightmare I mean let me just show give
you a brief example of what that looks
like
it's been a while since I've looked at
QT so you'll have to forgive me it takes
me a while to get you know through the
various pieces there right but it's like
alright so here's some stuff you know
that's like I don't know let's talk
about a calendar widget so I want to
make a calendar widget here's the
documentation for the calendar widget as
you saw I just clicked on it here right
and it's like all right where is all of
this stuff and what does it mean like
how do I place the calendar widget
somewhere like I just want to make one
of these how do I put it somewhere or
put it into a layout or something like
that right um and what you very quickly
kind of end up seeing is that well
in order to understand how a calendar
widget goes about being placed somewhere
you have to look at like all of the
things that a calendar widget like
inherits from right and so you got to
start like you end up climbing right so
you're like okay okay okay okay so a
calendar widget doesn't have anything to
do with like where the thing goes it's
like a queue widget that says where the
thing goes maybe right okay so what are
the things that says how do I know how
do I place a qwidget somewhere right
like okay I guess I have to do you know
move maybe well there's something so
that that's got a in X&amp;Y in there right
that seems like a way I could do it so I
guess I call move maybe on my calendar
widget
maybe I mean I don't know let's see
[Music]
move okay it doesn't have any
documentation for what it does so I
don't know it's a setter function for
the property pause okay does pause say
where the widget is okay it's the
position of the widget within its parent
widget so now I have to go well okay so
what's the parent widget like the parent
widget I didn't set so I guess if I
create one of these cue widgets I
probably have to put it inside a parent
widget so maybe I just call set parent
widget or maybe not like I don't know
right I'm not sure those sorts of things
are not that hard to figure out right so
like you know I can stumble through
those and be like okay I get it right
like you know I know there's a hierarchy
here somewhere and it all works out
right once you start getting into things
that are more complicated than that
that's not just like things you might
guess what they are like position this
structure becomes impenetrable because
then you're like alright I need to know
what happens when like the person clicks
on that date of you I need to make that
like do a thing over here so I need this
guy to like respond to that thing that
the other person is doing and you are
just crawling through these docks just
inundated with stuff that has nothing to
do with anything
right and you're just crossing your
fingers that you can find out what the
magic set of crazy like parented things
inside things that are routed to other
things can possibly do right
that's just learning how to use it so
that doesn't have anything to do with
whether it's good or bad even like as a
library that's just that's your life
from now on is understanding a bunch of
crap that has nothing to do with your
user interface
it's just implementation details because
these people decided that a calendar
widget was a widget and a dock widget is
a widget and also other things are
widgets and you have to know which ones
those were and alright and oh and by the
way widgets are objects as well so
sometimes you got to end up in here
looking at things all that stuff right
she's still learning a complete mental
ontology that has nothing to do with
what you were trying to do you just
wanted to create a calendar widget and
you didn't care about any of that right
that's not even starting to talk about
the quality of qt that's just talking
about the cognitive overhead that QT
forces you to learn rather than you just
being able to state what you were trying
to do um if we go to like something
that's like a tutorial that's a meta
language let me let me try to open up I
just want to load some sample code so I
can start talking about why I think it's
bad in general which is to say assuming
you're willing to accept the cognitive
overhead of a giant class hierarchy that
means nothing
it's like irrelevant it's just how they
chose interface it but it's all exposed
so you have to understand all of that
let's say here right okay
so if you want to make a cutie thing
you're already in the thick of it
because you're just you're you're always
inheriting from and using all kinds of
C++ stuff so if you don't like C++
forget it right you can't use QT so you
got to buy into C++ first and assume
that you want to do that kind of stuff
so your stuffs always gonna look like
this it's always gonna have a lot of
like an inherited style stuff happening
and that's just you know it is what it
is okay
so when you actually start using QT you
know you can see right here how the this
stuff starts to kind of work out right
there ends up being all of this garbage
where you have to constantly connect
things to other things like nothing in
it is immediate mode it's all like a
giant retained graph behind the scenes
where you have to wire all your crap up
together and they even have like three
processors you have to run sometimes to
make this happen I remember it was like
really ugly the project that I was on
that was actually using this stuff it
was super heinous so let's try to get to
some actual code that actually does
something here right so you can kind of
see like what is going on here starts to
get kind of squirrely like all right so
here's what they're claiming is the end
of the implementation of save as so I
create a queue file dialog and I pass it
myself
which presumably is because we're
inherited from window right so then I
say well I'm gonna make this thing
Moodle I'm going to like I don't know
what set accept mode does it I have no
idea I don't remember I'm gonna you know
set some of the things then I'm gonna
call exec and I'm gonna wait for a
return value I guess so
what is happening in here
what's happening I mean if you're a game
you've got to be running frames and
stuff what did what is happening like
this is actually gonna that's gonna stop
that's gonna go into their code and
you're gonna be sitting here in the
middle of a save as loop what you can do
right so now are you gonna make put this
on a separate thread like I don't know
right you certainly can't drop through
so the dialogue exact call you know is
blocking call basically I don't even
know what to make of that
right that's unusable already and we
haven't even gotten anywhere yet right
same here I don't know what that's
supposed to be you've got these weird
string wrapper things going on here
this is again a blocking modal call your
app can't be doing anything while that's
happening or you have to create a thread
right to have that happen then I mean
like just look at this look at all this
stuff right all of this kind of stuff
that's going on tons and tons of typing
that's unnecessary right like what's all
this like I don't even know this is all
this code is just to create stuff all of
that is code that actually is now
retained so every time you change the
state of your program you've got to go
through and all this stuff has to be
stored - right like you have to remember
what these things were if you ever
wanted to change them right I've got a
I've got to be able to get to all this
stuff so it's not like I just have like
in our code where we just go like one of
the things that we want to do this frame
let's do them here you've got a retain
you know everything you've got to retain
uh if you're okay with retained mode
then all right so you know looking at
this thing it's like I read I've got to
create an icon and maybe that's fine
because you know maybe you know what
else you gonna do right you got to make
an icon somewhere here I'm not sure what
the from theme stuff does but it
probably lets you like remap it or
something right so that's probably fine
so you're creating an
come here and the action it looks like
has you know the string kind of bound
with it and the action is bound on a
window so like whoever I am that's gonna
presumably feedback through me I guess
right so now you've got like this sort
of key sequence stuff presumably you
wouldn't have to do that maybe you do
have to do that which case that's kind
of bad but that's alright
you know load from there and then I'm
gonna like attach you know the tooltip
to it that I want to display or whatever
I've got this connection again that I
have to do in order to get this thing to
come back through me I have no idea
that's just wasted work there's no
reason for that because you already have
one of them like you already have you
already had to create an action so why
you can't just test to see if the action
gets called I have no idea so I don't
even know what the point is of that I
guess that's to say instead of me having
an if statement I just want you to call
this if this happens right and then
finally you're gonna add them in so
what's wrong with that like maybe you
like retained mode you're like that
looks great it's horrible why because
every single last thing in here is now
non-responsive nothing here can be
dynamic right if you wanted this tooltip
to say open existing file only in the
case where you could open existing file
and you wanted to say something else
like file is not available or something
when that wasn't true now again this is
stored state you have to keep in your
program somewhere to reach in and set
the tool tips all the time and you have
to set them correctly every time rather
than just you having a code path that
knows which one to do and it pops up you
know like this is why immediate mode is
like always my preference for how you
write the user level code for this is
that way you just have all the knowledge
already inherent in the path that goes
through the code you don't have to have
two separate paths one that creates the
standing structure and one that updates
it same thing here maybe I want it to
call open window in some cases and I
want to call something else in other
cases in that case this is just dead
letter right all this is do
is wasting my time because now I just
have to bind it to a function that is
the function that would then see which
function I'm going to call right so
again it's just all of this almost the
entire thing when you start and you're
like a basic UI programmer you think
this maybe looks good because you don't
think of all the complexity you're
eventually gonna have in your shipping
app right but once you do all of these
things end up being irrelevant you have
to fix them all later and every last
little one of these things is gonna be
an update synchronization problem but
you're going to have later and that's
why when you use an app like a QT app or
a c-sharp app because they follow these
models that's why we get all those weird
things we're like remember the other day
we were just using it and the like one
of the menus for the debugger was still
popped up even after I switched which
application I was using stuff like that
you get all the time because they're all
based on these standing data structures
that you just hope you wrote the code to
like update them properly for the
current state of your app but you never
do because no one can it's too hard
right
there's too many possible state changes
that go in there so let's see if they
ever get to anything hmm
more complicated here cuz this is all
really vanilla basic stuff which any UI
library can you can do like it's not
gonna be a good test of whether this
thing works well so let's see if we have
anything maybe that where they've got
like a like it like an actual
interrelated user interface stuff that's
got to happen yeah so like maybe well
you know let's see how bad drag-and-drop
is I don't know it's probably not that
bad how bad could it possibly be that
looks okay I wouldn't complain about
that
so let's see here
trying to get down to where they
actually have this looks like mostly
discussions and the code here
sort of more what I wanted to get to
I have to page him back all my cutie
knowledge this is taking a little while
this is just a ton of code so I maybe
this is a bad thing to look at it may be
hard for me to like give good examples
of how its problematic without actually
going through a complex example that
I've already looked at because this is a
massive amount of code if you look at
all the stuff that's in here so it's I
can't really assemble it on my head fast
enough to give a good example because
I've never seen this example before
right
here's a list of examples okay so let's
see if we can find something a little
bit more complicated here let's say we
want to animate something seems
reasonable right see what animated tiles
is all right so here's our animated
tiles code let's see what it's actually
doing so yeah you know we create an
application and it looks like it's
making a bit of graphics there which is
fine yeah so it looks like I mean I mean
I don't really want to rag on this too
much because I don't know how
high-quality this sample code supposed
to be but I mean seriously like you're
passing strings to say what this what
the values are that you want to have
animated for this thing I mean I guess
that's fine if you really don't care I
mean I suppose it's okay so anyway it's
you know they're going through here and
they're creating like what amounts to
what's items count here in this case
there's 64 of these things
I guess so they're creating 64 items and
they're creating points for each of
those is that right
yeah uh and I mean just look at this
stuff this is the animation example I
mean this is how they're saying you
would animate stuff you know how we
animate stuff right it's very easy you
just have a little piece of code that
just says what the path should be you
don't really have to do anything else
I mean it's nuts right it's all retained
mode and these things are just horrible
to work with I don't know I mean maybe
people like doing things this way but
it's so unresponsive I mean all of this
stuff gets created ahead of time it
can't possibly react to the user because
in order to react to the user you'd have
to recreate this entire thing so all it
can do is just like trigger something
that's gonna make a big gigantic
animation right and that animation
cannot ever respond to the user because
it's been pre described not to mention
this fact that look at how much of a
pain in the butt this is to describe I
mean we're talking about a thing that
makes that right I mean it's one little
for I loop an assignment of cosine in it
and they had to do all of this stuff
create tons of standing structures they
had to use the position by making a name
out of the position they had to go
through and set all these ease curves
and durations on everything they had to
add these animations to a group of
animations they had to create
transitions between them they had to
bind those to the buttons I mean and all
of its non-responsive so if we had done
this code right this code would have
just been called straight path so when
you actually went into it you could
change every time it was called anything
that you wanted about it right here
imagine what's gonna happen if all I
want to do is have a slider and this is
probably the most concise way I can say
yqt sucks this is true about everything
in it let's say I just want a slider
that says how big the circle was
right or you know how how many things
around the circle there were I would
have to delete all of these and recreate
them again every time you move the
slider right so it's like all of this
state including stuff that it's totally
not stateful like this is not state you
never want this to be state everything
is state everything's an object and it's
all going that what if the animation has
a fit in memory what if I wanted an
infinite number of those things like I
wanted it perfectly smooth I don't know
like it's just it's nuts
and everything's like that so you're
always creating these huge standing
structures they are so unresponsive so
you end up with really brittle UI is
that they can't react to what the users
doing you know I don't know it's not
good I would like to provide a more
complete answer because I could really
nitpick almost every last decision in QT
but that would require me to page it all
back in again right like but it's all
bad like every last little decision in
here is bad pretty much there's there's
no good ones in here and you know it
just all flows from the fact that you
just there's a massive cognitive
overhead because there's billions of
objects most of which don't do anything
they're just like meaningless sort of
API glue and you always have to create
them and string them together to get
anything done which forces you to keep
this massive backlog of Qt crap in sync
with your own stuff and it's just a huge
nightmare so rather than just something
in an IM GUI style where you just go oh
what do I need alright just draw this
right now you're building all of these
huge structures all the time and it's
just really really onerous and slow for
coding and in error-prone is the other
thing you know so that's my feeling on
it again I wish I could give you a more
concise answer a long time so
used it and so getting down to more
specific concrete like let me show you
each thing they should have done and why
to disentangle it all would be a pretty
big undertaking but trust me you can do
it
just made a new version for dump you
feel free to come back to this after the
Q&amp;A is ended oh cool
regarding the cutie slider example so if
I get this correctly and I'm doing one
just goes through UI elements and just
draws them depending on whatever the
slider value says yeah exactly
so the point with I am doing RM GUI is
an interface point it has nothing to do
with whether you store stuff or not so
an iamb GUI can still behind-the-scenes
store as much garbage as QT if it wanted
to right you could do that
the point is really whether or not
things are represented in code or data
and generally speaking in a UI library
you want almost nothing represented in
data on the user side because if the
user wants to represent things as data
they just can write they don't need you
to do it so for example in a QT library
I'm just gonna in fact you know what I
should have started with this in a QT
library let's say I've got a list view
and there's stuff in the ListView right
yeah here right so I've got a list view
and there's just there's things in the
ListView right so the ListView has items
in it and I need to be able to add items
how do I add items here this is the
classic QT thing I just want to add an
item to ListView where where is it of
course it's not here why would it be on
the ListView it's probably like you
create an item and parent it to the list
view or something right yeah of course
there's no add function
here you go alright so here is an
example of what you have to do with a
ListView right in order to just I just
want to add stuff to the listing view
look that's all I want to do this is not
the C code though I really want the C
code for it
here so take a look at this right what
happens in a program when you want to
make a list view I guarantee you all of
those things are represented in your
program somewhere already right so I've
got all the elements in my game I want
to put a list view that lists them right
so I already have all of the elements
now what I have to do if I want to list
them in one of qts Lister's is I have to
create an actual entry for every single
element in my game inside their list
thing so now I've got two lists of
entities the one in QT and mine and
because that's a heavyweight operation
because it's actually recreating a giant
you know 10,000 entry list thing in QT I
can't do it every frame I'd better do it
conservatively so now every time I
create an entity in my game I've got to
add to the QT list and every time I
delete an anaemic game I gotta delete
the right member of the QT list that
means my entities now have to either
store pointers to the QT lists or I have
to store a map that has a mapping
between the two I mean it's just
unusable bad right this is just horrible
design you don't ever want these things
they force you to do all of this work
for no reason all you want to do for a
list view is say hey look one of two
things either every frame I'm just gonna
call you and say here are each of the
list entries if I don't want to think
about it right or I just want to make
one call at the beginning that says
tell me the range of things you need
right and then I'll tell you just those
if it's too many - if there's a billion
of them right so we're just gonna use a
subset that's it right I don't want to
maintain QT widget lists that's
ridiculous
right like it's just not good and so
pretty much universally when when you
look at something you go oh you know
someone might think QT is good because
they look and they say oh look I can
just add things to list you and then
they show up they don't realize how much
of a pain in the butt it's gonna be once
they're in an actual application that
has all of its own state and is trying
to expose that state through the user
interface it just completely falls apart
and you end up doing like tons and tons
of work to micromanage the UI to get to
do anything reasonable you know it's
just bad so yeah I can't stand that
stuff regretting keeping audio-video
synced Wendy when you did the order
system you were very strict about
playing without losing one frame that
was before you move to OpenGL and now
there's latency between when we're
issuing a frame until it's actually
rendered how are we gonna keep them in
sync I guess for Emily here something
huge deal but I'm curious area opinion
about how to keep in sync so actually
you can't really keep them in sync on PC
as far as I know that was true even
before we switch to OpenGL so the thing
you have to remember is when we were
using Windows before when we were just
using it to display our bitmaps it still
goes through a compositor which can
still which still delays your
presentation so we weren't getting an
immediate display necessarily we were
just trying to limit the number of we
were basically trying not to add any
additional frames of latency to the ones
that were already there so that hasn't
changed it's basically the same if you
want to try and get sync to be perfect I
I don't think Windows really ever added
anyway
for you to do it I just don't think it's
possible I could be wrong about that but
I think it's not my recollection is that
on macaws it is possible so for example
on on macaws I believe you can ask for
two timers one is like where we are
where when I submit this audio where
will it be played and the other is when
will the next frame be flipped to be
viewed on the monitor and you can
actually try to line those up properly
how that helps
thanks for the Lister example that made
it pretty clear where do you think it
comes from that people build those
reverse CBI's that don't give you much
less well yeah um it's because what they
do is they've just made the UI system
and then they just make you program the
actual stuff right so if you think about
what someone's it's time to make a UI
library what they do is they go okay so
I need a ListView so obviously I need to
remember what each thing in the ListView
is so that's what I made and then I'm
like what's the API to that ok the API
to that is here user you tell me anytime
you want to make one of those things in
ListView right so that's the mentality
is like let me just completely expose
whatever I wrote internally as the API
and now you've got to do it QT APIs be
egregiously bad because because the
programmers were heavy c++ audit
oriented style programmers you also get
all that class larga stuff that was how
they chose to do it internally as well
right so you get all that shoveled on
you as well but even people who don't do
that stuff they still have that problem
because they don't think about what
should the API actually look like to
this thing right like what would the
user actually want to say they probably
don't want to have to micromanage all of
my state they probably need some better
tools for just articulating to me what
the parts of the state are that they
care about at this particular time and I
should be responsible for doing the rest
of the work necessary to make all this
stuff work out right and so that's
really the the design mentality problem
and so most UI libraries have this
problem because they don't realize that
an api to the UI library shouldn't just
be about you having to micromanage
everything the UI library does which is
what they usually are
if we're 10 minutes to bed why have an
immediate green sticker over the desktop
mobile market yet um so I think they
actually have I'm pretty sure I am
gooeys are actually now almost
everything and the reason for that is
because at some point and I don't know
why the web community got the I am GUI
bug and so now my understanding is like
all that stuff like react je s like all
that stuff is I am now or at least
partially I am QT is not a common
application layer to use for most at
most things you know that 99% of the
things people use today are not Qt right
and they're not retained mode either so
basically like these all of these things
these like JavaScript stuff like that's
all immediate mode they they went that
way so the answer is they have nobody
who ever uses an IM GUI will ever go
back to using an RM GUI right it's like
it's horrible to go the other direction
so once communities get understand how
to do those interfaces they will that's
just a given
does that help and it has nothing to do
with whether you're a game or anything
else every UI should be responsive you
know it should be recipients should
respond to changing conditions as fast
as possible
so you have an array of some struct type
and each item has a name which is what
you want to represent as an item in the
list for the end user to choose from
would be a good idea to hand the UI some
pointer to the first name and specify
some stride to the next or how would you
do it it doesn't really matter usually
because you eyes don't normally display
enough things at once to hat care about
the push through so typically all you
really need is some way of windowing
what needs to get articulated on a
particular frame and then you can
usually just make a call per and it's
fine this is why websites are slow they
are trying to impose the I'm be a
paradigm to retain style and suffer with
performance let the compare data graphs
and find difference as an implied
changes to retain model yeah it's
definitely the case that if the web had
just been immediate mode to begin with
you would have had a lot better
performance I don't actually think
that's why websites are slow though
websites are slow for a lot of other
reasons and you know data graph
comparisons are probably not they don't
help but they're probably not the main
reason if you fixed that you probably
would still be pretty slow because
there's a lot of bad stuff going on
there right
and by the way 0lp p.m. i'm not giving
these as good examples I'm just saying
you were asking why people didn't change
to it they did everyone did nobody
thinks are I'm doing is good anymore as
far as I know
I'd like that days over the question is
just how the IM GUI stuff should work
and which ones are good because you can
still make a very bad I am GUI right
it's not hard to make a bad API even if
the paradigm you pick is better it's
still bad right does that make sense
so I was in no way trying to just react
this is good I've never used it so
we do think annotation based programming
I don't think I know what that is
I don't know what I'm looking at here
all you have to deal with is a single
job or a profession I guess what I would
say is I don't know what this is so I
can't give an opinion about it
it doesn't I'd have to look at it more
carefully but it doesn't look like
actually a thing it just looks like
regular programming it just looks like
programming I mean just because you
chose to call something annotation
doesn't change the fact that it's still
just programming it looks like you added
some stuff to your programming language
that just is now changing the
programming language isn't it is there
something else
all right anyway I'm gonna wrap it up
sorry I wish I could give a better
answer for the annotation a friends that
I don't really know what that is
so dr. gesture profiling huge websites
it's pretty common to see 100 500 most
like I've spent on things like relay
adding or recalc you see s cells or just
purely inside the JavaScript
I made a purely dear I am gooey WebGL
web Bazin website it takes 0.5
milliseconds per frame to compute the
layout that's cool yeah I mean like I
said it I don't know I mean it's totally
possible that some websites are that way
other like I said I it's just there's a
lot of slow stuff on the web so you know
I'm sure some of it is that fact but I
think depending on the website you're
gonna have more or less of that it's all
I can say right like some websites are
gonna have a lot of that some websites
aren't some of it you know may have
nothing to do with the act of doing that
comparison and just the fact that
JavaScript itself is not very well
optimized for certain things and just
just the act of running the code is bad
you know because the codes written
poorly and that sort of stuff so it's
just it's really hard to say I have no
idea but I don't doubt it right like in
the words I'm not saying that it's
probably not a problem I'm just saying
that it's it's probably one of many
problems you know I mean like some
websites you fix that and maybe that
fixes the whole thing other websites
it's probably like like you could fix
that and then you still have ten other
things you gotta fix you know
I like the idea of that WebGL thing
though all right I'm gonna wrap it up
like it's just it's it's fun - I am GUI
WebGL is that's just cool like I like
that idea
please make a neutral nice people need
to buy some games for Linux it's really
up to people to make that happen because
there's tons of people shipping games on
Linux like a lot of people tried and it
just doesn't catch on you know what I
mean it's it's a it's a social problem
not a development problem because people
tried like a lot of people ship games
which then you can get a lot of games I
think it's not a big market you don't
it's not even worth the amount of time
it takes you to port usually and so it's
just there isn't enough of a market
there and the problem is probably that
like you know when you're talking about
market where you need to get a hundred
thousand people together to buy
something there just aren't that many
people buying games on Linux to create
those numbers for one individual game
you know that seems to be the the main
problem and I don't know how you fix it
but if you could fix it that would be
pretty awesome because having Linux be
I've oftentimes I hoped I was hoping a
lot when the steam machines came when
when CMOS was gonna be a thing I was
hoping that was gonna convince people to
do it it didn't really end up being a
thing but you know like I said tons of
games around Linux now it has not
created the market so it's not a lack of
games at the moment it's it's that
people aren't buying them and you know
it's not that no one's buying them some
people are but just not enough to create
a market that's that's really the only
problem and so that's why people just
don't consider it a priority so in
general what ends up happening is people
usually just like go to SDL and ship
that and don't really support it and i
think that's mostly what you're gonna
end up seeing on linux right it's just
it's just not a primary platform it's
not gonna be till someone makes that
makes that happen socially it's entirely
social all you would have to do is get
those numbers up the first time someone
a hundred thousand copies of an indie
game on Linux everyone will make Linux
the main platform like all you need is
an example that the market is there
right and I don't know how you make that
happen but if you can make that happen
you just make that will be heard right
like you know you it's just a social
problem it's just a social problem
convincing people to use it it's
obviously not a money problem because
Linux is free it is sometimes a
compatibility problem because Linux
doesn't always work so well on people's
computers laptops are a big problem on
linux desktops usually are better right
so there there are some issues there too
but you know mostly it's a social
problem can you convince people can you
convince gamers to actually run Linux
and you know I don't know I don't know
how you do that but if you can do that
you'll you'll be a big hero if you can
do that right
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for those say the hand made here it's
been a pleasure talking to you as always
if you want to follow along series at
home you can always career to the game
on hand made here at or --get comes with
a source code so you can play around
with it we're doing surprise streams all
this month and next month in honor of
Krampus love and so I'll see you back
here probably real soon
we'll see until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet
take it easy everybody