hello everyone welcome to hand me here
oh sure we could a complete game live on
stream we have our user interface stuff
working now to edit attachment points
but it's not quite complete
so we did the work necessary to kind of
use our debug UI system as well for
doing editing and we got that working on
the last stream but there's a couple
things that we didn't implement yet and
we sort of have options of how we might
do that and you know we'll we'll see how
we want to well see basically how we
want to kind of fuss around with that
but we've put ourselves in a good a good
position to attack it now so what I like
to do is jump in there figure out what
other stuff we need do and just
basically clean up that interface into
in a usability sense adding the features
we need to actually edit some of the
elements and adding anything else that
we need to make sure that it feels ok to
actually do edits on it and you know
we'll we'll see if we can get by the end
of stream to the point where we reading
those points fairly reasonably so that's
all we're gonna be doing and it's a it's
a fairly you know nicely contained
problem let me show you where we're at
on this and I'll mention sort of things
we're going to do probably in order but
there is no real importance to the order
it's just probably how we'll tackle them
so here's the game running right and we
go ahead and jump that full screen
there's a couple of you I do so the deep
of you I lost it's snapping stuff
because we kind of changed how the
render would week we want these things
to probably snap to the upper corner so
I'd like to kind of get that going I
don't want to have to keep dealing with
them going where they're going there and
and you know if you go like this then
they're off the screen entirely right so
you know I think we should try and
restore that folks like Allen that would
take very long it's something we should
probably fix but that's neither here nor
there that's just one we should take a
look at so when we have this interface
stuff you can see all we did is we just
kind of slammed that UI into the center
of the screen so the first thing you
want to do actually move this over here
so that it's kind of in the corner or
somewhere where it's like a window we
can actually interact with in a more
meaningful way that isn't just
at 0-0 because that's what I typed in
right not a very good reason we want
these to look more like buttons and we
also maybe want them to be a little bit
harder to hit I don't really want the
Save button like right next to my undo
button so you know we we want to kind of
get this UI into a more UI like state
right because we all we did was just the
bare-bones wiring necessary to have it
be in there and we didn't really spend
any time on actual human factors we
could do a little bit more there to get
that nicer right so I'd like to do that
again because remember this is just all
we're doing here is just this right all
we're doing is getting these debug
features here that we've got we're just
putting that in here that's all we've
been doing and so you know it's not it's
not really we haven't implemented any of
this stuff specifically the editor we've
just been using these buttons that we
made so like we made a long time ago so
you know we want that to work and so
moving that over there and having that
be some kind of a thing that we can more
conveniently access and use that's good
and then what we want to do is work on
these right here so some of these are
going to be pretty simple like to parent
is just a toggle right so clicking that
on and off that's gonna be really simple
same thing here with like type right
like that's just going to be like either
a click we could do a quick to just
toggle through things or we could have
like left and right arrows to go back
and forth between the different ones or
something but since there's not going to
be that many of those we probably don't
even really need a drop-down list or
anything so I don't even know that we
want to go through the trouble of
implementing something like that because
it's probably just overkill for what
we're looking at so we could probably
something simpler there as well we've
got this size and that's again also very
simple because even just a simple
interaction that would allow us to drag
up and down on it would be sufficient
and we already kind of implemented one
of those so we've really that would
probably very simple for us to implement
so really the big one that's a little
confusing that we haven't really done
much with is this percent P again though
we could just choose this out this is
just for us doing basic alignment work
so we could just mix anywhere week-old
on it and just move
around and it just adjusts the values of
it or something as we move you know so I
don't really think there's gonna be a
lot of work involved in doing these
that's not the primary part of it I
think it's gonna be pretty
straightforward right so I think we can
hack those in there pretty quickly and
they may just be good enough we do want
to pretty this up a little bit I think
like I said and make it a little bit
easier to use so there's some of that
that probably should happen so we'll
take a look at that but the biggest
thing that I think we're gonna have to
do in an implementation sense is once we
allow that sort of dragging ability like
of the size and that sort of thing what
we're gonna do is we're gonna we're
gonna run to a problem where our undo
just buffer just fills up because as you
drag it around trying to push on do unto
a new dota on there right and so one
thing that we probably want to do is we
need our like undo redo system instead
of adding an undo for every modification
that you make we needed to understand
the concept that when you start an
interaction you would create an undo and
when you end the interaction
you would write to that undo but no
matter how you drag the thing you're
only gonna save the initial state and
the end state and you're never going to
do any kind of any kind of like
recording of what all those motions were
you just need to know what was the
original size and what was the final
size cuz that's all the undo and redo
are gonna care about so we don't it's
gonna be way too difficult for the user
to deal with 8 million undos for their
drag they've got the whale on the undo
button forever to like get that undo
done so we don't want to do that right
so we're gonna have to dress that and
that's more of a real implementation
prom which we're gonna have to do a
little bit of thinking there and make
sure that we do that correctly in a way
that's easy to use so that as we add
things to the system if we add more edit
operations it's not a problem to to have
them still understand and go through
that system right so that's what we're
looking at and so let's start with just
the basics let's just warm up with some
basics here let's try to get these
things to be editable so like let's just
do you know get each of these things
editable and the other thing that I
would like to do here
is sort sort of consider the fact that
the that when we are done making these
things editable we should also stop
allowing click through on anything
that's sort of in this window region
because right now if you don't have a
valid thing to interact with it's
considered a selection so for example
let's say click on this which is not a
thing it actually just looks past it and
grabs whatever is on the other side as
opposed to what happens if I click on
this which is an own button it actually
it prevents the selection which is what
we want so we would like to also while
we're in the you know while we're going
through process we would like to think a
little bit more seriously about how
we're going to say what is and isn't a
valid click through and probably
everything within like a window region
of this editor - more or less right now
know how we want to say that maybe we'll
just make a size that it is over the
corner or something that is just gonna
be off limits so you click in there and
it's never gonna do pick through because
that's just confusing and it's almost
certainly not what any user would want
to have happen like they're not going to
be just because the thing wasn't
interactive that they're clicking on
doesn't mean they want to select the
thing behind it usually you know maybe
they do but you know it's probably not
the most likely case so you know
principally surprise and whatnot there
so going over to the editor side of
things here what you can see in like
when we when we have all the stuff that
we were working on like the undo system
and stuff like that we've got these
buttons and the buttons have like an if
and then you do something in it and it
returns back the you know the true if it
was pushed and false otherwise right and
if we look at what happens with these
things here like editable boolean and it
will type double size you know those
sorts of things um the problem that we
get there again is that like I said
right off the bat we end up in a
situation where those things are gonna
push on undo records every time they
change now that may be a reasonable
thing for type and that may be a
reasonable thing is for it to parent but
it's not really good for size and
percent P so
as I'm looking at these as I'm doing the
actual implementation of the edit to
begin with what I would like to do is
maybe upgrade my notion a little bit of
what this end edit block actually is
going to get as a return and what I'd
like to do there is say look what if we
could switch on the end edit block
instead of just an if what if in here I
could say like you know edit block begin
modification you know edit block you
know and the modification that kind of
thing and so in here I could say look
here's a bunch of edits that happened
with these align points I'd like to know
whether we started one or whether we're
ending one right and with that
information I can go ahead and and you
know do something reasonable we could
also include the concept of cancellation
in here which is to say if you were
doing a drag and hit the Escape key or
who knows what our semantics would be
for that it's decaf by the way I don't
normally drink coffee this late but I do
like to drink decaf this late so if you
do want to cancel the modification we
could have that you know be handled
directly in here by just not committing
that undo at all right so what I'd like
to do here is just look at what that
would entail exactly and one of the
interesting things about that is if you
look at what happens with edit a line
point it's kind of got a couple
different phases to it right if you look
at what happens here it's sort of a has
the begin and end in it right it kind of
has those stages all going on inside the
routine you can see like it looks like
this like this is and this is you know
again and this is during in a sense
right so you can kind of see what's
going on there and what we need to do is
break that up or you know we need to do
something that will allow us to renew
something that will allow us to
aggregate that now there's a couple
different ways we could do that and you
know thinking it through if we really
wanted to be a little fancier about this
maybe one thing we could say is what if
we just leaned on the undo system and
said maybe the undo system itself is
responsible for aggregating these things
you know maybe there's sort of like an
interim idea there that that maybe
there's like an interim idea there that
we can lean on that we don't have to
actually manually go through these
processes in the first place either
right and so maybe one thing we could
say is like maybe we could say something
we're like all right maybe the original
way was fine you know maybe maybe we
don't need to really think about those
things and maybe what we can do instead
is just say hey we've got this notion
already in the editor of these sort of
lists of changes so we've got these
things right and maybe what we want to
do is say like a in progress
you know list and maybe what we say is
when you're doing editing maybe instead
of things going on the undo stack maybe
they all go into the in progress stack
right and then only once you confirm and
edit will those things actually go on to
the undo stack and until then they won't
what that allows us to do is it gives us
that cancellation ability right but it
also gives us the ability to merge so
when we say
edit a line point maybe what we can do
there is merge those changes when you do
this operation we can change it from
something that allocates a new one of
these to something that first looks to
see whether or not there already was one
edit of this type and if there was we
merge them together right that to me
sounds fairly compelling I like the idea
of that and so I think I'm gonna run
with that instead what that means is
it's nice we can ignore this for now we
can leave it exactly the way that it was
we don't have to change anything and
what I can do is just implement these as
I wanted to and then we'll come back to
it later in and get this working right
that sounds like the right approach to
me and that's what I'm gonna go with and
by the way the reason it sounded like
the right approach to me was what I
imagined my head was I was like okay
since I don't have a real reason to pick
one of the other in this particular case
what would a more complex case want
right if I because I don't have a reason
to pick one of the other here what would
our complex case want and in a more
complex case we might have operations
that do a bunch of things like
complicated loops that look over things
and make changes
I don't want those loops to have to be
aware of which points they've edited so
far in which ones they haven't I want
them to just go ahead and edit whatever
they want to edit and then I'd like the
undo system to go ahead and aggregate
any changes that have to be aggregated
as that as a consequence of that process
that to me then said oh okay so I need a
basically like a little in-progress ring
that I can just say here's all the edits
that have happened that are not
committed yet that are up for
aggregation and up for cancellation and
then I'll just deal with those in bulk
that make sense
hold on well I'd each app
so if we now just go in look in this
part here knowing that I'm going to
handle that part later I can now do
things exactly order I said that I want
to do them which is just implement these
actual editor functions here and then
we'll deal with the the fallout from it
in a minute I'm gonna use the same trick
we used before to speak about which ones
of these things are actually happening
so I'm just going to go ahead and here
and add this a this sort of unique
identifier to each of these because I
think I will like that ability to sort
of track that as we go forward and so
because that gives me the option of of
having like multi-step UI and always to
know which one of them I'm talking about
and so on so now if I come back to here
and we go back and look at where those
things are being called like editable
boolean both type edible size right so
where those things were getting called I
now want the ability to do the same
thing I was doing before which is to
pass a dev ID here so that any
interactions that we have will kind of
work with these right we'll work through
these IDs so I'm just gonna sort of spam
those in there and how so each of these
will take one of those things now the
easiest thing by far to implement here
is the edible boolean the reason that
the easiest thing to edit is the edible
bullying is because really it's just a
button right so what we can do is we we
don't even really need to implement
another piece of code what we can do is
just call the button code and leave it
at that so for example in here editable
boolean Slyke label label text instead
of calling label we'll just call this so
when I come through here I'll say all
right and I can I would really like to
stress a lot of people are used to
looking at weird class tortured class
hierarchy sorts of stuff for UI it's not
great you don't have to do ridiculous
stuff like inherit from a thing in order
to get the functionality of the thing
functional composition works it just
works so if you have something like a
boolean and you just want to use the
button code for it just use it right
just write it as a function and then
they compose they compose
well you don't need to go through all of
that ridiculous object-oriented nonsense
to get basic things like composition it
just works
it objects are not needed that they're
just not relevant to it right it's a
separate kind of concept functional
decomposition just is a basic thing that
works in programming
it doesn't require these sort of overall
bearing mindsets to to get to so what I
can do is I can just say look the
boolean it's just a button so if that
button actually gets you know actually
gets pressed then I'm gonna take the
value and not it right so that's all I
want to do there right that's how that
works and so we can implement the
editable boolean really really trivially
once we have those IDs flowing through
properly and really all we need to do
there is say well we might want some way
of saying which one it is I don't know
that I need that to be like a colon true
or colon false or anything you know we
could make it be like a checkbox or
something like that it's hard for me to
say what the best way to do that is I
really don't know okay so one way we
could do it is by leaving the label call
in so we passed the label text here you
know I'm saying and then in here with
the button code we actually just switch
on the value and say well either we're
gonna draw nothing in the case where
it's not set or you know we're gonna
draw something or maybe to be a little
bit more specific we'll do like that
right and again you know a fancier UI we
draw something like a check box or
something like that but in this case I
don't know that I really want to go
through that kind of trouble because
again this is just a simple little UI
for us to use and so something like this
is really all that we want to be able to
do now I need to get this actually
working and for some reason I'm not
getting my
my call back there which I'm not sure
why we wouldn't because that should
properly give me my bow I never mind
that is working just fine we didn't
finish the last part of the problem so
beginning edit block is the thing that
controls whether these things ever get
written back right so in here where we
do our edit a line point this has to
return true in order for us to ever
reach this part of the code and actually
do the change so what that means is in
here when we're actually doing this we
have to these pieces of code have to
write to the layout and let this edit
block know right whether those changes
occurred so let's do that it's really
easy what we're doing here is you know
edited edit occurred or something like
that right we just want to set that to
true and all of these want to do the
same right they want to set it to true
as well okay so what do I do now is when
I sit that that edit occurred right I
want that to be tracked and probably
throughout just the layout struct right
so I want that to be tracked here as
edit occurred and what I want to do is
in UI n o'clock now you'll notice and I
said this when I added it remember I was
a little bit cryptic about it but I said
this very specifically which I had some
water I forgot my water what I want to
do here is I want to make it so that
it's free to nest these edit blocks if
you want to write so I want to be able
to do like a begin begin and then amend
and and I want that to work I don't know
that I ever will use that but just I've
learned from having program for so long
that it's really free for me to do that
if I just leverage the function stack
the actual execution stack to do that
for me so you'll notice that when I
wrote this when I wrote begin an edit
block I had begin edit block return Debu
I edit block and I had that
passed in here why did I do that well
the reason that I did that was because I
wanted to make sure that I could store
the previous state of edit occurred
somewhere and that gives me a place to
store it so now we know what's gonna go
in here right and now we know what's
gonna happen here okay so now when we
come back in here the result is very
easy for us to produce it's just didn't
edit occur didn't it and we can preserve
the nesting behavior by just going ahead
and taking whatever the blocks previous
value was which we saved and restoring
it if we had the mat and we wanted that
behavior we would have needed our own
stack here and that stack would have had
to have been limited or dynamically
allocated or some other less efficient
thing whereas if we just track the
program stack it just works right
because the program stack always has to
actually have that shape to it so that's
usually the way you want to do that
because it usually gets it for you for
free there some cases where it can't
specifically if you actually have things
that are non recursive that do their own
stack walking but even in that case this
can usually just go into the stack
storage so you almost always get it for
free if you do it this way and that's
much nicer right so I highly recommend
that and that's why I wrote it this way
that means now we're done right that was
a whole thing it was literally like four
lines of code or something the tracking
of whether anybody edited anything
during that block and nesting and all
that stuff just a couple lines of code
really really simple right and that's
why I like that construction it's just
that simple um so here I can I can set
this thing on and off like you can see
and you know for some reason like I said
we were having some problems with our
baseline computation I don't know why I
don't know when that happened do you
notice that like we lost our baselines
and I feel like that was was that
something that happened when we upgraded
our
format I want to look and see if that
was the case because I'd be interested
to know when that happened exactly we
should probably look at that we could
even look at that now
but anyway I think that's fine so so
there's the code for for the editable
point again really really simple again
one of the things that I really like
about these constructions is they they
let you do a tremendous amount of easy
work that you know you don't you don't
have to be too fancy or inherit base or
a stuff to do it's pretty nice now
coming up here is something that's a
little bit nasty because it's a case
where you want to be able to have more
flexibility but you as I think you'll
see in a second it turns out that we can
probably do a few quick gyrations and
actually still make it pretty easy to do
what we want to do so what I'd like to
do here on the dev ID side of things is
I would actually like to make two
buttons when I'm only getting called
with one dev ID you can see why that's a
bit of an issue right I because that
makes things a little bit more
complicated than them you know we would
have liked it to be but one of the
things that we can look at there is that
that actually because the interactions
themselves can have different states I
could probably get away with doing
something a little bit I can probably
get away with some shenanigans to make
this work but we can also just consider
making our dev ID a little bit more
expressive that would also be a totally
valid way to go so we'll have to see
which one we want to do but here's what
I want to do I want to basically have a
way to increment or decrement this
particular value that's here so I
effectively want to be able to do
something roughly along the lines of you
know this so we can basically increment
or decrement this thing and the Edit
occurs depending on which one we do
right and then we just have some like
you know crappy left or right arrows
that allow us to make those changes
right so it's two sub buttons this would
just work if we had some way
of taking a dev ID and making sort of a
subordinate version of that thing that
allows us to do more than one type of
edit to it which is the moment we really
don't have right we don't have a way of
making a subordinate version of the dev
ID and that's kind of a problem we would
like we would have liked there have been
some way for us to do that and at the
moment there really isn't much of a way
for us to do that so the question is
what's the best way for us to make this
a little bit more flexible and how there
be some way to do that right well
there's a couple things that happen in
here that we may want to take a look at
so if we and I'm not sure which one I
want to do yet so I'm kind of saying
this more as a provisional thing but I
want to go into dev UI and just take a
look at how this stuff is generally
structured right so in here there's some
things that we call some general things
that we ask that's what we use the the
dev you I stuff the dev ID stuff for we
do things like asking if two
interactions are equal right or asking
if two interactions are hot and what you
kind of see there is the interaction
actually is a much richer structure than
just the dev ID so if we were to make a
more expressive version of our button
call right meaning this right here if we
were to make a more expressive version
of that so for example maybe something
that looks like this where we pass the
dev ID and a target parameter let's say
or a generic or something like that you
know like other information that we may
want to have on there so we know it's a
button so we know it's a button
interaction but maybe we want some other
things so I can add another thing here
which is like you know some other
operation like up you know
something like this or a classifier you
know then what I could do is when I come
through here I can set that classifier I
can set something there like the target
can be this or I can have the generic be
set to that whatever I want to do now
I'll actually be getting some
discrimination there what that means is
that when I call this function I get
more than I was getting when I called
one of these and so what I can do there
is I can now go all right when I call
this function I really just thump
through I say I've got a dev ID and I
don't have one of these classifiers off
we go and I just return whatever the
result is that I have now I've got a
more powerful version of the button and
so what I can do there is call that
version when I need to do things that
are more complicated like this right and
so it's pretty easy for me to do
basically whatever I want there I can
make up any old thing I can use this
string pointer if I want to write I can
do anything I want so I can literally
just do something like you know left
label right label right
and at that point I should be able to
have both of these things right they
should both be there now what's gonna
happen when I actually allow this
editing is we also need some notion of
what would be a legal value because
we're gonna immediately set these to
some pretty invalid values if I let that
actually be the entirety of the editing
right but it would work so this is you
know you can see them highlighting
separately so I think we're good to go
there right so what I want to do is I
want to also I suppose we should print
this out because we're not actually
printing this out yet either so we also
want to do this right I don't know if
we've got where's our label F yeah we've
got our label F so I should be able to
do my label F here and correct me if I'm
wrong but I think we did some kind of
thing where we passed a Capitol yeah so
we actually already have a way of
outputting one of these strings that's
much more convenient than the normal C
way where you have to pass like the
count and then the length is two
separate parameters so we should also be
able to print out what the type
currently is and so you know that gives
us again another kind of like you know
we've got the type field there and I
should be able to kind of cycle through
these of course it doesn't look like I'm
actually cycling through these for some
reason so I have to see why but that's
basically all we're talking about there
right and so again we want to clean this
up it looks horrid and I also need to
figure out why we're getting those weird
why we're not getting proper baselining
on those values I really don't know why
but it may be that we're interpreting it
the wrong way round two I'm not sure so
we'll see what's going on there but so
let me just take a look at why we're not
getting the correct strings coming
through there or maybe if the
isn't happening properly would be the
other thing so we should probably take a
look and see if there's something weird
going on there but let me see what's up
so yeah if I look let's see here
so we're sort of doing a u3 tube pointer
if ocation of this which I'm not sure is
a good thing what we may want to do here
is actually grab it in a way that's
editable more like that just to be safe
let me make sure cuz I don't really know
if that cast is okay there it's probably
a problem so yeah if I want to call that
I have to cast it back which is fine
with me let's see here editor line point
I just want that to be you three two
because as I passed that in here I don't
really want that to be I don't want that
in the mix let me make sure that wasn't
part of the problem and then we'll go in
and debug it as we go yeah you can kind
of see like we're just not getting any
changes to the to the value there for
whatever reason and so I want to go see
why that's happening I also want to look
at this again - I don't remember what's
actually happened there so we're calling
a line point name from type so we're
calling this and it's always returning
this for some reason and so I don't know
why that's happening and we'll have to
take a look because yeah I don't I don't
know why that would be the case it seems
like that should be
incrementing but what I was gonna say in
addition to all of that which will go to
vote now is once you know that it edit
has taken place we need to actually
check the bounds so here we need to do
like if the type is greater than
whatever the the count is of these
things so these these types here that
we're using for align points we want to
count in there and we want to say that
if we've gotten out of the bounds of
what's allowed here we want to make sure
that we wrap that properly right and so
there's two cases that could happen one
is that it gets decremented on zero
right and that would wrap us round of
course once you decrement to zero you've
effectively killed the type so it would
actually have to be recreated so I'm not
sure that case really matters much but
if we come out around here we would want
to wrap back around to probably to the
default I want to say you know two one
if we got past count is my guess and if
we got to zero so probably if we got to
zero we would actually want to set it to
count minus one because I we don't
really want you to ever set it to zero
because that's the same as deleting it
so we would rather have you click on the
delete key to make it clear that's what
you were doing and so that would prevent
that from now now we just have to go see
why this operation doesn't seem to
actually be doing anything I'm gonna
switch ourselves over to debug mode just
because if I'm in a step to do something
I wanna be able to see everything more
clearly
Divac modes doing really only real way
to do that with the visual studio
debugger it's not very good at debugging
release mode code so I'm gonna set a
breakpoint at editable type that should
just allow me to go in there and and set
a breakpoint once I actually have a
break let's actually break on
this function itself I'm gonna get rid
of that break point and then a set one
inside the two buttons so when I click
on one of these
I should see this occur right I should
get an actual operation that makes that
that case get hit so here if I select
one of these and I go over here and I
click on it right
I should see and I do right so I should
see this this occur so let me take a
look at what the watch variables are
here let's look at what that value is
it's properly set to default right now I
I don't know what I was thinking there
that's that's not at all what I wanted I
just didn't want that at all I wanted
that so don't ask me what I was thinking
about there because I don't know so yeah
what I wanted to do was not that I
effectively want to do this actually I
guess I should do it more like that what
I want to do is just think I might have
decrement this thing so that was
probably the entirety of my stupidity
wrapped up in that little equal sign
that wasn't supposed to be there all
right so let's take a look at that real
quick and just see if that fixes our
problem
it doesn't still okay so maybe I wasn't
as stupid as I thought I was although
that was still stupid so I kind of was
whether we like it or not so if we stop
here here's that value I just want to
see that value change so it went up to
one so that's good and now I want to
take a look at why our value annotation
now what's interesting is if the value
was zero there that's actually kind of
strange because does that mean it it did
both of these that because that could be
what happened let's take a quick look
there
okay so that's what happened it
decrements then increments those gonna
say looking at the old mobs like it
still should have worked it was just
really stupid-looking code so when we're
doing the button for some reason the
interaction is not properly registering
as having occurred or not and you know I
I think why I think it's basically
because inside the dev UI we we didn't
properly
we didn't faithfully maintain the fact
that these should have been interactions
right and and we want that to be the
case so in here I think what I want to
do is say yeah we want to create this
interaction and we want to do in our
equals for those right and that's
actually what we're gonna check and I
need to go see what the name of that was
its interactions are equal I don't
really know that we want to type that
every time our are equal would have
probably been better but you know life
goes on so we wanna yeah we want to just
make sure that whole thing is solid
and that should do it
so now we'll get the proper tracking
which is what I wanted and we should be
able to just move on to the next thing
hopefully let's see here yeah there we
go so now we can sort of set those and I
would probably prefer if we had some
better rendering of them so we're gonna
have to go spend a little bit of time on
that so things aren't horribly ugly but
otherwise it looks like our UI is now
working just fine right so I can cycle
through these things here and off we go
right so that's all good and so and to
parent is toggleable as well so other
than the fact that it's horribly ugly
and not very usable in that sense it's
all implemented properly now and so
we'll do the size and percent as well
and then we'll just clean up this line
so it looks pretty right that'll be the
next thing that we want to focus on and
maybe get a window around there as well
you know maybe that sort of stuff so in
terms of like size and percent P again I
think these are just gonna be draggy
kind of kind of operations right and so
if I if I go into the dev UI what I want
to see in here is first of all I
probably want to print out what the
values actually are somehow right I want
to build see them which is the moment we
cannot do and so inside editable size
what I probably want to do here is say
yeah call the label F we'll pass in
something like this
maybe I don't know exactly what I want
to do there but we'll do something like
that
and the same will be true here I don't
if we just do drag manipulation we could
avoid passing the min and Max as well I
don't know what I think about that
because if you wanted to have ways of
controlling what the range was I think
we're still gonna want it so I think I'm
gonna keep passing that honestly that's
just my that's just my guess so yes so
here's the X here's the Y and then what
I want to do is add the ability to drag
those around right have a way of playing
with those and so in here if I select
one now we can see that those are
actually printed out there and so what I
want to be able to do is like highlight
one of these and drag it around right
have the ability to actually to actually
move that and so what I think we're
gonna have to move from is like label F
right I don't really want to do in that
case what I want to do is I want to
actually do more what label F is
actually calling through to like basic
text element where I can define my my
own interaction that's gonna happen and
my own like specifics about all of this
stuff right so let me go ahead and call
that I don't know if I care about the v2
I don't think I do
but basically what I want to do here is
just say okay
when you do this right and we've got
that label F call right when you do this
just go ahead and make this out of what
you've got
like that and then call basic text
element yourself with whatever the thing
is that you that you've got the
interaction here can be whatever we're
going to make it and the rest of these
things we can set however we want I
probably will keep these I don't really
know about the border part of it the
backdrop color obviously can just be
some yeah I don't know what it should be
whatever it is for these things right
like
so we should be able to do something
here where now we can take more control
that process and make an actual widget
for lack of a better term that just lets
us do the drag interaction that we
wanted which I don't really know what
it's going to be but you know we'll
implement something that we think is
reasonable so yeah so in here like if I
[Music]
have this thing now you can see that I'm
drawing it there I feel like it wants a
boarder probably I don't know how big it
wants the border to be I guess why did I
recompile I could've just done that live
and probably should have so let's try
that so the border didn't seem to do
anything did it I can't see I don't see
that doing anything what is basic text
elements use of the border or maybe
that's just too tiny
oh that's in pixels okay that makes a
little more sense so that's more of a
reasonable thing right
and so you know I don't know how big we
want to make that really but it might
want to be bigger than that right it
might want to be more like six right
that's a pretty reasonable size to click
on and then I can kind of you know zoom
around on it right I think we also want
more spacing in between these two but
that's kind of a you know look I said
when we go to pretty up this line we'll
take that a little bit more seriously so
yeah again same exact thing happened in
here and in this case again we just have
kind of another different type of
editing operation that's gonna happen
there I also don't know if maybe this
should just be a part of V to like
editable v2 I think that might have been
just dumb that I didn't do it that way
and so we'll see we'll dress that in
in one moment so looking at the dev yuan
interaction we know we can introduce a
thing here like for example toggle value
I'm sorry a drag value which we have we
can do something like that but my
question is like what's the editing here
and so if you look we've got like a star
P that it's being edited what we
probably can do is make that start we
can probably make that star P we can
probably make that star P be something
that works whether you're dragging one
variable or - right because that's
probably what was happening in the
previous drag value stuff so I think the
only real issue here is there isn't
anything that says how far the value
should move relative to your drag right
like there is no we're just not
including anything that gives you
information about that and that's
unfortunate that's about the only
blocking factor because we'd like to
include some stuff about like what the
boundary like what how fast it should
move when it's moving the Delta you know
essentially and that's just not that's
not forthcoming
[Music]
so I don't have a lot of ideas about
what the right way to do that would be
there's a lot of options but I don't
know that there's one of them that I
find particularly compelling necessarily
what I can say is I do think that
reinforces my sort of belief that these
should largely be V twos right so here's
the thought if we do feed this back then
I guess we don't really need to do that
because we are sort of doing a thing
that returns results more immediately
what I could do here is just return the
total mouse movement in question and
just use that so that does seem
reasonable and so if I come through here
and say oh yeah like the hot interaction
or just the interaction that's currently
ongoing is my interaction so if I'm
basically saying look yeah if this
interaction is the one in that's that's
actually happening
so I am currently interacting with this
thing then we could just do this right
so like the D Mouse P and the emails can
why those take effect if this is the
current thing that's getting interacted
with right and so that seems pretty good
so all we would have to do there is just
actually stuff the dev ID in there so
inst in here where we're actually doing
the ID and the type just has to be equal
to any any type really we we don't
really even need a different one we can
just make that be sort of a generic
thing so immediate button you know I'll
make another one we don't even really
need it as I guess what I'm saying but
it's just a draggable interaction I
guess you know any draggable so if you
end up interacting with it as a
draggable thing then we just that's all
we needed
and we're you know we're good to go that
should be fine because then we can also
do like a dxdy here sort of a situation
and that allows me to take the min and
Max and use those as ranges right so I
can basically say look the the amount
that we want to move here is gonna be
the max minus the min you know I want
some fidelity of the range so you know I
want like a hundred steps of that so you
know that is how far you should move
when you drag this thing back and forth
right um that seems good to me
reasonable you know
seems good to me and so that allows me
also here I don't know exactly how I
want to edit this particular value in
this case but that's mostly all we're
talking about so here what I can do is
say well you know I want to be able to
do this probably Y could be X plus y I'm
not sure which one I want to do but
something like that so what I want to do
in this case is I want to sort of say
well I want to move this thing but I
want to move it proportional to how big
it already is right so if the thing is
you know if the thing is 10 I want to
move it you know 0.1 each time or
something so I kind of want something
you know that looks like that right and
the problem with doing it that way is
that doesn't properly respect the fact
that it's a continuous thing so because
you end up in a situation where what
you're essentially writing here is an
ordinary differential equation an
equation where the change in the value
is proportional to the value handling it
discretely like this leads to some nasty
edge cases so we may want to say here
handle this as a real OD II might want
to actually happen right okay uh so
anyway let me make this happen just so
we can compile and get this working so
we need to obviously have the UI be
something that's that's known to these
functions and we also need to be able to
let's hear this is interaction we also
need to have this actually be handled so
finish printing these right now remember
we only have immediate button oh god
what have I done
there we go we that's the only thing
that we actually have to so we need to
make sure that we also have draggable so
really as you can see you know we don't
we don't really need two cases because
they're basically the same so in either
case they can just be going through here
and it's you know good enough right so
let's see how that shakes out if I want
to start dragging one of these well I'll
be honest not working particularly well
not great not fabulous but at least it's
highlighted so you know okay not a
stunning victory you know now sending
victory it's true but let's take a look
at what's going on in here and see why
that's happening okay okay so
the UI interaction here should
definitely these should be equivalent
because we're setting them to the same
things far as I know right so when you
do a mouse down on those it should be
setting the hot interactions should get
taken here so I'm not really sure why
that wasn't working
[Music]
hmm Saudi mouse pee may not be set
during that run through I'm not super
certain about that let me just make sure
and then we'll just step through it
after I check that out
so during beginning you I frame know
it's set I mean there it is right so it
sure seems like that should be valid
I'm gonna go ahead and step in there and
then and just see what's going on
because I don't know hopefully it will
be clear and we won't have to puzzle too
much but if it's not that's just the way
of the world
that's just the way the crooked crumbles
all right so let me go ahead and set a
breakpoint there let's just look at
what's going on in that at that piece of
code right so in here we're we're doing
one of these we'll just say okay let's
let's break in one of these anytime I'm
dragging I should hit that so I am
hitting it oh did the same thing you
never learned you never do learn do you
as I said before and as I had to well I
guess I predicted it before so I didn't
actually have to debug to find it but it
you know it's still not really a valid
excuse we need to say whether edits
occurred because otherwise nobody in the
outside code will know that they need to
update what they're doing so technically
this should always look like this right
we should always set edit occurred after
we do something where we where that the
edit system should respond you know
anyone on the outside who needs to do
work should respond I so we've got that
working now and we can go ahead and see
if this happened yeah so that's fine all
right so now I can i can drag left to
right and i can drag up and down so
that's good so i should be able to set
these percents pretty easily now and i
need to cap you know make sure those
things stay within bounds
i'm not sure why it's doing like a mod
style thing there oh i know why because
these are stored in a way that
automatically clamp
that's why this also looks like it's
working just fine so I think we're
pretty much good to go
that's that's all the things we actually
needed um so yeah not really very
difficult right pretty basic stuff
nothing too hard there and now
everything is properly being ended again
the undo stream is getting spammed left
and right so let's let's do one thing
real quick let's go into the WI system
and I just want to put in the clamping
there so I want to do like clamp and I
want to do min x max X there and I want
to do a clamp here as well mmm so oh
whoops
and again I just want to do that clamp
because since we are passing them in and
max in we might as well just do that
work for the user because everyone
obviously who hasn't been and Max is
gonna want us to clamp for them
that's just unsurprising right so that
way we can't go below one and we can't
go I'm sorry can't go above one I can't
go below - right so that just allows us
to edit that you know easily which is
what I want okay
so that's simple no issues there
this one doesn't take a minute max so it
doesn't clamp we could take a minute max
if we wanted to I don't know whether we
want to or not
that's really up to us so that's all
simple pretty simple and straightforward
and I again want to just underscore the
spamming part that's probably what we
should go look at next and then we'll go
look at the beautification aspect of it
just to try and make things less ugly
right so here I am wiggling this all
around right and now if I want to undo
that what you can see is I've got to
undo like the whole thing right and it's
just like that's not what that is right
when I do an operation like that I want
to have some way of bulking those up so
let's go upgrade that system a little
bit before we go on to the
beautification beautification so what we
want to do here is well as a couple
things you want to do here but what we
want to do here is we want to make sure
that we have a more robust way of
tracking these things write these
in-game edits and so what I'd like to do
is change the way we're getting those to
be a little bit more to be a little bit
saucy err right so when we do one of
these edit operations what I want to do
instead of allocate editor edit here I
want to do like a find editor edit
really right so I want to do something
more like this
something like this or you know get or
create/edit in progress you know like
because I want to essentially I want to
essentially look to see if I have one of
something and then if I do I will use it
right uh so how I do that exactly is its
gonna change a little bit the way that
this stuff works so first of all this is
gonna want to be more down here right so
this is gonna be a regular function now
that just operates directly and this is
going to be the function that actually
does the thump through okay so well
thunk through on that in some way and
then we'll we'll use this that that in
game end it to work so the problem that
will run into immediately is that how
edits are merged will have a lot to do
with what they're storing and so what we
need to do is we need to do more of a
provisional push where we say look this
is the information that we are gonna
need to be true can you get us something
that has that which means this isn't
really gonna be how we're gonna want to
do it not exactly what we're gonna want
to do here is like say this is what
we're looking for
this is our match if you will and so
when we set the match we would set like
the type and the asset index and the
align point index because those are the
things that actually matter right so
what we want to do here is say okay like
let's put those things in place
what's this called so we wanted to say
alright get us you know get me one of
those things and I'm gonna pass you the
match type for that and I want you to
return me one that I can use you know I
mean um to me so we're gonna need to use
something like that right that's you
know we're gonna need to do something
like that and I'm not sure exactly how
I'd do it
I guess one way I could do it too is I
could do it like this the align point
edit where I do the match right I could
do it more like this sort of a thing so
I just pass an abstract match sort of
type here something like that if that
gets used in the matching and off we go
that seems plausible so you know in
there if if it works if it's a new one
it'll just assign whatever this thing is
to it maybe something like that
I don't know right so it'd be something
like this and
[Music]
maybe like this sort of thing right so
we'd say okay here's the initial value
that we would have saved
we'll give you that will then ask you to
give us back either one that exists or
one that doesn't exist if it doesn't
exist I'm assuming you will set it right
and then from there I'm going to change
make the change and store the new value
seem fair maybe I don't know
does it maybe it doesn't but I think
that's good like I think that's roughly
what we want to do and so in here what I
want to do is I want to say all right
this will take a void star that's like
here's the match data to use so when we
come through and do the getter
create/edit in progress we want to look
through all of the things that we
currently have in progress which will be
this stuff here right and we want to see
if we can find one that matches so we
want to do like in game edit test equals
in progress sentinel next and i want to
say this can't be equal to this because
it's a sentinel based list so we have to
go until we hit the sense of all right
so that would look over all of the
things we want to test and then what we
need to do is look in there and see are
the align points the same so I mean that
unfortunately is a case based thing
right we can't we don't want to check
the change part we just want to check
these two so it's actually specific to
the type so the align point editor here
right we have to say like
first of all if the test type equals the
type then we can check otherwise we
can't check it all and then what we do
is we say well this is the only one
we've got
so we can't we can't match anything else
you know what I might not do that I
might say that anything else doesn't get
merged because we only want to merge
things that we actually know merge right
so if we were going to edit this a line
point in the current in-progress edits
then what we want to do is say look is
it the same asset and align point index
if it is then it's a match so then what
I would on all so I guess what I want to
do is have a way of getting out of this
loop right so I would say if the match
version and in this case again I kind of
know what this type is now because
you've given me the match version of it
you know I might say let's be piggy er
there let's actually do that let's just
do that
that seems reasonable um and that way we
could just say okay you know this is
in-game edit
there's the match and this this will do
that this will set the whole thing that
seems better it's not the cleanest thing
in the world but it's alright so I'll do
that we'll look at that one and if it
works we'll will assign it other you
know it this will just do exactly what
it was doing for everything will work
essentially the same and we probably
don't need this cast anymore either cuz
you know we're we're just not that
specific about it now so we probably can
just do this like that so I'm I'm and
then we don't need this and this seems
better so there we go we'll look for the
match
assuming that we find the match meaning
if a line point edit a set index equals
[Music]
test the line point at it that's it
index and of the align point index close
test light index index I'm sorry edit
we're good and we're good to go
so when we come down to the bottom here
what we need to do is say like look if
we didn't find anything and maybe found
is the wrong word here maybe found
should just be results right because
it's what we're gonna return so what we
want to do is say look if you found a
result we can just return it because
we're good to go
but if we didn't find a result then what
we need to do is say give me a new one
right which is this code right here and
I want to be the type that they were
asking to try and match when we actually
get it back you know inside here right
when it does this push first and it sets
the result type and so on that's not
constructive we don't really want that
anymore because that allocate editor
edit actually you know I I don't must
say let's just get rid of this I don't
know that I want this at all so I'm just
gonna pull this down here like that and
I must say this goes away and really
what we're gonna do now instead is we're
gonna put this onto the in progress sack
and we're gonna when we do this push let
me get back the results there we're
going to romp over the allocated memory
that we got and just set it equal to
what they gave us because we're gonna
assume that's what they wanted to start
with right so that allows us to stack up
those in progress edits I and anytime
you're gonna do the same operation it'll
just use one that already exists right
so I mean once we get to once we have
that down then what we need to do is
actually have some way of committing
these back right so when we do editor
interact what we want to do is say okay
any time the mouse goes up and we're
going to clear an interaction we
probably want that to be a more specific
thing that happens right so that's like
an end so this is like an end
interaction state and what I want to do
here is say that these are just end
these are interaction
things does that make sense if the mouse
goes up that's when it ends whatever the
interaction is that we were doing and
then that can come down here so that
anyone inside here who wants to say that
this was an interaction ending thing can
just do that right and so here when we
do tech asset we can see that that would
do it as well
I think this only wants to happen in
here probably so those all want to do
interaction ends when we get to that
point right then what I can do is say
all right when we go to end an
interaction all in progress things move
on to the undo stack right so everything
gets pushed on as an undo now the
interesting thing about that right is
that there could have been multiple
changes in that in progress Sentinel
right now we know that can never really
happen but if we were to make that
happen what we want to do and I'm going
to put to do for this right allow chains
of undos so a single undo can represent
many undos when we get to that point
this is the place where we would do it
we would take the whole chain and just
put it on to the undo stack as one
single entry so we can do that we just
don't we don't need to do it now it's
not really gonna make it life any harder
for us really so we can just do that as
the need arises but in the meantime what
we
we're doing is we'd be saying while you
know while whatever the in progress
Sentinel list is while it's not empty we
would just do a push first pop first
right where we say take whatever
whatever you got on that in progress
sense and I'll put it on the undo
Sentinel okay so again we just what we
basically do there's we created like a
holding cell right for all of our
changes so that we could know how that
got written as text so that our changes
would buffer in there and we could
coalesce them right we could combine
them together and so then what we want
to do is move those off of that any time
we finish an interaction because that
means all of the changes that happen
during that drag operation or whatever
else is happening that needs to now get
retired as an actual valid undo change
that we want to record let me see what
else we got here
that's just oh whoops
still still wrong no no no no this is
just always that it's not that's not the
type we're talking about Lili use of
this type so especially yes that doesn't
need to be there anymore and this is not
the UI sorry my bad
that's just the editor
all right so you know that was unhappy
about this I know why as well that needs
to be initialized again you notice how
annoying it is to have to have clear to
not have clear to zero
anything that's clear to zero just
always works and anything that's not is
just waiting to be an initialized
variable problem and that's a lot of
times where you get people who really
like constructor system is those are
really not necessary if clear to zero
just works but there's a couple things
where it doesn't and it's unfortunate
you you know I almost don't want to use
those kinds of methods specifically
because of that alright so let's see
here so let's say I undo back and let's
see if this works so I'm dragging this
all around now right
and then I'm dragging this all around
now and then I'm dragging this all
around now so the first thing that
should happen is that should undo it
does now the next thing happens is this
should undo and it did and now we should
undo this back to ya amber back to
another um so that all looks pretty good
to me like that seems like that's
operating pretty faithfully and you know
we can we can do all of our stuff here
we can toggle things we can change the
sizes we can redo stuff we can undo
stuff so that feeling pretty good I mean
that interface is pretty solid now I
don't know how much time I have left
probably about a half an hour do I want
to say that's probably about right I'm
gonna go ahead and yeah I'm gonna I'm
gonna go ahead and say I've got
something like that and I'm gonna I'm
just gonna take that time to pretty it
up right I just wanna I'm just gonna
spend some time putting up
maybe if I also have time I'm gonna make
these things properly snap to the upper
corner of the screen because they're
annoying me that they're hanging around
like this and it's just it's annoying
right it's it's it's super not not what
I want super not what I want is like it
is a new thing and there is one other
aspect of this system that we have to
consider at some point and again like I
said I avoided doing anything with it
because I'm not really sure what I want
to do but we need some argument excuse
metaphor paradigm for what is supposed
to happen with the debug UI when it
coexist with this UI like I said I don't
really want them unified completely
because the debug UI stuff should kind
of compile out entirely probably whereas
this will always be available for people
who want to import art into the game
even end-users I think and so I want to
say that the best thing to do there is
gonna be to have some sort of a modal
thing that says if you're in editor mode
the debug UI just turns itself off or
something like I just I don't want them
getting involved
I want the debug UI to stay completely
separate so we'll see what we can do
about that
you know we'll see by the way while
we're on the subject of this I do want
to know what the story is with that
baseline stuff is is it just a case of
like this going the wrong way
like when we call get baseline was that
just going the wrong way or something
like it's just supposed to be plus
because we used to be we just have wide
going the other direction Juno I'm
saying like is it just is it just a case
of actually everything's fine
and when we switched the order of those
coordinates we never fixed that you know
so it should just be something like this
you know and I don't know I like I have
no idea I'm just wondering if that has
something to do with it no it definitely
doesn't okay so that looks like not it I
do want to know then - about the text
out function so in here you know how
does that do its adjustment because you
know when you do the what it's actually
drawing the text right it doesn't a
bitmap offset and it's got like an
addicts in an @y and stuff like that so
when it does that I'm wondering how it's
computing the offset of the actual you
know the glyphs themselves to figure out
like how they should be aligned on the
like you know on the off of the baseline
and I'll be honest I I don't see that
information here which is a little bit
strange because you need to know how far
up it is in order to make that
determination so I'm guessing that what
was happening is everyone was aligned to
the top when we originally made the
fonts because pixels were going down and
then when we switched to having an
upside down
maybe we just never did the revert like
the actual realignment of it maybe it's
a bit of a stretch you know I'm reaching
a little on that I don't mind telling
you but it seems likely so you can see
here we've got a glyph very no
information in here about alignment so
I'm assuming that what actually is
happening there is you have to back up
to the baseline and then come down right
you know that that's what I've seen so I
would guess that really what we're
seeing here is the fact that the the
actual alignment of this thing when we
do you know when when we're actually
doing this bit mombasa I think this
actually has to have baked into the why
sort of a like a baseline alignment for
lack of a better term so what do we need
to do is it would need to actually take
whatever the dimension of the thing was
right it would need to take this and say
I need to go I need to go that far I'm
at the bottom I need to go to the top
and then back that however big the
character was to align it to the top so
this at Y needs to be like plus whatever
the total height is so ascender plus d
sender which i assume is baseline like
that kind of thing I don't remember what
was happening in there
[Music]
let's get starting baseline why what
does that do
so that's the center right I don't know
if a sender height is the right thing
there um I'm not sure because it's been
a long time so we've looked at this
stuff
um but either or that's okay you know we
can fool around with it and figure out
what we actually encoded there I'm gonna
go ahead and say it's something like
that like that's roughly what's going on
here if not you know exactly what's
going on here so it's getting a little
closer not quite right
and I guess one thing is the bitmap
scale here would also come into place so
the ascender height you know like this
also would have to multiply these right
but that is I think set to one at the
moment so that ain't gonna help us cuz
that we would only have errors there if
we yeah if we if we did it backwards so
you know looking at that it's like that
aligns everything at the top in a weird
way so it's not quite that so what what
could be causing those just the symbols
to be lowered like that I don't quite
get
I mean maybe we need both of these
still not quite right there
but you can see how those are now more
correct right and these are now more
incorrect it's very curious so I think
we're on the right truck we just it's
mainly just a problem of not really
remembering exactly how we bake these
down I probably should go look just to
see how we were actually encoding them
in fact I could just do that so here's
you know our sender D sender height
stuff let me take a look at how we were
actually pulling these things out so
yeah like you know here's us getting the
bounding box of the thing
oh my
oh how interesting
Wow so we really got saucy here you know
I'm glad I looked because I never would
have guessed that that was that's some
pretty fancy footwork there my friends
yeah Wow okay well we didn't we didn't
pull any punches on that one so
effectively what we did there is we said
yeah let's just bake how that glyph gets
aligned to the baseline into the align
percentage of the bitmap because why not
right so the align percentage which is
going to offset the thing is going to
offset it by this value problem is this
alignment was probably going the wrong
direction that'd be my guess
right
that is kind crazy
so there's one of two things could have
happened thing number one is that we we
just never fixed that for fonts when we
were messing with our coordinate systems
and stuff and so it was always wrong
another is that it actually is right and
I'll go through the math here and try to
determine whether it is or not so
that'll be the way we'll figure that out
but the other way is that actually the
math was right for this and this should
be correct but what happened was when we
took and when we did our import there's
like a bug in this code that makes the
align percentages not work properly or
something like this right
and you know it looks like they'd be
fine because it certainly looks like
it's getting undressed there let's take
a quick look at it shall we
so let's go into handmade Hero data and
let's just ask for a dump of the test
fonts and let's just make sure they've
got some same values that right this
will do that yeah and I'll load that up
in the tab view let's see
and so those look you know that unless
we did something really wrong looks okay
look tiny
you know but I could I could be
convinced those from right you know I'm
not really and say those are those got
corrupted yet the fact that they're all
pretty low you know doesn't necessarily
seem great but you know it's sixty one
half dozen together so that could be one
problem if I do look at set a line point
let me go in there
if I do look at set a line point there
you know it doesn't look like there's
that much room for error so that that
seems like it's probably working okay so
I think let's I'm gonna say it's a it's
hard to say where to look first but I'm
gonna say let's start with the math of
this like I just want to look at this
situation so we're starting by saying
all right we took and let me let's let's
pop over the blackboard just so like we
can draw these out and have some idea of
like where they actually are
so looking at this here we've got a
couple different things
we drew a bitmap right and this bitmap
is not bottom-up right it's top-down so
when we're actually specifying this
thing you know I don't know do we flip
it here we're using this fonts from
windows path and so you can see here we
we kind of we kind of work from the top
down
it's a weird code dude
so both of them go from the top down
but why
right I mean there's no reason for them
to go from they I mean not from the top
down from they all go backwards so they
all start at the end of the image and go
backwards but there's no reason for them
to do that is there it's like it was
gonna flip them around but then it
doesn't flip them around
I don't get it so I don't know why
that's doing that does not need to do
that I don't think
I don't I don't understand that very
well at all so you can see here right
this intentionally leaves a one pixel
apron and it starts writing at the last
row and it's gonna write backwards this
one starts also at the last row it moves
back by the min X but I by the min Y but
I'm not sure what the point of that is
really but I guess it's just saying
don't go that many up so I I got nothing
I mean that's just crazy I have no idea
what's going on here this code is kind
of super crappy and nuts it's in the
test asset builder so you know there is
that but anyway when we go through these
yeah I don't that's just bizarre so
that's gonna make it a little harder to
work through this because we don't
really know why it's doing that and that
could affect this construction which is
not my favorite thing but let's look at
what these actually refer it to so bound
height here must be something that's
discussed further up so here we have the
the height that I guess the font would
say that this character is right so the
font says you know it's this big we
asked it for the size and it comes back
with that so bound height is like how
big that text is I think that's probably
going to be usually tight but maybe not
right so the fact that we're checking to
see what the stuff is here suggests that
it's not that tight actually
because otherwise why would we have had
to do that like we wouldn't have had to
have done that right so the bound height
is probably gonna be something right
like if we imagine like here's a capital
a the bound height is probably gonna be
something like that where it's like you
know it's a little bit much I'm just
guessing the TM descent is how far the
descenders go so that's like this
distance right you imagine if there is
like one of these it would actually be
you know like that distance right but
I'm just saying like that's the part
below the line so we're taking whatever
the boundaries were subtracting off the
descent so that's that value there is
effectively we've now got this this is
our you know at the moment our and we'll
call that B let's say so that's B so
we're taking our max Y which is the
highest value that we've seen and we're
subtracting B from from I'm sorry
no we're yeah we're subtracting B from
it right
and so we're just fry I guess that a
line point is just trying to figure out
if we were here and we needed to go up
to where we would start where would that
be it's a pretty tortured way to do that
but I can sort of see why and so max why
is the maximum value that we could have
achieved and that's where we want to
start our drawing so normally we would
go to that max Y okay so I'm starting to
see what the problem is here - if we're
assuming that you can align outside of
the zero to one range which this could
definitely do because there's no reason
why these have to be constrained by this
right so you could have a negative value
that presumably is quite a bit more than
the height value so you could end up
with negative larger than 1 or negative
something like negative done that'd be
there you could end up with less than 0
and we don't currently allow that
right um so if we wanted to make that
aligned percentage be able to properly
handle the fonts that looks like
actually the problem so that value might
be correct and it may have we may have
actually done the flip around because it
kind of looks like it is doing that in
there but I think the reason that we're
actually getting those is actually just
because it might be requiring us to
encode them better which we could do if
we wanted to do that all we would have
to do here is just allow for things to
be offset so you know what do we want
the range to be right like what do we
want that mapping to be you know because
it's kind of up to us so when we do this
P percent here and we multiply this out
by the u16 max what we want to do is
just precondition this value really you
know what I mean so we want it to be in
the zero to one range and so what we
want to do is say whatever it is let's
do a clamp zero one map two range on it
and give it a minimum acts right so
we'll say in here that we've got some
min and Max whatever we want them to be
so you know okay you can do up to a
negative two to two or something right
like we support you know a wider gamut
there of percentages that are allowed
and then when this thing comes out right
so when we do clamps are two one map to
range we just say look put this thing in
between there and give me back a zero to
one value that actually works when we
then create this thing we know we just
need to start at negative two and go
out by however much that percentage
gives us to re spread out to the entire
range of the thing right so we can do
that if we now run the program we should
get nuts no stuff right because it's not
encoded that way on import but what we
then can do is say well alright you know
now let's re-imported Atta that we had
before
so you know here we've got all these
tests hhas right and so if I want to
derp the v-0 directory there and I want
to bring all of these back in in a bulk
import right I can delete all of my hhas
in question here including the text
files and then I can just update those
so do a rewrite v-0 intro art HHA and
each of these I can just do theirs test
one two
three antis fonts and also I guess I
should have put the v2 on this um so
yeah that was a crazy one but you know
you notice it was exactly correct so
yeah there you go
debugging is debugging if you go find
the problem
turns out fix is usually easy so let's
make a local and let's let this Rhian
port but that was good so we've got that
bug solved and that was our fault with
the HHA upgrade we did not properly
account for some of the uses of that and
it turns out was pretty simple for us to
do so so we just did now this stuff is
more properly aligned I think it
definitely looks like it is so the
beautification pass would be much easier
now and now these are all proper so
that's good well let's go to a brief Q&amp;A
there and and then we should be able to
next stream will do the beautification
and get that window editing window
looking nice
what does pound pound mean I looked it
up but I don't think understand what
it's use is is it supposed to link
different variables into one variable so
pound pound is he's actually it's only
available in preprocessor macro
expansion and so that's why if you
haven't seen it or aren't familiar with
it that's probably why it doesn't it's
not actually in the C++ grammar for a
code it's only in the preprocessor uh
and so when you see that pound pound
operator what that's actually saying is
you know normally I've got something
like here's my macro and I've got a and
B right and the way that the macro
preprocessor works is when it gets to
parameters it then looks inside the text
that's coming for the macro expansion so
the expansion of the macro this is the
expansion here right it's gonna look at
that and it's gonna say anytime I see a
recognizable token so in the traditional
C sense of the word token so an
identifier is a letter and then some
series of letters and numbers with
underscores right anytime I can pluck
out a token I will look back to see if
that token matches one of the named
parameters and if it is I will
substitute in the result so if I was to
do this and then I typed this okay what
I would expect to see as the result in
the resulting code is this okay because
as it expands this it looks at the a and
says well it's what it looks this
essentially goes let me read the
expansion first token is this the
expansion does that match grammar no a
does that match parameter yes what was
the value of it okay put it in place
right does this match memory yes what
was the value of it put it in place okay
the problem is it means that if your
goal for this was to produce that
you can't do it because typing that
makes it look at the token as if it were
a B and then it can't find either of
those here so it just does that and
that's not what you wanted so this
operator actually what it does is
nothing it actually does nothing but the
key is you needed some way to have
nothing there so that it could see the
two different tokens so what it actually
does is it just serves as a noting that
you can insert between two things so
that can recognize them so now what
happens is it goes what's the first
token this is the expansion okay put
that in the output it doesn't match
anything what's the next token a what
does that match this put the value there
so it does that right what's the next
thing pound pound what does that
evaluate to nothing so we're still right
here and ready to go what does the next
token equal B what's that this okay
output the two and so that's how you get
the 12 right so that's really all it is
is nothing but sometimes especially when
you're dealing with text processing
nothing is very important because then
nothing is what allows you to glue those
things together that's why it's called
the paste operator glues things together
but it doesn't actually do anything it
that's not it the operator isn't
actually doing that I guess is where I
would say it what the operator can
really call the nothing operator if
that's what you want cuz that's what it
does it just so happens that nothing is
exactly what you need hopefully that
helps answer the question skin pop I've
been trying to implement the wok system
from a recent talk the talk made the
point that shrinking the wok edges
trivial I've made it that far in my own
code but I haven't been able to figure
out how to do the shrinking without
testing all edges against all segments
of the wok edge that approach doesn't
scale well so I was wondering if you
could say a few words about how you did
it assuming you had another approach so
let me just make sure I understand
what you're saying you tried testing all
edges against the segments of the walk
edge no that's that's correct
so I guess what I would say is know that
you're doing the right thing
the only thing I would say is you have
to implement it in a way that does scale
well so let me let me give you a real
quick it's just really off topic here
but I'll try to give you the idea so
what you need is a fundamental operator
on the grid on the walk rid right so
I've got the grid and what you need is a
fundamental operator that says I have an
edge apply the edge to the grid if you
will right and so if this is my edge
then I have some fundamental operator
which rasterizes that edge effectively
into the points of the grid that would
be affected by it
makes sense because you know it's like
this or something so you're doing the
right thing I think but I guess I would
just say you might be doing it in
slightly the wrong way instead of
testing all of the edges in your system
versus the walk edge you need to think
of it more as a spatial query that can
very easily determine like you know much
more easily than checking all of these
edges which ones fall within the
knockout region of that of that walk
edge right
so you don't want to be testing like you
should never be testing this edge
against this because it's simply not in
the spatial domain so you want to write
all of your code to only iterate over
the possible poles that could be you
know involve an edge it's exactly
analogous to anything else you might do
in a game where you have a large play
field and you're doing like collision
detection and stuff you only do it on
the local on the things that are local
to that and you usually have a way of
fast lookup right you have a way of
doing fast access to your - like buckets
that only contain things in a in a local
space and you need to do that here as
well does that help
since there's just hi do you know how to
rotate a font do you use SVG or anything
so no we don't use SVG front-running
because on handmade here we don't use
libraries so we just directly go to
win32 and we get the font that way
however one time on Shawn's birthday I
did do a demonstration of how to use STD
TrueType so there is if 0 dot code that
shows how you would call this to be true
type but we don't use it at the moment
um as far as how to rotate a font so I
guess what I would say is we do all of
our rotation in real time because
obviously that thing that's very easy to
do if you already have a renderer that
rotates sprites you could just rotate if
I wanted to rotate a font I would just
rotate it when I go to render it I
wouldn't pre-rotate the font so if
you're actually talking about how do i
pre rotate the font and like save it out
as a font that has been rotated which I
can't say sounds like a good idea but
let's say you were going to do that then
what you're gonna have to do is you're
gonna have
to either leverage the underlying
library you're using to make the font if
you have one to ask it to rasterize it
originally in that angle which for
example even though we're not using any
libraries we are calling windows to get
the font and it happens to have a thing
that allows you to set the angle of a
font for rasterization I if I remember
correctly so you could actually do that
in some sense it's more powerful to not
use a library to rasterize your font
than to use one because windows if
you're getting the font from that
directly it actually is in a sense a
giant library it just so happens that
almost all of it is useless for games
right but it is a giant library that you
have there and you can use so in some
sense not using true type s to be true
type it's actually a benefit because if
you go through Windows I think it does
have two billion clips up the flap for
you if you wanted that I don't know if
that's you're asking um
OpenType so more complete font i was i
sv true that's like a one header you
know it's supposed to be small right
suppose we compact easy to use to in
your project um more complex libraries
like open type or free type or whatever
it's called that might have it to the
ability to tilt I don't know but I don't
think a subi TrueType does because it's
kind of outside the scope of what su
btrim I was down to do so if you only
have access to say something like s to
be true type which rasterizes the fonts
um and you need them to be rasterized
rotated then you've got two options one
you can go edit SD be true type to
rotate the curves
prior to rasterizing them okay that's a
mod has to be true type not particularly
hard when probably but it is a mod two
you could write a true type font loader
that loads a true type font rotates all
the curves and writes it out as a new
font then pass a test to be true type
that would work too or
no pain let su be TrueType or whatever
library using rasterize the flop
right-side up and then you write
something like we have on handmade hero
when we wrote our software rasterizer
that takes a rectangle and can rotate
the rectangle call that into an
off-screen bitmap we grab the rectangle
and save it out I mean those are options
I would however asked again are you sure
that you want to actually rotate the
font and not actually just take the
output of the font as unrotated and
rotate it at runtime you know be sure
you actually want what you want before
you go too far down one of those one of
those roads right so all right let's
wrap it up
okay thank you everybody for joining up
sort of handmade here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along series at
home you can always peer to the game at
handmade hero org and it comes to source
code so you can play around with it if
you're interested in learning engine
programming and you want to follow what
we're doing on this series that's a good
way to do it I will be back here for
another Krampus loft surprise stream
probably tomorrow let's be honest
there's going to be a lot of streams
this month and next month so hope to see
you back here for that surprise I can't
promise when it's going to be but it'll
be sometime soon until then have fun
programming I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody