okay so this today I wanted to do and as
you could see from the previous session
I kind of wanted to do stuff that was a
little bit more experimental compared to
last year meaning I wanted to try some
new kinds of sessions so like you know
the session on muscular and and physical
problems related to programming I see
not the kind of thing that you would
normally necessarily talk about at a
programming conference but I think
really important to talk about and you
know that was that was a fabulous
session so I think that was exactly the
right thing the other sort of stuff that
I wanted to try we're getting some sort
of discussion oriented things into the
you know sort of the the way that the
handmade con format works and so what I
wanted to do with this session was
there's sort of this this I don't want
to say that it's like a thing we do as
programmers but there's a sort of a way
that problems get presented when you are
talking about them and you know
presenting them to other programmers
it's usually you present them after
they've already been solved so for
example if you went to look at
somebody's blog post on something or
somebody does or write-up or a
presentation at a conference typically
what happens is they're like okay here's
the problem as you know we solved it
here's how we solved it and sometimes
they give you like a little bit of
background of like here's you know sort
of what did work what didn't work kind
of stuff but rarely do you actually sort
of go back to look at what was the
actual process by which the programming
happened that got to this solution and
the reason I think this is really
important is because not all programmers
in their career depending on where
they're at have had the experience of
having to tackle a completely new
problem meaning not just something
that's slightly different from what
people have done before but really
something that's completely different
from anything anyone's done before and
having to go through this process of
figuring out what the problem even is
and then solving it and this is one of
the most rewarding parts of programming
in in my experience when you do get to
have that experience of pushing ahead
somewhere where people haven't really
explored and it's a lot that process is
a lot less about sort of the
perfecting of something and a lot more
about just the like exploration and
figuring out stage and like putting all
of the pieces together so what I want to
do with this session is take a look back
at something where this happened in
history which is sort of the the advent
of texture mapping real-time 3d texture
mapping in games and real-time 3d
texture mapping now we sort of take for
granted because a graphics processing
unit in your computer will do it for you
right it's kind of like a purpose-built
thing that does this there's tons and
tons of infrastructure there for you and
there's really no question that nowadays
you know unless you're doing something
very specific you're never really going
to have an encounter with this part of
the code directly but when games were
still running entirely just on a CPU
they were you know mostly 2d at the time
and they're making the leap to 3d one of
the things that nobody really knew how
to do was to actually do texture mapping
fast enough in games or even really what
texture mapping in games would mean
because again all of this stuff was
happening kind of way back and you know
that this is early 90s kind of stuff
when you didn't have an Internet full of
information at your fingertips where you
could just search for texture mapping or
what that is or what all the you know
tutorials on it you literally had
nothing to go on but maybe you're you
know colleges research library or
something like this can we ask how many
people were at high school or after in
the 90s in 1995 how many but most people
are younger than that yes so so what I
wanted to do here was sort of gather
some of the folks who actually did this
kind of work and we're part of the
process of the game industry sort of
figuring out how to do this stuff
getting it into commercial games and you
know getting the process to the point
where it produced like good visual
results at speeds that you could run on
what as we're going to kind of go over
we're very very slow machines compared
to the kind that we have today so with
that please welcome Chris Greene Sean
Barrett John miles and Chris hacker
so Chris I'll start with you because
you've actually made some slides to this
which I think I made these at 8 a.m.
this morning Ellen you are the only
person who's ever brought slides too so
why don't you just get a story by giving
us sort of a little bit of information
about like what where what was your
first encounter with this or what was
the situation like the the period in
time when this sort of work sort of
first started happening from your
perspective so so actually the first
time I tried to get something like
texture my working I was working at a
company it doesn't exist anymore called
sublogic which was the flight simulator
company I did the a couple of mica
flights and letters and we wanted to get
a little more exciting stuff on the
screen we just tried a couple approaches
and the first thing I did I did this
really bad texture wrapper that involved
starting a rectangle and recursively
subdividing down to the pixel level in
the code and then output a 1 or 0 okay
and I managed to get a smiley face on a
billboard at a very slow framerate to
tell us a little bit about what so a
flight simulator at that time though
yeah what did it look like before the
texture - oh so this is I guess maybe
the second generation of the sub lot
excess Microsoft Flight Simulator where
we switched from wire framed everything
actually being solid colored and we had
16 different colors in the environment
and you know you know hundreds of
polygons so sometimes you know I think
our I think our plane model you know we
had an exterior plane you could look at
I think it I think it was over I think
was over a hundred polygons and we
worked hard to get it to that size and
so largely what you saw
there's no guru chaining large you saw
just a lot of big blank rings and we
would put vector graphics on the
delivery there's a lot of lines and
markings to CT something and randomness
in color it didn't look anything like
flying over landscape does and
particularly just taking off airports
are full full signs and stuff like
that's actually we wanted that sign
something more important that was
completely impractical it didn't ever
ship that I tried another one I was
trying to get trees or something on the
horizon and I guess I'll go way in the
weeds here this is on the Amigo which
had a hardware lined drawer and the way
that hardware lined drawer worked is it
had a pattern register that was you know
to do sniffles or dashing and so what I
did was I I set up a line to draw on the
horizon and I would stuff 16 bits of
texture of binary texture into the
pattern register and output like a line
so basically I was running as - I was
mapping it this way he's in a line
drawing hardware and the pattern
register - a little more practical if I
understand correctly so using the
hardware line drawing in the Amiga yeah
had a number of custom chips over there
is a glitter component which was used
for kind of moving bits around I guess
it could it could do like a resin hammer
that it was cycle through through every
pixel so basically stuff fits into that
and have them show up in Flint okay so
essentially what you do is just draw a
series of lines with the pattern and the
pattern register and that was actually
fast enough but the problem I had was
actually getting the lines - I probably
could make it work now okay but there
wouldn't be much to used to make it work
but I couldn't get the lines to fill the
space okay gaps okay so this was on the
Amiga and you were looking at this sort
of thing and this is generally the
company in general is looking at this
and going we need to figure out ways to
get more visual detail because that
that's the genesis of the why we want to
try and do this yes particularly
particularly landscapes in science now
why did you did anyone there know what
texture mapping was because there is
research around yeah there's good can
you give us a little thing about the the
relationship I don't think we ever used
the word texture mapping okay we didn't
ruin again we didn't really understand
it the way that I guess a lot of
graphics particularly there were a lot
of ways that may be thicker there we did
the 3d math and transformations and the
precision that actually made texture
mapping not even if you had a texture
map again we've been hard to fit into
the pipeline because
oh there's a lot of old fixed-point
tricks and I guess I could describe it
as by the time we have a polygon we
don't actually know it's 3d coordinates
and we can't get them back okay because
if you're trying to fit everything in
eight or sixteen bits of precision once
we need a three transform after you've
subtracted the origin you can multiply
or shift the result by any old number
you want and it's still the same point
on the screen right but it's not
invertible back to what it was before
okay and so our point transform is
always doing that it's always shifting
stuff into in a certain size so we
couldn't actually I couldn't figure how
to clip it or do anything like that
because it was kind of impossible so
basically what you're saying is that
when you were do cuz I mean I guess the
other point we should this is sort of
the discovery of like the floating point
math sort of thing is after this point
in time yeah I would I mean and this
offers originally developed for so the
amiga even though the amiga is 16-bit
yes not only doing that I mean we're
getting the amiga was amazing because we
had a multiply instruction instead of a
giant macro that goes up for four pages
to multiply two numbers is the Bruce
artwork who ran yeah like maybe was so
far ahead like you guys were using
quaternions before anyone even knew it
Bruce artworks flight simulator book
from yeah there's a classic old school
would all have you wrote a book guys
it's kind of it was a full event down
there my computer graphics displays talk
about the Apple and forgive me on
commercial point simulators they'd
worked on and kind of have a lot of
esoteric things at the time we used to
joke about the quaternion chapter on
there because like it was the most
impractical useless piece of why did you
put this in there I do understand it why
you know oh it takes more multiplies to
transport by that while you do that
versus penned a long time multiplying by
a three by three matrix already okay so
let me pause for a second there so what
year is this this would be like
okay let me see so 88 let me ask John
so in 88 you're at origin yeah when just
so I make sure I kind of oppose it
am I the youngest person on this panel
besides you because that's never
happened to me I'm 46 yes at what point
just so I can at what point did origins
start thinking about 3d graphic stuff so
I have that because obviously doing much
of ultima stuff was there there was no
3d content and the ultimate is at that
at that point this I was I would have
been working on Altimas 5 transitioning
into Ultima 6 we were finally leaving
the Apple 2 behind there was a lot of
wailing and gnashing of teeth about that
but we got over it the the first the
first appearance of 3d kind of happened
shortly after Chris Roberts showed up
looking for a looking for someone to
publish a 2d role-playing game that he
was working on oh is this a game that
ever got published no that this was a
game called times of lore it's not a
very well known game but it was it was
kind of a roguelike
okay 2d 2d platformer almost but Chris
really wanted to do a 3d game and he
ended up he ended up pitching Wing
Commander at the execs at origin and no
one really believed it could be done
because you know something like that
almost requires texture mapping and can
you can you give a little bit of a
background for people who didn't see the
original Wing Commander what that
technology was cuz I remember it well we
Wing Commander was kind of an
interesting technological problem
because it wasn't actually it looks it
looks like it was texture mapped it
looks like a you know a game where
you're flying around and you know fully
rotated and
Aled and oriented bitmapped ships and
shooting at other ships you know that
look the same way but at the time the I
think a 386 machine was the latest and
greatest thing on the market
I remember Chris's Compact 386 20
machine I think he paid like fifteen
thousand dollars for that if I remember
right basically you know there goes half
these royalties from his last game but
but you didn't have you know you did
have a multiply instruction but you
didn't have much more than that and you
had really slow main memory and you also
more important you had a bunch of people
who really didn't know what they were
doing so Chris ended up writing I think
I think it was around fourteen thousand
lines of x86 assembly code to do what's
called a forward transform mapper which
which works completely differently from
anything that we've later come to
understand its texture mapping but as
you know conceptually it's another way
to get to the same it's another road to
get to the same destination
texture mapping starts with you know do
you need do you want the pen no well
maybe later the the idea is you maps you
map pixels on the screen back to source
pixels in your texture that's what
everybody tends to think of it's texture
mapping and that's that's what you might
call inverse mapping forward mapping has
some advantages in that you're stepping
through each you know basically
horizontal line in your source artwork
and figuring out where it goes on the
screen so this ends up being faster for
shapes that have a lot of transparency
because you don't spend a lot of time
jumping around pixels that you're not
drawing but it but it turned it
inevitably turns into just this
hellacious collection of special cases
which is why it was like 14,000 lines
and why he looked like he was ready to
you know bring into Z to the office you
know he was really on the edge there
so that was kind of the first attempt at
texture mapping and it was wildly
successful but it's it doesn't
generalize as well as as true you know
tech inverse transform texture mapping
and that was that was whom we started
looking at the strike commander
technology that came after Wing
Commander and that would have been in
there in the very late 80s early 90s
okay so now that I've got this to go
through and also so when were the
texture mapping articles Chris because
those are kind of the Cap'n's like here
we've come April 95 okay so this is
there's a pretty big span of time
actually this is like from okay it's
actually seven years before it's kind of
what was it what was SGI doing at the
time they had harder text me oh yeah
yeah like really nice filtered like a it
was known how to do all these things you
just couldn't you didn't have the Flexi
better hardware at the time had texture
mapping but it was essentially done on
video scan out those machines right
didn't even have polygon rendering right
but towards the early 90s they got they
got extra metal trying yes and iris or
whatever yeah okay towards way anything
I think the early 90s literally means
yeah it was right around that time
because they I mean we just didn't know
any of those people and we didn't pay
any attention to them and so they knew
exactly what they were doing
mathematical bit about that actually
anybody who's like yeah at that time and
possibly the Internet the relationships
community so I guess you're saying is
there there were people who had done the
research on this sort of stuff for
hardware or none of the books avila
I would just read that I hadn't read my
articles since April 95 Vince I'm sorry
I was while you were trying to get the
PowerPoint of you were going I was like
oh I better read some of this and
the beginning talks about the lack of
information in books like bullying Van
Damme didn't really cover it very well
and it this is Sean subtly without
naming it no no my articles do because
it's like and you can get these text
files off like x2 FDP dot oh you like
but they're totally incomprehensible
with no working code that's John
we didn't know each other at the time
when did you first post the text all
because I'm gonna talk about that later
as well
okay so who's that post my name's
underworld yes after underworld yeah cuz
it was about the underworld I got into
it because of unrest okay these are
their LG then I was contracting okay
so let's jump back then now so we're
good okay so we're in 1988 we are
looking for ways to add sort of more
detail to the flight simulator yeah and
essentially we at this sort of similar
times people in other industries have
been working on tech fire stuff but in
general like why is there no understand
there's because you don't even
necessarily know that these other people
are working on the sorts of things or
even who you would ask kind of stuff
like give me a little bit about that
because most people can't probably
relate to that because nowadays you just
type in an internet and go right yeah I
mean so I mean you're talking about
getting information yeah all my graphics
information at the time I had to get on
my bicycle and drive to Stanford library
and start xeroxing stuff which I
couldn't even generally couldn't even
find I was looking for so I literally
just go and just look through journals
and Xerox well I'd come back with a pile
of whatever looked interesting yeah at
the same time and then I didn't have the
math background to figure out most of it
so I would just stare at it over and
over again to like I think that I think
John mentioned that earlier which is
like there's the like oh yeah this
hardware was crap and blah blah but also
we just had no idea what we're doing and
I would be really interesting given the
math knowledge that's pretty standard
among engine programmers now to go back
with the shitty hardware the important
thing back then was that we weren't any
good at math yeah but neither were
computers
hold-hold goal for you know from the
morning when you got to work you know
from the from the time when you leave at
night is to figure out a way to avoid
doing math but you can avoid doing math
by knowing math which couldn't you back
things we didn't know enough now to some
extent yeah but but but but it but also
I mean you don't spend a lot of time if
you don't know the right way to do it
you don't spend a lot of time beating
your head against the machine to do it
away from there's an anecdote from the
forum enacting books the numerical
methods that usually work book where
he's like these engineers came over to
the beginning like they had to invert an
8x8 matrix over back then in the 40s was
like oh my god yeah well they were using
rooms of computers which were women and
so they so he they came to him as the
numerical analysis guy and he was like
they're like we need help with this
we're not he can't keep it stayed over
what do we do about this matrix and they
he does a bunch of math and he's like
okay well wait a second it was
orthogonal like it was like he's like
wait the inverses they said they
inverted on the like it takes hundreds
of hours computer time he's like notices
this thing is like if you just had like
actually write out the equation okay so
that kind of thing happens a lot once
you've got the overarching math
knowledge and so I think you could go
back to these texts Ram is way better
well the other thing too one one thing
that's kind of interesting about it is
sometimes having a lack of knowledge
does lead you to a solution corpus
callosum and like I think there's a
chance that some of us might have
rejected with the solutions we came up
with as to imprecise right never work
it's - right right
looks way better than nothing yeah yeah
I think that's also a part of the
problem here too is defining what you're
trying to achieve is difficult because
if you look at old games they're super
shuddery and shaky and what I think it
but it's still that's as good as it
could look at the time you know it's
like Christmas saying we just wanted
duffle you scream like that just like
you like that line it's kind of grass as
long as it moves in 3d I was looking for
screenshots from car and driver this
morning with it some texture mapping on
them and mostly what I saw is like
patterns of like colored guys like super
low resolution screen but it's so ok so
let's keep going so in 88 looking for
that right you tried sounds like what
you've tried doing first is taking
rectangles and subdividing them so yeah
processor if you can remember lecture
was why was that what your guys because
it's because a picture is a rectangle
like a bitmap is a rectangle like how
did what are you trying to do well so
again I've got I've got a
two-dimensional image which in the quad
and I've got a quad of three dimensional
quad and screen and I'm like how could
you even figure out which pixel would go
where I know the ones that are in
between a verge to find the middle pixel
yeah yeah is my rectangle smaller and a
pixel right so never occurred to you
like oh it wouldn't actually be the
center pixel no I know I know I mean I
was wondering even what I would see
right yeah but did you know that it was
gonna be wrong perspective warp wise or
no I drew pictures I said oh well of
course no perspective work because these
these edges will shrink and a central
still be tall so don't look like that if
you've got like I mean everybody in the
room sever's people facing exactly
forward I mean the side of the screen is
smaller than this side of everything on
this side and like if you subdivide the
screen right in half it's not gonna be
halfway through the quad that is
the texture your mapping because their
perspective is happening the thing that
the same thing that makes it smaller
shifts everything in a certain direction
and this was I guess this was unknown
because you're sort of thinking of
moving just sort of putting this work
see it cuz the thing right but in I mean
it's kind of like the it's kind of like
the quaternion thing that you were like
you thinkin just average these because
that's what the worms not that bad the
one is visual you detected a lot more
than say of rotation so so continue so
you tried that and it works it sounds
like but it's part of the purpose is it
saying yeah I showed it to people it's
about and then when was the next time
you tried I tried the booter thing okay
targeting explicitly drawing some hills
or something on the horizon yes I was
that's true did you try and pile up
lines yeah okay that's what you're
saying you're getting games you didn't
know how to likes offset it right yeah
yeah again I'll go back and go on the
emulator so I'll see if I can make it
work because I think I left there I said
a couple of items there and I went out
and I worked moved to California worked
for this guy Ned Lerner who was doing a
lot of games I'm sure a lot of you've
heard of him he was one of the
cofounders of Looking Glass and I worked
on flight Sims for him for a while and
then started doing a not very cold car
and driver not good we were trying to
get better graphics in it and we wanted
lane markings but the big thing was with
the VGA came out because we've been
working the PC the games under before
were these 16-bit color 16 color games
and particularly not even the number of
colors but they gotta push me to motive
that palette could you you could set a
pallet you said 16 fix colors but
another system you it was designed to
write scan lines yeah sequential blocks
of constant of the same color like it's
almost like they designed it to fill
polygons they didn't but it was very
good at feeling solid polygons today and
so particularly there was this crossing
point when the VGA came out so EGA
everything before that all the if it
seems
you never did any graphics where you did
instructions for individual pixels okay
you bleed you shifted some bits and
you're right eight pixels on the EGA you
wrote to one register and outcome for
pixels etc and it was you know it's kind
of impractical the process there's a lot
of pixels on the screen the six five or
two only is a one megahertz processor my
pictures don't wait do it the the
original IBM PC has nowhere near but
eventually the to a six and the VGA
meant that you kind of had to do one
instruction per pixel yeah that's them
anyway because their bytes so so
basically you know you've nowadays you
kind of think of the graphics card is
something you sort of ship instructions
and stuff over to it does some work but
of course at that time the graphics card
that's in say a PC of some kind is
really just something that you're kind
of writing to meant the CPU itself is
running to memory on the card directly
and that writing is happening like a
pixel at a time like I need to set this
pixel to this color and this color and
just so you were sort of saying the EGA
style or the pre pre VGA yeah you when
you did that right to the card you had
to fill a bunch of pixels at a time
because that's the way it just got
central yeah and yeah and so once you're
on the VGA and you maybe have like a
simple memory fill operation that
forever 16 if every pixel in there and
you start to think well I could probably
fit another instruction in there and one
or two more and so we tried to do some
stuff the first thing we did was uh a
lot of games of this I don't know I
don't think we're the first on this at
all but we did scaling where you could
basically take an image and size it on
the screen directly and we would use
that for we used it for clouds we did it
doesn't really work in a 3d game because
as soon as you start yeah like that but
that was our first thing and we
basically iterated from that like wait
we could do Goro shading okay because
that's only that's only maybe one extra
instruction an ad in a store and cut and
then we realize we could maybe do bitmap
rotation
and at that point it looked like a few
more tweaks and just texture mapping
before reverse mapping the bitmap
rotation we did we did reverse mapping
all the time so instant our bitmap we
had high speed bitmap scaling I mean
this is producing itself you know so you
gotta you gotta mention your scale to
screen it's still a rectangle all the
lines are so straight particularly every
lie every scanline its output is either
if you're scaling up some of the lines
are copies of the line that you scale
before so when you're scaling up you can
save a lot of perf there yes but you're
gonna be the scaling pattern where
you're in a sampling like oh I grabbed
this pixel that I skipped this one when
I grab the next to it and that's gonna
be the same pattern on every line and so
we wrote so much silver code that
basically generated a set of assembly
code to generate a cell firing code to
output one line in the current scale
thing and then it would just jump back
to it so let's talk about that for a
second because that's actually something
that I totally failed to think about but
it was very common at that time so
nowadays typically because of the way
processors work you generally don't want
to change code on the fly because they
have processor cache and all these sorts
of things
I'm sorry instruction cache on the
processor so typically when you write
code we think of it as just we write
code you know you compile it or whatever
and that's the code that's going to run
but of course that's because we have all
of these things like hey you know
instructions are cheap enough that if
you just have if statements in there or
variables in there that you're accessing
it's okay at that time like literally
every little tiny thing you might do was
a cost and so one of the things that
people did and I guess I don't know this
probably predates I don't know when this
started being a common thing but
self-modifying codes to big deal writing
something that would just output the
instructions to do a specific bitmap
scale rather than a general bitmap scale
would be common so is that was that
something you guys have done before or
no all right so so basically like this
is thing we sat down got you got a
bitmap scaling let's just work through
the prop like how did how does that
process go you just know it was more
like we thought about bit mo scaling and
thought it was Impractical
this okay again we were targeting we
were the three six was a high-end chip
that some developers would buy for
developed systems the systems we are
targeting were not eighty three sixes
okay
let's know once we said wait a minute it
could probably be fast enough if we did
that that we did it okay
similarly talking more about the
hardware the time n shinned we did Goro
she a ting that's that's really simple
it wasn't even hard then except for one
thing so nowadays you have when your
screen is let's you have any RGB pixel
you want any location you want you just
say what color you want you get it the
VGA is a chip where you have to six
dollars period on the screen total end
of sentence and you can decide what TV
six you wanted people to choose from but
that you and so you could map images and
they didn't look really good at
necessary it's it's a good compression
thing but it makes it really hard to do
calculations involving color you can't
say a color 120
you know I've what color is red plus a
little bit of blue you can only do that
by either making lots of mapping tables
or having your pallet be all black
people would take their pallet and make
it just shades of 16 different colors at
that time all colors were palletized
meaning a color was just an index into a
table and that index may have no
relationship to what the color actually
was so you couldn't just take two colors
and blend them together you had to take
two color indices if you wanted you
can't lend them together so John was
saying like there was no performance to
do actual set up these pilots so that
they happen to have correspondence or
big tables so like underworld had this
thing where it would darken the texture
mapping farther away and it worked by
having a bunch of three six entry tables
that were like Oh in this in the palette
the closest color to 25% dimmer the net
color is this one I got
would do that so you kind of look up
into the table I have this color what's
the what's this slightly dimmer version
of it and if your palates no it's not
guaranteed to work there would not be a
color that bad but it would just give
you the best yeah I've seen that table
is filled you are that makes that color
that we would generate it but someone
had I think our palates people generally
did not choose like I'll make a perfect
palate for a game they choose something
like 16 green yeah wouldn't exactly Bank
dammit correct so somebody would you
generate the darker color but then an
artist would go and go like that color
is not as good as this other choice or
or they don't remember actually I think
we just generated in code because at
that point got the bitmap scaling going
yeah and you're sort of like well okay
now well if that's fast enough maybe
what else is fast enough it sort of
sounded like yeah so it's kind of like
this mutation of loops where okay wait I
can add rotation to the scalar okay wait
this it's kind of doing two indices now
I could probably could do a little
fancier with that and realizing that
could probably map so it's kind of like
a slow step by step process of like oh
well that was fast enough what how can i
it sort of starts with one working
example of something that's the most
basic thing and then it it adds a little
feature as it goes to see how far I can
get okay so what ended up shipping in
Car and Driver then so in the car driver
we shipped all those things a lot of
signs a lot of billboards we tried to
put markings on the roads but it wasn't
you know so those guys so if you
actually those games use large a lot of
same code that an underworld uses the
same kind of kernels mostly oh really
there's operations yeah Ultima
Underworld and current drivers yeah I
was actually working on current driver
and contracting for a single looking
glass for that and we were selling
basically the tech from car driver that
basically the texture mapping went off
there was in our assembly language the
engine was taken and put into their
engine so the engine the underlying
engines are very different from each
other but but just a couple of things
yeah interesting okay oh no actually no
bunch of the engine was in there too but
there's this we had this we decided to
kind of base on what we did for flight
simmers which is kind of like your map
format is more like looks like an
assembly language file meaning that like
there's these up codes like oh if the
camera is outside of this region then
jump here or 12 this object here and it
had all done it so Blahnik by literally
my hand okay and it's it's pretty
effective no we in line rule so it's
full it's for like what's a drawn for
what but but then under world wanted to
have you know it's okay for fighting we
used a lot of digitized data and Leslie
Heights and stuff but you know
underworld wanting to have a map and a
map editor in particular and a map
better to let you change things that
just a lot of something not suit up for
that so essentially that and it had
stuff like occlusion yeah we didn't
worry about what was in front of what
about collusion in our games because
mostly was the ground okay and so that
was you so basically the the sea and an
underworld was changed to generate the
opcode stuff what when is so let's let's
jump back to origin here for a second so
what's going on with you sort of we're
starting to talk about the strike
commander stuff what where does that
line up with Ultima Underworld its
release well the big the big thing you
have to keep in mind about what we were
doing on strike commander was there's a
big difference there's a wide gulf
between what we're calling a fine
mapping of keen mapping i'm not sure how
you say it and perspective mapping
perspective mapping is what you need if
you want to draw one polygon that shows
perspective across you know the single
polygonal surface it's much harder
needless to say almost needless to say
it's much harder to do that than it is
to just do a simple two-dimensional
bresenhem's solver to to do a simple 2-d
affine map like life flight simulators
tended to do we were able to get the the
inner loop and strike commanders texture
mapper down to like eight or nine cycles
on a on an early early pinion or late
486 class machine but the
the per pixel divide instruction they
classically you would want for a
perspective mapper that alone would have
probably taken four times that time that
that much time just just to do the / Z
at each pixel so it just wasn't going to
happen and that's why I mean when you
have to remember that Ultima Underworld
came out around the same time as doom I
guess it was how much later was it the
world was 92 him was 93 okay was first
yeah underworld was actually first and
what was amazing about that is that it
was almost right it almost actually had
full perspective mapping you know Chris
cheated by doing it perspective and and
I guess direction but not in it if you
go back and play Ultima Underworld
you'll and then position yourself next
to a wall you get this crazy warping
event which some of you may have noticed
too is that not just a street a fine
mapper it was something weird it was I
thought we would subdivide in 3d it
would do this thing for walls where I
would actually calculate the column
right there in columns right but I kind
of I didn't even understand actually how
to solve for what columns how the
inverse map that so I had this thing
where I'm like wow I know what I'll do
this only matters when things have blown
up right because they're small it's not
that effects not that big so I basically
forward mapped it because I knew how to
divide I knew how to do perspective
divides but know how to invert first of
all let's start with one thing which is
that yet so the interesting thing here
is you mentioned doom
so doom does not allow you to
effectively correct it but you can't
turn your head right so they think that
kind of line that's a classic Carmack
thing which is like those general
problems
we were still at a point in time right
when you warned by not doing man right
so that's completely different now it
was a great knee of the curve like yes I
mean totally the opposite thing which is
like no we have to be able to walk
through this dungeon yes and like you
know you're walking you're high heads
bobbing you look everywhere because
there's that's why I thought those of us
who were in the industry were more blown
away by I mean we were blown away by
both doom and underworld but I
personally was like having actually
tried some of this I was more impressed
by underworld just because they were you
know so much earlier than anyone else
doing they were just different I mean it
was an interesting of engineering
approach to do different things I mean
under well if you recall was also a tiny
window or on a 320 yeah under well just
to be clear on that so in Doom they
solve this problem by just fixing the
screen and the reason that that's
important just you know is if you know
that all of your perspective changes
happen in vertical lines obviously you
can make a bunch of optimizations in
terms of what you're doing but in
underworld you could turn your head for
real so though the world would rotate
like a modern 3d game rotates which now
means that the texture mapper has to
handle anything it can't assume that
vertical lines are where the perspective
goes if you care about the perspective
warping you know the thing is in a
dungeon crawler both do more this the
closer you get to the wall the worse the
affine because the more the distortion
happens so you just get this like it
looked like the wall was about flight
simulator which is a bunch of polygons
on a 3d object the vertices are going to
be correct so rotating like spaceship or
or airplane doesn't matter issues a
plane mapping you don't care so but so
it's just impact that so the the problem
when you're looking up and down is now
you don't have these convenience sort of
vertical lines of perspective change so
when you're doing the mapper for this
yeah they wanted unpack those things
you're saying you tried so you've got
these sort of large wall tiles cuz again
everything at this time has to be very
low poly because the whole but just the
transforms of the vertices costs you
plenty of work as well so you can't
afford to just have really densely
tessellate stuff because that would have
solved the problem as well right yeah
super density tessellated genomics
would've been fine but then you'd get
killed by the transfer so here you've
got large polygons on the screen you're
trying to sort of get rid of the warping
that happens there which but you're not
really necessarily sure exactly I'm not
exactly sure of where all the warping
culture I remember it commanded I
remember drawing a piece of graph paper
and drawing walls and columns on it and
convincing myself that it wasn't a fine
vertically and it was only close there
were some warping there it seems a lot
more complicated than what I was
assuming I was assuming that you were
always prospectively correct at the the
scanline endpoints because of doing
clipping in 3d actually that helped a
lot because essentially you know you got
your polygons there halfway off the
screen you've got to find the corner
points and a lot of people would do 2d
clipping or hybrid ones where they would
just kind of like skip you know if some
probably goes a little bit off the
screen they don't 3d clip it they just
don't draw the pixels that are off the
screen but because the texture mapping
then you and equipping if you do that so
the clipping is actually perfectly
mathematically correct absolutely but
this but what ends up on the screen
isn't and so you get these effects where
imagine there's a wall like this and
it's just sliding off the edge of the
screen and it's it's not quite mapped
it's got perspective distortion the
problem is that perspective distortion
starts shifting and so we would suddenly
would take large polygons we'd feel a
big wall like that the first thing I
would do is I'd say wait there's a big
wall it's close to the eye that's the
thing that always looks bad I don't
quite know why but did you guys have UV
coordinates yeah we did and so I would
take that and cut into four polygons cuz
like Sean's original paper didn't have
you recorded another breakthrough
conceptually was the idea of like I have
the texture what's it yeah yeah this
idea of like there's you don't have to
use UV cords you can use a plane
equation that just describes where all
the pixels are right but I'm just saying
we didn't understand the math yeah and
that was a great point was yeah to just
approach it from at
yeah okay so yeah let's so I just want
to finish this the straight grain apart
as well though there it's so Shaq
remembers later that wasn't it his way
post later than what oh wait I'm trying
to place you're saying 46 and Pentium
it's just way before way after we win
commandership tried as as the the 486 is
work coming out I remember no Wing
Commander I guess would have been around
91 or so yes that would have been a
little pre-owned yeah yeah strike
commander took a long time for reasons
unrelated to texture map it's funny you
say that because it's hard to actually
like it was just the topic you talked
about like you'd be at GDC see GDC back
then and you betta dinner table with a
bunch of people and all you talked about
was texture mapping like okay so we
tried this other than literally the only
problem to solve in yes just so can you
just give us a little bit of background
because we really talked about how did
that come about right so you had chris
roberts had done the crazy 14,000 line
of code affine mapper for wing commander
that shipped I guess potentially a
little bit before underworld or
something but obviously has nothing to
do with the sort of stuff that under was
doing I guess sort of a little bit more
like the stuff that was doing a current
driver even though the algorithms were
different so now you're looking at that
and going we want to do real 3d I guess
because I guess the thing we didn't talk
about with Wing Commander is with Wing
Commander yeah you can you can rotate
the sprites this way and you can scale
them but you can't do anything in you
know rotate this way so what have you
had to capture all these pre based on
vector to the ship that you're rendering
so what would happen there is you'd see
these you know as the you know be
super smooth rotating this way and then
a so I assumed is that the impetus
behind sort of this I talked a little
bit like what you were trying to do how
you approached it what happened there
around the same time I think if I
remember right LucasArts
had
game that actually did full texture
mapping first it didn't have all the
nice shading options and other options
but it basically was like a bucket of
cold water in Chris's face he wanted his
he wanted to do this space game first
and he was he was happy with it as he
should have been but for doing his
combat simulator follow-up to Wing
Commander he once he saw the I think it
was it secret weapons of the Luftwaffe
something like that yeah once he saw
that you realized that you know we're
gonna have to go to texture mapping or
you know this is you know our cool
combat simulator is gonna look like crap
so that that's when he you know there
was sort of an informal competition that
kicked off among people at origin and
people who had recently left origin
meaning me to get the you know the
fastest inner loop for a simple affine
mapper that's suitable for you soon you
know you know texture map flight
simulator so we went back and forth and
back and forth and the person who really
should be here is Michael a brash whom
I'm sure a lot of you know Michael
couldn't be here but but Michael had
what what what he really contributed at
that time was he was writing all these
magazine columns describing for the very
first time an easily accessible public
print how texture mapping worked and he
would provide a lot of example code this
was in a defunct magazine called dr.
Dobbs Journal that everyone in the
industry subscribed to at the time
hugely influential I saw the work that
Michael was doing and I realized you
know this is how actual general purpose
you know texture mapping works which is
something I've never really got before
so that that kind of kicked me off on
the whole you know his sis code takes
like 30 or 40 cycles to do to do one
pixel and then I'm you know eventually
it goes down to 20 when I'm messing with
it and eventually I get it down to 215
and somebody at origin has it running in
ten and you know we're we're like we
have we have this you know friendly
little pissing contest going to get
every last cycle out of that inner loop
and what do you want tell the funny
anecdote about that the said Mike I was
at Microsoft we worked for Mike he was
my boss at the time and right before
that and like he had heard John at a
nine cycle version and his was like 14
or something like that I've got it like
you know and he got an eight cycle
version but John didn't ever have a nine
cycle version knowing something is
possible is and there's a whole chapter
in his big black book of graphics
programming on that taught on that exact
yeah I experienced that Michael and I
had you know going back and forth with
each other and and he makes the very
good point of you know he wouldn't have
tried yeah if he didn't think someone
had already beaten him and I wouldn't
have I wouldn't have you know had
something to shoot for if he hadn't
published you know the forty cycle per
pixel version or whatever so just just
having that existence proof in places or
not for the existing the perception of
an existence and and then later in a
file that's that's probably too obscure
to really bring up on a screen here Ken
Silverman the guy who did the build
engine most famous for Duke Nukem he got
it down to force was it four cycles per
pixel something like that we could I
don't know how in life so I was kind of
out of the game by them but but there
was kin and there was a Stafford I think
probably Stafford is the one because
people switch to perspective at one
point and then you had to subdivide and
then the cycle counts went back up but I
I believe you know basically all the
stuff that I was doing all this
chest-thumping over getting it down to
eight or nine cycles or whatever you
know ken was at this at the same time
more or less Ken was getting it down to
like half that so there's always another
cycle yeah whether it's worth going
after you know maybe maybe not
all right so let's let's I guess move
forward a little bit so eventually
because I kind of want to talk about the
second half of this process so Shawn
tell me a little bit about because
because Chris was that looking-glass
earlier and then you came to Looking
Glass I guess around this is around
system shock time or is that that's
in-between underworld two and system
shock in 94 and system shock was
basically done when I had done all the
work on like the texture back okay so
let's talk a little bit about that
process so basically like from
underworld to system shock they've kind
of gotten to the point where the
perspective stuff is under control are
not really like it give me a little bit
of background of like what happens at
looking glass during this period of like
okay so Chris has got the first one
going for underworld and then they've
gone through kind of two iterations and
I think Minh was the person who did some
of the work on this I never was able to
find contact information he's the only
person I couldn't invite but yeah under
will - I don't know really any of the
details just as a user I can see that
the mapper was different I don't know
whose work that was it looked like the
main thing was that for the perspective
mapper they split quads into two
triangles and just drew two high fine
triangles okay which way they were all
straight lines across the triangles
there were no curves but you would get
this weird split one that was a
perspective thing you would have to see
men but you know if you draw a grid the
grid bond just wouldn't why would I not
crossing the diagonal and then for
system shock so there was no there
wasn't really a lot of stable technology
they just kept he was the newest part
thing car that's because you know the
machines kept evolving right they even
the instruction set is changing but even
without that the micro architecture is
being different met the performance
trade-offs over different which meant
the thing that was a fast loop on the
386 wasn't going to be the fastest loop
on the 46 god it's a so system shock the
main thing that they did was that they
did have a solid perspective mapper
without warping and without cheating and
which was done with what was called the
lines of constant
zmapp okay which involved two normal
battery withdraw scan lines you would
you would do this inverse mapping and
you would process a single scan line of
the polygon and then because it's when
you had four mappers and wall mappers
though that was a constant step and a
half line step in the source texture map
okay you could just trace that along
very efficient so what you're saying
it's very affected yeah you're saying
that walls and floors are special but
that was the doom the lines of constant
Z on a floor if you can't tilt is you
can't help because the walls the logic
of Z are vertical and if you know that
that changes right but the wall the
really the reason that floors and
ceilings are special that way is because
the rotation is doesn't affect that
plane right that it is the same but so
walls and floors we're using this
already I guess is what you're saying
but so the idea there is that Doom was
already doing yes all like just relied
on that and that's how it was perfectly
perspective correct by restricting the
world and the player in such a way okay
so I don't know the exact details Chris
said there were multiple mappers to
handle those cases so they could be
faster and more correct looking in some
of those cases so in System Shock they
introduced this lines of constant Z map
or where there are some on a polygon
there some act some on-screen line that
is a line of constant Z across that
thing and will be at every effect move
it along that line it never goes into
route any further back or closer to the
same I mean just take a plane in slices
for your world and there are your life
when you were doing the thing of looking
at looking at the wall and lines are
still straight lines that are still have
fine they're just not right the screen
wall or but you can render in the
and so that's the system shock tech is
the lines of constant memories I guess
one thing I should ask this time when
did that concept of having multiple
mappers start coming out because it
sounds like you were saying for perhaps
our underworld to over 100 even
underworld one had this okay so we don't
really talk about they all you just the
way you did things back then was have
all the keys yeah okay so basically what
would happen is there's a whole bunch of
different kinds of mappers there's
something you I'm assuming this process
comes about because you're optimizing
the code you realize you could make an
optimization if some one thing was true
so you just like okay can we test if
that's true and then branch two to two
completely different versions of this
are similar or different loops for long
for little tiny sections of polygons
versus long ones because it's worth in
mining but that's not that's not a
texture mapping
ok so Sean so as far as coming on around
the system shock time one of the things
that you did is this text file that kind
of got oh that's before looking at okay
so can you kind of give me some
background on that and how that kind of
because this is one of the first things
that at least I know if that's like
publishing it out in the game industry
kind of what texture mapping even is for
people who you know didn't didn't know
it and along with like sort of a doctor
job girls I don't know what
so I I'd been reading journals and stuff
in the library what library back in
Maryland I was mainly following into non
real-time stuff and it really didn't
have a good understanding of the real
time stuff and and just launched into
that in 92 or so probably got all my
information from used at like definitely
read the doctor table stuff that was why
I started doing the 3d program was a
brushed articles and the frustration I
had was that nobody really explained the
details
what you need to do accept the details I
knew from the non-real-time stuff but
for the real-time stuff I felt like
there was no real like a brush did have
his thing I don't remember the details
and all of that but it's just like and
at the time I wasn't scared of math okay
and so one of the things that I did is I
just sat down and I said what actually
needs to be happening in the math for
this to make any sense I mean at the
time like you are now or you mean
compared to everybody else you said at
the time I was not scared I'm now way
more scared at the time I was in my 20s
and fearless okay so so essentially if
I'm getting this right you've had
exposure to the actual technical
literature in terms of what people
non-real like like people who are doing
maybe rate tracers or something is that
what you mean by like a lot of people
would recommend like this image warping
book that like had no useful information
there's like there was a lot of kind of
bad info okay well I think a lot of
filtering stuff if you cared about
filtering none of which we could afford
to do but MIT mapping and stuff was in
that book but it was definitely very not
yeah like it was weird yeah so I kind of
just said I gonna solve it from first
principles okay was what's what I was
tackling doing and the article tries to
cover everything so it's like here's the
math you need to know and here's an
optimized inner loop and well single one
okay you know whatever so it kind of
covers a whole breadth of things and I
was working on doing that work and 93 I
think I put that arc on 94 the whole
point there was we had used that but
used that it was actually transitory
used that was this thing that came and
went it was you the article came on your
thing and they kept a week of articles
if you were lucky or something like that
and then it was gone again so you had
FTP sites that had various pieces of
information okay and this one guy was
like this is terrible let's like collect
all the good information that's been
going by and put it in this thing he
called the PC game programmers
encyclopedia okay all the information it
was probably useless a year later but it
was a you know an attempt
but something on the FTP sites that
would have a lot of valuable stuff and
for whatever reason I got drafted to do
the texture mapping article and I don't
know for sure but I bet you is the exact
same thing adds the a browse articles
and a lot of other columns and stuff
that you read which is the person is
writing this from a position of
authority but they had no idea before
they start writing the column how to do
it they just solved it while they were
writing the column okay experts so what
is that process like for for working
this I thought you said work it out from
first principles like what do you mean
like again coming at this from the
perspective of like hey trying to solve
a hard problem you have no information
to go on really you just kind of know
here's what an inner loop kind of looks
like it's it's the other side of the
math was the the issue and so it was
like we know what the 3d transform is
and I can characterize where in the
bitmap a particular point on the polygon
is in math and just run it through the
normal 3d map so the whole thing like in
a 3d perspective transform comes from
dividing by a number divided by Z right
yes and it turns out that the inverse
transform of the texture mapping
requires dividing by inverse V or
something like that yes yes you know you
might think the inverse would the divide
turns into multiply no it turns into two
by right and so the final thing you end
up with is like some math that says you
have to do two divides at every pixel
one for each going thing I see if you
just sit there and crank out a bunch of
math um but as Chris was saying part of
the way of doing that was to actually
formalize the problem in a different way
than what people were actually doing in
practice and I don't know where I got
the idea of doing that from it was like
maybe the only way I could think to make
the math work don't they have to go
through that and I can explain what I
mean by that if you want you certainly
can
so the basic idea in texture mapping is
you have a bitmap and you have
coordinates in the bitmap which we call
UV or St and you say you have this
polygon with vertices and you say and
each vertex what UV coordinate in that
bitmap
you want to map to that point you do
that for all the points in the polygon
and you say you know in purply between
and as soon as you have more than three
points it's possible for you to specify
a fourth vertex that you can't there's
no normal you can't do a linear
interpolation and get that result which
is why GP is all use triangles is right
then the those coordinates are planar
they they're purely linear in those two
points but if you have four it's not
really very well-defined and I in those
in those days because we could only draw
a hundred polygons you didn't turn
everything into tribal aspect that you
just drew polygons right and so you had
four or five sided polygons so you've
had this problem of doing this now it
turns out you can take any three and do
the math and get the right results but
you also for when you're trying to do
quality things you sometimes do this
thing where you interdict introduce an
extra vertex along a line you'll have
three vertices on this edge okay to join
up with other things cleanly so you
don't get cracking oh yes okay I see
what you're so you're talking about T
Junction okay so if you do that you have
these three vertices they'll all have UV
coordinates that are on a line because
they'll be consistent and if you tried
to do them even when you go to do the
mapping you see I need to do some math
get some stuff yes and you do that math
on this stuff if you pick those three
vertices because they're on a line you
get garbage results I see right so
basically what you're saying is you need
three well for most points to figure out
the plane of this texture mapping if
they do generate to align I need to be
linearly independent they cannot
asteroids yes matrix afraid of math now
the matrix has to not be degenerate it's
not linearly independent as the cracker
and so for example at looking but after
I did all this anyone to look in glass I
was talking them they were like yeah I
have to certain I'm trying to generate
the math for the constant Z perspective
mapper and I'm searching for a set of
three vertices that are not collinear so
that I can get stable math out of it
there it turns out there's other ways to
do it so I stepped back from that
problem and I said well I know the UV
coordinates should be planar in the in
the not on screen button in world space
right should be plane like they should
be well-defined they once you've defined
three there so let's go this thing came
from something in the world that is
supposed to be flat so it's also the
only way the mapper is going to work
only no you do it that's true so let's
assume that they're playing so let's
just start by assuming we have plane
equations for the coordinates instead of
starting with UV coordinates at each
vertex that was the the weird thing
about one of the several weird things
about my way of doing texture mapping
that was in this article
okay well the funny thing about it that
is when I was reading it I didn't know
enough math and even really know what a
plane equation was at the time it's like
what the hell is a weird ass thing
that's what's happening on I mean
they're all equivalent under the hood
like they all exactly the same but if
you don't have the math skills to and so
this this article kind of makes its way
out into the world I guess at this point
some around the system shocked over a
little bit before it's assumed it was 94
before I went to looking left so yeah it
would have been before system shock you
know is this the first like it was that
one of the first ones that was published
in terms of for the game industry for
perspectives though for perspective the
only thought I didn't actually I gave
the Quartus I didn't try to solve the
perspective with mapping problem there
was a separate article in the thing
which proposed doing lines of constant Z
but it wasn't your thing had like to
point we want a plain equation two over
another plane equation s yeah you didn't
actually do anything here's the two
divides you have to do yeah
all right and so now Chris this is
because I kind of think of you as being
the person who could codify a lot of
this stuff only because I remember at
that time those like texture mapping
articles were sort of they're like the
final publication on it that makes right
I was just friends with all these people
because I was at Microsoft and I got
Microsoft to get let me go to GDC okay
and so I met Doug and then through Doug
I met everybody else well Doug enjoy
axiom John and John introduced me to
Doug so what happened was I worked for
Mike so Mike and I learned 3d graphics
Mikey brushed on Bix this is before the
internet okay I mean the internet
existed in colleges and stuff so right
around the time he was learning 3d
graphics I was on Bix with and we like
kind of like helped each other learn 3d
graphics together and then I went to
work for him at Microsoft and then I saw
some flyer that had like computer game
developers conference that was posted in
the like you know some hallways I'm on a
bulletin board like literally and then
just because you like games games are
the cool thing but then I went to John's
talk which is about the texture map or
what Bo is about I've the hold I have
the molder 3 which is a video game that
John does like wrote all by yourself I
think right you just type those in it
was some D&amp;D license something rather
I'm but you talked about text wrapping
in there I guess well I think we
actually had a sponsored session at one
GDC it wasn't a sponsored session but we
thought long story short it looked like
we were trying to sell our texture map
or at GDC and I think right it wasn't
yeah yeah this is before I was on the
board or anything like that so I just
was like this guy in the audience and
like I think I asked a question or
whatever and I went up afterwards
and I was like oh my K brush was my boss
like you know I'd like to talk he's like
oh cool have dinner with us and then he
needs me to Doug and Chris and Matt
talks a lot would be to saying all that
but so anyway I was good friends with a
bunch of these people and so and back
then when I was writing those columns
for a game developer I downloaded
Shawn's article I was you know I'm using
it and trying to figure all this stuff
out and like it was kind of a hot topic
like I said it was like just what you
talked about when you were with people
is how to make your texture mapper work
better and that was right around the
time that people were trying to figure
out how to go from affine mapping which
worked if you had small polygons to
perspective map name which is just
general okay I'm like there were just
eight billion ways of doing it was like
this Precambrian explosion kind of crazy
lines of constancy and you know like
subdividing this way and so dividing the
actual triangles and they all had
different costs in trade-offs and
everyone
figuring out and but I was like it's
similar to Shawn I was just frustrated
because no one actually knew anything
about what was going on like there was
not that much understanding about what
was actually happening on a per pixel
basis so it's kind of trying to solve a
problem without really defining the
problem quite like I think this kind of
improved the quality is thing because we
did it and we saw that a lot better but
we didn't necessarily have a you know
the understand to measure what was there
was no like here's the divide per pixel
perfect code let me optimize that right
that's not the way it happened at all
right so which I think there's the it
sounds like there was some agreement
earlier like thank you yes you won't get
off into these crazy little areas if you
necessarily strictly follow that like
you want some again your simulated in
the algorithm you want a little bit of
heat to Bob out to a randomization thing
but at the same time like man if you
have that reference implementation that
you can do so much more and actually
understand what you know here's the slow
perfect thing but some things like how
good are crazy thing is but some people
and this may be true feel that if you've
got that it's hard I mean kind of mean
that's similar like the note cycle
anecdote it's hard to pop out of that
because you're always focusing on yeah
but so anyway so I saw Shawn's article
and I met Shawn years later so this is
the funny thing and Shawn and I shared
an office for a long time but so like I
but I saw Shawn Barrett like it wasn't
was it P map we're talking figure out
the name of the text file was okay
there's like P map text or text map
something anyway but and I just could
not understand a word I believe that it
was I mean I downloaded from the
internet so it must be all it's on this
like game programming it sounds like
this guy must know he's talking about
but I literally cannot understand
anything going on here and so I was at
Microsoft then doing this is right after
doom is a pre quake and there was a
couple math guys around who like we're
really good at discrete mathematics
though the one that the biggest takeaway
from this talk is you should buy this
book called concrete math man
by Graham Knutson patashnik it's just
the best book for all kinds of likes the
Fabian was talking about we were both
talking at rad the other day about how
awesome this book is like how to think
move things in and out of floors and
seals and like how to get rid of yeah
it's just a great clear floors and seals
it's called concrete because it's
continuous and discrete that's where
math that's where game math lives right
it's gonna end up as pixels on the
screen or as a thing is you know and so
it's just a great book
but so there's a I got turned out of
this book by this guy who I think his
name was Kurt he worked also work for
Mike at the time at Microsoft and we
were just I had started trying to fumble
around trying to figure out this thing
and started being more rigorous about
the Phil conventions and Halleck what
should the actual definition the pixel
actually be and then I realized it would
just be value because I've been writing
so I mean again trying to work through
the mindset of how these sorts of things
happen why does the Phil convention come
into your brain at all this point is
this because your mother craps things
like give me everyone's trying to
improve the look of their game yes right
so what do you got going wrong you've
got cracks in the polygons like
underworld had this crazy thing where
would like fill the buffer with purple
or pink and then run random cam camera
angles and search the buffer for pink
pixels and then like print out where the
camera was no yeah I mean this is like
no one knew what they were doing like so
I mean that's how you find bugs right
and so so I was just kind of talking to
all these people and like you know if I
was working games myself but I was were
gonna win G which was the game library
before direct decks that Microsoft that
we did and so reported doomed to that
and like it was the thing people were
trying to improve the quality right and
it was like oh well perspective is a
huge thing making sure crabs don't you
know when you if you're ever gonna write
a triangle rasterizer you want to get
your fill convention right that's one
thing Mike was really rigorous about
early on although he was yes once you
add dimension is just which pixels are
yeah yeah exactly and when they share an
edge like you don't decide who gets
which pixels and all the stuff it's all
stuff that the hardware mostly handles
now but like we've got back then when
you were doing
you had to do it okay so people in the
in the industry generally knew that
these were problems because they saw
them right they had these the cracks or
they had a but they wouldn't necessarily
they didn't necessarily know why it was
a hard problem it was an uninteresting
problem and so we all blew it off and so
we all had cracks in our right so
sub-pixel is another thing was once you
start perfect once you start do we know
why that was because like if so when Mac
was working on this stuff did he just
not talk about it or did people not
realize that that solution would also be
something you could okay so it was so
special case that if you're trying to do
a general map or none of the tricks he
was doing quality was image quality was
a priority friend right right but yeah I
mean it's not he was talking to Mikey
and email occasionally because but
anyway so I mean just in my head just
because I guess I'm not maybe explain as
well at some point he must have thought
about sub pixel precision I don't think
he thought he didn't know it was called
sub pixel how did he end up getting a
thing like that then you think he just
kind of was like oh that looks way back
to the doom code it's not actually sub I
mean I I don't know for sure but I'm
sure no it was way more sub pixel then
not like if you just truncate to the
nearest integers like crawls all
over the place and it wasn't doing that
because he filtered every line before we
drew it meaning he pre-stretched it and
then did the thing so if you do that
right yeah all right so it could be that
he wouldn't really have known the like
abstraction that will allow you to then
apply the same thought problem because
he also had Wolff before that
Wolfenstein was a similar I mean it's
only like the thing about the break from
doomed the Wolfenstein was the ability
to have things that weren't just box
which required a little bit more math
the columns on the floor yeah because
the floors was hey that line of constant
Z is moving in the texture map but
anyway so uh so it's just it was just
it's hard to it's hard to overemphasize
how much mental power and conversational
power graphics took up then it was just
what you talked about if you were a game
programmer right like knowing care I
mean I'm sure some people did but there
was no game design like it as a thing
that you talked about there was just
like how fast can you get your texture
wrapper okay right and so it's just like
what people all the hardest core highest
and all the like everything was just
talked about it's like everyone license
smile sound system or whatever was
called hale and then like spent all
their time on their texture mapper and
then so but so in image quality was the
thing because we had although like i
mean the computers were getting faster
and so we had the cycles and it was like
image quality so it's like fixing your
cracks and getting some pixel accurate
and like all these things and so I just
wrote these articles I want to figure
out myself yes and like Sean was saying
the best way to figure things out is
actually trying write an article about
it as an expert because they assume
you're an expert temporarily write the
article and then at the end you start to
be like I really want to be able to
write an article about this from the
point of view an expert so I better get
there and there's a deadline on the
article right you'll attract attention
from the actual experts right so okay so
when you're doing this though you're
you're looking at this and going okay so
people are saying that they've got these
sort of cracks and dropouts and stuff
with the pulp fill convention stuff was
handled earlier but I just wanted to
document it really okay so who I mean
that's all just been like I mean it's
just like pulling been named I think
talk about fill conventions I think I
can't remember that's been that was more
resin ham is about fill conventions
things like that just like what's in and
what's out I was like you have to know
if you're gonna once you're mapping
something on to a surface you have to
know where the actual how'd you have to
step to the pixel center from the edge
of the thing so you have to get your
fill convention right with the floors
and the ceilings so that is that if it's
right if the lines right on a pixel
center then what
what do you do and just there's just a
whole bunch of little math there that is
not a lot of code once you know the math
it just all drops out into like I add
one in the low significant bid on this
thing and it worked
but getting figuring that a lot of
people would just literally have a
second to somebody I it's a couple days
ago I was like oh yeah we owe it was we
were talking about so under Kelling moon
was another game that had a crazy
advanced texture members it was really
garbage he really crawly but like it was
full general and it was like 10 frames a
second maybe yes they were doing lots of
polygons and lots of it right so it's
like but Jeff was just saying that Bruce
Bruce Hartwick but Bruce doll increased
awesome no it wasn't Bruce Johnson that
he just had like a magic number he added
literally he just had like a 1 in the 16
you know in the fruit foot in the
fixed-point like and like he just I
don't know why this fixes it and like so
my one of my articles is like and what
it was doing it was converting a floor
to a seal or whatever like you add none
and then truncate and then boom it was a
seal and that was a sleepy Friday plus
one I was like hey yeah yeah whereas
this guy I think his name was Kurt but
concrete mathematics talks about like if
you and you the concrete graphics
doesn't like the artwork look words I
doesn't talk about like fixed-point and
whatever but like you know if you
realize what's going on you can see all
these floors and seals and you just
write out the math and then you grind it
through in the right way and then like
oh you should add one here you should
subtract one there and then you should
you know truncate or whatever so I just
wanted to document all that stuff cuz
there's all this stuff in lots of
different places and as we went towards
image quality it seemed like to me you
know coming from a basis I mean I just
reread the intro to my article just
onstage here while you're doing the
thing and it was like if there's one
thing 3d video games have to have now
it's a perspective texture map err words
to live by
I know this sounds like I'm trying to
pin down something specific everybody's
still not quite sure
so I'm dodging on the fact that I don't
remember any of this I'm trying to like
bob and weave
I just wanted just to see though if I
can get it which is again people are
having problems with these
in other words games in general are not
necessarily doing the right things for
their fill convention so at some point
somebody and maybe it's you know was
other people or something but had to go
wait a minute there's this information
in these other places that's about how
to fix that so I'm just asking what
happened there was that talking to
people at Microsoft I mean think it's
like lose net and look to everybody
talked about this all the time so some
people connect right but the thing about
the the so the fill conventions of how
to fill triangles was well understood I
mean Mike and written about eight years
before like not I mean it was my kiddin
I mean it's like that's just in early
graphics of textbooks do it it's just
like right well yeah I mean right and
then just but when you add texture
mapping all that stuff gets worse
because you have to be on pixel centers
so all of a sudden makes you could have
had a crappy like Paul and solid polygon
filler or even a gross shaded one and
not notice that you are off though if
once you've got texture mapping on there
there's just this high frequency
you're an idiot which is the the floor
mappers scanned scan converted
horizontally and the wall mappers can
convert it vertically okay actually hard
to make consistent right like that was a
subtlety that no one talked about
because it was a unique thing we were
trying to write probably there's an easy
math solution to yeah yeah yeah but
nobody right also in the in general
outside the walls and geometry people
generally used T junctions without even
caring Yeah right yeah or bowties is a
similar yeah and also we rendered
concave we rendered concave polygons who
can afford to break those things up
right and it's really hard to get that
so yeah I just remember just the final
state of the articles they're so well so
the perspective correct part of that I
guess was kind of something that came
about partially it was just what was
happening then like people trying to
figure it out or figure it out and so
Mike had written the a fine ones but you
couldn't make a game
very successfully because things would
just warp it was cool
and he had its little like you know you
had polygons 3d stuff going on the
screen and so we were friends and you
know work together then and so and doom
it was just clear that perspective had
to happen for it to be general enough to
use yes and so so yes it was just
documenting that and figuring out and we
worked on the assembly code and like
like you know the math behind it and
then how to write the assembly code to
make it work and how was getting the
math behind it a question of cuz again
Sean had written the articles which you
saw so those were all plain equation
based like there are UV coordinates in
his articles so like the way you
actually do a pipeline with this stuff
the way you actually the way it's more
intuitive nowadays maybe it's a six 1/2
knows the other cuz I know more math but
back then for me like the idea of like
you've got some source bitmap and you've
got a triangle and the triangle has got
coordinates in the source bitmap that
you then want to put on the screen made
a lot more sense so I wanted to figure
out from there that's actually the way
the hardware ended up working ok you
know I mean that's the way it's actually
before this two guys that's so yeah so I
wanted to derive the math from there but
if you look at the articles it's a ton
of plain equations yeah if you have to
be able to detect them and you just yeah
yeah I would like but most of whose name
we think is Kurt well I think he's not a
game he's not Kurt but but that was that
stuff came mostly that's not what's more
eye-opening for the fill conventions for
the for the subpixel like gradient
stepping stuff that was basically like
if you if you're off by like one bit
like you're you're gonna find little
bugs yes if you just you can get it
exactly right in fixed point even to
match the correct math if you just do
all the stuff that was really
eye-opening to me cuz that stuff that I
still use now like it really is so
that's just real math and say we're like
math carries across you know like I
haven't written on ssee kind of assembly
language in a million why would you ever
write that right I just don't need to do
that anymore
but but that math is useful everywhere
now that you know that like a floor and
a seal like seemed impenetrable like you
can't get anything out of here because
it's changing the number but you can
like you just have to know it's a
concrete mathematics it's a it's gram is
the first author and Knuth and patashnik
got it
it's a great book well we have to break
for lunch I think we probably got to the
end of it just about
[Music]
[Applause]