hello everyone and welcome to handmade
heroes show we code a complete game live
on stream i am taking steps last weekend
and this weekend to basically give us
some more how should I put it
a more modern Lee file format the reason
for this is we were doing we decided to
allow sort of more integrated artwork
and pipeline art pipeline stuff in the
game just because we have the
opportunity to use that now and so while
I was in there I just decided let's make
sure that this stuff can be used to
trade asset files and stuff like that in
some way that'll actually be useful and
so I think that's really all we're doing
right now we mostly finished the other
stuff which was getting the PNG like
being able to update art assets in real
time using the PNG that stuff we did
okay and so now we're doing it's just
kind of like settling in on a file
format that has some additional
information in it so that not only can
we maybe use this file format to help
with the art asset reloading just to
make it a little cleaner but this will
also allow us potentially to like let
people do more with these files than I
was originally anticipating we would
allow people to do with handmade here
when it comes out so if we go ahead and
take a look at what we were in the
middle of doing you know we we kept the
code compiling in cleanly and all that
so we actually are still running on the
old file format v-0 but we made a new
file format v1 that was in there and so
you know if you've run the game it's
still exactly the same as it was it
still can load its old assets and all
that stuff so that's good but we're now
taking a look at making it so that we
can do a conversion to a new file format
and also basically do that anytime we
want to and also we want to make it so
that we can sort of have maybe hopefully
this would be like sort of the last file
format hopefully we won't have to do
much more
maybe we make some slight tweaks but I
don't really want to have to fuss with
the file format very often obviously so
looking at what we used to have you can
see we had here like three three things
that got changed and so this was the old
file format we've got the new file
format kind of documented here here's
the header we added some research stuff
in there just in case we want to add
some new arrays we won't have to break
the file format going forwards to add
some new erase the one and then we added
this annotation stuff the point of the
annotation stuff is just now we would be
able to store information about where
assets came from which will make it
easier to hot reload them and it also
make it easier for people when they
trade files to know what assets they
have and where they came from
if they want to you know so that seems
good the last thing I think I want to do
is take the HHA asset struct and we have
a couple of choices here one of the
choices we have is to make this HHA
asset struct a little bit more verbose
so actually put in there what kind of
data everything is and so on the other
choice we have is to add that to the
annotation I think I want to put it in
here and the reason I want to put it in
here is I think I want to say look let's
just since we're going to make this a
more flexible file format let's just go
ahead waste a little space but let's
with every single asset let's say
explicitly where it is in the file how
big it is and what type it is so that
any individual HHA asset can even if you
have no idea what you're looking at
right like you have no idea if it's a
bitmap or a sound or a font or maybe you
don't even know what fonts are like you
have you're just a utility that's
operating on HHA file you have no idea
how to read those something that still
allows you to effectively edit
the file so basically what we're doing
here is we're putting in information
that that you wouldn't actually need if
you knew probably what you were doing
but to make it easier to write utilities
that don't have to know everything right
this also makes us a little more
future-proof it means that if we have an
HHA editor that allows you to let move
assets around like let's say you make a
thing called HHA merge and it allows you
to like maybe it showed like let's say
summit community makes HHA merge it's a
thing that loads to HHA files and allows
you to pick which assets you want from
each and then writes a third file out
that has just those com the combination
of those two assets right well that
utility would have to understand a bunch
of stuff in order to do that right now
why because all we store in the hh8
asset is the offset to the data in order
to know how big the data is so that you
can move it from one file to another and
copy you know copy it right you have to
first know the type and then look at the
action will type in for me the the
actual struct information here to figure
out how big it should be because in
order to move a bitmap you have to come
in here and read the dimensions of the
bitmap because the definition of a
bitmap is of 32-bit integers that are as
many as the dim zero times the dim one
so without read without knowing it's a
bitmap and reading out the dimensions
from the bitmap you can't actually move
the data associated with the asset right
so you can see why this is a
particularly annoying thing right so
what I would rather do here is I would
rather regularize this and say ok we're
gonna be a little more upstanding
citizen here the original file format
was just made for our simplistic
purposes let's be a little bit better
about that make something a little more
robust and editable you know because
we're looking past just shipping file
format to moddable file format almost
and the things you want to do there
become you want to waste a little space
and get back its
flexibility those are you know things
you might want to do it's nothing really
about wasting space you know I wasn't
super concerned about space originally
or anything it's just you don't spend a
lot of time putting in features that you
don't need right these are features we
don't need but now we kind of want to
have them so that going forwards we can
use them right so you know we need them
now or want them let's say so what I
would like to do with the HHA asset is
say ok let's say that there's the v-0
version of the HHA asset like so right
here's that v-0 version and now the new
version of this will actually have
additional information it'll have a data
size and the data size will say okay if
I go to this offset how much do I need
to read and then it will also have at
the end of this a data type right and
then I'll tell us whether it's a bitmap
a sound or a font or anything else we
might want to add right so now there's
an enum HHA asset type and in here we'll
just say bitmap I might put an unknown
or none something where we just
basically say like look there's nothing
here yet I often put that as the 0
element so that if I want to have an
uninitialized one I can and I can test
for it
but right now we just have bitmap sounds
and fonts that's what we've got and so
that's what we're going to say so now
what I want to do is I want to have it
so that I can come in here and I can
specify the data type and the data size
for every asset so now if someone wants
to move an asset from one file to
another they don't need to know anything
about it they just need to know that
they're going to move this much data and
then whatever is in here now in order to
make this also again a little bit more
flexible I want to make sure that the
amount of storage that goes on here is a
little bit more predictable as well so
you can see we've got a bunch of things
we've got like a sound and a bitmap and
a font and there are certain size so I
want to still
maintain that flat structure so they
could just be copied around but I'm
gonna actually put in this union here a
thing that says the maximum size we ever
expect everything to be right so like
maybe we call this you know max Union
size or something right and what we
could do is set that to something that
we think is reasonable like something
that all right I'm not supposed to use a
calculator anymore there we go what I
want to do is set that Union science to
something that I can actually anticipate
being a reasonable block size to ever
move around it's got the bitmaps this
out the bitmap the sound and the font
yeah if you look at how big those are
right now right you can see that they're
not particularly large it looks like
we've got five 32-bit integers here
three here and four here
right so if we said something like this
that would be far bigger than anything
we have right now in plenty of room for
anything that we might need and so if I
go in and see how big that would be
let's suppose we have 10,000 assets
seems maybe let's go even larger than
that let's say we have a bunch of fonts
like 60,000 assets right and then we
want to see how big the asset load would
be for each of those let's actually go
through let's let's make this since this
is one two three of those let's actually
make this so that they all line up right
so we have one two three sixteenths we
have 16 total you 64's which is 16 times
8 right so that would be 7 megabytes for
the asset store that's not even in the
realm of problematic considerations for
us so that's totally fine I could even
bump this a little bit more if we wanted
to just not sure we really need to
assets don't really need much
information because the bulk of their
data goes into the flexible data store
this is only the part that is stored for
use in the actual processing of the game
so I just don't anticipate it ever
needing to be particularly large right
so one thing we can do here I don't know
that we ever did a CT assert oops yeah
we didn't so one thing that might be
nice to do is to assert that this thing
never changes size right and that's
something that you'd like to do in all
of these you'd like to assert that none
of these things change size so you pick
typically you pick what the size of them
should be and then used to assert that
they can't ever be a different size than
that right and so typically what you do
is you have something that's like
compile time assert and you say like
okay you know let's compile time assert
here let's compile time assert that you
know the the size of an HHA asset is the
same as what I just said it should be 16
you know 8 byte entries right
Negus I could just multiply 16 by 8 and
put it in there but I decided not to do
that for reasons we're not quite sure
why so if we you know 1 do that we could
also make these be more cash aligned I
suppose but well you know it doesn't
really matter because we're only going
to touch the first part of them anyway
so they'll generally be that first 64
bytes will generally be in there so
keeping the padding won't actually
matter so I think that's fine so there's
these these compile time asserts are a
thing that we'd want to say look I just
want you to assert this at compile time
and the way that that you do this in
modern C++ is they actually have one but
you can actually create one from you can
actually create one from like
by using like tricks right you can
actually create your own compile-time
assert if the compiler doesn't have one
and the compiler never did have one like
back before 2012 or 2013 or whatever
there was no such thing as a compile
time assert built into the language so
you couldn't do something like say I
require this to actually be true alright
so what you had to do was you had to
figure out some way of triggering an
assertion where the compiler would fail
in the case where the thing wasn't true
right and so let's suppose we want to do
something like that let me take this out
for a second here and we'll just try to
reverse engineer how to make something
like that so let's suppose I wanted to
declare like a global variable or
something like this that just never gets
used right so let's suppose I want to do
something like you know global variable
foo let's suppose I did that right what
you can see here it is oops more time
right there we go so let's suppose that
I wanted to create one of these things
here right well if I created something
of size one it would work if I created
something of size zero
it wouldn't work right so if I want to
generate a compile time error based off
of some expression well what I could do
is I could say look what if I just took
some expression that I could evaluate at
compile time and then made what I
declared this variable to be based on
that so if it's equal the way I want to
be I'll evaluate to 1 which will work if
it's not equal I'll evaluate to 0 right
so what you can see here is that this
worked because it is equal to that size
if I change it right so now I say oh
yeah by the way there's like an ant at
the end of this thing
you can see that now it will error make
sense so you know this isn't probably
not a particularly great way to compare
our time sir it's just the first thing
that came to mind so I just want to show
you how to make it pole cloth you could
probably look up better ways to do it on
the internet there's probably people who
have like thought about the cleanest way
to make a compile-time assert if your
compiler doesn't support it but that's a
obvious way to do it right you say CT
assert right let's say I want to make
this macro now I want that to work I say
okay CT work here's my expression that I
want to be true I just basically do this
right where I say okay I've got an
integer array foo and I want this
expression to be true so whatever the
expression is I want it to be true and
then I'll do this thing enough it'll go
right now of course one problem that
I'll get if I actually do this is that
when I actually run the X like this will
work oops so if I do this it'll work but
and you know it errors out as it should
one problem is that as soon as like good
and make a second one so let's say I
wanted to make sure also that HHA
annotation was always the same size one
two three four five six seven eight nine
ten eleven why are there eleven oh there
it is twelve twelve I don't know why we
have twelve one two three four five six
seven eight nine ten eleven twelve
we've got twelve for some reason that
doesn't seem like a good number I feel
like sixteen everyone likes powers of
two better so if it's twelve I would
want to add 4 to that so we'll just say
that so there's the annotation struct so
I want that one to be 16 large
oops so these are both the same size now
and the problem that we get as you can
see here is I'm trying to assert on two
different things but the problem is that
since I gave this thing a name it's
going to conflict right these are both
going to try to talk about something
called foo and that is going to make it
so that I can't have more than one
compile-time sir
now one thing that people will often do
to fix that is they'll say like oh okay
you just pass in a name right and
that'll work but it's a little annoying
because we'd rather just have it work
without the name right so what we would
rather do here is have something that we
can define in some way that you know
doesn't have that problem right so some
way that we can generate a name here
that we know will be unique right and so
we've done stuff like this before
what we would like to do here is is
maybe use the paste operator right and
stick a counter in there or a line
number for example and when we do that
this would work just fine if it weren't
for the fact that the paste operator is
defined as not having not evaluating
this value until until after the paste
so this will actually stick underscore
underscore line just the actual words
right which isn't I wanted it to use the
line number and it's not doing that
right so what we'd rather do here is
have some way of this actually using the
line number or something like or a
counter or anything like that to
actually get us a differing value here
and so what we want to do is use that
weird trick where we keep calling down
until we get enough deep to make it
actually have evaluated the line and
turned it into a number right so if I do
this in theory I should be able to make
this happen
except that actually has to be the value
so now it will actually turn it into a
number so the first one down will pass
this into here the second one will turn
it into a number and pass it here and
then the final one will pay some number
on the end the C macro thing is not
great I admit that I believe you can't
do it just this way because the first
time in it it just passes the think the
word line it's just just a disaster it's
a bad macro language what can you say
however this will work and so what I can
do here is make a little like CT assert
so no one will ever accidentally use
this name and now we're good to go
there's one sort of a million's here
and what that is is that well okay so
we've got this thing and now what we're
doing in a lot of cases is where you
know declaring something that looks like
that well that's actually a data member
and you know probably the compiler will
get rid of it but who's to say is some
compilers like GCC are really bad with
static data members or global data
members rather I remember there were
versions of GCC that if you ever had a
switch statement that could have looked
at a value in the data segment then it
never got rid of anything in the data
there was some really ridiculous stuff I
remember crazy stuff in GCC that would
keep it from ever removing
data segment stuff so you know do we
want do we care that much no not really
but is there an easier way for us to do
this well let's you know this is the
thing that we need to have error out
right so the question is could we just
turn this into something else like a
function declaration or something that
wouldn't actually you know cause a
problem like could we just say oh you
know you know can we just throw it into
a struct right and see if if that causes
a problem right well the first thing you
can see here is it's warning us because
we have a symbol that can never be used
right and you know maybe we could just
move the name outside it and do that and
we'd be good you know looks pretty good
so that's a little better if I zeroed it
I will get the non-standard extension
error I don't know will this give me a
better error no it's still the
non-standard zero it's still announcer I
want a harder error than that trying to
think if I can get a harder error than
that
[Music]
well you know what this is okay that's
an error we want so let's see that
compiles that doesn't so that's really
all I need for my compile time assert so
I'm going to go ahead and just grab that
I'm gonna put it in here and we'll go
from there so here's my struct name
right here's my brackets expression oops
and off I go so now I should be able to
just loft this up into our platform
library that everyone can use where the
standard assert is and you know here
we've got sort of our debug stuff I can
go ahead and drop this in it's
completely like you don't need it
doesn't need to be compiled out ever it
can be always compiled in because it
doesn't actually do anything so it's
just purely compiled time checking so at
that point this is just you know we're
good to go so what I can do here is I
can place these anytime we've got one of
these I can just place these and we're
saying we need these to be specific
sizes because from now on we're gonna
expect them to be locked in place right
so I can just kind of step in here and
say okay each of these things is you
know gonna be a particular size if
anyone changes it they need to make sure
that they understand that we actually
load these and operate on them directly
so please don't fuss with them and off
we go
so this is one two three four so that's
four sixteen of those so that is 16 for
byte values plus one two three plus
eight eight byte values
let's compile this there we go and now
if we touch anything
[Music]
we should get errors immediately and
that's good
and that's all we needed so that's
that's all we needed so now we've got
our file format laid out the way that we
want it looks like I already had the
asset data type ID stuff I had already
started on that I'm gonna leave that as
hij asset type I think I like that
phrasing better
so we'll just go eliminate that and I'm
gonna get rid of that so now we're just
left with these I don't know what font
type was meant to do
exactly I guess that was just this for
picking fonts I guess that was just for
picking fonts who knows
so anyway looking through here we now
have I think everything that I actually
wanted us to have is it's now specified
not to be cleanly I can move this up to
the top
that's the data type there I want to do
one more thing in it kind of like the CT
assert there that we've got I want to do
one more thing the thing that I would
like to do is make a way for us to
specify which type we were referring to
as kind of a bit of documentation if you
will so the way that I like to do this
is right I mean let me just give an
example so what I would like to do is
here's the data type I'd rather it be
that but the problem is that until very
recently C and C++ didn't have a way of
saying this is this enum is a u-32 so I
want it to be 32 bits the compiler was
free to make it 8 bits or 16 bits or
however many bits it wanted it didn't
have to do any particular size but I
want it to be this size
but I would also like to notate to the
people who may be reading this that it
comes from a particular place so I just
usually do a thing where I pound to find
enum 32 and flag 32 to basically have a
type that is ignored
so they both evaluate to you know 32 a
you 32 as if they were a type but they
allow me to just stick a little date in
there so for example I can say enum 32
this is supposed to be an HSA asset type
right and this is the data type right
and I could just say type right in the
sense because it's that's what it is
it's just the type of the asset okay
and similarly anywhere else that I had a
flag like that I can have that so this
right here you know we had to notate it
like this before I can make that a
little cleaner by just saying okay HHH
sound Shane there we go so now you know
well it's a 32-bit number but it
actually said it's just one of these is
all it's actually trying to tell you so
that's kind of a nice way to do that and
then similarly like with the tag up here
same thing this is an ID it's an HHA tag
ID or what is it called asset tag ID
like so and so now everything is kind of
properly marked up with you know what
it's supposed to have and it's easier
maybe a little bit easier for people to
know what that's supposed to be I tend
to like that if you don't like it no
biggie
you know it's not a thing I think is
particularly important it's just
something I tend to like to do makes
things a little bit nicer to read
alright so that's the final file format
that I think we want to go with right
now and so what I would like to do is
now I would like to just finish the
importer thing right
and so once we imp what so that we can
import everything into the new file into
the new file format from the old file
format so we can still run all of our
old stuff exactly the way that we used
to just as a proof of concept and then
from then on we can just focus on
importing new stuff and how that's going
to work I think that's really all we
need to do now you know looking at these
things there's a couple there's one more
thing that might be arguably a good idea
so if we look at the values
not sure how to state this properly so
one of the things that we want to think
about is how are we going to quickly
access these assets and when we're doing
something like the asset matching we
have a lot of ways we might be able to
accelerate the lookups for example we
know that for something like the head
there might be two things like the
expression that likes you know as the
smiling is it whatever and then the
facing direction right which direction
is it going and one of the things that
we would know about those is we always
know that there's only a certain lookup
like we know there's only four facing
directions or something right so we
could think of trying to do things that
allow us to access those more quickly
the problem with that is it starts to
cut down on our ability to make changes
to those like maybe eventually we want
eight face and directions or sixteen
facing directions having a
floating-point value means you can
always subdivide your range pretty much
forever because you know you're never
gonna really hit that 24 bit limit so
it's hard to say so I'm tempted to do
something like that but I'm just gonna
say look we'll just deal with it on the
back end that's something we'll just
have to write optimized lookups for and
let's just leave it as a floating point
arbitrary bag of crap and we'll just
deal with that after the fact because
that is the thing that would let us have
the most expressive file format and
that's sort of what we're doing here is
letting that happen all right so now
what I want to do is I want to make a
thing if we pop over to the HHI editor I
want to make a thing that allows us to
low in an asset get all the information
that we need out of it and then be able
to write it to a new HHA and that's all
I'm going to try and do today is get
that basic stuff going now the
annotations got
little more complicated since we first
type that in so let's make sure we get
them all in there right so here is our
loaded HHA annotation and what we want
is all of these things right this all
should be in there so we want the source
file date and the check sum the source
file based name offset is not a thing we
need because that's just like actually
going to become a pointer right so
that's that that's the source file base
name down here the asset name and
description and author all the same
right we should also put those reserves
in here I suppose because we want to
carry them through so we'll keep those
in there we have the source file base
name count the asset name count script
count author count those are all
implicitly caught in here so we don't
need those then we've got sprite sheet X
Y and the reserved those we do need so
this is the TV that comes from the file
this is the data that is loaded out of
the file like so and really these are
counted strings this is basically like
the buffer stuff what was that that we
had here that was really the buffer I
don't remember where we defined that
stuff to be honest it's in shared so I I
really want to use a string here like I
said I I feel like that's the best way
to do things typically so I probably
just want that like so and we'll make
sure that's defined somewhere right
that's in what shared
um okay so I would like there to be easy
ways to define these things so let's go
ahead and make some of those inside
handmade shared I don't know if we
already have one but specifically what I
would want here is a way to define a
constant string I don't think we ever
did one of those but basically a way to
define a string in a convenient way so
if we wanted to do something like that
I'm just gonna call it rap Z and
basically all this is gonna do is it'll
take and it probably needs to be we have
a string length somewhere right yeah it
looks like we've got that so it's
external anyway so what I want to do is
say okay if you're gonna take a string
and you want to produce one of our sort
of counted strings from the kind that
see unfortunately defaults - this is our
D string here then what we could do is
you say alright let's convert that it's
gonna be the count is going to be the
string length of Z and then the result
data is just going to be the pointer to
Z and then return it so it's just a way
to like make a wrapper around it and for
what it's worth we can do - we can do
different versions of these we can make
one that works on constant strings as
well so for example in this case we
could make one like this
something like that
and what that would do is just say okay
a constant z string where we have the
string in here there's the Z or whatever
we know that we can make one of these by
getting the count and then having a part
of a data well here's a porter to the
data right let's just do that so we know
we can get a point of the data really
easy what we don't really know is how we
would get the count but remember if this
is a constant then what we can do there
is just say well we know the size of it
the size of it is just going to be
however long it is including the null
terminator so if we just subtract the
null terminator away that would give us
a constant right so what we can do in
this case is say well alright we can
wrap this guy just fine and then these
guys can be constants and they don't
even need to spend the time to do the
string length they'll just know right
and and that should work right what is
this complaining about for string to you
64 that is true that's these parts here
I'm gonna go ahead and do that this way
this would probably not work as well
because the compilers not going to want
to do that assignment in earlier
versions to see it probably work in this
one base name this is not parse to be a
base name so we should probably do that
so this what shouldn't really be done
here the reason for this is so modern
version subsidy allow you to do the
brackets as an assignment older versions
don't
so do in order to maintain some more
compatibility with older compilers I'll
just actually call rap Z in that case
and again that's just just as a courtesy
to people using older compilers 2012
would not have compiled that I don't
know if 2013 would might have but it
might not have as well so anyway this is
not a base name here so I don't remember
if we actually have anything that did
that parsing and don't think we actually
did I think it was just baked into some
routines we could make something that
parsed it but you can see here this will
give us the default annotations that we
wanted and we're gonna leave all the
rest of this blank because we don't know
any of it right we we don't know any of
the other information these are not
probably relevant I mean we could set
them to the information that comes from
source file base the HHA but it's just
probably not useful okay so what we want
to do now is proceed through the process
of loading and all the v0h a file and so
that we can write it and we also I think
want to make something that will dump us
get give us a quick dump of the contents
of an HHA right and I think we we made a
thing look at info - info so I think we
want a similar
that that would in addition to just
printing out the basics of the file
something that would print out all of
the asset erase and stuff like that so
you know let's take a quick gander here
let's go to handmade data and let's use
HJ edit - info to look at you know test
that out no that's pretty good okay my
bad test one done HHA um so this tells
us just that information let's print out
anything that's we could find out from
the header right so let's print out
stuff like the tag count the asset count
right and we could also remember whether
or not it had annotations by maybe just
storing information about that like
something that we could store so we
could store the tag count the asset
count
and then have annotations yes or no
right so then when we load one of these
in here one of these is just not going
to have it so V ones might have it and
we'll set that flag but you know these
never would have it because they just
don't have annotations so this sells us
all right there's 13 assets 25 tags no
annotations it's version zero right and
so then what I want to do is just add
another one of these here which would
say alright let's also have a dump and
the dump would probably print out both
of these things so let's pull this out
into like print header info like so
maybe I'll also do this
it's called source file name right you
know I love that let's do it this way so
that way we can print out one of these
things right and you know get a get a
good groove on there
so then in here I'm just gonna do hey
let's print header like so and then that
way if you do info or dump
you'll get that part first so there's
info there's dump and off we go now
you may be wondering why I started doing
that well if you are familiar with the
bonus pack from handmade from the
handmade fund those who don't know like
if you go to fund here if you contribute
to the handmade fund you get a bunch of
stuff by me like old source code from
old projects one of my really old things
that I wrote but that I've still used
today is this program called tab you
it's just a really it's the smallest
piece of code I mean it's an 8k
executable from 25k of code right but
it's pretty handy and so one of the
things that you can do with it is view a
file that you want to view in a
hierarchical fashion so for example if I
do this and overwrite that test that out
file for example or maybe I can do that
if I was to look at test1dot dump in tab
view you get a little list that you can
you know kind of collapse and stuff
right makes sense and if I hit f5 it'll
refresh the file so what I want to do
now is just kind of lean on the fact
that I have that kind of utility sitting
around to just mean that if I print out
some of these things in hierarchical
order I can also take advantage of any
utility like tab view that can parse
things in based on indentation
right and you don't need to use tab you
could use something else right but since
I had that line around that just seems
like a good thing to do that way I'll
make sure their outputs compliant with
that for easier viewing right okay so in
here when we go through and take a look
at the info dump create stuff and so on
what I want to do here is do like print
asset array like so on or print contents
I want to go ahead and take the contents
as well and print those out
so I'm going to loop over all the assets
here and I'm gonna print them all out
and so much as possible I can also do
the tags separately although we'll
probably want to print those with the
actual theta what we can do both
alright so I'm going to go through the
asset indices here I'm gonna actually
skip 0 because we know that 0 is not a
valid asset so in here we've got our
assets I'm gonna print a particular
asset so this is a set you know number
whatever the number is and then we want
to see we've got information like the
source file base name and the
spritesheet X&amp;Y
and that sort of stuff that's all we've
really got here so I'm gonna use that as
the information I'm gonna use that sort
of as like the name of the asset and
then we'll go from there right so I'm
gonna say let's print the string that's
the source it came from and then let's
print the X the spritesheet X&amp;Y
that it came from that'll be just part
of our way of identifying an asset
loosely speaking so what I need to do
here is get the annotation up for it
I'll just call that a for now or an it's
called an loaded HHA annotation N equals
HHA annotations plus asset index so
that's the asset index there and I can
also grab the HHA asset because we'll
want to print out some data from that as
well
a set equals HHA sets plus I said index
so now that we have those two I can say
first of all all right here's the asset
oops not good asset index and also
here's the annotations I want to know
the source file base name source file
face name dot count and source file base
named data and if I recall correctly
this is actually not because this is a
um M this is like you got to do this
unfortunately right because you need to
actually know what the this has to be 32
bits if it's going to a you write
because we're not printing 64 bit values
there so I'm sorry if it's going to a
width specifier I think maybe that's not
true
maybe that does take a size T I don't
know what it takes
let's see what the compiler says well
we'll see what it does to sprite sheet X
sprite sheet why because I don't know
yeah I don't know what it expects for
that that's a good question I'll find
out
okay so it is an int well I guess
technically it wants
literally an int so we'll give it
literally in it so that's how that
printout would work and now let's try to
make that actually happen so when we
read in one of these files you can see
us kind of sort of maybe a little bit
reading in the assets here like so
the problem that we have is this is
actually not correct anymore because
these are HHS at these zeros that
they're coming from so in here where we
load them the source assets it's
actually an asset v-0 not an asset HHA
regular and so we need to up convert
right so when we actually live this here
and we say this right here this line
should fail now it should say like hey
that's not going to cut it and so what
we need to do now is actually assign the
individual elements of the HHA asset in
a way that will actually work right so
now let's do that it's it's harder than
you might think
some of it's pretty straightforward but
it's harder than you might think right
so we'll see what the EES will do the
easy ones first
JJ asset 0 source assets equals these
horse assets ok so we've got the
distance at data offsets and we've got
the dista set data size and the discus
at first tag index the desktop set one
pass those tag index and the desk a set
type and then we have to do like the
bitmap parts or the sound parts or the
fonts part right so we've got to do
something alright so the first thing I'm
going to do is say that desk asset
equals null asset
clear anything that we don't assign I'm
then gonna take the parts we actually do
now so for example the source asset has
the correct offset in it so that's good
and I feel like the tags so we are not
gonna add any tags anymore we were going
to but we're not anymore
so the tags will be correct as well and
so the things we don't know are the data
type size and the type and then here we
need to do a check based on the type we
need to do one of these so we need to do
a switch on the data type here and this
is going to be an invalid default case
because we should never hit in a v-0
file something that like this that we
don't understand although I could just
print it out
right so we could actually we could
actually be something like that now I
don't really understand why the source
asset index and the desk I set index
aren't the same index does someone want
explain that to me
oh right because we're common that we're
doing the unpack right so we could leave
them to be that we could leave them as
the same indices but we don't have to I
feel like you just would though I feel
like we don't really need to do this
right cuz source asset index is just a
set index here so I'm just gonna say
this is asset mix we're not adding any
asset of the C's here so that should
just be asset index right and that's
fine that all looks good to me okay
so in here what I want to do is say hhas
oops a asset bitmap and all I'm doing
here is just assigning the portion of it
that I care about
and so depending on which one of this it
was we just take that data and that data
is correct we don't need to update that
data at all right we don't have any
annotations to speak of so we just have
to give it the default annotation that's
all we've got and then so the two things
we really need to do here is figure out
what the data size is going to be and
then figure out what the type is right
so the data size actually is something
that we have to determine sort of like
after the fact right like it's something
that actually has to be determined like
kind of in line oops with each of these
so once we actually snap the value then
we can figure out how big the the data
size is often you know in data land
there and so I think if we take a look
at the asset loading we should be able
to figure out how that was going I feel
like that we should have had a thing
that said how big it was like you can
kind of see here yeah I mean
unfortunately looks like we just kind of
we kind of winged it right like each
time here we have so you know one of the
nice things about doing this conversion
is going to be we wouldn't have to do
this anymore like the loader would just
know how big it actually was going to be
so that's kind of nice as well and
[Music]
yeah kind of feel like that's a nice you
know this I feel like this stuff could
get simplified quite a bit right
because you can see this stuff is a
little bit annoying right it's like it's
it's fairly complicated to get that size
right you can see why I don't want that
anymore because even though it's fine to
have this happening in the code here
like a simple utility that needs to like
update these things shouldn't have to
deal with all this crap right like it
should just go like all right look I
don't know what font sorry I don't
process them but I just want to move
them from one file to another or I'm
updating this farm it's gonna copy them
you want to not get that wrong and if it
everybody had to always do all these
computations based on all this stuff
you're totally gonna get that wrong you
know sometimes right so I feel like we
really want that part to be more
sensible right so I like the fact that
we're gonna be pulling that out so yeah
anyway like basing this on we've got
here
all the stuff seems pretty
straightforward so I'm gonna go ahead
and just do it wrote here and then we
may merge these into two into a place
where we could keep it consolidated in a
single file that gives us the
information that we're talking about
here right all right so if we said data
size for the bitmap I'm gonna actually
go ahead and say a church a bitmap
bitmap pulls bitmap so that's the data
size of the bitmap the sound might do
the same thing and then in here we can
just say you know star sound and then
the data size for the sound is handled
similarly right it's like hey whatever
the sample size is which is always that
apparently we don't have multiple sample
sizes and then we've got like a sample
count
and a channel count so that's how many
of those were gonna have and there so
that's all fine then we've got the data
assets aunt part of things
oops found apparently and this again we
got to do that computation up it's nasty
right it's kind of ridiculous this is it
it's it's actually this this here that
you know two computations worth so we've
got the font lift count squared for the
horizontal advance table we've got the
glyph blue glyphs themselves and then we
have the Unicode map and then we off we
go
right so it's actually this and there we
go so you can see why I want to put this
in the file now because now this stuff
if it changes utilities don't have to
know right it can get you know sort of
fussy if it wants to but it won't affect
anyone who doesn't actually have to
understand the data they can just treat
it as a blind block and just go from
there so I think this is all good here
looks pretty reasonable so we're just
down to type and type is a bit nasty the
reason type is a bit nasty is because in
our old sort of our old school like
here's the stuff that we're storing you
were just supposed to know right which
one's these were so what I really need
is a cracking table like I need a table
that will translate these and so what I
effectively need here is like hey let's
find out what the HHA asset type is I
can put in here I suppose
so the what's the HHA asset type so like
type from ID v0 or something like that
right and then what i need to do is say
hey for all of the stuff that wasn't
here what was it right like what
actually was it and so looking through
all of these we've got well none was
none right so this was an HHA asset none
the bitmaps are all here right so this
is HHA asset pit map bitmap bitmap
apparently there's no stairwell bitmap
bitmap bitmap bitmap bitmap bitmap
bitmap and then we've got font and I
believe bitmap again right
I believe that's what these are saying
then we've got sounds
like so and then we're back to bitmaps
right so we've got an array that would
translate these for us now we have the
opportunity here to do something a
little bit fancier if we wanted to and
maybe we want to so what we could do is
say well in here where we've got this
like asset name and we don't know what
the asset name is in this case we could
say well we sort of know maybe what the
asset name is if we were to make this
more of a compound translator of some
kind we could do this right and actually
when we do this trance up translation we
can actually tag these oh that's ones
not included we can actually tag these
with what they actually were and again
you could kind of see why this wasn't a
great system right in terms of
flexibility future flexibility which is
not what's designed for us so I have no
problem with that but I'm just saying
it's why I wanted to change it is
because again you want these if you're
just using it as a date back in
datastore it's fine if you're trying to
do something that would allow like
modding or things like that you need
ways of being more flexible about saying
what things are and where they came from
because that information is just makes
it a lot easier to munge the files
around right and interoperate between
different versions of things which once
you start to get a lot of that in the
mix you just want support you want to
make it easy right and so that's what a
lot of this the difference there is none
of the stuff we had originally was
problem with the problem really but it
just isn't
super flexible for doing something other
than just shipping the game as it is uh
so here's a little type from ITV zero
translation table here's the type here's
the name and so then what we can do is
we can use this as a table to crack open
the sort of secret otherwise
impenetrable asset type fields that we
get in here right so we can say like oh
okay
we now have a type in foam and that type
info will point to the first one of
these unless the asset type that we
received from the file which has the
type ID in it right here right if that
is valid so it's less than the size of
this thing
so we understand that the type is if it
is then let's grab it out and then we
basically say let's take a look at the
at the the type IDs Tran whatever the
translator was so we go down into the
type info and we can now do better for
the default annotation right this part
here we can actually make our default
annotation have a little more in thin
that so the asset name could actually be
something that comes from a buffer here
so what I can do is you know make a well
I guess doesn't need to come from a
buffer I guess it can just be that
string exactly that string so whatever
this is here
is the name that we're going to use and
furthermore we now have the type as well
so the type info can give us that
information so now we have a pretty
fully featured I think import for that
and now we just have to go through and
debug it's looking through here what are
we doing here one past last asset index
that's supposed to be last tag index
that is also supposed to be that and
what else we got okay this is a string
right so this has to do a rap Z and off
we go
okay so now we got to debug this like we
don't know if it's going to work I did
the dump but we don't know if it'll
actually do anything here's what the
dump actually came out with here's each
of the things that was in the file right
and so maybe it loaded correctly maybe
didn't load quickly I have no idea the
only way we can really find out here is
let's go ahead and start expanding on
these so make our make our dump print
out the information that's in them and
see if they're accurate right so in here
we've got our print stuff let's expand
on it first of all let's print out the
tags tags actually we also will want a
cracking table for those are these
values right here so we'll go ahead and
make a little cracking table for those
this just needs a name
and again you can see why
metaprogramming is so useful this is the
kind of thing a partner should never
have to do it's obvious that these are
the same thing and the language to
support them
C++ doesn't I mean I won't belabor the
point I've said so many things about the
sleep of a standard committee and how
bad they are at everything just
reference that this is just obvious
stuff that every programming language
should have had since like 1980 and how
it doesn't I don't know but it doesn't
so here we are typing stuff manually
still um even the most basic meta
programming features would solve that
for you right so anyway we want to get
the tag name out and so that we can
print that let's just print out the tags
real quickly here that's really easy for
us to do we'll just say tag index like
so load out the tag and then I will
print it out
and so all we've got here is effectively
the tag index the name of the tag and I
guess we don't need a string printer for
that because we're actually only getting
it from that array it's the tag name and
then the tag value itself now we don't
want to just print out the tag name
directly what we want to do is first
test to make sure that it's valid
because again remember these files can
get corrupted or someone could write one
wrong and we don't want to just crash on
them and have them not know so we should
at least say look if the tag ID is less
than the array count of that array we've
got then we'll do it right but only then
so we'll say car tag name equals unknown
and then we'll just say okay assuming
you could get at the tag name equals one
that's referenced by this okay so now if
I run this again there we go what we
should be able to see here is okay not
particularly good there those are all
unknown good yeah no totally good
absolutely what I wanted fantastic
do we just not load tags we just don't
load tags
so really we just need to copy the tags
here so let's just do that these are
always the same at the moment so the
tags are just the tags we don't need to
do anything to them we might in the
future if we expand what a tag is or how
it works but at the moment we wouldn't
have to do that
so let's see here
here's a bunch of tags here's some stuff
that doesn't look right there's 25 tags
and we don't know what any of these are
those all seem good those don't
ah that's because we were gonna expand
the number of tags and we're not anymore
so that goes away now we're good okay
so now we've got our tags we've got our
assets now let's go see if our assets
are correct also we can try a different
file and see how that works
this claims it has no tags can that
really be true maybe it is true don't
remember well enough
so I don't
it seems kind of
not possible maybe it is that there's no
tax its triumph intro art
I mean it looks like we're working
properly so maybe those just don't have
any tags in them because they were they
just weren't differentiated in any
particular way they were just like here
here's a rock it's got no tags it's just
a rock you know all right well that's
fine with me
what is structure to art bitmap Oh
lovely so I'm just gonna go ahead and
expand on this and I'm gonna make it
print out a bunch more stuff right so
that we can have a better picture of
what's going on and then I think we're
more or less done with the reading we
just need the writing version right
which shouldn't be too complicated
because most of the hard work we already
did like figuring out the sizes of stuff
so now it's just like a copy it just
like grabbed and copy so that's kind of
nice right
all right so coming through here what we
want to do now is expand on the asset
information that we have so what I would
like to do is take a look at file
formats there and I'd like to go through
the file format and print out everything
that we have right so I want to print
out all of this stuff right so I want to
print out all of that and then I want to
do a switch on the type and then for
each one of these things depending on
which one it is I want to print out the
rest of it right so I want to do like I
want to print out those if it's a sound
I want to print out those and if it's a
font I want to print out these
and then for each individual asset I
will print these common ones first so
that we just know what those are and
I'll print the tag array separately like
so it's like hey here's the tags that go
with it
so in here you know it's just like
whatever the asset type was that's what
we'll we're going for here and if it's a
thief if it's some other kind we just
don't print out any extra day it like if
we don't know the type we just don't
print out the information right and what
I can do here too is I can also say like
you made me do it like this
so if it doesn't know the type we'll
just say like hey man it's this type I
don't know how to print that out but
everybody else can print out the actual
like thing that it is right and so then
oops there's just not enough data here
to really worry about making it be
indented I don't think so what I'll
probably do is I'll just consolidate
this and say it's like you know let's do
that
and then I'll just print out the hotspot
or maybe I'll just say alignment right
so something pretty simple like this I
think that's all we really need to do
there and so I'll just do a nature tape
bitmap here just to make it easier to
print it out save the sound this can be
the same and then it's got a chain mode
so it can be like whatever the sample
count was and the channel count and then
the chain value we can switch on and see
if we know what it is and if we don't
know what it is then we just won't so we
have inside file formats we've got the
various chain values somewhere in here
here they are
I don't really remember if there's
anything no there isn't so the chaining
[Music]
the chain value I think just means move
to the next asset index automatically so
I'm pretty sure that that's all that is
right
so think what I'll do is let's just do
it this way let's crack the value first
so let's say okay you know mode equals
unknown and then we'll to say mode
equals la mode equals looped mode equals
chained right and then we'll just say
like that so that we can say here's the
mode of that sound fontina yeah I guess
we'll just print it out
something like this so we'd have these
two pieces of information and then we'd
have like sent I don't know what
external letting was I assume that's
just like hey this is how much you would
go total from line to line
but I don't know maybe it's the park in
addition to the ascender and descender
height I don't know what we encoded that
us so now we're printing out all of that
information which is nice and now let's
just also add to the beginning of every
font here something which tells us the
like basic layout of the asset itself so
wait so this actually needs to be
when I do a lot of coding that does
massive jumps like this I make a little
system that automatically handles the
tabbing I'm not gonna do that here but
if you spend a lot of time doing stuff
like this you want to do it because
otherwise it ends up going pretty
bananas on you as you might imagine so
we need a way to print out a 64-bit
value here I never remember the stupid
way that that actually works it's
something like that I just cannot
remember so we're gonna have to look
that one up sorry about that
we'll do that
so we want to set the tags here
and then deal with the type so I would
also like to actually print out the tags
and so in here when I actually yeah go
to do it I would like to be able to do
one of these but what you'll notice is I
already Jimmy I already implemented this
code down here so what I really want to
do is change this to be so that the part
that I actually care about can be reused
and don't have to do it again right so
what I'd like to do is make this part
here where we actually print out the tag
information I'd like that to work so
like I don't have to do it twice if that
makes sense
so I want this to effectively be a thing
where it's like print tag and I just
passed the tag and it just does that
right so if I go ahead and take that out
I can make that function here
and this will print out the tag
information for me so then I can do that
here and I can do that
here right so I can say here's the that
tag and rather than implementing this
again I will just do this
so you look up that tag I just need the
tags array plus the tag index enough we
go we should probably put in some things
to check the bounds on the tag look up
there so you know maybe we change this a
little bit
we'll do that one second well you know
we'll do it now
so we we want to check to see whether
the tag index is inside the bounds and
if it is then we'll print it right if
it's not then we just want to print like
some bad error like no bad stop please
do not do that everything is horrible
right so here we can just say like
alright go ahead and print that tag
index and over here we'll say go ahead
and print that tag index and then you
can do your bounds checking so that we
don't end up in la-la-land right we
could do the same thing up here right if
we wanted to we could check to make sure
these are out of not out of bounds so we
could say like look if asset index is
greater than or equal to
HHA asset counts then I'm sorry less
than then do this for the thing
otherwise you know definitely don't do
that because it's it's just garbage
right
yeah
so assuming that works then off we would
go put the type in for a name in there
that's good and so I mean here we just
need to say this is an error and again
that just adds a little bit of error
checking case someone makes a bad HHA
file somehow I don't think it's ever
gonna matter but you know so let's go
ahead and try this again we do the dump
we reload that so there's our tags they
look right again which is good here's
our assets and now we should be able to
look in here and see a little bit more
it's like here's the bytes
there's the offset we've got some tags
it's says there's 47 tag I think we
might have flipped those I think I
probably flipped those yeah it should be
the other way around so we'll fix that
in a second there's the two tags in
question here's the type it's a bitmap
of that size and here's the alignment
and that that all looks pretty good
right
so that looks that looks pretty good so
let me just go fix that typo there for
the from the tag print out so in here
where we say you at you it's actually
that's the count first
there's count and there's the first
otherwise that looks pretty good so that
looks like we're loading these pretty
well right so assuming that we're
loading them well means that at that
point we can probably just start to
write them we'll do that tomorrow and
then we'll be done with that we should
do a reader for v1 hhas as well that'll
be a lot easier because it won't
actually require us to do anything you
like it can just load directly the only
thing we'll have to change is the
annotations we'll have to actually get
locked it up so we'll have to have an
annotation like reader in there but
other than that we're fine so now we
should be able to to
company one of these and see the actual
data like test fonts for example we
should be able to take a look at so if I
do a dump on that please load that up
here so here's all of our assets just
bitmaps right if there's no tags we
should probably just skip the tag fields
maybe like so you know like if we're
printing this out just to make it a
little bit easier to read if there's no
errors and we just don't think there's
any tags maybe we can just say look the
tag count is this
if the tide count is valid then we print
out the tag array if it's not then we
just don't print it because we don't
need to see a tag array that isn't there
right so then we load we load this and
we get all of these have no tags now
right there just like here's the bitmap
data and it's fine so that's all good
and then there should be an actual asset
here that is font or whatever right I
think that's all good the only weird
part is and that looks good is maybe
this should be like the Fock thing
should be up in here maybe kind of
probably possibly so I almost want to
say like we kind of want to crack that
name out early like this like thing here
not sure the best way to really do that
like I mean I could just do this thing
twice
I don't know it's good enough for now
alright I'll go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
here but I think that's pretty good it
seems like the file formats pretty
reasonable now and this this gets us our
import like so now we can use our old
files if you want to which i think is
good I would like to know about these am
I actually doing these properly oh we're
not printing out the annotations I take
it back
I'm not going to the QA yet let me just
put in I wanted to make those those
annotations come out as well so I take
it back we want to print this stuff out
as well so in here where we get the
annotations after we print out the the
asset I want to go ahead and do like the
asset name so the asset name we could
actually put on here as well
we could put that right here if we have
one you know
so that would be cool and then the other
pieces of asset information I should
probably put in there as well so if I do
this on a file that well even these
would would have it right because
everyone should have it now so if I look
at them right you can see what they are
their asset font glyph right an asset
font
so okay and trying to think if there's
what's the other annotation data here
that we want to put so we've got the
spritesheet x and y so description and
author and stuff right
so let's just print those out so if an
asset description dot counts if an
author duck can't if well we can just do
this where it's like it's from this
source file and the fact I guess we
don't really need to put that up here
and like maybe that could just be part
of like a from line so we would just say
like okay it's from this file at this
sprite information the date was that the
checksum was that just so we can see
that date as well so source file date
source file checksum and again I don't
remember if percent llu is actually the
right thing we should look that up
somebody remind me in a second since
we're gonna do QA somebody remind me to
look that up
because I don't remember and one thing
I'd sort of mentioned as a meta comment
again I met a comment I'm a tapper
turning so you'll notice like almost
everything i typed in today was just
busy work that the compiler could have
done for me if again if c++ had ever
added anything good to the language it
wouldn't have had to happen right it's
all wrote stuff you could have written a
little routine that just reads the
structs and it would just print right
and that could just I mean like every
other language has that right like you
can if you just want to in JavaScript if
you just want to print out the contents
of a thing you can write a little
routine that does that and there's a
built-in one that will just do it for
you if you don't care right but you
could write one yourself really easily
to write so you can it's really because
you can access the type information and
that is like the fact that CPS doesn't
have that is nuts it's been 30 plus
years and they still don't have it is
crazy I know they're working on one now
but now is not the time the time was
like 1984 was when you should have been
working on that right like the time has
passed for you for that to be considered
an acceptable thing to not have in your
language
the time passed about 20 years ago yeah
so this looks good here all right so I
think we're good all right to the Q&amp;A
Martin says that static assert is a C++
11 feature and is supported by M SVC 13
so that's probably okay then if it
really is supported by by 2013 that's
probably fine because I think we use the
here Docs which are that if that makes
sense
so I'd be okay with that if we want to
do it that way let's see if this works
okay should we should be able to do it
either way
oops so I don't really need a message
but we can put one in anyway so we could
say look the message is just the
expression so that would replace the
static assert with the C++ eleven way
and if I then changed one of the file
format in theory it should complain
right so same test right so that's fine
I'm down with that we could be fancier
and say right and then it would print
that out as the message right so maybe
that's a little too cheeky maybe we
would just say that
right so and I'm fine with that and we
can flip it back if we need to
Jim zeroes he destroyed do you have a
trick for getting a number for file to
use in the struct name assuming you
don't have a trick for using that in the
struct name
[Music]
how would you do that
well you could
[Music]
you could what I mean you probably can't
turn the address of it into yeah no I I
don't I don't have a way to do that
whoops I have typos something says let's
look at that thank you
in earlier episode of handmade here
around a 160 you answered a question
regarding your plans splitting handmade
here in two parts first for any engine
second or in the game and there was
clarified you still do you still feel
your mood towards that goal or do you
feel this better when you move to the
game code to still work on the engine
head features no I mean I think it'll
still be pretty clear I mean we will
always its our engine so we'll always
allow ourselves to go fix something if
we don't like it but the goal is at some
point you know day 500 or something to
just say alright everything's good you
know it it's pretty much does what we
want it's pretty close to doing what we
want now there's a few things like I got
to finish up the lighting stuff and I
would like to do a little bit of cleanup
on the entity stuff like there's
probably some stuff I'd like to do but
there's not I think we got mostly
everything down there so we should be
good how do you deal with concurrency in
C++
well I mean usually you with concurrency
there's it's kind of a large topic and I
would rather not go into - note to dip
right now it's not really relevant we we
did concurrency related stuff earlier
but the problem I see with concurrency
most the time is that I have never
really seen any good ways of dealing
with concurrency systemically that
aren't slow a lot of the stuff that I've
seen people where they propose like here
is a system for handling like how you're
gonna thread this thing it's just much
slower than a version that was actually
written customized to only do like the
minimal amount of you know locked
exchanges necessary to implement the
actual algorithm now of course that
doesn't mean you always want to write it
because the
miss concurrency is very hard to get
right and you always have bugs in it and
you've got to work to get the bugs out
of it and that work may not be worth you
can afford to do at that time or so on
so it's it's difficult in that regard
right and so I would basically say that
the main things you're looking at when
you're talking about implementing
concurrent things in C++ is dividing
things into probably two parts you know
one where you have a sort of somewhat
generic system you made that just calls
people back to do work concurrently
we've done that in hand made here oh how
the lighting works that's how the
renderer software under worked and you
just assume that that'll be fine for
most cases where things are just doing
computations that don't interfere and
then you have to have some more special
purpose code that you write for data
structures who themselves have to be
handled concurrency concurrently because
that just ends up being hard to do and
it's usually very sensitive in terms of
you can very easily end up with code
that runs slower than the single
threaded code if you aren't careful and
you just are locking all over the place
or doing bad things like that so you
know we do a bunch of concurrency and
handmade hero go back and look at those
episodes if you're curious about it but
it's not a really a silver bullet kind
of thing yhh a version one still
important is it only to convert the few
existing assets yes and also I just
wanted to show how to do it so you know
you could imagine a project where you
had a lot of stuff encoded in an old
file format and now you want to get it
out this is the case this is how you
would do it right we don't need to do it
because we didn't store our data
permanently in that format or anything
so it's not really the end of the world
but it's just I want to show how to do
it
how do I feel about the progress of
hangers are really good actually
it's I mean I don't we don't have a good
thing that shows how many weeks of
programming it has been equivalent but
it's not many it's not even a year of
programming yet and we have just a ton
of stuff in there
so I'm pretty happy with it it feels
like a pretty decent engine for what
it's designed to do and it I feel like
it showed how to do a bunch of stuff so
I learned C or C++ first is there good
advances to us ours well it's a tough
question really the answer is it depends
on what you're trying to do so if you're
just trying to work on stuff that you
wanted to work on and you know you want
to program sensibly then you can really
just learn C and you don't really need
to see this fuss for anything there
really it doesn't have very many good
features in it it's pretty it's pretty
poor language it's just it's just not a
good language however if you're trying
to get a job programming in games you
need to learn C++ because a lot of
people think it's good for some reason
and they you know poop out C++ all over
the codebase and you need to be able to
read it and work with it right that's
just a that's just the way it goes so
you need to learn C++ eventually if
you're going to get a job in an industry
that uses C because most of them use C++
as well I would start with C and learn
it because you can't use C++ at all
without knowing C C is the prerequisite
so keep things simple learn C first then
learn C++ as you go after that but
regrettably most the time you probably
will have to learn a fair bit of C++
even though most of it is garbage and
that's just because of the industry
given that zeddicus turned his language
feature and you can't really plan it
yourself why not just use it because it
doesn't work on past papyrus it's a new
it's it was recently added we were to
look at printf stuff yes I should do
that
see here hopefully psycho dude psycho
forget it right did they get it right
well they did what we did so let's say
that that's right I don't know uh I
should look it up for real stack
overflows wrong all the time let's see
if I can get a actual documentation from
ya
long billion I know we haven't done much
with in-game text in the series yet but
could the asset system be used as it is
for storing Story text tagged with
language tag for translation and other
relevant data tags maybe we would want
custom tags restoring long codes or do
you think it better to make a different
system suited for this purpose also
tabview is looking cool all at ease now
is that kind of came in here a dark
theme good point um I yeah I don't see
why you couldn't I mean you'd probably
want to make a new type called HHA
underscore text and store that as an
asset type and then you could tag it
with yeah like you know information
necessary to know when it should be used
seems fine to me we could do that I
don't know what we want to do with that
really going forward but we definitely
could do that one past last asset index
is not an asset count that's why we
don't do that we wanted to store one
past the last one not account if we do
we store account we do call it count
when we store that
maybe you could add the line to the
message or did it print the line numbers
it prints the line numbers for you the
compiler gives you an actual error here
that you can just jump to so we don't
need to print the line number does the
CT assert fail if you have two asserts
in two files in the same line yes I mean
I it will that's why people often do a
thing where you pass in a name here but
you can usually get away without it
because there's just not that many of
them I'm interested in knowing how
telling a patch or DLC is getting
installed and changes existing code
works would that be covered at the end
possibly in our particular case you can
add stuff to the game by just dropping
in a new HHA so we kind of already
covered how that works
so I guess what I would say is the patch
part where you patch an executable is
probably the ship into executable cause
our executables are tiny how did you
recompile reloaded yellow when load
library seems to keep a lock on the file
well you can just unload the library
right you just do free library but yeah
you can copy the DLL or just change the
DLL name why not use negative 1 instead
of 0 is there a length to get a harder
error you could yeah you could but the
error seemed pretty hard at the end
anyway so it seemed okay but yeah we
could do like that it seems like a good
idea
[Music]
yeah
long-long is not the same as in 6040
type it is 64 a bit but GCC clang will
still complain that llu does not match
you meant 6040 the proper way is to
include int type set H which provides
compiler specific PRI you 64 string
literal as a define so we need to do
printf percent it pry youth 64 comma are
you kidding me who did that and why
Martin's Martin's why would they do that
that's horrible
does the preprocessor parts before
include directive and then resolve the
line after the included parsed no it's
the it's the line it's well okay so I
should specify underscore underscore
line I'm just where underscore
technically expands to the line counter
that is set at that stage of
pre-processing
it doesn't even have to be related to
the file because you can actually change
it so let's suppose for example we did
like
or like this how can I make this
actually show me something trying to
think of how I can show the line number
in an error message cleanly and I'm not
thinking about I don't think you can't
do this can you yeah thank you
it's too bad ah probably can't do this
either I apologize for the incredibly
annoying actually it should only need to
be do this I probably can't do this
either can i all right uh so let's just
do this here's an error right and you
can see that it says it's on handmade
platform that h2 78 right so really
what's happening there is when the
preprocessor starts pre-processing a
file it sets the line counter and the
file to be that files name and the first
line but that can actually be changed at
any time so for example I can just do
this and say what I want the line number
and file name to be now I don't remember
which order they go in because you
hardly ever type this it's which order
is it digit sequence file name okay so
if I want to I can see this is now line
56 and now it says the error is on line
56 which hey it's not but it's not
something that the compiler maintains is
important it just says hey you told me
that that was the line so that's what I
printed out right similarly I can say
like you know oh it's actually on real
fruit-flavored H and now that's where it
thinks the error is right so the real
answer is that file in line are actually
just convention
that the compiler sets normally to the
beginning the name of the file and the
line counter at such a time when it goes
to process the file but you can set it
to whatever you want later right use at
your peril
the good news is that starting with c99
printf supports you modifier for size T
so zu or Z X would work doing the Z
modifier for size T I'm confused
so so are you saying that if I wanted to
I could could I do this could I do this
now and be okay like would that work
okay so that works that's cool I think
that's good Martin's will that be okay
across on GCC I am always afraid on GCC
because I know that they a lot of things
break over there
have you ever changed the line number or
file name in that way in an actual
project yes actually if you do
metaprogramming you probably will and
the reason is because you generate a C
file from a C file and you will want to
set the error to go to the original C
file potentially right okay Martin
zeusie modifier yeah yeah okay so I was
just asking can you just use zu then is
that just safe now
is that just the right way to go from
you know 11x forwards or not really
it will only work for a size t type not
a UN 6040 type okay but that's okay you
know it's at least compact right so you
know I'm okay with that
hmm would that be acceptable on GCC
yeah so hopefully that's okay all right
I'm gonna head and close it down
thank you everyone for joining me for
the episode a handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to file on the series at home
you can always pre-order the game on
handmade hero org and it comes with the
source code so that you can play around
with it yourself maybe you would like to
try your hand at writing out the HHA
files tomorrow before I do and you could
try that tonight in fact we also have
some other stuff you can I point out
today on the stream the handmade fund is
the place you can support community
projects and it comes with some fun
stuff for me as well like that tab
utility and the source code to it as
well as a bunch of other stuff we also
have a watch page you can use to watch a
serious it also has an anti episode
guide on it so for if you want to catch
up with old episodes the series you can
search it it's pretty awesome and jump
right to the places you want to go so
check out that watch page as well and if
you want to see any of the other
products for working out Molly Rocket
just click on the handmade hero head it
will get you to all of our pages nice
and quickly that's about it for today
I'll be back here tomorrow when I'll
just do the agency writing and I think
that'll be about it for HHA maintenance
hopefully from then on where you kind of
have nice smooth sailing for
manipulating our asset files and playing
with them however we want to which is
good we can even write a marriage
utility or other stuff like that really
quickly I think now that's about it I
hope to talk to y'all tomorrow about
that till then f and programming I'll
see everyone on the Internet take it
easy everybody