again like it kind of in keeping with
the the talks the the you know three
game industry talks from today because
the compression talk was definitely the
kind of a more theoretical one but I
kind of tried to select all of the talks
from today to be about the sorts of
things that I can't really address on
handmade hero directly right they're not
the kind of things that you're really
going to talk about when you're looking
at something from the perspective of you
know one or two people who are working
on something and you're you know you're
never really going to get to the kinds
of either personnel scale or data scale
or any of the other things that really
start to introduce these sort of other
problems that exist for no reason other
than scale they're like scale only
problems and so what I wanted to do was
sort of get some perspective on just
like okay for for you know a big
triple-a title one that's like you know
supposed to be kind of a flagship game
where you're you're gonna be seeing all
kinds of like you know high-end visuals
high-end audio these sorts of things
what exactly is sort of the workflow
like on one of these and you know
especially in the case where you have
sort of like a pedigree engine or
something where it's been refined every
time like what does it look like when
this thing's working well and you know
also when it doesn't go well certainly
but just like give us some perspective
on the things that have to happen there
so I invited Jason Gregory to talk to us
about how they do things at Naughty Dog
which I think is going to be fantastic
as I know nothing about how your stuff
is architected at I'm really excited to
learn so please give them a warm welcome
so give us some background on you again
so the people who who aren't familiar
with you kind of know like how'd you get
into the industry like what's you know
what's your background obviously yeah
yeah absolutely
I actually won Canadian hmm
I went to University of Waterloo and I
took something called systems design any
Waterloo P that sounds like it yeah okay
awesome
I took something called systems design
engineering and actually at the time I
thought you know I thought I'd get into
robotics or process control or working
on rocket ship - I don't know something
something that melds different kinds of
engineering because that's what we got
we got a little mechanical a little
electrical and so on but as it turned
out programming was something that
excuse me I was doing at home and I was
I had a lot of experience with and all
the jobs and things I was getting was in
that vein so I ended up going down the
just straight-up programming route so
I'm just a software guy now don't do a
lot of hardware then a little bit of
experience so and it's funny after when
I got into gaming history I worked
outside the game industry for a while
and then when I got into it my mom
actually we were talking with her and
she goes oh that's really great news but
when do you ever want to get a real job
[Laughter]
okay explain that actually games is
probably one of the best places to be as
an engineer because you get all this
wide breadth of different technology
right so certainly that's kind of how I
got into it started at Midway and San
Diego and then EA and then finally at
Naughty Dog okay so that's that's like
actually quite a bit of different
experience with different places yeah
yeah absolutely yeah and so you know at
Naughty Dog like currently you're I
guess you've you've kind of been there
for a pretty wide span of games to give
us a little bit back like when you came
in no dog in like how you've kind of you
know what you've been involved in yeah
yeah I'm very close to being a decade
dog actually we call it so almost I
started right when we were in the middle
of uncharted one and it was interesting
time actually because we were we were
kind of going through a big change from
the way we used to do things on the
Jacke games to what we were gonna do on
the new engine and everything was being
rewritten in C++ and so it was there's a
lot of sort of technical upheaval if you
will we say you guys see the sauce it
was originally written in straight C
you know actually Jack and the games
before that and crash everything was
written in a language called goal which
is a lisp based thing amazingly yeah and
it was pretty amazing because they wrote
their own like custom and I mean Lisp is
not a difficult language to parse and
it's a relatively minimal language so
it's conceivable that you could do this
but they basically built their own
compiler their own language and it was
based on there was C under the hood and
some low-level assembly language code
for the really high performance stuff
but everything else was built like
everything was built in this Lisp
language so what do you mean by
everything like give us an example of
the lowest level component that's still
built I mean it wasn't your code base so
yeah I don't actually know for sure but
I do know that for example the game
object model so anytime you have a crate
or Jack himself or whatever that was a
gold sort of object right and there was
gold code and the cool thing is you
could do this thing called control T
where you could rebuild the code and
have it live update in the game so you
might be iterating like crazy as it
turns out we actually still have that in
C++ you know how you can in Visual
Studio you can do apply code changes
under the debug menu and before that
when we were on ps3 with SN systems
compilers we actually worked with us and
to make sure that that that work that we
could live update your code because it's
super important to be able to iterate
like that that's the workflow that
everyone was used to you don't want to
give that up just because you're moving
away from growth right okay and actually
an another interesting point is that we
still use a lisp like language today but
only for two things we use it for data
definition so this is a rapid way of
getting data that can be expressed
easily in a text format into the game
and I can talk about in more detail
about that it's kind of interesting and
then we also use it as a runtime
scripting language so you literally are
scripters when you're a designer Naughty
Dog the first thing you do is you get a
book on scheme you can get to learn the
basic syntax here and what you basically
learn right what you basically learn is
that
you know function argument a a comma are
gonna be just turns into function a B
there you're done you got it well not
really but it's kind of like that so
yeah we that is actually pretty
fascinating yeah it comes partly from
that history and it also comes from the
fact we've considered changing this many
times because believe me this language
has its issues okay
it's it for example it takes us to build
our entire game from scratch you know
well now we're actually doing a
distributed build and it's even faster
but it used to be maybe maybe seven
minutes or two ten minutes I'm going to
build the entire game and then 15 to
build this stuff yeah like it was really
yeah okay so it's if you mean just to
ingest the text and output whatever the
final format was for at these data
definitions yeah so on because what
we're actually doing is we're running
steam code and so here hearing lies the
reason why we still use it
scheme anybody who's familiar with okay
racket now one of the beautiful things
about this language right because it
basically blurs the line between code
and data right like that there could be
a function f with arguments a and B or
it could be a data array that just
contains values F a and B and moreover
there's a very very powerful macro
language built into racket and scheme
that allows you to transform one what we
call an S expression which is a
parenthesized expression like this into
another and so you can basically have
code that writes code and so what it
means is we can define custom data
structures like for example we have a
system called the animation overlay
system where we can take animations from
one character and we can say no for this
new character all of the animations are
the same except for these ones where
we're gonna overlay new animations and
to do that we just make a little syntax
where you just you know do something
like you know source animation gets
overwritten by destination animation and
then you have a whole list of these in
some other big data structure that's
like define you know and I'm overlays or
something oh and by the way hyphens in
this language are just symbols so it's
not - it's just part of the name it's
weird but anyway so we can just define
custom syntax and then that just spits
out data that our engine can suck in
yeah so essentially you've in in your
data description language you have
metaprogramming which you are sort of
doing on the fly here and I guess as a
consequence of that it's like yeah there
could be fairly complicated meta
programs running at invest time so it's
not as straightforward as just saying I
took in this text yeah I uh put the
Spiner exactly yeah the alternative that
most other studios do is they'll say
let's go with xml or json or let's write
our own custom parsers yes excuse me
anytime you want to add new data you
have to write more parser code and some
programmer has to do that here well it's
the same some programmers to us to do it
but they do it in scheme alright so
they'll literally just write a macro and
a lot of times it's really simple like
there'll be this thing called syntax
rules but literally to say if you see
this pattern of code transform it to
this pattern of code and that's it
there's like a pattern matching element
to it but then it can get way more
complicated in that and so usually it's
the programmers that are doing that
stuff more than the designers although
they dabble in it too so essential is
that I guess you know when you're so you
know and I guess not to dive into too
fast too quickly here's what so if I'm
looking at this and I'm saying wow it's
taking 17 minutes or something to
process this stuff how essential is it
to have that flexibility there is it it
actually no we really use this stuff
like it we couldn't just build twelve
transforms that we tend to call upon and
have that work it's nice could you give
some yeah so first of all when I say
it's like twelve or fifteen minutes a
build that's if you're to rebuild
everything from yes and so the iteration
time though if I just am building I make
it small change to my animation overlays
we have this thing where you could just
say okay just build that one file it
builds in you know maybe 30 seconds ten
seconds it depends right it's pretty
quick and then it's it sends a message
directly to the game using a Redis
server where it's like a remote
procedure call of the game basically and
pipes in the new data and so we can just
live update that data so they can be you
know designer or an animator or whoever
can be just working the game and and
make changes very quick I want to unpack
that whole thing in a second here but
but before before I guess like get into
that yeah yeah you said just just before
we started here that you were like I
want to tell like a
emergency fire story yeah you know after
having listened to Chris's what once you
go ahead and do that so I've got that in
the in this sort of totally totally I
might draw some more so yeah he's
hammered rawr so so yeah it's
interesting because I mean every studio
has this right you develop a big game
you start off thinking oK we've got all
our tools in place everything's good
we've shipped a bunch of our games it's
going to be fine and then you realize ok
like the the jump let's say from
uncharted 3 to the Last of Us uncharted
3 we thought was a big game and then we
got to the last of us where honestly it
was really more of a ps4 game that was
just trying to be squeezed into a ps3
and then that's why we made the
remastered version actually because
honestly it was really almost ps4
content and and then the jump from the
lastest remastered to uncharted 4 was
another I'd say depending on the kind of
ass that you're dealing with it could be
2 X it could be 5 X Wow in terms of just
the amount of data the amount of just
the size of the levels everything was
much much bigger so we had our own
growing pains and I used to think our
problems were bad until I heard Chris's
talk yeah but so what's really
interesting about this whole thing and
this is something you learn with
experience right is that depending on
the decisions you make early on right in
or the decisions that have been made
over years and years of your studio and
the technology you have it leads to a
certain class of problems or certain
kinds of problems that you'll hit and so
the problems that we hit were completely
different than the problems that they
had was with hailer and destiny just
because we made different choices and so
it led to a different right it's kind of
like a chaotic system depending on the
conditions yeah so no you're gonna have
something bad happen it's gonna be
exactly so in our case we we do it okay
so let me actually back up and I'll give
you guys a little bit of a flavor of the
way our pipelines look at a high picture
level okay so this is something that I
found really interesting when I first
got to Naughty Dog we have this
philosophy that I haven't seen in any
other game studio where you know da we
spend a lot of time on dealing with okay
we're gonna publish a stable version of
the game and that will go out every
couple of days and then we'll have
people working on branch
and they can integrate in carefully and
and it was all just very staged and so
on and a Naughty Dog it's Wild West it's
like we just we just run the latest
version of the code all the time and we
run the latest versions of the assets
all the time there is no such thing as
it works on my machine really okay which
is amazing actually in a way by the way
he has a conference room whose name is
it works on my machine so it's a really
different way of thinking about things
and so check it out so what we do is we
whenever we check in code we have
another different code branches for
things like this game is already shipped
and we're doing DLC versus this is a
game that's being live developed you see
code branches you mean in your source
code control system yes yeah so in
perforce services we'll have a branch
that is main which is the main tip of
development for all the games that are
actively in development and we'll have
branches for like when enter before
shipped we branched that off and now we
have you know you for final and that
branch is just its pristine and it's
clean and then if we're making bug fixes
or we're doing a DLC we can do it in
that branch and not and we meanwhile
they can be Wild West on the main branch
again we're out for whatever else we
keep were kind of off and now it's like
you know people who are trying to
maintain that already shipped project
are in there everyone else is on is on
your wild wild west mainline exactly and
people will jump back and forth I mean
the other thing that's interesting about
Naughty Dog is we have a very small
actually very small engineering team
considering the size of the game so so
so I would say we have about I mean
again orders of magnitude we have about
10 programmers who are just focused on
graphics maybe 15 to 20 that do what we
call gameplay which is basically
everything else that's runtime that
isn't graphics and there's specialties
in there like AI physics like but to
give you a sense we have one guy who
actually for a while it was me and one
other guy that was working on it and
then it's this other guy and but it's
generally one or two people who own a
big system like physics for a while and
then they might move on and own
something else and somebody else comes
into that role so maybe 15 20 gameplay
programmers doing all sorts of stuff and
at the for most of the time I've been
there - tools programmers which is crazy
yeah and so how in the heck do we make a
game and honestly I don't really know
sometimes
wondering yeah I'm still kind of trying
to figure it out now since then though
so one of our leads Christine yearling
has moved into the role of just look I'm
gonna own the tools and he's now built
up that team to be four people including
himself which helps a lot I mean it's
doubling the team size and they're
starting to really help solve some of
the technical debt that we have so what
do we describe here it's not my work
this is mostly Christine and his team
and also Christoph Palestra who is our
co-president and he sort of acts like a
CTO for the company okay he's also
working on a lot of this this stuff it's
sort of his area that and back-end
servers and things like that so we built
up the to the tools department to some
degree but anyway so what that means is
relevant small team and people take big
chunks of the engine and kind of own it
okay so back to the rough structure of
our the way we do things so we run the
latest version in the game a program
we'll check something in and that we
have this little bot that's running it's
just a Python script that's running on
on a machine and any time it sees a
change in perforce yeah it says well is
it relevant to the branch that I'm
trying to build yeah okay it's in this
branch great build meaning each of these
branches has their own bill bonds yes
exactly and machine or is it one
machines running lots of build it can be
both or either yeah so sometimes we have
one machine dedicated or whatever okay
and maybe different flavors too like we
might be building the development
version of the game and also a
specialized excuse me final build of the
game there's debug overlays or these
sorts of things and you do have two
different bills so everyone's running
the latest version of the code yes a lot
different people could be running
different sort of flavors of that piece
of code based on whether they want yeah
yeah and actually it's it's so as an
aside it's an interesting point
different flavors building different
flavors of the game has pros and cons
and one of the cons is that if you're
not testing there's a final version then
you don't really know what you're doing
so we we only limit ourselves to two
flavors we have the normal release build
and we have this final build and QA
needs to test both and we actually as we
get closer to the end of a project we
start actually building real packages or
disk images and they test off of the
real deal because of if they don't we're
kind of film so you don't have a debug
build at all no but we do have this is
another cool thing actually that there's
a lot of segues here sorry for that but
um so it's all cool stuff that I hadn't
a lot of this is stuff I hadn't seen at
other studios so we have a thing called
a hybrid build and we used to do
everything with make files and what you
do with this is you just have a special
m'kay file that's for you like okay
Gregorio m'kay okay and it lists a bunch
of files in their CPP files that I want
to have built in debug and everything
else will be released so I can say I'm
working on animation I'm just gonna make
all the animation files a debug and
everything else will be released so the
game still runs reasonably well I'm
super super useful and so anyway okay so
that makes sense so basically what
happens there is it is individual
programmers are in fact running some
debug code you're only running the debug
code that they actually care about a
particular time and I mean I guess
there's nothing to stop them from having
star in there we all just like give me
the whole yes and although well there is
actually one thing which stops them
which is now our game is so big that if
you do that there isn't enough room for
all the code in the space of our budget
so you really don't want to do start
because it cannot actually run yeah but
but yeah so generally that's helped you
work okay so when I check something in
the build bot builds it and there's a
web page you can go to that shows you
like each check in and it goes green if
it's built successfully and then it
publishes it and that just means copy it
up to this network drive that we call
the Z drive okay
now this is another interesting thing is
that Naughty Dog is a hybrid Windows and
Linux studio okay so we're just we're
really old-school yeah the reason for it
though it's partly historical and it's
partly because Linux I mean honestly is
just better at certain things and I'll
give you an example of a little bit
later on of one place where Linux really
shines but a couple of examples maybe so
what ends up happening then is yeah so
the bill gets copied out there and then
we have all of our source assets like
Maya files and so on and I mean if I can
maybe I'll just sketch out so you know
you've got source assets over here can
everyone see that yeah terrible and
writings right so you've got you know my
files and you've got Photoshop now PSD
files and you maybe got some ZBrush
files and
who knows what else and you've also got
these dot DC files which are basically
our scheme these are text files that are
our scheme racket stuff we've also got
what we call our well there's a tool
that's a world builder called Charter
and it has a little database of files so
this is like I'm laying out a world and
there's gonna be some crates over here
and there's gonna be some bad guys
spawning over here it's that kind of
stuff hoarder there's gonna be some
splines or trigger regions it's all that
kind of if you will kind of light data
that it goes into describing a game
world and then kind of on top of all
this is what you might call a metadata
asset database metadata oops
DB and what this is it's metadata about
all these other assets in cylinder form
in cylinder form I'm trying to use the
traditional database symbol oh yeah yeah
so so so for example let's say your
billion animation an animator might find
it really convenient to do a bunch of
run cycles and squatting and jumping
into an all in one big Maya file with
with a timeline but I want to break that
out and say okay this is the run cycle
this is idle and this is jump and so on
and so I have frame ranges so that's a
really simple example of some metadata
that would go into this thing where we
can say okay there's an asset called
player you know Drake jump or something
and it is this Maya file of this frame
range and also these compression
settings and whatever other metadata
you've got I see so in some sense it's
sort of like a manifest in some sense
it's like hey look you're gonna have to
pack this stuff up and deal with it I'm
sort of giving you not only the source
of it but also some sort of like ways
that the source is going get extracted
in some fashion is that just just to be
clear so that is not also in the lisp
way that's just that's got some separate
listing format that's more
straightforward yes and a fully program
yes and in fact I say database because
it acts like a database but our current
implementation it's a bunch of XML files
or sometimes just custom text formats
that are
stored on a perforce server so when
you're dealing with that metadata
there's there's a tool that you have we
call builder although it's a silly name
because it's really more about the data
than building but you go in there and
you can specify assets and all this
stuff and it just saves it by checking
files in and out of perforce and
updating data that way and what's nice
about that is like text formats are
great this is this is a another sort of
fundamental philosophy at Naughty Dog is
is the kis philosophy right keep it
simple we leave out the stupid part you
but so keep it simple and if something
really really simple works do it and
only solve the problem when it becomes a
problem right and sometimes that's bad
because you you can sometimes just think
a little bit close you know near term
right right the good thing is we have a
lot of I think very good senior
engineers who are good at thinking about
like okay here's my near-term solution
but in the back of my head I know that I
can jump from there to here to here to
here to get to this final solution it
might take me to projects to get there
but that's what I've got the plan yeah
exactly it's really important to because
it's kind of one of those things where
you know that that allows you to not
make the mistake of let me do too much
work right here and build something we
didn't really need and over complicate
things but it means that I'm not gonna
hit that sort of integration wall so if
I were like oh now we have to tear the
whole thing down right that okay exactly
and I mean that is so I'd say the
younger you are as a programmer the less
experienced you are the more prone you
are to this which is this sense of how
programming is amazing I can do anything
and then I'm gonna solve the general
problem in fact I'm gonna solve the
problem that can you know I'm gonna file
everyone's taxes while I'm making the
game solving system that they can put
their own taxes on yeah taxes in any
country exactly so
ya see you really want to avoid that and
so we are very very kind of everyone
from Christophe to the leads to just
everybody kind of tries to exude this
this idea of keep it simple solve the
immediate problem have a plan for long
term and deal with the issues as they
come up and then it also comes back to
like premature optimization for example
the old 80/20 rule who's heard of the
80/20 rule right
most people yeah good so like you know
80% of your time is spending 20% of the
code or sometimes it's more like ninety
ten or whatever so you don't want to be
optimizing that eighty percent that
doesn't matter
so we're very big on that so anyway um I
swear this metadata and we have all
these source files and then what happens
right is we have various tools now there
are two ways you can do this
one you can say okay I've got a final
asset at the end so let's say it's in
animation we say do this you mean do an
asset build yeah so some sort of asset
bill so we we have some animation and we
actually package these things into into
things called so let's say we've got
this is maybe animation hey and we have
like anime player layer and this is a
so-called pack file and a pack file is
just a binary format it contains
sections of data and it's so it's
reasonably robust just being able
divided out and say I've got different
kinds of data in this pack file but it's
usually on the realm of like okay I'm
animation player so I've got all the
core animations for the player and that
includes his run cycles and jumps and
everything else maybe in different in
different demeanors but then let's say
the player needs to swim that might be a
different pack file of all the swimming
animations and then there might be
another one that's just this one in-game
cinematic is all just in this one pack
file and pack files can contain other
things so animations they can contain
skeletal rigs they can contain geometry
textures although we've kind of split
those out a little bit but textures
materials all that kind of stuff and
then we have special pack files for this
charter data that are that we call in
game pack files but really it's kind of
a silly name again what it really means
is it's a it's a light pack file that
contains rapid iteration rapid iteration
type data so things like the spawners in
your world splines regions
lightweight data that can be built very
quickly and that you're gonna want to
iterate on quickly okay so actually I
mean kind of thinking back to what Chris
was saying right is to sort of get a
little bit more perspective on that okay
so you're saying that these these are
actually separate formats for this no
it's actually built into the same format
but it's a different kind of file that's
built separately in this in this
pipeline so so it's really just more
about what goes where but the format's
still the same
I'm not fundamentally building a
different kind of file just because it's
light right exactly yeah what the
contents of the file are different
because each of these files has segments
of data of various formats got it but
yeah so there's a there's a process Oh
anyway so yeah there's a process whereby
we take let's say assets that come from
Maya files and textures and they first
of all the Maya file can be exported out
into this is kind of funny too we have a
tool called Maya 3 and dB now what does
this mean well NDB is the Naughty Dog
database format or something it's like
the naughty dog like intermediate format
my okay so my 3 NDB used to be called
Maya 2 NDB with a number 2 but it meant
like the word - and then somebody
thought next version by a 3 NDB
so anyway so you get your NDB yeah oh
well whatever there's a lot of fun stuff
like that in EM so you get this crazy
NDB file and then it goes through
various other processing and eventually
gets packed together with other assets
into a PAC file and then you know and it
could be ZBrush assets it could be
whatever DC works differently it goes
through the our DC compiler which
actually DC stands for data compiler
although the programmer Dan who works on
it we used to say it was Dan's cool
language but it's actually David Clark
and that turns into I think of the bin
file which is a special format charter
database like I say it goes not through
an NDB file per se but it eventually
also becomes a PAC file and all of this
metadata is getting sucked in to just
know how to build all this stuff so is
the just to try to get an idea here so
when these lines are going across here
we're talking probably fundamentally
about a different program doing various
ones of it because like for example you
said Maya 3 NDB it's its own program
it's not some subsection of the acid
build right so the metadata all of these
programs are reading out of that data to
figure out how they pack things so it's
kind of like a common format among
everyone no matter what you're reading
you're out there touching it exactly
yeah exactly and there's and I'm over
simplifying here so my main DB is the
first step where you're taking a Maya
format and you're extracting only the
bits of the scene graph that matter and
putting them into this format that we
can then use to process from there we
might generate we might send it through
havoc to generate some collision data
and other things we might send it
through our geometry processing to get
it down to that format that Chris
Butcher was talking about where it's
like highly optimized for that platform
we there's bits that are gonna process
shaders and build shader code bits that
are going to deal with textures and so
on and so there's a whole sort of
pipeline so that's why these arrows
really represent you know various tools
that might be running and usually what
with so what we'll do is I'll say I'd
like to rebuild an employer so excuse me
so we have a little tool called BA which
stands for build actor which is another
really weird name but actor really just
means basically a pack file okay
and so we say ba annum player and what
that does is it looks to the
dependencies and if you think about this
there's a whole dependency graph right
we're given an employer I say oh well it
contains animations a B C and D
those animations depend on these Maya
files and those depend on these metadata
database assets and these things depend
on these ZBrush assets and whatever it
is in general all of that graph is
coming from the metadata DB or some of
that coming from inside the Maya file
because like a texture reference with
this it's coming from a bunch of
different pieces so basically a graph
links in this graph could come from a
variety of sources yeah and there's
there's pros and cons to this so for
example is many of you probably know
Maya is good at referencing other Maya
files and you can build up a composite
Maya file out of hundreds of other Maya
files if you want so there's those kinds
of references there's references in
those Maya files to our materials and
our textures and stuff which are coded
relative to the project but just as pads
in a file system and so like if I've got
a texture that's blah blah blah got TGA
and it's sitting in this folder then the
relative path to that is embedded
somewhere in that Maya file it's good in
the sense that it's super simple and
it's easy to reason about and so on but
it's hard it's bad in the sense that
it's actually tough for us to pull on an
asset and find out all the dependencies
because have to parse the Maya file all
the things are and presumably and I'm
just guessing here knowing the way
artists would typically use a Maya setup
yeah it's not as simple as saying
anything that's referenced is used I
actually need to do the work to walk the
tree and say oh that was a hidden node
so I don't need to look at that
reference and that was a you know this
texture is just for testing or something
so exactly it gets more complicated than
just what early ex-raf signifies right
exactly exactly
it's it's tricky so and we're actually
working on solving that problem right
now Christian and his team are doing
some really great work on building up an
actual like SQL database you know
relational database that stores this
information anytime you build an asset
it updates those references so that the
next time someone builds you've got that
data yeah because I actually wrote a
tool one point we wanted to be able to
grab some you know assets from let's say
uncharted 3 and pull them over into the
last of us just as a test you know just
to until we had real assets yeah and so
I wrote this thing called grab asset
that would like grab those things
one told me I should shorten it to grab
we're trying so but what that thing did
is it literally would have to it was
slow because it would have to open up
all these Maya files and read and the
our technical directors who are that's
our our TVs are not like a normal TV
they're they're more like technical Maya
people who do Python and they do rigging
and they're they're super smart and they
know all that stuff and that's kind of
their area they're like honorary
programmers that work in a kind of
extended tools programmers um so those
guys actually came up with a way of
storing all of those references at the
top of the Maya file in a special node
so you could just only read the first
you know K of the file and then get all
the references so so that's good but
even then it's ugly so we're moving
towards having an actual database where
you can just query and find information
a lot easier so that's gonna help a lot
but and so essentially that database in
if we look at how this thing is
structured what we're really saying is
okay when I build an asset I'm
essentially producing two files right
I'm producing or two outputs I'm
producing the actual output that I was
trying to build but I'm also producing
this secondary output which is possibly
going to be shared with other people
because normally I guess you see you
only build the one for whatever the
particular machine is here yep in the
other case it's like know every time we
parse it's Maya file we know that no
matter who else will ever build this for
any reason we only need this particular
set of data to be processed when that
asset changes so let's share it yeah and
in fact there's more than one kind of
intermediate file so when I'm building a
single thing like an employer there
might be a bunch of intermediate files a
good example is we have a thing called
streaming animations where you can have
a very long animation and it gets
chunked up into into little chunks that
can be streamed in over time and then I
started and so we might have like a
little intermediate file for each chunk
we might we might have intermediate
files for havoc etcetera so so basically
a small number of or well sometimes a
large number of source assets turn into
a very large number of intermediate
files eventually boiled down to a single
PAC file and yeah so and are these
intermediate files in general I mean
obviously we're talking about the one
where okay we want a pre pre process
sort of the dependencies out of here and
put that in great file you
it's obvious what that gets used for are
these intermediate files generally just
byproducts of the build process or they
but do they have a lifecycle where it's
like oh yeah no we'll reuse one of those
if the person you know like what kind of
intermediate file were talking yeah yeah
so in theory we could reuse them in
right now we don't and it and it's a
problem so yeah so and actually all
right so here's the thing when you build
one of these pack files there's two
places they can go and one is and so one
is our so-called z drive z z drive and
in here maybe we've got like an
uncharted 4 folder and then in here we
have like the build folder and in here
our various sub folders for different
kinds of assets and all of the assets
that the game reads come out of there
but then every user also has their own Y
Drive and the Y Drive is actually it
actually maps to Z slash your user name
so it's all in the same file server and
I could have my own local you for in my
own local build so what I can do is I
can say alright I'm going to build this
asset locally and the game has a mode
where you can say run it in in local
mode where it says alright I'm gonna try
to find the asset on Y and if I can find
it I'll use it otherwise I'll go back to
global and that means I can be as an
animator testing just my animations but
still having the rest of the game be
current
now the Z Drive is shared by everybody
so if somebody builds an asset globally
it goes up to Z everybody will see it
immediately as soon as they rerun the
game or reload that level BAM they see
it right so now just literally a
byproduct of the map drive it's like hey
Windows will try to load it from there
and so it's gonna get whatever the last
thing copied up there yeah basically
it's actually the ps4 reading that and I
can talk a little bit about how that
works as well because normally you go
through this thing called the target
manager through your PC and then it
talks but we actually wrote a special
file server to make it faster but I can
talk more about that later but anyway so
the idea though is that I'm building
these assets globally I'm building the
glue the game globally which also gets
published up to the Z drive and anytime
anybody runs they're running the latest
latest version of everything and of
course the code and asset code in assets
yeah and also those those bin files and
just coding assets and so when you first
tell people that they usually look at
you with this kind of horrific face like
what how can you be
do that that's totally wild wild west it
won't work but it totally works and
here's why because so as a programmer if
I check something in and and it doesn't
compile I see it immediately in the
build button I get a get a message and
that doesn't break anyone because
they're not gonna get an on built
executable exactly exactly so that
doesn't break anyone it just makes the
programmers that go Harry I can't build
the code right so you immediately
quickly jump on that you fix it
worst case you just roll your change
back and then you take your time to
figure out what you did wrong or if you
can fix it you just fix it if you check
in something that breaks the game at
runtime it's kind of the same thing you
start getting a barrage of emails from
people saying hey by the way what did I
do
roll it back or you figure it out
quickly and you solve it but here's the
thing what's the easiest problem to
solve the one that you that you
introduced into the codebase a month ago
and you're not really sure what you did
or the problem that you just introduced
10 minutes ago
right so it turns out that that's just
really really valuable for us and it
same applies to an artist you know I
check in something and I and somehow I
managed to unlink a bunch of animations
from the pack file so now nothing works
oh my gosh what did I do well I was just
working on this oh that's what I did so
it was exactly the reason why pretty
much the standard reason why we always
try to reduce the turnaround time is
because hey seeing the results has all
kinds of positive benefits to it so yes
there may be some downsides to it but
that's really the most important word
yeah exactly
yeah and it turns out stability getting
your stability that way is better than
getting your stability in kind of a fake
way by staging it because now you've got
stability because you're running a game
that's a week old yeah and so so we like
it that's not for everybody I'd say it
works better when you have a maybe a
slightly smaller team yeah yeah yeah but
it definitely works because coming total
people are we talking about running so
I'd say at the height of uncharted 4 we
were probably about 300 plus people in
the studio close it's pretty high yes
it's you know every hundred you add is
is that as
a bad curb but it's like it's like it's
not like oh we had fifty exactly and in
terms of programmers programmers plus
the TDS who are kind of like our
extended tools Department it's maybe
total of thirty forty people at most
right so in fact probably more like well
let's see and yeah maybe about thirty or
so so that's a small enough teaming and
we also kind of have the luxury of we
tend to just we hire people who are
pretty senior so we don't have an
unfortunate that it's bad news in
firstly that there aren't any
internships at Naughty Dog generally
because we just don't have the bandwidth
with such a small engineering team yeah
to be able to manage them to just to
invest the time in training up a new
intern or whatever yeah so I will point
out the fact that although we've talked
about a huge number of things so far
you've still not told us the story that
was supposed to start yes before we got
to yeah no no it's good this is
background that's actually important to
understand that story okay yeah okay so
so in fact the nice segue because the Y
and the Z Drive what do these things
really look like well they're really
this thing called the net app which is a
kind of like a giant NASA if you will
like a giant network attached storage
super-powerful machine that serves up
these massive drives right this is just
tons of Drive stuck in it sitting in
some room somewhere yeah exactly
basically yeah and I mean I honestly I
don't I don't administer the machine I
don't think I've ever physically seen it
but okay I've seen it in my head and
it's very scary okay so so we believe
there to be yes you must seem of this
nature right if there isn't then it's it
maybe it's some guy who's just writing I
don't know but I think it's I think it's
a machine so anyway what we discovered
is so for all the way even into the into
the Last of Us which was a big game we
had some problems intermittent problems
we'd have like tools randomly failing or
you'd fail to read in a file or things
would get slow and nobody quite knew why
but and we would look at various things
on uncharted 4 as we got into crunch it
really hit us because we actually have
we have a farm of machines that build
our assets so when you build locally
what it's really doing is it's sending
off jobs to this farm and on our
previous games it was maybe you know
something on the order of I don't know
four hundred nodes on this on this farm
and now we've got like 2600 nodes on the
farm just to give you a sense of how
much bigger
uncharted 4 got and what we started
having are these kind of nightmarish
things where the whole company would
kind of go down and the network adapt
wouldn't be responding and we didn't
know what's going on it took forever for
it to serve up files so we started and
by we I mean not me but you know so they
what they would do is the net up has
some nice graphing facilities on the web
so you can kind of see what's going on
they would do packet traces and bear in
mind that this is like we're talking you
do a ten second packet trace and get you
know the tens of megabytes of data that
you have to sort through and they
because all of those packets are just
asset Transport for it's gonna be I mean
it's Consul exact response yeah people
are building things all the time and
everything and so they would trace it
down to one person's machine let's say
that's like whoa whoa there's one person
kicked off these jobs that are really
slowing things down and they'd go maybe
say okay kill your build and so it was
kind of like a manual form of load
balancing where he'd say here too many
people are building at once so this guy
stopped and you know she's gonna stop
and he's gonna stop and then everybody
else can finish their bills and then
they'll kick theirs off later and okay
it got kind of crazy we didn't but why
was the NetApp machine I have trouble
with yeah okay that's about
so so so your business just my
mitigation you realize okay we just need
this to go away there right now and
we're gonna dig into this exactly so
good so as we dug in we discovered for
example that so one of the issues was
our exit sometimes our tools would just
fail they wouldn't launch yes what's
going on and so we found it that Windows
actually because Windows is now talking
through SMB to the net app which is
effectively a Linux kind of world right
and Windows has a timeout where if if
just too long goes by between when
you've requested something to run and so
it'll just timeout and it'll stop so we
okay well to deal with that let's move
our executables only on to this low
pressure drive a different drive right
we started moving a lot of our assets
off of the Y Drive on to our local C
drives so like the programmers all have
their code on C now instead of Y just do
me a lot of those kinds of things and
that helped another one that we
discovered that was awesome is you know
how Windows if you change a file and
you're in an editor the editor go bling
such a sense file has changed so called
change notifications well the entire Z
Drive was doing changed notifications
for everybody so we turned that off and
that was very bad so that was an issue
okay and so then we're like we need to
upgrade the hardware and so we're like
we got a better net app that's wider
it's got more cores but each core is a
little slower but we're like yeah it's
okay it's good it's a lot wider it's me
good and it actually got worse like what
the heck's going on okay so Horace you
mean so that drives 19 cores yes actual
the CPUs yeah okay yeah because this
thing is basically a bunch of drives and
some CPUs that are sitting there running
like an operating system that can deal
with all these requests that are coming
in which are coming in over over network
packets right to say things like stat
this file or give me open this file give
me a file handle to this and so on it
seems kind of surprising to me that you
would need particularly heavy hitting
hardware for this process but you would
think but okay because there are just so
many I mean and it's partly because of
the granularity like just to contrast it
with like in Chris's world you have you
have like a giant blob that is the whole
game or that is a whole level and and so
there's almost no granularity
which led to a whole bunch of terrible
problems right but on our side we have
very fine-grained files right so like
each individual animation and there's
lots of little intermediate files so now
we have the problem of large numbers of
files all in different folders and so on
and so we discovered something about the
way that the net app works and when you
think about it it makes sense if you've
got lots of different people you know
doing requests like give me file handle
stat this file these kinds of things it
turns out that the net up has no option
other than to serialize all those
requests because otherwise you get into
a situation where you you say oh
so-and-so this file is this big but
meanwhile someone else is changing it
and right it's a sort of a basic
multi-threaded kind of issue you've got
a choke point and that choke point is is
the net up serializing everything so how
many clearly have no choice but to do it
I mean it would take more logic for it
to do it which it does not have so it
cannot go like oh I realize that these
two file operations will not conflict
right or go I'll let them go and
parallel whereas these two I'd better
hold one of them right okay so it just
goes anyone who touches the metadata is
going in step yeah basically yeah and so
by getting a machine with more cores
where each core was a little slower it
actually made our process worse and so
with that insight we were able to again
change some of the ways that we're doing
things moving files around not having
for example a giant folder with all the
material the intermediate files all in
one giant folder but putting them into
subfolders so that you know you could so
that if you're querying something you're
not querying a huge amount of metadata
all occurring small amounts of metadata
that kind of thing and it's still to be
honest we managed to ship uncharted 4
with a lot of these problems but we
didn't fully solve it and now we're
actually looking at doing some other
things like for example taking some
blobs of data that really don't need to
be files and serving them up some other
way ok so so we'll see how far that goes
but it just I guess kind of goes to show
that you know this mental model that you
might have of a file server is just this
idealized thing that yeah you asked for
fine we'll give you a fine right no
actually it's a it's a computer just
like you know your PC and it's got
software and it's got limitations and
yes also they are presumably optimized
for a specific thing - and if net apps
primary thing that they tended to test
on was not lots of little operations
felling the metadata and rather was just
like what's the sustain transfer rates
for large files and the sort of thing
then obviously they're going to have you
know no idea that this is a crucial
problem exactly exactly I think they
learned a lot from from us howling about
food saying ok ok this is a problem yes
ok but so yeah so those are kinds of
some of the things we did to to deal
with that with that issue yeah no okay
so let me ask some questions here from
because there's a lot of stuff now that
we for sure that we got a lot of yeah so
you kind of talked a little bit about
everyone running the same version of the
game right and so when I'm when I'm
thinking about that I'm just going like
ok so we're all using the same asset
base yeah and I am you know if this is a
very mature type of asset so we've
gotten to the point where we totally
know how it works we're not really
fussing with anymore
I get how all the things you said are
kind of just true it's like yeah ok can
you know all makes sense is good but I'm
curious about the the points in time
when either like I need to make a change
to how this asset fundamentally is
stored or something like that because
the runtime will read it in or you know
maybe I
I'm sure I think it like cases where
that sort of thing happens how do you
deal with the fact that ok I need to
check in a change which the runtime is
gonna need to read this new format of
asset and I know all the assets are not
in that format but everyone's reading
off that and they may not quite have the
look like so they seem like there's this
kind of weird issue I don't want to say
hey everyone stop for a second I'm gonna
update all the ass all right
so I'm gonna see like do you put in both
versions of the code you do like to tell
me a little bit about you know am i
imagining this problem does it actually
exist what doing what you know when I'm
sure yeah basically we just never change
anything no you're absolutely right
there's a whole staging process and so
again SuperDuper simple what's the
simplest thing you can think of for
doing this we do we probably do that ok
so one example is let's say there's a
wholesale change to the pack file format
like we're introducing some you know
you type of thing that just go in there
yeah what we actually do inside these
build folders if I go - oops gonna get
it right if I go to you know build and
maybe I've got like animations and so
it's like annum you know like a
streaming animation and so we just have
like a version number on this folder so
it might be like anime and then there's
a bunch of assets and the game is
configured to read and I'm 50 if I need
to make an animation change format that
that is just sweeping and I need to
really make some major changes I'll
introduce a new folder called am 51 all
right
and I'll start building those assets as
a tools programmer I can just build all
those assets I can kick off because we
do have scripts that will automatically
build all our assets and then we do
actually towards the end of a project do
nightly builds of everything
okay so we're cycling through everything
and making sure that it's all checked
and it's all working okay um and so I
can just build everything I might take
all night but I just build everything
the next morning we testing the game
maybe I get a few people to switch over
to 51 and we try a bunch of stuff and
when we're confident okay it looks looks
good fingers crossed
hold on to your butts and then we we
flip it yeah okay
and then everybody is on 51 and worst
case it all blows up and everybody says
we get a hundred email saying broke and
then we flip back to 50 and we figure
out what we did wrong and then we stage
again that's one approach for smaller
grained changes a lot of times you can
get away with just doing something
that's much more incremental so example
some of our some of our data formats
might have a little bit of padding so
that you know room for growth kind of
thing and then I can introduce some new
flags or some new fields in there and
it's not gonna break anything cuz not as
reading that data it's just zeros in the
original they have it another thing we
sometimes do the geometry the folks were
working on geometry processing so on
introduced this their own little
mechanism where they have a versioning
system within the pack file where they
can say okay I've got geometry version
47 and now I'm gonna do geometry version
48 and I'm gonna write some code that
says if I ever read a 47 here's how to
transform it into a 48 okay so we see
that might put some like logic in there
that's basically saying like hey okay I
think it's not too big of a deal to put
a little translation in there let's just
do that and then I don't have to bother
with this whole thing like hey everyone
switch over to 51 I think we're good
exactly and so that helps you and the
nice thing about doing it that way
actually is that yeah you can gradually
introduce the asset another good example
actually
excuse me is animation so you know an
animation is dependent on the structure
of your of your skeleton of your
hierarchy right and if you introduce a
change to that hierarchy you have to
rebuild all the animations in theory but
we introduced the ability to do some
live retargeting which is super useful
so we can take an animation of Drake and
play it on Chloe just as Anna you know
maybe just as a temporary thing or maybe
even to ship the game if it looks good
and so we use that also to to basically
say all right well if I've got an old
version of the rig or animation that's
targeting the old version of the rig and
I've updated the rig I can have all
those old animations still reference it
so now you have this situation where the
game is never a hundred percent on a
certain version it's got like some of
its current versions some of its one
version back maybe some of its even two
versions back and then hopefully by the
time you ship the game you've been doing
nightly builds and we do this thing
where we lock down towards the end of
the project so there's a there's a
there's sort of a fallow period where
people aren't changing too much yeah and
where things can kind of settle out and
at that point pretty much everything is
100% on the latest thing you know since
you mention it here this is one things
on the list to talk about too let's
let's ask that lockdown question you
said that you do have this sort of
lockdown process and you said you have
soft lockdown and hard lockdown yeah
there's it's kind of not just one
lockdown there's like you know lockdown
and locked in there's really like that
exactly
so yeah just since it came up watch it
give a little bit can give you a little
yeah exactly I mean every studio does
this in some form right you it at some
point you got a ship and you've got to
just stop changing stuff right because
and you know you've got the designer
it's like oh I just want to tweak this
one thing it's gonna be so much cooler
and you got to make that judgment call
and I think this is one place where
Naughty Dog's really it's one of our
core competencies is making that
judgment call between what's worth
fixing and what's not and there are
times when we'll do stuff right up to
the end that other Studios would say
that's crazy you can't do there like
some some you know development directors
somewhere with his you know spreadsheet
or her spreadsheet is going oh my god
like don't you know yeah how can you be
change to this but we feel super
important to tell the story properly or
to or to just get that level of quality
and on the other hand there might be
something that nobody's ever going to
see and
like no we're not fixing that one
breakable cover way over there that
nobody's ever going to go to we're just
going to leave it because it's too risky
to fix it so the way we do that is we
basically before a big deadline like III
or we're actually shipping the game we
go into lockdown periods in in there's a
soft lockdown where basically you have
to coordinate with your lead to check
something in but usually we say yes so
people are still going at maybe 75 cents
speed right so it's almost a nominal
part to just say like okay look now
you're gonna think about it a little
because you have to at least tell me yes
before you do it exactly exactly and
that's probably not gonna say now yes
exactly and and speaking of the way
Blizzard doesn't where they have code
reviews for every check-in for us we
feel like that's - it's too constraining
so we'll do like little code reviews and
stuff during that time like someone will
you know one of the programs will come
to me say and say okay I'm fixing bug
number whatever and I'll say okay well
tell me what the problem is and what
your solution is they'll talk through it
and we might even do a little code
review look at the diffs figure out what
what happened and then I might raise a
few issues like I say well wait a sec
what's the ramifications of that and say
oh I already thought about that it's
blah blah oh I haven't thought about
that and so that's a really nice period
of time to just make sure things are
gelling and it also gets people thinking
about to get them out of that mindset
right because when you're developing
it's full steam ahead make as many
changes you can and get all the cool
stuff in that you want and it's simple
you have to make that mental shift -
okay it's more important that the game
is stable than that your little feature
makes it in right like um so that helps
with that now when you get really close
this is it's essentially honor system
it's like we're not actually sitting
there like you know having to push a
button for the check in as your lead I'd
do it it's more just like look you're
supposed to tell me if you didn't tell
me like what's going on yeah exactly and
we do once in a while someone will be
like oh I didn't hear I didn't hear that
we were in lockdown sorry I checked this
in and then we have a look at it you
know post facto and we say all right
well it was all right it's good or okay
let's back that out or whatever and so
that might be depending on the deadline
it might be that might be a week before
it might be just a few days before or
whatever and then just like really close
to the deadline like on the order of
days we'll
this hard lockdown where you have to get
approval for any change from like one of
the principals in the company so be like
heaven and Christophe or the game
director Bruce Straley or a creative
director or like Neil druckmann in the
case of the Last of Us or in check for
whoever is in that role and then
possibly also like a programming lead so
that we can kind of chime in as far as
the the technical ramifications of that
change and so at that point it slows us
way down right and now any change we
make we're making it with a full
understanding of the risk versus reward
hopefully okay that's the principle of
it anyway and so that's the complete
process essentially for going into those
lockdown things so it's kind of just
like basically saying we're we're
putting impediments in place yeah in
increasing like sort of orders of
magnitude until we kind of get to the
point where everyone agrees the game
it's done out we go and a few other
subtleties there to mention so different
departments lock down at different rates
- so a good example is you know like
sound and particle effects tend to be at
the end of the pipeline right because
they can't be done until other things
are done right you need to see how the
animation looks at a time the sounds and
exactly and if a change in the
animations timing happens the sound has
to be already done sometimes so so what
you end up with is you have you know
design and story at one end and then you
have you know like maybe animation and
geometry and these kinds of things in
physics and then you have sound and
particles at the very end of the pipe
and so usually the lockdown will be
everybody except particles and sound and
they just keep going okay you know it's
it's a it's a wave process it's like as
people you know the earlier you are in
the dependency chain you're getting
locked earlier a little bit earlier
because you know there's these people
need to go home to see their families
yeah there's certainly and and more more
also and just equally important that
because there's there's a chain effect
right so if a design decision has
changed it can have a big ripple effect
now that said yeah and this is another
thing I think not abducted as well is
that we we don't make that a hard and
fast rule it's not like right what
design is locked I'm sorry
even though the game sucks if we don't
do this we can't do it no sometimes
we'll do it and sometimes protocol and
sound will hate us for it right right
usually those decisions are made like a
you know vast majority the time those
decisions can be good decisions that
have a really good impact on the game
although again that's one of those
places where we're trying to find the
right balance because you know there is
a very real impact on people's lives yes
it's not just the game at that point
it's like well you know we have to sort
of be considerate because they are in a
different position than we are because
they are there are the people who have
to come in last right exactly and in
fact it's a big it is a big issue
especially for particles and sound where
they do tend to work till 2:00 a.m. for
a I'm crazy crazy crazy stuff during the
end and we are trying to to be more
cognizant of those ripple effects so
that we can recognize when they happen
and we can make those decisions really
really carefully actually so we're
trying to get better at that now awesome
yeah okay so let me look at first of all
did you have anything else that you
wanted to go down there because I don't
want to hear okay one other detail I
should mention is Rory said that we
branch our code whenever we've shipped a
product it isn't after it shipped it's
actually well before we ship and so good
example was during the development of
the Last of Us uncharted 3 was still
going in fact 1 2 3 was close to
shipping while myself and a small
skeleton team was starting to get the
last of us going ok and during that time
the last was branched off into u3 final
branch or whatever and they were all
working there meanwhile we could
continue along in in the main code
branch and push forward on the last of
us unfettered right so that's another
aspect of the lockdown so there's partly
on our system and there's partly a
branch and that's because like in that
mainline branch you actually don't
really distinguish between you know
either that's the engine codes the
engine code and so on and so forth or
actually that's another thing that's
interesting is that is that our code
structure is kind of like there's a
bunch of shared libraries down here and
then there's there's something that we
call common which is really part of the
game but it's built like it so it's
shared code but it's built in the
context of that game so command whoops
comm
yeah common you can use that eraser that
you did you kept yeah I don't know where
it sits on the back of the mmm oh this
isn't I believe look at that like it
okay so common so this is code that's
shared but needs to be built slightly
differently for different games okay and
then there's the game code itself and so
and all of this lives in let's say the
main branch when we branch off we would
make another branch that is let's say
you are you three final let's say back
in those days and it would have the
shared code oh and and the game of
course there'd be two there'd be like
there'd be you three and there'd be tea
Lu or whatever yeah so in the show here
we would still have the shared code and
we'd have you three but we wouldn't have
the last of us in here at all because
who cares because it's it's you three
final right right meanwhile The Last of
Us and can still continue developing
here it can change common code it can
change shared code and not break this
which is now kind of lost my give me an
example of something that goes in each
of these layers I mean I can maybe guess
but just like for to be explicit about
it so what goes in share what goes in
common what goes in yeah yeah perfect so
something that would go and shared would
be like the core animation engine you
know a lot of the low-level rendering
pipeline and and all of that pretty much
you know a large part of even like the
havoc like dealing with rigid bodies and
rag dolls and these kinds of things
common might be something like
initialization code that sets the engine
up and it's it's like a boiler plate
where it's the setup is mostly the same
but it's a little bit different for
different games okay so we want to be
able to build it differently for
different games but it's still shared
and then game code would be things like
you know Drake's code that does the the
rope and the sliding and all of these
games like player mechanics and and very
custom you know weapon things or or
whatever now another thing is that we
will often you know just for expediency
we sometimes with this develop code in
the game and then eventually we realize
hey actually this is shareable let's
move it down so a good example is we we
came up with this system for a character
dialogue that we call the Vox system and
it started out in game and then it got
kind of migrated down into
and just as a staging point because
there were still some dependencies on
the game and we're actually still the
process now just removing the last few
of those dependencies so that we can
migrate it and sort of promote it if you
will to true shared code at which point
any game could use it and it's zero
dependency on the game itself
no can again sorry to drill down on this
one point here because I'm just I'm not
sure I totally get it though
okay so you know I've got my shared
layer and that seems pretty
straightforward right because it's like
I'm literally thinking of this almost as
you know like a middleware library so
this is like I could give this to
another game team and they could
potentially use it right but the common
layer I'm not sure I quite understand
exactly what something in there looks
like so you said for example the
initialization code might get built
muffle ways but I'm still fundamentally
talking about the same piece of code are
we talking about pound if thefts are we
talking about so the difference is that
common lives in the same directory
structure that all the shared code lives
in okay and it's treated as shared code
but in terms of the make files and how
it's built it's built as part of the
game and so I can build the shared
libraries and not even know which game
I'm building right I don't say I want to
build the you know the such a shared
library yes and I don't know what game
I'm building it's just stuff it's just
code it's a library but with common I'm
building it in the context of either you
three or the Last of Us or you four or
whatever and so I can do things like
pound you know pound if I'm going for do
this special thing and I say big fire
that was our code name for you forcing
you for it pound if you for I do some
special things so that's all that is so
so essentially that's like you know the
code itself is actually not changing at
all
we're strictly talking about
pre-processing kinds of operations that
are happening on it but we like to keep
those sort of segments segmented out
because anyone who puts something in
shared we kind of want to make it very
clear that it's like look this thing has
to not have any of those pounds just in
there that we don't want this to be
something that we're it's got kind of
like you know janky stuff but maybe
building differently yeah I mean so just
as an anecdotal thing when I was a TA I
was looking at low level material code
like shader code or whatever and there
was something in there that said pound
you know Pacific assault right right do
this thing for the players helmet or
whatever it's like really like in the
lowest level so we actually disallow it
like our make folks don't even past
those pound of fines down you can't do
pound if you know you for in the shared
code because it just won't compile but
in the common code you can and so we
it's it's like a nice staging area for
moving promoting things down to share it
and also just for places where you don't
have any other choice
and now obviously there would be I mean
if I'm understanding you correctly there
would really be no cost to you in sort
of the the pragmatic sense I suppose of
allowing people to do such pound ifs
anywhere they wanted to right so this is
more of a discipline thing where it's
like look we we don't want to constantly
be having this thing where I go into
like you said the shader code and I see
all these pound dips in there and I I
just started The Last of Us and suddenly
I'm trying to wade through but you know
the jak and daxter someone's or whatever
and the other thing but so it's like
we're really just doing this as a way of
are tickling to the programmer what is
expected by the time we get to this
thing so ya know that this is something
that we can just go with yeah but
chances are we don't really want to make
all of this code 100% general because
there's some things that are just a lot
more expedient to do with that if if
that goes into the common layer that can
now there's another so actually let me
speak to the reason why we do that first
so um it's partly just that it's good
housekeeping and yes there's and it sort
of feeds my OCD which is nice exactly
keeps you honest I guess a little bit
but there's other reasons for example if
the shared library is quite large it's
it's a good majority of our code can be
in shared and if I can rebuild a shared
library and then actually literally
share that binary you know Lib between
two different games rather than having
to build it differently for different
games that gives us a benefit so there's
there's that and that is from the
perspective of for example a engineer
making a change
who wishes to see that change in both
engines and would like it's relevant so
at that point it's like well I cut in
half
the time for it perhaps not happen but I
am saving a little bit there a little
bit there exactly so so those are two
kind of good reasons I guess the third
is it again canna forces you to just
think think about your architecture and
make a good mental distinction between
something that is that is game specific
and something that isn't um now that's
it you're quite right there are various
hooks that we have in the shared library
so that you can for example have well
like the dialogue system there might be
a place where you need to make a game
specific decision as part of a normal
logic and so for that we use like a
little like a callback system or a
virtual function or like a you know a
function pointer or something great a
mechanism in there that will allow us to
say now now thunk over to some game code
run that game code and then come back
and whatever the results are right there
there are mechanisms for talking to the
shared library in that way right in a
way the shared I think of it more as
almost a framework for our engine more
than a library person got it and then
the game kind of slots in the back of it
so in some sense it's it's like the the
shared is is a very large piece of the
code base and in general we're trying to
kind of keep the game part that we swap
in and out being actually much much less
so if we can promote something shared we
will yeah exactly and I mean again all
this is tempered with pragmatism so you
know when you know there might be times
well especially let's say when we do
this branch we do you for you three
final or you for final if I'm making
changes of the shared code in the main
branch I certainly don't want to be
propagating it up to the other branch
because it could be risky right and so
you know it's all it's a judgment call
but that's the basic principle that
guides how the sheriff okay that makes
more sense
all right so okay but I guess I should
ask n is that every is that everything
if you want to cut cover from the stuff
that we talked about there before I
think so yes if you think of it certain
I just want to make sure so I feel like
I kind of missed I dropped the ball a
little bit on this one because I'm
imagining although this may be somewhat
this this may be a incorrect imagination
kind of like I'm trying to imagine the
mythical NetApp device and so on right
so you you mentioned in the in the
preamble that there are some places
where Linux really shines was this
related to the Y Z Drive situation
and if so yeah I just want to sort of
say can you tell us what that was I've
got to crack that Easter egg yeah we
kind of missed over that a little bit so
yeah I guess um and again I'm I'm not a
not a network administrator so I'm kind
of echoing what my colleagues have told
me about what happened but well so
basically if you're talking if you're
talking to a Windows machine and trying
to talk to over samba right tuna to like
this Linux box that's serving up all
your files
turns out Samba as a protocol is very
chatty there's a lot of network traffic
that goes back and forth and so on and
then you've got issues of Windows itself
like the timeouts on the executables and
these kinds of things yes um and so like
the standard way that a ps3 or ps4 comes
to a developer there's a thing called
the target manager that you run on your
PC and the idea is that it'll serve up
files probably just from your drive or
from a networked PC drive it wasn't
really designed for this whole hybrid
Linux Windows thing and it's kind of
slow to load data from that so we
realized that actually way back and
kristoff are you know co-president said
all right well I'm going to just write a
server on Linux that's effectively like
a web server that just serves up blobs
of data okay and then the PS the ps3 or
the ps4 can just you know resolve that
IP address and talk directly to it and
just get its data that way right so
effectively all the normal things of
some it does like discovery of who's on
the network and why do you have this
drive name and also it's like well look
we all know yeah who we're talking to
let's just get rid of all this that give
me the data exactly and so although from
a sort of a morphological point of view
you're still pinging from ps4 through to
to a machine a Linux machine and then to
the net app versus ps4 to PC to the net
app it turns out that path is faster
quite a bit faster and like you say we
can eliminate a lot of these extra bells
and whistles that we don't need and just
serve up the data and so we end up we
got to a point actually where the game
couldn't keep up with the amount of data
we were feeding it because it was just
so efficient so it's really nice and it
also means that now it's not exactly the
same if I'm running off of an actual
pack file that I've built like a rather
I should say a Sony like package file
right a disk image or if I'm wrong
yes exactly the the loading behavior the
streaming behavior of our engine is
actually a little different off of that
than it is over our network but we aimed
to try to get the throughput to be like
say actually the network's faster than
reading off a blu-ray or reading off of
the hard drive yes yes so so anyway but
that's another aspect actually to making
a console game where you've got it
you've got to think about and test it
both ways because the performance might
be different I'm not sure I understood
why Linux shines in that example though
I could think I might have missed that
part it sounds more like you shined your
team it's it's a little that but it's
also that I guess the NFS protocol is
just inherently a little more efficient
too so okay so even if we're just
because ultimately yeah I'm not a
hundred cent clear on that but I believe
yeah it's one of those hand-wavy things
or it's again Linux is more efficient at
the side yes okay
so I guess that took care of those two
things there because I had file server
as well which I guess is exactly that
thing with Linux okay yeah so one of the
things that that you had mentioned when
you were sort of saying here's some
stuff that would be just talked about
from the sort of things that we do I
guess I'll randomly pick the order here
because I'd like to get to both of them
we have about 20 minutes left I think so
you mentioned that you guys sort of do
you said custom version control for
assets and I was wondering if that that
because you did a thing there were you
like okay well I can have different
directories with data is there something
beyond this like okay so so yes give us
a little perspective like what you've
built there you didn't just want to
check it into your source code control
system right cheese for code yeah it's
good it's good to remember that one yes
so when you think about like the
different kinds of asset files that
you're dealing with source code and also
like these these racket or scheme files
right these DC files JSON files text
files all that stuff it it works well
under perforce and perforce is great
that those cans think relatively small
files text formats that can be diff you
can look back and see the history and so
on not so good for gigantic maya files
right or big textures or PSD s or ZBrush
files
so what we do is anything that's that's
on that sort of big binary blob of data
versus the small text file we and I've
seen this at some other software
companies so it's not a new idea I don't
think but we came up with a new kind of
asset control system and we custom-built
it for better or worse I mean now it's
it's a bit of a thorn in our side
because we have to maintain it but it's
also really it can be very powerful and
it's got some limitations but it works
pretty well the idea of it is that okay
so any of you guys who have worked in a
studio might know that you know you have
that whole ritual or you come in in the
morning and you sync the latest assets
and then it takes fifteen to twenty
minutes or an hour two hours in you
don't have a coffee and talk with your
friends while you're waiting for all
your assets to come down on the witness
I believe we actually had a thing that
someone wrote that does this process for
you before you get to do this let's just
make a thing that does it for you yeah
you talk to the iPhone like the location
services like always like you just like
it 4:00 in the morning it yeah so but
the thing is if think about it like we
got the giant database of very very
large files Maya files all over the
place and any one person doesn't need
all of them well we need all of them but
we don't need all of them to be editable
and to be actually on a machine so
speaking each artist is only really
working but some very specific some
small yeah in some small world that's a
certain set of Maya files and so on and
so this kind of asset control system
like I say I've seen it elsewhere
it uses UNIX or Linux symlinks okay for
basically so you have like it master
repository with all the assets there and
there's one copy of everything that's
like the latest version and there's also
previous versions that are encoded in
some way using directories or file names
or something right right and then you
just have some links to the latest
version on your local machine so on your
Y Drive under you know why you four
there would be an art folder and that
our folder is actually managed by this
tool that we call BAM which I don't know
what it stands for Oh actually I think
it stands for a big asset manager
because big was the codename for
Uncharted
and so that's an interesting anecdote I
went so I guess Jack had a codename of
next cuz they were like it's the next
okay and then so big was was big the
uncharted was big and then the last of
us was things so then we had the next
big thing so yeah so anyway but it's
pretty amazing
I mean you guys cannot start another
franchise we got to come up with another
catchphrase here I guess this period
could be ellipses yeah and we go on yeah
I don't know anyway so so what was I
saying so all right so you've got
symlinks and some links yeah so any
given artists on there why Drive they've
got all these sim links to every asset
in the game and it's the latest version
and then they've got this tool which
we've also integrated directly into Maya
so they can just go in and when you
check out a file what it really is doing
is kaat is removing your sim link
copying the real asset down so you now
have a copy on your on your Y Drive you
edit it and do whatever you want to do
it's it's now locked by the server so
nobody else can edit it and when you're
done you check it in and it becomes a
symlink for everybody and then there's a
little server that link is visually mark
as like read-only or something so
someone doesn't this is this file it's
so part of that process of checking out
that breaks the sim link also turns it
into writable file so you know if you
Maya would say I can't write file or
something if you were do something exact
if it's process wrong exact exactly so I
mean there's obviously a lot of benefits
to that because everybody has the latest
versions of assets all the time if
someone checks something in everybody
just updates kind of magically which is
cool but there's you know there's
obviously downsides as well like that's
a custom tool so if something breaks who
are you gonna go to we gotta fix it
right and the people who wrote that have
since left so now somebody else took it
over right
you know we've got poor Jerome who's on
our tools team and he valiantly took up
the cause and he's kind of owning it now
but there was another engineer before
that and just so there's a cost to it
and I feel like that kind of tool
especially has the cost because you're
tough once you're talking about
something that the artists are supposed
to use typically it makes a big
difference if it's integrated into an
art package once you're talking about
integrating
to an art package you're talking about
maintaining you know compiled builds for
each version of this art package which
now are basically were frequent in it
definitely kind of opens up a can of
wear cerise includes should be simplest
we deal with some of that complexity by
I we exposed I guess if I'm I believe
I'm correct about this we exposed like a
Python interface to that tool so that
coupling yeah so we we and that's that's
the thing actually like too much
coupling in general is always bad right
like especially yeah very tight coupling
and as evidenced by Chris's talk where
everything was super tightly coupled and
you make you change one float and
everything rebuilds so here we're
breaking that by just saying okay we've
got Python interfaces to things and then
you can just which it's much more
portable and you don't have to worry too
much
but even then every time we move to a
new Maya version there's a big effort of
just making sure everything works
because they'll change stuff under the
hood scene is so implicit in I guess
what you described there so this would
mean that you essentially just store
every version of every asset meaning you
just buy more drives you just keep keep
piling drives in every day to this this
NetApp yeah that we don't know if it
exists or is that kind of except that we
do allow ourselves to purge assets after
certain time so we might keep the last
ten versions of something like a purge I
say and what we usually do is we wait
until just in our you know sub head of
IT starts screaming that our drive is
running out of space okay we better run
a purge on this stuff and we'll get rid
of some old friends but it's dangerous a
little bit right because if there's
something that we need yeah and so back
to the compression thing if you could
predict exactly what you needed then it
was great but we can't so so we've
definitely a few cases it's just very
rare where we've had to go back to it to
a tape backup or something to get
something
oh so you do like off-site these and
several knots off-site but you do have
like a sort of a purge to permanent
storage it doesn't per you like it went
away forever right right well we what it
is really is that we're backing up the z
drive and yeah and everything else
periodically and so if even if we purge
something there's probably a backup from
before that has ok so I'm going to ask
one more question then I wanted to ask a
sort of a tie-in question
so you mentioned that this was again in
the email we can't talk about this you
mentioned that you tend to use command
line tools like simple command line
tools a lot and that was part of the
keep it simple about mentality there but
then you said lately you've started to
do more stuff like c-sharp cutie pie
cutie tools right sure yeah and so is
this just sort of you were finding like
we need more like we're not able to
really do everything we want to do in
like meier something or and this we need
our own custom editors and so you've
been experienced that can you give us a
little like you know that's that's three
different things sort of there right I
mean that you into to sort of say why
three different things is it because of
what people are comfortable with are you
experimenting they're going to
consolidate like hi what's what's going
on there it's um I would say it's
largely that excuse me that you have um
you have a team and different people
have different ways that they want to
solve the problem and we you know so
we'll end up having different solutions
coming from different areas of the
company and that's fine so a good
example is if there's a tool and the
artists say they come to the to the TV's
right and they say hey we really need
this thing to be automated like I need
some way to manage my rig and I'd like
to have a graphical interface that looks
like this they go I'll do that in Pike
QT cuz I know Python and it fits really
well into Maya because Maya has got the
whole Python thing now and so that's a
good solution for that problem whereas
let's say our level editor the
programmer who worked on that dave smith
was well versed in c-sharp ice and you
know it's got opengl hooks and all that
stuff and like let's just do that but we
didn't have I wouldn't say that we've
got any kind of overarching studio
policy that says thou must write their
thing in QT or whatever right so we're
pretty flexible on that um and that
sometimes bites us in the butt because
like some people might not be familiar
with c-sharp and they go to try to
change and now they're Charter and the
whole thing and they got to go and talk
to David you okay let me give you a
quick you know primer on how to build it
and everything and then you learn it but
so pros and cons I think we are starting
to move more towards Python for those
kinds of things in QT kind of as a whole
but it's not like it's a mandate it's
just something it's still kind of in its
earlier stages of training maybe you
know five years now you're like okay so
this is how we generally go about this
process
right we're kind of feeling our way
later yeah and I mean some things the
other thing to be aware of too is that
not every tool is ideal as a UI right
like as a GUI because you know there
have been ideas floated sometimes well
let's put all this stuff in a sequel
database or something and then we're
like but wait a sec what about looking
at the version history or what about
doing a simple text search to just be
able to find something right and so we
tend to again try to take those those
ramifications into account and say you
know let's choose things that are going
to remain simple enough that we can
actually let's not lose some of the
benefits as we move towards these things
so I will say - this is kind of
interesting the way we build assets
right now it tends to be on a per asset
basis so and the way that our the way
that our game worlds work we have a
streaming engine so we can stream in
pieces of a world and so just as an
example I don't know let's think about I
don't know you choose a scene from I'm
sure you know in term 4 where there's
maybe like a big cityscape or something
sure um that geometry would be built as
maybe the buildings that you're actually
standing on and moving around that's
maybe one what we would call a level but
it's run just a chunk of geometry data
and then there's like a mid ground where
there might be a bunch of levels that
are like this area of town in that area
of town and then there's maybe one
that's like a wide that's like all the
really low res geometry that's way out
there that you're never gonna get to got
um and those those assets are built
they're divided up into pages say you
know whatever some standard size like I
think we're at like one mag or two Meg
pages now but it used to be 512 K and we
can load in and out pages and so as
you're just walking through a level you
can stream ya pages in and out right but
those levels themselves each one of
those is a pack file so if I'm trying to
build this entire cityscape I might need
to know that I've got seven levels that
have to be built and as the background
artist I know this and so I'm like I was
working on the wide so I'm just gonna do
a BL which is the equivalent of BA but
four levels still just generating a pack
file so BL this and this the wide for
this into the city and so that model is
you could think of it as a pole model
right where I say I want this end
product
and it pulls back on all the
dependencies and figures out and
eventually sucks in the traditional make
yeah very much like make very much like
make although the differences that make
make is very because it's based on on
file times that's really the only
criteria can use right right yeah and so
it's it's usually actually way too
granular a really good example is uh I
let's say I add some special joint to
this rig that's only used by the game to
query the position of my nose right at
the nose position joint sure doesn't
affect the any many animations at all
but if you're to use make it would say
oh the files new or rebuild animations
right so we want to be careful of that
so we actually you really want your
graph to be as explicit as possible
because that reduces the number of
things that get touched on a repo
exactly so you wanted to be granular and
you want it to be yeah explicit so so
like in that case we will have this idea
of a hierarchy ID and these little
helper joints aren't maybe aren't part
of that so it doesn't cause a rebuild as
an example so anyway it's a pole model
but what we don't have right now and
we're moving towards it is this idea of
like we have nightly builds but that's
really just like a a bot right that is
pretending to be a user and pretending
to be manually going BL this now be okay
and it might be out on a bunch of
machines so it's in parallel but it's
really just somebody's just building so
the problem that we have right now is
that when you build it like so I'm Joe
user at Naughty Dog and I sit down and I
say BL some level what it does is it
actually it's pulling your version of
the data and the reason for that is we
want to be able to iterate and we have
this idea of a local build but there
were bugs in it and sometimes the local
build wouldn't turn out properly so we
we wanted to reserve the right to be
able to do effectively a local build of
a global asset using my data and the
idea is I would do this I would test the
game and if it's all good then I would
check in my files and it's good I'm done
okay if something broke then I could
like I can undo my change BL again and
it would put it back to the old way and
then we're good to go
but so what this what this means is that
mistakes can happen like for example
let's say I go into perforce or BAM and
I check out a file right and I'm working
on it and trying something
and I build a few times and then I'm
like I don't really like that so I asked
my you know I just all right just wait
till the nightly builds over writes my
file and I'm good but I forget to undo
that check in that check out right so
now I've got an old version of the file
okay so now if anybody in the company
builds this level it'll be fine but
whenever I build it it'll go back to the
old version that's checked out on my
machine we had a bunch of problems like
that actually where why does this asked
to keep reverting I thought that it was
so and so we go over and go undo the
check-in and oh sorry okay and then it
was it was good so we're moving now
towards having a pristine global version
of the assets that are built by this bot
and that nobody can touch and that way
it's absolutely for sure and the only
way to get a global veil to to actually
go out to the company would be to
actually check it in and that way you
just don't have any of these these
issues so we're moving towards that but
it's not quite there yet so last
question I'll try to sneak in here five
minutes left okay not from the list
okay so when Chris was describing their
asset system this is why I kind of like
having listened to both of them now I
kind of just was sure Darius it sounded
like one of the really difficult
problems they're in some of the things
they were dealing with was just that a
lot of their processing wanted to look
across a large number of disparate
assets right yep and this was a
fundamental problem in terms of why the
system got slow because if that was not
happening then it would be very easy to
start isolating these these graphs right
right so it sounds like you know your
system just doesn't really even have
that happening very much yeah
and so what I'm wondering is do you did
you find this to be a limitation and you
just we live with the limitation or is
it that no actually we we compensate for
that by doing a lot of more runtime
processing of things or you know is
there you trying to see where I'm going
with this
why don't you find that you need these
things that that kind of umbrella out
right right well I think I was thinking
about this myself during during his talk
of trying to just try to get my head
around why why they had these big
problems we did and I think and
unfortunately he's not here
there's talking but I wouldn't I would
have liked to get his input on this but
it seems to me like there's two factors
at play that caused that that monolithic
thing right one of them is that you know
you have you have a bunch of assets of
just little dots each of these is like
an asset that goes into the game yeah
and you've got a whole bunch of source
assets right and it seems like their
dependency graph looked something like
this
right like where everything depends on
everything and so what I end up with is
you have the make game button right and
when you press that 15 million tasks go
off and it tries to build everything
right but if you think about what the
the structure of this and maybe some of
that comes actually from premature
optimization I don't want to put words
in his mouth but it seems to me like for
example not building a certain shader
feature on a certain crate in a level
just because the game isn't referencing
that anymore is maybe once you know
bridge too far right so like what we
would do is we would say okay this crate
needs to have that capability I know
that it's used at least one place in the
game with that capability so just in the
asset database in our metadata we just
say support this feature in the shader
and if nobody pulls on it whatever you
know it just supports it and so it's a
little less optimal but you you now have
a very loose template yeah okay so now
the game object can either pull on it or
not who cares one way to say this would
be like okay so rather than trying to
automate all this stuff and actually
have this you know intelligent system
that goes out and figures these things
out it's just like just let the artist
say that this is what they wanted to
have happen during the build and if they
get it wrong it's okay because they'll
see the results yes but we now know that
they using their intuition you can
fine-tune that to the degree that it is
exactly so it boils down to fully
automated versus maybe a little bit more
human intervention mentioned but the
hammer and intervention always wins
right because humans are smart they want
okay so like if you think about the
dependency tree in our game might be
more it might look more like it might
look more like this where you've got you
know this thing depends on those things
and this depends on these things and
this depends on these things and once in
a while you might have something that
depends across you know
but the tree looks more like this and so
there's all these very lovely natural if
talking about splitting the graph
there's all these lovely sort of natural
split points in this graph and so what
you really have is a forest of lots of
little trees instead of one giant
Gordian knot of dependencies right right
and for that reason we can just pull on
one of these things and the build maybe
takes five minutes or fifteen or you
know and now if it's a light baked then
maybe it takes hours but depending on
the type of asset and we also leverage
the fact that we have different flavors
of assets and each one has its own
requirements whereas it seems to me like
in the in the halo system they were
trying to it was kind of like who here's
a cool hammer everything's a nail you
know put it all into this one tag file
system and everything's a tag which
sounds cool it's kind of like in you
know in UNIX everything's a file it's
awesome
but maybe again just one step too far
and may not leveraging the fact that
different assets have different
qualities and so we can say like hey
animations only depend on this stuff and
we know that it's a bounded problem so I
think that's probably that's probably
why there's that if that's different
yeah but then like you said the flip
side is that we then buy into this idea
of having large numbers of little little
files on a file server and we ran into
that and also I suppose you also how the
situation is like well okay so now there
is cognitive load for everybody who's
ever dealing with these where like I now
have to understand the concept that I
need to set these dependencies up
properly and think about how I'm you
know specifying what needs to get built
for what which you know if you imagine
the intelligent system had worked right
right you could get rid of so it's like
it's kind of this thing it's like all
right but we're just saying you know we
just don't think it's gonna Rhino we
don't think we're gonna get there or
yeah exactly I mean think about it like
any game you ship if there's this
absolute sort of platonic perfection of
the system and then there's the reality
of what you actually ship right and it
sounds like they were trying to go for
as close to that platonic perfection as
possible with zero human error but the
cost they paid for that was just massive
real times in this explosion where as we
like to we actually go the other way
where we say let's just make errors as
obvious as possible so really
example is if there's a missing texture
it's the scrolling you know rainbow
thing it's just very obvious right or if
something fails to connect properly like
you know this guy said that he wanted
that asset but the asset was renamed and
so the connection is broken then it'll
just have a red error message over the
guy's head saying could not connect to
my nav master whatever these records
right so that's that's a port we take
yes we're gonna miss some things there's
definitely stuff in our game where
technically like we might not notice it
till we're playing it at home were like
oh darn it look at that that's a stupid
thing how did that get through you know
but that's the trade-off yeah well we
are out of time thank you so much for
[Applause]