hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream wanted to mention something at
start a stream and we can actually
probably use this for some stuff I
wanted to do on the stream so yesterday
we kind of made the mistake of thinking
that the crash message from render doc
was because render doc was crashing
which I didn't really understand but
turns out they just display the error
messages weird if your app crashes it
says that render doc crashed which I
don't understand why that is exactly n
site does the same thing and so we
thought they weren't working properly
but then we actually figured out further
in the show that that was what was
happening we just set the path wrong so
there's a couple things I want to do
first of all I want to avoid that
problem in the future and we've never
really done any hardening on hand here
so I wanted today just do brief like not
really much hardening but it's a little
bit where like if you run the program
and it's not set up properly it would
produce some error message so that we
know just again in case we're using a
utility like this on stream I want us to
be able to see that it's not working
properly and not just crash right and
then we might as well do that anyway
because you know you don't want that to
be the user experience so when we go to
ship we would need something like this
anyway so it's not wasted and the second
thing I want to do is then today we can
render render dock a little bit learn
how to use it and use it to do a few
more clean up things on the graphics
pipeline that I'd wanted to do as we
roll into the lighting pixel doing pixel
shader lighting so I feel like we kind
of do all of this today and do some nice
stuff with it so hopefully that'll be
good and also I was really really
impressed with the tech support on
render doc maybe it's because they know
who we are or something but I don't know
if it's the normal result but like that
when we submitted the thing they
literally sent back something within
minutes it was in my email I noticed
that after I ended the series under the
stream yesterday where they were just
like oh this just happens if there was a
null pointer dereference it could be
because of render doc or it could be
because of you if you need me to track
it down or how abstract it down let me
know like I never get tech support like
that from hardly and
thing except the like the stuff that was
handmade like like remedy or for coder
right like so it was a really really
good experience and I was very impressed
by the level of I mean I'd pay anything
for that software right I would I would
buy something like render doc and you
know that they just give it for free and
then we're supporting it so I don't know
how that works if they're supported by
somebody or just really like doing
another goodness of their heart but
either way I thought that was really
impressive and that made me want to use
it right because I kind of felt like if
I did the work of reporting bugs and
stuff like that that somebody might
actually fix them which is pretty
different from the experience I get with
say Microsoft Windows where you know I
can report bugs all day long and even
have conference calls with the people
who make it and they don't even
understand what I'm talking about most
of the time parentheses I'm I'm looking
at you Visual Studio thank God we don't
have to use that program anymore all
right so let's go ahead and get started
here on that process so here's our
insight we got that working just fine
render doc we've got here and again it's
just another you watch me install
yesterday if you didn't see that show
you can go back and watch but I mean all
we did was download it from the internet
it's pretty easy down the internet you
install it there wasn't really much else
to do so if you go into render doc I you
know you'll get the icon here I'm gonna
go ahead and pin it to the taskbar like
I've done for some of these that way you
know we just have along here all the
stuff that we tend to launch at all so
I'm gonna go ahead and click on this and
get render doc up here and then I'm
gonna launch our process and we're gonna
do a few things with that so if we open
oops I don't want open it capture
it's launched application that's what it
is so I'm gonna do load last settings
this is what they are and as you can see
here now if with the with the directory
path set properly it runs just fine so
what I want to do is go ahead and fix
the problem that we had which is that if
you give it the wrong directory I don't
know that for example or who knows where
you just get you get garbage so in fact
I don't know if we in the data directory
here yeah so if we actually try to
launch from here you can see that that's
when the crash happens uh and yeah you
know the the thing and and I actually
mentioned this to them in text for it
and I think they were like oh yeah we
should I was just like this makes it
sound like render dock thinks it crashed
you know it doesn't sound like an
indeterminant crash and if it said like
if it just said something like if your
app axes that you know has done anything
wrong you'll get the same dialog box so
you know we don't know where are you
crashed if you're pretty sure you didn't
you didn't crash then go ahead then then
I would have probably gone like oh I
should go look and make sure we're not
doing anything wrong there right so I
think that probably needs to get fixed
but other than that so I would like to
make it so that our app doesn't crash
when you give it the wrong directory
just some a little bit of hardening so
that the initial setup state if it
happens to be busted it doesn't do
anything particularly bad and so what
I'd like to do is just spend a couple
seconds getting that working it's not
super hard we just need to add some way
of reporting stuff when we can't load
our fonts like normally we would render
stuff to the screen ourselves but like
if we don't even have the ability to
load any fonts then we certainly can't
do that and there's other kinds of
critical failures like if we couldn't
open an OpenGL context or something like
that so given the fact that no no no no
no no don't open you I just delete that
program off the hard drive it's such a
horrible pile alright so if I actually
load up handmade
and run it normally what I want to do
now is be able to set in the session
here if we actually get this and put
this to a very bad location that won't
have any of our files in it I just want
to start fixing this and so what you can
see here is we get this kind of crash
that's because we can't load the font
that we normally use to display stuff
that's the one thing that we we always
need to have right and so what I'd like
to do is just have some way of making of
sort of notifying or yeah just just
having some errors I'll remove this I'll
fix this crash and then we'll try to fix
the errors and we'll go from there so
let's first take a look at I'm gonna go
into debug mode and see what the easiest
way is to make sure we don't crash on no
font load and then we also kind of need
to pop up an error message telling
people what is wrong and since we can't
we don't have fonts in this case we're
gonna have to use like a system message
box of some kind right okay so here you
go with get font info and you see it
calling this font ID here and you see
the assertion firing when we went
through here what we would want to do is
probably let's see so when we when we
get the font info if this came back is
zero then that would really be all we
would need to know I think and so let's
see how do I want to do this I'm gonna
first see if we go in to get font info
so if we go into get font info here and
we assert that this type equals HSA
asset font I'm wondering if maybe what
we want to do is I guess what we
probably want to do here is assert that
it's either that or nothing so in other
words if you can't load the font you'll
get back a 0 handle I just want the
assertion in there to prevent you trying
to load something and it have ended up
being some other type right
now when in release mode these wouldn't
be in there so we wouldn't get that
assertion right but I'm curious what
happens now okay
so I'm not sure what this does exactly
[Music]
so that looks kind of garbagey to me so
I'm curious to know where that came from
let's just take a look at what's going
on here and again I'm just pushing I'm
just like pushing through the code
slowly to see like what happens if you
can't load anything to get rid of any
paths that sort of like don't handle
zeros well so here's us calling
simulates here's this updating running
our entities here's us doing our push
cube and so this bitmap ID here is what
would be busted presumably here's what's
saying get bitmap on this ID and you can
see the ID is zero that texture handle
on get bitmap zero I'm not sure what
that's doing I want to see what that's
doing so it looks like asset texture
handle is so this get asset if that's
zero I want to say we're not probably
handling that properly so in all of
these cases I feel like we kind of want
to do something a little smarter than
that we probably want to do something
like this you know what I mean just to
make sure that that basically people
will crash out immediately if they're
not handling the zero case we could also
give them back a garbage version so like
another thing that we could do for
example is have some sort of global zero
handle like for example something like
this you know something like this and in
that case we could just say look either
we're going to give you back the right
one or we'll give you back the the null
one right and so in this case we don't
really need to do anything like that
we can't instead do just look did we get
the asset if we got the asset then use
this otherwise don't write but maybe
what I'll do instead is something more
like this if asset then do this branch
just so it's a little clearer and then
we'll have in here a path that will it's
a path that will just set the oops a
path that will just leave it set to zero
so that it you know you knows what's up
for sound samples we need to do the same
thing but in this case it looks like we
sort of were doing the same thing and in
this case week so in this case we could
just say look if the asset exists and we
get it then we're good
unfortunately like all of these sorts of
things need to be inside the checking so
basically like here we need to push
these down to where we've already
checked asset for validity
I guess that argues against doing it
this way as well so basically we do look
here's the null bit map we'll look
inside the asset only only if we know
that it's okay so something like that
and that looks pretty good to me so now
these are a little more hard they're
hardened they're they're not going to
have that crashing problem I just want
to push that through to the rest of
these so same thing here like when we're
doing these lookups I just want to check
to make sure that the asset actually
exists before we do anything this HHA
asset here will get set only in the case
where it actually can otherwise it'll
return zero to you or you know again I
could do this right I don't know maybe
those should be in the game assets
itself I I'm I'm not sure about that how
I want that to look that's kind of a
that's kind of a different question
maybe maybe it should
so if we go to game assets here like for
example down in here like maybe we just
put the null stuff in there so there's
like alright there's an HH a bitmap
that's the null bitmap and every time we
return one of these right we would just
return whichever one of these is is the
right one so we take one of the HHA
assets here and we say look if we got it
great we'll return it otherwise if we
can't then we can't I think that's
that's really all we're looking for
so in this case we say this is gonna be
assets null asset otherwise we actually
look at it Owen and that's the actual
hhj I suppose so it's it's actually this
oh no no it's actually already the
agency well so maybe we say no HHA
that's it
just to be clear that it's not a
know-nothing elf or the other kind of
asset and then up here where we did that
for nil bitmap I just want and maybe
I'll put no Agent J bitmap as well I'll
just put that in here as well
and then I think that's a little bit
nicer when we've got let's see
no likes it when we've got fonts we
probably want the same thing so there's
like a loaded font here called null font
or something like that and maybe we just
put that in there I don't know if that
will work properly or not so I don't
know if it's better to return 0 or to
return the null font so maybe we'll I
don't know we want to do there but
either way we want to check dupes we
want to look at the asset and we want to
return the loaded font I'm gonna give it
back a no font for now and so this will
give back an old font and then what
we'll do is if you know we get the asset
will actually
properly provide the font it looks like
you're supposed to provide a zero anyway
in this case so I guess that that
suggests to me that zeros always okay so
I'm just gonna make that happen okay so
we'll just do it this way let's say and
then finally for font info it looks like
basically the same thing so if we can't
get the flock out then we'll give it
this null right so in this case it would
be if the asset exists we assert it and
we get the actual data out otherwise we
don't and the result is that no so again
just patching those pointers into like a
block of zeros so that anyone who wanted
to use one without knowing whether it
was valid or not will just get 0 values
and go okay I guess this font doesn't
have any characters in it so I won't
display anything that kind of thing um
that is wait
that is correct isn't it what's the
problem empty oh thank you all right so
that's about it let me go ahead and run
that and just see what we get
perfect so we now run properly when we
don't have any hhas and we can't see any
fonts but that's still pretty pretty
solid right and so now at least we
wouldn't have any crashing but we still
haven't really notified anyone that
something seems wrong and so what I
would like to do is maybe just have some
way of notifying people you know sort of
a thunk through in the platform layer
you know we've got sort of these limited
set of platform services in the platform
API these are these are what we expect
the platform to provide and so if we
look at these what I'm thinking is you
know maybe here there's also like a
platform fatal error
kind of call you know what I mean
and so when we call down to that
platform fatal error we can run the game
and if something happens that that just
makes it like completely impossible to
continue we can call that and issue that
fatal error message so the way that
would look is like inside the assets you
know let's say we load up and we look at
the assets here and we just see that you
know there's none of the things that we
expect to be there are there so for
example if we look at the asset count
and there's like no assets like or if we
look at the file count and there's no
files right and we we can just display
something like hey man not good right so
let's add something like that if we go
into the asset loading where we're
actually loading the files let's just
take a look and if we find that there's
no files loaded at the end of it so in
here we go through and we do like this
kind of thing not sure we're set that
file count here it is so when we look at
this file group and we look at this file
count here if this ends up being you
know nothing would be one example or if
we never load any assets might be
another one and we can just issue a
warning
so maybe what we'll do is just look at
the asset count we know we set the asset
count here right we set it to zero we
Inc it to one after the zero asset and
then we go through and load as many
assets as we can so maybe here I'll just
say look if assets
asset count equals one we'll just say
here we can sort of say look we need we
need you to do something about this
because we probably or I should say exit
out maybe so cuz we you at least need an
HHA that's like the basic things like
the basic font and stuff like that and
so if you run the game and I guess we
could probably do it this way and I
think about it because if you run the
game if you're building in him a
internal we do need to give you a chance
to import some assets because maybe you
were starting fresh but then we should
probably issue a fatal error if you can
literally not owed load any assets we
should probably issue a fatal error
I would assume right and I guess I could
call this maybe there should be multiple
ones maybe maybe I'll do it more like
this where we can do like an error
message and maybe we can say whether
it's a error message or a warning
message or something like that so it's
more like this
so something like this where I can say
which kind of air we're talking about
and so baby in the air message I say
like this is non-fatal because
technically we still run but it's
probably bad something like this and
that just implies kind of how this would
be set up so we would have a platform
error message call here and it's
something like this and it probably just
takes a platform arrow type for the type
of message and then a string right for
the message so the platform error
message basically says you know display
this to the user using some kind of
built in platform thing that hopefully
won't fail it looks like this
and I think that's all we really need so
then I just need to implement one of
those the platform layer and let me see
undeclared identifier that's true this
go first
okay let's see okay uh so now if we run
the game here we should get a crash of
some kind
ooh looks like remedy was unhappy there
I don't know why everybody was unhappy
there
we could probably grab a mini dump let's
find out so that's a jump to zero
actually George if George is watching
looks like jump to zero is a crash
possibly let's let's uh let's see if we
can repair this for George because
otherwise I don't know if you you know
can't debug something can't reproduce
let's just double check and make sure
I'm right about that if I just make
something right here
I could see oh yeah so if I just
literally in this directory right here
just make a file that's like in void
main and I say type def void function
void like so function star function
equals zero function I'm just going to
save that into the temp directory W temp
function or jump to zero crash dot CPP
and I think if I'm right then that was
probably all it was right that's it oops
right so there's that crash which is
what we expect now let's try it into
remedy well I forgot to update the
remedy too
well actually I thought that I did him I
this is the right version right - wait -
nope I'm wrong okay I guess we got to
send a mini dump then I thought it would
just be his jump to zero might crash it
but it didn't so this is a weird bug
let's see what happened because I was
supposed to it was supposed to jump to
zero then I was gonna like that
we didn't set the pointer so let's go
set the pointer that's what I was trying
to have happen
weird and it works here man I should
have saved a mini dump now we have no
idea all right sorry George we missed it
I don't know I don't know man but
hopefully if we catch it again I'll just
I should just take a mini dump anyway
moving on what I was trying to say
before that happened was just that this
is a zero pointer so when it calls this
an error message it should just
immediately crash which we saw it there
now correctly crash and so what we need
to do is pack that in and the window
side right we've got to make it so that
we call a valid function that will
actually display this error message so
let's go ahead and do that now in the
win32 layer we've got sort of this bunch
of stuff where that's actually happening
I'm going to go and put platform error
message in there I've been through two
error message and all I'm gonna do here
is just have Windows output an error
message and then we're gonna exit
process so exit process and maybe with a
negative one just so people know that it
died right and so all we're gonna do
here is just immediately say here is a
message box saying that everything died
and then we're gonna go and then we're
gonna go and exit so if I don't print
anything right oops do that if I don't
print anything then all it will do is
just exit and so it will still you know
it would still close our app but that's
not very helpful right oops we didn't
actually set the pointer let me search
for memory
so in here we'll be set up the table of
API pointers error message this winter -
error message right and then we're
pretty much good to go so now we just
close cleanly but that's really not what
we wanted to do the whole point here was
to inform the user that something had
gone wrong and so I'm gonna go ahead and
try to do that
so looks like I put this in the wrong
place because that's where all of them I
shouldn't put it up by the process stuff
but I did yeah all right
sorry about that let me move that so
let's take error message and move it
down to where all the rest of the win32
calls are because that was actually what
I wanted to kind of be what I should
probably put these callbacks in like
their own file or something so you can
see the entry points a little bit better
but yeah so there's like file closed and
all that stuff and allocate memory so
anyway in here where we do win32 error
message and we have exit process one
what we want to do now is say well first
of all we want to check to see what the
type of error was so if I am fatal I
want to exit but if I'm not fatal I
should probably not right so if it's a
platformer of fatal will exit process if
it's not we won't so then we just need
something to put up a dialog box to the
user and you know message box the X is
probably the easiest thing to do it's
hard to say but here's message box CX
you can see what it contains
it's basically a pretty simple call you
pass it an ASCII string and you pass it
you pass it a string displays the
message and a thing for the window title
you say what kind it is and then you say
what your H window was that you wanted
it to pop up on top of you have an
optional language ID in our case it's
just zero because we're not actually
going to be
customizing that message or anything
then you could pass one of these flags
and you can see which one you want okay
in the case of a non fatal error is
probably what we want and abort in the
case of a fatal error is probably what
we want so we just probably switched
that based on the type so if we take a
look at what that is it's a human value
so mbox
type we're gonna set that to whichever
one we want by default we're just gonna
use idea okay but we're probably going
to want to do this so we're going to
look and see we're gonna set the unbox
type to abort if it's a fatal error and
then we're gonna exit in here we're
gonna call the message box the X call
that's this right here so we'll do a
message box see X and we need to pass
the H wind which we don't necessarily
have one so we'll need a way to see
whether we have one or not we'll take
care of that in a second and then we
need like the text information so we've
got the message and then we have a
caption and so the caption I guess we'll
set dynamically here and so what I'll do
here is we'll pretend that the caption
is an made hero warning and then if it's
fatal
we'll do a handmade hero fatal error and
I will just stick that at the top of the
window then we've got the message box
type we've already determined that and
the language ID is just going to be zero
so really all we need is to know about
what the window handle is now we
typically just use one window handle in
this game so presumably we can just
actually look it up if we go to like the
global win32 state here and we look at
what that store is in it I believe
that'll just have the window handle if
we actually have one see
so I thought it would looks like we're
not posting that window handle out to
here so I would like to post that window
handle out so if we look back at yeah I
guess if we look back here we never post
it we just leave it in here so when we
go to window here probably what I'll do
is I'll just save this out just do we
have it right
why that's weird so when we get this
window handle out and I want to have it
go into the global win32 state that
global win32 state is something that we
initialize right right here right and so
I'm just gonna set it to the window
handle when we get the window handle
back like that and we'll just call this
the default window handle so you know
probably not above the ticket mutex
maybe something like that
so this default window handle will give
us what we want if it's 0 at 0 if it's
you know valid its valid and either one
is okay to pass here and then I think
we're pretty good to go just clean up
our compile errors and that should be
that yeah so if I run this now in theory
you can see here we get the warning
message I don't know why there's a
cancel box because I didn't want one so
I think I've set that wrong because
there's no there aren't two different
things you can do there so that's a
little bit busted so let's take a look
at what the actual settings here are
ah I was setting them wrong sorry I was
looking at the wrong flags these are the
return values so this tells you what got
pushed I actually want these here so MB
okay it's actually what we wanted for
the type normally and and I think that's
it so we would start with just that it
looks like and if it's a fatal error
you know we've got it's these icons that
are probably what we want so we probably
want em be icon warning or I can't stop
right and so this way to penny in which
when we are it should show a different
glyph they're basically just built into
Windows so there's the warning one and
let's just double check I'm gonna try
doing a fatal error now on that same
condition just to make sure again that
the you know that the function will work
if we did have a situation in the future
where we wanted a fatal error I want to
make sure I you know double check that
that actually puts up something
indicative of a fatal error and then
closes the app so if we pass a fatal
error here so you can see now we got the
full error message if I hit OK it closes
so I think I think that's pretty much
all I need right so now that we have
this - I want to say that there were
so you can see here there's at least one
place we had errors happening in fact in
here I think we probably have some too
like logging right so in these in these
cases we probably want to put forth the
fatal error as well right so that's if
we couldn't register the window handle
that's okay you can look at these so if
we didn't get samples yeah and if we
didn't register the window class so if
we didn't register the window class
again that's a fatal error so we can
just put those in here right
so basically in all of these places that
we weren't printing out error messages
before now we can so in this case these
should never happen like it would be you
would be in some kind of really severe
Windows is broken kind of way if you
can't open a window but so let's see
here the samples pointer is just an
unable to allocate memory for sound
samples so something like that and then
you know I don't know if there was any I
guess we could have logging so I could
just lurk look for logging that's just
misc framerate so I don't know what else
we've got yet there's probably some
other things in here we could go through
and clean up and put them in there but
for the most part I think we're good so
that's all I wanted to do just really
simple you know what I mean
and that that should cover us in most
cases we'll see if there's anything else
that we really need later but that's
what we want to see and so hopefully now
if we just go ahead and reset this
I'm not sure what happened there why are
we not loading anything anymore
that was weird let's go down with that
looks like all the data is still there
unless we rewrote it
Oh Soph bean come on up hey puss is with
us sure seems like we got plenty of data
there
so what's did I mess something up when I
was I thought I I thought I did this
properly
there's handmade W handmade that's all
we really need right how come I'm not
getting any heck of I'm not getting
graphics what happened just look at our
lovely sphere and our light probes
though which I feel like is good what
you doing beam do you want to help debug
us join up to buck this huh do you I'm
gonna go ahead and look at what happened
to asset loading wise oh I wonder if
some of those guards are wrong so
actually that makes some sense meaning
if I in here if when you do the bitmap
if I guarded one of the bitmap calls
wrong that would probably do it as well
so if all right we got a saucy we got a
saucy beam beam beam what's wrong what's
wrong what are you looking for you know
we can't program if you're in front of
the keyboard you know that right what do
you want to do hmm you smile look out
the window that's not gonna get the code
done that's not gonna get the code done
you know that and you refuse to help you
never type anything good you always type
garbage n I don't know what you type in
code in cat language which doesn't work
on our computers you probably have more
advanced computers on the planet that
you're from there you go
all right so what I'd like to do is just
go ahead and look at those calls I
modified they're like get bitmap and
make sure that I didn't I may have like
accidentally garbage to those up so
actually in here you can see this was
not supposed to be this way anyway
probably want that um let's see so make
sure all the results okay so we didn't
we did this wrong the result isn't here
anymore for some reason I accidentally
deleted it but that's that's why right
it's supposed to have like a get texture
call how did I delete that accidentally
I don't know so this is the problem
right here right you can see that render
the result here is it's not getting set
to anything I think that's what we
needed right
just looking at whether or not any of
these also did the same thing
so it looks pretty good now let's take a
look there we go
so I think that's all that we really had
to worry about
so now looks like we're back in business
so what I'd like to do now is again try
it with render doc and make sure that
we've fixed the actual problem and then
take a look at a couple things that I
wanted to look at just a separate sort
of issue so if we open up render doc
here and we're still got a setup wrong
I'm hoping now that like when I launch
we won't crash render doc we just pop up
a warning message and so that's just
more pleasant right okay this time it's
them I want to say so maybe it wasn't
really our fault maybe it's only half
our fault
so I don't know now granted we don't
really need it to handle that properly
because you know we saw them we know
what's wrong we saw the message box so I
guess we're okay yeah I don't know but
piping we can run it and so everything's
fine now we can we can look at the
performance and stuff like that and if
we take a look at the performance of the
application again there's some weirdness
and I don't really know what it is so I
would like to take a look at it if we
turn off requesting vsync so we're not
actually asking for for vsync anymore
then what you can sort of see is we we
don't quite always get a solid frame
time right we we sometimes are missing
60 we're like sort of stuttering between
60 and and 30 right and you can and you
can kind of see that happening here
right and so I would like to know a
little bit more about why that's
happening and I don't really know so we
looked at the memory issue and you know
there could be still some of that
happening but I kind of doubt it so I
think it might have to do with the fact
that we're sending these vertices down
too many times for no reason I was just
kind of hypothesizing that that might be
true and so I was kind of hoping to get
a look at that so if I ask render render
dock to capture for us and we go back
and look at the capture so here's the
capture uh at this point I just want to
kind of know like alright what do you
think is going on here and I'm not sure
right but here's here's my theory I'm
just giving you a theory there's a lot
of guesswork involved in performance
profiling certainly so this to rate
these duration information things I
don't know that they're particularly a
cure
it like I don't I don't know that this
helps you with anything because this is
a seems to be a nonsense number there's
no way that our game takes 35,000
microseconds I don't think that's
plausible I I mean it's
maybe the worst case time is that but
like if you look that that would have to
be the worst case time I guess is what I
would say because if the game ever ran
at 60 then you know that you know 1,000
divided by 60 is 16 right so that is
what we would expect to see somewhere
like between 16 and 22 or something like
that right the lowest we saw on there
was like 42 frames a second or something
so 23 so this number just seems
fictitious and not representative of the
performance we're actually seeing so I
don't really trust it but what we could
say is maybe the magnitudes are relative
so you know maybe it does correctly say
that you know this is the place where
the time is being spent or something I
don't know but anyway what's nice about
this is we can see our passes right we
can see them happening so there's the
first pass there's the second pass
there's the third pass there's the
fourth pass right
so basically we're rendering the slices
that we then composite back together and
what I'm hoping is the primary source of
our slowdown but I don't actually know
but what I'm hoping is the primary
source of our slowdown is that we don't
right now really do any work to make
sure that when we send vertices down to
the graphics card that we do that in an
economical way and there's two stages of
that we could do one is we could
actually be really careful about only
sending down vertices that have changed
from frame to frame that's like the most
hardcore and that involves actually
tracking changes to the system and stuff
I don't really want to do that not
yet anyway the second thing is just
making sure that they don't get
submitted every time because we have
four passes here and in the naive
approach the OpenGL driver may be
sending down those vertices all four
times even though they don't change
right we know that the exact same
vertices for four render passes we want
it to know that they're the same and it
doesn't have to resend them over the bus
or copy them into driver memory or
anything like that other than the very
first time and so that's the main thing
I'd like to do is actually go make sure
that that's not happening and so my
assumption is that it is happening and I
would like to take a look and see if we
can actually eliminate that so looking
at the timings here if we were to
believe them which I don't but let's
just say they were accurate or at least
relative we would expect these draw
calls to take time and these calls to
not take any time except perhaps the
first one so maybe this call takes some
time but these calls should be free
right because they're actually the same
data you know I'm saying so I'd like to
get that worked out and see what happens
there to see if that improves things at
all and like I said I don't I don't
really know if it will but I just want
to play with that a little bit so again
running this this guy if we launch it no
I don't need you save that capture if we
launch it I might want to turn vsync off
so I don't have to keep doing this right
so we may set request vsync to to false
that's in the Renault test
yeah so we're just setting this here so
what I think I'll do is I what I might
do is say look if handmade internal so
it's s we don't want to set it so by
default we'll ask for vsync nice lock 60
frames but when we're doing our own
internal testing we turn it off so that
we can see what our frame rate actually
would be so that we can make sure that
we're optimizing for that right so let's
go ahead and launch there we go
right and so that's a nice that is a
nice 60 frames a second and then you can
see sometimes we get into situations
where we're starting to climb right
it seems to be mostly when we're moving
which makes no sense to me I have no
idea why that would affect anything
actually
it also doesn't seem to be locked at 60
even when it says it is that may be an
average frames per second so anyway
let's see what we can do about that I
just want to see what we can do to get
that a little bit cleaner so let's start
with some basic stuff and then we'll
we'll get more will get more unbasic as
we go so inside the OpenGL driver here
just to take a look at what's going on
you can see when we enter a render entry
textured quads here you can see that we
bind some textures and then we do the
draw elements base vertex here right to
set what we're going to use for those
and then when we're done we actually
yeah in fact we actually go through and
say are these are these the slow is this
the slow dispatch path or the fastest
batch path right and you can see us
using them here and it depends which
style of use we're using right you can
see that for passing the indices or not
and then when we actually bind the
vertex buffer you can see that happening
up here we do bind vertex buffer i-s it
probably just has to load them out and
it doesn't really have any idea yeah so
I think it may have to kind of just grab
those every time right and we really
don't want it to do that so what I would
like to do is kind of take a step
towards a more optimal render dispatch
path and say what if we just sent these
down as one like clean pass so we said
here's all the vertices and indices open
jail for this frame and then when we
refer to them we need you we want you to
be able to know
that they're not going to be changing
out from under you so you don't need to
resend them every time right and so in
order to do that we need some way of
telling OpenGL like what's going on with
that and there are ways we can do this
so if you look at say dock set up in
jail which is a good look we've always
used this for looking at our OpenGL
document since people pointed it out on
stream it's been really useful and if we
look in here you can see that there's
ways of actually giving opengl
information about buffers that are
specifically there to tell it that these
are not touched or more specifically we
can tell them when they are touched
right
and so geo map and unmapped buffer is
one way of doing this
GL buffer data is another one and we can
decide kind of which ones we want to do
but let me kind of give you the layout
of how they work and unfortunately these
things change over time so which one's
the right one to do and OpenGL kind of
changes it's one of the bad parts about
OpenGL the advice before used to be one
thing and then it was another thing and
it's just a long story but point being
what this allows you to do is if you
think about what's going on in the code
here right and we look at this what
happens is I'm effectively saying all
right look I want to bind these buffers
here's the vertex buffer here's the
index buffer right at some point I told
you what the data was using buffer data
I can see it here right so we sent it
down and we said that this was something
that we were going to draw and then
later we said all right you know let's
go ahead and draw it using GL draw
elements base vertex right and in theory
anyway well actually now think about it
if we alright we're already using gel
buffer data I'm about to say we should
use it of it but Birdy's go for it that
should have sent the data down and kept
it there
hmm so this should only send the data
one time you know just looking at this
so I guess yeah again you know what we
already did the thing much like
yesterday we already did the thing
although yesterday we didn't ever really
actually use it but I we already did the
thing that I was expecting so I'm not
actually sure yeah again where the
slowness is coming from there let's run
the GL profile in insight one more time
I would like to know if maybe someone
can tell us what the graphics card is
actually having trouble with here so I'm
loading up insight here
I'm going to go ahead and hop around
and so yeah again I guess maybe I don't
know if it's just Windows compositing
that's the problem maybe when I'm full
screen it gets no you can see like it's
spiking up right we're missing 60 right
there very consistently so if I actually
if I ask what's wrong I'm curious what
it tells me how do I get I can't seem to
get insight to want to come to the front
how do I get incite to come to the front
dear end site I this is not helpful
there we go so I guess I said to Ulta
for that window I don't know what that
was supposed to be anyway so if we look
at the profile on here just trying to
figure out what the actual slowdown is
there it's kind of again a little bit
hard to tell because you know if I look
at what these are you know draw them in
space vertex that's this call right here
supposedly I look here here's another
draw in space vertex right here's a draw
arrays of size 4 it thinks that was
taking a ton of time and that's the
multi sample resolved right there right
so it thinks it was taking one point two
seven milliseconds to do that multi
sample resolve which I maybe it is I
don't know but I'm not sure why that
would be the case it's kind of tricky to
say but I believe right I mean just
looking at where that probably is in our
render stream I believe if this call
here resolved multi sample where we're
basically saying like look draw this one
triangle strip here and we're using the
resolved multi sample program so you
know maybe the resolved multi sample
program really sucks and that could be
right look maybe this this program is
really bad and it takes to milk too long
that seems totally plausible right and I
guess I don't know but you can kind of
see the code here it might be because
hey it has to fetch all of these texture
samples that could definitely because
remember it's a multi sample and we're
trying to resolve the multi sample down
and
just trying to look at what's going on
in here I will I guess I'll agree
looking at it it looks too long
so this is the actual path right here we
set the DEF min and Max we look at what
the different depths are in the depth
sampler like this we take half the
difference between them because I
remember we heuristic lis determined
that was the best way to resolve
multiple samples
I'll be honest I don't understand why we
really did that I'm not sure why we
didn't just I'm not sure why we didn't
just use the one that had the highest
alpha
so I'm not it's fairly sure why we did
it exactly that way but anyway we looped
over the sample count and we sort of
combined these together right I would
guess what I would say is the first
thing I'd say is looping versus a
constant so this loop can't be unrolled
we probably want to unroll it and so
what we would rather do here is have
sample can't be a constant so this loop
can be unrolled by the compiler
just because we probably do want that to
happen and you can see us doing our
color combinations here we do the color
combinations with our own multiply which
I don't know how intelligent that is and
then again this in sample here have to
be a real inversion because it doesn't
know what this value is so a lot of that
stuff just doesn't make a lot of sense
so we could probably fix some of this
stuff I don't know to what extent we can
really fix it but without going a little
bit further down the rabbit hole but
presumably we can do a little bit better
than this so I don't know where the
Alpha comes in I'm not sure why there's
why we're not outputting any Alpha but I
guess that's because we don't actually
use it in any subsequent passes mmm we
just use the depth I guess just looking
at it here and I'm just not seeing any
alpha pasture right I mean you see us
setting services book maybe service
lvesque dot a got set up here yeah so
it does it does preserve the alpha I
take it back
so it's kind of confusing and I guess
I'm not really 100% certain but what
probably has to happen here
is that we probably just want to start
by making this be a constant and so
let's go ahead and do that so it's
pretty easy for us to do instead of
sample count getting passed down what we
can do is in the fragment code here we
could just pound to find the sample
count like this okay and so here we're
just gonna say the sample count is a
constant value and so you can use that
constant value everywhere and optimize
this code when you compile it and so in
here what we do is we would just want to
insert that in there you can see us
doing basically that thing here right so
I'll say something like this and then
we'll just do a format string
and instead of doing the instead of
doing this as a string constant
we'll just like printf that's basically
and pass the sample count here so we
just need to know what that that multi
sample account actually is at the moment
and so when we're passing that when we
actually go to use that multi sample
program we were obviously passing down
the actual value somewhere let's take a
look at where that actually happened so
you can see here right we were getting
that result sample count out so what I'd
like to do is just remove that so
wherever that sample count actually yeah
right here I'd like that to go away and
then I want to see what we were passing
down there who was actually setting that
into what so you can see it's setting
the the sample count to just the max
sample count so that should be pretty
simple to emulate right so we just we're
just setting that like so
all right um I don't actually want
handmade here to be running over there
how do I terminate the program there we
go so I'm going to terminate handmade
hero so we get rid of it there and then
I want to debug this you know different
you know this sampler with the
hard-coded constant in there and I may
want to look at it a little bit more as
well just beyond what we're looking at
here and I want to make sure that it
actually works right but sure looks like
it works right
yeah so I think that's working just fine
now and if I actually look at the come
by the compiled multi sample now so in
theory it should just be unrolling those
loops hopefully but it's still gonna do
like sixteen fetches there right and
stuff like this so I don't know what the
most efficient way to actually do that
would be I will say that like we're only
using combined color now so obviously
like commit and NPL are going away
I'm not super sure what else to really
do here I assume this value is smart
enough to not be computed recomputed but
just in case it wasn't what we could do
is actually pass down in sample account
as well so so basically that would just
be a percent groups percent F there Oh
Molly beam that's an unhappy kitty so we
could do something like this as well
just to produce whatever that value is
as a constant so that way we know that
these are coming through as constants
and not as any other kind of value so
that we know it's not actually doing any
work there cuz I don't know how smart
the shader colors I think it's pretty
smart so I wouldn't I would have
suspected it to have done that transform
automatically but I just want to make
sure that it is so since we know the
in-sample account we also can probably
just let me see here taking the square
roots not great so combining in in
combining an sRGB we're taking the
average in srgb space versus taking the
average in bris is taking the average in
in linear space this is a place where I
think we probably would want to start
leaning on the graphics card so having
an actual direct srgb transform and
using real srgb would probably be
significantly better here because this
Texel fetch could automatically do the
srgb for us and it would probably be
free whereas here it's costing a 16
multiplies which is you know it's a lot
of multiplies and I think that would be
nice to get rid of right so yeah
so I don't know what I want to do about
that
similarly we'd get rid of the square
root but that only happens once so
that's a less concerning value right I
don't see much else in here that we're
really doing what I would say is why are
we looping over these twice though and
in fact what are we even doing this this
depth is not used so I feel like we can
at least consolidate this a little bit
the feeder compiler obviously already it
probably knows this I'm not sure it
really matters but what I'm thinking is
we just moved VR before combined color
up here and then in here where we're
doing this nonsense we can just
literally grab just the one part we
wanted which is this and do it inside
here right because this doesn't actually
depend these are not dependent they just
are separately computed so I think we
can just do it in one loop like that and
be done with it so I'm gonna give that a
shot and again I don't know I don't
really know looking at this how much
that sRGB if we had srgb in there I
don't know how much that would help us
but I'm not sure so looking at the
profile here doesn't look any different
again really just have no idea what's
causing that let me look at full screen
see if there's any difference yeah we
just we just have no idea like like we
have we are completely blind as to what
what the total frame time action is
there so here's the frame display time
and you can see like right you can see
that that difference there and I have no
idea who's doing that right we have no
idea why that's happening we're not
really changing what we're doing much
and I guess debug collation is an issue
so you know maybe we should be turning
that off to a certain extent because you
know if we look at the the timings here
you know debug collation is taking up a
pretty big chunk of it that's what's
going on inside game update game update
and renders taking all the time we don't
have much more updating render entities
sim region running tests so you know
looking at this too
just in terms of the amount of time it
takes us to get the frame out to the
card we could up to be we could that's
good optimi we could optimize that guy
quite a bit looks like we've got too
many vertices going through that path of
the pipe inside update and render
entities we know what's taking all the
time there
so when Meowth output that grass stuff
right just take a look here so when
we're drawing the ground cover right
like if you were to turn ground cover
off you would take a load off of the the
vertex pipe quite a bit and I'm just
curious to know what that looks like
frame rate wise so the ground cover has
been turned off and if we take a look at
the frame timings right we get a
definitely different view here so
there's the wing in the frame display
there's the debug collation there's the
game update time total game update time
and you know if we hop along through
here we can kind of see what we're
getting for a frame time and it looks
pretty consistent there so I guess what
I would say is I don't know we're
getting some very odd behavior and
behavior that I don't like which is that
and it could have to do with the fact
that we're doing the multi monitor
streaming stuff but you can see as I hop
around here we're getting clearly not 60
frames a second there's like jerkiness
but it's unclear where that's coming
from
or why right like the our frame timing
is not reporting something different you
know what I mean we're seeing the same
profile but that but when you actually
look at the world you get a completely
different perspective on it right so I
don't know if you guys can see this but
like it's jerky it's it doesn't look 60
frames a second to me and again I don't
know that could just be because of the
the problems with outputting to a second
monitor for streaming and that is
happening at you know 30 frames a second
or 60 frames a second mandatorily right
it can't do anything else so it may be
like as if vsync is on even though we
have turned it off on this machine and
it's really hard for me to say because I
don't know what's going on there with
the streaming right I don't know if
that's if the Windows compositor is
affecting us there right but what I can
say is at least from our profiling we
know that we're spending a bunch of time
you know in that in that way right and
debug collation here obviously taking a
lot of that time too
which again is unfortunate that's just
looking at all of our debug in event
information so you know if I turn that
off we could also see to what extent you
know when we're running in an actual
environment here what we would get and I
don't know so when I if we look at
handmade debug or handmade slow I'm
curious what stuff actually
I feel like we probably want to have a
way of still recording just the basic
information about the frame time and
just not recording the rest of this you
know what I mean so you know if I go
into here and we set handmade slow to
zero if I go look at the profile we're
still gonna be spending a crap ton of
time in debug collation right
and so handmade slow doesn't really mean
what it means yet I mean what it says
because you know here's the here's a
process list out and almost all the time
is being spent in debug collation all
Sun right and so what would be nice to
do is to get rid of most of the debug
collation stuff and so you know all of
the all of the block data output and the
timing and all of that maybe that kind
of needs to go away right so
[Music]
you know looking at looking at how we've
got this here I'm just trying to think
if we can selectively enable some of it
and disable some others so here's a
bunch of stuff that happens looks like
all of this stuff is probably fine timed
block probably not so like these you can
see we've got like a separate set of
these coming on afterwards so you know
getting rid of this it's probably pretty
easy it's just this just needs to get
cleaned up you know so you know you can
imagine doing something like this and
trying to make this work
[Music]
so that would take out some of it so now
for example well no that didn't work I
would have expected this to go away
right so we said if defined supercilious
and him eternal and you're not oh that's
because it should be and the handmade
slow is set okay GV said event recording
macro redefinition yes so these and HUD
time function were up here they were in
the separate block so they were up here
and so that makes sense why those were
in the wrong place let's see what else
fails frame slider under third
identifiers so debug UI element looks
like it's not going away for reasons
that I'm not sure why so debug UI
element is to find where so debug UI
element is just calling record debug
event but debug UI element should be
nerfed right oh I was just missing
that's all it needs to go away
looks like debug hit and debug
highlighted also I can't say why those
are the same so really these just need
to be if not defined right so if you
didn't define these functions we then
will define them otherwise we don't do
them and then I think we can eliminate
the stuff that that you know is
providing editable values but that's
about it and then we have to just make
something that we're timed blocks you
know would get turned off as well so if
we look in here right now
when we open we should get nothing I
don't know why that's an error let's
look at that but you can see like these
are turned off right
unfortunately that doesn't yeah and you
can see that doesn't really help and
also like I said it's I think it's
mostly the timed blocks and stuff that
are the problem there so if we were to
say all right let's let's not care about
that so much
let's care about this so we basically
say like alright these things time clock
time function begin block frame marker
set event recording HUD time function
right
maybe these are actually the things that
we go with slow on so we'd say something
like this and I don't actually know
so in here we would hips side
so basically what I'm saying is look if
handmade slow is not turned on then
don't time anything right and then debug
collation should not take any time
because we're not actually doing any
debug collation but of course yeah again
like you can see the jerkiness really
didn't help and that was because even
with debug collation ah we were still
well within 60 FPS so I'm pretty sure
this is just Windows compositor sucking
would be my guess but again I'm not 100%
sure one way or the other so looking
through here right and as I hop around
of course I can't actually look at any
information because we don't actually
have the timing so what I'd like to do
is just move it out just a little bit so
I can look at the time I can look at the
overall timed blocks maybe just the most
important ones and then maybe no nothing
else right so if we look at like frame
marker for example maybe frame marker
has to be there
so frame marker is always set and the
code for frame marker is yeah so like if
I just put frame marker so we can time
like frames for example and then I take
the frame marker and I put that out here
so you know we turn off all of our time
functions but we leave on the ability to
just see the frame time itself so then
we can at least see our milliseconds we
just don't have much visibility into
anything else and we could have a top
level like we could have one more thing
that just shows us that breakdown but
you know so here's here's sad KC and
we're looking at the frame time and it
says it's 10 milliseconds so I don't
know I'm expecting a nice smooth 60
frames a second I'm definitely not
getting it thank you to Windows it's
clear that I'm getting it sometimes
right but I don't think I'm getting it
always and it could be something else
we're doing wrong
I don't really know so with that Set
let's pop back to insight let it do a
little profile for us right and see what
it has to say and so you can see it to
thinks we're we're lock we're lock 60
right like it thanks for getting 60 no
problem which again makes me think that
it's like Windows compositor just being
completely unable to do the stream at
the same time probably should just I
should probably just bite the bullet and
get some kind of I don't know if there
is a device that has a zero latency HDMI
pass-through and that also then splits
but I should just buy one if there is
anyone out there no does anyone know if
there's a thing that takes HDMI output
splits it into two but doesn't introduce
any latency to the frame so that on the
main monitor you're still seeing it real
time I don't know I mean I was gonna
introduce a little bit of latency but I
mean like you know no no real latency
not countable in milliseconds latency
yeah I mean because I'd like to get to
the point where we could run this thing
reliably maybe turn off Windows is
nonsense
so that we're not trying to stream out
to ports at the same time you're and I'm
saying
and so basically a lag free splitter
does it exist if so tell me
also in cybot just said something
awesome for those of you who are
watching in the chat alright so right
let's terminate here I'm gonna do one
capture and just see if anything's
different about it I don't know why we
can't terminate my program without
crashing it but that's just where it's
at
I'm gonna go ahead and do this launch
game profiler I'm gonna get a profile in
some place that's drawing a lot so like
you know
here let's say it still claims we've got
60 I don't know why it's claiming that
when we're not but again it's probably
some windows thing that's awesome we'll
go back here take a look at the
breakdown and so if we look at the
breakdown you can now see that you know
the draw calls versus the dispatch so
again if you believe what we're seeing
here this would imply and again I don't
really know why but this would imply
that the GL draw a is call where we just
do the multi sample resolve that that is
by far the most expensive thing and so
the question is how do we speed that up
I wish I was a graphics expert because
I'd probably have some opinions on how
to speed that up but you know
see if we can learn anything from these
numbers
so fragment shader in vacations to
billion that's the number of times that
it that did the fragment shader I want
to say that if we speed crunch that you
can see exactly where that number comes
from right so for every pixel on the
screen exactly it's it's invoking our
fragment shader which is exactly what we
would expect for each invocation I don't
know what these numbers mean but looking
at them like this is looks like it's
waiting on texture fetches perhaps I'm
not sure math pipe throttle presumably
would mean that we were waiting on the
math pipe I don't actually know if
that's accurate but I don't care about
that
more draw calls and dispatches doesn't
really make a lot of sense to me I'm not
sure what that means more draw calls
than dispatches
hit rate on the l2 cache is almost
perfect so it'd be hard to argue with
that the hit rate on the textures is not
so good but I'm not sure what you would
really expect I mean it's got to pull
all that information in so I'm not sure
how it could possibly remain in the
cache we don't care about the user
metrics at the moment I don't think
looking at the
so I don't really know that there's that
much I can really gather from this but
you know if the only thing I can really
say is it looks like just the fact that
that shader is too complicated is what
takes most of our frame time and so I
don't know we could so let's say we
wanted to determine whether that's
fictional or not so let's say I went
into here and I just said hey you know
what the max multi sample count is now
gonna be 1 or something right so we just
we just straight-up lied to it and here
instead of this where I'm actually
outputting real values I'm just gonna
say 1 and 1 right so now we're Bo and I
got a determinate this guy terminate I
know you can't seem to figure out how to
terminate sometimes but just to
terminate trust me so if I was to force
it to just take one texture sample each
time instead of 16 texture samples each
time then what happens
so I mean it looks like it's not lying I
mean look at how much faster that got
right again didn't improve the actual
visual frame rate very much because it
seems like that is just jerky because of
other windows issues but if I go to the
same place now and I go back here and
take a capture yes I know and I want
that if we take a look at what's going
on here you can see that now the resolve
and the drawing take about similar times
right and so looking at that draw call
again I don't know what okay that
doesn't seem good
hello uh yeah who knows
so anyway point being looking at these
two you can see that now the resolve
took significantly less time according
to the profile here and it's more
commensurate with the time it took to
draw the screen that strangely enough
that actually seems kind of accurate so
here's why here's my made-up explanation
of why that seems kind of accurate so if
the multi sample count is one what you
have to remember about multi sampling is
that multi sampling doesn't kick in
unless you actually need to draw
multiple samples at the pixel right and
so at the actual pixel if you only ever
had to take one sample because I'm sorry
if you only ever had to fill all the
samples together because those samples
were taken from entirely within one
polygon there wasn't an edge going
through it then you only ever had to
update one piece of data not sixteen
when you were drawing and that's gonna
be most of the time for us because most
of the time were not on an edge that's
the whole point of multi sampling the
reason it's better than super sampling
is because you only pay for it on actual
edges when we do the resolve we're
reading all sixteen so drawing the
screen only had to touch one sample per
pixel on average right
but resolving the screen has touched 16
pixels on average pixels I mean there's
samples not pixels right so here's my
question
inside the fragment shader is there any
way we can ask OpenGL how many samples
you actually took like if all the
samples were one value we can get a fast
path in there and maybe hit it most of
the time and be okay and and presumably
also if I actually looked now when we're
only taking just one sample shouldn't we
see some of the baddest yeah so if you
in here you can see like all these edges
are super crispy now right and that's
all week that's all we really needed to
fix with the multi sampling right
because our depth peel takes care of the
of the depth sorting so if that all
works right you can see I go right
through the tree it works perfectly on
either side right which reminds we
should fix our occupancy stuff but
either way um so when we look at this
here what we can see is really our only
problem is these crispy lines and that's
what the multi samplings for so the
question is if we looked at GLSL is
there any way to get that piece of
information and let's take a look
this may be the wrong place to look
so
this doesn't look like it finds the
fragment shader stuff though
and not really
so I'm not really sure if we can get
that information or not and that's
something that would probably take a
little while to research but let me just
explain what I want and then we can
probably take a look next weekend and
see if we we can get it so the only
thing I was trying to say there was well
look you know in here so you can see
this path has to sum up a bunch of stuff
right it's got a loop 16 times and do a
bunch of work but when we actually look
at these samples when we look at like
text effects maybe I'll look at that as
well like so you know Texel fetch
documentation do we have that anywhere
so I'm just curious like can we also
just ask for that location that you're
going to sample can you tell me how many
samples were taken or were they are all
the same you know what I mean because
that would allow us to skip most of the
resolve that we're doing and I just
don't know if we can or can't do that
right
yeah
so it says using GL sample ID or GL
sample position would could be used to
work around this but those are methods
caused entire fractures revalued per
sample rather than per fragment
yeah I don't know
it's like dice took down this
[Music]
so the coverage masks being output again
doesn't really help us we're not looking
to improve the output we're just looking
to optimize the resolve I wish we had an
Nvidia person here or AMD person here to
just tell us if that's possible because
all we that's all we really want right
is we just want an if so in other words
this could just be one thing right it
would just be the following
actually we don't even need to do that
just do this so we would literally just
do like yeah if we're in this path which
is like the slow path right where I
would just say if we're in the slow path
you got to do all of this if not you
just fetch it just once right like so
and similarly like this stuff don't
don't gotta happen neither right so this
whole thing here only has to happen
there and this could just be like blend
unit color equals whatever it whatever
it equals right so basically you can
just fetch once so we could just do an
if like look if there aren't any samples
here so if you only took one then just
write that one you know what I mean
otherwise do this whole disastrous
rigmarole and off you go
and so then we should be able to set
this normally debug this guy and just
have it so that we're always going to
have a switch there that can switch
between one sample or multiple samples
looks like we got a error there though
if one combined clerical zero depth map
min max
for samples fetch them and add them then
set the frag depth set the surface
reflectance set the blend unit color
otherwise set it this way what did I
that should be exactly the same right
did I do something busted there there's
the multi sample
[Music]
that seems correct to me I don't know
what am I missing there
I'm not seeing the bug maybe there is
one but I don't actually see it like our
resolve is it's not working after that
change let me back it up and just make
sure I didn't mess anything up because
that's pretty easy change to make so
I'll make it again
all right so that's one then we just
want to move these up right so combined
color goes here all of this nonsense
goes here and we don't need to do the
depth because we've already done it
right
good to go and then I just wanted to say
okay like this entire path here so I'm
gonna move the frag depth down so here's
the output of that path right looks good
and then I just want to put an if one
around it so here's if one if one you do
all of this and if not you do some other
thing right and so right here what we
want is our frag depth is just the fetch
of this and our blend unit color is just
the fetch of this
of zero not sampling and in theory like
that's just gonna call this code right
it's never gonna call this code because
it's an if one so in theory it should
just work okay what's going on it has to
call this code right am I missing
something
thanks I don't know how many characters
it is but it's not it's not 4096
characters it's hardly any so something
is up with that putting this if one in
there it doesn't really like it so what
happens if I just delete the else Clause
just curious
still nothing and then delete the f1
clause
so somehow putting in if one in there
changes the behavior of the program
how is that possible
shouldn't if one just always work like
if you put an if one around something
the only thing that changes is defined
variables but they're not getting used
outside of there as far as I know so I
guess that's just an invalid program
somehow that it's not that's not liking
all right
here's in video one more time
launched it up
and I don't see any error messages oh
well can we get these I get more
information about that let's take a look
what is the not a valid program there it
is so it was giving us an error but we
didn't catch that error message for some
reason I thought we generally did catch
those error messages and would output on
them but it looks like there's some kind
of an error message getting generated on
there I would like to see the error
message but of course we can't let's
take a look here
so I'm not sure why
let's take a look and see why we're not
why we are selling it because that error
message should be there right when we
compiled the program in here I thought
we were asserting like right here
oh we turned off sessions because we're
in handmade slow that was why
okay so now we can see what the problem
is vertex pairs fragment errors etc plus
a cast from int to what oh man all right
you gotta be kidding me
you gotta be kidding me folks well it is
what it is so we gotta do this
apparently and switch that between true
and false because 1 &amp; 0
oof wouldn't want that alright so let's
go ahead and actually oops I put that in
the wrong place and actually try to grab
this information out here so imma go
back to a previous version there we go
alright so now presuming so now I should
be able to do an if true and that's
where I'll leave it
so if true now this should always run
that path and we should get our standard
output which we do with nice smooth
edges which is great
none of that Chris penis and then if we
set it to false we'd get the crispy
edges and presumably if there was some
way of testing whether the samples were
we're not all together then we could
actually do something about it so
there's the crispy edge version so I'm
gonna put if true here and then I put
like to do Casey
asked some
GPU people if this can be optimized with
a call instead of true that says whether
a particular location in a multi sample
texture has all one sample or actually
contains multiple samples because I know
the graphics card knows the answer to
that question so we'll see all right
let's go to a brief Q&amp;A now seems like
we got everything we could have gotten
squared away and I think we're just
gonna have to ask some GPU people be
like hey can we get can we get this data
so Neil suggests texture samplers
texture samples parentheses sampler but
doesn't that just say the maximum number
of samples or can you because you need
to be able to pass an actual UV
coordinate right let me take a look but
I'm pretty sure that texture samples
just tells you how many it would have
right or is that not true maybe not I
don't know we'll see yeah see that
that's just going to tell us the total
number of samples for texture so it'll
just return sixteen we want this call
but we want this call that takes a UV
coordinate so basically we want the
equivalent of this call that says hey
graphics card how many did you actually
pack in there right
brian says you can have Windows
automatic after crash dumps for you
check if this key exists HP local
machines suffer Microsoft Windows
Windows they're reporting local dumps at
if so well on that comes to local
AppData crash dumps that's pretty cool
so let me do that thanks Brian Ridge
edit so he says HQ local machine
software Microsoft Windows Windows Error
reporting local dumps
[Music]
what do I set it to maybe it's already
set and if so then you said it would be
local AppData crash dumps
Oh
so we've we've had this the whole time
it turns out
all right so now that's pretty great so
now I hear the crash dumps I can grab
all these and then we can see what's
going on so that that sounds good
I will send those all to George and it
looks like the probably the ones from
5:11 524 those are probably useless but
I'll send them anyway that's pretty cool
Bryan thank you for pointing that out I
did not know that I could do that
oops but that's great because now I can
send all these along
handmade hero org watch has numerous
coated France when will you be streaming
next it depends that's what gets updated
every time I put in a new block of
stream times so it's usually every
weekend but you know sometimes it gets
modified but it's usually every weekend
special thanks dude Linux wouldn't even
work trying to run something on Linux
that goes through the GPU and outputs to
two monitors at the same time one of
which is at a fixed frame rate and one
is which is vsync zero chance
Linux GPU support is absolutely terrible
it can't even run you know an optimist
display let alone probably something
like this so no definitely not like
Linux would not help at all it would
probably only hurt it has very very very
bad AV support by comparison and don't
get me started on audio
let's see let's see any other on topic
questions actually
rational coder someone had asked whether
or not that would optimize anything
since the GPU has to execute both
branches no the GPU doesn't have to
execute both branches so it's it's worth
remembering that GPUs do do full full
ifs at least most so basically what
happens is if you hit an if statement
then what its gonna do is look to see
whether all of the pixels in that group
all evaluate to the same thing on the if
and if so it won't execute the side of
the branch that nobody goes down right
and so in this case most pixels almost
all would not have multiple samples so
most of the time the block of 16 or 32
or however many of the GPUs pressing it
once will probably all hit the same side
of the branch and only blocks containing
an edge running through them would not
so I think we would get a significant
speed increase from if we had that if I
don't know I just don't know if that is
ever exposed in the shader
not sure if you're joking when you said
to ask but if you have the time and feel
like it I would 100 cent be down to see
the lectures from you in about the
resting animation system yeah no I I
would I will do that at some point sure
I don't know if anyone what the status
was on the on the know if anyone cares
about these it's the only problem but so
no one really cares about this stuff
unfortunately as far as I can tell right
it's it's pretty much just like a
standard standard view count right and
so I don't know like how useful it is
for some of these things cuz like if you
look at what stuff is tends to be more
viewed some of ours are actually that
way so you know if you look at like
things like some of the other ones where
I go over stuff they do have a lot of
views and things like that
but in general like you know the I think
the 3d animation stuff probably doesn't
because it's very advanced and I just
don't know that there's very many people
who can really follow it probably or use
it but I don't know so you know if if
the skin animation wanted had had like
tons of views on it then I would say
okay this is something people really
wanted to see right
I don't think putting it under chat does
make it less clickable and flashy
thumbnails like none of them have flashy
thumbnails so I'm comparing apples to
apples here but if you take a look at
the chats it seems like the ones that
are interesting people actually get a
lot of views so like not many there but
like any of these other ones had
actually quite a bit so like this one
had you know four times that many or
three times that many right
and so the chats do seem to be fairly
popular most of the time much more
popular than that this one which was
done the day prior had twice as many
right so I'm just trying to go by like
you know chats are a sort of a separate
thing we do they're not really part of
the series and just looking at to what
extent people actually get value out of
them I don't know how many people are
actually getting value out of the 3-step
it seems like something that's just too
far afield maybe you know because yeah I
think that might be just if you're if
you're at the point where you're
implementing a 3d mesh skinning system
you probably know enough that you're not
watching this show or if you are
watching the show you just do it for
like entertainment purposes you don't
care about me covering it right like
you're not you're not watching the show
at that point because you're trying to
learn something from it you're just
watching the show because you like
having the show on or something which is
also totally fine but definitely a
different thing
so all right I'm gonna wrap it up anyway
but it's point being it doesn't mean I
wouldn't do it it's just I don't feel a
pressing need to get to it right so you
know that's all really girlfriend
watches and tells you most of the things
you said about Linux or old school
issues would you like would you like me
to stream trying to install several
different Linux distributions on an
optimist laptop and watching how
ridiculous it is because I do know the
series of steps it takes to get them to
work because I've had to do it but we
could do that if you want we could also
demo how you like I have Linux machines
running right like I'm running a Linux
machine right here as the streaming
machine and it breaks all the time right
the mouse right now isn't working I am
moving the mouse and it doesn't work why
because Linux right it's very unreliable
for hardware support you know if you
think Linux I mean if you think Windows
is bad for hardware support well Linux
really like ups that game people who run
Linux always insist this isn't true I
don't know why it's I don't say these
things because I don't like Linux I like
Linux and I've use it fairly frequently
right it just doesn't work half the time
and in general like the problem is if
you happen to have a machine that works
on Linux great maybe you don't have
these problems I don't have any machines
that work properly on Linux they all
took a tremendous amount of massaging to
get them to actually run stabili and in
general Windows isn't that way I get a
lot more reliability on Windows in terms
of the amount of time it takes me to
install the system and get it working
now granted pretty soon I'm gonna have
to run Linux everywhere because Windows
10 is rapidly trying to make it
impossible for anyone to ever run a
Windows machine reliably so eventually
Microsoft will succeed in making it so
that even with all of the brokenness
Linux is still the more reliable
operating system and that that day is
coming like I wouldn't have thought it
possible but that I think that at some
point that day probably is coming right
because Windows 10 gets is been getting
really bad and continues to get worse
the only way to really run a Windows 10
machine is to have an unplug from the
internet which is how I run my Windows
10 machines right but that's only gonna
last for so long and so I do feel like
in general you know I think the people
who have believed that Linux is reliable
on Hardware I don't know what to tell
you I think you're kind of having a bit
of a Stockholm Syndrome situation there
but that aside I you know I do see more
Linux in my future
only because Windows continues to
increase the unreliability and the
maintenance nightmare they keep pushing
it up and so at some point those lines
are gonna cross and the amount of work
it takes to get a stable Linux desktop
or laptop running will cross and it will
now be more likely that you will spend
you know right now maybe it takes ten
hours to get a stable Linux system
installed and it takes two hours to get
a stable Windows machine installed or
something and that's gonna keep Linux is
never gonna get better it's never gotten
better in my whole life you know
installing Slackware probably took
similar amount of time because I had to
rebuild the kernel every time right as
it does to get one working today because
by the time I act and and it never quite
gets working right the mouse still
doesn't work on this machine but you
know what are you gonna do eventually
Windows will also have the Mouse not
working often enough right
it will also be several hours to install
and won't really work right and you'll
have to do all kinds of weird registry
hacking right and so eventually those
lines will cross and when those lines do
cross then there's no reason to use
Windows really other than to have a test
machine because you know yeah
stuff on it but eventually those lines
will cross Microsoft has made it very
clear that those lines will cross and
Linux doesn't have to do anything right
they can just sit there they don't have
to improve their reliability they don't
they don't even have to do anything
and eventually Microsoft will just push
those lines you know so off you go
yeah I sympathize for the person on chat
says I have an arch links machine it's
dependencies are now broken and will
take weeks to get working again yeah the
package managers don't work at all
they're super broken for example this
machine has to have no js' installed
because it requires no JIT you when you
use firebase for for distribution you
have to have no js' because that's the
only way it works it's pretty amazing
you have to use nodejs to copy files now
uh and every so often it's just broken
that's it
the package manager cannot actually
update it and you just have to wipe the
whole thing and completely reinstall
right that's just--that's Linux it's I
mean that's the bottom line and and I
really don't understand why people say
it's better you don't have to pretend
that Linux isn't broken it is broken
windows is broken to it you don't have
to fight about it right
these OS is our garbage let's just
accept that fact whether or not one is
easier or harder for you personally
depends on your hardware setup depends
what you're trying to do right and I
think we can all agree that eventually
Microsoft will destroy Windows I mean
it's been getting worse for a decade now
and it's not gonna I don't see any
reverse on that trend so even if you
know you are mad because I'm saying that
Linux is still broken look I'm not
saying that Windows isn't heading
straight down the toilet it is right and
so in general I would say you know it's
it's six of one half dozen the other but
please be realistic about the quality of
these operating systems they're not good
Linux is not good it may be better than
Windows in some respects is worse than
Windows and others both of them are
terrible they are lousy operating
systems they do not do what you want an
operating system to do which is run
reliably without requiring updates on
the hardware that you have neither of
them can do it they are both highly
unstable small changes to either one can
completely break them in ways that take
quite some time to repair
and the chances that they will work out
of the box in both cases is quite low
windows is better than Linux I think in
that respect but still bad Casey please
dispel the myth that Molly one two three
and I are the same person rupan three as
a crazy conspiracy going on I can't
shake I don't know how do I know whether
you're the same person or not right so
alright
for what reason do you like legs if it
breaks all the time um so two things one
it doesn't force me to update right so
unlike windows if I install a Linux
machine it updates when I say it updates
and I value that right so that's thing
one thing too is that it is better set
up for working with servers like if you
just want to SSH to your server it's
like already you don't do anything right
it's just set up it just works you can
move files back and forth you can shell
to one you can do whatever you want
right windows good luck like you've got
a you know use there you've got to do
all kinds of nonsense and Windows 10
finally added like SSH this board to a
certain extent but it's still not as
good as on Linux and so just working
with that kind of stuff it's just
cleaner on legs and it's because people
that's where people use that kind of
stuff right so it's just kind of nice
right the terminal works better the
Windows terminal they haven't updated in
years they just recently updated it and
like one of the main features they added
was that it can be transparent so you
know unless that stuff works better so
you know I I do feel like Linux does but
there are better aspects of using a
Linux machine and again so I think
anyone who thinks that like one
operating system is like clearly better
they're not they have strengths and
weaknesses
and and I wish I wish that there was
some good operating system that I could
sit here and be part of the OS words and
say no you should use bla OS but there
isn't all these operating systems suck I
don't really blame them sometimes
because it's a hard problem I mean
supporting such a wide and unreliable
hardware base as is on the PC is very
difficult problem but just because I can
respect the fact the problem is hard
doesn't mean the results aren't awful
right so like yes it's a hard problem
for a number of reasons there's a reason
why tens of hardware doesn't work
properly on Linux I mean right now for
example I have one printer there's one
printer in in this place Linux lists
five they're all the same printer but
you can only pick one of them and have
it work the rest just error out that's
Linux right I mean that's Linux
you can't expect stuff like a printer to
work on Linux it's just completely
unreliable why I don't know I've never
looked at it I couldn't tell you but
that doesn't happen on Windows Windows
lists one printer and when you print it
prints to the printer that's generally
what people want to have happen with a
printer right so again like don't sit
here telling me that Linux actually
works it doesn't it has tons and tons
and tons of obviously broken stuff and
that doesn't mean that I don't think
it's a valuable operating system I run
it
it's just be honest these operating
systems are awful Windows and Linux are
not good operating systems we don't have
a good operating system right now that
just doesn't exist
so there's don't waste your time arguing
with people or me about whether an
operating system is good or better than
ours it doesn't matter these operating
systems are garbage and I don't see if
you're proving I don't see printers
working on Linux tomorrow I don't see
Windows 10 stopped rebooting half the
time with updates I didn't ask for or
curtana
taking 50% of my cpu time because some
update broke how
runs like that's just forget it it's not
changing for quite some time
so have a lousy day right you're gonna
have a lousy day because your OS sucks
that's just that's the truth about
computing right now I wish I could have
Amiga das back I can't what do you want
from me right anyway on that note let's
wrap it up thank you everyone for
joining me for anime here it's been
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
because pre-order the game on anime here
at Otto are gonna come to the source
code so you can play around with it
yourself
maybe you can figure out how to get
those month to sample counts out of
there it may be impossible it's wishful
thinking the graphics card does know it
uses it for optimization so I'm pretty
sure it has the information whether or
not it's ever been exposed to the GLSL I
don't know or whether or not they just
don't want to expose those kind of
features because they need the
flexibility to change how they work that
could be too so I don't know it would be
nice it would cause a lot less time to
be spent in our resolved shaders I think
I'll check with some GPU people if I can
and find out what the deal is with that
but that's about it I'll be back here
next week probably I'll update the
schedule sometime between now and then
to have the streaming scheduled but we
will then put in maybe some pixel
shading for sampling our lighting
sources
we'll get that working and then we can
kind of tie the lighting around and kind
of have a nice renderer you know it's
not the world's most amazing renderer
but it's pretty darn good for a 2-d game
it's pretty awesome actually the number
of artifacts we have is pretty low
actually I think we're looking really
really sweet in there and our lighting I
think will be pretty good too
so I'm looking forward to that hope to
be back here for that next week until
then have fun programming everyone don't
try to tell me that Linux is good and
don't try to tell me that Windows is
good and certainly don't try to tell me
that Matt glass is good until next week
I'll see you guys then techies everybody