hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero code ah show
where we could complete game live on
stream
sorry i'm a little slow this morning
we did a few streams that weren't
uploaded to youtube
uh that were just trying to get
my for coder configuration into a place
where everyone else could use it uh
because i want people to be able to code
the same way i could on stream that was
kind of always a goal and it kind of
drifted out of that
because i kind of had like a hybrid
version of four coder that was never
released and my custom layer was never
released and so on
and so we're trying to keep that under
control now
and i think we've basically got it more
or less
where it needs to be a mirror the editor
that i
use like the way that that works
effectively
for most things that matter and
we did it in ryan flurry's custom layer
which is maintained on github so i
should be able to just like
push those changes back uh eventually
well we already pushed a bunch of
changes back
but for coder still needs to
have a new point release because we
worked with alan to get a few new things
in in order to support some of the
things that i needed
and so that should be coming fairly soon
i don't
have a date for it because i don't know
what alan's doing so i don't actually
know
when it will be released hopefully it'll
be released soon
um i'll try bugging him about it but uh
basically we did that work so today what
we're gonna do is start
editing on the game again and i'm just
gonna try and keep track of anything
that i noticed that's like weird or
idiosyncratic
with the editing that i think we need to
fix and then i can fix it and i can just
fix it off stream it's it's
not important obviously because it has
nothing to do with the game
but i'll just like make a mental note or
i'll i'll keep note of it here i've
actually got
a handmade hero notebook so i can just
write it down
and i'll remember to take care of it
afterwards
so there was already one thing that was
broken and that was that the d key was
not doing the right thing so we had
bound the d key to delete range
but instead and i'll show you what i
mean
effectively what happens is if i
actually should go
to the handmade hero directory um so if
i'm trying to edit
uh like here in the handmade hero code
base uh and i go to uh
i go to some place the way i always have
my keys work
is that the d key deletes from
where i am to the end of the line and if
there's nothing left on the line then it
deletes
the line feed so basically like d if you
tap d
once it deletes to the end of the line
if you tap d
twice it deletes like it sucks whatever
was up on the previous line on the next
line up to the previous line
so the problem is right now if i hit d
it actually deletes the range
um i'm not sure why i bound to that but
you can see like that would delete like
all the way at the beginning of the file
in this case because that's where the
the marker was
so i really don't want that because i
hit the d key a lot and that'll just
completely throw me off
so i just need to replace that one
function
other than that i don't remember
us noticing anything weird so hopefully
um we'll be fine if we just fix that so
i cut and pasted the code that deletes
the current line from the four coder
source
uh and effectively what i'm going to do
is just see if we can modify it a little
bit
so you can see here it gets the view in
the buffer it then
looks to see how like what the actual
range of a particular line is
and then it adds one to the end of the
line to encompass the
carriage turn character uh it then just
goes ahead and
uh i guess does a clamp
and then replaces the range so i think
all i need to do here
is just muck a little bit with this
logic here so the range that it's
actually using
is i think all i would have to do um
i don't think there's anything else so
my assumption is
that like so this range size equals zero
thing
and then it looks to see if it should
delete the thing
it looks like it already does some kind
of a
new line eating here so we it
i don't really know but it may be as
simple
as just saying hey let's
delete let's just take the range
and make the beginning of the range be
the current cursor position
so i don't really know because i don't
know a lot of what four coders
conventions are for things so i couldn't
tell you
but i believe if i just say range start
equals pause right then what will happen
is the end will still be the end of the
line the position here
will now be where the cursor was and
that's the start i won't include the new
line
right it'll then just go do its thing
where it starts doing some clamping
and it'll look to see whether the size
is zero if we were on the end of the
line
already that's what would that's exactly
the case where i needed to suck up the
new line so in this case
i don't know
i don't know if this code does the right
thing
but rather than write my own
and assume that it doesn't i might just
try it because i don't know
and we'll see what happens so i'm just
going to go ahead and save this
i'm going to build this and i'm gonna
bind this new
casey delete to end of line um
i'm gonna bind that to my uh
so to the where what the d key was bound
to delete range before
i'm just gonna go ahead and bind that uh
to mine
so in the bindings file uh it's just
this delete range
so it's delete uh casey delete to end of
line now
and so let's just go ahead and build it
so that's an
for coder custom
for coder flurry i think yeah um so that
will rebuild our four coder there
and now if i open it uh we just have to
see like does it do
anything like what i expect and i don't
know
so the most likely thing of these to
work properly is if i hit
d here it should delete to the end of
the line
so uh i don't know if that quite worked
that may have also
deleted one extra character it did
so like if i go yeah so it looks like
it's pause
plus one that we actually needed let's
try the
new line thing as well i don't know so
let's um
let's just fix that one problem first
because that does seem
uh relevant here so if i just say pause
plus one
that should be where i actually i guess
want to delete
um so anyway all right so i think we've
got the first part working just fine
if i go in here now and i just say okay
delete that's good and then delete again
doesn't do anything okay so
we do need to rewrite that other part so
in here what i think we would want to do
is say all right if the range start uh
if it
i don't really know what will happen if
we do the pause plus one here
when we're at the end of the line
technically so
i'm not quite sure
i i i would would have thought actually
that this would have
done the right thing so my only question
is it might be this
so it may be that this is like if range
size equals one might be the one we
actually want
um
in fact it might be more like this so so
if we
assume
so if we assume actually i think this is
easier than i'm making it out to be so
if we assume that this
end range is actually always correct
then i think we can actually just do
this
we can just say if range uh start
um
or sorry if pause equals range end so if
we're on the end of the line
right then we do something special
otherwise we don't that might be all we
actually need
so in other words here if we're on the
end of the line already we just push the
end out one
this i guess always happens it's not
really an else
we want that always so we just say um
you know range end equals pause plus one
and it may be so if the end of the line
is actually
technically a new line character then i
guess we would want this now that i
think about it
right maybe
um again i'm just really not sure
because i don't know
what the um what the size is here
so i guess we would leave this part the
same
because we don't know what this does i
just have no idea
uh what this is supposed to do in four
coder um
so i'm not going to try and guess but
anyway um so i think
something like that would probably work
we'll find out
uh so here we are in asynctask again
let's just go over here that deletes
that deleted the whole line though
hold on a second did i miss something
here
oh yeah so we do need this to be
always equal to pause in that case right
so it's got to delete the new line so
it's trying to
uh it probably needs to keep it as pause
it wouldn't advance it by one because it
still needs to replace something
so all right so hopefully that's good um
we'll see i think that will duplicate
the behavior that i'm used to so it
won't catch me by surprise anymore
um so yeah
yeah all right so i think that's all
good um
and then the other thing we should
probably do while we're in here is
you'll notice like
when i hover over something the um
the color of the parentheses
is the same color as
like the line highlight for some reason
and i don't know if that's like that's
going to drive
me insane because i can't see that
they're there
so i don't know what exactly that
comes from if it comes from anything i
may need to update to the new
four coder flurry that he recently
pushed
and we can try that i'll be doing that
after the stream
either way but we may also just be able
to hack that because i don't really care
about updating to the new one at the
moment
but some of these things are just a
little bit nuts like i don't know
uh if i can actually get rid of that one
or not
but everything else seems to be good um
so we'll see i mean maybe i should just
bite the bullet
and do it um we've come this far let's
just take a
let's just take a a whack at it i
suppose
um if i just go ahead and grab the new
one
we'll see what we'll see what transpires
so um
let's see here
i'm desperately trying to download this
but of course like google can't really
download
things anymore i i don't really know
what the deal is like
gmail has basically melted down almost
completely and i and i have no idea why
um like gmail and google drive are
almost completely destroyed at this
point i don't
i don't know who maintains these things
probably because there's not enough
advertising in them or something
they just don't work anymore it's kind
of nuts
the number of things i use which are
just rapidly degrading i constantly have
and in this like
position of having to like
worry about what i'm going to use for
basic services because they degrade
so rapidly it's nuts i mean you know
it used to be that i could relatively
rely on that gmail would work and now it
doesn't anymore
google drive is just complete nightmare
it doesn't work hardly at all
um it's just nuts
anyway um so i'm gonna move this over
here
uh while i'm at it i might as well grab
the new remedy i mean while we're while
we're moving stuff onto this machine
because there's been a patch uh for the
latest
it's 3-1-1 now
all right okay
so uh here's our four coder flurry
and we'll clean up those uh color issues
and here's our four coder
here's our remedy bg we don't need this
anymore
so remedy bg
can just get romped
there you go
and four coder flurry is a little harder
because um
well we have to save our bindings and
stuff although actually
it looks like none of this is
that way i don't actually modify any of
these files as far as i know
so i believe that we can just take them
all
wholesale because the only thing that i
actually need to do
is go and include my four coder
casey file which
obviously isn't included in his
but other than that i think we should be
fine
so let's take a look um let me close all
this stuff out
uh okay i guess i didn't save that
um and i'll back it up as well just to
make sure
um we'll see
okay uh and then we'll give it a shot
so here's apps for coder here's the
four coder flurry layer that i currently
have
um my themes file is actually in here
and my bindings file
is is here so we're not actually
changing any of that
um but you know what i'll just i'll just
copy the whole thing anyway
um i need to push these out to the
github
to the flurry github at some point so
they're backed up better
i'm not sure exactly how bindings files
would get backed up but
i don't know i don't want to know
so all i should have to do here is just
overwrite my stuff
and i may have to do some extra work
because
the like the theme example
file here um that's probably something
that i'm going to have to look at now
because
even though i'm not using it it's all
the color definitions
so if we go and you know we look at
this theme example file
um i'm not sure
so i'm not sure these are all new right
and that's relevant but i thought there
was some stuff
like in terms of like dimming
the in terms of like dimming the
the pain that you were on i thought he
mentioned that that actually got
defined in here somewhere but it doesn't
actually
look like it so that may still be in
there but
you know i can i can certainly uh
try to figure that part out separately
some other time
all right so if we actually just rebuild
we should get an error um well we
wouldn't really get an error but on four
coder load we'll get an error so if i
if i open up four coder um oh my
that doesn't seem good does it
okay i don't know what that was about um
so if we if if i rebuild this
uh it's not gonna it's not gonna include
my custom files so when we actually
launch my
my special key bindings and stuff
wouldn't work so
i need to do one modification to it
which is i need to be able to have the
four coder
uh i need to make sure that for coder
flurry includes me
that's really it um so in here where
it's got all this stuff
i just need like four coder flurry
casey cpp i just need that to be
compiled
right um and that's all that should
matter
um
oh that's not true all right so yeah
that's right so i will have to do some
merges okay this is okay so this is
actually
once again we're not gonna probably
actually get to doing any real work
today
um because it looks like right i'll have
to merge
my cursor drawing code
um with the new cursor drawing code
because i actually put in some slightly
different code here
so i'll have to look at the difference
between these two
and try to merge them reasonably that's
the only thing
i'd forgotten that i had to fix because
the way the cursor was drawn
was sufficiently different that i was
like i should probably
do this myself so we have beyond compare
here
um and i do recommend this utility
i never remember to import my license
and i don't want to do it on stream
because then everyone can just use my
license i think
um so uh
i do actually like this utility i don't
love the new one
um it's a little bit webbed up a bit
much
but the at least i still use the older
one
i use beyond compare i think two
this is what four yeah i used two i
believe
um and i've always used it for stuff i
like it it's pretty good
um so i i would still recommend it
i don't know about the most modern one
what i should probably do
is copy the old one onto this machine
and import my license
um because i would rather use the old
one than the new one to be completely
honest
that's true of most software so okay
going on to
w apps backup i just have to look at the
cursor code now so
our cursor code um oops
in here so our cursor code is on the
left
and now we need to open the new one
on the right so
here uh and
i don't know to what extent we'll really
have to do much
it depends on how much this was changed
in ryan's stuff so you can see here like
these look like they're all
pretty easy to import for the most part
uh this is all stuff that i
you know basically did um i don't
actually want to replace
the f4 render cursor symbol thingy
necessarily
i would probably rather just insert it
but you know what i'll let ryan deal
with that
because i'm just that charitable so i'm
going to go ahead
and copy all of this and just
romp the my version over
the other version right and then i'm
just going to go look in here to see
if if any of this stuff was really
changed much it doesn't really look like
it was
so these have to get moved out to color
bindings uh
eventually but it looks like it looks
like really
ryan hadn't touched this much
um from what i can tell
like it seems seems fine
so these i don't want
um so again i just want to get rid of
those
because they were moved up to here
um
[Music]
yeah so i mean i i think for the most
part it looks like ours
is just straight up you can just use it
right like there doesn't seem to be
anything
and i should really merge with ryan's um
so we should
we'll get together and handle that
separately i just have been too busy
uh to do it but it looks like everything
else is fine
so really we just want ours so we could
have just copied it over i just wanted
to make sure i didn't know if there were
any other color
things that were happening up here right
so
that should basically be it
so if that is the only thing then we are
now building but what was the weird
purple thing
like what's going on there
um that must mean that there are color
values that are not
set up for this thing or something
i wonder if ryan's around because i i
have no idea why that would be the case
it looks like what he did at least my
assumption would be
um that jimmy
that anything that isn't defined in the
file
is now purple right um so my assumption
is that
i mean i could be wrong i often am but
if we look at the for if the theme
example four coder
if we look at our theme i wonder if
that's just
things we haven't set yet is the only
problem there so like if we go
uh to my theme file which is
theme casey and i try to open that in a
new window i don't know
um let's see here
oh no what how do i open a new window i
don't even know
there we go um so if i look at these
side by
side uh and just look at what's in there
it looks more or less like all of this
stuff
is just the standard stuff so none of
that would have to change
but all of this looks different now so
these
these are maybe in there maybe not
um like i don't actually see
oh there it is okay so what we could do
is just kind of grab these
rearrange them and then set any that we
want to set
differently right and maybe that just
works and then we're done
if not we talk to ryan and find out like
where the actual colors are that we're
not
defining so i'm just going to go ahead
and put this
uh sort of at the end there
um so that it's easier for me to read
just what the list is it's just a little
hard to find everything
and then i'm going to look at which ones
i already had and put
plop those in there and then hopefully
that'll be it
if we're lucky because then we'll just
be able to you know
say okay this is this is all good
no more issues because the editing seems
fine it's just the colors
there's a few color things that make it
really hard to use
and so if we can just change some of
those colors
um hopefully we'll be fine
and really what we should also do at
some point but i'll do it off stream is
add our cursor color stuff in there
so basically right now i just hard coded
those two cursor colors so
what we'll do is we'll put those you
know
we'd make a casey color cursor or
something
right
all right so looking at these
some of them we already had so type
function
macro and four coder command uh
those we can just replace with our own
versions
so i'm going to put those up at the top
because those are the ones we knew that
we had
then we've got this and i don't
see like cursor mode
that that doesn't seem to exist maybe
at least it doesn't seem like it so from
what i can tell like these are not a
thing
these are um and they have not been
touched they're the same
so that would be all of the colors that
we can define now
so that seems like it's working right
and so now if we're lucky and we may not
be
we should be able to do something about
this stuff so
let's see what we can do um with some of
these highlights
so the the token highlight is like way
too much
right um and if we look
at where that was here the it's it's
this thing
we would want that to be backed down
quite a bit
and we already have like a there's a
line highlight
uh in here i believe yes it's this one
highlight cursor line
and all we would really want for that is
to just be the token should just be like
a little bit brighter or something right
so
you know maybe just bump it up a little
bit i don't want it to be like
shocking um then there's those
the parens uh which already i don't like
the fact that they're
so dark i mean it's just kind of hard to
read
in my opinion so i don't know where
that's i don't know what that's coming
from
actually so that may be
like brace highlights
uh probably not because it would have to
be something
that's the same as the line background
right so what is the line background
the line background was was this ff1
right um and so somehow that's
being used or something
like i really just don't know i really
just don't know what
where that's coming from unless it's
it's like that but that seems
nuts if that's the case right
so it would be nice to know where that
was coming from um
[Music]
it might be this actually
um so let's let's try that so if i put
this nonsense back in
is it just this it might be
oh wait i don't need to build i just
need to run it
so let's just see if that's what it is
yeah so that's what it actually is
um also what is going on with that
i have no idea what's going on with that
um all right so we've solved one mystery
which is just that it's it's this back
cycle text cycle thing
so i don't really love that very much
um i i definitely don't want the back
cycle probably
it's hard to say but i don't think i do
so i think i probably want this to be
still the zeros so it just doesn't draw
anything in the background
the text cycle clearly we do need
something but
maybe it's just uh much more subtle
right like i don't want anything too
drastic there so in terms of just the
default text color
which is this i feel like maybe we can
just
if we want to do something subtle we
could but just nothing particularly
onerous like the current version so you
know maybe it's just
like i don't know maybe this just goes
up one
or two like like this
um and then this one goes down
uh one
yeah i don't know
i don't know what that'll do i don't
know if i need to use
four of them or not uh we'll find out
and that seems fine right it's just like
a subtle
highlight although again you can see the
braces are highlighting there that might
be a different thing though
so in terms of the paren highlights that
seems fine
it's not too onerous it's just a little
bit more bright
um and that's fine so the real thing is
i don't get this
i don't understand at all that erasure
that's happening there
um so that one i just have no i have no
idea
we'll have to find out what that's
coming from however we're
almost there i think i don't again i do
not understand why
the these are darker
than everything else i don't think
that's normally what i would do so i
must have said that somehow but i'm not
sure
where or how that got set so we still
kind of have some more work to do that
would be nice
this says braces semicolons and stuff
um
that must be
the that's the darker version and again
i i don't really know that i want that
so it's really hard for me to say um
what this should actually be but
probably i don't want it to be that i
could knock it down like
one again just keeping it really subtle
i don't like how bold that it was
um but yeah
i also don't know like why operators
would need a special thing but again
they could just use
the same thing inactive pain overlay
um never that's the one that i guess we
needed
so this is the one to stop the dimming i
definitely don't want it to dim
at all um
file progress bar is the thing above the
top that says for the cursor i don't
know that we care too much about the
color of that
brace highlights so scopes containing
the cursor
so that's that really onerous one and i
don't think we want that
um so maybe we would do the same thing
we did here which is just give
the brace highlight a slight increase
maybe
right um
these are probably subdued enough at the
moment
um we'll see cursor macro
cursor power mode we don't need to
change token highlight
we definitely do and the token
highlights
well we already fixed all right um okay
so
we're getting closer i would say uh
but still not there yet so
now you can see the braces just
highlight a little bit which is fine i
don't know if i want them to be even
more than that or not
um because i don't really see that as
being valuable like
i don't know when i wouldn't know what
scope i was in
and that's certainly not going to tell
me i do feel like the connector lines or
maybe a little bit
much so turning those down a little bit
would probably also help um and so
really my only concern now i think
most of it is just that it's that
weird um
i i don't know where that's coming from
um so that that is a bit odd and
i feel like that probably has to be
fixed uh
but other than that i think we're good i
don't really want the
the mark displayed here but we'll take
that so i'm gonna write these down so i
can take them
care of them off stream but don't think
we need anything else
um from what i'm seeing here
so no
mark annotation
uh why do tokens
disappear so something there's something
weird going on there but i'm not sure
what
uh and then like i guess i can take care
of the less
bright scopes right now
i would also prefer it if this thing
went away
so like the no
active pain
[Music]
border would be nice um i don't i don't
care for that either
uh so i think we're good and
you know even that i probably could live
with for a few
uh hours anyway so i don't know that we
we care too much about that so i'm going
to go ahead and do the
couple of remaining low hanging fruit
things which is just um
get rid of the
the scope lines being so bright
uh and then maybe we're good
i also might turn down the roundness on
that
on the cursor so there's uh quite a bit
of roundness
happening um this
and i don't really like rounded things
just in general so we'll have to figure
out how to make that happen i'll write
that down as well
roundness parameter
and uh we'll go from there
okay uh and i think that's all good so
reasonably oops i don't know what
happened there
uh reasonably happy with all of that and
again like i think
the only thing we really need here maybe
is like these annotations are just too
much so maybe if we just turn them down
to like
you know i don't know if we need to be a
quarter
of the brightness but like maybe
more like that in terms of alpha
um see if that's
more tolerable yeah so that that
wouldn't really get in my way
yeah so i think that's all good
and i'm also going to make a note that
the cursor
interpolation stuff seems kind of broken
a little bit
um so i might look into that as well
like there's just too many cursor
interpolation artifact
artifacts
okay um and we'll take one last gander
i guess i'll rebuild this as well so we
can get the roundness removed
oh whoops
looks like i missed one
did i
yes i did all right okay
so now we're back to
non-rounded cursors which is much more
comfortable uh for me
i also think the thickness is maybe a
bit much
looks like i didn't do that though maybe
the thickness isn't getting piped
through
it looks like it's only looks like it's
only on those little guys and this
the main one is like bigger or something
i don't know where that's coming from
all right well we'll take a look
thickness of cursor question mark
so i'll have my stuff for afterwards so
i think that's it i don't think we can
fix
the text i mean maybe we can if we just
guessed right but
since i have no idea what of this would
be involved in making the
token disappear like that um
i really don't have any idea where i
would look
right like just looking
token highlight
i'm not sure there's really much else to
this um
i mean it could have something to do
with this i guess but that wouldn't
disappear
right that's still that would show up so
it i mean i just don't see
so i don't know where that's coming from
so i'm gonna go ahead and just uh i'll
talk
to ryan about that and we'll go from
there
uh so let's try doing just
to see what happens if we edit because
we may discover some things
um along the way i don't know uh so if
we go ahead and build
like right and just see if we can jump
to errors and stuff like that
um because i don't know if we can of
course we don't have any errors at the
moment but we'll go make some
uh and
it seems pretty good
i would say it for whatever reason it
seems a bit dim i'm wondering does this
monitor a bit cause i think they're the
same colors
um no that's as bright as it gets
maybe i'll turn the contrast up a little
i don't know maybe that was a bad idea
we'll see
um it seems a bit dim
to me um it may actually be also like
the font
is not the font i'm used to so we might
have to go like set the font to
something else
that may be part of the reason why it
feels a little bit off
so
yeah i don't know that'll be a weird one
too
it's weird we can kind of see these sort
of things you're like oh that's a little
bit seems a little bit wrong
all right
other than the dimness which seems a
little bit
annoying like the dimness definitely
kind of bugs me i don't know why it so
feels so dim but it definitely feels
really dim i don't know if it feels dim
to you
out there at home but it definitely
feels dim to me
and i'm not sure where that's coming
from um
hard to say all right so yeah we can
compile just fine
um let's see what actually happens if we
try to make some edits here so we go in
and let's suppose uh
that we're gonna go into the entity
system and do some stuff so one of the
next things that i might do
for example is i had kind of thought to
myself well
i might want to uh
i might want to go in
and start removing the idea of end
of entity pieces
because one of the problems that i have
right now
is that there's just kind of too much
cruft involved in how these entities
work
um so i don't really know if any pieces
should exist or not
but they're kind of a little bit broken
at the moment
and a lot of this depends on what we
want to do
with the tag matching long term as well
uh because what i'd like to do now is
i'd like to be able to get to the point
um now where we're pretty it's pretty
easy to like move stuff around
in the game in terms of like what art
goes with what things
uh and right now that's definitely too
weird right there's just too much
involved in it
and so what i'd like to do somehow is
sort of rework that system a little bit
and just
just basically cut down on the
complexity because at this point
you know we know exactly what the art
that comes in you know how it's
working exactly so we should be able to
do something here
where we can uh
where we can make it easier uh to set
things up right
and so that's the main thing that i kind
of wanted to do next anyway
um i think we'll just kind of leave
lighting for a little bit and we'll come
back to it
uh later on but anyway so
it's one of those things where
we would definitely like to um
we would definitely like to be able to
to streamline and simplify this process
you can see that it has this like tag
system here for like
going and finding what it's actually
matching and if we look
into the the sources directory
um we've got like uh
the tags files here so we've got like
basegame.hd
right and you can see
that these things have you know
this is a particular png file and it's a
head
right and it's got you know these tags
on it or whatever
and i guess the thing about it is just
that like i feel like this was too much
work for us
right it just doesn't
it just doesn't really help us very much
it would be easier if we just
said hey this is the
identifier for this head and then we
pick
you know in in the game and so
simplifying the tag system down to
something where we literally just ask
for one thing
and then you just have a parameter that
picks out of there because
that's all you can really do with the
art files anyway like
you know when we load these things in
uh if we go look at
if we go look at like one of these right
this is what the
orphan head files look like right
they're just laid out
in a particular fashion so we know that
they can only have
just that one whatever it is that
they've got
um and so we don't really need any kind
of elaborate tagging anymore we can just
use some kind of a direct lookup
which would be way more efficient and
much easier to specify
right and we would lose the ability for
the art to be flexible with respect to
the code
certainly um so
yeah i mean it's not that there aren't
some drawbacks in sort of a
broader scheme but just in terms of this
stuff
we could just make it a lot easier uh
than than what we did right
and so we still kind of need the
complexity of this stuff
sadly because there's no way like one of
the real
bummers about the way things work if you
do
kind of just pngs as your source assets
right is there's no markup ability
in them right there's no way to say like
where the snap points are and that kind
of stuff
it's a very like you know um
this is just an unavoidable consequence
of the fact that 2d image creation
software has not evolved since
we started doing games and so you can't
like do the kind of complex stuff you do
with like 3d files where you say like
this is an attach point and
it snaps to here and all that stuff so
we still need to be able to do that
stuff but
what i was saying is that you know in
here we can certainly just try
making these things more explicit so
that we just
we apply this stuff in code rather than
exporting it out to the art side of
things
right meaning we don't try to
have there be this elaborate binding
stuff because it just takes time
it just takes run time it doesn't really
get us anything because we always are
setting the tags to try and pick a
specific thing anyway
right so
again i don't really know whether we
want to keep the pieces part or not but
i guess the first step here would just
be to like
stop doing the tags this way right and
instead you would just say
look for each of those pieces so for
each of the
entity piece this thing here this would
actually be the thing
that tells you what the piece is like
which one you're getting
and so you just need
you just need an asset file and then
like you would need to set up
a lookup code for it and the problem is
that the lookup codes
are actually the things that would be
specific uh to the file
so like a head file is
a head file is going to have a specific
indexing scheme
and so really i think
that's the thing that this would need to
say
so it would need to say what kind of art
piece it was
and then it would need to say what
indexing scheme it
needs right and then it would just use
that indexing scheme
i think that is more or less the
entirety of it
right like i don't think
i don't think we would need anything
else
so if we go into the asset system as it
is now
um and we just look at like the tag
stuff
uh i would think that we can just sort
of
not do that anymore uh
and you could almost tell that that you
kind of knew that was true
already in a sense because uh
we had the previously we
when we made the import right
we actually had these like tag matrices
that we build
right and then we apply those tag
matrices to like
like it's this it's this import grid
stuff right
we apply the tag matrices on top
of the asset files but we know for a
fact that they
always have to be that
set of tags because that's how we're
applying them in the first place
so if we just saved these sets of
tag matrices if we just thought of those
as hard-coded things that were in the
game
right and then all you were doing when
you
marked up one of these asset files it
said well
it's you know it uses this particular
tag matrix
then we don't really need the constant
of tags anymore because you now know
it is this particular 2d matrix is how
the lookups work
right and so that's really just like a
massive simplification
that we can do there
um and again you know we can't
we can't simplify it all the way down to
the thing that we started with which is
that the file name itself tells you
everything you need to know
um unfortunately that just is never
going to happen
and like i said that's because we need
these alignment points in here
we need the ability to save these out
from the game
like we do currently because we need to
be able to adjust
how these pieces snap together
so they're really the only thing we can
fix um
is the part where you know you're
picking these things out by using sort
of a diffuse set of tags i think that
was just a little bit too much
it also and again just to tie it back to
how things were working
in the actual entity system uh
is that if you look at these visible
pieces
you wanted each visible piece to
actually have its own tag set
in the old system and that was kind of
not clear how that would work
right and so what we really want to be
able to do is just replace
this so instead of just the flags it
also would then have
um a thing which said this is the piece
that i am
in some you know big set of identifiers
for pieces right
and then we can just use those you know
we just have sort of a standard
enum set that just says here's all of
the the different stuff that we have
and i think that's probably just better
i mean
because again like we still can leverage
the fact that these files have multiple
things
in them to avoid having to have too many
enums so like when we look at something
like this
we don't have to define enums for each
of these we just need an enum
basically like per file so you can say
like what's this thing oh it's like
fire particles and then there's just a a
big thing of fire particles in here
right and that's all we really needed to
know
so i think that's what i would like to
do next and that way we can just start
to decorate the game more
which i think would be nice um and we
can put each of the different
uh orphans in there correctly because we
have all the different orphan bodies and
orphan heads and stuff like that um so i
think that's probably the best idea
um for now right and
uh and so i think that's what i would
like to do next
and looking at some of this stuff
so blocks are fine um
oh it's krampus um and
yeah so i i i think that'll just work
that's my theory anyway
all right so
effectively what this would look like is
that when we build
one of these asset files uh what we
or rather when we load i guess i should
say these asset files
what we would do when we merge the asset
files together
is we try to just figure out of all of
the tags of all of the
i guess not tags but um of all of the
things we have and we could
call those tags i guess if we want to um
we would just need to figure out
each of those would map into a table
where the table just said what the file
you know an id that corresponds to that
file
and we would already know in the code
which kind it was so if it was a head if
it was a
you know a particle etc etc
so there'd just be something and i guess
we don't have a tags
uh section here or whatever but
we have a thing that that has like the
file format information in it so like
these
right they've got all of this stuff
right
and you can see just why i think this
kind of
system didn't really work out that well
it's just because you end up defining so
many things anyway
that you should have just used specifics
and let the code handle it it's one of
those things where you
are inserting too much slop
and the idea is that somehow that slop
will become useful but it never does
right um you never actually
end up having sort of um
any of the the play in the joints that
you thought was going to be really
useful to you somehow
never actually ends up becoming that
right so
um so if we look we know that uh
we know that some of this stuff right
like head
body that sort of stuff um block
these map these are basically the things
that tell us
how to index into the files so
the basic category i think would more or
less
survive unchanged and we should probably
go through
and like cut out some of the old
unused stuff now um
and just you know condense it down but
it's the tags really that is the thing
that then we would change and we might
you know maybe what we should do
is actually keep the tags file
just keep the tag id as the thing and
then we just change
tags to meaning specifically
which one of these things you're talking
about right
so when we look uh at those files all
we're really doing
is mapping this stuff to the files
right and maybe that's how we do it
so if we look in the base game hht file
what i'm basically talking about here is
for each of these
when we do tags right instead now we
would just
call this like forest 01 right
um or just forest
right because if you look at what's in
block forest 01
so let's take a look right it's just a
block
and so if we wanted to have variants of
this block we could have them stack up
but you know all we really want to say
is look when we're doing forest stuff
that the tag for this
is like you know i don't know
forest block right
and there wouldn't be multiple tags
really
i i guess you know one could argue that
you need multiple tags to like put
things into more than one place if for
some reason you've got a single asset
file that you want duplicated into two
places but i don't know why we would
ever
do that so it's probably just
like tag right
and so if we were to look at what this
would be so we got block orphanage here
so we would do orphanage block right
and because we have sort of
a different conception of what this
would be
if we may want multiple tiles of this
right
so this is like just orphanage wall
probably right and this is like forest
floor you know what i mean
uh and and i
we could also adopt some of those team
like forest basic and orphanage basic
or something like that
i don't know what we want to call those
right but it would be something like
this
um and we've got block orphanage o2
apparently uh no3 why is this
there we go okay so there is floor
there's
there's stone floor okay okay so now i
was right the first time
i thought maybe there wasn't there so
yeah so this is orphanage
basic wall this is forest floor
let's do it this way
um that's not high spell orphanage
and this is orphanage
floor wood and this is orphanage floor
stone
and these would just get parsed and
they'd just get slotted directly in
there
right and then from then on we don't
need to do
any tag matching anymore you just use a
specific enum
that goes directly with this now
normally the underscores here is not how
we do enum so
you know it might be more like this
right uh and off we go
so i think that's more or less what i
would want
and
and i guess when you think about it when
we do a game build
yeah we would just hard code those into
an enum list and they would parse out of
here and that would just be the end of
it
right so then if you imagine those were
in here
right if you imagine that now what we
had was actually just the list of the
things so we just had like
this stuff in here
right
so that's a pretty weird thing i'm gonna
have to take a look at too
for some reason moving one token
goes past the semicolon but the
semicolon is a separate token
so we have to look at that
token move skips over semicolons
the good news is we haven't noticed much
else so i think our editing situation is
seeming pretty reasonable right um
so if we imagine these just got lined up
like this
uh that seems yeah that seems pretty
good
i don't know i'm i'm down with that
so these would just be
named by the people i guess
uh although i guess these are the body
types so i'm not sure how we want to
name the body types exactly
uh
it looks like the bodies are basically
named you know
by their properties so like these are
just orphan
body earth i guess
we could also try this sort of thing so
we could also do like wall
orphanage just so it's a little clearer
floor floor
i don't know
that might be a little better just for
our own ease of use
so we can see what's what more quickly
might want to get rid of the cursor
trails as well
they're just too much uh so there's a
battery saver mode actually we can we
can already kind of do that
that i think yeah gets rid of the them
it's much nicer without them
i would i think actually they're just
too noisy for me
all right so looking at the orphan
bodies here
these would just be
pretty straightforward
i'm not sure if we had really much plans
for what these
meant but
yeah sorry it's a little slow for me
today like
some of those little idiosyncrasies like
the fact that it skips over a semicolon
for some reason
make it hard for me to edit fast because
it edits differently than what i'm used
to
so i'm not sure how to really fix that
part
um
you know like uh i guess that's just the
code for that what determines a token in
that setting is somehow different
and so it's just a little bit tough
all right
so this is again something where it's
just kind of really annoying because
this stuff is really not stuff you
should ever have to do
it's just because c plus plus is such a
gigantic pile of crap
that you ever have to do anything like
this yeah this is what computers were
supposed to be made for but they're too
busy worrying about
like ridiculous crap in the spec about
things that literally have no bearing on
programming at all
but you know they can't be bothered to
actually get something that
makes it automatic
for you to have things like enums that
are also strings
it's insane
never let anyone tell you can't program
kids
just go look at the c plus committee if
you ever think you're not good enough to
be a programmer
there is no bar too low
oh that's a spelling error
op ron
so that's all of the orphan bodies
and you know i don't know but
maybe walls and floors get separated in
here if you imagine
right uh
and i assume we want this to just be tag
right
and eventually these will all have
alignment info
stuck in there because you know there
we have to go into the little editor in
the game
at some point for each of these and
actually like place where those
attachment points are so all of these
will eventually look like this one
you know because it will have had the
alignment data
generated by the game editor but at the
moment since we don't have that
um all of these are basically all they
will all they have is just the tag in
them
all right uh so this is
still a body i guess right this is cat
body
fred
cat body hannah
um and cat body
oh wait that's not cat body where's
molly
oh there's molly somehow krampus got
inserted
um in between i guess because we're
going in alphabetical order but let's
keep the cats together right
so we've got molly who you just saw on
stream earlier
right
uh so we've got the cat bodies and then
we've got just krampus
um
i guess these are actually
all in one file though
so don't they have heads and bodies
so i guess for some reason these are all
together
but i don't actually know why
like why are they not
i don't know why these wouldn't be in
the same file
um so that to me seems like it should
probably just get fixed
uh because there's no real reason not to
do that
like i mean they are still just heads
and bodies right so i mean
why would we not
just have them i don't get it like i
don't know why we did that
unless there was some confusion as to
how they should be created
um i feel like we should just fix that
so i might just say like
you know these these should probably
just be
more like this
i mean yet another way to say it was
since there's heads as well as bodies
and the type
tells you the difference between those
two maybe you don't even need that like
maybe it's just this
right um
i'm starting to have a thought
i just had a thought that maybe i can
get exactly what i want
without actually even changing this
so riddle me this tag man
if we just said look
we're going to keep most of this stuff
but just flatten a few of these tags
what if we just had a basically you
hash the tag
into a
match which you just look up in table so
for example
this is basically already what we want
it's just orphan hero orphan earth like
if you read it
not as two tags that are used in fuzzy
matching but is in specifics so i just
have to match these tags directly
i mean who cares if i put an underscore
between them or not i can make the code
already do what i need it to do right
and so if you just clean up a few of
these and you say like oh this
is you know um
cat fred and cat hannah and cat molly
probably instead of
you know what was here before or
something
um it's still basically the same thing
so i feel like if we just collapse a few
of these
we might actually be fine
so let's try that because that's
actually pretty compelling
right so we just left everything exactly
the way it was
and then we just changed the lookup
system so instead
of there being so
you know when we load it right you can
see what happens
during the asset actual loading process
when we actually go through here and
load these things in
we load in all the different like um
we load in all the different tags and we
load in all the different assets and all
that stuff right
and once we do that we just have tag
lists
and when we go to do the matching
we have to literally go through like
each of those things so if you look
there's like one of these um
where is it here um
it's it's like first asset of type
right so you go look uh at the category
you're talking about if you say that
this thing's supposed to be a head file
it goes in here
and it starts looking for all of the
head assets or crap like that
right and i think what we actually
want to do here is just say look instead
of that
just have all the tags that aren't
directional tags that aren't like
that aren't picking from the matrix
thing
have all those tags actually just be
things that you hash into a hash and you
don't care about
uh the type anymore other than just as
something that's part of that hash
matching right so there's something
like this uh like asset
um match
i don't know we want to call this asset
um
i don't really know what this would be
called exactly we'll think about that in
a second
but effectively what we get here is a
hash of of the tags that are involved
and
when we check the hash we
would just check against the hash value
first so there's something in here
uh like a you know like a hash
tag hash um and
then in here is whatever the asset
number actually is
so the asset index in as it is currently
loaded
um
maybe that oh no
is my completion not turned on ah
so completion is not in hold on a second
we're gonna have to fix that i i
live and die by completion so the
completion
is not is is erroneously only in the
command version
so if you take a look at
where completion actually is happening
here word complete
um you can see that it only happens in
the command version
that's not acceptable right that's got
to be
that's got to be up here
all right let's just go ahead and reload
that
um what buffers have i modified i don't
even know what buffers have modified
asset hash entry next
so we'll get back to you in a moment
it all looks good there um we can also
at the moment
turn off extra compilation to save time
so
like light prof and sphere and such
don't actually need to run
right we can just jump right to the
actual game and compile it
um so i think that's
what we probably can do here with this
system so it's not really
it's not actually as far off as i was
imagining it was
so we probably can just do something
much simpler
oops that was power mode i didn't mean
to do that
i want battery mode there we go okay
um so in theory completion should be
working now
is it let's see yes
so uh let's go ahead and
look at the asset
hash entry so if we just imagine that
we've got
our assets hashed and we have like the
asset index in the table here
on load we can put all of these things
into one of these
hash tables so we can basically have a
like tag hash
here where we just look up things by the
tags directly
and that way when you ask for one of
these things you can just ask for it by
the hash
now there's a couple different ways that
we can
look at this and
my assumption is that actually what we
can do is not have to use an
a a real hash anyway
because presumably we would probably
only have
something like you know less than a
thousand tags
anyway even in the final game
so what we could probably do is just
pack the bits
in so we'll say you know you've got
64 bits of hash and since you've got 64
bits of hash
we know that if you want to have say 10
bits
of tag data you can fit
six tags into a single 64-bit id
so the hash rather than thinking of it
as a hash
it's it's actually more like the act
it's just is the tags
right um so you wouldn't have to
secondarily match or worry about hash
collisions because
there it would literally it's really not
a hash
per se it's it's more like just actually
the thing
right it's actually the data in in a
sense
so in here we could have um our tag hash
right
and we can have something you know i
don't know how many of these we want
um to have it doesn't really matter for
now because we can look at the
performance of that at some other time
but if you imagine we would just have
these hash entries in here and then we
would do is just stick
in
the various pieces all we would then
need is something that allows us to do a
tag hash on say like four tags
let's say four tags total or something
like that
and in fact if we assumed that each tag
like i said was like 10 bits or
something and we assumed no more than
three tags we could even use 32 bits
there's no real reason we don't care so
64 is probably fine
uh so i'm going to go ahead and and just
assume that that's what we would do
be doing and we would have something
like okay
you know get tag hash
or something like this and in here we
would pass those
tags that we were getting from the hht
file format stuff so in here where we've
got these
file formats with the different tags and
so on so these tags for
whatever is happening here
these tags would be
like fused together
so when we go to produce the actual
um composite of these
we would just say yeah each one of these
gets converted to you know
a u64 and they just get ored together
and we just shift them up so like the
first one
doesn't get shifted up at all like the
second one gets shifted up 10 or
whatever
right um the next one gets shifted up
20 and the final one gets shifted up
30 right uh and so it's
it's nothing special it's just pretty
much what you would expect
uh but that's how you do
is this oh so this is backwards also we
have one more thing
in our bindings here apps four-footer
bindings
the mapping for home is
is broken so it's it's actually the
opposite of what it's supposed to be
so this
and this are flipped
let's try that again
so if i exit out of here
and load back up there's probably a key
to like reload the bindings or something
um but i don't know what it is
so
okay much better so if we
assume that we have this way of
generating a tag hash then yeah like
all we need is just to remember that
for any piece that we might have and
like i said it would be compelling to
force these things to always fit
um into a u32
just for compactness sake so i'm sort of
tempted
to say we should just say that you only
get three of them
uh because i think eight bits is too
small
like we definitely want more than eight
eight bits
but
i don't know even 1024 is is a little
bit
squinky so like if you assume 64-bit you
could even say like each one of these
things could be 16 bits
right um and you would still be fine
so four tags 16 bits per tag still fits
into u64 and you can use that for
perfect matching no matter what it is
like there's no
possibilities that you have any issues
so that does seem pretty good to me so
it
i mean maybe we just do that and so if
you
if you think back now to the problem
that i was having before and was
was worried about now this just gets a
lot simpler
simpler as we start to want this entity
system to actually be good
uh and we start to think about how what
we're going to
be doing to it to make it actually you
know useful
this is just sucks right it's hard to
deal with
these sorts of things you don't want to
have variable length things lying around
if you can avoid it you you know because
they always lead to inefficiencies
um whatever your final implication is
basically anything that is variable
length is always an extra consideration
um when you when it comes time to think
about performance
if you ever choose to think about
performance and so
i tend to try and eliminate those things
where possible and obviously sometimes
it's not possible and that's fine you
know you deal with
those sorts of things or you don't if
you like i said don't care about the
performance
then you just don't have to care because
you can do whatever you want but
assuming you're actually trying to think
about the efficiency of the overall
thing
then when you actually look at something
like this um
you know it just looks ugly and you're
like you can kind of see that this sort
of wanted to be a variable thing and it
just kind of isn't
it's just like a weird like oh you know
um
we've got sort of eight of them i guess
or something like that
and it's just like it still takes up way
too much room and blah blah blah blah
and it's got values and a flexible count
a lot of stuff
so something like this is way easier we
just say look at 64 bits
we fit the thing in there and it can be
a direct dispatch on that is much nicer
right so in here and then oh and also
and now we don't care about that we can
put them directly in the pieces because
they're relatively compact
so they can just go in here and say look
there's a tag
hash on this and so
the basic category plus the tag hash
gives you
what you need right and
i don't know that we actually want the
we could so there's a decision to make
here which is do we want the asset
category and the tag hash to be welded
together or not
and of course i don't really know the
answer to that question
because on the one hand
it seems somewhat compelling to be able
to just pass around one value and so if
you imagined
so let's say you took this right and you
said well the asset category is fairly
small so if you imagine
shaving a few bits off of this you could
actually fit the asset category in here
basically for free because we're not
going to have 65 000
tags like i couldn't even understand
them all if there were that many tags
maybe if you're red dead redemption 2
you can have 65 000 tires because you
have like a project manager for every
tag
um but like
you know on on a game where one person's
doing all the programming that's just
not
gonna happen right it doesn't even make
sense because they couldn't possibly
write enough interesting stuff to even
use that many tags
by themselves so it would seem somewhat
compelling to say
let's just float the basic category in
there
and so you would then have like okay so
there's
there's four asset tags and also an
asset basic category
i'm attempted to sort of say yeah let's
do that
so in here we would do um
the tags would would all be
shifted up slightly so we'd say like
okay you know maybe
asset basic category if we look at this
thing
most of this is garbage like right now
it's mostly just
a couple of these for the basic
categories there's
you know these are not really
actually representative you know what
i'm saying so
if you look at how many there are like
it looks like it's pretty unlikely that
there would be
uh more than 16 of these anyway
but even if we wanted to be very safe
and
call it let's say eight that would only
be two bits less per
um so we could just do that right we
could say
all right there's the asset category and
that doesn't get shifted up at all
um then we or in
uh that needs an extra parentheses
there we go uh then we orient everything
and these just get shifted up by that
eight
so you know uh we start out eight
up here then rather than adding
16 right we just take two from each one
to make up the difference
uh in the eighth that we lost so instead
of adding 16
we add 14 to the eight uh
so this this only goes up to 22 instead
of to 24.
um and then again we add 14 instead of
16 again
so we end up with 36 and then we add it
one more time
so we were at 50 and then 14 would bring
us 64. so that's correct
right so this tag hash
would just give you the entire thing and
then when we look it up we may not look
it up as a tag hash quite in that way
um or we might you know i don't know uh
so anyway
this tag hash would be all we would need
then so then if we went into
the uh if if we went into the asset
system
where we're actually would be looking
these up
or i guess i should say in the entity
system where we're actually specifying
what we're going to look up
instead of having the asset basic
category here and have the asset
category
piece there we would just have the tag
hash
part of things and we would
use just that for the lookup right
and so probably that's like a primal
thing that's basically saying look this
is what we're getting and then we have
like these other pieces here
that we're using and i think that's all
we really would
need and so then this becomes
a lot easier to work with because now
the tags on the entity
we just would get rid of so you wouldn't
actually
need the tags on the entity anymore at
all like this stuff
wouldn't need to be there right um
so now if we actually do a compilation
here
we can sort of take care of some of
these errors um
i'm also going to write down like
full width compilation
window all right
um so this goes behind my head so i'm
saying like you know having this over
here would be pretty nice right um
so switching the way that this thing
works back to the old way i had it would
be nice it looks like we've got a syntax
error here probably because
we've got um just sloppy sloppy parens
right
um so let's try and fix that so if we
look at this
what's going on with that indentation
like that's
should line up with that right um
but for some reason it doesn't
is that like some kind of four coder
nonsense this used to work just fine so
i don't feel like it's something's weird
about that
anyone know what that is
right i mean that should line up
properly with the parentheses but it
doesn't
like foo equals
yeah that's just weird right i don't
know what's going on there
let's see paren
[Music]
indenting busted
man my handwriting is terrible today
i'll be lucky if i can even read that
um so yeah that
should be lining up properly and isn't
that's going to be really annoying
but we'll have to figure out what's
going on with that later
here's our shift stuff
you can see here that it's all lined up
like so um
[Music]
and then we can balance our parentheses
so
should be that oops not that
there we go so i think that's all good
um so now if we take a look at what
happens here
right where we do get best match bitmap
from
hopefully now we can just turn this into
a straightforward lookup
where we just hand it that 64-bit
identifier which is
like the welding together of the tags in
the category and such
and hopefully then it will just do
what it needs to do directly now
the problem that we'll have and like i
said we need to
this probably will affect the import and
we'll take a look at that next week
because i don't think a lot of time
today but
when we look at the tag matching here we
don't want any of this stuff anymore
right
so what we actually want to do is we
want to pass down
just a simple vector of the parameters
and you can see what the parameters are
already
right um
we already have them defined here and if
you imagine getting rid of the weight
vector because the weight vector
is not useful right
um so we imagine getting rid of the
weight vector so weight vector goes
goodbye
um and we take a look at how the tags
are these tags are now going to get
replaced so we don't care about these
i'm not sure what the heck this was
about
so if the thing is
grass it wants to weight that more
heavily and that must have been some
hack for like getting the picking
correct or whatever right like i don't
even know
but anyway we have like an entity facing
direction here
and so the entity facing direction is an
example of a parameter that actually
needs to go
into the tag matrix
um part of things which again like i
said now can just be
more of a direct match kind of a thing
but we still
do need that so when we actually call
the matching
uh we need in addition when we go
and pass the the asset hash entry stuff
right
we also do need to pass like something
like a vect4
that has like the parameters for this
thing
that include like the facing direction
[Music]
and anything else that's parametric
along the
uh you know inside that matrix and
the thing that i don't know is to what
extent we actually have
anything happening in there
so we've got like i think there's like
the dodging is in there but i don't i
don't know if we
actually use it i think we don't um
so to the extent that we ever have this
it's usually like just variance
is mostly what is going on with that
picking right
um
so i i it may just be facing directions
and and i don't know like
if it's like like the the the horizontal
axis
just is not really used for anything
um other than variance as far as i know
so so we kind of have to like
um see how that progresses a little bit
more but at the very least at the moment
we can say pretty definitively that like
it just doesn't matter
at all because all we've been using is
that so maybe in the future we don't
like it's unclear that we even use
um those slots for anything
it looks like there's some expressions
in here so there maybe is an expression
[Music]
um feel but like basically we're just
talking about passing
a few things down so i think we can
afford to do something like this
which is like our match vector or
something and just say look
we're just gonna pass down the facing
direction for now
and we're not going to pass down
anything else
right so this goes away and all this
crap goes away
goodbye um and you know we'll
see what develops if we ever need
anything else it may be that we end up
with it's not even using
everything in a v4 anyway because none
of our stuff
actually cares i don't know but what we
would say is all right
there's the assets here we know there's
a tag hash
that we're getting from there we're
gonna pass in a single v4 match vector
um and that's it like that's how we
match our bitmaps now
right so if we look at get match
get best batch uh bitmap
and we look at what that's actually
going to use now oh
uh can we turn this thing off
um no
like i really strongly dislike that
thing it it
makes it impossible for me to see my
code um
so while you know i don't mind that like
it's helpful
that it's showing this information but
it should show it like over here
right or something like it should show
it some it should pick a location on the
screen that's the least likely to be
something that i would actually
see um another option would be
so okay here's an idea is ryan here he's
probably not
why would he be um
um i don't know why he's here but or if
he was here or
what but here's the proposal ryan this
is what i'm going to propose right now
is ryan on the chat let's see
i don't i don't see any flurry in there
but here's my oh he is here all right
never mind
so here's the thing ryan i've got an
idea
so i like this thing that shows the
stuff
but it's always in the way like i can't
see my code when it's up
here's my new proposal are you ready for
this
it's just like it's just where it's at
so rather than this thing we do a single
window across the bottom like i used to
have that's like
only four lines long this thing
just shows up down there right so you
can always look down there for the
for this stuff it doesn't interrupt code
when you build
if you when you hit next error it will
show you the build happening in that
same window so it's just like
the multi-purpose crap that you need
to see occasionally but that you don't
want to overwrite your stuff
window does that seem plausible
maybe
i don't know what else to do because
basically like it does seem like i mean
i'm not used to it
i would just turn it off for now because
i'm not used to looking at it anyway
but it does show useful information so
if i
started getting used to it i would
probably use it
but i can't handle that it overwrites
what i'm looking at
so i feel like it just needs to be moved
somewhere but i don't know where
but if we took the compile window and
made that be the constant
like hud basically
um then we could show that stuff
and it would possibly solve both
problems i don't know
maybe it doesn't i'm not sure
my other idea was that you put it over
on the opposite pane
so like it's across from you but then
that probably obscures something you
were trying to look at as well so
i just don't know um
i don't know
anyway i gotta send i gotta make a bunch
of changes and then send you my changes
anyway maybe i'll try that and see what
happens
i don't know it might be just a bad idea
i have no idea
um
yeah we could make it be that the
control key pops it up i think there's a
co
the code peak thing there already is a
code peak thing that happens
that i don't really know much about um
that right
uh so it like it
it pops up like a whole thing there's
just a like
there's a lot of stuff in here now
that's actually really cool like you
know you can just hover over something
like get first asset from or something
and
um and hit that although so like random
choice right
and then you can hit the code peak
thingy so you can say
like which i don't have bound anything
right now but
um the flurry code peak thing it'll just
jump you
and show you like it'll jump you right
to that
thing and show you what it is in like a
pop-up which is great
in theory but just not particularly
useful in practice because
it's unclear like
it's unclear how i keep editing and
still make use of this information
so i feel like it's very useful but it
needs to have
some way to show itself
in a location that doesn't make it
impossible to keep
working and that's the part that i'm not
sure
um exactly what the right decision is
i still need to think about it i don't
know
but that's the problem like right now
the problem is actually design
not features like there's more features
than fit in the like
graphic design of what's going on
if that makes sense
well think about it yeah the a peak
buffer that you stick into a panel is
not a bad idea but
again
i just think the problem is
fundamentally speaking it needs to be
smarter about what's going on
so when you're doing like a code peek it
needs to try to get out of your way
i mean i might almost suggest like
it goes in the other pane on the
opposite half of the screen
from where you are right
yeah jump to definition i use a lot as
well people are talking about that and
and i made a new key command actually
also which i think
didn't i go to code peak i don't know if
that's bound to anything though
um is it let's see
uh quote so i do have
here like if i go um if i want to go to
the definition of random choice
i can just hit quote um and there i am
right so
i do have the jump version of this
where i do already do have that one
right
um and that seems pretty good like it
does seem like a good
feature i have to get used to actually
using it but
it seems pretty good right um
so yeah what if you only have one paint
i don't care
i don't care at all what happens to
people who only have one pain that's
their problem
if you only have one pain then you need
to do your own design
work right um
i strictly do double pane editing so
i'm only really concerned about things
that happen with dual pane editing
um so yeah jump history
well i have jump history um
in my in my normal editor that i use
for day to day work um i don't know if
four coder has the jump history stuff it
i think it does
anyway doesn't matter point being here's
the get best match
uh bitmap stuff and really
this bitmap id nonsense um is just a way
of making sure we keep things straight
this is going to be the same lookup for
all of the different assets we now no
longer need this stuff so we're really
just talking about
one of those tags we probably should try
to
insulate ourselves a little bit here and
say
that you know asset tag hash
something like that
i probably should make sure that this is
an actual type we've defined
and that way we know that you know
people aren't just
accidentally passing an integer like uh
because they got the function order
wrong or something just to keep us a
little bit more type checked
and just lean on the power a little bit
there for that but otherwise we're fine
so we've got the the tag hash and the
match vector
those two things would just go in here
and yeah and off we would go
so this all should be basically the same
um
i guess for get first bitmap from
i don't really know that that
matters anymore but we'll humor them and
just say well you just pass
zeros as the match vector and that's
you know you call it a day so when you
call
get uh also why
yeah this this is not really gonna make
much sense anymore so so really
none of this it's not even best match
like none of this this this is just
gonna there's just gonna be one thing
it's gonna be called get asset from
right so it's always gonna be now called
get asset from you're gonna
pass at the assets you're gonna pass it
the tag hash
and the match vector it's gonna do
this whole rigmarole you can see
so random uh assets we're not using at
the moment which is fine
and we don't care about that anyway so
really this is the match
bit here and
so we need this to get superseded here
so we're going to say get asset from it
returns the u32
i don't know that it really needs to be
a time function anymore because it
should be quite fast
now whereas it was quite slow before
but uh when we do a get asset from we're
going to look it up in the hash table so
if we now look at what this was doing
it's going to do something uh quite
different so
we shouldn't need to do this anymore we
should be able to look up directly into
the hash table
so there should just be this this tag
hash um
we wouldn't need this first asset of
type uh
i don't think for anything anymore
um and
i don't know if i should delete it just
yet i'll just make a note
but in here we would take the tag hash
value and look it up in the hash table
so it would basically just be hey yeah
mod by
whatever this thing is um
and unfortunately we may need this to be
sort of a prime number hash
uh
we can take a look at that and the
reason that i say that is because
what we're going to get here is the
problem of
we wouldn't really get any mixing on
these tags
we stack them in the order that we
actually care about them and that's
great but the problem is so you can see
well you can already see what the
problem is so in order to look this up
in a relatively oh
well actually but we can just mix it
first
because we actually have the power of a
thousand suns
if we want right um
[Music]
because i think we allow sse4 or
whatever right don't we
what's our what's our situation here
don't we
i don't really know i don't really know
what we allow and what we don't allow to
be completely honest with you
um at this point i have no idea
about what we're actually using and what
we're not
um
yeah i don't know but if we wanted to
so we just have a to do for this right
um
so i don't know like i don't know why we
would at this point because we've gotten
to the point where
you know if we just take long enough to
make handmade hero
we don't have to worry about backwards
compatibility
basically the longer you take to make a
game the easier it gets to make a game
which is not true at all in the mental
sense but it's definitely true in the
compatibility sense
so if you look here it's like it's
basically complete like nobody on steam
can't do that
um so you pretty much can just ship i
mean you could ship avx nowadays if you
wanted to you're talking about seven
percent of the user base on steam
that you would be worried about not so
much ssc
4a nobody really likes that um
but there you go don't ship avx 512
though folks
not great market penetration there intel
um so you know we probably just can
uh if we want to so what that means is
if we wanted to
we could just do you know some some
hardcore
hashing here right so if we have
one of these tag hashes maybe we just
maybe we just actually do
um something fancy here
you know like we want to produce
a 32-bit look-up
um from like
some 64-bit values or whatever
i don't know right so
uh we want to call some kind of hash
or something
maybe i'll call it hash 32 because it
produces 32. you pass it two of these or
something
and we just want to produce a perfectly
distributed number from that so we
we don't want to have to use prime
number
slots and weird divides and crap like
that
and still get kind of questionable
results so maybe we'll just have a hash
here
and what we'll do is we'll pass in the
tag hash value thing so we'll just say
okay the tag hash
value uh we we do a hash 32 of that
and then we uh mod off which here which
would just
you know do a truncate and that gives us
our hash slot
right
and to do this uh we we can just do
um we can just do some
aes rounds so basically like aes rounds
you know they're they're specifically
made for
doing encryption right so they're
they are specifically made to scramble
the bits of a sequence
in ways that are exactly what we would
want for a hash table
because they're very unpredictable and
so they shouldn't
they should take all the bits and
scramble them
a single round of aes only
gets you bite
to 32 so it goes each bit
goes out to 32 bits worth of
variance right and
so we need to run two rounds to make
sure that we propagate our bits forward
enough but that's all we should really
need to do to get a pretty perfect hash
out of it i would think
so if we just said okay you know the
uh
if we just run a few rounds of this so
we basically say like okay the
the hash value is going to be an deck
of whatever the value is starting with
so
we would just need something where we
can load
um two of these i don't actually know
what the most efficient intrinsic is to
tell it to take
two 64 bits because there isn't really
such a thing
you but so you kind of need to
load into each side and or is probably
what you would do but let me just check
what the
intrinsics are for this sort of thing
these days
so assuming that we're doing something
like this
um that's actually loading from so
do i want to call this convert what is
what is your terminology here
mr intel
all right so so this is this is probably
what would tell
the compiler what we want for the most
part
so like set epix48x
right that's what we're trying to do so
i think that would tell the compiler as
best as possible like we're trying to
put these things
in to uh you know
uh into a single register so i'm gonna
try this
and and hope that that tells compiler
well enough what i'm trying to do
right so here there you go
um we don't care about the order it
doesn't matter because we're hashing
them so as long as they both go in there
it's fine
um so then we would just need basically
like a seed
here so i'm gonna make sure that
the seed is loaded up in there
and i'll just hash this twice
and then we'll call it a day
so the result of the hash um
we would then need to do an mm convert
so that we can pull out the
i don't remember the syntax they use for
these but we basically need to do a
convert
out to a register
this intel syntax always drives me nuts
because i never remember um so
not that um
not that either
oh for the love of god just extract the
thing okay
uh it's this
so let's convert si 128 so the si120
goes on the inside
so it would be mm well actually you know
what it's probably an extract
technically though right
yeah so
we only need 32 out of it and we just
need the zero with one so
presumably that's the right one to do
i don't know i mean arguably you
maybe ju if you only want the bottom one
they
might have had a better one so i could
see
um asking for an epi 32 here just to
make sure
that i'm not totally wrong about that
so those all still seem like the same
level so
i'm not sure that it really helps but
just looking because that's the one that
that would do what we want
right
i mean it looks like that's the only one
so
i'm just going to say that that's maybe
what we want so it's extract dpi
you know
so extract dpr32
and a immediate so
it would just be hash zero
so that would give us a pretty nice hash
right and it you know it it takes
probably like that would be something
like
eight cycles to get a really nice hash
which seems
fine um i mean even if we just think
about like what the divide
just the divide would have cost us
just to get the prime part um
of it right uh a div on an integer
is is pretty bad right um it's it's not
really what we want to be doing
so if we do a div
uh or i should say a mod um
let's see here
i mean it's just bad right
it's just bad so eight cycles for a
perfectly distributed hash is very good
because
even just the divide alone would cost us
probably almost that much
so i would say we just stick with this
and and go from there so we'd
load the hash slot this way um and
yeah the seed value we just need some
random seed
that we can use so it would you know
it's just
garbage it doesn't matter in fact i can
just put it in here
so there's just some seed value that's
16 bytes long
that is what we would hash with and
you know for the sake of of you know
being a a good random
user can i just get some randomness in
here
um
so
[Music]
sequences maybe or raw bites
i would like hexadecimal bites
16 please
look at these delicious random bites
all right so there's my seed
value which is just a mixing value
because aes deck
xors you know it's going to xor
um we don't really care about that xor
at all um because we don't
really need it to do that so we could
just xor it we could probably just xor
it with zero if we wanted if we honestly
if we wanted to would be fine
um but
you know for the sake of since we're
gonna
see it anyway we might as well just do a
mem up
and point it there it's basically free
for these purposes so you know
it should be fine all right so whoa
i don't know what's going on here
something's unhappy oh
just the commas
all right so
we can just pass zero for the second one
and actually i'll probably make that a
default parameter so that people don't
have to care
so so that it's clear that they don't
need it so you know
let's do that um
and then uh this part here where we've
got the tag hash
uh
assets by tag is probably a better name
for that and i'm supposed to stop
programming now i think because
we're out of time right but
that's what we would be doing
this after we look it up none of this is
now necessary
um except for one thing which is the
match vector
needs to be able to generate an index
based on the actual
uh so you can see it like looping
through the tags of the particular asset
right
and we don't actually want that what we
want to be able to do is
basically use a lookup that goes
directly to
the index in question based on the
type of thing that this particular file
type whatever that is
uses so facing direction is the only
thing we have right now and may be the
only thing we ever have
but there was something in a file like
that had expression so
facing direction going down
and a variant going across
seems like the sort of thing we would
need to know
there's also particle files which have
variant going across and down
so we need something here that's
produces
like that coordinate if you will uh
like the thing that basically says like
here's the look up
here's the way we would look up
that 2d grid and so that's really the
only other thing we would be doing
and the way we need to do that is to
look at which
kind of asset it actually is and make
sure that the match vector
pulls out the correct two pieces uh
for the x and the y so it would be
something like this
right like x index y index right
and it would be like you know match
vector
and in both cases we would have pulled
so the tag hash value we would pull the
asset basic category
out of the tag hash which is trivial
because it's just the bottom
eight bits right so at any time we can
just say
the asset basic category um
just kind of comes out so like get
category from
tag hash by the way this should
obviously produce one of these things
like so what is going on with that
indentation
someone tell me right now i do not
understand
um
so the asset tag hash produces this it
can then undo that
right
by just saying
uh the bottom eight bits
produce the
the category right so
these are pretty straightforward
um
so once we have the basic category we
would just need to know these two pieces
of information
uh and then we would need to know how to
actually expand the value and round it
so all of this code that was really bad
and dangerous right
um would presumably go away and then we
would have that look up
pretty straightforward the problem
oh
so okay actually
we might as well just also match on that
so if you think about it once you know
which of these you're going to do
you can roll them into the hash
which would also make a ton of sense and
hey guess what we have the extra room to
do that
because in addition to that base tag
hash value
we could also just say well we have the
coordinate
value right
that comes in here as another u64 which
is just the
two coordinates packed together
right so if you imagine producing here
from the match vector with like the
facing direction all that crap
right um we should be able to do that
now there are some
difficulties here you can see that we
kind of have this problem
where for matching things like the
facing direction
it kind of does need to be like fussed
with a little bit
and honestly that kind of seems like
something that should probably be
back in the other um that should
probably be in the code that happens
before we pass it down
so i'm going to leave it to do we should
stop i'm overtime to do
um you know move
i'll try to remind ourselves of what
we're doing here so
move coordinates into hash move
uh sort of preparation
of facing direction out
into um
the calling code so it prepares
the match vector
properly and maybe like
maybe match vector is actually
called something else and
is just an integer set
or something i think probably
like it probably should just be an
integer set like it probably should just
be this
so there's an asset tag hash right
and then there's a separate thing you
have which is
an asset like chord hash right
and that's
a separate way of packing in what those
coordinates
are right um we don't i don't know if we
want to find that way but it would
so we would then have a thing called an
asset match vector
and that would actually just be a series
of parameters
so it's it's effectively like however
many of those we have like facing
direction whatever whatever
you would pass those down like as the
match vector
it's not actually floats anymore because
it's assumed the person who's calling
in has already prepped each of the ones
based on the type of thing that they are
so
facing direction gets bucketed into the
four facing directions and so on
and so then here before we actually go
to do the lookup what we would do
is say okay the indexes here we
pull out of the basic asset category
depending on which category it is we
would say all right
for the assets um there's like a layout
you know like a uh
like a category layout we pull the
category layout
for whatever this category is and then
we know that for each
of these things we have
which ones we use so
so once we get the layout we would then
know that oh okay
we pick the x element and the y
element right so out of the match vector
which
we could have as many of these as we
want that's getting fed forward by the
entity system it's like look here's the
parameters we have
we just say look for this particular
type of asset like if it's a head or a
body or a particle
what's the layout like how do we
actually produce those things
right and then it pulls them out
you know what i'm saying so once it has
those then it would just say all right
weld those together
in fact we don't even really need to do
this we could just say
look weld them together directly well
you know we'll
sure we'll we'll do it why not so then
we
just say the coordinate lookup is just
the x index
um or with the y index
right
so then you just hash these in the whole
thing
and off you go
so that looks really nice because now
all of this crap goes away
right like this is all gone and so now
it's a very straightforward process to
actually get this thing
so you hash it you
you know run through the slot you find
it you know if you found the match
good for you congratulations you're a
huge hero
um if you didn't you just returned zero
right um
so we would just run through the hash
slot here and we would just look for
matches that
now which ones exactly match this and
then we return it right
so that would be like way faster than
this garbage
i mean this was terrible right i mean
computers are so fast these days that we
weren't really struggling
even though this code is complete
garbage because it's just amazing like
i don't know how people manage to make
things as slow as they do when i look at
some of the things that i make
that are running at still like 60 frames
a second
and you're just like this is complete
garbage code i don't know how you manage
to make it so garbage that it's like
web browser slow but you know they do
somehow
so i don't know so we'll stop here
and then we'll move on um
uh we'll we'll we'll stop here for now
and we'll move on next week uh
to finishing that okay questions
from people
just put four vms in front of the code
well it's not just for vms right
um it's like also just like straight up
interpreters
like a lot of people use like php or
python or stuff that's not even like
compiled to bite code
off topic feel free to ignore but
someone told me that on playstation
games run in a sandbox and if you forget
to free any memory you allocated when
you exit that sandbox will be kept alive
in the background
um
[Music]
i guess i don't know
i'm not really a playstation expert
my recollection on like the playstation
4 was that it's just got a
map primitive so
i mean you wouldn't be allocating
memory per se in the same way that
you're talking about it there like
there's no
forget to free quote unquote like you
would have to have
the base layer that does the mem mapping
remember to unmap
stuff at map but you can't you wouldn't
be doing an map
per alloc anyway so you've already got a
system at the bottom
and it would be trivial for that system
to just chain its maps together so
even if you were worried about something
like that you could just
keep a list of you know the 30m maps you
actually did or something
and when you want to exit the program
just on and
un mem map them you wouldn't have to
worry about
actually freeing per se individual
allocations because
you aren't doing individual allocations
through mmap right
or if you are haven't helped you um
you've got other problems but
i don't know i'm not really a
playstation person and i don't have
um like you said it may have something
that like i may not be able to talk
about more smoothly without an nda
breaking thing anyway uh but
the real answer is i just don't remember
and or no
uh because i don't do a lot of
playstation programming so
it's it's less about nda and more about
just like that's not something i'm super
familiar with like i've programmed the
ps3
two and four never the three
um and i didn't really program the two
like i sort of just ported some stuff to
the tube but i didn't really like
seriously do
fancy stuff on it
i'd like to hear a discussion between me
and john about mega programming metaphor
and philosophy as soon as you asked
what's that driver satisfied in terms of
meta programming he said the way
throughout the program is really
different from the way he thinks of it
he thinks i'm wrong about it
um yeah i mean john and i don't think
about programming similarly at all
is a probably a better way to say it
um and so
it wouldn't really even just be like
meta programming that we think about
differently
it's also one of the reasons that i
can't say for sure that i would end up
switching to jai
because my guess is that the way that it
probably works is not really the way
that i think about things anyway
um so i don't know
but i don't think there's a wrong or
right there and if john thinks i'm wrong
about meta programming
that's a little weird because
i don't know he doesn't do a whole lot
of meta programming so i don't know what
the chances are that i'm like
like wrong wrong but i definitely think
there's probably
multiple ways of trying to conceptualize
that
and you have to sort of decide it's
you can't have it all one way or the
other so
there's probably not a universal right
answer
right
so you know but if john thinks there is
then
you know he thinks there is but i
couldn't say uh about that right i like
the fact that ji takes meta programming
seriously it's got a lot better features
than most things
but it's not the way that i would do it
um
right because so the way that john
thinks about meta programming as far as
i can tell is that
the language is still mostly not about
meta programming in the sense that
it's still very defined in terms of that
the language is this thing that
you've specified a bunch of policy for
and then meta programming is just the
thing that lets you mutate the ast
when you start right
and that's uh
that's still way better than most
programming languages which don't really
let you do that very much
they're really clunky like ji seems to
let you do meta programming in a more
like as a more serious operation that's
not
busted right um
but i still think like meta programming
[Music]
is actually about full chain flexibility
like
like the ability to write out an
executable
should be something that's written into
the meta program to me
right that's the way i would do it and
the reason is just because i
and i so often
encounter all of these things that i
need to be able to do and i can't do
them because the compiler just does them
in one particular way and you can't
actually
do anything about it right so
so many questions that are totally
random i have no idea
um
why are new compression techniques such
as microsoft direct storage
ps5 compression needed for instant
loading
why are nvme speeds not enough what's
the bottleneck
well sorry right
um if you take a look
i mean let's try to get
a value here right
um
where's my speed crunch
so you know i don't know
i just randomly ask you because i don't
know exactly what the current rate
for read write speeds on these things
are
but you know 32 giga
is that gigabytes per second yes
if it's 32 gigabytes per second is the
um nvme speed
i don't know what the speed is
of a drive that can be placed in the
playstation because
that may be much more expensive right
as well so let's take a look let me see
ps5
ssd speed so it's 5.5 gigabytes per
second so
the first thing to understand right
there is if we're looking at those two
numbers let's assume they're accurate
for now
because i don't remember these numbers
at all but let's say they're accurate
then you're talking about like at least
you know something like six
there's a 6x drop in nvme speed
in terms of what you're actually going
to get from your playstation
because it you know this this is it's
not
a two thousand dollar piece of hardware
it's like a what i don't know what they
cost
six hundred dollars four hundred dollars
so
the ssd that's in the playstation
is not going to be like the ultimate
data center ssd or something
it's it's got to be like
cost effective enough right
so you're instantly down to 5.5
gigabytes per second
if you think about 5.5 gigabytes per
spec per second
right so 5.5 gigabytes per second
um and then we say like well how much
memory does the ps uh
5 have right um
where is the that's
not memory can we get memory please
is it 16
okay everyone wants me to accept their
cookies
what if i don't want to accept the
um so 16 gigabytes
right so if you assume 5.5 gigabytes
second peak throughput
and you take 16 gigabytes of memory and
you say how long does it take me to load
a game
that take that you know to load in the
full memory of the game
well it's three seconds right even if
nothing else had to happen it's three
seconds
so if you want instant loading and
you've got 16 megabytes of memory
and you know your drive can only produce
5.5 gigabytes
per second peak throughput then if you
want instant loading you are a factor of
three
at least away and that's if you accept
the second loading
what if you want it to be like a
fraction of a second
right so
when you look at this you're like if we
can boost this
by getting let's say two to one
compression out of it or something
it starts to look a lot better 1.5
seconds is a lot better than three
seconds
right um
so if in practice you're getting 5.5
peak
and you know you've got 16 to fill
hopefully that gives you an idea of why
this isn't a solved problem
right so nvme bandwidth is 32 gigabytes
max at that rate it would take half a
second to fill the memory
so even if you imagined a theoretically
maximal
nvme drive which like i just said they
can't afford anyway because that would
be some
heinous gigantic array of chips with
extremely
massive heat dissipation or something
right
um so
this is why it's not a solved problem
just to say well we don't need
compression because we can just load the
thing
right and so it makes perfect sense why
they would want to invest in really
good compression technology and try to
do
chip assisted decompression and stuff
because
it's simply not a solved problem if
you're trying to get down to instant
right if you just want relatively short
loading screens
i totally like that's probably fine
three seconds
you know i don't like that kind of delay
but that's probably something gamers
would tolerate but if you're trying to
get to
instant to like this is really instant
it's not a solved problem to just say
well the ssds are fast enough because
they're not
right so
does that answer the question i don't
know
um
i don't know what all the questions are
here
um
way too many topics
i just oh uh is that you roman
i i moved to the east side i just moved
out of seattle i'm still
in the like greater washington area but
i i don't live in the city
if i go from ssd to nvme speeds
are not improved well okay but so
just to be clear ssd and nvme
are not different things right so
ssd is just solid state drive it just
means
that the thing is a memory based
architecture like right like not
a spinning platter nvme is a bus
specification
so nvme is just saying this is
how the thing will communicate and and
so
do you are you meaning to say if you go
from sata
to nvme is what you mean or something
like i'm not ssd and nvme are not things
you go from or
to like an nvme drive is an ssd drive
right it's it's sol it's a solid-state
drive yeah
so nvme is just a protocol difference
designed to allow for higher bandwidth
but
if the ssd isn't itself particularly
much
better then the speed doesn't get
particularly better right so nvme
enables much faster speeds
but the actual drive you buy may not
may top out well before that and
therefore you wouldn't see
you know some drives don't wouldn't even
saturate
your whatever the thing is you were
switching from right and so
all right there's just too many
questions i'm going to wrap it up for
today
let's close this down
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow the
series at home you could always create a
game on handmadehero.org and it comes
with the source code
also i saw a lot of people in the chat
asking about star code galaxy and when
it could be available
um i'm hoping it will be available soon
i am working pretty hard to try and get
it out in short order uh if you
want to be notified when it is available
you can just put your name
in here go to the star code galaxy
website and put your
address in here and hit subscribe and
then it will tell you
um when it is available that's it for
today i'll be back here next week
and at that point um i'll go ahead and
implement the tag
system that we just talked about today
and basically did the first half of
cleaning that up i think will be pretty
great and it'll just let us really
quickly
put match what assets we want in which
places which was kind of really onerous
and annoying right now
so pretty soon we should be able to get
that straightened out uh and then i'll
probably just
do some stuff where i just try to add a
bunch of stuff to the game and we should
be able to see
like what's annoying pretty early on
right like we should be able to get a
good feel
at that point for
what stuff is still kind of annoying to
work with
and so that's what i'll probably be
focusing on
all right that's it for today see you
back here next weekend uh until then
have fun programming i'll see you on the
internet
take it easy everybody