okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show recode a complete
game live on twitch no engines no
libraries we do absolutely everything
ourselves and that's both educational
and for entertainment purposes let's be
honest I kind of think it's fun if you
want to follow along with today's
episode and you have pre-ordered the
game on handmade hero org using the
little nifty pre-order button you can
download the source code and be advised
there are now two source code zip files
one for the first hundred days and one
for the that we're in currently make
sure you download the latest one and
unzip day 100 source code because that's
what we're using to start with here on
day 100 so that's what you want to get
on in terms of synchronizing with what
I'm about to do with what I am about to
do now we left off yesterday we had
basically finished everything but we
hadn't debugged it so we're running and
we're doing all the things roughly that
we need to do but we have some things
that are either definitely or probably
bugs and so like it kind of said at the
end of last episode it's like all right
it's a little late now to start the
debugging process so tomorrow we'll just
spend the time to step through and debug
it and if you remember we had a couple
different things that were bugs first of
all we weren't transforming our normals
right and so if things rotate it's not
correct so we have to take a look at
that we were fairly certain when we were
using the sphere normal map that it
isn't seem to be bending the correct way
that we think it should so we think
we've probably got a little bit of a bug
there so we're getting close to having
normal maps working properly we just
don't have sort of the fine details
nailed down so what I'd like to do first
is let's just go ahead and start
thinking about how we're gonna fix this
transform problem since we're already
set up to do it we can see that we're
rotating and yet we're always still
pointing essentially up and down as we
rotate our bitmap which is not at all
what we actually wanted it to do so if
we come in to here to our Emacs and
I don't have an Emacs open do I know it
seems like I've got a lot of things open
why this week things
what have some things open all right I
come over here to Emacs and there we go
and I open up our renderer so when we
actually grab that normal out right
we've we've done the work of grabbing
that normal layout and what we want to
do here is we want to be able to
transform our normal but you know we
want to be able to rotate it we've got
it to do in here rotate normals based on
X Y axis we want to be able to spin it
so that the normals are facing the
correct way that they would be facing if
the bitmap is being spun now if the
bitmap isn't spinning it's no big deal
but you know and because then the
normals are all facing the correct
direction and so probably will want to
have a fast path in here eventually
because there's a lot of things that we
simply wouldn't need to do in all cases
because a lot of times we just have
bitmaps that are blip that that don't
rotate right they're just in one
stationary forum without any rotation so
it's kind of a waste of time to do some
of these things but in order to support
them all we at least have to first make
a path that does everything and then we
can sort of work on boiling that down
into the cases that we actually need and
can optimize so if we want to rotate the
normals right where is the pen that is a
problem I don't actually know where the
pen is for our blackboard there it is
it got slid up when we were when I was
fussing with having to change the
keyboard in the beginning of the stream
so if we go over to the blackboard for a
second and just think about what this
means it's it's pretty straight forward
if we but we kind of just have to make
sure that we we you know work out the
math right right it's a pretty
straightforward thing that we're trying
to do basically all we're seeing is that
we've got a map right and in it it's
essentially got some vectors that are
embedded in it right it's got
information in there where there's
vectors and when we read those vectors
out of the map we're treating them as if
they're just as if the map was just just
right-side up like
right and so we have you know an X and a
y-axis or something like that you know
here's our y-axis here it's our x-axis
we have this X and y-axis and even if
those those axes end up being rotated
that's like so right
we are still grabbing when we grab this
out
right the texels in here still have the
same direction so when we grab out this
Texel it's still going to be pointing
like that even though we've rotated like
45 degrees and it should have been
pointing like that right and so what we
need to do is we need to use these axes
to rotate our normals as well now if we
if we're doing non-uniform scaling right
meaning the the the X and the y are
gonna get scaled non-uniformly
which we're currently allowing this gets
a little bit hairy and the reason it
gets a little bit hairy is because you
have to sort of consider what actually
happens with normals in that case right
like you know if you imagine that this
is a is a vector that goes between two
things if I was to scale up the Y right
you kind of have to imagine that the
normal there is gonna stretch kind of
like this right you know like it's it's
gonna end up being well I guess if I use
to draw it exactly correctly it'd be
something like this if I was to scale up
the y axis right my normal is gonna
scale up in that in that fashion just as
if it were kind of a point that would be
it would that was being scaled up right
and the question is is that actually
what we would want to happen if we took
the surface that was being represented
here and did a similar scale right and
so what I want to sort of draw for you
first is just to sort of you know if I
can get you thinking about this let's
say so pretend we have let's let's
pretend we have something that's maybe
like a shape that looks kind of like
this
maybe it's the edge of like a gem or
something like that right and so you
know the normal is pointing let's say at
kind of a 45-degree angle here right the
normals pointing off like that okay and
what I want to show you here is that if
I were to take the y-axis right if I
were to take the y-axis and scale the
y-axis up right so if I were to increase
that then the shape that the normals are
coming from that the normals supposed to
be representing is going to elongate
right so I'm basically going to get
something that looks like this right I'm
gonna get well it's gonna shear
essentially so it's gonna be like draw a
little bit better version here right so
you know imagine this is getting scaled
up a bit
and you know so it's gonna elongate this
piece here as the whole thing scales up
right well if I was to scale the normals
by that same amount right you can
actually see that what'll happen is the
normal will also scale in that same way
if I was to use the same axes right but
if you look at what the surface did
really the surface is implying a normal
that would do the opposite thing as that
right
meaning the normal to this surface will
actually point this way more it'll
actually point more down this way as
this surface you long gates so really if
we are to support non-uniform scaling if
we actually want to do the normals
correct it's not simply the case that we
can just scale our normals by the same
thing as we scale our our regular images
by right and that's because you know
this is one of those places where if you
happen to have a lot of linear algebra
knowledge it it's helpful because this
would be obvious to you but if you don't
it's not and so I'll try to kind of give
a little bit of the background here
again not a mathematician so I can't
give you kind of the full deal but I can
sort of give you a a window into what's
going on here right so the deal is that
actually vectors are not all the same
okay and there's a lot of reasons why
vectors might not be the same obviously
you know you could think of things like
okay well if I have an RGB color value
or or let me give you a more specific
example if I have an RGB a color value
right and this is premultiplied alpha
you've already seen that it operates
differently than if I had an RGB a thing
and it was non pre multiplied right we
know that this one will allow us to do
linear operations on and it works
whereas this one it doesn't right and so
we've kind of already seen that vectors
are a way of bundling numbers together
at their most fundamental level they we
treat them as sort of a way of working
on numbers together but that's a very
mechanical notion of vector which is not
the same as the theoretical notion of a
vector that might exist depending on
what kind of operations you're doing and
we kind of can see that difference here
like premultiplied alpha is a proper
linear conceptually linear vector that
does the things they might want to do
and non P bolts Y Delta is not that way
it's a different thing it's sort of a
different object in a sense mathematical
object not programming object and so you
really do have to understand that
vectors behave differently and in this
case that's sort of what we have the
points that make up this shape are one
kind of vector or one kind of point you
might say but one kind of vector that
goes from the origin to that point right
that's one kind of vector and behaves
one way when the coordinate system
changes but these normals are a
different type of vector and there's
actually a terms for this I believe it's
their covariant and I want to say
contravariant is that right I don't
really remember the exact analogy so I'm
not going to write it on the blackboard
I don't want to be able to be wrong but
basically there's different types of
vectors when you talk about having a
transform that you're passing them
through and so if I have some transform
like we have this elongation we'll call
that F right when I put one of our
points through this F and we get out a
new point
if I want our normals to come out so
that they obey the same properties that
the normals want want to obey it's not
the same transform right it's not X
anymore it's actually a different
transform that you would have to push
the normals through now again if I
remember correctly what happens and you
know what we should do we should ask
pseudonym 73 for these terms he will he
will know these terms for sure they're
very standard linear algebra math terms
and it's just been so long I used to
know them even that's that's how common
linear algebra they were is I used to
know them but I've long since forgotten
but basically normals and and the points
in the plane are treated differently and
you actually see this in linear algebra
you see it actually written differently
even where as you will often see vectors
that are these like sort of point like
things they are often written as column
vectors so you might have px py PZ right
but normals are not normals are actually
written this way they're written as row
vectors right they're actually not even
the same shape in the math they are
transposed as as compared to to these
guys and the rule for how covariant
train have orient or well I guess we'd I
don't want to use the term how normals
are transformed is that if you have a
transform that operates on your points
there's actually something called the
inverse transpose that operates on your
normals and in order to sort of get into
how this actually works we'll probably
have to open up matrices a little and I
don't know if this is a good idea for
today it seems like we may be going down
a little bit of a math hole but
sometimes you have to go out in the
manhole so maybe we'll introduce this
concept and we'll think about it a
little bit okay so what was I doing
before right in terms of constructing
these these P vectors right well we had
stuff that was in 2d right so I had a px
and a py
right these were points in space and
what I wanted to do was I wanted to
start treating these points as if they
were in some coordinate system right and
so what we did is we constructed a thing
where we would say okay the point that
we actually want in on the screen right
or I guess we could call this the screen
space point or something right what we
ended up doing is we took the two
components of this thing that we were
describing and we would multiply them by
like an x-axis vector and a y-axis
vector and remember this was our
coordinate system test thing that we
made where these are you know they vary
right these two things are vectors 2d
vectors that vary and they were what
allowed us to do like rotation stuff we
would rotate these vectors and then all
of the point values would
correspondingly move with them right
remember we had that little grid that
was moving around and everything and we
could scale it we could rotate it and
that was the basis that formed the like
basis both literally and figuratively of
what we were doing with getting rotation
and scaling to work for our texture
mapping ok well this we can actually
write this in matrix form and we haven't
really done much with matrices yet but
now might be a reasonable time to do
that and so if we think about writing
this in matrix form we have to just kind
of go back and review how matrix
multiplication works so that we're all
on the same page there cuz like we
haven't done it very much and I don't
want to spring that on you without
giving you a little bit of a background
on it so let's say I have a matrix that
is you know a 2 by 2 matrix and matrices
and vectors are basically cut from the
same cloth
right they are arrays if you're a
programmer you can think of them as a
raise of numbers that go together right
and so if I have a vector here and I
have a matrix well you remember how we
sort of we did one extremely similar
example to this when we did the dot
product right when we did the dot
product we had something where we did
like an 1 X Y and 1 you know we did we
did 1 vector times another vector and we
did the dot product right and we said
that that was whatever this vector is I
guess I don't know call that v-0 and
we'll call this v1 right we said that
that was v-0 transpose V 1 right
in fact I just do this here v-0
transpose V one right and we wrote it
that way for our dot product and
remember we wrote it that way because we
were turning this vector on its side and
that's what the transpose operator does
right it turns things on their side and
we're gonna see that a little bit more
more explicitly what that means for
bigger shapes than than just vectors in
a second here but that's how we wrote it
and then when we did our multiplication
remember all we had to do was just go
okay we just add the terms and we line
up multiplication right so we start with
the first one in each we multiply to get
a X and then we add we start with the
next one down we multiply and then we
add and we would just keep going no
matter how long the vectors are and
that's what produces that dot product
well a matrix multiply is no different
right or I should say a matrix times a
vector multiply is no different but
really none of these are different
matrix times matrix would be no
different either all you do is you start
with the column and the row the first
common row and you do that dot product
you take the first term right and you
multiply them together
you take the next term you multiply them
together an ad right and you would keep
going if you had more when you're done
with that you go on to the next one
right next row column so it's CX plus dy
right so really what we have here is two
dot products right we have two dot
products we have this dotted with this
and we have this dotted with that okay
now you may ask well I don't understand
why you're telling us that because this
is not dot products what what are you
doing like what how are these related I
don't understand right and that's true
it's a little opaque what's happening
here and that's because this is just one
way of breaking up the terms you can see
those dot products there right and this
is the conceptualization if you were
thinking about it in terms of dot
products or inner products right these
are the same thing same term right so
this is the inner product view but
there's another way to look at this
right because if you take a look at
what's happening here
right you can actually see that there's
another way we could break up what's
going on in this particular
equation right because if you sliced it
this way instead right you could imagine
this as being the sum of two different
vectors right this is also just reading
it off the sum of ax C X right plus B Y
dy do you see how I did that I just
grabbed these and I grabbed these and I
broke them out into two vectors write
this if we added them together would
also produce the same thing right so
this this product that we did British by
using the matrix multiplication rules we
can also see it would work the same way
here and what we also see is each of
these vectors has a common term in them
so if we wanted to factor it further we
could say this was X AC right plus y BD
right by just pulling that out because
remember scalars multiply into a vector
they just multiply straight on in there
right so this is actually another way of
looking at this matrix multiplication
which means that this if you imagine
this was an x axis here and this was a y
axis here right it essentially means
that the columns of this matrix are the
axes right of our transform format that
we have been using so we could just
trivially if we wanted to start thinking
in terms of matrices just purely by
packing our X and y axis into a matrix
all we would do is create the matrix
that has our x axis as X at the top our
x axis is y at the bottom our y axis is
X in the the next column over and our y
axis is y underneath this is the
fundamental transform for rotation and
scaling for our 2d that's that's what it
is right that's what that allows us to
do and so here's our x axis here's our y
axis here's our matrix okay and so
really this whole time we have been
doing matrix math by writing this
manually but we didn't have to we could
have been doing it in matrix form if we
wanted to now you may ask why would we
do it in matrix form and the reason is
because if you start thinking about the
in terms of matrix form where I just say
okay I've got a matrix and here it is
you can actually start writing matrix
math which is much like what we did with
vectors we could have done all of the
work that we did with vectors in scalar
but we chose not to because once we
elevate up to vectors it's much easier
for us to build up sort of a grammar of
what we are saying we want to do that
just operates on the vectors and that
allows us a break free from having to
micromanage all of these scalar
quantities and the same thing is true of
matrices right that's exactly the same
thing that happens with matrices we can
build up the transforms for example
there is operations which multiply
matrices together so if we were to have
one set of Trant of rotation and scaling
that we wanted to represent and we did
it this way if we then made another one
right so we've got another one here
that's got some I'll just put dot dot
dot there that's got some other set of
axes if we wanted to know what a Zane it
system would look like transformed by B
we can actually just make another matrix
which is these two multiplied together
and then this one will represent the
combined transform without having to
store any more numbers it still only
stores a two by two but it encapsulates
everything that was happening with these
two matrices furthermore matrices in
addition to having multiplication they
also have inverse if I wanted to say the
opposite of the transform that happens
with a I can do a inverse and and they
also have you know other things like
addition and so on but we probably won't
really be able to do much with those
those are usually for more for numerical
solving and stuff like that inversion is
something that's pretty tricky we'll
talk about that in a second but if you
take a look at matrix multiplication
that is actually trivial I've already
taught you how to do it all you do is
literally do the exact same thing I just
sort of harped on up here this process
if you do that is exactly the same with
matrices if I was to say have you know a
b c d and then i wanted another matrix
here which is just going to be you know
you V w-why or something I don't even
know why I picked those you do exactly
the same thing and you know what I might
do I might spread this out a little bit
just to make it a little easier for us
to see it so let's call that UV W X
let's say all right there we go
so if we were to do this again you are
trying to form four different products
because you know and I guess I haven't
mentioned this yet but whenever you do
matrix multiplication and you line them
up like this you get as many rows as you
have on the on the the first term side
and as many columns as you have on the
second term side because you just line
them up like this and you could actually
see right where they go right when you
do that multiplication you can really
just do it mechanically when you want to
solve for one of the terms you know
you're gonna have a two by two when you
want to know what that that term is you
just read it off you take the the terms
right au plus BW right that's my first
term just that straight dot product
exactly how I would do it you want to do
the next one
same exact thing V a and V X and B right
go down to the next row same thing UW
and CD no problem see you + WD you want
to do final one here no problem CV plus
DX right and that's how you do much mate
republication there's literally nothing
to it it's just a series of these dot
products which you could do totally by
rote nothing fancy so if you just write
it in this tabular form it's pretty easy
to see exactly how it works and that is
all you need to start compositing
transforms now we don't have a lot of
need to composite transforms which is
why I haven't done me of this yet
because we really just don't have a lot
to do with that but now when we're tired
of talking about these these covariant
the different types of vectors and stuff
um how they transform it becomes handy
to start talking about it in a more
linear algebra sense and the reason for
that is just because a lot of these
things yeah a lot of these things become
clearer if you can start talking about
something as the inverse and we all know
what that actually means conceptually
rather than having to sort of go through
and
arrived it so if we actually want to
talk about the two operations that I
mentioned so we have two operations a
transpose ranked and we have a inverse
so we have this is the inverse and this
is the transpose now you've already seen
what the transpose does it lays things
on the side right we we did that here
right so here's what the transpose does
the transpose lacings outside well what
does that mean for a matrix well
actually what it's really doing is it's
actually sort of doing a mirror around
the diagonal so the transpose is an
operation is a thing where if you have
this right and you want to transpose it
what you actually end up with is you
draw that diagonal you imagine that
diagonal going straight down the matrix
0 0 1 1 2 2 and so on for the
coordinates in the matrix right you
leave that untouched because everything
flips around it but all other things
they exchange around the diagonal they
mirror so the B would come down here and
the C would go there right they would
flip that's the transpose and that's
true no matter how big this matrix got
if I had more values here right so if I
had stuff like this basically these two
would have exchanged these two would
have exchanged just like these 2 did and
you can keep going it doesn't matter how
big it is however big the matrix is you
still are doing that exact same thing
everything on the side of that diagonal
it flips right so every single thing
flips right that's the transpose
operator very very simple to understand
we'll get to why it's important in a
second but it's extremely easy to
produce because in some sense you don't
even really need to do anything it's
it's literally just a reordering of the
things in the matrix and often times you
actually do do the reordering because
you're trying to make it flow through
properly but you could almost imagine
Swizzle the indices on a matrix would be
you know how one way to do a transpose
on you could almost just have a flag
that Swizzle be interested in the C's
that would do it if for some reason it
was expensive because they were big
matrices or something right so that's
how transpose works now inverse on the
other hand is more complicated if you
have the inverse of a matrix the inverse
of a matrix is defined as whatever the
matrix it's x you know
in fact I guess I could draw this out a
little bit bigger so if I have a matrix
here like so the inverse is defined as
the matrix where if I was to multiply it
by the original matrix right I would get
ones in the diagonal and zeros elsewhere
okay
and this is a special matrix which is
actually usually called the identity
matrix right the identity matrix is the
one that does absolutely nothing to the
things that come into it right and you
can see why that would be if you imagine
multiplying a vector by one of these
guys right you can see what happens when
we actually do the math that I was
saying incomes the vector it's going to
multiply XY times 1 0 well that's just
going to pick out the x coordinate right
and the Y is going to get multiplied to
0 so there's no additional term same
thing if we do the math here right it's
going to know if the X is going to drop
out Camilla flobiz 0 and the y is going
to be right there right so we end up
with just getting the same thing in as
out and the same thing would be true if
we stacked a matrix up here we get the
same thing so an identity matrix is just
something that does literally nothing
it's completely inert it has no effect
on anything that multiplies by it now
technically this is the multiplicative
identity right and furthermore it's the
multiplicative identity on the right
right because technically we're
multiplying it we're multiplying it on
the right side of this term if this was
a and this was a inverse we're talking
about the one that comes on the right
now that's not something you really have
to think about in anything that we're
going to do but technically there's left
and right inverses and matrices when you
start getting into matrices that are not
in the same kinds as we're doing so I'm
not even to touch that but suffice to
say technically this is like I don't
know if this is the right term for it
but these are the properties it's the
multiplicative identity it's the one on
the right but furthermore the reason
that I said that multiplicative identity
is because it's a multiply it's saying
it's the identity in terms of
multiplication you could imagine the
additive right identity
the additive identity would not be that
if I was gonna add make sure together
adding matrices is exactly the same as
you do with vectors you just add each
component right if I was to add I would
end up with a plus one BCD plus one
which is not the same matrix right so
the additive identity is just all zeros
is a matrix with all zeros right and
that's the same on the right or the left
but that's a that's a separate issue
right so again additive identity
none of this stuff we care about at all
I'm just pointing it out so that if you
want to go read linear algebra you're
not totally left in the dark and we'll
get back to the stuff that we actually
care about so the inverse is the matrix
that would go here such that we could
produce the identity right and so if you
think about it we know what this this
matrix multiplied out to be right we
produced it here right here's what it is
and so we can think about how we would
get an identity matrix out of this you
know out of how would we make this these
UV W and X what would we make those
values if we wanted this to come out to
be equals 1 equals 0 equals 1 equals oh
sorry equals 0 equals 1 well the answer
obviously is you've got a system of four
equations and four unknowns you could
just solve them right we don't know you
V or W or X we do know ABC and D and we
know four equations using uvw X so all
we would have to do to produce @nd is
solve the four equations and that would
produce what we want right now that's a
pain in the butt I'm sure everyone
thinks it's a pain in the butt because
honestly as soon as I see something like
solve four simultaneous equations I'm
like hell's no right because I don't
even want to I don't even want to go
down that route right I don't want to
solve two simultaneous equations let
alone four it's just an invitation for
me to make careless errors in the math
right but fortunately I feel like that
is where Gao steps in right and Gauss
who is also known as like you know
arguably greatest mathematician of all
time I don't know if pseudonym 73 wants
to step in here and and comment on that
but you know just in terms of this of
sheer quantity of stuff that the dude
figured out by himself I feel like he's
probably that guy there might be one or
two other people who could be
competitors but like Gauss is pretty
insane and like I said I think an
earlier stream he even invented stuff
that other people had their names on
like the Fourier transform I think was
actually him he just didn't publish it
or something but he actually got it
first right so it would be called the
Gauss transform if he had bothered to
like put it out there right so he's
crazy but point being he didn't want to
do this either because he was just like
why am I going through all these steps
there's got to be a better way at least
I'm putting words his mouth you probably
didn't say anything like that honestly
but point being we have a thing called
Gaussian elimination which actually is a
pretty easy way to deal with situations
like this where you want to solve
equations and and invert matrices and
that sort of stuff this is actually a
pretty easy way to produce those
inverses when you have small matrices
and you're not super worried about a lot
of numerical Finnick enos now
Gaussian elimination is not something
that you actually use to invert or solve
large matrix systems in the real world
where the matrices are huge I mean a lot
of times scientific computing you're
talking about maybe sheaves with
hundreds or thousands or tens of
thousands or millions even if you're
really unlucky of elements and there's
just no that's not on the table Gaussian
elimination I believe is an O n cubed
algorithm so I'm pretty sure you're not
gonna run that on anything large so they
use other things and furthermore it's
numerically unstable in a lot of
situations so there's other things that
are better for when you're dealing with
floating point numbers and that sort of
stuff so this is not a power tool that
you would be using if you really cared
about matrix math but we don't actually
we're talking about very simple things
very simplistic two-by-two matrices that
are well-formed they don't require any
special handling and so if we want to
think through how we can solve one we
can actually use Gaussian eliminate
fairly easier so what is gas elimination
well it turns out that matrices well
surprise surprise matrices actually
weren't invented for computer graphics I
know it's talking but they actually
weren't they were they were actually
invented to solve systems of equations
that's what they actually were so
typically what you do you went you know
the reason that people created matrix
math in the first place is they had a
lot of stuff that looked like this they
were like well I've got you know some
stuff that looks like that e^x + FY plus
GZ dot dot and they would just have
these systems of equations where they
just had tons of tons of equations and
tons of unknowns and they're like you
know what this is all the process of
solving these is all very mechanical and
we're doing the same thing every time we
should come up with a more
straightforward tabular way of solving
these that's more regular and when I say
they I guess I should say Gauss because
I guess he's the one who invented it and
what they realized was well if you've
got equations right and you've got you
know these sort of common you've got
them all in a bunch of unknowns that
you're trying to solve for and whatever
you can actually put them into a matrix
just put the coefficients into a matrix
write a b c e f g h i j don't know why
we skipped d there but we did you can
actually just put those into a matrix
and consider the matrix to be the
coefficients of the equations that
you're looking at and there's some other
steps that you would go through here
normally you do a thing where you've got
you know you've got this you would put x
y&amp;z into a vector of unknowns and you
would say ok we've got some product here
and then we've got equals whatever was
on the other side of this equation would
be out here and something called a BF
vector and you'd end up with something
called ax equals b which is the standard
matrix problem we don't care about that
at all right now I'm skipping it point
being
what happens here is if you think about
the way that you actually would solve
equations in multiple unknowns so let's
say that we just had a b c e f g h i j
here and we were working with those
right so what we wanted to do is we
wanted to start solving for these well
what you do is you first try to knock
out terms right you you know how you do
this when you solve right you start
eliminating terms so you get down to one
term which is like you know this last
term equals something you then divide by
the coefficient and you get Z equals
something you can then plug Z back into
other things and you can back solve for
each thing going you know going upwards
and so on so what they did is they sort
of regularized that process what they
realized is that well since any
equations right any equations that we
have we know that if we take and this I
guess for people who are not aware with
math I guess I'm blowing through so much
math this is turning into just a giant
math episode sometimes that happens on
handmade hero sometimes it happens you
sometimes you end up going down the math
hole and you're in the math hole so I'm
sorry that's where it's at we're just on
the main the math well today nothing
else is gonna happen
we're just entirely in the math hole
alright so in the math hole so if you
what was I about to say applying these
things into into into the matrix I
totally lost my train of thought by
thinking about the math hole I don't
even yeah it's a strange term I like it
hmm that's a bit word all right I don't
know what I was going to say so I'm just
gonna skip it and go back to talking
about what I was talking about and
presumably I'll just end up saying it
again when I come to that point again
alright so anyway what they realized is
all right if we if we are to build one
of these things right if we're to build
sort of the the the matrix out of just
the coefficients of the unknown of the
that are on the unknowns that we wanted
to solve for what we could do is we can
oh that's what I was about to say I knew
I would get to it because I have to
describe it I'm like I wouldn't
scribing if it wasn't a prerequisite for
what we're about to do so if you have
two equations right if you have an
equation you know here's the left-hand
side of an equation and here is the
right-hand side right and these are
whatever you want all I know is just an
equation well if I have one equation and
I have a second equation right what I
know is I know that these two terms are
equal and that these two terms are equal
so if I wanted to it's totally legal for
me to just add these two things together
right I mean I can just add anything I
want to both sides of an equation as
long as I add the same thing to both
sides so since I know these are the same
thing they're equal I can just add right
lhs2 and I can add RHS too because I
know that LHS - and RHS - are the same
value they're equal right so what this
means is you can add any two equations
right for free right yes you can totally
fine you didn't violate anything by
doing that you can do that name all day
long
furthermore you know you can multiply
these by anything you want right if I
was to say add 2 LHS and to RHS to both
sides
totally legal - right because as long as
I multiply them by the same value
they're still the same value on either
side right I'm still adding the same
amount to both sides so since I can do
that what they were saying is well ok
now that we've tabulated these what we
can do is just think in terms of
operations on the rows and columns of
this matrix right and we can regularize
it right so what we can do is we can say
oh okay right if I take this top row
here right I take this ABC row and what
I want to do is start knocking out this
bottom row like the hij right what I can
do is say well if I wanted to eliminate
H all I would have to do is say well
what is H divided by a right what is
what is the amount of a I would have to
add to get me to get it to be equal to H
right I'm not sure I'm explaining this
in a particularly good way you know
let me do it let me do it with a number
so you can see because otherwise it
might be a little pretend we're not
talking about letters right now let's
just say we were talking about numbers
right so I've got five two three one
seven six and then like ten four nine
right and I want to knock out values
here I want to eliminate right
essentially eliminate terms right so I
want to luminate this term so what I can
do is I can say well how many of a would
I had to have to add to this right H
over a tells me how much I would have to
add of a to knock out two if i were
subtracting it to knock out the 10 right
and in this case you can see that that
would be 2 right so what I can do is I
can take this row multiply it by 2 and
subtract it from this room right so that
would give me 10 for 6 right and now I
can subtract it from here and that
totally eliminates this this term it
actually happens to also eliminate this
term I didn't actually mean to do that
but that's what happened right so then
instead of this row I would now have a 0
right I would have another 0 and then I
would have a 3 right so now I have
accidentally eliminated two terms I only
meant to eliminate one term my bad
but now I've eliminated two of two of
the of the three terms and now I have
just one term left and that would
correspond right to just having like
this this JZ term here right I don't
know jay-z's a rapper I believe but this
is not his term this is our term so
anyway if you are to do this process you
can then divide this this last remaining
term the 3 right and instead of actually
bothering to eliminate or I could
actually go ahead and actually eliminate
it by using one of my other things but
that's not that that's not productive
right because I don't know if you can
see how this would work here but if I
was actually to do that I would it would
be hard for me to eliminate this without
adding in quantities to these things
here right so six of one half dozen
either but point being once you've
eliminated things you can then divide
this by whatever the target is that you
were working with over here and you can
eventually produce what you want to end
up produce
is that identity matrix right now
there's more steps involved here so I
kind of have to go a little bit deeper I
just want to make sure you understand
this one process right here which is the
ability to add rows to other rows right
the ability to sort of say I'm taking
one of the rows of the matrix and adding
some it multiplied by something our
since a subtracting or multiplying by a
negative and then adding whichever way
you want to think of it I'm basically
using a row of the matrix to eliminate
members of another row of the matrix
right okay so that's kind of very handy
in what you can sort of see shaping up
here is this is much more computer
friendly right like thinking about how
to solve linear equations think about
how to solve this may be a little
confusing as to how do I have a computer
do this do I have to start making like a
symbolic algebra thing or something like
that but this is a bag of numbers and
that operation is something we could all
right very easily right so you can start
to see why might be possible to program
something like Gaussian elimination into
the computer alright so let's take it a
little bit one step further and talk
about a little bit more explicitly how
this would work right so what we want to
see right what we want to actually have
here as I was saying before us we have
ABCD right and we want to produce
something which when we multiply it
together right we're going to end up
with this right so we want like
something up here and we want to produce
this you know this this this matrix
right so we want to be able to multiply
by terms that are going to result in us
getting a one zero zero one right
so another way that we could think about
this I'm trying to think if there's a
good man it's been a long time since I
didn't done this I feel like there's a
good way to motivate you can actually do
a very simple trickier that makes it a
lot easier to conceptualize how to do
Gaussian elimination to produce the
inverse basically you do the Gaussian
elimination on this but I'm trying to
think of how I would explain why that
works it's been a long time since I well
I'll just keep I'll just explain out the
full thing and then we can
see if I can think of the the other way
the simple way to do it maybe I can go
look in a book tonight or something in
then and show it on tomorrow screen
so anyway play being so we got two
things her in fact I'm out and you know
what I'll do we won't even talk about
the inverse yet because maybe I can I
can go look up what that nice trick is
and that'll be an easier way to sort of
explain it more easily let me talk about
the regular solution form first right so
the thing we were talking about before
we'll just make it absolutely explicit
so we know what this produces right we
know that this produces this and right
we know that that's what that multiplies
out to and here we go let's say right
that we have some values that we want
here right so let's say because here's a
system right we know that this is how we
would do this multiplication of vector x
matrix right that's what we're doing
vector x matrix we know what it would
produce we would know how to do it
forward if we had to do it forward
meaning if I gave you this matrix if I
gave you a matrix a and I gave you a
vector we'll call the vector X even
though I already put an X in there that
was probably unwise and we'll call the
speed right if I wanted you to produce
the quantity ax I showed you how to do
that if you know what X is right you
know that you just multiply it like so
and here's the result right this is ax
right we've done that but the question
now and the place for all this
elimination and such as and so forth
comes in is what would happen if you
didn't know these so that's the case
that we're talking about here you have
the coefficients of your matrix but you
don't know what these values are and you
want to solve for them so I have some UV
over here I have some values I know B
right let's say I know the result so
instead of trying to find this result I
know the result I know what this
evaluates to what I don't know is what
are the values I would plug in to make
that happen
it's the classic solve so this would be
a solution of two equations in two
unknowns right and so that is where we
kind of get into this is that is where
we get in
to how we could do the Gaussian
elimination again remember these are
just equations right so if I want to I
can just write this and say okay this is
just my ABCD right my XY equals UV right
that's that's all we're doing here and
if I want I can actually do the Gaussian
elimination on the entire thing at once
right
because again these are just equations
it's you can you can think of these as
two different equations written in two
rows right so if I want to I can just go
ahead and straight up do the first step
of the Gaussian elimination right I can
say I've got my a I've got my see I want
to knock out that C so that I can solve
for y right and so if I want to do that
it's pretty easy and you know what I'm
gonna throw something in here because
maybe this is a good way to introduce
the trick but I'm not throw something in
I'm gonna throw a little phantom guy I'm
on the side here I'm gonna throw a
little phantom mmm oops
I wrote him wrong pretend he's not here
he's just hanging out he's just hanging
out over there right that's not part of
the equation we're gonna leave him there
so let's say I want to do that right how
do I do that well the first thing I need
to do is I need to knock out that C and
I we already said if I take C divided by
a that'll tell me how much I would need
to knock to knock it out how much I
would need to add this robot right so
that means I want to take this row and I
want to multiply it by negative C over a
right then I want to add it in and
that's gonna knock out that C term it's
gonna turn that C term to zero right so
let me just do that let me just rewrite
it that way with that added in there
right so I've got a B I've got my x
equals right I've got my you come on
over here got my one my zero but now
this next line I'm gonna add the top
times negative C a to what we've got
here right and so obviously in here well
if I have negative C over a times a plus
C right you can see that what happens
there is the a is canceled out and the
C's cancel out which gives me the zero
right which is exactly what I thought so
that's the zero then in the D term we
just have D right
and then minus CB over a right so that's
just adding those together we're not
going to actually bother figuring out
what this guy is right now because these
are the unknowns anyway so we don't
really we don't really care about those
guys the moment we're going to be the
same thing to our to our UV over here
we're gonna do that same ad right so we
would take our V and we would add two
I'm sorry
it's subtract from it see you over a and
now while we're at it I'm going to just
go ahead and do the same thing to this
make this identity matrix over here
right and so I'm gonna take my zero
right and I'm gonna add I'm sorry
negative CA times the top so that's just
a negative CA there right because it's a
one right sourcing of CA and the same
thing here I'm going to add negative CA
times this to this guy which would still
just be one right because there's
nothing there's nothing in there right
and so that produces now for me this is
called an upper triangular matrix it
produces for me a matrix which has
nothing no valid values below the
diagonal right I've got my zero in there
my zero is just kind of sitting there
right but it's not quite done yet
because while I actually do now know the
answer for one of my unknowns right
I could actually solve for one of my
unknowns now if I wanted to write I've
got this right I've got D minus C B over
a and I've got V minus C u over a right
so if you think about what this meant
right in the in terms of the actual
equations I actually do have one
straight across equivalence that I could
write right i could say D minus CB over
a y equals V minus C you oops see you
over a right and I could solve that if I
wanted to for y I could just and that's
actually looks like that sorry I could
solve that for y by just dividing this
over to the other side right I just have
the D minus CB over a right and so I
would just have my y equal to this term
so I now know
what why actually is right but although
I can read off the why from the tab from
this tabular result right I can't
actually read off what the X is because
the equation on the top still has ax
plus B y equals u right so it turns out
we can eliminate this one further
because now that we have a row that's 0
and one value here right we can just do
it the same thing we were doing before
to knock out the value above it because
now that it's got a 0 here we can use it
to eliminate things without touching the
other column right so if I now take B
and I divide B by this value and
subtract that I would finish eliminating
right I would end up with a 0 because
this is not going to get touched and if
I just divide if I take B over this
value and add it to be I end up with the
exact same cancellation that we have
here so I'd have a 0 right and I have D
minus C B over a down here don't care
about the unknowns for the moment and so
then if I come out here and say ok do
the same thing to it I have to do that
same multiplication so I have to take
again B over D minus C B over a that was
the the coefficient that we were using
right negative that I have to take that
and add it up here so I would end up
with and it's a little bit ridiculous
right but I would end up with u minus B
over D minus C B over a write times V
minus C u over a right that's what I
would end up with and again this this
term would be the same down here right
so that's the solve right but don't
forget I wanted to do the same thing up
to this sort of phantom matrix so if we
keep the phantom matrix going right we'd
have 1 we'd have that negative C over a
although actually now I think about it
that would actually get multiplied up
right that would actually come up so
what we actually have here is a little
more complicated right
we have one and now here's our I'm a
little further negative B I need I
almost need oh you know what I need
look at that that was awesome
all right so I have to take this and I
have to multiply it by that and add it
up to the top row right so I would have
this one I would have a plus because
this is two negatives so these are
actually gonna cancel out there I would
have C over a times B over D minus C B
over a right I would have negative C a
still in the bottom right I would have
still my one down there and then when I
up in the top here I would have just
this term times the one that I'd be I'd
be subtracting up so I'd end up with my
mega to be D minus C B over a right now
the chances that I did all that without
making a careless error somewhere are
like zero percent right so there's a
zero percent chance that that's correct
but there's like a 100 percent chance
that that was a reasonable approximation
of how goths the elimination works
mechanically meaning if you had not done
it incorrectly right and then what you
end up with is just a system of solved
equations right you know that this
equals this and you know that this I'm
sorry I should say this times this
equals this and you know that this times
this equals that right so finally if you
wanted to you could simplify the whole
thing by just dividing the top by a and
dividing the bottom by D minus C B over
a right because it's free for me to do
so and in fact probably what I should
have done again if I was smart if I was
gasps because I'm sure Gauss would have
done this but I'm not when you got down
to here you'd do the divide first in
fact that's how Gauss elimination
normally works I over complicated things
you could think of
you could you could ignore this step if
you wanted to and say oh okay right here
divide you know this guy divide
everything in this row by this and then
it would just be a 1 in there and that
that makes things a little simpler but
the reason I didn't do it that way
doing it this way is because we're
working with equations not numbers when
you're working with numbers it's free
for you to do that divide there because
the numbers just do it whereas it just
gets even more complicated if you
actually do the divide right so anyway
six of one half dozen of the other you
can totally see how that Gauss
elimination works out and what's kind of
cool about it is if you keep the Fantom
matrix on the other side now we didn't
quite we haven't finished because we
have to divide we have to divide by a
math that divided by d cv but if we were
to do that to these two rows this
phantom matrix actually becomes the
inverse which is kind of interesting and
again I don't actually remember the
motivation for why that's actually true
I'm just not sure what the reason is why
it's a neat trick you can do where you
can actually solve for inverses while
you do it
by putting it there but point being so
if you see how this sort of all works
out
that's the Gaussian elimination pattern
that allows us to actually sort of do
that solving on matrices when we want to
do it now what we would probably want to
do is actually do the divide out finish
it here and just bake it down so that we
can actually just not have to even worry
about actually solving this ever right
because we would we would just be
wanting to produce inverse matrices but
I kind of wanted to show you how it
works through for Gauss elimination
anyway don't ask me why I guess now that
I think about it I suppose we probably
don't really need to do solutions like
this and I mean here oh I don't even
know I'm trying to think if we're ever
actually going to have to do that
yeah I don't know point being I got a
little overexcited there but I wanted to
show you how that works and so that is
how that works and you know that's a way
that you can actually solve arbitrarily
large matrices as well it's just it
turns out to not be particularly good
once you get up to very kind of like
ill-conditioned very sizable matrices
you usually have to switch to something
that's not going to be exact because
Gauss elimination is like an exact non
iterative scheme and you typically end
up switching to something that is an
iterative like a convergence based
scheme that kind of like converges on
the right result rather than trying to
solve for a result using what I just did
where you're kind of looking at it like
you know solving for you're actually
basically doing the mechanics of solving
for an equation yourself right solving
the actual terms separately so anyway
unfortunately we're out of time because
I just spent too much time down the math
hole and we didn't quite get to what I
wanted to get to which is this guy the
inverse transpose basically I was trying
to lead up to what the inverse is we'll
sort of have to finish that up tomorrow
I guess and then we can talk about what
this is I told you what the transpose
where is we're sort of trying to see
what the inverse is the inverse and now
that we've sort of almost got it over
here as well the inverse like I said is
the thing where if you were to multiply
a matrix by its own inverse it's the
thing that gets you that identity back
right and it's also if you think about
it the thing that allows you to talk
about solving equations that involved
whatever that thing was right and so if
I had some kind of an unknowns thing
like I was talking about ax equals B as
a problem where normally the way we've
been doing it is we've been focusing on
we are given X we are given a and we're
producing B right and we've done this a
bunch of times now right this is this is
the thing that we've basically always
been doing it's the it's the PX times
the x axis py times the y axis thing
that's basically this so we've been
doing the forward thing we've been we've
been basically doing ax produces be
a bunch what we haven't been doing is
given a b and an a how do you produce
the x right and so what you could see
from this equation is if you had a
inverse if you knew what a inverse was
right which was what we were building up
to there you could multiply both sides
because remember you can multiply both
sides by the same thing you could
multiply both sides by that inverse and
you would solve the equation right
there's the equation in terms of x so
the inverse of something times b is what
gives you which x you would use to
produce be under that transform so you
can see this quite literally if you had
a situation where let's say in exactly
the sort of thing that we were talking
about before where we have an x-axis
know how many times I'm gonna do that an
x-axis and a y-axis right we've got them
and typically what we've been doing is
you've been saying okay here's our
actual our coordinate system and we've
got some point that's relative to this
axis system produced the point in this
outer axis system right and we've been
doing that by essentially if this is a
if this was transform a we've been
producing a P right we've been saying P
prime equals ap that's what we've been
doing right and we've been doing that
you know we've been writing it out like
PX times the x axis plus py times the y
axis but like I showed earlier in this
episode you can just write it that way
as well if you wanted to write well the
inverse thing solves the opposite
question if I was to say all right let's
say that P was actually not described in
this space at all it was described in
this space right so it's P prime now
it's this given this a tell me what is P
inside a I want to map it back into the
coordinate system that it was coming out
of before right I want to do that that
thing that is this salt right here right
that is instead of ax produces B that is
we have the a we have the B right this
is the P prime here and this is the P
instead of being given the P and
producing the P prime we want to go the
other direction and that's exactly what
that inverse allow
to do we would allow it would allow us
to multiply both sides and produce the
vector that we actually want right so
we're not quite there yet unfortunately
we ran out of time largely because my
Gaussian elimination is slow but I will
will try to pick it up tomorrow and I'll
pick up where we left off here about how
you produce the inverse and then we can
sort of see how we would how we would
produce this and why we might care about
a inverse transpose hopefully you can
see why you would already care about a
inverse up here but we have another
thing to talk about which is when a
inverse equals a transpose which is a
separate thing as well but that's not
the case here anyway all right that is
the end of the math hole for today I'm
sorry I sprung it on you I would have
prepared people had I know and I was
going down the math well I didn't but it
is time for Q and a it is time for Q and
a if anyone liked to ask questions as
long as that question is why are we not
why are we in the math hole I can
probably answer it this I like the fact
that this thing has been in here the
whole time right it's been doing that
multitasking
for inverting two-by-two matrices a
simple cofactor equation is quite
efficient a simple cofactor equation
okay you have a link there but I can't
really read the thing now mr. forts
vendor sets all the steps in elimination
can be represented as a matrix starting
with M and multiplied by all those
matrices you get the identity so those
matrices multiplied together are the
inverse multiplying them all about the
identity gives you the inverse is that
the trick you are alluding to yeah you
know what I think that was it's been so
long since I've done any linear algebra
I mean like crazy long it's easy for me
to forget but I think you might be right
about that I think that's the that is
exactly how you do it
so if you think about what I was doing
here right let's take this very first
step and thank you mister fourth
dimension for saying that because I
believe that is exactly what I would
have had to go look up and now I don't
have to look at it so the trick here
right is if you imagine having this this
guy right so I start with this this dude
right here and I wanted to do this
operation on it right I wanted to do
this operation where I did negative CA
times the top row and added it to the
bottom row well actually I could do that
just I could create a matrix that
actually did exactly that right and the
matrix that did that does exactly that
the matrix that does exactly that is
just the one that produces this result
right so if I take the that a B right
I'm gonna do it this way right if I take
that a B I need whatever the result is
here to still produce a and there's only
one way to do that right which would be
1 0 right that would still produce a
here which is what I need right and in
terms of what would produce B in this
slot I would need wait how does this
work again what am I missing here did I
do that right 1 0 because this has to be
the negative
see a version wait a minute
because this needs to be a this still
needs to be B this needs to produce zero
and this needs to produce D - C B over a
or rather negative C a times B so that
negative C a has to has to yeah I guess
we'd have to come in I'm not sure you
know what I'm gonna hold off on that
it's been too long so I've done this I'm
I'm just totally doing this wrong
because I'm trying to think of how you
actually do the matrix that produces
that elimination and it seems like you
would still have to end up in order to
produce a B on that row you still have
to produce you'd still have to produce a
0 a 1 0 at the top which doesn't seem
right to me
because once you do this guy right you
need to you need to reduce a different
vector here right yeah I'm not I'm not
sure I remember how to do that let's
think about it for a second let's not
give up quite so easily because yeah
you're suppose that do the permutations
on this matrix that eliminated
eventually but I don't remember what
exactly they are because it seems tricky
to produce this so if I just wanted to
add negative C a right time if I just
wanted to add negative C a to this row
right I would have to produce I guess
you could almost imagine as producing
negative C here right and so this
no I don't know how I would do that I do
not know how I would do that in a way
that still produces the a there yeah
that's too much for my math brain right
now
robot chocolate dyno to find the inverse
matrix couldn't we just rotate by the
negative angle and scale by one over the
amount that we scaled by originally yes
that is how you could construct the
inverse matrix and oftentimes you will
do that in graphics because it's easier
than inverting the matrix potentially
depending on the circumstances but I
wanted to talk about it a little more
generally because you don't always know
where your matrix came from right that's
only if you happen to know and so to be
more explicit about what happens there
right if you know that your matrix right
happens to be a scale times a rotation
and you know what that scale and that
rotation was right then instead of
computing a inverse right you can
instead just go oh well if I wanted to
compute a inverse I could instead just
take the inverse of SR right and this is
a little more than I probably wanted to
get into but basically that's the same
as this and if you look at what these
guys are right the inverse rotation and
the inverse scale matrices are exactly
what you just said if I have a scale
matrix it looks like this right it's got
an X scale and a Y scale and nothing
else in it it's a diagonal matrix that
looks like that right and hey lo and
behold what would produce right
what would produce the identity so if
this is my s what's my S inverse right
well no surprise there right it's 1 over
X because 1 over x times x equals 1
right and 1 over Y with zeros on the
thing that would produce the identity
right so that's exactly what you were
just suggesting of doing is that right
there and the R inverse is whatever
would rotate you back to where you were
it's a little bit harder to show why
that works compared
with this one but if you think about it
hmm it's actually not it's actually not
too difficult we might be able to kind
of show show how that works here so
let's say we have that rotation and like
I said that was that's just those
rotation matrices like I said before are
just putting in those the x axis and the
y axis right so if I have the x axis and
the y axis I have xx and XY and YX + YY
if I have that in my rotation matrix and
I want to know you know what times that
is going to equal 2
oops it's going to be equal to the
identity then I'm what I'm looking for
right is I'm looking for a vector here
that when dotted with these two things
when dotted with when dotted with X X X
Y X and went on up with X y YY produces
1 and 0 right and so what you can kind
of see here if you take a look at what's
happening right is you're trying to
produce a vector here which is
essentially the same as the vector here
right because we know that if we take if
I have two vectors we know that all of
these are unit length if it's just a
rotation right then we know that the the
x-axis length is 1 and the y axis length
is 1 right so what we know is that if we
were to dot the x axis with itself we
would get 1 and if we were dot the y
axis with itself we'd also get 1 right
we also know they're perpendicular so if
we were to dot the y axis with the x
axis we would get 0 right similarly it's
symmetric right so you know that the dot
product is is a is commutative that way
so we get that right so what we're
asking for here is okay what would the
thing that would that would would
multiply with these guys and produce a 1
right well we sort of know that if we
just were to take this guy we basically
know if we were to take this guy and and
dot him with himself we would get
one right and if we were to take this
guy and dot him with the other vector we
would get a zero right so it turns out
that when you actually produce the the
the inverse for our you literally get
exactly what its transpose was right so
you can actually see here like if I
finish it out XY y Y you can actually
see that all this is is it's the same
matrix but with these two guys flipped
and then when you do that math out you
know you get x squared you get x squared
plus y squared you get x x squared plus
y x squared which equals 1 and you get X
Y squared plus y y squared which also
equals one there right and the other two
were zero and again the only reason that
that's true is because all of these
things were also true so we know those
relationships between the scalars but
yeah we should really go into that in
more detail if you really wanted to be a
little more explicit about it because
it's hard to see why changing it's kind
of hard to see why that actually works
out the way that it does but try to
think if there's another way I could
sort of show you what was happening
there because this vector is not the x
axis right this is like half the x axis
half the y axis right if you think about
it it's the X components of both of them
so it's just a little bit it's it's a
it's a it's a little bit confusing as to
why that that works out the way that it
does right so yeah but we can go into
that in a little more detail maybe we
should do a section on like rotation
matrices and why they work that way but
that's how that are in inverse works and
that is just the opposite rotation right
so in 2d you can almost I mean one way
to think about this is to remember the
perp operator right where we did the
serve of perpendiculars one way to think
about it is that sort of what's going on
here right remember what the perp was so
if I have an a vector X Y and and that
represents some something
right so this is this is my vector right
here's my vector XY if I want to produce
the perp to that right what we did is we
did negative Y over an X right we
swapped the order that they were in
right and so you can kind of think of
the same sort of thing as as yeah this
is not very good explanation either
let's hold off on this I'll think about
this a little bit to think about how I
could more easily explain why this works
out for transposing right because I want
to be able to show that a little bit
better than I showed it I don't think I
did a very good job there and so if you
have you know and an x-axis and a y-axis
and the columns and then you go ahead
and and want to produce that that
identity matrix from that and you end up
with the x-axis like in the right in the
rows like that it's just kind of a
little confusing to show it so I guess
you know what so alright so this is a
little cheesy but here's one way I could
show it by doing it the opposite order
right so let's suppose I have X which is
our x-axis that we're using and I have Y
which is our y-axis right so let's
suppose I just drew it the other way
here's our rotation matrix right and we
have the x-axis as a column and we have
the y-axis as a column here this is a
much easier way to show it so I
apologize for not having an easy way to
show it the other way but I just it's a
little bit more confusing right so if I
want to construct the inverse here I've
got one yeah this is much easier if I if
I if I put the inverse on the left side
even though they're equivalent putting
them there makes it much easier to show
this right so what did I say
I said x transpose x equals 1 I said X
transpose y equals 0 I said Y transpose
y equals 1 right why is that true well
it's true because any unit vector dotted
with itself is 1 and any unit vector
dotted with a perpendicular is 0 we
covered that a you know in previous
episode so we know that those are true
right so we want the x axis
dotted with something to produce one
well obviously that the x-axis dotted
with its own self is one and if I did
the x-axis dotted with the y-axis I'd
get zero right that's just what I wrote
over here exactly right that's what I'd
get and similarly putting the y-axis in
here does the exact same thing x-axis
dotted with the Y is zero y-axis dotted
with the Y is one right so you put them
in this order you can see really clearly
when you do the dot products why they
come out to be the things they are doing
it the other order is harder to see
because you're you're in the column
picture of the matrix which is just
harder to you have to then write it
broken out and we could add it up the
column way so I think the way I'd have
to do that was remember up here where I
sort of broke things out in that other
way I was like here's the other way
here's here's the other way we wrote it
I think you'd have to actually do it
that way and then you could see why it
would work but that's it's much easier
to show the dot product Christian cuz
that was just as you saw from when I
just did that it's a really
straightforward thing you can just read
it directly out
let's see Holly Holly I remember doing
this by putting the identity besides the
original matrix in before and I need
step 2 performing each step to each yeah
that's what I did
and you that actually does produce if I
don't remember why I don't remember the
explanation as to why that actually
works right oh wait duh I know why yeah
it's just been a long time I'm sorry I'm
really rusty on my leg Roger bruh I
totally know why it's very simple if I
have a right as a matrix let's say I did
AI equals AG right so I already said
that I is the multiplicative identity
right this is the multiplicative
identity so I know that a time's the
identity matrix equals a right so I just
have ABCD there's my a matrix I have one
zero zero one and I have that equals
ABCD I don't know why I couldn't think
of this it was like yeah just been too
long one of the nice things about the
stream is I like have to remember all my
math which is good I mean it's good to
keep it active in the brain right so
this times this equals this we know
that's true we already said that that's
exactly what that is so a times the
identity equals a so then you just do
the elimination here right you do the
Gaussian elimination
until this equals the identity right
like I was doing above you knock out the
terms and you divide once you are done
with that you will end up with the
identity right some matrix here right
equals the identity on the other side
right because if you if you eliminated
the terms here and this is the same
thing you would eliminate the terms here
what is this
right what is that that matrix that you
would end up with sort of in the middle
right oh wait no that doesn't quite work
because you'll end up with the matrix
here but why would it still do the
inversion all right never mind I'm still
I'm still not sure about it because then
you don't quite end up with the right
thing right
thing because you'll end up with AI
something equals AI if you do it all to
both sides which in theory means
shouldn't this have to also be AI that's
a little confusing
this is confusing you know what I'm
gonna say math is hard let's go shopping
I'm gonna have to study up I'm basically
have to study up a why because now that
I think about it yeah so this is just
this is just hard because I feel like
you should be able to do the elimination
with an identity matrix and then the
identity matrix comes out to be the
inverse which would leave you with a a
inverse equals I right you should end up
being able to do some elimination that
way where you do where you where you end
up with swapping the two darn it I
thought I had it don't have it
if you had a matrix such as int 2 2 with
the example of ABCD as the variables in
place couldn't you just swap a and D and
make C and B negative you mean making
the inverse well you can verify whether
you can or not pretty easily right so
what you just said was I'll pop me down
swap a and D so there's swapped a and D
and make C and B negative so there you
go
so what happens if you multiply this out
well if I do the dot product I would get
ad minus CB so you can already see it's
not the identity right because this
should be equal to 1 and it's not right
me blow I understood none of today's
episode would you recommend that i
rewatch it or do you think all may
become clear tomorrow I don't know it's
fairly complicated stuff so I would say
watch tomorrow's episode and then
possibly rewatched today's I will try to
go find where the trick is for this just
so we can finish that up and then we'll
go implement something that actually
does the inverse
so naysayer 88 says here is the
explanation for computing the inverse if
you write a and then I next to each
other okay and then apply which is what
I was sort of doing or trying to do
there but okay if you write 89 next to
each other and apply a bunch of
operations you're computing t3 t2 t1 a
and t3 t2 t1 I because you ended up at
the identity t3 t2 t1 a equals I so t3
t2 t1 equals a inverse therefore T so
that's hmm so that's interesting I guess
I'm not I feel like there should be an
equation there but maybe there isn't
so what John that was John below saying
that what he was saying is well don't
worry about the fact that that this what
you're about to do here don't worry
about the fact that you can't do it as
an equation just write a and I next to
each other anyway and he said when you
apply a bunch of things to both of them
so if I have a and I have I when I apply
a bunch of things to both of them right
then whatever the thing is the steps are
he was calling them t1 t2 t3 whatever
the steps are that reduce a and this
actually makes some sense
whatever the steps are that reduce a to
the identity right because we if we do
all these steps and we make a the
identity right then obviously they must
have been equal to a inverse because
they produce the identity right so
whatever this is times this if we ended
up with the identity right then this
must have been a inverse so if I applied
the same steps to the identity I would
just get the inverse right because there
is no anything else there would just be
t1 t2 t3 so that's why that trick works
right that's why you can Gaussian
eliminate this neck
- this right that's why you can do the
Gosselin Easter steps as long as you the
same steps to this you end up with
basically the matrix you end up with the
identity matrix turning into the inverse
when this turns into the identity right
so when this becomes I when when a
becomes I I becomes a inverse and that's
a pretty good way to explain it right
whatever the steps are that you applied
to a they must have been the inverse if
they drove a to the identity and so you
know if you wanted to if you wanted to
apply those to an identity matrix you
would end up with just the inverse so
that's a pretty good that's a pretty
good way of thinking about it thank you
John
so I guess we're done actually with the
trick we can't actually go back here
this is crazy how much math look at this
look at that this was all where did we
start where did we start on today it's
crazy right
it was like here or something that's
awesome I love zooming out on the
blackboard that's great so yeah okay so
we didn't quite get there
but we almost got there and thanks to
John we also have an explanation of why
the thing I was showing there would have
worked or should work right which we did
not have before
all right so we'll have to do is we'll
have to postpone for day 102 we'll have
to do we'll just leave it right here
we'll have to do inverse transpose oops
inverse transpose a inverse transpose
because we still have to talk about that
now that we sort of know what this is
although I should all try to do a little
bit better job quickly explaining a
little bit more of that mm-hmm since we
got a little bit bogged down today
I'll do try to do a little bit more
concise job of talking about a inverse
we already know what the transpose is
and then we can talk about why normals
are transformed by a inverse transpose
not a and I sort of drew out why that
was on the previous one okay I will go
ahead and save the mischeif blackboard
close that down and this okay thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of hand made here it's been a
pleasure today going down the math hole
with you it's always good to have other
people in the math hole as always if you
would like to follow along at home you
can pre-order the game on hand me here
org it comes to the source code so if
you want to play around with a source
code that's a good way to do that you
can also subscribe to the patriarchy you
want support the video series we've got
one up there we also have forums that
you can ask questions and get ports to
Linux and Mac of the code base so that
you don't have to do that yourself you
want to follow along on other platforms
and similarly it's got an tight episode
guide up there if you want to catch up
with previous episodes we also have a
tweet bop a tweet the schedule so if you
want to catch up with the episodes as
they are aired you can always use the
Tweetbot to kind of figure out when
those are happening so how do I
recommend checking that off you're tryna
catch the series live that is about it
for today I will be back here again at 5
p.m. tomorrow if you would like to see
the conclusion of how to do our normal
transform so that our normal Maps will
work properly you can go ahead and come
back tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Standard
time same place or on Twitch and we will
do that hope see everyone tomorrow and
thanks for tuning in take me as everyone