hurting start recording hello everyone
and welcome to handmade Hero the show
where we code a complete game live on
stream on Twitch no engines no libraries
it is it is literally a complete
investigation of every piece of code
that makes a game tick right down to the
most my new detail and all the way up to
the highest level stuff that's our goal
here on the stream that is what we do
and right now we are in the middle of
doing something that's actually kind of
interesting and we're we're almost done
with it it's it's our prototype ground
texture basically what we're doing is we
instead of having like a tileable ground
where you just kind of walk around on
the ground always looks the same what we
decided to do was make it so that we
would have sort of an infinitely non
repeating ground that's different
everywhere you go and that we would have
the option sort of like we would have
like an architecture in there so that as
the game progresses when we're actually
developing the mainline game it'll be
easy for us to kind of put stuff into
this ground texture as necessary and
work with it to sort of change you know
what textures you know sort of what it
shows and that sort of stuff and we've
done a bunch of the work for that but
there's still a little bit left to do
and so I would like to get that finished
up this week and we've got today and
tomorrow to do that and so I'd like to
jump right in on that right now and you
can see when I run it you'll be able to
see kind of where we're at now before I
begin if you preorder the game on
handmade hero org you should have gotten
a link in your email that email link
allows you to download the source code
and so if you'd like to follow along
with me please unpack date 86 this
source code here on day 87 because
that's where we're at
that's what I'm working with and so if
you want to match up with what I'm doing
that's what you want to do all right so
let's take a look at at the state of
things here just so I can remind
everyone where we are oh and you know
what there's one thing that I want to do
before we get started I lied somebody
pointed out in the forum's that we have
a typo a lot of times like I said I make
typos on the stream because what I'm
talking when I'm coding it's hard to pay
attention and there's some typos that
sneak in there pretty regularly
maybe not won an episode but sometimes
won an episode or
sometimes more than one an episode so we
got a I appreciate people's vigilance
and catching those because again it's
really hard for me to do that while I'm
talking this one is bizarre and I'm
gonna even step into this here so you
can see why this worked at all because
this should have crashed right away when
we typed it in the first time but
somehow it didn't and I feel like it'd
be nice to just show why it didn't
because I feel like one of things that
again we tried to on the stream is show
how memory works and really get you for
comfortable with working with the memory
yourself and this is kind of a good
example just to just show like wow okay
so weird stuff can happen when you're
just talking about like memory using
memory directly right because it really
is just a big old flat space that you
write into and that you have complete
control over it's not like in
higher-level languages where you have to
always obey all these rules that it sets
out for you like you know it's pretty
much anything goes and so you can do
whatever you want and so what's kind of
interesting here is if you take a look
I'm gonna I'm gonna set a breakpoint
here and step into the code we we just
quickly threw in the code to initialize
the transient arena that we were using
and if you notice what we well what I
typed was incorrect this was supposed to
use the memory for the transient storage
but instead it just used the actual
storage size right and so if you think
about it this is literally this should
not have worked at all because this is
not memory this is just an integer
somewhere right and we're using that
integer as if it was a pointer to some
memory does that make sense and most of
the time the reason we don't really have
bugs like this hardly ever on the stream
is because most of the time we're we
have ways of pretty carefully checking
to make sure that we don't do that but
in the case where we first initialize a
memory arena obviously we're going from
nothing to something so we kind of have
to cast it up and so we can make a
mistake there but why did that work at
all and the reason if that worked at all
is kind of interesting right if you take
a look at it so if we take a look at our
transient storage size now it just so
happened that the transient storage size
we picked right
happened to be you know one gigabyte of
memory that's just the size that we
decided to pick for you know here in our
in our debug session right that's that's
what we were doing it's a gigabyte of
memory we didn't pick a frame pick the
reason we're not using nearly that much
memory but that's just what we picked
for a flat array to play with for now so
basically what's happening is the
transient state is getting initialized
to point to something at the one
gigabyte boundary right that's what's
happening now if we look at sort of this
at what we've got here it's a little bit
odd because really we shouldn't have
been able to access anything that was at
that one gigabyte boundary right because
if you take a look at where our stuff is
our permanent stories in our transient
storage the actual memory that we've
reserved is nowhere near that one
gigabyte boundary so something that has
been legally allocated is sitting there
right it's it's it's basically point of
some page that's actually valid and
we're just flat out using it we have no
we're over writing something right now
and we have no idea what now it could be
something that we allocated prior right
it could have been something that we
were allocating before and so if you
take a look at you know some of the
stuff back here I don't know if it's one
of these things you know one of these
things might have been there that wasn't
we also had there was there was another
virtual Alec for like bitmaps and stuff
so I don't actually know what was there
we have no idea what was actually there
and it's not really super possible for
us to find out because it could be some
you know just random stuff that we
allocate in a person I have no idea but
because there was nothing there it
actually lets us access that right
we're totally allowed to write into that
without crashing and we actually use the
state that was there we actually used
whatever was there and make some stuff
right which is crazy so that shouldn't
worked but it does when that memory
happens to be legal now it should be the
case that that memory will not always be
legal like this should crash on other
people's machines potentially or just a
different run on this machine and we
just got very lucky there so really that
should have crashed it was pretty odd
that it didn't
but unfortunately there's not that much
you can do at an it time when you're
first building your memory you've got to
be careful because you can pretty
trivially they make that mistake because
you're doing a cast they're most of the
rest of time we don't do casts so we get
some protection to make sure that we're
not doing something ridiculous like
casting it I meant like that but anyway
so what we really wanted here was to use
the transient storage pointer right then
say is that initialized and then when we
initialize the Arena we wanted to again
use transient storage not the size to
point to where we were going and I
believe that's the extent of kind of the
typo that had snuck in there we're just
using the size instead of the thing and
again that that won't actually change
the running at all it's just that should
have crashed it didn't crash because we
got I guess unlucky really because we
would have preferred it crashed right
away we would have been like oh yeah
whoops so anyway let's get back to what
we were doing so what I was saying
before is we we wanted to produce an
endlessly tiling ground texture and
there's two things we haven't done yet
to finish that up as you can see there
is a ground texture beneath us right now
and it is different everywhere but it is
seemed right so you can see the seams
between it so the first thing that we'd
like to be able to do is turn that
ground texture into something from
something that has a seam to something
that is seamless right so that it always
lines up kind of with its neighbors and
doesn't ever show like an artifact at
that boundary right that's actually
pretty easy to do I know it sounds a
little bit difficult maybe at first but
based on the way that we've architected
things I don't think that's going to
particularly difficult so really that
first but then we have another thing to
do which is gonna be a little more of a
think through although we could just
again do a pretty basic implementation
now and come back to it later when we're
doing more performance optimization
again you'll also notice that frame
stuttering there that's something to
keep in mind that's when we when we are
building new ground textures like I said
before another thing that we're not
going to do for a while this is totally
performance stuff again is making that
happen in the background overlapped but
we're not going to tackle that for a
while so anyway after I go relatively
far actually I've got a ways to go here
because we may be set that number of
cached ground tiles a bit high but right
now we never evict any ground tiles from
our cache so basically eventually you
get to the
and there are no more ground cast tiles
to fill and we run out of textures right
so what we need to do as our second
thing is we need to be able to evict old
tiles tiles that were back kind of you
know at the start that we didn't
actually need anymore when we got here
we need to be able to evict those out of
our texture cache that we're using right
now to cache that gross ground but first
we need to get rid of those and then we
need to generate new ones for these
areas so obviously we know how to
generate the new ones we just don't have
a thing that actually evict so that
eviction scheme is gonna be the other
thing that we do alright so let's talk
briefly on the blackboard it's really
like I said pretty simple actually the
first thing we're gonna do so let's talk
briefly on the blackboard about what
we're gonna do to get seamless tiles in
and then I'll go implement it and then
after that we'll we should have some
time to start work on the eviction
scheme I would hope but it again it
depends on how well things go I suppose
we could run into some hairiness that
takes longer then it then it would
otherwise so alright so here on day 87 I
believe that's where we're at right yeah
day 7 so here on day 87 mmm again for
those of you just joining us each day is
an hour so we're 87 hours into the
coding right now or are it's like our
third week of programming if you thought
of it that way basically if you think
about work weeks they're like 40 hours a
week of programming or something like
this somewhere somewhere there or if you
only work if you only get to program
about 30 hours a week which is actually
kind of difficult for me sometimes I
only get to program 20 hours a week
because I have to do a bunch of other
stuff management wise and and art wise
and things like this it could be more
but basically like if you were actually
a full-time programing all day so think
about this is we're in our third week of
programming here all right so here we go
here is a tile and the way that we're
constructing these tiles right now right
is we're splatting textures into them
that have soft edges and by splatting a
bunch of things in here we produce a
nice ground texture right and the
problem that we're having right now is
we do that completely irrespective of
the hard clip boundary that sort of gets
enforced like so right and so what we'd
like to do is we'd like these we'd like
these to be seamless so whatever was
getting splattered
over here we'd like it almost to be as
if we had had done that splatting you
know as well as the splatting up at the
top and the splatting here and so on so
that all of the splats in the nine sorry
in the eight neighbors actually
contributed to this flat and then it
would be seamless right if you think
about it because we know that seamless
inside so if you thought of this as just
one big splatting region we know that we
could grab out this part and it would be
correct
so really at least right now all we
really need to do to make these seamless
is actually do exactly what I just said
splat an entire 3x3 and only extract the
middle part right now that wouldn't help
us at all if we just did random slotting
across this but if we actually ensured
that each of these was doing the same
splatting that it actually does when
it's generated itself then we know that
all of our slats will line up and
furthermore we know that the composite
order will be the same if we always
enforce a rigid order when we walk
through these right so if we always do
you know upper-left you know this one
this one this one this one this one
right and so on although really since
our coordinate system is why up this way
you might think of it as doing this one
first then these right but doesn't
matter as long as we always do them in
the same order we'll always get the same
overlap pattern as well for any given
tile so that's really all we need to do
and of course the good news is since
this is our bitmap code already does
clipping we actually don't need to do
anything special to do this extraction
we don't need to actually produce this
3x3 we can just still set the clip clip
region here and do the splats you know
as if they were up here and ones that
don't land in the thing will just get
early rejected by our clipping and won't
hardly cost us anything either so that's
pretty nice too so even before we
optimize this at all we're getting a
little bit of a bonus there just in the
fact that the bitmap clipping which has
to happen anyway to avoid us overall
writing memory bounds will basically
take all that out of us for us so all I
really need to do to fix this I believe
unless you know sometimes I'm wrong on
the stream right you know when you're
programming it's
not a cases you're always right kind of
thing that's that's not how it works Oh
which that was how it works not how it
works
so yeah okay so what I want to do is I
want to you know modify this right here
to basically do you know a three by
threes worth while still using the same
area for filling the ground chunk okay
so if you think what through what's
going to happen here we're gonna use a
random seed with our chunk X chunk Y
chunk Z only instead of using them from
the actual chunk that's passed in we're
gonna introduce new synthetic variables
for X Y and see that we're gonna iterate
over now we're not doing any Z handling
here so actually a chunk Z for now at
least and probably for always because we
we aren't doing three-dimensional
texturing or anything like that for we
don't we don't need the the Z to be
seamless that doesn't even mean anything
in our world at the moment so at the
moment chunk Z will stay the same always
but the others right chunk X and trunk y
we will loop over now right we will loop
over those and the way that we want to
loop over those is we want to start with
that chunk P that we would have been
using and we want to go back one right
then we want to go from there to plus
one right so we're doing you know that
that sort of extra that three across
kind of thing and we're going to do that
both in the X and the y directions and
it's pretty arbitrary what order we
choose to do these in as long as we do
an enforced order I believe we should
get seamless chunks out of it but again
like I said we will have to wait and see
so then we come in here and we do the
draw loop exactly the same as we have
been doing it and now it's going to do
that splatting in all nine of the of the
sections instead of just the middle one
now what we do need to do though is we
need to make sure that our Center
accurately reflects the fact that we're
in sort of a different a different chunk
area and to do that I think you know
what I could do here I'm not sure this
might actually be the easier way to
write the loop is I could just go in
here and actually compute these two
on the fly and use an offset value here
instead so it'd be like chunk offset Y
if that makes sense and just have that
loop from negative one to one instead so
that I can do an additional computation
with it in here to compute what I want
the center point to be I'll show you
that in one second so I'm just gonna
move that in here and say that okay it's
gonna be whatever the chunk offset is
like that that's gonna happen in x and y
you can kind of see what's going on here
right nothing particularly special I'm
just reconstructing but changing the way
that the loop loop offset works so that
I can you know use it more directly so
there we go we've got our negative one
and we've got our one and it's inclusive
so it's gonna use negative one zero and
one when it does this right those are
the three that it's going to do and it's
gonna do those in both times we're gonna
do a total of nine all right so we
compute our chunk X in our chunk Y right
and we could even put chunk Z in here
just for completeness you can see them
all easily and when we have those I now
need to compute the center point like is
the bitmap the the actual center how
should I say this
so the actual center of the bitmap per
se was actually not being used I'm
trying to think of how to explain this
so previously I think I need the
whiteboard just to kind of give you the
idea so previously we were using the
bitmap Center and we were like picking
where we're gonna splat by moving out
from there and so since we're trying to
do each of these individually when we
say bitmap Center what we really mean is
a different is the center of whichever
one of these chunks were on and so
really I need to kind of change that
meaning right I need to change the
center meaning here to basically mean
the center of the chunk we're currently
on so this would be the chunk that we're
on right if if we were in the middle
chunk but we need to subtract one in in
you know width or in height or whatever
we need to like subtract or add
depending on what that offset is right
and so essentially what we're gonna do
is we're gonna say all right let's
suppose we started with the upper corner
right so this is the center right this
is the center that we were using before
let's say that we actually wanted to
subtract write the width and height from
that you know I'm saying so we were
start up there and then what we would
want to do is add in a width and height
that's proportional to whatever the
offset is right so I want to take the
offset X the offset Y like so hmm right
and for each one of those I want to move
with in that direction right so if I go
ahead and compile this you can kind of
see in fact I think we might be almost
done this is a little inefficient right
obviously what we're doing here is
saying we're gonna move half the width
and height forward and then we're gonna
move back by the width of heights again
so you can see I can just kind of
algebraically simplify this it's kind of
like 0.5 a minus a that's just negative
0.5 a right now pretty simple and off we
go so I'm not sure if I totally did
everything right there but I think the
center is all we would need to change
and then the random seed is just going
to be off that chunk so we know that we
will always use the same set of random
points each time we go so let's take a
look here when we do this we've got our
stamp a standpipe we do a width times
height
random unilateral for the offset off of
the bitmap Center that seems pretty
straightforward I think we may be done I
don't know let's let's do my step
through and check but let's take a look
at what we actually get when we produce
these now again they take a long time to
produce unfortunately well that isn't
seamless at all all right so we've still
got a little bit of nastiness in here so
let's find out what I'm what I did wrong
all right so let's think about this for
a minute we are still doing so okay so
we come through we do our blitz we pick
our random seed the random seed should
be constant because its base of Charlie
off of the chunks the absolute chunk
index which is what we want that center
point should be correct negative with
the heights up to the top yeah and then
it's going to be whatever the trunk
offset is oh no sorry that is incorrect
I lied
that was not right so since we're the
chunk offset ranges from negative one
zero plus one
I was overzealous there that I did the
computation as if the chunk offset was
zero one two so that was that was just
done so if we start from the center this
will properly move us back to the upper
left one and down to the lower right one
okay so let's see where we're at with
that and then start to pucking because
that was just yeah stupid computation
error on my part so let's see where
we're at at this point all right so yeah
that is that is not immediately obvious
to me what the bug is there it still
looks like we've got something
relatively significant like we should be
able to tell if this makes sense we
should be able to tell if we're getting
close by whether the things line up you
know in a in a relatively close way or
whether they're still pretty far off and
those looks still pretty far after me so
we have some major logic problem and
unfortunately we don't have a whole lot
in the way of debug services yet it's
still before we've gotten to the point
we write those so we're still kind of
flying a little bit on intuition but I
think we should be able to do it again
this shouldn't be too hard so let's just
take another look at it and see so we
know we're doing wait a minute wait a
minute this isn't being used people what
this was just old code oh for crying out
loud all right well we need that to work
obviously that's hilarious so if we were
doing an offset without that we need the
center to be in there people really I'm
gonna I don't know that I want to put an
owl of shame up for that I mean he's
peeking at us right now for not checking
but you know I don't think he's really
there entirely but yeah so okay that's
obviously pretty dumb and so if we're
gonna do that offset what I would need
to do is if we're just doing the offset
there I would need to make that offset
be just the upper corner because it
looks like we're using random you know
for the width and the height so yeah I
suppose that is an a love shame like
before you go modifying some code you
should probably look at it to see what
it does like I just assumed I knew what
it did because I wrote it but I mean you
know hey I program all day on a
completely different codebase and then I
come back to this thing it's not
surprising that I forget all right so we
are now seamless across X but we are not
seamless across Y so we're getting
closer right you can see how how that
how that is right now does that make
sense so we've still got a bug and our
bug is in the Y I assume that's because
we've got the Y flipped in some bad way
or there's something weird happening
with the Y that we are not doing
properly so let's take a look and the
other thing you know what I should
probably do is let's let's just take one
of these out of the equation here so
that we can take a look at at the Edit a
little simpler all right
so taking a look at this now we've got
why do we still have grass
why don't we still have grass chunks in
there if I if zeroed out tuft oh because
this is doing this is doing either of
those two I see so those were the Tufts
that we were putting in there all right
so nevermind done even though I wasn't
even looking at the Tufts all right so
if we take the test out of the equation
and this is actually building it so now
we know that we're just looking at in
here so we don't have to worry about
this guy yet so let's take a look what
are we doing differently with the Y so
we have the bitmap Center that's the
center of the thing that we're stamping
we have the offset and that's an offset
inside the the bitmap and that's getting
moved sort of by whatever the center is
of the one we're doing and then we're
subtracting away the bitmap Center which
is basically the thing that we're
stamping down and then we're doing that
draw right now the center is properly
computed as whatever the chunk offset
with that - it's subtracting that or
adding that that looks relatively sane
to me so I'm not exactly sure why would
we be why we would be getting a weird
result from the Y I'm trying to think if
maybe there's an overlapping problem
that
not thinking of something that has to do
with the fact that we're doing why as
sort of like a major what the fact that
we're why major instead of X major so
what I'm gonna do as a debugging step
isn't gonna flip the Y and the X to
change which order they're done in so I
can see whether it's just whichever
one's done major and so you can see that
it's not whichever one's done whichever
one is done major right you can see that
that's not the case and so that tells me
very definitively that it's not an order
problem it's not an overlap problem it's
a problem with how we're actually
handling the Y so what is wrong with our
Y handling what's going wrong here let's
see when we do our chunk Y that looks
correct to me when we do our width and
Heights here
height that looks correct as well
although I should think about this just
for a second so I wonder I wonder so
since these are stacked because we're
flipped in the ground chunk filling
relative to our coordinate system it's
probably just that our edges are lining
up in the wrong order meaning our top
edge and our bottom edge are inverted
because we're going in the wrong
direction if that makes sense I want to
see if that's actually true
let me check let me check and see if
that's the case because if that was the
case yeah that was the case so basically
it's because again of that Y flip that
we always have to account for
but now we've essentially got infinitely
tiling ground texture which is nice it's
not a particularly nice ground texture
because we're not actually doing
anything intelligent with how we're
actually compositing it but it's pretty
good to go in terms of where it's at now
what we could do probably to make this a
little more straightforward is if
instead of doing this random choice we
just made it always be grassy for
example or always be stone
so let's say I did this like so oops I
could go ahead and hmm you know what I
just thought of two I just thought of
something fun well alright anyway so if
if we go ahead and make it just one of
them it actually looks a lot better to
like you know if we if we just stick to
one thing it certainly looks better we
still got I feel like there's a little
bit of artifacting potentially like I
feel like right in there looks a little
odd to me it doesn't look like what I
might expect but that could actually
just be think so I don't know for
entirely bug-free yet but yeah it's
starting to look pretty good and you
could imagine once we got some more
splats in here than the ones that we
have at the moment we'd probably be good
and also especially if we went in and
actually had different patches so
there'd be regions that were grassy and
regions that were you know stone and
that sort of stuff which is what we'll
want to do eventually let's go ahead and
put the Tufts back in there let's let's
go ahead and just say all right let's
let's switch back to grass like so and
put the Tufts back in make sure the
Tufts don't have an overlap problem and
then we'll call this good for now
because this is a system that Wilkes
will sort of expand later on so yeah it
also looks to me like maybe we want a
little more like they look a little
clumpy to me as well which I assume is
probably due to our random number
generator not being around in our chairs
just a random number table at the moment
if that makes sense so I guess I I won't
say that that's too much cause for
concern but you can kind of see you can
see the holes in the random number
generator assuming that's actually what
that is right assuming that isn't some
kind of a well you know what else is the
other problem with it is if there's
alpha regions around those sprites then
you would have that problem so you know
we could also say you know give it a
little bit of slop there just to see if
that was something I could say
to do Casey how much slop do we want
here but really they should kind of
touch I feel like that's not you know
now that I'm saying it since we're using
the Centers I don't think that's
actually true yeah so I think that may
just be a random number generator it'd
be nice to put in a real random number
generator but again we gotta you know
first every every little bit at a time
all right so I think we're in good shape
now I think everything is reasonably you
know it's okay so I'm gonna say let's go
ahead and start tackling our other
problem but before we start tackling our
other problem I'd like to have some way
of seeing it happen more quickly so what
I'm gonna do is I'm going to force us
into a case where we have two so I had
that you saw me at the beginning I had
to walk all the way up to find a place
where we would actually run out of where
we'd actually run out of tiles and so
what I need to do is I need to sort of
exacerbate that situation I want to make
it so we run out of tiles right away so
that I can see that our eviction scheme
is working right without having to do
this huge walk up to the top and so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to go into
that allocation where we said how many
we had and I'm gonna drastically reduce
the number right and and furthermore we
haven't really we haven't really decided
how many of these we want anyway but
there we go
so when I run this I'm hoping that now I
won't have to walk very far before we
run out of tiles right although it looks
like I guessed wrong that still was
relatively far so let's try even less
tiles will just use 16 tiles now
and we'll hope that that gives us a
quick out so there we go
so we woke up here and we're totally out
of tiles right away which is what we
want and so now our job is to make it so
that we fill those in by reusing old
tiles okay
so the first thing we need to do is
we've already got a loop that does sort
of the this ground chunk filling but the
problem is this empty buffer thing right
here we basically don't have any way to
get more empty buffers after we fill up
the 16 that we've pre-allocated right so
what we want to do is we want something
that will tell us what is the least
important one of the 16 chunks that are
currently in existence which of those
would be the best one to replace does
that make sense and so there's a number
of ways we could do that I guess like
for now what what I'm actually thinking
since we shouldn't probably be doing too
much of this until we're on a more
official engine pass with a little more
knowledge I'm thinking maybe what we'll
do is actually do something where we
sweep over the whole buffer which is
again very inefficient but it might be
the right thing to do instead of trying
to put in an LRU scheme or something
like that when we really don't know what
we're doing it and it might be premature
so what I'm going to do is say okay
we're trying to draw something here so
yeah we're trying to draw something here
we're looping over this buffer and while
we're doing this loop let's just keep
whatever the least the furthest from the
camera actually is right whatever is the
the chunk it's risk of camera from the
camera because we know the relative P
here so it's pretty free for us to just
get distance from camera right for the
chunk it's pretty free for us to do that
we would just say whatever the length
squared is of the relative position of
this thing and I'm gonna just take the
XY because I don't care how house II it
was so the distance from camera I'm
gonna go ahead and say all right this
empty buffer is actually just gonna be
furthest buffer now
and what we're gonna do is just take
whichever buffer would have been
furthest from the camera so when we loop
over these these ground buffer indices
and we go through here so what I'm
actually computing the wrong place
I actually want to compute in here right
so if we found it if we didn't find it
then we're gonna take that distance from
camera in here so we want to do this
right and again that's a little
expensive and in fact we could we could
mitigate this a little bit by storing
the last time that we did it I'm not
sure if we want to do that or not but we
could totally do that again this is not
supposed to be performance code yet this
is just something to sort of have it
working so we kind of know roughly what
has to happen and then we're gonna pull
this out and we can fiddle with it when
we get down to something where we're
actually thinking more about our
performance all right
so this is our our test buffer right
here right so this is like buffer P and
we're gonna get the centered chunk point
for whatever its position was right or
actually we don't even need that gets
buffer P it actually already knows right
it's actually just ground buffer P right
that's what that is so basically what we
want to do here is say if it's valid
we'll do this way if it's not valid
we'll immediately just take it right
it'll be if it's something that has
never minissha lies before then that's
gonna be our buffer for sure that's
immediately what we would want to use
because it means that there's nothing in
it and that's gonna be the best one to
use all right so at the start I'll
initialize furthest buffer length s Q
and so the one that's furthest away at
start is just going to be real 32
maximum which I don't know if we
actually have that did we ever define
that I want something that's never going
to not be picked right and let's see
what we've got here where our type def
there a platform right
I don't know if we did or not it doesn't
look like we did so I'm going to go
ahead and pull in the ability here for
us to get the maximum real 32 value
right and the maximum real 32 value in
this case is defined in limits dot H by
the actual C compiler right so we can
actually just get that for whatever that
this is like a synthetic header file
basically where the compiler is required
to tell us for the platform we're
compiling on what is the maximum float
value but we could even define it
ourselves we really needed to because we
know it's a float 32 so that's the point
but anyway so I'm going to initialize it
to real 32 maximum which is the maximum
value could possibly have which means we
know that we will always pick something
if we haven't picked something yet so
when I come in here I'm going to say all
right let's if this is valid oh and I
guess I'll set further stuff in this
case furthest buffer length sq I'll set
it to 0 so that no one will get picked
no one will take priority over an empty
buffer because nothing will ever be less
than no length will ever be less than
that if that makes sense or further
oh wait I'm doing this backwards we want
further there we go so I've got these
backwards we want it here where we
actually do it so that the furthest
buffer nothing can ever be further than
real 32 maximum so we do that rail P and
we take the length squared now that's
the distance from the camera of this
particular ground buffer we can then see
whether or not that distance from camera
whether the furthest buffer length
squared I should call this like maybe
you like camera length sq or buffer
length sq something like that so I've
got buffer length fescue if the furthest
thing away is actually closer than the
one that we're testing then I'm going to
accept that one as the new closest one
right so this is just a standard again
really really simple not clever brute
force way of finding whatever buffer
would be best to to actually replace
here and again this code is horrible
just absolutely terrible because it
means we're doing however many there are
like you know 16 of these or something
we're actually looping through all of
our ground buffers every time and it's
just a testament to how fast computers
are that we can even do this and so
again this is not something that we
really want to to leave stand but it's
going to be something that I'd rather do
a little bit further down on the engine
so that we don't spend a lot of time
optimizing something that may never get
used exactly the way that that it is
being used today so again this is just a
voiding premature optimization but don't
fool yourself this code is awful right
so anyway let's go ahead and compile
that and fix the the compiler is there
float max did I make a mistake there oh
sorry it's not limited age that's for
integers it's float dot H my bad so
furthest buffer it now can be filled
like so and that should do it now let's
just double check that because I kind of
was trying to talk through that and I
wasn't doing a very good job of
explaining it so let's just try it one
more time and of course we don't really
need found anymore because for this
buffer would probably do it I would
think let's see here
draw buffer screen P screen P dim well
we kind of do need to know for drawing
don't we how is this doing its thing so
we did his chunk Center we got the thing
are the same trunk
thanks left four squared phil gramm
chunk when are we actually drawing the
ground we're drawing the ground trunks
later so yes so we actually don't need
to probably do that although when we do
are found yeah so so we don't need found
because found was just to tell us
whether for this you know family just
tell us whether we needed to fill
anything here but what we could do is
just set furthest buffer equal to zero
when we find the actual valid chunk and
then this won't execute right so we
don't actually need found so let's let's
just get rid of that and that we're a
little simpler
alright so we do is we start out saying
that the furthest buffer away from the
camera that we've seen so far is zero
length away right which is means that
anything will be further away from this
initial value and then we say that
furthest buffer we make a pointer to
save it in we then loop through all the
ground buffers and we say for any
particular ground buffer let's see
whether or not it's in the same chunk as
the one we're looking for
to draw
for this location because again we're
looping through all the ones we want to
draw for the screen if it is then we've
found it so we can just exit we don't
need to fill one it's fine right but if
we haven't if that isn't it then what we
do is say if it is a valid ground buffer
let's see how far away from the camera
is and however far away from the camera
it is right which is what we get right
here if that is further away than the
furthest we've already seen then we want
to accept that as the new for this
buffer right otherwise not otherwise we
wouldn't fill this one we'd fill
whatever one we found before
and finally if it's not valid at all we
want to accept that as the one to fill
because we don't want to fill a buffer
that's got contents in it if there's a
buffer that doesn't have contents in it
we'd obviously prefer to use that right
and so I think that's at least the
basics there and hopefully that will
fill things up for us let's see okay so
it looks like 16 is too few for the size
that we're doing so you can actually see
that it's like over filling itself so
let's give it a little bit more to work
with and then we also probably want to
tighten up the bounds of what we're
drawing there potentially but yeah so
let's see let's take a look let's go to
32 and see how that is but we may also
have a bug in the loop and that should
tell us whether we do or not yeah so
that looks good and now we should be
able to walk kind of arbitrarily long as
we go and we should never run out of
ground right it should be good to go
it's looking pretty good it's looking
pretty good people I like it yeah so
really I don't know that we've got
anything else we would really want to do
with this at the moment I mean the only
thing I can think of is that we'd want
to do something as like with being able
to put in we're sort of grasses and
where stone is and that sort of stuff
but I don't know that we want to quite
do that yet that's more of a world
generation thing
but yeah looking good looking good
looking good so yeah I guess we kind of
have the problem now that we've come to
a point where we want to start something
wholly new but I don't know oh that's
kind of interesting so there's something
we could fix right so do you see what's
happening there with those where where
these these clumps got kind of
overwritten that's because we have two
layers of ground and we kind of want to
always splat the detail splats on top of
sort of the ground splats so what we
could do right is we could if we wanted
to fix that we could go ahead and do
something where we said oops infill
ground chunk we could say do this loop
right we want to do this loop more than
once so that we we do it once for each
of them which is a little owners right
but if we did that if we split this up
into two passes right so we did these
first right and these second that would
would prevent that sort of situation
from happening right so let's walk a bit
and then come back there so that was one
screen to the left and one screen down
right so I'm gonna walk back on the S
and see if that fixes it right so let's
go ahead back there
there we go and so now you can see that
we don't have that problem anymore so
that's kind of nice and yeah and we'll
have to make a little more intelligence
as well in that in the sort of the
ground compositor to handle a lot of
situations like that but that's a pretty
easy way for us to just fix it at the
moment so that we don't have that
particular problem so yeah yes I like it
so what time do we have here well we've
got 15 minutes left what should we do in
15 minutes because that's that's kind of
an interesting question I guess what we
could do is start on handling multiple Z
levels in those chunks because that's
kind of and then that would roll into
tomorrow I guess let's let's let's say
that's true and so something else that
we could do to you know what else we
could do this might be kind of fun I
don't know if this is a good idea or not
but one thing that we could do is we
could make something that would allow us
to whenever we reload the code in
because remember outside in our win32
layer that does the code reloading we
could have something in there that was
smart and told us when the code reloaded
so that we could regenerate stuff when
that happened does that make sense that
might be a good thing to do too so let's
let's let's do that let's do that I
think we should do that
so we inside win32 hand-made and I'm
gonna open up the platform layer here so
when we pass through our game memory
here right because that's that's
basically we've got game air we got game
input what I'd like to do is pass in
maybe some things that say like okay
executable reloaded or something like
that right just a variable that tells
the game whether the executable reloaded
and then inside here that allows us to
that'll allow us to put in some some
debug code for example that we can use
in in you know in
case where we want to do something
special right and so what we could do is
say all right you know if input
executable reloaded then what I want to
do is go ahead and clear out all of the
the things that were in that cache right
so I'm gonna go in here and just say all
right all of these guys you now
officially have nothing in you right
like so
so they'll just wipe out that background
cache completely and off you go so if we
were to do that all we'd have to do to
implement that is in here when we do our
our reloads right because we already
have the thing that does the reloads it
does like load game code this thing we
just have to look at how that clos path
works and when we find that we have
reloaded we want to go ahead and and set
that input to be true now load counter I
don't know what that is somewhat tell me
what that was doing I think that was
something that we used to use for how
often we would reload but we don't use
that anymore so that's not relevant so
when we do our with our win32 load game
code I'm just going to be the simplest
possible finger and say that new inputs
executable reloaded now equals true
whereas normally executable reloaded
will equal false right that's it really
really straightforward so basically it
sets it to false and then if it actually
does its reload then it reloads now I
don't know if we returned anything more
specific here in fact you know what I
could do I could make this actually be
equal to that but I don't know we'll
leave it this way for now so there we go
we've got that go so we open up the game
and here we are and so now what I'd like
to do is I would like to make it so that
I can change the routine you know that
so I can change the routine that does
that compositing so let's say I go in
here and into that that fill ground
chunk what I'd like to see happen is if
I just turn off
the splatting of the grass chunk the
grass Tufts for lack of a better term if
I turn that off before if we were
compiled nothing would have happened now
if I do it I want to see that change and
hey it did that's that's pretty darn
awesome that is just pretty darn awesome
you got to admit that's pretty cool
yeah live code editing is the way to go
man
it's so much fun even if you don't ever
use it for anything productive it's
still just fun to just sit there and
kind of play with so that you don't have
to wait for for your turnaround and so
on so yeah that looks pretty good to me
I'd also like to go double check I'm a
little concerned that we're kind of
drawing too much yeah so let's I've got
a couple other things we can do since
we've got some time left I want to know
why we're actually drawing so many why
16 wasn't enough I'm gonna make those
draw rectangle calls that we have this
draw rect the draw rectangle outline
stuff that was happening here I'm going
to actually make it so that this ground
buffer thing I'm actually gonna make
that happen up above here right I'm
gonna make that happen up here which is
actually bad like it's not actually want
to do but I want to see those those
debug regions over it
so to do KC this should really not be
here exactly
oh well that's not actually true so
really it's this thing this should
really you know what the only reason I'm
even saying that is because this thing
will fill chunks and then this thing
will draw them so you want to fill the
transfer you draw them but this is gonna
be on a separate thread anyway so I
don't even know why I'm notating that it
does not matter at all so let's see how
many there actually are on the screen
one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten eleven twelve thirteen fourteen
fifteen so actually having only 16
really wasn't enough so yeah 32 might be
too many but 16 actually legitimately
wasn't enough so I'll give I'll give
that to you so that's okay and there we
can see the boundary is nicely so it's
all good yeah
so I think we're in pretty good shape
there I'm totally fine with that now we
have another issue to address which is
RZ layers but I think I want to maybe
we'll start on that tomorrow I don't
want to start on that now so yes there
anything else that I kind of wanted to
do here I do wonder if how if these
chunks are too small now although based
on the number of entities that are in
here 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
based on the number of entities I would
say no probably not
I mean I don't know we'll have to see
how much our what our memory footprint
looks like and how we're doing when we
start there whether whether these are
too too big or too small for ground
chunks sizes but that's pretty good
that's pretty good I'm happy with that
ok so now I'll go ahead and move this
back below it for now or actually guess
I won't I'll just comment this out and
if we want that again we could turn it
back on but that should do it
alrighty then happy day we are now at
our giant ground texture is there it is
happy it's working well so that's good
news and I think we can probably call it
a day
we can probably go ahead and get that QA
started here a little bit early a little
bit early so let's do is the bot
operational the bodies back the bot is
back people all right it is time for the
Q and a and the QA is for asking
questions about the code we just wrote
please prefixed your questions with Q :
so I will see them and try to keep it to
stuff that we've actually done
programming wise so there jazzy Josh are
the randomly generated floor tiles being
cast yet yes they are they are being
cached
do you think having things in place like
static cast to put more checks eg into
pointer is useful over standard c-style
cast with just ignore all type checking
wouldn't a set a cast I've found that
bug at the start of the stream so again
like anything that is of that nature you
have to decide whether adding new
features into the codebase is worth
doing
or not right and there's there's even
additional reasons why you would care
about that today that aren't necessarily
true in the past either and one of them
I point out is I think C++ isn't long
for this world
like I do not suspect that we will be
programming in C++ you know five years
from now I suspect we will have moved on
to AC variant like maybe hopefully John
blows language that's like has the C
stuff in it still but not the C++ stuff
and I think it will be much easier to
port code bases to the non C++ language
if you don't use all kinds of C++
garbage right so I try to keep C++ out
of the codebase as much as possible
because I think it's probably gonna go
away if you know you're going to use C++
and you love C++ then there might not be
any reason not to introduce those but I
tend away those things relatively
heavily right putting that aside in this
case that's a bug I've literally never
had before so in my mind that's a stream
bug and so you know do we want to do it
on the stream I don't know it's probably
not necessary that that's really not
that big a deal we would have caught it
I don't think that's a pretty important
bug to guard against because we don't do
it that often
only the initialization of the arena's
which only happens twice so I'm not that
concerned about it it's a bug I've never
had before in regular code so it's not a
typo that I actually make and like I
said many times you only want to spend
time guarding against things you
actually do which may be different for
you than for me so if you find yourself
actually making mistakes like that
fairly commonly in your actual code not
when you're trying to talk and explain
things but in your actual code that you
do then and you find that they're hard
to debug that would be a good
to introduce additional checking if you
don't find yourself making those errors
then you're just wasting your time
and you know it's a good idea not to
waste your time so that's the advice I
give on basically all the things that
people ask about that are of that nature
it was like figure out how much time you
spend debugging those bugs and if that
amounts to a significant amount of time
then consider steps to mitigate them if
not then don't and you'll note that we
have gotten through 87 hours of
programming here without ever having
that bug before so and we've had only
one of them so far so if we never have
another one of those again I would say
it would be a really bad idea to start
introducing random stuff like static
Const that we don't actually need
whereas if we start hitting these fairly
regularly and we have another one next
week another one week after that then
that is the time to say hey this is a
bug we do let's let's take care of it do
you think the clumpiness is actually due
to splat distance from the center of the
chunks so I don't know what it's it's
from but I suspect it's from the random
number table of being awful right and we
could we could check that quickly if we
really wanted to right so one way we
could check that right is by using C's
random number generator which it's is
not great but it doesn't have the
problems of our random number table so
if we wanted to
I'd okay so I'd have to get back let's
see here let's see I'd have to get back
our our very clumpy grasses so I'd have
to crank this number up and what I'll do
here is I'll just crank this number up
to like a really absurd number right so
we can kind of see it see here it's kind
of hard it doesn't look that clumpy so
you know what I think that what we were
seeing was actually the fact that we
weren't drawing these on top that's what
we were actually seeing so I take it
back it wasn't the random number
generator was just it was that thing
that bug that we fixed where we weren't
drawing these in a second pass so that
the next thing that abutted would
overwrite you know some of the grasses
so we're
actually so it's fine I rent 'm number
table is still lousy like we when we
switched to a random number generator
that's good we'll get some benefits but
it looks like this is not actually a
problem so well we'll go back to
something what's a good amount of grass
I don't know let's say that much of
course normally we would only want the
grass to be on the grass but that's it
that's the story for another time I
suppose although I guess we could do
that pretty easily here as well do you
know why the trees are wiggling around
sometimes yes so we don't have a
renderer right now I know that's a weird
thing to say because there's stuff on
the screen but all we did is make a very
simple lit bitmap call and that's all we
have so you notice there's a bunch of
artifacts that you can already see
because we don't have a real renderer
that's something that's coming up later
in the stream and so what do you
artifacts you see for example is we
don't sort anything so like I can pass
behind things sometimes right like that
and that's purely because it
there's no sorting it just depends on
what order the entity is we're getting
dealt with right that's it and so that's
you know that's an example of something
the render will fix another thing the
render will fix is
we're not sub-pixel accurate at the
moment so the reason the trees are
wiggling like you can kind of see that
is because they are snapping to integer
coordinates they are floating-point
positioned but they're snapping to
integer coordinates and when one rounds
up to the next integer coordinate but
the other one hasn't yet right you see
their distance change a little bit and
so that's another thing that that the
the renderer will fix for us because we
will be sub pixel accurate in our
renderer and you will get a nice smooth
interpolation there which is you know
it's it fixes that problem but strictly
speaking we could fix this problem
another way it's just we don't actually
want to we want to fix it by um by
actually doing the sub pixel stuff
because there's you know that makes for
motion that's much smoother on things
that are slow moving as well
that makes sense what is causing the lag
oh okay so if you haven't been following
for the past couple days then you don't
know what that lag is so that lag is
right now well we've got two things
there are two reasons for the lag if you
will and I assume you're meaning that
pause right there right so there's two
reasons for it the first reason is
because we are not generating those
background chunks on a separate thread
we just generate them right when we
decide we want them and it's an
expensive operation so we get Lac
normally what we'd want to do is overlap
that processing so that it doesn't hurt
our frame rate right but that said it
really isn't enough work to actually
make the lag that you're seeing so the
reason that you're actually seeing that
the lag would be there it'd just be a
minuscule amount and it wouldn't
actually affect the frame rate because
we're not overlapping right but the
reason you're actually seeing it here is
because we have really for producing the
ground segments they're calling a bitmap
flooding routine like it's the same one
that's bleeding into the screen which is
completely unbiased and is the slowest
possible thing you could ever imagine
for putting a bitmap to the screen and
so really also we're not even compiling
it in a release mode so if we were to
compile in release mode we'd also speed
up a little bit so for example if we
were to say in build dot bat if we
wanted to change our - oh D here right -
- o - to get some some measure of
optimization happening in the code you
would notice that the lag is is you know
reduced right you can see that it's a
much shorter hiccup than it was before
but that's you know again that's kind of
more about just the fact that the we
haven't done any optimization on the
code and so that's like why the lag is
as substantial it is because it's
running very slow code right
are there still places where the
background color shows through the
ground tiles um probably not anymore but
we haven't done really the things that
we want to do to guarantee that but
those have more to do with with actually
those those have more to do with how we
generate the ground tiles than anything
else but if you want to be able to check
that one thing we can do is is put in a
hideous pink it's not perfect but it
would let us see a little bit more
readily where we were getting problems
it's not a perfect check honestly but
you can kind of see now that there's
you're not seeing much background
through at the very least but you can
also see when we when we don't quite
have the tiles filled yet when they come
on the screen you can see them kind of
flashing in there right and similarly
what we'd probably want to do eventually
is is we're going to need to do
something that that kind of predicts ask
for tiles that we haven't that we
haven't needed on the screen yet right
that's something we also want to do but
yeah
is this chunk code already prepared for
adding holes to the ground holes that
could be any size yes really all we have
to do is then cut out the Alpha later on
right so if we wanted to for example I
mean I'm just totally going to make up
something here right but if I walk back
to the starting room here I think this
is the starting room right yeah nope not
quite if I walk back to the starting
room eventually well I'll just restart
if we wanted to we could add holes
already right it's it's pretty easy so
all we need is there's a draw a bitmap
right routine we need to draw a bitmap
that can basically draw solid alpha it's
not really it's like a matte bitmap
insertion and so what this would be is
it's a little hard to explain but let me
just copy this routine and I'll show you
what I mean so if we did something like
draw Matt okay and in here if we changed
what we meant by the RG and B colors
that are in the buffer right if we made
this cut out a hole in the alpha instead
of filling it in that would allow us to
punch holes in it right and so just a
simple example we'll start with let's
say we did something where we had a
equals 1.0 - whatever that source alpha
was right something like that is that
right
so RSA 55 yeah something like that
- si so that that would be it was 55 -
si and when we were drawing in here
maybe we don't actually touch those
colors we just need to multiply so yeah
I'm trying to figure out how to do this
relatively quickly but
so we want to make a real alpha
composite up here so yeah don't I'm just
I'm just sort of not thinking this
through half at all but let's say we
take the destination alpha right and we
multiply it by the inverse source alpha
right so that it reduces it down to what
it so if the inverse source if the
source alpha was being drawn brightly it
would get very dark on the on the on the
DA and we we don't add in any color at
all so all we're doing is strictly
dimming like removing power from
whatever is being written in there if
that makes sense
so if we do that then what we've got is
the ability to match something out and
so I'll show you what that kind of works
right so if we compile this and I go
into ground that ground chunk generator
thing right Phil Gramm chunk if I just
in the middle of the ground chunk or
something well actually you know what I
could do let's draw their ground toughs
as Matt right and I'm sorry I kind of
did this hastily but so do you see what
that did right that allows it to punch
holes that will see through to whatever
is underneath remember we drew pink
behind it so so yeah it's real easy for
us to add holes we just have to have an
idea of like a bitmap that we want is
like what the hole shaped like and then
we punch it through really really basic
stuff yeah so nothing complicated there
if that makes sense I should put in the
draw Matt routine because the draw Matt
routine I didn't really think that
through right we should we should put it
let's check this math oh hey it already
has one from the previous one but I did
actually I did actually look up to see
if this was correct and I believe it is
so we could we could validate that later
but yeah
could you make code that ensures a
certain framerate but uses extra
available time to generate the ground
textures in the background maybe we're
generating a low quality version for us
to avoid having no texture at all yes
you could do that there those are two
separate things right what the lower
detail versus higher detail and the
certain framerate thing the reason why
you don't generally want to write code
like that anymore and this is true
especially now that the Raspberry Pi has
gone for a core is you need something
for your 4 cores to do right because
you're gonna have two cores at a minimum
most gaming machines are gonna have 4
cores and so you typically want to have
background stuff so you typically need
to have extra threads doing things and
so putting it on the main loop and doing
it as a frame rate guarantee a frame
rate limited thing just isn't very
leveraging of the way processors work so
you typically want to have a bunch of
tasks that you do and they kind of are
operating on multiple threads as a way
to use up that CPU time that's sitting
there that makes sense all right
looks like we are out of questions is it
true we are out of questions
I think we're out of questions well if
we're out of questions then that's it
we're all good all right folks
that is another handmade hero it's
working pretty good now I'm liking I'm
liking that we've got some graphics in
there so he's grooving add graphics add
a when you add graphics eyes feels good
it looks good it's fun so tomorrow we
could start on our final Z layer stuff
maybe you know it's gonna be fun to have
rooms overlooking other rooms so I think
that'll be a good push we'll start
tomorrow and I'm sure it'll go next week
we'll be we'll be mostly doing that
because that's a lot of work to get all
that stuff right that we've kind of been
sort of working towards but it's got to
all come together right but we finished
that that round of generating ground
textures and we did it in a way that
allows us to generate ground textures as
is as many Z levels as we want which is
kind of cool too because that cache can
just cash any tile anywhere really so
it's kind of handy
but anyway enough about that thank you
very much for joining me for another
episode of hand made here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always I
hope to see you back here tomorrow same
time same place 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time on twitch TV come a few
minutes early if you watch at I'm
usually here about 15 minutes early
actually if you would like to follow
along at home you can always puro to the
game on handmade hero org using the
handy dandy pre-order button so if you
want to check that out you could do that
and get immediate access to the source
code which you can download and play
with which is a good way to learn if you
like sort of learn by experimentation
which I highly recommend we've also got
three other things check out one is the
news and forum site which basically has
a place ask questions
ports to Mac and Linux and a annotated
episode guide so it's a lot of good
stuff you can use to help learn from the
stream that's pretty cool we also have
the patreon if you want us to help
support the video series you can
subscribe to that the videos are free as
always in our archive so that's just if
you're if you're just nice and want to
help us that's that's a very nice thing
to do and finally we've got the tweet
Papa tweets the schedule highly
recommend checking that out and
subscribing to it potentially if you
would like to know when
Stream is every night because sometimes
it moves around and especially now we're
trying out a new timeslot we used to be
at 8 p.m. Pacific same time we're trying
out 5 p.m. this week and we may switch
that currently so we'll see how it goes
anyway thank you very much for joining
me and I hope to see you here tomorrow
have a wonderful I guess it's Friday
tomorrow is it I don't remember
abner Coimbra Coimbra if I'm saying that
right one of our fearless moderators had
a thing at the beginning where he
eloquently stated the order of the days
that would occur and here I am not
remembering I think tomorrow is a Friday
it is tomorrow is a Friday so have a
wonderful Friday and I hope see you
tomorrow evening if not have a wonderful
weekend take it easy everyone