all right hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero sure we code a complete
game
live on stream uh i am
going to just go ahead and do whatever i
want today because i don't think
we had anything actually on the table
um i could be wrong about that but i
think we pretty much
we had a lighting bug we wanted to fix
and we fixed it
and we weren't really working on the
lighting right now so i don't think
we need to do a lighting quality pass
which is what we want to do eventually
so i don't know what i want to do today
because we didn't have anything
scheduled
uh but if we're just running uh you know
we're kind of at a state where i feel
like just
just throwing in a bunch of gameplay
stuff which is not my thing
um those of you coming from john's
stream know john
i mean john's like one of the he's not
one of the best game designers in the
world he's just the best games around
the world i don't know anyone who
designs games
as well as he does even if you don't
like the types of style
stuff games he makes it's kind of nuts
just how well designed they are
so i don't really do game design stuff
but
i want to basically you know be able to
finish up our engine and call it done
uh and so in order to do that i need a
game in here
uh and so you know we've got pretty much
everything else that we really need
we've got as much testing as we kind of
can
i think without actually putting in
gameplay stuff that we can then say like
you know
is this relatively complete are all the
things we need to have happening in a
game happening
and so on the only way to really get to
that point is to put it in
so i think what i'll start doing is just
throwing in
game stuff that i think uh would
would test out you know uh gameplay
stuff
in in whatever order i want and
that will allow us to basically clean up
the entity side of things
and and get to a place that we're happy
with it uh
and once we feel like all of that stuff
has solidified and we're just like all
right this
is completely representative of of you
know a real
game there's nothing missing out of here
uh that we think
uh is important then what i can do
is flop back to doing pass on all the
stuff we want to do quality wise like
uh like lighting and so on uh where we
where we kind of left stuff on the table
where we're like we gotta go clean up
you know make this look better make this
uh faster do whatever right
so that's what we need to do um and we
just have to
uh we just have to start so what i'd
like to do
is uh if you kind of see what happens
when you hop
out here we've got sort of this idea
that you know you can go
downstairs and you can go into like a
little dungeon area
and so on uh what i'd like to do is
start
by adding for example like some doors
that are
locked uh and then a way to unlock the
doors
so the reason that i want to do that is
because when you
look at games of this style that
typically the way that they work
is when you enter a area you
are forced to confront something uh in
order to proceed from that area
that isn't just about getting
antagonized by monsters
and what i mean by that is that if you
look at games
um like oh does someone say steal his
head okay
um i will steal the head of the monster
um if you look at games that
that are like this like zelda or binding
of isaac what happens in those games is
you enter a room like a typical example
be i hop through here and i'm in a new
room
and uh in those games it's very extreme
not only does the door in front of me
lock but the door behind me
actually locks i don't know that i want
to go that far uh
i don't think i care about that for this
game but i i want
this door to lock right so all right i
mean another way to say it would be that
door should just be locked so you enter
this room
and you have to do something in the room
in order for the door
like here to uh
to to let you pass so i i just want to
put a door there
and i want that door to obstruct right
the movement through the uh
i want the door to obstruct the movement
into the next area
uh until you've done something in this
room so
let's just start there and that'll also
uh we can go do some cleanup that we may
do for a while and that is that
if you'll notice our transaction occupy
points
we broke uh when we were doing our
entity system stuff you can see i can
hop onto these trees
which i should not be able to do and so
this will have us fix that as well so
we'll both fix that
and just have the little uh you know
some kind of doors
that you can't get by and then they can
go down right
um so let's do that uh what i want to do
first is just take a look at our
transactional occupy code
and i would like to fix it so it's not
broken
uh that should be the easiest possible
thing
and uh you know
we if we can't if we can't do that we
certainly can't make a door
because you just hop right through the
door so
the way that this stuff works is again
it doesn't actually use
a collision detector for this it's not
collision code
uh what it actually does is it has this
sort of transactional occupation thing
that we wrote a very very long
time ago very early on in handmade hero
development
we've got this transactional occupy
thing and what you do is you pass the
simulation region that this is happening
in which again is just the thing that
contains all the entities
and what they're doing right um
and we pass the entity that is trying to
do this so the entity
you know this particular entity wants to
occupy a particular
square on the board it's trying to like
hop forward or something
and then we pass like a traversible that
it's trying to
use and a traversable that it wants it
to
be right so it's basically saying i want
to go from here to here right
and you can see uh sort of how we work
on that code
in this in this routine so you know the
way this works is first it
grabs the traversable that's saying it
wants to go to
which is this one you can see it looking
to see
whether there's anyone occupying that
traversable
um assuming that there wasn't it will
then
grab the traversible that it's coming
from
again which is this one uh it will say
okay
go ahead and take me off of that one so
no one's occupying that one now
overwrite it with the one that i'm
actually going
to and mark the fact that the one that
i'm going to
now has me occupying right
so it's really that's all there is to it
right it's pretty straightforward
most people probably don't remember that
but that's what's happening
so what we want to do now
uh is take a look at why this isn't
working
we know that we're calling transactional
occupy
and we you know uh
at least well you know what i guess we
shouldn't assume um
let's actually see but i'm assuming we
call transactional occupy so let's
double check and make sure that we
actually do
oops
so here are the places in the code where
we call transactional occupy
that's the actual function uh here is us
calling it
in a function
where we call update and render entities
okay so this is just
us doing okay so here is just
if you're using boost squares these were
just things like
little teleporters uh we don't even have
those
in here right now so there's probably no
chance that that
has anything to do with anything we care
about for this
um here is the code inside the brain
uh of the entity which is exactly what
we
you know would assume is happening for
the brain uh the hero
so this is this is the code we actually
care about
you can see uh the get close traversable
code is doing this transactional occupy
call
so that's the verification that it's
looking for that's actually being called
um you can see here we've also got the
snake which is the little guy
hopping around right now um
there's you know
there's calls everywhere we think there
should be so so i
you know i don't see don't see any
evidence that there's any issues here
um and so let me just see
if actually i don't actually even know
maybe we didn't break this code
let's see if we can hop onto the same
square as
one of the um of one of the enemies if
we did
then actually the code is not broken it
works just fine and the only thing is
we're probably not removing
uh points with trees like we're probably
not marking trees as being on points or
something
right okay yeah so i can't hop onto the
same square as sky
so actually our code for transactional
occupation is is not broken this
probably isn't even a bug
it's probably just we don't add points
for the trees
right yeah i can't i can't hop onto this
this square at all um
so i guess i would say
probably no bug it's probably just when
we were doing the room gen stuff
we just hadn't gotten around to doing
anything with the trees
um aprons don't matter here because
aprons aren't occupiable anyway
so we're probably talking about in here
uh
at some point we're placing our trees
and
we let's see how we do
that so
here is our um our place tree
call here and
you know honestly it's
probably just this there's two
so so okay there's two ways we can do
this
one is we can have the tree occupy the
square
the other is we can just mark it as
unoccupiable ever
i don't know which one we want to do at
the moment i'm just going to say it's
unoccupiable
but in the future we may want to say
that the tree just occupies a square
the reason i say that is because maybe
we want you to be able to knock down
trees
eh i don't know right
but at the moment um i'm just gonna say
look
if you place a tree uh
you know then it's not open
right uh trees block block your path
so i'm assuming that was it i don't
actually know
but if i hop out here to the closest
outdoor area
um i'm assuming ooh
that was weird why
did that
why did that not actually put the tree
there
well i wasn't expecting that i was
assuming that we just wouldn't call this
but it looks like because place tree is
here
add piece of clutter oh but actually we
still need to place the tree
interesting
so we still need to place the tree
and it looks like i guess so uh yeah hmm
interesting
so i guess we treat the tree placement
so we actually set up this code
specifically because we wanted the trees
to
not be the same as walls
right like we don't do that for what
interesting okay
well i mean if that's the case that's
fine all we need to do is just say this
part
here right where we do where we place
the entity
um this part here we
we want to make sure that we actually
mark it as occupied
right and so here's the traversable
reference that we've got um
if we call jen energy at traversible
that should have put the tree there
and so i guess my only question is what
happened in genetically traversable that
should have actually just worked
right here's occupying
so that should have just worked right so
something's a little busted here
so it looks like we do actually have
like a real bug um
in this code because this should have
worked here's the occupying
um record where we're saying that this
tree
stick you know is on this particular
point
in the world and so that should have
marked that point
as being um as being occupied by the
tree
so i'm guessing that we do have some bug
here that has to do
with how we uh
packed those or unpack those or
something
uh and we'll have to look at
how that actually is is being unpacked
in the entity code so like when we
unpack
an entity and
uh again it's been a while since we've
done this so i'm not actually sure
what we were doing uh with these
but oh and hey does this code still run
this might be handy
assume this just takes a uh
so we don't really need this probably
all right so if we change this push cube
to
actually just be the new way that we do
push cubes
then we should be able to run this as
well which i think would be good uh
we've got the
the position value we
have render group
bitmap position uh
radius color
default cube uv layout and emission
i assume we wanted these to be
emitters i guess
because we just want to be able to see
them right
am i wrong about this
look that seems like something we do
want i guess that may be too
many is that actually complaining about
how many quads there are total
i guess that could be if we're rendering
too many of them
but you wouldn't think that would be the
case right
you would think that that would be
relatively fine
let me take a quick look i want to see
we probably should have a thing where we
just allow render buffers to get as
large as we want them to be
so that we can do stuff like debug
rendering more easily
oh no wasn't that it's just that
emission can't be larger than one
so i don't know what this value was
doing before who knows
all right so i think that was the only
thing yeah
so i'm going to leave that on for a
little bit uh just because i want to
make sure
that we can see where these things are
and hopefully we can get some
information about
uh what's going on so when i hop around
on these
uh what i should see is that they should
be like
you know if i look i don't know if i can
actually see the ones unfortunately
they're like underneath me
maybe i should have made these like
easier to view but
i should see these change color when i'm
on them so
interestingly enough like even though i
wasn't
like i'm not seeing them change color
underneath me which is a little bit
weird because
even as i hop forward i should see that
so actually there's something a little
bit weird here which is the traversable
occupier
here um is is not actually happening
so it's worse than i thought um
so that code even though we're calling
the transactional occupy
code somehow we're not like preserving
these
so i'm going to take a look at the sim
region um unpacking code
which when we unpack entities
into the uh into the world
we're supposed to keep track of those
traversibles
right and that doesn't look like it's
happening
and maybe we're doing a bad job of this
uh
it could be i'm not sure but we
we you know it could be that we need to
do this in a way that's better
because you know what we're doing at the
moment maybe isn't isn't the best idea
um and in fact
you know honestly thinking about that
it kind of feels that way too like the
way that we were doing this where you
actually have to think about
these traversable points as being things
that were
a sub like that were contained inside an
entity
is actually kind of dumb like there's no
reason that these can't just be handled
like everything else
where they're just like hey they're just
numbers assigned to these traversible
points
and you can either be on them or not and
there's
only a conflict if you have two people
who try to be on one traversible
that seems totally reasonable um so i'm
not sure about
that but we'll go ahead and and uh and
take this one step at a time so i don't
want to make
uh any you know uh any sort of
decision about it till i actually see
what's happening
um so what i'd like to do is go into the
code that actually unpacks these guys
so let me just
let me just jump over there
uh nope that's what we want
so here you can see where we take an
entity
and we do an acquire unpacked entity
slot
we unpack the entity we fill it
and we register it um
what you can see here is that the
register
entity call is really the only thing uh
that's happening
looking in here nobody preserves these
so
so there was a bug in here which is just
that when we
redid this and we may have even said it
at the time it may be a known bug
um we don't on we don't unpack occupancy
right we're just straight up not
unpacking occupancy
so i think what we want to do here
i would assume
is just leave occupancy raw
so if i go to entity here
uh and we that is not entity
there we go oh it's just jumping to the
yeah sorry
uh i i do have a request in for the four
coder jump stuff to not do that but we
haven't gotten there yet
so if i jump into entity and we take a
look at what's happening here
we have our traversibles
and they
look like this which is stupid like
there should not be a pointer in here
and i don't know why
there is right and so i think what we
probably did is we said look we don't
need those anymore they should just be
entity ids
and this should not be happening right
because we don't need a pointer for any
particular reason it can just be an id
and that's all it should be so i'm
pretty sure what we want to do
is just change the way this works now so
that you don't have to do any management
of these they just manage themselves
and so the entity traversable point here
should really just be
one of these which is who is occupying
it
right and anywhere that that code was
getting used before
uh should not you know should should
just be
using it like an id so when you say is
occupied you just get
the traversible in question and you need
to check to see if it's occupied
um
what is the question here
do we not have an is valid for
[Music]
editing ids that doesn't seem right
see yeah like just like i'm saying like
when we do function overloading we need
these in for coder
like in mine it doesn't do this but you
know when we switch to the default
branch
we lost the ability to see the function
prototype which is which is
tough because if you use function
overloading
you need to see the parameters right
um otherwise you have no idea what
um you know which one you're looking at
which doesn't help
um anyway so yeah we need
the way to test whether one of these is
is
valid and i don't know how we
possibly could have not had one of those
right
um so it feels like we should have had
one and i'm just
not sure um why we don't have one
that's really weird so
i'll put one in but that just doesn't
make sense you can see here
like it even has a clear so why you
wouldn't have
um and is valid i don't know
oops
so probably we're just that
and i i how is that not there already
that is
that i i literally have no idea no idea
um
i'm so weirded out right now because
like how did we write the rest of the
code
this is what happens when you work on a
code base once a week i mean
who knows right
but uh otherwise
it's pretty straightforward uh we can
clear the occupier here
i guess which is what it wants to do uh
here we need just the id
uh which obviously we have um
all that's fine looking at this code
this is just a
check on that make sure it's not
occupied
not much else to it when we're iterating
on cure we need a way or we want a way
to get the occupier so we want to be
able to do
just a get entity here and
and i think that's all we would need is
just to say look give us the
the one that's there um and this is
again just a and is valid where we would
say
you know is there somebody on there uh
this is also
so so i don't know what the point of
this is necessarily
oh this is just creating a thing these
should have already been zero
so i'm not sure what the point of that
is i'll leave that on there
because fine right it doesn't hurt me to
do so
um but it's also not really relevant
so that should at least now preserve
those values
properly now whether or not they were
getting cleared
in some other place i don't know so we
we still may have a little more work to
do
so right like you can see that's not
that's still not
actually showing up properly so i don't
think we're quite
out of the woods yet you can see i can
still hop onto here
but at least now that's running through
a that's running through a system that
actually doesn't use
pointers for that for that
preserving right
so we take a look at the traversibles
i want to know everywhere that that's
getting
mucked with just so i can see how it's
supposedly preserved or not preserved
it's in the part that's not discarded so
it should remain
um
this is just for boost stuff which
shouldn't matter
this is the rendering code which again
it should just be fine
um here's where those traversals being
accessed here's where they're getting
created originally and generate rooms so
that shouldn't really be implicated
during play
uh at all uh
oh and hey look this is what i said
before
right uh we already talked about that
so i don't see anywhere that that's
getting cleared
so i'm not sure i understand
why we would ever have any
weirdness like why those aren't
remaining set
right so something's a little bit weird
so i'm going to go ahead and just step
through the code there just so i can see
if there's something that i'm not
understanding about what's going on
because that shouldn't be a big deal
all right so i'm gonna
take a look at the
transactional occupy code
um and when i try to jump forward
right i should come in here and i should
be able to see uh this code
happen right so if i look
at the two people in question so here
they are
uh and you can see that like the
this is the place that i was coming from
so it's this entity
entity 7584 which is just some
presumably ground piece and it's the
first reversible on there
i'm trying to go to here which is like
this position
in the world um which is basically
zero but 0.5 of z
and i want to
to occupy this place that no one is so
it should work
right so let's just see what happens
we take a look and say oh the
destination
um you know it's not occupied so the
destination um
i should have watched that happen um so
this destination here which
should have been on entity 7584
will get cleared to zero i'll step
through that again so we can watch and
see that it gets cleared not that we
really care but i just wanna
you know i just wanted to step through
it once uh we're going to set the
desired location so the one we're going
to
the occupier for that which is this here
should now be set to us
right uh and then
we should you know continue on with our
with our fun
right and there's not anything else
that's going on here
right so now we're just occupying that
location
so you know to me that looks fine
um i'm not sure what this transaction
will occupy like who's calling this
no one should be calling it again so
this may be something
buggy um
so that may just be well
so that's a little bit weird right like
i'm not sure how we got into this again
like how is that being called so many
times
that seems broken right because i
shouldn't be really
hopping forward i mean i guess if i had
to argue
with myself i would say it was because
the key is down like maybe it didn't
pick
the yeah so the key is just stuck down
because hey it never saw the up because
if the up went to this other app and we
aren't checking for that yet i guess
so i guess i could believe that um i'm
not willing to say that's totally wrong
uh but yeah so if i
like try to look in here um real quick
i'm just gonna take a look at
the uh at the points
so you know we watched it set this
uh this
we watched it set that traversible
supposedly to be occupied and yet when
we look at it
it's not drawing as occupied so that's
what we're trying to fix
right here and if we look at where
that's actually being drawn
so in that code that we had
right here you can see that it's saying
loop over all the traversibles
for each traversible that's in there um
if there's an occupier on it it's
supposed to set the color different
oh but you know what this isn't being
used
all right
that was stupid all right so
that is working now good uh mystery
solved there
um and so now we just have to take a
look at those trees we may have fixed
them by using the permanent
the permanent id obviously but we may
not we may have a separate bug there
so our next question is like what's the
status of these trees
right over here uh so i'm gonna go ahead
and just
hop over there you know we should have a
thing that lets us click
and move directly to where i click in
the world
seems like that would be handy right
um especially in debug mode where
everything runs really slowly right
in debug mode we could have a thing that
turns off lighting and then everything
would run quickly
you know what i mean because when we
don't lighting is the only thing that
takes our time um
but we don't have a way to just turn it
off do we
yeah we don't use like if we just have
this lighting disabled actually do
something
that would probably that would probably
do it so you know we probably should
just saying um all right if we
uh take a look in here and i'm gonna try
and
look and see like the ground cover uh if
i
just kind of look on the other side of
it i should be able to see the
transaction points
so you can see that they're they're not
right so they should be like this amber
color
right or i don't know what it is orange
um
those should be set that way you can see
that they're not
and so the you know the coloration on
those
what we need to do now is figure out why
the trees aren't
taking up those slots right
so i think and
if i you know based on the searches we
just did
i think it's actually pretty
straightforward the reason is going to
be
because when we do the gen entity thing
um in fact i almost want to say that if
i just run this code we may actually see
this bug on the hero itself
hold on a second let me actually um
let me switch to release because i
actually don't need to be in debug for
this
so i su suspect yes so
basically at startup we're always wrong
and the reason is because in gen entity
in gen entity at traversable
we just don't set it right
so transactional
occupy um
is probably what we should call right
like if we just did this
this this would probably be what we want
so the standing on reference
is the one that we want and
the uh
the result occupying oops
um is the one that we're we're trying to
set
right and then the entity
we don't actually need an entity like
this doesn't need an entity
it needs an entity id
right so i don't know why it's
actually taking that um it should just
be able to do that
right i think um you know
could be wrong but i think it doesn't
actually need an entity so
you know don't pass a pointer if an id
will do
is a pretty good rule of thumb
um you know just just my opinion
just my opinion
uh just because it means you can run the
code when you don't have a pointer yet
and you don't want to generate pointers
for things that don't need them
that might be the way to say it i don't
know anyway so assuming that we have one
of these entities here
uh if we just call transactional occupy
on it
um we should be good to go we
don't pass
results we pass region and then i think
we're good
right um
so now you know i can't hop into the
trees and so those transaction points
are set properly so i think that was
it um and and we're good
right uh so no no worries
so now what i want to do is like i said
i want to make those doors
uh and so i want oh
somebody's supposed to be there and
isn't
creepy that was useful
that was very useful
so we have some other things we're going
to want to do
here right so those points
are generating entities that are
standing these are the points the
talking
you step next to the thing and you talk
right
um and you can see that we can't go on
it anymore because
now those are actually getting
uh standing on traversibles which we
didn't actually want them to do
so we will need something that says no
you don't actually do that
that's not you don't actually want to
put an entity
there that occupies the space you need
to allow people to hop
onto that space right so that's
interesting
i just have i
i'm sorry i just happened to glance over
the chat and someone was like what is
this built on and someone said unity
[Laughter]
um it's it's built on nothing it's built
on top of windows
sorry it's a totally legitimate question
the only reason i was joking is because
it's funny to be this far into the
stream
where like you know most of what we do
is implement game engine stuff
and people are wondering what it's built
on a totally fair question because
i'm sure all the rest of the programming
streams besides john are probably built
on unity so that's you know
makes sense makes sense if you ask the
question it was just funny because i
just happened to look look over there
yeah maybe windows is maybe windows is
built on unity
right um
maybe maybe microsoft built i mean it
would explain why windows 10 is so
so freaking slow uh
if and and they're both c-sharp
disasters
right like unity and windows are both
filled with c-sharp garbage that doesn't
work
uh so you know there's that
anyway uh if we so if we look at what
happens here
there you know those those conversation
points you can see
it was this sort of thing right um they
add these collision volumes here
and so what i'm assuming happens is
we didn't have a way like in the room
generator code which is still kind of
crappy
because we haven't really tried to
generate much of interest
um we oh someone said
uh someone said you'd actually be
surprised how many are working on their
own engines games from scratch it's
pretty encouraging
um that'd be great yeah if there's lots
of people working on from scratch
engines on twitch that is awesome
because that is not
what it used to be like um and just more
engines equals more
better right now just just because i
don't think the engines we have are very
good
for for universal purposes you know
um you know what i'm saying
uh
like we need more engines we need more
engine programmers so we can have better
engines
it's just really that simple we just
need more engine programmers because we
need better engines the engines right
now are not what they need to be
you know
that's all oh uh and no
like of course windows api is being
rewritten in javascript
that's that's actually true right like
there's tons of javascript that's going
into windows now like for the start menu
and all that stuff
i think that's actually true but
anyway
anyway uh so what we want to do here is
just say look
when we create these things like this ad
conversation thing
i think what's happening is when we add
these groups
we look at the tiles and they they get
like
gen entity at traversable is called we
don't distinguish
uh right between ones that need it and
ones that don't
so in here i think what we want to do is
we want to do
something like this where you don't call
transactional occupy
if the entity creator
in question doesn't want it right and so
the problem that we're going to have
here is we've stripped the call that we
actually need
um for this like we we strip the
parameter we actually need
so in here there's a gen entity and if
we go to the gen entity
you can see it up here we we have like
the creator and we've got
information and stuff like that and what
we want to do is probably add
a bool here right where we say like was
this thing supposed to occupy the square
or not
like you know we want something like
uh occupy uh
trans or occupy traversable
right um and we set this to true or
false now
since most things will occupy their
traversables maybe we do the other way
around
like do not occupy
traversable um
and then what we would do is we would
just make sure that we set that
to true on the few things that don't
like take up a square
that are that are just like floating
right
um we could do that and uh
oh and we we already have that it's
actually right there
okay so so we're actually even one step
ahead of ourselves turns out we have
flags and we already have a flag for
that
so really what we need to do is
something like this
right that's what we want but like i
said we stripped the parameters so it's
not
on there so that's the problem that we
currently have um
did we use this
so we didn't so we knew we would need it
uh and we just
hadn't actually used it yet so i think
what we want to do
is look for you know where did we
actually um
where did we actually start setting up
these conversations
right so in here where we did this and
we do
like add conversation
right um that seems like what we would
want
uh
and the only thing that i'm confused
about is
that would explain one of them
this explains the one directly below the
entity
i don't understand where the one to the
right of the entity
is coming from because that's not
obvious to me here right
but but this this is the example right
so
in here if we were to say like okay
you know uh
this thing this conversation here
is is not you know
yeah this conversation here is not an
occupier i feel like that's all we would
need
the problem is just then you know we
stripped out where the flags would go
so when we actually call this here i
don't know if
maybe we want to
pass the flags i mean we could
right um that seems fine
uh
it's called gen flag sorry
uh and then whenever we do uh our flag
creation we would want to actually
uh pass whatever we think the flag
should be
so i want to say this stuff is all fine
um at the moment those should actually
be ones that are
you know that do what they do but in
here where we've got things where we're
actually placing
an entity so here we're doing pending
entity creator right we can just do
pending entity
flags and that should work
sorry gen flags
uh and now we should be able to
just hop around through things that that
have that set
and not through things that don't the
trees should not have that set
right because we pass zero for their
placement flags because they're just
getting spammed out into the world and
it's fine
uh and then like if we look in here the
idea is
these should now be open and they are i
guess
i don't know why like the there was one
being used up there so so this all looks
good now
conversation squares are working fine um
and so okay but yeah so see there what's
that about
like we just don't know what that is
like i have no idea what that is so we
should we should go find out like
who is getting placed there and why and
you can see there one here too
are those just orphans that were like
placed in there somehow that are not
right so
something's up and well i guess we could
see
so they can't be orphans because if they
were orphans they would have something
here
so so this is busted and it's not their
square because they're actually
correct so something's up with that and
it would be nice to know
like what was getting placed there
something's getting placed there
something we can't see
and it's erroneous right
um so that would be a nice bug to fix um
or just even just to find out
what is happening like what is getting
placed there even separate from fixing
it
at the moment um and what we'd like to
do here
is uh now that we've verified that all
this stuff is working okay
uh get to the thing that i actually
wanted to do which is just add a door
type like add a type of thing that's
just the door
and the the way that i wanted to add
doors to this uh is is
you know kind of complicated because i
need there to be
some way where you can
um where you can unlock the door
by using the states of other entities
right
so there's there's a couple ways you can
do doors
um one is that you can
one way you do doors is you just have a
way to like make the door go down
right and you have something that
triggers that
and it happens another way is you can
have the door
checked to see whether the criteria for
it going down has happened or not
and you know my first inclination is
usually to just have the to do it the
doorway like have the door check
but i think i want to channel uh
what small amount of of inner john blow
i have here
and say that that's probably the wrong
way to do it the reason
that uh i think that for game design
wise is because
if we think about it you know you may
want a lot of things that can make doors
unlock so so like if you have a door
and the thing you're supposed to do is x
to unlock the door
well you may want to add things that are
external to that like oh the player gets
a one-time use spell that unlocks
a door right if the door is sitting
around checking
and that's the way you know whether the
door is uh unlocked or not
you know what i mean that wouldn't work
because
now you don't have a way of just
triggering the door to unlock separately
so my thinking is that what we probably
need to do is make it so that doors just
are told to unlock and then they do and
then what we have is
anything all of the things that could
make that door unlock
um are are set up to
call that as opposed to having it look
the other way
right
so there all right
um so what i would like to do is just
add that
um and and i i want to do it sort of in
here right so so the idea is like that
would now be a door obviously i don't
remember
us having any door art at the moment so
probably what i will do for the time
being
is i will just use uh one of the
the walls but before i say that
i should look and make sure that's true
because i actually don't remember
um so like if we go in here to
the source directory for the
game art which is in here
um if we look there's like
there's just those three things right
so there's no door texture right now
um
we we will have to just ask for one uh
so
so yeah i don't know why i'm belaboring
that point it is exactly as i said
so what i'd like to do is create an
entity that's a door
type of entity um
and and have that go down now
i don't there is really no typing that
needs to happen here because a door is
literally just something that occupies a
transactional it's just a piece of
scenery we we don't really need it to be
uh anything special like we don't need a
new brain type for it or anything
because it's just something that will
get taken down
if it if it needs to be right so
um what i'm gonna do is i'm just gonna
try
literally just placing a wall
like entity that looks like a wall for
now
on top of the existing entity that's a
floor
and that's our door because until we get
some art for it
it doesn't matter
so if i go in here and
uh and and go to the gen entity code and
i just
make a like you know ad door
call i guess right i mean again this
this isn't
super complicated but you know that's
what it is and in fact
i can probably it looks like ad obstacle
is is basically what we want right
um
i mean that's that's it so probably i
can just do ad obstacle
and and that's our door
um so really all i need at that point is
just when we're doing our sort of room
generation
for dungeons and such uh
we would just need to make sure that we
add those so so actually
it seems like we're mostly set up for
this already
um and yeah
i guess it shouldn't be that shouldn't
be that bad
so let's take a look and see
what's actually happening here uh as far
as that's concerned
so here's the code for create dungeon
right
um and you can see like it putting the
little like snake in there
which we never really did the code to
add the extra pieces onto the snake now
and the new thing remember we you know
we used to have like little
pieces of snake we should do that at
some point
but uh yeah you can see us doing
stuff for
for other types of rooms whatever
and so the problem that we have here is
you can see here that we've got to
connect
um where we're connecting these rooms to
each other
that go along a path uh and then
like there's some some extra rooms that
live off of those
right and what we want to do is say that
this connection between these two rooms
has like a door in it
right um sometimes i mean it doesn't
have to
right so if we look at
the way that the
tu the way the connection works here
so when we do this we want to be able to
say that this room has
like a locking door on it and then
when the rooms get generated and the
connection gets placed between them
a door gets placed it onto that
separator right on the side of the room
you're coming from
because presumably doesn't lock or at
least most of the time
it doesn't uh like
when you go backwards right it doesn't
actually
need to lock you out most of the time
so if we look at the connection the
the rooms presumably both point to a gen
connection
uh which of course again can't get to
there we go um
so yeah i guess what i would say is so
so we should probably just have two
types of doors
uh two types of door flags or you know
whatever you want to call out here
you know when we generate these
connections we would just have like
door from a to b and dora from b
to a right and so
there's two squares there and we can
make doors
that lock from either side so you could
have a connection where you have to
complete the room on either side
in order to open but like so there's
there's a door on both sides
or we can have one where there's just a
door on one side if it's just like for
forward motion or something so depending
on how like the dungeon
that part of the dungeon is laid out
these could be set
right so and then when we actually
generate the room
um
i'm assuming um
[Music]
i'm assuming that this is relatively
yeah
so so you can see here like we go
through the connections
that are placed in here
and we we just
we can just handle the door like right
here so we look at like the connections
we've got
if we're supposed to have a door in this
particular location
then we just do this code kind of sucks
i mean obviously it's kind of crappy
it's entirely implicit meaning we loop
over each tile and then do all the
things we're gonna do for the tile so
this is this is just like garbage right
you wouldn't
do it this way um but you know
it happens right
a lot of stuff happened on the chat
today is that because there's so many
people viewing probably because there's
so many people doing
um anyway back to
our story so if i want to
i should be able to still flip stream
this in there and you know like
maybe we need to like improve this code
a bit and we'll do that
like as we go but for now we just want
to probably look and say
hey if this this particular tile
um and you can see here like this is the
thing that would tell us about the tile
if this particular tile is where the
door would be for one of these two
things
then we want to create that
door right now we don't know which door
we don't know which room we are so
right we want to see like which room we
are of
a or b because we don't need to generate
the door
for the other room it will generate its
own door
there right and so
i'm gonna probably say let's do this the
reverse
way around in terms of creating it
because it's just probably easier to do
that
like i'm gonna say like hey let's just
make this thing in fact like let's even
go one step further
and say like after we create this crap
um and we're down here and we're like
spamming out entities
like right before we do that let's loop
over the connections
from this room to the other rooms and
let's find out if we have any doors like
if
on door from a to b
um you know and we're door a
or con door from b to a
and word b right you know this this kind
of thing right
so what i want to say here is like all
right if there's a door from a
to b and we are room a
so so the the um
the con a is us right
um alternatively if there's a door
from b to a and we are b
in either case then we have a
responsibility
what did i miss that
yes i did
[Music]
right right
um so in that case where we have
a um
where we know we have a door and we know
that it's our door
then what we want to do is take the
volume of this thing
and intersect it with us so that we know
where we're gonna place this thing right
uh where this door should be or at least
somewhere where the door could be
so we would take the volume of the
connection
and the volume of the room and just do
the intersection um
so enter sex
let's say i'm sure we wrote that
right um
i really gotta update the four coder
stuff
okay so if i take the volume of the
connection
and the volume of the room and i
intersect those two
that will produce the location where the
door should go
um and then i just have to actually
create the door
and so for now i'm just gonna do add
obstacle
because i can and so in the same way
that i'm making like
uh the trees and stuff like here's
here's us placing a tree right so we
could just place
a door like this and all we have to do
is just call add obstacle
um i don't actually want it to be a tree
but i'm going to leave it as a tree
for now because hey that's fine i can
see that it's working
um and so i want to be able to place
this thing at this location
and so in order to do that i would need
to know like where this thing actually
is
and so like when we are placing entities
you can see in here uh we've we've got
the
the grid and the grid
helps us do our construction
so i want to
get like i want to get the
i i want to access the grid's actual
stuff like get this right
and so this is relative
so the
so you can kind of see like it would be
nice if there was one of these that was
sensible um and and
at the moment it looks like there isn't
right we don't have a get
like absolute location so
that's kind of annoying and
i think i'm just going to write one my
only question here
so so one of the things that's kind of
weird and i don't know that we
really said too much about it
but i just want to verify before i go
any further
down that route that these volumes are
actually
absolute space so
yeah the gen volume
and
yeah so these volumes are in absolute
space
i hope uh and then the connections are
too i think so it looks like that's all
good
so really uh this is all fine and the
only thing i'm saying is like so when i
do this intersection
right i need it to be i need to be able
to get like the tile
out of here that's like the actual tile
um
based on the offset so like you want a
get
tile abs right i want to be able to say
um something like this
so you when i pass a a gen v3
here i want to say that this is offset
uh by the min tile so basically this
p value here would be like p abs
and p ab p would be p
abs minus uh the min pile right
does that make sense um so that way
what would happen is what
i don't know what that is that doing
there that's interesting
um so
that's that's that's well i don't know
what that is
that's something so anyway uh if we
go and go to the an editor
get a generator traversal here uh what i
want to do
is just be able to say like look get me
where this thing's supposed to be
so whatever the door volume uh location
is
there should be like a min uh right on
that it doesn't matter which one it
should only be one wide so we'll just
grab them
in and we'll say hey uh get the the tile
here
uh the tile in question and
uh that should give me back one of those
edit tiles
and the edit tile would presumably let
me
create the thing that i actually need
right
and so how we get the
actual like placements
i'm not sure
how were these guys getting the
placement so
when they go in here they say gen room
tile query
pending
[Music]
grid region creator
asset ref
so it's edit tile contents
all right
so something like that
uh and presumably this just has what i
need
right so presumably it's just it's just
that
the traversable on that on that entity
um which there sort of has to
be
this should be cleaner
like because this is too much code
there's there's really no need for
this much garbage to be happening
um so we should probably fix that
uh anyway so what would happen now if i
close the game and rerun it is you know
nothing should be different so if i hop
down there because we never set like
none of those connections are set to
have a door
so in theory if i hop down there we'll
see nothing
because nobody should have run that code
and there shouldn't be anything in it
and then what i'll do is i'll pop over
and set that code and see
if we see any changes right so if this
is the
the area you can see there's there's no
doors anywhere
um and so now what we're hoping for is
we can turn on doors
by like in the world area like the
create dungeon
um if we want to set a door we can just
set one
so in here where we do the connect call
presumably we were smart enough to have
that return a connection
we were
so now we can basically say like okay
that connection door from
a to b is true um and then like you know
maybe our code just flames out and dies
which is entirely possible
but at least we'll know it's running
which would be good
um all right it didn't crash which is
not great because probably that means it
didn't run but you know
hope springs eternal it may just work
and
you know if it does it does don't look a
gift code in the mouth
is what i always say um
i don't actually always oh and there it
is
so so there's our door and
uh you know once we have a door created
the only thing we now need is something
that actually like unlocks the door
and i don't actually have
a super good idea about
what that would mean per se
i assume it means something like the
door just kind of like
sucks down into the floor or something
maybe um in other words like when when
like let you know i wanted to like hop
on a tile it unlocks the door or
something like that right
animation wise i'm not sure
what i actually want that to look like
but it's probably just it sinks into the
floor that seems like a zeldy
isaac-y sort of thing that would happen
maybe um
let's just say that that it was i don't
know
um so so you know that's probably what i
would say
is we'll just have it so that that you
know it sinks on into the floor maybe
that's what i'll do next time
um because that now we're now we're good
um and yeah we should be fine
so a bunch of stuff to do uh we'll take
questions now but
we're good
stock overflow says you must use smart
pointers the handmade hero code base has
no smart pointers how can this be
um so
so roughly what i would say
um about that is
you can imagine if you imagine like a
programmer's
life cycle um
you know we it looks something like like
the following
so you know no one's like
just a born knowing how to program
it's something that you learn and inside
your brain
you learn to program in
in very definitely in stages right
and the stages are pretty
uh consistent i think and so we won't
like i won't try to you know do them all
here
but at some point when you go through
these stages
you get to stage n and stage
n is i guess what i would call the
individual element thinking
right um
individual element thinking is when you
think of each specific piece of data
in your code as having its own lifetime
um so for example if you're going to
create
like in our code we have entities
you think about every entity
as getting like a new
or a malloc or you know the first time
you create it
and then you think of it having like a
an end point
that it's its own and that's where you
call like delete
or the garbage collector you know cleans
it up
or a smart pointer in this case
automatically deletes it because someone
else is owning it or whatever right
and these architectures tend to look um
like they have like raai style
um they have like you know
uh literally like thousands or
millions of new delete you know or
malloc
free uh they have
giant nests of pointers from things
to other things right
and this is just some place you get to
in your in your thinking about how uh
this is like with respect to
architecture
right
now a lot of people never move past this
point
sometimes they don't move past this
point because they never program in a
language that doesn't have a garbage
collector
if you're always in a language with a
garbage collector you probably don't
think about these things very much
and to the extent that you ever actually
will it will only be because you're
trying to do something performance
oriented
and you have to start pretending you're
actually managing your own memory even
though the garbage collector is
and most people who write games in
garbage collected languages have had to
do this
but if you're just doing things that are
not like performance critical in that
way
you wouldn't know you'd never have to
get past here
right um
someone on the on that's the twitch said
try catch and i'll put that in here as
well
so this is individual element thinking
and
it's it's you know it's something
everyone does i've
definitely had a period where i was
programming that in so i
i don't want to say that people who do
it are stupid or something because
everyone does it like like there's no
not doing it
i don't know anyone who ever
successfully avoided this stage of
thinking
the stage is stupid meaning the code you
write will be stupid
but you are not stupid because everyone
does this
at some point the key is you have to get
to n plus one at some point
which is group thinking right
and group element thinking stages this
tends to be
like large collections um
created uh destroyed at
the same time you know uh almost no
uh you you very very few
uh new delete malloc free
um a heavy
use of scratch space
um typically like hashes and reuse
show up in here a lot
so i when you're talking about
making this jump when you make this jump
from n to n plus one so smart pointers
live here
right so at the stage when you're doing
when you're still stuck thinking about
individual pieces all having their own
lifetimes
the problem that you run into is that
there's so
many of these things i mean there's
literally millions or even
billions of them in a program
if you were to manually always be
allocating and freeing all these things
individually
you can see why people say well you've
got to use smart pointers because
otherwise you have to remember to always
in two places you declare the pointer
and then in the destructor you have to
add a delete manually
you can see why why people think in
their head
smart pointer makes sense here because
it's a way of typing something
i can just look at one line that's the
declaration of the pointer and know that
it's going to get automatically freed
right
now the problem with this is you're
really just patching over a flaw in your
architecture
if two things are inextricably linked
such that you
have one get automatically freed when
the other one is freed
in all but the very very rarest of
circumstances what that means is those
things should actually have a combined
lifetime
and so what should actually happen is
you should have just had
one large pool that
all of those things got created in that
is just streaming into that pool
so that you never have to do that the
pool gets freed together
so you don't need to have this rat's
nest of pointers
that you crawl through to make sure you
eliminated everything
so that's what we do in handmade hero we
just have pools that get freed at the
right time
and everything that goes together goes
in the pool
so i never have to sit around running
around
grabbing pointer you know which is what
a smart smart pointer chains that's what
they do
one person gets freed across the next
person gets free calls the next person
gets free
right it's extremely inefficient
and so you're just wasting the user's
time by
dynamically discovering the scope of a
group
that you should have already known right
um so basically
when you move from here to here smart
pointers become irrelevant you really
don't need them anymore
right because you just don't have
ownership
concerns like the kind that you have
here right
um you could say uh owner
ownership is a constant concern
uh and mental overhead right whereas
here like
ownership is obvious
and you know uh trivial
in 99 of cases right
um so so basically like the thing to
understand here is just that
that all of the advice you see online
pretty much
is is for people thinking at this level
which is not where you want to be
like you you're going to have to go
through it at some point to understand
what's going on but your goal
is to go from here to here so
advice like use smart pointers or um
the rust borrow checker like all that
stuff
those are for people who are still not
very good at programming right there's
they're in a stage of architecture
that is very limited and
not appropriate for modern
high-performance well-architected code
it's an
old way of thinking that just still is
very prominent and you're just seeing
advice from that
just the goal is to move move on right
so don't waste a lot of time learning
all of this crap
you will have to go through this stage
because everyone does eventually
but the goal is to get out of it as fast
as you can because 100
of all code written in this style sucks
there is no such thing as a good piece
of code that has
these ideas in it because they are
inherently inefficient
bug buggy and over architected right
they're just not good right
so so this is what you're looking at and
so it's hard to discern when you see
advice like this
you're like where is it coming from and
what does it mean that's what it means
it means the people
are in this land and this is where they
live and
you know until they move from end to end
plus one
they're going to constantly be thinking
things like raii or smart pointers are
good but they're just not they're just
lousy architecture and when you move
past them you
notice immediately you're like oh wow
like actually all of that crap
that i used to have to spend time
dealing with is just gone now
does that help
the good of having to learn the h
handmade hero code base
is that the use of internal
impose the inability of use the stl as
it is there to define improve accomplish
[Laughter]
awesome okay
sun coder says n plus 2 is when you've
reached guru's stage after 30 years and
your code finally looks as simple as
written by someone at n minus 3 but is
free of all the bs
you're absolutely right like basically
my code
now looks a lot like my code
from 20 years ago minus a few
very critical stupid things right but
it's
hard to get there that's why i say like
you know i try not to
be too derogatory to people who talk
about these things
because it was me right
the temptation is once you know that
something is stupid
to say that someone who does it is
stupid but it's important to remember
that you were all so stupid
right so
you know stupid is as stupid as right so
like i've done all this stuff
and so i know that you go through that
stage
um so the so i can't say like
don't do this it's stupid because
actually
everyone will do this at some point what
i'm trying to say
is that like look it's a phase we go
through
it's not a good idea but and so the goal
is just to move
past it as soon as your brain is capable
of grappling with what's
actually going on right
you can think of a similar thing is like
it's like the
scope of your thinking has enlarged so
at this point your brain is
only capable of focusing on like a very
small piece of code
so obviously it has to think in terms of
things like rai
or pointer nests because you can only
think of like this
little piece it's just it's one of the
also reasons i think people like oop
is because it allows you to think very
small
you're just thinking about a little
small piece and not how the whole
program
works right and as you can get
even just a little bit larger so maybe
you're not at like the whole
system yet but you're a little bit
larger and now you're thinking of
systems of of the in the code
then you can move out to like oh
actually these things
flow to and bind together right
and when your brain can get there then
you can just throw all this away because
now you never need it anymore
right and you're you're up to here right
hmm
if you look at the old id code
wolfenstein 3d doom quake
there they already think of large groups
when it comes to memory or at least they
allocate just once and then go with it
why did we go backwards is what i was
taught at university from professors who
around the doom time
what happened um
i mean i guess what i would say is that
like
it's kind of an unfair comparison i mean
john carmack is like one of the
best programmers that's ever lived
and like your professor at university
like definitely isn't
right so comparing what
the person who wrote doom
knows about how to structure code
uh to somebody who's probably never even
shipped a commercial piece of software
which is like what most professors
are i mean is not
is not fair to the professor right
because this kind of thinking is about
production code it's not about computer
science quote unquote it has nothing to
do with the halting problem or whether
the lambda calculus is like a good
representation for like
proving something about computability
right it's not computer science
it's computer it's software engineering
right
and professors generally aren't
engineers
so uh the other problem is unfortunately
these days like language designers also
are very rarely engineers like they're
rarely people who ship lots of
production quality code and have like
really studied the problem sometimes
they are but oftentimes they're not
and so i think the problem is just like
yeah like that's not what happens it's
not like just because john carmack
knew something everyone knew it and
accepted it as true
right that's not what happens
6289 said nowadays engineers aren't
engineers
you're right yes
so uh uh joe ppp
there uh i mean i don't know how much
more vocal i can be
i say this all the time on this channel
and in my videos
and on twitter in the discord
um the the truth of the matter
i think is that you know people are just
saying stuff and we don't have metrics
to measure so you know it's hard to
prove that things are right or wrong
right but we're loud it's just
people choose not to do this they choose
to think that you know these other
methods are better so you know
that's that's on them i can't force
people to program a certain way
and also i don't really care if they do
or don't i mean it doesn't affect my
code
so
does this stuff apply to game engine
programming only or also
corporate logistics it's it's true for
all code it has nothing to do with the
type of code you're writing
your code is always better if you think
about things in terms of groups
that work together as opposed to
thinking in terms of pigeonhole elements
right
so
so yeah and i i'm not sure about the nn
plus one like series thing
like i don't know if it's possible to
teach someone
in a way that makes them skip and
altogether
it it might just not be right it might
be that you
be like i said it's a scope issue like
your brain has to start thinking
of the fundamental unit as not being
little micro
allocations right because the individual
element thinking is about
microallocations
right it's about lots of little tiny
things that get allocated and deleted
that all have dependencies on each other
and the benefit of that is that your
brain
only has to think about the one tiny
thing when it writes it
right and that's why you see
like what i would sort of call like
there's there's a separate thing in
stage and there's like this paranoia
too it's like it's like
a person in a room with a tin foil hat
where they're trying to guard
against every possible thing that could
happen to this type at any time
and people think they're doing
good programming when they do that but
it's
actually the opposite if you are trying
to prevent errors
that by the structure of your
architecture cannot happen
you are literally creating worse code
code only should do the minimal number
of things that it has to do to do the
job
anything else is just like ruining the
environment
right you are literally just expending
entropy
into the environment to melt the ice
caps that's all you're doing
right there is nothing clean
about code with 57 000 try catch
statements
and 50 million objects just to open a
file
right it's actually terrible and and
never should be done
because it's a tremendous amount of cpu
codes spent to do
absolutely nothing and the reason that
people do that is because
when you have this pigeonhole view and
you're just
you can only program or think about this
tiny little thing like
all you can do is write a file handle
that's the only thing
that you're working on and you refuse to
consider the rest of the system at all
what else can you do if if your
programming problem is
by definition that that you cannot
work on anything larger than
paranoia of course sets in because
anything could be true now
you have no preconditions no post
conditions you don't even have
during conditions you don't even know
that the things that you're calling they
might throw exceptions they might do
whatever right
and so when you when you start doing
that
what you've basically decided to do is
spend almost 100
of your time not actually working on the
problem you were paid to solve
and rather spend 100 of your time
solving problems you don't actually have
and creating problems for the people
upstream
because now all of this like
uncertainty is injected into the system
and so so it's not that if you are if
you are doing this kind of architecture
it's not that rai isn't necessary it
actually
is because you've actually made very bad
decisions about how to structure your
code
such that now you really could fail at
any time because you're doing
a million allocations any one of them
could fail
if instead you had just allocated as a
block
now you never need any of that error
handling because either it succeeded or
it failed
once and now you don't need to worry
about all these little micro allocations
right if i allocate a block
that stores a complete data structure in
all the pieces
i only have one thing to check when i
start did i get it or didn't i
if instead i allocate each little
individual piece and wire them all
together
every single allocation is a failure
point
so now it's not paranoia to go i need
all these try except blocks and
exceptions
like no that's true now because you've
chosen a very poor way to structure your
code so now you
created all of these problems that you
must now solve
right
so the key is stop thinking that way
instead of thinking i have to create
a million little tiny things that
conspire to produce a result
start thinking about what are the
minimal
number of resource uh requests i can
issue
to do the entire thing i need to do
and once you do that you find that
everything actually becomes mostly
trivial
for all this stuff right
so i can i can tell you a simple example
of a step from n to n plus one that
so when i was when i did the first
version of the character animation
system at rad
i i still was at stage at
and when i did the second edition i
moved to n plus one
and the small step i took at that time
the first step was going hey if i have
something
like a character that has a certain
number of
bones and a certain number of meshes
right
what i used to do is i used to like new
a character
and then i would knew an array of bones
and i would knew an array of meshes and
then the meshes would
array vertices right all i did
in that first step was i just said oh
actually when i create a character i
made this little thing that allowed me
to say
here's all the memory that i need i need
this many meshes this many bones this
many that this made this for the
character
and i just had a little utility function
uh facility struct i wrote that allowed
me to like say here's the stuff i need
go and it would then try to allocate
that entire block of memory that would
be needed for the whole thing
and it would parcel it out so that it
would like set the pointers properly
automatically for me
that changed five six seven
eight failure points into one failure
point which is way more reliable
right just that one step makes it eight
times less likely that your code will
fail
that you have a bug somewhere right
and so it's just a case of just like see
just start to start wherever you can
anything you can do in your code base to
to do
less uh to make less
calls or operations that can fail
right just try to start collapsing them
together
and and eventually right you get to the
point where you've got
like the typical thing that me and john
blow do now
and and i think dice does this too so
even like the ea games do this
is every frame you just have an arena
for that frame of memory
and anything that's specific to the
frame just goes in there
this eliminates literally like
thousands to hundreds of thousands of
allocations that happen
in the kinds of systems that don't think
this way just that one thing
and it removes almost all possible
failure points
because in general you can put a bound
on that number
and know that like as long as you can
exceed that arena with a certain amount
of memory you'll always be fine
so you can even base you can basically
say like look this is just fine now we
literally got rid of all those failure
points
whereas if each of those things had been
a new any single one of them could
technically fail
right
and because you don't even really know
right you have no way of even guessing
how much memory that
thing requires because you you have no
way to even measure it but once you
group them together it's trivial to say
okay we've
we've looked at the peak or whatever and
we just have it right
and off we go steps i take now that are
past that are i just design out the
failure entirely
so what i do is i take arenas now and i
stream into them and if they
can't get more memory to grow when they
need to all the code is usually
written to handle when something comes
back
it just produces a stub rather than a
real one
and all the code still works so that's
the way i do those things now
and they literally can't fail even if
you run out of memory in the middle of
something that you don't even know what
the size should be
it still just works in the sense that it
doesn't crash
it just can't draw like the rest of the
things
you know what i mean
i've been concerned at all with secure
coding concepts to cover undefined
behavior with people looking to exploit
it um
so i mean that's a separate thing i'm
talking about
failure cases that are natural right
so i'm not even talking about
adversarial failure
right adversarial
failure is completely different that's
like hardening
however as with all things
it is much easier to harden code written
in the grouped way than it is to harden
code in the individual way
because again if every single thing you
calls if every single thing you do
allocates does a new allocation
it's very hard to make any statements
about
bounds or where things are or when they
come in
to existence or not it's very hard to
keep that safe
because it's just a sprawling mess of
pointers that point everywhere
right whereas if everything uses ids
in an arena it's way harder for an
adversary to crack in there
and it's way easier for me if i have to
go harden it for some reason because
like it's something that's going to get
exposed to a net area or whatever
to work with so i would say n plus one
makes it way easier to harden
as well but i'm not talking about that
right now
i'm strictly talking about just failures
that happen
normally right so failures that happen
without an adversary
and just to be clear like usually what i
do is i use growable arenas so i don't
allocate them up front
they're like the ones in handmade hero
now they just grow as necessary
so basically like you you just keep
pushing onto the end of the arena
and you have two choices for how you
want to handle your failures
the way i like to handle failures is i
just like
if you fail to push something you just
get a stub back
right because i don't i don't want to
have to check
those for global arenas so you just get
a stub back
that's all zeroed right
and then the uh
when you actually run through your
performance
what you usually want to do then is each
arena
has an initial allocation size that you
usually tune
to try and make it so that it doesn't
have to really do growing very often
right because time you've got this
system in place
you get another huge bonus which is
allocation is like
very cheap it's like one check and one
ad
to like move the thing forward right so
you can also get a huge speed boost by
then just looking and saying how big
should these arenas be in general
and setting their initial sizes to that
because then you also don't
hit the actual allocator almost ever
right
let's say i want to push some dynamic
amount of data and i run out of space
the calling code expects n bytes and
we'll write n bytes but i don't have n
bytes
how do you handle this case in that
style uh you've got two choices
so one choice is that you actually write
your code to look at what comes back and
handle it right
and that's still the end class way
i usually do that though and the reason
for that is because
it's usually actually not that hard to
do right
um i i tend to check those things anyway
but
you can decide not to do that what you
can do if you'd like
is you can just return a ring mapping
so similar to what happens in when you
call map
on linux where it just maps the same 4k
page repeated like forever
right so then you can just return a
pointer to that page and
people can read and write to it for the
rest of time
and they'll never crash but they also
didn't actually do anything
right
so so that's a good option if you
literally like if you really just want
to go look
i want to handle any failure cases here
but i also don't want to
introduce any overhead into the code or
possible mistakes for
because a lot of people are going to be
using variable size things
i don't want them to have to test
anything
i that almost never happens it's really
rare because most things aren't variably
sized so that's why i usually just
return a stub
that you write to but if it's really
truly variably sized
right you can just return a repeat
mapped page
which is this which is a stub for
arbitrary sizes
right so you can do that if you want
so
so the way that i do stub stuff is i use
what i call zero as initialization
so it's like r-a-i-i but good uh
zero's initialization just means that
memory is zero by default
which is true anyway any member you get
from the operating system is zero by
default you have to be like on an
embedded system or something before
that's not true
but for security concerns on windows mac
linux whatever the memory you get back
is zero
so the way that i handle stubs is all
code is written so that zero is the
default case
which means that you can always return a
stub which is just a block of zeros
so you just have a stub in memory that's
a block of zeros and anytime something
fails you just return that one
instead then when the person actually
reads to it
or reads from it or writes from it it
just
doesn't do anything and then at the end
you just clear it
right at the end of the frame you just
clear it or every time you're going to
go hand it out again you clear it
right
is a repeat map page an os thing or is
it something custom
it's it's an os thing i'm not sure what
you mean by that but basically
when you um when you do
uh memory mapping
you can choose to map the same
4k backing page to many parts of memory
so let's say you're going to do
allocations and
for some reason you decide you just
don't want the code
to ever ask whether it actually got
the memory or not right which again i
don't recommend like i don't do this
but let's say you wanted to like you
were like i want subs for
everything even
arbitrary size stuff then what you do
is you say okay i'm going to
i'm going to at the start of the program
allocate one 4k page
that i use is my stub page and then i'm
going to call like map view of file
a freaking billion times to just map
like a gigabyte of address range all to
that one 4k page
right
have i read the paper fast efficient
fixed size memory pool
no loops and no overhead by ken wright
uh
no i haven't i i've never heard of that
no the the code doesn't check to see if
the struct is a stub
it just assumes that the struct is
something you can use and uses it
right
i do the same thing for like zero
handles now
so like for example if you call get
entity with the id of zero
these days i don't return no i just
return
a all zero entity and then everyone just
uses that
that's just what i do right
i just find that it removes so much
error handling and just kind of works
pretty much so that's just better you
just lose a lot of your handling code
it's it's nice so so i highly recommend
zii
and stubs it simplifies things
tremendously
um handmade hero doesn't use them very
much because
it's sort of something that i've only
developed in the past couple years
but you know i highly recommend it now
if i was doing handmade hero today we
would absolutely be
zii and uh and stubs everywhere
i in handmade here we still are to a
certain extent
but not as much as we could be right
someone's asked about this paper they
posted a link to
[Music]
um
i i mean i can't really read a paper
fast like and have an opinion about it
on stream right i've got to think about
it a little bit but
i mean i guess i'm not sure
i don't think i quite
see
uh honestly to be completely honest i
have no idea what the heck this thing is
supposed to be
this doesn't
what what is this supposed to be
this is literally like we literally have
this exact thing in handmade hero in a
bunch of places you wouldn't write a
paper about it
it's just a free list
what does this propose to do i have no
idea like i can't tell
i can't even tell what this paper is
claiming to have done
i mean this is literally just a free
list
it's everywhere in handmade hero like
did they wrote a paper about a free list
is that really what i'm looking at here
can someone confirm or deny that this is
literally someone wrote an entire paper
about a free list which is something
we've known about since like 1970.
how is this a paper the fact that
someone thought this was a paper
is absolutely mind-boggling to me unless
when i go read it more closely
there's something else in there but this
is absurd that in 2012
professors at a university would think
this was a paper
are they nuts like have they ever even
programmed
this that's that's nuts if it's actually
what i think it is
that you would write a paper in 2012
thinking that this was something that
everyone did not already know
i i i mean i have no i have no
i i i can't i don't even i can't even
believe what i'm looking at
i so yeah i have no opinion on that
paper other than i'm horrified that that
was a paper
but
i i just don't know
i mean maybe just no one ever publishes
a free list
in the section on background unrelated
work they say like
it's a modification whereby loops and
initialization overheads are removed
but like there's no initialization
overhead in a free list you set the
initial count to zero and the free list
pointer to zero that's it
that's the whole thing and they're
already zero if you're zii so you don't
even set them
like like i don't know what they're
talking about this is very strange
right like that does not make any sense
to me i don't know how this is a paper
presumably it's a paper and something
that nobody reviews
but i don't know
am i familiar with richard fabian's data
oriented design book he's an advocate of
laying out data in normalized form
representing relationships between data
season tables
um i am not familiar with
that book but i do use that form
i wouldn't necessarily use the phrase
normalized form that's a very specific
thing if he really means normalized form
i probably disagree with that because
that's
rarely what you actually want but
the idea that you use an id
to refer to tables of data
rather than having pointers in the data
that point directly to somethings
is something that is valuable to do it's
just
not universally the case meaning you
it's it's one technique out of a few you
should know
so i have not read that book i don't
know anything about richard fabian or
who that even is
but i i will say that
using a tabular form with ids
which are similar to how sort of a
database would work
is a good idea that you should know
about and should have familiarity with
for sure
and to be fair like there's nothing
wrong with publishing a paper about
something obvious that everyone knows
but you should probably say that like if
you publish a paper in 2012
about a free list and you don't say hey
this is something everyone does
it's a free list and we just wanted to
write down that it's a free list
so that you could know how a free list
works
totally fine but like we have developed
this awesome no
loops no overhead new allocator that's
perfect for real-time applications that
removes a bunch of problems from earlier
techniques like no you didn't
maybe you're ignorant of what people are
doing but you know
that's a bad you should be if your job
is in academia
like one of the things you should do is
find out what the heck people already
know
like if you're not doing that what are
you spending your time on right
a a production programmer has a good
excuse
to not know how something is done
because it's not their job to be aware
of what's going on in the industry
in terms of knowledge but an academic's
job
is to know what the knowledge is in
their interest that's all they do
right they're supposed to survey the
knowledge and find out what needs to be
advanced
so you know if you're writing a paper
about a free list
in 2012 you have an issue that you
should probably address
right
and uncountable yeah that's the part i
was reading the on the other hand the
technical study is not novel business
modification of existing technique
it's it's not a modification these days
it is an existing technique
like it's exactly like we literally have
this in handmade hero
i also want to say it looks like they
didn't quite do it as well
um i i'd have to actually really go read
it now
but it looks like they actually screwed
up one part of it
right um
no no no it's okay it's the same as
hammer here right it's exact same
standard hero it goes
if we have one left we use it
um you know in the initial sort of
stepping through otherwise we push it
off we pull it off the freak
it's ex like you can literally find
exactly the code here
in handmade here it's just how you
implement it's how everyone's always
done
free lists as far as i know like i guess
there was a way where people
built the free list by initializing
things
um published and not the other way
we have them both in handmade heroes
sometimes i like to string the pointers
first
if i want to simplify if i want to
reduce the checking in the code
um so i think we've done it both ways on
handmade hero
maybe no one ever published the fact
that you don't have to do that
like they only published one of the ways
i don't know which is crazy but that
might be true
somehow i doubt it
could explain about ecc memory not
really because i don't know anything
about ecc memory
basically the only thing that
i know about ecc memory it stands for
error correcting codes i believe right
is that because memory can have errors
meaning it's not perfect like you can't
just assume
that the memory store is what you put in
there exactly
you can have interference or just random
failures and when you get up to having
you know a terabyte of memory or
something like that
like some servers do these days
you will get some random bit errors
potentially
so the idea behind ecc memory the only
thing i know about it is they're just
like look
we use some extra it's like less
efficient or more expensive
um or both we
store some extra information with every
row of memory or something you know at
some granularity
so that we can detect when there's an
error and potentially recover
right um that's all i know about ecc
memory
i really don't know how they implement
it i don't know what they use
um i don't even know if ecc memory
actually
implies anything particular it may just
be a term that you use
anytime you're talking about memory that
does
some kind of error checking in recovery
and it may be that different
manufacturers have different ones i
really don't know
but that's what it does it's trying to
make it
less likely that you have a random bit
failure
because when you get up to very large
amounts of memory
that becomes a very real possibility
right
um you know if your failure chance was
one in a million
for every megabyte of memory back when
computers only had
a few megabytes of memory it's not that
likely
when you now have a terabyte of memory
it's a guarantee
right if it's one in a million um you
definitely will
right so you know
i that's that's what ecc is
and i don't know how sophisticated they
are now like i don't know how good the
error checking actually is
i think originally it could handle like
one error like if one bit got set to the
wrong value
it could the error correcting code could
could probably repair that one bit
right um
i don't know if it can do anything else
people in chatter saying can correct one
bit flip and detect
a two-bit flip so
so maybe that's it i don't know like i
said i don't really know
and handmade hero do you align the
elements you put into the arena someone
told me that nowadays on desktops the
alignment for read write is not as
important but it is probably better to
get as many things into a cache line as
possible
um yes so i don't remember exactly what
we do but we don't do much alignment
in the arenas normally no and
what the someone told you is correct for
desktop cpus especially x64 cpus
alignment doesn't matter very much the
only
particularly nasty thing that can happen
is if you're trying to gather things
that happen across cache lines
um so like it behooves you to maybe
allocate on at least four byte
granularity
so you don't cross cache lines
unnecessarily and you definitely don't
want to cross page boundaries
so you don't want to straddle a 4k page
boundary if you can't avoid it
you just pay penalties when you do those
gathers so if you're just four byte
aligned
or eight byte aligned you are totally
good to go
um if you're not if you're literally
just bite aligned
um which is which is not aligned you
may get some issues it's not safe to say
you never will
um you can actually get a penalty if you
try to gather
across a 4k page boundary um
it can be an issue now it's important to
note that
issue means you know a few dozen cycles
of stall so at the end of the day if
it's just an entity
and you only read you know you're just
going to read like one field out of one
entity
will occasionally straddle the cash line
so every
i don't know how many like every 30
entities you have one field that
straddles the cash
that straddles the uh page boundary
you're probably still fine
honestly right you're probably still
fine because
you know you're paying the penalties so
infrequently
that you probably just don't care and
like the someone told you
fitting more things into the cash is
always good so using less memory is its
own benefit
so again for all you know the
space you saved by not doing any
additional padding for alignment
may have solved that problem right
normally i don't tend to do that anyway
though
because look anything we do
struct wise is the structs are usually
going to be four or eight bite
uh granular anyway so i would typically
put
entities in their own arena at some
point anyway
or you know stuff like that so it
usually just doesn't matter because
they're
automatically aligned you know what i
mean
can hyper threading cause false sharing
i don't see how it could no
hyper threading is on the same core so
two hyper threads
that both need to access a cache line
are using the same
l1 cache line so so i don't think you
have
if you if you hyper thread
two thread two hyper threads on the same
core i don't think can have a false
sharing
uh penalty because
it's the same l1 cache right
all right my voice is getting tired so
we're done we're done
uh and infinim one last thing someone
was asking if i had a back problem
sitting all day or just buy expensive
chair and problems go away uh no so i
would say don't sit all day get up and
move around
every hour or so uh but the other thing
i say is i don't have an expensive chair
i've recommended the chair that i have a
couple times before
uh i love them and they're cheap um it's
my
favorite chair um
let me close this down here
uh i use
the space chair
um whatever
uh amazon
i love just what is like
it's so weird right like
yeah uh anyway so
i i use the space
chairs
it's this thing um
so like super not expensive
um i love these things they're way
better like i don't like the fancy
chairs like the herman miller
aeron chair or whatever i
hate those i can't sit in those for
hardly any time i like a firm base
and a tight like a back that's that's
fairly
you know hard i like to be like kept
fairly rigid in the chair so i just i
don't like
um yeah any of that and
yeah these are these are not my because
i don't use this so i just get to see
what other people have searched for
and what it's based on so like i just
searched for a chair so now it's just
giving me chair related
right
ah google i hate i hate that company
all right um
so i think we're i think we're good uh
i think we are we are good we are good
to go
um so thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if
you would like to follow along with
series you can always pre-order the game
on handmadehero.org
it comes with the source code if you
would like to play around with it
that's it for today i'll be back here
next weekend when i will add the ability
to unlock doors to the game
um which will start to add actual
gameplay to the game which is terrifying
because i don't like designing games
but uh what are you going to do there's
nothing left to do
so that's what we're doing i'll see you
folks back here for that until
then have fun programming and i will see
y'all
on the internet take it easy everybody