alrighty hello everyone and welcome to
the handmade hero live stream where we
code a complete game you know i'll be
honest i thought we was gonna take us
longer to do asynchronous texture
uploads we ended up doing it in two days
and most of the reason it wasn't done in
one day was just because we never set
the flag to actually tell it to download
the textures so that was incredibly
quick but there is one thing i wanted to
note so before we get started today is
day 2 45 i'll simply say if you're going
to be flowing along today's coding
unpacked day 244 so skirt source code
into a directory if you pre-order the
game on hammer here or when you download
that you want to do 244 that's what i'm
starting with today but i wanted to
mention something which is that somebody
asked about whether pixel buffer objects
would be useful for asynchronous texture
downloads and I wasn't really sure why
they would be and so I went double
checked about why you might use those in
that context and ice eventually figured
out why what I think might be the reason
why you would associate them with
texture downloads even though they
really have nothing to do with texture
downloads per se and that is I will draw
this on the board quickly
so here's day to 45p BOS so pixel that
for optics and OpenGL are something that
I don't use very often they're they're
kind of old they've been around like
actually very long time they're not a
new feature but there's still
potentially relevant feature and here is
what essentially I would think you would
do with them if you were trying to do
fast texter downloading and you were
going to use them for something so
here's what actually has to happen and
I'm going to draw a diagram that's a
little more complicated than what we've
been drawing before so you know we've
been drawing GPU memory so here's GPU
memory this here is what i call GPU
visible memory what I'm sorry what I'm
going to call it not what I cuss like I
made up that word and here is the CPU
memory okay and these are actually this
is actually all cpu memory so this is
main memory in the machine but the main
memory and machine is not necessarily
all the same and the reason that the
memory in this in the machine is now the
same is because certain parts of the
memory in the machine may or may not be
accessible by the GPU over the pci bus
and some of it might be now the reason
for this is because the GPU when it
accesses things over the pci bus now go
all the way back to a meter when we
first started talking about memory
remember there's virtual addresses and
physical addresses
right now what are these well virtual
addresses are the addresses that we
actually think about and use all the
time right that's in our code when we
say malik when we say this is a pointer
and we look at the value of that pointer
to the bugger we're looking at a virtual
address that is not actually the
physical bite in actual ram that we're
reading so byte 0 a pointer or the value
of zero in our world is an invalid
pointer and it false if you read from it
right a value of zero in physical
addressing might just be the first bite
right these things are not related so
like we know and we covered many times
so go back and watch it if you're not
comfortable with this virtual addresses
get translated to physical addresses in
the CPU itself the CPU has something
called a TLB this is a translation
lookaside tickets look aside buffer and
what this is is the thing that
translates virtual addresses into
physical addresses so when your program
says I want to access this bite it's
thinking in its virtual address space
the CPU actually looks in the
translation lookaside buffer and says
what is the actual physical address for
this thing and the TLB is like a cash
for addresses right now if it's not in
the TLB it's going to look up to the
actual address translation tables right
it's going to look up to the actual
tables in the operating system that have
set up for the whole translation and
this is a slower process but most of the
time it's hitting that translation
lookaside buffer and you're just
figuring out with the phys lab in you're
going get it ok we're not going to
recover all of this because we talked
about this a long time ago and handmade
hero we're not going to talk about that
instead all I'm trying to point out is
the GPU doesn't have access to any of
that the translation lookaside buffer
and all the other stuff that's used to
translate virtual addresses into
physical addresses is not present on the
GPU its present on the cpu and so when
the GPU wants to access a memory that's
in main system memory because it's
trying to read like
example our texture data out of it to
bring it down to the card so that it can
store it it's just trying to fetch it it
has to use a physical address and what
that means is that while this is going
on while it's grabbing texture data if
here's a big chunk of texture data it
can't be something that's being
virtually addressed somewhere by the CPU
in a way that could move around right
because remember one of the big things
about virtual addressing is we don't
even know if our memories resonant the
operating system could take our memory
and page it out to disk and just leave
it there and then only when we go to
accesses again and cause a page fault
it'll go oh wait he was axing that
memory I put that memory on the disk I'm
gonna go get it and I'll put it back
here and now we're good right or even if
it doesn't choose to do that it could
rearrange the memory in physical space
if it wanted to for some reason and just
swap where our virtual pages were
pointing to in virtual space right
because all we know is our virtualize do
we have no idea what the physical
address is underneath so what that means
is during the operation during the
transfer of the texture that whole time
the texture has to be in memory that's
visible to the GPU which means it has to
be in physical right memory it can't be
paged out to disk or something because
GPU and access in the disk ask me in
physical memory and it has to be locked
down meaning the operating system has to
know that it's in the middle of a
transfer and it could not decide to
evict that page or pages of memory from
physical memory into virtual storage
memory on disk because that would
immediately ruin the transfer and the
GPU would get garbage so what does that
mean to us in practice well what it
means to us in practice is that if we
have a call like GL text image right and
we pass a pointer to some texture memory
like we did and we say here is the
texture memory we want you to transfer
it well what it's going to have to do is
going to take it from our texture memory
right because this is our virtual
addressing pointer that we're passing
here that memory was allocated by us
right it has no it has none of the
criteria that the GPU might require the
operating system has not been told that
it was locked it is not necessarily in a
range of memory that's accessible to the
GPU if there are range restrictions on
what part of the physical act memory it
can access like maybe can only access
the low four gigabytes of 16 gigabytes
of memory right could be altered it
could be aligned wrong maybe maybe GPU
access memory has to be aligned on page
boundaries so maybe the pointer has to
be out of the page memory who knows
there's all sorts of things that could
be true none of that's true about our
pointer necessarily so what the driver
has to do first is copy it from the
pointer where we loaded it into CPU
memory not transfer GV just just a copy
just a literally a mem copy into some
region of its driver controlled GPU
memory that's set up for the GPU to read
it and then it copies it across the bus
so when the person was asking about
texture downloads being optimized by
pixel buffer objects and where we use
them I believe and I'm not a GP you guys
so again you know take my take my ex
nice with a grain of salt they're
roughly correct I suspect however I am
NOT a grep GPU expert in so there's
probably details that are not quite
bright and these things change every
year is the other thing but anyway so
the answer is pixel buffer objects don't
help you do texture transfers to the GPU
at all they are completely unrelated and
would not optimize the GPU transfer at
all but what they would optimize is this
copy because if you were to use a pixel
buffer object but a pixel buff Roberts's
is a piece of GPU memory that you can
lock and right into so if you were
worried about the cost of copying the
texture in the download from the cpu
memory to the other part of CPU memory
which is required for the texture
download then the pixel buffer object
would help you so if you find that you
need to further optimize your texture
transfers it could be the case if you're
stripping them if you're out stripping
memory bandwidth CPU memory bandwidth
not
the pci bus bandwidth but cpu memory
bandwidth is becoming a bottleneck for
you then that absolutely could be a time
when pixel buffer objects could help you
potentially if that is what your problem
is right so they're never going to
accelerate this part of the process but
this is only one part of the process and
this process part of the process over
here they could help you with
potentially now again that depends on
the card it depends on the driver
defense of the vendor depends of the
operating system all these are the
things whether that really can help you
or not whether the pixel buffer actually
is better or not blah blah blah blah
blah right but the point is that is
where they could come in so I wanted to
clarify that from yesterday because I
didn't really know when the person has
question I was like I don't really know
what those would do for you but that's
something that I believe they could do
for you and so you know that if that's a
situation that you found yourself in
that might be something to examine and
we could implement that relatively easy
on him a hero what we would do is we
would create one pixel buffer object
probably actually a pair I'm guessing of
pixel buffer objects for each of our
worker threads and then we would write
into one while the other one was
downloading and then swap right so we'd
like ping pong our pixel buffer objects
back and forth basically and I don't
really know maybe in certain
circumstances you might even want a
deeper q than two because remember it's
locked memory so you wouldn't want to
like lock the pistol buffer object copy
into it unlock it transfer lock it again
copy into it transfer because that
second lock is gonna thrash right it's
like it's gotta wait for that download
to continue or remap the pixel buff
Robert to a new location right and so
what you'd want to do is make it so it
doesn't have to do that and so you'd
want to have kind of a rolling set of
pixel buffers where you could lock and
right into one while it was transferring
out of another then switch so now you're
reading writing into the other one law
is transferring out of a new one and you
ping pong back and forth we do that for
each of our worker threads and then they
could all do just hammering on that all
the time and that'd be a really easy
thing for you do if that's what you care
about exercise left for the reader I
don't particularly care about that right
now but a very easy to implement that's
what we would do you'd go get that get
those
extensions load in the function pointers
those tensions create the pics of
efforts for each worker thread and then
when you wanted to do the texture stuff
instead of the allocate texture
happening after the load we would run
the allocate texture before the load and
really all it would be it we probably
wouldn't actually be an alki texture
what it would actually be is just a call
to to get the free the currently free
pixel ever so so there you go i think it
might have been cuba Caleb who answered
that question who asked that question
who's a long time for the series I just
so I just wanted to clear that up for
him or her I don't actually know I never
actually know what the right pardon is
for for a lot of people because i only
see a handle on the chat and handles are
usually genderless so anyway let's go
ahead and save that off and then close
and get back to what we were doing which
was just cleaning up our OpenGL startup
code to do something that it was not
doing originally that's not super
critical so if it doesn't work meaning
the graphics card doesn't support it for
some reason oh wait I don't need my
Emacs anymore we've got for it if it
doesn't work for some reason that's
actually okay we can actually live
without it and so our startup code is
written to essentially ignore it if it
doesn't work but we did want to try and
make it work if we could and what that
is is srgb on the destination frame
buffer because like I said all of our
rendering we did in hand right here was
attempting to be roughly gamma correct
it was actually using squared instead of
full srgb mapping in order to make it
faster in the software renderer but you
know we still wanted to have that gamma
crack step and so we're in we're trying
now to make it so that the frame buffer
is marked that way and so if we take a
look at win32 handmade in here we have
our srgb frame buffer request oops we
have our srgb frame buffer request in
here somewhere at least I think we do
rain buffer
you ever put it in I guess we didn't I
guess we haven't gotten there yet I
guess we're still using wiggle choose
pixel format without it in there yeah it
doesn't appear to be in there so so
nevermind I take it back we haven't
quite gotten there yet so what we were
trying to do is we were trying to
specify that we wanted an srgb frame
buffer now in order to do that you can't
use the standard way that opengl creates
context which is the old wiggle way of
doing it with choose pixel format this
goes through GDI basically with choose
pixel format and then set pixel format
well you actually have to do is call
this extended wiggle choose pixel format
ARB which is an extension to OpenGL
which allows you to specify a lot more
different things and you specify them in
this little parameter list now you can
see here that we've done all this work
we wrote it and we're like okay good
we're ready to go unfortunately it turns
out you can't actually do this because
wiggle and we sort of knew this wiggle
get proc address doesn't really work
until after you've created a context
okay so this thing right here where we
call wiggle create context on this
opengl SRC and wiggle make current that
process actually needs to have happened
beforehand so we're left in a situation
where we need to essentially move this
right here we need to move this down
right this needs to actually happen
after we already have a context created
okay so that's like something like this
if that makes sense so here is what we
would need to do we need to do wiggle
make current and then we could go ahead
and get our get proc address for choose
pixel format and if we got it we could
do a new pixel format right but the
problem is we've already set the pixel
format and we've already called wiggle
make current and so what we would have
to do here and I thought about this and
I think this might actually work so I'm
going to go ahead and try it and also I
guess this stuff right here comes down
as well right so that goes in there and
this is always now has to happen
right all of this is stuff that has to
occur because we always have to do this
this path at least once so we need to do
a choose pixel format the old way one
time set the pixel format to make sure
that our create context will succeed
assuming because i I don't I don't
really know if we can guarantee that all
machines wiggle create context would
succeed if we didn't first set the pixel
format to one that supports OpenGL right
so that's why I think we have to do that
so then we come down on here and we do
this sort of separate pixel format
situation right and by the way I suspect
that we're going to have to do a thing
here where we set double buffered to
false potentially in order to make
streaming still work so we'll check at
the end of the stream to make sure we
can this is again the sort of the
streaming situation but anyway so this
this GL double buffer arm set to true we
may have to set that to false basically
in order to get the streaming to work
we'll find out but point being here we
are after the wiggle make current and
what I'm thinking and I don't actually
know if this is the case or not but what
I was thinking is why couldn't we just
do this if we just get rid of that
context entirely right and say say like
we just straight-up deleted or leave it
in place and delete it later or who
knows what can we just set the pixel
format again right and I don't know I
have absolutely no idea if that's true
or not so we'll just see if we can I
don't know if it's well documented I
have absolutely no idea but we can
certainly go ahead and see in here we
could say if extended pic worked right
then set the pixel format seems like
it's worth a shot so I'm just going to
see what happens if we do that because
I'm curious and we'd have to test this
on multiple machines potentially to
figure out a bunch of stuff to figure
out essentially whether or not you can
actually do this I have no idea but
here is a version that does it that way
and I'm going to go ahead and to the
bugger and step in and see if that works
and maybe we can check with some OpenGL
driver people to ask them if it actually
will if it does work if it works on if
it would work on people's machines in
general so let's go ahead and step
through here we make current this this
guy which is our old school context
which can't do anything then we make
current zero which says okay this thread
no longer has a current opengl context
this thread doesn't have one at all so
now we see if we can get wiggle choose
pixel format ARB we can't so it looks
like the wiggle make current would have
to happen after we got that call I guess
right so I'm going to see if I'm gonna
see what happens if we do that you have
the other thing too is I don't even know
if we have to do the widow make current
now that i think about it i'm gonna you
know what i should probably just try
this first like can we just straight up
set the pixel format yeah can we just
straight up set the pixel format without
that and i don't know so here's a will
make current there's our choose pixel
for my ARB and we got it assuming we get
it we can now do to fix a format again
we get the extended pic back and we've
got our stress and pistol format indexes
to you know I should have looked what it
was before hand probably the same one
right
such a visit furnace one all right so it
actually goes back 20 probably cuz the
double buffer we do an extended pick is
24 that means there are 24 formats that
matched right so now we're going to try
doing set pixel format and I think set
pixel format probably does a return that
tells us what happened I would suspect
so let's go ahead and see what it
actually returns now i'm going to verify
that it's at pixel format i'm assuming
that it has like a bool return or
something bool so presumably just as
true if it succeeds false if it doesn't
so we're going to see what that actually
was now you notice I didn't capture
Turing value here but that's ok because
like we talked about in streams it's a
couple days ago on the pre stream the
return value is always stored in eax if
it fits and of course a boolean would
absolutely fit so when we call set pixel
format and we go through this call here
if you look at the registers and we see
what's in eax and again i always call
eax force of habit it's actually called
our ax when you're talking about the
full 64-bit range eax is only the bottom
32 bits it's just that's how they it's
always like expand it was ax and it was
eax it was our ax write it like keeps
getting extended as it gets bigger in
size but anyway so we do our call to set
pixel format and it looks like that did
not succeed right that's a zero in there
so it looks like we can't quite do that
without getting rid of that initial one
so again i'm just doing trial and error
here because this is the thing i don't
know and i don't have any good
documentation for it that i know about
so i'm kind of flying blind so i'm going
to just go ahead and see all right what
if i was to destroy that context some
time a little bit later right what would
happen there so let's see if i was going
to do set pixel format on the window DC
could i do something here where I you
know do a wiggle make current to get rid
of it maybe even do a wittle delete
context right which would cause the rest
of our code to fail but we'll deal with
that in a second I just want to see if I
deleted the context entirely so it's
gone would that be enough to allow me to
set the pixel format again right so here
we go
I come through here I get my arm call
back which is good I you know unmake
current the thing so it's not on my
threat anymore I delete it it's gone
right so thatthat GL RC is now dead I
and I try to suggest set the pixel
format pics of right to and no dice so i
don't know i'm not sure if maybe that
just means you can never set a pixel
format twice maybe i'm not sure let me
see if the docs say anything about that
because i'm out of ideas there so the
only other thing we could do is create a
dummy window and use that which is not a
problem but it's just a lot of sort of
unnecessary business so i wouldn't do it
if I you know didn't have to so let's c
sub pixel format changed the best form
of the window setting the pixel format
of a window more than once can lead to
significant complications for the window
management for motive abdicated so it is
not allowed so there we go so basically
we don't have a choice it would seem as
far as i can tell we pretty much just
straight-up have to set the pixel format
on some other window on this a dummy
window and then we can use that window
to load up all of the stuff we actually
need and then do what we need to do so
i'm going to go ahead and back out these
changes like so and just restore it to
what we had before which i think is
basically what we want and then i'm just
going to go ahead and restructure this
code a little bit to use a dummy window
to to do the loading of the opengl
wiggle extensions and then we will go
ahead and and clean up this path so that
we use those extensions as as necessary
alright so i'm going to call this like
load wiggle extensions and load wiggle
extensions i think what we want to do
here is we already have plenty of ways
of creating a window right
so if I look here we've got you know
create window exa and for this you know
we sort of created this fader window and
we register in class I i think i'm just
going to literally take this exact code
just for creating a window i'm just
going to create that a dummy window and
then i'm going to immediately destroy it
afterwards so i'll just create the
context use it to load my stuff in and
then after that we will immediately
destroy it so be coming through here we
don't care about any of this stuff right
we don't care about the window procedure
this can be just def window proc oh no
oh poor for kodir I feel like for coders
tab completion has hit has hit a very
unfortunate wall am i right about this
let's see what happened to it forehead
hmm it's not using very much as a
working set or anything so it seems like
it's probably just some kind of a thing
where it got confused during parsing i'm
not sure i don't know if we can save a
mini dump for Alan uh so can I get it
maybe tone of this not sure well let's
take a look
alright so at least we know where we are
I guess so here is where it's saying the
fault is I guess is that where it's
saying the fault is unhandled exception
ex violation reading the location 0 X
FFF FFF FFF so the app pointer got
corrupted somehow I guess let's take a
look watch one app nope that's all fine
so what is it trying to if it's trying
to load from Q R opponent how is how is
that or as rcx is the bug RC x is 0 that
correct this is not sure because that
says x violation reading has I want this
to show me are we ah there we go that
just showed me that was just jumping to
the first part of my code so we're we're
in here we're in exec command which
makes sense because it's probably
exacting its exacting the the word
complete command right and then we're
four levels deep and here's where we are
on the stack so in theory if he's got
the map he could figure out who we
crashed in and we're crashing on a test
instruction so we're trying to compare
uh something to one so probably probably
the true would be my guess in the source
code so yeah we're doing a comp we
looked at something this looks this is
all all these imp three heroes make me
think this is like part of some kind of
a partial function like this is where
the function started I would I think
this looks a little ott like the start
of a function to me so I think we're in
the top of a function here that's going
to test against one assuming that it
doesn't have some kind of a comp to it
so yeah I don't know hopefully that
helps Alan a little bit maybe I don't
know if I can save a mini dump can I
can I save debug the debug cars from
Diagnostics quick watch save save dump
as that's what I'm talking about me dump
with heat bro all right all right me
dump with heap coming right up for kodir
new folder jumps here comes the dump
this is for read word completion crash
dump there you go and by the way this is
just a good thing to know about in
general when an application crashes if
it's you know like with forehead where
it's like an alpha version that we're
using really early in development it's
really helpful to the developers if you
can take a moment since you are a
programmer and do the right thing with a
crash so that they can get some
information about it potentially if they
don't have their own automated crash
reporting or any of that stuff yet which
you know they might not if they're not
on the platform that supports that or
whatever so yeah not that hard to do
like you saw me do it just then it's a
nice thing to be able to do if you can
so it turns it's just down here in the
debug menu i was like i'm pretty sure i
could save a crash dump and i can so
that's good and also just take a quick
look at this and maybe look at the you
know just given that if you can alright
so that's it for for a poor little
forehead I'm sorry for read it was doing
very well I will say but we will have to
relaunch you all right back to our back
to our story so here we are again and
through handmade and i'm just going to
do oops I didn't mean to do that I meant
to load handmade that proj oh I did go
animate the project okay good
so what I want to do here again is I
want to in it opengl by creating that
sort of fake window right i want to
create a window and I want that fake
window to do the things that it needs to
do to get me the extension pointers
because really until I have those
tension pointers I can't do anything and
as we saw before there's really no way
to use one window to get the extension
pointers if I have to choose the pixel
format using an extension it's like a
catch-22 so I need something like win32
load wiggle extensions here right and
what that's going to do is that's going
to load these these sort of mandatory
things that I I can't load without
setting up a window first so let's go
ahead and grab that code again with the
create window code that I was going to
use here for the fader window basically
we can use that exact same code and so
if i go back to wiggle extensions place
that in there so all I'm going to do
here create the wind class and this is
literally just like handmade wiggle
loader that's all it does it doesn't
need any of this stuff we don't care
about that we don't care about this this
is the only thing we really care about
get module handle 0 and def window proc
w I think Jeff window proc we were
calling definitely to proc a yeah
reminder Colin tip window proc a so
different a pocket uh so that's all we
really care about doing here I don't
think we even care we don't even care
about the style we don't care about any
of that stuff we don't want any of these
things right we don't want to be layered
the class name is going to be whatever
the window classes that we register here
obviously this stuff we don't care about
at all like this is this is actually I
guess just 0 like there's no probably
any flags at all and so we're going to
go ahead and do that create this window
like so and then immediately destroy
this window
so that's all we actually need to do
right we just want all that stuff to
just be to be dead and in between there
now we can do the stuff that we want to
do before with choosing the pixel format
so what I'm going to do with that is up
here i'm going to say okay internal void
choose win32 choose pixel format what
i'm going to do here and I'll probably
actually have to pass that some things
but I'm going to take this sort of code
that we had here right and I'm going to
make this code into something that sort
of works depending on whether you have
the extension or not right and so what I
want to do is I want to sort of revert
it back to sort of the old school way
that it was working before I want to say
suggested pixel format index soup
suggested thankful for my name I want to
say suggested pixel format index I want
to see whether we have the extension or
not if we don't have the extension I
want to use this way always right
because that's just better than not
working so we're going to use that if we
don't have the extended way and if we do
have the extended way that we're going
to use this this one down here right in
fact this is basically the code that we
want so if you have the extension we do
this exactly the way that we use to
where we do the extended pick C
limitation there we go okay so if you
have the extension this actually goes up
here if we have the extension then we
start going the extension itself is
going to be loaded elsewhere so I'm
going to load the extension in this dl
load extensions do that so that's
actually gonna go down there now so I'm
just going to test to see whether or not
we have the extension if we have the
extension then we use the extended path
in so much as we can right and i'm going
to put
this guy out here as well like I said
with the extended pick thing so you had
the extension we try to use it and I
will reinvent this line there we go like
so and then if we didn't get it then
we'll use this one and I think I sort of
had that path Yeah right here so what
I'm going to do is say okay if you
couldn't if you didn't get to extended
pick right then pick it this way so what
I could do to is I suppose really I
could just let this thing over right
suggested pixel format I don't know this
is probably the safer way to do it there
is just if we have the extension run the
extension path if we see that the
extension pick something don't run the
old paths and then either way after we
run it try to set the pixel format on
the window seems reasonable right so at
that point that's really all we need to
do for setting the pixel format so
that's it that's the code that I'm
looking for and wiggle choose pixel
format could just take and maybe this is
the right way to do it i think probably
it'll just take as a pointer this
extension because the only extension it
actually needs to think about so i can
just pass that in and say hey here's the
pointer so when you do wiggle choose
pixel format if you pass that pointer in
italy and it's a valid pointer it will
actually try to use the extended version
if you don't then it'll just skip it
right so then we come into winter q lo
extensions and now we know that that's
going to be the case we create the
window and after we create the window
what we're going to do is we're going to
call into that went through to set pixel
format what was it called choose pixel
format sorry I really want set that's
the right it's actually called set
because choose is one part but but said
is the other part right so I really want
win32 set pixel format and it'll set
pixel format on this window you know I'm
saying or I guess probably maybe it
should take a DC so maybe we'll say
window DC and we'll just say that the
person who calls in will get the DC for
you so there's the window DC so here
we'll say the window DC equals get DC of
the window and then we'll do a release
DC on the window and destroy the window
right yeah perfect so I think this is
what we want to do right we want to do
the window to see we get the DC we set
them as the format we don't actually
probably want to wait and releases and
see down here obviously I don't know why
this seems to think that we're indented
more than we are I guess it's this is it
this that confuses it yeah i think for
I'd got confused by that yeah it did no
it didn't sit this I'm not sure what
confuses it but it's confused about the
annotation level and I don't know if
that's me or if I've got like a hanging
thing or not anyway so point being
here's 13 to load wiggle extensions we
create this window we get the DC we set
the pixel format on it and then we are
going to go ahead and try to create
context like we did before whose sole
purpose is to get extensions for us it's
not going to do it's literally not going
to ever render a single thing of OpenGL
it's just going to get the extensions so
here it gets the extensions right it
gets it does a tues pixel format ARB or
whatever so it gets the extension and
then if it gets that extension will have
it for our you know for our use or
whatever if it can't get the extension
then no big deal we just we would be
using the old paths right and we can
also put the rest of our stuff in there
that we were using with wiggle I think
to write so we could for example take
this will create context attribs ARB
that could go in here too and so
basically all of the stuff that we were
calling we can call in here if that
makes sense and I think there was was
there one other thing that we called in
here I can't remember if there was or if
there wasn't doesn't look like it Oh
swap interval
so all of these can now be things that
we sort of wrote you know expect that
will be loaded in this function if they
can be loaded which we don't always know
that they will be able to and so I'll
put this these up these guys all here
together where is where is swap interval
there it is all right so we try loading
all those and hopefully we get them all
right if we don't get them all it's not
the end of the world but that's what
we're hoping for so there they are and
everything's good so after we load all
those we can destroy the context right
so we can get rid of the context that
we're using and we can destroy it
wiggled destroy context and I can pass
the window to see to that whoops I mean
the open GL RC and I don't know if we
actually ever need to do the make
current but we might as well because we
can like I don't know if we need to do
the make current in order for that to
work but we'll see oops and then
obviously we don't actually need to do
to make current outside so that seems
reasonable to me i'm going to compile
that see where we're at a build that is
not recognized as an internal or
external command really what are you
talking about there we go alright so
instance is just window class H instance
and then I think we're good so win32 set
pixel format in this case we don't have
the extension yet so we're not going to
use it in fact I guess what we could do
now is we don't even really have to pass
it because it'll just it can just use it
as it would normally use it because it's
a global variable it's like if it's been
loaded it'll use it if it isn't loaded
it won't right so off we go destroy
context it's actually not destroy
context its delete context that's just
my
I miss remembering the name and off we
go so now in win32 and opa joe with this
in mind what we can do is first call
this load extensions thing right so we
can call wiggle load extensions and know
that we have now created dummy context
and gotten rid of it but loaded the
functions that we need to load we can
get rid of all of this stuff because
it's been sort of abstracted out into
another function that we know we can
call so what we can literally do here is
say okay I forget all this stuff forget
all of it instead what we're going to do
is we're going to see whether or not we
have a modern of the ability to get a
modern context right and if we do if we
are able to get a modern context then we
will and if we won't then we won't right
so let me go ahead and actually reinvent
all this here we go so in this case we
don't need to get this anymore because
we you know we'd already have queried it
so we can do is we can call wiggle
create context oak attribs right and
what I'll do is I'll say here is our
Open GL RC the one we're going to return
it starts out being initialized to
nothing I assume 0 is an initializer for
that yeah it starts out being
initialized to nothing if we can we will
try to get one like so and I guess we
don't really need to pass that that was
just for illustrative purposes before we
can get rid of that so here we go we try
to get the modern open GL RC and we can
actually just call this open GL RC now
right and we can put this stuff down ok
so we try to get the open GL RC this way
if we can't get the open GL RC this way
so either you know if either we end up
without that function or this ends up
failing so we say ok if we can't get it
then we can just try the old school way
of doing it will create context and see
if that works right and if either of
them work then great then we're good to
go so then we can come through here and
say okay why don't you go ahead and
initialize that all the
opengl stuff that you actually needed to
do but first we probably need to
actually set it as the context so we
would call we would call this this stuff
right like so similarly if we happen to
have swap intervals we want to call that
and then we're good so that's like a lot
cleaner now too right I mean it's three
functions now so it's a little bit
stringy er but it's like it actually is
a lot cleaner of exactly what's going on
so let's see if we have any more luck
getting this to do what we needed to do
and can we add the srgb in there once
we're ready right alright so modern GL
RC undeclared that's true what we
actually wanted is open GL RC here and I
think that was obviously wrong oops and
then we've got what have we got cannot
convert argument open Jillian it be 32
oh it's just whether or not it's modern
I guess so we need this thing right here
so we'll assume that we got a modern
context but if we get here it's false
and go from there all right so let's see
if that helped us at all and if any of
that works because again we're just kind
of trying to get windows to do what we
needed to do here and you know windows
does what it does so let's start by
seeing if the extension loading works at
all so here we go we register our window
class that looks like that worked we get
our window the window is is there we get
the DC we try to set the pixel format on
it and we try to set create NRC we get
one we make it current we try to load
our extensions we got one we got to we
got three so all the extensions load we
get rid of the context on our thread we
then delete it we release the DC and
destroy the window now hopefully we can
still now use those callbacks that we've
got I don't actually know if that's true
but hopefully it's true so we look to
see if we've got wiggle create context
of tribes are we do so now we try to
call it with our default attribs we are
unable to get the
open GRC back which suggests to me and I
guess I don't know it suggests to me
that we still do need that other context
around potentially right I don't know
I'm just guessing that's just my my
hunch right like we still need to have
the other the other context active when
we actually make that call which is
unfortunate because that makes it again
a little bit more kind of weird but what
you gonna do all right no biggie so that
just means that we kind of have to we
still have to keep these two things
welded together we can't actually
separate them right and what we would
need to do is when we create this this
kind of do dad here right when we create
when we do with ritu ended up in jail
let me come through here and we create
all this stuff what we need to do is
before we actually unmake the context
right we would then need to sort of do
the the old way that we were doing it
where we sort of say okay let's go ahead
and and and create that that context
from from whole cloth right so like yeah
oops no stop okay there we go so when we
come in here we've got this context
current we see whether or not we could
maybe make our actual context that we
actually care about we see if we can
make it while we still have the other
contacts current then we make it current
20 then we delete it and then finally
down in the end we see did we actually
get a modern context if we didn't we
record the fact that that's true and we
try creating an old-school one on our
actual window that we actually care
about right so now we need to do is we
need to sort of differentiate between
our two window dcs right because now we
have to DC's and we're actually trying
to set in the dummy one so now we need
like a dummy window DC and we need to
make sure all of these are operating on
the dummy window DC not the actual
window DC a lot of fun right
and then these other ones here when
they're doing this they're all working
on the actual window DC the one we're
trying to set not the dummy right so
let's see if we have any better luck
with that are we having fun yet thanks
Microsoft thanks for everything so
anyway here we are went through to an
end up in jail we come through here we
set up our window class you register the
window class we create the window that's
hidden no one's actually we're going to
see that we get the W ater to see from
it we set the pixel format on that every
window to see to support OpenGL we
create the context then we've got an
open GL RC we make it current we then
choose the pixel format context attribs
swap interval functions get them all
right they're all loaded we then see can
we create a context with disconnects
active and these attribs will that work
still doesn't work you know what that
may have been premature I didn't call I
did I forgot to call set pixel format I
forgot to call us at pixel format maybe
it would have worked should we back it
up and try it should we I think we
probably should right because that's
what we need to do we need to call set
we need to we need to do this we need to
call set pixel format on the window DC
right and I forgot to do it so that
that's why the older contract that would
have made the olden fail so maybe we can
still do it the other way that we were
doing it so here's what I'm going to do
I'm going to take this right here and
I'm going to save it off to a temp file
basically what do I have like to do yeah
that's just getting saved into the temp
file now we're going to see if this
works
set the pixel format on the wood WC and
now we got an actual alright so maybe
it's okay to do it the other way which
case I would like to do it that way so
let's and also let's see here if we get
a pixel format assess pill for meant to
and that actually works as well so
that's pretty cool right I'm pretty
happy about that pretty happy about that
yeah yeah alright so I think that may be
the end of that so I'm going to go ahead
and try reverting those changes right
undo undo and do and do and do undo undo
all right so I if I leave it this way
that I think is a little bit nicer to
read right so we kind of have it in in
something where it's a little bit more
understandable what's going on there now
I think I should be able to say okay
when we do win32 in it opengl the only
problem probably with this was that I
didn't do set pixel format and so I'm
just going to go ahead and do set pixel
format now let's see if this still works
or not okay so wiggle extensions off we
go did we get the extension yes we did
did we set the pixel format we try to
and there we go so that looks like we're
okay I think we're okay I think that
looks good to me let's dip in here just
one more time and make sure that the set
pixel format works in this one
yeah okay so we can still do it in the
in the slightly cleaner way and so
that's nice so that's everything there
and now the only thing that and I wasn't
really sure about this to be completely
honest with you I was unclear on whether
we had to or not we now need to put in
here the srgb extended attribute that we
actually want right this is the thing we
did all this work to get is just this
one line of code we wanted to be able to
add here right and what that is is
that's frame buffer srgb herb we just
want this right so we want to be able to
specify wiggle frame buffer srgb capable
arm we just that's the only reason we
did any of this is just that that's it
and so what we want to do is be able to
put that guy right that guy right there
we want to be able to put in here and I
guess we say GL true we'll see I'll go
read the docs but so we need that wiggle
we need one more wiggle thing we need
that and this is the extension now
here's the part that I don't know I
don't know whether we can include that
and just trust that if the driver is not
a driver that accepts it it'll just
ignore it or whether we have to query
the extension string see whether it's
there and only if it is there put it in
because I don't know what the spec
requires of us or how the drivers are
typically written because that's that
let's be honest the end of the day
doesn't actually matter what it says in
the spec it matters what the drivers do
if the drivers puke on it if it's in
there and they don't recognize it then
even suspect says it's okay doesn't
really help us right so we'll have to
see what the actual what that actually
is a practice so if i compile with that
now now i think technically we should be
getting an actual srgb frame buffer
don't actually know if that's true but i
believe that should be the case and so
again very difficult for us to tell we
would have to actually run some
structured art tests through the
pipeline to even know if it was working
because again that's going to be
relatively subtle difference but in
theory now we are getting gamma
correction on the frame buffer as well
in theory so who knows maybe we are
maybe we aren't like I said we'd have to
actually do some real testing to even
figure it out but at least now we have a
plausible path for that and we've got
the code structured what we think is
proper for the windows startup and
that's important to get right even at
this stage of development because again
we want to make sure that when we comes
time to final everything we don't want
to be in a situation where we're doing
everything wrong right so yeah so it's
looking pretty good it's a nice cut
scene you know so let's try the other
thing so I'm looking at the cutscene
right now and i'm assuming i'm just
going to guess that nobody else can see
it but me and you know why i'm guessing
that is because we were passing double
buffer equals true and it is silky
smooth on my machine and when we weren't
when we were doing the one that was
streamable I it was super jerky and so
I'm just assuming that that's true so
I'm going to go ahead and and go ahead
and take a look at that I'm gonna go
ahead and say okay so stream black
screen yeah so you base people are
saying this luxury that's why I thought
so what I'm assuming we have to do is
the same thing here we have to do if
handmade streaming and the double buffer
line is going to have to be set to false
I think I don't know I just assume so I
think we're gonna have to do this and in
theory that will work but we don't know
because it's sort of just a random that
it worked at all I think originally I I
don't really know but there's there's
our
there's our one that maybe isn't a black
screen
can you guys see that yeah you can okay
good so yeah and what's interesting is
that was a kind of a good test cause
like we talked about again people were
asking if it was if what the jerkiness
was from if that was Twitter or not it
is absolutely that flag because when I
don't have that flag set when I have a
set to double buffer it's silky smooth
when I don't have sent over you get that
dorkiness and I think that's because of
going through the windows compositor
perhaps whether it's hitting it properly
or not I'm guessing that probably what's
happening in there is that either twitch
can't get access to it in the other mode
so the twitch doesn't introduce whatever
jerkiness was happening or it's just the
fact that it's not double buffered it's
like not getting vsync or not getting
whatever and so it's not silky smooth it
just kind of depends on whether it hits
the refresh or not right so all right so
I think that's it for today that's what
we wanted to accomplish and we did
accomplish it so that's good and yeah so
let's go ahead and let's go ahead and go
to the QA for about 20 minutes maybe
Caleb aren't pretty much all games
double buffered if so why doesn't OBS
have problems catching game footage for
other games so two things about that
first of all in my experience OBS has
trouble capturing anything I have never
seen a stream where OBS successfully
captured things reliably the whole time
like I i watched John blows streams
right plays games and it's like every
other game it's not capturing you have
to go like reconfigure it and change
what's went right so OBS can barely
capture you know itself let alone stuff
Roma so there's that but what I was
going to say is actually if we wanted to
OBS certainly could capture handmade
hero if we specifically target it to
capture just the handmade hero window I
believe that does work even if it's
double buffered what we couldn't quite
figure out how to get to work was having
it capture the desktop if that makes
sense first and then when we run the
game automatically capture the game too
that was just not working for some
reason and I don't know if maybe there's
a trick of like adding the game on top
as a separate thing that would go up go
over it or not and maybe let make that
happen and so on but yes so that's the
only problem and so what like an long
book is asking does this mean that hmh
cannot be let's play and the answer is
no it could totally be lets played
because normally the caster wouldn't be
worrying about this they would be
setting it to capture ham a hero and
that would presumably just work right so
yeah so we can we could if we really
cared make that work but it's way easier
not to do that it's way easier to just
do it like this where yeah it's not
quite right because we're not running in
double buffer but that's fine for us and
it lets us develop and and do it
properly right
and nicks and and Neil saying you can
send up to switch scenes when the active
window changes so yeah like like I said
maybe there's some things that we can do
that's clever in in OBS to make it work
or whatever I assume that that would
work I don't know that I care enough to
make it happen but we could try
Cuba Caleb shouldn't we also get pixel
format to make sure we got what we
wanted um so I guess what I would say is
no and the reason is because as we
unless so there's two things we could do
if you want to be super fault tolerant
and you want to write something that was
going to go iterate over all the pixel
formats and try to choose a backup one
or some like that then you could do that
but if you're going to do that you would
never call chew sticks before in the
first place you just iterate all the
pics Lawrence and actually use your own
chooser right but if you're not going to
do that then there's really no point in
checking the pixel format that you get
back because there's nothing you can do
right if the face of format you get back
isn't suitable for what you want then
the games just not going to work you
don't have some other option right and
so you might as well just let open jail
try to render with whatever you have and
if the user like isn't happy with that
then you know they're going to file a
bug reporter but there's unless your
game actually has a back-up plan
actually has something it's going to do
if it doesn't get a pixel format that it
thinks is the right kind because we'll
know if we don't create a context right
but as long as we create a context it's
like you might as well try rendering
through it because if you don't do that
then the game just straight-up doesn't
work and you basically increased the
failure right so
huber caleb so for games that is fine
but for someone like photoshop i'm
assuming you would have to care uh you
mean well so one thing you would
probably want to do is if your photoshop
you would want to have a thing that says
just so you know here is the format
you've got i still think you should try
to run you don't want to not run right
my egl enable GL framebuffer srgb after
creating the motor cars didn't we
already do that pretty sure that our
code already did that it's right that's
that that guy right there right so in
OpenGL in it we we enable a frame buffer
srgb
I think we are out of questions I'm
looking at the stream by don't see no mo
any atomic have you started thinking
about cross-platform support I've missed
quite a bit of the stream i believe so
since i said i said this up that at the
very beginning of hannah here and don't
think that's ever going to change there
will be no cross-platform handmade hero
till the end we will have the complete
game on Windows first and then we will
move to other platforms and that's just
because it reduces the amount of work
because instead of maintaining multiple
platforms when you change your mind or
ad platform civic features you only do
that once for each additional platform
so yeah so there's not going to be any
cross-platform anything until until the
end now granted people everyone else is
already ported it to sdl and OSX and i
don't remember what else they ported to
sew on the github there's actually
people who've already ported it because
we isolated the game from the platform
completely so it's trivial deport all
you have to do is port the platform all
we have to do is port 1 3 204 handmade
but you know we aren't aren't doing that
ttb JM is the GPU doing pre
premultiplied alpha so the GPU that's
sort of the wrong way to think about it
if that makes sense the GPU doesn't know
whether it's doing premultiplied alpha
or not it's just whether you set up your
textures that way and then you set your
blend mode essentially to be whatever
will work out to use it so because we're
using the same textures by definition
we're using premultiplied alpha because
all of our things are premultiplied
alpha we pre-multiply the alpha into
them and so the only place that the GPU
ever even knows about it is right here
when we say GL blend funk and remember
we went over the blending equation we
have GL one GL 1-4 safa whereas if it
wasn't premultiplied alpha it would be
GL source alpha chi 0 1 minus or failed
because this is the source multiplier
here and so in premultiplied alpha it's
the texture coming in is already
multiplied by alpha or go you don't need
to multiply by alpha again so it's just
dl 1 x 1 which doesn't change the value
obviously that makes sense but nothing
else actually needs to know about that
because premultiplied alpha is just a
thing you do two detectors originally we
store them in that format r g and b are
all x a everything the GPU does just
works with them as rgba values doesn't
know whether they're p multiplied or not
so when it does texture fetches and by
linear interpolation and whatever else
it's just doing it to the values and it
has no idea whether in people's we're
not only at the very end when it goes to
blend with the flame refere it just
needs to know do i multiply this by all
for naught and you have to set it to the
right thing because if you set it to the
wrong one it's not like it would be a
some kind of subtle bug you would see
like a pretty serious fringing I think I
assume we'll find out
alright I take it back I would have
thought you would have since attrib I
guess you're only going to see it clip
in on the edges so it's kind of I guess
not super for an ounce but you can see
maybe you can't even see because of the
because of the compression or not but
you can see sort of the heavier lines
but yeah that's it that's the only place
to any of it I would change if you had
something translucent you would see it I
guess more pronounced than that but that
wasn't even as bad as that that was
pretty subtle so you could even set that
wrong and you wouldn't know let's see
are you staying with immediate mode oh
you mean as opposed to putting the
vertices in a buffer I don't think we
would pretty much get any speed from
that at all to be honest because we just
don't have enough stuff to shove down so
I don't know that there's any real
reason to not use immediate mode we
might if we do particle systems need to
to think a little bit more about that
but right now we would have no use for
vertex buffers guten twone could we do
srgb with a shader and not with GL and
able um so not really is the answer you
you obviously can because a shader is
very highly programmable these days so
you know if you wanted to implement srgb
in it you certainly could but it's going
to be a lot less efficient if that makes
sense because the card has a color
lookup table in it that will do the srgb
conversions for you properly or they've
got a little circuit in their design to
just do this you know it's like they've
got they've got this worked out if that
makes sense whereas if we do the srgb
conversion either we have to upload a
texture and use the tech
as a lookup texture to do the srgb or we
have to write the code to do it which is
going to be more expensive and so
basically there really is no case where
you would actually want to do that
unless you had some other really good
reason right like assuming you're just
doing basic apps like we are where we're
just you know combining sprites and
stuff I can't think of any reason why
you wouldn't use the sRGB that's
built-in because it's going to be
exactly what you want and it's going to
be the fastest way to do it far as I
know anyway we're dominant are we still
going to do work on the debug you I yes
in fact I think that's probably the next
thing we'll do because we don't have
very much left to do but this stuff we
haven't ever finished up here and so we
should finish that
every time you go to answer question and
the cutscene loops a pink screen appears
yeah if you don't remember the pink
screen is where our title screen will go
we just we set it up so that it goes
like you play the cutscene or can go to
the title screen and the title screen we
don't have any thing drawn for yet so
you know it's just pink right now
someday we'll have like some title art
or something I don't know what will go
there but something will go there
alright that looks like there ain't no
mo q so I'm going to wrap it up I'm
going to wrap it up close
alright everybody thank you for joining
me for another episode of handmade here
at some pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along at
home you can always go pre-order
handmade here on the hamb a hero to org
and it comes with a source code even now
so you could follow along every day by
downloading the latest source code and
doing exactly what I do on the stream
it's going to be to learn from it or you
can play around with it and do different
things so I do miss Jenny which is even
better way to learn we also have a forum
site you can go to ask questions you
have a patreon page you can use if you
want support the video series and we
have a tweet bot you can go to if you
want check out the schedule the editor
that we use on the stream is called for
coder and it's written by someone
actually on the stream and it's kind of
getting better all the time if you want
to support that project you can always
go to the fore coder website just type
for kodir into google it's got the
patron page here it's a great product to
support and it's already pretty usable
as you can see I can do a lot of editing
in it already even though it's you know
it's just been like a spare time project
for Alan it's already like you know a
lot more enjoyable to use the new max
honestly so check that out as well
that's about it for today we'll be back
here tomorrow for the last stream of the
week on Friday 5 p.m. pacific standard
time and so it helps you hope see you
back here for that if you can make it
until then have fun programming and i
will see you guys on the internet take
it easy everyone