hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the shore we code a complete game
live on stream we nominally and I guess
we don't really know because we haven't
had any particular stress testing of it
yet but we actually implemented our own
PNG reader over the past couple episodes
and it appears to be functional at least
for the PNG s that we have tested so far
which means we can proceed to step two
of our plan for world domination which
is trying to put some art into handmade
hero and actually as part of that
process in addition to putting art in
handmade hero making it be able to have
something in the way of an easy-to-use
system so that an artist who was running
the game who wanted to replace an art
asset in the game could do so without
having to know how to program or
anything like that something that can
work in this way so that's our goal for
the next couple episodes is to work
towards that we've put ourselves in a
situation that none of the architecture
in our game really will probably will
have to change because we already
support on-demand streaming of assets
and when you support on-demand streaming
of assets it means that you could just
for free replace an asset because since
all of the game already has to be
written you know in a manner that makes
it so that the the game doesn't know
whether the asset is present or not
replacing the asset with a new asset is
fairly trivial now there are some things
that we may have to work on that that
aren't streamed like there may be some
things that we count on being consistent
that now won't be consistent but we've
already done the bulk of the work which
which is to say that not knowing that an
asset is always there is really the hard
part of hot loading and we've already
done that so we really we're gonna have
a much easier time of this than you
would have if you were retrofitting hot
loading into a game that had never
considered the possibility
that an art asset wasn't present because
you know that's the part that usually
trips you up and we won't have that so
that's the good news the bad news is
well we probably want to do some
architectural changes anyway because now
that we know that we want to support
Hardware rendering because we have a
hardware renderer now we probably want
to take this opportunity to also enforce
some kind of a rigid texture size so
that we can use texture arrays and avoid
all of the draw call restarts that we
currently have to do because we allow
textures to be arbitrarily sized so we
may end up doing some architectural
changes anyway but again those should
probably be much more limited than they
would have had to been otherwise had we
not done a streaming asset system so
streaming asset system kind of coming
into play here I noticed some people on
the chat saying that they are mesmerized
by the bobbing orphan on the webpage yes
that is kind of a fun little animation
we made for the handmade here a purchase
badge we thought it would be fun if our
if our websites all had sort of animated
badges instead of the kind of lame
static badges and we just had fun making
them so Anna drew this one and and it's
it's yeah it's just kind of fun
we actually have those for the handmade
fund as well now there's a little one
for that as well so you get you can get
your pick of little animated icon there
yeah and if you haven't ever used our
website now our new website is pretty
easy to use there's just a button bar at
the top you can get to whatever you want
on the handmade hero stuff and if you
click on the main hero head you can
actually get all of our our websites you
can jump directly to them actually so
you can jump to 1935 if you want to
which we'll be updating actually in a
couple months with some you know
screenshots and trailers and stuff so
that'll be used to know we've got the
comic that Anna's working on right now
which should come out soon as well so we
got those got handmade here we got our
main site which you can always go back
to you with the blog and so on and then
we have our personal pages right like my
page
it's on there with with all of my stuff
on it you can go to my blog for example
and see stuff that I'm posting or
whatever so it's pretty handy and then
Anna's got kind of an old school blog
she still has one at tumblr with her old
artwork on it and stuff like that so
anyway it's pretty easy to use if you
ever want to browse around there and
just find my Rocket stuff it should work
really well on mobile too so if you're
you know just killing time or something
like that anyway
so let's go ahead and get started what
we need to do now is actually we should
prep before we integrate the PNG reader
in a hammy oh shoot we try to figure out
whether we can even load the files that
we need to load so what first thing
you're gonna want to do if you're
following along at home is there's a new
art pack up on the download link that
you got to get so this is the new art
pack it's handmade hero art pack 1 zip
and it's a bunch of test art in the
right format that that is basically
examples of all different sort of stuff
that we want to be able to load so like
character like NPCs playable characters
like block tiles cover coverage stuff
you know a title screen and so on so
like all the stuff that we might want to
load is in there so the first thing
we're gonna have to do obviously is
we're gonna have to unpack that stuff
into some place in the handmade curio
directory that we want to load things
from now we've got a data directory here
in the data directory has a bunch of
stuff in it that's what the game loads
what I want to do is make a
differentiation between those two things
so I want to create a separation
directory separation just to make it
clear between data that the game loads
and data that the artist works with and
what's in this art pack is for the first
time because we're trying to get a
pipeline that runs at run time in the
game running now where it'll suck in art
as it comes in at run time is I want to
make a different sort of directory for
the source files so I'm going to make an
art directory here for the first time
and I'm gonna unzip this this art pack
in there to differentiate it from data
because data is still I think we're
still gonna want to have these HHA files
which are like what we consider to be
the running package that we would ship
at the game so this art is really not
what we will be loading for the actual
game necessarily it's just what the
artist would dump art into and expect
the game to load it right so it's
different so anyway if you look at how
these are structured there's a couple of
different things in there there's like
for example this these template files
I'm gonna use the Photos app to view
this here actually you know what I don't
like
do I like for us well that's fine so if
you take a look at the template file you
can see that it's got like a little bit
of information on it like for state 1
for state to Warren and then the
direction the things facing there's one
for character files as well where is
that character templates can I just have
this there we go okay uh so if I open up
the character template one which you can
see here I don't know why it insists on
get like you just have the lines go away
it's like it's it's blending thing like
gets rid of the lines or something and
that's sure what's going on there how do
i yeah you can see there's lines there
and they like disappear and that's
that's some pretty questionable that's
some pretty questionable zoom code there
Microsoft anyway so what you can see
here is just just a template file it's
got a grid in it maybe if I load this
into a program that was written by
somebody who knew what they were doing
we'd be able to see those let's see here
let me go and load that keep that yes so
you can see so you can see the grid here
because this was written by someone
who's you know ever heard of graphics
and knows how they work so you can see
here there's like a grid and it's got
columns and rows default dodge left
dodge right move hit attack you know one
attack to default surprise anger this is
how the artist laid out the different
things and they just packed them into a
file so that they're easier to load all
and you can see here the body is at the
top the heads at the bottom and there's
directional arrows like right up left
and down and these are just to remind us
and we will use those as well to remind
us how we're doing there so also before
I go I'm gonna go ahead and switch this
back because whoever wrote that program
is really should probably be fired I'm
gonna go ahead and switch it to a
program that actually can resize an
image without losing all the information
in it because I think there is a like we
need a viewer like the old viewer that
actually works let me see here because
isn't there usually is one that used
there's just a photo viewer thing that
actually works right or at least there
was one maybe if I click on a other type
of image or something
coping with so those are set to canoe
right now yeah I just don't know how to
get back to having it open in like
that's default one you know the one that
I'm talking about that just comes with
it where is that one because that one
actually sort of worked
what XC is the windows 7 default Photo
Viewer
hello seven forums wellness Furies
remember ideal host okay start for the
command line you would use this
[Music]
okay so it looks like you can maybe set
default programs maybe that will work
looks like think it looks like they got
rid of it though like from those
settings so we something with Microsoft
it's like they can't even draw a picture
that's that's where we're at they can't
not even load an image they were like
yeah
sorry man I got nothing I have no idea
how to draw a picture to a screen let's
see here default programs set your
default programs now it's going to
launch that thing again yeah
you
so let's see
I don't know maybe you can't get it back
there must be some way
thank you for like in the dating methods
but that didn't work
copy the code of this post time for us
into notepad and save it as a reg file
don't look like your new reg file all
right we can do that so here's the Photo
Viewer stuff yeah we could try this this
looks legit it's only modifying those
classes let's give it a shot
can't believe I have to do this to view
an image this is a new low even for
Microsoft who honestly is like the
expert of plumbing the lows lately
all right I don't know if we would have
to launch Explorer for that because it
looks like
I still don't see it oh there it is yes
yes all right
thank you seen it now
there we go all right so seen I don't
think they're loading the transparency
right on these pings so there's that but
at least let's see yeah so at least it
can show the grid right so the first
thing you wrote this wasn't like a
complete tool they had some idea what
they were doing not a whole lot but at
least they can sort of do something
right so now we can at least see that
the file in some semblance of what it
actually contains all right so what we
want to do here is we want to start
taking these files and we want to start
bringing them into the the game and we
want the game to be able to process them
so you can see we've got some NPCs here
right that we can stick in to the
orphanage just a bunch of random orphans
and then we also have the handmade hero
one who's the actual main character
which has some test lean animations as
well not animations but extra frames if
that makes sense
and also some expression test stuff so
we can play around that and see what we
actually want know stuff some cats which
is important these are some tile sets
right for so that we can actually have
so that we can wrap some things onto our
cubes that maybe look like wood or like
stone or like walls right so we can play
around with those as well and then we
have some base green green ones we also
have a little title logo we can put up
there and some some example like ground
cover stuff and basically the goal here
is just to take some of these things oh
and some attachments for characters like
the hats hands things like that also
ground cover and stuff like that so
basically we have stuff we can play with
and our goal here is just to put these
into the game and get them working so
that we can then take it back to Anna so
that she can actually draw stuff in the
context of the game and see what looks
good you know because at the moment
there's really no way to do that right
she can't really get any feedback about
how the things should be drawn or
what they should do right okay
so that's really all we need here so
we've got all this stuff so you can see
our our path is completely laid out
before us here I should probably put
this photo of your reg thing into the
misc directory potentially because
honestly like we may need that again if
Windows decides to give us another
crappy photo viewer that doesn't work so
I that's all you should need to do with
the art pack once you've got that all
unpacked in there you can get rid of the
zip file we won't need that anymore we
just need it to be in the directory
where we can get it and so then we can
start the process of trying to figure
out how that's gonna go in there now
like I've seen before I go any further
because I don't really want to get too
into the I don't want to go too far down
the process of getting handmade hero
ready to read PNG files and integrate
them into its data set until I actually
know whether we can read these PNG files
in the first place because we've only
tested the PNG reader very lightly and
so what I want to know first is can we
read these files these were output by
Photoshop that's who we want to be able
to read the files from and so I want to
start testing these files to see whether
Photoshop puts anything into it span
geez that's different from the PNG s we
were testing from because that way
I can tell whether there's any kind of
stuff that we forgot to implement or
implemented wrong that we just like
cases we just didn't hit because we did
happen to ever see them like they didn't
occur they don't occur when you're using
giimpse compressor is different
than photoshop's compressor probably
right and so we want to be able to just
get a sub perspective on whether or not
we're gonna see something different here
so if I go to the handmade art directory
here like so I can just pick something
maybe we'll load the character for the
hero
so just character hero dot PNG
and then we'll just write that into the
temp directory as a bitmap and we'll
just run the program and see you know
does it even work does it crash whatever
so this is perfect right you can see we
found something already this should not
have happened so this is what I want to
debug first and I wanted to bug it here
because we've got a nice simple program
set up which is designed to just do one
PNG read so we can find anything that is
not what we would expect right so when
we were parsing to PNG here we went into
some kind of a bit into a consume bits
run where we were trying to copy a giant
in fact this is a this is a block copy
of this is a copy of an entire large
chunk of data oh you know what this may
this may just be a very simple problem
actually now that I think about it we
don't really handle huge block copies
that cross multiple i dot chunks do we
so that could be a problem of course
looking at this I don't this is only one
IDOT chunk so there must be a different
bug in here right I think so anyway we
should we're we're gonna have to take a
look at this a little bit more carefully
because there's only one on that trunk
so that's not the problem but I do think
if I'm not mistaken I feel like consume
size in this case wouldn't work if it
was split over more than one eye that
chunk you know what I'm saying so I
might I might slap what to do in there
just because I feel like we for
completeness sake did that's not the
problem here but I had not thought about
that before this really needs to be a
loop that consumes as much as it can
from the current I that chunk and then
moves
so just to leave that in there because
I'm pretty sure it would just wouldn't
work right you'd call consume size and
consume size would say I want 50 bytes
but there's only 30 bytes left in that
idaite chunk that'll just fail right
there's nothing you can do to fix that
and so what we would need to do is is
make it so that once you get the length
there's like a thing where you're like
hey consume as much as I can up to this
amount and then if I can't consume it
all I'll just loop inside there doing as
much as I can so this would have to have
a four loop in it basically right you
know it would have to have a thing
around the hole around the outside but
that's not our problem currently because
this is a single I that chunk at the
moment so we shouldn't actually have
that issue here so we should be able to
debug this separately what's going on
there we go we should be able to debug
this separately because since this is
inside a single eye that chunk we
shouldn't have that problem so we start
off here doing some bit consumption
right the standard kind that we normally
do let's see what we get we decompress
this stuff blah blah blah just copying
some literals here let's see what
happens when we exit out I don't know
why I can't set a breakpoint there
probably because visual studios do
butter keeps getting worse
eventually what's gonna happen is a
really bad debugger for Windows is gonna
be better than Visual Studio because
it's losing all of its features it's
nuts
alright anyway so I just want to take a
quick look I'm finna try for how to set
a breakpoint that will actually work
there so this is probably the my best
bet set a breakpoint on the the case
that actually breaks out okay
[Music]
so it goes through it goes through many
regular blocks and those all seem to
parse okay because you know you know you
notice we're never hitting like a little
encount problem or anything like that
so it looks like our Huffman table at
least for the most part works correctly
many times for what it's worth right so
we're at least not completely messed up
what I don't know is let me see where we
are in the image right now so we know
that the length of this so if we go look
for example at how big the image is
right so here's the file were actually
reading so if I look at the details here
you can see it's 81 92 by 81 92 right so
it's an 8k by 8k image so each line of
the image should be 81 92 times 4 bytes
per pixel plus one byte for the filter
so if I want to know how many rows this
is so far down I should be able to
divide this by 81 92 times 4 plus 1
right to give me which row were actually
on so we're on row 47 63 supposedly and
you can kind of see us jumping through
the file here jumping through the file
jumping through the file bla bla bla bla
bla bla and still jumping through the
file
[Music]
okay so is this just us handling some
kind of a padding thing wrong it looks
like we do
looks like we decompressed basically the
whole image let's take a look at the
actual bite count difference here so if
I want to know how many bites are in the
image right again 8192 times four plus
one is the size of one row so eighty one
ninety two of those is the total what
you can see here is we've gotten to
almost the end thus far let's take a
look at where we go from here so we're
gonna do one more so we fit I'd like
it's that's the end like the images is
done it's over so so be final should
have been set so I mean the only bug
here as far as I can tell is that be
final isn't said what's going on be
final still isn't set even after we've
decoded did I do this calculation wrong
or something I mean that looks like the
whole that that's the whole image right
I mean we've decoded the entire there's
nothing left to decode why how's it be
final been set
are you folks as confused about this as
I am
alright so here's what I'm gonna do I
miss most I want to see what the image
was because we've decoded all the bytes
did we get them all wrong are we just
like way off here or something I'm gonna
set it to just run straight to here just
straight up right something to call PNG
filter reconstruct - do you know the
back transform on it and then we're
gonna write it out because I just want
to see what it looks like so if I go
load that up in so that's in our
temp directory it's this guy right here
so I'm gonna open that up I so here's
what we loaded the Alpha Channel does
not appear to be there which I don't
think is our fault
I think that's this programs fault I
don't know if we have anything that can
actually read the Alpha Channel out of a
bitmap my recollection is that that
screws that up now of course we may have
set also we may have set the channel
information wrong for that I'm not sure
I don't know if we need to set other
information for that but ignoring all
that like we read the image I mean
there's no chant we were not garbage so
we read the whole image so now my
question is what's going on with this
stream is there something in the spec
that says that you don't need to put in
a B final chunk if you know how big the
image is you can just stop you know I'm
saying
design making sense a much like is there
something that says hey look I don't
need to set a be final I don't need to
set the final if you know how big the
thing is I'm just I'm just gonna end
without ever setting that cuz it seems
like what's goin on
I mean that really seems like what's
going on there I mean unless I guess let
me check one more thing is it possible
that the width and height are not what I
think they are or something like is it
not what was specified in the file you
know also we can get rid of this now
can't we
no I mean that's what it is
so what's going on here I guess I can go
back and look at the spec did we miss
something or is this are these PNG files
just garbage PNG files
look at these Photoshop just write them
wrong I mean cuz one of the other has to
be true because it doesn't look like
we're getting anything wrong it looks
like we got everything right so either
we're just wrong about the spec maybe I
guess
[Music]
so yeah all right let's see here
so let's look at page five
yeah I just I don't see anything in the
deflate speck which would suggest that
so how about the zips back
I'm not particularly illuminating check
PNG
so we've read this a bunch of times
before
I mean it says a marker bit in the final
block identifies it as the last block so
I mean either these are broken or
somehow we read just that bit wrong like
just that one I mean maybe it's possible
that just that one bit happened at just
the wrong time in the stream that some
in a way that no other bit would ever be
wrong seems far-fetched but you know
TNG all seasons compression in method
zero and ina Suzuki says we don't care
about those we don't read those so I
don't see it
there's some kind of like a pendeks
gamma handling color handling alpha
channel creation DEP scaling pallets
the intruder may divide the compressed
data stream to edit chunks ever wishes
multiple items are allowed so that
encoders may work in a fixed amount of
memory typically the chunk size will
correspond to the encoders buffer size a
PNG data stream in which each I touch on
contains only one data byte is valid
though remarkably wastes lose faith zero
like thatit chunks are also valid either
even more wasteful current processing
use of private chunks errors in a PNG
dishum will fall into two classes
transmission errors and syntax errors
transmission error is blah blah blah
detect area possible decoder can have
confidence the data streams tickity if
the next thing but to edit blah blah
blah there's really nothing
critical or ancillary is not really
relevant to us
I'll see anything here that suggests
that we wouldn't expect the final bit to
be set though non-square pixels can be
represented but viewers are not required
to account for them
sorry not swear pixels rather that's
fine is important up so that identifiers
are no semantic significance to occur at
any point - and there's no required
correlation to the image data yep the
complete image data is represented by a
single Zealand data stream that is
stored yep
of course is named worth so they're
correct something could actually may
emit the issues of which some of these
sources are indeed related but decoders
cannot rely on this that's fine
[Music]
interlacing a progressive display I
don't care about that
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah
we may need to look at that alpha
channel processing stuff to get the
Alpha right eventually as well if just
for gamma stuff or whatever because
there might be information that we need
but
so I guess what I would say is I'm kind
of tempted to just put in a thing that
checks to see if or at the end and if we
are we consider that be final you know
what I'm saying
yeah I don't know
yes people don't generally refer to it
as B final so I don't know I don't know
what to make of it I mean I did my due
diligence reading there here's what I'm
gonna do first because I really don't
know how to proceed from something like
this since I don't have much else to go
on what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna look
here and say that when we come back up
to the top I'm gonna say this and I what
I want to do here is just see am i right
that we actually if we terminate at that
point does the rest of the I mean does
it just work right because I don't know
how else to interpret it it doesn't seem
like we could have a bug where we it'd
be really hard to have I mean maybe
there's a way to have it but it'd be
really hard to have a bug where we can
put into D encode the entire thing
correctly and the only thing we get
wrong is just the B final bit like I'm
not sure how we would do that you know
maybe it's possible but it seems pretty
tough so I just want to see what's going
on how come that didn't what happen
there how come that didn't show me where
the where the breakpoint was okay so
there isn't one so if we just run then
we get the image back and it's right the
B final bit isn't set and I don't know
what to make of it
let's try a different one can we get any
other kind of error to occur
[Music]
I guess to view my next question so
let's suppose we took like I don't know
just some other random one
I mean it just it's so weird right I
mean it looks like they're encoders just
busted
I mean that's what it looks like I don't
know what else to make of it again it's
possible we've got it wrong it's
possible we're doing something wrong I
mean we've there we've done very little
testing on this PNG reader so it's well
within the realm of possibility that we
just did something wrong however it's
kind of a pretty tough it's hard to
think of how that would happen right
like that's a pretty tough thing to get
wrong in a way that only does that
because those bits aren't even encoded
right those bits are raw we're not
putting them through a Huffman table
they're not getting translated by any
kind of algorithm we're not looking them
up in one of those extra bits tables we
are literally just looking at a bit in
the file and saying isn't 0 or 1 and it
seems like it's zero and it should have
been 1 and everything else is correct so
it looks like
you know if i zoom in on the last row of
the image I mean I don't see any garbage
there either so not only you know this
looks exactly right this is what
Photoshop does by the way in the color
channel the Alpha is probably right but
we can't see it if that makes sense it
would be nice if we could and I guess we
will be able to see it soon we maybe
we'd have to do a tiff reader I remember
like almost nobody reads alpha out of
BMPs correctly that's my recollection
anyway so in order to see if the alpha
channels right we would have had to have
done something else there if that makes
sense what we could do there are some
things we could do if we wanted to in
terms of making it a little bit easier
for us to see that we could do something
like blends instead of just swapping the
R&amp;B rhythm and blues we could actually
blend to a pink color or something that
would make it clear so even though the
alpha channel is getting ignored we
would still have some way of seeing what
the actual alpha channel was but I'm not
so concerned about that at the moment so
anyway just looking at the Y this is
still here uh I don't know I think I'm
just gonna push forward in it I would
I'm gonna put it to do there I think
it'd be interesting for someone to
research find out whether we screwed
something up or whether the Photoshop
P&amp;G writer is just wrong and it's busted
so we'll see I don't think it's worth
going down that road at the moment
because like I said this PNG reader
really only exists for one purpose and
that is to get the art into the game as
long as the art is loading properly we
don't care if we hacked around something
so I'm fine with that
I would like to know the answer because
while it would not surprise me
even the weed it would not even raise
the smallest amount of surprise within
me to learn that Photoshop could not
write a PNG file correctly because that
is so typical that would not surprise me
at all I just don't know that that's
true because since we have very little
experience the PNG loading we only just
wrote this thing in a couple hours and
it's our first time ever looking at the
spec that said etcetera I'm not in a
position to say that they did something
wrong or did something right so I would
be interested to know a little bit more
about that maybe ask some people who've
done PNG readers before have they
noticed that discrepancy we could look
and see if there's any docs in the FTP
libraries about that if you know for all
I know you might have mentioned that
like Sean might have been like hey
Photoshop files don't do this right or
we could look to see like
what's this is your PMP
so this is the image transform stuff
yeah you can see here you go
so let's see here
here's parsing a single Huffman block
here's the Huffman code generator here's
the uncompressed block
[Music]
so type three so it looks like at least
here
it doesn't look like there's any kind of
special out there's a bunch of return
zero kind of stuff but
yeah so I don't know I'd be interested
to try running the code and see if it
actually like run it against us to be
image or something and see whether or
not it properly gets the final right I
mean or something just to see if if
we're totally out to lunch on this one
or not because I don't see anything in
here that stops that stops it that way
right it looks like it requires final to
have been properly set just like we do
and you know I don't know I mean what we
could do here too right is we could just
run this right now let's just run st the
image on it see what happens
that seems like worthwhile I don't know
I kind of want to do it because I'm just
curious I don't understand how we're
able to decode everything else properly
so it would be nice to see what goes on
in another compressor so we could see
how we could even have this bug so let's
put STV image in a temp directory here
and then all I'm gonna do is just go
into the temp directory and make like a
simple file that uses it right so this
is FTB PNG test dot CPP pound include
STV image dot H name and this will just
we'll use the exact same thing here it
just will just do it with STP image in
this program so that we can see we could
just so we can step through it right we
just need something to build STB image
so that we can step through it and we
don't need to write we don't even need
to write the output because we don't
care whether SUV gets the output right
or not we only care whether we only care
to see whether or not it gets final back
as a one that's all we want to see so we
should be able to just say from here in
fact
doesn't need an out filename you can
just do that this of course is more
correctly that way um so all we need to
do here is replace that part of the code
with something that loads it from spb
let's grab that there should be an easy
example in here that we can use let's
see
ping support blah blah blah where is
some example code please I don't know
how to use this basic usage alright so
there you go
so that's all we're trying to do here
oops we're just trying to load from in
filename and we just we just want to be
able to step through that right so now
if like if I pop back over to the shell
and I go into the temp directory I
should be able to just build this right
and oops
what's said I should be able just build
this and then if I ask it to load the
same file so that we were asking it to
which was the character hero bitmap we
should be able to now go into the bugger
and watch that loop run to see what they
got does it get the same thing we get or
does it get different because it'd be
interesting to find that out so the art
in question here is the character hero
oops it's not test art character hero
PNG so if I just run it like so
we should now be able to jump in there
and see what it got and that's really
all I want to know so I'm gonna go ahead
and do an Emma step on that oops um no I
love how you can't tap complete in the
middle of one of these like it deletes
the rest of the line so good
whoa Oh a that that was funny
it actually loaded that PNG I think
that's not what I meant but okay it's
fine
good job that's good it did it alright
so there's the argument and so what I
need to do in order to bug this I'm
gonna have to actually pass a debug
string to it there so what is that
that's like slash z7 or something is
that what we want yeah so we should be
able to step through this now you know
what I could also do I don't I don't
think it will by default but we can also
just make sure that optimizations are
disabled because we don't want to have
to deal with that either so if I step
through here I should be able to step
through the STP image loading code just
see if Sean gets the same thing we get
and if not maybe we can get a hint as to
what it is we did because it's weird
that I just don't know how we could have
gotten everything else right and that
wrong it's kind of bizarre so we should
be able to do this ping test here it
should return true and we should be able
to do a ping load so here's the ping
load we can set a breakpoint now
somewhere that's actually more relevant
to the ping should be up here somewhere
[Music]
create pinging image is not really what
we're looking for we just want that one
loop that I was just on I could search
for it but instead I'm just kind of
scrolling up like I had mindless
automaton so we've got a bunch of Zee
Lib stuff here this was where it was
right it was right up in here somewhere
so here's the Huffman codes so it should
have been right down below here tonight
a scroll just right by it see out to
code buffered code nut chunk header
check PNG
there's that part so it should have been
like right here I must have scrolled by
by yes I did
or maybe not
where is it I just I had it up just a
minute ago right
it's svi parse z lib it's online 4140
how did I miss it just blind I guess
alright so this is what we actually want
to see so let's let's jump in here parse
is the Z Lib header and we start running
so I don't really know like I said I
don't use this library I don't really
know much about it
but presumably if we take a look at the
data structures here we should be able
to see you know like Z out I assume is
like where the pixels go or something so
I'm assuming that like this start and
end tell me something about that so let
me see if I do Z out and minus Z out
start oops
you know is that yeah that's the size of
the image so we know where we are in the
image by looking presumably at the Z out
value minus the Z out start value and so
if I want to I can kind of loop through
this decompressing the image as we go
just like we did in our routine and we
can just kind of go up till we get
within striking distance and then step
through to see what happens on the Z
final for that final chunk and that
should tell us you know what's going on
right so here we go decompressing the
image exactly like we did compressed it
in our code
nothing is probably happening a typical
right now I would assume micros I don't
know off we go
not particularly exciting getting closer
now okay so now let's take a look and
see if final is ever set because that's
what we're interested in and so at some
point here we should see that flip 201
so this is the last block final is not
set to a 1 at least I think it's the
last block so let's step through this
here now we're at the end finally it's
not set
what is typeset to 0 just like ours we
go into SV stb I parse uncompressed
block which is exactly what our decoder
did so so Sean's code is doing exactly
what our code did he's attempting to to
decompress the header of the block think
I'm not sure getting some bits there and
let's take it let's take it and
disassembly so we can see what what do
you what he gets out of this if and then
[Music]
took the jump
so he matched these two Oh interesting
so he got a length of zero but we we
didn't did we
so that would make more sense if did we
read are we reading the length wrong is
that's what's happening there because
theoretically you could put a block in
here that has a length of zero right
like this is just a nod this doesn't do
anything
this is a weird decoder so assuming
again that it's right it's just got a
bunch of zero length stuff at the end of
it so do we do we have that part of our
code wrong
you know that's are we reading this
value incorrectly like maybe is our
flush flight function incorrect you know
do we do something where where where we
don't deal with the end of the stream
properly
you know I'm not sure but we do we can
see a very obvious difference between
what we read there and so I'm just
curious to know what's going on with
that let's take a look because we should
be able to do it if the SDB image
library does it then you know they're
doing basically the same thing we're
doing so the question is what did we do
wrong here got to take this out
what I might also do here is I'm gonna
assert this because we never want that
to advance past the end so I'm going to
assert that if it's even if that if it's
at the end it's ok because like we now
know there's chunks that happen after
the last chunk that just our length zero
so let's see so ok we got to go back to
this one let's give it a whirl
[Music]
why can I not why does it not know the
file doesn't make a lot of sense
why can't it
my wrist is something
how is it different from the one that
was built
all right what is it this time Microsoft
what did you do so let's delete that
build so now we know there's only one of
those and we just built it with our
current source code unbelievable
all right so anyway now we can actually
get in here and so here we are on flush
byte and let's just see if there's
something that we're doing wrong in here
that we can fix so here's our buffer at
the time there's 12 bits supposedly
still in the buffer
Oh hmm so maybe that's what it is
our flush byte call here's what it
probably is our flush byte call is
flushing potentially more than a bite
that's what it is so I think that's what
the bug is right like our flush byte
call in this case should only flush 8
bits total and these should be things
that still do a consume bits and they
should consume 16 bits right to make
sure that we still work on the even
boundaries that seems like the right
thing because flush byte right now can
flush more than that what it should do
is say flush up to the next eight bit
boundary so if it's like 12 bits are in
the buffer you want to flush 4 bits
right you want to flush Mahdi the the
bits right so I think what we want to do
here is flush byte should really do a
thing where it says like flush count
equals buff bit count Maudie so like
what's the remainder and then I want to
do a consume bits on buff of whatever
that flush count is I think that's
actually the more correct thing
yeah okay so I think that's that may
have been the problem is just where the
bite boundary was so let's see when we
so now when we read it we get the right
answer we consume a zero size which is
no problem we come through here and
presume I guess we have a whole Huffman
table that doesn't do anything it's just
a 255 okay you know who knows why
Photoshop did that all right so we have
fixed that bug that's awesome
thank you to Shawn for the reference
code so yeah that was a good bug fix
while we're in here should we do
something about this I'm not sure what
we want to do about that basically what
the consumer that wants to do is say hey
look I might only be able to consume as
much left as there is right so you know
we could bound it on content size so
like it would look something like this
i if we look at consumers
yeah so you could see here like if we
consumed exactly that we could just make
a function here right and this function
just does the operation that is the fill
you know what I guess now I think about
it I suppose we don't even really have
to do that now we do
oops I think we do want that so what we
could do is say all right look
make sure the buffer is filled at the
top so refill if necessary so make sure
the buffer is filled at the top and then
say look we're gonna have a like a
concept called Uslan and we're gonna try
to read len but if we can't then we'll
just read as much as we can
then if the end we'll say this right so
what we'll do is say all right if the
use length is greater than the comp date
the whatever the component that the
whatever the compressed data is although
in this case is not compressed because
this is the B type 0 block but if the
content size is not enough to fill to
fulfill the entire read we'll just read
it as much as we can so we'll read up to
the end copy that out and then we'll
refill it again at the
of a loop right I think that should be
sufficient there okay so I think that
should do it and now we don't have that
to do there we can get rid of that
because now we are actually looping and
we'll try to grab as much as we can so
that can straddle the iTap block
boundaries just fine
yeah so I think that's pretty good while
we're in here since we're gonna start
doing a stuff now the reverse table
thing we don't use anymore
so I believe this table can go right
that's not in there anymore so I think
what we should be able to do now is
start moving this into our mainline code
and so tomorrow we can start actually
getting these images in because it looks
like everything's fine it looks like
we're reading them properly we did have
a weird bug there where we don't handle
0 blocks but now we do so I think we're
good
and we should be able to proceed so
looking at this stuff what I want to do
is I want to now split this out this
code out into sections where I can I
want to basically have in so far as I
can the PNG reader code is just in a
thing that can be included in the game
or steal any little test app like this
because although I think we're pretty
good now you know we're we've got a fair
number of test cases we've debug forth
there's still probably some other bugs
lurking in there maybe write that one a
day maybe we'll counter another one
tomorrow we don't know so I want to make
sure that we can steal pretty easily
compile the PNG reader outside the game
as well as inside the game so I want to
make that I want to pull out the test
app part and I want that part to be
still compiling the same code as the
game so the first thing I'm gonna do
here is I'm gonna change I'm gonna split
that code up right into two parts so I
want like you know how in here we have
like the like simple coprocessor
preprocessor tests I felt right I'm
gonna do a test PNG dot CPP file the
woman do is I'm gonna start
grab stuff out of here and plunk it down
in here as necessary right and I'm gonna
leave just the very straightforward part
of the code that does the actual
decompression of the PNG that's the only
part that I'm gonna leave in there right
so just just a decoder is that all that
goes in there right so all of this stuff
is stuff that's gonna have to get done
in the that's gonna have to get done in
the actual game so we're gonna start to
modify this code but let's see here what
else we got
yeah all that stuff okay so all of this
stuff is stuff that we'll want to still
have happen and we're gonna have to sort
of make accommodations for all the
things in there that maybe wouldn't
won't work or that need you know like we
can't F printf anything to standard out
so we can't report errors in here and
it's like that so we're gonna have to
figure out how to do something then
that's fine we don't have that's not
going to be a problem so that'll all
work fine we just need now to go towards
look merging those two paths right okay
so we've got handmade PNG eh as well
again that's got some things that we
probably don't want to put in there
either so we'll see how that has to go I
think all of this stuff does want to be
in there the only question is image you
32 I don't know if we have something
similar to that currently in the asset
system something like a loaded bitmap
that's got that same week if we could
just reuse the struct if we've got
something similar to that I'm not sure
so I'm going to take a look here and see
if you've got something similar there so
we've got a loaded bitmap in there
but that's not what I was looking for we
want like that one so that's not really
what we want either
yeah so I guess we just didn't have one
of these I guess it just didn't happen
so I don't know I don't know what to
make of that
so we will need something like that and
we can promote that maybe up to a more
aggressive type at some point and we'll
see how that goes all right so anyway
going back to where we were so all of
this stuff is in the header file it can
exist in both places it doesn't use
anything that's specific - yeah - that
either way so the first thing we're
gonna have to address here is error
reporting error porting in this case is
not going to be able to go to montgomery
else and so what I'd like to do is start
to figure out how that's gonna look
right so what I want to do here is talk
about this image u32 thing that we had
here perhaps and I want to think a
little bit about how I want to do errors
so what I would like to do ideally I
think is I'd like to have it so that the
errors just get buffered up and we can
you know maybe have some way that those
errors hoovy get recorded for later
display right so there's some kind of an
understanding of what those dreams are
so I'd like the debug I'd like to
basically have those and they're not
really debug per se they're things that
actually should run in the actual game
in a sense because if you were modding
the game after the fact or something
like that even these are pieces of it
Meishan that you would want to have like
oh you tried to load a pig and the thing
was corrupted or you know the the reader
couldn't read it for some reason that
Dios palletized and we don't support
that so it's kind of like real error
reporting does that make sense so we
kind of want to be able to support that
sort of thing so what I want to do is
maybe have a thing here where where I
just have something called a text stream
I don't know I'm just thinking out loud
and I just want to make a thing that
Daisy changed these together so I have a
text stream I have a text stream entry
so there's kind of like a doubly linked
list in here and you know maybe in here
I've got so you know so I can just kind
of daisy chain these together uh to some
degree I guess I don't care that it's a
text stream maybe I just call this a
stream because I don't care what I
stream out into it you know it could be
text could be anything else I don't care
so I could just say look it's just a
stream of stuff right so it's just
something that I couldn't buffer up
information into and I can dump things
into the stream all day long if that's
what makes me happy I could do it and so
off I go right so then when I introduced
something like the streaming the input
buffer right it can have associated with
it some kind of a you know a an error
output where the error should go when an
error happens on that particular stream
and that seems pretty straightforward
now what you'll notice is these are kind
of symmetric right so what we could do
just make one of these that functions
for both input and output and it would
work right so what you can kind of see
when I started to sketch this out is
this and this actually look the same so
what I could do is just say look there's
this is now what this is these are
basically the same I can make the
content size be six sixty four-bit if I
want to I'm not sure if I want to yet or
not that's the only thing that I would
have to think about there but otherwise
these things are the same and so I can
just kind of implement these using the
same structure so that tells me that I
just have a thing that I want here right
I want a handmade stream file I want to
have this thing in it I'm probably going
to want to rename it to just stream I
don't think as you all stream in it like
we don't need to make a gerund out of it
for no reason so here we go right we've
got the two and I can just put all of
those stream informations in there right
so all of this stuff consume endian
swapping is kind of just generic that
can be put inside some other file but
yeah all of this other stuff here like
peek bits discard bits to bits flush
pipe reverse bits all that stuff can
just go in here and I think that's all
we need right
yeah um so what I should be able do now
is I should be able to rename these it's
a strong it's a strong um so what I
should be able to do here like I said is
these this streaming buffer should allow
me to like stick stuff into it and and
pull stuff out of it now right and I'm
gonna just rename it from streaming to
stream because yeah no point in really
doing that
inside handmade PNG now I want to
include that sorry inside not handed PNG
but test PNG and also inside the build
file I I want I don't want to build a
handmade PNG by itself anymore it's
actually test PNG that's what I'm
actually building and I'll have to
change the program that we're launching
accordingly
so anyway inside here we've got to
change the name of this as well but once
we do that we should be pretty good to
go alright so if I then go back and look
here I've got to include it like so and
I've got include the handmade PNG code
as well yeah okay so also in here I
would I will need the actual code so
I'll need handmade PNG dot CPP oops and
handmade stream that CPP alright
okay
so next thing we've got to do here is
handmade P&amp;G is no longer a thing right
it's test P&amp;G now and so test P&amp;G eggsy
is the actual eggsy we need and in here
I can set up its arguments to do the
stuff that we wanted to do just like we
were doing it before so we should still
be able to run it and it should still
work like I said but we haven't really
made any modifications to it yet we've
just begun to split things up so the
first thing I'd like to do is maybe not
allow access to any of these things
inside the code that shouldn't have
access to them so I think we want to do
something more like that and that way
when we come through and do the compile
the compiler will now point out to us
all of the places in our code where we
are using things like an F printf that
we should no longer be using because
this code wants to be shared between the
external reader and the internal like
game code and F printf is not gonna cut
it for that because we don't even have
an F printf in our game code so now that
we've done that split and we've talked a
little bit about how that stream stuff's
going to work so what I want to do here
is say all right if we've got an output
stream so maybe we change stream buffer
because that's not very necessary
anymore we just call that to just stream
like so
there we go
anybody else still doing that stream
alright so now we need to do is make a
version of this F printf right that
actually is going to be targeting a
stream buffer instead of a C stream so
inside our stream function here you can
imagine us but you know taking a look at
how we would get this in there we need
some kind of a function that writes to
one of these buffers so you know we
could do something like okay you know
we've got a stream target here we have
the format string that's the you know
this thing whatever this thing is and
then we've got you know a bunch of bunch
of extra parameters that get stuffed in
there as as we go right now the question
is do we want to make this for it
potentially a macro I think we might
we don't have an odd F anywhere else do
we oops
so I think we might want to make this a
macro and the reason that I say that is
because if we make this a macro like so
then what we could do in this
circumstance is actually provide
additional information to the out F
function that we wouldn't have had
otherwise so for example we can provide
file on line number information here
which would allow the streaming
information to have additional like
debug info associated with it for
example which might also be handy again
just looking for words so something like
that may be interesting and relatively
easy for us to do pretty cheap so if I
change all of these and say okay from
now on every F printf is actually an out
F right now all of those functions will
be correct
however they have kind of arbitrary
stuff like standard out or whatever in
them what's the light that's a weird
error did I mess up that macro I don't
think that should be the area that we're
getting here I totally messed that up
don't ask me what that was supposed to
be that's where I wanted to put that
let's try that again yeah so now we're
fine the only problem that we have here
is that when we're doing our F that
first part they're like standard error
or whatever that isn't actually a real
target right we need to provide an
actual stream of some kind that we
use and we're gonna want to make that a
little bit more we're gonna want to make
there be some way that it can
automatically tell what it does
consumption of us on a stream where the
error should go so what I want to do is
have every stream can have another
stream that it just points to and it can
it can do so or not it could be a zero
and I'll be fine with that and if it's a
zero the areas this won't get reported
anywhere but if it's non zero then the
errors on that stream will get reported
to the error stream we're actually just
get dumped in there and maybe on the
stream chunk thing here we'll also say
that this can have a file on line number
attached to it as well
right so basically we can we can keep
track of where any given stream trunk
came from and then we also have
information about for any given stream
where the errors go on that stream so
what I can do here is say all right we
know where the errors would go here they
go to the errors on an underflow right
let's keep looking
so in here for example when we load in
the this PNG what we could do is say
well you know these aren't none of these
are errors these are informational so we
could do is say look when you parse the
PNG you can also give me a stream that's
just like an info stream so just you
know a place where you want me to send
any informational output that I'm gonna
have
right so all of these are just
informational they have nothing to do
with with errors so then when we have
our errors again on this we know exactly
what we're talking about here it's going
to be the errors stream of that
compressed data for the filter
reconstruction it if it's going to have
an error in there that needs to again
have an error stream we don't have the
buffer here so we're gonna have to pass
it so then when we come through here
again that's the comp data errors I
believe and then in the PNG filter
reconstruct groups same thing so then
when we parse the PNG we want to be able
to provide both of those things we want
to be able to provide the the us we want
to be able to provide a stream for
information as well as the stream for
errors and so that's what we're gonna do
here so what I want to do is start up by
creating two strings
and all I'm gonna do here is say look I
want you to make a new expandable memory
stream and maybe it's not even an
expandable noice you're me I'm just
gonna call this like an on-demand memory
stream so like basically every time you
need to put something in it
you know allocate more space right just
I don't know you figure it out for now
so we'll we'll get a little bit further
down that road in a second
we should probably pass a memory arena
here that the stream would use for
growing its size but you know we'll
cross that bridge we come to it so these
now again can also be done this way so
we can kind of unify this stuff into one
place so that we don't have multiple
dependencies here so we don't depend on
the C library for things we don't really
need to
[Music]
so that would would unify all of that
and then if we take a look up here we
kind of have some other things where
we're like okay you know read entire
file that has errors we can pass a
stream there for errors as well and we
want to do that because when we have
this stream that comes through as a
result we want that stream to get the
error stream that we're talking about
here right so this will also be an F
that goes to whatever the error stream
is for this result file because that's
where that should go same thing would
happen up here where we do the right top
down image we print out an error for an
unable to write the output file we might
as well again just go a whole hog and
have the error stream be passed in there
like so and
okay you need to implement that but once
we do all of that then this stuff would
just work okay parse P&amp;G also needs to
take the info screen but I think that's
it so then we're down to just okay now
we get these things the info stream in
the air stream those streams are things
that now have all of that stuff baked
into them what I would like to do now is
just have a way to recover that
information and of course it's pretty
straightforward for us to do that what
we can do is now just say all right
let's do a four I loop through the
chunks of the stream that we're talking
about here so let's do stream chunk
chunk equals info stream or I should
let's just do it this way let's say
stream first chunk chunk next that loops
over all the chunks in a stream then
what I can do is say all right
whatever the dest is I'm gonna do an F
printf to that destination with whatever
the contents of the stream actually was
I can actually view that as an F right
in this case because we know the size
ahead of time
so I can just say whatever the it sector
like that whatever the chunk contents
are I'm gonna put them out to that
destination file and I'm just gonna put
do that for all the chunks right now
what I would also like to do is in
between those I'm gonna actually just
because I can print out the file and
line number information because why not
so what I'll do here is say okay here's
the file here's the line and then here's
the stuff as it came
so the file name and the line number
these are optional we don't have to
print these out I'm just deciding - so
that's all good what I can do is then
make this into a little function this is
going to be called something like jump
stream to see runtime library and what
this will do is it'll take one of our
streams and then take one of their
streams and do the copy so then when we
get to the end I can just say alright
let's do a dump stream to see RT of the
info stream and the error stream this
will go to standard out this will go to
standard error and what I can also do
here is actually just do an F printf
that says info and then another one says
like errors or something like this so
those will be separated out and easy to
see I think that's all we really need
for the boilerplate so what we need to
do now is just actually have some way of
getting these things allocated if I go
to the stream functions here I can
define this as something that we will do
like so zooming and then our problem is
that you know these two functions are
now getting used but they don't exist
anywhere so if I come through here and
actually make them exist somewhere as
you can see
we should compile and moreover we should
actually run and what will happen now is
we just don't get any output right and
the reason we're getting output because
those streams don't dump anywhere that's
totally fine we don't care we can
address that later so I'll go to the Q&amp;A
now and then tomorrow we'll start
integrating that stuff in
so what is the focus now this logging
air system Wells not only a system it's
just some place to put the errors on the
PNG I don't know that it's a focus
right I mean at the risk of restating
exactly what I just said about 20
minutes ago so if a PNG fails to load we
need some way to see that it failed to
load but we need to see that fail to
load in the game and moreover we need to
be associated with the PNG that failed
so instead of these things going to the
console they need to go to a buffer that
we can print in the game
make sense so everywhere we call a
printf we just want to make it shunt
over to somewhere else it's not a system
it's just it's really straightforward
I'm not sure how that's I don't know
yeah I don't know how that got confusing
but point being you can't call F printf
if you're not a console app right so you
need somewhere to put that error
information and furthermore artist is
not going to look at a console so what
you want to do is when they put the PNG
in and it doesn't load you want to have
a thing in there that's like hey this
BMP named this that you just tried to
load here's the errors and you want them
split the reason I split them into two
different streams info and error is
because the errors are the only ones the
artist should probably be seeing you can
do that in a couple different ways but
what is the focus now this error like a
system we're answered that I haven't
been following the PNG streams closely
but how satisfied are you with the code
for the reader it seems fine to me
I mean I'm satisfied as long as it reads
it which it seems to be so far so I'm
pretty happy with it it didn't take very
long to write and it reads the files
that's really all we cared about we
don't have any other requirements for it
if that makes sense so in other words
that we don't need this reader to be
fast we don't need it to do anything
other than read just the bits of the
image so you know as long as it does
we're done and it seems like it does so
I'm happy with that could explain the
bug that was solved again sure so the
bug that we had was that the PNG
specification specifically says that if
you not the PNG that's slightly
misstated the deflate specification
which is the algorithm that PNG
references for its compression so it's
the it is effectively the spec for PNG
but it's not in the spec for PNG it's a
it's a much earlier compressor that the
PNG is just saying we're using it the
spec for deflate says that if you get a
block that is uncompressed so it does
not go through the Huffman and stuff
then first before you read the sizes to
copy uncompressed you must flush any
bits that you were still that you still
had left over from the Huffman stuff
right the problem was our Huffman bit
buffer was 16 bits long but the spec
says only flush up to the byte boundary
I flushed the whole 16 bit boundary
which means that we flushed 8 bits more
than we should have because we had 4
bits left in the buffer plus 8 bits
because it was 12 bits total I should
have only flushed 4 bits and then
started using the 8 bits that came next
instead I flushed all 12 bits so the fix
was just only flush up to the next byte
boundary don't accidentally flush a
whole extra byte if your bit buffer
happens to have that in it that's all
is to do comment still in the code I
don't know which part are we talking
about it's like that's the only one
we've got we've got plenty of to do's
elsewhere in the code but that's the
only one that's in that particular file
so
[Music]
and he plans to switch to LLVM anytime
the series no although when we compile
the code on Mac or Linux assuming report
to those platforms at some point they
are clang based so we would we would use
LLVM on those platforms it's the native
it's the native compiler
and that's a good question by the way
Asaf about whether you can load BMPs
with alpha inside Visual Studio I have
no idea doesn't look that way
or we're just we may be setting the
bitmap values wrong but it doesn't even
think there is an alpha Channel right so
I don't know if we need to set something
else you know maybe maybe we need to set
some other flag in the header to get it
to understand I seem to remember us
having to do something like that
originally I don't know I don't much
care because we don't really need to
know that but you know for reference if
you care what the Alpha channel is and
you only have a bitmap writer you can
also it's pretty easy right to add test
code that will get will give you the
information you want so you know what
you do is you just say like
something like this so what you can do
is you say like oh yeah okay so you know
something like this
so when you come in here and this is you
know because since this is not
performance critical code you can just
have a flags that just says like or you
know pixel ops it's like hey do you want
to replicate the alpha out and do you
want to swap something like this and
then you just implement those and you
can write out the Alpha Channel and see
what it actually is so you know in this
case we would just say okay the Alpha is
just C shifted down by 24 and then you
just you put that in every channel
right so this allows you to make
something that'll do a bunch of pixel
ops to the thing that you know whatever
you want to do and so then when you
write it you can write it twice you know
so you basically say like oh yeah you
know there's an RGB and an out a and we
check to see should be bitmap to write a
bitmap file to write or alpha and then
we just write both of these like so so
we just need to put them in in the flags
field which one of those we want to do
so like pixel op swap bar and pixel up
rip away or whatever
so that's that's really it and then if
we were to run this code we should be
able to then ask it for both of these
things um so like there's an RGB version
and then there's a W temp character here
Oh a you know an alpha version and you
know I kind of slammed that coach I'm
not sure if it's right but you get the
idea right so here you can see let me
delete this
I messed that up straight there so if I
run that now it should put one chip at
the RGB out to one bitmap in the Alfa to
another right so here's the Alpha
Channel right and you can see it's nice
looks like what an artist probably made
right and then you can see the the RGB
part here and you know you can have
other stuff you could have other ops as
well ones that you could multiply you
know you could have the Alpha replica
like the Alpha could multiply the image
to like put out a premultiplied alpha
right if you want to so there's a lot of
things you could do like if you know if
you want to see something like this
to isolate the channels right so that
gets us out channel zero trail one
channel two we get out the alpha then we
can do is just like multiply each of
these right by the Alpha now the thing
you have to remember is each of its like
to be five times 25 is not 255 right
this is that floating point so you end
up with an alpha value that's not
actually correct there so you need to
shift it down by eight this is a lossy
multiply so you actually two to five
took two to five shifted down by eight
is gonna leave you with one bit missing
so instead of 255 you know I can show
you what I mean so if I take 55 and I
multiply it by 55 its 6502 five right
dividing that by 256 I don't get 255
right so I lose one bit at the bottom
just so you know if you actually want
your 255 that's we've got to equal to
vibe you have to do the math a different
way and we're not gonna do that right
now we don't care about that at all in
this code but it's just so that you
understand what we're talking about here
so if I then repack the results now
we've got a multi and I could put in
here like that so another thing we could
do is for the RGB Channel right if I
wanted to I could put in a mul channel
up there so that you know when we run
this thing it'll it'll
clear out the parts of the image that
were not that didn't have a positive
alpha values or whatever Oh
or not what did I do wrong there have
school did I swap the channels c0 oh no
I just didn't use the swap Channel I
need to still do that
there we go so of course it helps if I
actually call it
sooo Michael I don't know what I called
that there yeah I so now what I call it
it should clear out you know the part of
the image the part of the RGB that
doesn't have an alpha value will get
cleared and so you can kind of see that
composited together if you care right so
this is a premultiplied alpha image now
just gives you ways of viewing them so
if you only have a three channel output
and you need to see these it's not the
end of the world it's still pretty
simple to do so will there be any blog
post on my rocket for any of the
products anytime I kind of missed those
yes actually there will be maybe a month
or two so no crap I am confused while
you shift the multiply down by eight
bits wouldn't you want to mask with oxf
f no so what you have to remember is
that when you do a fixed point multiply
which is what this is the basis gets
multiplied in and must be corrected for
and that's really what's happening here
and since we've never really well maybe
we have covered this I'll just say it
again
so what happens here is we're really
trying to say that we have a number
between zero and one
right and ideally this would be zero to
one where we include both ends of the
interval an in floating-point this just
works we have zero point zero and we
have one point O and anywhere in between
these work exactly right to within
floating point precision so 1.0 x 1.0
equals 1.0 right 1.0 x 0.5 equals 0.5
these are exactly what we want to have
happen half of the 1.0 is 0.5 right but
what happens in FP could also be fixed
fixed point so let me just say in float
right but in fixed point something very
different happens right because when I
say that I have zero to one in fixed
point what I really have is 0 to 255
over 255 right makes sense so it's not
this it's this so when I look at these
values if I have if I look at exactly
these three things if I have zero point
zero that's actually 0 over 255 right if
I have one times one equals one
what I actually have is 255 over 255
times
255 / 255 right that's what I actually
have and I want that to equal this is
what I want that's equal to 55 over 55
right that that's what I'm actually
trying to do the problem is it's just
happening in the cpu in an integer
multiplied it doesn't know there was a
secret over 255 in the mix it just says
255 times 255 and so if you get rid of
all of these divisors which is what will
happen in the CPU its 255 35 is it 255
25 times 255 right is that number we saw
before 6502 5 right you see what I mean
so every time you do a fixed point
operation you must yourself right you
must yourself do the multiplication of
the denominator which in this case also
comes out to 6502 5 right you must do
that and then you since you are
interpreting it as over to 5 you must
map that denominator back to 255 you
must do this equation 6 5 o2 5 right /
what so what is call that x equals 255
right and you must find that value and
in this case as you can see right that
value is going to be 25 right if you
solve for X here you get x equals 255
makes sense so yeah the reason you lose
a bit this is 502 5 divided by 2 to 5 is
be cut loops sorry
6 did I just type that right 6 5 oh I
think I did yeah the reason that you
lose a bit there right is because if I
was to actually divide by 255 which is
the what I want to do I would hack
should have to actually do an integer
divide here
I chose not to because a shift is faster
so I shifted down by eight which
actually divides by 256 so dividing by
256 is not the same as dividing by 255
so you lose that one bit of precision
when you do it that way so now your
recommendation was why can't you just
and with Oh X F F well what would that
do
shifting by eight right is the same as
dividing by 255 I'm sorry
256 which is very close to what I wanted
to do which was divided by 256 I'm sorry
to 55 ending with Oh X F F is nothing
like that that is mod 256 so rather if
you look at what happens rather than
take here's our 16-bit value the color
that we want is up here and there's 200
there's a 8 bits of fractional right
because we multiplied 25 by 25 we got
the colors up here with and we've got a
bunch of fractional precision down here
that we're trying to throw away this
shift moves the color back into the
position we want the the and we'll just
get the fractional precision so all
you're gonna get is a fractional
precision of how close in between those
two values between the lower color on
the higher color that we can actually
present where you were in there so an
and is exactly the wrong thing here
because we're trying to divide to move
our value back into the range hopefully
that makes some sense
can you briefly explain how the binary
reverse works you in fronted last week
uh it's just it's totally dumb it
doesn't do anything it's it's the
dumbest possible thing we literally just
have like if we have a number like this
we literally just go through we hand out
one of the bits we see if it's 1 or 0 we
get that value and we and it into the
opposite position so we just we
literally just swap bits that's all
weird it's like the dumbest possible
thing we we don't do anything smart
there at all actually let me see where
that actually is there spits where is
that here it is this should not be in
the stream that should actually be in
the pantry um so you can see it's right
here we just loop through the bit count
right we say look grab out that bit and
let's put it back we'll flip it to the
opposition since we know this is a
symmetric operation let's also just take
wear whatever the bit was in the flipped
position and flip that one as well so
basically we swap right we read this one
in this one and we switch their
positions right that and that's all this
is doing this grabs out the two
different bits on either side and this
slides them up you can see these are
symmetric right we grab the bit that's
at bit index and we shove it up to the
position that's the opposite of that and
then we grab the bit that's at the
position that's the opposite and we put
it into the one that we just grabbed
right so we're just swapping them in the
or allows us to build up the value
periodically there's probably way
smarter ways to reverse the bits than
that I'm guessing I think we look some
up on stream but we just don't care like
we don't care we only use it for
building the Huffman table so it don't
have to be fast
alright looks like we're all done okay
alright thank you everybody for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with this series at home you can always
peer to the game on handmade hero it up
or come to the source code so you can
follow along with it and if you want to
be up-to-date on what we're doing at
Molly rocket including handmade hero
stuff you can always drop your email
into our mailing list it's finally up
they did the hammer here web page so
it's cop the mailing with sign up on it
and subscribe we send out email only
when we've got something to say so it
will clog up your inbox that's it for
this week I will be back I'm sorry
that's it for today I'll be back
tomorrow we are not done for the week
where we'll finish that stream buffering
for the errors and then we'll try to
move the PNG reader into handmade hero
proper so we can just load that art and
from there we'll start to figure out how
we want to do like testing to make sure
we can detect when art changes and stuff
like that
so we'll be going from there again this
is gonna be a couple weeks of work for
sure because we kind of are making a
whole system for ingesting these aren't
files but you know I think it'll be
pretty smooth saying there's not too
much complex stuff in there it's a
pretty straightforward process we're
doing there's just a couple different
things we got touched so we'll be doing
that hope see you back here for that
until tomorrow have fun programming and
I'll see everyone on the Internet take
it easy everybody