hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show we code a complete game
live on stream we are going to try today
to actually do some graphics debugging
yesterday we wanted to do some graphics
debugging but mostly what we did was we
worked around two very classic villains
in the development world windows and
graphics drivers so one of the things
that's annoying about programming
graphics one of the things that I think
is kind of the worst sort of part of
graphics programming that's happened
over the past you know 20 years or so in
its evolution is that the actual chips
that run the graphics now are not really
designed with debug ability in mind so
you know one of the things that you have
to appreciate is an Intel chip you know
an X 64 or something like this actually
has a tremendous amount of engineering
in it specifically for you know ease of
use basically by developers and by
system administrators I mean it has all
sorts of things like the ability to have
separated rings of access the ability to
have threads that switch in and out the
ability to put in hardware interrupts
that can you know cause things to happen
and all of these things are designed
quite well to allow you to have a good
debugging experience and a good virtual
machine and process swapping experience
such that you almost never have any
problems with multitasking or debugging
that are due to a chip right it just
sort of works and that's pretty great
actually GPUs on the other hand don't
have anything like that they are not
really designed for consistent use in
that way they're getting a little bit
better but they don't really have a
coherent complete standardized story on
things like virtual memory and hardware
debugging and ring access and all these
other sorts of things
they are trying to do that slowly and so
hopefully you know someday we'll get
there but the reality is you know if
you've been programming with GPUs over
the past ten years or so I you typically
have an experience like we had yesterday
where it's just extremely laborious to
even get basic rudimentary debugging
functionality working not because
there's some kind of extraordinary thing
that you're trying to do with respect
that debugging but literally just like
even just stepping through a shader to
see what it does is kind of considered a
you know Herculean task so that if it
actually works you're you know
flabbergasted that it didn't crash and
that it actually ran and didn't do
something like render doc did yesterday
where it flames out and can't like do
anything at all so we had that problem
and we're using insight now which sort
of kind of works it's extremely slow and
error-prone but it sort of works and
then we also ran to a secondary problem
when we were trying to use insight which
we had not encountered before because
this is our first time developing on
Windows 10 and apparently we or you know
we hit what is I guess a Windows 10 bug
that is absolutely abhorrent they send o
X 738 to your window procedure
infinitely if you're not careful this is
a kind of a blatantly illegal thing to
be doing as far as the API is concerned
that's a WM user Raines message which
should never be sent to anyone's window
it's only for people to send to their
own windows basically so we had to debug
that yesterday which was also a whole
heap of fun because you're not expecting
that to happen and that's apparently
only on Windows 10 so that's great but
now in theory we may finally be able to
do some actual development today and so
that's what we're gonna try and do now
remember all we really want to do here
is see if we can take a look at what's
being done in the graphics driver for
our light rendering code and that's you
know that
really the the long and short of it you
know like there's there's no other
fanciness that's it's trying to happen
here we just want to take a look and see
if we can understand anything about the
the textures we're submitting and what's
going on so I'm gonna try to avoid using
the graphics to bugger still like kind
of like we used to be debugging it where
we didn't really use the graphs to debug
err very much the reason I'm gonna do
that is because you saw how Genki it was
yesterday so we'll use it when we need
it when we can't figure out another way
to test it but we're gonna try and use
it lightly so yeah I mean I don't know
what to say other than this is this is
why GPU programming sucks and it would
be nice if someday we add a stable GPU
experience with development just like we
do on a CPU and sometimes we take the
cpu development experience for granted
and probably we shouldn't because just a
quick attempt to do program debugging on
a GPU should remind you just how bad
GPUs are at this and just how good CPUs
consistently are with no prodding you
know like nobody has to beg Intel or AMD
to ship a chip that you can debug
cleanly alright so for starters I'm
tired of this weird like developer news
page nonsense coming up and I believe
you can switch that in here so I'm gonna
yeah I like we like we ever want to
download content from Microsoft while
we're developing that's an interesting
idea so I'm gonna go ahead and verify
that we can just launch our program
directly when we open up visual studio
from now on let's eat there it is so
that's much better so where are we left
off we fixed that Oh x7 3/8 bug that
Windows 10 had introduced technically
what we did is we fixed a bug in Windows
10 in our code we did not actually have
a bug ourselves but there
you go so when I hit the f1 key this is
recomputing a lighting solution and I
believe this lighting solution is
actually somewhat correct it's not a
great letting solution but it is
actually like a real life solution that
we computed and it's not all black and
we can verify that by re by turning on
the old color using the colors that
don't come from the lighting solution so
in here where we do our lighting
computation we use this while loop to
look up the lights and so on what we can
do instead of over writing this this use
light stuff here I believe if we just
tell it not to over write we would get
the old color that was being sent down
directly from the engine and so yeah you
can kind of see that here so if I hit f1
to do the lighting computation you can
kind of see that it actually is is doing
some lighting meaning you know there's
some yellow lights here that we're
seeing there's some white lights here
that we're seeing and the light probes
that are around here that the lighting
element points that are doing the
reflection actually do have correct
colors I mean like I said we're not
doing much in the way of a good lighting
solution or anything like that at the
moment but we are actually doing
something that resembles lighting where
as what we're getting when we actually
go into when we actually try to use that
letting solution we're getting just
blackness so what we're trying to do now
is kind of claw our way back to having
this work properly which currently it is
not so the first thing that I'd like to
do is try to figure out whether the
Texel fetch stuff is working at all or
whether you know there's sort of like
two parts of this program that can be
broken the first part of the program
that could be broken is the lighting
lookup itself so you can see we've got
this kind of weird situation here and it
looks like we're stuffing a value for a
lookup right now
that we thought was one that should have
had some light in it I think that's why
we were doing that testing before if you
remember correctly I forgot that we were
doing this exact thing here if you
remember we looked at this yesterday
actually and I was like I don't remember
why we're doing that this was the front
emit thing I guess I'm not sure why we
were looking I guess we're just looking
for something where the front emit red
was greater than 0.5 something that
would have a bright cell in it this
debug XD bug why debug Z is probably
just what we filled in here so we were
forcing the issue of looking up a light
that should have had something in it
right but instead this light I this is
never getting entered the reason we know
that it's never getting entered is that
we never get any green at all here so
there's two possible things that could
be happening the first one is that this
lookup is busted and instead of actually
looking up into this location like it's
supposed to it's actually just totally
wrong you know like maybe it looks up
into the wrong place and the texture or
maybe this 6 5 5 3 5 +5 stuff doesn't
work so the cast like maybe we're not
converting it up converting it to a
light index properly and so we can't do
our textile fetch correctly you know who
knows right we have no idea what's going
wrong here but it could be any of those
things once we come in here this part
we've taken out of the equation so we
know that this can't be wrong because
we're just stuffing the light value with
green so if the light look up here had
succeeded at all then we would get into
this loop and we would see green right
of course the only thing I'm not sure
about is we wouldn't get out of the loop
well I guess we would cuz we'd still be
looking it up this way
so I guess that's okay we could force
our way out of the loop if we wanted to
we could break here right out of the
loop or change this to an if right so in
that sense we could do it so but anyway
so something in that light lookup could
be wrong and so that's one thing we have
to worry about but there's another thing
that we have to worry about and that is
that we're not actually sending down in
the valid texture data so we know when
we output our cubes right when we output
those cubes we know that they had the
lighting values that we were expecting
to see what we don't know is whether or
not the texture has that property right
we're trying to send down a 3d texture
that will mirror the information that is
in those cubes we don't actually know
whether that's succeeded and that's you
know another whole part of the problem
that could be wrong and so maybe this
code is actually correct or even if it's
in error maybe it doesn't matter that
it's an error yet because we just don't
have a valid texture set to look up into
we're packing it wrong we're sending it
down wrong we're setting it up
incorrectly so the shader can't read
from it correctly all of those things
could be wrong and again since we can't
step through anything or see anything
it's always this nasty problem of like
okay we've got to start blackbox
debugging it all right so let's start by
saying how are we actually putting these
things together right at the moment I
think what we're doing is we're trying
to do when we output our lighting
textures right you can see us doing it
here I think this in this piece right
here is pretty much where we're doing
all of the packing I can watch this
thing pack by using this if statement
we've already got in there
right so if I go ahead and and pause
over to that I thought there was there's
also some way how do we leave windows
pinned I know there was something about
that that you can do
[Music]
yeah solutions no shipping just a rush
of pin button and pinned tabs maintain
pß damage from well manifest be opened
in the preview tab I think that's what
we don't want
so anyway I'm gonna take a look in here
in output loading textures and I'm gonna
run and now I hit f1 I should get in
there I'm gonna look to see when we hit
this and I'm gonna just to see when
we're when we've arrived
I'm gonna take a look at what that that
debug XD bug Weiss and I'm gonna watch
it pack it so here's the debug X oops
x-man that is just awful is there that's
another setting it would be nice to fix
is there a way to make it go to the next
line in the watch window because man
they change that from the old one and
that just yeah I have no idea why you
would ever change that it seems nuts
because it's literally just worse but I
don't know I don't know if they even
like realize they changed it I can't
imagine that they did but maybe cooking
general
[Music]
know what just my code is but it sounds
not good
oh man it looks like we're sad there's
nothing on there
I really hope one of the handmade
debugger projects gets functional soon
all right
126 113 27 I'm gonna take a quick look
and make sure that's what it would yes
so so you can see exactly what we were
doing there right we were just trying to
take the first voxel that we knew had
something in it and we were gonna try
and use that so let's see here I guess
we should really be compiling this in
debug mode but anyway so in the P next
texture here and the look up at texture
all right let me actually do this in
debug mode so we can inspect all our
variables I just want to see if like it
looks like we're putting stuff into that
location or whether it's kind of looks a
little bogus I'm not sure which we've
done yet because it's been a long time
since we coded due to the difference
between debug and release for this is
pretty dramatic
all right so here we are I'm gonna take
a look at various informations so the
PAC index here the PAC index is just
which one of these were actually at
right we plus plus it instead of you
know we plus plus PAC index instead of
pack and X plus plus because we want to
leave the 0 with elements as nothing
because we want to be able to have the
idea to specify a null so light index 0
is like the non light so light index 1
would be the first to me pack we've
packed a great number of these already
612 this one right here our packing is
number 613 we are asserting that it's
within the range of lights that we are
allowed to pack which we you know we did
and so now we're taking a look at the
actual element we're gonna pack here so
here's P next it's got a floating-point
position of nothing and the next pointer
of nothing and now we're going to
specify that the element which is the
the actual light we calculated we're
gonna specify that the position value is
going to be is going to take on that of
its element which it does and that's
good we're gonna make the next one be
whatever was at the lookup already at
this moment which was nothing and then
we're gonna set the lookup equal to our
pack index so now it's basically a
singly linked list that points to this
element and that does not have any other
element in it like it doesn't have any
other there's not some other light that
needs to go in there so then we're gonna
come through I wonder if again we'll
have the same one 129 113 27 so I guess
not
we're actually we've moved a little bit
so I wanted to see whether the
daisy-chaining was working
but it doesn't look how I'll be able to
quite that way I don't really care if
the daisy-chaining is working yet to be
fair because it looks like we're having
a problem more significant than the
daisy-chaining
so it doesn't look like it's really that
important to debug that part the desk
color part I'm not sure we really looked
at that what's going on in there I
assume so we are packing a pretty
reasonable value into there as well so
all of this looks you know saying to me
I don't see you know I don't see a lot
of a lot of cruft there so I'm going to
come in here to where we do our render
element this is what's going to transfer
the lighting actually down this is the
record that flows through to the
renderer and if we look at what we
specify here I want to make sure that
we're doing the right thing with respect
to sending these textures down so here's
our P next value that we've specified
and I just want to look at like the
first 32 values of it right and what you
can see I don't know why it's showing me
I guess we declared it as a float
[Music]
that's just a float pointer I guess we
declared this just as a pointer to
floating point data which is probably
makes sense because we're probably
sending it down that way but anyway you
can see that it's got reasonable stuff
in it I mean it's got positions and then
it's got occasional next pointers it
should anyway if we look down there
should be some floats that look absurd
of course they won't be any of the first
ones probably it would probably be more
of ones later on let's see if that's
true yeah so what you can see here is
we're starting to get next values their
reason they're ridiculous floating point
valves because they're actually integers
right so if I if I took this and said
instead of you know you don't don't
think of it as a float I think it was an
integer then we can see we get like
bogus integers and then real for the
position values and then real integers
for the next values right the P values
are you know those are actually float
and these are in so the you know that's
that's a pointer to the data that we do
actually want to submit that looks like
it's correct you know so that's good and
then we've got these other ones here and
I'll just take a look at them that's C
is the color channel and these all look
pretty sane
[Music]
that's an alpha value of zero and I'm
sorry an alpha value of one and the rest
is zero let me make sure that some of
these somewhere have some color value in
them yes they do
right so you can see that those are
colors and so finally we'll take a look
at the lookup
here's the look up and this is just the
first for any given voxel cell this is
the first light that it should use not
seeing a lot in there what I might do
here is say alright let's take a look at
how big this guy actually should be and
actually just look at all of it to see
whether it's filled out at all so if we
do that that is in handmade platform and
we can see the dimensions listed here
I've got a pound to find for them
it's 256 by 2 2 X by 32 and so 256 by 2
X by 2 so there's 2 million entries in
the voxel and so I should be able to
take a look at Memory they're gonna get
a memory window back I should be able to
take a look at the memory here actually
I think I will leave it down here and
take a look at it's a little bit behind
my head was the only reason that was a
little hesitant there
so I believe well actually it's actually
a two byte integer right I think was the
way lookup currently works and so we can
just kind of scroll through here if we
want to know what the address would be
where we would end we now know that it's
2 times 2 million right so this is the
last address of one pass the last
address of our voxel lookup so what I
can do is just say well I'm starting at
the 110 let me just scroll through and I
know that until I hit that end point
that that we're all in the voxel right
so admittedly not seeing much here right
we know we have to e so right now it's
DD and we know we have till II so you
know maybe it's just all this stuff is
all zeroes for most of it there was one
you should get in some areas that are
pretty dense though like one look up and
the entire thing does not seem good
there's some more
I will say it's pretty sparse I wonder
if we messed up our voxels somehow
because in theory it should be fairly
tightly bounded like we just used a mill
well we don't actually know that there
could be something throwing off our
bounds we should probably look at what
the bounds are of the voxel so I think
maybe the right thing to do just based
on looking at this is just to visualize
the voxel maybe and verify that we're
not stuffing anything incorrect in there
it's hard to say because there's the
voxel is so big and this is this is the
bane of three dimensionality right it's
it's got it's got two million entries
it's very hard to think about that and
go well just looking at this array does
it feel like it's correct you know
and yeah I mean it's really hard to make
that a judgement call so I think it's
probably something we want to draw out
because they don't think it's reasonable
do you expect me to be able to guess
whether we're you know maybe this really
is still correct because there are
entries in it it's not completely empty
the fact that it's fairly sparse might
just mean well hey we're still looking
at the beginning part of it maybe it
gets really dense later in the parts
that we expect but even then if I see a
dense part later we still it could be
that we're not aligning properly and so
when we go to look it up it's wrong and
bla bla bla bla bla right so yeah so
we've got a lot of issues there to say
the least
all right so let's think about this here
let's take a quick look and see if
there's anything we can tell about our
voxel lookup and the other thing we
could do here is if we read from the
voxel lookup maybe we can make something
that puts cubes out into the voxel
lookup that would help us understand
what we're actually seeing in there for
example so one of the things when we hit
f1 that we're doing right now one of the
things that we would like to be able to
see is could we get those cubes to show
us more about what's going on in the
voxel and when we do output I guess
what's output lighting verts that we're
doing are we doing a protection debug
yeah so when we do output texture debug
that we come through here we're we're
pushing cubes we are pushing cubes based
on what we stored in the voxel so we
know that the voxels lighting solution
is actually all stored in there what we
don't know is that they're actually
properly aligned with where the voxel
thinks it is so for example when we push
these cubes on
we are working through what's in the
voxel at any particular location but we
don't actually know whether or not that
voxel whether or not the light that's
stored in that voxel the one that has
this p-value we don't know whether it's
actually a whether that p-value is
actually contained inside the voxel
right so for all we know this could be
completely bogus so what would be nice
to do is actually try to translate this
out in some way where we figure out
whether or not the voxel whether the
things that are in each voxel sell
properly correspond to lights in that
region all right
so let's go ahead and see if we can get
any information about that so what we
would like to do here is say okay let's
take a look at this this loop here and
let's have two ways that we can do it
right
so the first thing we want to do is
instead of actually outputting things
that they're a real location we're gonna
output them at the center of the voxel
so we can see where it is we're still
gonna do the push cue but we're gonna do
it outside so we need to have a thinker
that says like where we should put the
element right so what I want to do is
say if there's anything in this voxel
you skip it if there's nothing in it if
there's anything in the voxel compute
like the average color value something
like this so we start out with a black
color we sum up all of the colors that
there are in there and then at the end
at the end we'll just divide by however
many there were right so this will
produce an average value for each voxel
cell that has anything in it and then it
will put a cube at that location with
that color value now the only thing we
don't have here is we don't know where
to put this guy because we don't have
any way to compute that yet so we want
to do is we want to get the voxel x y&amp;z
out by using that dimension value so we
want to do is like you know min you know
locks little min corner plus X times you
know well basically this
so whatever the voxel dimension is we
want to multiply that by wherever we are
XY and Z integer y's and we want to
offset from the middle corner the voxel
that would put us at the corner of this
voxel we probably want to be at the
center of the voxel so we can also do
like an 0.5 F times the voxel dimension
plus write another way to do that would
be to add point five to each of these
but either way all right so that's what
we need to do we need to take a look
here at where that information is going
to be how that information is going to
get to us is the only thing because as
you can see here where we do lighting
solutions solution and lighting textures
textures I don't know that we actually
store that anywhere you can see in here
it doesn't look like we actually store
that data unfortunately so what I might
do is say let's actually put that in
there so that when we come through here
and we store like min corner max corner
that crap
let's go ahead and actually keep that in
here as well right
so let's say that we've got a min corner
in a max corner and a seldom and in
seldom like so and that way when this
thing produces the lighting solution we
can actually store these values and have
some idea of what they actually are so I
think that just this
nothing much to it and that'll store all
those values off so that now we can use
them anywhere that we want to if I come
back up here I should be able to now get
this out of the texture set so there's
the voxel main corner there's seldom and
there's Seldon a second time so that's
that's really it that's all I wanted to
do and that way I can just kind of see
if these things are roughly in the right
place I think we called that v3i that
would be through you I thought we had
something like that I guess we only had
v2 uninitialized local variable right
you are sir thank you compiler so now
I'm going to run the lighting and I'm
gonna it's gonna take a little longer
because we are running a debug mode I
could probably go back - OH - if we want
to but probably it's not that long so
this is the lighting solution running
now we are going to do the voxel
creation we don't need to stop here for
any particular reason
so yeah not reassuring right I see
nothing but that's kind of good because
I mean maybe there's a bug in this but
if it turns out that there isn't a bug
in this then that puts us a little bit
closer to understanding what our problem
is
as if this is actually word incorrectly
now and we're not getting anything
that's a good indication that our voxel
lookup is kind of borked let's go ahead
and step into that and see what's going
on in it maybe it just has a bug and we
shouldn't get too excited
or maybe we've actually found something
only one way to tell
ah okay so the first I'm going to do is
see if we ever get in here right we may
never but we did so we know that there
are some voxels that have indices in
them which we believed already to be the
case because when we looked in the
memory window and scanned the voxels it
did look like there was stuff happening
there so that's good
when we sum up the color value here that
doesn't look very promising it looks
like the color value is zero but that's
okay actually we should still see a cube
maybe there just wasn't any light there
so that's actually fine so now let's
take a look at what we're getting in
these in the actual location values so
negative 35 to 35 the cell dimension
that's totally wrong oh I see because we
only ever compute inverse cell dimension
this is actually the whole voxel
dimension my bad
hey I named it correctly I just didn't
actually do it so let's go ahead and do
seldom here
and what you can see is basically we
just do the divide the other way around
so this is how much we have to span and
we divide by the lookup value and there
we get the Selden so that's fine let's
try that over time
so with that bug fixed it looks like two
things one it looks like we have
correctly stored the voxels where they
are right I mean that looks right to me
too
we should probably run that again to
make sure that the color values are
right in there so what I'm going to do
here is just go back to the OpenGL path
and where we slam the green in there and
do the the index loop I'm going to go
ahead and recom nth out the value that
I'm going to read comment the part where
we assign the value over the default
light the value that comes from the
render stream so yeah this so I'm going
to let it use the lighting value that
it's being told I'm leaving it as o2
because we're just kind of testing now
we don't need to step through anything
so when I run this this is viewing these
created from the voxels positioning so
it looks like they're placed in the
right location as well so we now can be
relatively sure that our pre pass is
more or less correct meaning when we're
setting up the texture data it seems to
be correct so that means we can now move
on to step two of this process which is
taking a look inside the part where we
submit the textures and seeing whether
or not when we submit the actual
textures whether we set anything
sensible for them or not right so
because again we we now know that it
looks like the texture date is being
prepped properly in memory we what we
don't know is whether or not OpenGL ever
gets that texture data so like right
here
you can see where we do our submissions
entropy next entry C entry lookup we
don't really know whether any of this
stuff worked right like we don't know we
have no idea whether any of this stuff
got put in properly it could be
completely incorrect right so that's the
next thing we got to take a look at we
also don't know what order these are
stored in and this is kind of a big deal
I guess I and it looks like I didn't
give it much thought when we first put
this in here so maybe I was just in a
hurry and didn't have a chance to take a
look at it but if you see here we've got
X Y &amp; Z as the three indices here I
don't know if that's actually what we're
doing meaning I don't know whether we're
storing them that way in the actual
voxel writing routine itself so for
example if you look at what's going on
here we're indexing by X as the least
significant factor Y in the middle and Z
is the most significant factor I don't
know what OpenGL is going to do I assume
it will do it in that order but we would
probably should go look at some
documentation to verify that that's
actually correct
so when we do these text sub image calls
I want to take a look to make sure we've
defined these textures correctly as well
so if I go back to where we're doing
lighting where we're going back to the
lighting P next and I look at these and
see how we're storing them I mean this
looks wrong to me already if you take a
look at how these are being sent
when I say GL text image 1d I'm saying
that I'm passing an unsigned byte which
I suppose doesn't matter because we're
not passing any data but I'm saying that
the internal storage format is only 8
bits wide but we said that our internal
storage format was going to be quite
different than that we said it was going
to be 16 bytes correct so this is not an
r8 I mean this is an R 16 this is
relatively correct it's 32 F meaning
it's gonna be our g and b float then the
final float which is actually the the
next parameter is gonna have to be
stored as a float anyway but we could
we're gonna I guess convert it out of a
float into a different value we're gonna
reinterpret it as an integer which I
assume is okay but we'll cross that
bridge Pig come to it so that was not
right I don't know how much of effect
that would have had but you know any of
those values above 2 to 6 would have
been getting truncated so I don't know
that could have been fairly significant
it's probably not the only bug but it's
definitely a bug so all right so we hope
that this actually produces the empty
space for the textures that we actually
need and record their storage format
properly but we don't actually know that
and we don't actually know whether or
not any of this data actually got down
to them properly sadly I'm not really
sure a good way to check to see
if it did I'm gonna try inspecting this
part maybe in the graphs debugger and
we'll see if they can help us here what
I can do is make sure that the Vox min
corner and Vox in vim seldom are set
correctly because those are just values
that we can inspect and verify at that
set time as well as when we set them in
the shader prep right all right so if I
go ahead and look at that so if I go
ahead and look at that inside the open
geo path I'm gonna have to
okay open jail render commands what I
want to do here is make sure that we're
setting like the voxel look up
parameters properly so I want to step to
right oops that's the wrong key so I
want to take a look here and make sure
that those two values got set to the
this you know what we were expecting so
here's the voxel min corner here's the
voxel inverse seldom that
that looks about right so if you imagine
the math that's going to happen here
we're gonna take the min corner and
we're going to subtract it away from
whatever box lookup we have and we're
gonna end up with a value that's gonna
run from like negative 35 - 35 we're
gonna subtract that 35 from it again
with this one zero - like 60 or 70 and
that times three is about 256 right so
it does look like this is properly sort
of you know pushing us in the direction
we expect to go I don't know if we're
actually setting those values properly
so that's where I think we could maybe
hopefully a little bit sort of kind of
if every windows in the GPU decide to
cooperate with us we could see perhaps
some information from the graphics card
to corroborate that which would be nice
I'm gonna go ahead and try that here I'm
not particularly optimistic but here we
go so I'm going to go to the pause and
capture frame we're gonna wait 17 years
and after that 17 years has elapsed we
will hope that maybe we will get some
graphics analysis to look at
okay so now that we have the graphics
analysis we're gonna try to look at
these textures so if we jump into a you
know one of the render passes here you
can see like our render target passes
these are our depth fields here I
believe happening right depth field zero
one two three if we jump into a random
one and you know in the middle of the
depth feel or whatever we should be able
to go see the lighting values because
they're involved in every render right
there set for every render and we should
also be able to see in the fragment
shader we should be able to see the
voxel corner and stuff be set so there
they are and so hey that's a nice thing
that graphs the burger did for us that
verifies that those values are actually
being passed down correctly as we wanted
them to be right so that's nice so let's
see if we can take it a step further and
see whether like our our textures here
whether we can get any information about
those I don't really know what this is
showing me exactly but I think it's
because it's too disease but yeah okay
so since despite to about thirty two
this is correct it's showing me the 32z
levels of this you know texture right if
I take a look at one of them
I would have expected to see something
here like I'm not seeing any pixels at
all right everything appears to be zero
I and that's just not good we know these
are 16-bit integers
let's get somebody here we know these
are 16-bit integers I really don't know
how to do anything particularly clever
here but well so there's some so there
we are sending down something right it's
not very dense but again it wasn't very
dense when we looked at it in our memory
window either right it's because hey
it's a sparse voxel I it even in you
know if it's being done correctly it
will not necessarily be particularly
dense if I go back here and look at a
graphical representation I don't know
how to actually not actually see this
one here's the color sampler for example
I don't know why this only shows white
when it actually doesn't show that here
but anyway here's the color values and
you can see RGB a rgba and again that
looks like what we thought you know that
looks I don't see anything particularly
unusual there and same is true for this
I don't really know how to say much
about the position one I could look at
it s 32-bit floats here and you know
those look like valid light positions
certainly I seem literally no next
parameters which is weird that feels
wrong I don't know if maybe we just
never fill our voxel any deeper than
that but it seems like we should have to
at some point there should be two in the
same place but I don't see that ever
happening which is a little bit weird
that maybe because you can't send down
bogus floats it may be that we have to
switch this to 32-bit but
again even if that were the case that
that as a bug should not actually be
causing us any harm because we know that
we're not even seeing a first light
value anywhere at least as far as we can
tell because even if we set all the
colors to black and weren't sending any
of that down just if there was even just
a lookup hit if we ever hit the lookup
properly even once we would see green
because we're stuffing a green value if
the lookup value ever succeeds so we
don't even care about the next corner we
should be seeing some green somewhere if
we were not completely busted so we know
that something is much more busted than
just that well hey the graphs do bugger
did something useful right that's a good
thing we can applaud that we were able
to actually see you know some some
corroboration here that we weren't nuts
and that we were sending down to our
values properly so that's good so we
think those are relatively correct the
next pointer it looks like that's
incorrect so it looks like we will have
to send down that mixed-mode texture it
looks like we've gonna have to do more
work there we could all we could
possibly send that down as part of the
other one who knows what we can probably
do something but but we've we've got
some issues there so anyway let's go
take a look at that shader maybe there's
something that we're doing wrong in
terms of when we're doing the lookup
that we could you know fix and and see
what's going on there
so let's see here
so there's a couple of things on the
table like I was saying before we don't
really know how the indexing is working
inside OpenGL when we send down that
texture it could be that we got the
indices backwards I don't really know
because we are assuming that it follows
the same convention as XY textures where
the X Y values are specified in the GL
text image call you get X Y but when
you're indexing they're actually
indexing X minor y major we assume that
X Y Z follows the same rule meaning that
X is still minor Y is more major and Z
is most major but we might have to
verify that because we don't really know
that it's necessarily true we're just
assuming this true I but anyway inside
here if we take a look at what's going
on it seems fairly straightforward we're
taking the world position which we
believe we have correct it gets passed
in from the vertex shader directly so
that's an unmolested world position
right so hopefully we take that
unmolested world position there which is
includes the Z bias which is what we
want actually so that's all fine we take
that unmolested roll position we
subtract the Foxman corner from it looks
like they miss somebody with the
position we floor that that all seems
like reasonable work to me
we are currently over writing the value
by looking up into a place where we
believe there to be a value already
we're doing a Texel fetch into that
lookup sampler with that hard-coded
address and you know we're grabbing the
read value out of there we're
multiplying that read by value by 65535
and adding 0.5 I don't know I don't
really know the specifics of how that
Texel fetch is working
[Music]
so when you do something like a Texel
fetch in open jail I always have trouble
remembering how you how you're supposed
to tell it that this thing we're looking
up into is a 16-bit value and I don't
want you to turn into a float right I'm
not sure I mean let me take a look at
that right now what we're doing is it's
turning into a float and we're turning
it back
yeah so this is let me see we've got two
things here not from particularly great
sources unfortunately let's see
this is old like luminance is not still
a value so that's not going to help us
so I guess it's true I'm not passing you
I which I should however yeah is you
sampler available in what we're using
right now because that I probably should
be doing right like that would be better
and I'm not sure whether we've got that
or not I believe we're still set up to
error when we have a compilation fail so
I'm assuming that we will hit that but
what I would like to do here is yeah
like the these two we actually want
float at least at the moment but use
sampler 3d for this I think is what I
would would ideally like to use so if
you do a youth sampler and you do a
textile fetch I wonder if you can get
out exactly just the the integers there
I can also make sure that inside the
OpenGL loop again I pass
in here instead of an R 16 I wonder if I
can do in our 16 UI hopefully so if
that's the case it the you know OpenGL
would then know exactly what I was
trying store there and maybe I can get a
more direct look up here so when I fetch
this out you know it would just be like
Texas fetch and don't know can I
actually do that
oh OpenGL program yeah I don't why did
it break all the way up there I don't
really know this is probably something I
can configure in the new thing right
over anyway that says what I wanted to
have happen so now I can actually look
at the error so that's fine
vertex errors fragment errors program so
that's actually good implicit class from
you int to end that's great because that
basically means that that text will
fetch now is producing an unsigned
integer which is fantastic that's what I
wanted that's what I was hoping for so
let's find out if that flies
125 what we don't look up into the look
up sampler anywhere else though do we
I guess right here we're assigning to
light I
is it just that textile fetch wants an
actual int not a you ain't all the time
like it can't use a you ain't kind of
looks that way it also looks like for
some reason it's complaining about this
like I guess zero is not one of those so
I guess I'll just do this for now and
see how we do oh right forgot it
forgot that opengl has the sort of
function style cast so we got an error
what is the error
texture type and format combination is
not valid so it didn't like it didn't
like this for whatever reason so our 16
UI it did not want me to specify it
looks like
so I can't say I know why it would be
particularly upset about that because
that looks like the sort of thing that
would be relatively straightforward I
mean all we're doing is saying hey you
know we're we're not even sending down
any data you know it's just a zero
pointer so all you have to do all we're
doing is telling it the internal storage
format of the texture which we want it
to be 16-bit unsigned integer but it
doesn't like that and I'm not sure why
so does that imply that 3d textures for
some reason cannot be unsigned integers
which I mean and again we don't really
even necessarily need a 3d texture cuz
we can do our lookups manually we could
you know we could easily do this with a
non 3d texture just a bigger 2d texture
or something like that but I'm not sure
why it would care what the internal
format of the texture was just because
it was 3d it looks maybe more like it
doesn't know what that format is
so let's see
let's see
so inside internal format this is old
news let me see if I can get something
that says what we should be able to
specify there
so interestingly enough it actually
specifically says right here that that's
one of the constants that would be
allowed right
and GL red is also accepted here not
that we care because again we're not
really sending anything down
so I don't see anything
hmm so I don't really see what we can do
there differently that looks like
something that should work unfortunately
they're not giving us enough information
to know what it doesn't like about it it
said format and type are not compatible
I believe and I guess technically that's
those two unless it means this and this
but they look correctly compatible
because that are 16 you I would in
theory be exactly read unsigned short
right I mean that's exactly what you
would expect to have there because that
is what an R 16 UI is it's a read
unsigned short so it doesn't seem like
it would really be complaining about
that I'm not sure
so strictly out of curiosity what if I
just asked it for an even bigger one
doesn't like that how about a floating
point one so it's totally fine with
floating point floating points no
problem
but it really doesn't want an integer
texture I guess so I could store a
32-bit float per texture channel in the
3d texture but I just can't have an
unsigned integer of any size at all so I
wonder what happens what happens if it's
just signed is that also bad yep so it
has to be float why I don't understand
what's magic about floating point values
that it really wants to store floating
point values it really doesn't want to
store anything else
[Music]
well I can't say I know what the deal is
here or why anyone would care because
we'd really just want blind to texture
data we could change to using some kind
of a buffer lookup I suppose because we
don't really need I mean yeah I mean we
don't really care about the texture
aspect of this right
we're not asking it to texture from it
really in the way that you would
normally do these lookups but I guess
what that means is all right if we're
gonna have to do a float if we would
have to do a float then we could do a
float right and that would be fine
we could just have a single 32-bit entry
that was a float and the floating-point
value we decrypt right I mean we can
just store this thing as a floating
point value and that's no big deal I
really just don't understand why integer
isn't on the table because we know that
it's already an integer I mean like rgba
eight for example he is already an 8-bit
integer format right we know that it can
store textures that way so I'm not sure
why it doesn't really want to store them
in some other way but you know that's
just how it goes I guess so if it wants
to store them only as float that's okay
we can do that for now but it would be
nice to know how to convince it not to
do that if we were going to do that then
what we'd have to do is when we look up
this value we would yeah we'd have to do
essentially what we're doing before we'd
have to multiply it by 6 5 5 through 6
when we do the textile fetch and make
sure it around right
and so when we go to submit that texture
I don't know if we want to submit it as
float as well just to make sure but
that's the basic idea so I don't really
know why that's going on there it really
doesn't seem like it should have to
happen but but there you go so one thing
I would like to know is can we step into
that shader I don't know if that's
asking too much it probably is but let
me see here
go ahead and capture
so all right if we want to take a look
at one of these shader calls here's the
fragment shader
you
let me just see if it will let me insert
a breakpoint here doesn't look like it
will unfortunately I was hoping we could
do something where we could actually
take a look at some of the I was gonna
see if we could take a look at some of
the shader code there in action
but that doesn't look likely
let's see I have done this before
successfully I just don't remember
exactly how I convinced it to work I do
remember it took a little while of
course I've never done it in this
particular version of Visual Studio or
or in sight but
you see so let me look up because I
really do think you can do this step and
say at least under certain certain
circumstances
access the sheeter debugger start
debugging your graphs project from
insight windows shaders okay there we go
I knew there was a way to do it it's
just it's been a while there it is
alright so in theory
let's see here so in theory we want
program 21 which is this one right so
there we go
all right the following table shows the
possible states of the symbolic status
ready jitter has not been used that
application no symbols have been loaded
not a dub Bugaboo later however where
does that get listed I don't see any of
those things listed anywhere I don't
know why it says debug info none ah
shader debugging is not supported for
this GPU well I guess that answers that
question
I don't know why shader debugging is not
supported for this GPU do I need to
install a debug driver perhaps so maybe
that would fix it because I would like
to but maybe this GPU just can't do it
so it looks like they maybe just don't
support modern GPUs for shader debugging
like they like shader debugging just
went away
which I guess that's just like kind of a
future regression maybe because we are
using the latest version so I don't
think it's a question of having to
update n site I guess it's just insight
you know their GP is no longer support
trader debugging I guess that would be
bad because we want them to go towards
supporting shader debugging they
actually support less jitter debugging
on this than they did on the old series
that would be bad but I'm not sure
let me just double-check just want to
make sure there isn't a different
version of the driver that you have to
install
hmm I don't know so I'm not sure why
that is I we'd have to ask someone at
Nvidia I guess
whether or not we're supposed to be able
to do that or whether like you just
can't debug shaders anymore you have to
go go buy an old your older graphics
card in order to debug a shader I have
no idea however for the time being
anyway we will not be able to do that so
that's fine I if we wanted to do
something
I don't know like if we wanted to take a
quick moment to try and display some
more debug information here one of
things I'm gonna do is I'm gonna get rid
of this to see if we ever get into that
light loop anywhere I mean it looks like
we don't right no matter where we're
sort of pinging I also we we need to get
rid of that debug like our voxel is
shrunk down quite a bit from what its
compressed way more than it should be
because of this bounding solid that
we're sending down there and I really
don't want that to be included in the
solution so that's like kind of a bit of
an issue there let me see if I can just
get rid of that really quickly as well
so we don't have to contend with it
so here's push volume outline push
direct outline all of these I'm gonna
get rid of all of those and so now we
shouldn't have anything off the distance
there don't so we should just be dealing
with just this segment right okay so now
in here where we're looking up into the
light index and we're doing our textile
fetch into our lookup sampler
we're never getting a valid value out of
it
which is kind of nuts I'm gonna go ahead
and not even try to do the integer
casting I'm gonna actually convert this
down to just do like look here's a light
I value
let's just actually take whatever we get
and make that be the use light see so
I'm going to do a textile fetch into the
lookup sampler at Vox I in fact I'm just
gonna draw this directly
I won't even do that I'll just do world
P - Vox min corner like I'll just do
I'll just do a lookup at Vox eye and see
what I get if I just return it directly
right cuz I don't really have any idea
why we're having such a hard time
pulling out of this texture but we seem
to be so I'm just gonna try and get
something showing up any anywhere on
screen at all and I yeah that seems
somehow almost impossible but I don't
know why because you know we are sending
down values for this thing so I just
don't know yeah no what exactly is
happening there
so inside OpenGL I also want to look at
where we're submitting text sub image 3d
here and we're sitting down inside
shorts which is what we expect so yeah
again that just seems like that should
work just fine
I would think but we're just not getting
anything right we're getting this is
like the graphics card hasn't given us
any any help here at all if I wanted to
look up into the voxel by a floating
point value I should be able to vote
divided by I should be able to take the
vox eye and turn it into a vox UV by
dividing by the like constant values the
light dimension acts the light dimension
why
and the light dimension Z right that
should also if I want to look up that
way
I shouldn't have to that though I should
be able to look up by integer values so
it's kind of weird that I would have to
do that but yeah so yeah I don't know
I don't know why we're not getting
anything back that seems really broken
like it seems like that should be
clearly giving us something back we
looked and verified that there was
something in it however one thing I will
say is we even though there were clearly
values in it those values didn't seem to
come out properly in the texture preview
like when we looked at the the image
that the the insight was showing it
didn't seem to actually ever show us
valid data there in the memory view it
was but in the actual render it wasn't
and I do wonder about that as well
because I'm not sure why that was going
on but now in this you know these should
be floating-point values stored in here
so we should be able to get an RGB value
out of it and the fact that we're not
getting any RGB out of it no matter
where we're looking is just nuts right I
don't understand what the problem is
there this is why I hate GPU programming
because yeah you get no information it's
all the worst aspects of debugging once
again is because you have literally
nothing to go on it's like who knows and
this stuff is all SPECT so poorly that
it's like all right yeah I don't know
like there's all these parameters you
can specify but hey like where's just a
bunch we don't allow and we don't tell
you about that so have fun so yeah we
need to figure out why we are not
getting anything out of our lookup
sampler because that's obviously the you
know we're just not getting anywhere
until that thing gives us a valid result
out for our voxel lookup and in order to
get that I don't know what we should do
like I don't know how we can prod it any
more than we're already prodding it one
thing I could do is start trying to look
it up into it in some way that does not
involve integer lookups so I could try
specifying you know a manual look up
here that was gonna just do a regular
text
ol textbook all right so if I did
texture and I asked it to use the lookup
sampler and I pass it Effect 3 here
maybe one that I've sort of pre divided
by the lighting value the actual
dimension values so it's still 0 to 1
like a UV coordinate should be see if
that helps
I doubt it will
nothing so yeah I really just do not
know what it is objecting to there
I should probably have the game startup
windowed now because insight doesn't
work when the game is fullscreen so it
just saves a step there I constantly
have to remember to like alt enter
so
here's a look up sampler and again we
see no pixel data in it however if I
switch to memory view at least as before
we do see values in it part of the
problem I suppose is that those values
will just be very low because they're
only representing like a tiny fraction
of what we actually can specify gonna
float and maybe we're just encoding
those wrong I don't know so if they're a
floating-point value let's let's see
what it encoded here for example let's
find an area that's got some stuff in it
really don't understand why there's so
few of these and yet we tried debugging
the voxel and it it had actual it seemed
to store all the information just as we
expected it to
yet I just see so few entries here like
how is that possible right it just seems
like something's busted let me double
check again something doesn't make a lot
of sense but I just don't know what it
is I guess the other thing I could do is
I could manually force that voxels data
to be floating-point like when we submit
the texture instead of submitting it as
as 16-bit values I could just force it
to be floating-point right so this
lookup here
so if I was gonna do that then when we
create one of these guys what I could do
is say like alright yeah when we write
the lookup at value in addition to
writing it this way like so I'm also
gonna write it this way so I'm just
gonna store a floating point value
that's exactly the value that I actually
wanted new adulteration whatsoever so I
should just be able to see it directly
in there right and then in the render
group where it goes to push that value
on
we'll just say whatevs you know it's
fine
so all I'm doing is sending down a
completely parallel version here that I
know has been unmolested to try and
eliminate I don't know just some one
thing like open Jill's screwing us here
and I don't really know exactly how so
you know I don't have any other options
so when you don't have any other options
you have to just start trying something
to see if you can convince it to do
something resembling anything so if I go
ahead and do a text sub image here and
instead of doing it this way I actually
do it the opposite way so I say you know
I'm sending GL floats down here you go
and then when we look in here we do the
same and I don't know that we actually
need to do that because we're not
submitting anything here but hey so now
we've got a floating point texture that
should have value stored in it when I
actually go to do the f1 here now what
I'm expecting I forgot to do the
Starcraft thing
now what I'm expecting is if I go look
at those values they will actually be
even into indices into the array as I
wanted them to be so I hit f1 I pause
them capture frame
ah crap and I forgot to on window
ourselves
boy I hate programming creepy you so
much why did I ever let myself get
talked into this all right so let's try
that one more time
yeah that time we worked here's the
texture I I'm not sure what happened
there so now it doesn't think we
submitted it at all did I not hit did I
not actually maybe I didn't hit f1 let's
hope that's the case
okay just shoot me now just really put
me out of my misery all right so
basically the I've hit that problem
enough times I'm just going to go switch
just to not be windowed by default
because it just takes there's just too
many steps and I forget to do them all
there we go so f1 and now I can do it
alright so in theory now we shouldn't
have that problem anymore because we'll
start regular windowed so I can't forget
to hit the enter key before doing the
little magic dance to actually get the
debugger to sort of do something
resembling anything so we still wait a
little bit
how're we doing here there we go so if I
don't need this window open yet
but thank you if I take a look at where
that texture ended up here's the look up
sampler alright so now we can actually
see the voxel right and it's populated
so I don't know I'm gonna stick with
this then because at least we can see it
which is nice and if I go in here to
like a volume slice I should see some
values somewhere I would think of course
I don't
shouldn't I be able to how do I get out
of this volume slice hello is there some
way to control which slice I'm looking
at here
oh boy
so it doesn't correspond to that because
this says volume slice 19 shouldn't
there be a thing that lets me switch
through flip through there something I
don't really care about that
all I want to do is get back to the
screen I was just on but that seems like
it doesn't want me to do that
is it just me like am I just like crazy
or something like how does this stuff
even end up this way so there's got to
be a way to get back to it like that
doesn't involve that I would assume so
when I click in here there must be a way
to get back to the previous thing okay
so I right okay I right-click in the
white area looks like the magic sweet
merciful baby Jesus all right so if I
come down here and look at this like
volume slice 19 I see a bunch of values
in here but they're all just bright red
which also doesn't super thrill me I
mean that doesn't sound particularly
good so that's why I'm 619 look at all
those values there now I come over here
and I say let me see volume slice 19 I
should see a ton of values right okay
good
there we go I'm like I shouldn't it
shouldn't be impossible Z's so all of
these values are good right that's
exactly what I want to see so that's
fantastic look I am a happy camper about
that that's very good
so let's now take a look and see if you
know if there's anything I can do to
prod to get you know heaven forfend get
the GPU to actually read those values
when we're actually doing some shading I
know this is a big ask but here we go so
here we are in the Z bias program I'm
gonna revert back to the previous path
here to just see if I can pull a Texel
value out of there
like so all right so when we do a
textile fish fetch at a particular voxel
location we just verify that the values
are actually usable directly so in
theory that this textile fetch right
here should return us in integer it just
it's in a floating-point value but it is
actually just the integer we wanted so
we should be able to just go ahead and
use it directly as an integer right we
can then go ahead and test this part of
the loop and see if we ever get anything
that's not zero right here we go and
magically we still get nothing I have no
idea how that's possible right none
whatsoever
because we're searching over a fairly
wide area unless this math is wrong
maybe it is when we're doing this
textile fetch we should get those values
out somewhere right we should get those
values out somewhere but we don't
actually seem to so I have no idea why
literally none whatsoever so inside here
where we're saying the the I've x3 one
thing I could do here is again try to
let's try to debug this value just to
make sure that maybe we're using a valid
lookup of some kind so I'm gonna try to
make the Vox UV value here I'm gonna set
use light
I'm gonna set use Lightsey to actually
just be equal to the Vox TV for now so
we can actually see where we're looking
up in the voxel directly as best we can
so I'm gonna take Vox P and I'm gonna
multiply it by one over each of our
dimensions so you can see in here
alright we've got this voxel position
this is going to come out as like a zero
two two two six zero two two six zero
two thirty-two assuming that we did this
math correctly I'm going to change that
to what I think is a UV by just dividing
by what I think the size of the texture
we're looking up in is we don't care
about the rest of this because we're
ignoring it right now in fact this this
and this are all superfluous now so what
we're gonna do is just draw that UV
value all right that's all I want to do
so here we go this is the UV values that
we're drawing
uh they don't look correct to me at all
so I guess that's good information
they're not totally bogus but they are
somewhat bogus so what should be
happening is we should be getting a
gradual increase in green and gradual
increase in red a gradual increase in
blue and we're sort of getting that over
here but it tops out too quickly so it
looks like I've done something stupid
with respect to how I'm computing the
voxel position I or something like that
right like the voxels not aligned
properly or something like that so I
want to take a quick look I know it's
time for questions but I want to quick
look and see what's going on there and
verify that I don't have something
really dumb going on all right so let me
just make sure that I've got those
values correct you can see it's two six
two six 32 so there's two two six threes
thirty-two so in theory right we should
always be getting something between zero
and one for all of these voxels assuming
that the min corner is actually where we
think it is and the inverse seldom is
actually where we think it is right so
yeah I could also do something else here
so I'm trying to think but another thing
that I could do here is I could just try
to do an if statement and set the light
C equal to a certain value in either
case so what I could do is do like it's
black everywhere that it's in but if you
know Vox UV x is less than zero or Vox
UV Y is less than zero or box UV Z is
less than zero box UV X is greater than
one you get the idea so basically I'm
going to do is we're just doing a bounds
check here
and I'm gonna set the color to be red
everywhere that it's outside the voxel
right just so I can check my sanity so
it does not appear to be here right so
I'm not sure why we were getting such an
odd color ramp I don't know if that's
because of some kind of gamma correction
that's happening there I don't know why
we were getting such a weird color ramp
there necessarily it's a little
troubling because if we're never outside
the voxel then we should have been
getting something fairly stable there
and it didn't look like we really were
so that's a bit odd and probably warrant
some further inspection but yet so the
next I'm going to do is I'm going to
change it to slightly inside the voxel
so I can see whether or not we're
actually properly getting the bounds to
be so I moved the voxel boundary in by
about a quarter
all right and so I'm still not seeing
any of that so this is just bogus right
our Vox UV value oh that's great or I
just did the test wrong all right so our
Vox UV is wrong it's always hitting that
case and you can see there's a little
bit of it that's inside the voxel and
most of it is outside the voxel so it
looks like we've got a voxel alignment
problem here something we're doing to
try and create the UV values is is
incorrect
so this Vox P you know I guess I can
also I can try to start debugging this a
little bit more pushing it up a bit so
Vox P we know what that should be as
well right that should be just this
because we know the dimensions of our
voxel and so we know what we think that
should be as well so as soon as it
exceeds those values we know that
something has gone wrong really it's
it's actually for being specific it's
actually that cuz it can't even hit you
can't hit 256 either that would be bad
so here we go and running it so that
actually looks correct that's roughly
what we would expect to see looks like
our voxel needs a little bit more room
there on the side to give it some error
tolerance but otherwise our voxel looks
to be fit properly
so this line was wrong this Vox UV
was incorrect somehow
however I can't say that I see how at
the moment
mmm-hmm
that should have worked right if we knew
that value is between zero and fifty six
and we divide it by 256 we should get a
number of 14-0 and one that seems like a
none controversial statement so I'm not
sure why the UV test was failing in such
an odd way it looks like the UV was
never really getting divided by that
number and I don't know why we don't
need that value in the computations
that's okay I'm gonna move on to the
next one for now if we take a look at
box I we should now be able to look at
the values as integers and verify that
the same thing is happening
and it is so I don't know our voxel
lookup looks really solid there that
looks like it's looking up into exactly
the correct place I do not understand
what it is having a problem with so I
have no idea why this textile fetch is
failing that looks like a very
reasonable thing to pass to the fetch
yet the fetch seems never to produce a
value of any kind and I have no idea why
right I do not know why our Tech's will
fetch always produces zero no matter
what we do
so I guess that'll be the puzzle for
next weekend
for now I'll go to the brief a brief Q&amp;A
so anybody who has a question can put it
in now
all right so in Safari says try using
geo read integer instead of GL read
I am totally down with that as an
attempt to get it to use integers so
here's where we are storing this value
out right and the problem is that if we
change this to an R 16 UI and leave this
as it is it got very angry with me right
and here's where that call was happening
right here so the question is well can
we change it to something else
and have it work so if we were doing
this which i think is what you know and
insofar as I think was suggesting that
we passed red integer you know will it
work we need red integer to be defined
which we don't have at the moment
here it is
and hey alright thank you insofar as I I
mean I would just like to take a moment
to say again how ridiculous that kind of
thing is like that is just nuts like why
would you hang up a programmer on
something like that it like there's no
reason for AP AP I design of that nature
it's just kind of inexcusable I mean
doesn't even make sense but you know off
you go
anyway so let's go ahead and fix the the
tech sub image calls well then because
that's all we needed there in so far
essays today insofar us by the way is
the the famous author of in cybot who
you may have seen on the chat it's
basically I mean there's a lot of talk
in Silicon Valley these days about
artificial intelligence and cloud
computing and all these sorts of things
but basically in sohbat is the
embodiment of all those things it is not
only cloud computing artificial
intelligence but it's so far ahead of
anything they've got in Silicon Valley
it's ridiculous like in Saibot makes a
Alexa and Siri and Google's whatever
voice thing just look like such a joke
it's not even funny
I mean it's it's it's it comes up with
the best witness isms anyway let's take
a look here and see if there's anything
else I need to do I think that's it so I
would just specify the regular lookup
pointer here and I should get those
values out
let's take a look yep
so now I am specifying integer textures
finally and that is very good I also
need to go specify when I get those
values out now I think I can use a youth
sampler in theory of course we weren't
getting anything out of the other
sampler either so I'm not sure that it
necessarily matters yet but what are you
gonna do so let's just set that back to
what it was supposed to be set to all
right so Zee bias program sit down here
there's our look up sampler I'm gonna
set that to use sampler 3d and in here
as we go we want to see if we can get
this to sample
directly well almost
I always cast the wrong way I'm never
going to remember that there we go
perfect so we have debugged our stuff at
all but at least we can say that thanks
to insofar as suggestion we are able to
get OpenGL to stop complaining about us
just one restore that texture in a more
sensible format than floating-point
which takes up twice the space for no
actual benefit let me go zip through the
final questions here needs more seven
three eight I totally agree
what what do I think about GPU open I
don't really know much about GPU open
how much prep to do before every episode
there's no prep for the episodes the
whole point of the episodes is actually
to do the opposite of the normal thing
which is you know normally you when you
get like tutorials or perdón anything's
like that you just see a programmer who
already did all the work and then they
just sort of walk through the result so
we tried to the opposite of that so on
some streams if we're doing something
easy it may look like it was prepped
ahead of time just because it happens to
be easy so there's really no struggle
with it but other times like for example
this episode you know it's something
that's you know kind of API nightmare
stuff you'll have you will see me do all
the stuff I would normally have to do in
my day job where I'm just like I don't
know why this is black and here I go
poking a bunch of really simple tests in
just to try and find you know what
OpenGL doesn't like or what the GPU
doesn't like it's so on tt BJM I'm
curious to fixing the WM message bug
also fixed the crash in a render doc I
can test that if you want
oh so eventually they will support
shader debugging in Maxwell and Pascal
so they they didn't like remove it from
the hardware or something it's still
possible to do they just don't have
software support for it or something
bleeding a high KC my experience is very
good for developing geocell to keep
shares and files and have the stuff
right um a curio of them if they're
changed yeah I agree with that and I
avoided doing that originally because I
didn't think we were gonna be doing
anything fancy turns out we did end up
doing some fancy things so I wouldn't
necessarily be adverse to going that
route now so we'll see all right so let
me quickly just capture this here
every shoot-off topics it's okay ignore
and hurry do you have experience it's
rendering impossible spaces like an
antechamber or the secret levels of Duke
Nukem 3d no I've never really done
anything along those lines
you could probably include in that like
what they did for portal for example
would be another example of that I mean
they there's usually not a whole lot to
it it usually boils down mostly to sort
of doing recursive rendering where you
render from one perspective then you
composite that into a rendering from
another perspective and you can posit
that into renting for another
perspective right so you just like
rendering repeated renders that all like
pick a different camera point you know
and there isn't you know sometimes
there's more to it than that but usually
that's the basic idea right if that
makes sense
so here is our integer image
I don't know how to verify that we
actually evaluate circuses always so
sparse but there they are right and they
look pretty good I mean that looks like
it's working right so all right so I'm
going to go ahead and close down and I
will also just because someone was
asking about it I'll check to see
whether render doc can debug now
so here we go launching and this is with
the 738 bug fixed so here is you know
what we would want to capture I hit f12
it's working on it
it's done I've closed the application
and now it's doing its thing I can't
imagine why fixing the 738 bug would
help render duck because it's not
running my application anymore so I
don't know why that would matter and the
answer is no it's totally froze again oh
well that's better than it was sort of I
mean it's still pretty not usable
I mean it's so slow it doesn't seem to
be no it's yeah no it's it's pretty bad
I think we just have too many draw calls
maybe remember we can simplify our draw
calls a lot by adding our textures and
maybe we would need to do that if we
wanted to use render duck I'm not sure
but no I mean I can't even close it
right so I don't think that really had
anything to do with it because it
doesn't run our application during that
time so I'm not sure why the 7:38 bug
would even be relevant to it anyway
thank you everyone for joining me for
this o handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow the series at
home you can always peer to the game on
handmade here at work and it comes with
a source code which I update after every
programming session that's about it for
today I'll be back next weekend for a
little more coding hopefully we could
figure out why the graphics card refuses
to look up into that texture and from
there we can maybe start playing with
our lighting a little bit more which is
what I would like to do until next time
take it easy and I'll see everyone on
the
didn't we use everyone