hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here the show recode a complete game
live on stream no engines no libraries
just us and what we're doing right now
actually is we are finishing up some
work from Friday we had dropped our
sound mixer into Cindy but we didn't
have a chance to do the inside of the
loop largely because I completely forgot
how's tues comp well I guess I didn't
forget how two's complement worked I
forgot how chip adding worked for some
reason and so we kind of went down a
little rat hole of me remembering and I
guess the good news is that I did
remember and was able to show what I was
trying to show on the string but the bad
news is that took way too long and so
basically Friday stream instead of being
about writing a cindy mixer actually was
mostly about me not remembering a bunch
of stuff from when I was a little baby
anyway and if you didn't see that
episode you stuck it out actually did
draw a little baby me it wasn't a good
drawing but it was a drawing nonetheless
so anyway what I like to do today is
pick up where we left off it is
extraordinarily swelteringly hot here in
Seattle as it tends to get in the summer
so i am going to be sweating this entire
program and so i think we just want to
focus on writing this MV and getting it
done as soon as possible and trying to
ignore the fact that we are overheating
because honestly if the more i think
about it the more uncomfortable i will
be so that said let's go ahead and
remind everyone that today is day 1 45
so if you want to follow along at home
you want day 144 source code and that is
what i am starting with here so you know
keep it in mind so yeah the way that we
had left things nothing particularly
broken everything still works the way
that you would expect you know our sound
mixer code is still running playing
music and other things but we did not
quite finish with the simdi part of it
and so there's a bunch of things that we
want to be able to do there that we have
not done so i'm going to go ahead and
get that going the first thing that we
want to do is finish up that inside loop
vicinity and then i'm assuming that what
we would like to do as well in addition
to just keep everything nice and simple
in this mix
code as a writing it is we'll probably
wants to change our sort of thinking
elsewhere in the application to think of
for samples as one sample so that we
know that everything is always going to
be a line because right now we allow
things to basically be on individual
16-bit sample boundaries for Channel and
I think what we would like to do
probably further on down the line is
think of things in terms of either four
or eight samples even perhaps and the
reason that I say eight samples is
because eight samples in 16-bit
obviously would be one full width
register if you think about you know 16
right times eight of those is 128 bits
which is the width of those sse2
registers and so we may want to go ahead
and do it that way just to make it a
little bit cleaner right so what I'm
going to do first is I'm going to go
ahead and write this routine pretending
that we can do anything like that that
we want but without actually doing it
and then we will sort of bubble back up
again to the code outside and you know
make that work right so if you take a
look at here you know I've got sample
count a line for and we go ahead and do
that sample count line for stuff so what
I could do here is change us and say we
actually want to do sample count align
eight meaning that we expect sample
buffers to always be aligned to eight
samples instead of four and we can even
make our own little you know alignment
code here for those in in handmade
platform I think of somewhere those guys
actually live right we could make a
align it here something that's you know
just a wines value eight like so so if
we want to we can just say you know what
there's always going to be a multiple of
eight samples and that's just a
requirement now so when you call output
playing sounds you just have to give it
that and so I feel like that's the
easiest thing to do and if for some
reason you really don't want that
meaning you really need something else
to happen then I guess you would modify
this routine but I feel like that's what
I would what I would like to see happen
if that makes sense so let's let's go
ahead and make it that way and I'm going
to go ahead and allocate these guys so
if we have sample count eight here what
that means is that our real channel
buffers will have to be a little bit
bigger right they would have to be
larger they'd have to be twice the size
of whatever the sample count it is right
and what i could do is also say that you
know i could have the sample count for
here as well which is just going to be
two times that sample count forward for
these other guys and I don't know how
this is always kind of annoying with
simdi see just isn't really that
equipped to handle it no languages
really are it's really more of a meta
programming thing where you kind of want
lots of different conceptualizations of
sort of the width of that things work at
but for well you know we'll muddle
through it and usually it just means
there's a little more debugging time
because usually you make a mistake
somewhere with one of these counts and
then you're like I you know so it's not
really a huge deal but it just means
it's a little more inconvenient a little
more stumbly as you kind of go through
things so all right I guess actually
these are the same these are still
sample count for right these guys we're
all cleaning out sample count for so
they're going through and they're just
clearing out those real buffers then we
go in here right as we pull these things
in and we're going to iterate over
samples in here what we'll do is we'll
lock these guys to sample count eight
and then when we come through down at
the bottom we're still using sample
count for although actually so I guess
at the bottom we wouldn't wanna do that
the bottom we do want to use sample
count eight because what we'd like to do
is well no I guess that's not true I
guess since we're reading since we're
writing in lr 0 and lr 1 then that's
fine so I think the only person who
really needs to worry about eight wide
loads is going to be in here where we're
loading from channel buffers that have
eight thing you know that that are
packed 16s that are not interleaved
right so yeah so let's see here let me
go ahead and
and let's see if this runs at all yeah
so that's fine even though right now
we're not actually doing the work of
making sure that that actually does do
the alignment I guess we could make sure
that that's going to happen by going
into handmade win32 see your groups code
win32 and sample count is presumably
already being or are we actually doing
this yet bites to write can get samples
so it looks like it looks like we are
not yet actually we're giving it the
sample count so I guess the only thing
we really did was we just made sure that
when we allocated the size of the thing
we used maximum possible overrun here to
make sure we had room for it to kind of
right over uh but that's not you know
that's not really what we want it to do
at the end of the day that's that's
really not not really correct and the
reason that I say that is because we we
always want the number of samples we
actually asked for to line up with this
so I think that's something that we kind
of need to do here so we we do want to
make sure that we have extra room there
perhaps for overrun things although I
don't know that that's restricted
s-sorry either but basically what we
want to be able to do in fact I really
don't know that this code I don't know
really why I put this in here maybe just
because it was a stupid day like before
but really we could say you know remove
max possible overrun because I don't
think that's really necessary what is
more necessary is in here when we're
actually doing sort of this work where
we're trying to figure out how many
samples we want to write you can see
that we've got this this bites to write
value here right and bites to write is
computed by figuring out where we want
that target cursor to be right and the
problem that we have is that that bites
to write might not line up on an eight
sample boundary and we want it to so I
think what we would rather do right is
we would rather force that down too
you know whatever the you know the next
lowest power of eight actually was and
that's how much we would I'm not the
most part the next lowest multiple of
eight so I'm just gonna take a quick
scan through here this code obviously
isn't just test code we you know we
haven't shipped a win32 platform layer
but I just want to go through and look
at it here we look at bites to lock we
look at how many things we expect to
have till the flip we see where the safe
right cursor is and we see whether or
not we would hit it we try to determine
whether or not so low latency audio
situation assuming it is a low latency
one we take a look at where we should
write it otherwise we just put it at the
safe location and that target cursor is
where we are thinking that I guess we
would like to to leave our rights at
right okay so let's see here so if the
bite to lock is greater than the target
cursor versus not so it looks like it
looks like the but normally this is the
case where we're not rapping whereas
this is the case where we are wrapping
right and it's going to do to rights so
I think all we would really have to do
here is make sure that when we actually
do do this bites to write that we're
going to round it right and I the only
reason I'm not sure about that it's in
that one hat shirt I don't remember what
happens when we actually go to output
the audio back in there so what I want
to do is see when we do win through to
sound buffer what happens in there as
long as Phil sound over can accept any
value four bytes to write than I think
we're fine and it looks like it does so
that's that looks like that's just
totally totally fine and if we take a
look here it looks like it also updates
sort of the the the samples here for us
a sample count unlock well so how does
it know
oh so I guess it doesn't actually all
right well I think we're okay though I
think that should probably be fine
because we don't ever actually ask for
that so yeah that that's fine so yeah so
what we want to do here I think is just
take bites to write and make sure bites
to write ends up getting rounded up
essentially so what we want to do is say
okay place to write minus divided by the
bytes per sample is how many samples we
want to write what we want to do is we
want to align that to the eight sample
boundary right to make sure that we're
actually going to do an eight sample
boundary and then we want to do is
change bytes to write back to whatever
it would have been right if it had come
out correctly in the first place right
like this and so we're just going to go
ahead and actually just force that value
to always be aligned by eight and so
then what I can do there is I can
instead of doing this now I can just
assert that that this is always going to
be true right I can just say you know
what this sound buffer always has to
play in chunks of eight that's just a
requirement so we can just assert that
you know this those bottom bits are
never set right of the sample count so I
think that should be good let's let's
find out
you
seems pretty reasonable and so what I'd
like to do in addition now is i'd like
to go ahead and ensure that sounds
themselves always get updated in
multiples of eight samples and that's
actually not difficult to do in terms of
the way that we structure the code here
with the exception of the fact that this
samples to mix thing is all in terms of
individual samples and that's kind of a
little bit of a mistake right what we
want to do is think of all of these
values in terms of multiples of eight
and similarly what we could do in here
when we talk about loaded sounds and
that sort of stuff so if we go into you
know handmade asset dot H if what we do
here is just say sample County we could
say note Casey this is the sample count
/ 8 what we could do is just make
absolutely everything always work that
way meaning no matter what the sound is
it has to be sort of in that that sort
of chunked you know in that chunked it
has to line up on on those those eight
boundaries right that's just a
requirement that we're going to say that
you have to do and you know that might
create some problems for people who want
to make looping sounds right but I've
never been a huge fan of doing looping
sounds anyway that makes sense I kind of
hate looping sounds I I try very very
hard to never actually use looping
sounds I instead just compose lots of
overlapping sounds to make longer to
make things that go on forever mmm
because looping sounds just you hear it
you know you hear it so I don't care
about giving that up at all other people
might and they could make a different
decision there I would not hold it
against them but you know my code base
my rules so I am totally fine with not
having any looping sounds at all because
as far as I'm concerned I don't ever
want to hear a looping sound ever pretty
much all right so let's see here if we
have sample count eight in
sample count you can see what we were
doing here is we were actually taking a
look at how big the data was and then we
were doing this sort of copy here and so
we need to be able to do is we need to
be able to change this here so that in
the case where we load a file which
might have had more I'm sorry not a
multiple of 8 which is probably fairly
common just randomly we want to Pat it
out basically so when we do all this
right you can see us doing it here we we
set all this stuff up where we we create
you know whatever we need to create we
do the D Swizzle and all that sort of
stuff right and you know we sort of swap
that sample data out and it looks like
we're just doing that essentially in
place right we're just we're totally
keeping that sample data entirely in
place at the moment and so what we want
to do is just go ahead and force that
out to eight now that's a little tricky
because in this case we don't really
know since the file it's almost like I
think in this case we would probably
want to allocate some additional space
and copy the stuff in but it's kind of
annoying to do that just because if we
were to do that if you think about it in
me the once we have these things p plus
an asset file there wouldn't be any need
for that so we'd be introducing
something in here that's sort of an
artificial need that this thing has
which is the ability to allocate memory
and I don't want to make that be
something that people are thinking about
meaning I don't want to be thinking
about that as we're doing the work on
stuff here so what I'd rather do I think
is just again cheese it out here and
assume that we can just Pat out and you
know if we have to we can always make
sure that there's padding on the end of
debug platform read entire file or
something to make sure that we don't
have overruns but what I want to do is
make this work as closely as possible to
how it would be working in terms of
engine requirements to when we actually
have everything pre-processed properly
right so what I want to do here is just
say ok when we load in this stuff it
looks like
let's see looks like what we would want
to do here is just at the end we would
want to Pat it out if the sample count
was not correct so basically in here
we've got a sample you know pad samples
and pad samples is just going to be the
result sample count whatever that was
it's going to be a line eight of that
and minus you know the the actual sample
count I guess the other way we could do
it is just do sample count eight equals
the line eight like so and then we could
say that we're going to set the sample
capped at that and all we need to do
here is just make sure that we set those
ending samples to 0 for all of the
channels that actually exist which of
course I think only one channel can
exist at the moment so I don't even know
why we're bothering but that's a
separate issue okay all right so what we
want to do here is say for each channel
we want to go over sort of the the
samples that are missing if that makes
sense we want to say that we that from
the sample count eight or i should say
sample count a line eight right from
sample count a line aight i want to go
from there up to or i should say that
was so it's like Miss speak there I want
to go from whatever the sample count was
to the new aligned eight sample count
and I wanted to stick into the actual
sample area I want to stick in the zeros
that we would need to Pat it out and
then when we're done we would just set
the sample count equal to sample count
align eight right like so but since we
want to store this I think a sample
count eight which is the divided version
we would go ahead and divide that by
eight right and so then what I'll do
here is take result sample count and
turn that into just an actual
thing instead of using result sample
counts as there is no result sample
count anymore it's only example count
eight so changing all of these it's to
sample count which is now a local thing
and then in here rank we just still use
sample count every any everywhere let's
see here sample count sample count
sample count and then at the end is the
only place now that we would set it
right that's that's about it I think
let's take a look okay so now we know
the sample counts are always aligned
eight then we should now be able to do
just about everything in that aligned in
in the math where everything is divided
by eight which is what I would like to
be doing so that just everything is in
these little 8 wide chunks so let's see
how we would do that total samples to
mix right what we want to do is for
total samples to mix we're going to be
using that sample count eight that's how
many we're starting with we're assuming
we're doing the whole buffer right and
now we're also going to be well I guess
we'll do one thing at the time so I'll
still use I'll still use these things as
reals for now and then we'll switch up
later so total samples to mix is now
total samples to mix eight right and so
what we want to do is sort of propagate
that change through again I'm using the
fact that i'm adding the eighth to the
end to show me all of the places it was
used and kind of guide me through the
process of updating everything that
would therefore need to be updated right
so in here now we have a real sample
remaining and sound again this is going
to be by eight I guess and we would say
that there's the sample count for the
loaded sound it's going to be eight and
we're going to take a look at the
samples played which is also going to be
by eight right and let's see here
you know there's going to be something
that's going to be kind of tricky here
now that i think about it which is that
the pitch shifting which wants to go in
the middle of samples is going to force
us essentially to it's going to force us
to have this kind of weird shift that
goes on if that makes sense let me think
about exactly before I do this let me
think about exactly how this has to
occur right because I think the pitch
shifting makes it so that we have a
problem keeping things aligned as nicely
as we would like them to be aligned if
that makes sense so maybe this is
actually not necessary what I'm doing or
I shouldn't say not necessary but it
would mean that if we wanted to do if we
wanted to actually keep things aligned
we wouldn't actually be able to like we
we would not actually be able to do
things in nicely aligned chunks we would
have to basically always read on the
line so here's the reason I'm saying
that right is because if you take a look
at how this is going to happen if
everything was playing at its normal one
to one rate then we're totally perfect
right because what would happen is you
know you have a 128-bit read here at a
128-bit read here and what's in there is
basically eight sound samples right like
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 2 and have another 10 1
2 3 4 5 6 7 right and so as we come
through you've got the output buffer and
it's you know going along and it's going
to have you know L 0r0 l1 r1 l2 r to l
three are three and so on and so when
you're coming in you're just loading in
one of these guys right you're
processing 8 wide essentially you're
you're doing 24 wide paths right we do
we do this half in float and then this
half and float right and then we would
output them into one of these buffers
and everything would stay nicely aligned
as we played through because the next
time we you know the next sample would
essentially be here and we do the exact
same thing again aligned right but the
problem is if we are actually playing
along at some other sample rates so
instead of one point oh we're playing
around at one point nine or something
like this that becomes really
problematic because now instead of
advancing from here to here the next one
is actually going to be like from here
to here right so it's going to it's
going to first do this and then it's
going to do that and so it's it's it's
got this nasty problem where if I want
to support that variable samplerate I
can't have things nicely aligned and I
can't really think of any of any real
way I could avoid that right like if I
want to support the pitch Bend I it just
doesn't seem like there's any way to
keep it aligned you're going to end up
having to do on aligned reads from the
sample buffers and yeah I don't I don't
know what we could do about that so I
wonder if maybe we just have to bite
them we have to bite the unaligned reeds
and there's really not much we can do
about it and we'd always process aight
output samples at a time but yeah I
don't know I don't think we can do it
guys I don't think so maybe think about
that a little bit see if you can think
about it but it seems like we wouldn't
actually be able to do that and so I
think we still want to keep doing
roughly what we're doing here but it
does mean that that we it's never going
to be aligned so meaning this stuff
right here is not actually going to be a
line samples to mix will still be
aligned to eight and we'll move along
but real sample remaining and sound uh
yeah
no this parts going to be this parts
going to have to be all of aligned and
weird so yes so I think that's just the
way it goes I don't know what else to do
so I guess we keep it this way it's on a
line but who cares and we'll keep
everything in multiples of eight for now
and we'll see how that goes so we've got
samples remaining and sound equals you
know whatever the when we round this
real samples meaning and sound again
this is all in units that are divided by
eight we then look to see whether the
samples to mix so that the eight counts
is going to stop early and if so we
stopped at early like this so we're
really doing exact same thing just
everything's / 8 now we then do the same
thing here with volume ended eight and
when we come through here we've got the
both volumes at the same time bye baby
we'll take a look at the end but we
don't really care about that at the
moment but we'd like to fix that to do
eventually as well come through the
channel indices and let's see what we've
got here so we want to do exactly the
same thing that we've been doing we want
everything to be on an eight count now
so if we've got the Delta volume we have
the target volume minus the regular
volume that's the difference right and
then we've got the sample count so we
want to do is figure out in counts of
eight how much is that going to be right
so we would have the Delta volume
divided by the the d volume here and we
drowned that out right but before we
cast it down to a u32 what we would want
to do here is again divide that by eight
right so we would want to essentially
multiply on the headend 1 over 8 to get
that to get that sort of contraction
there right how do I do that one over
8.1 25 right like so so we want to do
this so now that's the volume sample
County and again we do the same clamping
that we were doing up ahead right I
don't know why I said this is volume
ended eight that was kind of stupid
that's not it's just a boolean all right
so then we come through here we have our
sample position right and that's going
to be samples played and we're going to
again make that be at eight you know a
multiple of 8 thing the
only difference is its floating point so
really when we multiply it out we're
going to actually respect its sub
position instead of rounding it to a
multiple of eight so we're pulling we're
going to have to load unaligned from the
sound and that again is just to make
sure that we can support that variable
pitch right so off we go we take our
sample index and our sample index is
going to be floor real 32 to n 32 of the
sample position eight right we're going
to multiply that by eight to get it back
up and then we're going to floor it
right so that's all good that's all well
and good right frack works the same we
then have our samples here and the
samples are going to be done sort of
eight wide if you will and so what we
probably want to do here is actually
emulate that in in our loop so we can we
could emulate doing them eight wide if
you will and then I'll kind of jump over
that loop since that's the main thing
that we got to work on here let's see
let's do that and then we'll fix this
loop by moving it into simdi if that
makes sense so yes so the volume right
is going to be something that gets
incremented now by eight times the Delta
volume if that makes sense in fact I
guess what we could do is this d volume
we could just have the eight you
multiply into that right so that way
when we increment it as well it works
the same way right so we have D volume
here this is actually going to be d
volume 8 so it's eight times the rate of
change that we were expecting to see
right so yeah I think that's good and d
sample would presumably be handled the
exact same way so this is actually eight
times the increment of the sample right
so let's take a look what else we got
here so this is divided by D sample so
oh I guess the problem with that though
is that this calculation wants to know
about that movement right it wants to
know about this not not x 8 it would
seem right because you want to know
because you've already pre divided these
guys by eight which I suppose we could
just not / ain't not pre / 8 and since
we're already dividing by D sample maybe
this is just an excuse to say oh you
didn't really have to change that you
still need to do the padding so you
don't overrun when you do your your wide
read but maybe you can just leave these
guys as they were trying to think of how
that would play out right I think that
would work right you could do it this
way and then that would produce real
sample remaining and sound right I guess
this should be samples remaining in sand
yeah I don't dislike that that seems
that seems somewhat reasonable to me
that seems too unreasonable to me maybe
it's just the intense heat here but that
seems somewhat reasonable to me so okay
we've got volume ended here we've got
the stuff working Delta volume we're
gonna have to step through this a little
bit more carefully and see everything
because I'm making a bunch of changes
and sort of change in my mind as we go
through things and so that's always the
case where you going to have to kind of
scrutinize a little bit later but that's
fine so becoming here we've got our
sample position stuff working the way
that we would think samples played if we
were to actually make that B naught
divided by eight now we would end up
with just sample position right and if d
sample eight wordy sample eight then
that means that now sample position just
actually is x d sample
I'm sorry just gets moved by B sample a
and is just a regular value and then we
wouldn't have to multiply them here so
that does seem like maybe that's just
the smarter way to do it I'm totally
willing to believe that that's just a
smarter idea they're right so let's keep
going with all of that nonsense when we
get to the end here we look at the
current volume we can still set it the
way that we were setting it before we
can still do these endings the way we're
doing before those don't change we can
still assert that the total samples to
mix 8 is greater than the samples to mix
8 or equal we can still say that the
samples played equals the sample
position and we can still subtract out
the samples to mix 8 this is probably
more properly written like that all
right so let's see slaying sound samples
played equals loaded sound sample count
that's all fine and we could as the
samples played advances it may advance
past the end so what we really want to
say if it's if it's greater than or
equal to the sample count then what we
want to do is is see about that having
that next one in there right yeah so
that's also I guess sort of got the same
issue that we would have had before
so we do have one other thing that's
actually kind of tricky here this is the
exact same thing as our bilinear
filtering without edges case right and I
didn't even think about this week we
actually had this problem before and we
probably just didn't notice it but I
think it would get worse when we're
doing it in chunks of eight so if you
remember the one we were doing our
bilinear filtering we had this thing
where we wanted to make seamless
textures right where we wanted it to be
so that you know we'd have these things
on the seam if this is the seemed like
we had like this was a ground chunk
right and here's a ground chunk we had
things where we had like two things one
on either side of the chunk wrote one of
the one in either side of a scene in
different chunks and what I was saying
is when we were drawing this chunk we
didn't know what this chunk would
actually be and the bilinear filtering
would fail across this edge and so what
we did to solve that problem right is we
actually introduced an extra set of
pixels along the edge so that when you
have a here you actually insert be into
the edge of the other chunk right and I
think that's exactly what we would need
to do here for those streaming chunks
right what we want to do is make sure
that we can blend over the edge so that
when we take eight samples and we're
doing that by linear and we're stepping
anywhere inside the eight samples we
know that as we hit the end of one of
our streaming sounds we will blend
properly between the two right so we
would have had this this problem before
right if you imagine here is a the sort
of a scene in the sound if you will
right so here's one loaded piece of the
sound and here's another loaded piece
right and if you look at what's going to
happen here the same problem would occur
if here is a sample a and here's a
sample be when we would get to the end
if we were trying to sample from right
here we would pick up a zero that was
like the padding at the end of this
sounds buffer because uh you know that's
just whatever is actually after in
memory but what we wanted to play
with us actually be right so we want to
do is pad the end of this loaded sample
with whatever comes next right and so
that's actually what would just
automatically happen right that's
actually what would happen if we just
didn't do anything and that's probably
why was working before and we didn't
hear an error although it may have just
been because we never hit a case where
you could actually hear it very well
because since we were loading the whole
sound every time so it was debug code
would naturally have had that padding at
the end of it and so what we want to do
here for padding I think really in the
asset in the asset stuff where we do
this padding here we don't want to do we
do not want to do that padding right we
want to leave that padding undone and we
have to just put it to do in here which
is like all sounds have to be padded you
know with their subsequent sound you
know out to eight samples past their end
right we don't really care anymore about
a line eight a line eight is simply not
interesting anymore what's actually
interesting is and I'll sort of get rid
of this for now because well I guess we
could do is say in the case where we
weren't one of those long running sounds
right what we would want to do is we
would want to do this padding only in in
that case right in the case where we
yeah in the case where we weren't doing
it so so we can just go ahead and say
we've got the actual results sample camp
in here go count sample camp and so when
we're not in that like reloading out a
little bit of a chunk
yeah we would want to yeah we would want
to do this so you know what I think we
want to do it probably always if the the
end is us if we are the end of the sound
so if the first sample index plus the
section sample count meaning where we
would actually get to is equal to the
sample count we're at the end of the
buffer right I and yeah yeah we're at
meeting we're at the end of the buffer
but that's going to be true no matter
what happens here because we're over
writing it all right so how do I do that
how do i do that i think i do something
like um i guess i just do something like
if you know add end i think i just do
something like this add n equals false
or i guess i should say Adams is
probably always true except in this case
where we say addend is if we were going
to be at the very end of this sort of
thing that was streamed in peace mail so
assuming that we're at the end of
something meaning either this thing was
not a streamed in guy so he's going to
be he's an entire sound in himself or in
the case where we are streamed and sound
but were at the very end what we want to
do here is pad with the subsequent we
want to pad the zeroes right because
this the fact that we're loading the
whole sound will take care of the
padding in the other cases but here we
want to take care of that padding again
this will all be handling the asset
preprocessor normally so we really don't
care but we might as well just try to
emulate to a certain degree here so when
we do this what we want to do we want to
do something like this right where we'd
say essentially the sample count eight
past the sample count we will pad that
with zeros just to make sure that anyone
who reads off there isn't get any actual
data and then I think we're okay I think
that's really all we needed to do since
we have to be unaligned all the time
anyway
I think that's all we really need to do
and now we can load right off the end
and that's fine so let's go ahead and
here and say you're in three two sample
offset equals zero sample offset is less
than eight sample offset + + now we have
a way to offset our sample and so our
sample index is always going to sort of
the jittered it's going to be that I
shouldn't say jittered but offset by
whatever that sample offset is if that
makes sense and so when we go ahead and
do this here I think everything else
should be fine I think if we were using
the other path we could do that as well
and I think that's really it so this
would this would do that that movement
by eight there right that would that
would do the movement by eight for us
it's all good so let's take a look here
if d vol.8 what else we got alright so
we've made a lot of changes there some
of its kind of janky so let's see where
we're at
surprisingly we still play sound alright
so now that we're moving by eight it
should be possible for us right to drop
this this portion into simdi relatively
easily because this is all happening on
actual eights right so if you take a
look at what's happening here we're
doing some fairly basic stuff we've got
some multiplies we've got some rights
and we could start by doing the simpler
case first I'll go ahead and get rid of
the bilinear blend for now right first
write the linear blend right so we've
got just a regular case what one Sophie
coming here you know what we also aren't
really testing variable speeds I suppose
so we could also say that d sample eight
times one point you know or 0 point nine
or something like this right 43.9 f
sounds a little janky so think we might
still have some some problems in there
yeah you can kind of here so i'm not
sure that we've quite got that working
properly although i guess i also don't
know how much we tested those guys
before let me take a quick look at this
one as well oh duh so sample offset here
is actually not going to be correct is
it because the sample offset has to
actually be a real value right so it's
actually the sample index here the
sample position is what actually has to
get changed right sample position has to
be a you know sample offset right times
whatever d sample would have been right
it has to be it has to be just regular d
sample like that so that's that's why
that was was janky right hopefully you
can see what I'm talking about there
alright so yeah I don't I don't think
that's probably too much of a problem
and we have to deal with that Miss md
stuff anyway we have 50 minutes since we
started late today so ignore the QA
begins now part of things so there's the
oops I didn't want to duplicate that I
want you to hate this so yeah so we've
got that in both forms here we go still
a little wrong sounding so we've got d
sample and we've got d sample eight so
that's all good we've got sample
indexical sample position plus sample
offset times d sample which is what i
think it should be we've got
fractional value being what I think it
would be sampled value yeah that looks
relatively good so I'm gonna have to
think a little harder about where that
bug is yeah so this part is not
particularly interesting we don't care
about that I think it's just this guy
who's problematic let's see when we
update our samples played for samples
position that's all fine so yeah I don't
I'm not seeing it I wonder if I'm
staring right at it but I'm not seeing
what the bug is there we want to do
eight samples at a time we are doing
that we want to offset them by however
much a single d sample step is which we
are doing ah but sample position
actually needs to be this this is not
actually correct here right because this
frack would be wrong I don't think
that's probably what's causing the
problem though so this is offset sample
position I guess right yeah yes that's
right so there's our offset sample
position and then we would we would do
it that way and that looks better well I
take a fact that does seem to be what
was causing it
alright so at this point I think we can
drop this into simdi okay so what we
would like to do in terms of making this
work with simdi is we've got a plus
equals here so obviously we're going to
have an mm load PS to load in our desk
right again just standard sim do stuff
that we're doing here so we've got our
d0 like so and our d1 and we are going
to have to load those guys in now we're
doing eight samples at a time so we
actually have I guess something that's
actually a little bit more confusing
we've got it looking more like this
right we've got a load in more samples
than that we've got we've got a load in
two destinations because each one holds
four floats and we're doing eight
samples at a time right so actually what
we're doing is we're loading something
more like this right we're loading
something probably should write it like
this desk 00 01 just 10 best 11 and of
course we have to cast these two floats
for reasons that only Intel knows and so
when we load these guys out then after
we are done loading them we would do our
work and then at the end we would go
ahead and add two to them right we would
advance them by two and here's the work
that we would do in there so yeah and
then afterwards we would do you know
after loading them we would do something
where we would store them out like so
and again these are going to be aligned
loads and stores because unlike the the
pitch stuff unlike what we're reading
from which cannot be I think we've
determined that that probably can't be
aligned we can't align all of these
these these should remain a lion I don't
see any particular reason why they
couldn't
aligned always so that should be fine uh
yeah so let's see we'll do our loads
from desk we'll do our stores back to
test and I guess I gotta put some a
dressers in here there we go and our
desk itself we would like that to
actually point to M 128s now get rid of
that passing and yeah so those will be
advancing by two which is eight floats
which is eight samples which is how much
we're doing them by we can get rid of
our sort of outer sample work there and
the volume and sample position stuff
still would be advancing pretty much the
same way so now we've got this stuff in
here that we need to do right we need to
multiply by the volume we need to
multiply by the master volume and then
we would need to write it back so we can
do that pretty easily I can just
essentially do all of these guys could
just be mmole PS and we would assume we
have a master volume for essentially
that's replicated I guess I'll just call
that master volume and that we'd also
have a volume 4 will do it this way we
can multiply these two together and then
we can multiply yes the result by
whatever the sample value is right and
that sample value we would add we would
then add the same so I guess I should
probably call this a little bit
something else let me think about how I
want to do this so we have the sample
value and then we're going to compute
its attenuated version so this is like
the volume version and then we're just
going to add it in right we could do it
all in one step I just don't know if
that's getting a little bit too verbose
right but you can see I have to do the
ad as well right so I have to do and add
you know basically adding to d 00
whatever the mole here is
for these guys right so multiply the
master plan by the volume and that by
the sample value and that would give us
the results that we would actually want
right and this is pretty much all the
same right so we would just need to now
have these master volumes the master
volume is going to be in two flavors
right there's going to be one for
channel 0 and 1 for channel 1 I guess
and the volume itself is going to be the
same way right so both of these have
essentially to you know two versions one
for the left channel 14 the right
channel all right so that seems
reasonable right that all seems pretty
good and the sample value is the same in
all cases just gets loaded out so really
all we have to worry about now is
loading the actual sample value right
that's the primer the primary part of it
and then we would have to worry about of
course also getting these volume samples
and all that stuff initialize properly
okay so if we want to do that what we
need to do first I guess let's try doing
it without the bilinear case so in this
case we have to do this this stuff right
so we have to figure out what our what
our sample value is by doing this with
this round here so we have our sample
position and our sample position right
is now going to be something that's
actually going to be 8 wide if that
makes sense we're going to actually have
sort of a you know a sample position
that's that's that's that's got eight
separate
well no now I think about it we don't
really have to do that well we'll be
able to do only one load but it's
unclear exactly how we would want to to
index into it right this is kind of
bizarre so think about this for a second
right what we know is we have a sample
yeah this is kind of ugly actually not I
think about it because man the
difference between when your pitch
bending and when you're not pitch
bending is pretty drastic in terms of
how bad it would be how much uglier the
code is uglier is probably the wrong
word but how much more work the code
would actually have to do so one way we
could do this is by doing 60 and
separate fetches right but that's really
kind of a waste I'm sorry eight
different fetches but that's really kind
of a waste of time because most of time
most of the time like let's say you're
playing back at speed of one point oh
all of the samples you want are right
there in one single load so it's kind of
janky it seems almost like we would want
to actually special case that and have
two different loops one that does it you
know per per sample or something for the
pitch bend case and one that doesn't
because man the difference between those
two is going to be vicious right like
I'm just trying to think if you imagine
going at a rate let's say you pitch bend
it at a rate of 0 point 9 or something
right then the actual samples are going
to blend between or like you know these
two these two these two I'm sorry it's
like those to those to those to those to
those two and then like those two again
and then those two and then those two
and so on right so inside that loop it's
really kind of nasty because there's no
way to really shift the buffers around
yeah I don't really know and that's even
even in the non by linear case it's kind
of annoying right because I do this load
from
sound and I guess let me draw it out
explicitly so here's the sound and here
are the samples like so right and if I'm
pulling from them at a rate of one point
oh I could just read this whole thing in
and do ops on it directly it's exactly
what I want right I'd load this part of
it into float I'd load this part of it
into float I do my ops right and then
I'd write them out to the buffer right
so this is like float conversion here
this is like volume add and then you
store it right so be super simple it
would be just be just really really
straightforward but as soon as I
introduce the concept that the speed
might be different then we get this
problem of like okay even without by lab
even without linear blending I might end
up in a situation where this is what i'm
reading but what i want to actually
operate on is like 0 0 0 1 1 1 2 2 or
something right and that's just a really
hard thing to make happen I mean it
almost seems like there's just no way to
make that happen any faster than just
reading the things piece mail out of the
out of the buffer right I mean I really
just don't see how you would do it so I
mean if that was the case we could not
bother going by eights and actually just
go by forest because if we're not able
to load ate at a time then there's that
but you can see that's that's kind of
nasty right that's that's pretty ugly in
my opinion
yeah that is just that's really
unfortunate because it means that I just
don't know if there's anything you could
really do here that would be
particularly clever without just special
casing the loop a couple times for cases
where you did know that you were doing
relatively consistent reads from there
so yeah so I don't know so this part
really easy right that part is is
trivial the other part not so easy it's
least not so easy to make go fast what
it would actually look like if we don't
actually try to make it go through the
Cindy path and just pack it at the end
we would essentially have something
looks like this we have sample value
right and that's going to be an M and
set PS and then what we would do is we
would load the sample indices out here
write something like this right and
these guys obviously we didn't quite do
all of their and yeah it just looks like
at that point you just don't care about
eight eighths at all eighths is just not
that useful you might as well go by
fours right least I can't see any reason
why you would so anyway yeah you got
these guys and then you would just
actually have to load them separately
you know you would have to load them
basically using this this exact equation
here so I think I might actually just go
ahead and copy that in like so
what did that do that is some weird
piece of code there we go oops so we
take the sand position we load the
sample office times the D sample and
that's X the sample index that we would
use and we would have to literally do
that and load it in in order so we would
go like this and I think that's just you
know 0.01 point O two point oh three
point oh right so we would literally
load the samples out like this and then
the second set would would load it out
like that and yet just not again really
kind of annoying i but i just don't
really see you know just to be honest i
just don't see what the alternative is
there right i don't know what we could
do that would be all that much smarter
than that so let's go ahead and wrap
that up well think about this maybe for
tomorrow see if there's anything that we
can think of that would be better
where's my M 128 there it is so for
setting these two guys up front our
master volume and our volume for the
master volume is always constant right
it's not changing so the master volume
is is easier that's just whatever audio
state master volume is that's just a
replicated value right that's an mm set
1 p.s but the volume for this one is
actually a little trickier because you
think about it it needs to be ramping
like the first value that in it and the
it's it's actually operating I guess I
should should jump over here let's see
to the whiteboard
if you think about what's going to
happen there right you've got this
volume and in it it's got v-0 v1 v2 v3
right because we are multiplying by this
guy right we're multiplying this as we
go with our samples so we'd have sample
one you know to like so on right and
when we multiply these down this can't
be constant because each individual
sample is supposed to be ramping up or
down its volume over time potentially so
we need the values inside the volume to
actually be pre incremented like this
should be the base volume level and then
it should go up by the d volume at each
individual you know at each location
right so that when we multiply them
together we're getting a volume ramp in
wide so these guys actually have to be
set ps2 something that's a little more
clever right it needs to be set to
whatever the the let's see here we would
need to do the volume regular again get
that out so the volume and so in here we
want something like the volume and it
would be the first one right and then I
guess oops the first one plus what
nothing times the d volume right and
then the next one is going to be 1 point
0 times the d volume right and then 2.0
then three-point oh right so we step we
like it's like pre stepped that volume
ramp is right and so then when we come
through here and we actually do that
that volume edition right you know the
the actual volume I guess I don't know
do we actually ever use that that does
that guy do yeah so we actually do use
it we can probably just make it cheaper
to extract this guy out here but then
what we would do is say
okay we've got our d volume four and
that's actually equal to or i should say
84 we need a better naming this is this
this is getting way too hairy for naming
if it wasn't the end of the stream here
we rename things probably right now but
anyway so we've got the d volume like so
right and we cut and paste these guys
because we've also got the version for
the other channel right so there we go
yeah we really need a good naming we're
going to have to go through here and
rename these these names are awful
there's so many different permutations
of things that we need some way of like
making this naming a little bit more
consistent now that we actually know
what it is that we need to do and we
could simplify things a little bit by
the fact that we don't have step by
eight Boyett step by four so we're gonna
have the same problem permutation wise
if that makes sense so yeah so if we
have these guys in here I think that's
pretty much all we would need to do so
in here we would have our our volume for
right it gets added the same way like so
and so those are actually track now
right and the master volume of course
like I said doesn't actually ever need
to to to be tracked in any way although
we do need to do both versions again
yeah
uh so okay let's see here oops and these
guys are obviously wide editions now so
those are mm add PS is and there we go
alright so yet not quite done yet
unfortunately and we're five minutes
over so we got to end soon unfortunately
but let's just make sure we left things
in a semi usable state so we we read all
the samples out here and put pack them
in we load out of the dest into two
different channels and two different
sets we really need to switch back
switching away from doing eight is going
to be crucial here to cut down on the
number of the denominator since we know
we don't need to do it anymore so then
we go ahead and do our moles here it
looks like these these are correct but
this guy has to be done in two portions
right this guy is is actually d volume
40 if that makes sense or I should say
yeah like this this guy is actually that
it's it's an ad of these two that makes
sense because of the fact that we're
stepping like we are so again super
janky and we could get rid of this man
sometimes I just hate programming on the
screen because you know I want to like
actually go do this properly I want to
remove the the fact that we're going by
eights and then I want to change all
these names so they make sense and I
don't have the luxury of doing that on
the stream and it's it's very
disappointing so anyway yeah so let's
see I think that's it for that yeah and
it's kind of all annoying in a really
annoying way so I can drastically
simplify all this I just don't have the
luxury of being able to do it today
and that's unfortunate but you know
we'll least try to leave things in a
compiling state they just won't be in a
working state so I think all that's good
we can do our remote we do our multiply
ads here those all seem reasonable we
track our volume still which is correct
we advance our destination which is
correct yeah we're just going to not be
playing anything reasonable let's see it
wasn't as bad as I thought we were going
to be I'll admit that so let's go ahead
and change it back to the normal speed
so you can kind of hear we messed up
some stuff right which is exactly what I
would expect to happen certainly but
again we're completely out of time so
I'm going to have to leave it there and
then tomorrow what I'd like to do is go
through here remove the by 8 and turn it
to just being by 4 because again the
only reason I wanted to do it by eight
it so I thought we'd be able to load ate
at a time out of the 16 bits and
blubbers but really we can't do that
because I mean we could only do that in
a very specific case which is where
we're not changing the pitch so that's
unfortunate but that's just the way it
is and so we'll go through and we'll
remove that which will clean up a lot of
this kind of ugliness in terms of the
notation and then we can tomorrow go
through it and actually clean up you
know go carefully through the code now
that we know everything that it actually
is going to do and that should hopefully
help us as well clean you know get rid
of some of the errors and that sort of
thing and debug it so again not in bad
shape but again really wish we could
just go an hour hit another hour here
and then we could finish all this stuff
but we'll have to wait till tomorrow and
so with that in mind we will put we will
put this episode to bed and and go to
the QA yeah so please if you have any
questions prefix them with q colon and I
will answer them now and yeah hopefully
I mean there really isn't much left to
do here we're mostly done so really we
need to do is gank out the x 8 thing and
then just clean up you know this this
stuff is is typo tastic right it's so we
just need to clean that up and make this
not be so so ridiculously weird there if
that makes sense see if this is reading
a sample position yeah so that reads out
the samples by going along d sample so
that's that's all nice
and the volume stuff isn't changing
right now so I feel like that should
actually not be really affecting us so
i'm not sure where our actual bug is but
i'm assuming that it would be will be
relatively clear tomorrow where the bug
is that make sense
uh oh thank you for someone on stream
already caught lot of typos these guys I
didn't actually change when I put them
in there okay I guess that was the
primary problem
it's always nice to have people watching
on the stream they catch all my typos
it's pretty nice yeah what's in the
eight bits we've been working on is it
frequency and volume yeah if you missed
previous streams so what we're doing in
the sound sampler is we have D sample is
the speed at which things are playing
back so it's basically you know the
sample location so that changes the
pitch if you change it and then volume
is just how loud it is why is there a
command override 0d with auteur it's
it's OD and 02 so what's happening there
is just that because we wanted to be
able to keep the renderer running in
optimized mode because since the
renderer does so much work and is
carefully well not carefully but is
designed to run particularly quickly
right now we wanted to always run with
it in optimized mode so it's broken out
in its own line here and you can see it
uses minus 0 2 and so I just want to
keep using common compiler flags which
are set to either debug or release one
of the other and then I just over wrote
it with an 02 so that only this one file
gets gets compiled without my visions
can you skip the 0 point 0 times D
sample and only do one two and three yes
you can but the compiler will usually
automatically remove that so i usually
don't bother i usually leave it so you
can see what's supposed to be happening
there that makes sense not sure if it
does or not but that's the idea
any other questions since we went a
started late today I guess it's a good
day not to have too many questions
because we can end on time
what does minus OD do that's not when
I've come across before it simply
disables optimizations so it's basically
telling the compiler don't do anything
pretty much at all to the code just
literally straight translate it into
assembly and the reason that that's a
useful switch is because it means that
if you want to go look at something in
the debugger nothing has been moved
around or optimized or changed it's all
extremely straightforward and does
exactly what you typed in and so when
you're doing development it often helps
to have minus OD on because that means
debugging is is usually pretty easy and
we can do that for most of handmade hero
because we don't have a lot of speed
critical stuff in in it right now but
the renderer just processes a ton of
pixels right it's doing a huge workload
and so it needs to be on Oh to all the
time or our frame rate at 1920 x 1080
isn't good enough so and that's what
handmade optimized is all about gasto 5
it's just about making sure that the
renderer which does the vast vast
majority of the work is always built
with 02 so that we get a nice fast 1920
x 1080 frame rate and we don't have to
constantly switch between debug and
release build we can always just have a
debug build that's still fast enough so
what do you think about the engine used
at overgrowth and its sound capabilities
I have not actually looked at what it
sound capabilities are so I don't
actually know
I'm guessing that without specifying
some sort of optimization flag there
will still be some optimizations done
which you want to explicitly not do yeah
I mean the idea behind it is just that
you're specifying to the compiler
definitely don't do any optimizations
right and so the compiler may have been
defaulting to do some optimizations or
maybe it wouldn't be I guess it could
depend on the version of the compiler
you're using or what its default
environment variables were set to or who
knows what right and so really all the
minus OD does it says no matter what you
were going to do by default don't
instead just straight translate the code
with no optimization thought put into it
whatsoever cast 05 is this the last
stream for audio no we've got to clean
up this mixing code tomorrow and just
set it up to go by fours instead of by
eight so we got to do that but then then
we'll be done and we can go back to
finish up the asset stuff which really
is just about memory management and then
we should be able to convert over to
asset files which would be really nice
looking forward to that that's going to
be nice so hopefully by the end of the
week we will have like an asset file
formats pecked out you know something
that we can say this is going to be how
the assets are shipped from now on
instead of as like bmps and webs
all right I'm gonna go ahead and wrap
things up since we still got more work
to do tonight figuring out how we're
going to do this this whole github
situation all right I'm going to close
this damn save all right thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to follow along at home you can
always pure to the game at handmade hero
org and it comes to the source code so
you can play around with it learn from
it experiment with it which is good way
to learn you can also ask questions on
our forum site and take a look at anti
depa sewed guys get porch to mac and
linux that sort of thing we also have a
patreon page you want to support the
video series you could subscribe there
and finally we have a tweet bot which
will tweet the schedule so every weekend
you can find out when we're going to be
live that week and it will also tweet
during the day when the stream is coming
up so you can make sure not to miss it
so if you're trying to get to stream
live that's a great way to do it that's
about it for today I have a bunch of
work I got to do tonight and probably
all week trying to figure out exactly
how we're going to get community github
repository stuff going we're trying to
make that happen since enough people
have requested it but it's going to be
it's going to take a little while and
there's so much things we have to sort
out but we're working on it and
hopefully there'll be some more news
about that maybe next week or sometime
soon so thanks everybody who's been
helping out with that I really
appreciate it and you know i look
forward to hopefully getting everything
resolved so that there's something
usable at least as usable as github can
be for people who want to work with the
source that way instead of downloading
zips all right everyone take it easy and
i will catch you I will catch you
tomorrow same time same place 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time so until then have
a good one and i'll see you online