hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show that we code a complete
game I should say where we code a
complete game live on twitch no engines
no libraries it's just us and one of the
things about it just being us it means
that we have to debug all our code
ourselves of course and one of the
things about debugging code is that it
can be really difficult sometimes to
debug difficult bugs if you don't have
some tools at your disposal obviously
one of those a debugger but another one
that's very common in game development
is actual debug tools that you write
yourself that are built into the game
that help you narrow down the spaces
where bugs could be or help you find the
bugs in the first place and that is what
we are doing right now on handmade hero
we're taking a look at some things that
we can build into our code base that
will allow us to find bugs more
effectively and allow us to sort of if
you will like percolate bugs to the
surface to in cases where bugs may be
hiding or lurking around so we're trying
to make bugs more visible and we're
trying to make them easier to find we
just got started on this yesterday I
gave a little bit of an overview and
then we kind of started programming but
we haven't gotten very far so today will
really be our first full day of coding
on this and we have plenty of stuff to
do so I think we should trust go ahead
and get right into it now today is day
177 so if you preorder the game on
handmade hero org what you want to do is
download day 1 7 unpack day 176 is
source code into a directory and you
want to start working with that because
here on day 1 7 that's what I'm starting
with so if you want to follow along at
home that's the way to do it now if you
remember where we left off yesterday I
had just started making a handmade debug
H which I just wanted to make a separate
file we could start putting debug stuff
in because we're gonna have a lot of it
and I'd like to keep as much as possible
the debug code isolated from the main
code so that we can kind of see what's
debug and what's not and have easier
ways to turn it on and all that sorts of
stuff cuz we've got a bunch of work that
we have to do there so I'm just gonna
start dumping it in this file so that
can kind of keep it separate now what we
did here is we made our we started to
kind of work on our debug cycle counters
and that's because we had already done
them and so I thought the first thing
that might be fun to do
with the debug code and getting that
sort of stuff up and running was to sort
of make these debug counters into
something that was a little more usable
as an exercise and so that's what I'm in
the middle of doing okay so we pretty
much finished that that very simple step
of just making a you know a macro that
instead of having to do a begin and an
end for every time clock that you might
want to do you could actually do it so
that you just have a structure which has
a constructor and a destructor which
will make it so that the compiler will
automatically insert the constructor in
the destructor into the block and then
you can get a start in an end that
happen automatically right but that
still doesn't quite get me in fact it's
not really even getting me anywhere
close to be honest with you to the level
of ease-of-use that I actually want in
my timing system because remember as we
talked about there's a bunch of things
that we want to have happen here in
terms of ease of use and one of the
biggest ones is whenever we have one of
these times like a time clock thing I
want it to be almost free you know as
free as possible to just drop one of
these in anywhere but that is not the
case right so why is that not the case
well first of all so we replaced the you
know the beginning end at the at the
front and end of this thing we base that
with time block so that took care of
like some of that extra typing of having
to go down to the bottom and the block
and do it that's fine right but suppose
I want to time a new function so I want
to time say draw a bitmap right I put
something in here I say draw a bitmap as
far as I'm concerned that's really all I
should have had to do right I should be
able to just go ahead and do it that way
and I just hit compile and now I've got
a new time block but you'll notice with
the system that we constructed earlier
on we don't have that at all right it's
gonna give us an error and the reason
that's gonna give us in areas because
that draw a bitmap needs to correspond
to some kind of an ID that's been sort
of written up in here right and so it
forces the programmer in the middle of
thinking about whatever they're trying
to do it forces the programmer to stop
what they were doing and just to use the
debugging system
come out and remember how this works add
a new debug counter to it right it's
just not that's not the mental flow that
I want I want to be able to spam this in
here and be done right and you remember
we have sort of this with asserts right
I can just say assert buffer is not
equal to zero or something I can just
type that in and now I've just added
some nice debug code that I never have
to worry about again it just works it
does what I want and I didn't have to go
think about any code structure or jump
to another file or anything so that's
where we want our block timing to to end
up I think that's really more where I'd
like to see it be so how do we get there
okay well there's a couple problems that
we have there's a couple of things that
we need to keep in mind the first one is
that this kind of a thing like with
timing a block is somewhat performance
critical the whole point of timing a
block right the only reason that we're
going to time a block is because we want
to know the performance of that part of
the code so the last thing that we want
to do when we go to time a block is
insert a lot of unpredictable overhead
or expense into that operation because
the more expense we insert into that
operation the less we will be able to
use it first of all right if it was
really expensive that would limit the
number we of them we could even do so
that's not good but even more
importantly the more heavyweight the
operation that the block timing has to
do the more it affects the performance
of the code that it is trying to time so
if I'm trying to look at how drawbitmap
performs and I do something in time
block that goes and walks a bunch of
data structures and and copy strings
around and does who knows what I'm going
to be in a situation where the state of
the cache on entry to drawbitmap could
be significantly affected by my attempts
to profile it so it's worth noting here
that I'm not just trying to make this
easy to use I'm also trying to make it
very efficient so that to the extent
reasonably possible it will not undo
we modify the state of the computer as
it rolls through because the more I can
the more I can avoid sort of Heisenberg
in it the more accurate and useful this
timing information will be right okay so
this is going to require some work on
our part it's some relatively major work
that I've been putting off for a while I
came to that at the very beginning of
handmade Hiro
but it's going to start you'll start to
see why some of these things take place
and and we'll kind of show how to deal
with some of them and and all that sort
of stuff but it's it's a good thing so
don't you know relax don't worry too
much about it this is the kind of thing
that I like to do in programming all the
time and changes that are major in my
opinion should not be things that scare
you as long as you are confident and you
keep a good eye on what you're doing
it's not really too much of a problem
but to start with we're not really gonna
go for the major change for it yet we're
gonna go for the minor change and we're
gonna kind of work our way up to it so
first things first how do we get rid of
our IDs well it turns out that in --see
there is a relatively easy way that we
can get some information about where
this time block is in such a way that we
do not need to introduce some additional
enumerate for telling where it is right
and those are the preprocessor
directives that we've already kind of
seen right well actually you know what
now that I think about it maybe we've
never seen them have we ever used these
maybe we haven't all right I guess this
is the first time so that's totally fine
let's go ahead and show what they are so
if I wanted to at any point in see the
preprocessor right the thing that does
like handles pound include and pound to
find that thing right if I want to at
any point in a C program I can go into
and I'll put this right at the beginning
so we can see it I can go into game
update render or anywhere else for that
matter and I can use a set of directives
and here they are right this is just a
couple of them file
chin line these directives will actually
expand to exactly what they say if I
want to I can get the file name of the
file that's currently being compiled
just by using that directive I can get
the function name right by using that
and I can get an actual you know integer
line number by doing that now sometimes
there's some con string nonsense that
happens there so sometimes you have to
cast them and that's because people who
I you know would would slap around a bit
if I got my hands on them think that
forcing people to use cost is a good
idea you know we'll have words we'll
take him out back behind the shed it's
fine but you can always cast that stuff
away so it doesn't pose up too much of a
problem but I'm saying some compilers
like LLVM will give you warnings there
and you have to cast them so we may have
to deal with that when we're going to
other platforms but for the moment on
Windows it's still relatively sane so if
I go ahead now and I make a breakpoint
at game update and render and I run now
you can see that when I step in here
those variables will have the pieces of
information that I asked for set right
so what the compiler is doing here is
the compiler is actually going to embed
these strings into our code when it
compiles it right so it's not like at
this point in the code it's going and
asking some Oracle what the file name is
there anything all it's doing is on the
compile pass it's actually seeing that
this existed it's seeing like say what
function it is or what file it is and
it's actually adding to the string table
that string and pointing this at that
piece of the data segment of the
executable right so it's just adding
basically constants but those constants
are automatically defined by the
compiler so we don't have to worry about
doing it ourselves or making them
out-of-date we don't have to go oh it's
line 843 and put 843 there and then
worried that when we add lines begin the
file that becomes wrong right so it's
pretty nice so the line number 843 that
is what it is right the function name is
game update and render which it is
that's great we have the filename which
is also a they're 841
and there's one other which I to be
honest with you I don't super remember
whether it's it's actually allowed in in
all C compilers I think it probably is
at this point and so I'm gonna kind of
show you I'm gonna show it to you and I
think at this point it's probably safe
for us to use I don't know if we'll have
to use it but I just want you to be
aware of it because it can be kind of
useful for certain situations that we
may find ourselves in I can't really
predict if we will or not but I'm just
gonna go ahead and show you so assuming
that M SBC supports the sky which I'm
pretty sure he does or she I don't know
the gender of Visual Studio probably an
it would be my guess so I'm gonna run
through here and you can kind of see
that each one of these guys now takes on
a value that is the number of times that
underscore underscore counter has
actually appeared in this file
now there really isn't too much of a
point in doing this other than the fact
that in theory if you were trying to use
something like a line number to
disambiguate something in a macro if two
of those appeared on the same line they
would have the same number so counter
with especially when we're dealing with
debug situations counter is a good thing
to know is available because if you find
yourself in a situation where multiple
things on the same line want to be able
to be distinguished by some kind of a
preprocessor number you've got a way
that you can reliably do that and so
that can be kind of handy right so those
are some things that just to be aware of
because now we're gonna start using
those to help us do some things
automatically and again this is not
typically something that you really need
to use too much in your action in your
actual production shipping C++ code
sometimes you do but it is something
that you will absolutely use all the
time in the debug augmentation of that
C++ code and here is a perfect example
of where we're going to do that so what
I'd like to do now is if I go ahead and
take this time to block here
and I have that drawbitmap what I would
like to do is be able to and let's just
you know go hog-wild here let's just say
we want you know we want everything
let's say we can just go okay we don't
want to be able we don't say anything we
just want to say time block and the
block is timed I don't want to know
anything else about it I don't care I
just want you to time that block and I
want you to display it for me in some
way later on that's going to let me know
what block was time so that I can go
find it again if I'm curious right
that's what I want okay so in order to
do that we see this time block we know
that we're going to instantiate one of
these so this part stays basically the
same right but then this part is going
to be a little more complicated we don't
have any way of using an ID here or
anything really right too
you know we don't have any way of
disambiguating this because the person
hasn't passed in an ID but that is again
the perfect place where we could go
ahead and stick say the line number in
so now we know that even if someone has
x the same block multiple times for some
reason we know that this timed walk will
never name conflict with itself right so
that's a perfect example of a way we
could use line to disambiguate so now we
can just do time block we don't to pass
an anything
okay that's step one step two is okay we
can't pass the bug cycle counter right
because debug cycle counter is this enum
sort of thing so we have to switch to
using something again that isn't going
to be you know isn't gonna be something
we have to predefined but in addition to
that we also need some way of
identifying where it is right because
since we're not gonna use any kind of
predefined values anymore we're not
gonna be able to know when we see the
results of this timing we're not going
to be able to know where the actual time
block was in the code so we see
something comes up when it's like hey it
took 4 milliseconds oh well maybe we
should go optimize that too bad I don't
know where it is it just says debug
counter 4 or something right well that's
no good so clearly what we'd like to do
here is pass some information that we
can use to both disambiguate which timer
this is in our debug code but also be
able to determine where it is when we
actually then go to
to display it to the user and so again
we already kind of know the stuff
because I just showed you what they were
it's pretty trivial for us to say
something like this where now we will be
passing all of this useful very useful
information about the location into the
into the actual time block so we can we
can accept it here right we can get the
file name we can get the line number and
we can get the function name so we can
pass that useful information in and so
not only will that allow us say with the
file name plus line number would totally
disambiguate it because we know we're
not gonna have multiple time you know no
one's gonna write this right but even if
they did if we wanted to we could if we
found ourselves in that situation we
could even go one further right so even
if they did want to do that for some
reason we don't care but if you did you
could you could even go one step further
so that is an easy way to make sure that
we can both disambiguate it because file
name plus line number will do that and
then we also have plenty of information
because file name plus line number and
function name which we can just print
out as a convenience so the user doesn't
have to look and see oh it's that's you
know what's in that file line or oh it's
draw bitmap now we know it's just just
draw a bitmap no problem right so that's
pretty useful so now you can see that we
have enough information to do our jobs
but we don't really have a way of
actually doing exactly the same work
that we did before because in order to
do that exact same work we would have to
have some way of mapping a file name and
a line number down to an ID which we
don't really have right we don't have
any way of kind of collapsing that thing
so we now need to start to think about
what we're gonna do to translate a file
a name line number into an ID now
there's a lot of pretty trivial ways we
could do this right anyone who's had
intro to computer science or as program
for a while at all or anything like that
knows that we could make something like
a map for example where we can just
search you know look up you know we
could make a binary tree or even we
could just do a brute-force search we
could do anything we wanted to try and
match up
file name line number pair with you know
other you know with other ones of its
type so we could just you know make a
little thing that's gonna store our
counters we look to see if the file line
number is there if it is there we
increment it if it's not we make a new
entry for it and off we go right so I
could just start typing that here you
know find you know find ID from file
name line number right and then I could
pass in the file name and the line
number it could go do that stuff and
then we'd have the ID right and then all
this stuff would work totally fine right
everyone's happy
no problem we all know how to write that
however not so useful potentially if we
get in a situation where that's gonna do
a bunch of actual work because now our
timer code right is going to be in a
situation where it's doing traversals of
a binary tree or searching through you
know some list of memory or something
like that to find matches to things and
that's exactly the sort of thing that we
really didn't want to have happen now it
may be right
it certainly could potentially be
plausible that that is still the best
thing to do and I will tell you why in a
second but I would like to at least
mention another method that may be the
one that we'd like to try first because
it has definite distinct advantages
certain certain very distinct advantages
okay so the thing that I would like to
do here instead is what I'd rather do is
just store the file name line number and
then not have to ever find it until
later when we go to print out this
information right because if you imagine
something like this
where I've got a timer record and I can
just say something like okay let's say
I've got a thread index or something
like this I've got a line number I've
got a care star filename and a function
name write something like this and then
I've got whatever the the you 64 is it
it's the RT t SC value right the time
stamp yeah so if I do something like
this when I use my timer record one sry
timer record if I do something like that
then every time through here and here I
could just do a time stamp and just
write out one of those structures right
so all it is the only pollution that it
does is writing that thing out and it
really you know you could even I could
imagine doing something absolutely
ridiculous here in trying to even do a
non-temporal store or something really
close like this so that you didn't
really pollute the cash at all
potentially right so that's one option
the reason I bring that option up is
because if you are planning on calling
this a reasonable number of times like
if I'm planning on not calling it say a
million times that might be a good idea
if you are planning on calling it a
million times
well now you're adding you know several
megabytes of right bandwidth to what
you're doing and that could affect your
performance as well right so it's kind
of hard to say one way or the other
which one of these things is going to be
you know the most efficacious now it's
worth noting that if you take a look at
this right you could imagine trimming
this down a little bit potentially I
don't know how much but you could
imagine doing something well to be
honest it's going to end up being you're
gonna need an 8 8 byte value for the
timestamp the pointers here I feel like
there's not a whole lot you would be
able to do with those unfortunately I
wish that C++ allowed you to do things
that weren't pointers for string tables
because man
would help a lot of stuff because really
these could just be pretty much 8-bit
values if the compiler were actually you
know flexible and good you know it could
this could have been something as simple
as this basically right at least and so
that's literally 128 bits it's 1 mm op
right to write that out and again you
could do that completely in a way that
maybe even bypass the cache if you want
to be super fancy so that would be a
pretty great thing unfortunately that's
not the situation we're pretty much only
gonna be able to have these guys like
that and so at that point this pretty
much ends up being a fairly balanced
truck it's just twice as large as what I
would have liked right so it's you it's
a eight bytes eight bytes eight bytes
eight bytes right so it's it's basically
you know 32 32 bytes right so every time
through on the time block you'd do a 32
byte write on you know on the on the
entry and the exit so it's 64 bytes 4
times block written but that's basically
it so the are m tts c plus the 64 bytes
written that you know might be the
easiest thing to do I don't know I'm
just pointing it out and then you would
collate those later on so I don't know I
don't know offhand if it's been a long
time since I've written a debug system
and I haven't done a lot of testing on
modern machines I don't know which one
of these they would prefer I don't know
if they would prefer to have these
things collapsed before or after the
fact what I do know is certainly when
the number of timed blocks gets low
enough you would almost certainly want
the log version but that's about all I
could really tell you okay
so I'm gonna do the log version because
I think the log version is a little more
interesting to me it also has some nice
properties that allow us to do some
stuff a little later that is a little
bit harder to do in a multi-threading
context if you don't do the logged
version but you know that's kind of
separate well that's that's not really -
that's that that may be overstating in a
little bit to say the least
alright so anyway this is something that
we would like to do and by the way it's
worth noting that really all of this is
just compensation for the fact again
that C++ is not a particularly good
language and so one thing that it cannot
do in a particularly easy way is
aggregate this data out what you would
rather do is you'd rather have something
that generated this effectively exactly
what I did here you would want it to
collapse down a set of indices and those
indices correspond to you know numbers
which are like where in the code do
timed blocks occur right and you would
want to be able to bake that number into
the thing although you know what I'm
having a thought I'm having a thought
right now a thought that I have not had
before and that thought is because we
are doing a single compilation unit well
we have two compilation units
technically but even so does that mean
we could just use counter to actually do
that list collapse because it kind of
feels like we could
are you thinking what I'm thinking
I mean it doesn't say specifically but
you know what let's just do a test
because you know this is something that
you can't come pretty sure counter since
it's a preprocessor directive if you're
normally compiling in the way that most
C++ products are compiled where you have
one file you know separate file per
class or stuff like that you can't do
this but if you compile everything as
one file counter actually will expand to
a unique number for every place that
times lock occurs so technically
speaking I think we might actually be
able to totally cheese out on this and
just get around the entire problem by
leaning on counter in a way that I'd
never thought to do before because I
never really thought about how you write
a debug system under the single unit
compilation schema so we've only been
doing for the past like six or seven
years and I haven't really done much
with new debug code in that time ah
let's I'm kind of interested to try that
let's try that shall we okay I'm I'm
really interested I am legitimately kind
of interested in what's about to happen
here I don't really know what's going to
happen but I am legitimately pretty
interested
okay so let's test this out so if I have
my time block thing here so instead
we're gonna have a thing that's like
okay it's gonna pass the counter is the
first thing or something like that right
so if I'm passing the counter is the
first thing and I guess at that point I
would want to do something where I turn
I guess we've got another time block
down here somewhere right so we don't
let's turn that off for a second
oops this guy's got to stay in there
okay this is this is very interesting
this is gonna be pretty interesting if
this works out to be if this turns out
to be good I'll be pretty I'll be pretty
interested interested right okay so if i
do that now i guess handmade render
groups the wrong place to do it cuz
that's actually in the one other
compilation unit we have but what I'm
gonna do here is I'm gonna put one in
make sphere diffuse map right and well I
guess I'll try do something that can
step into a little bit easier so we'll
put one in debug reset and then I'm
gonna go into the asset system and I'm
gonna put one in the asset startup okay
and these are in totally separate files
I want to see if we end up with the
value 0 and one for our counters that's
what I'd like to do so I'm gonna just
make a breakpoint at the constructor for
the time to block I'm gonna step in I'm
gonna see what we get past counter is
zero on the first one and that's for
handmade asset 539 allocate game assets
okay oops and counter is one for
handmade dot cpp line number 675 debug
reset well then that is pretty darn
interesting that is pretty darned
interesting
well then I suppose there's only a few
things we would need to know in order to
make this work pretty much exactly the
way we want it to we only have two
translation units right the two
translation units are defined at our
build batch file here they are right
we've got this one right here
handmade optimized yeah we've got this
one right here handmade that's EBP right
those are the only two translation units
we have so at the end of those
translation units we know exactly where
they stopped right hand made here at CBP
is here that means that if I were to put
counter right there that would be the
number of things that we actually had
the number of debug things that we had
well that means debug record something
like this right debug records brackets
counter and I could call this main debug
records or something like that that
would give me an array that I know has
all of the debug records in it that
that's big enough to hold all of the
debug records right and furthermore I
could make a second one inside the other
translation group which is the optimized
one right where is that optimized which
is here draw a rectangle quickly oh so I
guess yeah render group I guess wasn't
in there it's just all returned quickly
so I could make a second one in there
right up timaeus debug records now I
have two arrays that I know are big
enough to hold all of the debug records
that I might have with there with those
counters right
I mean presumably you can see where this
is going so now I really don't have to
do anything if I want to be able to
store to map this info in I pretty much
just overwrite it every time so if I go
into handmade debug and I want to make
this time block thing work
well the counter tells me exactly where
to look it up right so I've got
something like this right and in fact
you can kind of you can see I mean
there's only you know exactly what I'm
about to do right this is kind of it's
almost self-explanatory at this point is
that what we want to do so at this point
all we have to do is say all right when
we compile are optimized we just do
something like defined debug prefix
equals optimized minus the debug prefix
equals main and now I know which one I
am doing right optimized because debug
prefix depending on the compilation unit
will actually give me the you know will
tell me which one of these I'm going to
want and so in order to access the
proper set of debug records all I would
have to do is and you know you I could I
could make this a little bit I don't
know if the forward declaration of this
would work exactly well I'll show you
where I'm going with this in a second
and you can see we'll play around it and
see which one will work okay so if I
were to say struct debug record in fact
I probably can I get that now can
extract debug record in here just leave
it like that so if I wanted to I don't
think I I don't know if I can pre
declare this like this I'm not sure if
that'll work I doubt that it will
yeah that's fine because this will get
one soon enough so that's actually
totally fine let's just make sure that
works though we'll take it out of here
first and look at in a second so it
looks like we can pre declare that just
fine so actually we're totally good I
think I think everything should be just
about peachy so we just have to do
something like this
pound - fine declare forward we're debug
records with that or forward player
debug records like so and we just make
that a macro which passes in the name
and all it does is it creates one of
these by using the paste operator with
whatever that predefined thing was in
the build right so I'm just trying to
get two of these one for each
translation unit that I've got right so
I do declare debug records I pass in you
know declare debug records debug records
there we go and now presumably that will
just work right then in here if I want
the debug record that properly
corresponds to the one that I want I
know that all I have to do is take
whatever the debug records are here
right so something like access debug
record and it would be like an index
right something like that I'm assuming
maybe right then all I have to do is
just do this debug prefix prompt debug
records plus B index yeah
and that should give me the debug record
in fact I could do it like that as well
so I just do debug record counter and
I'd be done
yeah what is the problem here index is
an undeclared identifier oh well I
should probably make that pound define
alright uh debug prefix oh the paste
operator ah right
this is that nasty thing man
alright this is gonna make our lives a
little bit a little bit harder um I take
it back
I'm gonna make this easier on myself the
way that the preprocessor paste operator
works is really annoying and you can't
you it can't do the pasting with names
cuz they don't get expanded beforehand
unless they were a macro parameter and
all this other nonsense which is what's
going on there and there's a few tricks
you can do to make that happen but I
guess what I could do instead is just
debug record array right dude debug
record array equals like debug records
optimized and here we could just do
debug record array those debug records
main I could just do that and that way
we don't have to deal with all its
nonsense right then there's no there's
no funny business there I can just do
something like ok debug record debug
record array and it'll you know the
macro will sort of substitute that and
then we just say ok we pre declare it
and then accessing it is just as simple
as saying I want to go ahead and and
grab the counter at one like so and then
the at the end of the pan made and those
guys don't have to do anything else I
could just literally do you know do that
you know I mean and furthermore I guess
this one because they're in both I could
do something where I do debug record
array where were those things that build
back debug records
so I can just pre declare them both here
because that's totally fine there's no I
don't think there's any harm in doing
that well no that's not true
there is a little harm in doing that
because if I do that then it'll have a
multiplet affined symbol in the two
compilation yes so we'll stick with what
I had before
all right so now I think we've managed
to screw it that entire problem and we
now actually are just getting the diva
record arrayed collapsing for free like
it was just done and so now all I have
to do is just write do that one right
and it's just writing to a known
location so it's not gonna proliferate
the amount of data or anything like that
and it's just gonna be totally fine
right I think I think it's literally
just that's it so if we take a look at
this we've got the line number and
function name stuff yeah I think we just
say okay there's the record we do file
name equals file name we do record line
them because line number we do record
function name cuz function name we do
record clocks you know plus equals the
our DTSC and we'll have to kind of watch
it to do a little work there to make
sure that's macro Bowl right actually I
guess it kind of works the other way
subtract the our DTSC and then when we
come down here again the only thing that
we'd have to store here I think is we
just have to store the counter value
right so I think that would work yeah
this is counter an it
count 3 equals countering it and sit
them down here all we would have to do
is get that debug record back and I
guess technically we could just store
the pointer to the debug record actually
I think about it we don't actually need
the counter in it stuff we just go like
that
and then down here we just say okay that
record the clocks plus equal started
keys I think that just works I'm kind of
surprised I never thought to do that
before because counter was never
available the first time I made well for
a second third and fourth times I made
debug systems so never thought of that
but I think that just works I don't
really know why it wouldn't so let's
just see if it did what would we need to
do to see if it did well we've got
printouts now to some degree so let's go
ahead and just just replace everything
with this instead instead of what we
were doing let's just pull on say ok
inside handmade platform you know what
just vaporize all this stuff it's gone
right and we can we can get the hip
count and put the hit count back in here
if we want to - right just keep that
sorted like so
all we have to do for that is just you
know Inc the hit count every time now
this is not thread safe or anything like
that so there's some things we might
want to think about there as well but
you know one step at a time
well alright so now that we've got that
if I just blow this stuff away right if
we just say this stuff is gone
so goodbye write debug cycle counter is
gone now when I come in here we'd get
rid of these counters and we'll get rid
of all this stuff right I guess here's a
10 time block counter thing so that's
one that we may want to support as well
how come begin time block didn't give me
an error is it still defined begin time
block okay these are all still defined
so I'm gonna also go ahead and just give
these out for a minute like so so that
all of those things will get errors so
I'm going to change this to ty blach
draw a rectangle quickly I'm gonna
change this to time block process pixel
get clamped rect area fill rect over to
is that is that actually known it here
it is so what I'm going to do here is
I'm going to do a timed block and I'm
going to pass that in with the count
because we can actually get that for
free as well
right we'll just pass it in here and all
we have to do for that is just say okay
the time to block stuff is going to take
a number potentially so when we do time
blocking I guess oh and they don't even
take a name right okay
I think this will work don't quote me on
that a time block I guess this doesn't
have to do that either we can do time
block with aver arms I believe and then
we can just do a paste on like so so
that will get those extra parameters in
here and so then we can just have a
default value which is that the hit
count actually plus equals some kind of
a hit count that you pass in by default
it will assume that you just want to
count it once but if you want to count
that block many times you can do that as
well right so that's another way we can
tackle that alright so time block
including handmade H that means that it
was handmade H not include handmade H it
should have included handmade debug time
to block it's right there is it just
because it doesn't have this Wow okay
well that's fine doesn't matter no
worries
okay so process pixel wants to be like
this you got I'm just trying to maintain
the feature set that we had because it
seems fine right doesn't it's not
onerous for us to do that time block
underscore oh yeah
so this not sure why it didn't like that
I guess because it won't expand this if
it's part of the paste hmm hmm I say I
would like to expand line right I would
like line to be expanded so that I can
just have one per line I guess
this is that same unfortunate problem so
I may have to do something like this
where I call another layer down with
like the number or something like that I
don't know how many times you have to do
that this is always really annoying to
me I hate this the C++ preprocessor is
like the worst thing ever I mean we can
all admit that but you know since that
doesn't have the language features that
you'd want for a lot of these things you
have no choice but to use it most the
time but so I probably will have to do
something like this where it gets
translated through the macro multiple
times I feel like you need to do this
twice even two layers there's this
really weird stuff with the with the
macro produce processor I think once
doesn't even do it so if you do this
it's still not enough it has to actually
go through one layer of translation
right so we'll see but you'll see what I
mean in a second I think that's what
will happen
yeah number dot that dot yeah you can
see that that doesn't actually fix it
right it's still doing that i'ma try it
one more time and then I gotta I may
have to look this up this is something I
never remember like ever I never
remember how to do it but there is there
are tricks I've done them before how is
it done oh that's not quite right yeah
so I don't know you can kind of see
there some pretty ridiculous shenanigans
on a second let's see what's going on
here time block yet so I hope you see
what happened there this is kind of just
a vagaries of C++ preprocessor nonsense
thing there's no rhyme or reason to it
just how it happened be written so what
happened was I wanted to use the line
number right to expand on here but
unfortunately if it sees the pasted
operator which is something that sticks
two things together it actually just
graphs on whatever the text was and so I
have to pass it through itself multiple
times to make sure that the number gets
expanded as a number which it will in
this line so that it never no toot no
entrance of the number of the use of the
line macro plus the actual paste have to
be separated by one hole round through
the stupid preprocessor don't ask me why
I even know that this is just one of
those things that you know if you
program C++ long enough you have to deal
with but hey we finally got it so it's
fine again nothing particularly special
or great about that that's just the way
it goes all right
so you got a few more things left to
deal with we're not we're not totally
done yet right we're not totally we're
not totally at the at the end of
everything that we might need to do but
we're close
so overlay cycle counters that would be
what prints out the cycle counters for
us so we can go down here to the end
right and we have debug record array we
just put it down below here so we know
that it can access that right and now we
can know that we could use our debug
record array we could use the array
count of the debug record array and that
would actually print the thing out now
of course we don't actually want to only
do that one debug record right because
we actually have multiple people record
rates but we'll deal with that a little
bit further down the line it's a guess
it's actually debug record to me and I
think something like that right yeah so
what we want to do here and there's some
other like I said there's gonna be some
things we're gonna but we're kind of
running out of time so I wanted to kind
of finish this up for the most part and
then we can look at it a little bit more
all right so let's just finish up what
we've got we'll go ahead and put a time
clock in there for game update and
render as well we'll just go ahead and
put that like so inside our end time
blocks we no longer need them at all
right overlay cycle counters we're gonna
have to forward declare because we're
calling that after sort of the
definition of these things so that's
fine but we'll have to kind of do a
little forward declaration up here there
we go and in here this is going to be
debug record and this is going to be
that debug records name
okay so let's continue strict debug
record debug records optimized not
defined is that really true I think it
is it's right there so we just gonna put
it in I'm just going to debug records
oops
it's good actually spell it the way I
wanted it to and then down here we've
got the debug cycle counter print out in
win32 we're gonna nuke that for now
because I think we don't probably ever
we probably will mute that for good
actually but we'll leave it kind of left
in for the for the immediate moment all
right and now let's go ahead and run
things and see where we're at right Hey
look look what we just got those are
actually coming from our actual thing I
believe right although now actually
they're still probably using the wrong
ones because I don't think we changed it
quite yet right they're using this name
table but we don't need the name table
anymore
right so it's not quite hey look yet we
can just get rid of that and in fact I
guess we can get rid of all this stuff
right so what we want to do is go
through each counter and then instead of
looking it up in the name table which we
don't actually need to do at all anymore
we can just take a look at the counter
and look at it's filename cannot convert
r1 from Kara to Kara Star oh my bad
awesome we probably want
we're probably gonna want a slightly
smaller font for debugging just putting
that out there but man that that turns
out to be pretty darn easy actually so
now we need to sort of augment our
ability to print things out but now we
actually have it such that we can put
debug times throughout our entire code
and it's completely free we don't have
to do any work really the amount of
effect on the code is almost zero right
I mean all it's doing is just this work
right here that's it that's gonna be
pretty great I mean you can afford a lot
of those right so yeah that's as good a
place as any to stop I suppose because
that is the not the entirety of what we
want to at time blocks we might want to
do some call attribution with our time
blocks for example but man yeah okay I
don't know why I never thought of that
before but that just totally worked all
right well you learn something new every
day I'm gonna go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
and yeah like I said that was what we
wanted and we kind of got it so there's
some more stuff we'd like to do but I
mean pretty much that's what we wanted
and so tomorrow what we'll be able to do
is we'll be able to kind of go in here
and work on our ability to print things
out so we can start to actually see the
numbers right because remember we were
kind of using a we were using some
library code to print that and so you
know we can go write our own our own
text print out routines that they
probably won't be great because we don't
care they're just for debug but you know
we should at least do them all right
well
if you have questions now would be a
good time to ask them go ahead and
prefix them with Q :
so I'll see you
let's see Elsa noised says there's an
alternative way to start and the counter
instead of using constructor destructor
pair you don't have to store the data in
the struct maybe not as convenient but
it's worth mentioning I use it quite
often when I have to begin X write code
end X it's basically a hacked tweaked
version of C sharps using statement I
think you'll find it interesting check
out the small snippet if you please
what do you think well let's find out
let's see
destructor x block pound define using
for oh interesting well I'm looking at
this and I suppose I should probably
sort of show the the way that it's being
done here so the way he's suggesting to
do it is you can do a thing that's like
pound if I'm you know using using object
data and then he does a for loop done
equals AAB begin using data oops don't
wanna go beyond my own head not done
done equals AUB's
and using data so it makes like a for
loop right and the for loops exit
condition is just going to be this not
done here and then it does the end at
the as the the update step right so the
thing I don't like about that is that
that it that introduces at least as many
new variables into the function as this
does though so I'm not sure there's
really any benefit to it
in fact I might say there's definitely
no benefit to it it's strictly adding
more code to your code than this does
right yeah so I don't know I I don't
think I'm a fan I haven't thought about
it long enough so maybe there's other
reasons why I might like that but that
doesn't seem like a good win to me that
might just be me
James Whitman I feel like I missed
something why is the arrayname need to
be different between builds so the
reasons the arrayname needs to be
different between builds is because I
want to print out both arrays and so in
here I'm going to need in like the next
episode right when we do our actual
printout of this data I'm going to need
to be able to access both of them now
they can't both be named the same thing
because if they were I wouldn't be able
to exter in the other one and access it
from here right so the reason I just
made two different aims I seem like the
easiest way to make sure that that
worked you know so that's that's all
that's the only that's the only reason
twitch makes me itch s how do you move
your typing cursor around so fast is
that an IDE so there's a macro well I
have my Emacs set up to be like if you
hold down the control key it moves by
words and if you so control key plus the
left and right arrows moves by words
control key plus the up and down arrows
moves to empty space
I just find those are easy ways to get
around and then similarly I have like
alt-j bound to like jump so I can jump
through a function or something like
that so I just I just have some shortcut
keys that help me they're not
particularly fancy they're pretty
they're pretty basic really
could you expand on how you would have
done the care star file named star
function name with un s-- instead yes so
what I was trying to say there when I
was kind of bagging on how bad C++ is
all the time and of course to be fair
you know it's possible that they've
added some features in the eight billion
features that they add every year or
every couple years he is I don't
actually want a pointer to a file name
what I want the compiler to do is take
all of the files that there are in the
project enumerate them from zero to
whatever the maximum number is and then
just have a table called file names that
I can look up with a bracket that way if
I want to store the file name I can just
store a new 16 called file name index
which I know that the compiler you know
vacuum that I can produce like this like
file name index and it just gives me an
index of the file name into that table
that would have been the way any sane
person would have done this right but
you know same people are in short supply
and SZ underscore this is awesome you
have a few minutes left could you output
the results or show them in the debugger
yeah I mean we certainly can really the
the thing is just we you know we need to
use a library to do it because the
reason I wasn't doing so I want to we
want to go write ourselves like I said
we don't you know we try not to use
libraries on handmade hero so that I
show how to write everything but you can
you could just you could just use like
one of these one of the functions from
the C standard library if you needed to
I don't know if we can get that in here
exactly I don't know what the
consequences would be here of including
say standard IO dot H if that would work
it looks like it sort of does so if we
wanted to we could go ahead and actually
like let this this happen we could say
let's do this right and then we can have
we could have that that print out so
that the text buffer that we prepare
right so let's see cycle count is is
what it's clocks so I'll change that
second
so that's that's really it
I think and there you go so that's the
that's the the printout and we're not
resetting these yet so they're just
gonna kind of go up ad infinitum so you
know if we wanted to reset them again
we'd need to to do the stuff that was
what's happening what's happening in
here so that is yeah that is handled
debug cycle counters so we just need to
kind of reset the stuff and so we could
we could do that as well here I don't
know that's where we really want to do
that long term but that's an example and
you know we could we could go ahead and
make this instead of the counter in it
we could we could use the function name
for that and so yeah does that help
yeah so my debugger reset that doesn't
make much sense
why is debug reset taking all of the
time
oh we are actually timing debug reset
turns out so yep that's what that is
Gaming update and render well game
update and render so we do have one
problem with that which is that game
update and render which is the other
thing that we're timing is actually not
right it's it's not it's not blocking
that so in order to actually make that
block we would we would need to do
something like this
right we'd actually need to open a block
for that so that we know that it doesn't
we know that that gets closed that block
has to get closed before we would
actually overlay the cycle counters
right which is again kind of annoying
because what we would and this is
something we need to address so I'll
just do it temporarily but it's not what
we would actually want to do right yeah
we we want to do this we want to do this
a little bit more tomorrow there's a
bunch of things that are kind of packed
in there that we want to handle but you
know I could I guess I could do a couple
more things just to just to show that
it's working right so I could put time
block in here for example and that would
be another one for for that would be in
there for debug updating render so right
so there's our actual times one and this
one's just not right because the block
is never closed that make sense so yeah
so we've got we've got some stuff that
we have to do and basically what it
boils down to is because we are the
renderer we need a way of counting the
amount of time spent in the renderer but
the renderer is the thing rendering the
debug information so what we want to do
like I said you know we're kind of
jumping the gun here by but you know
since you want to see it we saw it so
that's good it's fine what we want to do
is we want to postpone the information
for one frame so that on any given frame
we're printing out the like data from
say the last frame the pre
his frame so that we we can count the
renderer properly but still have the
render or render the debug information
right because it's sort of like a
chicken and egg thing there so we we
can't really you know we gotta be a
little bit more specific about that but
that's not hard
well it'll be easy enough for us to do
but we have to actually do it Nicko 3695
you recommend taking game programming as
a major or programming in general i
don't know i did not go to college so i
can't really help you out there Ellison
says what other useful pre proc bell use
we could use other than file function in
line I don't know that there are very
many other ones that are useful for this
purpose I mean a counter obviously was
the other one but that we ever used it I
don't really know that there's anything
else that I can think of for debugging
the other stuff is usually for other
reasons but you know I could be
forgetting one or there could have been
one added recently that I don't know
about like I said counter was actually
added long after I'd written like the
previous iteration of my debug stuff I
haven't really touched it since then and
so I never really thought about the new
things that it could add so yeah so
there might be some even newer ones that
I don't know about and maybe they'd be
very useful I don't know I should
probably go you know to take a spin
through them and just see I'm not really
sure if I fully understand you need
builds so you need bill is when we
compile everything into a single file I
don't think that's the case because we
do have multiple source files in HMH
so five source files is not really the
important part it's how the compiler
sees those source files when you pass it
and so in Hammer here we really have
three separate compilation units and
compilation unit is the right term to
think about here because that's what the
compiler actually sees doesn't matter
how many files they're all right because
like you can imagine you have handmade
HMI that's EBP if handmade thought to BP
includes hammer a that H and you only
pass him E that's easy to the compiler
well there's only one cop
relation unit there because the compiler
doesn't think about handmade H as being
a separate compile pass it's just a
separate file that gets stuffed into a
me that's AP before the compiler
actually goes to work right and so what
we do on and main here is we just pound
include all our CPP files so we actually
only have three translation units one
that's the win32 binding layer and
that's there so it can reload our code
and we can do our loop live code editing
stuff so that's one thing to is our
optimized code and the only reason we
have that is because the compiler is too
dumb to let us say hey optimize this
function it has to be in a separate
compilation unit for some reason I have
no idea why and then number three is the
rest of the code and so we only have
three of them and that's why I say that
we can kind of do stuff like this
counter thing plain flavored where did
the whole weird eye interface see class
style of programming I see everywhere
come from uh yeah I don't know I mean
calm I remember introduced that whole I
interface naming convention I think but
I don't know if they made that up or if
that was something they got from
somewhere else right so I yeah I don't
really know who started all that kind of
stuff
why do you have both u3q and you and
three to type desks what's the
difference there is no difference it was
just that I decided to switch recently
like even though I'm pretty old I still
change up my programming style fairly
frequently actually to just make small
modifications or whatever to it and you
32 and un 32 I started off the product
using you and 32 and I decided to go to
you 32 so really eventually we'll
probably just delete you in 32
altogether and everything will just be
you 32 so that's more of a migration
there third is there are no different or
exactly the same
if exceptions are bad then what is a
good way to handle errors just return
error codes a global error value like an
error no or get last error what do you
think of the idea of having a central
area Lang function that we call and pass
it the error ID and it acts accordingly
so in general I would say the right way
to handle errors is to not have them so
that's thing 1 right so a lot of times
people like will have a more error
handling than they should have because
they allow errors they allow things to
be errors that shouldn't have been
errors so that's step one step two is
when you actually have legitimate errors
that can actually happen in practice you
want to figure out where those come from
and you want to make those explicitly
handled by the code path so like for
example one that we will probably do on
hand made here at some point will be if
the asset file suddenly starts to not be
readable right and if that happens what
we want to do is actually detect that
case and set it up so that we then print
out you know a message on the screen
that's like hey man you need to figure
out why the asset file just disappeared
because you can't run the game without
the asset file but on the whole there
really shouldn't be a lot of error
conditions right there are error
conditions there's so few ways that you
can really be in a legitimate error
condition usually it should just be part
of the program like the program itself
should be written to consider the error
condition as actually just a condition
that it handles because if you didn't do
that then you don't really handle that
error at some level right like either an
error is actually a technical error that
shouldn't ever happen in practice or it
isn't and if it is then you really only
need assertions or things like that to
handle it but if it is a real error then
you need to handle it and you need to
write the coach that it does the thing
that user would want done in that
scenario which makes it not an error at
all it makes it actually the way the
program works and so the answer to how
to handle it is no different than how
you would handle anything else hope that
make some sense why use record file name
and set a record function name I think
we did end up using function name I
think that probably is an old question
let's see
I am new I'm kind of Li the stream is
there a reason you hate C++ so much yes
there is a reason I'd say most plus so
much and that is because I have to use
it
so I like C I think C's a pretty good
language I would really have liked the
updates to see over the years to have
been done by people who knew what they
were doing because C was you know is
1970s I think C was actually made in
like the late sixties even so it's like
really old and it needed a bunch of
updates to be able to do the things that
we would want it to do for modern
programming and instead what we got was
C++ which has been routinely updated in
ways that are absolutely ridiculous and
pretty much useless and so the reason I
hate C++ instead of just ignoring C++ is
this the thing I have to work with and
it's really darn bad and so I'm kind of
mad at the people who constantly do
really stupid stuff and leave me with a
garbage language that I have to use
right whereas I'm not mad at the people
who made Python because I don't know
maybe pythons a bad language maybe it's
not but I don't have to use it so I'm
not gonna hate on Python because I don't
use Python right you can't really build
up hate for something that you don't
really interact with you know because
you're not cost like sitting there going
if only the people who made this
language had a clue I'm never saying
that because I never have to use it
well this compiled with only the visuals
to decompile at work with GCC it works
at GCC GCC is actually the place that
introduced counter the reason I was a
little hesitant about counter and wasn't
sure about it so I couldn't remember if
M SBC got out of it
I thought they have I couldn't quite
remember GCC has like oh we said counter
I mean it's not like they always had
counter but I'm pretty sure that jesus
with the people who introduced counter
originally so I knew that they would
have it so LLVM GCC i that your code
will work fine there but I just wasn't
sure MC it turns out MCC added it if you
go back far enough like m/s BC 2005 or
something maybe might not have counter I
don't know but you know obviously the
later versions have it so it's totally
fine
just nice general program question do
you see the use of public variables
being accessed outside the class bad
practice versus using a getter accessor
function I would say that I don't even
like the premise of the question in the
first place
getter accessor functions are almost
completely useless and should never be
written under any circumstances in my
opinion I I don't like the concept just
fundamentally I don't ever think that
private private is like just shouldn't
even be used so I don't even use classes
I just do struct so that everything is
always public and that in my opinion is
the correct method so there shouldn't be
any get a getter shouldn't be any
accessors of any kind the times that you
add those is when something specific has
to happen when that thing is accessed
and what people typically do and I think
this is a very very bad programming
practice is they pre-game that so they
go okay I'm gonna make a class called
foo it's got an int in it which is like
the data but I don't want anyone to
access the data directly right I want
them to do this so they wrote that
instead of typing this and everyone who
uses it who has one of these now has to
do right every time
it's absurd it's absolutely completely
absurd
I mean look at all that typing and now I
want to increment this value well
instead of being able to just do this
right now I got to do this it's insanity
all you're doing is spending your whole
day typing for absolutely no reason you
get nothing for this zero and the reason
I say that is because the only thing you
have to actually do if on the odd rare
circumstance where you then need to add
some kind of fancy business to accessing
this stuff is you just go like that now
everywhere that access that code is
going to be a compile error and you can
go ahead and change it to the access ER
at that point so never ever ever ever
put in an access er until it actually
does something not to mention the fact
that everyone who wrote that code was
not expecting it to do something so they
didn't test it that way
you don't know if it's a performance
bottleneck right someone might be
thinking they're just you know
incrementing a variable and that's free
but it turns out now you added like a
hash table lookup in there and all of a
sudden the performance goes yeah it goes
to crap right so never ever ever ever
ever ever under any circumstances do
this thing this is like awful code just
absolutely horrific this is like you're
fired right like I fire you immediately
if I see anything like this never ever
if there is an access err it had better
do something in there day 1 . and that
is all I have to say about that
insofar as how would you handle parsing
errors or exceptions being a recursive
descent parser that's a that's a little
bit of a big question you'll have to
hold that one until when I do handmade
parser what early Mun the internet says
counter started on V C++ oh really huh
um is that true I had no idea cuz I just
thought it was on GCC that's where I
first heard of it and I didn't think
that you could do it on MSP C but if it
started on MSP C then that's that's also
cool I mean we're looking at the
predefined macros specs for GCC so
obviously it's on GCC and if MSB C was
the first one to have it then yeah I
mean I think we're totally golden on
that
I think that's it for questions
looks like that's it alright well spin
down people's we will spin it down well
that was a pretty entertaining stream
today and that is probably going to be
something that I go put into the Mali
rocket codebase now that I know that
that's that simple I just never thought
of counter before for some reason and
that's that's why rewriting code is good
sometimes too I mean you know like I
write something and I reuse it and then
I forget you know the limitations under
which I wrote it and then I come back
and look at it again and it's like oh
well why am i doing it that way there's
a way smarter way to do it that I just
didn't know about or that wasn't
available or I hadn't thought it through
at the time who knows why and there you
go imagine that anyway thank you very
much for joining me for another episode
of hand made here oh it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with this
code at home you can always preorder
handmade hero of the game on handmade
hero org and you get the source code as
we're working on it so it's kind of
available from day one just as we go
every night I upload the source codes
you can download it and play with it
yourself and experiment and kind of like
reinforce anything that you may have
learned watching the stream so i highly
recommend that's a good way to go if
you're trying to learn from the series i
also highly recommend checking out some
of the other stuff we've got here
there's a forum site you can go to ask
questions you can go get community ports
to Mac and Linux the people I'm working
on you can get an antidote guide people
have been working on you can also go to
our patreon page if you want to support
the video series and I've got some
exciting things to talk about coming up
with the patreon a little bit later as
well we have a tweet bot which tweets
the schedule at you and that is kind of
handy if you're trying to catch the
stream live so yeah check that out if
you want to come come back tomorrow 5:00
p.m. Pacific Daylight Time is the next
time they'll be streaming but if you
don't if you ever don't know and you
just like I want to see the xm8 hero
that tweet bot will always tell you and
so you can kind of figure out if it's
gonna be a time that works for you
anyway tomorrow we'll go start cleaning
up our print out ability there because
now we've got some debug counters we'd
like to be able to see them and so now
would be a time for us
start maybe doing a little work on the
actual debug overlay stuff because again
that's a very crucial part of our debug
system and now that we've got something
we actually want to see it would be a
great time for us to go start working on
that and making a nice little thing we
can use that actually is you know kind
of a good sort of debug overlay that we
can actually manipulate and do
interesting things with so that's what
we'll start doing tomorrow until then I
hope everyone has fun programming and I
will see you guys on the Internet take
it every Z everyone