hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show that could show the show
that goes that's good the show where we
code it would be cool to show coded
itself
I guess that's more of an AI show than
anything else though really but the show
were we code a complete game live on
stream I we are coming back from last
weekend when we did depth feeling in our
renderer which allowed us to do some
pretty cool stuff we basically have
order independent transparency now by
doing a few def peels which is really
cool however we only just barely
finished that up last time and so it's
time now to kind of take a little bit of
a closer look at some of it and to just
go okay let's see can we improve some of
these things going to clean up some of
these things is there anything else we
want to sort of prep for in the renderer
before we kind of tie it off because at
this point I'm getting pretty happy with
it I like sort of worth that so I feel
like it's getting into a state where I'm
okay and let's go ahead with the game
proper
and because the everything seems to be
kind of like holding together pretty
nicely everything could always use
improvement certainly so there's tons
and tons of things we would rather do
better than we are doing them obviously
but for the time being everything you
know that's that's the way it is in
programming all the time right no game
ever shipped in like the history of
games without the programmers being like
well you know if we'd had another month
here's the things we would do right so
programming is kind of one of those
unsatisfying things in that way which is
that you're never really done you just
eventually decide that that's good
enough and you can never really get to
perfect because there's always more you
could be doing usually at least in my
experience anyway so let's take a look
at where we're at today is day 383 so if
you want to follow along with them the
programming that I'm going to do today
you want to load 382 source code
into your handy editor and let's go
ahead and and just remind ourselves
where we are and they're specifically
the first thing I want to take a look at
is some artifacts and what we might be
able to do to mitigate them or why they
occur and so I just want to kind of get
us back to where we are so we played
around a little bit with some things
like depth fogging of stuff but this is
the game running through the depth
feeling renderer and it's in pretty good
shape I like I'm pretty happy with it
and everything seems pretty nice the
problem with it at the moment that I see
anyway is just that when you look at
this from the perspective of someone
who's maybe you know a little bit of a
stickler for artifacts what you can see
is that in certain circumstances and
it's not necessarily always trivial to
get them to occur but you know you can
there you go you can see that we get
some odd artifacting here where we have
like for example looks like where maybe
there were some shadows that overlap you
can see it there right you can see
something kind of happening there where
we get these black splotches and I don't
really want to just dismiss these black
splotches out of hand
or you know assume that there's some
artifacts of me because I don't really
know exactly what they are there's a
number of things they could be but they
definitely have some bizarre behavior to
them that weren't some further attention
and I feel like we don't really have a
solid understanding at the moment of why
they're occurring so a couple of things
that strike me as odd about them just to
kind of give a little bit of a
background as to what you know why I'm
I'm a little skeptical here so if you
take a look at what's going on it looks
you know what where I would expect to
see artifacts I think we're doing for
depth feels maybe we're doing three I
don't remember how many but I think
we're doing for depth deals right now
there's a lot of depth deals and I don't
know if that's actually necessary you
could see a lot of feel those black
splotches there where you
just at the border there but anyway I
like look at all those particles are
generating those black splotches at this
at this layer so the the thing that's
really weird about that is it feels to
me like that maybe is some kind of an
overflow color bug or something like
this and not a depth peeling bug or
something or it's like a - these are
being equal or something bug I don't
know but basically I feel like there is
evidence that this is just a straight-up
bug and not a limitation of our
technique and the reason for that is
obviously the solid black color it's not
changing at all it's just a perfect
black so it's almost like it is drawing
something with an overflowed color value
or an under flowed color value instead
of the Alpha being properly zero or
something it's showing up as black right
and so I feel like maybe our technique
is actually better than this and the
shader is just wrong and it's not
clamping something that it actually
needs to clamp or something right the
other thing that could be happening
there and again I'd like I said I don't
know is we don't have a solid argument
right now for what happens when two
things occupy the same Z position in our
depth field one of them will get thrown
away arbitrarily in that case I think
I'm not 100% certain exactly what will
happen in that case
but when two things are exactly the same
Z I don't really know that we handle
that exactly properly now again though
that I can't say I can think at the
moment anyway of why that would be like
like I just don't know why that would be
sure black as the result right I would
think that I would get like flickering
or something as a result of that as the
draw order changed or something but it
but pure black again I can't get there
in my head like I can't rationalize why
we would be seeing pure black with this
technique which makes you think
something else is up that I don't
understand yet right that I haven't
investigated correctly and also most of
the time I feel like it's just good
policy to investigate artifacts with an
open mind and don't assume that you know
what the artifact is because unless it's
glaringly obvious you might miss
something in the code that's wrong when
you go to like say oh this is why this
artifact is happening right okay so you
know just trying to figure out what the
situation is here I want to take a
gander kind of at how we're doing things
like our peel compositing for example I
want to make sure that we can't overflow
a color value for example and so one
thing I could do right is I could come
through here and I could try to you know
I could try to analyze it very carefully
and so on and so forth but it looks like
it's at the moment anyway oh that's good
I like how we have a times here not a x
equals that's going to say that that's
not right at all that's supposed to be
at x equals inverse a but okay so when
we're adding things together here right
just looking at this it seems like
there's really not a lot of ways that
this can go wrong you know what I'm
saying where we've got four color values
here and so if we assume that the
previous stage worked which again we
have to verify that it actually did
because we don't know if it did or not
but assuming that the previous stage
worked we look at these color values and
we say okay we're going to add these
color values here
and we're going to add them at the
inverse of whatever their alpha is right
so if we take a look at how we're
blending stuff in here right it looks
like that would be pretty safe from
overflows what is because we're always
using one minus the Alpha and the Alpha
so we can't sum to greater than one
right however that assumes that the
alpha value was properly pre multiplied
in right it assumes that pele zero one
in two all have their alpha values pre
multiplied into their color values so if
we weren't pre multiplying here that
would definitely give us the possibility
of overflowing our color values now we
can't start fiddling with this like I
could multiply this by its alpha values
on this side to ensure that that wasn't
the case and then we would get perhaps
incorrect color mixing if they were but
we wouldn't necessarily see black
however what I'm going to do instead is
just see whether this is an overflow by
clamping the color values right just so
I can get some semblance of a of knowing
whether or not I overflowed so I can
eliminate that you know creating an out
of bounds value as the reason that we
were seeing black in a situation where
maybe we shouldn't have so I'm going to
go ahead and say GLSL 3.0 quick
reference card as we normally use on the
stream for looking up the function names
so there's a function that will clamp
things for us and this is it right you
can kind of see here there's a zoom in
so you can get a better view of that
there we go
so you can see here we've got a variety
of functions that we can use to clamp
things and you can see that they
basically take the form here's the thing
I'm going to clamp here's the minimum
value here's the maximum value and you
can kind of do that in a number of
different with a number of different
data types but it's basically the same
thing so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to say I want to clamp oops it's
lower case I want to clamp that result
color so in a pass the result color Ian
I just want to clamp it between zero and
one and that's all I want to do
and so again all I'm trying to do here
is verify that I didn't get any kind of
weird problem where I am you know where
I'm overshooting the color values and
that was really kind of interesting
there wasn't it that background changed
which again it's kind of a red flag for
me there so looking at it though that
did not in any way improve our situation
you can kind of see here that we got we
saw some very strange values going on so
you can see you can kind of see there we
got the the fringing happening however
we also get white fringing which is
really interesting to showing through
that great value that's very strange
so clamping the color value between zero
and one I'm not sure I understand why
that would have changed our background
color at all right because the
background color wasn't out of range in
that way I'm wondering if I did
something odd here that I shouldn't have
done I don't think there's you know as
far as I know clamped with a vector just
clamps the individual components so I
don't think there's any difference
between writing what I just wrote and
writing this but I'll check and the min
and Max values should be 0 to 1 that
should be our color range that we're
outputting as far as I know we should
not be outputting anything else we
should always be staying in that range
entirely so I don't really know what's
going on there that's awfully suspicious
yeah that's
I really don't know why that's happening
hmm
so I literally have no idea what that's
happening I want to change the Alpha
value to just be one here because I'm
interested to know if there's any sort
of play with if the Alpha has anything
to do with it and it doesn't really look
like it
so the clamping on the background color
appears to be from from the RG and B
getting clamped so when there's only a
peel three that's the thing that's
getting clamped somehow how I do not
know so let's take a look if that's
correct so if I look at peel three which
would just be the background anywhere
that you can see just the background so
this is the background here and I don't
have any idea like how that's looking
black like that so let's see what
happens if I don't clamp and instead of
clamping I just past the are the G and
the B values here like so so there's my
RG and B values from pl3 so even just
straight assigning those I don't get
what I would expect so that's really
strange so what happens if I look at
peel two instead in this case I must be
really out to lunch here because I have
no idea why this is happening so all of
these appear to be black
so I think that is very interesting and
possibly has to do with our problem I
have no idea how that clamp is resulting
in that but it does suggest to me that
the peel the peels are not having their
destination alpha and their color set
properly
I guess because peel 3 at the very least
anywhere where there isn't anything
should be precisely the background color
so let's see if we can figure out what's
going on here I'm going to say that
result color well here's another thing I
can do so we've got this inverse alpha
offset thing here let's stop doing that
as well so let's see what peel 3 ends up
being because peel 2 we would expect to
be black because peel 2 is supposed to
be premultiplied alpha right so that
makes sense but peel 3 is supposed to be
gray okay so it looks like that alpha
inverse computation is just wrong so
we've got our peel 3 here it's
multiplying by the inverse of its alpha
and somehow getting a totally wrong
result there black I guess so oh you
know what so that actually does make
sense now that I look at how I wrote
this so the problem there right is if
the peel 3 alpha is actually equal to 0
then we will multiply by 0 right but I
guess what we really wanted to multiply
by in this case was 1
and you know what I think we may want to
remove this anyway because I feel like
the other thing I wanted to do today was
make it so that peel 3 didn't ever have
alpha in it at all all right so let's
let's see here let me get rid of this
just for a moment and so now we are able
to see that gray I suspect right if I
say result color you can skill 3 we
should see that gray background yeah all
right so that's all fine so now we're
back to the same question we had before
though which is where is that weird sort
of fringing coming from but at least we
kind of have that have that other part
there under control all right so now let
me see if I can put my clamp back in and
get what I expected to get when I
originally put it
so now we can see that since I'm
clamping that at least in theory those
those black splotches are not coming
from a color overflow here right they
may still be being caused by something
overflowing or something happening
somewhere else but this particular part
of the compositing is not the problem
right let me put it to do here so now
we're kind of left with a question of
how do we get solid black at all right
so what I am trying to determine is if
peel 3 is going to be written directly
right and we kind of know I mean I guess
it's a little bit hard to say because we
don't really know well okay here's what
we can do so let's suppose we colored
these peels based on where they are so
we'll set each individual peel to a
specific color so we can see which peels
are which right so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to say that peel 0 is going
to be our blue peel and then we get you
know to our red peel is P you know it's
going to be blue green red is the third
one back and then you know maybe I'll do
yellow is the third one back and then
red is the final peel right
and so what we want to see here is we
should be able to look at the screen and
see what sort of peels were using in any
particular you know place right and
actually what I should do is is change
this a little bit so what I'm going to
do is I want to put an if 0 here around
the real code I'm actually going to go
ahead and do this as an if I think so
I'm going to do something like
I cannot think if there's any way I can
get that third peel to be anything in
particular we just have one more appeal
than we have colors to work with here so
let's try this let's get rid of peel 3
for the moment I guess and we'll just
use the standard composite but we'll do
it with red green and blue assigned to
the different peels and now we should be
able to do is look at the color of an
individual pixel and see what the
contribution of each peel is by how much
of each channel there is in it right so
when you look at the screen now what you
can see is the overwhelming majority of
screen is blue and that makes sense
because that's the front most peel right
and what you can see basically you know
when when you get to 2 like when you're
looking at shadows for example or when
you're looking at the most a couple
different overlapping heads what you can
see there is you can see that it becomes
cyan which means that PL 2 is also
contributing which is again exactly what
we'd expect and where you see white
white means that either we have all the
peels contributing or we have three of
the peels contributing unfortunately we
can't really tell the difference between
peeled two contributing and peel 2 and
three contributing because we don't have
another color channel for for you know
for peel for peel 3 which we did okay so
you know what we can see here is I think
we can at least identify where those
black splotches were are definitely
where
yeah are definitely where we had a lot
of overlapping peels
let me also do this let me multiply each
one of these by its alpha correctly like
so and that way I can also in it won't
if peel 0 is non-contributing we won't
see it right
so that's kind of odd I think I did I
mess that up so that suggested me again
that there's something weird going on
here because like take a look up here
right that should just be blue because
it's pretty much a frontmost thing and
if we turn off the shader we don't see
like what we're looking at there is we
see that we're supposed to be seeing the
second def peel is primal but I don't
know why that would be the case oh I
dunno okay now that's actually correct
so that's where the shadow of this tree
is and this tree which is actually
getting drawn behind it is the second
def peel and so it is you know it is
showing itself through because the
shadow was what was behind it and then
where the two shadows are that's where
we get that lid so that's okay it all
makes reasonable sense actually so now
if we look at what we're seeing here
it's pretty clear that the the place
where we get the error is where we have
lots of peels overlapping right so you
can see we get sort of these these def
peels happen here what's interesting is
something feels off about this because
these values seem to have faded out
entirely from alpha I mean maybe they're
just really low but it seems like
they've faded out almost entirely and
yet this is def peel 3 at this point but
are there really two things that are
alpha out there that seems a little bit
strange to me
it seems like our fogging is not able to
get the Alpha to go quite to zero but
but that front clip plane should be
doing that so it's a little bit strange
so we take a look at what's happening
here we've got our got our code here for
how we're doing our alpha right
and you can see us modifying the frag
the output fragment color by the the fog
distance here by doing a clamped range
map and in theory you know that zero
when we get zeros there that should that
should kill it I'm interested to know
what happens if I up if I increase our
threshold a little bit and say let's
kill things a little prematurely right
let's kill things a little bit before
their alpha value actually gets to zero
and let me see what happens there with
those red values see that's just really
suspicious right that is just that does
not make sense to me because now I'm
killing I'm killing it Oh point one
alpha and how am I seeing this at all
without something in front of it at that
point like why is that thing on depth
appeal three if I can't see anything in
front of it if the Alpha gets clamped
off at 0.1 that just doesn't make any
sense
right if the Alpha is getting clamped
off at 0.1 something's busted
hmm I say I mean let's go even further
let's say that the Alpha has to be
extreme like you've got to be half
visible or we will not show you now what
happens same thing right
so I'm miss concerns me quite a bit
right like something's happening that I
don't understand for sure because unless
I'm really unless I really have it wrong
if I click if I'm saying that the
texture oh okay I see I see now this is
the problem right here this is the
problem all along so the texture sample
is just the texture color so we're not
discarding on alpha anymore we forgot to
do that we need to move the mod color up
and we need to we need to compute that
right here so we need to take the
texture sample then we need to do the
multiply right to figure that out now I
don't really know how the shader the
shader compiler will probably reorganize
the scalar stuff in here so I'm guessing
that really all I want to do is do this
outside so because you know at the end
of the day the shaders have to exude
everything in parallel anyway so can
only early out in some certain
circumstances so I'm going to move those
before the if and here middle oh that
texture sample do the srgb fix-up if we
need to compute that mod color and then
I'm going to talk about mod color alpha
so now with mod color alpha we're
actually taking that fog into account
see we were fogging things out but then
we weren't taking them out of the depth
peel and that's just totally wrong you
know I'm saying so now those should not
be perfect okay perfect perfect perfect
so that was really stressing our depth
peeling out in a way that it never
should have so let's take a look if this
improves our situation at all in the
case where we are
Bing alpha normally so now let's take a
look at what happens in there and now
it's looking a lot better right in there
and I don't know if it's good enough but
steadily looking better so let's take a
quick peek back
at the at the rendered version just to
see where we're at in those terms right
so now let's let's go ahead and we'll
hop down here like so ah and so now you
can see we've really mitigated it quite
a bit it still happens a little you can
see it happening right there just at
that at that one at that changeover
point right where I guess we've got too
many things alpha it up on top of each
other I'm not entirely sure right
exactly what's causing that but it's
pretty close you know I'm saying it's
getting pretty close okay so the only
problem now that we have besides the
fact that we still have a little bit of
that artifact there is that I still am
not 100% confident I know what the
artifact actually is right and so that's
the reason I originally started this
investigation it's not just to fix it
but to figure out what I'm not
understanding properly so I now have
some information which is it is a place
where there are a lot of depth fields
and so what I'm wondering is I guess is
that just a place where there's too many
deaf deals so the bottom most def peel
is not enough information or something
like that I'm not sure so I'm going to
propose another test that we should do
here which is to see
to see where we're seeing the final
depth peel so to do that what I want to
do is I want to say basically peel three
in all cases is going to be you know
bright pink right so I can see where the
final depth peel shows through
so as I'm hopping around here I can I
could see that the hero actually sees
the final depth field where it's got a
lot of things stacked on top of each
other actually but otherwise it's pretty
much just the background now what I'm
expecting to see is when I come through
here I should see purple at the place
where we flash and yes we do right you
can see that purple there
so that seems like we just have too many
depth peels are sorry too few depth
peels for the level of complexity that
we're looking at depth complexity
but I'm really not sure hmm so a couple
things we could do here right one thing
that we can do here is we could say well
let's just increase the number of deaf
peals right we always def peal til we
get something but the problem with that
is it has this nasty failure case of
like well you know when things just keep
stacking up on top of each other
eventually we're going to fail right so
what we'd rather do is have it so that
once we get to a number of things
stacked on top of each other like that
we are you know we're going to degrade
more gracefully now one of the things I
would point out in that situation is by
the time you get to 4 def peels you know
you can't perceive the results very
accurately at that point you know the
person looking at it you're blending
four layers together at that point it's
just it seems to me like that's just
excessive right because the visual
fidelity at that point for you is not
good enough you know it's not going to
be good enough to really perceive how
that blend is being done so it feels to
me like what you probably would want to
do there is
is produce something that's going to
properly average things together
Russians they properly produce something
that like say you know deaf peel three
is always the an opaque background color
that is whatever the unit whatever
however far back we had to go to get
something opaque so you know past one is
the closest thing past zero is the
closest opaque thing and then like in
the middle is just a averaging together
of their results or something you know
what I mean so like in between is all
the things that are alpha'd and they're
just averaged together by their alpha or
something like this do you know what I
mean
because essentially what we know is you
know when we've got things stacked on
top of each other we're always going to
have a situation where we're always
going to have a situation that
fundamentally looks like this there's
going to be an opaque color even if
that's just a background color but it's
whatever the last solid object was right
and then there's going to be the
frontmost pixel right and then in here
if there's just a bunch of alphab stuff
because if it wasn't outside we don't
need to keep DES peeling right if it
wasn't outside you're never going to see
what's behind it so we always have
between 0 and n alpha things in the
middle and we've got a front in the back
that kind of sandwich them together
right this is presumably the most
important thing usually unless alpha
gets really low but then all these are
averaged together or whatever and then
we've got this you know opaque thing so
I'm wondering if we could do something
where we just mix everything together in
here or something like that and then
guarantee that we always get one opaque
thing back here and then you know
composite those together
and basically what that would mean is
you know right now the way we composite
things together in alpha blending in the
alpha blending world is we say something
like well you know we've got a like a
front and a back
right we've got the thing that's like in
front of and the thing that's behind and
we're going to blend those together so
typically what we do is we say well the
Alpha value of the front times itself
plus 1 minus the alpha value of the
front and I could be more specific about
that times the back is how I cover this
is like you know on top of I think is
how it's normally described in terms of
what the shading operation is like I'm
going to put this on top of that right
so as the Alpha of this fades out I get
you know more of this and vice versa now
we could choose to mix things together
in a way that doesn't have an order
dependence to it right we could choose
to mix things together by saying all
right what if we just did you know a F +
BF I'm sorry a F plus a B right so we
took the alpha from the front let's let
it by the front to the alpha in the back
multiplied it by at the back right which
is what we're doing accumulate these
together into something to produce
basically an average right if we just
average things together and we just
accumulate these things together and
then normalize at the end so instead of
you know a - 8 bit per channel frame
buffers that we accumulate into we'd
have 2 16 bits per channel frame buffers
or something like this that we would
accumulate into and then we would
renormalize at the end right
now I don't know if that really makes a
lot of sense because it severely limits
the kinds of effects we can do with our
alpha so it's a little hard to say
I'm just not sure it's obviously not as
good as depth peeling in terms of
getting that coverage correct but it's
something to consider or perhaps
something to just try and see what it
does however that said again I still
want to make sure that I actually
understand this correctly and so let's
think about let's see if we can try to
figure out what's actually happening
here in terms of where the bug part
comes from so let's switch back to the
regular view
and so as I come through here I want to
be able to see that glitch it's really
kind of hard to see the glitch now but
you know I can kind of I can kind of get
between it there there's no real frame I
guess that I can find that I can hold on
it unfortunately maybe if I well
probably want but I'll try hopping down
one more flight of stairs because maybe
that will work
and I can't I unfortunately can't quite
get it to reproduce that
hmm well it would be nice if we get
three percent maybe I should add some
kind of a pause or because you know I
can use the debug camera but then
fogging is turned off on the debug
camera unfortunately so I guess I could
turn fogging on to the diba camera but
the whole point of the debug camera so
that we can expect things so it
typically I have it turned the fog off
so we can see the status of things right
but uh but yeah we know that those areas
are the regions where we're seeing peel
3 earlier right we're running out of
deaf peels but and so I guess the
problem is you know if I had to sort of
hand wave it here the problem is that
there's too many things overlapping this
area and because there's too many things
overlapping that area what that means is
that you never get to the background
grey color so even though you know
somebody in the background there has an
alpha value that's actually fairly low
and you should be seeing a fair bit of
grey through it there is no gray coming
in because peel 3 is still alpha doubt
right so I wonder you know what we could
try is just sort of a simpler version of
the scheme I outline which is saying
well let's do our def peeling but let's
make sure we always get eventually back
to an opaque color you know and maybe
that helps reduce those artifacts you
know I don't know maybe it'll just
introduce different artifacts but I'm
just interested to know like what if we
had our def peel you know do something
where it would be able to throw out
things based on a programmatic alpha so
for example here's the fragment shader
and you know I've got some stuff in here
like the fog color that's coming in from
the outside I'm introduced another one
which is just an f32 that's the min
alpha value right I
and maybe I want to do that a little bit
differently maybe I want to do that and
say that it's the well because I want to
make it have to be exactly one so I
guess maybe I don't really want to do
that maybe I want two different versions
of the shader I don't know because
basically what I want to do is I want to
change this line so that instead of mod
color a is greater than zero what I want
to do is create to be equal to one right
but you know I don't know maybe that's
too aggressive maybe what I really want
to do is just make it so that that's
actually just some high number
all right well let's do that let's just
say we do f/32 which is just going to be
an alpha threshold and the alpha
threshold value is just going to be the
thing that we use to quit so be zero on
the first couple def fields but then the
final depth peel will jack it up to
something high so we're only going to
record into that found ethical guest
skip anybody who might have been in
front but just who had an alpha
threshold that was just simply too low
right so I'm going to go in here and
just make sure that we can actually get
that value so here's our Z bias program
I'm going to add it here to alpha
threshold and I need to grab it at some
point as well so that'll get us the
location of it and then all we need to
do is set it and so up here when we're
doing that that peeling stuff basically
what we want to do is say well okay
let's take a look at the peel index and
we want to set this based on that so
what I want to do is when we do use
program begin here after that let's see
here we've got that
here's our use we're going to begin with
the render setup path to it for the V
bias program what I want to do here is
is pass in the alpha threshold and now
anywhere that we're using that which of
course is only one place you know we
have to pass NASA threshold and so what
I want to do here is I want to pass the
Alpha threshold based on the Pele
configuration so basically the Alpha
threshold is always going to be zero for
pretty much all cases except the case
where the peel is where we are doing
peeling right in fact I could do it like
this where we are doing peeling and
we're on the last peel so at that point
you know maybe we say it's going to be
you know 0.9 I don't know I'm making
this number up so we are peeling and
then we want to say oh is the peel index
you know the last peel right so is if
peel index equal to max render target
index so you know we know that we're
basically done and this is the last peel
we're going to get all right so now what
we're doing is we're basing hey we're
trying to produce a final layer that
will always have something in it right
and we'll see if that helps with those
artifacts at all so it you know it it
definitely helped there's but I still I
still see a little minor little
artifacts like right here you can see
one there right
it's really pretty minimal but it's
definitely still there
and let's also see whether whether we
can get we were having those artifacts
when one of the snakes would come by and
all those particles were raining down I
don't know how to get this thing to do
that again there they are
hopefully the snake will come come
through that again it doesn't seem like
it wants to at the moment but so the
question is yet will we get any there
there I'm seeing some raining down and
I'm not seeing any artifacts on those
now so it seems like that is a pretty
effective fix for the vast majority of
the artifacting actually which is pretty
nice oh the snake came down the stairs
so that's good there the snake goes now
we got two snakes alright maybe I'll go
down the stairs one more time because
there's two snakes on this level that
should produce a lot of particles that
will rain down to the floor below oops
I got to go up one deny how do I get up
one leg up like that okay so that's yeah
that's a very effective fix for a lot of
those artifacts again I still see it a
little bit in certain circumstances but
it's pretty darn good
hmm so yeah try think if there's
anything else I should do here that
would help
so I guess the other thing is if we
always know that that background alpha
is going to be something high right and
I feel like when we clear it it should
have been cleared to an alpha value of
one as well or at least I hope that it
was I don't know if it was or not so
let's let's actually see what we're
doing there like so this kind of has to
be 1.0 now so if that alpha value is 1
then that means that in the shader there
is no way to ever have an alpha value
that isn't high because nothing would
get drawn if it wasn't so in theory we
should also be able to undo any
premultiplied alpha that's happening so
that should now work and we shouldn't
see any bugs from it I don't think in
fact you should be able to do this
directly so basically undoing the P
multiplied alpha where we're just going
to you know multiply the RGB by the
inverse of the alpha to unpretty
multiplied if that makes sense
so that actually looks worse which
suggests to me that maybe the pre
multiplication of the Alpha isn't
happening properly or something I'm not
100% certain what's going on with that
so like if we look in here to me
here's the thing that produces all of
our fragment code so we're fetching our
texture sample and our texture samples
are premultiplied alpha or at least they
are supposed to be right now there is
one problem that we have here and this
could be the kind of place where it
actually does matter the problem that we
have is that our bundler our pad our art
asset Packer doesn't properly handle
srgb it was made for the old renderer
which just uses squares and square roots
so the problem we then get is that that
means that our alpha is always a little
bit wrong
because well the pre multiplication of
the alpha is a little bit wrong because
instead of pre multiplying by the
correct alpha we're actually pre
multiplying by a slightly different
instead of pre multiplying the sRGB
corrected colors and storing those were
pre multiplying squared colors and
multiplying those right which is not the
right thing when then the card does an
sRGB correction I don't know that that
would show up in this situation but it's
worth remembering that it's on the table
because you know when you're getting
down to little artifacts you have to be
thinking of everything but anyway so
when we do the texture samples here we
produce a mod color we then go ahead and
yeah you can see here we we then kind of
go ahead and take the fragment color and
x at X sample now here's the this is
doing pre multiplication properly here
right there's a frag color it's the
entire thing is being multiplied by the
alpha amount that's coming out of the
fog their fog itself of course is not
handled that way but that's okay we
don't really need to be handled that way
so that's fine
I am curious was there a reason there
must have been a reason but I don't
remember what it was what was the reason
why we didn't use the fragment color to
do the fogging oh right because since
it's clamped
actually that's an interesting point
since these are since these values are
clamped they really can't be done in a
vertex shader can they like isn't this
kind of wrong because if you clamp
something it will be wrong if it's done
at the vertex level if the pixels don't
all have the same values of the vertices
of the things you're clamping on right
so I feel like that's actually not right
I feel like that actually has to get
done in the pixel shader wouldn't you
guys agree I feel like that
I feel like that's just kind of true so
I feel like what we can do is we can do
the the fog distance computation we can
definitely do the fog distance
computation but I don't think we can
actually do these like I think these
have to be done down here to be
completely honest right I think this
stuff has to happen here because correct
me if I'm wrong if you think about
what's going on we've got some some
sprites or whatever and we've got maybe
some fog so let's say the fog is going
this way well if the fog max value is
like you know this line or whatever
right then if I clamp these values
they're wrong right because I'm going to
interpolate along this thing and I want
to get the max I want to go from the min
to the max here but if I'm clamping
these I'll actually go from the min to
the max over this entire thing because
the pixel shader will interpret it will
interpolate it between those end points
so so I don't think that's correct I
don't think that's correct at all so I
think what we can do is say that there's
a smooth out f32 fog distance but I
think that's all we can do and I think
this stuff has to be computed here I
think this stuff has to be computed and
so the start and end distance is like
this stuff has to get looked up
right and so I just want to make sure
everyone kind understands what I'm
talking about and again I'm not claiming
that I'm right here this is just what I
was looking at I was like this doesn't
seem right
essentially you know we've got two parts
of the pipeline right there's the vertex
shader and then there's the fragment
shader and what's going to happen here
is the vertex shader is only outputting
things with the vertices right so if it
wants to it can do you know fog the it
can do like you know the point times the
fog direction right because that value
is just going to produce a scalar that
ranges over the pixels linearly not
pixiv linearly over the triangle
linearly right so whatever this triangle
is I can produce a value that skate that
you know is cleaner in those triangles
and it'll get interpreted properly in
the pixel shader right the pixel shader
will do the perspective correction
everything correctly and so it'll give
me the right values but I can't do
something like that's going to clamp
this value right if I start clamping
this value then what's going to happen
is when it feeds to the fragment shader
it's not going to get the correct
interpolated values you know I'm saying
so things in map that get clamped can't
be specified only the vertices because
you don't know where inside the triangle
it actually would have gotten clamped so
that seems like just a bug to
straight-up bug so I think we need to be
able to do this stuff here at the top of
our pixel shader
tell me what my error message is oh okay
that's not why I want to see okay so
we're just crashing straight up inside
what I assume is the compiler that's not
great but I don't know what to do about
that exactly we're getting the fog
distances as a smooth smooth in so that
should be correct we've got the fog
start/end in the clip start and end
distance those should be there the
fragment color that's coming in is
getting multiplied by that and then use
down here we don't really have to
multiply it that way I suppose we could
just say hey the alpha amount is going
to modulate you know the whole thing
yeah I don't know I don't know what it's
what's wrong unfortunately that the
driver is not okay great so just
reorganizing those things made the
driver not crash okay I don't know it's
a that's just how that goes I guess
so what's interesting is now you can see
the effect is totally different actually
right it actually looks very different
now that that's happening
very very different and interestingly
enough it also happens I want to get rid
of the uncorrect there because the
parent we're still doing this which
apparently is wrong although we don't
know why it's wrong yet also doing it
that way reduces the degree of unwanted
over blending that's happening during
the fade-out so it also means that we we
aren't getting the artifact which is
kind of a nice thing because just not
because it fixed the artifact or
anything but just because the over
blending now is less so that explains
why I had to set the range up so high I
might want a little bit more of that
range though I don't know like maybe we
don't maybe we do I don't know that's
like tuning the effect or whatever but
yeah so
I'm really relatively happy with where
we are at the moment I think we could do
more certainly but I'm pretty happy with
that I think that renderer is shaping up
to be pretty nice it's order independent
now uses the Z buffer for sorting really
the only thing that's kind of stupid
about it is the fact that it has to
change textures so often that's not good
at all but it's pretty nice otherwise
and we get that nice fade in effect
there which I like when you go up and
down the levels particles are looking
pretty good
you know I don't see a lot of
artifacting in the particles
so yeah about the only thing I would say
that I noticed is that you know if you
just had you know if you had a fast
graphics card I would say that probably
we would want to still do multi sampling
right like let's just say you just have
fill rate to burn then you still do get
a very edgy artifacts like right along
the edges there of the you know of the
buffer of the of those sort of cube like
structures those lines don't get
anti-alias by anything right all of our
bitmaps are nicely anti-alias because
the bitmaps themselves are anti aliased
so when we've lit them on and you know
do proper bilinear filtering on them we
just we get a nice smooth result that
doesn't have any objection artifacts
there we don't have at the moment any
such thing for actual geometric
primitives which we are using in the
case of those cubes and so I do wonder
if we want to allow a switch I think it
wouldn't be very good on this machine
but allow a switch that turns on just
the whole pipeline runs through multi
sampling because again you know somebody
runs this on a GeForce Titan or
something like that there's really no
reason why they shouldn't be able to get
multi sampling because it's not going to
affect our pipeline at all in any way
that I can think of so if they just have
fill rate lying around to light on fire
I feel like we should let them light it
on fire
right I mean they paid for the graphics
card after all right
so what I'm wondering is if we can just
turn on multi sampling here as well so
when we create the buffers will create
them as multi sampled buffers and then
at the end we'll still do the SmackDown
if we need to right and so here we can
kind of see how that would work so we've
got you know this is our actual ending
where we do our def peel compositing so
this is happening here the only change
that would have to occur is this vine
frame buffer call which is currently
targeting the final frame buffer would
instead have to target a temporary frame
buffer and then we would just use this
exact code that we were using before
right
that's really all we would have to do
now there's a little bit of fussing to
it because this parts going to be
different the draw region min/max part
is going to be different so there's
there's a little bit of a of a
difference there but that's about it I
think so what we should be able to do is
say like okay let's let's move let's
move this up to here and just take a
look at Luke's that's not what I want to
do here we go so this is again just the
same pipeline running I so what I can do
is say well these are the only things
that would change right so what I could
do is say if multi sampling oops else
right and so what we want to do here is
say
well I guess we don't even have to set
these because they would just be always
correct so it's really just if we're not
multi sampling because aren't they
preferred well you know they might not
be a rumor I'm gonna set them either way
you never know with copic you um so if
we're multi sampling I would want to do
like will resolve same buffer and this
is just going to be a temporary thing
over that we create it's going to have
the standard dimensions and
you know now I think about though this
is going to be a little bit more tricky
than I thought it was going to be
because when we do the DEF peel
compositing I don't know if shaders can
automatically just use the right multi
sample index well you know what we'll
just try it
we've got a half-hour left let's try it
and we'll see what happens all right so
here's multi sampling we don't want
window within window height what we want
here is the actual like rendered size so
we want these this you know saying do we
pull that out into anything ever so I
think we want to pull that out so that
we're always using the same stuff here
so there's the draw with to draw height
and yeah let's it's done a lot huh
so I'm not sure so this is interesting
so the draw region versus the commands
width and height when are those
different I thought those were always
the same
so what's the difference between the
window with the window height and the
draw region the draw region is the
portion of the window we're actually
drawing in so that's actually kind of
busted the way we're doing this is a
little bit wonky I'll leave it for now
but I don't know if we really want to do
it that way forever
yeah I wonder if we want to change the
way this is being done a little bit so
if you look at the way we're doing it
right now we create frame buffer targets
that are the size of the output but I
don't know whether we really want to do
that I I feel like we might want to
create a specific sized render and then
stretch it to the screen the reason I
say that is because we might want to do
stuff like oh we render it you know
1080p on a 1080p display so it's
one-to-one and it looks nice if you run
on a 4k display but your graphics card
can't handle 4k kinds of fill rates then
we would still render at 1080p and then
stretch up to 4k is definitely what you
would want to do there right but with
the current way that we set it up we
can't do that we're always going to
render at the width and height of the
actual like output this book you know
the actual size
so I feel like that not great you know
like that just doesn't seem good and if
I remember correctly we're actually
setting this in here right like we you
know we've set this stuff up so the
buffer width and height is whatever the
dip section is there I don't know what
we do on WM size nothing apparently
right
so we're kind of doing this right we're
kind of doing this already and so when
we set the commands
I think we're always going to be using
1920 so yes so I feel like what we want
to do is I feel like we want to actually
do that drawing correctly the way that I
suggested that fix that
all right so let's just let's just take
a look at this so we also know that
we're kind of not super great right now
it's scaling like we kind of broke that
like at some point they're right so I
feel like now would be a good time to
just fix all that stuff because we might
as well get this right for the final
sort of wave the renderer is working
here which i think is pretty much where
we're at I can't think I'd like I like
the step you'll render I think this is
the one to go with so let's just say
that we've got sort of the draw with the
draw height here and those are going to
be the commands with and the command
pipe so the actual size that everybody
thinks the thing is that's what we're
going to do basically everywhere so we
create all these render targets and we
create them at whatever that size is so
the size the game thinks it's running at
is the size we use and then when we're
doing render targets again this scissor
is going to be exactly the same for
everybody for all of the targets they're
always going to be the exact same GL
scissor there and and this clip scale
stuff I don't know even where that's
being used right now so yeah I feel like
that's just that's just totally wrong
because now that scale is is scaling for
something that we don't want to scale
right that was stuff that was adjusting
for the fact that we might be rendering
directly to a screen window that was
larger or smaller in pixel space than we
were thinking and so that's just not
going to happen now
and so now we're always rendering to
something that's the size that the gain
is running at right and so then what we
have to do at the end is we have to
scale down now at the moment I think
that will just work because what's
happening is we're setting the draw
region now we do the GL viewport GL
scissor bit here and off we go
so we really just need to clear the dead
area for our frame buffer right so we
would need to do like this so we could
get black bars in there but otherwise we
should be able to now make this work a
little more cleanly so let's let's start
getting that going all right so first
off this clear wants to happen over the
entire thing so the first thing we want
to do is is start with a full screen so
we want to do a viewport that covers
everything I don't know what window
width and window height actually are but
I think they're supposed to be the whole
screen right oops so this is kind of
like that should clear the whole screen
and this should be more get width for
our region if that's just wrong we don't
want the draw to the whole window we
want to draw to the part of the window
we were told to draw to like so
and so I'm going to reclaim the word
draw it here and I want this extra me to
render with right because that's a
little clear about what's going on and
then draw height is going to be render
height
all right so now okay so now we're
getting somewhere
now we properly have the sort of black
bars the letterboxing whatever you want
to call that which we had before is
happening correctly so it keeps you know
maintains the aspect ratio there as you
scaled this around just what I want but
now we have to make sure that we
actually do the blit to the correct size
so let's go ahead and figure out how to
get that to work and then we're in
better shape here okay so in here we've
got that that set up you can see the
viewport scissor happening here how
that's working by yet using the the draw
region that's getting passed down mmm
and I guess
I'm not sure exactly what so it's a
little strange because with the way that
this is set up I would expect this to
lift the incoming texture to the entire
screen but that's not what I'm seeing
right so let me just let me just see
something here so I'm assuming that I
won't see any pink when I do this and
I'm correct so what we're doing is our
actual our actual rendering is off it's
not it's not this this students fault
our actual rendering like viewport stuff
is off where do we set up the viewport
right here so when we call open jail
buying frame buffer this window with
window height bit is wrong so that's why
that's happening I also don't know where
we're calling fine frame buffer exactly
so here's opengl bind frame buffer so
basically passing the draw region for
all of those is just not what we want we
just want the width in height there so
what we want to do is just have buying
frame buffer take the render width and
the render height that's really what we
wanted
that when that path really isn't
supported anymore we'll probably have to
re-enable it someday when we do the
software renderer update here we go so
now we run that and everything appears
to be right here
switch to windowed mode and now that's
nice and clean right lovely so the other
thing we should now be able to do as
well is if I go to win32 hand-made we
should now be able to stretch up so if
we want to draw a smaller game so let's
fill rate use less graphics card
resources now we can write and so this
is us doing that right this is
stretching up
it's interesting about that is there
some weird artifacts you get that I see
there around the edges of things I'm not
sure why those are there only when
you're stretching up are those there in
1920 by 1080 but we just can't see them
well can I take a screen capture I don't
know
so it doesn't really look like that
fringing is happening right
it looks really good like that rendering
looks very solid to me
this guy always noticed had a weird band
on it and I wasn't quite sure what that
was made weirder by the fact that you
don't see it on this one even though
they're the same sprite
let's take a look
so which direction is that facing that
that's this right so I think it seems
like we're just getting basically what
amounts to scaling artifacts that could
be because of the sRGB let me let me
play with that a little bit I just like
to see so let's switch down to the lower
resolution so this is like half
resolution right and you know we should
we should expect to see jagged or edges
on things and blurrier imagery but what
we shouldn't be seeing is all of that
fringing there so I'm I want to know I'm
curious to know what happens if I force
multi sampling off in the OpenGL I'm not
mother sampling if I force real srgb to
be turned off and instead force it to
use the fake srgb so you know here where
we do this I'm just going to say you
know don't allow GPU srgb and so the
other place that that happens is it will
actually guess this whole thing
so it does kind of feel like that is
what that is so I feel like what we're
seeing here is the fact that the Alpha
is not computed with actual srgb so it
doesn't quite line up right when
stretched
hmm
hmm so this warrants this warrants
further investigation if they believe I
am interested to know though this should
compute it correctly because now if we
force the shader to do the square square
root that should produce roughly the
same calculation as we were doing
ourselves in the software renderer which
is what the art is prepackaged as at the
moment in this art pack so that srgb
computation should now be exact right
because what we should be doing is we
should be running through shader sim you
know text right and shader semtex read
that is what should you know should be
happening in both cases so every time on
load and store we should be getting
precisely that same in and out that we
were doing before which is square on the
way in square root on the way out
and so that really feels to me like that
should have corrected it
[Music]
so I guess and I really couldn't say but
I guess what's happening there is you
know my best might my only real guess is
since that's the depth peel composite
that's doing that the bilinear filtering
on the depth field composite is
therefore incorrect right because this
is actually not a substitute now that I
think about it right because you need to
do that squaring before you blend the
bilinear samples together so if we were
to just take a raw Texel sample then I
think we'd actually be ok I don't know
exactly how we would do that but it
would probably look like this
and yeah so there you go well so that's
definitively what the problem is with
that and what you can see there is that
that the depth feeling draw this out
because it's kind of tough to explain I
think how I would say that I couldn't
think of it so the duct peeling works by
saying okay I've essentially got a stack
of things right because I can draw that
a little better there
I've got a stack of things and I'm going
to produce one of them right so it's
going to take these and it's going to
collapse these down by blending them
it's going to take this one and blend on
top of this on top of this on top of
this one right per pixel but once you
start stretching what's going to happen
then is rather than sampling right at
the middle of each pixel and doing that
composite once for each pixel exactly
you're actually going to pull from a
bilinear sample so you're going to be
you know here or something on each one
of these guys is going to be you know a
four sample pick so you've got you know
peel 0 peel 1 kill 2 peal 3 and you're
pulling from the same place on all them
but it's a blend between all of their
you know the constituents right around
there and so when you do that what's
going to happen is you're going to get
incorrect results if you don't blend
those together exactly right because
since it's premultiplied alpha one of
the problems with premultiplied alpha is
it's got to be done correctly it's gotta
be exactly correctly and if you don't
actually do it correctly you will get
too much or too little color
contribution which will lead to black or
white fringing right not pure black or
pure white but you know a lighter or
darker shade around the edge of
something where it should have gone to 0
both the color and the alpha but they
didn't both go to zero at the same time
so the color went to zero but the Alpha
stayed up or the color didn't go to zero
yet and the Alpha went all the way down
you get like a clamp the edge right
hmm so what that suggests to me is yet I
don't know if we've got another bug
somewhere that is contributing to that
but unfortunately I'm not really sure
that we could test it yet because what
we need is we need our assets like our
textures themselves to properly be an
actual srgb because if they're not
actually an sRGB we won't be able to
test what happens when the card blends
them properly
so I'm not sure how we could investigate
this further at the moment I could
certainly build the next art pack with
proper srgb adjustment of the pixel
values you know that's not too hard to
do but I don't know I don't know what I
can do prior to that to analyze this any
further now what we can do and what we
possibly just want to do anyway because
it might be just be more efficient in
the general case I don't know maybe it
wouldn't really be more efficient it's
hard to say possibly not but we might
want to leave those at nearest sampling
anyway and just do a temporary always
composite to a temporary buffer so when
we do that smack down we would always
composite to a temporary buffer on that
anyway you know again hard to say
whether we want to do that or not but
that's certainly an option
so I think that's the tack I'll take for
now so that we don't ever stretch those
buffers directly we composite first to a
final image and then we just stretch the
final image and during that composite
pass we could also do some things like
if we wanted to do some light blooming
or things like that we could also do it
in there so I don't know maybe that's
the best way to go so the way that that
would work is actually this multi
sampling bit would actually it would
always work this way
so the multi sampling part wouldn't
actually happen yet if that makes sense
so what we would do if something more
like this where we always go to a global
resolve frame buffer first that we pile
everything into so this would produce an
intermediate frame buffer that frame
buffer would now have the proper Jeff
peel composite we then switch to the
thing we're going to do for bleeding
and I guess so the interesting thing
about this is this blips frame buffer
support stretching
so it's just the intersection of the two
so this would not so we need to do a
second one of these passes basically
where we are actually going to draw with
a shader but that shader simply doesn't
do anything right we can't just do a
frame buffer but here because a frame
buffer blitt is not going to a frame
buffer bit is bligg is not going to do
what we needed to do right a frame
buffer but in this case is going to keep
the size of the thing the same and we
want to stretch it so we want to be able
to take the image that we just rendered
and make it larger or smaller with
bilinear filtering right and we would
even potentially if we wanted to stretch
it down a lot we would potentially even
want you know mipmapping but I don't
think we would ever do that because we
probably what we do is we just change
the runtime size that we're rendering
the game so that we never rendered the
game at let at less than at more than
twice the resolution of the output right
because there's no reason to so I think
this would be okay so what we want to do
here is we want to say all right you
know we did we did this program dispatch
here and we pretty much just want to do
the exact same program dispatch again
but with a slightly different program so
we would do
this and this part has to stay out for
now so I'm just can introduce a new kind
of program which is the final stretch
program but just all it's doing is that
that's sampling and so what we want to
do here is you know we're just going to
do a bind texture so here where we
switch to the global resolve frame
buffer we also have to have a global
resolve texture and so all we would be
doing is this right we would set to the
final stretch program pull from the
global resolving texture draw you know
and then in that we go
and that's really all there is to it I
think
all right
so let's say we did that we would then
have final stretch program there we go
and the final stretch program I think
will just be a single texture right so
this is the image stretching that's it
and so if I go ahead and make one of
these I think we don't really have much
in the way defines I guess I'll leave
those in there in case we want to do
something with the srgb but for a
compiled peel composite this is actually
compiled
final stretch so in this case we've got
no color values just UV and then in our
our fragment code here just got the
image
and really we don't probably need to do
anything so I think we're just going to
do the fill color equals texture image
frag UV and all of this stuff is gone I
think that's the entire program I don't
really think there's anything else to it
yeah so this has no Verte color right
that's not in there although I think we
still have to get it here and I think
that should be about it and then we will
need a corresponding binding for just
that image so when we do our use program
begin here it's always going to be flat
zero because there's only one texture I
think that's mostly it oops
all right
so that compiles us another program and
really interests to pass through a
program that just stretches the texture
that's all it does I probably won't do
anything else so I don't think there's
much to worry about there however we do
need to do a slightly more delicate
operation here which is we need to
create a frame buffer for that temporary
purpose right
and so we've wanted to curious we want
to have one other frame buffer I and so
you know in in sort of this right here
we want a global resolve frame buffer
and a global resolved texture and those
need to get created at some point so
probably during initialization is when
we would do that and we probably want to
just cut and paste this code and modify
it a little bit because it's basically
the same but it's going to be enough
difference that I don't even really know
if we can reuse the code I suppose we
might be able to make sort of an uber
frame buffer generator I don't really
know like maybe we can if you could do
something like this where it's like
allocate frame buffer or something or
create frame buffer and maybe that's
possible to just take this code and boil
it down to something that just has a
bunch of ifs in it and you can pass in
some flags or something that says how
it's going to go right so for example
maybe one thing we could do is say well
there's a Glu int for the slot and
that's you know no well you know what
maybe we can even make this a little bit
more user-friendly so maybe we say like
okay is it multi sampled you know you
tell us is it a linear filtered you know
or just filter filtered you tell us
something like that and maybe I'll even
make those flags
just to be even clearer equals slides
and the Fangio flames over full-size
samples
flags and capris you'll framebuffer
tilted still in here we've got this glue
in slot thing and really what I'm just
going to say as well is it multi sampled
because if it's multi sampled we're
doing this if it's not we're doing that
right so there's not a lot of ambiguity
there we're going to be destruct OpenGL
frame buffer that structures going to
have two things in it right it's going
to have a filament for the texture
handle and GL you into the frame buffer
handle right and since we've probably
thought I don't really need to call
these well I don't know we'll call them
what we call so that's what I'm going to
return so I'll just say is open stream
buffer open gel frame buffer a result
here and so I'll get rid of this and
just say okay you know GL gen textures
result frame buffer handle no sorry
guess we really want to talk about two
things color handle def handle right
I'll call gen textures twice because
just I could call it with a pointer to
color handle but you know why be cheeky
if people reorganize those members I
would then you know the code would be
wrong so let's not do that
so we'll do GL gen textures and we'll
sort of allocate those two and we can
also gende the frame buffer handle as
well frame buffers sold give up for
handle
so that's like the first step right so
now we want to do say okay we've got
this and we're going to need this here
like you know open Jill same buffer
depth flags and open Jill frame buffer
color so we could actually specify all
kinds of stuff here and see which ones
we're going to have all right so what
we'd want to do here is say if color is
we'll say house color if have steps and
then what we can do is sort of create
the ones that we actually need
now what's interesting about this is
these are pretty similar bits here so we
really could save some code if we wanted
to I don't know that I'm going to do
that right now
but I'm just pointing out that we could
sort of make a texture creator call that
would also save us some time our save of
some typing echoes or with some
redundancy but I don't think I'm going
to do that just yet but anyway we'll get
rid of this you'll find frame buffer
global chain before handles so we don't
want that either we want result frame
buffer handle and then when we do she'll
remember for texture 2d I think
I think but don't quote me on this that
we will then need to move this stuff up
a bit now I don't know if this will be
valid the way I'm doing this here we'll
find out but what I'm going to do here
is say you know after we Jen the frame
buffer will bind the frame buffer and
that way when we create these we can do
the color attachment right away
that way you can exist inside the has
color and have depth and that should be
pretty good right okay so we need to
pass distant flags and we need to
specify what these enums are right so
this is a video frame buffer flags and
in this case what I'm going to do is to
take exactly what I said I wanted in the
code and make a Flags set a flag for
them all right
so obviously we need the width and the
height and I might just make that be the
first thing that comes down so let's
just go ahead and grab that everywhere
it's
there we go and same with you and
alright a result color handle and this
one is going to be results depth angle
okay so now we can create a frame buffer
and do all that stuff I want to have
filtering be controllable too so the
other thing I'm going to do here is
check that function deal text parameter
I
[Applause]
yeah
and that's a GL inte it looks like so
the one that we happen to be using here
is GL inte so I'm going to remember
which one I think that is so I'm going
to say if we're filtered then turn on
linear filtering otherwise turn on
nearest filtering and that way we can
say oops on both of these so I'll just
pick up the filter type from that that
test and that flag alright so now that
we can create a frame buffer we could
use this to create all the frame buffers
that we currently are using in fact
which is kind of nice right but the only
one I want to do it for at the moment is
just this one here that I actually
needed and so I'm going to go ahead and
create one of those frame buffers and
you can see that we know exactly what we
need for that final composite frame
buffer right which is this global
resolve frame buffer thing here we know
exact what we need which is something
that looks like you know that size right
so what I want to do here is the first
time we come through when we're doing
the sort of max render target situation
thing here right global frame buffer
camp what I want to do is when we come
through here this first time I want to
create that one as well so I want to do
create frame buffer and gel frame buffer
and what I want to do is I want to give
it the render within the render height
and I want to pass the right set of
flags so here are the flags that I might
want I just want it to be filtered oops
and to have a color it doesn't need a
depth lever and then what I can do is
say global resolve frame buffer equals
resolve that frame buffer handle
Louisville resolve texture equals
resolved texture handle and so now I
have that resolve buffer in theory if
our routine works at all we don't know
if it does its color handle is what I
want it there
we got errors enable vertex at rib array
so that's just a question of that common
part there doesn't have a frag color
anymore and so when we do use program
comment and it does does this bit that
doesn't work if like one of these arrays
isn't there right so I think what we
could do in this case is if I line these
up I could do something like this sort
of thing which is that great but you
know it's cute enough for now and so I
do the same thing here because I assume
you can't disable one that isn't a valid
one
but we'll see
all right so now what we're doing in
this case right is we're doing the
composite and then the stretch and it
looks like it's working right so that's
actually pretty good right it looks like
it's it's doing what we want to do here
I think don't quote me on that
let's actually go verify that I did
enable the path correctly and everything
so here we are with the frame buffer
binding that we rendered the global
resolve buffer then we come through
render a second time and that does look
roughly correct right that does look
like you know what I would expect
so that's fine and we fixed that error
so that's all good and this means we can
really just under sample as much as we
want so in theory now you know if we
really needed to for some reason the
Earth's I don't know what the reason
would ever be because I don't know how
you get a machine that had such a slow
had such so graphics and such fast
everything else but you know if we
wanted to yeah we could basically make
this even one one further smaller so you
know if we want to do 480 by 270 oops
not by 280 we should be able to do a
super blurry one and there we go and
this would be good test two because we
could turn on multi sampling in this
case when we get the multi simply
working and although it will be blurry
we should be able to get rid of all that
shimmer eNOS right a lot of that shimmer
eNOS should go away and so that'll be
good test for tomorrow turning on that
the multi sample right so I think that's
pretty good
I wonder hi
I wonder if we should just be like hey
you know what let's just just like let's
make this really pixelated because why
not right Oh can't can it not do that
what wait 0:06
how did we end up with 0 and 0 as the
render with and render height
huh
that's pretty unusual wouldn't you say
oh I never called it that's why it's
zero and zero so I'm interested to know
if you can make like pixel hero by him
by doubt like having the sampling really
low and then turning off the turn
turning off the blend so instead of
having this be filtered you just you
don't don't filter it right so it's like
all of a sudden it's like a pixel art
game not a very good pixel heart game
but it's a pixel art game just the same
right and here we go down you know our
pixel hero is pixel around doing pixel
things and you know that's just how that
goes it's you know maybe that's maybe
that's what you're going for I don't
know you kiss today and they're pixel
art you know I'm Sam alright we'll do
some QA
the puddin
okay
so John blow has has shown up as far as
I can tell
simply to say OpenGL sucks that is that
it's prefixed with a Q :
so he is he is not even asking the
question OpenGL sucks question mark he's
merely stating OpenGL sucks in the form
of a question kind of like jeopardy when
it's like this API is an agglomeration
of years of mistakes and he's going what
is OpenGL so I guess what I would say
about that is I agree with that
obviously but I actually like the if you
were to use opengl 4.5 like AZ do I
actually quite like the problem with
OpenGL that I find mostly is that
there's it seems like there's people who
know what they're doing who have figured
out how to actually make a good API and
they made it and they're NVIDIA and if
you go use their extension specifically
and locked just to that API it's exactly
like the way I want well not maybe not
exactly but real close but the problem
is that's not the reality of using
OpenGL the reality of using open jails
you have to write up in jail that works
on everyone's drivers and and when you
limit yourself to that or like worse yet
what I'm doing on handmade here which is
kind of backwards compatibility no so
it's actually pretty old up in jail it's
awful
I'm and I would not disagree with that
so I actually think there is a really
good API inside open jail and I feel
like I don't know if that's just because
you know there are people who kind of
get what it should look
like and have tried to do that as much
as they can but they only have a certain
amount of influence on you know the
committee's that decide these things and
so you know they can't quite get there
or what but there are some very good API
design things in opengl 4.5 AZ do stuff
that get real close to how you would
want an actual graphics API to look so I
will defend that part of OpenGL opengl
3.0 x is an epic disaster and that
happens to be what we're programming in
so there's that
and John says the problem is there is no
way for me to know what the good API is
anymore yes I agree and also I mean I
would say that it doesn't matter that
you can't figure out was a good API is
because like I was saying or sort of
what I was trying to say before was you
can't really use it anyway because you
would you would be targeting a very
small set of potential users with it
necessarily because you know you you
know you might just not run on Intel at
all like Intel GPUs are out of the
question right at that point and AMD
cards you could run on but you would
have to remove a couple parts of the API
you would want or something right and so
you know it's worse than just the fact
that hey there's all this API in there
that's not good and that you wouldn't
want to use but now you don't even
really know that there is some good API
and there that you could go use it's
worse than that because it's like well
yeah but even if I told you here's
here's the good API I you know I pulled
it out of OpenGL and I said here you
know if you just look at these api's and
use them they're real good that won't
ship you a game right so that's that's
the actual problem if they just like
flush the toilet and got rid of
everything that wasn't basically Nvidia
AZ do OpenGL right and that was OpenGL 5
I think it would be pretty awesome right
because I like a lot of stuff they did
better than the way they did it in
Vulcan because Vulcan still did a bunch
of weird backwards compatibility stuff
that I don't want you know so yeah I
don't know you're damned if you do
damned if you don't
it seems like it there's nowhere to go
for a good graphics API like that's
that's just that's not on the table you
don't get to have that I don't know what
the best middle ground is you
the reason I programmed opengl on
handmade zero stream in particular is
just because it's the thing that works
on the most platforms so it's the thing
that probably gives people the most
foothold in to be able to do graphics
they could write on Android and it would
look roughly like this they could write
on Linux in it would look rough like
this they can run our Windows and it
looks reflect this thinking around iMac
and it looks rough for like this so I
feel like that's the best thing for a
teaching stream what's the best thing
for shipping a game it seems like there
is no best thing it's like hey yeah use
DirectX on Windows and use metal on
Apple and use you know the console
specific API that you have to use on the
console and use you know OpenGL ES on
Android and blah blah blah blah blah
it's like well you know it's just a
disaster no matter what you do at that
point and so yeah I don't know I don't
know what to say it's but it's really
bad I wish it wasn't this way I don't
really yeah
let's see and went through two ended up
in jail why do you use two different
forms for assigning modern OpenGL
function pointers I using winter to get
up into a function macro for some but
assign goes directly that's just because
we only made that macro like partway
through so we could go back and do the
other ones that way as well
we just haven't done that yet if we were
cleaning up that code we would because
the macro is cleaner it's easier to use
and results in less duplicated code so
you know that that was just because we
only created the macro a little bit
further on serial killer just so you
know your stream no longer shows up in
either the game development or
programming categories on Twitch it's
almost a hidden stream now just for
those who already followed I don't
actually know how twitch is doing that
so I'll try to remind myself I don't
know how I will remind myself hold on
one second
I will try to remind myself right here
let's see
all right I have I have made a note
let's see what else we've got
I tried during on honest union strikes
trick and the compiler Agito screams at
me saying I need some label in the
struct name to conform to the standards
so I looked it up on Google and appears
to be undefined behavior chooses trick
should I be afraid of that well it
depends what you mean by afraid my
personal opinion is that I don't really
care about language specs or compliance
to them I really just care about what
compilers do or don't do and do or don't
accept so I typically just say and this
comes from two reasons one is because I
think the C and C both suspects are
awful I just don't agree with most of
the decisions they tend to make so I
would rather program in a language
that's closer to what I want and so if
compilers give me the option to turn off
things I just don't like like I never
want caught strings ever that's just not
something I ever want to have right you
know I want to be able to turn that off
as I can and I'll program to that you
know turned off ability it comes from
that but it also comes from a separate
thing which is when I was programming
probably mid-career I'd say so you know
not when I was learning to code when I
was a kid but you know roughly when I
first started working in the industry C
both Pirates were still bad that
they didn't obey the SEC anyway that
compliance was not a thing that that was
even remotely expected and you know you
never got that so it kind of my mental
states on that as always like the spec
is not the thing I have to work with the
spec is something that is for compiler
vendors and pedantic people the actual
thing that I sit down and type into is
the thing I'm trying to program and so I
need to know what those are and how they
work and what they create and what they
accept
we'll do you know so that's usually how
I approach it there are downsides to
that obviously and if that's if you have
a compiler that can literally only
accept exactly the spec you have a
problem I don't tend to worry too much
about that
because as far as I've been able to tell
you can always even if worse came to
worse you could run LLVM to transcode
your thing into C or something you know
I'd write a text translator or something
that would convert my code into
something that the compiler would accept
if that's what I had to do but I
wouldn't solve the problem by like
ruining a good like language features
that I find makes coding better just
because some people who make aspect
don't know what they're doing right
because if you did that every time man
you'd be really unhappy with your
programming because I mean there's a lot
of things in the spec that make a lot of
kinds of codes that you would think
would work properly or should probably
technically not work right that's the
whole undefined behavior nonsense that
you often see where people are like what
how did the why did the compiler do this
it's like well technically if you add
two numbers together that's undefined
behavior so anywhere your program adds
two numbers together well you know we
don't actually have to add them together
right you know and I'm exaggerating
obviously they're in for mocking effect
but you know you know what I mean
there's a lot of that kind of thing
let's see the cursor always seems to be
on the loading icon' is there a way to
fix that I'm running into this issue and
not sure if there is some Windows
message I need to process so I guess the
answer could be yes it could be no I'm
not sure so let's let's just really
quick to check its weight cursors are
more complicated than they should be in
Windows it's a it's a weird legacy kind
of a situation so let's take a look here
do we even process the set cursor
message we don't right now we only did
that on that weird overlay window thing
that midlow made us make that time let's
see here
so it looks like for whatever reason so
we are specifying it here right here's
the main window callback and we're
calling def window proc when the set
cursor call is coming through and it
looks like diff window proc is not
thinks we're still sending cursor now
that may mean that we just should have
done something else that could mean that
there's something we're not responding
to that we should respond to and I
wonder is there a Raymond Chen article
on this because you know one thing we
could do that would probably fix it
right is just set the cursor to the
arrow cursor in the case where we're
showing the cursor right so for example
here where we in our passing age cursor
here we're calling state cursor 0
because we don't want a cursor at all
here what we want to do is pass an
actual cursor so what we want to do is
say you know don't do this instead to a
set cursor here and what we want to do
is we want to load a sort of a an
arbitrary cursor right we don't want to
sets our own actual cursor so there's
built-in cursors you could load out of
Windows the H instance in this case when
you call load cursor is saying curious
the executable whose resource for con
look at to find this cursor we don't
want to do any that we don't want to
bundle a cursor inter executable like we
don't wanna put an image in there blah
blah blah right but what you can do is
if you specify 0 for the H instance you
can load out of the default set of
cursors and those are identified by
these IDs right so what you can do is
you can say make entry source which is a
macro and if it's well we can see what
it is but we can use the make entry
source macro and we can pass one of
these like the standard arrow cursor
right and so if we do that we should be
able to set the cursor to something
specific I would think all right well so
that's interesting
so it works but oddly enough we still
get a little bit of a loading thing so
there's still some some miscommunication
there I wonder if we have a problem with
responding to activate like if activate
has to return true
we really should look this up because
there is some set of things you're
supposed to do I don't know let me let
me take a look at what activate app
expects and what activate expects it
should return zero so that's probably
not they want let's see
Raymond 10 wait yes sir
yeah we should look I mean I remember
there being a thing and I don't know I
don't know how to search for it I
remember there being a thing that
basically said here is what Windows
looks for to determine whether it thinks
your app has finished loading and
there's like you know there's criteria
and I do not remember what they are
unfortunately so probably the answer is
yet there's just something we're not
responding to because you can see here
where we actually manually said set
cursor it responded to our set cursor
but it didn't actually seem to to take
fully it still thought we were loading
long after there's any way we could
still be considered loading right so one
thing I do want worry about here is you
know are we actually after create window
are we actually making our window active
or are we somehow not doing that quite
right and so like when we do toggle
full-screen here for example and we do
set window close I don't know that we
actually ever get the window activated
in that case so I wonder if we need to
like you know call activate window or
something like that called that's not
what it's called by the way except focus
maybe
you know maybe setfocus
so I'm not sure I'm just going to see to
play around with it here to see if I can
poke it into submission so that doesn't
help get rid of that now one thing
you'll notice is if I click which is
pretty interesting so it's not it's not
going away from wait cursor right it
stays on wait cursor if I click in here
it does so it's like activating the
window somehow is not properly happening
and I'm not really sure why that's the
case because clicking in the window
should really not do anything that
setting the active window doesn't do so
I'm trying to think of what it is that
it's actually that it's actually worried
about
and we could try set foreground window
I don't know
still no dice and so for whatever reason
yet it's like until we actually do that
click it doesn't work so I'm not sure
what exactly is going on there
I could try doing it repeatedly like I
wonder if there's something startup
related about that but it does it really
does seem like maybe there's a window
message that we're not responding to if
that makes sense
frosti ninja says you can set the cursor
on the wind class struct which dot h
cursor equals load cursor 0 rd c arrow
that's true
we can do that i would not have thought
that that would be different than
setting the cursor inside the set cursor
call but maybe it is so if we want to do
that here right oh but wait we are doing
that that's exactly what we are doing
when we do load cursor IDC arrow
shouldn't that be making resource ID
Ciara wonder if that's the problem now
so I really don't know I have no idea
I just we need to find that
documentation again because I guess what
I can tell you
let's see here so you said the stream
let's let's take the last question here
you said on the stream that you don't
need header guards because you have only
one translation unit
I guess you meant that you're sure you
only include each header once because
even if you only have one cancellation
you still can have a problem if you
include the same header twice well sure
but if you only have one translation
unit it's almost impossible to include
the same header twice because you just
include all the headers in one place
right so if you take a look at handmade
eh that's where all the headers are
included nobody else includes headers
right so you don't have to worry there's
only one list of includes basically I
mean technically we've got two because
we do the platform has some so there's a
couple in here I don't remember where I
thought they were oh maybe they're not
yeah here so technically there is one
extra one right but otherwise you know
you've just got a list and the same is
true for Hamid at CPP right like here's
where all the CPP files are so you know
forget headers CPP files is saying you
can't include them twice right but
there's no need to put an include guard
around them because you're just going to
list them there aren't going to ever be
any other pound includes you're just
going to list all your pound includes in
one place and that's dumb right that's
completely done so so yeah I think
that's it and now close this case I
asked about multiple anonymous unions
yeah but I'm not sure I thought we
covered that although maybe I'm missing
something I mean I guess I don't know
what you mean by multiple anonymous
unions but but if you look at like
and a platform where's our v2 at here we
go
so here is an example of multiple
anonymous trucks inside something and
multiple anonymous unions inside the
structure but not on the outside of the
struct I don't know if you're talking
about something other than that but that
is you know we do multiple anonymous all
the time
multiple anonymous is a very common
thing for us to do so
alright let's wrap it up
Wow no all right thank you everyone for
joining me for those sort of handmade
heroes and a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home you can always pre-order the
game on hand made here at Oregon it
comes with a source code so you can play
around with it you also have a forum
site you can go to if you want support
I'm sorry if you want to ask questions a
patreon page for about three or series a
schedule bot that tweets the question
the schedule at you if you want to know
we're going to be live and an episode
guide that helps you catch up on old
episodes I also wanted to take a moment
to announce that there is a new
supportable project that is related to
handmade hero and it's actually kind of
exciting there's a couple of these kind
of going on but I don't know of any
other ones that are supportable at the
moment so let me go ahead and show it to
you
it's on handmade network as a lot of
those projects are what you can see here
is a embeddable debugger that's being
worked on and the idea is to instead of
having you know a particular debugger
that you have to use and it's like oh
it's Visual Studio or whatever else the
idea is to build sort of a debugging
library that you can use where if you
want to put a debugger into something
else
right like a text editor that you
particularly like that happens to be
customizable say for coder in my case
you can use this library to quickly add
debugging features to that existing
editor and so this is really exciting
because if this worked out and you know
we had a good library we could use for
debugging we could completely get rid of
a lot of the stuff that we are currently
using like gdb front-ends and you know
visual studio and cetera et cetera and
so I would love to see a product like
this come to fruition where there's like
a clean good API library for debugging
and so everything that you know we might
want we can stick a debugger into and
have good debugging facilities would be
pretty awesome right
and it would also be part of the sort of
handmade Network school of thought there
so it would actually be something where
it cared about how the API was it would
be easily usable without you know
installing Python and all these other
sorts of things or who knows what the
typical kind of thing that you expect
when you install a library or try to use
a library right so you know I can't say
much about it yet other because it's you
know still pretty early in development
but it is kind of a really interesting
potential project and so if you're
interested in that it does have a
patreon I don't know what the easiest
way to get to it is probably just doing
like what I just did
but what you can do is you can go to the
patreon and support it and that would
presumably really help the project up
because if this number got higher a lot
more time would get spent on it it's
probably easiest to get there by just
putting ly s a dot handmade Network but
I also assume that if you just were on
handmade network you could also probably
find it in fact there it is on the front
page right now but it would be under the
project section so you could find it in
here if you forgot what it was called or
something like that right
so yeah just wanted to bring that to
your attention because I know that a lot
of people have been really good about
supporting stuff that we use on handmade
heroes for example for coders now very
well supported and that's really awesome
because I rely on it every day and so I
support it and I you know very much
appreciate that other people support it
because it means that we have a really
good editor now which I never had before
you know I had to use Emacs before and
it was not very good so you know if we
can get a few more projects like that
into position where it's like these are
really good alternative development
tools that are you know high quality and
that we can use that's I think that's
pretty awesome so hopefully you'll check
that out and and see if it's something
that you might want to support or be
involved with that's about it for this
weekend no this this today I guess I'll
be back here tomorrow sorry I haven't
had coffee yet today so my brains kind
of scattershot
surprise the programming went as well as
it did anyway I'll be back here tomorrow
and we'll take a look at doing some
multi sampling so that we can get rid of
some of those jaggies and we're pretty
good on artifacts now there's very
little artifact tang in the def peeler
rendering so it's pretty good
I'm feeling very good about the renderer
we might have to take a look at making
sure that like our cutscene stuff still
works but other than that I think we're
in pretty good shape and and we can do
it some more cleanup maybe the weekend
after and then and give it give it the
official seal of approval if that's the
render and off we go
all right thanks for joining me I'll see
you back here tomorrow till then have
fun programming I'll see you on the
Internet tegus everybody