hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here of the show recode a complete game
live on stream it is today 271 here or
hour 271 I don't know that we have a
tally of hours because there's been a
couple of times when we've done like a
four hour stream so it's probably
actually our 280 or 290 but yesterday I
think I accidentally started programming
some game code I don't super like game
code I think I've said this before I
like engine programming and so but one
of the things you have to do if you're
shipping a game by yourself is you have
to write the game code as well so what
are you gonna do so I started doing that
and I think I'm gonna go ahead and
finish doing some of that stuff and
that's also useful engine wise as well
anyway because everything else that we
do probably from now on is gonna be
pretty heavily dependent on the game and
so you know I don't want to like like
all the rest of our engine work I think
will be based on exactly how it's
getting used in the game so we'll be
like like getting the game of running
we'll see what slow and what works and
what doesn't work and we'll look improve
the engine components based on that
because I think in terms of general
stuff we've got everything in there
that's that we would normally have and
so it's just a question of like driving
things forward by having specific use
cases so if you want to follow along at
home to today's day 271 so day two
seventies code is the code that you're
going to want to unpack and start with
and that's where I am at at the moment
now if you remember from yesterday what
I was talking about when I was like I
want to get the movement code working
and then some of the world generation
stuff working what I was trying to
explain and what we sort of started to
implement as well I started cleaning
some stuff up is that I want to have
specific locations in the world that you
stand on and unlike even a traditional
tile mapped game these really don't have
very much to do with the graphics
necessarily although we are going to
want to reinforce them by making sure
the graphics clearly show you where the
places are you can stand but that's a
game design concern
engine technology concern what we want
to do here is I want to make it so that
you literally stand directly on these
points and when you move you choose to
move between these points specifically
and you're either on one or the other
when you come to rest so you're not
allowed to come to rest like in the
middle right you can't stand in between
those two points obviously to get from
one to the other you will cross between
them but you won't ever like like land
here you have to land here or here and
so the way that we've got things right
now right all we do is just move kind of
a sprite around so what we need to do is
we need to sort of improve that that way
in which the movement happens so that
we're going to like move around in that
way and that's what I want to sort of
get working and I want to sort of start
to build out the little world
environments so that I can have some
examples of moving around and places to
start rendering and that sort of stuff
so right now we're drawing those points
in the world that I've created and those
points are attached to entities so
essentially we've got entities that
represent places you stand and those
places that you stand have these sort of
traversable points marked on them and so
as you move around the idea is that
wherever you're going to go you're going
to go to one of those traversable points
so what I'm going to do now is I'm going
to sort of modify the way that the hero
moves a little bit and it's going to be
a little bit terrifying at first to say
the least so what I'm going to do here
is I am going to essentially dissociate
the hero head and the hero body if that
makes sense so when I come into handmade
world mode here what I want to do is I
want to we add right one of these hero
things whenever somebody joins the game
whenever a hero joins the game we were
currently adding one of these hero
entities and I believe
actually to be honest with you don't
really remember it's been a long time I
don't super remember how we chose to
mark that but I believe it was just
called here yeah so we add one of these
entity type heroes so if you take a look
let's see here entity type hero
where we at it's here
so when we do an ad player you can see
that we do a thing where we say like
okay we added an entity and we add an
entity type hero and that entity type
hero is just one entity and what I kind
of want to do here is say that there's
two separate entity types that I'm kind
of deal with here that are going to be a
little different
there's essentially an entity type hero
and then like here a body and an ende
type hero head that makes sense and I
know it's a little bit strange to be
honest I guess I don't I guess here's
the thing there's two ways I guess I can
do it maybe I'll keep it as one entity I
can make it two entities or one and I'm
not sure which one makes more sense I
feel like two is better I'm just gonna
say it's two so I'm gonna make a hero
body and a hero head just for now and so
when you add these to the game I'm gonna
say that you you know you get both of
them right so I'm gonna add a hero head
and I hear a body and those are going to
be added separately and I I'm gonna
actually change these like player
collision things to be a little bit
different so that you know the hero head
is has a collision that's high and the
hero body has a collision that's low if
that makes sense yeah and so when we
actually record the entity I'm going to
say that the hero body
is the thing that has the information on
it for now and I'm not going to actually
put any more information on this for the
time being although you know we could do
a little more but we're gonna do the
entity system probably coming up soon
here and this stuff will all change cuz
this is pretty you know basic right now
and really just there for us to sort of
get things working so when I do this I'm
now gonna have some compile errors
because there's stuff that depends on
this sort of thing
again I don't know too much we care
about this break point but we'll leave
it in there for now and when we're
looking here you can see how the control
works I'm just gonna make it so the hero
head is actually the thing that you
control pretty much the entire time and
I'm gonna say that the hero body is the
thing for now v that the familiar looks
for and then here we've got our entity
type hero ahead again same thing here
and then what I'm gonna do is I'm just
gonna not push the rest of the bitmaps
on so you know for example I can in fact
I'll just flip them for now I guess
right so here is my entity type like
your body and that will actually push
the other things on there like so and
yeah we won't draw the hip points on the
head so here's a shadow here's the torso
here's the Cape but the head is gone and
then this one will probably not have any
of these at the moment and we'll just
push just that head on so that we can
see it and the particle code I think
needs to not be right here because this
is kind of annoying so the hero head
particle code is going to go away and
we'll just put that you know like file
somewhere do we have a file that we
could put that in sort well you know
what I could do I can just put it down
here
case we ever wanted again right and so
now the problem that I'm going to face
is I'm like these things are gonna be
overlapping and kind of colliding with
each other so I won't really be able to
actually use it the way that I would
like because like all those be
constantly colliding so I can't actually
move so what I need to do is I need to
fix the colliders for these two entities
you can see here that we've got like
player collision what I really want to
call this is like here a body collision
and like hero head collision and so in
the places where we were storing these
where we have kind of player collision
and you know I'm gonna do hero head and
here a body and then we can make that
more explicit so here's euro head
collision here is euro body collision
and I want to make sure that the yeah I
don't really this all this stuff we
should probably start to work out but
again I'm kind of taking it one step at
a time as I pull it up into a the place
where it's actually doing what we want
for the game so this may not be the best
way to make collision volumes either
because they're kind of a little bit
aspect weirdly but anyway the hero head
collision in the hero body collision you
know this was the height of the thing
before and you know I don't know how big
we want them each to be but I feel like
since its kind of a little bit you know
fungible there I'm gonna say that like
the body is six and the head is like
four or whatever and maybe there's point
two in between them I don't know right
I'm not sure how we actually want that
to work out maybe there's only point one
in between them something like this okay
and so when we now talk about the hero
head the hero head itself I want that I
don't really want the grounded collision
thing because it's actually up off the
ground right is where the head is
so a drownded let's see here where is
that simple grounded collisions there it
is so one of these grounded collision
things the problem with it is I don't
really want it to be on the ground but
as you can kind of see it is gonna be on
the ground because of the way that the
offset P stuff works right so it's gonna
be I want to now raise it up by that
displacement which what I couldn't like
you know I can sort of make a
displacement here but I guess what I
probably would want to do instead is
just make something that's I don't
really know what I want to do to be
honest I'm gonna put an offset Z in here
just for an up for no apparent reason so
if we want to lift it off the ground we
can make simple grounded collision and
so in here when we do the hero head
since it's 0.6 off the ground I'm gonna
go ahead and say it's 0.7 I guess
because it's got that one a bit of
displacement and so now in theory they
should be disconnected now okay
so now I can't move those so I didn't
quite get everything right there so
let's go see what the problem is there
so curieux head collision I just want to
make sure this is set up properly Hiro
head has the your head collision here a
body has the here of body collision
right right
and the body's got the hit points the
moment which is what I wanted and let's
see the the
cameras following the body which seems
okay and I'm gonna now go see what the
deal is with my hero head so in the hero
head here is where we loop over the
controllers and we look to see this is
kind of weird but anyway like I said all
this stuff now will start to clean up so
it's okay if it's weird
I'm just looking through here so if we
have the hero head I'm not sure we just
take the DDP and we're adding it to it
and I guess that's all fine because the
DDP is presumably applied yeah at the
bottom so there's the move entity call
right and the move entity call is just
gonna try and move by that GDP so we're
definitely trying to move by the DDP and
so the question is why are we colliding
with anything so the first thing that I
want to do is I want to verify my
assumptions or rather I want to test to
see whether the grab the collision
volumes are what's preventing me from
doing this and so what I might do is say
let's assume that the body at the moment
the hero body collision is actually not
a Collider and so now there's only the
hero head and so in theory I feel like
that would make it so that if collision
was our problem the head would move and
the head is not moving right so it seems
to me that that is just broken right and
that something else is broken that's not
necessarily the collision that I
accidentally changed there and you know
I can also say I could also say here I
suppose if they're both no so now these
cannot collide with anything they could
just move around in theory they'll just
move
yeah and again no no movement at all in
fact no control of any kind so I think
something's still busted there and I'm
not sure what the deal is with that so
well actually you know what let me let
me add this back in in case that's also
a problem we'll just take it out of the
equation for now
so when we call ad player here and we're
gonna do
adding obscenities here we add the hero
body ah that's the problem the thing
that we return is what the controller is
going to control so that's probably
that's probably the issue right there so
although this is the thing we wanted
yeah although we wanted the body to be
the thing that we had the hit points on
right and that sort of thing I kind of
have to make it so that the rest of this
stuff isn't that way so this is going to
be right that's gonna be body and then
here is ad low entity result head and
the head is what's actually going to get
returned here see what else we've got
this body and that was a bug as well
there too okay so this is this is head I
guess but the sword is not our hero
doesn't even have a sword so I'm not
sure why that's even there anymore but I
guess that's beside the point anyway so
we're gonna follow the body like I said
for now and that seems fine so now we
should be connected properly at least I
hope Oh
famous last words and we totally aren't
so wait head is the head and we are
returning the head right so when we do
add player that should capture the head
properly right yeah there's entity index
right there so in theory the conure and
the index should be now set to whatever
that head index is right which was
obviously a bug from before but
we weren't yeah we weren't actually
using it so alright so in here what did
I do wrong what more did I do wrong
let's see so we tried to add a grounded
entity for the hero body and for the
hero head we track them both as body and
head we add the flags for nope that
would do it okay all right good so now
we have head that can move around which
is always good very very important and
now what I want to do is I want the body
to follow the head if that makes sense
so as the head moves around I want the
body to move with it but what I want to
do is I want to make it so that when the
body moves the body only moves to two
traversable x' so you know the head as
the head moves I want the body to just
go to the closest like the closest
traversable to where the head is that
makes sense so I'm gonna start by
essentially cheating that out so during
the sim I'm actually going to to make
this be quite a bit like I'm gonna make
this be super crappy and not the way
that I want or anything I just want to
get it working in a basic capacity so
when we go through and do the simulation
on these guys when we do the simulation
on the the hero head and we're just
moving them around right which is here
then what I want to do is whenever we're
simulating one of the hero body things I
want it to just look to see for the
other entities that are in the world and
this is going to be the same kind of to
do basically we're doing exactly the
same thing here but instead
searching the entities for entities
which we want to follow or things like
that instead what I'm going to search
for is I'm going to search for any kind
of traversable point so I'm just gonna
search through the entities to try and
find mm-hmm by the way why is by his
tests entity index kept here oh I guess
it's just for this yeah I don't know
anyway so as we go through these test
entities I want to see whether or not my
corresponding curio head is is in there
and that I want to follow it now I'm
sorry that's not what am I talking about
I want to take a look to see if any of
these things have collision volumes that
have traversable points in them if that
makes sense
so we're going to essentially go through
all of those now I believe everyone has
to have a collision volume so really all
I'm gonna do here is say like point
index and I want this to be less than
the volume go ahead and jump in here so
we hat we're gonna have one of these
collision value groups I'm going to go
through the traversable points that are
here right
and those traversable points are the
things I'm going to check so I've got
the traversable count here I'm going to
get the sim entity traversable point out
of it the reversible point and yeah I
guess this is actually the group and I'm
just gonna say okay whatever this vol
group's traversable z-- is I'm going to
add the P index of that and that's the
one I'm going to check here and I'm
gonna see if this if this P index is
closer than mine right so I'm going to
say whatever this entity's position is
right plus its position this way and
really that's a thing that could rotate
and do other things so we probably want
to get in the habit of actually getting
these sort of transform for us so we
probably want this way or like since
paced reversible or something like that
so I probably want to say like okay in
this sim space I want to take you know
this entity and I want to get a this
particular traversable out of them right
and then I want that to transform it for
me by whatever the entity sort of
transform stuff is and so once I have
one of those points what I can do is I
can test to see how close it is to my
head right wherever my head actually is
which does require me knowing what my
attached head is if that makes sense and
so that's something that we're gonna
want to store presumably
so in here oops if I want the attached
head the attached head is gonna be
something it will figure out in a second
and I'm gonna know what it's P is so I'm
just gonna assume that like my best
distance is real 30 to maximum right I'm
gonna assume that my best distance is
very far away and my best P is whatever
my current P is so my entity P is is
that right so then what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna say all right we're assuming
that we have the head I'm gonna say
here's my test point I want to get the
distance squared and I guess this is
I'll just do distance squared here right
so it's exactly the same code as this in
fact it's literally this exact code this
is all I'm doing I'm just saying like
all right go through here and say for
this point I want to take the distance
from wherever my head was to wherever
this point is that we're talking about
here and I want that to that to be
considered the closest point to stand on
right now there is I guess a caveat here
which is that the point can't be above
the hero's head because then I'd be like
so it has to be below the hero's head so
it probably would also say if the P if
the Z position like yeah if the Z
position of the head was or I should say
if the Z position of the traversable so
whatever that Z value is is greater than
wherever the the head placement was I
would ignore it although you know I'm
not gonna put that in just yet because
since we're still a little ad hoc with
coordinates think that's only gonna make
things worse
we'll take care of that we'll cross that
bridge when we come to it all right so
anyway I'm going to take the link
squared here I'm going to say that we
have the closest distance squared and
the closest P so here's my closest
distance squared and my closest key is
going to be equal to that P that we're
looking at the one we're talking about
and the closest distance squared is
going to be the test distance squared so
once we have that I'm just gonna go
ahead and set that so for now we're not
gonna try to do any even any animation
to it I'm just going to literally say to
get it working first I want to take
whatever my position is and I'm just
gonna cold set myself directly to it
right so that's all I'm gonna do okay um
so yeah so now when we go through here
and we say
what's the head because that's gonna be
our main problem here right is our head
doesn't that we don't know what our own
head is our because our volume group
collisions volume group is is actually
fine we do know where that is that's
just this thing right there's collision
so our sim entity collision volume group
it's just that so the question is where
is the head empty
right and so the way they're gonna do
that again from now is I'm just gonna
use we do have this enemy reference
concept but again that's probably all
this is gonna get changed but so I'm
just gonna put entity reference head in
here and again that's on all entities so
keep in mind like that means even your
head has a head of reference which again
obviously like I said we're gonna be
redoing that stuff so you'll will we'll
talk more about how that sort of stuff
works a little bit later on but anyway
for now we don't care we just want
something that works reasonably and so
in order to get the sword you can kind
of see here how this works really all we
have to do because those references I
guess work in a particular way all we
have to do is say okay the head entity
is just going to be whatever our
entities head pointer is it should give
us back that and we're gonna assume that
we have one if we don't have one like if
we just don't have a head because our
head got chopped off or something maybe
we would use some other code here right
but for now we'll just only we'll just
stay stationary if we can't find our
head and so inside our synonymy stuff
you can see where the sword thing
happens is actually some code that makes
this happen you can see the
decompression step stuff here how that
works you can see store entity reference
and load entity reference those are both
things that need to actually happen so
in here we need to do a load entity
reference
rolled mode sim raven entity head
and same thing below door entity
reference stored so now all we really
have to do is implement this and this is
pretty straightforward actually right
now because we actually don't have the
concept of entity rotation in here at
all right so sim region itself we can
sort of have in here this this concept
that there is a way to get the traversal
traversable back and this is a really
simple operation all this is saying is
that if you take a cement ax T and one
of these indexes you can basically take
this cement a traversable point that you
would get if you looked at the collision
group and we can assert here that this
index is within the range that's allowed
because we know the traversal count so
you might say hey make sure that's
actually valid when we get this result
out we can then take the P that it has
and we're just going to transform it by
offsetting by the enemy's speed and we
could say like you know to do this wants
to be rotated eventually because at some
point we probably want to the concerts
that entities can turn and that they're
their points that you would stand on
would turn like if you imagine there
maybe there's some like platform with
some points you can stand on and it's
kind of moving throughout the world
right it makes sense to say that that's
you know going to rotate or spin
potentially so okay we've got this
traversal account situation and
and now we've done that transform so now
let's see if we can get the body moving
the way that the body should move the
other thing that I would like to do by
the way oh well there's one other thing
we have to do which is actually set up
that head head reference because we've
met we've not told the body about its
head yet kind of a funny phrase but so
if I go back to world mode where we do
add player right where we construct one
of these things we've got this sort of
body head situation and what I want to
do here is exactly the same thing that
was done here I want to say like oh okay
the body's low sim head index is going
to be the heads index so now it knows
which one it's talking about and so
there we go
textures what's going out those textures
what's going on we're caught in a loop
oh that's good yeah turns out for loops
don't really work super well this is
this is the pro tip you know from an
experienced programmer sometimes if you
don't increment the variable in the for
loop it won't work as well I mean I
don't know like it's probably some bug
in the in the CPU or something you know
but like you got to increment it or
something I don't know it's stupid oh
hey that works actually exactly the way
I wanted to but unfortunately I'm
setting the camera up to move in the old
style way so what I actually don't want
that anymore I want the camera to stay
room based yeah okay so now we've got
that working much more like I wanted it
to work actually that's that's quite
nice actually yes
and so in theory - the other thing
that's nice is this is not based on the
grid so this is actually something that
works regardless of whether there's a
grid or not right and it's also kind of
nice in that the body won't follow
beyond where there are actually
traversable points which is also kind of
good so that's fine you know what I also
should do though I should also reenable
the collision for the things that
collide there we go okay so for the
things that collide here now we've got
now we've got that oh I and let me go
ahead and set this permanently that's a
room based so that's global render
camera room based I don't actually know
where we set that room based
sit in the same region yeah so is that
mean config dot H I guess so we just
need to say that the room based stuff is
true now all right so yeah so much
better so now when we start up it should
be fine
the other thing that I'm gonna do that I
would like to do is when we actually
start up right now one of the things
that we're doing is we're going into the
cutscene but since we're working on the
game part of the game right now I would
like to make it so that we start up
directly into the game because that's
gonna make it like save me a lot of time
when I'm starting up right so what I'd
like to do too is you know you've got
this game state game mode here right and
by default it does the play intro
cutscene and so that's all fine and good
but I'm just like that's what it should
be it's just for now I would rather make
it be like play game or whatever in fact
I don't even remember what it actually
is to start that it's like what is it
play title screen play world that's what
it's called so I'm just gonna call play
world at the outset instead so that when
we start we're just looking at the game
directly hopefully anyway just play I
thought play world would set up the
world is that not true
that should that should set up the world
for us should it not
hmm although that does always come
inside here but I don't think that
should have mattered I'm not to see what
that because I think we this should be
allowed and so the fact that that
doesn't work is bad so let's fix that so
the problem here is that world mode is
null and I'm not sure why let's jump in
here so there's world mode when does it
actually set game state world mode
that strikes me as a little bit peculiar
because here it is creating world mode
we come through here we create a bunch
of stuff that we need to make the world
and so that's great you know everyone's
happy and that's fine but after we do
that I don't see us actually assigning
it ever to the actual word a load
variable so how does that ever how did
this ever happen how is that world mode
supposed to get communicated I'm super
confused hopefully I'm not the only
person who thinks that's confusing so
let's take a look here so you can see
update and render world
it passes game state world node but I
don't know when people write to game
state world mode
the answer is never so how was this ever
working does someone want to explain
that to me this is weird enough that I
just want to make sure we know why so
here's the old version it's great and
run it and here's me launching the game
and the game is working right we could
all agree on that I think so my question
is all right
how was game where you know who is
actually initializing this and so let's
actually in fact we talked about data
break points where we're talking about
in the about debugging let's actually
use a data breakpoint here to find out
how that was ever happening so let's say
we come down here and right now I've got
my game state and presumably world mode
is not not valid right
like there's nothing in it although
there is there is a pointer to a world
mode so the actual mode itself exists
but the world pointer does not right
wait let me jump back over here as well
so here is a world med that's okay right
cuz it does a push struct here and it
pushes on this world mode but I don't
know why in fact let's go into the
cutscene just for one second - I want to
see how this one's how this one does it
you can see like this like sets it right
and this one - like it sets it up so I
don't even know I want to know - like
who whoever set this up at all why is
there even a pointer in there in the
first place I'm gonna start all the way
back like when did that happen
I guess the game mood
yeah I don't know so I'm gonna start all
the way back to the beginning so here we
go we have not initialized the game
state so we're going to initialize the
game state now so here's the game state
and the world mode has nothing in it so
we come through here there is nothing in
it still nothing
so the world mode is just empty which is
what we would have expected it to be we
create some stuff for our task transient
modes all that stuff it's all good
we creates environment maps which was
nine things we use anymore but there
they're good for them we've put some
debug arenas in place just for fun
we're sorry we print them out and then
we actually start going on with our with
our situation oh okay
that's just a union so that's fine
that's actually totally fine
so that's crazy so I know exactly how
this is working now that's just super
accidental so here's what actually
happened what actually happened is we
just it just so happens that if we've
already allocated the other mode we
happen to put ourselves in exactly the
same place so we didn't have to set the
pointer like I bet this just turns in
this address is exactly where it happens
to push the other mode let's find out so
here's our cutscene we're running
we're running along right and I started
up and now I want to know hey where is
that world mode hey look it's exactly
the same place so that was pure luck
there's actually a total line of missing
code that's a incredibly important
that's straight-up not there this thing
this exactly needs to be in here right
so here is it working now and then if I
was to change back to what I wanted to
do before oops
yeah and that was right turn off the
cutscene now it should actually work
because someone's actually setting that
value although that that actually that
actually did not go to the world mode
that went to the title screen we are
setting the game mode to world so in
theory that should call this yeah and
I'm not hitting escape or anything oh
but you know what when there's no
players when there's no players we just
revert back to the title screen so I
guess there is a problem of will enter
game mode and then go back to social
because there's no players so I guess
that is a little bit of a problem how
are we getting around that though
I guess we're we just counting on the
fact that you happen to push the same
button because it seems like yet all
we're doing here is real like hey this
guy started and he's gonna start playing
the game so then in the other code in
world mode it hasn't no one's actually
joined the game yet right and so what
happens is when it gets down to the
bottom I think it's just like oh like
there's no heroes so go back to the
title screen which is exactly what does
so I guess I need to also force it to
start a new hero which I guess actually
isn't that hard because I can do like I
can force an initial controller press of
start if I want to so that's not really
a huge deal but we may want to I don't
know if since this is only really for
debug I suppose that's not really a huge
deal but still it's not great probably
want to make it more formal so I can say
like play world and add player but you
know I can do this and say like
controller your back like ended down or
something
so I could in theory force it to be like
oh yeah and by the way someone pushed
start right and I'm not sure if I can
actually get away with that exactly but
I should be able to do something so
let's see uh-oh it's actually starting
that back start so I'm basically just
like over writing the actual input with
the start button so that it adds one
hero so it's as if someone pushed start
and I suppose for that matter
technically that means that really you
can actually have play cutscene have
actually happened and we don't actually
have to call play world what I can do is
just say like oh you know if I want to
like force the start button to be
pressed
I just force to start button to be
pressed and we actually start in the
game even though we don't force it to
start with the other mode so that's fine
I'm fine with that
all right so now I'm just gonna say well
okay like I kind of want to see uh I
want to see what what our DT per frame
is here I want to check out the DT per
frame also somebody reported a bug that
is relevant here I don't know if I can
go to github can I sign in there we go
so if I'm here on github how do I get to
the issues issues there it is so hmm
someone was saying that DT forever so
has won over mono refresh rate over to
this off by a factor of two or more
Effie sink is disabled so that I think
that means that we're passing probably
because of some thing debug oriented or
you know whatever that we were doing
yeah so this is a good catch by Kim
because this is just some stuff that we
work sort of hacking in there and before
we ever did vsync or any of that sort of
stuff and we really want this to
actually start passing an accurate value
because if we're gonna start making game
code we need to sort of have the game
running at the proper or frame rate
right so what we need to do now is say
that well the game update Hertz is gonna
be whatever it is for now
right and let's see where this actually
gets used target seconds for frame yeah
so at the moment if we're just always on
vsync which we are for all of our
testing purposes that should be the
actual amount that's correct
yeah so it was a little bit
before of course that also means our
cutscene timing is probably off
well that actually kind of looks fine we
don't really have any we haven't tried
to sync the cutscene to an audio track
or anything like that yet so I guess
it's going to depend the speed of each
of these things is going to depend
entirely on how we want you know how we
decide to or rather how long the audio
ends up being all right so that's
actually more the speed that I thought
it should be as well so that's good I'm
glad we've got that squared away if that
makes sense but I I guess I'm almost out
of time so I'll probably end up there
but I also just want to do a little bit
of a test here with the the hero's body
I want to see what happens if I animate
him a little bit from point to point
right so let's say in here in world mode
dot cpp and here's my sim region so I'm
going to go ahead and say like okay I've
got the the P and I'm just going to say
there's like
well I guess you know what I can even
just do it in a simpler fashion for now
I guess all I really do is I'm just
gonna run that code that was on the
familiar so you can see that we had this
this sort of DP is based on the distance
from the hero
kind of thing and I guess we just set
the move spec for this guy I'm gonna set
those all for the for the hero body so
assuming that we had the head what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna instead of setting
the end of these P to the closest P I'm
just gonna use the exact same code that
we were using before and I'm not gonna
do any of this stuff I'm just gonna say
like whatever whatever it was it's gonna
be doing the square root of course this
value we need to make sure we actually
ever I guess we need to make sure we
actually found somebody because
otherwise the square root term will be
kind of ridiculous right because this
will be real 30 to maximum so yeah I
mean we could make this close to
distance square it'd be some thing that
was like we don't ever want to move if
the head gets further than this away
right we could say like oh if it's if
it's more than a thousand meters away
then obviously it's not gonna happen and
then this term won't blow up and it'll
be fine so that's probably fine as well
so I want to take a look at this
hello mr. movement so my DDP poopy -
entity pee why are you not accelerating
and I'm not sure why aren't you
accelerating is si is this because of
the collision
are you colliding with something right
now I don't actually know what turn off
your collision for now let's see - turn
off your collision would be pretty
simple I would just say the entity
collision equals world mode no collision
right so it's not a collision problem
you're not colliding with anything but
you're also not going anywhere
why aren't you going anywhere
okay so let's take a look at what the
various key values are so there's
closest to P and M - V P yes so those
are like nothing like each other and so
in theory they should be that should be
enough to move the guy so what's the DDP
the DDP is a totally valid value I'm not
sure
so that should have worked is movable
not set movable set so what's the
problem
so he's moving at that speed whoa
move speck drag times entity DP my
entity DP is complete garbage how did
that happen so if something went
horribly wrong closest distance squared
is whatever this is so something bad
happened there let's let's take a look
at the first time through this loop
hopefully before that ever gets messed
up so let's let's jump in here so here's
the first time through Oh duh when
they're right on top of each other that
wouldn't work either right right right
okay so that was that was just be being
stupid if these things are too close
together then obviously it can't move so
I do still want that ability right so I
would that was me being dumb so the
closest distance squared that closest
does have to be we were checking for we
were checking to make sure it wasn't too
close and and I just spaced on that for
some reason
okay so now if I like we're gonna I'm
gonna want to animate that a much much
better but I just want to kind of see
what that ends up being like so if we
assume I don't know why acceleration
what acceleration has to do with it
because this is actually the thing that
determines the speed so that's I'm not
sure I feel like the familiar code was a
little bit janky in that case cuz it
doesn't really need to do what it's
doing here and in fact none of this
stuff really makes any sense because
this code takes care of all this so
really this is irrelevant to some degree
I think right I'm pretty sure that that
actually this this doesn't ever need to
happen I think you can just say that
this is what you actually wanted the DDP
to be in fact I don't know can you just
do this directly and just say that's
what this is
I feel like you can't yeah that's what I
thought
so that familiar code is just stupid I
don't know why it was bothering because
that code actually does it for it
okay and so if I want to I can make this
guide track very pretty closely right
and if I make this drag oops
relatively high I can make it probably
feel pretty neat there that might be a
little too high though
so that's roughly what I wanted and so
like we're gonna have to make that
animate correctly but in terms of like
actually the speed at which this was
going to go that's roughly what I had
envisioned and I think that's going to
be fine
yeah so there's a couple other things in
here which we'll try tomorrow just in
terms of getting this guy going but then
but that seems to be working relatively
well and that I can move around just
fine and you know my body will track me
but it will never you know it will never
my body will never come to rest on
anything that isn't one of these
traversable 's and so then really the
only other thing I need to do other than
making working on animation for how
that's gonna you know for making that
look nice because I so we don't want
like a detached head and all that but
all I really need to do now is just make
it so that this I want the head to snap
back to the body when you stop pushing
so when I'm pushing right like around
this this is correct
but then when I let go I want it to come
back to where it would normally be
neutral if that makes sense
so all right let's go to the QA
UHN when I write event-driven code I am
often forced to use dynamic memory
allocation to preserve some state until
it is needed by the callback how do you
deal with those situations I guess it
depends on the circumstances obviously
but there's a couple things first of all
dynamic memory allocation isn't bad
right it's just you should make sure you
know like what you're actually doing so
my first question is can you just use a
simple free list like we use that's
usually like basically you could think
of it this way a general-purpose
allocator is usually just a bunch of
free lists that a bunch of additional
code has to run to figure out what free
lists to use when you need some memory
right and then it has to split things up
and merge them together and do all this
extra work most times even with dynamic
memory you can be like well you know
most of the things I do are about 64
bytes long and I usually only have about
a thousand of them total so I can just
use a free list with of things that are
a thousand bytes you know 1k or whatever
and oh and I'm done right and everything
that allocates something just grabs one
of those and pretends the size is
whatever the size we actually want and
then does it and then you return it back
to the free list then you have literally
no memory allocation overhead whatsoever
right it's like two instructions or
something you know to make this happen
well two sources like ten instructions
to allocate and ten instructions to free
or something and you know nothing can
ever go wrong right there's no there's
no possibility of fragmentation there's
no possibility that you run out of
memory there's no nothing you just know
like that's commit so I would say like
don't like I would never think of things
in terms of how do I avoid dynamic
memory allocation in the sense of
sometimes I need one of these as some as
I don't that's perfectly fine and a very
normal thing in programming the question
is just do you actually need a full
general-purpose allocator and is that
really the best way to write the code or
are you just using it because you like
learn to call new and delete at some
point and never really thought through
what the program was actually doing you
know are those actually the best way to
do this thing right
would the hammock debug view enable
viewing strux like world mode yeah you
can print out any value that you want so
if you wanted to see the stuff in the
world mode you could print it out
long boolean when moving diagonally will
it be clear to the player which way the
body will go to get to the diagonal
entity right now it seems kind of random
so I guess I guess I don't know if it
will be clear or not and I guess what I
would say about that is I don't know if
you'll even be allowed to move
diagonally if that makes sense I'll have
to think about that you may just not be
allowed to move diagonally we'll see
what I'll probably do what I'll probably
do is make a decision at some point
about what we what it feels like because
that's a very feel oriented thing I'll
make a decision about what it feels like
and when I if I decide that moving to
agonal feels good then we'll probably
just make the picking code for these B
so that in this middle area here if you
hit here it does the diagonal so that it
it never goes to either of those when
you move diagonally it won't like it
won't look because you can see that
actually sometimes it does actually do
the straight diagonal more or less
because it it go it picks this guy you
get to this guy before it ever really
goes to one of these so I could make it
so that it would pick the diagonal in
here if it wanted to like I could I
could hack soar that in fact actually
it'd be really easy to do that I think
already
so there's there's a there's two ways
that we could do this right so the way
that I'm doing it right now is I'm
looping over the points and choosing a
point based on which one is closest to
my head's position but there's a
different way that I could do it right I
could do us a very different thing here
what I could do instead is I could
create the direction like desired
direction and the desired direction
would be what's my heads position - my
current position and that's like a
vector from the body to the head right
and so then what we would do is when we
actually do this testing instead of
testing the length so instead of testing
the distance between them what I'll do
instead is I would test how closely does
moving to this point align with my
movement in the direction of that I'm
pointing right so if I look in this
direction which points do I see closest
to like that that heading right and so I
can weight that factor in there so that
would just be that's just an inner
product right so I can do like a dweet
we have normalized zero right I'm
assuming do
so we don't have normalized zero man all
right well so there's a function that I
like which is called normalizer zero and
what that is is it's basically an
automatic epsilon check it sort of says
well okay figure out what the length of
this thing is right and if that length
is not greater than some like you know
it's gonna be I don't know what we want
as our epsilon there but if the length
is greater than that then actually do
the normalize otherwise just return zero
right so basically we just say like okay
the result does equal what it would
normally equal but only in the case
where I have have determined first that
it won't blow up if I do that so it'll
just become the zero vector normalizer
unit is another example that would
return a unit vector instead and so if
we have this desired direction in here
then what I can do is I can inner
product that right with I can take the
inner product of that direction with the
direction to the various points so in
this case like I can have or I should
say test direction maybe test Delta is a
better name for this this is going from
I guess lovely name these more
explicitly so this is head to point
right and this is body to point right so
this is the vector that goes from from
my head to the point and this is the
vector that goes from my baudet body to
the point right so if I want to know how
far away I am I can test the length of
the vector head to point which is what
we were doing and that's the previous
way we were working on it but if I want
to know whether or not moving to this
thing would be roughly in the same
direction as the head is from me then I
can add another term here which is like
you know my test direction and that's
just the inner product of the body to
point and the desired direction now the
problem is this thing will be scaled by
how far away the thing actually is so
it'll be you know it'll be the cosine of
the angle between them right so it would
be one if it was directly pointed in the
same direction negative one if it's the
opposite direction zero if it's
perpendicular right but then it's gonna
be scaled by the distance and
unfortunately for us we don't actually
want that because that would mean that
it gets higher as it gets further away
which we would actually want if anything
the opposite of that so in addition we
probably want to normalize that vector
as well so now we just have a measure of
how closely it's pointing towards us
right so now we can sort of say like oh
the closest distance squared is not
really closest distance squared anymore
you know it could be close distance
squared and it could be you know we can
now use this test direction to say well
it's got to be the closest thing and it
also has to be like within some some you
know reasonable range so this thing in
fact I suppose since this is the more
expensive operation I could put it on
the inside too and I'd say well alright
if it's if
it's better than the previous closest
thing that we've got then what we'll do
because we're not going to take it
otherwise or whatever then what we'll do
is say well let's also see whether it's
within sort of that desired direction so
here's our test direction we want to say
it's it's pretty close maybe to that
what did I do here yeah so now we kind
of filter out on something that's got to
be roughly in the same direction as the
head is pointing right
I'm not sure why that is able to stand
in the middle
oh I understand why it's able to say in
the middle yeah
so this closest P also I guess has to
always be like this has to be wherever
it thinks it's going to be standing so
in order to in order to not always pick
the closest point we would also have to
do this
so yeah that's something that we would
want to store for future use or we would
always pick both so we'd say like if we
haven't picked yet like you know we'd
say pick 10 equals false or whatever and
then I suppose in here we would say
something like ok if if the closest is
we do we'd say if we haven't picked any
or the test Direction is greater than
that then we'd say pick 10 equals equals
the tester oops something like that
oops let's take a look see if that was
any better
so I'm not sure why I get that sort of
wiggliness there I guess yeah I'm still
not quite doing that correctly so I
would need to do a little bit more there
I need to say like like I said I need to
know like where you're going and then I
need to like pick a new one based on
that but it's pretty much that's this is
rough for the code I just need a little
more time to get it a little bit better
but basically like if you haven't picked
any if none of them have been in like
off in the direction then you still want
to keep the closest one but if you
haven't picked any if you haven't found
one that actually does pass the tester
test then yeah then off you go but I
kind of think I mean I guess it's
because as you move
yeah I guess what I would say is I need
a little more time to write that well
because there's actually a number of
reasons why I also want to be able to
know like I'm coming from here I need to
know that old point because I'm always
gonna want to use the old point the
original point that you start from and
since we're gonna have to do a bunch of
animation stuff here anyway I guess what
I would say is yeah that's not good
enough so I'm gonna leave it the way
that it was before it cuz this is this
is not good enough to actually replace
it yet but we can eventually replace it
so there's the original back again but
it won't be too hard it's just a
question of having the right variables
so we can know what it was that you know
that you were sort of doing and again I
also want like I said the head is going
to have to do some snap back so we have
to code that as well
this may just be an illusion but it
looks like the body is steppin to the
corner of the tiles usually in tile
based games entities occupy the center
rutile so no that is the center of a
tile remember the tiles are actually
we're drawing the traversable points not
the corners so there is no collision
volume for the floor tiles at the moment
but let's see here what is it floor
collision makes them before collision so
yeah so makes them before question if I
was to actually put in the volume part
of this so if I said there is a volume
count of one and it had you know well
you get the idea if I was actually put
these in there and then draw them
let me go ahead and that stuff has done
it startup so now you can actually see
the tiles themselves and so you can see
that like it is standing on the center
of the tiles right
let's see other cues in the loop
no durga at the end of the Q&amp;A can you
announce their reminder that the forums
are going down shortly sure i thought
they were already down i think so
thought someone said six i guess it was
around six but i will announce that yes
alright so anyway but yeah like I said I
don't actually want there to be any
collision volumes for the floor at the
moment okay
so let's go ahead and close up shop
lovely hmm okay now we're all closed up
thank you for joining me for an episode
of hand made here oh it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always do so by pre-ordering the
game on handmade hero dot org it comes
to the source code so that you can
experiment with it and you know that
sort of thing we have a forum site but
the forums are going down now or very
soon because this weekend they're
getting moved they're actually going
somewhere else they're going to handmade
Network on a new forum system or
something I don't actually know the
specifics
basically I hate running forums I hate
anything web related really let's be
honest
so the handmade network people have a
bunch of forums stuff that they were
working on so that's where that's going
to live from now on and so pretty soon
that will be the case but I believe
they'll be down this weekend which is
basically just them migrating them and
doing testing on them to make sure that
they're working and then they'll reopen
on Monday I guess or sometime next week
when people are relatively sure that the
forums are not you know gonna eat all
your data or self-destruct or anything
like that so that's what's happening and
keep an eye out if you need to know
what's going on with that you can just
click on this link and it'll come to
this page and this page will presumably
you know there's the code discussion
button this will presumably go down soon
and we'll have something in this place
that says like come back later
so you should be able to sort of keep
tabs on it through the weekend by
checking that or rather next week when
it's back up by coming there we have a
patreon page you can also subscribe to
if you want to support the video series
which is always much appreciated and we
also have a tweet bot that tweets the
schedule at you if you would like to
know when the series is going to be live
that'll get updated this weekend with
the schedule for next week so be sure to
check that if you're interested and
that's about it
have a good weekend programming everyone
and I will see you on the Internet's
take it easy everybody