hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are going to well
honestly we're gonna do what we were
going to do last weekend but we ended up
just having a giant discussion about
caches because that was some questions
that people had and so we kind of went
through all of the stuff that you you
know kind of want to have as background
information on them and that took up the
whole two hours so today we're actually
gonna get back to what we were trying to
do which is to start to extend our
entity system to have some larger
storage in it and the idea behind what
we did just prior was to set us up so
that we could really take probably I
mean not not literally infinite but we
could start to use basically as much
storage as we want in our entities
because we don't have to keep it
permanently so it only we can have our
entities when they're actually being
simulated and they're in the local
region that where the player is
currently playing those can be quite
large and quite sophisticated because
they then get packed down later into
smaller sort of more concise versions
for long term storage so that's the
two-tier structure that we ended up
creating and already is working now so
we've got that done but we haven't
actually added anything to it to
actually use this sort of this sort of
model for any productive purposes so
what we want to do is start down that
road so if we open up the game here in
remedy which is the debugger written by
George man Arnie's X 13 pixels it looks
like we're still in debug build I guess
we didn't build a release mode for some
reason not sure why let me go ahead and
switch into debug build there so we can
hop around one interesting thing we may
be able to to is if our if we do
improved lighting which is kind of on
the schedule here for stuff we want to
do with the larger energy store improved
lighting would also get rid of the fact
that our debug go slow because all of
our time in our
game is spent in the lighting and we can
do better right we can make a better
lighting system so you know that's
that's a sort of an interesting side
effect that we can do there so anyway
what we wanted to start doing is to
utilize that it's twofold one is you can
see the lighting is still just sort of
our little test lighting volume you can
actually see the edges there as we move
around it only contains a small region
of the world at the moment yeah you know
if we actually zoom out you can see
there's just that's the region that gets
lit and what we want to do is be able to
light a much larger region than that as
we go forward and have it be much faster
so we want like faster simpler better
lighting right we just want we just want
a general improvement of that system
which is always hard lighting is one of
the most difficult things that you
encounter in games certainly largely
because doing it correctly is impossible
so you're always dealing with trying to
do some approximations that give you
good results but have reasonable speed
right okay so we want to do that and the
other thing that we want to do is
indoors right like this is roughly what
we wanted to look like in terms of what
the general layout is we've got these
sort of little tiles I wanted them to
sort of be like rough and you know
uneven and stuff and and have a texture
on the top it's like whatever wood grain
or stone or something and as you can see
here like that's pretty much done like
that
that is fine like that looks the way I
wanted it to look I don't really have
any problem with that so that's all good
but what's not so good is if we go
outside this is not what I wanted this
this is not what I want the outdoor
regions to look like so we tried
spamming some trees in there and that's
all fine so I think putting down trees
when we want to write our final tree
distribution you can so you can put
trees we got snowy trees we got non
snowy trees whatever stumps that all
seems to be fine what what isn't fine is
just I wanted to be able to sort of spam
ground cover around on these on these
sort of small like I guess not sure how
to describe it really but just I want to
go through on these
grass tiles and just put a bunch of
little like flowery like grasses coming
up and things like that
right and so what we'd like to do is
we'd like to just have some way of
spamming that grass out when something
comes into the active set so you know
this region here just spam it out there
and produce like whatever we're gonna
use for for the grass right so we want
something like that but then when the
thing goes out of the active set meaning
you know I up up here right and then
stuff well I guess I have to actually
change rooms first but let's move out
here and you can see it happened more
specifically so as I walk up or through
this hallway these things will come out
of the active set right you see they're
gone now
right they're just disappearing and so
as things come out of the active set
like that what we want to be able to do
is we want to be able to throw away all
of that data about where all the grass
is because that's just going to be a ton
of extra information there that we don't
really need to be storing now in order
to do this stuff and keep tabs on it we
also have a new friend with us this is
our memory arena and as you can see from
here it basically keeps track of
everything that we have allocated and
tells us who's using what and where I'm
not sure why this is not broken up into
tinier pieces currently because I
thought I thought the last time we
checked into the two here this was sort
of partitioned into little chunks but I
guess that's not happening oh right
because we haven't actually looked at
this since we did our major changes this
is now just a let's go back to the the
sizes so this is now inside our game
storage we now just have a giant cache
effectively of entities that are
expanded
and they just go in that giant pool so
that is just one big allocation that
stores the entire game active set at any
given time and then we only get little
world chunks when things have to get
packed back in and I would wager I guess
I don't actually know but I would wager
that right now we're actually not even
spilling probably so the whole world
just fits in the unexpanded version and
we don't get that so you know that's
that's kind of interesting if we went
back to the world mode here that's right
not the world no of the world and we we
take a look I just had forgotten that
would actually happen but that is what
would happen you don't need to pack
anything if things stay in the active
set I believe what we would see here is
if we were to change this number revise
it down so let's say it was more like
that right then I think we would start
to see more in the in terms of packing
right if I now take a look at that
memory set there you go okay wow that's
cool right this is why I really like
these visualizations right even when you
are the one who wrote the program you
oftentimes won't remember like or won't
think through how things will change and
when you can see them operating you can
tell so here's the cash this is
unexpected
expanded entities that are capable of
running directly and simulating right
and these are all the compressed entity
chunks right now right now we don't
actually do any compression that routine
just stubbed out and will likely remain
subbed out for a while because we don't
care about actually doing the
compression for a while and during
developments it's easier not to bother
but as we start to like tighten down the
memory requirements for the game we can
get a lot of win there right and so you
can kind of see that process setting
itself up nicely so that's pretty cool
you can actually watch that cache
getting used and at the size that we set
it to which was four times the the
maximum sim region count at that point
you've really got enough that the whole
game just runs
out of it at the moment because we just
don't create large enough worlds in the
future will be creating much larger
worlds will be me and not just spatially
but just there's more stuff in it right
because right now it's mostly empty we
haven't put like the game design stuff
in there that will create lots of new
entities and stuff like that and also I
think there's only like one or two
levels of the dungeon I don't know three
levels I don't know how many levels of
dungeon it went down but it's not much
so as we add more we should be actually
utilizing more than four times the
maximum region and account anyway but
that's sort of a separate issue right ok
so I think that's roughly what we're
looking at here and what I want to do
now like I said is look at maybe doing
some of that ground cover stuff so that
as entities come into the set like I'll
sort of spam ground cover out onto
grassy areas and you know things that
want to have grass will have them right
alright so if we go back into our entity
set let's let's just take a look at the
entity structure itself here if we're in
the entity structure and we want to
start adding this here's like the stuff
that we have for lighting storage and
here's the stuff that we have for ground
cover these two things are both elements
that don't really need to be there and
you can see there was a to do here for
the lighting elements that don't really
need to be there when there isn't some
when the entity is it's sort of packed
away it's not in the actus that's not
being used and there's more down here in
addition to that that could be as well a
lot of this animation sort of stuff
right like all this you know these angle
swipes the and base and all that stuff
all of the things that our animation
related also don't need to be there so a
lot of this stuff can sort of be packed
up into like a more concise format and
you know we can just truncate the entity
as we go so what I'd like to do is start
by actually doing something like that
where we kind of have some knowledge
about how it might get truncated I'm
gonna do the simplest possible thing
first this is just a really really basic
idea but I'm going to start with it
which is here where I sort of say okay
we're gonna have some extra data with
our entities I'm gonna I'm gonna do
something like say well maybe and
there's two ways I go with this I'll
just tell you what they both are way
number one would be that we keep the n
destructive this size and we just
truncate it when we pack it so when the
entity gets packed down to a smaller
size
we just don't pack down the ending bit
right we just leave it off you know I'm
saying so that's one way to do it
another way to do it is these could
actually now be things that are more
complicated so for example we could have
secondary rings of data for things like
ground cover that we just allocate to an
entity when the entity comes into
service and then remove from the entity
when it goes out of service and I think
that's actually more like what we're
going to move towards as we go because
things like ground cover at least maybe
not lighting Point State but maybe but
ground cover at least may reside
entirely on the GPU right because the
GPU could know how the ground cover is
arranged and there could just be like a
vertex buffer that's stored that says
here's where the ground cover goes and
so we wouldn't really need to store the
ground cover data on the CPU side it
could always just reside in the GPU side
and so then the entity pack unpack stage
still very important just instead of
being there for modifying CPU memory
it'll be there for modifying GPU memory
right and so I think that's where we're
gonna go with it eventually but I don't
want to you know run before we can crawl
here so what I'm going to do for
starters is I'm just gonna define a
boundary that says at this point in the
code everything after it can
get discarded right and so this is kind
of just like a temporary way we're gonna
deal with this for the moment and it's a
really easy way for us to just do our
packing and unpacking so what this means
is here's our lighting and our cover
information
masae that all of our entities you know
I may go back here temporarily and and
sort of do this again as well just so we
can watch it happen all of our entities
are gonna have all of this stuff in them
when they're in the cash right now so
when we run and we look at sort of this
part right and we look at how this is
getting distributed you can see that
we've got all the packed entities here
all the cash tracer these entities and
these entities currently have all that
data so what I'm gonna do now is just
remove that data just from here so when
an entity gets packed so out of the
actors set this storage will no longer
contain that extra space right so how
we're gonna do that well inside the
world struct we know exactly what's
going on when we call unsure region is
unpacked we know that those pieces of
information are going to come into being
right and so when we go well actually I
think this does both of them right
but anyway point being when we come in
here and we call acquire unpacked in the
slot that acquire unpacked and the slot
call is the thing that preps that region
so if we look at what that does you can
see here that it just kind of grabs it
and then gives it back and so we want to
probably at this point unpacking
something we want at this point to do
something a little bit more than just
taking whatever the source data is and
slamming it back in there because now
what we're gonna do is we're gonna start
using a smaller size for the actual
packing right all right so how are we
gonna do that
well first of all we need to start
maintaining an actual pointer here so
we're going to use sort of a read
pointer and I want to do
I want this to start looking a little
bit more like a streaming construction
because like I said in the future I
think I'm going to want to do some like
more advanced compression these sorts of
stuff with it and so I wanted to start
looking a little bit more like our PNG
sort of stuff right and so if we look I
think I mean I don't know but I think we
may just be able to go ahead and use our
stream here because if you remember how
our stream worked you could just make
these calls like consume this much from
the stream and you know this is this is
what I want you to give me for data
right and so if we have something like
that that we use on top of the stream
that may be the easiest way for us to
really work this stuff out now there's a
couple things that aren't probably ideal
about it namely it can't read across
boundaries so this stream was made to
just only work on a single boundary you
can see that happening here where you've
got the file under flowed thing being
true because I think this refill if
necessary right this thing is only
getting called once so what happens is
while the stream is reading it can read
out of multiple chunks but it has to
read individual things out of it in as
as a single block right now I don't
really need to replace that now because
I that may in fact that limitation may
be fine just in general but it's worth
noting that it is there right and so
it's something that we just want to be
like aware of if that makes sense but
otherwise you know I think this is
something we probably could use if you
look at how this is set up we've got
this stream chunk here with the the
buffer contents and that stuff I could
however also just make a custom one just
for the world and the reason why we
might want to do that is because again
these entity blocks we already have are
kind of doing something relatively
specific there and so on and so forth so
I don't know kind of hard for me to say
what I really want to do there
I think what I may do is just say yeah
let's let's just kind of clone just that
one consumption sort of operation maybe
and I'll implement especially here
because I think the stream is just not
quite compatible enough I don't want to
shoehorn it in there and this is
probably gonna be a relatively important
part of our program so I'm gonna I'm
gonna keep it more straightforward than
that so what I'm going to do here is
just pretend I have the thing I need and
I'm gonna write the two sides at the
same time just so I can make things nice
here where we have this this code right
here this is where we pack an entity so
this this part of the code right here
packs an entity into a waiting stream so
you can see it here doing the
adjustments for the entity location then
you can see this getting space for the
entity there that it's going to try to
write in and then there there it is
writing it right and so what I want to
do now is kind of figure out yeah I want
to kind of say how do I want that to
work on this side and this side where
we're not reading out an entirety Randy
well the basics here would be just say
all right how much do I actually want so
if I take a look and I say like total
entity size or maybe packed enemy size
right what's that gonna be well I know
that this is how big the entire entity
is but I also know that inside my entity
struct I have write like this discard
everything after I have a point that I
don't want a store passed right so I
want to look and see where is the you
know where is that actually going right
well how far in is it so a long time ago
we wrote this macro which is just kind
of an easy way of saying how far is this
member from the beginning of the struck
it says assume we're starting at a
pointer value of 0 so this the struct
starts at 0 memory the base of memory
how far we have to go to get to the
member right it's just using the address
of operator for that and so what I can
do is I can say all right if I know the
offset of that thing in memory right
instead of saying size of entity what I
could just do is say
how big would the how far would I have
to get if I went all the way to this
discard everything after that's the size
of all the things before it right so it
gives me this sort of easy way of
figuring out how much I need to save and
everything else after it would get
discarded so if this was the pact entity
size here then I could just change this
code to use that size so I could say
well let's just instead use oops pact
entity size so we'll use that much chunk
space when this comes back I'm not going
to do entity star I'm just gonna call
this a void star and then I'm just gonna
do a regular copy of the pact entity
size and I'm gonna say go from the
entity to this destination right now
this part isn't going to work this
clearing part here because we've we've
now sort of destroyed the ability to
access anything that's okay this is just
saying don't actually store these you
know for all intents purposes and so
what I want to do is just let's now use
our packing for that we have DDP and we
have DDT Bob it's saying don't pack it
well all right let's just not pack it
so this stuff will now just get
discarded and that means we don't have
to do anything with it here right so
this is what we're doing you know that's
our code I'm gonna pull this out for now
because it happens to be shared at this
you know at this stage and so what I
want to do is in here where we do this
operation I want to make a symmetric
version on the side that actually does
the unpack right so where we do this so
when we acquire an unpacked NV slot I
now want to make sure I can copy the
rest of the stuff into it and what
you'll see here is that this code is
actually kind of wrong and I guess I
should update the other piece of code as
well first so you can see here when I do
my use chunk space this is only going to
advance by however much space I really
know I'm looking at that to start use
chunk space call who updates how many
entities there are
okay so what you can see here is we have
the entity count getting updated as well
and again that's something that I pretty
much don't want to do anymore
the reason for that is if our entities
start becoming flexibly sized which I
would like to get to as well because
eventually I think that's probably the
right way to go we don't really want we
don't want to be doing stuff with a unit
block size entity right we want to be
flexibly reading the data so I think
what we want to do here is just treat
this again a little bit more like a
streaming thing and say this is not
there anymore right and we've got this
entity data we're just gonna use this
entity a to size to say how much of its
filled and that's what we're actually
going to use so this entity data here
with this world block size my 16 instead
of 16 we're gonna trim off 4 bytes from
that right and we're gonna we're gonna
say okay it's just an 8 up to 8 byte
pointer and then a 4 byte size and
that's all that's gonna be in here so
once we trim that off we can get down to
to just 12 there now when we look at any
data and we say do we really need entity
data size there to be 32 a 32-bit
integer what you can hopefully gain from
this is like well hey that's not right
here this world block size at a maximum
is only 16 bits and we know that we've
already taken up some of it so actually
this can just be a 16-bit integer if we
want to and then we can save an extra 2
right so now we've got roadblocks size
-10 worth of storage which is basically
just room for the next pointer and a
little thing that says how far we should
go to the end right now even that's
probably not actually 100% necessary we
could do something even squeakier if we
really wanted to but for now I'm gonna
stick with that and I'm gonna get rid of
the Edit account stuff altogether right
so here is the block MB count I'm gonna
get rid of that and I'm gonna recompile
now and just get rid of it everywhere it
is and then we're gonna go from there
okay yep so we don't want that and this
when we do the plus equals size here
this size value is a 32-bit value that's
okay when we do this has room for check
that will take care of it so it should
be a safe front gate to you 16 here
where we can just say that's only we're
only gonna use 16 bits of that data all
right so as you can see the packing side
is much simpler it doesn't really need
to know how many entities there are
because it's the one creating all of
that used chunk space in the first place
it just streams it out till it's done
and that will track how much total space
is used when we get back here and we go
through these blocks as we are unpacking
our entities the problem that we're
gonna have here is again without this we
don't know when we're done but since we
have the entity data science field
that's gonna tell us how much we have
left so really in here we can do change
the the nature of this to a slightly
different way of looking at the data
right what instead we could do is have a
u16 here that's like at will start at 0
I guess I could do it this way right
we'll go until we're under the entity
data like when we get to the entity data
size we have to stop right and so then
as we read in here we can just advance
that pointer once that pointer has read
all the data in the block we know we're
done with the block right now this will
get more complicated and we'll want to
pull this out to an actual little struct
probably that like streams things in for
us as we go but at the moment since we
only since we're not renting out
entities in pieces we can still keep
this structure of doing one nd at a time
inside the inner loop with this actually
being a loop around it that's actually
totally fine but once we get to this the
the part where an entity might be stored
across two blocks which there's no
reason not to do
pretty easy for us to extend to that
then this has to get lofted up into a
thing that just does the check every
time right so it would actually be in
here where we would say you know make
sure we haven't reached the end of the
it would be a four loop that goes and
gets a new block if it can if it can't
we're done if it or start I should say
if we it checks to see if we've run out
of bits in this block and when we have
gets another block if it can't then
we're actually done right so it's just
it won't be as complicated for it won't
be as straightforward for a loop it'll
be something that looks more like that
with the actual code inside and a break
statement right but for right now we can
stay with a simpler version because we
know we're only packing whole entities
at a time still so it's a simpler
process that we're doing so we don't
really want to do any of this anymore
right we do want the dest to do the
acquire app unpacked any slot but here
this is going to be more of the the same
where we take the packed entity size
that we expect we're going to take the
destination here and say we're going to
copy into that so then we just need our
source so we need the entity data for
the block plus where we're actually at
in the block that's where we're gonna
copy from and then when of course it has
to do the unpacking of the position as
well when we're actually done with that
read we also then want to advance our
app pointer to be that packed entity
size so again we're just consuming that
much out of the packed stream right so
now in theory barring problems that I
may have introduced hopefully that is
correct
meaning hopefully we've got the right
logic in there now and if once we just
debug that we will still have our game
running exactly as it was only now when
we store our entities for long-term
storage it will strip off that large
section at the end of it and so if we
take a look inside the arena's now you
can actually see how much there's
drastically less storage being spent on
the entities that are in long-term
storage right it was like two three
times the size of that four right and so
now when I'm
around in theory as things get packed
and unpacked in through that set we
shouldn't see any bugs and we don't so I
guess maybe I did that at least roughly
right
we haven't stressed that system or
tested it much so it's a little
premature to say anything like that but
certainly it's not obviously busted
because as these entities are coming in
they're working just fine there's our
little saucy gentleman hopping around
and the lighting is all just fine now
let's go back to an into an area that
was packed up again we shouldn't expect
to see anything different here because
since our world generation code uses the
world system as it is in the first place
if unpacking was broken we would have
expected to be broken the entire time
not just when we pack and unpack and
repack and so on but you know I don't
see any particular issues here we don't
really know how hard we've tested it
like I said but that seems fine all
right so that's again the first stage
and that just gets us in the habit of
having this packing work now as you can
see when we have ensure region is
unpacked here what I want to do is when
we actually go to do an unpack which is
here when we call register entity we
kind of want register enemy now to
potentially do more stuff right
or rather we want I guess we shouldn't
say do more stuff we actually just
probably want a separate call because
register entity needs to be done when we
just use entities that are already in
the set as well so here what I'd like to
do is you know fill entity or something
something like this so what I want to do
here is say hey we've got an entity it
was packed long term storage now we have
unpacked it and it needs to recreate
like any stuff that you know gets
generally discarded we got that's got to
start coming back in now right and so
inside well and in fact I guess this
could be just in the entity code itself
I really don't know exactly where I want
it to be completely honest with you but
what I'm gonna do for now just say all
right let's just say
there's gonna be this call I don't know
where it's gonna live we can get to all
that later but for now what I want to do
is have this little entity death
situation going on in here and all I
really want to do now is just have some
way of creating that ground cover every
time one of these entities comes into
existence and so you know creating the
ground cover is gonna be pretty simple
at least at first I actually have a kind
of so if you go out here and look on the
interwebs on my blog for example I did a
bunch of stuff with grass generation and
ground cover for the witness which is if
you've never heard of it it's a game
it's a game by Jonathan Blow that does
like it's a it's a complete 3d world
like walk around kind of like
first-person he sort of game and so the
on the ground there's lots of grasses
and flowers and things like this and
there was a planting system that there
level editor had in it and so I did the
replacement for that it was very slow
and had a bunch of problems so I did the
replacement version and while I was
doing that there are a couple things
that I looked into this particular one
here was sort of a separate thing I
figured out after the fact doesn't
actually appear in the witness so this
this particular pattern doesn't appear
in the witness but this whole series you
can see actually here we go starting at
visually pleasing distributions this
whole series kind of talks about the
subtle aspects of ground planting and
how you want to do them and that sort of
stuff
so yeah take a look at that if you're if
you're interested in I talked about like
blue noise and stuff like that and
things we'll cover here on here a little
bit probably too anyway you can spend a
lot of time on grass packing on grass
distribution stuff I don't know to what
extent I really want to do that much
with that on stream but point being
we'll do something
probably better than white noise which
is the very worst kind of grass
distribution and so we're gonna start
with white noise and later probably
replace it again because I said it's
terrible
so if I wanted to do that I need some
way of creating a random distribution of
grass on this thing I'm just gonna hack
in some of that right now so that we
could start testing this stuff out if I
go in here and look at how we're storing
this right I've got a ground cover thing
we go up and look at the ground cover
it's got you know what bitmap did you
want on there what was the location how
big was it and what color was it right
and a guy I think we're gonna we're
gonna go through a couple iterations of
this so don't fixate on that this is
just one way that we're gonna put that
in there but it's yeah things will
things will progress from here because
we're still we're gonna want to simplify
the amount of work we're doing for some
of this stuff anyways so I want to do a
couple things one is I do want this to
be time function because I do want to
know if our unpack fills are taking too
long if we if we start putting more
complicated stuff that goes on in here I
want to see that show up on the profile
is a separate issue and not bury it in
some other buddies timing so what I want
to do is distribute the ground cover
here I don't know how we want to pick
that amount but for now I'm just gonna
do the maximum amount so we're gonna
actually just fill that to the brim and
we especially I think we want to do that
at first to get cuz we're gonna want to
stress the system see it'd be really
slow and then improve it so it's nice
and fast and that kind stuff so I'm
gonna go with the maximum count for the
ground cover right now and just let that
be sort of the the high-water mark for
her slowness and then we'll we'll pull
it back all right so we've got the cover
index here we're gonna loop over those
and we're gonna fill each of these as we
go so here's a you know here's where the
ground cover goes this thing is going to
need some kind of a random point
it's gonna need one of those bitmaps
right it's gonna need a color and it's
gonna need a scale and so at first you
know we can't just keep this pretty
simple this is gonna be the thing we're
gonna have to randomize for the
placement but that shouldn't be too hard
and then the bitmap is a little bit more
complicated because we're gonna need
some sort of a idea about where these
bitmaps actually are right we're gonna
have to do something where we pick sort
of you know ask the the asset matcher to
find where where these crafts bitmaps
are and figure out which ones we're
putting in there and why and that sort
of stuff so we need to do those two and
that'll be most of what we're gonna do
however obviously when we're filling an
unpacked NNE not everybody gets ground
cover only the actual grass tiles or
other tiles that we deem suitable for
having crap scattered on them and
remember we may want this system to do
other stuff like scatter rocks around
the dungeon or splotchy little stains
bloodstains
who knows how gruesome they can get when
Krampus is involved but point being we
will probably use the ground cover
system for more than just grass as well
but either way the point is not everyone
gets it only entities that are supposed
to have ground cover get them and that
particular ground cover probably wants
to come from a set of ground covers and
also maybe have some settings on it
about what it should actually be and so
in here I want to store that information
I'm going to say that maybe we've got
some information here that tells us
about how our ground cover works so like
we've got something like the density
value maybe I don't know
and then we probably have a type of
ground cover that needs to be there um
here's what I will say I don't actually
know
I don't actually know how we want to do
this exactly when we look at our let me
load up our tags files cuz I just don't
I don't even remember what we've got I
know we've got ground cover in there
he's got some grasses and some I don't
remember what we did with it so here's
our tags file I and so somewhere in here
we've got some like grass and crap here
we go so we have like grass one two and
three we've got some rocks I'm not sure
what Puffs are let's take a look at
these actual files because like I said I
don't really remember what we've got
here we've really never looked at these
before so sources base game arts so it's
in the particles section here fire grass
this stuff so it looks like grass yeah I
don't know I think these can just be
fairly interchangeable so you know it
looks like these are maybe little
splotchy things whereas this looks like
thicker cover maybe these are flowers
right so I'm not sure really want it
let's look at those rocks though okay so
the rocks are kind of like more
occasional scattering so I don't really
know how I want to do this but I'm just
gonna go I'm assuming this for now so
I'm going to do a cover type thing and
I'm just gonna say look we're gonna have
a field
and then I'm just gonna sign craft of
the field because I don't know right let
me do it this way and so I'm just gonna
make a few cover types here that I might
want and so I'm gonna say look if you
want you know thick grass brass watch
and rocks I think that's what we've got
at the moment Oh flowers I'm just gonna
say we got a bit field and that has that
in there
and then what I'm going to say is that
that density value I guess tells you
what that is like how dense you want to
be although now that I think of well you
know now that I think about it that
doesn't really work particularly well
does it because you probably want to set
the density differently for each type of
cover that you wanted to splat on there
so thinking about it you probably want
something like this or like that and you
probably want to say that it's going to
be some kind of a packs value that gives
you both of those pieces of information
like separately right so you probably
want something like this maybe
does that seem reasonable and so then
you would do something more like Grande
so the cover types again I shouldn't
have deleted those there they're just
you know they're the same they're just
not gonna be bit fields anymore they're
just an int that tells you which one
you've got something like this and so
you can have 256 different types of
ground cover
well technically 255 one of them is non
cover and then you can send a density
value and that density value will mean
something but I don't know what
and so each entity can get that piece of
information right so the ground cover
type here density might just be how many
there are at this point for us as well
so something like that so anyway inside
the ground cover type thing we'd pick
one of those and then you know over when
we're doing we're doing this this can be
a loop itself that's sort of like let me
loop over the ground covers that are
specified for this particular place and
we'll boot them forth right and so like
yeah you get some number of this you can
you can splooge on there and after you
do each of those you're done right so
okay seems reasonable to me so what I
want to do now is say all right in that
case the way that this is going to work
is more like this
loop over each of the cover specs that
we have exhale so we're going to go
through each one of the ground cover
specs and we're going to process them in
order if we hit the end of the amount we
can store which would be this we want to
stop then as well and then here actually
I suppose we can just put that one here
so this would be our complete set now
we're gonna know ahead of time like we
don't really have to do this check-in
line because we are gonna know ahead of
time where that would actually be so for
example what we could do instead is say
all right let's get that density count
out of the spec first right then let's
say alright how much room would there be
if we if we were to use all of the
remaining space in the ground cover
array and we can just clamp that density
count down from there right so if I did
a thing that said like in fact here I'll
do it this way this would be the easiest
way if I just said look the density
count is going to be however much room I
could afford at the moment - how much I
have used so far that's how much you're
going to put here but if the spec
density is actually less than that right
so meaning if the density count would
exceed how many I was asked to plant
then just clamp it
and you may ask why do that well the
reason is because if I clamp the value
first then it doesn't have to check it
every time to the array after the loop
it can just check it once right and then
we do both of our checks with one if
right it just simplifies the code for
the CPU so basically you just pick the
minimum of the two here and then when
you do your loop you're only looping
over one and off we go so when we do our
ground cover
now we're assigning it across multiple
specs as well which is nice and this
doesn't have to be here anymore either
so that can go away and so I think
that's all good now what we want to do
is actually pull out that spec I never
actually did that also we now no longer
need these two and so here I want to
pull out the spec in question and now we
have I think what's completely
functional for all our n DS and this
loop will never get entered because
nobody will have set any ground cover on
themselves so we won't generate any and
that's fine however if we actually did
want to generate some we're gonna need
some additional stuff here to finish
which is the spit map and the placement
gonna start with white noise on the
placement which is again white noise is
just purely like is what you might call
real entropy it's white noise is an
unpredictable completely unpredictable
value obviously we can't get completely
unpredictable values out of computer
really Intel claims that they sort of
can on their processor but I don't know
how true that is
either way white noise is literally
random in the truest sense of the word
it's trying to just be completely
unstructured grass in the real world is
not completely unstructured you will not
have be as likely for two Tufts of grass
to appear directly next to each other
because they're competing
for sunshine and rain so you will much
likely much more likely see grass based
at sort of regular distances but
irregular patterns which again is a more
blue blue noise like pattern which is to
say randomness constrained by
non-overlapping that is how organic
things tend to grow again because they
compete for space and resources so they
tend to grow into cellular like patterns
that are distributed so we would
probably want to move to a more blue
noise pattern or something like that as
we go forward but for right now we're
just going to use pure entropy in order
to do put your entropy we need to be
able to pick a random point on top of
this entity here and so to do that we
need our random series so we have our
random series let's see here
so we don't really need to do a
four-wide randomizer just yet we have
one here that does four at a time
obviously that's going to be a fancier
version that would be faster right so I
don't really know that we need to do
that although I guess we could
so I maybe we'll just use the the PCG
for now I don't know maybe we should
just do four at a time
maybe we should so I guess what I'll do
is we will we will do a random seed with
the random series and we'll I guess
we'll do forward time I guess
so we'll do random series and this will
be our cover series here and what I'm
going to do is our cover series I'm
going to initialize when we do the
random seed so here what I'm going to do
is I'll use the same stuff we were doing
here
so this but what I'd like to do is I'd
like to seed it with the entity ID as
like an offset so each entity will get
its own slightly different random series
so if I just do this right that produces
an offset series that gives me a you
know sort of randomized version for each
of the entities separately but it also
means I'll generate the exact same
ground cover for a given entity every
time I process that entity which means
that even if you went off-screen the
entity got packed you go back find the
entity again the grass pattern will
still be exactly the same because it
will have been generated with the same
generator and that just helps keep the
world a little bit more consistent right
because unless something has happened to
that particular tile the player wouldn't
expect the grass pattern on it to change
because why would it right um so that
kind of helps us keep the things feeling
of
more solid and I might suggest to in
here that we would potentially want
something like this something like this
where we just say oh okay let's do our
random seed here and then we will just I
mean basically just this do this for
anyone who wants it so if something like
that and that way this sort of thing
this looks more like that and that way
we can also like improve this this is
probably not the best way of doing that
so we could maybe make this better over
time and then anyone who needed to do
stuff like that could just get it this
way right so I don't know something like
this so once we have one of these what
we're gonna need is we've got sort of
the ability to do random muta laterals
and random bilaterals and we can get
that data out you know any time we want
and so what I want to do here is I would
like to if possible take the bounding
rectangle of the top of my entity and
just pick a random point inside that so
the question is where actually is that
right and if we look at the entity
structure I believe that what that
amounts to is in here we have the
position of the entity right so we're
gonna start with entity P and then we
have a collision volume that specifies
where you know what the bounds are
relative to relative to that P so we
know that we would
like you know get min corner or
something of collision volume right or
something like that would get us to like
the bottom of it or I could do get max
corner so I can do various stuff or I
like pick out of the the collision
volume but I thought so we have a way of
mapping in but we don't have a way of
mapping out we went through this exact
code before we should have made a
function for it because we're just doing
the same darn thing again right so when
we do like when we get the ground points
right when we when we get the actual
yeah so you can see here we actually all
right well I'm gonna go look up that
code
and I'm gonna see where we're doing that
stuff I just want to see if this can be
put until oh yeah all right well here's
what I'm gonna do since I've believed I
wanted this function before I'm gonna
write it now so that I can have it so we
have a thing called get barycentric and
what that does is it takes a point and
it gives you back the barycentric
coordinates for that point relative to
the rectangle right but I kind of want
the opposite here right I want the like
this where you kind of give it like
here's the uvw barycentric coordinates
here's the rectangle give me out what
the point would actually be right and so
when we look at something like this what
we'd be saying is all right the result
is going to be the linear blend between
like the a min X and the a max X along
the you know T value specified by my uvw
you see what I'm where I'm getting that
from so we're just gonna say you give us
a number between 0 &amp; 1 on each of x y&amp;z
and we're gonna pick out the point in
the rectangle that is that point right
and that just makes it easy to sort of
say stuff like oh I want to ran a point
inside this volume pick a random number
between 0 &amp; 1 on each axis there you go
right so I believe that that would be
the easiest way to do it so because then
I can just say well take the collision
volume that you've got and then you know
take our random uvw
and we're good to go right so we just
pick three of those and then and then
we're done now we can see here is
actually we don't want to ran a point in
the volume I mean that might be
interesting for other kinds of cover
that was like gas or something that was
filling up a volume but we're only
trying to fill the top so we know that
actually we only ever want this value to
be one because the Z value should be the
highest it always can be so we only
actually want randomness on these two
right makes sense and so now we've got
our random point distributor so the
final thing we need is an actual bitmap
here and again that bitmap is going to
come from the cover spec so what we want
to do here is figure out is the spec
actually something we want so if the
spec what's that called type if the spec
type is valid then it says you know it's
actually something we want if it's set
to zero then that means this isn't used
this ground cover isn't used right so
once we test it what we then want to do
is say let's we need to sort of have
like a bitmap sort of table or however
you want to look at that for looking up
the various ground covers that we have
and there's a few ways we might want to
do this it's kind of it's kind of one of
those places where we've said many times
we need to read you how we how our tag
matching works and that's very very true
because I don't think we want to on
every bitmap actually make the call to
do the asset matching because calling it
64 times it's way too many times so what
you really want is just a table that you
can look up in and get those variants
more quickly where you just pick a
random number in that zone I'll start
with the crap
version which doesn't do that and then
we'll go from there so if I look at the
code just slightly above this particular
code you can see us doing the bitmap
retrieval using the matching vector so
you know you can see this here like this
for example and so here we don't have
really any other information at the
moment except for the fact that we've
got a variant here and the weight vector
wants to do that too
and what we're gonna do is the match
vectors variant part itself will just
have to be randomized every time so each
time through here we would do random
unilateral and we would send the cover
series down when we actually then go in
to get a get mass get the best bit map
this is the code that would have to
actually run right and so this asset
category thing here is go this asset
basic category and that's just gonna be
particle I believe and then the rest of
this is is all good right
okay so because we have to do asset
queries in here to assign these bitmaps
that does also mean that when we're in
here I we're gonna need that asset
system and so that's gonna create a
little bit of a call chain issue for us
so we're gonna have to make sure we pipe
that through properly but otherwise
that's what we would want to do now the
rest of this stuff facing Direction is
not really what we want to be pulling
out there so what we want to do here is
we actually want to do sort of a switch
statement on
spec type here where we actually look at
these ground cover types I defines and
we want to see which ones of them we
want to say how they're gonna get looked
up right so we've got rocks flowers
thick grass and splotch grass we can go
into the HST and see what those are set
to and so here you know you can see
we've got cover set and then we've got
flowers set and then we've got I guess
what we where the rocks stone is that
right um why the flowers aren't set to
cover I don't know because that seems a
little bit odd but you know whatevs so
in this kind of crappy system that we've
said many times we need to redo and have
never redone we then need to just kind
of laborious ly fill this garbage out
all right so uh we need something like
this and you're gonna see how
ridiculously crappy this is I mean like
this is not gonna stay in the game it's
just a terrible idea for so many reasons
um but you know got stuck with what we
have for now so in here we got a look at
this weight vector here and say okay for
Rox what is it that we're going to use
so for here we want tag Rox
why is that not a thing oh it was stone
cover and sighs actually I don't think
we need the size for this one right we
don't care about size because there's
only one size of rocks at the moment so
there are flowers
looks like it's just that for here we've
got cover and oddly enough there's
nothing else on it seems bad shouldn't
it at least be labeled like grass and I
my totally off-base here
so splotch grass was the smaller one and
thick grass was the larger one and off
we go
so again really crappy and theories just
to be clear the reason it's crappy is
because what you want most out of an
asset system is you want to deliver
assets to the game in the way that the
game wants to use them and so for
example here what we want is we want to
just be able to say give me the rock
data set how many are there right and
then I'm going to distribute them so it
doesn't want the asset system to match
it wants to do the you know variation so
it really just wants to be given like an
array like here's what they are right
and so I think probably even even if we
just kept the system the way it is now
it's actually fine we just need to move
to a system where you could ask for that
and get back the array as something that
that's a queryable that you just do once
and then you can distribute it from
there so we can do that without too much
upset but as it is now it's really
pretty crappy alright so we now have our
fill unpacked entity here I don't know
what some of this stuff is doing or if
anyone's even calling any of this stuff
we should just test to see
and we're gonna have again to route that
asset system through because again we
need that when we're unpacking the mb's
so we know that's true let's see what
else we gots random seed offset cannot
cover everyone from entity ID so I want
to look at what nd ID is I probably need
to get the value out of it yeah so we'll
just do that entity undeclared
identifier I agree with that it was
supposed to be called nd but we didn't
call it entity yeah there and that was
just a typo so hopefully now we're down
mostly just to the routing issue there
so ear fill unpacked entity we need to
find a way to get the game assets
through which means that when we're
calling this part of the unpack here we
need to have that right because I don't
believe the world's knows where the
assets come from you can see here it's
unaware of that so when it calls inshore
region is unpacked somebody at that
stage has to be able to provide the
assets and you know easier said than
done because I think that's typically
not yea happening in here so when we
call begin world change and that's when
you're doing sort of that unpacking
that's where we would actually need that
data to be to be given all right so
let's just force it through
and again I'm just walking up the stack
and requiring everyone who was
previously making a call down this chain
to provide that information
[Music]
so how is this guy yeah so this guy
needs the game assets what doesn't have
it and so the world sim struct itself
should have that in there meaning
although I guess the world sim work
structure actually could have it in
there I don't know that world sim itself
needs it so it's probably more like that
right if the game states there though
game state assets actually has it right
so I could just do that sorry that
although now that I look at it does the
game state get past here it doesn't okay
because say if simulate has the game
state it could do it but I guess not all
right
so let's see game state assets does Jen
have the assets
again this is just kind of busy work
oops
so I feel like the room gener the world
generator should have the assets because
it's going to need those for various
querying purposes so we probably need to
put that in here so yeah so in here
where we're like doing begin world
change we want to and then that just
needs to get actually set when we start
the world gym so that's going to be in
the world Jen CBP and when that stuff
gets initialized probably delete a lot
of this crap now it's like we saved a
bunch of room stuff in fact I'm just
gonna get rid of all of us so when we
first create the world generator right
here this code is going to need that
and so we're we call create world we
will have to pass the assets as well and
so I think that's everything it's a
little bit long-winded but we really do
need those because when we're randomly
distributing detail features we're going
to need to ask the asset system like
which ones are they right so I think
that's all good
all right so I think we're mostly done
with that and now we can distribute
points on our stuff whenever we want to
now there is one issue that we have not
addressed that we do need to address
though and that is that when we are
creating our entities they will not have
been actually updated for like with the
ground cover right the reason for that
is when we first when we initially
create our entities we don't do any of
the unpacking stuff right we just create
the entity and that's it
what that means is that all of the
entities that get created that if not
been packed will not be unpacked and
therefore we'll never have that called
so actually what we want to do before we
you know after we Jen the world right so
when we do create world call and we do
this crap right what we want to do is at
the end of it all so when we do like
begin world Jen and then we do end world
Jen the end world Jen stuff actually
this needs to tell the simulation system
like the world system to flush the
entire cache because everything should
get brought in afresh right so inside
that handmade world system here we need
to flush that where is that
ah okay so right here so that unpacked
in any count that says how many entities
we have start unpacked that just needs
to get set back to zero right so that's
that's what we need to do so how would
we do this well there's a couple
different ways we can do it at the
moment we could literally just set it
back to zero but if we start to
introduce things that maybe manage other
resources as a result of entities coming
in and out of the active set we want
that sort of happen generally in one
place so we don't screw it up right and
so in order to do that what I want to do
here is make sure that's let me just add
the call here before I forget
so inside and world gen I'm going to be
we're unpacked edit cash in world and so
then here in the world calls I want an
ability to do this where I can just say
write and like I said that's not really
what I want so I would like a way of
unwinding everything there and so in
order to do that just to again just to
keep it clean so in here where we do
this operation and we take the the
entity position and we remap it and pack
it and all that sort of stuff
I guess I don't actually know why the
chunk okay there we go looking for
something and it wasn't seeing it so
this entity P here we do the map into
chunks face I guess I'll be honest I'm
not sure why is that happening outside
here still so if you look at that I was
starting to be inside and it wasn't um
if you look at that entity P you can see
it's only really used ah there it is
okay
because it's used in here I was like why
is that outside uh so if you look at
what's happening here what I want to do
is effectively have a way of making sure
that this stuff happens consistently in
both cases and so what I'm thinking up
here this is just kind of my loose kind
of opinion of what I kind of think I
want to have happen is when we do the
the D unpack origin here I think I want
to pull this out into its own sort of
separate pass so this
I think I just want this to be a
separate function that gets called here
by default something like this so that
we always go through kind of like a
known case if this makes sense but then
have two ways of running it one way that
clears the cache and one way that
actually makes the decision something
like this now I guess the other thing
maybe it's better to know what I'm
looking at too though because that's
sort of it also calls register in there
maybe we don't really quite want that
you know maybe we want something more
maybe want something more like only
taking the interior part so like
literally just this maybe
so if we did something like this where
you would say PAC entity and it just
packs that entity into someplace that
it's going to go yeah maybe that's
better so we call PAC entity here and
then we'll have a loop here that calls
PAC entity so this would sort of take us
through the entire set you know why
would I do that that's just that's just
unnecessary let's write it clearer so
I'm just going to loop through I'm gonna
say for each one of these entities I
want you to pack it back up and then I'm
gonna say that we've gotta none right
okay so now the only question is what
does PAC entity actually need to do its
job so it needs a couple of things first
of all it's gonna need the world right
because it's gonna pack that up in there
it's gonna need the pack entity size but
the packed entity size is something we
can know off hand and that's fine and
eventually it'll go away because the
entity's size will vary right so we're
gonna need that we're going to need the
chunk Delta and that will be zero I'm
sorry the chunk Delta the the entity P
so when we actually map it into chunks
face we're going to need this value
right
there yeah I think that's everything
looks good okay
and so in here where we do pack enemy it
needs to simulate those so it needs to
be able to do that pack and the way it's
going to do that is just using the
unpack origin that was used last time
because it knows that there have been no
updates yet right so it's literally it
is the same call right
it's just that but we're just doing it
outside because it was needed here for
other reasons so I think that's all we
actually need to do and that allows us
to do a clear of the cache that packs
everything right
of course it would also help if I pack
past the actual entity that you're
supposed to be packing all right so here
we've got the enemy P and the entity
itself that we're working with those are
both known here we need that entity
again other than that I think we're all
good so I think this will properly clear
the cache and it calls the same code in
both cases so that as we change that
code to do that packing in other ways
hopefully that will work right didn't
like that hold on a second I may have
forgotten to wait world gin
seems like that should be okay shouldn't
it well we'll see so I'm gonna go ahead
and compile debug Mook
we're gonna do bug this and then I think
we're probably getting towards the end
of the again end of our time today but
we've got the ground cover distributing
and hopefully all that stuff is is
functional now and so if we drew it we
would presumably actually see some stuff
all right so on our call of clear
unpacked entity cache it looks like the
world structure is set to 0 for some
reason so I guess
well I'll be honest I'm not really sure
why that's the case ah right because we
cleared our memory uh so I think we can
test this now and see of course we're
not really going to know whether or not
this is working because we're not
drawing the ground cover but I think
we've got everything in place for the
ground cover to work just fine now
albeit perhaps a little bit slowly I
want to take a look at that profile real
quick and then we're gonna hop over and
and actually put some drawing code in
there so we can see about the ground
cover we've got to actually ask it to
generate some ground cover and then we
have to actually draw it in order to see
if it worked so in here we can see our
memory usage if I look at the arena's it
looks roughly the same as it did before
which is you know more or less what we
would expect if I go over to the profile
I just want to make sure there's no
weirdness going on there as we're moving
around light propagation as you can see
still taking pretty much all the time
you know nothing nothing unusual there
it's exactly what you would expect
yeah I mean really this is just exactly
what we would expect there's nothing
nothing interesting here it's just
lighting calcs eating up all the time
and that's what I wanted that's what I
wanted to make sure all right so if we
now go and actually set some ground
cover on our crafts entities so for
example inside room Jen oops let's go
look at where we're getting some grass
selected here and so when we do this add
tag tag grass what I'm gonna do is say
when we add tagged grass I'm also just
going to go ahead and and hard code some
ground cover in here and then later we
can make a system that thinks a little
bit harder about it but for now we'll
just say if we were going to set the
thing to a grass type I'm gonna set one
of these ground covers here with the
type and the density so what I'll say as
well all right we'll take those ground
cover specs zero and we'll do like a
density of 16 or something and the type
will be thick grass right so now we're
like asking for ground cover to actually
occur and so now we should we might see
it show up on the profile but probably
not because it's probably not really
doing very much but we should actually
be getting calls to it now right and
looking at like the yeah there's there's
nothing happening here in particular as
far as I can tell mm-hmm sir
I don't even see it on here
it's called Phil right Phil entity but
it's not even not even on there
I mean it should be in there somewhere
but I guess it doesn't get called except
when you unpack and you only unpack of
it so it probably bloops on and then
bloops off right so now that we've got
it you know asking to do that cover what
we need to do is actually try to draw
that cover somewhere and so if we go
into the enemy system and we look down
where it's actually doing that drawing
you can see here like for example this
is the part where it loops over the
pieces of the entity and draws those
let's try to do you know that same sort
of thing let's try to do that for the
ground cover here so yeah maybe I'll
make a little section for that and we
can isolate this out maybe
[Music]
so the p-values now and I think about it
those actually want to be offset by
where the entity is right so if we take
a look at how the entity fill is
happening I actually don't want this
right because that's the enemy moves
around the ground cover should move with
it so on here like you imagine like a
floating platform that was like moving
around or whatever you want the grass to
go with it you don't have to go update
all the grass every time and so I guess
what we want to do here is say okay like
let's go ahead and say draw this thing
like that and let's make a little
function here that draws that ground
cover and we'll see what that looks like
so here's my draw ground cover so what
would I actually need for that
particular part of things well in here
if we're doing like a push right call
which I assume is roughly what we would
want to do
so we need to be able to do the load
bitmap in the case where it fails but
other than that I don't think there's
particularly much there so we don't need
any of this whoops so we're really just
looking at this so we need the render
group we would need the game assets and
that's about it and so the rest of the
stuff we can actually just get out of
what we have right now so I think that's
where we're at we would want to do this
sort of thing
and popping over here it occurs to me
that we never really stored into the
entity how many pieces of ground cover
there actually were and so we probably
want to do that although I suppose we
can just bail when we see a bitmap idea
of zero and that would be sufficient
also but I don't see any reason not to
just go like that so I think I may in
here in space instead say do this right
all right so I'm gonna do it this way
I'm going to loop over these in order
for each of them I'm gonna get out the
bitmap like this I'm gonna load it if we
can't get it I don't know that this is a
particularly good way to do this part of
the code but you know as we've
streamlined the rendering of the
entities I'm sure we can take care of
most of that but then we really just
need to know what the actual layout of
this sprite is and we can probably use
our existing code for that although for
ground cover because there's so much of
it and because it's very specialized I
could see us wanting us a particular
piece of code that operates just for
ground cover to figure out kind of how
its arranged and where it goes so if we
take a look at update and render
entities here when we actually create
that sprite bit here again not really
sure exactly what I want this to look
like but we'll figure it out so if we
look at the x and y axes those are going
to presumably just be the same as what
you'd expect so we're not really gonna
be modifying those again this is why I
say this should
be welded into something that doesn't
take into account any kind of morphing
of those or deformation because it can
be much faster right for the align P
again don't really know what I want
there
but I'm guessing actually I guess I'll
just do it this way I'm guessing I want
something sort of like this look and
look at that a little bit later and then
for the world dim that's how big I want
the thing to be in the world and that
part is a little confusing because again
we need the texture information for that
and so I don't know how the world dim
actually bakes down like in terms of in
terms of how we want so you can see it's
using the bitmap info for the thing here
to actually do it getting the getting
the actual dimension of it that way
again just a lot too much going on here
what we could we probably want to do is
actually bake this down into the ground
cover that's what I'm guessing because
it's just way too much fussing
just just wait wait wait wait wait wait
too much fussing so if I want to get the
actual bitmap info there for that for
that particular bitmap that's actually
not very hard though we can do that
pretty easily so we just say okay give
me that I and in here I can just say all
right whatever this thing wants to be I
don't know what the height ratio yeah
that's that's a that's a thing for sort
of change so together in terms of how
big we want this I think that's going to
come from the cover scale value so
that's how big you want this thing to be
so I think that's fine all of this
should cascade together now and we
should be able to draw oh and this
actually comes from the cover as well
right so I think that's roughly right
but again there's too much work going on
there and so I think we want to do is
over time migrate that and saying that
just builds the correct render set and
then we just offset that and move it to
where it needs to go but other than that
we don't touch it right okay so this is
actually not bitmap ideas just bitmap
and then draw a ground covering these
asset and the render group sets render
group entity we do get passed the assets
here as assets yes yes
okay that should do it there's one error
there we got to look at up at the top
push bright is unhappy what is it
from bitmap ID to a render texture so
this just wants the texture handle at
that point and it also looks like it
wants it looks like it wants those axes
in world space so these are actually
VIII's not be two's know which one was
it complaining about
oh is it actually the fact that it wants
a v4 for color that's probably what it
is so we actually want the v4 here just
because we can specify an alpha value
any sense
so I think that actually would attempt
to draw the ground cover now and so now
we have to debug the system and find out
okay first of all is art well we're not
seeing it so no but first of all we have
to make sure the ground cover it's
actually getting generated and then we
have to once it is generated make sure
that's actually getting drawn so we've
got ten minutes left let's see how far
we can get in that and what we don't
finish we can do tomorrow so first
things first let's make sure that we're
actually ever getting any ground cover
generated in the first place because we
may just never actually have any ground
cover set in which case we're never
hitting the rendering code so that's the
first thing I want to verify we're
actually doing so I'm gonna set a
breakpoint in fill unpacked entity just
so we can do a spot check on that and so
here where we're actually creating one
of these things I just want to see that
it's actually you know ever ever
happening right so you can see us
switching on the ground spec type here
do we ever get in here we do so somebody
is correctly setting the ground cover
specs for at least some entity in our
game and it looks like thick grass is Oh
already thought of one thing I forgot I
said I wanted to start storing the count
we never stored the count so infill
unpacked entity what we want to do here
Jimmy is instead of actually using this
cover index we actually want to use the
entity ground cover count I can actually
just use cover index though if I want to
on the outside so when we actually start
this right here I can just say okay the
entity ground covered counts equals the
cover index and then we're done right
so that needed to happen let's run again
and just make sure we know what we're
seeing now because we may see something
different and then we'll change our
strategy for how we're two plugging all
right so I'm still not seeing any I feel
like there should be some ground cover
over here right and I'm still not
seeing anything in particular or at
least if I am its microscopic so there's
nothing there so let's go ahead and
again take a look I must set a
breakpoint there when we come through
here I'm gonna see what we're actually
generating in terms of ground cover just
to give myself a sense of whether the
values make any any sense whatsoever
um so I guess I would say the collisions
volume maybes isn't set properly these
are all zeros which is not good right
yeah and so you can see the collision
volume here for this entity that has
ground cover on it it's actually set to
not be anything I thought we were
setting collision volumes on all of our
grass stuff though so I don't really
understand why that would be happening I
thought like for example when we when we
actually set these they had collision
volumes and that's what we were also
using we were drawing them to in fact
let me just okay I didn't mean to do
that I just like ran the game in a
separate way or something there so
that's pretty odd and I guess I'm gonna
go take a look at that because I want to
make sure that that makes sense to me
first cuz I don't really know what's
going on there
so let's take a look at when those
collision volumes actually get set I'm
guessing that they yeah they don't
actually get set inside here they get
set presumably when you actually create
one of the entities so here we're adding
an entity
yes so I don't know collision volume
isn't ever getting set there but didn't
we use this specifically because it Oh
interesting
hmm so we don't create collision volumes
for our non apron entities
so that's an issue because I really I
think we want those right I mean we want
those collision volumes to be there and
they don't have to get used for
collision but we need these volumes for
a lot of stuff such as distributing
grass on the enemy there's a whole bunch
of things we need it for right so when
we do this collision volume here I think
we want to do that in both places when
we do regular entities as well so this
part here where we're actually creating
this thing and we're adding the piece
onto it like this right here I think we
want to create the collision volume for
the entity in exactly the same way so we
want to do
we want to do a get volume from Minzy
kind of a situation here we've got the
wall height and we just need that that
entity relative bit so I think I think
we want to just do the same thing now
the tile in this case we should have
that tile in both cases and we do so I
think we should be able to do that and
it should be okay right
we'll have to debug that and possibly
visualize it but I do think that's what
we want and then when we come through
here in theory this collision flank
should not be garbage anymore
yeah so that's that's more what we want
and that's good so now we should see
these values being more valid at the end
of this so I don't have to stress about
it right so let's take a look at what
the cover value is now okay so that's
much better
right that all looks good looks good
okay so that's one good thing the other
thing we're kind of gonna need here as
well and I guess I didn't think about
this when we we were doing it when we
first typed it in inside draw ground
cover I don't think I ever actually
moved this thing based on where it was
originally so for example when we're
doing this push Pride call and we have
this right min P here when this is
actually getting created when are we
ever offsetting it by the entities
position itself right because I don't
see that happening in here anywhere and
you know this this ain't gonna do it so
I feel like the min P was probably
getting offset in the other code in a
different way and we didn't do that here
so we need to that's the other thing
that would be why we wouldn't be placing
the grass in the right place potentially
so when we come through here and we look
at what it's doing like yeah you can see
here right we're offsetting it by a
bunch of information so I feel like that
that probably needs to happen as well so
what we want to do I think is in here
where we do a push right of the min P
what I want to do is take the entity
position and offset it by that right
because that's not getting counted for
all right getting closer but probably
still not quite right so let's see where
we're at
here's this is the debug belt so it's
excruciatingly Li slow what I'm gonna do
now is I'm going to break inside that
entity render call and just see forever
getting there so just the draw
ground-cover part and that will
hopefully give me a little bit more of
clues as to what's going on here so some
entities will have no ground cover and
some will have ground cover so i well
turns out the first one had it so that's
good because guys say we got a break
inside one that actually has some ground
cover if we look at what's ground cover
count is 16 that seems fine let's start
to take a look at what we actually
pushed down for sprites so the texture
handle was valid that we got and the
cover that we have here is seems pretty
reasonable right uh the only thing I
would say is the Z being negative that
seems wrong and I can't really think of
why the Z would be negative if it was
I would not think the Z's should ever be
negative so that that just seems bad but
regardless let's just look at what we
were gonna say here so if this entity
placement whatever it is there's the Z
value what's its collision volume here
so its maximum is actually below the Z
of the thing so I guess that's
technically correct I maybe we're saying
if there's volume wrong so we'll have to
go debug the collision volume as well
that's the that's the other thing we'll
do but otherwise let me look at the
sprite values see what those are
so all of this looks pretty reasonable
right so I don't think we're far from
working look I don't think we're in like
a ridiculous territory but we're
definitely not quite there yet right not
quite out of the woods yet the other
thing I would say is we're not
generating grass on the apron
now think about it so the actual grass
is not going to be there let me let me
go get us over to an area well or I can
just tell the you know what let's just
tell the apron to do it so when we
actually create the apron which is not
actual places that the player can go
it's just there for visual effect let me
go ahead and slap a ground cover on the
apron so that way we can see it right
when we start up so here when we create
this stuff and we add the tags I'm gonna
set it here so that it gets the same
thick grass ground cover because why not
and now when we run we should see if
there's any ground cover happening on
those apron and these or not right and
so you can see some but they're
obviously kind of weird and wrong right
but we're again we're getting there so
that's good so let's let's try and
figure out what's happening with with
that code I'm gonna look at just a few
really quick things and then we'll go to
the Q&amp;A so all I want to look at now is
when we do unpack our sorry I should say
fill unpacked entity I want to make sure
that this part of the process is working
okay so where we do the random UVW and
we get the point here for the cover P
and that we unpack it right I want to
make sure that there's nothing
particularly bizarre going on in there
okay so you can see so I forgot when I
wrote this code I didn't use the cover
key at all right so that's just totally
garbage
so this is actually that right so that
was probably a big part of that problem
as well okay so I'm gonna probably call
it there and we'll do more debugging of
this tomorrow but I think we're
basically where we want to be we've
we've done the systemic work there's
just some tuning but I think we're good
so if you look there you can see that
we've now got like rudimentary ground
cover sort of working I think the Z is
wrong on these so I think the collision
the collision volume is actually in the
wrong place so we need to debug that
tomorrow but you can see the ground
covers working okay now right and and
honestly that's pretty much it so we're
almost there the ground covers it's too
big at the moment you know it should be
more like that but other than that I
think we're okay the other thing I want
to take a quick look at is can I just
fix that Z value and then at that point
we're pretty much going into tomorrow
with mostly done and so then we can
maybe start looking at lighting and
getting the ground cover lit and all
that stuff all I wanted to look at here
was inside the room gen right when we're
actually this one we know that these
have correct collision volumes I believe
although I don't know if we Mankowski
some of them I don't think we do right
yeah so when we're actually creating the
collision volumes in here I'm putting it
sort of in the wrong place I just kind
of slapped it in there the question is
what was wrong with what I did why is my
Z getting kind of off I want to look at
how the piece is getting added at the
inside this one here how are we adding
it the the display piece there you can
see it's calling get radius and get
center on this thing called Vall which
is is actually the collision volume of
the unit what I'm assuming is this right
here
yeah I'm assuming that this is just
garbage we should be really doing this
ad piece call the same way we're doing
it here I think so I think what we want
to do there is when we get that wall
height right we just want to do this so
I'm gonna say yeah the ball is gonna be
the wall height and it's gonna be
relative to that p-value we're gonna
come in here and use the same stuff we
were using for the piece and get that
ready the oh seven oh seven part again
should be baked into the tiles automatic
creation of that stuff so then I'm gonna
call get center here so and I think
that's now those are in line more so
when we call this vowel call then the
place where we set the collision volume
to that should now be able to just use
that value directly now again I don't
really know why we were getting the
wrong Z there cuz I think that should be
basically doing the same thing but let's
just see what happens here I want to see
where we're at
okay I see what's going on so basically
that it's because the the volume wasn't
offset by how by whatever the stagger
was all right so let's just fix that and
then I think we're done for the day
good I'm glad we looked up what that was
that was gonna bug me if we didn't so if
you look here what happens in terms of
the staggering so
I guess I'm not sure why that would have
flattened everything out though what am
I missing there because that p-value
there's the randomization sort of of the
up and down float of that nd
oh I okay yeah I see so when we're doing
this make relative to and we're saying
we want this volume to relat to it this
is not offset yet so it hasn't been sort
of you know sort of triggered for any
kind of displacement that you might want
it to have like an uneven displacement
right so really I guess you want to do
this which is a little wonky and again
we probably want to streamline these
more now that we have good utility
functions we probably want to make those
a little bit more clean so that it's not
so weird and hard to parse there right
oh that was weird so when we actually
take the wall height and we get the P
here then we just need to do our
displacement right that's all we don't
need to take the wall height into
account at all and then when we displace
the entity the vault the collision
volume will just go with it
right so I think that should be fine the
only question is yeah where do we place
the like part you're actually standing
on but I think that should be fine so
then when we place the
when we place the actual part you're
standing on which it would be here this
needs to get sort of put at the top so
it sort of needs to yeah it needs to
take into account what the actual
collision volumes Minzy is for the area
so that because the ground P is up on
top of it right so in this case yeah the
ground P would be what
I guess it's just in the center which
that would be and then it's actually
well it's just the max of the the volume
right so whatever the offset is for the
entities actual top part that's what
it's gonna be
again I don't like having to do all this
math in here we really want this to be
something you can ask about entities and
I think we should kind of maybe tomorrow
that's actually what we'll do is clean
that up so that we're not constantly
talking about all these little pieces
like this but yeah the volume actually
has a right get dimensions I believe and
so you just want to go up to the top Z
wise and that's where you would place
the actual traversal point that entities
are standing on I think right well it
doesn't look like that actually worked
right because that's what when I
actually place where that ground P is
gonna be although we're we're not
actually using it
so when were we actually planning on
specifying that though like when are we
adding that traversable it's the
traversable that I wanted to change
when's that getting added
I don't know I don't know oh there it is
okay I'm like I'm losing my mind
so this is actually the part that I've
meant to change right so this actually
needs to be offset up from the ground
that traversable by whatever the amount
is here that you're actually using so
when it creates this information it
needs yeah it needs to know this ahead
of time right because that traversable
is always going to be however far up the
volume actually is and so yeah when we
come in here we've got to do like okay
what's the wall height and actually know
where the wall height gets set
differently okay it gets set differently
in here right so when we set the wall
height then we'd have to do this and
then we'd have to do this right so
assuming that we want a traversable on
this particular thing we need to place
the points such that it exists at the
top of the volume we know what that
actually is because we have the volume
here right and off we go I think this
could also be called get minzy's entropy
yeah so we can also just sorry maxi's
entropy so I think we can also just ask
for that position that's at the top of
that that volume and again this is all
relative to the entity so that should
work all right so I think that's all
fine the only thing I don't know now is
to what extent does that still line up
with room boundaries let's double check
that nothing particularly odd has
happened here
this looks fine so I think all that is
pretty good looking at the size of those
I'm just gonna adjust that now and then
we will call it a day so on my fill I'm
gonna say that those should be about
point 5 I'm also gonna say that maybe
there should be more of them and then
we're gonna say that that is that and go
to the q-and-a don't really know what we
want to do with some of these ground
recoveries things in the future but um
yeah so you can kind of see that we need
to start lighting them because they're
drastically different colors than the
things under that they're underneath but
that was you know we were going to be
lighting sprites soon anyway so that's
not really a big deal and we'll get to
that when we get to that we otherwise
are in pretty good shape here
I think these want to be maybe a little
slower than that they go up quite high
on the hero you can kind of see although
I guess they don't really when when when
the hearest well know that I guess they
kind of do so they are quite high so I
guess maybe maybe I was being a little
overzealous there of course I'm just not
sure how that maybe that the art assets
need to be drawn slightly differently to
sort of how we're doing these here but
I'm not really sure how they should be
set up to be roughly the right size
relative to the hero and and all that
stuff
so that might be more of the correct
size
yeah and then we just have more of them
and also even at this number if they
were distributed more properly I think
you would be fine with that too
right let's get the maximum number in
there just to stress the system as much
as possible
alright let us go to some Q&amp;A
oops that's not Q&amp;A there we go so I
think yeah I think we're in good shape
here but you can also see the slowdown
from it so I think like again that's the
saying we kind of want to motivate here
it's a frame display I don't know to
what extent we yeah like we're probably
stressing out the render too much we
also need and generate MIT maps and
stuff like there's so much we could do
to take heat off the graphic card that
we're not it we're we're really abusing
it right now and so you know kind of
going through that lighting pass and
making everything look nicer I think
that's a good like good kind of general
goal now that we've got you can all see
that there too sparkly right and that's
again because it's we need them to be
MIT mapped and we don't MIT map anything
yet and so it's it's pulling from a
drastically large amount of texture
memory for no reason right now - but
we're getting there I'm pretty pleased
to intend coverage to be used for things
like footprints and do you want cover to
be interacted with like grass shifting
as you walk through it to show a path or
someone has walked
so I guess I haven't really thought too
much about whether I wanted that or not
but one of the nice things about kind of
doing it the way we're doing it I
suppose is that that's pretty easy to do
so like for example if you did have some
parameter in there that you wanted to
modify now that becomes relatively easy
to do so for example suppose you took
the ground spec like if you want to do
something like that suppose you took the
ground cover spec and we made it a
little bit larger so we said in addition
to the 16 bits of data that's going to
say the type and the density like maybe
there's some other parameters that kind
of come in here that can be set by the
the game as people do stuff like who
knows what and so there's going to be
two more in here that are like reserved
a and reserved B for now because I have
no idea what right but we could totally
for each one of those set those as the
ground cover happens and then rebuild
the ground cover so for example you
could you could say that's every time
inanity lands on a section so like I
don't know where the best place to do
this would be but like inside the code
where we actually track when you land
down so when an entity is like hopping
along and it lands
[Music]
just trying to think about exactly what
needs to happen here
where do we actually do that
transitioning to planted that's what I
was wondering um so right here where we
do this you know you could do oh there
it is
that's spawning middle of fire so where
we do that we could at this point say
okay so whoever like is whoever you're
actually standing on we want to tamp
that grass down or something right
so like something like this you know I'm
saying and so when we call stomp on
enemy we'd probably say something like
well who is the actual entity that we're
now kind of stepping on right and I
guess that's the entity occupying there
let me make sure I have that right it's
been a long time since we didn't
anything with this but the but the
actual like thing you're standing on is
its I think called occupying right
answer traversable reference and so it's
gotten any ID in it right so I think
what we could do is say alright take
this this entity here and like update it
this actually spawned fire could happen
there as well but I guess we'll say this
person stomped on that person right
something like that you know I'm saying
and then what we do is we say that call
stomp on entity and that's really what
to name these here but I guess we would
call them the like stomper and the stomp
II um you know we could say all right so
who's ever doing the stomping they're
gonna like spew out some some crap right
but then we also want to take the stompy
and I guess in this case this section is
the ID look them up and see you know who
is that actually so the stompy equals
get enemy by ID of the stompy and if
that's actually a person maybe we want
to go in there and muck with it so then
we say like okay yeah the zombies like
ground cover
in fact I guess you could even make
footprints be one of the ground cover I
wasn't gonna do that but I guess you
could do that what I was gonna say is
let's just change like the color value
here so you know we would set maybe we
just say like okay the ground cover that
actually was requested in here so the
ground cover specs I'm just gonna reach
in I'm randomly doing nonsense here
right I'm gonna say that the reserved a
value is now set to 1 instead of 0 like
it was before or something right
and then I'm gonna say - like update
that entity so you know this this call
here I'm gonna call that again right so
you know that gives us some way of doing
something right we now are tracking
where you've stomped around and so maybe
we just want to do so what or will
actually heck sure forget the reserved
part for now let's do something even
stupider
let's just plant eight flowers
everywhere you hop right
make sense now in these you probably
can't really see them cuz they're
probably too tiny although it doesn't
look like they're actually happening are
we not properly oh because we don't have
enough space in the ground cover we're
out of space there we need more space in
our entity for the ground cover
lucky for me enemy max ground cover is
actually kind of cheap to expand because
again it's only in the local cache lucky
me it's almost like I planned for this
so I think you can just kind of go
through and do that and off you go right
and so you can do whatever probably with
a system like this you've got a lot of
flexibility you know I'm saying to you
now I don't actually want the hero to be
dropping flowers everywhere they go
particularly much that that doesn't
thrill me but you know let's say you
were trying to implement the like forest
spirit from spirited away you know well
now you've got it
I can even create it in my dungeon all
right those guys will do it too
so it's just kind of like a flower
festival here right you know which
depending on how much you like those
little flowers you may or may not care
for
will there be a sort of transition from
the doors to the outside
I suspect yes but curious of how I don't
think I know what you mean
transitioned from the doors to the
outside
got a fixed I have to stop taking that
alpha we got to put it to do in there
should just add it to our list can I can
I add it to our list err no because we
got logged out thank you so much
Oh will there be a transition of the
grass I so what I would probably say is
we will do a little bit but not much so
probably all we really do is right in
this region will have like less density
of grass and then will have more density
further up right but that's like we're
not we aren't even lighting our grass
yet so we're kind of not the point where
we're ready to be thinking about that
sort of thing obviously right that's
like a graphical update
if you step on a town more than once
with a flower sack only if we want them
to so right now they don't right they
they would just kind of you get one
splat of tiles and then they're done if
you wanted them to stack then what you
want to do is increase the density each
time so basically on here what you'd
want to do is say this is plus equals
eight so that they stack but then
remember you don't want to go too high
because eventually you'll overflow and
rap to zero I'll let it wrap to zero now
so you can see what I mean
but you would normally want to threshold
that value some at some maximum and then
don't go above that but if you don't do
that then what you can see is you just
keep adding flowers and flowers and
flowers and flowers and flowers and
flowers and flowers until finally you
wrapped the eight bit counter and then
you would get none so I should in theory
if I just keep hopping long enough I
should be able to wrap that value around
and then it'll go back to zero but it's
gonna thank me a little while to do it
there it is see it so normally you would
you would just threshold the value at
the maximum number of flowers you wanted
to put there right whatever that number
is but
all right
these guys have been this entire time
making flowers haven't they oh I guess
not because they wouldn't start until we
got here but they're just like little
flower dropping machines right
alright looks like no questions so I
think we're done I'm gonna pull that out
because I don't actually want that right
now but yeah that's how you would do it
we probably will do something like that
but not at the moment right and not
exactly that all right thank you
everyone for joining me for the upside
handmade hero it's what a pleasure
coating with you as always if you would
like to follow along the series you can
always fear it again and handmade he
rode up or gonna come to the source code
so you can follow along with it at home
I will be back here tomorrow at which
point I'm not sure exactly what we'll do
there's a lot of things we could be
doing right now and so we probably want
to do some of those things working with
the ground cover a little bit more is
probably a good idea however moving on
to the lighting is definitely something
I want to do because I'd like to get
that sorted and finished ground cover
and lighting were two of the big things
that we just had left to do that just
weren't done in the engine and so with
that I think that's probably it for our
cosmetics right I mean it's looking
pretty good I don't know yeah I don't
know that we have really anything else
we need to do in the engine why engine
land so I think at that point we're just
on gameplay I'll try to think if there's
anything else I want to do but we're
looking pretty good I like the look of
it now feels nice to hop around a
pretty-looking world so I think we're in
pretty good shape in terms of being like
nice nice visual right so I think like
just getting the lighting tightened up
and obviously improving also to a
certain extent the the ground cover
because we only just kind of hacked in
the first thing we probably want good
yeah better distribution there and
other stuff like that get the MIT maps
working so that stuff so so we'll push
forward on that and till then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet techies everybody