start growing hello everyone and welcome
to handmade heroes sure we could a
complete game live on stream and part of
programming an engine which we do since
we're doing everything from scratch we
have everything from the very lowest of
low-level codes to the highest of high
level bits well shouldn't say high level
we have all the code you can assign
whatever level to it do you want the
part of that is definitely debugging and
performance analysis and one of the
things that we wanted to do now that we
sort of have our basic stuff all working
is we wanted to get some visibility into
how the code works so we're making a
little debug system where we can
annotate our code with some markup and
then while the game is running it will
display for us a bunch of information
about what it's doing and we've done a
bunch of work to record that information
but we haven't done too much work to
visualize it and that's sort of what we
want to work on today so today's a
coding day for sure's so it's day 184 if
you want to follow along at home and you
preorder the game take a look at day 183
source code unpack that to a directory
that's what I'm starting with here so if
you want to follow along with what I'm
about to do that is the source code with
which to start now where we left off is
we have the platform layer and the game
together running through the same debug
system which is nice even though they're
on either sides of that DLL boundary
they're running together which is great
so you can actually see it all happening
here right and we're sort of getting a
bunch of readouts these are the
functions that are all there some of
them are in the platform layer some of
them are not etc etc and so what we'd
like to do now is we'd like to start
working on how we can actually view this
information in a way that's going to be
you know more exciting right we'd like
to be able to do something where we can
we can explore we can investigate what's
actually happening in a way that doesn't
involve us trying to make sense of just
a giant tableau of numbers which you
know admittedly would be pretty hardcore
of us to do but why do something our
selves when we can program a computer to
do it right that's kind of why we
program computers in the first place so
what we're gonna do today is start
looking at how we could sort of collate
this information and and sort of use it
in a way to to make something more
accessible and more readily
understandable for us so that we can
explore it easily right so what I'd like
to do is start by having going back to
some of that concept that I had before
where we've got sort of a bar chart
thing so we can see on every frame what
the bar breakdown is and then I want to
be able to do something where we can
sort of drill down into it right so we
can kind of drill down into the bar in
some kind of a way so we can start by
looking at what's taking the time very
quickly at a glance and then sort of
refine and refine downward to sort of
get more of an opinion about what is
going on now there's some tough parts
about this obviously and I'll just
briefly mention what they are and we'll
we're gonna have to try and kind of
maybe think about what the best
interface would be in terms of being
able eyes that stuff so let me just
quickly say what that is
here's day 184 and this is like perf
counter visualization right
so one style is very very simple for us
to do and well I shouldn't say very
simple for us to do I mean we had to do
a bunch of work now just to collect all
this stuff and all that but so I'm not
because a simpler work up get it all I'm
saying is it's pretty straightforward to
envision if I have something that's like
you know a graph of the time where I've
got some different things in like you
know routine a B C D and E are all
represented here and these are like the
five top level functions of the program
or whatever they could called
then if I want to investigate one
further I could know I could click on it
or something and then it would open up
that and show me what its breakdown was
right like what were all the things that
took time for it
you know I and the problem with this is
that let's say there's some common thing
right so let's say that I do that for D
and I also do it for a right and then
I've got in here I've got you know f g h
i j k and then here I've got L M G n o P
right when I look at D and when I look
at a what I will see is the fact that G
the function is not taking an
appreciable amount of the time
necessarily right it's like it's not
like I would single that guy out as
being like greatly more than anyone else
on here but if I start seeing this G in
a lot of places then I'm like oh it
actually turns out that in aggregate G
is taking a lot of time because it's
taking a bunch of time from Deen is
taking a bunch of time from a and maybe
taking a bunch of time from E and so on
so we kind of need two ways of viewing
things right we kind of want to be able
to know two sides of the same question
we want to know hierarchically who's
taking the time so if we're trying to
optimize D and we're thinking about D we
want to know how much time G is taking
up of D potentially so that's one thing
I want to know but we also might want to
know how much time does G take up of the
frame in general without having to drill
down all the way to every single one of
them and then mentally try to add up in
our heads how much that is
that's no good right so I feel like we
kind of want two ways of viewing it we
want one way which is sort of like we
want one way that's hierarchical right
so we want like a hierarchy view which
is this kind then I think we also want a
like top top slow people or something
right something which then says okay I
don't care about the call graph I don't
care who calls who don't matter all I
want to know is this routine whatever
this routine is I want to take how much
time it's spent say exclusively of its
children so I'm not going to count as
children I was going to tell this time
spent in that routine and I want to know
sort like all of the functions and put
them in here right or something like
that
or you don't even necessarily have to
sort them just draw them all in the bar
graph and the ones that are don't to
give me time will be tiny and the ones
take up a lot of time will be big or
something right
so that's that's what I would like
that's that's what I would like to see
and I think that that's probably good
enough at the moment is just being able
to view it in these two different ways
so I'd want to be able to like pick
between those two and and that really be
it for now okay so that's what I'm going
to try I'm going to try to make
something that works like that and so
let's just get started right let's just
see what we can do
pushing towards that and that'll be the
goal for next week is getting a nice
view thing in so today we'll just get
started on that so if you only have one
day where you know before the end of the
week we're not gonna probably get that
far but we'll just do what we can so
here we are in the debug code and we
have sort of our collate debug records
thing I'm pretty sure update debug
records is not used anymore right look
we don't even do this thing at all so
I'm just going to go ahead and delete
right it never gets called by anyone
it's it's old and so what we'd like to
do is kind of revamp what we're doing
here we've got these hex get hex things
what is that oh this is so this is for
that sort of weird debug text-align
thing where I indulge people's fantasies
of weird text on lines and stuff like
that
all right so I'm gonna skip that stuff
for now because that's not super
relevant so we have here we've got these
debug statistics I don't know that I
super care about those debug statistics
at the moment so I'm gonna leave them I
mean there's nothing wrong with it as it
is but I'd say but I don't think we care
about that too much so in the debug
overlay I'm just gonna start here and
I'm gonna sort of pretend that we can
you know kind of do whatever we want to
do here I'm gonna pretend I have
whatever I want and I'm gonna draw it as
if I had the data structures I want and
then I will go like reverse engineer
essentially what those data structures
would have to be and then I will make
the collation functions make them for me
right that's my that's my thought on
that so what I want to do at the outset
is I want to have two modes right I said
I wanted two modes so I'm gonna want
like one mode well I'm drawing a bar
graph but I have two sources for the bar
graph so I might just say that I've just
got the bar graph so maybe the collate
whatever the collate does produces a
structure that I can walk that is what
the bar graph should look like right
something like this and so what I do is
I'd say okay instead of any of this
stuff I don't even know I don't I don't
want to really know what this does I
don't care I'm just gonna like get rid
of it temporarily
zero yeah I don't care about any of that
stuff that's gonna go away for now
so I'm gonna come in here and I'm going
to say that yeah I'm gonna say that this
is essentially going to run very similar
to the way that it ran before so we've
got you know the settings here we have
like how high were charts gonna be this
is all you know can just remain the same
cuz we're just making that chart right
then we've got this snapshot index thing
and it's gonna run over however many of
these we want and again the snapshot
count I think at this point is now going
to mean something slightly differently
really what that's gonna do is like the
frame look back is what that's more
gonna mean right how many frames have
looked back we have and so these these
snapshots and stuff this is not gonna be
a meaningful thing anymore and I'm gonna
kind of get rid of that temporarily I
thought I think T bucks take to the
counter states yeah yeah in fact this
stuff doesn't really even need to be
stored over time but that's a separate
issue all right so what I want to do
here is I want to say we've got some
number of frames right so we've got
frames from zero to something which is
going to be like something in a frame
count so this is gonna be like debug
state frame count or something like that
and then for each frame I'm gonna go
grab whatever that frame is I'm gonna
say debug state frames plus frame index
like so and then inside here I'm just
gonna go ahead and do like for the frame
I'm gonna say that there's like some
number of elements in the frame right
and I will just go frame elements count
and I will what did I call this before
well they were events I guess it's not
really so it's not only an element it's
more like a region index let's call it a
region index
feel like a region index is good region
index is good okay that sounds
reasonable
yeah okay and so the scale here we're
gonna have to work on the scale a little
bit talk about that in a second so when
I come through these regions I have a
debug frame region I'm gonna call that
region I don't know what it means I'm
just drawing it right because I'm gonna
use the same bar chart drawing code
regardless of which of the view types
remember I said I kind of want hierarchy
and and top people I don't want to have
to like write to so code for the same
thing so I'm just gonna say that I just
don't know so I just got region
so whatever the frame is its regions
plus the region index is gonna get me
out whatever that that region was right
and so that's fine and then in there I
will have something that will tell me
how big you know this thing was supposed
to be does that make sense so there is
there is sort of one additional factor
that I'm not sure how I want to handle
and that is also the fact that I I kind
of need these things to be able to
support I suppose multi-threaded sorts
of stuff so I'm not sure how I want to
do that like you know if we're single
threaded we can just use the bar but if
we're multi threaded we really have kind
of like multiple tracks right so a
single bar you could almost think of as
having like multiple tracks so in there
you know you might have a thing that was
like doing this sort of nonsense where
you sort of have like this thread is
doing stuff you know and and and then I
guess we would you know we'd want to
have sort of a notion of when a thread
was not doing anything so we could mark
it it's not actually being used or
something like this but there's
definitely sort of this this notion that
when in trying to give like a nice
coherent snapshot of what's happening
it's a little bit tricky because you can
have sort of multiple different regions
of the code being active at the same
time because there's multiple processor
cores that could be executing those
regions so I'm not sure exactly how to
handle that maybe I'll just do it by
segmenting the bar if that makes sense
that seems like probably the right thing
to do but I don't know it might be too
much information kind of crammed into
one space maybe the smarter thing to do
is to have a different chart per
processor or something like this but I
feel like you kind of want to see them
on there it's just my thought just so
you can have sort of that quick visual
idea of what's happening per frame and
we don't have to have that many frames
of look back actually displayed like we
might want to store 60 frames to look
back or however many we can afford to
store without taking up too much memory
in the machine right we maybe restore
that many but that doesn't necessarily
mean we have to show that many so we
could make the bar is fairly thick
right we could make the bars be fairly
thick as they go across and at that
point it would be pretty easy for us to
show more in there so I think I'm gonna
just try that that's gonna be my first
sort of thing that we try so I'll do
something like you know channel width or
something like this or like core width
or something like that laying with maybe
and the lane width is going to be let's
say four pixels or something like that
or maybe it's eight pixels maybe it's
how wide it was before and then the lane
count is probably gonna be something
that actually comes from the debug state
so we'll just say that there's a lane
count that that's set there and so the
bar width is whatever the lane width is
times whatever the lane count is you
know and so we come through here and we
say alright that then gives us what we
needed to now which is you know how big
the chart should be and all that stuff
and the bar spacing the bar spacing
should really be based on the bar width
so it should really be the bar width
plus however much space we want however
much space we want in between bars so we
can leave that as something like that so
there we go chart height chart with that
stuff all stays the same I think and
that looks fine to me the scale again is
something that we would need to worry
about sort of separately I think that
might be something that we want to put
in here right so we'd have like a scale
value in there and I don't know what we
want to call that we want to call that
like the the frame bar scale right and
this is I guess would be the frame bar
Lane count it's not like that okay
so this is going to be the frame count
and the rest of this is pretty similar
so we come in here we've got the frame
we've got this stuff we don't need the
pre-second seni more we're not doing
that kind of dipping or anything like
that so in here we can just say oops
is that out and here we can just say
okay we've got the colors we take a look
at whatever the region index is I guess
and we just use that color so that we
just tried alternate colors as much as
possible even though we really don't
know exactly what's going on there and
so you know we also kind of want to know
we kind of want to do these per Lane I
feel like we kind of want to do these
per Lane I'm not sure I'm not sure how
to do this part exactly we'll see so I
don't know how to grab out the color
because I don't really know I mean I
guess I could use the lane index plus
the region index or some weird thing
like that but I guess we'll just use the
region index for now and we'll see we'll
see what we have to do to make that work
in terms of the proportion what we need
to do is just take whatever the thing is
you know the proportion the height that
sort of stuff we need to basically say
that whatever the region is that's going
to have the information in it then we
need to figure out where we're at now
it's worth noting that all of this stuff
is pretty much constant right so this is
going to be like a stack X that sort of
Val value I assume so we can just do
that right where we can say okay we've
got where we should be on the X on the X
for this bar and then all we really have
to do here is add in whatever the lane
index is so wherever this is Lane index
wise that's gonna have that Lane width
added to it
right so that way we can kind of move
the thing over so that should be it for
that and then the bar width instead of
being the whole bar width is just the
lane width now and in fact I guess this
is also just the lane width now as well
right so that's good so all we really
need to do is figure out what the height
is I guess and now the problem is our
stack Y is actually gonna be whatever
the excuse me the max debug lane count
is I suppose right
so whatever the like whatever the lane
count is for these bars we need to keep
a separate stack Y for each of them does
that make sense
because as we stack those things up we
kind of need to make sure of that now I
suppose we could force the calling code
to sort things into lanes but III don't
know like I said we can make that
decision later I suppose so we can go
through the lane index to be like
whatever this is I guess a red count
stack y plus lane index so we can make
the stack Y for all the ladies Nexus
start out at the min and then we would
always just increment whichever one the
lane index tells us to increment right
we could always just make it go up I
guess the other thing we could do is
just store if we're gonna know begin and
end times we could just store those in
there as well I'd have to think about I
guess there's really no reason not to do
it that way because then we wouldn't
need anything right then we wouldn't
need this at all we just use the chart
min like so and we just have it so that
the region itself has its min and Max so
essentially what we do is we'd say you
know this this Y and this height it's
just going to be or this min Y and this
max why is just going to be the stack y+
whatever our scale is times whatever the
region's min Y was and then this one's
going to be the same thing plus the
scale times whatever the region's max Y
was right or max I don't know what we
want to call it max P I guess cuz we
don't it doesn't have it's not
specifically Y or anything else so max P
maybe I don't know
so whatever we've got there should be
sufficient because then the thing can
just put regions wherever it wants to
put the regions and it has the ability
to kind of represent that data in as so
much as it needs to and so yeah then we
just added that laned index and that
that all looks like it would be pretty
sane and then we don't care about this
and we just have to make it use these so
it would be in order to get the center
of that right we just all we do is we do
this min Y Plus this max Y that would
give us the center and then the lane
width Lane height thing we now know that
the height is just the max Y minus the
min Y right so that should draw the
chart right I mean a match that should
do it I would think so yeah that looks
good
so at that point I think we have the
drawing down and now we just need to
figure out what that would actually
entail so inside our debug state what
that suggests is what we would need to
store is the sort of debug frame region
things write debug frame region we need
to store those regions we would need to
do a debug let's see we had debug frames
and that it looks like it
we just need to store those and so those
debug frame debug frame region those are
going to be exactly what they imply here
so we know that we inside our debug
frame we know that we've got a region
count we know we know that we've got
regions we know that there's nothing
else at the moment so then we've got the
region the put that in the wrong place
we know that we've got the region that
has a minty and a max T and also a lane
index yeah so doesn't look like it has
anything else does it that looks like it
for now just for the drawing purposes so
yeah let's see how that goes
so if we were to do this thing where is
the deal what is the debug states it is
it even get that it just gets it from
here right yeah it does so these can
just be this is kind of nonsense right I
think that's true in fact in fact these
can actually just be pushed and popped
onto there I think I think
that's probably safe because that's our
memory right we can do what we want to
do with it so we can probably just say
all right we've got the debug state it's
just got a pointer to the frames the
frames have pointers to the regions and
everything's fine and this stuff is just
we don't even care about this stuff at
all in fact can we get rid of this at
the moment does anyone gonna complain
about that all right so our debug state
needs to have a few things added to it
it needs to have the lane count it needs
to have the frame count and it needs to
have the frame bar scale and now it does
when we're doing collation we don't
actually want I think to do a lot of
this stuff at the moment actually I'm
gonna just turn this off for now because
we need to rewrite this function to
produce the data we actually care about
so we don't actually care about that at
all counter count all right so this
stuff is all pretty much done as well
okay so I think that should give us what
we want for the drawing routine and it's
given us the specs so I think all we
have to do now is actually fill it out
because obviously it's not going to do
anything until we know until we fill it
out so all right let's go ahead and make
a kool-aid collating thing that will
actually fill that out to some degree
yeah
okay so I don't really remember how our
debug storage stuff was working I'll be
completely honest with you I have
absolutely no idea so how was that
working these are the only two places we
actually get it when we told the overlay
and when we update the records it looks
like that's the case so I think that's
just how it goes
apparently yeah so that means we can
just full-on use this as a scratch pad
every time through we can just go ahead
and recreate it and that is fine so
that's good that makes it really easy on
us our work is simple all right
so yeah let's go ahead and do that the
way we would do that here is by just
using the I just use the mandala system
for that right I just use our I just use
our arena this stuff so I think what we
would want to do there is inside the the
debug state who initializes the debug
state might be one thing I guess it
never really gets explicitly initialize
it's just initialize to zero so
presumably what we want in here is
something that sets that to zero right
so in oops in here we have something
like you know initialized and that gets
set to zero normally and so in here we
just go like you know assuming that we
have a debug state if debug state
initialized is not set we know we've got
to do some work to get things up and and
you know properly initialized and so in
here what I want to do is I want to get
a memory arena that's our debug arena
and we'll just call this you know
whatever this guy is it's gonna be
probably like our our collation arena
so what I'll do there is I'll initialize
that arena like we do everywhere else
right let's see where that comes in here
initialize arena so when we come in here
I will initialize that arena debug state
collate arena I don't even know if I'm
spelling that right I don't know how
many how many ELLs does collate have
should we just ask that question it was
too good I win the spelling bee so how
about that so for now I don't know how
much space we want this to have I
suppose we can just use whatever the
storage size is minus the size that we
already took for the debug state I
suppose we could just do that and maybe
later we'll decide we need to parcel
this out differently but for now that's
probably fine so then we'll just say
okay it's it's whatever the debug state
+1 is that's where we'll stick this data
so now we just have the ability to kind
of like allocate whatever we want
allocate inside our debug pool which is
what we want so that gets us started and
then what we want to do I think is we
want to have a temporary memory write a
begin and end temporary memory sort of
thing and so I'm gonna do here is just
say begin temporary memory and I'm gonna
begin that into the debug state like
collate temp and the idea here is every
frame I'm just gonna rewrite all this
memory every time because we're reco
leading like everything basically which
I don't know how like I don't know if we
want to try and do something clever or
than that we probably should but for the
moment I'm not going to just because
it's gonna be a lot harder to do it that
way so if it turned out that this was
somehow fast enough we'd just use it
this way it probably won't be
unfortunately but you know we'll start
this way and then we'll look at ok now
we got to do something a little more
clever where we you know
we collate incrementally or something
like this anyway so if we do our
kool-aid temp and we do begin temporary
memory then what we can do is every
Frank here we will just go ahead and do
n temporary memory and begin it anew
like so so that's that's all I'm talking
about something that allows us to
rewrite everything every frame it just
kind of vaporizes the thing that we had
before and that's this yeah no I'm not
and that is all I'm talking that's
that's all I was that's all I was trying
to say really
so handmade debug needs to be able to
use that stuff and of course it's up
here so I needed to kind of be a little
bit below this stuff which is a bit of a
problem actually to be honest with you
because the memory arena stuff we want
to add debugging into there as well
so it's kind of tricky the fact that
these things want to also be defined so
I'm literally just gonna move just these
above there because I want to leave
everything else below it I think that's
my that's my feeling that's my feeling
on that but that's that's just how I'm
feeling about it I feel like it's
important so that should do it and then
I'm gonna go ahead and call this collate
debug records thing I'm initialize these
other things so yeah so this stuff
should all be set to zero I think I'm
gonna say debug state frame bar lame
count equals zero debug state frame
count equals zero cubic state frame
Barras scale equals like one point I
wear something equally stupid or zero
and then I'm just going to call collate
debug records maybe I'll even put that
in there
maybe we'll say that it looks like that
who knows all right so when I call
collate and I call it with the debug
state in the events and whatever that
puts me in a good position to like start
setting the stuff up right I think right
that's all good yeah and so now we are
running just fine and in theory we've
got that memory that's kind of like
sitting there being ping pong a bowl for
debug and that's all good too so now I
just actually have to do some work here
to actually produce some some type of
collation for these guys now the way
that I had it set up before if you
remember in platformer dot H I've got
basically a set of arrays of these
values right so every time we have a
debug event what it's doing inside the
stay bug table is it's going ahead and
like putting it in here and every time
we go to like read stuff out of the
debug we you know we flip that event
counter you know and now that I think
about that and I am thinking about that
now that I think about that it seems
like the more intelligent place to do
that is at the frame marker
I'm gonna leave it like it is anyway
so when we come in here we've got this
array of events and these actually go in
order they and in fact in some sense
this was stupid I don't know why I kept
that code in there I was like oh I
should keep that code in there but that
was actually not true because what I
actually want to do in the kuwaiti buy
records is I want to actually look at
all the events so what I actually want
to pass to collate debug records is I
actually want to pass dacoity records
what range of events it should be
considering when it is considering the
events that it considers and in addition
to that I need some way of storing how
many of those there are so in here I
also need something that's like event
count right and I need the same of key I
need the same in each of these so we
need something that's like here as well
max debug frame or max debug frame count
something like that and that's in here
so then when we come through here every
time we have the end of an event every
time every every time we have the end of
a like a notification on the end I'm
going to know how many events we had
because it's this right here and what I
need to do is I need to store that piece
of information
so whatever the event array index was at
the time I need to go into the global
debug table take the event count there
right and set it to what I now know the
event count to be so it's actually you
know just keeping track of that as we go
because otherwise we have no idea how
many actually got filled out in there
yeah so yeah and it also brings up the
fact that really we could have just you
could just have pointers into that thing
it doesn't matter but there's some other
ways we could have structured that as
well it sort of starts to become clear
like how things could be done
no no that's necessarily any better but
it's like okay there's some reasons why
you might do it a different way anyway
so when we go ahead and do the rest of
this stuff when we call collate debug
records what we want to do now is say
okay I know what event array index we
just ended on right so this is the one
this is the one that's done so I need to
pass that to collate debug records so it
knows that everything other than the one
that's right after that one is the one
that we could do right so I'm going to
pass it the one that we just finished
and then also the one that we now that
is now being used right in fact that's
probably just the thing to pass it is
just global debug table whatever the one
is that you no longer can use it needs
to know that and then add what the heck
I'll also pass right the one that's
that's just finished
so inside here we would say most recent
event
array index and here is the one we say
invalid event
array index okay and so what that's
doing is I'm saying I I have essentially
what is a circularbuffer of a rent
arrays right each one of these things is
like an event array that has like tons
of stuff in it and what I'm saying is
all right I just got finished writing
this one right so that's I want to know
which one that is that's the most recent
yeah and then I have one that I'm
writing to this one right here and so
you can't use that one that one cannot
be included because some like a variety
of different threads could be writing to
that right now while we're used
something else so what we want to do is
we want to assume that the one
immediately after that one is the one to
start with and that we would eat all the
rest of these up to the most recent one
so that's how we want to process these
event arrays as we go hopefully that
makes some sense if it doesn't make some
sense
well sometimes programming just doesn't
make sense I mean what are you gonna do
right I think this is actually gonna be
a wild it I think possibly now you know
what it could be a for loop so I'm gonna
go event
array index I am going to start just
like we said with whatever the one right
after the invalid index is so this one
right here I'm gonna start with that one
I'm going to say if the event array
index well I guess I should also I have
to do the wrap did I can roll the wrap
there though you know what I think it's
gonna be a while loop I think it's gonna
be one so we'll just do or rather one of
these like infinity guys so I can do
this in here but I'm not going to
actually have a condition for exit right
so plus plus event array index is in
there and the condition for exit
unfortunately I can't actually write in
there and you'll see why it's because
whatever it is that I'm here I have to
first check to see if the event
array index equals the the max event
array count right so whatever no I
didn't put that in there
whatever this is if it equals that then
I have to set it to zero because that's
a wrap as it increments and then I have
to check if it equals the invalid array
index at that point then I would break
because that means I stepped past the
most recent one so again this is why I
was saying we really only need one which
is the invalid entry index that's the
only one we actually that we actually
need and so what I could do is just say
yeah don't bother passing this one just
pass whatever is the one that you can't
use right now so that steps through all
of the event arrays right so we were
guaranteed to visit them all and we're
guaranteed to visit them in the order of
oldest to newest which is what we want
because we want to go in temporal order
right
okay so now inside each of these we now
need to loop over all of the actual
events that they have because each one
of these has has events so each one of
these can have max debug event count
events like so and we need to take a
look at what what each of them does so
each one of these debug events can be
accessed pretty trivially it's just
going to be the global table events
event array index plus event index and
then we have the event and the events of
course has all of this information in it
and they're really the thing that we
care about here is the type so we need
to take a look at what the type is and
we need to do whatever it is we're going
to do based on what that type is okay so
we see the event type and we take an
action and again we know that we are now
seeing the events in their order roughly
from earliest to latest now on any given
thread we know that they're definitely
from earliest to latest but when
multi-threaded is taken into account we
don't necessarily know that exactly but
we do know that for the most part they
happen in the buffer in order I just
don't know how serialized are DTSC is in
that sense I suspect on the current
processors it's pretty darn serialized
but that's kind of a separate issue so
as we come through here obviously when
the frame marker when we hit a frame
marker we know we're going to kind of
latch over to a new set of a new set of
bars right if that makes sense so every
time we see those we're going to switch
over to like a new set of bars so we had
the idea there of that being like frames
we had this concept here of a debug
and so we kind of have this concept of
debug frame you know current frame and
that's going to be like the very first
frame and so what we need to do there is
need to have a way of like doing you
know you know a next frame or something
like this so that when we come in here
or like an add frame you know so that
when we come in here and we get to a
frame marker we can just move to like
the next frame you know I'm saying
something like that and then in a begin
block and an end block we need to be
able to use that debug information that
we have here to sort of see what was
going on we don't actually know a core
index at the moment but we do know a
thread index the thread index is not
necessarily numbered in a way that we
want so we would have to look it up
unfortunately but that's just kind of
the nature of the beast
that makes sense also there are some
ways we could
there are ways we could probably make
the threads be a little more be numbered
sequentially and that would be to use
sort of Windows declared thread local
storage or something like this but so if
we don't know that we can necessarily
count on that on all the platforms and
we might want to have our profiler work
everywhere instead of just on Windows or
something like that I don't know we
might want to have the lookup sort of be
based in here right but so when we do a
begin block or an end block like either
of those two things we're going to be
doing more or less the same stuff in
fact to some degree we may want to sort
of have like we might want to kind of
have this stuff be relatively pulled out
here right so maybe at the top before we
switch on the event type maybe we do
some stuff here right
like so so in order to pull out the
proper debug record that should actually
be relatively straightforward right
because that's just gonna be whatever
the look at that there was a record
count oh that's a record count let's go
say not the event count it's okay there
was already there but that was a
different thing
totally fine so we would just do this
right we just do the thing that allows
us to go from an event to the source for
whatever it was so that's the source and
it's got the translation unit in there
and it's got the debug record index
which is what it uses to figure out
which one we were looking at for the
source so now we know both the debug
record and the event both hit counts
cycle count is not a thing anymore right
so I don't even know why me that's there
I have absolutely no idea that's just
garbage at the moment I guess so we've
got those two things and then we got to
look up some of this other stuff so we
have the clock but that's not
particularly relevant to us at the
moment so we should look at event clock
in a second but then we've got event
thread index and what we want to do is
turn that into a lane index so you want
to do something like get Lane from
thread index or something like this
right the core index at the moment we're
just going to ignore because we don't
even have a way of getting it
unfortunately and we've used these two
so that just leaves us to the clock and
what I would argue as far as the clock
is concerned is until we act and you
know what in fact this is true until we
actually see a frame marker we probably
just want to throw away all the events
because we don't actually have any way
of knowing how much of a frame we're
seeing until we actually see a frame
marker right so we actually want this to
be zero
so at the outset we just throw away
events we just throw them away until we
actually see
a frame marker I think that's probably
what we want to do that seems likely to
me and so as we come through here we
just do something like okay you know
when we get an event well okay I'll do
we'll do it a little bit we'll take it
one step at a time but point being when
we have the current frame thing we could
then say that the frame the that that
frame structure we could say that that
has in it the clock
the initial clock right in fact it could
even have like a begin clock and an end
clock because we actually know what
those will be
after we've sort of looked at this stuff
right so what we can do there is say
that we have a relative clock right and
the relative clock is going to be
whatever the events clock is - the
current frames begin clock that's the
relative clock for this event inside the
frame right pretty straightforward how
much time I got left five minutes of the
five-minute warning yeah okay then we've
got the lane index which we're gonna get
from somewhere and that would give us
what we need to know now like I was
saying I think we want to make sure that
that we kind of guard this stuff off so
this stuff will work no matter what but
this this relative clock thing will only
work if we have a violent valid current
frame so what I think we want to do is
do something like if event type equals
debug event frame marker then we do
whatever has to happen there otherwise
we just do here a switch on the event
type and if there's not going to be that
many event types you know honestly maybe
we don't really do anything else here
maybe we just make this be event type
let's debug event begin block else
assert event type
well you know I'll just for sake of
completion completeness okay I like how
that completed - nothing's found in
handmade that CPP is that from the
fountain awesome there you go
alright so begin block end block it's
all good
everyone is happy everyone is smiling
and excited about life and so then I can
just put that stuff in here right and I
know that I have a valid current frame
in that case so that's good
so in here what I do is I'd have the new
frame thing and that's going to equal
however we get a new frame which will
work on a second and then what we'll do
is say okay the current frames and clock
is going to be equal to whatever the
clock was here yeah
the reagent count well is just whatever
it is at the moment so that's pretty
much finalizes that frame right the fact
we can just do it like this and then we
can just say okay then current frame
equals however we get the new frame and
which will be trivial in fact I already
know what it is actually it's just going
to be right it's just going to be frames
frame count there it is yeah debugs
eight frame count plus plus so the
current frame is just going to be equal
to do you both state frames and that
just gets a new one off off of our I
think this one is going to say okay
assuming that there was a current frame
we said it's M clock once we have a new
one we want to set its begin clock equal
to the event clock and it's n clock
equal to I don't know what probably some
kind of value that lets us know that it
hasn't had an end yet and then its
region count is going to be equal to
zero all right
seems fair
I'll go ahead and compile this just to
make sure that it's all kosher looks
like it is and we'll make it not
implemented for this inline get Blaine
some thread
there's thread index and we will I
assume also probably have to do
something where we've got like a debug
state here to pass that and for now
we'll just return 0 and say to do
implement read ID
lookup okay so we're getting there we
got a ways to go before we have all this
sorted but we're getting there and I
think next week we'll be in very good
shape to make that happen it is
extremely hot here at handmade hero
studios I probably shouldn't be wearing
a sweater that was a poor choice of of
garment it's true but poor choice of
garment or no I'm going to go to the Q&amp;A
anyway so if you have a question please
go ahead and post it with aq : in front
of it and I will attempt to answer it
and a/c says you could have made your
loop this way for you 32 event area
index equals invalid event array indexes
one been erroneous is not equal to
invalid or minority mix event traitor
sequels it smacks you before yeah I did
want to save the modulo which is why I
didn't do it that way it's probably not
a big deal anymore
right like some of those things are kind
of habit habitual that there's really no
need to get out of the habit of so I
don't but it's true that a lot of things
like modulo are not really a big deal
anymore but it's like a part of you know
growing up with a certain set of things
being expensive like modulus is very
very very expensive in the old days you
would tend not to use it unless you knew
that the compiler or you could optimize
that modulus to something else and so I
still tend to not write things that way
I tend to write them in ways that don't
require a modulus when I know that one
was not necessary and I suspect that
that's something that people nowadays
probably don't do like people who grew
up programming you know over the past
five years was their first experience of
programming or something are not gonna
be afraid of modulus right they're just
gonna throw it around and that's fine
too but it's definitely something that I
avoid in cases where there really was
not necessarily you need to avoid it
like is it going to be a huge problem to
have a modulus in this loop I don't know
but probably not I wasn't in my head
thinking oh my god mod is gonna be a
problem it's just I tend to avoid it
kronole dragon says the track was a bit
distracted it happens elven what would
be the most important things you'd look
at when hiring a programmer what type of
questions would you ask does he have to
have like 20 plus years of experience if
I was gonna hire a programmer I don't
know that's a good question and it
depends on what I would want to be doing
if they're supposed to be programming in
parallel with me meaning they're gonna
go do something while I'm doing
something then yeah they would have to
have 20 years of experience probably if
it was the case that I was gonna have
somebody who was kind of gonna be like a
utility programmer for me where it's
like I'm programming stuff and then I'm
just telling them I want you to go make
this thing for me right now and then
like at the end of the day you give it
back to me
then that would be someone who I could
hire who I just thought was a good
programmer like that's like okay this
person is pretty good they don't maybe
have very much experience I don't
necessarily notice that what they're
doing all the time but like it's okay
because I'm gonna sort of like drive
that process and they just need to like
not make code that's bad which is itself
a total order but they don't have to
have 20 plus years experience cuz I'm
not expecting to make decisions I'm
expecting them to if I make the decision
be able to execute that decision and
that's a very different thing and so I
don't know these days the way I would
probably look for hiring a programmer
like that is now that people are
streaming programming I just say I want
to see your twist streams I want to see
your program on Twitch and I'm gonna
watch them and if I watch them in a
while I think you know what you're doing
then I'm okay with that if not that I'm
not because that's way better than
anything else because there at least now
I see how your programming I can watch
you program for a long time not in some
weird interview setting you're on your
computer with your editor doing code you
feel comfortable with and then I can
watch you write so I probably like show
me your twitch stream if you don't have
a Twitter stream I'd be like well why
don't you have a twist you get a twist
stream and call me back it don't gotta
be public
you could have it be private and you
don't have to talk you can just code
like pseudonym 73 does and then I'd be
able to see right Gary Johansson do you
think you do not need to ever worry
about modulus or divides any more um
it's not that you don't ever have
there's nothing that you don't ever have
to worry about it's more just like in
the context of what we are doing here
the amount of like data that we're
spinning through and the amount of
operations we're doing are probably such
that one modulus per loop iteration is
just not going to add up to very many
cycles by comparison to the total number
of cycles for the loop whereas in the
old days when you were talking about
like everything you know might have been
like one or two instructions that you
were doing but a modulus took like 40 or
more and memory accesses took like one
cycle as well or something like this
right that was a big deal nowadays a
modulus doesn't take nearly as long as a
cache miss right so it's just a
different set of trade-offs in your head
so habitually avoiding modulus is
definitely not though like it used to be
it doesn't mean you don't have to think
about it because just like everything
else it costs something but it does mean
that thinking about it as this big scary
thing doesn't really need to happen
anymore because it's not any more scary
than a bunch of other things that I
don't avoid right so that's really more
what I meant
which Linux debugger is closest to not
sucking and what is it missing I don't
even know man I don't know I don't have
a good answer for that I really don't I
wish it did but I they're all pretty bad
I don't know
original name 67 on a scale of 1 to
Visual Studio
why is he max of 1 and when will you
join the visual studio master race so
not to be too brutal about it but of the
good programmers I know I can only think
of one who uses Visual Studio only one
and he is somebody it's Shawn Barrett
and he is somebody who has in the past
used das command line edit for editing
and been fine with it
so I don't necessarily tend to take his
opinion of editor particularly seriously
or his selection other than him I
literally know zero good programmers to
program in Visual Studio there probably
are some out there but none of the ones
I know they all use something else Emacs
is not particularly good but it's a lot
better than Visual Studio because visual
studio is pretty bad
it's better than it was well it kind of
got better and then it got worse but
it's still pretty bad sorry this has
been asked before what keyboard using
this is a Das Keyboard 3 which
unfortunately I don't know if they even
make anymore
I liked the Das Keyboard 3 a lot I don't
like the Das Keyboard 4 so I'm kind of
been looking for a new keyboard a new
go-to keyboard I just ordered actually a
on someone's Twitter recommendation a
Razer BlackWidow stealth and I was gonna
try it out so I don't know how that's
gonna work but I'm still trying I try to
keep up labs 1 and it was a really well
made keyboard but just the keys were too
darn stiff for me
how did you get into game development
you know there's a big long story about
that if you're interested I think gosh I
think it was like all the way at the
beginning of handmade hero let's let's
see I don't know if the annotated
episode guide has it in there it might
so in the episode guide it might be here
but I'm not 100% certain no it's it's
not it's not there oh wait it might be
in the QA yeah yeah yeah so here it is
so you can go right here for that
actually this is it so
so intro to see on windows day 5 QA has
it and if you use the episode guide you
can get the little time markers so if
you go to what's your life story that
tells the whole story it's like a half
hour long and it has the whole whole
situation it's kind of a weird and
twisted odd path certainly it's not like
I woke up one day and was like I'm gonna
be a game developer and then went out
and developed games
Stevan last my girlfriend wanted to let
you know that she has the same water
bubbles you well
that is both good and bad for your
girlfriend good because I feel like the
glass bottle is nice for taste I feel
like things taste good and glass to me
but you know what the bad thing about
these is this this right here this is a
bad design all around a it's very hard
to make sure it's actually sealed
properly I have to like turn them over
and shake them in the sink to make sure
they're sealed properly because the the
ceiling onto the glass is often fraught
with peril and it won't get on there
exactly right and the other problem is
this part tends to break the like I've
had the rubber break like on here for me
so I'm not a huge fan
it's close to what I want but it's not
there yet they need a better top if they
fix the top then this would be like my
favorite water bottle but until then
it's got problems if your girlfriend
ever finds a better water bottle that's
glass please let me tell tell her to let
me know or you let me know
one or the other what decision process
you used to choose the color of sweater
to wear on a particular day it's
whatever is like the top of my laundry
basket because I just take when I take
the clothes out of the dryer I just put
them in oh I have like a few laundry
baskets I just take them out and I put
them in whatever like bin I have
available and then I just take clothes
off the top of it a slams here will you
please sign the contracts with twitch so
we can get good Casey emotes in chat
next time I talk to twixt which I will
ask them Elvan have you seen the poker
keyboard series it's very interesting in
that it has all the keys in the center
of the keyboard you never have to leave
the center row I don't know what that is
I have not seen it Steve unless we'll
keep you updated thank you very much see
x00 still using three-bin system for
clothes yes I am Elvan doesn't ever
happen to you when you sleep on a
problem and then wake up with a solution
we're just clicking your head yes that
happens to me all the time I've often
said that it's important to make sure
you get a good night's sleep because I
feel like you do a lot of programming
problem solving in your sleep if you're
anything like me anyway so yeah it's
it's a good it's a good thing to do I
highly recommend making sure that you
get a good night's sleep and let your
brain have some time to like work on
problems like my my pocket theory for
like how brains work is that at night
they do a lot of intentionally random
neuron firing which tries to build it's
it's like basically like if you've ever
seen a rapidly exploring random tree and
re arty like daytime is the drive to
point four
it's the drive to point phase for
concrete ideas and then sleep time is
the drive to point for random ideas so
like during the day you are trying to
get your brain to like build a path to a
particular solution of some kind and at
night what it's doing is it's randomly
going to places so that when you wake up
the neuron paths are already built there
for those states so that they're just
there all of a sudden and so when you go
to think about the problem again you
find oh there's one right next to it and
I can just hop right to the solution
from there right so it's like I feel
like it's one of these things you know
I'm talking about
and so like during the you know the
night time you are essentially building
new random paths onto your random tree
so that like when you wake up in the
morning you're like I'm trying to find a
solution that's like out here during the
day like you couldn't get to it but then
after a night sleep
it built all these extra ones for you
and so then like right there it's like
oh yeah it turns out it's like right
next to something I can toys you how to
get there I'm done right
let's see
Ashby igniter just for your sleeping I
don't know I'm not a neuroscientist so
this is just my theory based on what
I've observed myself how like it feels
so it's not really a science so I have
no idea it's just a purely random theory
that has no data to back it up
other than anecdotal all right I got to
wind it down I got to go soon
what time you usually go to sleep 10:30
I usually wake up at 7
could you please expand on what you
meant by in the future there won't be
dedicated hard for graphics you mean
it'll be more CPU cores and ridges and
said yeah my assumption will be my
assumption is that either everything
falls apart and they can't keep making
things faster which could happen or if
they keep figuring out ways to like make
better CPUs eventually the GPU cores
will just collapse into CPU cores and
we'll just have a mini core machine and
that'll be that
and so like yet maybe you still have
OpenGL or something but it's OpenGL
that's just implemented on those cores
but you could use them for something
else it's already very close to that it
just needs to take one big industry
consolidation phase for that to like
become a reality and so it won't
necessarily be ray tracing could still
be rasterization but it would be
rasterization on course that are more
are basically CPU cores and maybe
they'll be there still might be core
types in the sense of like what their
cache is optimized for or how their
memory is optimized or something there
might be certain things that still
change like there could be in order and
out of order cores or something like
this but in general they'll still be
programmable pretty much completely it's
my guess all right
would you think in the next five to ten
years they'll move us from 64 a bit to
hunch running 8-bit dude
they're already 256 bit Intel x64
processors are now - in a video 6 bit
and we're using hundred 28 bit registers
on the stream already but yeah alright
I'm gonna wind it down light it on down
yeah I'm saying little wind down the old
wind down alrighty thank you everyone
for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always pee order the game on handmade
here at work and it comes with a source
code so you can play around with it
definitely check that out if you're
interested in experimenting or doing
whatever sorts of crazy experiments you
have cooked up don't need to know about
it whatever you do you know like if you
want to do some weird things with source
code that's between you and the source
code right
anyway we also have a forum site you can
go to ask questions or get me an episode
guide I have a patreon page the patreon
page allows you to pledge the video
series just want to support the video
series that's place to do it we also
have a tweet bot the tweets the schedule
you and little reminders during the day
if you wanna catch the stream live it
helps you know when that's gonna be so
check that out if you're interested and
speaking of that we will be back here
next week on Monday to finish up our viz
code we got a couple days worth of work
to do to make some nice debug this stuff
there so that's what we're gonna be
doing so I hope to see you back here for
that and again check the tweet bot if
you wanted the exact time for Monday
because the schedule get posted sometime
this weekend so that's it for today have
a good weekend everyone I'll see you
back here on Monday until then where is
my thing
have fun coding and I'll see you on the
Internet viki's everyone