hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show Rico to complete-game live on
stream we have to go do some Huffman
decode stuff today basically we are so
we're implementing the PNG spec and we
did most of the like sort of outer
parsing stuff and now we're doing the
deflate portion which is probably the
hardest portion to get right I'm
guessing based on the spec cuz it's kind
of got the tweak iasts stuff would be my
suspicion so you know it's it's not a
particularly fun or interesting part of
things but it's just what you have to do
if you're gonna read compressed stuff so
there's not much more to say that's just
what we're doing and so here we go I'm
gonna go and load up our prj here I'm
gonna compile that and here's our PNG
reader as it stands right now and when
last we you know when we kind of
finished this up we were in here and
starting to starting to I want to move
this this is behind my head and that's
not gonna that's not gonna fly we were
starting to sort of decode the rather
squirrelly stuff that happens inside the
deflate portion of the PNG which is
right here and we have just a little
kind of crappy thing we wrote that gives
us bits at a time and the only reason we
did that is for convenience at the
moment because this spec happens to be
written bit at a time
anything that's Huffman encoded is
obviously going to be bit at a time
because the whole point of Huffman codes
is that you only read as many bits as
you need to decode a symbol so the
easiest way to implement that before you
start looking at things like how to run
more quickly or something like that is
to just go ahead and make it so that you
can read a bit at a time and actually
implement it literally even though
that's probably not what you want to do
if you were doing a fast PNG compressor
we're not particularly trying to do a
fast PNG compressor here we're just
trying to make one that works at all
okay so
back to our friend the specification if
you look in here we've got sort of the
the compression method stuff that we
were reading in the PNG and basically if
you remember it just referred us to
somebody else right it was kind of like
look when you get to the actual data we
don't want to specify how that works
we're just gonna use some other thing
that already exists so go read the
deflate spec which is an lz77 derivative
that's how we stored the data right so
it's like okay let's go ahead and do
that and so I believe this is also not
relevant to us right yes so I believe
all we really care about is this stuff
in here yeah so here's our deflate spec
and this is what we were working with
what we were told by the spec is that we
would get information here that told us
how to construct the huffman tables for
reading the huffman tables I know that
sounds a little weird but in order to
save space when they were tweaking one
of the things that happens with
compression right because you're trying
to like figure out how to compact the
most number of things efficiently you
end up having all kinds of TWiki weird
stuff that you just found happen to be
locally optimal for the kinds of stuff
that was in your corpus right they call
things a corpus a body of work basically
they call things of corpus which is
basically a set of things you test where
your compressor on to see how well it
does so what typically happens is people
make a compressor they run it through a
corpus they see how good the compressor
is and then they tweak parameters in the
compressor to try and continue to get
higher and higher compression ratios on
that corpus right so that's why you get
things like this where there's some kind
of a prescribed table in here that says
look we're gonna send you some number of
code lengths
and then we're gonna only send you as
many of them as we think that you need
and the order we're gonna send them to
you is not 0 1 2 3 4 5 79 + cetera it's
because a 16 17 18 0 8 7 9 6 10 5 11 12
right and why is that there well the
reason that's probably there was because
they just kept tweaking the order of
things in those tables until they found
the one that allowed them to truncate
the series as early as possible on the
most number of files right so tons of
stuff is like that like why is this 5
bits long well it's 5 bits long because
they needed to be able to specify
something up to 32 and that was because
that was the most that they needed for
figuring out how far back something
should be for the length of something
because on the data they tried six bits
and six bits ended up costing them more
and not saving enough above right so who
knows like all of the stuff in here
basically went that way that's how
compressor work were is that's how
people make compressors right is they
keep looking for more ways to save a bit
here save a bit there until they get it
down to what they think is the best they
can do for that particular design and
that's what you end up with so that's
why we have this kind of weird torturous
relatively obtuse thing going on it's
not because the people who made this
compressor were stupid or hated us it's
just because that's the nature of
compressors and this is also a very old
compressor so not only is it the nature
of compressors they also were doing it
in 1996 when this was probably the best
they could do nowadays there's probably
a lot of other things they could have
done that would have been better they
didn't necessarily know about them but a
lot of times that even makes them even
more complicated so it doesn't make
sense I really make it mean it would be
simple it just means that if you see
them going through a lot of lengths to
do something that seems like it's not
that great well don't forget it might
have been the best thing they knew about
at the time even though there's probably
better things that they could have done
today so let's get started on this part
here this is the part that we actually
need to to start working with what they
sort of said is we want to up sorry I'm
circling the run part I meant
this part so what they took a long time
to explain earlier on in the spec and we
haven't actually dealt with yet but it
is what we actually need to do is they
told us that the way they were going to
write Huffman codes out was rather than
store the code because the code itself
is what we actually need to know but
rather than writing out the code they
were just gonna write out how long the
code was and the reason for that is
because writing out how long the code
was is a lot less bits than writing out
the code itself right because for
example if you need to write out a four
bit code that takes four bits but if you
only need to say that a code is four
bits long that only takes three bits
right so again compression so rather
than specifying what the codes are they
just want to specify how long the codes
are why do they only want to do that
because it saves a little bit of bits
how does that possibly work well it
works because they don't care which code
gets assigned to which symbol
they just care how long the code is that
gets assigned to the symbol so the order
of assignment is arbitrary which means
they're free to pick one that is easy to
determine without knowing anything other
than the length so if we order our
symbols from smallest to least I'm sorry
from least to greatest like this ABCD if
we just know the length of the code that
is trivial for us to put that code in
because there's only one code it could
be at any given time right if we know
that the code 1 1 0 always precedes the
code 1 1 1 because we always put lower
codes before higher codes then you don't
need to tell me which of C and D is this
particular code you just need to tell me
that they're both 3 bits long and then I
know the first one we one 110 ISAT 1 1 0
and the next one will be 1 1 1 right all
makes good sense like I said it's
probably a stupid thing to do now
because you wouldn't even use a Huffman
code or something like this I don't know
after all
bloom he would tell you but that's what
they use so that's what we have to do
and it makes reasonable sense for what
they were trying right so what we need
to do is we need to follow this
pseudocode that they've specified here
count the number of codes for each code
length and let BL count be the number of
codes of that length right so we're just
gonna go through and I mean if we're
following a pseudo code we're just gonna
go through all of the links that they
told us and we're gonna just remember
how many of each when we saw this is a
histogram basically right it's saying
for every time you see five add one to
the five column right every time you see
two add a one to the two column and it
just gets you know a little histogram of
how many of each we've seen and then
it's science find the numerical value of
the smallest code for each code length
so that's just looking at where it
starts right then it says assign
numerical values to all codes using
consecutive values for all codes of the
same length with the base values
determined at step two codes that are
never used which have a bit length of
zero must not be assigned a value all
right so that's all we need to do
there's probably some subtlety there
we'll see in a second but they've laid
out a very clear course of action for us
if we just implement what they say
hopefully we won't get too many snafus
on the way but I don't know we'll see so
what I did when we were doing it before
and I didn't really know what we were
necessarily going to have to do there
because we hadn't looked at it in much
detail we have these sort of PNG
informational things that we've been
using and then we've got this guide here
which is the PNG Huffman technically
this isn't part of the file format so I
can actually move that out here these
are all in the file format right
whereas PNG Huffman is not so these guys
can actually be sort of like if that's
the file format this this is sort of the
the utility functions right so this PNG
huffing here is is what we need to use
to sort of store the
counts and we want to make something
that can like store the counts and then
process the counts right like so what
you can see here is we've got one we've
got this sort of thing going where we do
HC lense whistle to be honest I don't
know if I really need this PNG Huffman
thing because we probably don't actually
need that I may be a little premature
here to do this this probably doesn't it
this probably can be something that's
just an array but we'll see in a second
anyway so what you can see here it's
like we go through the the HCL and
swizzles thing we Swizzle the bits that
we consumed into that and then this is
the first time we have to do one of
these Huffman codes so what we were
doing is the eighth seal and Swizzle was
taking the bits that we read in we know
we have three for each of the filled in
indices and we're gonna sign them that
way so now we're gonna end up with
Swizzle data into a thing that's as long
as h.glenn
it's the h.glenn table that's as long as
H comes whistle some of that h.glenn
table has now been filled in with links
possibly all of it but we possibly
because we read it remember we read a
length here this right here we read a
length that length says how many of
these we had so we may only have the
first n and then there's just zeros
everywhere else right so then what we're
gonna do is we're gonna want to do our
first Huffman table generation here so
we need something that's going to create
a Huffman out of this okay so when we go
to do the compute Huffman h.glenn is not
really what we want here unfortunately I
think I probably did that a little bit
incorrectly this is actually this
because remember that so the way we're
doing this is we have a set of symbols
we have a set of symbols we've unpacked
them into this table right and now what
we want to do is we want to go ahead and
take that table and we want to scan
through the table and there'll be zeros
where there's symbols that aren't used
and actual values where there are
symbols that are used
so we need to go through the whole table
we can't just go through each clan
because we only went through each clan
we would probably stop before some
values that actually had some how do I
know because actually the high values
occur very early in here so even if the
value was only three we would fill in
like the 18th element right which is
like the last element of the thing so we
know that we have to process the whole
table so we really want to do a compute
often on that here's the table right and
then we want to produce a Huffman out of
it so what we could do is start to fill
in this function and then also we want
to sort of think about how we implement
a Huffman decode and that way we can
sort of start to figure out what this
PNG Huffman thing will be used for so I
have literally never written a Huffman
decoder before so I have no preconceived
notions about how you would do it I'm
sure the way I do it right now will not
be particularly good but that's okay
like I said this is just entirely about
showing how to implement something from
a spec if you have no idea how the thing
works at all
to be fair I do know how a Huffman code
works so technically speaking I guess I
do know something but I don't sit around
implementing Huffman decoders so it's
not like I'm like oh and then this is
just the way I like to implement Huffman
codes I make a table that looks like
this and something right that's not what
I would normally do so anyway let's go
ahead and take a look at this part
further and then after we do the basic
step of producing the table then we have
to think about how do we want to
actually store once we know what all the
codes are how do we actually want to
store this so that we can decode them
efficiently because there's a couple
Everywhere's like I think to do this one
way is if we know that the codes are
always small enough we could use a
direct lookup right we could basically
do something where all of the possible
values that have I'm not this is just me
like thinking out loud and some say it
that so you get zeros thank you thank
you so let's say we wanted like a really
fast way to decode Huffman really fast
is not the
turn let's say we wanted a really
straightforward but somewhat efficient
way right so let's say I wanted to make
a really stupid Huffman decoder so
there's two ways I could do it one way
is to make the slow and stupid and
that's basically like literally read one
bit and literally have like a node that
just says one thing or another right so
we literally build like a tree and we
read a bit at a time and go down the
tree right that's like the slow and
stupid way but there's probably a like
fast ish and stupid way then I'm just
thinking in my head here which is that
let's say we know our Huffman code is
bounded so we know that there are no
Huffman codes that are longer than let's
say seven bits long or eight bits long
right so we know that eight bits is the
longest code we will ever see because
probably in the spec summer where we're
looking at there's probably just it's
never going to be longer than this
because there's even if we assign
symbols maximally stupidly we would only
have this many or something right well
if that was the case we could make an
8-bit lookup table right that just had
okay if 0 outputs an a right and 1-0
outputs of B and one you know one zero
output sassy and one one one outputs a D
right so when we read a zero we output
an A you know I wrote those kind of
backwards because I should be actually
going LSB probably at the moment it's
hard to say what there should be left to
right order or right-to-left order here
but so like first
second third let's say so this is the
first bit that comes in this is the
second bit right so if I see a zero I
just have to put in a immediately if I
see a one I know I have to look at the
next thing so if I see a zero there then
I output a B if I see a one and A one
then I know I look here for one of two
different bit values then I get the C or
the D right so say that's my Huffman
code right and you know that maybe that
goes out to eight bits long eventually
or whatever who cares right well what
that means is I could just read this
number of bits in this case it's like
three bits right so it would be like a
three bit LUT and what I could do is I
can just put all I could put a x' in all
of the slots of the table that have for
all of the different combinations that
would be here so a three bit lookup
table is actually 2 to the third long
right which is 2 times 2 times 2 or 8
now there 8 aren't 8 symbols here so
what goes in the eight tables well the
eight things are this right 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8 right
here's all the entries so we know some
of them we know that 0 was a we know
that 0 1 was B right
we know that 1 1 was C and 1 1 1 was D
so what are we putting the rest of the
table well just imagine if we read out 3
bits that means that anything else we
saw here or here still codes for an A
and we want to just shift down one bit
so we put in here an A and only take one
bit right then into the other parts of
the table that also have a 0 but have
arbitrary other things up here we also
put a right I'm just imagining this in
my head I'm just thinking this through
again I've never implemented off the
minute I'm just talking out loud about
one way I could implement off in table
that came to me as I was reading spec
right so each time I write down what
symbol it is and how many bits to shift
out of the output right same thing with
B I know that could be one of two things
here so there's one B here's the other B
and that time I say take two bits each
time then for the C's I send the D I say
take three bits right here's my complete
Huffman decode table what I do every
time is I just look up a three dip bit
value based on the three bits I
currently have I output the symbol it
tells me and then I shift off however
many bits in my current value it tells
me and then I do the same thing again I
fill bits I fill in the bits that I'm
missing and I'd go again right makes
sense very simple so I'm just thinking
in my head how am I gonna implement this
right and that's one way I could do it
and that would allow me to do it with
just one look up so I don't need to go
down an actual Huffman tree looking for
a node which would be this like annoying
kind of you know skipped list thing I
could instead just do this and then I
just look up in a table and I get the
symbols output the symbol shift right I
don't know what you want to call this
let's call it let's call it the the
Lutton shift algorithm
you know patent-pending
2018 registered trademark TM so I don't
know so that's what I'm gonna say is the
way I might try to do it assuming that
the look-up tables aren't too big
because it seems pretty efficient now
the problem with this is if the symbol
length ends up being like 16 bits then
I've got a 64,000 entry lookup table is
not cool right 64 K lookup tables not
cool and probably not what I want so I'm
guessing that there's a limit to this
let plus shift algorithm
so you know yeah your mileage may vary I
feel like we could make a adjunct of
this like say like we did have to do 16
bits I feel like there's probably a way
to do it that breaks the that breaks the
thing down by just using a tree for the
top few bits and then a lot when you get
down to 8 you know what I mean so we
probably could do something like this
even if the codes get long but I don't
think about it some more my super
patent-pending awesome algorithm which
is not that awesome is probably amenable
to something like that if we needed to
extend it all right so with an eye
towards that I guess the other thing
that I'd say is so do we actually know
what the maximum bound is on the stuff
that we're looking up into these tables
because I don't really know about I
don't I don't know the answer that
question so be interesting to see in
here if that's like made clear one way
or another and so we could see so let's
see uh here's them talking about the
Huffman code so it says it right it says
here it cannot exceed certain maximum
code lengths so that suggests to me that
somewhere in here for every one of these
there someone should state what the
maximum code length is right
that's just talking about generically
how we do it
Bob what don't care about that don't
care about that let's see including 80
bucks to deflate for Microsoft secrets
of symbols drawn from three conceptual
jackpots literal bytes byte values or
lengths back for distance pairs where
the length is drawn from three to 58 and
the distance from 1 to 32 768 the
literal and length efforts are merged
into a single alphabet 0 to 85
[Music]
let's see so actually now that we look
at this with an eye towards my
patent-pending algorithm there it looks
like they actually already did it for us
right that's exactly what this thing is
they've got a Huffman for the first part
but then they stick extra bits to get
the rest right so it looks like they
already broke it into a small Huffman
table for decode guaranteed and then for
larger ones they didn't often those they
just put in some extra bits right so
that's pretty good we're not doing fixed
Huffman codes because that's not allowed
in the PNG it sounds like so we're only
doing these and it says let's see first
worth each codes of fire series of code
lengths for even greater compactness
blah blah blah don't care about that the
next two bits repeat the link so this is
not our concern because these lengths
are going to be smaller presumably than
the other lengths are I would assume
because 0 to 18 is a really small set of
symbols it's from a blah blah blah baby
boo-boo
black don't care about that
semmen code so where are they gonna talk
about the maximum code lengths they have
not stated the maximum code length they
said what the maximum values are but
they haven't said what the maximum cold
lengths are as far as I can tell
depress me limit further the ranges of
values fist-fighting oh well you know
what no they have
so this tells us right so it's three
bits for the code length of this right
eye and so for each one of these it can
only be three bits worth of symbol three
bits worth of length so that means it
can't be more than eight bits right I'm
sorry the the code that it's talking
about can't be more than eight bits
so that's pretty straightforward code
links for the layer using the code
length Huffman code and so that's like
code lengths of 0.15
[Music]
copy the previous code Bank three to six
times you're Peter link I'm so that
looks like the maximum code length is
two to the 15th or 32 K of values right
[Music]
so that would mean if we did want to do
when I'm talking about with a lookup
table it would be a 32,000 entry
well 32k entry table which is fine
I mean honestly even a 16-bit lookup
table I said that before without even
thinking about it but it's 64 K entries
if every entry we're talking about only
is like like eight bytes or something I
mean you're not even cracking a megabyte
right at that point so if we're talking
about two to the fifteen storing
something like eight bytes which I don't
even know if we need that many that's
like a quarter Meg and even if it was
it's only a half Meg so so I guess my
algorithm there is just it's just fine
it's probably not the right one to use
Charles bloom right now is is rolling
over in his task chair as I'm about to
write this I'm sure plate seems fine so
I guess what I'll do is I'll just do the
alga - said I mean why not right seems
like the easiest thing and it would just
work right so that basically lets us
know that like a PNG Huffman so we
probably don't want these PNG up and
sitting around on the fact though
because that's gonna put a lot of stack
pressure on for no real reason now
probably is okay but it just seems a
little more sensible to maybe allocate
those it just seems seems a little bit
Marie's n'e belite so we probably won't
hear something that's just like allocate
huffman and when you keep the huffman
table maybe you tell it how what what
you're expecting to be the maximum
[Music]
symbol size there so you know we could
make them all because we know that 15
bits appears to be the maximum size we
could make all of them be 15 but why but
why bother allocating member you don't
have to we might as well just use
however many bits the person says they
need because we know that there are
other places where we're gonna be coding
things that have a lot less bits than
that for example one of them only had
eight bits maximum so there we go so max
max code length in bits right so then
when you do that in here we can have a
PNG Huffman entry and the PNG Huffman
entry is just something that tells us
what the symbol is to retire so we've
got the symbol in here now the symbol I
don't know if we're always doing bytes
so I'm gonna leave it as a you theny two
for now but it may be that we always
decode bytes at a time and we don't
encode anything bigger but I think we
encode sometimes things that are bigger
so what we want to do here is probably
say something like symbol and symbol
length right and then this can probably
be split into two things like so which
is the symbol length and the like bits
used right so what I'm saying here is it
like okay we can store up to four bytes
worth of symbol which is probably the
maximum that we're ever gonna be asked
to code I think the maximum we're
actually an ASCII code is actually less
than that I think it's like 16 bits or
something out remember we'll expect to
go through it but I'm pretty sure we
wouldn't need any more than that so this
is like a just an 8 byte structure that
has 4 bytes worth of symbol a length
that tells us how much of the symbol we
actually use because symbols could vary
in size one symbol might be only 8 bits
long another one might be 16 bits long I
don't know
we might not need that in which case to
be pulled out here and then we have a
bits used so we could bring this down to
even shorter you could imagine if we
wanted to we could have something like
this eventually if we know if it turns
out that our symbols are always youth 16
or less then what we can probably do
here is just say look we can make this
just a 32 byte entry I'm sorry a 32 bit
entry that just has the symbol the
symbol like the bits used in code 18
half the space because really a symbol
like than bits used only need eight bits
anyway no matter what's happening so in
fact that could be even less than that
so we pretty much know we could always
go a little bit lower we could probably
even do something if we really wanted to
get down to it if we knew that all of
our symbols were flights which we don't
I think know that so I think this is too
small but we could do something like
this right and that would get us down to
only 16 bits per entry again doesn't
matter we can use the large version and
it will not hurt us I don't think
because there's just not going to be
that much of a performance thing going
on here we are not trying to make a
high-performance decompressor but just
worth noting like depending on how big
this symbol needed to be we could go
down as low as 16 bits without anything
fancy if the symbols small we could go
as low sticking bits just trivially by
packing the symbol and bit links into
two nibbles right so anyway moving along
I
we know that the PNG hufan just has a
PNG Huffman entry here that's like all
of the entries that it's got and then
we've also got a thing here that
probably says what the entry count is
and so when we actually have this
allocator what we're gonna do is say
well whatever the maximum code length is
in bits that's going to tell us how many
entries we have because the power of two
on that length is the number of N
so if they tell us the max code length
in bits is 12 then we know that 2 to the
12th is gonna be how many entries are in
our table because we know this code is
being kind of piggy an inefficient here
by just allocating and as many entries
as it needs without thinking about it
I'm gonna put an assertion in here that
the max code length in bits is not gonna
exceed 16 in any cases because if
someone came along and tried to use this
for something that had 24-bit Huffman
codes this is probably not the right way
to go and they should probably get an
assertion to let them know map they're
free to turn it off if they want to roll
the dice but it's probably just a bad
way to do it at that point my
patent-pending algorithm obviously is
super awesome just like all the other
things that people patent in software
that are so difficult to figure out you
know parentheses almost all of them are
very easy to figure out anyway so if we
go ahead to our Huffman allocator here
what we could do is just go ahead and
say all right let's make the result here
the results going to have an entry count
that's proportional to the max code
length in bits like I was saying so what
we do is we we take that and we just
raise it to the power of 2 as new by
shifting a 1 up by that many bits we
know how many of these we have so if we
have like 1 bit we have 2 entries if we
have 2 bits we have 4 entries and so on
then we just allocate an array that's
that's proportional to that so we say we
need that many entries so we just take
that number that we've already computed
and we malloc a number of entry is
proportional to that so the number of
parameters we have we now know we malloc
8 PNG Huffman for every one of those
entry counts that we have and that gives
us our complete structure right now we
don't want to fill any of these in
because what we're about to do is
actually you know generate this from
something that is going to figure out
exactly how the table should be filled
out and so we just leave it at that like
that's the allocated Huffman then we
want to do is later on when we go to
actually compute a Huffman which is this
thing here we need to actually
take one of these PNG Huffman's and do
what moved on to now oops I have some
like it got some backslash there now
what we need to do for the PNG Huffman
decode is actually now really
straightforward so the computer Huffman
is kind of a little more squirrely
because we got to go follow that
nonsense stuff in the spec that they
where they had all the weird like okay
count the code links and then assign
this way right we go today it's not
gonna be hard but it's gonna be
error-prone and we might screw it up so
it's gonna be annoying thing a little
writes fine so let's write this first
because we kind of know what we're
actually doing here so when we do the
Huffman decode when we bring that symbol
back off we go now I think when I'm
looking at this here I the way that the
Huffman to code works it looks like we
don't really need this symbol length
necessarily cuz the symbol itself looks
like it's the length because everywhere
now I think about everywhere that we
decoded the Hoffman I think we never
need to know the length then let me just
explain what I mean by that so there's
two ways you can encode symbols one is
that they are bit symbols and one is
that they are like numerical symbols so
a bit symbol is like 0 0 1 0 1 1 1 right
a numerical symbol is not that it can
only be like that right so a numerical
symbol can't have leading zeros why
can't it have leading zeros because the
number you know 14 there is no number 0
14 right there's just 14 and if you want
something in this place it can't be a
zero so zero zone Lee happen after the
first valid decimal they don't happen
before right bit symbols there's no such
constraint I can't really talk about the
bit symbols 0 0 1 0 1 1 1 that's not a
problem
I cannot trivially talk about the number
0 4000
932 right that's not a real number in
our system so it seems like everywhere
I'm decoding Huffman's they're real
alphabetical numeric symbols like that
now think about it so I think that means
I don't need another symbol line if I
didn't have that constraint I would need
to know how long the similarity is
because I couldn't just look at the
symbol and know that the zeros can just
be ignored at the front which means that
the symbol length is implicitly encoded
in the symbol itself so I think actually
this can be simplified right it could be
simplified down to symbol and bits used
which means that if we are fortunate
enough to know that the symbols are
always 64 K unless we can just go with
something like this which I think they
are so let's just say that that's the
case for now and go with this because it
looks like the bits used is the only
other thing that we need and so we can
just make each one of these be four
bytes long and then we know that our
table is gonna be like you know a
quarter megabyte which is like a nothing
burger for any modern CPU
that'll be sitting in the cache l2 at
least the whole time so it's all fine so
anyway what we want to do here is go in
the Huffman decode I know I've got to
return a particular value here that
value is going to be whatever the symbol
is that I end up with from my entries so
what I need to do is I need to look at
the streaming input buffer I need to
make sure that I have enough bits to do
1 PNG Huffman and if you remember
correctly what we've got here in this
training buffer is a thing that says
like a bit buff and a bit count so what
I want to do there is I want to make
sure that I can peak the that I can peak
the bits and so I can always just act
look at them without consuming them yet
right so rather than doing it consume
bits what I want to do here is expand
this function to ensure bits right which
just says this is how many I want or
maybe a peak
it's something like this and see what
that's gonna be is it's literally the
same function right it's exactly the
same function as as consume bits only it
doesn't shift the bit buffer down right
so normally we've got this thing in here
that that shifts the bit buffer down and
when you hit the shift the buffer down
you're basically consuming the bits off
so if I just want to peek all I do is
not shift it down right so that update
there just doesn't actually doesn't
actually do that so then what I can
do here is say all right here's the peak
bits it tells me how many I get and then
what I can do is do a consume like
discard bits and I can say how many I
want there to be like so and so in this
case we can basically have a peak bits
call which fills the bits up to the
amount that needs to be there ensures
that that many are there and then
assuming that it can it gives you back
the result that you asked for that's the
number of bits there and then I can
discard bits from that as well right
then what I can do too is I can do the
consume the discard bits which is this
part of it so what I can do here if I
want to is I can write consume bits in
terms of peak bits and discard bits
right so a consume bits is just a thing
that's like oh okay the result equals
the peak bits of the bit count and then
discard that many bits
right and that's pretty straightforward
now what we might want to do is set an
error flag here if we if we use too many
bits on the streaming buffer so we just
remember when the bit buffer has run out
if that makes sense
so we could have say in here that like
the streaming buffer has a thing that
just says look if the thing under flowed
you know we can we can say that so in
here we could just say like ah yeah you
know we ran out of stream you were
telling us to decode something and you
know we we just we ran out sorry so we
could do that
I don't know if we actually want to do
that because we may want to read at the
end we're still going to try to read an
entire Huffman symbol and that symbol
may be short so I don't know what we
want to do about that exactly I guess is
the way I would put it it's kind of a
little confusing so we'll see but anyway
we can't set the underflow to true there
if we want to that allows us to know
whether we've hit some kind of a failure
case and then what we can do is now
these are pretty clean right we just
like say peak bits if we need to fill
the buffer we do if we need to set the
underflow flag we can what I can do
there is say look the under flowed flag
is always gonna be just something that
tells us if we under flowed like so and
then that way this doesn't have a branch
in there for no reason so we just set
the results always equal to the mask off
of the bit counts you know we always set
that and then we just set the underflow
to whether or not the bit count actually
could have supported that many so right
pretty pretty simple then we on the
discard bits we just actually try to
discard the bits we only need to discard
the bits if we can so it's like a flush
to zero thing we maybe don't actually
need to do that we could just always run
this because under flowed would have
already been set so we wouldn't know
that we under float and we may
you just don't care about this then uh
so that's kind of hard to say I don't
know like probably we can just do this
because it's like once you under flow
who cares the rest of the data you're
gonna get is garbage so it doesn't
matter right so maybe that's fine I
don't know that's what we're looking at
all right so at that point this is
pretty branchless except for this part
here and that's because we wrote this
generic for the bit count we could make
one of these where you actually say how
many bits you want as part of the
function call and then this would be
completely branchless it would just go
right and so it's kind of a you can see
why people like Huffman stuff it's
probably pretty easy to write a nice
little efficient thing that just goes oh
let me shift some bits and have a party
right
okay all right so now that we're done
with that news to compile this here and
move on so now that we're done with that
when we actually want to do a Huffman to
code this becomes pretty straightforward
right you can see where I'm going with
this we know how many bits we want
because our Huffman can can tell us that
right bits per symbol is something that
our sorry bits per
[Music]
this is the this is the thing that we
got passed in its a really ridiculous
long name that so what we want to do
here when we go to do the hop into code
is I'll just say oh yeah you know just
give me that many bits please from the
input we'll look at how that value right
then we want to assert that that value
that we're gonna jump through here like
that we're not jumping but we're gonna
look up through here we want to make
sure that that doesn't overflow because
we should it should be possible for us
to do that right there should be no way
for us to ever get back a value here
with only that many bits that's not go
overflow the entry count but again we
would get exactly that in the case where
this discard bits thing well no this is
always masked so yet we should never be
able to get that back right if we only
ask that many bits we should only be
able to get something back that's less
than the entry count so we're gonna cert
that that's actually true
and then we're cuz if it's not we just
know our codes broken at that point like
whatever we did so then we're gonna do
is we're gonna take a look into the
Hoffman table I don't know why this is
why I put that in result it's not result
its entry index right so I'm just gonna
look through here at entry index I'm
gonna pull out whatever this this
Hoffman entry is so I grab the entry out
of the table it's got the symbol and the
bits used in it so now I know exactly
what I need to do to produce my result
right it's just
oh the entry is the symbol that's in the
table at that location cuz that's what
I've packed on a table and then the
number of bits that I need to suck out
of the input stream is just the other
entry in the table right so I know how
to say discard this many bits because
the entry itself says how many bits to
discard right easy peasy lemon squeezy
no weirdness there right so you can see
why
I said this was the fastest stupid way
it's because there's like no code to it
so it's probably reasonably efficient
the only problem is you've got this big
bloated lookup table that has a ton of
entries for the same symbol write small
symbols that are encoded frequently have
like 50 million entries in there and
because you know it's an 8-bit symbol
but you've only got one bit to encode a
so that exists 128 times in the table
right for no reason but there you go
right I did sighs I did so I call it
stupid right so anyway there's the
Huffman decode step so all we need now
is something that actually feels in the
table and that means we need to have
something that actually does that value
replication so there's two steps to this
the first thing is figuring out what the
code links are and assigning those codes
using the code lengths via that weird
structure that we read about in the spec
then the next step after that is to
actually flood the Huffman table with
all of the symbols in the right
positions that are indicated by their
symbol lengths as given by that bad
input set we're talking about right so
that's what we want to do here and I
think that's probably so I think that's
probably just a case of running over the
input and spamming out those symbols
into the table
I'm just not sure what the most
efficient way to do that actually is so
I think we just do it directly so we got
that part at the top that's going to be
based on the PNG spec nonsense that
we're going to flate spec nonsense
we'll go read in a second but I think
then all we have to do right
he is loop over each symbol we know how
many of those there are so really it
should be this eye so we know how many
souls we have we know what the symbol
code lengths are so we need to do the
thing that turns symbol code lengths
into actual symbol codes but once we
know that for every symbol index that we
have we know that we have the symbol
code length in bits right for that
symbol and we also know what that
symbols code is
that's the part that we don't know so we
need to figure out that as per the PNG
spec once we've done that we will have
both the length of the symbol and its
code right once we know that then we
should be able to span that into the
table everywhere that it should go right
so if we take the entry count which is
the like the number of places this will
be in the table what we know is the
entry count is exactly the inverse of
the code length in bits right so if I
know that the total entry count in the
table is X right and I know that the
number of entries this one will have I
know that the number of entries this one
will have is that shifted down by the
number of code bits right because this
thing will occur in the table however
many I'm not explaining as well usually
when I'm not explaining it well I need
to go to the little drawing board so let
me go so like I was saying before I've
got a Huffman code for this thing I
don't know what it is it's you know the
Huffman code for this thing is like 0-1
or something I don't know
right so it's 2 bits long but I know
that my simple table right or something
is 8 bits long so I know there are 6
bits here that no matter what they were
when I read this thing in as long as I
saw that in the bottom I know that I
output this symbol right because it's
got to be that it can't be anything else
because I just said that if I see those
two bits in a row that means this symbol
Huffman table is over truncate the rest
right so this 6 bits can be anything
what that means is one shifted up by 6
right or 2 to the 6th power
right which is 64 I know that that many
other places in the table it's gonna be
because any arbitrary combination of
these 6 bits has to all it but that has
this on the bottom how many are there
well they're 2 to the 6th
those in the 8-bit table right it's it's
all of the entries with a zero one on
the bottom and any other six bits on top
right so all I have to do is enumerate
through all those six bit values shift
up that amount or in the actual code on
the bottom and spam it into that
location of the table right that's it so
that's all I would have to do now if I
wanted to do this more cache friendly
what you could do instead that you know
what I don't care not gonna do that
alright so anyways so the entry count
here is just going to be one shifted up
by the like remaining bits right so the
what do you want to call these arbitrary
bits right so how many arbitrary bits
are there well the number of arbitrary
bits is whatever the huffman table says
there are right so the max code lengths
and bits how every bits that is I know
I've used this many bits so however many
I have left that's how many must be
arbitrary so the number of entries is
actually bad so the entry index for this
this particular symbol is going to be
that many entry right that's how many
there are so what I'd like to do from
there is say alright whatever the entry
index is I know the code length in bits
is used at the bottom so let me shift
the entry index up right let me or in
the code for this right and that is
where this thing goes in the table
like so so now I see well now we know
what we're talking about here I know the
bits used I can actually do this I
suppose and so then when I could say
it's alright the bits used is the code
lengths in bits and the symbol is just
the symbol right
it's whatever whatever one wrong now I
don't know if we want to also pass in an
array of symbol values because it may be
that the symbols themselves that we read
back want to be shifted automatically by
the table instead of having to add a
number to them so what we could do there
is specify a pre offset or a increment
or something like that we could make it
so that this is encoded a little bit
differently
we'll see if we want to do that here
like what I could say is you know an ad
end here that's equal to zero so
normally just doesn't do anything but in
this case you know we can just do that
so this symbol that we record is
actually shifted up somehow so because
like you saw a lot of things in there
were like oh it's the symbol value plus
three or something right well if we know
that the symbol values plus three out of
time we could just make that in the
table I don't know if we'll ever have
occasion to use that and maybe that's
the way they set it up just doesn't
actually admit any particular way of
doing that and so in that case we
wouldn't really be able do anything but
we you know we can deal with that a bit
later so anyway when we do our symbols
here like so what we can do is also
ensure that ones that we don't use like
symbols that that that don't get used we
can ensure that those are cleared if
that makes sense well actually I guess
they would just wouldn't occur so it
doesn't matter right so that should be
fine anyway so
I think if I remember correctly if the
code lengths in bits is zero then that
means that this thing never occurs
because you can't have one at zero it
has to have a code length of at least
one so what I'm going to say here is
just that all right you you if we see
one that's zero length we just skip it
we're not gonna do any more processing
on it right so that I think is the thing
that spams our Huffman table barring
typos or omissions that I made in there
that's the thing that generates the
Huffman table once we know what the
codes actually are so at that point what
we're left with is we need to have some
way of building those codes we need some
way of actually interpreting the
algorithm that we saw up at the top
which is not that is this we need some
way of actually implementing this
algorithm which is going to tell us what
the codes are as opposed to just their
lengths because remember all began as
input or the code length and using the
rules if they have specified for
determining what codes are based on
their lengths we're supposed to
regenerate the table ourselves for
obvious reasons so that we don't sit
around specifying a bunch of things that
we didn't actually use best by so let's
see count the number of coach reads code
length let BL count be the number of
codes that code length so that seems
pretty easy to do if we want to that
would just be something where we go
through like this and we say code length
count
symbol code length symbol index plus
plus right
so this is some kind of an array and we
would have to clear it to zero first in
order to count it properly we would then
go through all the code links we would
see how many of them we saw and off we
go now we can actually do this right on
the stack probably because the number of
code links cannot be longer than the
longest code length we know that 16 bits
was the longest code length that we
could see here so what we can do is just
say look that's what we're counting we
know we never gonna see more than that
right furthermore I can do PNG Huffman
max fit count or something like that and
just define that as 16 so it's easier
for people to see where that 16 comes
from and they don't have to sit around
wondering what on earth we're talking
about as we go right so the other thing
I can do is I believe we sort of made an
assertion on that in here we can also
make that assertion right depend on the
the Huffman back spit count right all
right so it's free for me to just do one
of these because this is tiny it's only
a 16 n 3 histogram table so I and you
know I could call this code like
histogram just to make it a little out
more obvious what it's actually doing so
as we come through we clear all that to
zero we look at all what the symbol code
links are we increment and what we could
do here as well is is again just take
this count and assert that the count is
less than or equal to the size of the
table which makes it so that if anyone
generated us bogus theta we would at
least sort of break in here in the de
beggar so we could go what's going on
right and if you were trying to do an
industrial-strength one of these you
would actually generate a an error here
or something right if you were trying to
make this for like Photoshop or
something where you wanted to present
the error to the user that the file is
corrupted right you'd put that in here
so anyway let me go ahead and implement
the symbol code thing that's the first
thing we need to do figure out what all
of the code lengths are add up to how
many we've seen of each of them that's
what they're telling us we want to do
first so we did that right
we we we don't we could
there's telling us not to count zeros we
could do that we don't really care
though
so we'll just count how many zeros are
anyway and we just will throw the value
away right we just don't have to use it
so the zero with entry in the code
length histogram will be counted there's
no reason not to count it we just end up
with a branch in here for no reason
because we can just never look at the
value right so it doesn't matter so they
say is they want to find the numerical
value of the smallest code for each code
length and that seems pretty
straightforward right we just go ahead
and search through them
I don't really know why you need to do
that what find the numerical value of
the smallest code for each code length
but why why couldn't you just go through
the table directly
I'm a little confused I apologize
find the numerical value of the smallest
code for each code length oh oh I see
what they're saying okay they're just
trying to say precompute the starting
value but okay okay when they said find
I thought they meant that there was
something like search e about it but I
must like it's always just the say I
mean there is only one value that it
that it is right so I was looking for
user but when you look at the actual
loop they're not searching for anything
they're just putting in what those
values are right so that yeah that that
seems pretty straightforward actually
I'm not sure
you
I also can't white tell why you would
need the BL count value there so that's
confusing because why wouldn't you do it
the other way around where you just
increment the bit code from zero each
time so that you don't have to do the
count first
am I the only person who's confused
about that on the stream I mean correct
me if I'm wrong but if you just went
through the table in order set each of
the bit count fields to just be the
first value that that is allowed for
that length ah no no I see why it's
because the Hoffman table is free to be
balanced on either side right so they
could choose they want to be able to
balance the Huffman tree however they
want for obvious reasons so they you
need to look at how many there were
because that lets you know how whether
or not you ever used a particular code
sequence because you could assign it to
some other code right so like for
example if you never use a 1-bit code
then you're free to use more two-bit
codes because you can use both values of
the bottom bit right but if you used bit
zero as an actual code then the only two
bit codes you can have are ones that
have a 1 in the bottom right or
something like that
do you know what I'm saying this they're
using the other direction here so I
guess that's a bad word say it so this
is the high bit right but so ok that
makes forever since I understand what
they're doing now I don't like to just
like type something and if I don't know
what's going on because like well I
don't like having a bad understanding of
it so it was like if I know there's an
error in my thinking or maybe the specs
just stupid I don't know but in this
case there's error my thinking I want to
correct the error in my thinking first
before kind of plowing forward all right
so once you have the code length
histogram then this is pretty
straightforward we can probably just
like it seems like you could just
obliterate you can do this in the same
array now I won't because I want to be
able to look at it but I'll say like
note Casey you could do this in the same
array if you wanted I so so this one I
guess doesn't really have to be assigned
to anything in particular here right
this next unused code
I guess doesn't really need to be
cleared because everyone who is going
who has been seen at all will actually
get a value assigned now so that seems
straightforward enough so if I go
through the bit in next year and I just
loop through how many of these there are
right I think like I said so they use
Bill account bits minus one and I guess
we could do that too since I guess we're
not gonna like nobody just I think you
just keep a run but you know whatever so
we assume like when we did this
summation before we assume that the zero
doesn't have any because like I said
even though we counted it we don't
actually want to ever use it it looks
like they did the same thing here right
so off we go we start with a code of
zero and each time here what we do is we
look at whatever the previous count was
we add the code that we actually
generated to it and we shift up by one
because we're adding another bit in
there right
so we basically say ok whatever our code
length histogram was also the biddin
that should start at one right yeah
because we're looking backwards one in
the table every time so we can't start
at zero right so we look backwards at
the table we find out how many of them
there were in that so we have to advance
by that mini codes and then we shift up
one for the fact that now we're adding a
new bit right so that's what the code is
and then the next unused code right is
just that now I feel like it's a little
weird that they chose to do a running
tally for one and not the other it seems
like to me so you know it just seems
like you would probably do this
wouldn't you just to be consistent I
mean that's the way that's their idea
not mine so I'm not sure why they had
code be a running thing and not neck and
not next in use code because it's just
like it's okay it's whatever the
previous one was right we we make the
new one out of that and then the next
time through the loop we just keep using
it right so it seems like that's the you
know that's the same way to do it right
so then we know what all the symbol
codes are rather than spam those out
since we now want to know what the
symbol code is here we might as well
just generate it right there you know
what I mean so instead of right because
because there's no point in us building
another table of symbol codes when we
know we don't care what the symbol code
is we're just gonna spam into our
Huffman entries based on that symbol
code so we can just create it right here
right so we can just do this right this
this loop is the same as this loop here
so we are doing exactly it we're doing
exactly that as well right so all we
need to do is actually assign the codes
here that's all we need to do
so we know what the code lengths in bits
is so if we just say alright once we
have that code length in bits we know
that that has to be able to go into here
right so I can assert that right so when
I pull out the code length in bits it
had better be able to be into this table
and then what I can do is say well the
code that I actually want is just
whatever the next unused code is for
this code length in bits and by the way
once you grab that increment the value
because the next person who uses it's
gonna have to use it every one right
then we just continue right where we
left off now we know what the code is we
can just use it and off we go
I think that's all of it right like I
don't think we need to really do
anything else to assign the bits here I
think you're pretty much just done so
yeah so I'm fine with that
I think it's fine
so yeah I guess here the other thing I
would want to do is say well let's just
make sure that we don't exceed our
bounds so let's make sure that that when
we up convert these guys we ended up
with the same thing that we expected
right and that's all there is to that so
I think we're done with that part of the
code I think I mean again that's just me
reading the spec and trying to guess
what they mean everywhere but it seemed
pretty sane and so barring like us
making typos there or me saying I was
doing something they're not quite really
doing it which obviously happens all the
time when your program I think we're
roughly in the ballpark there of you
know what needed to happen for that
right so I think all we need to do from
here on out is actually go ahead and you
know make these Huffman tables since
these are gonna have to be freed I'll go
ahead and put a little free in there for
these well actually know what I'm not
freeing so it's okay I'll go for it then
we'll deal with that later
so the Huffman decode and the Huffman
allocate part of this we now have to
make sure actually follows the rules
that I set so when we go ahead and do an
allocate Huffman down here we need to
allocate them so that they fit the
number of bits that we're actually going
to see so in each one of these we need
to do a Huffman allocation here like so
that has the right number of bits in it
and then we should be good to go from
there
so the these Huffman's
i don't really know how long the symbol
lengths are going to be
so I'm not sure for this one we know
that they have to be only three long
right or something no how long how long
are these guys yeah so these are three
bits long the symbol length looks like
so I think I think this Huffman is just
a three bit
Huffman because it's only allowed to get
three bits for each symbol length so
that's that's the maximum right for
these other ones here I'm not sure this
table is just one big table
so it looks like this one's just 15
right because anything that's up to and
including 15 that's an actual length
everything else is not so I think this
table is 15 what do I got here I got a
list Len Huffman and a dist Huffman but
they're both the same right and it looks
like they could they're each computed as
a separate Huffman table I guess we'll
look we'll see about that I'm not 100%
sure so then we do our we do our little
happy dance here and then we've got okay
so at this point we need to go over this
whole routine again because I want to
actually inspect that here but at this
point we have actually written the whole
decoder for the for the deflate part of
things there's another step we have to
do after this which is untransformed
so there's there's a little bit more to
the PNG than this according to the spec
there was that there was the filters so
we have to implement the filters but
we're basically there on the deflate
step and so now we just have to go
through and actually fix all the bugs
and stuff like that and you know and
what-have-you but anyway let's go ahead
and step through this and just see where
we're at I don't remember where we're at
on time today I think we've got a while
30 30 more minutes probably something
like that I'm not quite sure but
something like that all right so if I go
ahead and step into this thing I can
just get a sense for whether it's
working at all which is all I guys want
to see if we're if what if we've roughly
done anything resembling anything right
let me actually go here okay so here's
our h.glenn table I'm not sure whether
it's all correct or not but there's the
swizzle here's the table here's the bits
we consumed so here's what we've got
you know it's plausible but then again
anything would be because we're only
reading three bits at a time so there's
no real bogus values that can really get
in here particularly much so anyway now
when we go to compute the Huffman
let's okay so we're allocating one how
many are we allocating we're allocating
eight that's exactly what I would expect
right because it's a three bit Huffman
so in theory if you can only have three
bits there's no way to get outside of
the seventh entry right or the 8th entry
0 through 7 right so when we come in
here to compute hoffman here's our code
length histogram that's you know set to
0 so what I want to do is jump past that
histogram computation and then I want to
look at the histogram here's what we see
three values had nothing the rest of the
values okay there were some three some
fours some fives some 7s and that was it
right that's what we saw now does that
comport with what we actually see in the
data I don't know so let's actually take
a look I don't remember how many of
these we have so tell me oops
symbol
we had nineteen symbols so let's see 3 7
7 7 5 5 4 4 3 3 3 3 4 4 7 5 so we should
see threes fours 5 7 s that's it 3 4 5 s
and sevens 3 4 5 7 and that's what we
saw
perfect so then we come through here and
we start to assign these codes let's go
ahead and look at what the codes we're
going to assign are here's next unused
code we know that this is an array that
has sort of the the number of bits as
the parameter there so we're gonna go
through and assign those and what we
will see hopefully is we will see these
assigned only to the values where actual
things need to occur there we go so yeah
I so I guess I don't know if the rest of
the table is meant to clunk up that way
they did it mean that's what they did so
they don't if zero around that and so I
assume they just want to float because
they're never gonna use these values so
these are just bogus values anyway but
they're there just to make sure it's
clear when you get up to the higher bits
that actually are used if they if they
are used that you reserved that you kept
shifting it up right so I think that's
fine I think so let's go ahead and see
what we get for codes here so the first
symbol symbol index 0 where's our symbol
code lengths here we go is a 3 so that
means we should actually process it what
is its code its code is 0
is that right apparently so think that
through
yeah I mean that actually does seem
right wouldn't have to start at one
you know what no it wouldn't have to
start at one because they're pre saying
in fact they showed this their priests
saying that what they do is they leave
the one value as the repeat value so
it's the highest value that's not used
not the lowest value so yep that's on
the table seems fine
so the arbitrary bits here code length
in bits is three oh well there's a bug
right there
we forgot to initialize that value so
that that's not gonna go far that's not
gonna have legs so when we allocate the
huffman I need to actually put the maxx
code length in bits in here sorry about
that let's try that again so right back
to where we left off the arbitrary bits
here the Matco length in bits is three
the code length in bits here so that's
not right either is it that's that I
computed that incorrectly the max code
link then bits in this case is not what
we actually want
so those are two so those value that
that's not what I meant to say so max
code length in bits it's
so this value here the max code length
and bits that we're talking about there
was talking about how many bits would be
used to encode to encode a bit length
but it's not the actual number the
highest number that can actually be it's
not the highest Huffman code length at
that point it's the highest it's the
number that encode the number you would
the highest number of its you would need
to encode the count that is the bit
length does that make sense
so actually what we want here is is is
just the entry count the max code length
in bits I guess is not relevant am I
wrong about that
yes so this is not this is not the
correct value right what we actually
wanted to know is how many bits we
needed to read which is actually the
entry count right trying to think of
what I've I messed that thinking up
you know what no I didn't okay so I take
it all back I think the only thing so
after looking through it I don't think I
did I think the only thing that I did
wrong was saying that this was a three
but it's not a three three is how many
bits are specified for the code length
right but the code link is there for
eight right so so the number of entry
counts you actually need in the PNG
Huffman is the is the value shifted up
there right so so it's like a double
shift up I guess is the way to put it so
like if I say that it's three the max
code length in bits is is eight right
and the entry count is 256
I believe that's so that was where I was
kind of going wrong there so in the
allocate Huffman this is actually a
little bit this is kind of focus really
what we want from max code length in
bits
this was actually specifying max code
length length in bit right it is what we
actually passed in so it's actually this
and and it gets shift that gets shifted
up right then to get the entry count we
have to shift it up again so I think
that was just a I kind of like alighted
those two things in my head because it
was just getting a little Squinkie so
let me try that one more time and I
think now we're in better shape here
right
yeah and so so well I mean I guess the
other problem here so that those other
ones are specified wrong so I guess the
other thing is I could do is just
actually do this and change the
specification for that one because I
think yeah these I specified the actual
bit length right which was 15 and here I
specified the bit length length which
was three right so maybe the right thing
to do is just specify this one is eight
but like those have to be the same I
guess is the right way to say it okay so
now we're starting eight from three
which is what I actually wanted which
gives me five bits arbitrary which means
that this goes into 32 places we're
gonna spam it like so so we say whatever
the entrance is shifted up by the code
length and is three ordered with
the code we slap it in there and then we
keep slapping it in there a bunch of
times right we do all that and then we
should actually have our Huffman now
that's the results so here is our
results we have 26 entries in theory and
so if we look at what they all are we
should see like you know all a bunch of
these all are three right so like this
one's three that's three etc it looks
like for some reason we've got codes
that aren't used I think maybe that
means we've got a bug in there right
presumably all the codes should go to a
valid symbol unless there's just empty
space in the table which there might be
right because it might be that you don't
need to use all the codes because you
don't have an even number like Huffman
tables maybe get balanced in a certain
way that mean there's some things that
just you don't ever get right or
something like that
I don't know hmm although I guess and I
think about symbol 0 was a real symbol
so but but bit 0 sorry wasn't so yeah so
if it's used as 0 so one thing we could
do there
you you know what how we can check to
see if we've got a bug there is also we
can assert in our decode huffman that we
never have that case so inside having to
code I'm just going to assert that bits
used is not zero right so that way if we
do encounter a symbol that we really
shouldn't have shifted we'll know that
that was an empty space in the table and
so we just screwed up when we made our
Huffman table right all right so we've
been coming here let's see what we get
when we encode alright so yeah so we've
got a bug there right now there's a
couple different ways we can have a bug
there and I'm not sure which one we have
so when we are shifting bits in one of
the problems that we're gonna have here
is that we have to make sure the NDMS
matches up right so when we're when
we're gathering bits from the input
stream we have to make sure that those
bits are put into the value that we're
looking at in the same way that the the
person who wrote the spec thinks they
should come in right so if they think
they should be shifted on to the bottom
and we're shifting them on to the top or
something like that then we're gonna
have incorrect problem incorrect results
right so the first thing we should
probably do before we even look at the
Huffman table stuff is now we have to
actually get serious about the bit
consumption stuff because we really
don't know how that's going and we
should probably try to make sure that we
do have an idea there so let's first
look at that part and get that right so
let's see so I'm gonna read section 3 1
1 carefully because that's the part that
talks about this or at least should talk
about this
this document does not address the issue
of the order in which bits of a bite are
transmitted on a bit sequential medium
says the final data format described
here is byte rather than bit oriented
however we described the compressed
block format the compressed block format
in below is that a sentence as a
sequence of data elements of various bit
lengths not a sequence of bytes we must
therefore specify how to pack these data
amounts into bytes to form the final
compress AIDS notes
Dana ants are packed into bytes in order
of increasing bit number within the byte
ie starting with the least significant
bit of the byte they don't want other
than Huffman codes
oh so it's backwards data elements other
than Huffman codes are packed starting
with the Lisa give a bit of the data
element Huffman codes are packed
starting with the most significant bit
so it's the opposite if one were to
print out the compressed data as a
sequence of bytes starting with the
first byte at the right margin proceed
to the left with the most significant
bit of each byte on the left as usual
one would be able to parse the results
from right to left with fixed width
elements in the correct that's fee to
LSB order and Hoffman codes and get
reversed order with the first bit of the
code
okay so does that mean that I have to
consume have two different ways that
bits get consumed one that packs one way
and one that packs the other way or can
is there some way I can more
so that is so there's one of two things
that's true now either when we go to
actually write this code it turns out
that that ends up being a convenient
good thing to do and so like it's fine
that the spec was written that way
because it was just written so that the
implementation would do something some
efficient thing if not WTF man why would
you pack bits one way for one thing and
the other way for the other thing why
would you have two different ways of
packing bits
does that make any sense so hopefully
that's just something that when we
actually go to do it it's like oh yet
it's like make sense like that's what
you would do right
if not then WTF so anyway all right
let's take a look at that how we're
processing our input stream here all
right so when we go to bring bits in
we're going to read a byte and then the
byte what it's saying is that normally
they're packed least significant bit to
most significant bit I guess
right which means that if we just look
at the byte that's we got what we wanted
right I mean that looks like what we're
saying so when we consume au 8 if we
read the bits from the bottom it sounds
like that's correct that's what we
should do right so if we consume three
bits we just consume the three bits on
the bottom and they're in the right
order with the least significant on one
side of the most many other right but if
we were to consume them for a Huffman
code it's basically saying that they're
backwards right so I think that means we
have to to invert
ferb it's the other way around when we
go to put them into the Hoffmann code
and I and I don't I don't have any I
don't know why right I don't know why we
would do that I don't even know what
that means now that I think about it
because since you're creating the
Huffman codes yourself anyway why would
you care which way they went in just
give the way you build the table and it
won't matter right
but yeah that seems really unfortunate
because so we know that at least some
Huffman codes are our 15 bits long so
that means they will have to read 2
bytes the bytes that we read in then the
bit order for the Huffman so what does
it mean if you read 2 bytes but you want
the most significant byte bits first do
they want you to read the bytes in the
normal order I assume so so as we read a
byte at a time we're just talking about
for the Huffman codes we read off of the
top rather than the bottom for who knows
why just because we do
well alright so if that's the case then
the most efficient place to do this is
to make the table backwards right so it
seems like while I have no idea why you
would do that then the most efficient
place to handle that would be here so I
was making the code with the assumption
that the most significant bits were the
in the other place and here we're sort
of assuming the opposite of that so I
guess the first question I have is when
they said this right here so when they
said this is this creating the Huffman
code that way or I assume the answer is
no because I assume this code they're
giving me the pseudo code for the wrong
Huffman values right this is the pseudo
code for the backwards the way that the
Huffman codes would be generated in your
CPU but then they're basically saying
well we're gonna pack them the other way
round right I mean that that sounds like
what they're saying and maybe I'm way
off base on that but that seems like
what they're saying so then when the
bits actually come in and they come in
in this order right I need to look I
need to flip my thinking about the bit
order when I do that lookup so I guess
and maybe I might be totally off-base
here right and this is why I say the
spec is not particularly good I guess
what I'm trying to do then here is say
ok well this packing into the table
should actually pack the other way when
I look at the index and I say this this
index has my bits going in the reverse
order so I actually want those bits like
flipped around right
Yeah right uh so when I find that when I
look at the code right this code is is
backwards so I guess I'll write
something that flips the bits here in a
really inefficient way and then assuming
that we get that working and we see that
that really is how dolphin code is
encoded then I will go ahead and
actually try to make it more efficient
because we don't really need to do it
this way
so if we go through and we say each
individual bit that we're talking about
right it's free for me to invert this
because what I can do here oh actually I
could put this in here right so this is
really slow and you know don't do this
at home so what I can do here is when we
say what the index is I'm just going to
reverse the bit pattern of the index so
for each one of these I'll just say like
okay you know the index ended with one
here so or in whatever the base in next
value is that I have what I want to do
is for a particular bit index right I
want to shift it down to get that bit
out I can by the way do this for only
half the bits because we're just we're
just going to flip them right so I can
take the base index I can shift it down
by that bit there's also probably an
intrinsic for this but that's beside the
point
I can shift it down by hover any bits
I'm doing I can end that part and then
shift it up by the by the opposing
number right
so what that's gonna do is that's gonna
put you know bit zero we'll go in the
like bit fifteen slot and then bit one
will go in the fourteen slot and so on
so it'll just invert right where they
are
again not really sure that's what they
wanted me to do but it's what it sounds
like they wanted me to do so let's take
a look right so here I'm gonna just go
ahead and look to see to what extent I
actually successfully flipped this so
let's just take a look at some of these
here oh and I need to know how what my
actual max code it's was so it's eight
so one two three four five six that well
you know what I can do
so here you can see us flip them around
so now this was the fourth byte in and
it looks like I'm off by one there right
zero zero one that should have been that
should have flipped to that position so
I think I actually need to do
[Music]
there we go that's more flippy that's
wrong Oh duh I obviously also need to do
the corresponding bit flip sorry
so I'm just going to take this value
here we go
so he looks like we're flipping down
all right so that's like you know our
flipped huffman table so in theory now
that is like sort of what we're actually
talking about I guess so if that's
really what they meant then we're gonna
have to have the bit patterns packed in
the opposite way and the reason that we
the opposite way is because that now
means that when we look at the actual
value it's going to be packed around
backwards the further complication at
least I think if I'm not very much in
error is that now when we consume the
bits we have to pack the bits onto the
top right I guess the other way we could
do this is flip before we look up the
bits that seems really inefficient
though because you want the table to do
that right so I feel like you want to be
able to
hmm yeah now that I think about it I'm
not even sure you can really do that
because it seems like you'd have to just
flip the bits of the code every time
because when I get new bits in normally
I'm sticking them on the top now that
should that should still work so this
should still work because yeah like I'm
just looking at that value and saying
well they're telling me it's most
significant byte first so it just means
that when I actually look it up in the
table the tables like flipped around
right so I think that's okay so let's
investigate further but this is the part
that's gonna be really annoying right
because we have nothing to go on
like we just have to read so I can be
like I don't know like seems like this
is what they want but we'll see so now
let me jump down here and see what
actually happens let's go to peek bits
so we know that we want eight bits I'm
not sure how we got a bit count of one
in there I guess that was one we didn't
use previously but anyway so we're gonna
consume a you wait and get some more
bits in here so now there's nine bits in
there and we're just going to take the
bottom bits of that thing and we have
not under flowed so there's our results
right so we got back in 95 that's the
value we're going to look up into our
table the table that we get there is
symbol 10 it says that we use three of
the bits to decode simple 10s we say
okay then we're gonna go ahead and
discard those three bits and and that's
all fine so then we do some nonsense
here we don't know if any of this is
correct right so we're low ignore that
for now so then we come in here and we
want to look at the understa again now
we get 75
what's our entry this time it's another
ten who knows if that's right look we
don't really know
we should probably try to get some known
good data in here that we can you see
the code come in check but okay we keep
shifting so if we go so question when do
we actually had our first error cuz I
don't actually know when that happens so
eventually we hit an error here where we
hit a symbol that we shouldn't hit right
that wasn't encoded and our problem is
we don't really know we have no idea
whether the first set of things we
decoded was right at all like we have no
idea we're just getting some data and it
could be right or it could be wrong
and that's all we have to go on so I
don't know how many times we actually
it looks like this is not yeah so this
this is this loop is busted so I don't
really know so I don't really know how
far along we are yet so we'll see in a
second anyway this lit Lin count in the
link out this is how many we're gonna
get so this value should be incremented
but it's not clear to me that it ever
was it was set to zero which doesn't
really make any sense
because so the lens caps come here so
this I feel like this is busted right I
feel like this is supposed to be lit
lend count here because this was never
getting incremented similarly this is
supposed to be the prior one like that
so I think Len count link out should
never be used inside this loop so that
was just a typo alright so let's try
that again and now now I want to see
when we crash out right because now when
we get the wrong symbol I just wanna
know where we were so we're on like
symbol 11 right so let's also see I'm
gonna try it both ways here so since I
really don't know what they mean by this
if I don't do this
when do I crash out on the non reversed
version right okay so the reversed
version if only by accident definitely
gets us further through the process
which suggests that that is more correct
they do really mean that they reversed
the bits just for no reason like who
knows I don't know why they reverse the
bits they just did right so yeah that's
pretty special so I don't know all right
that's the end for today tomorrow we'll
pick back up at that place I'll go to
Q&amp;A now but yeah I also think there was
somebody had posted a issue on the
github about a typo I can go take a look
at that now I don't really remember what
it was but I think that someone had an
issue that they mentioned let's see
wrong value in little n disk table for
value of 17 the implementation says
three bits of length but you typed copy
pasted consume bits of 2 for the encoded
17 case let me go ahead and get that
yeah we have to like check this whole
thing so this should have been a three
here
apparently okay yeah all right
so anyway I don't think that effects I
think we're still wrong at 11:00 anyways
so we still have to kind of look at
what's going on here and again I don't
really know how right this is at the
moment so we've got some work to do
there we don't even know if we're
unpacking the huffman correctly like we
know nothing
right but anyway I'll do it I'll retire
this to do here as well so day 45 goes
to comment let me look at the questions
now
ratchet freak don't the bits when
reading the table need to be reversed as
well
don't the bits when reading the table
need to be reversed as well I guess I
don't know where where you mean can you
be more specific about where you think
the reversal should be I mean ours long
as series midlow can probably answer
that question for you
I know I'm not gonna talk about volkens
error handling now that's really pretty
far off topic you said both the times
that Pina spec does not allow fixed
Huffman codes but this is not true PG
spec a statistic says that both fixed
and dynamic Huffman codes are allowed
okay so so we might get that then I
guess laughs we can do so oh did I have
a typo there
this is why I always use macros for that
normally I don't like using malloc ah
thank you because of exactly bugs like
that look you noticed and handmade here
I never allow that sort of a thing to
happen because if you do it like this
you can never have that bug but if you
do it like this you can have it all the
time right we'll move it over to that
when we get there also so let me go look
at section ten Martin says it allows
that I thought it said it didn't I guess
I was confused where is it 10 1
you're right so right here it says fixed
Huffman codes
dr. faker in reading the three bit
lengths you'd read for example B 0 1 1
but I believe it should be B 1 1 0 so is
that really true though because the spec
at least as far as I can tell
suggested it's the other way around
right so it says data elements are
packed into bytes in order of increasing
bit number within the byte starting with
the least significant bit of the byte
data elements other than Huffman codes
are packed starting with the least
significant bit of the data element
Huffman codes are packed starting with
the most significant bit of the code so
doesn't that mean that only the Huffman
code would be reversed that's how I read
that do you read it a different way
ratchet freak
and by the way traffic I'm definitely
not trying to state that that's the case
I'm just saying that's how I read it
like I said this is the first but first
time I've ever looked at the PNG spec
even a glance so I have nil opinion on
the correct way to read it I am just
doing my best
from the verbiage they placed in here
and at least it seems like they're
literally saying they chose to pack bits
in two different ways I don't know what
the reasoning is behind that it might
you know what I just don't I just don't
have any idea what the reasoning is for
that because you can choose to interpret
the Huffman codes either direction when
you're actually building your Huffman
tables so I'm not sure why you wouldn't
have just picked the same way for confer
uniformity but I'm not a compression guy
so maybe this was there's a maybe
there's a very obvious reason that you
would know if you were right
wretched freak yeah you are correct well
I don't know that I'm correct I just
know that that's what this says so
that's the that's the reason I didn't
reverse it everywhere else is because it
seems to suggest that the way that we're
reading bits currently is correct but
not for the Huffman codes so we have to
have a way of reversing the bits for the
Huffman codes the thing I'm not quite
sure about is when we are shifting in
those bits and looking at them I don't
know if that means we need to shift the
bits in in the opposite order or somehow
I think we we I think what I'm doing
right now I don't think it works to just
reverse just the table part so I think
we might be Sol on that and we might
have to like shift bits in and flip them
or something right
look I can't that's a hard thing to work
out in my head I got to think about it a
little and baby draw it out but I don't
know if just flipping the table that way
actually works beak it worked it works
for one Hussman code the question is
just when you then shift bits in I think
you're shifting the wrong bits out does
that make sense so I'm pretty sure we
can't do that because we we used a
different different bits than left
possibly
it's that you know I know it might be
okay might be okay yeah it might be okay
I mean something's wrong because we're
not parsing it so we know that at least
one thing is wrong in there you know but
the question is just what and we'll try
to find out tomorrow
only Epping codes are bit reverse from
looking at the bit from the first byte
to the last and most of them a bit too
LS right and at the moment I think since
we're only looking at bytes at a time we
don't have a byte boundary reversal
problem in theory yet although maybe we
have that too you know so what we got it
like I said we're gonna have to dig in
here and figure that out
you
alright well if there's no questions I
can close down the stream
thank you from Philips on a handmade
here it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you want to follow
along the series at home you can always
hear the game on handmade here org and
it comes with the source code so you can
play around it yourself if you want to
see the exciting conclusion of how to
interpret the Huffman codes in a PNG
file we will be back here tomorrow same
time same place to do exactly that hope
to see you back here for that until then
everyone have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet ticket news
everybody