hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero we're gonna start off a little bit
differently we're gonna program normal
handmade hero in a couple seconds but
someone was asking on the pre stream
about whether we had a bug in one of the
memory things and we might like there's
a couple things that could easily be
bugs that you know what it's the Pacis
we haven't done any hardening really of
most of our stuff so I just want to go
look at it and let me explain really
briefly what the the problem was so if
we go to handmade hero here if I jump
down to the place if this is sort of a
little bit tricky because it you know it
well may not be a bug of ours but we
don't know yet so I just want to look at
it really quickly what the person was
talking about the pre stream was they
were trying to run a handmade hero
through an address sanitizer now what an
address sanitizer is is it's a piece of
static analysis and dynamic analysis
depending on which ones you're talking
about there can be a mix of both code
that looks at your program and tries to
determine whether or not you're doing
any kind of illegal operations with
memory that just don't show up because
they happen to work right so for example
a pretty classic one would be you freeze
some memory but then you still use it
after it's freed because that memory is
usually just going back to a free pool
you would never know right and so it's
just a bug that's waiting to be exposed
by some changes to the application like
maybe then later you change it so
someone allocates something there and
then you end up in a situation where
you've got that use after free suddenly
suddenly causes a crash or causes a bug
that you didn't know you had because
before no one was allocating it in
between the place where you freed it in
place were using so that's like a
classic case of something you might find
with an ADD - sanitizer overriding a
buffer like by one bite or something so
that it's it's overwriting but it
doesn't matter because there's there's
room there's pad at the
because of the way allocations work they
work on 4 K pages if that won't crash
right we've done some stuff that we can
use to detect some of those things that
we haven't done it particularly
stringently yet so you know those might
be less likely for us but still not
really because we didn't really do the
stringent version of it which we'll do
probably before we ship but anyway in
this case it was a question specifically
about bootstrapping we use the bootstrap
call and this is the equivalent area in
the win32 layer the parts that are
talking about it was the cooler air in
the cooler of the accessing info era era
platform in platform open file so we're
looking specifically a platform open
file which is this there we go and what
they were saying is that info platform I
think they probably mean result I think
they're probably talking about result
platform
Minoo they're talking about this this is
what they're talking about right here
info platform so info platform info is a
parameter here and it's accessing this
thing and so it might we have to go look
to see whether if we've got something
bad happening here with this info
platform now let's take a look at where
that was set first of all this is the
place where the person said that they
were getting an address sanitizer issue
was this not this line of code but this
line of code on Mac right so either
we've got a bug and we might or there
was a bug in what they were doing on the
Mac version of it but you know I just
want to take a look at it and then check
on the stream just to see you know I
want to help that person out anytime
someone reports like something where
it's clear that they were doing some
work on something and got confused we
you know we try to help because you know
I want to encourage people to do work on
their own and figure stuff out right so
all right so let's take a look here
win32 open file it's using the info
struct here that came because back when
you started the enumeration right
it was gonna fill that out so if we had
a bug it would it would probably be in
something like this right where we're
doing the bootstrap push struct here to
get the the file group that info
presumably is the thing we're talking
about now let's open up the definition
of these functions just so we can see
whether that's actually true right so if
we come back in here and we take a look
at like you know platform Open File and
stuff like that we see that there's the
file group and then there's the platform
file info right and so it's the platform
file info in particular that we'd be
taught that we'd be asking about if
that's what the address sanitizer was
concerned about and so if we take a look
in here where we've got info arrow base
name like this sort of stuff this is the
code that would be suspect so you can
see what it runs all of this is not
really relevant right because all of
this code is just doing basic wildcard
setup we then enter the loop where we're
going to allocate the information we
actually need and what you can see here
is that particular thing so if you if
you if we look at info platform this
piece here right if you look at that
particular thing where we set the
platform is actually a push at least
that's what we're doing here is actually
a push of this string that's getting
copied right so it's the win32 file
grouped memory in particular this push
what are you doing what's going on come
on up come on up that's a good place
okay um so what I would say here is I
don't see any way off hand first of all
I don't think this would implicate the
the stack stuff at all because you know
this allocates well I guess we can look
at win32 allocate file info and make
sure that it's okay
so in order to do this we grab the
platform off of there we allocate a new
struct off of the win32 file group
memory we fill it out I mean I just you
know just looking at this everything
comes off of the file group memory so I
I don't know I don't see any way this
could be using stack memory I I don't
know like do you see what I'm saying
everything here is allocated off of that
memory block so I'm not sure what would
actually be a problem for a address
sanitizer there I don't really see
anything so I kind of feel like maybe we
would need more info and or and or maybe
it's just something that you did weird
in the Mac version you know I'm Sam does
that help at all
do you have follow-up to that I'm just
gonna wait one second while we look to
see if there's a follow-up comment at
all on it but just looking at the code
it all comes from from that memory array
so I'm just not sure I'm not sure how
that would end up with a stack pointer
to anything really
I'll just wait a couple more seconds see
if there's any follow-up to it and then
we'll switch over to working on the the
variant stuff working on the variant
stuff alright maybe I'll just continue
then I don't see a follow-up to it maybe
I'll just continue and it can we can
take it that offline all right there was
a sticker on the bottom of my chair this
entire time let's throw that away and
then well okay alright they said they'll
check it out again and add some more
detail in the forums if necessary okay
that sounds good
also if you're working with like a MacOS
platform layer there may be people on
the forums who use mac offs who can help
more specifically as well right like you
know we don't do a Mac platform layer
here we haven't done one yet and so you
know the the best people to help with a
Mac platform layer are gonna be people
in the forum's anyway for what it's
worth you can look out the window prompt
us do you want it why don't you go in
your cat tree much go in the country
okay let's go in the country that's a
better place for the prime puss here
here you can still look out you can
still look out yeah there you go
there you go see all right I think we've
we've gotten the prime puss into
position so now we can go ahead and and
do some programming okay so let's go
ahead and move to these things that I
was going to do today which was take a
look at our problem with variants so let
me explain what this is if we jump into
the game here let me just load it up
so if we're in the game and we go over
to someplace that just has some variants
in it right that we were looking at so
let's let's take a look at this for
example what we were doing is we were
saying oh let's put some trees in here
right and you know we haven't actually
bothered to mark up the trees yet so
they're like the wrong size and stuff
like this
but so a reason I can't oh there we go
so if I select like one of these you
know what we would normally be doing is
we'd be saying like oh okay you know
that one's got like the size and stuff
specified this one needs to have that as
well so we would add like an alignment
point here and we would you know sort of
size it up to the correct size whatever
we needed it to be and and sort of
position it properly relative to you
know where it was going to be and all
that sort of stuff right so what we
would normally be doing right now is
like going through and like prepping all
of this stuff and you know like I said I
don't really know how we want to do all
this stuff in the future I should
probably make these things so you can
drag past the past the top of the screen
there but anyway like you know you we
could start going in now and aligning
all of our tree stuff and all that kind
of thing and that's the sort of stuff
that we will need to do as we sort of
build out the world so all of that seems
to be working great
no complaints there we could stand to
improve this editor a little bit which
we probably want to do as we encounter
like issues and stuff but in general you
know it seems fine so you know this this
would allow us to get all of our trees
in play and make all this stuff work
okay oops
and and and set up our alignment points
pretty good and then we could test them
right so all of this stuff seems pretty
good and and I'm happy with it like I
said we probably want to do a little bit
of work on it and improve the editor
stuff a little bit but otherwise we're
pretty good however what you'll notice
is if we actually look at it though this
is a random distribution that we were
you know supposedly a supposedly random
distribution
these things but it's really not that
random obviously a normal situation
wouldn't be picking from all of these
things for the same area like the snow
you know we'd have snow covered ground
for the areas with the snow trees and so
on but actually it's very far from
random and the reason for that is
because the way that we're assigning
variant numbers right now is not is
based on where you are in the grid
squares which is not what you actually
want to do right when you're actually
picking a variant what you want to do is
you want to select variants based on how
many things there were so if there are
only two sprites you want to assign
variant numbers to the range based on an
equal distribution of two things over
the range zero to one whereas if there
were four different types of trees you
want to assign four equally spaced
points on the range from zero to one but
instead what was happening for us is if
you only have two things it assigns them
in the zero and one position of a zero
through three distribution of four
points in the range 0 to 1
which means that everything is skewed
towards the second point out of the two
because anything that would have picked
the third or fourth permutations which
don't exist will map to that second one
so it doesn't properly cover the range
if that makes sense and so what we end
up with in this scenario yeah is kind of
a thing that's that's like totally
busted we're picking from a supposedly
random distribution it's almost always
going to pick the wrong one or not the
wrong one the same one right so there's
nothing really all that random about it
you know what I'm saying
and so that was the thing that we kind
of needed to fix and there's probably
other bugs in there as well
in terms of the assignment and picking
of the random stuff because we haven't
looked at it that much but that is a big
problem that we need to solve before we
go any further because those assignments
are just completely wrong and that's
that's an issue obviously right so we
got to fix that
another thing we should probably do is
when we view one of these things we
don't show the tags but we're probably
gonna want to write so when we look at
one of these things we're gonna want to
see like what the tags are for for any
given one of these sausage gentlemen
here right so that's that's something we
also want to be able to do another thing
that's a little bit weird is the sizing
for these things right like we probably
need to work on the size normalization a
little bit more too because it seems to
me like we're maybe when we extract
stuff somehow were it's not filling the
box size properly so so like for example
I don't I don't know I think we want to
like size things probably more manually
what we were doing right now I think is
maybe recording that size and sort of
preserving it but not preserving the Box
size because you can see like these
things that are set to 2.48 they have a
really like very very large box size
whereas this stuff here as a small box
size for the same roughly sized thing
yeah it's just a little bit weird so you
know if I if I was to grab say this
thing and size it up right you know it
gets it gets much larger for the same
box size like look at how wide it is
versus how why this thing is and they're
given their two box sizes right so it's
it's just a little strange and I'm not
sure I feel like we probably want to fix
how some of that's working as well all
right so let's go into the code here and
start to tackle some of these issues I'm
gonna open up handmade hero and I'm
gonna go to in the import library sorry
the import code I want to go take a look
at how those things are being assigned
and if you look at how very
or being assigned they use the tag
arrays to do that so there's sort of
this like create art star set of things
create art star grid or tag grid that
creates the tag grid for importing
something so for example in the case of
the trees and particles of the other
kind in the case of the trees that's the
scenery tag grid and what you can see
here is the scenery tag grid tags things
based on variant without knowing how
many there are and that would be fine if
we knew there were always four but there
aren't always four so just to be clear
about what's happening here
and I haven't drawn on the blackboard in
a while I don't want people get lost
what we're fundamentally talking about
what's the day day 536 what we're
fundamentally talking about here is we
have variants of the same art asset that
want to be picked
among potentially randomly for example
and so we're going to have a range of 0
to 1 and we're gonna essentially pick a
random point in here right so we're
gonna pick like this point or something
right this is going to be picked at
random now in order to make this
actually be random what we therefore
have to do is make sure that we assign a
distribution of matching points across
this thing so that the chances of you
being closest to each of those points is
uniform across the interval so for
example if we only had one point right
then we would know that it doesn't
matter where we put it because no matter
where we put it it would always be the
closest point and you can't pick
anything else so if there's only one
point it can go anywhere if there's two
points then we need to make sure that
the distribution across this range makes
this point be closest to either of the
two points at random again
right now that can really be anywhere in
the interval here and here right so the
first point can go from from the center
point here we can go out as long as we
go out an equal amount it doesn't matter
so for example we can put one here and
one here we can put one here and one
here and it doesn't matter as long as
they are equally spaced from the center
we will end up with a equal distribution
right so this is equal distance from
Center is really our only requirement
that's it so now the question is what
happens when we get to 3 because 3 &amp; 4
are also cases that we have and for
particles we actually go from 1 to 16 so
we need to come up with a general rule
here this is not going to cut it anymore
because we've got three things and so if
you think about how the point 4 3 gets
distributed well what you want to do is
actually divide it into three equal size
buckets right so we want to make sure we
have point 1 bucket 1 bucket 2 and
bucket 3 right we want to make sure that
when you fall into each of these buckets
you correctly map to one of these points
so where they're gonna go well they're
gonna go in the center of the bucket
right so at that point once we get to 3
there is really only one distribution at
that point that gives us what we want
and that is Center of three equal
buckets now the nice thing is as we go
up from there you can kind of see that
it's always going to be the same thing
this is gonna be the center of 4 equal
buckets five equal buckets 6 7 8 9 10
right so we know that what we
fundamentally want to do is take the
range of 0 to 1 right take this range we
want to divide that range by the number
of buckets right so we want to say okay
divide it by the bucket number
and that's gonna give us our bucket size
and then we want to take exactly half of
that bucket size start there and then
add an entire buckets worth for the rest
of the points right so we want to do
like half bucket to start and then plus
bucket each time and that produces exact
distribution that we need so the math is
not hard right that was very very simple
I didn't need to really think about
anything you can just draw it out and
you get exactly what you need for the
math the math is easy however that is
not our main problem figuring out the
math our problem is creating the
systemic flow necessary to produce that
because what we have is we have a grid
of things that grid contains an
arbitrary number of sets of variants
right so for example in the case where
talk about scenery there are four rows
each containing up to four variants so
when we look we're going to have to have
a system that looks for groups inside
counts the number of things in that
group and then correctly assigns the
variant points to those based on how
many it got does that make sense and so
that's really the thing that's going to
create the headache for us is putting
that system into place and so if we look
at how we're doing it right now it's not
gonna fly putting in variant tags a
priori right ahead of time isn't going
to work so our tag grids are fine and we
can leave them for everything else but
where we put variants isn't going to
work and so what we need to think about
here is perhaps the easiest thing for us
to do would be to say for any variant we
need to reassign the variants at the end
you know so we can still put them in
there
but then when we iterate over maybe we
look for variants and reassign them to
new values before we export or something
like that right okay so it's not hard to
imagine how we might do that if we knew
how many variants there were while
something like the particle grid which
is literally just a grid of sixteen
possible variants would be easy you just
count the total number of images that
you found inside the PNG and you're done
we cannot do that so we cannot do
something that simple for the scenery
why because there are four different
variant groups in the scenery each of
which needs its own count and so what we
have to do is imagine that our tag grids
are more capable than they currently are
we will probably have to do something
that looks a little bit like this for an
import tag grid which is this we
probably need to say something like this
well I guess we don't really need to do
that we could just do it here and here
we would say that so for every tag
that's in the grid we would specify a
variant group number where zero probably
means it is not part of a variant group
and one through n means that it is part
of that variant group and there's
probably a maximum very group number
which tells us how well in fact it could
just do this so for each set of grid
tags we would just say look how many
variant groups are there and which ones
are members of those variant groups we
would then go through here and say okay
for each of the things that has an ID
tag variant on it we would not actually
build any variant tags instead we would
just say here is where you know this
particular thing has a variant tag on it
and that'd be the end of it right so
let's take a look at how that might look
when we do the import good tag stuff you
can see here when we do the end tags
the way the result field works here I'm
gonna go ahead and initialize this guy
to nothing just so it'll get a very
group of zero by default if you don't do
anything else and here let's see what
else we're doing import body and so on
so I think yeah this stuff's all fine
and all we have to do is look for any
place that we were doing a variant and I
don't really know whether we want to do
this or not to be completely honest but
point being once we actually get the tag
at the end we can specify the variant
group for that thing so I'll leave the
specification of the variant tag in
there
just cuz and then for the variant group
I'll say look this guy has a variant
group of one for everybody because it's
the particle tag group right there's
probably no other variants except for
what items yeah so this one has a
variant group in this case and okay so
this very is based on the ROE and
probably looks something like that
and so there are variant groups there
for cases 0 and 1 and so here we would
set the variant group based on that
finally for the scenery Tiger it's the
one we were actually looking at with the
trees same thing we would just say hey
the very group for this set here it's
just going to be it's just going to be
set to whatever the Y X is plus one
right it's just whichever row you were
on so I think that's all good and when
we do the variant group count here we
can just set that directly probably for
now but we
auto count it in the future if we really
felt like it but the variant group count
here right is just there's just five of
them right so whatever the Hawai index
here was and the same is true here and
then here the variant group crap is too
right
so we can do that you know what the
other thing we could do is just not
bother and just have a call that
actually counts it and that seems maybe
better to me so maybe what I'll say here
is you know maybe we'll we'll produce
this by scanning you know we'll leave
this for now but like maybe I'll do like
to do scan to compute this value rather
than manually setting it right so once
we know the very group count and the
very group indices now we have the
information necessary to do this but
we're still not out of the woods yet and
the reason for that is if we go into the
the actual import code for for multi
tile exports so it's this one if we go
into the process of multi tail import
code what you can see here is we're
gonna pull these things out and to the
extent that we get one that's gonna
produce information about how many of
these variants there were so we kind of
need something in this part of the code
that will actually register how many of
these things we saw right now we can do
it here or we can do it elsewhere and I
think probably the way we would want to
do it is I'm guessing when we do the
update when we do the update metadata
Update asset metadata um when we do the
update asset metadata call then when
we're looping through these and looking
at the any individual piece of asset
metadata what you can see in that code
is it's going to look to see for any
given one of these whether or not
there's actually anything in it right so
I believe or is it oh it already is so
here it is right so what we should be
able to do at least in theory I think is
for each one of these asset indices we
should be able to go and do a pre
summation right where we look at each
asset that was here and we count how
many their variants there were in the
variant set and then when we go to
export these tags for example right in
here right what we could do is just
switch the variant tag so that it is now
set to the correct value right seems
like probably the right solution yeah so
anyway here's the why index ex index
scan here's the asset index that's
coming off of it we're gonna need to
know this and we're gonna need to know
the variant group right and so the way
we would probably do this is say alright
if the if there is a variant group on
this then we're going to update like a
variant count for that variant group and
that way we then know like what for any
given
one of these were on we know what the
the value should be and so when we're
done with that we could then produce the
bucket sizes so we would basically have
the bucket size for each variant group
and does this not I mean this should
have
I'm not sure why this doesn't have I
guess this doesn't actually use any
temporary memory that's kind of crazy
but it really doesn't so this would
actually need to use some temporary
memory right because it needs to
precondition those tags technically
though actually what I'm looking at it
here
it doesn't actually need to do that
because we could do a separate pass that
does that if that makes sense so we
could actually do it in sort of a
separate way which is update asset
variants like this and this one could
actually do it
and this would want temporary memory so
this would want to know that it could
just create some because we don't we
could just hard code them but why bother
I mean why not use a temporary memory
set to use them there's no reason to
limit the number of them so we might as
well not I so what we want to do here is
say okay let's grab this stuff out
we will loop over all of the contents of
it we will look to see how many variants
there are for each of these and just
summing at that so let me do a push
array here of you thirty twos and I
don't know whether the type comes first
of the count will have to look but what
we need to know here is the total
variant count right Frank recap so if we
know the import grid tags for this thing
which would be this at least I believe
that no not that's alright what's this
the grid
so if we know the import grid tags like
so then we know the variant group count
for that one we can fast track this if
we know that the grid doesn't have any
then we don't have to do anything
because if there are no variant groups
then we can't then there's never going
to be any variant tags assigned right
because we wouldn't have any groups to
assign them to and that would be the end
of it
so what we want to do is say if there is
any variant groups then we'll make a
very account array the variant count
array will hold you know all the variant
groups we could ascertain here that
nobody did anything untoward so we could
assert for example that the variant
group count that we are started the very
group index that we observed is less
than the variant group count that they
said there was so that we you know we
know that we don't have a bogus grid
that we're operating on the same thing
would go for right here where we say
give me a variant group count of F 32 s
here for the bucket sizes and then
that'll allow us to properly move
everybody we can also do one for the
sort of the point that we're assigning
so that allows us to do pretty much
exactly what we want with our variant
groups and once we've summed how many
there are
it's a simple matter of looping over
them to compute the bucket size now we
need to these will get initialized to
zero because push a push array by
default clears and so when we you know
when each of these things gets cleared
it will then sum up we may end up in a
situation where they're you know if this
is our variant group index
and we're looping over the grid here we
may end up in a situation where there
actually isn't you know there actually
isn't anything in that variant group
because the artists just didn't put
anything in that whole area so we need
to be able to say look whatever the
count was when we get it out we want to
set the bucket size to zero
probably regardless so don't try to
divide by zero here check to see if the
count is zero and if the count is zero
leave the bucket size zero if the count
isn't zero then set the bucket size to
be equal to 1 over the count right and
so that way if there's like two things
we get 0.5 which is how much we want for
each one and if there's three things we
get a third and so on so that produces
the correct bucket size and then at the
end we can go back through everything
looking to see where things were filled
in and remember at well you know what we
could do this right here as well
when we actually start these out we want
to take the app point we want to start
halfway through the bucket right so we
want to set our app point to be whatever
the bucket size is that we ended up with
and maybe I'll save this value here
something like that you know let's try
sighs this is I called it sighs so we're
gonna compute the size here and I should
effort to that just to be safe I would
probably warn me it would say you can't
divide because you're gonna lose okay
there whatever um so we get a bucket
size here that's equal to this then like
I said we want to start halfway there so
that starts us halfway through that
bucket
just where we'll place the first point
and then each time through there what
we're gonna want to do is take whatever
that at point was and we want to add to
it right whatever the bucket size is so
this is the point that we're at oops
essentially what we want to say here is
here's what we want to set the variant
to right and let me just go ahead and
grab this out
so we want to grab out the variant group
index which we've done we want to make
sure that it's not out of range we want
to find out where we should put this
point and then we want to make sure that
the next point that's in this variant
group goes somewhere else by the way
that should probably just do this so
that's pretty much all we need to do but
we now know the point we haven't written
in anywhere yet so we need to go through
and replace any mention of a variant in
this tag set with the correct variant so
in order to do that we would have to
loop through the tags like so so we
would want to do something like this and
we could probably do that up at the top
there and so when we loop through these
source tags what we want to do is say if
the source tag type is a variant then
we're gonna change the value of that tag
to be this point right and now what
we've done is like every time before we
pass this array down for writing we're
gonna do that modification now I'm not
super thrilled about it and I'm gonna
put it to do here
because we probably could clean up the
way we're doing these tags pretty easily
so that we just kind of like append the
variant tag here and stuff like that and
we just did it in a sloppy way we write
all of the tags into the asset system
for no real reason and so I feel like
we're gonna want to change that in the
future so yeah and that wouldn't be hard
to do but that's basically what we want
let's go ahead and fix errors now
compile errors so if we look at update
asset variance which is the routine we
wrote here it needs some stuff it means
the game assets so let's make sure it
gets them and what else does it need it
needs the oh it needs the source file
right it needs it needs this
and then that needs a identifier alright
so the asset itself here is never
actually referenced but it does need to
be and so if we look at updates single
asset made it metadata in theory that
should just be directly referenceable
off of the asset index and that should
be the end of it right so we should
actually be able to just do that and be
done I think let me look at the tag here
so that's an ID and then we're done so I
think that is at least the sketch of the
code that correctly allocates variance
based on how many were seen which is
what I wanted because I didn't want
artists to have to do that right I want
the code to do it automatically so
looking in here when we're actually
doing the update asset metadata what I
can do now is just call this update
asset variance call and then pass it
what it means which is that that oops
really Butterfinger II today that and
this the temp memory is it's this
I think that's it
all right um so the plum that we're
gonna have kind of right off the bat is
that I have no way of knowing whether
any of this worked like maybe it'll
crash or something and then we can debug
it but let's say it doesn't crash did it
work
and so I think what we want to do is
because right now I don't have any way
of viewing what tags were assigned to
things I think we want to expand the
editor to do that so in the in-game
editor we're gonna want to go and I'll
run it first and debug any crashing or
anything like that but after we do that
we're gonna have to we're gonna have to
add something that lets us view tags cuz
otherwise we're just gonna have no idea
if this worked right we just we just
don't know and we want that anyway like
we want to be able to look at tags for a
number of reasons and so you know that's
that's not a bad thing
so if we look at where we actually
display stuff in the asset editor what
you can kind of see here is we've got
some nonsense going on and then we add
some annotation to it what we want to do
is have a way we can display tags here
so and that's probably more important
than a lot of this stuff possibly not
more important than errors but you know
it's pretty important so what I'd like
to do is grab the tag set out of this
thing and dump it right so if you look
at where this you know stuff is coming
from you can see we've got the HHA here
so the it the HHA asset has a tag array
built into it if you look at that struct
it tells us where we would get it right
it's this stuff right here so we should
be able to do something that right in
line lists all the tags that were
assigned in this thing so that we can
actually see them so if we go and say
you know hey let's get a tag what I can
do is just say give me the first tag
we'll run through the last tag and then
we can just out of the asset system grab
that tag now there I think we're calling
some kind of a get asset call here I
just don't know if we ever made a get
tag call let's assume temporarily that
we did even though I don't think we did
yeah we did him so if we make a get tag
call that will produce the tag for us it
won't be hard it's literally just an
array offset but I want it behind a
function so he can check to make sure
people are asking for tags that are
outside of the tag array so if we go
ahead and get the tag here what I want
to do is take the tag index grab the tag
look at the ID for the tag and print
that out plus the value so in order to
do that I'm thinking like probably
something like this
maybe so we do label F yeah like the tag
name which i think is a real string and
then the floating point value of the tag
right so if we grab the tag like so we
would get the name here like get tag
name or something we have a function for
that so we'll grab that and then we'll
look at the value of the tag and put
that in there now in the file format
stuff we have a way of getting that I'm
pretty sure a tag name from ID and that
is you know pretty nasty it's a search
which is not great we could fix that
obviously by making a lookup table that
is it I think
all right so if we take a look at that
code and clean up the errors I'm
assuming the only thing we need to do
here is implement get tagged because we
don't think we have that I and this has
to actually be a tag so we have to cast
that to asset tag ID and then I think
we're good so inside the asset system in
handmade asset what we want to do here
is go to the get asset call which is
this and we just want the exact same
thing for get tag so you know everywhere
we were doing tags here because I don't
think they turn into a tag strut they're
literally just HHA tags so we would just
say what's the one that you actually
wanted when you get the tag back it will
then check to make sure that there
actually are that many it'll look for
them oh god it'll look for them and
return it to you like so I think that's
all we need there so what I want to do
first and you know before we go any
further with it I'm going to test it now
I'm gonna comment out the thing that
actually does the update asset variance
because I want to see what the values
are before we do that so if we go run
the code now like so what I want to do
is look in here and I want to go pick
something that would have had a variant
on it like this stuff out here I want to
like pick one of these and see what it
has so it's got a variant number of 0.75
it's got a facing direction of nothing
it's got a basic category of 24 it's a
tree it's not winter dark energy fall
right zero tags should probably get
optimized out eventually but right now
the way the picker works is a zero tag
means something so we don't actually
that but yeah okay so let's look at
something that has two variants because
this should help us so for example this
is sort of gonna be picking exact one
exact case that I expect to see and I
want to see it change so if I go to the
source code of the source art assets for
the base game and I look at the tree
stumps which is actually one of the the
things in here those tree stumps there's
two stumps so these should be assigned
to two buckets and it should be like
0.25 and 0.75 right is what these two
things should be assigned to right so
that guy should be 0.75 which is what
this guy is what you can see is it's
actually 0.25 now why is that the case
well it's the case because this guy got
0 and this guy got 0.25 right that's
what they were assigned to which was
wrong to begin with and I think I even
made it a comment about that separately
but anyway so what we want to see is
that guy gets set to 7.75 and hopefully
we'll also then see the other stump show
up once in a while because right now it
looked basically never would because you
have to pick a number that's below 0.1
right for that to ever happen because
it's at 0 and well 0.125 right which is
is much much rarer it's like 1 in 10
although we should still have seen it so
the fact that it didn't pick it it's it
reassuring right but yeah anyway so now
I'm gonna go ahead and comment this in
and debug it and see if we can get that
number to be correct which would be 0.75
9.25 so now if I go back and run it and
and we go back and look at these things
we can see what did it actually do if
anything right so let me go ahead and
pick one of those guys that's not right
so it looks
it worked at least it did the one thing
we expected which is it set that to be a
variant of 0.75 which is what we wanted
it set this to 0.875 I don't know if
that's correct let's look at what that
file has in it so if we look at this
scenery tree here that's this one so
looking at what that value looking at
what this actually should have been
there are four of these which means the
buckets point to five which means that
that one should have been one point
point one two five away from the end and
it is so it looks like our variant code
worked spectacularly well shockingly
enough which is a bit surprising let's
see if this guy got it correctly as well
so yep there's two of those so that is
exactly what we'd expect and we got both
variants of those oh wait no we didn't
this is the deprecated ever Evergreen
version which we have to remove at some
point so I guess what I'd say is
particularly weird here is we're only
ever getting the highest variant it's as
if that value is always set to one you
know what I mean
but it looks like the variant code at
least now is working which is what I
wanted and if we go look at what that
room gen code is doing like is there
something bizarre happening there with
the tagging and I don't know so if we
look at when we place a tree
actually it it looks like that's weird
it looks like we never pick him a
variant if we're never picking a variant
I'm not sure why we would be picking the
highest instead of the lowest so you
should probably look at why that is oh
you know why it's because we don't care
we ignore that tag if it's not set I
think that's how that works so if we
actually set a variant here how many
tags can you add to an entity by the way
I don't actually know at the moment
8:8 should be enough for everybody
there's no question that eight is the
right number just don't even talk to me
about numbers other than eight eight is
the highest number forget about it it's
the highest number all right so now we
can look and see whether we're getting
variants here and now we actually are so
I can see a bunch of here that haven't
had their sizes set yet right so if I
like pick these guys right you can see
that we're picking the various variants
so that was fine and that's good but you
know if we wanted these to look properly
they would have to have some adjustments
made like you know to see like how big
they should be you can see there's like
so this was one of the reasons we did
this test you can see like the
perspective is different on these and so
like this one is probably the right one
for us even more than that even more
exaggerated than that would probably be
a better perspective right like a top
more top down tends to look better for
us because of the way the camera is kind
of a top-down perspective or trying to
be but yeah so you know good on us a
happy happy day I can't seem to pick
that one because again the Box picking
those boxes are so huge that you can't
get them but doesn't matter because we
can suck other things in the box we
planned for this so I don't know how big
these trees should be but probably
something like that
I really gotta have some way of not
having that clip so I can just kind of
keep pulling on it all right yeah
oh there's one more guy we don't have
any way of picking behind the that thing
either which is not great so yeah let me
go ahead and
and some size to that guy wonder what we
could do about that I'm not really sure
all right so that's all good
oh one more
so like yeah I would consider that
problem solved
that was quicker and easier than I was
expecting it to be we can see we've got
some art bugs in here so I don't know if
you can see that I'm gonna raid that one
there's like a pink line that's actually
in the sprite you know I'm saying so
that that should get fixed let me try to
raid a reasonable bug on that so github
the github z' github Hey look there's
like a sponsorship thing I do find it
kind of unfortunate that like you know
modern Internet company is worth
billions of dollars largely were built
on software they didn't write and then
they don't pay for them
you know which is unfortunate it would
be nice if the people who made the
software like that powered Instagram
which was largely not Instagram you know
or something got paid part of the
billions of dollars right like those
people who made all that opens are
suffer should all be rich but they're
not so anyway inside my projects there
should be or repositories are not
project stars and main hero issues I
guess github would be another perfect
example right anyway we want to create
an art issue here
oh and hey we just finished that
and so what we want to do is create an
art issue here that's like a pink line
in three feet part of the template grid
looks like it's I'm gonna replace an
named tree sheet here with an actual
name of the file to make it easier for
Anna to know which one we're talking
about doesn't have to go hunting for it
so in here I'm just gonna look at which
one of these it was this one you can see
it right there
so it's scenery 303
and so that'll just be something that
gets cleaned up eventually we don't it
doesn't cause us any problem right now
but it's just a little something that
needs to get cleaned up before you know
you were to ship the game or something
so someday it has to get fixed but it's
not causing us any actual immediate
issues I don't know that there's any
more of that there might be I guess
we'll see it it wasn't it was nice that
it showed up so clearly so like
hopefully that will generally be the
case where something like that it will
be pretty obvious to us right away that
there was a problem so okay I think that
concludes us doing the variant handling
there it seems like we're in good shape
and so I think we probably want to start
doing a little bit more in the way of
cleanup here maybe cleanup of that tag
stuff I don't know if we want to start
that now but we could and the other
thing we probably want to do here is
again start looking at how we're
actually editing and saving those things
to try to extreme line that process up
like maybe fixing that Mouse Delta issue
there so for example you know when we're
when we're picking one of these I forgot
that I could do this so I guess I guess
we don't have a problem with picking
because we can do this right I was like
how do we pick stuff that's under there
and I forgot that we like have a perfect
debug camera now that can do anything
you want it to do
I forgot we got around to that so I
think what I'll do since since you know
we accomplished what we want to
accomplish today we don't have a huge
amount of time left but there's a
there's a decent amount right I mean
there's like 45 minutes I don't want to
start on ground cover because I want to
start on that beginning of a two-hour
block probably because it's gonna be a
pretty big push so we'll start that
maybe not next weekend because I think
I'm away next weekend but we'll start
that in two weekends so maybe let's try
to clean up some of our quality of life
stuff here and just say look dragging
these things is a pain
in the poop chute so we want to go ahead
and try to produce some code in the
platform layer that will help us be able
to do stuff like when we do this we we
don't hit the edge of the screen
right look I want to be able to just
drag that as far as I want to drag it
and I don't want to care if the mouse
hits the end you and I'm saying to you
so we would like some way of being able
to get that so they basically the the
mouse Delta that's occurring there and
there are definitely some issues with
that that make it particularly tough to
do and the reason for that is we don't
actually like we know that a mouse is a
differential pointing device so if you
think about what's happening with a
mouse it's pretty easy to say like oh
yeah let's let's just use the Delta that
you moved to adjust the value the
problem is like and this is not
hypothetical suppose that you know Ana
was using this and she's using like a
pen right well a pen doesn't have a
delta you know what I'm saying so we end
up in a situation where I'm not sure
that it's like if there's if there's an
obvious way to solve that problem by
just like assuming that the mouse is the
thing that you're going to use and so
you know I wonder if we want to do
something like create a spinner widget
so you can just like drag in a circle or
something cuz that would work with the
pen be in the same way it would work
it's really hard to say I mean there are
other ways we could do it too so one way
of doing it is another you know like
another option that we could look at
would be that normally what's going on
here is you're picking something and you
know if I were to size it in here we
would not have that problem so another
way to look at it would be like okay if
I can add this thing and then when I
click on this I am in a mode where I'm
going to resize this thing or reposition
it you know what I'm saying that would
presumably solve the problem because
then you would be interacting with it
where the limits are not relevant to you
like the reason that we get a problem
here is that if you touch that value you
end up you end up manipulating it in a
space that's totally abstract and has
like arbitrary boundaries if you're
manipulating it here it would just work
right you would just be able to do it
how you wanted so I I wonder like is
that a better way to do it should we
have it so that you click in there and
then it uses the projection to properly
figure out how much you should be sizing
that box right
I kind of feel like that would have to
be the answer
hmm hmm I say so I guess I don't have a
strong opinion on it that seems like the
right way to go on the other hand I
don't like the extra complexity that it
kind of adds into the system because now
you're talking about the code in the
game has to have even more garbage in
there for you know doing this sort of
like dragging and picking and stuff and
so on I don't know if I love that idea
one of the nice things about doing it
this way is it's totally isolated over
in the editor code and doesn't really
affect anybody but I don't know I mean
that doesn't mean it's the wrong thing
to do so maybe we need maybe we need to
just embrace that and just have it so
that it you know puts that in there and
that way you can just kind of drag these
things around like where they live and
then this stuff over here is more just a
way of you saying like what you're
editing you can just pick one you click
on that and it and then you can edit
that thing or maybe you just click on
like which one of these you want to edit
and then you know you add it the
position and size together like there's
a handle and you grab it or something
like that um I just don't know I don't
see anything simple we can do to fix the
problem really I mean one thing we could
do is just not move them by so little we
could make them move faster but I don't
know so that maybe isn't such an easy
change so I'm not sure yeah I'm just not
sure
[Music]
yeah I don't know um so let's see here
do we have anything else we can do
that's minor I guess we could we could
do so look take a look at some of these
things that have been reported oh you
know what this is definitely one thing
we should do this right here okay so I'm
gonna update the complete asset pack so
that people can just run directly since
now everything kind of loads and imports
properly with no other issues so what I
would like to do is fix our readme all
right so this is now different than it
used to be so
the director should contain at least
okay so let's take a look at what this
actually should have so if we go into
handmade bingo what are you doing you
coming up baby or what are you doing the
exploring we got a saucy puss today
you've been on stream all the time
haven't you
are you coming up are you coming up
where you staying down what's the
verdict you're coming up okay so what we
want to do is take a look at what's
actually going to be in here
so the code directory obviously we know
about the dated directory
does not exist as a thing now because it
will just get sort of created so what we
probably need to do and in fact that's
something that we may need to make sure
that our game actually does meaning our
okay
meaning our game what's going on plus
we're trapped we're trying to return a
program you want you want the game to to
be done right you're in it there's a
Molly in there did you know yeah yeah
that's right
so we want the we want the data
directory probably be created on its own
meaning if you don't so that's something
we could do today as well in fact maybe
that's what we'll do after we finish
this we want the art like directory is
not a thing anymore that's going to be
source sources
handmade misc is other stuff that's
actually true and then we've got tags
boo bingo
it's not time for typing case is typing
okay you got it wait so Casey's done
typing and you can type later all right
you're not gonna you're not gonna code
right now Casey gone code
Casey's gonna code okay Casey's gonna
code right now you want to play with the
chopstick don't play the chopstick okay
uh so then we've got misc and that
should be it right yeah
does the build-up bat-file so this is
probably all we really need to do so we
can make this say if not exist the
directory that this is okay seriously
why do you need the chapstick though why
do you need the chapstick do you want to
eat it you want to eat it okay I mean
why do you want to eat the chapstick
it's not tasty it's not sandwich flavor
okay so what we want to do here is say
look we're gonna have to make the data
directory so it's gonna create W
handmade data and yeah I think that's
all we really need right and it'll push
that in there we could we could have the
game put the art assets in the build
directory but I don't know that we want
to do that what are you doing kid okay
now you want to eat you want to eat the
almond biscuit
are you a hungry puss what's going on
alright good you just use a sit right
there that's good that's a good place
for you all right so I yeah like the
handmade data directory we can make
ourselves in here when we actually
launch this build right the we're in the
code directory so we're here so right
that's where the build that bat file is
so what we would want to do is just say
like look make a data directory if there
wasn't one
and we can test that as well so the
handmade data directory so we could say
and when after you run build bat for the
first time after you build for the first
time these directories will be created
for code for executable and packed asset
right
all right so I think that more clearly
explains what's going on and so now I
can update those things and we can
probably still call it latest art I
don't know if we should call it like day
underscore art zip or something so maybe
maybe we'll change to this
all right
okay so I think that's probably fine and
we'll pack up art assets as of a
particular day and you know you can just
always grab the one like ya could say
this unpack handmade here add a blah and
the hammer here are into the same
directory we recommend W handmade and
then what we would say is the art is
updated less frequently than the code so
you just need the art zip that is most
recent art zip that has a lesser or
equal number day member than once you've
been zipped those zips the directory
should contain at least these things and
after you build for the first time these
directories will be created for the
executables impact assets to build the
game that all looks good right so in
theory now we should be in a place where
[Music]
if I build it will try to create the
handmade data directory automatically
and let's just see if that's true so
let's suppose that you know somebody's
download the game for the first time and
so we've got this data directory and
they're retired thing I like I'm gonna
go ahead and get rid of the this this
data directory I'm gonna cut it though
and put it out into a retired thing out
here just in case we want to look at it
again so the data directory
is gone right all this stuff it's just
gone so when we go into
[Music]
so here's one thing I guess that'll get
packed up automatically - so that's all
flat so even the fonts will work that's
kind of nice
don't ask me what that's doing there
alright so in theory when we build now
for the first time it should create the
data directory and then when we run the
game it should build the pack let's see
if that's actually true so if I go to
handmade code and I hit build you know
did it create a data directory right it
did and then if I actually run the game
it should pack everything in there
hopefully yep and that'll take a while
away
I suppose we should probably put
something in there that's like a
progress meter for those people who
build for the first time it's probably
pretty intimidating to have nothing
happen right but yeah I'm not super
motivated to do something with that
because it's not clear how you would
display the progress meter you'd have to
you would have to have built a font into
the game executable because you haven't
loaded any fonts yet that's the whole
point is you're processing the assets
for the first time so it wouldn't really
be super plausible that you would be
able to do anything where you could
where you could display a progress meter
with not actually having a thought I
suppose you could just fill a rectangle
that maybe would work right
or you do the windows thing where it's
just a little circle that spins around
for a long time so that's looks like
it's almost done building everything no
and it is done building everything and
it ran correctly so hey good on us we
can do a complete rebuilds and
everything looks like it's in place all
right
okay so I think that's all good
how much time we got now because again
like just whittling down the list of two
dues here because I didn't want to start
the next big thing and we finished the
variant stuff much quicker than I
thought we were going to so neat to
observe that this was done on day 536
closed for comment looks like we've got
about 25 minutes left so let me see if
there's anything else I want to do here
minor issues naming in returns we could
clean up some of this stuff minor issues
handmade render LTP push render target
doesn't return a value does it never get
called how does that work let's go look
at these again just trying to find
something productive to do without
starting something big so push render
target does anyone call this
that solves that problem what else we
got the function prototype is out of
date and hanmi render geometry H
ah yes it is it's world P from the line
okay
that's fixed two mystery names in the
open Jill code
look those a secondly assert code will
be compiled away by clang yeah it will
work if it's cast to a volatile int oh
okay perfect
so let's do that
that works for me
create forest okay
create forest it's not a thing do we
call create forest we do not so I'm
gonna get rid of create forest for now
because no one's using it and we will
add it back in when we actually have
something for it to do so that leaves
just this end of this this is in
handmade renderer OpenGL and we're
talking about GLX texture srgb
[Music]
so I'm not sure I understand two mystery
names the OpenGL code one info GL x
texture srgb and one info GL x framer
for srgb instead of the info dot OpenGL
X texture srgb and OpenGL extra frame
buffer 1315
so I'm gonna have to reread this code to
remember what exactly it was supposed to
do so in here we've got in the opengl
info we've got opengl x texture srgb
OpenGL text frame buffer srgb and OpenGL
ARB frame buffer object this one has
nothing to do with this RGB oh I see
this code just isn't happening at the
moment it looks like we right we've
turned that off so and the reason for
that is because we're not doing actual
srgb in our sprite processing which
maybe we should switch to at some point
but in GLX texture srgb and GL x frame
buffer srgb
these just we renamed them and never
recompile this code so it's really just
that and you see the crow you looking at
the crow okay there's a crow outside and
I'm always trying to figure out how to
get down there you can't baby baby you
can't get to the crow I know it's sad
for her she want to go get the crow it
would fly away plus it would fly away
go watch the crowd yeah yeah yeah
chatter at the crow it's a cute noise
and so the same is true here right we
changed it to to this one so he was just
pointing out that we hadn't there's
nothing complicated there just we must
have tried compiling that path which we
don't use anymore because we use the the
squared non not srgb version so I'm
gonna go ahead and just comment that
back out and so then the last thing was
he was asking if there was way we could
stick the have the platform renderer
have a pointer back to the platform as
necessary and this is like like stuff he
wanted like the
x11 information alright we're getting a
lot of oh here Plus okay so there
I can I can try to describe for you the
problem that's happening outside there's
like tons of crows I don't know why
they're gathering they're kind of just
hanging out on like a power line and
then one of them is like down on the
ground and they're all just like chillin
and the primeplus is like you know
transfixed by this she's like super
ready to go down there and catch some
crows unfortunately that is not
something the premises can do prime
press is not allowed outside for safety
reasons isn't that right prime place
sorry baby
but as a result I'm getting the tail
like smacked in my face here let's try
and tuck that a little bit back here
we'll slide the keyboard up here so this
is a pretty reasonable request there's
no reason we can't add a void pointer
there to just sit around and allow
people to tuck some data in there if
they need it so I'm gonna go ahead and
put this in here and say note Casey this
is currently unused by us but we've
added it for other platform maintainer
so they can put some context pointers in
here for their own use and so I think
that is probably all we really need to
finish up this one so I think we've done
all of these we did that did that did
that did that did that and that all
right
okay primeplus you can't catch the crows
you don't have to hunch down okay
there's a window between us all right
baby I can't even get the keyboard now
the prime puss it's like squatted onto
the keyboard what else we got um so it
looks like we've got a few kind of weird
ones here that we could look at because
we still got about 15 minutes and you
know if we don't have something major if
we can't start something major we might
as well try to clean stuff up this I
think we did too that's been a long time
coming
and so now we're just kind of down to
this stuff prime plus what am i okay we
need to relocate the prime Chris she's
freaking out these headphones are
impossible to use that's such a short
cord on them too but I can't even like
really put the prime puss in their perch
very well there that's the best vantage
point that's why it's there my keyboard
is covered in cat hair now like like
absolutely spammed with it we got to get
the brush in here all right I got to put
it I got it good I'm coming to go to my
bay or did something and get a brush
today and just bring it back and put it
here cuz this is the same there is cat
hair everywhere and I mind you I brushed
her yesterday or maybe was the day
before it's been 1 or 2 days since the
brushing like it's tensed brushing
alright so so I think this is a case of
people were saying that basically what
we want to do here is since we require
open jail 3 when we actually do our
startup that we shouldn't check for the
parameter
this one so OpenGL our frame buffer
objects me yeah so this code here where
we look to see whether OpenGL
look like this nonsense is apparently a
problem because what happens is that the
opengl 3.0 context on mac don't report
that they have it
even though though they do because it's
part of 3.0 and so the idea here was
since we're requiring 3.0 anyway with
the you know when we do the major
version you know maybe we could just do
it the same way in fact that we're doing
this right so we could say something
like if major version is greater than or
equal to three and we don't care what
the minor version is right so if the
major version is more than three no
matter what then we just always say that
we have this
right so that would just bypass the
realm you would still do the check but
it bypasses any ill effects from the
check in the case where we have a reason
to believe that the major version is
larger and so you know I'll just say
okay um so what else we got
win32 render or test asserts because we
can't find the frame buffer we'll have
to take a look at what that is that can
these are on other platforms I believe
we've got a that older all that old
windows full screen bug here I'm just
going to pop all these open so we can
look at them sequentially all right this
one like this one like a resurfaced
we'll have to take a look at that
Martin's pointed out in case there are
no ops in the texture fq sizable does
not have the most optimal value current
code looks like this where each block
calculate size bill but else branch will
overwrite size available in case
transform instrument first use it will
have a smaller value than the actual
memory available this piece should
probably look like this so let's go take
a look at
wait what's the difference between these
two lines oh I see it looks like we were
missing an else right he's saying you
should do an else because otherwise
you're gonna hit this bottom block so
I've probably forgot to put the else in
there that may have been what we were
anticipating but we screwed up right so
let's take a look at the begin texture
up here and just see what's up so here's
the code yeah I mean we're not touching
this so that I feel like this was just
dumb I feel like that's probably what we
meant and we screwed it up right so
thank you Martins I don't think we need
to really check that too much because
that that almost certainly is what I
probably meant to do and I just screwed
it up
so let me just double check that we
don't hit anything weird
as a result but all right
maybe not
so we get an assertion that the transfer
member used
hmm
so I take it back maybe there is
something else going on here
too bad Martin's isn't watching but so
it's hard to page all this back into my
brain it's been a long time as we looked
at it but we're taking wherever the last
place is in the transfer queue that we
used and we're saying that's where we're
going to put this thing if we're at the
the outset right if we're if we're
starting the starting that this is the
very first transfer
well that's not really true it could be
either it's either that there's no
transfers outstanding or we've used them
all up so we just looked to see what the
opt-out is and if the OP count is zero
we assume it's that right so okay
so basically this is the exact
so wait I don't know this actually does
seem to be the case because if this if
this size available does get does end up
being used for this right you do like
I guess that's really the only thing
that would have to happen right so I
think Martin's is right but you need to
do this because if you're going to
transfer the entire if you're going to
use the entire memory you have to then
reset the pointer back to the beginning
in order to because otherwise you would
yeah you're somewhere random in the
buffer and you're gonna fill though and
you're saying you could feel the whole
thing but you'd have you have to reset
back to the beginning right so I think
that's the correct fix so he's right
that the structure should have had the
else but it also needs to have you
rewind because otherwise it won't work
right so I think that's the correct
solution
so now we've got inputs three parameter
not used in win three to get input file
location
[Music]
interesting
I'm gonna look at that one second oops
the reason is that the width and height
the texture that we create for the color
attachment are both zero because render
Jim hasn't been configured in the frame
settings I added this assert a zero with
the knife results a GL frame before
incomplete attachment interesting so
let's look at create frame buffer
so first let's get the assertion to fire
and then maybe we'll nerf it so that if
it does get asked to do that it won't do
it so I'm assuming you would have to
provoke this
because we don't have that happen in our
code so let's take a look at the render
test I guess
maybe that one does so in the build
render test I don't know where this is
supposed to run probably there there we
go so what we need to do here is make
sure that this obeys the same stuff in
the render test as we do outside it
right and the render width and render
height here I guess the problem is the
change to settings call is happening
before anyone has actually told it how
big it should be right yeah
so yes so in here we need to we need to
set those values but for whatever reason
looks like they aren't getting set is
that just because these come back a zero
I'm gonna compile debug mode by the way
so those both get set so how is it
possible why are we not are we not
calling like some kind of initialization
that was supposed to get called here
where are those values coming from they
are coming from
settings rendered in so did we not set
the setting it's the settings that we
are passing here right so
[Music]
it's OpenGL current settings and command
settings it's this one that we care
about so the commands the settings in
the command set are the ones we care
about and I guess those never get set so
inside here these are not getting set I
guess
so for example in here where we where we
create some commands we do open till
begin frame apparently like the render
dim just isn't set so inside the win32
hand-made opengl code well i guess more
in the winter there - handmade code we
must set the render dim ourselves here
yeah so what we presumably want to do I
would guess is when you actually call
begin frame we should probably pass them
both right meaning that begin frame call
here where we've got the rectangle - I
draw region and the window with window
height that code probably wants to set
the render dimension itself so in
addition to these we would also want to
pass the render dimension
so we'd have window and render
dimensions I would think
looking at the window dim that's really
just used for the final viewport stuff
so that's fine um so I think I'm gonna
go ahead and change that so what I want
to do here is say let's suppose that
that like OpenGL begin frame that that
is something that has to happen made to
look at the renderer platform definition
here so this call here their renderer
begin frame part of things
I wonder why is there a reason these
don't use this stuff like is there a
reason that this isn't this anyone know
Oh
cuz it cracks that's why I see so when
we actually record that callback we're
gonna have to actually have a pass
through here so the window within the
window height we can pass those in and
we also need the render width in the
render height let me do a begin frame
and so in here right we've got to do a
render dim with render Jim height right
and so if we look at what that frame
what those render commands actually look
like this is actually already a V to you
and so I feel like we should just have
like render dim those two should just
get passed as vectors right
so in here we should just do this and
then we assign them so there's the
render dim there's the OS window dim
right so I think that's what we would
rather do and then we can follow the
White Rabbit backwards oops and figure
out how to fix that okay so OpenGL begin
frame has a forward declaration
somewhere here it is so what we want to
do here is say we've got a V to U V to u
like so and then we should get a an
assignment issue right here so what we
want to do here say OS window dim render
dim and then the renderer begin frame
call that actually now needs to be
updated so where we define that call
and then that has everything we need
we'll call it a day right okay so now
the places where we call this are wrong
but that's okay
so what we can do here is say well you
know here's the the window and then the
render dim I don't know did we ever done
anyone actually ever specify what the
renderer dim was so I guess we were just
rendering we were expecting to render at
the dimension of the draw region
probably I mean I don't know what we
want to do there so maybe what we say is
we say like rendered in
so when we do aspect ratio fit will say
is rendered in with render dim height
and that way this will all like flow
through properly so we probably should
have done that to begin with but you
know for whatever reason we didn't okay
so this wants to take the render Jim as
well and there it goes and then we need
to do the same thing here so dimension
with and dimension height is the window
dimension that is already a v2 u so that
can just come in here and then now we
can pass render dim instead and I think
that gets us everything that we needed
so now maybe possibly we can fix this
error
let's take a look oops first of all let
me let me actually run hand-made hero
and make sure that we've got that we
didn't screw it up
not great what did I do wrong there
we're passing render dim to begin frame
and so open jail begin frame should
right set that and that's all we were
doing here so this should have been
equivalent but it wasn't why wasn't it
right I mean that should have worked
just fine but it didn't so let's take a
look at why not
so that looks like it's all set properly
which is what would expect when we come
in here we're gonna read that out of
there and we're gonna read oh no I was
supposed to set that sorry about that
guys
my bad
how was that okay so I'm was confused I
was a little bit confused about that to
begin with so if the rendered image in
the settings then why did I add it here
I don't know I must have just been kind
of spacing out there
right
so I guess I kind of see why we didn't
do that it's because that we almost need
a call for that because so in here well
I guess not really I mean you can just
pass it down every time right and it
should be fine so I guess that's fine
so I think we're all good there and
let's let's see what happens with the
random chance so still not right
although we don't really know if that
has anything to do with what we broke
right that could be something else but
we did fix that crash so we should
probably take a look at that as well so
I think we've done most of these we
didn't we're gonna have to look at that
one though and we'll take a look at that
later this seems like we I don't
actually know so so I guess the problem
there is the render test is is probably
not updated to use the new locations of
assets that may be the entirety of it if
you look at like where it defines like
what it should actually be loading right
you can see this stuff but I don't think
we've got any of that anymore right I
guess that was inside the test directory
so I could just go grab it
probably somewhere in here no maybe not
like I don't know where okay so it was
in here right so probably what we want
to do is inside the sources directory we
probably want to put that now so like in
here we can put render or test and then
this thing I don't know how it like does
its pathing but we probably have to just
start it in that directory right yeah
cuz it's just whatever it just does
whatever right so we'll put that in
there and then we'll say like okay the
render test starts in sources render or
test that's called and we'll save that
into our debug directory hand-made debug
to render or test and now we're good yes
so let's double check that the release
field still works and then we'll go to a
brief Q&amp;A off we go that seems good
no no real issues there
everything's fine and let me go ahead
and the load handmade and make sure
everything's fine there it looks good
and so I think we're all good so we're
just down to two issues in the an issue
stream well three so these guys right
here and these two should be pretty
trivial this one's gonna be bad cuz this
is like a Windows 7 compat bug so we'll
see about that but we're getting closer
alright so that was good it's always
good to do some spring cleaning get
those two dews out hey big guy still
with us good girl good girl you're gonna
get all those crows someday you can get
them all well you do all the platform
layers or leave that to the community
support we'll definitely do some
platform layers it just depends when
we're done which ones makes sense you
know I'm saying to you but we're gonna
do some ourselves whether we do them all
or not there are probably some platform
there's community people do that we
don't do you know will you add some
randomness to the sizes and maybe shapes
of the trees yeah we'll definitely do
some randomness there but exactly how
we're gonna do that I'm not quite sure
yet how we want it how we want that to
work at the moment each entity has a
size parameter so we vary that and we'll
probably vary the colors a little as
well
we do thing about using the mouse wheel
in order to drag values in the editor I
think it also doesn't work because
obviously pens don't have a mouse wheel
right so yeah and if you're making
something that an artist might need to
use don't use a mouse wheel right are we
doing more meow hash later tonight I
don't know I mean we got a we got to go
do a little bit more investigation but
man that was depressing some of the
problems probably just meow bench so
getting rid of that would be good but
it's not great
you
having just dealt with weighted
distributions and cumulative sum draw
when you add weighted section to the
tree selection Isum trees
maisha more or less common so not for
variance variants are supposed to be
interchangeable the other parameters
that actually are not interchangeable so
for example whether or not tree has snow
on it whether or not it's fall or spring
or whatever those will all be pulled
from actual distributions that are based
on what's trying to be created but the
idea behind variance is that we don't
have any information about them that's
the that's what a variant is it's one
that we have a literally no idea so we
could put a distribution in for them
that is not even but it's unclear what
it would be because since we have no
information we don't know that we should
pick one more often than another one
right so it's a little bit hard to say
we could do something where the artist
can weight the distribution or something
cuz that's not hard for us to do but
again we I'm gonna have to wait till I
see an actual like need for it I'm not
gonna probably do that without some more
information right
since we're producing equi spaced
variant points now it's it's really easy
for us to wait our our randomized
distributions towards something but yeah
I just I don't have a use case in mind
for that at the moment so it would have
to wait till we actually had some
something to do too much late night hash
[Music]
that was just awful if you were on the
stream last night that was terrible
that is just depressing that's
depressing programming so if that was
Wolverine a gator left like normal speed
right click double speed dragging or
some modifier cue the pen also has I
yeah I mean we could but I don't know I
just feel like maybe we want to put a
widget on there that way you can just
grab it and it just works you know and
that seems better to me depression
oriented programming that that is a
great term we should Corinne to new
terms do P which is depression oriented
programming and OOP which is oppression
oriented programming which is like when
you have to program in C++ right
I have watched an older episode where
you were coding player movement related
to a moving translation point will there
be any in-game elements using this
mechanic um I'm not sure I understand
what you mean are the monsters from Anna
draw is it going to be in handmade hero
to know what mechanic are you referring
to are you talking about the collision
detector and the answer is probably not
because since we are hopping only we
can't really use that it doesn't really
do anything for should say we just don't
need it because the logic oriented
collision is what we actually want we
will use collision detection to
determine when like projectiles or the
fist hits things so collision detection
will happen but the moving via moving
translation points oh oh are you just
talking about are you talking about like
the fact that this guy's on a point
right now and this thing it's on could
be moving around because the answer is
yes we may do something with that right
there may be like like rotating pieces
that you hop on and go around
do you know what I mean so yes yes if
the after talking about yes we probably
will do some stuff with that and we will
also do some rooms that have non grid
layouts probably as well right so there
will be stuff like that for sure
what's your coaching method to hide a
string in a project um I guess it
depends on how hard you wanted to be
hidden like if you're just trying to
hide it from somebody who's gonna run
strings on the executable then it's not
hard I mean you can do anything you know
rot13 it or anything you want right
anything will hide it XOR it with
something except the high bit on every
ASCII value right so if you're just
trying to hide a string from somebody
who's just like searching yes you do
have strings that's trivial if you're
trying to hide a string from somebody so
that like they literally can't find it
like they are gonna disassemble the
program and step through it and try to
find these strings and you don't want
them to find them well then that's kind
of that's a lot harder right that's like
sort of a different level of scrutiny
and I would say at that point you're
looking at things like trying to like
have very diffuse parts of the code pull
bits of the string and like recombine
them at different points in the code
that are not obvious and stuff right I
mean the best thing to do if you're
looking for information about that is I
would go watch old videos about how
people implemented copy-protection you
know because that's what you're
basically doing and just instead of
trying to prevent the game from being
pirated you're trying to prevent the
game from having string data exposed and
so you you'd want do all the same crap
right like all the same anti-piracy crap
where you're trying to hide the checks
for whether or not the disc is authentic
and all that stuff that's what you're
trying to do so you're trying to you're
just you're just gonna want to like go
look at that extensive history of
techniques and think along those lines
because that's it's that's what they
were trying to do right that's what the
anti-piracy people were trying to
they're trying to prevent leakage of a
piece of data and
piece of data was how it was determining
whether it was an authentic copy and so
that same most of that same stuff can be
applied to hiding a string okay oops
do draw a little dot there thank you
everyone for joining me for the episode
of hand made here at same pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow in series at home Yuko is
peer to the game at handmade hero org
and it comes with a source code which
you could play off at home and now as of
today for the first time in a while we
have a complete distribution that should
now be up-to-date forever because we can
just update the art assets where you can
rebuild the whole art asset data pack
including even the fonts automatically
so you should be able to go immediately
up to speed if you wanted to build the
game as it is at the moment so that's a
good thing and we want to do that for a
while but we just weren't done with we
never really quite got around to
finishing our data file and we now kind
of have and the art pipeline is actually
decent it still needs some work but it's
it's pretty darn good at this point and
so I will be uploading in addition to
today's code build I'll be uploading a
graphics zip which both can test out as
well
that's about it for today I will be off
next weekend because I'm not in town but
we will be back the weekend the
following weekend when I think we'll
start on the new thing maybe we'll try
to do the ground cover and get that
system in place cuz that's that's a big
push that does a bunch of things too
that I wanted to do separately and also
I may do like ground cover and lighting
at the same time because they're
actually interrelated in ways that maybe
not obvious but they will become more
obvious when I work on them all I'll
show you anyway so thanks for enemy uh
sorry I won't be around next weekend
hopefully everyone will have some
programming they can do on their own we
are covered in cat hair here so that's
always good maybe you're covered in cat
hair
where you are - so hmm has filled that
one have a good free weekend next
weekend and I'll see you the weekend
after take it easy everybody