hello everyone.welcome a handmade hero
show recode a complete-game live on
stream we are doing a little bonus
stream here again like I kind of just
wanted to stream I wanted to yesterday I
want to show you today um I don't know
exactly
we're gonna be doing on the game today
because again I plan to be on winter
break but we're not on winter break so I
don't know
so we yesterday when I did a stream like
this one just drop him we took a little
look at our list here of stuff and so
maybe that's what we'll do today again -
so just take a look at some stuff here
that we've got on the list of things and
try to clean up any loose ends that we
have here so you can see I really want
to filter out enhancements probably
because enhancements are things for kind
of at the end of the game like things we
want to add in potentially or maybe at
least things that should be second on
the list I don't know how you do that
because I don't use github you can see
here there's like a filter by label you
can filter labels that you want to have
in I'm not sure how you filter labels
that you don't want to have in if I
click on enhancement
I'm guessing anyway that would show me
just that I'm wondering if I can you
know can you do something here I don't
know like can you say not that thing
I don't know so hard to say if you can
do that at all but yeah who knows so we
made it set to leave those in there I
don't really know
and again the handmade ray ones
obviously aren't related to what we're
doing
those are further when we do our little
handmade ray streams that are just kind
of fun streams that are a different
project altogether
so we're mainly looking at the stuff
that we've got in here I'd like to take
them for it from the bottom on up and so
on because these have been sitting
around a long time they're just little
things that really haven't had a problem
with so here we have a segfault and
handmade brain and this is a thing where
it's just you know handmade brain is not
real code it's sort of placeholder code
for later when we implement things like
enemy AIS or the player controller and
things like
but if you look in there there's
probably some stuff where if you know
the head gets detached from the hero or
something like this we didn't actually
properly bracket it so that you can't
access those things and what you see
here is we've got like body facing
Direction equals head facing direction
yeah you can see it right here so the
interesting thing about this is that you
need to have both a body and a head for
that to work and it looks like it's in
there
so I don't think this particular thing
would actually have that problem it
looks like maybe we already fixed that
because you can see the body in the head
sort of already have to be on there so
let's see here head is no - not too
native there's if head blocks so I think
we changed this summer on the line so I
think I think we inadvertently fixed
this at some point looks like it's now
inside the if head and body block so I
think this actually already got fixed
there may still be problems in here but
again this code is not we're gonna do
some more work with code like that in
kind of in the future we we don't really
need to be too worried about this so I'm
not super worried about this anyway
because it's not really a segfault I
would care about it's in code that's
gonna get blown away and replaces
something better so it's not something
we have to be particularly careful about
so in here this is a different this is
not really a bug per se this is almost
an enhancement but it's one we should
probably talk about it's not really that
important to deal with now but we might
as well because it's easy fix so what
happens here let me just explain a
little bit about what this person is
talking about for folks who don't who
aren't familiar with this situation so
one of the things that happens if you
think about how a personal computer
modern person computer is constructed
you kind of know if you're a gamer
anyway you know what it looks like
you've got a big old case and besides
the fact that it's you blinged out with
tons of RG
lighting you also have a CPU in there
right that goes onto the motherboard
with a big old honkin heatsink on it or
water-cooled piping or god knows what
right and then into the PCI slot of this
thing you've got a gigantic usually
takes up two slots now a gigantic video
card with a GPU chip on it its own
memory right it's this huge thing giant
heat spreader fans that thing gets
jammed in there right and this is a huge
honkin thing and now if you've ever put
together computer yourself you also know
that that gigantic huge honkin graphics
card takes its own power plug right so
the power coming off the PCI bus isn't
sufficient to run this thing it now
needs its own plug sometimes too so that
structure if you think about it that's
powering like modern gaming at a high
level 4k graphics super high-end all
this stuff high detail settings 144
frames a second got you know whatever
all this other stuff right that whole
world draws a ton of power if you look
at the power draw of just that GPU the
power draw of just the video card itself
is usually more than the entire computer
it can draw 200 300 Watts these things
are insane sometimes right if you have
like two of them in there whatever so
the amount of watts going to the GPU is
more than your phone battery has or
laptop battery has total right in an
hour so one hour of running one of those
GPUs your phone battery couldn't even do
it your laptop battery couldn't do it
it's drawing that much wattage per hour
right but it's fine because it's plugged
into a wall outlet which has a ton of
watts and is used to running things like
washing machines and dryers which draw
tons of electricity or charging a Tesla
for if you're one of those people who
ordered a model 3 or if you're wealthy
and have a Model S um so it's fine for
desktop computing to be using it an
incredible amount of power but once you
get to a
top it just it doesn't really have that
kind of power available so obviously
you've got some other you know you've
got to have some other setup in there to
support graphics because the kinds of
stuff that you see in a desktop is never
gonna fly it could be in there to work
when you plug in your laptop to a wall
outlet for example but it's never gonna
work if you're just on battery power
flying on an airplane somewhere you know
going home for Christmas or who knows
what you're doing and you're typing on
your laptop that graphics has to be way
lower power because you just don't have
the draw for it so the solution that a
lot of laptops have adopted in the case
of the PC world is what they'll do is
they'll use part of the CPU die so
basically you know you got a CPU on that
die there's a bunch of cores right the
cores we have for CPU computing but then
there's also a little crappy GPU stuck
on the die so you've got some cores for
the CPU and some cords for GPU just on
one chip intel does this that's what
Intel integrated graphics is right AMD
does this that's what the apu czar and
that way you can just stick one of those
in there and the laptop does it and
those can be low-power that can be
throttled down just like the cpu is
lower power you can throttle down so in
your battery power it doesn't run very
fast or run slow convergence or Zenergy
right but if you really need to get some
high quality graphics on the screen they
will then on the higher end laptops
they'll throw in a mobile GPU part as
well right so there'll be another chip
on there which is also a GPU but that
ship will be dormant so it will be
basically completely powered off for the
most part most of the time so if you're
just you know typing into a text center
or something it doesn't need to fire
that thing up you then go and run some
piggy webpage or you run you know some
kind of a game and the game will spin up
the high end GPU and render on that now
this drink
your battery quickly so you usually
don't want to do it if the laptops not
plugged into something but when the
laptop is plugged into something you
want that GPU to get fired up the
question becomes how does the computer
know whether to turn on the GPU or not
right because it is a discrete decision
pun intended if you've got a CPU that
has a GPU a weak GPU on it and then
you've also got a beefier GPU sitting
there on the side that if I turn it on
I'm going to use a lot of battery but I
would get a lot better performance how
does a computer know which one to do and
the answer is it doesn't and it often
makes the wrong decision
so there's that but if the user is savvy
they know that there are things they can
do to help it out you can go to the
Nvidia control panel the AMD control
panel the intelligent graphics panel and
there's things you can say this
executable run on the discreet graphics
part this executable do that and
furthermore you can set those sometimes
based on whether things plugged in or
not so you can say look if I'm plugged
in use the good GPU if I'm not plugged
in only used a good GPU if I run this
particular program so now that brings us
to this particular issue what it says
here is we've got trouble with Nvidia
Optimus right Nvidia Optimus is the
brand name for when you have an NVIDIA
GPU in your laptop that sits dormant
until it needs to get turned on and the
Intel integrated graphics is what runs
most of the time and so what you can do
is the reason this person filed it is
because we don't warrant our executable
we don't recommend that it run on Nvidia
Optimus or AMD or anything we just have
a vanilla cutable so what our xq2 will
do is run the default right that means
by default we'll probably run on
integrated graphics but handmade here is
not really something that wants to run
at integrated graphics it wants to run
on the discrete GPU if it can and so
what we may want to do is by default
say let's ask the system to please run
us on the discrete GPU if it's okay with
the user the user can still disable that
and so the question is how do you do
that well one way of doing that is you
can weld in to your executable an actual
marker that lets Nvidia know that you
want to run the screen GPU and similarly
you can do that for AMD and you can see
the person who is requesting it here
helpfully cut and paste those in but
these are not secret you can find these
on the internet just by searching so
it's totally it's just a known thing you
can put in there and what you want to do
is you want to use these to tell the
default graphics setup that hey as long
as the user doesn't tell you not to
because the user may say I want to run
on low power so don't let this happen
there's not as you didn't tell you not
to run us we're one of those
applications that needs the power okay
so how does this work in practice well
if you go way back to the beginning of
handmade hero
do you remember and we've done this a
couple times since then to remember
there's this dependency check I don't
know if this thing ever worked the other
dependency generator that doesn't look
good this here it is if you remember
looking at the you see here we open up
ours first of all it's in build so we've
done this a couple times if I open up
win32 your hammer exe what you're gonna
see here right is a sort of a listing of
what our executable looks like when the
system goes to read it now remember go
back and look at the archives if you
don't know any of this stuff because
we've covered it all before
when you build a Windows executable
inside that executable or DLL but
basically actually O's Andy allows both
have these there's essentially a table
in there that lists a bunch of things
that the executable has marked so it's a
bunch of code right next table is a
giant block of code and data and stuff
like this and in order for that the
operation to use it it has to have some
a table that basically says you know
here's the entry point yours rise to
start running this thing for example but
it also needs to know like are there any
other things that I might need to know
in here are there other things I might
need to link to or options that I need
to know about and so what happens is if
you look at the handmade executable well
what you can see is you can see all of
the things that we import for example
here they are right but you can also see
all of the things that we export now
since this executable doesn't ever get
linked to by anybody else you can see
there's no exports here so the only
thing that's marked on our table and
it's not shown here but the only was
marked sale is the actual entry point
that the system uses but remember we
build some DLL scoops I didn't mean to
close that so let's open one of our
dll's one of the ones we use right so
here's win32 a hand made opengl this is
our renderer right and so what you can
see here is if we actually look at our
DLL you can see that we export a
function went through to load renderer
right that's our function that our game
calls we load that in and then jump to
it right so this is that table and we
can put as many things in there as we
want so you've seen me do this in the
win32 code right I load this DLL I call
get proc address and I look for get for
win32 load renderer right so I can see
you know an external executable can load
a DLL it can see what's in it so what
they chose to do for the Nvidia and the
a.m. AMD stuff the way they chose to
expose that preference right that says
this executable wants to be run on you
know Nvidia Optimus or on AMD's discrete
chip if it's there right if they said
just add some dummy stuff to this
ordinal table the export table just add
some dummy stuff with secret names that
we provide right and we're the only
people who look for that we'll look for
it if it's there rugged do anything with
it but we're just gonna see that it's
there and if it's there we'll know that
that's what you wanted right so they're
effectively using the export table as a
sort of preference as a sort of thing to
put a preference in there so it's
they're not trying to actually provide
an address like you normally would
instead what they're trying to do is
just say look let's dump some settings
in there right so instead of providing
an address that you know you're gonna
jump to or do something with instead the
address is just where do you read the
preference from right it's a good idea
right it's it works pretty well I think
it's a it's a smart use of that feature
and it doesn't cost really anything that
making that table a little larger
doesn't hurt anybody it's a not a big
table to begin with so all we would have
to do if we wanted to weren't that is
you know inside are went through two
handmade code in here we can just add a
little thing where we say something like
you know note we prefer the discrete GPU
in laptops we're available right and
then what we would do is we just again
include these secrets so here they are
right
conveniently supplied by the person
that's a great thank you for filing that
with the bug report so I don't have to
go search for them because otherwise you
search on the web and you gotta go dig
these up yourself right but here they
are right there just to exported symbols
one is called envy optimist enable
enablement when it's called ambi power
expressed requests high-performance
right and all they literally don't do
anything other than export those symbols
for us so now if we rebuild right all
that's gonna happen is when we look at
our code now if i refresh this and i
don't really know how to do that can i
refresh this I can't so I guess I'll
just reload it we go
or maybe that did refresh I was on the
wrong one so maybe I did there we go so
now when I look at the executable
remember there was nothing on here
before now both of those things show up
on the import table and both of them are
like it shows where the address is if we
went and looked at that address in
theory we should see the 1 &amp; 1 now I
don't know if they care about what those
are set to it made like I don't know if
they actually go in and look at what
those values are they may not it may
just be if it's there or not but they
may actually go in digital and read
what's out that app off set look and
then see if it's a 1 or not so we want
to leave it as the recommended setting
just in case they actually look but they
may not look they may just look at at
whether the name is there for all I know
so I'm not sure you can go read about it
one way or the other we don't care we
know that's what they want us to put in
their new name but so we're just gonna
leave it that way and that's it so now
on laptops that should just work so
that's all done and again if we wanted
to test that we could on a laptop or
something we can't really test it on
this machine but that's something for a
little later on in the process also it's
kind of a hard thing to test because a
lot of times those things are finicky
and so it's hard to know whether you're
really getting the right results or not
because there's so much cruft
in the driver that may do different
things or decide to do different things
sometimes it's kind of hard to figure
that out right whether you're setting is
what's causing it to run or whether it
was some thing the driver just decided
to do because it knows that it should or
whatever right so that's a little tough
if that makes sense all right so let's
go to Linux updates now I don't know if
these are up-to-date or not but this
this is you know from a while back and
so we want to see whether these see
what's going on let's see here
so let's take a look at some of this
stuff and try to figure out what we
could this one for example we definitely
haven't fixed so we could go try to fix
that for them the status problem here
looks like we've got an issue with the
window manager so that one we might want
to fix and then this one I don't know to
what extent we're still doing that but
we can look so all of these are things
we should be able to fix for people who
are running on links just makes it
easier for them to keep running on Linux
so let's see if we can we can deal with
that for them so in the OpenGL
infrastruc which we have right here
basically the issue is that these names
are as Mac defined as macros on Linux
unfortunately so what we want to do is
just just get them out of there right
something like this just just make it so
there's something not just name them
something else right and that way we
won't have that conflict the only reason
we're doing that again is just to
placate the macro preprocessor so that
it doesn't freak out that's not
something that happens on other
platforms but apparently it's true on on
Linux so again just renaming those
should solve that problem so that should
be good the status variable here in
hand-made open jail I don't know we can
just look for anything called status in
a in a dependent thing and check let me
just see if we've got anything here
that's using the word status as a bear
yes so this right here
status is a type name apparently of some
kind or something like this and so it
doesn't like this so I can just rename
this to frame buffer status or something
right and then hopefully that won't be
an issue we'll see how that how that
goes there that seems fine right and
then down here where we've got the this
one's a little bit more subtle so let's
talk about this one a little bit more if
we go into wizard do handmaid
what you can see for our memory
subsystem is that in here we've got like
you know the code that normally does
allocations you can see it's got like
virtual free and virtual a lock and
stuff like this right and so the reason
that we call like if you uh if you
followed handmade hero this far you you
know how we deal with memory and all
that sort of stuff at some point we have
to call the operating system to map
memory for us because obviously you know
allocating memory is something a lot of
partners don't think about these days
because they just use garbage collection
or a language that doesn't have that
concept and memory just kind of comes
out of nowhere and goes back to nowhere
and you have no idea what's going on in
Los Osos behind the scenes for us right
we actually are programming the actual
computer here and what that means is
that at some point we need to map into
an address space reserved we have to
reserve some part of the physical memory
and the virtual memory that the
operating system is thinking about as
well we have to have that reserved for
us to use and so the way we do that is
with the win32 calls virtual Alec and
virtual free now the way we would do it
if we were putting the computer 100%
directly is we'd be able to actually
modify the page tables ourselves right
we'd be able to actually create the CPU
page tables that say what the memory is
but we can't do that because we're
running on top of Windows and Windows is
the only person privileged to do that so
we have to ask Windows do it for us
which is fine it's just virtual Alec
virtual free virtual Alec creates a
mapping of pages for us to use virtual
free releases some of those pages back
right now here's the problem that that's
being talked about here on Linux
obviously when you port this thing to
Linux you also have to have a way to do
that same mapping and again even though
it's the same chip
they're both x64 is probably running
this thing I mean you could run it on an
arm or whatever but you know it's
probably the links were isn't probably
run in the next 64 as well that's
because we are not editing the page
tables we have to call the operating
system to do that it means we have to
different ways we have to call the
operating system one for Linux one for
win32 so here's the win32 version
what's the linux version well the linux
version is mem map and mun map I think I
can't member what the unmapped one is
just saying here I don't remember maybe
M map itself kimmm I don't remember what
the Lynx versions are it's been a while
but point being they are basically the
same as virtual rocket virtual free but
like all operating systems each one is a
little bit different and for virtual a
lock Windows doesn't need you to tell it
about the size of the pages anymore
after you do the first time so when you
call virtual a lock and you say I want
to allocate 30 pages of memory 34k pages
right if you ever want to talk about
that memory again you only need the base
pointer because Windows remembers what
the size was and you don't have to tell
it so when you call virtual free you
notice we don't pass the size we just
pass memory now if you look at virtual
free what you can see is the size is
actually there and is actually optional
but if you're not gonna do an operation
that has to do with partial with with
sub working out of pages if you're just
gonna release an entire chunk you can
just pass 0 because it knows what the
size is so it'll just release the whole
size for you right so that doesn't have
an equivalent on Linux on Linux when you
call mem map it doesn't remember the
size it has no idea what the sizes so
when you go to unmapped the size you
have to pass the size again which means
that the people who are porting this
game to linux they don't have a way of
conveniently doing this when virtual
free gets called everywhere it gets
called right so here's another one you
can see all of these they all pass zero
and there's no way for them to make that
call so what we need to do is go through
each place where we call virtual free
and work backwards to make sure
that route from a lock to free always
preserves the size the whole way through
that makes sense so that's what we need
to do now so let's start by looking for
this debug platform reading to our file
are we using this stuff how is this
stuff getting used
I assume it's getting used in the asset
system but I don't really know let's
just find out it's not getting used we
can also just delete it but this is in
our render test code this stuff doesn't
count so at the moment we're not really
using it but I'm disinclined to
eliminate it entirely only because I
don't know we may want to use it again
at some point soon right
because again well I don't know since
we've got these now this maybe should
just go away because maybe I think now
we've got open and closed we've got read
and write I think we should probably
just use these so let's say that this
goes away I'm gonna delete those and see
what happens it looks like we've got it
to do for exactly that
yeah so so those we don't need to change
I think because those should just go
through the regular system now and so I
don't think we really want to yeah I
don't think I want to bother with that
anymore
all right so those are all gone now and
so in the win32 handmade stuff where is
that winter to where is that debug read
entire file I don't want that to go away
here it is so this stuff here where
we've got free file memory read entire
file right trough that stuff just wants
to go away and now I just want to pull
out anything that was previously using
that so this stuff here this read entire
file free file memory yeah so that stuff
can just go away cuz we have real file
reading and writing in there now which
just makes more sense anyway so that all
seems good now we just need to deal with
the other ones that are there so there's
here and there this one we don't really
have to worry about because this one is
only for win32 and also the dibs section
stuff we don't use anymore right so
that's pretty much not a thing in fact
we could probably pull this code out
entirely at this point because right now
the only thing we're doing with that is
changing the off-screen buffer stuff we
could just delete this entirely because
the we always use open jail or whatever
the sub graphics driver is for display
so really it's just the buffer width and
height stuff that we're even using there
so what we might want to do is just say
look global back buffer you know is that
really a thing we should even be doing
at this point because that's kind of old
that's old news right and we're really
just using it for the render width and
height at this point and so I feel like
that kind of just wants to go away right
the this win32 off-screen buffer stuff
that just probably wants to die
so let's take a look at who's actually
using it and we'll just pull that out
because that's just another thing we
should just clean up right it just isn't
isn't really relevant uh so yeah let's
ditch this for starters get that out of
there I where we're actually calling it
we'll get rid of that so in here we'll
just have a thing that's like you know
v2 you render dim you can preserve this
and we can also have like you know all
of these could still come in here right
so if we just go ahead and keep all of
our old test resolutions because we
might want to play with those at some
point as well right
so that should be fine and then our
render dim we can just use later so
there's only a couple places we'd really
have to never I forgot to leave the
global back buffer I'm like we should
have a bunch of errors but we didn't
have any errors I'm like what
so the main thing we're gonna have to
deal with is this so I'm gonna skip that
for a minute we're gonna come down here
we now know that this rendered dim stuff
should be fine so if I just do render
dim X you know render dim I think
actually we can actually do that if we
want right no win32 window dimension I
don't know what that is so this is just
an int Winton I don't know I guess it's
an int so maybe we wouldn't want to
switch that over 2a v to you because but
assuming that they can never really be
negative we should probably just switch
that over to Abby to you as well
again that's just cleanup oops I didn't
mean to that meant to hit the N key
okay can I jump to the next one
2012 so yeah this is all nonsense
because this buffer is not used anymore
so we'll just get rid of that and so
we're really just down to this if you
look at what happens here we've got the
main window callback and when the window
position changes what you can see here
is we've got a like a switch for you
know fullscreen sort of stuff I think is
what's going on here I it looks like
I shall be honest I don't really know
what that's saying if the window
position is changing and the shift key
is down oh you know what this is
probably aspect ratio constrain so are
you allowed to resize our window right
now so we haven't played with this code
in a while let me just take a look at
what's going on there
oops did I delete some important code
there I probably did so my guess is
sorry I probably deleted since this is
the quickest way for me to show you I
accidentally deleted the thing that
calls the renderer to in it so in here
you can guess I could just search for it
this way I suspect we need to call this
still no actually no it's not in there
so I'm not sure why we well I'm not sure
why that was complaining because that
looks fine actually
right it doesn't actually call the
renderer there so what was the problem
why is this complaining show me why you
were complaining sir
the deputy account is set to zero which
means that nobody actually ever inside
the swap buffers here nobody actually
ever called the win32 in it open jail
call properly it looks like
so we're calling the in it here so it
seems like it should be fine
so I'm not really sure what's going on
there oh I see why it's because we only
have a partial rebuild here okay that
does make some sense actually so I'm
gonna hit this with an if zero
temporarily just to make sure we didn't
introduce another bug but I think that
was just because we had a partial
rebuild so these two things didn't agree
that our two pieces of code did not
agree but now they should be fine
yeah and they are alright um so what I
wanted to check was are we actually
allowed to resize this window this
window doesn't seem to be resizable I
don't know why we would have said that
actually that seems weird so if I go
down to where we do create window so
we're creating an overlapped window I'm
not sure why we don't have our size
border
uh so that's really weird isn't it so
here we just say here we say create
window XA we're passing WS overlapped
window we should just get a size border
right we're not actually calling this
because it's only in not handmade
internal so we don't go fullscreen so
what's the problem
how did we not how did we end up not
getting a size border a thick frame am I
miss remembering what happens with WS
overlapped window don't ask me why that
there you see W a thick frame right
there the window is an overlap window
same as the WS tiled window style
overlapped caption system nu thick frame
minimize box maximize box we've got
everything else but we can't size our
window ah so maybe the problem is just
we're not calling set cursor properly
but even so you can see we don't you can
see that there isn't actually room for
the window like like you know oh wow
okay so this is just windows 10 being
dumb so you don't actually see it
anymore
alright so it's there and we can resize
our window the only difference is that
they don't draw it anymore
we must not be calling set cursor
properly because you can see do you see
how we're not getting the size area
there we're not getting it changing to
the size cursor so it is thick frame
it's just not drawn
because you know actually showing the
user that they could drag something
would be a horrible user interface to
say them um so what we want to do here
is look at our get cursor call or sorry
set cursor call and we want to see
what's going on in there hmm so here you
can see what's going on this set cursor
call is well so we can see what the
problem is here we're calling I DC arrow
but I D Sierra wouldn't actually work
properly I feel like we should be doing
result deal separator but we've
commented that out we must have had a
reason to do so I'm not sure what that
reason would have necessarily been but
you can see if I do that you get the the
proper thing I assume the reason we did
that was because of the loading cursor
or something I'm not sure but I would
rather leave it like that so that we can
properly have have that work right I'm
also interested to know keep a global
show cursor so that just yeah that just
has to do with whether or not we're
running in release mode or not so we'll
have to look at that a bit later okay so
that's just gonna be better for us I
think so I think we want to leave that
set cursor there and you can see we get
this loading cursor I don't know why the
loading cursor continues doing that for
a while because we have loaded so I'm
not sure what the problem is I also
don't love like is this our fault I
don't know whose fault this is but like
up there up above the top it's pretty
weird how they decided to make this
thing work like is that how all windows
work or is that just us so basically
they just broke their window manager
their window man has just broken
I mean look so here is where I have to
put the cursor it's my cursors actually
in the title bar so it's where you would
normally drag and instead now it's it's
the up and down and so that means that
you basically don't get a play
to do that up here you have to move down
to the side lovely good job Microsoft
all right so if you just nowadays they
don't actually ship improved version of
Windows they just ship like things that
are worse than the one that came before
them it's like a constant downward
spiral it's like what do they call it c
fi t--
it's this right it's like you know
they're just intentionally driving the
plane that there was no actual failure
it's just the pilot chose to drive it
into a mountain or the ground right
that's this is basically like you know
this is Microsoft this is
right so like you know this is what
we're talking about here that's how they
make their decisions nowadays so let's
go ahead and and finish what we were
doing here so getting rid of that buffer
what we had implemented just here I
think as a request if somebody was if we
want this to maintain the aspect ratio
we could hold down the shift key and so
if we want that to still work then the
problem is that we had in here some code
for that it can't maintain the aspect
ratio if it doesn't know what the aspect
ratio actually is right
so the render width and height here have
to be set to something because if
they're not then you can't actually
figure out what the aspect ratio results
should be in this case so what we want
to do there is say you know well alright
let me do this too so we kind of need
somebody to do this now in a sanely
functioning system I'd just be able to
pass that in but of course Microsoft
uses callbacks so I can't pass it in and
so what I have to do is set a global
variable so that I can pick up this or I
could set it on the window or something
absurd like that but what I need to do
here is just say ok this is going to be
a global render with a little render
height or something like that get to it
this way right and then we can continue
as necessary so in order to get that
straightened out what we need to do is
have a pure be a thing where we're like
a little render Jim and then when I set
the render dimension down below what I
can do is is set the global one as well
so I can say global render Jamie let's
render dim and off we go I you know
that's an
the end of that so now in theory we can
re-enable that code path that involves
the aspect of where resize so here's the
non aspect array resize right but then
if I hold down the shift key what you
can see is we get an aspect of where
resize so now when I scale it always
perfectly fits the back buffer to the
window right and so that just enabled re
enables that code path and that's that's
that ok so that's all good that was
cleanup that we should have done for
sure and so now that's done and that's
good
looking at this win32 window dimension
thing I'm wondering if that can go away
and just be replaced by v2 you because
you can see it doesn't really make a lot
of sense that that's there like we could
just do this right and I think we would
be fine because it's basically the exact
same thing and so I could in theory cast
this to you 32 I possibly should
threshold it but since the right and
left should never switch in that way I
think this is probably fine famous last
words we could check for zero if we
really got worried later but I'm pretty
sure those should never be negative
right so anyway there's a v2 you there
and then I can just get rid of this and
not have this as a thing anymore because
it's dumb so that's good again just
getting rid of code that we don't need
you always want to simplify if you can
we now no longer need win32 off-screen
buffers so I think I can delete that and
we shouldn't have too much of an issue
there either so again just kind of you
know simplifying the code down it's
always good to do some deletions once
you have stuff that you know has
outlived its usefulness so that's all
good let's go back to the to do we were
trying to do there so what we want to do
in here is to in you know virtual free
virtual a lock land again want to go
find the places that we were calling
that so that we can simplify it for
folks on Linux and so now we should have
only one of those so you could see
there's literally only one call to
virtual a lock and only one called a
virtual free I think well this one's not
if that's that's a woman
never freed so it's really only this one
here so inside win32 free memory block
the question is what is the this what
would this parameter be if we had to
pass what's the size does the block know
how big it is and that's what we need to
know here so let's take a look if it
does if it does we're done if it doesn't
we are not done here's the memory block
and the platform memory block so let's
look at the platform memory block yeah
so it looks good it's got the size in
there feels pretty good right so I think
we have successfully put them there it
so note we're reporting to other
platforms that need the size to unmapped
pages you can get it from block block
dot size so I think that's all good
anything needed it other things that can
be stored in here right as well meaning
you would have Linux memory block which
could have other things as well so I
think that's all good so I think we can
safely retire this and see what happens
right so I think that's all good and
that takes care of that one which is
good because I'd like to keep it so that
people who are porting don't have to
worry too much about it so I'd like to
maybe do see if we could get through
these last two here because then we're
down to almost nothing this one is a one
that we want to it's not really a bug so
much as it's like a feature we need to
then go actually implement so this is an
obscure full-screen bug but we may be
able to well I don't know if we can
reroute it if it can we might be able to
fix it
so we might as well just following what
is said here open the game hold the
Windows key and press the left or right
arrow to place the window on half the
monitor and so just so you know what's
going on let me see here so right it's
this feature I don't know if you've ever
looked at this you can use the arrow
keys if that makes sense
ooh that's okay check that out that's
another bug we have so minimize looks
like it breaks here the frame buffer
breaks somehow probably because the
sides gets messed up yeah
so we gonna we're gonna have to do that
too so I'm gonna create another one here
so I would also add that to the list
here so in terms of things that break
when you're trying to do window standard
operations that's another one there and
maybe that was that as bad because
that's an assertion so technically it
would go away and you would just not
draw and presumably it would be fine
when it came back but I'd rather not hit
the assertion at all I'd rather like no
notice that we have a zero by zero case
happening and and fix it so let's start
by reproving the bug that we're talking
about though because we want to do both
of these now so open the game press the
opposite air force up to okay so the the
bug is you force the window use the
windows subsystem to force it over to
the other side there right then go
fullscreen so that's that right then use
the windows key to force it to the other
side of the screen so that okay so that
doesn't do anything anymore so maybe if
I do this so I can't seem to repro this
on anything else so I think this might
be a Windows 7 only thing because they
said on Windows 7
so we can't reproduce this bug so we
wouldn't really know if we'd fixed it
but we might be able to hypothesize what
we would do to fix it so if you think
about what would you know what's
probably causing that bug is Windows is
forcing our window to change its size
which means you know we're getting a
window pose changing call or a WM size
call so like somewhere in here right
where we would we would get notified of
this and you know we would get this call
and so we may want to do something where
if windows forces to us to change our
size to something else just because it
does we and we go out of full screen we
should try to reset our flags probably
or something right
[Music]
so my question mostly is just what's the
best way to do that and this is why I
really wish we could repro it because I
don't really know exactly what stream of
Windows messages would come in if window
suppose changes come in that might be
the one for it you know so let's let's
go in here to toggle fullscreen and so
what you can see here is this set window
long where we do like overlapped window
versus not so there's another thing that
we could do there which is like for
example in here when you hit that we
could remove our framing as well
potentially so we could think of it more
as like the set window long stuff should
actually it be in this part of the code
and it's like if the window position is
going to change based on if the window
position is going to change if we would
have ended up such that we will exactly
in Eclipse the screen change our stuff
to not have enough to know otherwise
don't so again not really sure what to
do about that but let's just I pathi
size what we would do maybe right
if becoming fullscreen get rid of it
else don't you know what I mean I don't
really know if you can set window long
in here Raymond helped me Raymond tell
me the internals of Windows
all right Google why did you show me
that if it doesn't have the thing I
asked for in it
so I'm not sure whether you can call
this like I'm doing we can try it and
see
so in here if I do set window long on
that I'm just gonna see if this works
it probably won't but you know we'll try
so in terms of becoming fullscreen what
we need to know is would we
exactly Eclipse the screen or not right
and you can see on here where we do the
get monitor info stuff you know inside
this call I could ask what that monitor
size was and see so after we do we could
say okay get me the monitor info and I'm
not gonna see whether I'm about to set
myself to exactly encompass the thing or
not so we would say excuse me
get me the monitor info look to see
whether or not I'm lined up exactly with
that monitor info so here's where all
that rect would be and I this new pose
here is a window put pause window pop
pose Widow pause have you run pronounced
that the window pause structure is gonna
have like the stuff in it that I need to
know so the width and height and the X&amp;Y
so what I can do is say look are we
exactly going to to encompass this thing
so becoming fullscreen equals false if
we get the monitor info and we look and
we see okay becoming fullscreen equals
this giant test to say does this equal
the right thing and this here's the
width and height
okay so I'm just saying look let's
compute all this nonsense here find out
what the width and height are and
instead of becoming fullscreen to line
up at that so the new pause it has the
what is it x and y X Y and then it's got
the CX CY and so that would just say
look if we look like we're gonna take up
the whole screen then do this otherwise
don't do it right so we'll try that
we'll see if that gets us anywhere maybe
it will maybe well okay so what's our
problem sign downside mismatch okay
term is not a value to function
you're right I agree with you because I
wasn't trying to call function and then
the style here has to we have to
actually get our window style like we
were doing let me take a look here
toggle full-screen all right so in terms
of calling set window long we don't
really need to do it if the style isn't
going to change so really what we need
to do is say if the you know we'd have
like here full screen style and windowed
style and you know it's those two and so
you could say is if we're becoming
fullscreen we could say like you know
style equals full screen style or it
should be more like new style right so
I'm really just turning this if into a
thing where we specify it more like this
and then I can just say alright if the
style changed so now I can see you know
what happened if the style changed then
call it otherwise don't bother because I
don't want to spam a bunch of like set
window lungs and make the operating
system think something's happening when
when we're really not changing it so now
when we like resize this window
presumably it should just work fine
right and nothing should actually change
in here it should all be good but if I
do that in theory well and it didn't
work I was gonna say in theory if we
compass the whole screen it should do it
although now I think about it that
actually doesn't
so it'd only be if we actually tried to
go fullscreen you can see it doesn't
seem to have worked right
there's fullscreen and it doesn't seem
to have actually done that done that set
window long so yeah not one of my not
one of my finer not one of my finest
hours there so let's take a look at what
what did I screw up I'm gonna convert to
debug mode here and I'm going to go over
to that actual code not here and I'm
gonna go ahead and inside that that size
changing I'm gonna just see what's going
out that window
pause changing I'm gonna see what
happens like do we ever call this at all
right so we do call it and we look to
see like what the old style was with the
new stella's so becoming fullscreen it
did correctly note that it is becoming
fullscreen there's the old style there's
the new style so the fullscreen style is
the old style without overlapped window
included right so we do try to do it
[Music]
right we do try to set the the new style
I'm guessing you just can't call it in
there
oops it's seven along
so that returned value will be zero in
the case where this fails let's see if
it is I'm gonna go ahead and go to
disassembly here so after we call it
it'll probably put the return in EAX so
we can even though we don't look at the
return I should be able to just look at
it here right so it should be in this
register so it looks fine
so I'm not sure why that didn't work oh
I see so it does set it but then it sets
it back so it looks like my calling set
window long kind of has the nasty effect
of undoing what I did I mean that makes
sense
so what we might want to do here is say
okay yeah this is this is kind of nasty
so in toggle full-screen what we may
have to do is call that we may have to
call that set window style anyway we may
have to change it first so I think we
may have to do that because I think
that's just yeah there's really nothing
we can do about that
all right so in theory we should be able
to get this to work without causing it
to do that code path but it didn't look
like it did there so I'm not sure why
so in here like we should be able to get
it without it should not call the pose
changing meaning it shouldn't actually
call this because the new style should
equal the old style in theory so this
should only happen when we detect that
we've changed sizes to something that
requires this
but again this is in the vagaries of
windows which is always nasty so so that
should set it off and then unfortunately
this looks like it's setting it back
right because there's the full screen
so why is it causing that to get called
with a wind 'red style
not really sure
I suppose we could use wind spy to see
what we're actually getting past so if I
open up wind spy here and I run this
application although let me switch it
back to what it well let me look at it
without that first so if I go to win spy
and say hey man I want to know what's
going on with this window please are you
serious right now
so if I view the messages here
how can I tell it to show me some
messages
show me the messages
this is supposed to show me all the
messages how are you not showing me the
messages
oh well that's the problem right there
where is our spy plus plus our our spy
64 you can see if that was the x86
version that's not gonna do us any good
we need the the 64-bit version which
apparently why wouldn't this launch the
64-bit version by default is there
something like how is that not a thing
hopefully we actually have it let's see
here
spy plus plus x64
[Music]
here we go
so this is what we actually want so
let's just change that because let's
like why didn't they just put the other
one here swell it seems like such a lame
excuse
I just want to see this
so is it actually in this location or
not I don't really know let's find out
yes it is so I think that should fix it
like now we should have the ability to
get the 64-bit version which why you
wouldn't you know that it's a 64-bit
executable so why you wouldn't launch
the 64-bit version of spy don't want to
know again we'll just bring this back up
here but let's go ahead and actually see
if it can capture our messages now right
here's our window here's my plus plus
here's our handmade hero window messages
ah there we go so now we finally got our
messages so now what I want to know is
like what happens during this change
like if I hit alt enter what happens so
if we look in there we can see looks
like we've got window pause changed gets
sent twice right you can see it I don't
want to move the mouse because then
we'll lose what we're doing but if you
look at the top the very top
it sends like you know window pause
change with LP WP that's the window
pause there and then it sends so what
does s are P SR SR PP SR what are those
tags oh that's the return value I see
so we didn't get it twice we only got it
once let's go ahead in here we don't
care about mouse moves so I'm gonna
filter those out so that we don't have
this problem messages oops
so let me go ahead and get rid of like
Mouse
we'll get rid of em see eh I hit test so
cuz we don't want any of that either
well I'll just do it this way
it's remarkable amount of stuff that
gets set even when you just do this all
right so if we clear the log and I click
on the window we get all of this crap so
just clicking into the window sends
window pause changing somehow don't know
how
am I wrong about that let's get this
back to this size and see it looks like
it mm I always yeah I mean you can see
window pause changing and window pause
changed
I suppose window pause changed maybe the
only one we actually need there it's
hard to say but that gets sent even just
on a click when we go into full screen
which I can do again by running let's go
ahead and clear that log does this still
work or did it have to do I have to
rehung for the window probably have to
re hunt for the window yeah alright oh
my god are you kidding me it resets the
logging options every time why would it
do that
okay
uh so let's go ahead here and see what
we could maybe do to fix this right this
seems to get called a lot and it seems
like maybe we can't really rely on that
now why it wouldn't always be reasonable
though to call this based on whether
we're becoming fullscreen or not I don't
really know if we actually change this
to changed I wonder if that would be
something that would make sense not to
do here so meaning we wouldn't actually
set it during this this just allows it
to do what its gonna do so meaning this
will just happen but then after the
change is done if we want to remove
those things you know does that do
anything for us and the problem is I
don't really know that it would I don't
really know that that would help but
basically we could just say in window
plus changed if you're not fullscreen
anymore then we would switch it out
right but let's see so WM actually let's
leave that up
fantastic so here's that message the L /
am looks like it's still the same so in
theory we should just be able to
continue doing this and right here we
can say look give us that thing we
probably want in here to still call the
default window caucus we don't actually
know what it might want to do in that
case right so let's go ahead and try
this out I don't think this is gonna
help but you know with Windows it's
always just experimentation see if
anything works right so that's better
we know that's a bug still
so that all looks pretty good so I guess
let's leave it at that
one thing I would want to test is does
this create a problem in toggle
full-screen suppose I get rid of that
now cuz I assuming I'm assuming I can't
do that I'm assuming that I that I need
is to clear that in order to get a
proper full screen you know but I don't
actually know so I'm just curious if it
would magically work right so it looks
like that actually magically works now
oops didn't even do that
so maybe we can just do that and see
again don't really know if how how
reasonable that is
so that's just a way to say look if you
end up with a window hopefully this will
always just set the flags based on
whether we're actually fullscreen or not
so that it doesn't matter whether window
sets us full screen or windowed or we
set ourselves full screen or windowed
we'll always put our Chrome on or take
it off depending on the actual state of
the window that's the hope I think we
still need a lot of testing other people
can run it now and see what happens
because we really don't know across a
wide setting of when of course a wide
set of Windows machines we don't really
okay Wow everything's dead now I can't
hit alt tab either that was freaky
wind spy must have worked us pretty hard
there I couldn't hit alt tab even that's
my stuff so yeah I think that should be
fine let me make sure that comment got
saved
yeah so I think that's all good and I'll
just I'll read that bug is finished and
then asked if they can possibly reopen
it right
all right so the only other thing I need
to do now is take a look at this part
here which is the the zero zero width
and height problem and and so looking at
how that's working I'm not really sure I
know why we're getting that so when we
have a settings change I'm not sure I'm
assuming that that's happening in here
and the game render settings are what's
triggering that I'm trying to figure out
why they would get set to zero in the
first place
[Music]
so
so I don't think we're ever changing
that value though right
like why why is that value ever getting
reported even in the first place it must
be here so we're passing this thing down
where we do render or begin frame I
think we just screwed this up because
we're not really supposed to be looking
at this stuff anyway and that would also
explain where we were getting those
weird positioning problems so like if
you look at what's going on here what
who is yeah in that begin frame call
that looks busted so I'm gonna look in
here what are we doing with window width
and window height like why are those
even being used anywhere because we
don't draw in there right like that
doesn't actually get placed in there
anywhere and the draw region is really
what we're talking about here
so this stuff is just kind of yet we
gotta pay more attention to this so who
is using that window width and window
height and why does that make sense
that's what I really need to know more
about now so I'm gonna go into the
platform stuff or actually guess that's
in the renderer I want to know what's
going on there cuz that that smells
rotten to me so this window with window
height soap so who's where is that
getting used right now I need to see
who's using that and why so we're using
it in there yeah so this is wrong and
this is why our UI was screwed up no one
should be using that so that should
really be called something else let's
let's make this clear
so drawer region is actually the thing
that we want to use and anyone who was
using OS window with an OS window height
before that's just bad right so this is
fine you know that's not a problem but
here for example I don't know if this is
right let me look
is that actually getting used and what
was it getting used for all right so
that's fine and this is not fine so this
should be like you know there should be
like a dim here where we say that
don't know if we have a get dim on that
probably not so the actual thing that's
that's getting passed in there is like
one of those rectangles right it's this
so we want something that would give us
the dimensions of that rectangle but as
you can see that's really only for
rectangle rectangle Center float at the
moment so we want a thing that's like
gonna do this probably where we can get
the dim out of it but you know what we
could do you could also just up convert
it like this
something like this oh sorry that
actually gets the dimensions I'd
actually want to give it the full thing
here so that way we could up convert
those and say look I want the
floating-point version of this rectangle
please and that seems good
then you here where we've got like the
width and height and stuff right this is
just a this rectangle this record in
really that just comes you know we can
just get the din of well we already have
its region to him so that should all
just work fine and then here we just
need like region gym with and region
doing with their I think that's all good
right it's not let's fix that
so I think that's probably gonna fix
that problem we were having with with
the alignment code too so in here I
don't know if you remember when we went
to like the editor it was like weirdly
not aligned to the screen and now it
should always be right and it is so
that's a good thing right
so that fixes that problem we were
having which is good because I don't
want to have that problem that's perfect
now everything's fine
so that fixes that problem but now we
still have to go deal with the original
problem which is that we were getting
bad behavior in there for when these
things happen to degenerate to zero and
I want to find out why that's happening
because I don't understand why we would
be getting that I didn't think anyone
was using the window with their height
so why when you minimize you get that
degeneration I don't understand so I'm
gonna switch to debug mode real quick
and see if I can't get a bead on that
mm-hmm let's take a look we'll run this
and all I should have to do is minimize
it and that causes the problem right so
we have a create frame buffer call the
width and height are zero so let's find
out who is doing that and why the render
with render height here are set to the
settings width and height so that's
saying that someone's setting our width
and height in the settings who is doing
that right I have no idea who's doing
that or why I just I do not know why
that's happening
okay so this so I guess I see what's
going on here so this is a bit of a mind
bender
so it looks like we actually don't do
what I thought we did which is to render
to a separate target resolution and then
change it looks like we actually render
directly to the resolution that's being
requested
so that's not really what we want
in fact the draw region isn't really
what we want either we want a separate
thing for the render width and height
like it's it should not be set to those
things that is incorrect does that make
sense
so like the draw region that's also
wrong right like like I actually didn't
do when I what I should have done there
if you look at the UI stuff in here it
should not get that either this is the
OS draw region so no one should be using
that draw region the region dim should
actually just come from the commands
width and the commands height the render
version of those right that should
actually be stated explicitly so in here
like really this should be OS draw
region
and we really want this and that should
be something that we that should be
something that we set manually that we
can set to other things because we may
want to render and downsample we may
want to render an up sample and we
supported all of that correctly but then
we don't do it for some reason and I
don't know why that may just been an
oversight or maybe we had switched it
that way temporarily and then just
forgot we should switch it back so I
feel like we want to do this and this
like so I so that seems like a much more
sane way to go so in here I would like I
don't know if I can do this but that is
that is what I actually wanted all right
let's deal with the fallout from that
so in here
I want one of these this way I can just
convert those anytime I want so I want
to get one of these back for my render
dimensions and just use that that should
always be the case oops I had an extra
period in there in here I want to set
the OS dim directly to those window
width and height that's what I would
expect there too
oh and if we do have a render within a
render height it's in the settings okay
so we did actually have that it's right
here
so that's what we actually wanted we
wanted that render setting there and so
we want everyone to drive off of that
now and we don't want this to be set
here right that is not what should
happen that is bad and should not occur
like wrong false incorrect we have to
set that somewhere else
because that doesn't change based on the
window height we could change basically
not but we don't want to be set to we
don't want it to be set directly so in
here now we should have this which will
give us both of those things in here
this is the OS draw region and should
only be used when you know that your
that's what you're actually trying to do
oops this is fine and that's all fine so
that looks good in in here where we get
the window gym stuff that's fine too in
here this is going to be the rendered
gym version so this was like I said this
is basically setup correctly it just we
were using it incorrectly and so I just
want to clean that up
I'm not sure what this part is for here
okay let's just set this up nicely there
we go
and this can just do it that let's just
pipe that through all right now one of
the things I'm not sure about is what
are we doing with the projection in the
math like where is the math library
pulling that from so in renderer when we
do set camera transform it does the
perspective projection I guess it just
assumes like how does that take into
account the region of the screen that
it's looking at I guess it doesn't it
doesn't look like it really does there
it is okay so this is using the correct
value as well we already modified that
so everything now should be fine except
for the fact that we never actually set
the render dimension right like we use
it everywhere we correctly separated it
from the window dimension and so the
only thing that we have to do now is
actually set it somewhere right because
right now we're not actually ever
setting that so in the place where we
set the render settings we need to
actually have that occur so setting
those initial values it's like we don't
really do here unfortunately so here's
where we do our game commands you can
see us doing this here where we do a
begin frame so when we get that out I
guess you know when you look at what
we're actually doing here I guess that
can just be set directly so I think this
here I think we should be able to just
set that and be good to go oh and I
should probably switch to go to mode so
now we will continue rendering to our
back buffer at the appropriate size even
as we you know shrink down right and so
we may want to like change exactly how
we're picking that because we may want
to switch to smaller buffer sizes as we
go but again that's something we would
choose to do and that way when we
minimize we can still be running
properly and so on and so that's just
how we want to do that now we may in the
future again want to change that around
so that we can use smaller sizes for
smaller screens or whatever but that's a
separate issue that will will you know
sort of play with later on trying to
think of this anything else I want to do
here so now we should be able to render
at a different resolution so if I wanted
to I could render hoops
I could render very small so for example
like really really tiny screen and then
blow it up and that should work now so
you can see like super fuzzy game right
hard to use the interface there uh and
we may want to fix that part too there's
things we could do for that as well so
if we render it a really low resolution
just to see what happens you can see
there's no issue there so I think that's
all good and yeah I think that's all
good so one thing I would say here is
you know maybe we take global render Jim
and Robo rendered them goes away maybe
what we say is a global enforced aspect
ratio and that's just always sixteen by
nine so then we know that when we
rescale the window if we force the
aspect ratio it'll force sixteen by nine
like that and then this won't do this
and we won't have rendered em because it
was only getting used here anyway so
instead we'll just move this down
because this is something we can do
later that's something we can do right
here oops
so then Global render dim is never a
thing it's just render dim is the only
thing that we actually do here and so
what that means is now when we're
running we can't always choose to change
those values if we wanted to write at
any time and so that's better right we
only have them in one place
and so the anime if we want to do some
other resolution like say you know this
one so that this would be fine like this
would probably be a reasonable
resolution to render to if you have a
slower GPU you know that looks totally
fine right that's totally playable and
so now we're getting a 19 by 1080
display but we're actually rendering
much lower than that just to for speed
right um so we can do that and that's
just better and we know that that can
change at any time - so that's good -
all right so I think that's all done and
so the only thing left I've got on here
that's a thing a small thing to look at
is the fog being broken I think we fixed
that already right pretty sure I was the
pre-multiply problem and I fixed it so
I'm pretty sure that if you fog you
don't get alpha bugs now of course I
don't remember actually seeing any fog
so that seems bad
although I guess the reason for that is
because there's nothing you can't the
fog always gets set based on the hero's
location so I don't know maybe that's
not
so there's the fog again it set the min
setting though is kind of in a place
where you know it's set to be the bottom
of the expected floor there which is
gonna be nineteen point four which is
below the hero so I don't really know
how to I think that's that's the closest
the fog can get it's like there I need a
way to like stop the camera but I think
we fixed it already I guess it's what
I'm saying I think the Alpha is fixed I
think it's actually correct
I just don't have much a way to test
that
we need something hopping around down
there um what time do we have one if I
count like one minute crap crap crap
crap a Tipu so what I would have to do
here is like I don't know can we add a
snake real quick or something so let's
suppose that I grab one of these things
for adding an orphan right and I add a
hopper snake add snake so if I wanted
that to be in here actually I guess I
can just make this thing so add snake
segment let's grab that make it a real
entity we can put in the world now at
snake and so here I wouldn't necessarily
know which segment index it was supposed
to be so I probably can't not sure
exactly what to do about that but I
guess I'll just for now make it like
that looking at what we're doing here I
think you know just looking at the add
orphan stuff we're gonna do the same
thing here that we would do all of this
stuff would stay the same adding these
pieces in probably needs to get modified
a little bit it wouldn't have a shadow
anymore that gets handled by the
lighting I don't know that we would put
a light on there but okay so maybe
there's a light on there who knows then
we've got the body head stuff and this
stuff is probably gonna have to be
changed to something that has tagging on
it at least in some way and we probably
need some connect piece to world stuff
right we would probably need to do
something like this
so we just connect it to the world and
give it its its go seems like it would
be fine we're not only doing hip points
at the moment so that you know might
work for adding a snake maybe I'm not
sure what the brain ID thing was for
there I guess the brain ID gets passed
in so this stuff is gonna have to be for
creating more complex things which we
don't have the ability to do at the
moment inside the generator we'd have to
add sort of that way of making that work
place entity it's not necessary right
just do this and then I think we can we
can't just add those yeah but so if I
want to add one of those to the to the
world now like if I want to have any
time there's a dungeon tile so because
we had like you know in the world
gencode we had like this notion of like
dungeon tiles in here which we don't
really do anything with at the moment so
you know there's create dungeon right
this thing so if every time we create
one of these rooms you can sort of see
in here we're doing like who knows what
we're doing here we're just doing like
create dungeon got floor entrance and
previous room and whatever else right if
when we create these things we just put
stuff in them so like all the chain
rooms for example we just added one of
those to it so we just said like place
snake
we said inside this room like that I
think that would work so inside the
orphan stuff we would just do the same
thing so we just say you know add in the
add a tag I guess I don't know what our
tags might want to be
seems reasonable so it's like a skeleton
ish thing I don't know if we actually
imported those yet and then we would
just place it in the room yeah so yeah
not sure what we want to do there can't
can't really say I think that would give
us one of those little snake guys
although we'd have to fear how we want
to add the other parts to it but
I think all of this stuff wants to go up
there yeah so let's see
well I'm jumping the gun here a little
bit but I don't know how to put any I
just want to look and see if the fog is
fixed and I'm not sure how else we would
do that you know what I mean
[Music]
looks like this is having a problem
figuring out where to put the entity
sir the
spirits of the ending there I'm not sure
why we'd have trouble placing that
entity let's go ahead and debug this I
have a little extra time I don't mind if
I go a little over today it's not a big
deal when we're the other what time is
it
so I 2 o'clock so I'm fine what what is
it complaining about so we added an
entity group that doesn't have anything
in it so why did we do that did I mess
something up with that placement let me
just double-check
add the entity we place the entity in
the room like so so that should just
work right
let's do an assert just in case hmm so
somehow when are we going here we're
getting an entity group that doesn't
have any entities in it and I don't know
how that's possible
because the only time we ever add an
entity group there should be an entity
in it right so I'm kind of at a loss
there
you can see that the only time we
actually call it is when we call place
entity and immediately after that we put
an entity into that group so it's like
it's getting erased somehow like it was
there and then it's not so how is that
happening
let's look at the call foreplay snake
which is right here is it possible that
the room is somehow not correct
sometimes or something weird like this
you know we're always generating a room
I don't think we're doing anything weird
with the room so here's a question let's
suppose we didn't do this
I'm assuming that that's the only
problem right like it's just we call
that and we get worked right so let's
suppose I added it to one of the other
rooms so in here we just say oh yeah
like you know the thing is in the heros
bedroom is it just the snake that causes
the problem like something about our
snake call sucks so the snake call seems
fine although I don't see it oh no there
it is there it's going
so it's hopping around out here there it
is
all right so if I want to put this body
piece up a little bit I might just do
that and I might also make its light a
little bit brighter I think this is this
the brightness or the size I don't
really know let's go ahead and change
that around all right um so yeah there's
one of those saucy gentlemen there
hopping around I may have made that
light too bright and I admit that so
maybe that's maybe that's inappropriate
so now I guess my I really just don't
understand why you know why I can't seem
to get that guy to be placed in a
dungeon so we have a bug in our world
Jen stuff which admittedly we kind of
threw a bunch of sort of like shoddily
constructive things I guess I would say
in there real quick cuz we wanted to do
some placement stuff and so I'm not
surprised but I also don't necessarily
know what the problem is
could this stuff be a lot better sure
but also just don't know why we're
getting that problem so if we look at
please snake and we you know we're able
to place the snake and then we go look
at why I can't move that around I just I
don't follow it because inside create
dungeon where we're making these rooms
it should be free for us after we create
one of those we should be able to just
say like okay you know and put one of
those into that room and then so we're
creating this chain and you know we're
connecting those up and that's fine
we're connecting things randomly along
the chain that seems fine too oh why are
we doing this
well that's almost certainly our problem
we can't we can't do this how is this
working
that seems super busted because you can
see us generating a bunch of stuff here
you can't do a temp memory on that right
because if you look at what's going on
there we've got memory and temp memory
it's ten memory being used where is that
being used
do we mess up yeah so that's using
that's like using that like a stack
which is really not what we would want
to do there that's the problem cuz we
need to use the temp memory to create
stuff I don't know what our idea was
here is the idea that the memory like
when do we use the memory okay so I just
this was this was my screw-up so we have
tenth memory and like so for example
here where we're adding these options
these should not be temporary memory
right I feel like these these are all
supposed to be real memory right so the
only time we would use the temporary is
for stacks and stuff that was that was
just me being dumb so when you add
entities and stuff those are getting
added to real memory not temp memory
so that was that was just dumb I should
make a note of that so we don't make
that mistake again the whole point of
having those two is so that we can flush
all the stuff away that we just used as
temporary and yeah I screwed that up
all right so in theory now there should
be people hopping around down there
right and there are I need a way to set
the fog in here
see what happens I want to make sure the
alpha works okay
so it looks like we still have some
weird stuff happening with the fog like
those things that are lit the fog is
wrong on those for sure right
so the Alfa's fine we fixed the Alfa but
the lighting now is not doing the
premultiplied alpha properly so in here
where do we compute our lighting because
that's not coming in properly so here we
go
bla bla bla fog amount you can see it
multiplying it here surface reflect RGB
multiplies by the lighting value so
that's this is the problem right here
this is not acceptable right so you look
in here we take the mod color that's got
the appropriate alpha coming in we then
have this lighting value that's getting
multiplied in here that is not that is
not going to affect the Alpha like it
should
although to be fair
right so that can reduce the Alpha calm
the Alpha addition of those values
I guess I'm honestly I actually am Not
sure that that's really correct
because we should be able to do the
lighting the lighting is just gonna
change the color which should be fine
because it has already been diminished I
guess if the Alpha value milk I don't I
can't I honestly don't know why that's
wrong that seems like that should be
right because the RGB here you know the
alpha value is just was already set this
RGB if it should have faded away to
nothing this should just I mean this
can't increase the value and I guess
maybe it can because when we do the
maybe the the problem is the L value can
be increased above one but that isn't I
really commensurate with what we were
seeing because we were seeing black
things that were blackened effectively
hmm
so I don't know what's going on there
right because you can see that this is
not a question of boosting above one
really because this this has no lighting
on it so it couldn't possibly be like
two or something right so why that is
not still properly set to zero in the
lighting region I don't understand
because multiplying by a value would
reduce the color that you're
contributing
but it should already have been set to
the Alpha should already have been set
to zero anyway and so should those
values that's yeah I don't see it I
don't see it
maybe someone else does but I don't
because you know when you once you get
into sunlight I guess you know part of
it is this should really be done I mean
well even that so that doesn't really
make sense because you can see that's
like there's no Alpha left there so why
I guess because the fog value here you
would have to check again so I guess
it's like we did the fog value now the
Alpha is effectively zero we lurked
between these two things okay hmm I can
see I can see I guess what's going on
there the Alpha value isn't really zero
at that point right it's like it's just
been fogged but it's not the alpha
that's not reducing the alpha the Alpha
is still full fog is not alpha it
doesn't fade out it's just coloring it
so I suppose that makes sense so what we
want to do is light before we fog I
think that's really the situation that
we're dealing with here so instead of
this I think we want this
so I think the Alpha is correct the
problem is the fog was actually not
correct so we need this to happen second
so mod color RGB needs to be set up here
right another way to say this would be
like surface reflect shouldn't have an a
right surface reflect should just be in
RGB so surface reflect does its thing
and then when we get back right and this
is just mod color RGB this is just
surface reflect here and we clamp it out
I think that's what we supposed to be
doing again a bit of a mind bender so
let's go ahead and check that out but we
were fogging we lit after we fogged but
fog is supposed to apply after lighting
like we're supposed to that the
attenuation from the fog happens after
the lighting so we were effectively
lighting our fogged values which of
course can make them darker so that is
what we should have expected I was just
thinking about it wrong so that's
another bug that isn't even the one we
wanted to fix so now we can see it
inside our lighting region here we can
see the lighting happening so let's play
with the fog now and we should be able
to get it to work properly now right
hopefully so that still looks as bad did
I still screw up that equation
Oh
whoops the compile didn't actually
compile because we were still running
oh it didn't like that it did not like
that all right so we got some swizzle
mask errors there let's take a look that
all seems okay
okay so that's not right does that only
exists on the mod color let's see if we
can get that better we should probably
put this in the hot loading set because
there's no reason not to hot load the
renderer
it's a dll now you should just load it
when it changes assignment of
incompatible types you are correct
alright now let's see if we've got our
fog solved
so it's better but we're we're now
getting the fogging is fogging 2-0 which
is not what I wanted I want a fog - the
fog color
so I think so I'm not I'm not really
sure
I'm not really sure why we be getting
that behavior
the fog color is a constant color we're
looping from the surface reflectance to
it
yeah and I don't I don't really know why
that's unhappy I mean you can see pretty
clearly that's fogging it now fogs
everything uniformly like it should but
it's fogging it to zero like it black
but it shouldn't be fogging it to a grey
cuz that's the fog color right so
something's weird there and I'm not sure
what it is because that lerp should be
forcing it towards the fog color by fog
amount no matter what happens and yet it
doesn't actually seem to do that so it
grabs the mod color which is the alpha
and fragment texture stuff right that
all comes through it looks to see if
it's going to proceed Smith is gonna
proceed it starts with that mod color
it's weird why don't why do we not have
a right here what's what's going on with
that why is this here shouldn't this be
at the end like why is that not there I
don't know that that has anything to do
with it but that should be over there
right because if we're simulating the
sRGB stuff it should be at the end not
at the beginning I don't actually know
for doing that
so it looks like we're presumably doing
that because allow oh no we're not so we
are going down that path so that could
also be a problem but we got a lot of
graphic stuff we can clean up yeah so
we're using this our own square because
remember we have different values for
those at the moment we have different
values for the squares and square roots
and stuff like that
all right I'm gonna take a look now
there we go so that was just a quick
case of us like we'd we'd like sort of
futzed with the shader too much and so
we were doing this square square root
for srgb
like our fake srgb we were doing that in
like the totally wrong places because
just got moved around so much so we were
actually just completely throwing off
our calculations from that so there now
looks like the Alpha is correct and the
other fog stuff is correct so if I set
the fog to a rather extreme thing there
so there's just a lot of fog we can just
double-check that it always works
properly looks fine to me there's like
our lighting of course still has like
the little tiny region of lighting so
we're never going to see that be
completely correct but
so that was causing all of our colors to
be off a little bit right all right
woof well I'm glad we fixed that and
with that I think we are down we are
going to start the new year with
essentially no to dues on the list this
one is just one that we want to
re-enable when we get back to audio so I
think we're down to no bugs outstanding
that we wanted to fix in the short term
there so that's really good all right
I'll go do a brief Q&amp;A
Oh
what happened here mm-hmm
[Music]
is twitch messed up
well alright I guess that may be the end
of it I don't know if I can looks like
twitch went down or something so I don't
know let me ask on the chat
I'd like to do a QA but no one can hear
me twitch is dead
so I don't know I don't know why I can't
stream to twitch maybe the route to
twitch got got forked or maybe my
internet cup work but I can see the chat
just fine
hmm so yeah I don't know if we can do a
QA probably not if that's the situation
I'll try really briefly to see if I can
reconnect it but I'm not hopeful OBS I
don't even know if we can change that
online it can't yeah they can't change
that
well I guess I'll stop streaming and
we'll just call it a day there cuz I
can't figure out any way like OBS can't
switch servers in the middle of
streaming it doesn't allow you to do
that as far as I can tell so there's
really not anything else I can see so oh
well that may be our last name I don't
know maybe I could I don't know if I can
do have time for another one tonight but
thank you for trying to join me for
another episode of handmade hero I'm not
sure why twitch went down but twitch
sometimes does go down so you'll just
have to catch up with these on the video
on demand because it was still recording
so we have the recording just fine just
wasn't broadcast live that's it for
today and probably until we come back
from winter break so until the new year
have fun programming everyone and I'll
see you online
oh and obviously for those of you who
are new to the series if you happen to
want to follow along theories at home
you could always pre-order the game on
hand a hero duck we're gonna come to the
source code so you can follow along and
do some programming on your winter break
on and if you want to do some
experiments so that's it take it easy
everybody and I'll catch it in the new
year