hey everyone its case from handmade here
here wanted to go over what the handmade
fund is for those of you who don't know
or even for those of you who already
decided to contribute but maybe don't
know some of the stuff that it does so
on handmade hero we produce a lot of
episodes that go over all kinds of low
level programming and that sort of stuff
and that's the part that I do but
actually ever since I started it there's
been a lot of people out there on the
internet who have made things related to
the series or that branched off or that
did things that were inspired by the
series some of which are kind of awesome
and we wanted to try and help them be
supported as they try to make them more
usable or more complete or continue
working on them and dedicating a
significant lot of time to them so
that's what the handmade fund does it
basically allows people who enjoy
handmade hero to contribute to a fund
that they know will pay out to various
people making stuff that goes along with
the series or that helps out other
people doing things related to the
series so two of the big things that we
do that we support on handmade fund our
handmade Network and the antidote guides
I just want to kind of show you what
those were handmade Network if you've
never seen it is actually the place that
hosts forums for handmade hero we don't
host any ourselves but they host forums
for handmade hero that lots of people
participate in it's a place where people
can ask questions about things that are
happening on the series and episodes
that they maybe need help following
along with or just general questions
related the series if they have and
there's tons of people out there who
frequent the forums who help answer
those questions and help people through
if they're trying to stuff like compile
something that isn't working or stuff
like that and it's a great resource for
that but it's actually so much more than
that
if you click on the main handmade hero
site so just go to handmade sorry if you
go to the made handmade Network site not
the hero portion of it then you actually
get a whole host of projects that are
kind of in the handmade theme right
things which are for example the STP
libraries that are very popular are now
hosted here people are making debugger
projects there's people making some
games that are handmade there's a series
making an entire like VLSI stack thing
and
handmade CPU and all this stuff there's
just great projects on here and of
course for coder the editor that we use
on handmade here was actually hosted on
here now forums for that so there's just
a ton of projects that go kind of
alongside of handmade hero that are by
completely different people doing
completely different things but that you
are probably interested in if you're
interested in handmade hero and handmade
network has gathered those all into one
place just a great resource and so one
of things we do on handmade fun is we
just pale all the hosting costs for that
and we'd like to be able to keep doing
that that's one of the really big
reasons why we want handmade fun to
continue to be successful so we can pay
for that because it's all volunteer
based they did an amazing job on the
site and we don't want them to have to
pay the cost of hosting as well so we
try to fund that and that's one of the
big things we do another big thing we do
with handmade fund is we fund this
amazing episode guide this was
originally a work of several people out
there and now it's maintained almost
entirely by one person and it's a
massive massive archive of time markers
that say basically everything that
happened on handmade heroes so one of
the things that's true about handmade
hero since it's supposed to capture all
of the programming for a game there's
just hundreds of hours a video there and
if you're looking for something specific
or just want to watch a particular thing
or have a question that you think might
already be answered it would be
impossible to find that if it weren't
for this episode guy it's amazing let me
just show you how crazy this thing is if
you want to see all the times that
OpenGL is discussed you can literally
just type OpenGL and not only does it
give you a huge listing of everything
that I've ever done that had something
to do with OpenGL or the file related to
OpenGL or a function that had open shell
in the name but you can click right on
one of these things and it will jump you
to that place in that episode I'll
discuss sort of some things that we can
do and some things that we can't do so
if you take a look at what happens in
our right and it's even got the time
here you can jump directly to it and you
can see all the rest of stuff that
happened now it's even crazier than that
it's got Webley
that reference for things that reference
out to other things you can actually
just get hyperlinks in here to them so
it's a great viewer for the series in
addition to just being a good way to
find things
it also has stuff like labels on them
where you know I've done things like if
I go on a rant or something it's got
that or if I say something related to a
specific thing it's got that in there
there's also the the credits list you
can see who contributed to this part of
the series there are other people
involved all sorts of stuff like that
right and even a quote thing which I
probably say a lot of stupid things that
handmade here well they're all captured
in here so that's another thing we fund
out of the handmade fund and we'd love
to continue doing that because it's
thanks to the handmade fund we can pay
to have it kept completely up to date
for the entire series and so every time
a new series airs it actually goes up on
there so that's what we do with handmade
fund right now and as handmade fund
expands if more people contribute to it
we will give more to those projects and
we'll also set aside money for other
projects as we can find them one of the
big things we'd like to do is get a new
debugger out there that we can use and
we'd also like to give some more money
to the image program that we use on on
handmade hero it's called Milton it's
this drawing program that I use every
episode that was actually made by
someone in response this series as well
and so there's just been so many great
products out there there is no lack of
people to fund with handmade funds so
we'd love to expand it and have more
money to give away every month to people
doing great things now you may also ask
in addition to those things that that
I've been showing that maybe you think
are worth funding another question would
be what do I get if I fund because it's
not nothing actually I put together a
little bonus pack as a thank you and
I'll just kind of go over some of that
stuff now basically what I did is I went
back over old code stuff that I had back
from when I was in junior high school or
in high school or stuff where and I used
to program
in das or in in the very early like win
3-1 days that sort of stuff that can
still be run on today's computers and I
kind of pulled that source code together
and I put together a little bonus pack
and it's something that will update over
time as we have more stuff to add to it
as well so if you take a look when you
subscribe to handmade fun no matter how
much you you pledge the support and and
it doesn't matter which level you get
the bonus pack so it's just included
with every contribution no matter large
or small and what we have in it is we've
got a concept art directory that we're
going to fill up with handmade hero of
concept art I put all of yankton's
original concept art in there we're
gonna put Anna's concept art in there
too as more comes online sort of stuff
so that and we'll probably put other
handmade hero related art things in here
eventually as we go as the serious kind
of goes more to completion but in
addition to those we've got all the
programs I was talking about and I just
kind of go over some of those right now
so starting really early on we've got
this das directory and I actually just
kind of rigged DOSBox to be able to play
these there's a number of different
amusing little programs in here that I
made for example this is my very first
triangle rasterizer you can see it doing
a test of a texture map Karoshi ated
triangle in das right you can see it
varying the colors it didn't have
differing it sees some really bad
banding there right for example and this
is just kind of like you know amusing
stuff that you had to do back then and
when I was first learning so you know
you can go in here and it's actually got
you know the original C files as they
were at the time that I wrote them and
you can go through and see what it
looked like some of it's actually very
similar to the way I program now some
things haven't changed
other things have changed quite a bit
and it's kind of interesting to see what
those look like so there's a bunch of
stuff like that other das things there's
like a little crazy like a flight
simulator thing that I had been working
on there that's that's really nuts it's
kind of when I was just first figuring
out how to do 3d stuff it's it's super
touchy I think probably because you know
I maybe it ran at a much slower frame
rate or maybe the mice were a lot less
sensitive back then I don't know but
it's kind of just a
what kind of back down memory lane when
I look at these things to sort of see
how you know things that nowadays I
would think are kind of laughably simple
to make or were like really hard for me
back then as I was just learning and
stuff and again all the source codes
included in that so you can kind of see
how those things were created as well
which is kind of interesting even for me
to look back at now I also included sort
of some other things here are some more
modern programs for example this is a
prototype 3d prototype that I did I
won't spoil the fun for you launching
that when it's kind of bizarre
it's basically well maybe I will spoil
the fun so if you go in here there's
it's basically a little 3d prototype of
sort of a inside of a cell with a bunch
of things in it and it was sort of a it
was a cool little prototype of a 3d user
interface back in the day my favorite
thing to do is right clicking in this
thing it causes the camera to follow
something so if you right-click on
somebody which is a little hard the
camera will actually kind of follow them
till it gets to them which it takes in a
while to do sometimes when they're kind
of squirrely and it's just kind of fun
to sort of follow them through the weird
sort of cell membrane thing and it also
had some fun code in it it's just like
it's not very much code but does all
sorts of stuff all this is software
rendered with line with like a brush and
ham line routine and it even has picking
and that all sort of stuff that's kind
of fun to see how it goes in there and
of course everyone was named after
people from the book hackers I think is
where that came from
anyway so it's got some of that stuff in
there also a little product I did
again a long time ago these are like
high school era stuff where I just made
like a little program for mapping
adventure games this one was kind of fun
I still really like the interface it
basically is a really quick interface
for making sort of adventure games we
adventure game maps that I thought was
kind of cool it's still like a really
fluid and fun way to do it I find it's
like a nice way to click through it I
really like the interface anyway so a
bunch of these things are here all of
the source is included for all of them
so you can pick through it and there's a
little thank-you file that actually
lists what they all are in case you
forget from my pretty poor description
there and you can kind of go through
those and again we add to those
occasionally when we find things that we
think would be interesting in there just
from the archivist we can put in there
maybe we'll add some more stuff later
but we update it you know once a year or
so with some new stuff as we as we find
it so anyway that's the entirety of
handmade fund we'd love it if you want
to contribute and we try very hard to
make sure that it's a lot easier than
say patreon or anything like that it's
pretty much just processing fees there
is no one who takes anything off the top
it's handled entirely by us so it's
basically just credit card processing
fees is the only part that comes out of
your donation and we tried pretty hard
to make the donation model be something
that would minimize those fees so for
example unlike on something like patreon
if you want to give a dollar a month to
a project that can be very difficult to
do because the credit card processing
fees on a dollar are quite high we've
put in things that allow you to do stuff
like pledge twelve dollars a year
instead of one dollar month to avoid
having those credit card processing fees
really add up or cause problems for you
so we tried to make that really easy -
if there's things we can do to make it
easier for you please let us know but we
hope that it's pretty straightforward
and again anyone who pledges gets the
bonus pack so that should be straight
for it it happens exactly the same way
as the handmade hero preorder works
where you get a send out will download
link and you can go download it anytime
you want as it's waiting ever it's
updated you can go download the new
stuff so hopefully you'll check that out
and thank you for taking the time to
take a look at handmade fund and look at
it we think that it's already done some
really great stuff and we're really
happy that it's something that people
have given - and that we've been able to
provide money to people who are doing
awesome stuff so we hope to continue
thanks everyone and I'll see you on the
next episode of handmade hero take it
easy