one welcome to handmade hero sure we
code a complete game live on stream we
are well we're doing whatever we really
want to do at this point everything is
kind of on the table and you know we're
at that point where you could kind of
just play around however you want to and
there are some things that I would like
to get to that are big items at some
point I don't really know that I super
care about them right now but like you
know at some point we did a bunch of
engine work and we've got so much stuff
in there that works now and like the
things that we don't have done that are
a little bit big like wanting to finish
up the lighting so it's more consistent
and stuff like that
can certainly wait I mean we have an
idea of what stuff looks like in the
world now so we can proceed with things
like having art done and stuff like that
and so I would say now is probably a
good time to again not be super
restrictive about what's going on
because a lot of the stuff like a couple
of rendering modifications that we want
to make to fix like glitches and stuff
like that shouldn't be too big of a deal
at this point so I feel like we want to
maybe just focus on on getting more
stuff in there at this point and you
know how how to how to adjust some of
the other stuff is it's probably not it
not as big a deal so what I want to do
today is focus on the camera you can see
right now like we kind of screwed with
it at the end of the stream last time we
have some issues that we're gonna have
to address like you notice when the
camera gets too close here it will clip
out because we were playing with where
the Alpha should happen when the camera
zooms in it'll clip out things like
right there you can see it's clipping
out everything but we wanted to do some
clipping right because we want to be
able to do stuff where in the you know
when we're hopping downstairs it'll clip
it out we also have the problem of
figuring out who's in the lighting
solution and not you can see right there
we get those bugs where we just right
now we're just kind of slapping an
arbitrary rectangle on there and saying
that's who's in the lighting solution
right and so those are two camera things
and so in addition to the fact that I'd
like to put the debug camera in a good
now I think today should just be camera
day and like try to get some of this
stuff cleaned up now lighting is always
a problem for us and so I don't know
like one thing that we could also
consider doing is adjust the lighting as
a stopgap measure before we try to
improve the lighting for more real time
you know quality and maybe move it to
the GPU one of the things that we could
do here is try to make it so that we are
using the lighting in some kind of a
adaptive way so for example when we get
to a scene like this and it's like oh
man there's all the stuff that has to
get lit we could do something where
things further from you don't really get
many rays cast or something like that
because we really just want to avoid
having this weird like artifact II sort
of stuff like this where you know so we
want everything in the lighting solution
so we don't see obvious bugs like this
but we may not need to really do great
lighting selves so far away so we could
also put in a stopgap measure a little
bit of something for adaptiveness there
which would just let us finish most of
the game without worrying about the
lighting too much and then you know at
some point when we wanted to spend
another concentrated period of time on
it go back and figure out how we're
gonna get the lighting really good right
and all that so I think today is a
camera day I'm gonna start off by adding
some parameters that we can tweak in
real time just to allow us to sort of
fine-tune like for example here right if
I want to fine-tune it so that we don't
you know we want to figure out where the
right ceiling level is and stuff like
that III want to get some fine-tuning in
there and I also want to add the debug
stuff so I think that's what we wanna do
today we have the ability here to have a
UI that we set up an area to put camera
UI in so I may want to just do that I
may want to just get some UI in here
that allows me to play with some camera
parameters and that would let us sort of
see what's up in that respect and
furthermore when we're doing when we're
doing our alpha fade one of those I was
thinking is the the whole point of the
Alpha fade is really not to be relative
to the camera it's to clip out stuff
like the
fluor so it's for that right there and
so when we do that really if you think
about what's happening there is we want
the alpha fade to be based more on on
the heights of things in Z and not
really on camera because since the
camera is tilted we don't really want
things that are closer to us in Y that
way to somehow not get faded and things
that are further away to be faded
because they will have deeper Z's
relative the camera and so I think what
we want to do there is is base some of
our values not on the actual camera
space but rather on world space and I
don't remember if the fog measurement is
the same measurement we use for alpha if
it is then we already have done this
because we already have the ability to
set the fog measurement axes and so you
know well you get the idea alright so
let's go ahead and do some some basic
stuff here the first thing I want to do
in world mode is start to take a look at
what we're doing in terms of bringing
things into the sim region I think I'm
gonna say just to avoid having
performance issues on our part for the
moment I'm also gonna say let's not
let's not simulate anything that's more
than one floor up or up or down so
there's only one floor away and then we
fog out I'm gonna just make that as a
thing just to keep things from getting
too crazy in the world so in order to do
that well you know what I shouldn't say
that quite yet we can we can maybe leave
it like that for a little while and just
deal with your artifacts so maybe I'll
skip that so I'm just gonna jump right
to putting in the camera stuff and we'll
try to work with with that as we go so
you can see here we've got our
parameters for the fog and for the Alpha
clip they're just something we hacked in
here right before we call the set camera
transform and we just set them new
whatever we wanted to set them to but
what we'd like to do here is actually
start making these measurements mean
something and we'd like to be able to
tune them as well and play around
and potentially so what I'd like to do
is have some notion of where these
things are generally specified and then
we can have those be you know can sort
of fiddled with in our in our debug UI
potentially and we can also try to have
these be set to something that makes
them a little bit more consistent the
Alpha clip being based on something that
doesn't have any relationship to the to
the world is not as good right and so
that's something that we probably want
to to change as well all right so the
first thing that I want to look at is in
terms of fog and alpha clip what I'd
like to do in addition to having the fog
be measured around a particular axis and
also I'd like the Alpha clip to be
measured the same way I'd like the fog
and Alpha clips to also be measured
relative to some point that I specify as
well right
in other words I would like there to be
some way of saying the the fog and alpha
clip are based off of like the current
floor that I'm on like the simulation
center it should be based more on that
then you know then some other you know
arbitrary thing that's that's based on
the camera location because our alpha
clip and fog are very they're very
semantic right they're very much about
they're very much about where we are
relative in the level and so the problem
that we're gonna have with the fogging
and the Alpha clip there is that we
would like some way of talking about
where the camera is in between floor
levels and we'd like to set the Alpha
clip to like match that somehow and I'm
not really sure exactly how we would do
that but I think what we could probably
do is we can probably just set the Alpha
clip such that the clipping happens
relative the clipping happens in world
space Z and we use the cameras position
versus the world
well I think we're gonna have to just
use I think we're gonna have to use the
simulation center and then the camera
position I really can't think of
anything else I mean let's draw it out
for a second and you can see the problem
that I'm having or will have right so if
you imagine what we've got is a series
of floors in our world right and then
occasionally we've got things like
stairwells down from the upper areas and
so what we want here is some way of
saying this area wants to fade out as
the camera moves and focuses on lower
levels so if my camera is here and it's
pointing down this way here is the
player standing here and the player
moves down here to this location the
camera is gonna interpolate downward and
eventually come to rest somewhere like
this now
the first thing you'll notice here is
like I saying going based on the camera
Z is erroneous because it's you know
doing stuff off of that will mean that
this which is a constant floor height
will have different alpha values as it
goes out which I don't really know that
we want if that makes sense so I think
we may want to rather specify it based
on the world space Z so that this whole
floor fades out at the same time now the
problem that we're going to have and
that I don't really know what the
solution to it is like I say we need
some good way of specifying this that's
consistent and it doesn't produce
artifacts is that the interpolation of
the camera from here to here might
happen in different circumstances that
are difficult to distinguish without
additional information for example if I
have a player standing in a small room
the camera might be here whereas if a
player standing in a big room the camera
might be here so looking at you know a
zoom between here and here
and saying well that should correspond
to some amount to fade out of this
probably because we're starting to come
down to go below it it's like well not
if I was just doing this so I think what
we're going to need is some idea of what
the actual fade-out level is that gets
interpolated along with the camera so
we're sort of saying look we interpolate
the camera position and we also
interpolate a value which is how you
know in Z we're measuring where we
should cut right so I think
yeah so OBS has crashed again because
you know crashy I have no idea why it's
crashing today it's crashed twice a day
whereas it almost never crashes on us so
something has happened that it doesn't
like but I have no idea what of course
where were we
what was the last thing I said
it's on a Linux machine it's not on
Windows it's on a Linux machine and it's
a dedicated machine it's not even
running the stream I mean it's it's
streaming the video but it's not running
this so all I was gonna say is I think
probably what we're gonna want to do is
we're going to want to interpolate a
parameter that tells us we're in here we
are so basically like we want to say
okay when we zoom we know what we're
focusing on we know where the camera is
and then we know that we want everything
that is inside this floor to be visible
so we can compute where along the camera
Z that is or in world Z how where that
is and we can use that as our clipping
boundaries and so I think that's all we
really want to do if that makes sense
so let me go ahead and and just sort of
sketch in what that would look like here
for us so first thing I want to do is I
want to just look at the shader and
remind us because we've written it a way
back when I want to go ahead and look at
inside the Z bias program when it
actually figures out what's going to
happen here I want to take a look and
find out what it's doing as far as the
lighting so you can see in here where we
do our Z bias program we compute the fog
distance by looking at that fog
direction there right and then we've got
in here the stuff that actually applies
the fog and other nonsense which you
know this this stuff will get finalized
at some point so it's not gonna happen
exact like this but this is the basic
idea so if you look at the the fog
amount the Alpha amount what you could
see here is they're both operating on
fog distance and that's actually good
the reason that's good is because it
means that everything will properly
align to the world z-axis if I tell it
to
right I can also tell to use the camera
if I want but it means that both alpha
clip and fog will both align to the to
the world Z which is what I wanted so
then what I really need to do is just
adjust these parameters dynamically to
make sure that they you know slide
around what those fogging places should
be so that they correspond more to where
the floors are and less to the actual
distance from the camera that you are
which is less what I'm going for like
I'm trying to have a more semantic
coloration of these things not so much a
realistic like distance based sort of
thing so if we look at how that's going
to go in here you can see the way that
this works is to compute the fog
distance we take the inner product of
the direction that we're trying to
measure which is what I specified here
and the camera relative vertex so we're
talking about the vector that goes from
the camera to the vertex measured along
this axis right and so that's really you
know fine with me I think we can just
about say that that's I I mean that
pretty much makes this trivial it means
all I have to do is set these values as
iterate it as interpolated camera
parameters and set them based on where I
know the camera is which I always always
do and we should be fine there may be
some squink enos there that we have to
do when we're doing like offset
interpolations to make sure that the
speeds don't get weird but we'll cross
that bridge when we come to it it's a
very subtle thing and it wouldn't be a
huge problem even if it was happening so
what I want to do now is take a look at
the camera code here so in the game
camera we got this nicely boiled down so
that we really don't have any kind of
additional parameters here that we don't
need so now what we want to do is again
we want to avoid adding any parameters
here that we don't need we want to make
sure
that we have the minimum number of
parameters for interpolation so that we
don't proliferate you know possibilities
for bugs there so looking at how the fog
and Alpha clip stuff shakes out what I
really want to know here is I know where
the camera is going to be and so you
know when I interpolate camera from one
person to another that's just gonna work
the P target peep interpolation will
just work and we have some you know we
want to put in some better interpolators
than what's in there now but it will
just work it'll just end up at Target P
and we know that so then what we need is
some way of fog and Alpha clip getting
set to the right values they should be
set up for this target P so we want to
parameterize this in some way that
allows us to do exactly that if we look
at how these are set up one thing that
we can say is they're probably always
going to be the same distance apart and
furthermore they're probably always
going to be aligned so if we look I'm
reaching over to my my drawing pad here
if we look at what's gonna happen to a
series of Z Heights here in world Z is
if I actually you know look at at sort
of the the separation here right what
I'm gonna do is I've got some place the
character standing on I know I want the
Alpha fade to like start somewhere and
end somewhere right so I know I want
like this stuff to have been faded out
or something so I guess actually
technically it's more like this like
there's the Alpha fade region so
wherever I'm looking at you know I've
got the Alpha fade region is like that
much above it or something right and I
know that the fog region is like this
much below it so probably what I can do
is just remember this value so I'm gonna
see if I can get away with just setting
like a camera basis V Z value there and
basing everything else off of just that
value so I'm going to do like expected
you know floor at Z value here and so
when we're interpolating that will be
the thing that we're interpreting
- and then these parameters will all be
set off of this expected floor at Z
value and again this we know will stay
the same because we always have and I
don't ask me why I did that when I could
have done that we'll always have
measurements being conducted in world
space we're not going to conduct the
measurement the measurements in camera
space because that's just not what I'm
looking for okay so if we know that
we've got an expected floor Z of some
value right what I want to do here is
say however far the floor is out I know
I want to go say one more floor down or
two more floors down or something before
I actually start to fog things out right
so if I know that from this floor to the
next floor is something like you know
five units or six units or something I
can set the fog values to something like
this and this should fog them out and
you know again these are parameters we
can play with that like - whatever looks
right and so that'll be us putting those
in the UI to play with as well similarly
for the floor Z this way we know that we
want to alpha put things that's behind
where the floor is so we're talking
about something that says well if I'm at
a particular floor level here then I
want to go up a little bit - no you know
okay so it's like three point five two
maybe five or you know four point five
or something is where that would be you
know again assuming that a standard
floor is maybe five five meters up and
down right that's what we set it to all
right so what we need now is then to
actually set and interpolate this value
in some way that's actually going to be
useful if I set expected floor Z at here
I'm sorry not set it expected floors
there we go
if I set floor Z equal to whatever this
is in the game camera so inside the
cameras you know struck they're grabbing
that out then all I need to do to make
this work is actually have this set to
something useful at some point
right which we can do inside the
simulation when we update the camera so
when we update the camera for the you
know looking at a particular entity then
what we can do here is say okay you know
this crappy interpolator will just do
the same thing here where we have the
camera expected floor at Z will get
moved in some way right and so what we'd
want to do here is say yeah do the same
exact crappy thing as before you know
something like this and again this is
super crappy don't do this at home we're
just putting this inner to make sure we
got a parameterize correctly and who
knows if we finish the debug camera
stuff to like you know maybe the next
thing we do is is good make a good solid
interpolator here right so anyway but
you know this kind of one will work fine
just to get you to the point where you
can see if it's working because it will
still arrive at the right values the
reason these aren't good is because
their framerate dependent so you really
don't want an exponential like framerate
dependent thing it'll lead to
oscillation and and unpredictable
behavior if you change the frame rate so
like that's we've talked about this
before but that's why you generally
don't you don't leave these in but
they're nice and quick if you haven't
put an interpolator in your codebase yet
once you have it interpolated code base
yet you just call it so at some point
we'll put one in and then we'll just
call it so here's our delta p step let's
do our delta z step in the same way so
you have expected floors the app and and
that's gonna be on the camera and let's
see here we know we need the target to
write so here's us taking the difference
between those two things and here's me
adding it back in right and so we're
just going to going to move towards that
target value as we go so that leaves us
with only one more thing left to do
which is to actually set whatever that
target Z is going to be and so when
we're in a room you know we can see here
we're doing all this stuff it actually
we don't even really need to compute
this value because what you can see here
is we're actually
already starting with it the offset Z
this target offset Z that we use here is
actually the Z value we're moving back
in the camera we could just use that now
again that's gonna be angled though so
we we still want to probably do the
measurement of how it's going to map on
to our camera vector I'm sorry onto the
world vector and so this right here
which is like the camera arm right the
thing that let goes from the target out
to the camera that is what we would
measure to find out the Z length now you
can see that this goes in the opposite
direction so that also means that the
the target expected floor at Z in
addition to just being the inner product
of it it's gonna be negative now we
don't actually need to take the inner
product because we know that we just
need the Z right we know that our
measurement is just along the z axis so
we don't really have to do that we can
just do this and know that that's the
actual value but again this Z is going
well that's actually still correct
because that Z's is going upward and so
if we were to negate it and look at the
negative vector it would still be the
same so if if that's actually exactly
the Z value that we want it just comes
right out of there
and and we're good to go right so once
we have all of that stuff set it should
just work I don't think we need anything
else going on there and so then it's
just a matter of a debugging this and B
makeups supposed to be build C and B
actually setting those values in the
other code to be something logical right
because right now they they really
aren't if that makes sense
oh that's cool what's going on there
it's like right at that height oh that
looks so neat all right also by the way
I kind of want to maybe start us off in
the orphanage because that has more well
know you know
this is fine that just looks so cool
I kind of feel like we're gonna need
ground-based fog after looking at this
it just looks really neat
again another reminder that our fog is
busted alpha value eyes but I think that
just looks really cool we're gonna have
to put some fog in there alright that
just looks so cool alright so moving
along what I want to do now is just go
like okay let's debug that let's have a
way of setting those parameters
ourselves and we could just tweak with
them in in the using commune oh the fact
that we can hot load code but the
problem with that is the turnaround time
is still even though our compile isn't
that long it's still longer than we
would like for tuning a value like that
so what I'd like to do is have a way of
using the camera mode here to somehow
edit those values right in the world
mode to just to just let us edit those
somehow and so what I want is some way
of storing these I want these values to
be exposed somewhere where they can be
edited to me and I don't really know
what the best place to put that is we
have the game state and I feel like
that's probably the best place to put it
just because I don't know where else we
would bother putting it at the moment
they're just sort of some constants that
could just be specified wherever and you
know at some point if we got a little
harder core about saving and loading
values we could make a general way that
you did that but at the moment I don't
really want to do that so I'm not going
to so let's just look at what we would
store here we need like our fog start
value and our fog end value we need our
alpha start value and our
alpha end value these are a little bit
ambiguous because it's it's kind of
difficult maybe I maybe will do fog man
fog max and alpha min alpha max just so
we know what they mean like the values
that are like the hires and lows if that
makes sense so in in a way you know like
if for example we just change this to
that right it would allow us to always
know what we were talking about here you
know what I mean
so I don't know that that maybe seems
like a good idea so I would say if we do
gamestate to fog men and I'll just
pretend that we're gonna set these into
some initial state here as well so the
fog min is 6 that's what or figment is
the case maybe
and the fog max is 30 right then here we
would have alpha min equals 3.5 and the
alpha max which is 4.5 and then what we
want to do here is just have that
initialized when we start up and then
allow the editor access to it so it can
just be edited so yeah look in here
where we just initialize some stuff you
know I'm just like okay there are some
things to edit if you want to and in the
editor will just say hey you know you
can edit that when you're in camera edit
mode and we'll pass the gamestate to
that function sorry about going behind
my head there and we'll just say that
the gamestate comes down here as
something that can be edited so that
seems good and then I just need the
camera editor to actually expose those
somehow
so not super hard I don't think I don't
know why we do begin row and row we
probably can just do new row so well
like tell me why we did that did we do
that for some reason it looks like the
reason we did that is because this no
line feed modifier was supposed to be in
the mix I'm not sure how I feel about
that cuz like we should like do how much
do we really care about no line feed you
know
does anyone even ever set that like do
we do we even have such a thing as an
airline fee does anyone use that I I
don't see anyone who ever could really
set it oh wait a minute
so does that does that mean that by
default you just are on a new line every
time if that's the case maybe I'm
smarter than I thought I was because
that means that you wouldn't even have
to do begin row and row for individual
items that's kind of cool so I want to
be able to put an editable
f32 in here right and you know we've got
it's sort of like an editable P like we
had before where you could do this sort
of thing where did that go edible P XY
so we pretty much want this exact same
thing but we want one that just does one
of these you know what I mean
and so I think I want to just for now
cut and paste this I don't really want
to reuse that code because I I don't
know how I really want these to shake
out I may want some like fairly
different stuff to happen in the case
where there's two versus the case where
there's one so I don't really want to
like regice it by saying that I'm going
to use the same thing for these two or
anything like that I want to just handle
it as a completely separate case that
can be modified yeah however it wants to
be modified so I think that's what I
would prefer so anyway we just want an
edible px thing here where we can say
yeah like just whatever it is doesn't
matter if this is the only one that's
ever going to be there and we're gonna
edit
whatever this label is we know what the
min is and what the max is you know
there's there's probably a pretty I
don't know
same max somewhere but we know that
we've basically got like this for the
Alpha if we do it as a plus or a minus
it's you know it's gonna be it it
depends on how we choose to do it here
you know if we do it as a minus right
then it looks like that versus a plus so
like I said I'm not sure exactly how we
want that to work out but in here I
think I'll just leave them all positive
and let it let it flow from that that's
really all there would be to it I think
that would just let us adjust those
however we want and go ahead and set
those up here I think that would give us
the ability to edit those just an in
real time right like we need these to be
addresses though so it can actually
change them and then that's it right i
hears handmade hero
if I actually go to the camera code Oh
nope gotta pass that too I think that's
no more errors now right yeah so in
theory those should have got initialized
if we started the game but we didn't
start the game if you remember so like
we we just did live code reloading so
they didn't get set to any initial
values so that's why they came as as all
zeroes there anyway you can see here I
can play with these however I want to
write what I don't know here is some
there's actually some more important in
for me
that I would like to have which is where
that where the camera thinks the floor
height is at the moment and so I want if
I could to get the world mode I'd like
to get that displayed right I would like
that to be shown here and so what I want
to do is have the world mode camera
actually get reported on so it can show
this this information now I'm not sure
exactly how I would want to do this but
I almost I almost want to say that since
all this stuff is happening in here it
almost feels like you know this kind of
should go like this all of this instead
of putting it there I feel like it
should maybe be in the you know in the
world mode itself right and then instead
of that in getting initialized in here
it actually gets initialized in the
world mode so like when you actually
create the world mode here you would
actually set it like this and once we
set that up instead of having the editor
being there I just wonder if we could
just put the editor here right so the
camera editor rather than getting called
this way actually gets called this way
you know what I mean
and then that feels better to me because
then we can also inspect anything else
about the world note that we wanted to
oops caps lock I don't know even why
that key exists on the keyboard so yeah
like if we just do this then what we
could do is say well whatever the layout
is that we're using here world mode wise
we'll just fill that out with this stuff
and we can place in here in addition to
these editable parameters you know I
could also put in what the cameras
location was at the moment so I could
say well you know that War Z or like
expected lore Z and it's you know this
is what I expect it to be you know what
I mean we could then say whatever the
camera is expected floor Z is we could
also say like this oops
so we could say what the target was too
you know so I feel like that would make
sense and and yeah
so game world mode versus world mode
know why we've got that there is no such
thing as world mode so I'm not sure what
how that got in there
so now we need to do is have some way in
the in-game editor of actually you know
we need some way to dispatch this off of
the world mode and there's a couple
different ways we could do that but we
can look at some different ones I'm
assuming the game world mode what's
going on here I'm super confused struct
game world mode oh it's alright I'm
having a bad morning it's game mode
world not game world mode ah ok so
looking at the camera stuff here we need
to get these values out of the camera
properly it's expected floor at Z anak
target expected floor at Z and think
that's mostly all we need there when we
call out the to the camera editor here
like I said I don't really think we need
that anymore so the interesting thing
here is when we call update and render
editor really it's just we want the
layout box stuff to happen so you know I
mean I can do this in a number of ways
and really the only thing is you would
need to pass the game the world mode
here if that was what was currently
being used and you know
we could look to see if the game-mode is
world right we could say like if game
state game mode equals game mode worlds
then we can run the camera editor
otherwise we can't you know and that
seems totally fine again it's kind of
just hacked in there it's not as thought
through as I would have liked but it's
fine
so yeah so once we have that we should
be able to see this a little bit more
specifically and we should be able to
guess to what extent these are correct
values as well so right now it's saying
that it expects the floor Z to be at 19
down right or close to 20 and I guess my
first question is does does that seem
[Music]
you know reasonable so if we look here
at you know get camera offset Z for dim
it seems like it's it is plausible for
higher stuff right I mean that that is a
reasonable distance to be off if the y
count was greater than 13 you know it
could be that Y just was 21 so that all
seems you know certainly possible right
so if the expected floor Z is is at that
value then what we're doing is we're
taking that and we're adding to it you
know the these values here so alpha min
is getting subtracted away these are
getting subtracted away and fog men and
fog max are getting added in so if I
were to take these values and add them
and make them really high right so that
means that the fog is not having any
effect similarly if I took these values
and made them very high it should have
no effect as well but you know what I'm
seeing here is that it does I wonder if
that's cuz these are backwards I think
that's what's happening there yeah so
alpha min and alpha max are actually
backwards in terms of how they're being
used in the computation so we should
probably rename those two right
right you can see it building up
properly that way so alpha min and alpha
max need to be swapped when they're
getting used in the world mode now
granted I don't understand why that
would be the case I guess I don't know
how we were expecting those things to be
used but I guess that's the answer is
like that and so looking at this like
this also looks wrong to me like so
again something's weird here because
just looking at those values I should be
seeing these happening in world Z and so
why they're not happening in a world see
I'm not sure right so like looking over
there the fact that that is fading in
differently then this is I don't quite
get so there's one of the things I think
I would do before we get further on
debugging this just looking at how those
are parameterised I think it's more
intuitive if I parametrize them the
other way round so maybe I could say
what is the fog point and what is the
fog span right so like the fog starts
here and the fog depth is set separately
so it's more like you know this you know
what I mean and so this is sort of like
saying well it's it's going to be this
so that I'm really just talking about a
length you know what I mean
I'm really starting to length there and
so I can set that range however I want
and I can set you know that separately
so here you know if we were to preserve
these values it would be 24 long and
here it would be one long and then you
could you could expand or contract those
two things separately so it's sort of
like making it a little bit easier to
adjust the thing you were trying to
adjust and I'll forget sue yes so
looking at those values there let's
let's try to play with some of these
values here so in terms of setting the
Fogg minimum like just looking at what's
happening there right and the fog span
what what I'm not really under just
looking at this it doesn't make any
sense so something really weirds going
on looking at the fog minimum I'm not
like this value what if it's set to that
clothes should be fogging out everything
and the fact that I have to set it down
to that makes like no sense to me at all
so I'm something about this is not
correct
like the measurements are not happening
in the right space or something but
something's borked right like something
is is very strange here
so let's go try to figure out what that
is I'm going to pop over to the Z bias
renderer here and just take a look at
this again so when I create one of these
vertices here you can see when I take
the Z vertex it shouldn't really matter
in either case here which one I'm using
just looking at these you know
there really isn't any difference
between Z vertex and in vertex they're
the same vert P X Y Z is all you're
going to the W coordinates what's
different front and we're not using that
so the camera position as it comes down
to us that's actually pushed on in the
shader and then we use whatever that
camera P that gets moved on there we are
subtracting those two to produce the
vector right now that's all in world
space and I don't really see anything
odd about that I am gonna double check
what we passed down for that just so we
can figure out if there's any weirdness
there but I want to make sure that the
camera P is set properly inside our code
here and and nothing weird is going on
so you can see our prog camera P there
with a set up camera P and all that
stuff so the render setup is getting
passed a used program begin and that
just comes in through the entries so
it's exactly what you would expect
there wasn't anything weird happening
there so whatever the camera P is that
gets passed down here is the one that
would go into the system right so we
should in theory see that camera P flow
all the way through and so it's whatever
we would be passing to set camera
transform that is what we would then use
for the camera P now this is bad so
that's part of our problem here probably
right in that for some reason this is
based off the near clip plane and that
was probably vestigial we definitely
don't want that so I'm gonna remove that
as well
that is should not affect our fog at all
so that's sort of a separate issue but
that will help us tune the Alpha clip
better so now I just again going back to
what I'm not sure is if this fog start
and end distance is specified there and
the direction we've got if I take how
far I am along the z axis from the
camera then that should correspond
pretty cleanly to those values we were
computing before so when we do this I
don't really know why we were getting
any problem there
that looks like a pretty sane
computation right we're just taking the
alpha amount
we can actually also see here why we're
getting our bug with the fog right
remember we were having fringing but a
bug with the fog
so remember premultiplied alpha fog
amount alpha amount here's our color
we're taking our texture sample we're
multiplying it by the fragment color
multiplied by the alpha mouth that's
correct because everything including the
RGB should get B be modified by the
Alpha to stay and premultiplied alpha so
that all works and the clip alpha work
would work properly we come down here we
do a surface reflect RGB equals lerp
between the mod color and the fog color
no multiplication by the alpha value
right so this really needs to happen
beforehand or it needs to be multiplied
here by the alpha amount so one or the
other but not neither right so this
needs to do this or something right if
we're just setting the a this way then
what I would say there is like okay
since if we're gonna blend just the XYZ
if we if we blended everything we'd be
fine but if we're gonna blend just the
XYZ or I should say the RGB well in fact
just looking at this I think we should
just blend the whole thing so I guess
what I'd say is we should probably just
do this and then set the fog colors
alpha properly right so when the fog
color comes in here went and we get that
smooth in I think we want to have that
fog alpha be set to some understandable
thing you know what I mean we want the
fog alpha to be set to something and we
want to pre multiply that something as
well so that it blends properly I guess
I'm thinking it through though since we
don't want fog to be alpha based I'm
gonna I'm gonna say
I'm gonna take that back I'm gonna say I
think the easiest way to do it would be
to do it ahead of time actually so in
here when we figure out the fog amount
and we you know take the text sample and
we do the alpha amount x frag Clark
comes text sample I think what we want
to do is actually lerp those values
before doing the pre multiplication so
we can basically take the fog value pre
multiply the fraud color then snap in
the alpha amount maybe in the end
shouldn't all just come out in the wash
the problem is that let's say the you
know what's the fog value what's its
alpha value going to be you know and our
thing's gonna become more solid as they
get fogged I don't know right like I'm
not that's the part that I'm just not
sure about it seems like you want to
preserve the alpha value but you can't
really preserve the Alpha value properly
if you don't blend in non pre multiply
it space so you get whatever the text
samples alpha is and you're gonna have
to multiply the fog by that all right
here's what I'm gonna do I'm gonna say
that the fog color gets multiplied by
the total alpha so basically whatever
the mod colors alpha is that's what the
fog color gets gets multiplied by and
then when you do this blended way it
should just work right because this is
now the same pre multiply as this so the
Alpha values are equivalent and then off
you go
that seems like the best plan to me
don't quote me on it
okay back to our show it didn't like
that what didn't you like
am I not I mean I may have to do it down
here because it may not want me
modifying a smooth in value which I can
understand that makes sense alright and
so now we shouldn't have that bug with
fogging either where we were getting
like fringing artifacts so that's good
alright so let's take a look at our
situation with the fog now and see what
was going on with it because I don't
understand like it's still kind of a
weird measurement domain it looks like
so there's like if we set the fog men
and we just have like a very short fog
max that fog man is set to basically I
mean it sort of looks like it's down a
little far it looks like the fog is
maybe a little bit it just looks like
it's starting somewhere after this
because this if this is zero then this
it should start at 19 for which we
should be like right here
you know what I mean and it looks like
it's soaring substantially further down
than that
like if the fog span is zero right then
then you fog right away right you can
stand you can see that happening if I
look at the game per se you can see that
I actually see quite a bit further down
though right
so I'm not sure well no I mean all right
okay I guess that's right
so you know you need some better
fine-tuning on those variables
that seems pretty good
we do have the problem if we want to
make sure that the player is within no
matter where we're focusing we kind of
want to make sure the player doesn't
come out of that alpha so I'm not sure
how exactly we want to do that but let's
see if we now solved the problem two of
when we zoom in on a player in a smaller
room if they are correctly yeah so we
fixed that now because again it's basing
it off of where we're focusing so I
think that's a pretty good system now so
that's that's pretty good
and again like now I think what we would
have to do is maybe set there to be like
a I wonder if we need to sort of have
two interpolated values there that are
sort of like our viewing bracket almost
so like it's just to sort of say look if
you imagine that in a situation like
this we always want to be able to see
where the person is but we're focusing
on this floor you know maybe what we
should do is say there's a bracket which
is if the player is like you know on the
stairwell and they're standing here and
then the floor is here there's actually
a thickness of visibility and the fog is
based off of this down and the Alpha is
based off of this up you know and I'm
saying
and so that bracket is actually used you
know sort of as two separate things and
so you know I'm just gonna try that just
in case that's good and so inside the
camera system here where we're
specifying these things we're gonna say
Minzy and Mack Z and
I'm gonna call this instead of floor I'm
gonna call it focus and we're just gonna
have like a focus bracket so we're
basically saying this is the range in
which I would like to make sure I am not
obscuring the ability to view date with
you know with effects you know what I
mean
so if this is the game camera then I'm
gonna call this focus focus
Minzy and Max Z and and then I'll just
like use those values instead so then in
cure what we would say is the target
expected like like this stuff where we
set it we want this to actually get set
yeah and just think industry in order to
tack this properly we actually need sort
of another value there as well which is
like the players location which will
always be included in the bracket so in
a sense in a sense I wonder a little bit
if I maybe want to do
you
so I think again this is a little a
little tricky but let's say I'm doing
this okay so let's say I was keeping
both of these values oops
so I'm keeping them in in the max and
they're getting interpolated but I need
to know what they should actually be
targeting right and so I don't actually
know what to set the expected target
here for until I've looked at what the
two values are and figured out which
ones the min and the max so I think what
I actually want to do is say the room
focus Z is going to be lets say the
entity focus Z and then if I'm in a room
then I set the room focus Z to be the
camera arm Z and then here what I do is
I set the targets for these two things
based on those so I would say target
expected focus Minzy and target expected
max V so these and I mean we're expected
probably come out of those now but
target expected focus Maxie and Minzy
those are now just the minimum and
maximum of those two values so the room
focused Z and the entity focus Z are
just going to be like the two things we
pass in here and we pick the bracket
based on whichever is minimum or maximum
that just leaves us with this but again
we already kind of know what that is
because we just you know when we do this
measurement to figure out what the to
figure out with the target offset Z is
there we just need something up here
that does the same thing
with the with the initial entity so we
just be like enemy focus e equals the
entity's position in Z right and that
just has to be relative to the camera
so whatever the cameras position is we
need to compute that off of yeah I mean
we just need to compute that off of this
I guess it if we don't know what the
target camera should be then it's kind
of hard to know I mean maybe we just say
look we don't know what that should be
but here once we actually have that we
would know what it was it's just the
whatever the camera arm whatever
whatever we expect the camera position
to be so that the target P
it just do this so I think that gives us
the bracket and it tells us you know so
it says here's the range of heights that
we're looking at in the world so you
know don't screw it up and so now what
we would do is say well the the Minzy
and the maxi which we're now actually
calling focus
we know that the fog wants to be off of
the maxi and we know that the Alpha
wants to be off of the Minzy and so I
think that's what we need nuts are good
so so the maxi is Right the Minzy is
nuts what did i do there
this must be bogus
[Music]
so I'm not sure why that would be bogus
though you know the room focus II camera
arm part obviously you know appears to
be working correctly it would seem the
enemy focus D part though doesn't seem
to work and we're taking the entity's
location which should be mapped in the
same way as this is right I mean it's
it's we're in the sim region and we're
subtracting the target position which
should also which is also in the sim
region and so this should be a vector
that goes from the camp the location we
want the camera to be at in the end and
just looking at where the entity is
itself why would that be odd
like why would that be it looks like
we're getting the wrong sign Oh which we
would because the MVP is always going to
be less so that was just a sign bug
right the entity P's always lure the
target P I was thinking well the vectors
going that way and we'll look but we're
not looking at its length so that yeah
that's just that's just a brain fart so
I think that should give us a reasonable
bracket now and that does look like a
pretty reasonable bracket and so we can
see whether that fixes our camera
problems where we're not seeing okay so
that is wrong and it looks like it's
computing the right bracket but the
Alpha still appears to be wrong
why is that
so what is the rub Wow off to a great
start today huh hmm it helps if you
assign the values to local variables
with the right names so in theory now I
should be able to test this right and
and that looks real good you know
because now like when you hop up to this
step you start to get a fade in and
you're never outside of that range so
that's really nice um so now a couple of
things that we think we probably want to
do let's actually maybe start looking at
our interpolation a little bit better
because one of the things that you'll
note here is that it's just - it's it's
much too laggy right like I get down
here and I'm already out the door and
the camera is like not catching up right
and we want the camera to be to be more
proactive more tightly tied right and so
you know we can sort of see why that
that lag eNOS is happening and it's
because if you look at what this
interpolator does it's stupid it all it
does is take the distance between where
you're trying to go and where you want
to go either in 3d or in 1d in the case
of just interpolated directly
interpolated values there and it just
you know it really doesn't do anything
interesting
it just takes those and adds in a
time-based
amount of that which is sort of like
saying I get faster to get to something
the further away I am right so if I'm
really far away I take big steps towards
it if I'm close I take tiny steps
towards it but while that leads to a
sort of rubberband II kind of way of
pulling towards things it doesn't really
do what we want which is provide a
guarantee that will like arrive in a
timely fashion at the target right like
we want to just know
the player is never more than a quarter
second away from getting to where
they're supposed to go right
so what we'd rather do perhaps is take a
look and see when we're interpolating
things from one place to another
can we specify these in a more time
based fashion that will pull us there
more I don't know how I would say it but
more deterministically so you know try
to try to make it so that we can put
some hard guarantees on how bad it is to
you know to get to to get to one of
these things by by some kind of
guaranteed time now this would be really
easy to do actually if we knew when we
were changing the location we wanted to
get to but we don't actually know that
and so we are in a kind of bad situation
where we're trying to interpolate
towards potentially a moving target and
so we probably want to have some kind of
a way of understanding that the thing
that we're chasing is continuously
moving right and that was the nice part
about these is you don't have to think
too hard this will always just chase
what you're go you know what you're
looking at but what I'd like to do is
try to work up towards something a
little bit better than that that's all
okay so the first thing I want to do is
I want to try and define a fixed way of
interpreting that we can think about in
an abstract sense that doesn't have very
much to do with our problem at hand
right I actually want to pull back for a
second and think about what we want to
do here and what I want to do is go look
we want to interpolate between two
things right so we want to interpolate
so I guess we should say from
to target right something like that or
from A to B you know and so if that's
what we're gonna do I want to talk about
the the speed at which we interpolate a
rigid linear interpolation between them
you know would look like that right an
ease in ease out interpolation you know
would look like this right and ease in
with no ease out would look like this
and in ease out with no ease in would
look like this right and you can see
each of the curves I've drawn there
right corresponds to a different feel
this one takes off immediately at full
speed and then gradually comes to a stop
up here this one takes off gradually and
then immediately comes from a stop up
here this one maintains the same speed
the entire way and this one does both it
slowly comes up to speed and then slowly
comes down again right and so what I'd
like to do is make it so that we can
freeze what we're doing in terms of this
approach right meaning I'd like to talk
about that behavior separately from
implementing how we actually map from
what we have into this space so let's
set up a kind of way we can play with
that what I'm gonna do here is I'm going
to say that I'm going to remove a
function of piece of functionality from
the camera first which is the ability to
continuously track the player and then
I'm going to add it back in okay so so
I'm going to to get worse before we get
better that make sense so the first
thing we can do this is I'm going to go
into the world mode
and we've got this notion of an in-room
like which room were in and what I'm
gonna do is gonna track which room were
in and I'm only going to actually kick
off an iteration kick off a change when
we change rooms okay does that make
sense
I'm not gonna do it any other way I'm
also gonna pop back over to the world
generator and I'm going to where does
that go I'm going to put us back in our
original
because that's a place with lots of
rooms we can move between quickly so
we're gonna start in this room and what
I'm going to do is instead of like
having the continuous camera track I'm
only going to kick off a camera
iteration interpolation rather when we
actually change rooms okay mix make
sense all right so in order to do that I
got to keep around what room are in and
that's okay I I can do that by
distorting the game camera so if I have
any of the ID much like we have in
special I'm gonna have in room and every
time we find ourselves in a room we are
going to set the in room value to that
room so that we know that we are there
so much like you can see here where
we've got in camera I'm sorry in special
and we set that end of the ID right here
we're gonna do the same thing now but
for every room so whatever room were in
we're gonna remember that ID all right
and then what I'm going to do here is
say every time we go into this routine
I'm actually going to add a predicate
here which is that if the in room ID is
not the same right to what we thought we
were in before then we execute the code
otherwise we don't make sense
remember how you check these I need are
equal instead of is equal I don't know
why I name those differently sometimes
it's annoying so when we actually are
running the game now you know if I go
from one room to another it should still
trigger but now if I go out to a room
where they were supposed to be scrolling
it will not scroll right so even though
I haven't actually removed that code
that was doing the scrolling before it's
just not going to
and because I never update the target
right except when we change rooms so now
every time I change rooms like you can
see that happening but only if I change
rooms
well what happened or not something were
to happen there what happened there
what I knew what happened what happened
there how did I get into a place where
it didn't trigger I don't really care
cuz we're not gonna use that code but I
would be I want to know if we have but
do we have some other bug that happened
there all right well anyway so i nuked
that piece of code and so now what I
want to do is I want to go ahead and
kick off interpolation that works in a
different fashion so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to say that when we do
that trigger I'm actually going to do
instead of world P target P I'm going to
introduce another thing that's like from
P and so in here when we actually
trigger a transition I'm going to take
the current position that the cameras in
and I'm going to set the from P equal to
that so we remember where we're going
from and where we're going to and then
I'm going to have a t of interpolation
that I use to move between those two so
I'm gonna set that T interpolation to
zero and then down here where we start
to do now that we want to start building
a real interpolator what I'm going to do
is I'm going to interpolate between my
two camera positions based on that value
on this T interpolation now we already
know how to do that right we know that
we can take a position for our camera
and we can say let's go from the you
know let's do the from P to P here if I
just take these values where I'm going
from and where I'm going to I should be
able to trivially interpolate it by
saying look just lurk between the p
value and you know the place I'm going
from and the place I'm going to just
interpolate between those two based on
that interpolation parameter and then
the interpolation parameter is actually
the thing that I update with the Delta
time
right so now we're just using a second
group you know we're using a way of
stepping back from the problem slightly
okay
so sue me
I forgot to clamp my value so obviously
when we actually increment this value we
have to also clamp it between 0 and 1
otherwise it will just keep going
forever we want to stop when we go from
0 to 1 and so you know I apologize there
oh and I don't have to pass that so yeah
sorry about that my bad let's try that
one more time and so now we're just
going to interpolate between those and
you can see that the interpolation is
linear which it should be because we're
calling lerp right so we are every time
step moving a constant amount from the
place we started to the place we're
ending right makes sense um but I don't
necessarily want it to feel like that
right and so you might ask well how do
we get some control over these curves
right like I was saying is right now
we're tracing this curve right we're
going straight from A to B what if I
want to change how the easing of that
feels well obviously if I do my
interpolation here if I want to
interpolate nonlinearly from from P to
target P I can still use lerp I guess
I'll use linear interpolation to do it
if I just take the scalar that I'm using
to interpolate between to say how far
between I wanna go and just make that
nonlinear right so if we wanted to make
you know some kind of a curve between
them I can just make this nonlinear and
then it will be so for example if I just
square this value which makes it
nonlinear I will get a non linear
interpolation between them
right see starts off slow and fast
starts off slow and fast similarly if I
were to do the opposite I think you know
guess what happens
starts off fast and slow starts off fast
and slow right so whatever the shape is
of the function that we feed into this
thing you know what I mean that's the
behavior pattern will get out so if we
want to create some kind of a you know
nice curve that we like what we really
need to do is look for the function here
that makes sense now if we were to use
sort of like I don't know I'm not sure
worth the correct site is to go to for
graphing these days but like what I did
there for example was I graphed the
square root of x right that was what I
did that last time just right that's
here so you can see what the shape of
the curve is specifically we're looking
at this region I don't know how it's
okay how do I actually get to somewhere
web graphing
let's try x squared so here's x squared
I want to just kind of zoom in on the
zero to one block here it is right and
so you can see why we start off slow and
end fast right because that's the shape
of the curve right it starts off slow
ends fast and so remember the closer
this value gets to 1 the closer we are
to our target the closer it is to 0 the
closer our starting point so we're close
to the starting point close the starting
point getting a little further away now
lot lot lot really quickly approaching
here and there we go in fact we're only
in the upper half in like the back third
or quarter almost of of this function
right so if we wanted something that did
ease-in ease-out or you know whatever
else right you can imagine wanting to
make a curve that has a shape here that
we might like now let's talk about how
we would shape curves to fit this ok one
of the things that you know you may
recall from your days in junior high
school or high school or if you're not
in America they probably different names
for those parts but pre algebra or
algebra when you're graphing functions
or looking at graphs of functions you
may remember that the power of a
polynomial determines certain aspects of
the curve so you noticed I did Square
and square root right I did both of
those things I don't know if this can do
ok there we go
so that was the opposite shape curve
right starts off fast and slow you know
but some things that you'll notice about
this either square roots or parabolas
right the parabola looks like this is
that they don't change direction more
than once right so they can only have
one bend to them ok and the reason they
could only have one bent to them is
because the power of a polynomial
determines how many zero roots it could
have and no matter how you shift this
function around right I'm
never gonna get more than two roots of
the function okay
I mean if it's x squared we know there's
two values that X could take that will
allow us to solve this equation you know
what I mean
and so those roots are important because
if you can only have two roots then the
most number of times you could ever
cross a single line is two which means I
can't have another wiggle I can't change
directions and then change directions
again right and so another way to think
about this is that you have actually
when you look at the power rather than
thinking of as zero crossings a better
way to think about it for our
perspective from so we're looking for it
for a mom a shaping perspective is that
there can only be one apex there can
only be one minimum or maximum point in
this thing not two there could never be
another curve like top of the mountain
if you will right and so and this is
talking figured out the shape because
all we care about is sake we look at
about the math we care about the shape
right and we need the math to give us
the shape but the properties we care
about are not the mathematic properties
they're the shape properties which
happened to be mathematical as well but
you get an idea so when we're looking at
that function it's crucial to remember
in our heads what are the kinds of
mathematical functions that could
produce the shapes we want and so for
example a line can never produce any
kind of curve so we know that for
example if I came back here if I wanted
to produce this one right this is like
an ease in ease out right well I know it
can't be a line because that can't curve
at all but furthermore now I also know
it can't be a second-order equation it
can't be power two because that only has
one curved part to it and I need to
write I need two of that I need that to
fundamentally change the direction it
goes right and so what I really need is
a third order polynomial
and you can see that right here you can
already see the shape of it looks a lot
like the shape of this right it's two
bends now this isn't the exact shape we
want but it is the right form okay
now you may be asking yourself because
if you're the type of person who always
thought mass was confusing up until you
know you start working with computers
and realize it kind of all makes sense
at least that's what happened to me you
may be asking well why you know why is
that the case why is it that you know
this has no why is it that this has no
bends in it why does that have one and
why does that have to right and the
answer is actually pretty easy to look
at if you understand the concept of
rates of change or if you've you know
done any calculus right I won't go into
it too much right now because you know
we could spend all day talking about
it's actually pretty fun to kind of go
and explore a little bit more so I'll
just leave that open for a future
discussion but if you look at what
actually happens with having different
powers of polynomials if you look at
what the rate of change is so you know
as I'm going from left to right let's
say if I'm looking at what the rate of
changes of X the value X right because
this is fundamentally graphing that
right I'm graphing Y the height of the
line equals x and I just didn't type the
why because this graphing calculator
smart enough to know that just do y
equals whatever I put in there right so
if I do y equals x as X goes this way Y
just changes exactly proportional to it
y pun intended
well it's because the only thing I could
do is take the input which is my X right
and I can multiply it by some value to
change how fast Y is changing right but
that's it all I can do they're directly
related to each other
only separated by one coefficient so the
only thing I can do is take my input and
make the output change faster or slower
everywhere so everywhere in the entire
graph I I'm powerless to change how much
the the speed of this thing is I'm
powerless to change it based on the
location it has to be the same
everywhere that's why you have a
constant slope right the input is X the
output is y the only thing I can do is
everywhere change the speed by a
constant factor right that's all I can
do now I can also offset it right by
adding a constant but again it can't be
dependent on the location so no matter
what I do I'm affecting the graph
everywhere always I don't get any if
statements I don't get anything that
varies based on x2 tune I just have to
say whatever X is I can multiply it by a
value right and offset it that's it but
now watch what happens when I square it
okay once we have a squared function
what does that actually mean well it
means that now I actually have two
things that depend on X right in a sense
I can write you know this a different
way
right I mean I can write two different
things in terms of X and the math now
has to be dependent on both of those
things right what that means is now the
actual offset of my function or the
speed of my function can be dependent on
X right because that's actually what's
going on here you know what I mean I can
specify two different constraints for
example that it has to hit at negative 3
and positive 5 and it has to do both of
those things which means that as
goes it's gonna come top to come back
around right and another way of saying
that is well okay if I've got something
that's like you know x-squared or
whatever that is right then in order for
this thing to be to say what the speed
of the change is well in order to know
what the speed of the change is anywhere
you have to know where you actually are
because the speed of the change is going
to be based on X itself since as X goes
forwards it gets faster at a speed of X
right that's the exponential part of
that as I increase X I increase X by X
not by some constant value right so if I
say you know this 2 times X just says
the output is always based on whatever
the X is x 2 I have no ability to change
that speed once this goes to squared now
I know that actually it's going to get
faster proportional to some X and I can
make that proportionality be work
however I want really right I can make
this part of it right bend it out I can
change that rate function dependent on X
now if you know derivatives you can see
this even easier because if I have x
squared then I know the derivative is 2x
right that includes X in it again it's
the speed is dependent on my location
now whereas if I have just that the
derivative is just 2 again the speed is
just a constant right so all this is
just a long-winded way of saying well if
we want a function that's going to look
like this we're going to have to go up
to 3 and the reason for that is because
if you want to changes in direction it
means that your acceleration right has
to be something that is non constant
I've got to be changing my acceleration
throughout it so that I can be bending
one way and then have the acceleration
change and bend the other way right so
now my change has to be dependent on X
the change in my change has to be
dependent on X
and the change in my change in my change
is the thing that we actually set right
and so if you have x-squared you've got
one derivative is X the next rivet is
the constant if I got X cubed then
derivative is x squared the derivative
is X and then a constant so it's just
getting us out to enough to get the dual
wiggle so we know right off the bat that
we're gonna need a cubic if we want to
have a shape like this and lo and behold
because that is the kind of shape we
typically want in graphics almost all
graphics is based on cubics cubic
splines aren't cubic for no reason
they're cubic because you need to get
that shape people want ease-in and
ease-out and parabolas can't do it so
almost every spline you see is power
three at least and usually not more
because there's well cubics are hard
enough as it is so usually you don't
want to raise your powers up higher than
you have to right but almost all
interpolation therefore it takes place
at least in the cubic domain for that
reason because you if you want ease in
and out represented in a single curve
you got to have it there's really no
other way to do it because a parabola
can't can't cut it right all right so
now we have to say well okay how do we
shape this parabola to get us something
that we want because obviously one way
of doing it would just be to say well we
know we've got an equation that looks
like this right something like that
where we have four things to play with
the coefficient on the cube term the
coefficient on the squared term the
coefficient on the linear term and then
an offset if we wanted it right and so
we could sit here all day trying to
figure out what it is right I mean we
could we could just say I don't know man
like I'm getting am I getting any closer
maybe you know I don't know and I'm not
sure how long it would take me really to
figure out what that would be but it's
pretty hard you know
[Music]
yeah like me yeah maybe that's got to be
negative let's say I don't know
yeah I mean it started getting better
maybe is it
I can't tell like it's not quite going
far enough over it turns back around
it's too hard of course now I'm kind of
into it it's like a game I was gonna try
and say look it's too hard but now I'm
like actually enjoying myself which is a
bit of an issue because I was trying to
motivate the reason to not do it this
way but now I'm like having a lot of fun
doing this this way
let's suppose that I had enough
self-discipline to not sit here for a
long time playing with the curve right
what we would like to do is be able to
talk about curves of this forum in a way
that was already set up for us so that
was it was intentionally making the
curves that would produce useful
graphical results based on the kinds of
properties we care about so someone who
has gone through working out all the
math solving for various things like the
beginning in the ending point and what
we want to happen in the middle and
putting them into some format that
allows us to easily describe the shape
of the curve that we want without having
to sit here and manipulate all these
things right and so if you think about
what happens there that actually is what
a Bezier curve is a Bezier curve is
bezzie a having sat down for you and
solving what will happen inside here in
a cubic so that you can set it to
something reasonable and let me just
sort of give an example of what's going
on there right if I was going to be
super hard chord mathy about it and I
want to make a function of T where I'm
going to say that some coefficient to
the cubed and then some coefficient
squared and then some coefficient linear
and then oops supposed to be a C and
this is what I'm solving for and I know
that I want to have certain things be
true like I want F of T I should say F
of zero to equal zero and F of one to
equal one then I know that I can start
to solve this and break it down till
there's only for example two parameters
to play with right and that is exactly
what the bezzie a system does right it
says let's make a function where I know
that I've been plug in 0 I get 0 and I'm
a plug in 1 I get 1 so we're only
talking about the curve between and why
right because yeah we want something
that
that makes curves of like this sort of a
caliber so they always end 0-0 and they
always end at 1:1 so we know that this
has to be true about them and then what
they said is well let's just say that
what we want to specify to control the
shape of the curve are the derivatives
so we'd say the derivative right at 0
equals some value that I want to specify
right lebih b we call that U and F Prime
at 1 which is the derivative here so
whatever you know kind of approach you
want to take and the start off you want
to take their right is V this oops and
this are just a transform of each other
right in other words this is some
equation I can compute these are some
things I want to be true about the
equation and what the Bezier curves are
is basically just a way of getting this
to be true right getting these things to
be true does that make sense
I don't know hopefully that does make
sense
now we could go through the whole thing
here but that would be a little bit of a
math headache probably although like I
could I suppose I could try it because
you know I mean I could write I mean
some of these things are kind of trivial
like you can see that basically you just
know that D is 0 this condition just
means that D is 0 right so that's kind
of just a non thing so you're really
talking about solving this for this you
know what I mean right and so you know
if we wanted to try it
plugging these various values in for T
and seeing what we actually get sure why
not I'm game I am bad at doing math on
paper so I think that promises but you
know let's say we wanted to so if we
want to actually solve this what we know
is we plug in 1 we get 1 so everywhere
here so that's effectively just saying
we have a plus B plus C right because 1
cubed
squared and one right is just a plus B
plus C we know that that has to equal
one so there's our first equation we
then know that the derivative has to
equal U and the derivative has to equal
V at these two points what's the
derivative of this right what's the
derivative of that equation well the
derivative is pretty straightforward to
compute right it's just going to be 3a T
squared right because just multiply the
three and go from there
plus 2b T plus C so there's our you know
there's our derivative in that case
right and furthermore since we're
plugging in 0 and 1 here we actually
don't have to worry about the t's
because they're gonna go away so we can
actually write this out now with a 0 and
a 1 so if this is our F prime of
something right of T then once we want
to write this out we would just say
alright 3a T squared what's T squared
oh it's zero actually right in fact that
whole term goes away this altar is a so
only C remains so in this case we just
have C equals u right why what's going
on there why is that so simple well the
reason that that's so simple is because
think about it if we want to specify the
derivative at this point well the
derivative of that point is just the
derivative as the function starts out
when it has neither its squared term nor
its nor its its linear term because it's
at zero so obviously the slope at 0 is
always going to be whatever the non T
dependent term is because all the other
T terms have gone away right they
haven't had a chance to start yet makes
sense these are the modifications to the
slope that happened over time so that
makes perfect sense this makes perfect
sense right we don't know what the heck
that means yet but we've got one more
thing to do here which is F Prime
1 equals V so if we did that these would
all be ones so we would end up with just
what 3a plus 2b plus C equals 0
oh sorry equals V right and since since
we know that C equals u everywhere we
already kind of have that term taken
care of so we're really just talking
about that's you know that's a
proscribed constant so we're really just
talking about this part of the equation
right we can rewrite these to be we can
we can rewrite these terms to be a plus
B you know equals 1 minus u right
and in this case we have 3a plus 2b
equals V minus u right and so now we can
just we're really just talking about
solving this system of equations for
these two variables right a and B so
doing that we can solve for a to
substitute back in pretty quickly right
because this is already we can choose
either of these two whichever one we
want
maybe we choose because it's multiplied
by 2 into the 3 I don't know it doesn't
really matter it's just a coefficient
doesn't matter which one we choose but
let's suppose we chose that we would
have be right in this case I'll just
write it out again B equals 1 minus u
minus a so here we would have 3a plus 2
1 minus u minus a equals V minus u ok
solving for a we would get 3a plus 2
minus 2-u minus 2a equals V minus u
again I'm horrible at math so I probably
made a mistake already but you know what
can you do that's 3a plus and you can
see here that we've got the a term the 2
and the 2 you want to go to the other
side so really what we want to do is say
it's 3a minus 2a right equals V minus u
minus the 2 minus R plus the two you
right so then we have 3a minus 2a
is just a and then here we just have the
V which we only use we only have one of
and then the U which we have to combine
so it's a - you in a to use so it's V
Plus u - - and that's what a equals
right I don't know if that makes sense
so there's our a term and then finally
if we if we want to actually find out
what B is now we have to back substitute
that in to something we can solve for
right so if we plug it back into this
equation for example the a plus B equals
one minus U to actually find out what B
equals right that would be B equals one
minus u minus V Plus u minus two which
is B equals one minus u minus V minus u
plus two which is equal to one plus two
am i right about that
yeah I think so minus 2-u minus B so
here are our values supposedly right
again I'm awful at working Mathews
those are probably totally wrong I
highly recommend getting a good computer
algebra system which I've never found
but let's say someone actually made one
someday I would very much love it um but
those are our coefficients and now we
can actually just use them directly if
we want to right we should be able to
just specify those directly in theory
right now it's probably wrong so that
probably did the math wrong but that's
the idea right meaning if you were good
at doing math through you would have
gotten equations that were right and so
coming back in and remembering what
these are this is the two derivatives
that we wanted to specify and so looking
at these two here we can specify all the
pieces that we actually need we know
that our C value is equal to U so if I
just rewrite these here right our a
value is V Plus
you - to our B value with some stuff
over there and our C value is just you
so that's what three - to you - be right
um so if we you know let's say that was
right then what would happen is we could
put those in there and set this and we
would get something interesting so in
here for example if we were to set this
up V + 2 v + u minus 2 let's say what we
want to do because remember what those
values actually mean our derivative at
zero is you right so u equals the zero
derivative and V equals the one
derivative so let's say we wanted
ease-in ease-out we just set those both
to zero a would be minus 2 B would be 3
and C would be zero right
and so basically what we'd be saying
there is I don't know it would look like
this B would be 3 right and lo and
behold I did the math right there's our
East curve shocking right
but look it starts out easing in goes
fast in the middle and then eases out
ends directly at one start strictly at
zero math it's amazing right
if only anyone ever taught it right it
would be pretty cool um sue you could
see there that you know all I really did
was I said what I wanted and then I
plugged a truck in even someone like me
who is very bad at this lucked out right
but if you have a computer algebra
system you can take the luck out of that
and actually know that you didn't miss a
negative somewhere or something right so
what this also means is we can change
those parameters I don't know if this
thing lets me make variables
so let's say I cut and paste that here
can I say stuff like I don't know if I
can all right um but anyway let's say we
did one more just for good measure let's
say we want it to be one here and and I
guess it would have to be one here as
well so we what if we plugged in just
like one one instead right
so we'd have 1 plus 1 minus 2 because so
that means the derivative it's linear
right so we should get it degenerating
to just a line cuz we're now not having
a curves at all so if we plugged in 1 1
what would we get
well we would and remember here what we
got was negative 2 3 0 right if we've
looked along we get well we get 2 minus
2 which is 0 so this term goes away
right we'd get 3 minus 2 minus 1 so this
term goes away and then we'd get one
right so we just have that term so 1
behold it's alive exactly what you would
expect because we told it that the
derivative should be unchanging and it
should be 1 at both points right um so
now if we want to do this if we want to
figure this out we can just make our
bezzie a magic here right and we can do
exactly what we just typed in before
well I deleted it but this negative 2 3
0 right so we know we can just do
negative 2 times our T value squared
which is this I'm gonna make that be
something I can see there a little more
clearly so T squared right plus 3
oh sorry T cube plus 3 T squared and
plus nothing there are no other terms
because the the C term is 0
right make sense so now if I specify
that value oops if I specify the bezzie
a magic value we should get an ease in
ease out over the exact time that we
asked for which was happens to be one
second in this case right but off we go
and that's what we got right so I think
we're out of time unfortunately but that
is precisely how you compute a nice
curve from scratch right we didn't look
a single thing up
looks pretty nice too let's go to QA
the slate actually had super frills it
was giving you a slider to edit the
values okay so if that's the case let me
just do that then because I wasn't sure
what was going on this is a this is I've
never used this before by the way this
was pretty cool
not sure what else I've put in here
exactly but all right so let's say I
wanted to do you equals zero V equals
zero and then down here I wanted to
compute these things as dependent values
I don't know if that's allowed but so V
Plus u minus 2 and then B equals 3 minus
2 u minus V and then C equals u right
and then what I can do is I can actually
specify my XY values here so I can just
say like look plot the y equals a X cube
oops cubed plus BX squared plus CX value
there and
did I actually specify that right
so
Oh coz I'm sooo good that's what the
problem is so that's right there we go
so there's one one so now I is there a
way to set like the boundary values oh
yeah this thing is good just you see
this stuff this is like this is serious
this is someone went the full nine here
my dude right but you can see how right
I can I can sort of change the shape of
this function here I wonder - you know I
could look at values that were sort of
further afield I want to right - so you
can see here if you if you don't mind it
going down below as well you can set it
to other things let me set it so we can
get a little more range so this gives us
one on a full one value on either side
that we can go to right so you notice we
still always end 0 and 1 because those
are hard constraints of the function but
now like the function can go outside of
its interpolation boundaries or it can
get torqued up pretty high right like it
is here and and so yeah like I don't
know negative 1 is probably not a useful
value but you know two more values
higher than than one here are probably
fine you know for it for certain
applications right but you can see you
know at some limit we start getting
things to go outside but if it's within
reason right you can see that that still
always stays within our interpolation
bounds pretty much right makes sense
so anything between zero and three is
pretty fair game here I should solve why
that is I suppose that could we also
describe the ease in out via a sine
function sure I mean it's a little
harder to deal with because sine tends
to be a little more finicky so I don't
know that you would ever want to do that
because the cubix usually are pretty
good and unless you really know you need
the sine function for some reason I
don't think you want to go for a
transcendental because you're gonna it's
gonna caught it's they're harder to
optimize you can still optimize them
pretty good but they get harder I
noticed that you use T times T times T
for T cube just TF support for something
like T times times three for exponents
not that I know of so the problem that
you end up getting is that if you wanted
to support that the problem is that C
syntax actually says that that's a
pointer dereference so for example if i
say you know a star star b the way c
actually parses that is you know a
multiply pointer dereference B right
so it actually does this so I don't
think you can I don't think C++ could
ever add an overloaded operator star
star in that way I mean you could but
you'd have to do that to do it which
seems probably not so good
whereas especially you can just write
that and define the function cube and
that's probably the right way to go so I
don't think you can do star star 3 even
in modern zeros list but maybe you kiss
modern cos plus adds the kitchen sink so
who knows like what's in there but in
the old days you couldn't have have you
test the new transition for going up and
down the stairs well don't forget we're
not done yet
this is pretty
is the start of the interpolator we need
to then spend like all I did we show you
how to get the E's curve right we have
to now actually do the other part of it
I'd rather wait till tomorrow to talk
about that if that makes sense and so
going up and down the stairs we don't
really need to test cuz this isn't the
right interpolator anyway if you just
want to see what it looks like just as a
point of reference I could certainly go
do it
right of course why I'm not getting any
alpha there oh right because I'm not
interpreting those values anymore
oops but yeah
by setting the unv value so negative you
can get things like overshoot with the
camera goes over then corrects back I
don't think it will be a good feel for
HMH but some case is really good yeah if
we wanted to kind of overshoot and relax
to it we could do that for sure right
and yeah you see like if I put that back
in you could see that happening at the
bottom of the curve there right
I guess we're overshoot you'd want it
that way right and so you know we
certainly could do that if I come in
here so that we can actually test value
specifically if I set the U and V here
and then do the a the B and the C you
could then say like okay so V Plus u
minus 2 and this is 3 minus 2 u minus B
and this is you right here we can we can
plug these values in directly if we want
to so you know if we had something where
we wanted a little bit of of ease in and
then we wanted a little bit of overshoot
you know maybe it looks a little
something like this
one of the reasons so and the other
thing you have to remember here is a
cubic is only so expressive so this
probably won't quite be right because
you probably want more damping there so
what you'd probably would you really
want to do if you wanted to do this is
you'd probably want to split the curve
as in two to cubics one that goes to 0.5
and 1 that goes from point 5 to 1 and so
that you can have more expressivity
there so I don't know that I would
really recommend doing this but if you
did want like overshoot but let you know
just to illustrate the point so if this
is the actual parameters that we put in
there mmm we should be able to see the
overshoot happen now in theory anyway
right although I'm not really seeing any
to be honest Oh
because I didn't use the variables that
would do it okay try overtime why am I
not what I do wrong here
that's what I did wrong
V and you are specifications they're not
the actual values so that's what we
actually need sorry about that
try that one more time
I still screwed up
you V our a is V + 2 + u e+
wait what d + 2 - you rather oh don't
ask me what that's about
so don't use you as a variable i guess
is the lesson cuz to you is valid
because it's unsigned i think all right
so there's with overshoot right but you
see how the overshoot is really kind of
unpleasant and the reason for that i
think is again it's just it's not it
needs it needs to overshoot and then
smooth out and you need a really a
Quadra whatever you've got quartic for
that or split it into two cubics but a
single cubic can't really express that
does that make sense
so anyway this is what I actually wanted
which is to say that I want the it to do
a nice soft landing there and so when we
actually run this this is what I kind of
want the camera more to feel like and so
I think that's what will mostly be going
with there and so that's gonna be it for
today tomorrow I will talk about this
the next step oh I kind of like this can
you save this what we made here I don't
I just want like a like a hot link to it
here we go
[Music]
yeah um there we go
busy a curve done so how do I can I
remove this so now we can go to handmade
Bezier curve and there is our beautiful
Bezier curve that's a cool website uh
whoever Decimus is thank you
for this website that was really cool
like four basic graphing stuff that is
really helpful because it lets you
illustrate points much more easily than
you probably could you know it would
take a while for me to draw all that out
and here you know and people can now
grab that link and play with it
themselves like that's that's great
that's like a really good educational
tool right Bravo sir like very very well
done
yeah it's wse 2:05 kqp L someone wants
to post that in the chat wse 2:05 k QP L
that's the link Decimus comm /
calculator with that in there yeah
all right folks hmm and it seems it
seems like it works it seems like you
can just grab that link and go all right
thank you one for joining me for this
sort of handmade here oh it's a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along series at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade here
org and it comes with the source code so
you can play around with it yourself and
maybe you want to play with the triple H
parameters and see what you think I'll
be back tomorrow for the second part of
camera interpolation so that we can get
the function structure it in a way that
allows us to update the target because
really right now it's not in that form I
just sewed the basic way to interpolate
from one point to another but we haven't
really talked about what we would do if
we didn't know like where the target was
or how it was moving around and we just
kind of have to speculate me update the
camera at any given time to make that
happen so what we want to do is kind of
like figure out a way to you know reform
that function using what we now know
about the interpolation and how we want
it to kind of ease in and ease out of
things we want to figure out a way to
get that working right so that's what we
will try to figure out on next time and
that will be a harder problem that's
sort of more of a finesse thing and
isn't quite so easy you saw today how
you could just write the math out and
just happens it's not so simple to do
the second part but we'll tackle it and
we'll get something good going tomorrow
so I hope see you back here for that
till then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet I'm
assuming John is still streaming so
hopefully we'll go see what John's up to
now
if that actually happened all right take
you to everybody