hello everyone and welcome back to
handmade hero the show where we go to
complete game live
on stream we uh have been away for a
while
but you know there's nothing in
particularly magical about
being away from a while oh except for
the fact that apparently
um we need to figure out why our four
coder isn't building other than that
we're fine looks like as long as i'm in
that directory it works all right
who knows uh anyway um when we left off
we had just modified the tag system i
think we still
maybe had some debugging we wanted to do
but we had just changed the tag system
over to something simpler
uh we're basically at the point now
where you know most of the things we
need to do are
for the most part done um and we're
really just trying to figure out like
what sorts of stuff we want to be doing
uh with gameplay and so we're kind of
going through
and just trying to make sure that we
have a decent
sort of setup uh where everything is is
kind of
um a streamline for putting gameplay in
and i don't actually know uh what i
thought we had a little bit of debugging
to do left on the tag update
uh you know it's working but it i think
there were still
a couple things in there that weren't uh
right if i run it in
retail mode now let me just see if i'm
right about that
um yeah so so okay
like right like we saw some stuff like
that that we had not seen previously
um like where where the lighting gets
screwed up
right um i i remember some of this
now it's all coming back to me now so
there's some weird things in here like
you know the lighting just kind of stops
working properly
for no for no good reason right we don't
have an explanation for that
and it sometimes works and sometimes
doesn't so
there's like something where we we like
something isn't getting loaded properly
we don't know right like we just don't
know
uh we've got a bug though and you can
see like that
kind of weirdly there like the it seems
like when we run
uh in debug mode we don't have this
problem
right so so here's like me running in
debug mode
and you can see that there's there's
nothing weird going on with the lighting
and so something's up right we've got a
weird bug because the lighting is
is in debug mode we don't see any
weirdness
right there it looks it looks like what
you would expect it to look like
so we know that something bizarre is
happening here
and the question is what uh
we've got to figure out like what we
broke when we were
messing around or you know it could be
that we didn't break something when we
were messing around
that all we did was like uncover another
bug
that you know that had just been lurking
and
what we're seeing here is the
manifestation of a bug
that otherwise would not um you know was
kind of
hidden or something was masked by
uh something that we were doing
previously and then when we kind of
jiggled things around we ended up in a
situation where
we couldn't actually uh yeah where we
didn't actually get to work
now here's another thing right like
where's that where's that guy
so that's another tag bug we have which
is presumably that the
um and also the down one doesn't work
right so we've got a bunch of bugs in
the tag stuff that we reported
and so really probably all we want to do
today is just get back into it
and go fix those bugs so try to try to
get um
these sort of weird bugs we introduced
back out of here which
is probably mostly about streamlining
what we've done
and cleaning up any rough edges and
looking for
you know mistakes the mistakes that were
made uh because it is weird
that works in debug but not release and
so on like that's just kind of weird so
you know that there's something funky
uh going on if that makes sense
all right um so let's take a look
at first of all um maybe some of these
these basic tag situations so
we we kind of had a
when we were creating those monstars
we know that uh there should have been
like a little skull with the monster
so maybe the easiest thing for us to do
first is just take a look and see
why we're not getting any of those those
monstars anymore
so if we take a look at where those are
being added
you can see that we've got sort of this
this create entity stuff going on and i
believe
that the enemies are added via
this routine right so you know they get
added
um much like the cat and the orphans and
so on
they get added by these little callbacks
that just like build
little um little creatures right they
build they build whatever
sorry i gotta turn that off um
battery there we go uh
we're still in the in a weird place with
four coder right now um
waiting for alan to update it or maybe
he has i haven't heard from him so i'm
not sure what the status is but there's
a couple weird things that
uh are are you know just kind of
waiting for a four coder update and i
don't really know what the status of
because i haven't been programming
in it um as you know i've been away so
if we take a look here at i think add
snake is what's going on
and uh right now those are those are
technically snakes they just don't have
uh multiple pieces because
we you know we're just when we put this
in we were just testing with that
so this right here is what
should have been uh working you know
this is this is what should have been
um creating the snakehead which is this
asset headpiece here right and then we
have this base asset
uh which was a thing that should have
been uh passed in
and and it's like what kind of snake uh
you wanted it to be
and so presumably the problem here is
that when we
did the add snake we ended up in a
situation
um oops
snake um we ended up in a situation
where whatever the base asset was
was not correct somehow
so you can see here that it's got a tag
bones
on it and other than that it doesn't
look like it has anything else
so i don't actually know what those
bones things were but it could be that
we just need to add the other tags that
we need
uh to specify the um
the sort of head piece skull
thing i don't know whatever you want to
call that so i'm going to go ahead and
look for that
we don't want mummy so it looks like
looks like undead is probably was the
thing we need
wanted there so it's so in terms of this
this is undead bones
so i assume you want like
that kind of a thing um
uh and and i'm just gonna see if this if
this makes
uh that part any any better
and so off we go to
[Music]
the wow that is weird that lighting
stuff is very strange i'm going to be
interested to see what's going on with
that bug
uh but we'll see so
off we go hopping down to the you can
tell it's like a
it's like an overflowy kind of a
situation but there okay there's our
fellow there
so it looks like the problem that we're
having um
you know now we've got the the skull is
fine
uh so that's all good but the it looks
to me like the problem we're having
uh the last thing i can see that's
obviously wrong about the tags
is that as we're moving around here the
downward facing direction
tag is not looking up properly it's not
really a tag it's it's more of a number
so the downward facing number is not
working
and you can see that both in terms of
the hero so if i
punch in any direction you can see the
hero switches to facing that direction
except for down right the the heroes
sprites don't change
direction for down and you can see that
that's also true
of like the skeleton so the skeleton
changes to face the direction the
skeleton's hopping
but never for down right
so we know that the down directional
like uh whatever you want to call that
the downward facing direction
is not working but we don't necessarily
know why
now it probably has something to do with
how we're mapping the numbers
but who knows so let's take a look and
see
what those numbers actually are or what
they should be
the downward facing one is the one that
goes is basically the furthest
all the way around so you've got zero
is facing to the right i believe is how
we do it so zero is facing to the right
pi over two is facing up pi is facing
left
and three over two pi
um it is down right
i think that's how it was done but i
don't remember it might have mapped zero
to one
i have no idea so we and we also do it
cyclical
so if you keep going if you keep going
past
uh three halves pi
plus a quarter pi which would be
seven quarters pi i guess
um if you go seven quarters pi
you would you would get uh a wrap around
back to um the zero
direction right because it's you know we
wanted it to be cyclical so that as you
got
back around that's where you would go uh
and i don't actually
think that would be implicated here
although if we screwed up that
calculation somehow
you know then it could be so
we can probably debug this pretty easily
by just looking at the selection process
for it
however i just want to look at that
routine first because i want to re
i want to familiarize myself um
because we haven't looked at this code
in a while which just like what we ended
up deciding to do here and you can see
so here's uh the routine that actually
looks for assets so what it does
when it comes in here is it asks for uh
based on the the hash so that's the
thing that says like oh this is like an
undead whatever
right um is you can
in here you can go ahead and
grab that out grab like that series of
sprites which is just the different
facing directions or whatever
uh and then it'll go through here it'll
look through the
the slots and it'll try to match um
whatever the match vector is and the
match vector is the thing
uh that actually has oh weird why is my
cpm
so high what's going on are we in power
mode
oh my god ryan
how are we in power mode right now i
haven't even been typing
what's going on
what
power mode should not be implemented yet
should it
well you know um
i do like power mode uh but we're gonna
have to sideline it for now sorry folks
um f4
power mode disallow that that breaks my
heart turning off power mode you know
i don't mind telling you um
but everyone you know you can blame you
can blame ryan he's on the he's on the
chat
you know the power mode i did my part
the sound plays back correctly for power
mode
um
so so you know i i consider myself
blameless here the cpm counter
you know that was ryan so i'm just
saying
you know i'm just saying ryan uh
you know this is this is it
what what happened there what what
happened right the cpm decay
not working um you know that that was
out of my purview
i think we all agree that power mode is
a critical feature
and that there's no way we can finish
handmade hero without it so
i'm just i don't want to say that
everything's riding on you
but everything's riding on you okay so
uh what we're seeing here is just that
we're getting some kind of a problem
with matching these these directions
and you can see here the way that we're
doing it is we're doing this uh
absolute value differencing nonsense
here right to try and match the circular
pattern
uh to you know to the correct uh
series of things and you know this is
uh i think what happened if i remember
correctly is i was like well this is
dumb
we shouldn't bother doing this we should
just match linear and then
i was like ah now well let's keep using
it whatever and all that was stupid
uh because honestly like
i'm not sure why we don't just add
a duplicate reference to
the asset
at 2 pi because that would just solve
the
problem right and then you wouldn't need
what's going on here right you just add
the asset twice
now maybe there's some like overwhelming
ali obvious reason why you don't want to
add an
asset twice and
i mean if i went and looked at the code
i
i might find that right and if that's
the case
then you can see why we need to do this
range-based mapping here
but it feels to me like we could
probably eliminate this
entirely just by adding uh
that additional feature now what i want
to do first
because i want to start removing prob
pieces of this
problem slowly is i'd like to get rid of
the range mapping
because i want to start by just looking
at the basics here
so i want to say that let's just do
this first um
[Music]
in fact let's just do this
and i want to get rid of that range
mapping and then i want to see if we can
maybe just
remove that range mapping entirely
because it's just extra stuff that has
to happen
uh for no reason in there um and so i
don't because we already have a bug
in that stuff there i don't anticipate
any problems with this because i mean
hey we've already got a bug there so we
shouldn't
uh cni and it looks all fine to me right
so it looks like
it looks like there's nothing weird
happening there
in particular right um
so that all seems fine uh so i'm going
to go ahead and say that we can just
yank this
and then we can go see what's going on
with that circular
system to find out why we're not getting
that final
match that we expect to have and we can
add one more
at the rotation point if we need to
um we may never actually need it in
which case we can just ignore it
entirely
so what we would basically do is is is
push this out of here
uh the difference part here would now
take this d0
um and it would put that in here
right and the only problem that we would
have
is we have to map this zero to one
so it wouldn't be zero to three to two
pi
anymore i don't know it to what extent
that matters uh
but in order to make this always work
properly we would want
um we would want to make sure that we
you know we always tracked the
difference
that way so i'm going to go ahead and
say that's
that's what we're doing here i'm going
to pull that tag range stuff out because
i
haven't liked it for a while and i kind
of chickened out
um on pulling it before but we're just
going to pull it because
i don't like it um so we're going to get
rid
of the tag rain stuff
entirely um i'm going to go ahead and
even just pull the variable
and it's gone and now again
i suspect that now we may introduce a
bug with that because i don't think
we're mapping on the zero to one range
so we might have one okay we don't
so it's still fine uh even with that
change
um and so now let me go ahead and go to
uh the entity code where we're actually
drawing this stuff so where we draw this
stuff
here um you can see this is the code for
entity
output which is massively over
complicated at this point and we
probably should streamline it at some
point but you know what are you gonna do
um water under the bridge so if we
take a look at how this is mapped you
can see it here
uh the facing direction coming through
here
if we want this to be mapped in a
regular pattern so zero to you know zero
to one
uh what we'd wanna do there is in the
so in the actual
asset import stuff right so when we
actually
import these um we presumably have
like a like a tau you know um
going on here you can see when we do
import body
there's this facing direction nonsense
and then we do a y
index mod 4 times tau 32 right go in
and wait what
what is that about
why index mod 4
times tau 32
how is that makes sense
and that's going to be 0 1 2 or 3.
and then we multiply by tau 32
isn't that wrong by 2x like that that
would have to be pi
wouldn't it
is that anyone
am i the only person who thinks that's
weird
because because i think that's weird
folks i don't i don't love it
chat hello is anyone paying attention
i mean correct me if i'm wrong right if
this is supposed to be facing direction
and it was supposed to be mapped in
the stupid world where where people
use for some reason pi and tau to
describe circles
which by the way i would never do today
we did that because when we started
handmade hero we were
not really being smart about it and we
used the stupid
math way of representing a circle which
sucks
um but town 32
[Laughter]
oh that was great oh that's so good
it was just just off the screen
oh that's beautiful so okay
that's so good look at that because i'm
like what were we doing like that's not
gonna work
um so that's fine that's fine
uh yeah we need the uh
line overflow indicators right like we
need
a little thing that says there's more
there of course i could have told that
because there's no semicolon but
okay we're fine now
uh yeah
it's in it's in star code galaxy the
circle stuff's in sarco galaxy so i
finally
like star code galaxy is my excuse to
record all the things that i ever wanted
to record where i'm just like this is
dumb don't do it this way do it the
right way and here's the right way right
so it's all in there
um but anyway uh
so yeah uh this part right here
is like again so
we don't really have any reason since
everything else is encoded zero to one
we might as well just encode this zero
to one as well
right uh like i can't see any reason not
to do that
so we might as well just have these go
zero to one and then we can just
map out of the tau range on the other
end
right so to me it seems way smarter
uh instead of doing this just just don't
right
like just don't don't actually do that
multiplication
because there's no point to it right it
doesn't do
anything for us so if we just do
y index mod four over four uh
that seems like a way better
deal right uh like like
you know i i just don't see what the
point is of mapping these out
uh to tau 32. so to me that seems like
the right solution
um and so everywhere that we're doing
that
that kind of garbage i think we should
just stop so let's just stop
uh because it makes things a little
simpler for us so
you know off we go now this
what what is this about
this looks like a just incompetence here
right because this this doesn't look
right at all
um this this looks like it's just wrong
because this this should have been just
that
right i mean i'm not sure
i'm not sure what's going on there
because the facing direction should
should never have been
um time should
oh i guess i know what's going on it
doesn't need to do a mod four because it
only does
four so okay nope that's fine
um and then we've got one more down here
i'll get rid of that one as well
there we go uh so yeah our tau 32s
have now been sort of exercised
[Music]
and i think that's all fine so if we
recompile this now
we will be mapping those tags the
problem is it won't
update our actual asset files
so that's a problem and i don't actually
remember
to what extent we do reprocessing on
here
i think if we change the hht file it
will reprocess those
probably um but i don't actually know
like like uh i don't remember to what
extent we
we tried to make that work i know that
if we change the tags
uh that it will actually try to change
it but i don't know to what extent it
actually does the
hha modification stuff um properly there
so
i'm not sure because we you know we
spent some time on getting the stuff to
work properly so it's not completely
stupid but it's also not you know a
particularly
exciting asset system so yeah
uh so anyway if we go into the
basegame.hht
and i just like make a slight change to
it like that so it appears slightly
different
i don't know if we now run um
if that will actually work yeah so it
doesn't look like it really remapped
that as well you know i guess we don't
know because we didn't change the input
code yet so
you know maybe it did i doubt it um so
let's say we can actually go check the
actual values too and see
but if these entity facing direction
things right now are still
on the tau front what we can do is just
divide by tau 32
and that will give us and you know we
don't even really need to divide we can
just do
a pre-inverted tau 32 here
multiply by the facing direction and off
we go
uh and so that'll map that from zero to
one uh
as well so now we you know we have the
whole thing mapped
on the zero to one range um and and
it looks good right it looks like it's
it's working so i guess we do
re-map the tabs the tags i guess we're
better than we thought we were
so now the only thing we have to do is
go back in and figure out why
the downward facing dog um
is not downward facing and uh
and by the way i like how hope pushing
the alt
key makes that happen like what is going
on
um
it'll be interesting to find out what
that bug is like those are weird things
right they don't happen in debug mode
something weird is going on if this
turns out to be a visual studio compiler
bug
i sure hope not because if it is there's
going to be a big old rant
uh so anyway we
just want to know why our downward
facing direction
isn't working and so our downward facing
direction
we would expect uh it to be
uh 0.75 right is what we would expect we
would expect its facing direction to be
0.75
when the hero is is facing downward and
our question is just like why isn't that
happening now if we
go first of all just to reacquaint
ourselves with what's supposed to be
happening
we would expect inside our source
directory where we have the actual art
that if we look at a particular orphan
they're all they all should be the same
i mean in this case we're talking about
the hero
uh it's supposed to be like going down
from the top
so that's 0 that's 0.25 that's 0.5
and that's 7.75 right so those are the
directions that the hero is supposed to
be facing
and i don't actually
really okay so people in the chat are
actually telling me that there are some
big code gen bugs reported and fixed
lately
ugh um all right well that'll be fun
anyway uh so the point
here is just that we
we would like to start verifying a few
things so first of all we want to see
we want to make sure that when we are
facing downward
we're properly filling in 0.75
for the match element facing direction
so that's one thing we have to verify
and then we have to verify that in our
actual get asset table
so in get best asset
uh so here
we have to verify that we actually
have an entry for that right we have to
have an actual
entry for the uh the asset facing that
direction so the 0.75 asset has to be
in here as well and then we have to see
that you know make sure that it's
matching the best which it should
because it should be
a match index of 0.75 minus the match
index of 0.75
right so it should produce an absolute
value of zero which will be the highest
possible thing
right because it'll be minus zero um and
so
presumably that will just work right i
mean that's the theory anyway
and uh we don't know like
what's going on here but but that's the
hope
so there are some of the things that
could be intervening like
we're doing a total match difference
here so if for some reason like that
that one particular body sprite import
if there was some other bug on the
importing where it was setting the tags
where it set some other tags on that one
that it shouldn't have set
then the total match value might be
wrong or it might just not even be
in this hash line right
so there's definitely some things that
could be busted
uh that you know we don't know so we
have really no idea
uh uh what's broken and we just have to
start
looking through uh these these various
pieces
now i hope and i could be wrong about
this because if there really are a bunch
of new code gen bugs in visual studio
because
you know it's that microsoft quality
shining through
um we
we don't know if maybe that's a problem
here i mean i don't think it is because
we're messing with the asset tag system
so
it should be our bug is my that's my
assumption going into it is that it's
our bug
not not some weird compiler thing uh
but that means we should be able to to
build in debug mode right we should be
able to build in debug mode because this
is not like the weird lighting thing
where it's only happening in release
that we noticed there so in debug mode
here
right uh i should see when i when i uh
swing the the the fist downward what it
looks like uh
just just trying here yeah so when the
hero is facing downward you can see that
you still get this
scenario where it's not it's not
happening even in debug mode
which means that we should be able to
take a look and see what happens in that
matching process
uh by by checking out the the entity now
there's a lot of ways we could do this
but i'm just going to use like code
aided debugging here because it's going
to be the fastest thing i think for
debugging this which is to say
that i'm just going to go ahead and say
well look
why don't we just first right off the
bat
uh ask for a facing direction that's
greater than
0.6 right
um and that will allow me to just set a
breakpoint
so that i know that you know there's a
bunch of entities being rendered and i
don't really want to have to worry about
like getting to a particular one
or or stepping through this a bunch of
times and finding it i just want a thing
that'll like stop
on somebody who's trying to look this
thing up right
uh and so what i'm going to do is i'm
just going to make a piece of code there
that i know
checks for the things that i want to
check specifically
and then i'm going to go try and you
know let me see here
entity
uh and and then i'm just gonna try and
and set a break point there and step
through and see
like how that matching is happening and
you know i highly recommend that kind of
coding if you've never done it before
inserting code into the actual project
that does a bunch of sophisticated
detection potentially and then has a
place to pre
put a break point is just really handy
right
and there's really no downside to it you
can always remove it later
after you're done debugging so it
doesn't really matter
uh of course that that assumes i guess
that there
is a way to actually stop the code here
so
that is bad uh
do we need an update or something
um did they break pdbs again
george anyone it looks like we can't
actually
load um for some reason
i don't know why like debug-wise that's
not
that ain't happening um
yeah so did they break wow
they broke pdbs too are you kidding me
so this is why for actual work
like on my main dev machine
i just don't update the compiler i just
have a static copy of it
that i like pulled out the compiler
piece from and i just never update it
right
so george if i update remedy will i be
able to set
a breakpoint or not
this is not the latest
do you think if i updated to the new one
we would be okay because i can do that
right now
should be able to okay great
let's do that
all right i am going to go ahead and
grab
a new remedy then
that is as soon as i remember where the
thumb drive is here it is
uh so i apologize
for taking a quick break
but we will need to grab a new
remedy bg from the illustrious
itch.io
always a pleasure
and
let's see
this is the music by the way that goes
with handmade hero
da da
[Music]
okay so i have now downloaded
i also grabbed the new copy of four
coder because i saw ryan saying
something about the fact that it exists
now
i guess i don't actually know
um so
i tried to grab both of those and now i
will
will put over to the other machine
[Music]
let's see here if this worked i don't
know if it did
um and we can try to grab i won't try to
grab
four coder because that's working fine
like we don't need to
mess with that um but i will try to grab
the new remedy so here we are
in apps
remedy and
we will close that down
and we will
delete this one because we don't need it
anymore
and we will overwrite those replace
and now we have a new version of remedy
in theory anyway
and we'll deal with this later
so now possibly
uh if i re-run remedy maybe
we will be in a good state i don't
actually know
um
looks like i have to open my save file
for some reason
okay for some reason everything has been
rearranged
and i don't know uh why that is
but we'll just assume there's some
reason why that is
um and
i'll try to reconstruct this stuff at
some point i guess
i don't remember how we had it uh but at
the very least it's probably something
like this
the watch window was up here presumably
this stuff was down here
and then i had the disassembly somewhere
there it is
um and that was like probably down here
would be my guess
uh and
i don't know that we ever used the
register window
um
on stream very often but you know
all right um maybe i'll put that down
here all right so that seems good i
don't know how
how do i save this uh can i because it i
guess it got you know can i save this
here
or something save
handmade hero
like that
all right so we're just gonna assume
that that's good
uh we don't know but we're gonna assume
that that's fine
and we are then going to go uh
try to get this thing to break
uh in the piece of code that i created
that is the breakpoint
so right there um and it doesn't work
apparently
so i guess i guess we're just
i guess that's the end of it um
and and that means we don't really know
that that could be
visual studio i guess um
because we're running the right remedy
now
right this is 333 so
i don't know um
i can force it to break there
by just doing a you know
an n3 or something but the problem with
that
is presumably if the pdb isn't working
properly we wouldn't be able to step
through the code
so it doesn't actually matter um
that that that's the case so i'm not
sure
that that'll help but i mean i can try
it
right um
[Music]
i think that's the msvc intrinsic for
that
i don't i don't actually know
um it's been a while since i've typed it
in
whoa what is going on
there's just some really weird things
happening
that are just super strange
so the debug break there
does not trigger even though i would
think it would
um
mean unless it was actually getting set
to like negative
pi so it never actually goes over five
which which could be possible
um so so i guess i'll
i'll just mean let's let's just make
sure that
anything's working so this should
you know any time if any entity can
render at all it should break
right okay um
so
oh hey look and i can actually so so it
looks like i can
actually debug this now if i debug break
in it
well that's a good sign right i mean
that's a plus
so let's take a look here so for some
reason we never actually break
in this uh routine which would explain
why we're never picking
um why we're never picking that
element so i guess the next question
would be like how is facing direction
getting set
in that case right like like what are we
doing for facing direction it must be
getting set in a
to like a negative value or something
such that you know it we can't ever
pick the higher values so so let's find
out
uh because i don't know um what's going
on there
so
facing direction
[Music]
i mean that's pretty obviously setting
it to what we want for
like the orphans for example and you
know what
so strictly out of curiosity what's
happening
with those orphans um
like how how is it possible that
if we set this to 0.75 times tau
how is it possible that we're not
getting that like what if we
what if we hop over to one of those
orphans like what's
what did the or what do we see
like now i'd have no idea
and like the orphans aren't there
curiouser and curiouser like that's
where the orphan
would be right
um and so that's pretty weird did we
turn
off orphan placement or something
because right that that would be this
this would produce
the orphan and the fact that we have a
conversation
area right
would seem to suggest that the orphan
must have gotten placed
right like like some something's pretty
off there um
if i go to add orphan which uh
is in the entity gen
so uh this code here
it sure looks like there should be one
right um i don't know man
this is getting weirder and weirder uh
so all right
so that seems weird because we should be
at least getting
orphans placed at facing directions 0.0
uh
0.75 times tau which should have mapped
to 0.75 when you multiply back out tau
again
um well we divide by tau right like
effectively
so that's very suspicious
like i don't know what to make of that
um
but it's weird and i don't like it so
let's
go ahead and and i guess uh
look at what the actual uh hero code
sets the facing direction too
so okay so that that
would be the explanation there
probably right for no real reason we're
calling a tan two which will which would
map to like a negative
right um because
a tan two's range is not is not zero to
to tau it's it's uh
it's negative
it's negative pi to pi usually
um so that's probably why that
isn't working but why the orphans aren't
there
that i don't know so we're gonna have to
figure out why we don't see any orphans
that that doesn't really make
make good sense so yeah
facing direction wise
i guess that to me suggests that if
we're going to treat that as our facing
direction
range which is fine um
then this needs to be uh remapped
so that basically like you know there's
something along the lines of
probably this
so we'd we'd take this thing and
we would check to see if the facing is
less than zero
and then assuming that the facing is
we know that we actually want to map
that area
right that was less than zero to
the um the region that leads
up to one right so assuming it's less
than zero we know that now
um because we did 1 over tau 32 we're
going to get
like 0 to 0.5 and that'll work properly
but then instead of getting 0.5 to 1
we're actually going to get 0 to
negative 0.5
so we just need to start right
at 1 and subtract what we were doing
before or i guess i should say add
because it's negative
so as you get more and more negative
you're just sort of
uh subtracting away from one right
and i believe that should be what we
actually need
um to make the facing direction be
be proper there right um
what's the warning
oh sorry
[Music]
so that was all we needed um and now you
can see that it's correct
uh in debug mode here
um so that's all good but we still don't
know why we're not seeing any orphans
right so where did our orphans go so so
let's
before we go any further uh let's
let's go in there and see like where all
our orphans done gone
um because you know there's orphans in
each one of these rooms in theory has an
orphan in it
but we don't see any orphan now that
could because the tags on the orphans
are wrong
in a sense meaning that like
you know
that would be why they wouldn't be
drawing anything but we had a debug
break
in here and we didn't actually ever see
it hit even though their facing
direction clearly should have been
uh possible for that to occur
so that's a little bit weird so i'm
going to try setting another debug break
in here
uh just for fun what i'm going to do is
i just want to see
if we get a a orphan
something that we can identify as an
orphan so
when we do um trying to think of
how to do this the brain when we when we
set the brain
of these in the the place orphan call so
or add orphan i should say
um when we place the orphan here
so there's a there's even more things
that are weird so this is supposed to be
a collider
so you're it's supposed to take up space
right uh and you're not supposed to be
able to walk
like where it is so that's a little
weird too
i don't know what to make of that either
there's so there's just a lot of weird
stuff going on
here and i'm not sure how to assess it
it's it's very strange
so uh we want to probably look at this
code and see
like maybe we just set a breakpoint at
orphan assuming we can step into it i
don't know if we can or not
um but assuming we can step into it we
probably want to uh
just see why we can why can we walk on
that square as well so that we might
have other bugs but we'll see
so let's start by assessing the tags
first so what would the tags be here
there's an asset body and an asset head
for the orphans and if we look at the
place orphan call
it looks like the way this works is it
has that orphan tag name associated with
it
it adds the orphan tag and
then it doesn't add the orphan
name tag anywhere
okay it does at the very end so it adds
the orphan
tag and then the orphan name tag and so
when we're doing a place orphan you can
see that there's like a bunch of them
so if we look back at the hht i'm i'm
now
just gonna look to see um
what's actually going on here so for the
okay i think i see what's going on here
so the problem here is is actually
pretty simple so i think what we're
seeing
is the actual bodies so here are the
heads right but the bodies don't line up
with those
right so we probably just need the
bodies to be the same names as the heads
is probably what we need to do here so
what we want to do is go to
like
i'm assuming that they're numbered the
same i don't actually know
but if they're numbered the same then
probably what we do is we just go to
like
head orphan and we just look at what we
labeled those
so like head orphan one is sunny so we
just say
sunny two is lambert
uh then we have carla
cassidy drew
cline
[Music]
giles slade
baby viva
dylan
[Music]
rhoda
and laird
all right um
so yeah so assuming okay cannot find
build.bat i don't know why we're having
trouble
with that either uh with the build.bat
but it must be because it's not in the
right i don't know
who knows um so anyway
if we uh
if we go ahead now and run it i would
suspect
that we probably will have orphans um
i want to take a look though at uh
at this in release mode
and then we kind of still have the
problem of like what's the weird stuff
that's going on with the lighting so
we don't we don't really know like where
that's coming from so we're going to
have to
take a look at that obviously but um so
if we take a look here
um that's so strange i don't know what's
going
it must just be a really bad bug so now
we should have orphans and
and luckily we do have orphans um
right you can see them there and if we
look the only weird part is they're
facing the wrong direction
so so that's a little strange and i
don't know
why that would be because we looked and
it looked like they were pointing the
right direction
so something's up with that that place
orphan thing is placing them in the
wrong direction
we also now in theory um
[Music]
so if we want to uh
to actually add the proper connections
here we can so they can have the heads
as well
uh if we do an ad and we we do a
placement so i i don't even really
remember how this stuff works
um so this is base of neck right
and we can like adjust where it is
um i like i said don't really remember
very much about how this stuff works uh
but if we
if we swap between these right we can
add the
i guess is it top of head no it's it's
just default uh
for this one so i don't remember how
this stuff works at all
i guess the this is like the connection
on the thing but i i feel like we had i
thought we had a way
where we could see it um right where we
could we could actually look
and see but it looks like we're not
drawing those squares properly that's
probably part of the weird rendering
bugs we're experiencing
um but so we don't really know like
where the placement point
is on this thing which is a problem
so we're going to have to debug that but
like i said we can actually have orphans
now which is nice
so the problem uh at the moment
anyway is separate from all of that
the facing direction here is like
obviously wrong
you know what i'm saying so we said that
they were supposed to be
0.75 but that's not the facing direction
they actually have
so something's up with that and i have
no idea what
um if we look at place orphan and
there's this result facing direction
thing here
i don't know if if like maybe this is
getting overwritten
somehow right um
you know who knows so
when this gets set and i don't know
maybe it gets
the place entity stuff overwrites it or
something
we could try stepping through this and
seeing
does does somebody get
um does somebody like overwrite that
in some way when it actually goes to
place the entity like does it even use
that
and and you know or does it forget to
use that or something
so i believe in the room gen that's
where this happens
um where it goes through and places the
entities uh
there's like right like in here
you can see it finds a place to place
entity puts the entity down
uh here's where the the thing happens
right the entity gets placed
and you know yeah like it doesn't
it doesn't seem like anybody does that
right um
so yeah it adds the entity
it sets the facing direction but you
know this is this is already an
entity so it feels like the facing
direction should just be
used there is it possible that the
facing direction is not
packed is not saved
i mean i suppose that's possible
so if we look at like
if we look at where this is actually
being processed
[Music]
so
it looks like we're we're really not
talking about this value in very many
places
this right here
so that's not used
right so that's wouldn't be an issue
we don't care about this or that
so yeah i mean i don't know why that
would get overwritten anywhere
this all looks like basically
that's that's for the snake so we don't
care about that
this is for the hero
yeah so so i mean i don't know why that
would not
be set properly right because no one
clears it
and i don't see any reason why it
wouldn't
just work right
like i don't see i don't see the point i
don't i don't see you
i don't see the point where that would
get undone so so i would have been
expecting that to come through
properly uh and it's obviously not
because if it were we would be seeing
the entity pointing
downward i don't really see
much of a way around that
so let's go ahead and see if we can find
out
what the heck's going on there uh
let's switch to debug mode and let's
step through
if we can uh the the place orphan call
for example just you know step through
some of this if we can
you know i don't know if we can yeah so
it's like only that file
uh or only the setting breakpoints in
that particular file was a problem which
i'm not sure why but it just looks like
something was wrong with that
um so in here
here's us setting this thing
if we look at the entity that we create
it's got a facing direction right there
you know it's setting it
pretty much exactly the way you would
expect so there isn't anything
particularly weird going on there uh and
then when we place the entity
it doesn't look like it it modified it
at all um
so that you know still looks pretty much
correct right like i mean it i just
don't see
anything particularly weird happening
there uh
[Music]
so
i can't say i would know what would be
going on
i i can't have any idea like why that
would be a problem
so if we go back here and try to set a
break
um inside the entity drawing routines
now
uh and and we just look i guess so
somebody is is like wiping that facing
direction
at some point somebody's clearing it out
right
and so i'm assuming that if we went in
here and
we set a check where we said if facing
is greater than 0.5 debug break
this is what we did before and i'm just
assuming we would even
though we know we should see it we never
we never see that right we never see
that case get hit
and so i have to push downward to get it
to go which is what we would expect
right
so now let's try hopping up i won't push
downward let's try hopping up to an
orphan and we won't see that case get
hit i assume
and so then at that point i don't know
maybe we set a data break point and see
who clears it
because i don't know why it's getting
clear doesn't look like anyone should be
able to clear it
i mean and you know um and there's our
orphans right there right there
and we can see that they're pointing uh
the wrong direction
so uh so something is weird
there um
yeah that's a mystery so
what we need to do now is yeah just see
if there's some way that i can
uh check to see why we're getting that
clear
what i might do like i said is to see if
i can set a data break point there
where we can go in here we can look at
the result facing direction
which is this and just see if anyone
wipes it out um so i'm going to try
sending a breakpoint
and let's see
i need to know i mean i need to know the
address i don't know
if i can actually take the address here
let's see
if i can so uh result
facing direction did that work
uh i mean it
might have
the only problem is i i need that to be
well hopefully it just kind of snaps it
and
stays so um i'll try
okay so
it does get cleared and so you know what
i think i know what this clear is
didn't we introduce a clear um in the
entity
system so you can see uh if you
look at the entities did we put that
below the line
perhaps because here's the clear right
no it looks like that's above the clear
though
so all right well so who is this
let's look at the call stack um
here's zero size push size
so
so this is just reclaiming so this
this memory is getting vaped
which makes uh you know it makes sense
right because
that just gets pushed
into permanent store like that's just
temporary scratch storage and it's gonna
get
moved it's gonna get copied right into
the um into the backing store the world
chunks
and when it copies it into the world
chunks you know we
we don't
at that point the this version of it
will just get thrown away so this is
actually
exactly what you would expect so that
method of tracking it's not really going
to work
uh we would need something that actually
followed it through right
but at least we know you know that is
happening there so you know do we have
some kind of
bug in the chunk stuff maybe like
where we forgot about something we were
doing where the chunks get pushed on
and they're like not copying the whole
thing or something
uh so like the packed entity size
right um something like that
so i don't know that's like one option
you can see
discard everything after is like
it's right here and it's just getting
rid of this stuff
so really yeah it doesn't look like
there'd be anything
strange going on there
doesn't look likely
hmm all right
so
i can't think of any easy way to debug
this
other than to start to track the entity
through to see what actually happens to
it
so like
like we track it on when it gets packed
back up
and we look at what the facing direction
was i guess
right i mean i can't i can't think of
anything else to do
you'd track it you'd see what the face
interaction was
um when it gets packed
and then when you unpack it again so
each each individual time right
we would we would do that and
so i'm just gonna do that because i
don't see i don't see a shortcut here
we're just gonna have to check so i'm
gonna go ahead
and and just do like you know
that and when we go to create an
orphan uh since all of the orphans are
broken
right there's no there's no it's not
like only one of them
is bugged out i'm just gonna say when we
go through and add these orphans they're
all just going to have debug set to true
so any orphan that you know
um
oh it is oh
it is a fake entity okay well that's the
whole bug right there then
okay so those do create gen entities
which just have a temporary facing
direction which we
didn't copy when we actually create the
thing
all right well so that was stupid it's
just been too long
just been too long uh since we since we
did this
that's pretty much it so never mind
never mind about it uh so that's all
it's just when we're placing these
entities uh when we look at these gen
entities here
uh get entity at traversible
i guess
this picks it wait but when does this
actually work so
we go through the entities we find place
to put an entity group
we query we loop through them we
then try to get the entity
at traversable but
what does how does that work
pending entity creator
oh it's gen entity wow
so i thought that said get my like my
eyesight's so bad
at this point so that was the whole
thing when i read that i thought it was
just queer unity but that's actually the
thing that generates sanity
so that's the problem right
so when this says gen an idiot traverse
at
traversible it does the generator right
and it's supposed to i assume do this
and it just wasn't
right um
it's it's the gen entity call though so
it looks like we don't have to actually
even pass that
so i guess i guess it has to be done out
here
like that
looks like
okay so i think
that solidar quote-unquote bug which was
just us being stupid it's not much of a
bug um
so i think now we're just down to the
whatever that very strange
sort of spooky lighting
bug that only happens in release mode um
the people on the chat are saying visual
studio might be implicated in which i
hope not i hope it's just our bug
if it's a video visual studio bug i
don't know what we would do about that
exactly um but i guess that's where
we're at so
we will go and start looking at that uh
but yeah since it only happens in
release mode that's going to be a real
pain in the butt but that's where we're
at
um okay
so now we're good that's actually the
correct thing
um let me take a look and see
if i can
so there's the base of of uh neck
put in there um again the problem that i
have here is i just don't know
i can't see the little squares so we
should probably go debug why we're not
drawing
why we're not seeing those little cubes
um oh
right you just have to turn to debug
camera that's it okay so let's go
through and like actually put in the
alignment points for our orphans so that
when we hop around we actually have our
orphans because you know why not
so i'm going to go in here i'm going to
[Music]
i'm going to edit this
and so if i add the alignment point
here that's the alignment point
i should be able to place it like right
at the base of the neck which is like
there right uh
and
this one
uh now needs like a top of head
placement
right uh and that goes to the parent
doesn't it right
oh not top of head sorry default yeah
and those should be aligned kind of like
that
probably i don't know
probably like that i don't know
um and then we can save
this stuff right so we just hit save
yeah um and now so i think
like that little built-in editor that we
made you know that seems to have worked
okay
right does look about right um
and and now we have we have our orphan
right it looks like that's a little off
though right like the place where the
head is placed looks a little
off because you can see the neck doesn't
quite work there so i feel like we want
it
to be down a little bit maybe so let me
i'm not sure who's more the problem
there but probably this one
i'm not sure how we're going to deal
with that it looks like
you know they're gonna slide a little
bit too much relative to each other
we haven't really thought much about
this right but
oh and that looks
yeah that looks like that's too high
as well so like yeah okay so i probably
screwed this up a little bit
so that's the placement there
this maybe needs to be
done slightly differently i'm not sure
how that's supposed to work though
yeah i think i don't quite get it like
this is
offset a little too much isn't it
or maybe not my recollection of how this
system works is not great but you know
these two points are for
aligning um
the the the different boxes here right
so
you can see me showing the uh
the different pieces of this so this is
the base of neck point which is where
that's supposed to like attach
this is the attach point for this thing
and the
offset is for uh making sure they move
at sort of slightly different
uh rates but i just don't know
like it seems like there's it seems like
you also need like an offset parameter
which we don't actually have
but i don't know um
so i'm not sure what we really do about
that
like it may be that this was just not
quite right i don't know it may be that
that needs to be lowered more
but again it seems like it seems doesn't
seem like this would work properly
because no matter what i would do here
i don't see how that's ever going to
produce a reliably aligned thing
and
you know because as you move to the side
right i mean that that looks pretty good
i guess i don't know
but it's tough fake fake 3d is hard
right
i mean hard from an art standpoint
because it's hard to make it
look 3d when it's not um
so
all right um
and we don't know maybe that's good
seems okay
gonna need more light can't see our
orphans they're in the dark
you
all right i mean it sort of works
i'm not complaining much too much
okay
all right um
yeah save okay
so yeah did that work did it not work
who the heck knows um
but that's what we're going with and
oh it looks like there's more
i feel like the scale is not right on
some of these two so we
probably should um
we probably should also be like setting
the scale
of some of these differently than they
are
um
which i'm not exactly sure i think the
scale of
the actual orphan gets set in the actual
code somewhere because
it's it's like how big the entity is
supposed to be
um i don't really remember but you know
that
that seems like maybe something we need
to do but anyway
yeah that seems fine uh
and so there's some more orphans how
many orphans did we actually place in
here we placed a lot of orphans
so wait did i miss a bunch of orphans
then potentially did were there orphans
down in these rooms too
no
so there are not orphans
there are not orphans in a bunch of
these places for what that
or whatever that's worth which is
probably very little
so where are the other orphans wasn't
there like a baby didn't we
place a didn't it say place a baby
somewhere maybe we didn't actually place
the baby anywhere
i thought the baby was placed somewhere
so i'm not sure
all right
there we go so i think we've got our
orphans though now
so that's nice um and that should all be
saved out so in theory now that'll just
work
um and it'll be good uh
and oddly now similarly like for some
reason
we don't have the light bug happening
is there some weird thing where like the
fact that we were picking
on a non-existent bitmap forced the
graphics card to do something bad and
that's why the lighting was busted
i mean it's possible to see you know i'm
not gonna
say that that's particularly likely but
you know i mean it could be
right so it
looks like everything is nominally
working
we have our orphans we have our weird
little you know skull dudes we have some
crappy lights
that we have placed there and
you know that all seems fine
yeah all right i mean seems all right
everything seems to be working okay
so
how much time is left in this stream
that i may wrap it up for today because
i guess that's basically everything that
we were trying to do
um is there a way i can provoke this
lighting bug again
though
somehow i don't seem to there we go
so i guess we can start looking at that
uh in the time we have remaining because
i'm like i don't
we didn't do like it should not have
fixed that right like it that seemed
weird
um and so i don't understand what's
going on there and
it's very peculiar like now it's just in
that state
and now it's not
right like like what is going on it's
very strange
um so i'm not sure exactly what's
happening there but i do think that you
know that might be something that where
we would benefit from running under
a graphics debugger so we could see like
who what is happening there there might
be some
some fairly obvious stuff uh that's
going on there that we could fix
right um but it's definitely like a
weird kind of
intermittent thing that that i don't
know what is actually happening
like like why is that happening
sometimes and it's it's very very
strange
and you can see that it's like a
massively over bright so it's like the
lighting has and
it has air like nan's in it or something
like something weird is happening there
uh and and i don't actually know what
that's from
what time how much time do we have
i think we have like
30 minutes
it's time to stretch everyone's stretch
stretch right away
stretch stretch
everyone stretch um
fred and luck said if i remember
correctly this bug was introduced when
you added the fade on load
what fade on load there there is
no fade on load is there
i i literally have no idea what you're
talking about we don't have a fade on
load do we
it also kind of seems to like
yeah i mean there's a number of ways we
can now start to to
track this down right
um
so let's see so uh we
don't anymore store any lighting stuff
in the end of these
as far as i know right you can see that
that this stuff
we don't really have anything stored in
there
um and if we look at like
where the sim region and world chunk
stuff like pulls stuff in
um i'm pretty sure we don't have any
like we got rid of the stupid stuff
where we were uh
where we were tracking like lighting
entities
i think um i don't know maybe we didn't
but but i hope we did
because i thought we were we did that um
so then like begin world change
uh ensure region is unpacked
so it looks like
yeah it looks like we don't do any of
the like stable
entity slotting or any of that stuff
anymore right so so don't think there's
anything
implicated like you know
i don't think there's anything
implicated
with storing these entities or like
having them persist stuff because we got
rid of that stuff
because we don't actually need um
for our lighting system no longer
requires any of that
uh so i think that's all gone and so
we're really just talking about the
lighting
uh being you know
being in the re in the in the standard
way that's getting pushed down like
something is getting screwed up in there
somehow
right and we just don't know
how
so yeah i guess what we should probably
do here is just
add a bunch of debug checks to
put in debug breakpoints wherever we see
like a lighting value go to some
ridiculous
thing so like maybe
check like
maybe we just want to start like adding
some some
lighting debug checking where we can
look through it
and just see you know what
is there weird stuff happening right
so i don't know uh so let's take a look
um
so i guess i don't know yet you can see
us here
one thing that would be interesting to
know is like does this is this have any
differences
in terms of like whether or not it's
threading
or not right um because this is the type
of code
where you could have threading bugs
pretty easily
uh if we take a look at like where we
call internal lighting core
uh you can see here where it passes
uh the lighting queue right here if we
were to like vaporize that
that would prevent uh any
multi-threading so we could also see to
what extent it might have something to
do with
with the light you know with a
multi-threading issue
um i'm not sure why it would because the
threads don't really communicate with
each other
in any particular way so i feel like we
should be able to get this to reproduce
itself even without the multithreading
but
you never know so if we do do letting q
equals zero here
and recompile this will single thread
the lighting
and so it will be much slower as well
but
and you know like yeah i could believe
that there was some kind of weird
threading thing going on there
uh because the reason i say that is just
because
you know one there's a couple different
things that can happen in debug versus
release builds
so one thing that can happen in debug
versus a release build is that there's
actually just a cogen difference and
that's the problem the other thing is
that a debug build is much slower
right so if you're talking about some
kind of a
of an obscure multi-threaded problem
that occurs
you can see how maybe you would end up
in a situation where
if your code runs slow enough the
multi-threading race condition
doesn't ever actually happen because the
code is too slow to ever
actually have it be a probability that
it will occur but when you
then run the code more quickly you find
that it does
right um so it could be something like
that
uh but we don't know because it's an
intermittent bug we can't
we can't reproduce it when okay so there
you go
so running the lighting single threaded
doesn't change this
right we know that so so that more or
less proves
uh that it isn't that because if we turn
off the lighting queue
it still happens
yeah there needs to be so someone needs
to modify
insobot so that anytime
anyone mentions rust
uh it it just times that person out for
60 seconds
right so if you say rust you just get a
60 second
auto timeout right
um so it doesn't
look like threading is particularly
implicated there
it looks like some kind of computation
initialization
problem is happening uh
or maybe like an accumulation problem
where if the time step is too large
you get some kind of a weird you know
state happening
i don't know uh
when we look at how the blending works
and so on right it looks like that's
just set to a fixed value we're not even
basing it on the frame rate or anything
at this point
it's literally just blending at a noise
threshold
so like it shouldn't matter what the
frame rate was there because
it's not actually using that um you know
it doesn't actually care
so that also not does not seem
particularly implemented
uh sorry does not seem particularly
implicated so i'm again
not really sure where to start looking
so what i guess i will do is try to add
something
in here that just can look through
and try to see if there's anything
particularly strange
um
i mean i suppose one thing that's
interesting is like in the update
lighting call you can see that there's
sort of like a
a case here right where
it does this every so often it does this
when
um the grid or the fundamental unit
stuff
changes and you assume that only happens
once at startup but you know
if that was happening multiple times
maybe something weird was going on i
don't know
even that doesn't seem it doesn't seem
super plausible to me um
so so i don't know about that
um
so yeah so if we look at where the
lighting information is stored
right we've got a thing um
in here where we're like okay we've
got uh
when we call the internal lighting core
right we've got the light atlases
that we're writing into and what we want
to do you know
is we would want to look at the spec
atlas or the diffuse atlas
and i guess we want like a spec
like we want a thing that will loop
through the spec atlas
and the diffuse atlas any time we want
and just see if anyone's written
anything absurd in there
right so we should be able to do
something like
in light atlas have a debug
function right so you know we've got
these light atlases right and they're
called the texels um
have something in the light atlas where
it would just say
look um
if you call this function we go through
the entire atlas
we know that's slow and stupid but it's
just for debugging
we'll make a function that will just do
a
uh validate atlas or something
um where it will just go through and
just check everything
and then we can just like spam calls to
this
like everywhere and so we should be able
to find the place
uh where it where it porks out
right um
so if we do like a thing that just as
dumb as possible
right just loops through everything um
like the entire atlas the whole thing
uh which you know i don't even remember
how to do
at this point but if we just loop
through the whole thing
and we say something like uh
get light atlas texels uh
for a particular location so
i mean maybe like this sort of thing
right here oops like get tile
uh unclamped yeah
so we can do something like get tile
unclamped although actually i suppose we
don't even really need to do that
we could just say look we know how large
it is
uh so if we just do like get light atlas
texels
we should be able to just loop through
however many textuals there are
right so if we say like
taxal counts equals tell me how many
there are
uh and then say like texel index is zero
textile index is less than textile count
plus plus textile index right um
so if we just leave through all the
texels and
we look at them
uh if we assume that these texels are
all
this like atlas texel which you would
think they would be
right so if we get all these
and we just loop through them
uh i mean
that should do it right so now we've got
our texel
we can just do like all right
so
if we look at the red the green and the
blue channel each
we should be able to check to see
if these values are sane right
so we pass a component here and
we can just say like if c is less than
zero
or c is greater than you know
a thousand right
if either of those two things is true uh
then we can
stop right like i think we have a
where's our assertion i don't even know
um
yeah then i'll just do assert
horrible very lousy
stupid code you are
not programmer
learn the variable um
and so in here we can just say all right
let's validate these components
um each of the components of the texel
something like this
and in theory that should just die
immediately whenever we
hit something um that's broken
it is value
um oh wait so
that's not quite right sorry so light
atlas texel here
is actually a thing that it retrieves
when you do this so actually these are
just v3s
um it's more like that
right um
so i don't know i think that is roughly
what
we would want
uh not 100 sure because i just kind of
hacked that in there
it's been a long time since we looked at
it but basically what we want is
something like that
i can now go in here and throw that in
and just see i mean we could just now
say like all right
so
take the spec atlas and the diffuse
atlas
do a little builds
run the codes uh and now
yeah so
you know i don't actually know if this
is working or not but hey it just
triggered
right uh which is good
and so in theory we can see uh
like we have the ability to detect when
it actually happens
right now we don't actually know that
that's true because
we don't know if maybe that just
triggered unnecessarily here but
but it looks like it at least sort of
did
so another thing we could do
um
is make it so that we can continue
running after that happens
so that we can see uh
i mean i guess here's what i would say
like like maybe we change this slightly
so this is like a b32
uh and the results is like
something like this
uh and then we say okay
oops
i don't think you can actually do that
but um
i can do this
so we just like and all this crap
together and then we return
so now what we would do is
when we do oop i don't know why i typed
that in
so now we would do is when we validate
one of these things
um
it's basically just gonna say okay
uh tell me one way or the other if this
worked or if it didn't work
and then we can take some action based
on that so like if validate atlas
right like if you can't validate the
atlas
we do something um and
so one of the things i could do here is
just add some
kind of like you know
break right um
that's not right it needs to be in both
of those
okay so if we can't validate the atlas
uh we need to like maybe we could just
print something out
you know we could do like an output
debug string i don't know if i can
actually do that here can i
no i can't um
if we just put forth something
uh that says that the atlas is busted
like using a debug uh out
of some kind right
so in here we could do a debug value
which is just do you think the atlas is
valid or not
um and
you know like some stuff happens and
then
a thing and whatever so
uh
if we for example put in the lighting
panel
just like a thing that was like could
you validate the atlas
or something like suppose we did
this um spec
valid
diffuse valid
and again all i'm trying to do here is
uh is just make sure that this trigger
actually does work so i can visually see
that the trigger happens at the same
time
that the bug happens that's all i'm
looking for
so now in theory like if i look
at the lighting system you can see that
it says that it's valid
right and it just switched to non-valid
just like that
and of course the bug hasn't happened so
that seems bad
um
so i don't know what to make of that
there's two
possible reasons for that
one reason is that uh
actually these bounds are too too tight
like maybe
like it's occasionally negative here or
something
right um the other
possibility is that there's actually
invalid values floating around
out there and they just don't
contaminate things normally so it
actually was
that actually is catching a problem uh
that is actually related and we should
pay attention to it and i don't know
which of the two it is uh unfortunately
what i will do here is widen the zero
bound
more i'll i'll make these more
ridiculous just to see
if it still happens right
and so i'm just trying to provoke it
there
a little bit uh and we'll see
all right
so literally just doing that
it changes sometimes right you saw it
change to zero
and i have no idea why right
but we really should not be seeing
lighting values in that range i don't
think
unless i'm misremembering like
how this system is actually functioning
it is true that the spec atlas
is like
i feel like the spec atlas is is no the
second
is persistent so i feel like it should
never
be out in that kind of ridiculous range
um
so i do i do think that's indicative of
the fact that there's probably something
bad going on where some values like on
the edges or something maybe
uh are are busted
so let's suppose we do again like
maybe we check a tighter bound now
and see it should be zero more often
uh so there's a couple of things going
on there so so
yeah maybe the check is bad the other
thing i was thinking is you know it
might be that the entire we don't
compute the entire atlas every time
either like i don't remember if we
intentionally leave
some of the atlas unprocessed but it is
kind of true that
it is kind of true that like
assuming that i'm checking this properly
it seems like we
maybe aren't processing all of our
textiles the way we should be
like something seems busted there
uh and i'm not exactly sure i know
you know why we would ever be actually
getting those problems
like it doesn't seem like that's that
doesn't seem sane
um and so so something's up
with that and i don't know what
yeah yeah i don't really know
uh also our trees are missing i should
guess so we should go fix that
part of the um for the tags as well
does our intro still work by the way
i haven't checked it in a while
it doesn't look like it does so our tags
for the intro
are also busted so we we should probably
finish the tag stuff
we can do that sorry in this wait so the
trees and the and this are both missing
and then we have the lighting bug and
then i think we're back to good
um and hey we also have our orphans now
we should also put our furniture in and
such
and start decorating the orphanage
um so yeah so i don't know those tags
don't look like they're working right
on the intro as well so
so we'll have to take a look at that
let's go ahead and do q a for now
stretching
yes the uh well so it depends what you
mean max trucks
about um
about rendering the computed light
bounce into texture
so at the moment we just do the lighting
on the cpu
we haven't ported it over to the gpu yet
because
it's not really quite as good as we
probably would want it to be before
moving it over there
um although obviously we would get a
pretty massive speed increase probably
if we did but um
so we don't render the computed light
bounces into a texture
in the sense that we don't use the gpu
to do it
but we do render computer light bounces
into a texture in the sense that we do
use the cpu to generate a texture that
has the light bounces
right so depending on what you mean by
the question
the answer might be yes or no but but
the process
is we have cpu side lighting that
does a bunch of bounce lighting and then
it renders
uh it produces a texture that it sends
to the graphics card
that the graphics card then samples for
the lighting
uh and there's no reason we can't do
that on the gpu
we just don't yet because as soon as you
move something to the gpu it becomes
even harder to debug
so you know typically for something like
this
i'm always going to do a cpu
implementation first and i'm only ever
going to move it to the gpu like at the
end when i when i want to like
uh provide the po the most optimized
possible
path uh but you know so for right now we
just do
a cpu uh implementation
and it is slower it is slower than it
would be if it was on the gpu
uh that said the cpu side one is
not too slow right now and it's much
slower than it
will be because even the cpu side one
can be sped up by probably a factor of
four
at this point because we're it's like uh
it's still operating on floating point
textile values
which are just completely unnecessary uh
and and massively like cash inefficient
right
so uh when we decide to kind of bake
some of that stuff a little bit more
for shipping even the cpu side one could
probably be made to
run fast enough when we when we trim out
the fat
um but we haven't like
done any of that
um
[Music]
uh
do i ever suffer from decision paralysis
when making a new feature
uh not really no um
i do have problems when if i'm trying to
like get a really high quality results
on something though of a similar thing
which is just that if you
if you imagine like
if you imagine the equivalent
of of decision paralysis
for exploratory coding where you're like
trying lots of stuff and nothing seems
to be
good enough right um
that is sort of similar it's just it's
happening
in the actual act of programming as
opposed to
the act of sitting around thinking about
it right
um and the
problem with stuff like that is there
really isn't a solution for it
the only thing you can do is just keep
working on the problem
or like you know shake up your thinking
you know try some crazy stuff or or
leave it for a week and then come back
to it and see you know you can do stuff
like that
but your only other option is to just
lower your standards right
so if you have to ship something and you
just have to lower your standards you
can do that
but there's no really other solution the
solution to
decision paralysis is just start typing
like like pick something and implement
it because you'll learn something
right so there's a solution to decision
paralysis there's no real solution to i
can't find an answer that satisfies me
um even with exploration there's really
not a lot you can do you can you know
you can ask other people for advice you
can
uh try some random experiments that are
wackier than what you're
doing you can read a book you know you
can you can try to like shake your brain
into different places to see
to force you to think about the problem
from different angles but you know if
it's not coming together it's not coming
together so i have
that happen sometimes um
and when you're working on a hard
problem you know that happens sometimes
and so so you know
when do i plan on releasing stroke
galaxy um as soon as it's ready
i mean you know was the bug mostly
in the start area once you start walking
it was better um
i don't know it seems like it's more
uh random and hiccuppy
so i don't know
george says for the breakpoint handmade
entity.cbp in
line 295. i believe what we're seeing
was the dll wasn't yet loaded
yeah i don't know if i believe you but
we can check
um so like here's it running right
um let's see
uh and so
maybe it was just like we were in a bad
state just then uh so where was that
code i don't remember it was right here
all right so it's working now so it
might have just been i don't know why we
were seeing a question mark
on it the entire time because it should
have loaded like right away
but either way um
it seems like it has worked itself out
of that
at least to a certain degree so so that
seems good
right
can you please go into more detail about
the lighting floating point and caching
efficiency
um sure so what i was trying to say
there was just that
uh while we're working on developing the
lighting
and until we're like okay we're pretty
much done with whatever we're gonna do
there
i didn't want to try to use a more
compact representation
for the lighting values
because like floating point i mean
f32 i mean obviously you could be even
sloppier and use doubles
but like f32 is like the laziest
encoding
you can use right because it takes 32
bits to represent a value that
honestly needs probably at most
10 or 12 16 tops
right so you know that
when you're storing rgb as three 32-bit
values
you're placing at least a 2x multiplier
on the cache usage right
every time a text has to be read in
you're reading at least twice as much
data
possibly more because if you just use 10
bits for everything you could fit them
into a single 32-bit value even right
so the way in which the lighting system
is running right now
is sort of intentionally probably
significantly slower than it needs to be
simply because we're forcing it to
process
massively more memory for for no real
reason other than because we don't want
to worry
about encoding problems we we don't want
to
have artifacts from the way that we
encode our textures
at the same time that we're working on
like lighting quality stuff and whatever
so
it's basically just a way of of reducing
the amount of possible places where you
can have bugs
and so that's why the lighting is
currently it's very piggy in terms of
cache usage there
what's the best game soundtrack you've
ever listened to i mean
probably monkey island too
um
like legend of zeldas is pretty good
like koji kondo music is very good but
sometimes it's hard to get like a
soundtrack to it per se
monkey island 2 is kind of hard of a
soundtrack as well because it's dynamic
you know both
both of those are dynamic scores so
so the koji condo and michael z land i
think
uh might be the person who the monkey
island one
uh verona chorus says hey you mentioned
programs used uh to do
port usage could you name some so i can
check them out i can explain the extra
report notation on ups
example one times pox for c-mob l
uh yeah i mean i think we've gone over
this before so i would search the
archive
um but it's pretty straightforward uh
to to do this stuff you just it just
takes a little learning
so um
if you go to ups dot info
uh that's where you can get all your
micro op tables from
right so uh if you take a look
uh if you go to upside info and you
bring up the table
and you look at something like you just
said see marvel right
uh the instructions will be listed
on the side they'll be listed for each
type of instruction because
for example like because uh
the x64 is not really a risk
architecture
like it is sort of a risk architecture
internally
in the sense that the micro ops are kind
of risk but the actual instructions that
you
feed it are are fairly complicated so
for example in a typical risk
architecture
you know and i'm not a hardware person
so you know take this with a grain of
salt but
if someone says to me that this
architecture's risk then i usually don't
think of instructions as being able to
like
use a memory address as a location
i mean as an operand for anything other
than just like a loader store
so so you wouldn't expect like an ad for
example
to be able to take a memory address that
you're using to add from
um but like something like x64 you can
do that like almost every
instruction that does anything
like that like an ad or something
can have an operand that's like not a
register it can have an operand that's
like an address in memory
right and not just an address in memory
but like an address in memory encoded
with actual like offsets and stuff
right so it's it's fairly complicated so
so xcz4 is kind of a
sisk instruction set kind of right
and so when you talk about a particular
instruction
you can't really talk about what
microops the instruction has
you have to talk about how many micro
ops
um and which types of micro ops a
particular instruction
and operand set have because even though
you take something like c
mob l and you say well that's an
instruction called cmov l
it's actually many different types of
instructions depending on what the
addresses were
right what the operands were so what you
can see here is
this lists all of the possible
combinations of operands that you might
have
like 32-bit register 32-bit memory
location
and what you can see is that the
micro-op breakdown is actually different
depending on which one there are and you
can see the difference
the difference is that in general if
there's a memory operand
it has a another part to it right so so
there's one part that's always there
and then depending on whether there's a
memory operand as the second operand
then there's another you know one here
so you first have to look at the side
and decide
what you're actually calling so if for
example you happen to be calling
a 64-bit register um cmov so that so the
the destination is going to be a 64-bit
register
and the source the second source operand
is going to be
a uh a memory location that's 64 bits
then you're looking at this particular
one right
and then the way to read this which is
the question like how do i read the port
usage
uh the so you've got a couple different
pieces
you can separate them by the plus each
part of this that's separated by a plus
is
its own micro-op right
so when you see this plus this these are
two
separate micro-ops that we're talking
about here
the one in both cases and the times is
how many micro ops we're talking about
in this particular category
so we're talking about one micro op
being issued from
this category and one micro app being
issued from this category
and they will both be issued right so it
requires both of them
then you get the little p notation here
the p notation tells you which ports it
goes on
so this is saying one micro op
that can issue on and this is read as
either so the p with the numbers is
either
one micro op that can issue on either
port zero
or port six your choice so if either one
is free it could issue
plus one micro op issued on either
port two or port three right
so that is how you read those
so if you want to know what is required
to execute this
you know that the front end will turn
this c-mob
l into two micro-ops
one of those micro-ops will be able to
issue
on ports two or three and the other one
we'll be able to issue on ports zero and
six
i believe but i don't know
that this is not in any particular
order the reason i say that is because
like logically speaking
this cmov l would have to load
the memory operand first i would assume
before it can do anything i mean i don't
really know that that's true
um so don't quote me on that
but you would expect so i can just tell
you ports two and three
on a skylake processor which is what's
checked here
ports two and three are memory
processing ports
so the ports two and three are used to
do the load
right there they used to like load the
information
into the processor and so you wouldn't
expect it to execute this micro up first
the zero six which is the one that's
actually doing the cmov
right you would expect this to execute
first and yet this is written second
so i i don't think
that that these are like when they write
it out i don't think that these are
written in
order they're just saying these are the
two things that will have to happen
right and they'll happen in whatever
order the processor thinks they have to
happen in but i don't think they're
trying to tell you that order here
right so
uh hopefully that answers that part of
the question and then the other part of
the question was like
how do i analyze these so like if you go
to godbolts uh
i can quickly show you what you set
um for that uh so if we take a look at
godbolt and we just say
okay like i wanna know what the port
usage is for one of these things
um the easiest way to do it because
intel has now decided to stop supporting
ayaka
unfortunately even though it was better
than this thing because this thing is
kind of crappy
i don't know if they've got it made it
better yet but if you select
a modern version of clang so x86 64
clang
version 9 and up probably has it i would
i would think
i don't really know um but if you go on
here
and you select a version of clang and
you're compiling for clang
you should then be able to add a tool
so in this little drop down here where
you do add tool
this llvm mca thing that stands for like
probably i you know i don't really know
what stands for but i think it stands
something like micro
micro code analysis or micro
architecture code analysis or something
like that
um if you add that tool
that will actually give you the port
breakdown
and it's not as easy as i'm making it
look because actually it's not
quite what you think it is over here and
we
talk about that in a second um but
for just just in terms of like
what you just in terms of of like
looking at how the port breakdown goes
just to start with this is what you know
this is what you were asking for right
so this is the thing
that goes and says okay um
here are the uh here are the
instructions
and this first part here uh and it will
tell you some stuff
about like you know stats basically
so this instruction it's saying uh is
going to
need three micro ops to issue
it's going gonna have a latency of two
cycles it's gonna have reciprocal
throughput of one cycle
uh and in terms of whether or not it
uses loads or stores
it does not use a load it does
potentially use a store
um and does not have any side effects
right and you can see here
like the the may store and may load
you know these are all going to load
they're loading because of this right
and so on so that's the first part
not super useful but you know it's like
a heads up view
or whatever uh then you get down to here
and this is one of the most annoying
things in the world and i have no idea
why they did this but you've got ports
numbered zero through seven
on skylake and they helpfully labeled
those
two through nine like all you guys had
to do was put the skx divider and the
xsp divider at the end
and this would have worked but no so you
get to mentally in your head
translate the actual listing
here like as if it was shifted down by
two
right um so it's like
right um
but basically what you do then is you
can read this and these are the ports
across here and they line up with these
so port zero is actually two
so the numbers that are in here are all
shifted so p06 is actually p28
on this right so sucky
um but that's just the way it is this is
why i say
iaco is way better it's way easier to
read this thing's really hard to read
for this reason
and no one cares but so we go over here
to resource pressure per iteration
and what you see is these
numbers here
[Music]
what they represent is like the chance
that the micro op got shoved into this
port
is usually sort of the way to look at it
i mean it's again it's kind of hard to
explain
what it's trying to show you um but
but just to kind of make it a little
more concrete
um what they're trying to say is like if
we were to just keep running this code
like all the time like we're just
running in this code running and running
and running it running it running it
running it running it running it
um where would we end up assigning
these things like and it's not really
it's not
a percentage chance because you can see
it's greater than one
and it's called resource pressure right
so
what that's basically saying is if we
ran it and ran it and ran it and ran
it right how much is it like lined up
behind
this port so it would max out like port
six and nine right uh and
and to the lesser extent these other
ports that's what the one in there means
right and it's kind of hard to
understand with something like this
because it's not a loop
and this is where the next part comes in
so
this is meant for analyzing loops and
you can see that up here you can see
like iterations right well iterations of
what like this is
not a loop it's going to treat your code
as a loop whether you like it or not
because it's made for analyzing loops
and it's going to tell you a bunch of
stuff
like the reciprocal throughput of the
loop right
which again you're trying to get that up
to
you're trying to get that down to the
lowest number of cycles you can and
you're trying to get the instructions
per clock up as high as you can
micro ops per cycle like like i said you
can usually execute four micro ups per
cycle
sometimes you can execute even more than
that um if they're fused
but uh in general four is where a
skylight is going to top
out so 1.61 means you could
you know you could potentially if you
really happen to really luck out and you
hit something the pros can do perfectly
and you wrote the code really well
you could get that all the way up to
four right
so let's see how to do the actual loop
constructs
um lvm mca i never remember
what the pound defines our um
uh they're in here somewhere
here it is uh
all right so in here you have to do
like a thing where you you stick this
garbage um in here
so let's suppose we actually want to do
this for real
uh what we would end up with is like
some kind of a for loop
right um so
and and the for loop usually you know
usually it looks something like this
uh and
so let's suppose we're doing uh some
something straightforward so account
um and value i don't know
and we do a while count minus minus like
float results equals zero
and this is result plus equals you know
value
uh so this is just like returning like a
running sum or something
right um and so we basically just wrote
something you know that was gonna have a
loop
um and you can see the loop here and
uh you know it's got like the setup code
or whatever's gonna happen
and then it just kind of like goes
through and does like
uh repeated edition right so
um we come in here we
we do the check to make sure we should
enter the loop assuming that we do enter
the loop
uh we do some garbage uh
we grab the thing we're gonna do we we
add it um
and then we store it back out to the
stack and of course this is unoptimized
code so
it's just gonna generate a bunch of
unnecessary instructions so you know we
can just tell it you know you can clean
that up
you know don't don't do that uh do
something more sensible and now you can
see like a fairly
reasonable loot it's not great um but
it's
you know it's reasonable you can see
we're just adding
from a memory location we're bumping you
know the
the uh the memory offset
each time and we are then checking to
see if we need to exit the loop
right okay um so now we got to get this
thing working
um this is supposed to be
over here yeah
there we go hopefully that's maybe sort
of right
um
and i'm not sure did i do that wrong
it's saying that it's not
valid
but but what what's invalid what did i
do wrong there is that not isn't that
what you wanted
oh um right i've got to do
[Music]
like a foo on both of them
so is it that
it's beginfu enfu right did that not
does that not work did i do something
wrong would it what have i done wrong
i never remember how to get this part
working
um i would love for it to work but but i
never really know why it doesn't work
and
you know like i said i i was much more
happy with ayaka
and i don't know why this didn't work
but it's supposed to work
um somehow that way let's try a real
search engine
i.e not bing
looks like the same crap though
i'm just going to search for those
strings and see if i can find
an example because what does it say it
says found an invalid region
end directive but what's invalid about
it did it not
does it not like my begin one
i also don't know why i can't see them
on here like shouldn't they be on here
somewhere
uh
oh you think i have to write the
function why would i have to write the
function name
i mean i don't see why i just write the
this is just all this is an identifier
that
that tells it what the output is right
you know what i'm saying um
so let's take a look and see if i can
find like something
that shows how this is supposed to
happen because
you know they probably just changed it
or something since they wrote the docs
or who knows what
this is the ubuntu man page okay
that's the same example and that
definitely didn't work
so i don't know i don't know why we're
not getting any love here from
lvm mca begin um
i mean does it is it needed to be inside
the brackets
it does what
so it just wanted them to be inside the
brackets but that's
not good right it needs to be outside
the brackets
um because if it's not outside the
brackets
then you don't include the port usage
for the comp jump
uh so it needs to be there so i'm not
sure
like and if i put it here then it
includes it
it would include the enter
code which you don't want it to do um
so i don't understand and it looks like
even that doesn't work so like i can
you know if i put that here i have to
put the other one inside the brackets
i don't know maybe i can do this just
putting more brackets around it help
yeah this is why i say i don't like lvm
mca i don't really you know maybe it's
just that i don't understand it as well
enough but like this is a pretty simple
thing i'm asked to do
it doesn't give me any constructive
advice on why i'm just trying to say
please do this loop like that's all i
want it to do
right but it doesn't seem capable of of
doing that
uh and i don't actually know why right
so
um
yeah so just to be clear the reason so
this
doesn't really help you because that's
not going to time the loop
that's not going to show the loop right
so you can see that the only thing
that's captured there is the add ss
but the problem is the loop is actually
this
right so you need you need it to have
the end marker
has to be outside the loop right
now we can be a saucy salamander and
just
get rid of the loop right um so for
example
like we could do this couldn't we um
and and then we would just say hey
like i know how is programming work a
lot
and i could just say like loop top here
right
and then i just say like okay
you know if if you're really going to be
that way and you don't understand a loop
well i know how to write a loop because
i am programmer right
um so what i could do is i could just
say okay put the
analysis on this end of the thing and
make it like
go back up to the loop top like that
right
and have it just do ads and then what
we'll do is we'll just
branch around the loop jump right we'll
just say okay
um if that's what you want then inside
here we'll say
if count minus minus
[Music]
you know is greater than zero then go to
the loop top
right or something um
so now we've got it actually working
right even though it's not what i was
trying to do
but you know at least it it maybe did
something
i guess right um
and if we look here at what it actually
ended up putting
out uh for some reason
it it actually took these two so somehow
this floated
up above here
i don't know it just seems like this is
kind of busted like
like that's not what we wanted we wanted
it to start uh
below there so i don't know can we make
it do that there we go
so that's correct now but this is
annoying so you can see this is annoying
i don't love it ayaka was better
but it's discontinued so oh well um
but now if you look at it you can
understand the port pressure
part a little bit better right um so now
you can see like all right
add right if we take a look at what
happens
on the ad um if you go back here you can
see that it's an ad ss call
that means we're going to have to turn
on sse right because it's a
it's an sse call what you can see here
is that
ads operate right
these are the ports that they can issue
on so ads can issue on zero
or one this floating point add condition
on zero one
and you know is it a memory operand or
isn't it a memory operand well you can
see right here it's a d word pointer rsi
so obviously a memory operand so it's
obviously going to be this
right so it's going to have to issue one
thing on port zero and one and one thing
on port two and three and like that's
exactly what we see
right so what you can see here is
there's no actual full port pressure
uh a third of the time it expects it to
issue on port two
and the rest of the time it expects it
to issue on port three
for the load i'm sorry for the add
because that's actually port zero and
one
right which is where the add can happen
um
and then half the time it will be
loading on port
two and half of the time it will be
loading on port three
right but at no time does it actually
exceed the full
1.0 so we're totally like it should just
always execute
right um
we get here and we say like again the
port pressure
uh looking at where this is distributed
it doesn't look like anything sums over
one here so look again it looks like
we're totally fine
um in terms of the percentage time that
it's actually gonna um
execute here you can see that this is an
add an integer add
and integer ads can execute like
everywhere 0 1
5 and 6 can all do it and that's exactly
what you see so there's 0
1 5 and 6 so it would just distribute
out across those like this
um same with this ad right uh and then
you get the test
uh which is again can can be exited on
all those
and then the jump right
now if you look at these um
i have questions
to say the least uh
so let's start by changing this to a
jump not equal
yeah um so because i wanted this to go
down to a comp jump
right which you can see it doing here
at this point
let me just restate some of this stuff
and then say why this is a little
annoying so
okay so again what's happening here well
this is a loop
so we're running it over and over and
over and over again
if you look at these instructions this
ad this ad
this comp and this jump have to happen
every time through the loop
the ad here this is completely
independent of this stuff
so the add comp jump is like a
completely separate thing from this
so the first time we hit this loop it's
going to pick
port 2 well port 0 or 1
to issue the first part of the add and
port 2 or 3 to issue the second part of
the ad
i probably said that right wrong way
around you probably think of it as it'll
pick
port two or three issue the first part
the load and zero or one to
issue the actual ad right
so we're going to the first time through
port say
say port 0 and port 2
are used the first time through
that means now we come down to this ad
right this ad needs to issue on a port
well
we know we just issued something on this
port right
and we haven't even gone to the next
cycle yet we're still on one cycle we
can issue these on the same cycle
so we would issue this ad probably on
this port
because we know we just used this port
before um
and this port's free so maybe we issue
it on this so we issue
one on this port one on this port one on
this port
right potentially on the same cycle now
again i don't actually know if that's
true for the ad because i
feel like the ad probably has to wait
for the memory to come back
to start the ad because you know how
else would it work so really what
probably happened is it issued something
on this port
then it issued the ad on the same cycle
as the load the first time through
because it couldn't have issued an ad
right yet the rss
um so probably issued the load not the
rss
then the ad so probably this port in
this port let's say
and then the comp has to wait for this
right so the comp jump are now blocked
right however this actually it's in one
cycle so on the next
cycle right if this happened to be in
the l1 cache which
let's say it was then that load will
have completed which means
now it can issue the add ss which it
will do
on say this port because it will have
issued the
ad before on this port right
um although i guess that's out of that
port now so it could probably issue it
on either one now i think about it
because
that will have already finished so now
it's going to issue something on one of
these ports
um and it will start the comp
right because the comp can happen now so
this is the comp on one of these ports
and the add ss on one of these ports
right makes sense
and then it will go ahead and when it
finishes the comp um it will like
well actually before it completes it'll
predict this jump so this
honestly this is nonsense i i
i i don't that's not i don't know what
that is
i i just i what i don't know what that
is uh that looks just completely
erroneous
um this this is not
you know that that's not an instruction
i i i don't know what that means
because uh that's just a front end
thing it's just a that's just a branch
predict it doesn't it doesn't
go like like it doesn't go to an
execution port um
so so i i'm sorry i just i just don't
know what that is trying to tell me
that just looks like a bug or something
um somebody who spends a lot of time
with llvm mca tel you know
it's if anyone out there knows um
what why is it printing that i mean that
that's just not that's just false
i think um
right uh
so so i don't know i don't know
i don't know how to get this over like
maybe i can make this
a little shrinkier so you can see it
there so that just looks like
completely wrong uh the jne
would be fused with the comp uh it would
just be something that happens in the
front end
and it would be branch predicted so
either it will be completely free
or when it's the one time it's not
predicted at the end of the loop
it'll cost you 16 cycles right
so so this is just nonsense like i don't
i mean i'm not a microarchitecture guy
so don't take my word for it but but
that just looks completely erroneous
and wrong which is unfortunate because
it means it will throw off the rest of
this as well because it will assume that
these ports were being used by the jne
which they wouldn't have been
so but anyway but you get the idea so
basically each one of these is kind of
showing you
how clogged it thinks the port will be
when it goes to issue this thing
where it stuck it right
um
and that's about the best you get i
don't love these there's way better ways
to
view this in my opinion i i don't like
that
i don't think this is a constructive way
to view it uh but you can see why
it allows you to like spot check sort of
how the parts are
so it's not useless it's easier than
writing it out by hand probably
modulo the fact that this stupid thing
uh
doesn't number the ports by their actual
number
right but there you go does that answer
the question
uh so i generally use ayaka
uh the older version of ayaka uh
and then a lot of times i just do it by
hand now
i i don't even bother um i have a
version of
llvmmca that i use to spot check
uh but it's just not very good
i i don't know i hope at some point
someone makes a better one
but i i you know i don't know at some
point i'll have to make my own
it doesn't matter anyway it's less it's
less relevant now anyway
because who cares like intel
like there won't be any intel chips next
year anyway like the only things anyone
will be optimizing for are
amd because the intel chips don't
actually work
so you know who cares um
we can just switch the architecture here
to to be a
amd or something right um and uh
and off we go there's an open source
tool called osaka really that's
oh um i would be interested in that
osaka micro
architecture
analysis
um that's cool
uh i have never seen this
but if it's any good that would be great
um here it is
um didn't want to see that
in my life uh
jesus okay so that's like a non-starter
right
like
like like i ain't installing python
um but it looks like it's integrated
into god bolts so
you know if you're using god bolt you
can you can just get rid of the ickiness
there by
by letting mr godbolt
install python for you uh i don't know
where that it would be here it is
um so well
you know there you go off to a great
start
so yeah
all right let's wrap it up
let's wrap it up
good progress today though we're in good
shape um
i'll have to start taking a look at that
lightning bug more seriously next
weekend
anyway thanks everyone for joining me
for the episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow the
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on handmadehero.org and it
comes with a source code
so you can play around with it yourself
you can go find that lightning bug
if you want for example you got all week
to find it beat me to it
um i'll be back here next weekend when
that is exactly what we will be doing
until then have fun programming
everybody and i will see you all
on the internet take it easy folks