hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the sure we could a complete game
live on stream we have our lighting to
the point where it's actually starting
to be kind of feasible to see how this
is going to ship which is kind of cool
because whenever you start down a path
of something like global illumination
you kind of know that you're in for a
little bit of hurt because no one's ever
really shipped a complete lighting
solution that's kind of the be-all and
end-all where we just go this is how you
do it and you're done
it's always kind of a little bit of a
hack and actually shouldn't say a little
bit a lot of a hack and so you always
kind of have to come up with something
that's good enough for your purposes and
that runs fast enough and
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah
right and we're sort of there I think we
just have to address a couple things
that we sort of we have to we have to
figure out how we're going to tackle and
specifically I think at this point the
the really big one that we have to
tackle is going to be how do we keep
from having our Montecarlo sampling
which is what we're doing at the moment
how do we keep from having that flicker
too much frame to frame to be useful so
let's talk a little bit about that this
is day 418 so Tuesday 417 source code if
you are trying to follow along at home
and I'll show you what I am talking
about in terms of what we need to modify
here okay so if you take a look at what
the game looks like at the moment with
our sort of test lighting running
surprisingly in real time which I wasn't
expecting it to because we haven't moved
to the GPU yet but somehow it is you can
kind of see as I move the light source
around we actually get pretty much what
I wanted for a lighting solution the
problem is just that it flickers now why
does it flicker well the reason it
flickers is because we're using random
sampling to determine what the lighting
should be so the question is why are we
using random sampling why does it cause
a flicker and how do we fix it but
that's really where we're at now because
most of what I wanted from a global
lighting solution is actually happening
now and so I'm pretty happy with where
we're at we just need to address a
couple things so there's two things I
want to address
one is that flicker if the other is the
skylight part of things which we also
haven't addressed yet so we could talk
about that a little bit as well but
let's let's just go over where we're at
because we're starting to get to a good
place and we need to start to talk about
how we wrap it up and get to a thing
that we're just like okay this is our
lighting for the game and we're happy
with it we're okay with you know it's
its limitations or whatever it's and its
downsides we've accepted and we have
gotten it to the point where we're happy
with it for the game so let's talk about
flicker okay so what does Monte Carlo
mean anyway we kind of talked about this
before but I'll just say it again
because it's relevant we haven't talked
about in a while so Monte Carlo just
pretty much means random right
it also means stochastic which is
another way of saying random and these
terms have slightly different
connotations potentially but in general
you can kind of think of them in the
same broad category which is to say that
there are schemes which use
unpredictable input some kind of a
random series or pseudo-random series in
this case to arrive at a solution to a
problem that would probably be
impossible to do otherwise right and
that's the that's the key thing to
remember is that you're not doing random
stuff because you want to you're doing
random stuff because you have to now
what do I mean by this well let's think
about the lighting equations we've
talked to them about a bunch of times
when we're talking about the lighting
equation fundamentally we're talking
about is that for every point on every
surface that we render there is a whole
hemisphere of information right a whole
hemisphere of incoming light that we
need to capture and that hemisphere of
incoming light every piece of light that
could be coming in from any angle would
contribute to the final result that's
how real lighting works in the real
world right a real surface takes letting
in from everywhere and radiates light
out to everywhere and it's just a
different amounts of each and what those
amounts are is what determines what the
surface ends up looking like along with
the prop
the microscopic properties of the
surface itself of course that is just a
tremendously huge amount of information
it's in fact an infinite amount of
information if you think about it
because it's a continuous thing there's
no discrete pieces it's not just five
angles or a hundred angles or a million
angles it's an infinite number of angles
we're talking about there right so the
question is how do you take something
that's so infinite and vast and has so
much to do with it
how do you come up with an answer right
and so Monte Carlo schemes are one way
that we have come up with and a very
common way perhaps the only real way for
certain problems that are so vast at
arriving at a solution to these problems
and what we basically do when we talk
about this we say look it's highly
unlikely that any function really
depends on an infinite number of inputs
in terms of what we can perceive what we
perceive about the result of that
function probably depends on a lot less
than that right because let's say
there's a relatively uniform amount of
light coming in and a regular relatively
uniform amount of light going out well
then if we just sample a few places
we'll sort of capture the general idea
behind the lighting and we'll get the
and we'll get out something that's
fairly close to the result right so the
main idea behind Monte Carlo is look
chances are there's not so much
dependent on these situations chances
are there's only a certain amount of
information that's really important here
and if we randomly look and perhaps I
can also say
if there's a concept of importance we
can talk about a second if we randomly
look or better yet look with a sort of
bias towards what we think will be the
most important parts of this function we
can probably arrive at an answer that's
just based on sampling random parts of
the input and seeing what they say now
you can understand why this might work
let's suppose we have a very simple
concept here right let's suppose that I
have a rectangle here's my rectangle
okay now let's say we don't know it's a
rectangle we have no idea yet that it's
a rectangle and the only tool that we
have is the ability to start somewhere
on the x-axis right and shoot upwards
and it'll tell us where we hit right so
very similar to ray tracing right I'm
talking about basically the same thing
we're doing with light where we're a
trace the services it's not a same thing
but we're just talking about finding the
the part of the function up here so we
don't no one told us as a rectangle we
don't know that right but this is what
it looks like all right
so how would we do this well obviously
it's impossible to do an infinite number
of probes and scan out exactly this
shape right but instead what we could do
is we could say well all right let's say
that we wanted to determine the area of
this rectangle so the goal is area of
rectangle kind of like the goal with
lighting is to integrate how much light
is coming in right we want to know how
much surface this this rectangle has and
we can start anywhere here and we can
cast up to the top right well if we were
to just do a regular sampling right so
we just do a sampling that kind of goes
regularly along it right then what we
would get is we would get some number of
these would hit the top and some number
of these would miss entirely right those
out here so what we would see if we did
a regular sampling
even even right we just do it a regular
amount each time and we say we're gonna
take you know 16 samples and we just do
a regular spacing each time we would
find that some number of them let's say
you know 12 of them if this is the
height of the rectangle 12 of them come
back hitting H and you know the other
four of I'm sorry the the other four of
them come back hitting zero they don't
hit anything right and I should
shouldn't say zero infinity right there
they don't hit anything they go forever
right so then what we could estimate
about that right is that whatever the
area is that we shot long right however
however much this area is that we shot
along this would be let's say our width
right or I should say our sample with
maybe we'll call this our sample with
right however long we shot along we
could estimate now that around twelve
sixteenths of it right
twelve sixteenths of the sample width is
probably roughly the width of the
rectangle we don't know but that's how
many hit right and similarly we would
know well the height appears to be on
average H because that's what we tended
to hit and we didn't hit any on these so
we don't count those we just know that
those probably weren't in the shape
right does that make sense
so this is a regular sampling and if you
imagine switching to a random sampling
you'd get roughly the same results right
let's say we just randomly shot
well we'd get a basically the same
result of this thing we would get
proportional to the to this sample with
the number of shots we took would fall
roughly in the ratio of the sample with
to the actual width that's how many
would hit and they would all come back
as H right so for a regular shape a
regular sampling would work and a so
would a random sampling right so with a
Monte Carlo or random sampling now let's
say I want to do a shape that's
different let's say I want to do a shape
that's like this right so now I want to
again take the same process and I want
to estimate
what happens if I do a regular sampling
well I might get very unlucky
maybe I pick a random sampling or a
regular sampling that happens to be
pretty close to that you know this
frequency in my random and my periodic
sampling happened to be pretty close
right so I pick here and I get that and
then I'm here right and I'm like dude
dude dude dude dude dude right like so
and what you can see was something like
this and you could imagine let's say I
do you know in the real worst case I
could get really unlucky and pick
something that only hit right about the
peak right or something right with a
periodic sampling any signal that
happens to also be periodic is gonna
have exactly this problem where you're
drastically over or under estimating the
actual area of this shape because I'm
hitting the same rough place in the
periodic signal right now contrast that
with a random sample which is just gonna
be like anywhere right who knows where
that was really bad random sample and
those random samples will not have this
problem it's almost impossible for a
random series to accidentally hit common
you know features at any kind of period
right in fact the more random the
sampling and the more samples you take
the less likely this is to happen
whereas the periodic sampling you can
always fall into that trap if the thing
you're sampling has periodicity the only
chance of a random sample has for doing
that is if the sequence the thing itself
that you're sampling is also completely
random and in that case it wouldn't
matter how you sampled it you're always
gonna get completely random results
right it'd be pretty hard to do anything
else there um so randomness actually has
a benefit that that makes it likely to
capture features no matter what the
underlying thing is that any kind of us
of a of a how should I put it any kind
of a uniform
sampling scheme can easily fall prey to
structures in the data that you happen
to line up poorly with in order to
sample right um so that's where this
Monte Carlo concept comes from is it
comes from the fact that we'll look if
we're talking about something that we
just can't uniformly sample in any kind
of dense enough way to know that we've
captured all the information let's just
throw a randomness at it and then we're
at least unlikely to fall into any kind
of gullies or Hills that would bias us
towards having a drastically higher
drastically low answer so you're using
the randomness of the sampling to try
and prevent systemic sampling errors
from occurring okay but this therefore
has a downside and the downside is that
if you are sampling randomly signals
that have very specific small features
that are important will get missed now
it's worth noting that uniform sampling
probably would have missed them as well
so it's not necessarily a downside of
Monte Carlo sampling versus unified
sorry uniform sampling but it is the
case that this can happen for example
either scheme let's say it looks like
this right now most of my samples in the
uniform case or the random case are very
unlikely to be around this peak but this
peak might be very important to the
function because maybe it goes really
high right so it's a very powerful part
of the signal that we're looking for and
it's very very powerful but it's very
narrow so neither we'll hit it neither
will correctly estimate its importance
right so this is where important
sampling comes in important sampling is
basically the idea that well we can take
Monte Carlo sampling because we know
that's going to be good at just
generally getting a sense of the signal
without bias biasing us towards any
particular part of it or any particular
pattern in it but what we can do is
concentrate our samples towards areas
which we suspect will be
most influential right and what that
means in the context of what we're doing
so lighting for example the same things
I'm talking about here are true in
lighting let's suppose you look at the
lighting of a surface right and that
surface happens to be diffuse okay so
all the light that's coming in from the
surface let's say it's skylight on a
diffuse surface so tons of light coming
in from every angle
tons of light radiating from every angle
any scheme will work well here a uniform
sampling scheme or a Monte Carlo scheme
will both be fine because any samples
you take will be right the light is
uniform the bounces uniform right so
this is easy any sample will be correct
so no matter what you do you're gonna be
okay now let's talk about a surface that
has more specular right so yes light
might be coming in from everywhere okay
but it's very biased as to how it puts
that light out right so it's like okay
you know it's if the light comes in from
here it's gonna come out this direction
flaw comes in from here it's gonna come
out this direction so on right again
easy
why because since the light is coming in
uniformly from everywhere it scatters
uniformly to everywhere even though it
tends to be highly specular right does
that make sense all right now let's move
on to the harder cases now let's say we
have light coming in from generally one
direction right and we have a specular
surface so it tends to go out in one
direction right the band One Direction
well now what we know is anything any
samples of incoming lighting we take
from out here are probably going to be
somewhat wrong right because a lot of
these samples are gonna say there's no
light coming in right and so we're not
getting any information from them we
want to concentrate our samples towards
where the light is coming in because
that's how we're gonna find actual
information we can use similarly any one
sampling this surface to see what it's
shining out if they're sampling from
here or here or here they're gonna get
not much but if they sample from here or
here or here they're gonna get light
right because the lights coming in here
and coming out here right so if you have
information about how a surface bounces
or information about where the lights
coming from you can see how you might be
able to construct sampling schemes that
concentrate their samples in particular
areas now this ends up being true in
sort of a general case for surfaces in a
particular way which is because of the
cosine term so any surface right
oftentimes has that property the cosine
theta property that we talked about
before which is that when in you know if
you imagine a shaft of light coming in
like so we've talked about this before
right the steeper the shaft of light
comes in falling on the same area of a
patch right the size of the shaft of
light that can fall on that patch right
he's much wider if it's coming in this
way then if it's going out that way
where it's much narrower right so the
amount of light transferred from oblique
you know from angles that are very sharp
to the normal is much less than the
amount of light that can be transferred
when it's facing dead-on so we already
know that this cosine term which we've
applied many times before right we
usually do the cosine of the angle
attenuates the light source right well
another thing we could do there say well
all right if we're gonna attenuate the
light by cosine theta what if we just
sample the light in a way that skews
towards upwards so take very few samples
out to the side where the attenuation is
high and take a lot more samples up here
where we know the light comes in
strongly right that's an example of
importance sampling right it's saying
how important do we think this will be
to the result of the equation right we
know the equation is like you know the
incident light right so we have the
incoming light times cosine theta equals
the outgoing light right
I should maybe just write this out
incoming times cosine theta so we know
that the equation is going to look
something like this where the incoming
light is multiplied by cosine theta we
know that cosine theta of zero right if
the if the angle between the normal and
the incident light is zero we know that
this is going to be one so we're gonna
get all the incoming light if the cosine
between the incoming angle what am i
trust a if we know that the cosine
between the incoming angle the incoming
of the light and the normal is surface
on the other hand was ninety degrees
right or PI over four right
I'm sorry PI over two if we know the
incoming angle was ninety degrees I
almost did Tao there I did you see what
I did I wrote the PI over four it
because I'm used to tell if it was tau
let's say over four but you know I'll
stick with the radians PI over two or
it's just a standard notation for
radians so if the cosine of the angle
was ninety degrees instead of zero
degrees right then we know that that's
going to be zero which means that none
of the incoming light will go into
outgoing okay so we know right here that
we can bias our sample because we not
gonna we're not gonna get any incoming
light from this so we know right here
that we could by us our sampling for a
lot of surfaces that have this property
which is almost all surfaces right in
the way that we're simulating them right
now there are things about about
glancing angle light that's there most
surfaces also have an interesting
property which is that if the light
angle is directly glancing off the
surface it does bounce quite
significantly this is how you get rim
lighting we won't quite talk about that
right now because we talked about like
diffuse light transport which is kind of
a separate thing but point being when
we're doing a reflectance function you
might see some things are a little
different than this but we'll cover that
a little later point being we know that
for our diffuse light bouncing around
typically speaking we have this property
that as we get to a glancing angle as we
come down further and further and
further we're
reflecting less and less of that light
out to everyone so we can sort of say
while sampling where we're going to
check we can easily say that we want to
bias towards checking in the cone that's
like highly above us rather than the
cone that's to the side or in anywhere
in that sort of side angle so that's an
example of how you can bend the
importance of the sampling you know to
to go where you need it to go to improve
the quality of your result right okay so
I just wanted to get that basic idea out
there for everyone so they understand
roughly what's going on here so what
we're doing right now is basically pure
Monte Carlo more or less right so what's
happening in right now is just pure
randomness now it's not white purely
random because we are our sample
hemisphere function is not quite random
right if you look at the render group
you can see the way we do this is we
normalize a random cube essentially
which means that our are hemispherical
coverage is not quite random but it's
closed right so it's it's basically it's
pretty close to pure Monte Carlo we are
slightly important sampled although it's
we're not really important symbols we're
just biased actually we're not we're not
aiming towards anything particularly
important
we're just biased towards certain
directions arbitrarily because of our
function that happens to generate things
a little more strongly so if you looked
at how we were sampling the hemisphere
right now
what you can imagine is say you take a
cube right and you make random points on
the cube and those random points are
randomly distributed on the surface of
the cube okay when you map that down to
norc because we let me normalize those
points down when you shrink wrap wrap
that cube onto a a dome right which
we're then doing what you're gonna see
is the lines so this
part of the of the shrink-wrap you're
gonna get a higher concentration of
points as you approach these lines
because they used to have more surface
area and now they're being folded down
onto that sphere so out here right like
right here where the sphere would touch
right these places where the sphere
would touch the cube the density is
correct but as you approach these sort
of corner areas where there was a larger
surface area on the cube that got shrunk
down on to the hemisphere you get a
higher concentration of points right so
here right here can't see it but here
and here right those points now have
much higher concentrations than they
should have it's not horrible but that
is the case so it's not really important
sampling it's just biased right it's not
important sampling is biased in a useful
way
this is biased in a none useful way it's
just biased so it's bad generally
speaking because it's sampling from its
sampling potentially a higher density of
points in directions that we don't
actually have any reason to believe will
be beneficial right so ideally what we
would do to improve this if this was the
main problem right now it's not but if
this was the main problem right now is
we would want to change that bias
towards being something useful right so
rather than generating Hemisphere
samples that are biased the way they are
now or even uniform we would instead
generate hemisphere ones that we're
skewed towards the top right shrunk this
way and that would be better for us
right okay so as long as you understand
that again that is not the problem we're
having really right now that's that's a
very minor aspect of what problem we're
having right now it's just something to
understand as we now talk about the
problem we are having with sampling all
right
so the problem we're having with
sampling right now is low sampling rate
versus discontinuities in the function
this is the problem and while it's nice
to know what the problem is
unfortunately it's a hard problem to
solve but that's okay at least we know
the problem is so what does that mean
well what that means is lighting is
something that has a really really
specific discontinuity in it always and
this is really what creates you know I
guess I would say the entire problem of
lighting really and why it's so hard to
simulate is probably you could consider
it this very this is the sort of the
essence of it almost obviously you know
that the fact that light a long array is
constant is maybe you could say the
fundamental building block of the
difficulty or maybe you could blame it
on the fact that there's so many photons
in the real world but really this part
right here is the thing that's the most
concentrating I think when you try to
develop algorithms to do lighting and
that is that when you are talking about
lighting if you were to look at the
actual equations we're talking about
they're pretty nice and smooth right
it's like I'm taking all this light in
and I typically have like a uniform
concept of how that light is
redistributed out or something I've got
these nice smooth lobe functions as the
light comes in it radiates out even for
specular surfaces it's still kind of a
nice smooth you know so the functions
tend to look like this sort of thing or
even that sort of thing whatever right
it's not that bad so why is this so hard
to - if it's so nice and smooth why is
it so hard to generate regional
solutions the reason is of course
because of shadows shadows are the
really big problem and what happens with
shadows is you get discontinuities in
the light this should have been a nice
smooth integration of light coming in
over surface but all of a sudden I put
this block in the way and now my
function that would have
been some nice thing I'm just drawing
you know sort of representational graphs
that would have been some nice thing
like this all of a sudden now looks like
this right there's this big old huge
discontinuous notch suddenly right in it
right and so again imagine back to the
thing I was talking about if shooting
right imagine shooting along this thing
well now you just instead of this nice
smooth function that you could have
imagined what it looks like just from a
few sample points cuz you just fit this
nice curve through it and you'd be like
oh that's the answer
right instead you have to determine all
exactly how big is this notch I don't
know I'd have to sample like really
close and try to like narrow in on where
it was to figure out how big of a notch
is taken out right and so what ends up
happening is when we say what is the
incoming light rather than just any set
of samples that happen to be like
reasonably distributed across this thing
rather than that giving us a nice idea
of what the light shape is that's coming
in we instead have this discontinuous
knotch taken out because of shadows
right and worse yet we could have
multiple notches okay
those notches can be big they could be
small but they are there and there could
be multiple of them in fact a normal
scene there's lots of them for any given
surface there's lots of notching right
now it's worth noting that shadow in
this case does not necessarily mean
shadow in the sense that I can't see the
light right take that out of it
what it really means is this you know
what surface do I see right so I've got
something like this or even the things
you know maybe they're even the same
place just two patches this one's red
this one's blue right and here's my
surface that's trying to figure out what
it sees right if I look at the blue
light that comes in over this solid
angle so I'm sweeping over this angle
I'm shooting out right here's the red
light that comes in
right I'm like uh you know this surface
goes on for quite some time so I'm like
ah as the cosine of the angle increases
here you know I'm just getting more and
more and more and more red light so it's
just like looking this nice thing that
comes up and then BAM it just ends right
there right not because the light
stopped but because a different color
surface was in the way right so here I
just have no blue no blue no blue no
blue BAM instant blue and then down with
the cosine again right so it's just
whatever surface I'm seeing even if it's
not shadow it's just the fact that the
things that are putting light in tend to
be hard
irregular right and they can be for any
reason it's two colors of paint on a
surface it's because there is a surface
in the way it just creates all these
notches in the lighting so what could
have been a nice smooth function because
the actual surface sampling is nice and
smooth a lot of times becomes a really
hard edged function with lots of point
sort of notches in it right and so what
we're looking at now is a function that
has like this kind of nasty shape to it
right now you can't really do quite that
right but it's like you know it's things
that look like this with all of these
nasty little notches in them where it
dis continuously changes and so
estimating this function becomes very
difficult right estimating this incoming
light amount becomes very difficult and
so if we just do a few samples even if
they're uniform or random no matter what
we do with them we're likely to not
really get the same answer twice in a
row so let's say we've got 64 samples
right and we're trying to sample this
this function right
well this function is going to be this
hemispherical function right so it's
it's this but in two dimensions over
Hemisphere and
as I'm shooting out I'm finding all of
these random value like these values are
just totally nuts right some of them are
super low some of them are super high so
if I tend to sample a few more samples
near the peak on one pass I'm gonna get
a higher value if I tend to have a few
more samples that fall near troughs I'm
gonna get a lower value and this is what
produces our flicker right since we
can't since we are under sampled versus
the number of samples we need to take to
really get the right answer because we
could we could take enough in fact here
let me show you what happens if we want
to take enough right
here's our lighting right you can see
that this it's it's super flickery right
as we go and in fact let me emphasize
that since we're using a we're not using
a continuous random value we're using
one that is the same every frame when
everything stops moving our lighting
sample stops flickering because we're
using the same random sample so they hit
the same peaks and troughs right that's
what's that that's what's going on there
but if instead for when we do our push
lighting we didn't do that so here's
here's where we do our compute lighting
propagation right you see we have our
random series it's always initialized to
one two three four right it's the same
seed every time so we do the same
samples every time if instead our
lighting solution was keeping a
continuous random value so let's say
that we did this where is that
like solution so let's say we have this
in here so it persisted so our random
series was changing every frame like so
and so instead of series here we just
said like oh okay it's actually solution
arrow series right did we do this so use
it and then we at the end we'll set it
every time like so so now we're keeping
a random value that's gonna go the whole
that's gonna keep going now we will get
that flicker every frame right so this
shows us what happens every for every
time we recompute the lighting we get a
different result and you can kind of see
how that result is is oscillating right
based on the fact that it gets very
different answers depending on where
it's shooting and you can kind of see
some regularity in in this sort of thing
and and you can see some of the obvious
things that happen as a result if you
look at where these things are sampling
you can kind of see that well you know
if I look at areas that are not
flickering much right so let's say I
take a look back here in the black area
why isn't that flickering well it's not
looking because no matter where it casts
it never hits the light source so
there's no risk of flicker because it's
never going to get an answer other than
can't see the light source similarly
this has very high visibility to the
light source
right because everywhere it looks is
going to get light more or less it has
very low flicker as well on the contrary
people down here who could either hit
the light source or hit the sky very
easily depending on how they're shooting
right flicker quite a bit people who are
very unlikely that the light source
don't flicker as much either right
because they only hit it once or twice
every frame so they flicker at a very
low flicker right whereas these flicker
at a very bright flavor because they're
your tenth you know going intense and so
on right and so you just get the biases
in the function just become
become Flickr I should say biases the
undersampling the the fact that the
thing is kind of nachi we then get those
sort of flickers in the function right
you know in our poor estimation of of
what's going on so what we can do is we
can increase our sampling rate up to the
point where we actually converge on the
right answer because we're sending out
enough points right and we can test that
by just turning this back into a slow
sample right so for example if I if I go
back to the where is that in world mode
let's say I I think we have a thing
where we set high we still have a debug
light P in here I don't want that I
guess I do want that
well let's ignore that for now not what
I was talking about
um so if we want to go in here and just
have a way of like switching it to slow
lighting in the case where we where we
don't want to output it every frame so
we can look here we can see okay here's
the lighting test at the output lighting
textures thing you know if updating
lighting or something like this right
then what we can do is this updating
lighting flag is something that we could
update periodically is supposed to do
here
three updating a lighting equals world
mode updating lighting right and we can
just put a bool in here and we can
toggle that on and off right so what
we'll do is we'll say all right if you
push certain keys so let's say that you
push f7 that'll turn updating lighting
on for one frame so I'll do one light
update if you do eight it will set world
mode updating lighting to the not
lighting so you can turn it on
permanently right if you have wants to
be three and four
so now if we look at it we're not doing
any lighting right because nothing's
happening I can do a single lighting
step if I want to pipe loops by pressing
the f3 key here right so that's one
lighting step right there's another one
so I can I can recompute the lighting on
a given frame if I want to and then when
I move the light source around it won't
recompute the lighting right but then I
can compute it again that makes sense
oops and so then if I want to run on
permanent lighting I can hit f4 and now
I get permanent lighting right so now
it's updating every frame so now I'm
free to go make a lighting thing that
takes way too long to run in real time
which we had before but then turn how it
ran so fast that we just started running
in real time but let's go ahead and go
back to something that runs way too
slowly so let's say we set the ray count
for sampling up ridiculously high so
we're just sampling tons and tons and
tons we have a much higher sampling rate
than we had before right so now if I run
a lighting sample it takes a long time
right or yeah there you go but our
answer should be more stable so if we
look at what what we get here and I run
it again very little change right did
you see how little that how little that
flickered it's a very tiny amount of
flicker right it's a very very very
small amount of flicker make sense
now compare and contrast that with a
much the much less accurate version that
we had before where we're only sending
out 64 samples right now it's the same
exact position same exact scene let's
run it again I mean look at how much
that lighting is changing right so again
the degree to which the light is the
light has kind of an uneven function
coming in the higher we sample it the
more we're going to capture the actual
structure of the light the the less
flicker will have the less we sample it
the more likely we are to accidentally
be sampling highs or lows right more
than the more than the opposite and so
the more we're gonna end up with a
flicker from frame to frame as we switch
between
the high is more some people knows more
inside etcetera so fundamentally
speaking that is what's going on here
and so what we need to address now is we
need to figure out good ways of making
it so that that flicker is not a problem
for us right that's our goal
so how we can do that all right so hmm
one thing we can obviously do if we want
to write is we could go ahead and take
this solution that we're using and we
could try to smooth it out over time
right because we know that the 4096
sample version right or you know in even
more you know we could we could do one
that was even more than that the
arbitrarily high right just keep
cranking the numbers we know that a
version that samples things much more
densely produces a much more consistent
result from time to time regardless of
what the input series is yeah so what we
could do is say over time we'll just
accumulate all the results we have so
that the answer just keeps getting more
accurate as we go right furthermore what
we could do is say well you know since
what we want to eliminate frame to frame
is that flickering then smoothing out
over time is just going to naturally
reduce it even if we don't improve the
solution at all in the process right so
we kind of have a couple different ways
we can think about having temporal
elements there help us out with that
flicker so the question is for that and
I shouldn't say the question the the
hard part about this and we're gonna
face this no matter what we do because
we're gonna want it
Lighting's gonna want to be smooth
over time because it's never gonna be
solved perfectly like I said what we
want to be able to do here is we want to
be able to make it so that there's some
way of corresponding surfaces from frame
to frame and this is pretty difficult to
do because it means that from one frame
to the next we would have to have a way
of figuring out which lighting samples
correspond to which other lighting
samples right and this is incredibly
difficult to do the the fundamental
problem is that if you look at a
particular scene it's very easy for us
to do something like create lighting
samples for every surface that we send
down it's much harder to figure out how
those letting samples should be used in
how those lighting samples should
correspond with the ones from the frame
that came before it unless you happen to
magically know which ones they were
right so we have to have some way of
figuring out how those are going to
persist and I'm trying to think of the
most efficient way to do this some
elements of this could be pretty easy
some elements could be pretty hard
I mean I guess if I think it through
I mean if I think it through basically
here's what I here's what I kind of
here's what comes to mind right so I
don't really want to have to worry about
determining correspondence spatially
right so there's so there's speechless
correspondence and that's kind of like
our voxel approach right
remember our voxel approach where we
said like alright let's divide the world
up into a voxel right and we'll just say
that like the light samples in this area
you can sample from and find out what
your sample probably is right we saw how
many problems we had with that just
because in general those those voxel
samples you don't really know which
surface phase belong to right you don't
really know like is this a surface that
I should be counting or not is it one
that would be in shadow relative to me
or not like it just it's not so good as
one's risk that where we say they're
right on the surface of this thing so we
know which ones are on like this side of
the surface versus this side of the
surface for light sampling and so on so
spatial correspondence I feel like has a
lot of downsides that I really don't
want to be involved in if possible I'd
like to avoid it so I'd much rather have
frame to frame correspondence of these
things based more on knowledge of the
fact that we drew the same thing twice
not that it happens to look like it
maybe is in the same place roughly if
that makes sense so you know what I'd
rather say is like oh all right let's
let's say we have something more like if
I have an entity that's sending down a
cube or something like this
right maybe that entity remembers its
light index so that if I send it down
again the next frame it just puts that
same light index in there right and so
this would be a nice clean scheme the
problem is how do you know how to
allocate light indexes at this point
because if I want to do this then I have
to have something that remembers what
light indexes are used on a particular
frame so that things that are new for
this frame don't use light indexes that
are still being used by something in the
frame right so if you imagine this is
like an alligator at that point where
you effectively have where you
effectively have some big block of
lighting chunks and what happens is
you're like oh okay somebody pushes down
an entity that says it wants this
letting chunk so it has to go there and
then someone pushes down an entity that
says I want this one so it has to go
there then someone pushes down a new one
and you're like okay well I guess I
better put it here in some new space
because I don't know which of these is
going to be used yet right
so you can kind of see why that's tricky
and
[Music]
you can see why that's tricky
though there are some rather
straightforward solutions to it that I'm
just not sure how efficient they are for
example one way you could do this was
just when you push these things down to
the renderer you just tell the renderer
hey here's the right back location for
the light index and it just doesn't
allocate light samples to the new things
until all the old ones have already been
filled and then it comes back jumps back
and places those there's new ones in
where they should go so basically you
know you're talking about second pass
over the buffer which is not a huge deal
you know
[Music]
and it kind of seems like that would be
fine so I don't know if it would be fine
or not but here's what that would look
like let's suppose I took a look at the
energy struct right and in here I
basically said like okay these things
have an array of these sort of pieces
that you can put in here and those
entity visible pieces need to have the
lighting index that goes with them right
like so that lighting index is something
that the visible piece
the visible piece will track and report
back
you know frame to frame you know if it
knows it and I guess I don't necessarily
know
the part part I'm having trouble
thinking through is that the lighting
index in a visible piece right you could
just track that and I think I can write
the thing pretty straightforward that
just makes it so that that always comes
through so that you basically have
frame-to-frame corresponds to the
lighting just fine the problem is what
happens when something then goes out of
frame entirely so an entity visible
piece is now no longer being used so it
is like you know it's not getting
rendered anymore it fell out of the
camera region entirely and it's just not
getting render it anymore
so that lighting index will now get
reassigned to somebody else as it should
but when this entity visible piece comes
back in to view it will have that same
lighting index right so it will now
accidentally pick up the lighting from
something that already that is not
correct
right it's the totally wrong it's a
totally wrong lighting index
now it's possible that that just doesn't
matter the reason I say it's possible
that it just doesn't matter is because
we could just throw it out based on some
kind of other piece of information
for example let's suppose that we looked
at the lighting index and said if the
lighting indices are the same we'll use
it unless the position of this lighting
sample that you're asking me to put here
is actually not is too far away from the
position that I last recorded for this
thing which would be correct in two ways
first of all that would get rid of thing
for the problem that I'm talking about
but it would also get rid of the problem
of the like entities that teleport right
so let's say it entity hops onto a
teleporter and teleports somewhere else
we would have to make special code to
clear the lighting index but if we were
just comparing positions and go it's too
far away the lighting would no longer be
accurate it would just set to recompute
that one automatically which is exactly
what we would want I don't know it seems
all right seems all right to me
I'm gonna give a shot I'm gonna give
this shot because if we can do the frame
to frame correspondence this way then we
no longer have the problem of spatial
correspondence which just spatial
correspondence tends to be really bad
you end up with a lot of visible
glitches when you do frame when you do
spatial correspondence in fact you see
this in games a lot nowadays there's all
kinds of weird things like you look down
at a puddle and you see the like
reflection kind of like trickle in and
then you move and it kind of smears and
it's like there's a lot of like temporal
anti-aliasing stuff that you look at and
it looks kind of bad and I think most of
the reason that looks bad is just
because frame to frame correspondence
that isn't tracked in some more
intelligent way can be really bad
although you know to be honest that's
probably just bad for other reasons I
shouldn't use that example because
there's a lot of other reasons that
would be bad um my my feeling that why
it's better to track frame to frame
correspondents logically rather than
positionally is just because I've seen
how hard it is to do reconstruction
filters for things like irradiance
caches in real time I mean it's very in
a non real-time rendering systems where
you basically have like light
information splats around the
environment and trying to figure out
whether you can use a particularly
example or not tends to be a really hard
problem that takes a lot of work to
reconstruct properly and there's pretty
good ones now but they are very
expensive still so do the reconstruction
stealth is actually a pretty tough
operation so so anyway I think we do
want to try this so I'm gonna I'm gonna
give it a shot I'm gonna see how it goes
so what I'm gonna do here is say that
when we do this this when we send down
these these things that are gonna get
lit I'm gonna try to figure out a good
way to sort of like actually line them
up frame to frame and we'll just see how
that goes right so yeah if you take a
look at what happens here mmm to me in
push quad
what I want to do here in push quad is
right now we've got sort of this this
light count light index stuff getting
set here as sort of an arbitrary thing
right and what I'd like to do is I'd
like to sort of upgrade this to being
something where we are probably passing
that down so when we do a push quad here
instead of instead of the emission being
the only thing that's kind of set here
and honestly the emission I don't know
that the emission is even something that
we will be setting in push quad anymore
but you know either way in addition to
the emission I want to set here at the
light count and the light index as well
so in here we're gonna have a light
count and a light index and those will
both be zero by default and the outer
code will do something with that right
so if we run the code now what we'll get
is no lighting at all like the the game
will just render the solid color of
everything because the the whole point
of this is that if you set the the the
path that we did for non non lit is that
you set them to zero and you don't get
lighting so that's exactly what's
happening here so if I want to go ahead
and and put the lighting back in then
what I have to do is take anything that
was gonna participate in the lighting
such as one of the cube calls which is
let's just just do lighting on the cubes
at first right so I want to on the cube
call the cube call would have to pass it
down so we should be able to emulate the
same thing we rambling before here by
saying like okay you know if the
lighting is enabled or not then we're
going to go ahead and assign a light
count to these things now we've got
we've got to draw all six faces of the
cube so we knew that our light index has
to be incremented by light count but
times six right if that makes sense
and so then we're passing down a light
count light index each time here but the
light index itself every time is going
to have to increment this one doesn't
really necessary
uh no to what push quad it didn't like
it is that because there's two there's a
second push quad here isn't there yeah
that does the pack oops
those are backwards thing are they
backwards how did I do this
light count light index some reason the
count comes before the index don't ask
me why it just does
so now in theory this should restore
lighting on the cubes but only the cubes
because those are the only people who
for who are having a light index passed
down so you can see sprites are non lit
they just come through as their standard
bitmap colors modulated by whatever
their actual sprite color is but they
get new lighting and then the cubes get
lighting so if I were to run a lighting
right all the cubes get lit right like
so
but the sprites remain unlit which is
exactly what we would expect so that
appears to be working properly so next
question is well okay if the you know
push quad does does that then how do we
now get the push cube function at which
we're calling here how do we get the
push cube function to do something
useful in terms of the light count light
index and the answer is now we want to
try and correspond these frame-to-frame
so we want to actually do a an operation
here that will allow us to try and do
that okay I think this so I can see
these better so this is push cube and if
we wanted to make it take an index here
a lighting index that we then tracked we
would have to sort of say like okay
we need to know the location of the
light index value that we're writing
back because we're gonna have to update
this right in one way or another so what
we can do here is say well okay if the
thing in the lighted next door is a
valid value that we can use then we will
use it if not we will assign a new light
index to it and use that instead
right that's basically what we're doing
here
yeah anyway so this value right here
would be the thing that goes into the
entity's permanent storage so when we
are operating on this stuff and we do a
push cube to push down the cube pieces
right and I believe that's done here
right so here's where we're doing a push
cube and the push cube right with all
this piece stuff that gets sent down the
push cubes admission value in this case
is nothing but the light index door is
something right so we would say like oh
yeah we're looking at the light index
door piece light index right so we can
send that down
thought I added that so now we would
have a way of tracking this piece of
information from frame to frame because
the renderer when it assigns the light
index to something could write that
light index back if it wanted to and so
that would be fine so what we could do
here is say like okay well the light and
next door if that's set to something
let's actually try to use it here and if
it's set to nothing so if there's no
pointer then we're just gonna assume
that the lighting is not supposed to
happen on this thing anyway right so
this would also allow us another way to
turn off lighting I suppose would be
that we just passed zeros down for the
light index but you know I can do that
in a more sane way here by saying like
okay right at the top if lighting is not
enabled then the lighting next door is
going to be zero right then down here
I'll just look at the light index door
and go from there so if the light in
next door is valid then what I'm gonna
say is like okay the total light count
is going to be you know we're gonna do
exactly what we're doing here we need
six times the light count per surface to
get what we actually need and the light
index is going to be assigned one way or
the other if the light index store value
is not in range and I guess in range is
probably the wrong term here I suppose
what we actually mean is if we have two
cases we have to handle one is where we
have an existing light index and it's
valid another is we have an existing
light index and it is not valid right
the positions are too far those are two
cases for the light index having an
actual Val value in addition to case
three which is the one where we just
don't have one at all right so we need
to first check all right if there's a
light indexed or pointer then its path
of all that the light index store
pointer is pointing to something that is
a light index versus one that's not so
if it's not pointing to something valid
right so if it's pointing to zero then
we would assign it I think so we just
say look it's whatever it is here right
otherwise what we would do is use it
here so we'd say like oh okay and I
suppose these are the same right and now
I'm glossing over a big part here which
is this actually needs to be an
alligator so this is just wrong
arbitrarily wrong right now so yeah take
that with a grain of salt this is gonna
have to actually like defer and place
this in a in an unused section of the
lighting array which is going to be the
majority of the work that we have to do
to get that to be a thing that works
efficiently but so here we've got our
lighting next our lighting the next door
where we just say okay use whatever you
used on the previous frame that's it and
so that should work relatively
straightforward of course we have the
fact that we're only really doing you 16
Sarah and off we go and so now if I run
this in theory I think this will just
still just work because well I take it
back
that definitely did not work what did I
do wrong I was gonna say it should just
assign lighting mixes to all these
things and that should be it right like
and then they're just gonna use those
light indexes going forwards
unfortunately that does not appear to
have happened why does that not appear
to have happened
ah so I guess the reason that's not
happening is because the emissive light
doesn't store anything so that push
light call that we do I'm pretty sure
this is the problem right this push
light call that we do here this one
doesn't have a light index anywhere
right so in we would need to track that
in order for it to work because it's
turning off lighting including
transmission of lighting and turning off
all lighting calculations period for any
light that that doesn't have an index
right so for the time being I don't
really want to deal with that fact we
probably want to support just things
that are only transient so they because
we have things like light sources that
don't reflect light those we need to
kind of improve our handling of
eventually so that would probably be
something we want to change in the
future at some point but for right now
it's probably fine oops
there we go
so now I think we will get our light in
there probably hopefully maybe yeah okay
so now you can see that we're running
exactly the same way as we were only now
in theory at least we have stable
lighting indices we haven't done the
work to actually make these work for
real because we need that allocator to
work for things coming in and out of the
lighting set right now we don't have
anything coming in the other lights that
because we're just looking at a tiny
little scene but remember this is gonna
have tons of stuff all over the world
that we're gonna be moving through as we
go and so we need to have it understand
how to take things in and out of the set
potentially now we could also choose
that by saying well we don't really need
to do that because we could just make it
so that we hop from room to room it
resets the lighting or something like
this
but you know just whatever we do it has
to be smarter than what we're doing now
which is nothing so okay so I would
basically say that's that's all we
really need to do for that that's all we
saw we really need to do for making sure
that our lighting making sure that our
lighting equations are getting a slot
that they can use to store things frame
to frame and so now what we could do
really at the end of the stream here
before we end because I guess we've got
we've got about 25 minutes left we could
actually try to do a little bit of work
with those two to see if we can reduce
the flicker just as an example of what
we could do that probably isn't the
final thing that we'll do but something
that's sort of similar to it's an
example of what we could try to do right
um so what we would do here is we have
to remember that what the reason that
our lighting resets every frame is
because we are manually clearing it
right we do an extract reflectors from
quads call and then fact reflectors from
quads call is doing this emit clear here
right so we have our
they actually have an emission value
coming in from the previous frame that
we could choose not to clear right if
this thing doesn't have any emission
that's coming down we could choose not
to clear it or we could choose to seed
the c1 lighting with what was in the c0
lighting last time I mean we have a lot
of ways we could try to sort of pull
that lighting in from the previous frame
right so let's see how we might do this
here as an example so when we do our
accumulation of steps as you can see
here is the dest emit C value right is
getting assigned to the source mitzi
each time so what we could do is just
mix that in this is gonna be a really
cheesy way to do this I suppose but we
could just mix that in by saying hey
don't clear the dust emit c1 instead
just set it to whatever the decimate c0
was from the previous frame I don't
really know what this is gonna do and
you know what we probably want to sort
of reduce the contribution of that a
little bit each frame or something like
this this is completely bogus I'm
literally just screwing around right now
okay
that doesn't look like it did anything
so I are we clearing these because that
should have mixed in a value there it
doesn't appear to have done so
[Music]
if I put in a mixing coefficient here
for that was it was it just that I
wasn't doing that one as well no that's
still let's see if I reduce the number
yeah that that really doesn't seem to be
holding much over per frame well let's
step in and find out why am i clearing
these somewhere I don't remember
clearing them anywhere when we do when
we do the transfer here I don't think
anyone ever clears them right am I wrong
about that
all right well I'm going to go ahead and
switch back to the debug compile this
way we'll be able to inspect the values
easier so here is the very slow running
debug mode flicker version right and now
what I can do is just step into that
lighting and see what's going on there
just I just want to take a glance at
whether those values are being persisted
or not right that's that's all I really
want to see here
all right here we go and I'm gonna hit
the recompute letting key so we'll jump
in here
and then we can see what our solution
thinks it has in these right now for the
various values right
so yeah let's take a look at emits e
zero for this light index what is the
light index actually let's talk about
that first
so this is light one which is what we
would expect because this is the first
time through the loop and hey there's
some values in there so that's good and
there's nothing in EM it's e1 so I guess
I couldn't say why there would be
nothing in EM it's e1
because in theory these should have been
roughly the same unless it sent out all
of its light maybe it sent out all of
its light on that step or something or I
mean I guess it's possible let's just
take a look at some other ones and see
is that a trend it does look like
there's never anything in c1 oh you know
what no that does make perfect sense
there shouldn't be ever anything in c1
because it's cleared even on the last
one we just we don't discriminate in
this loop between whether it's the last
loop or not so c1 actually does always
get cleared at the end of it so that's
actually not surprising at all I take
that back
okay so that's fine but we are getting
actual light values coming in here under
emit c0 right so we should be able to
mix those values in let's see if we can
do a better job of it so I think the
problem that we're gonna have here is if
we're actually if it's just that that
much flicker is introduced every frame
the problem is we have this is not going
to cut it just starting with with
existing values isn't gonna cut it
right also I realize this doesn't have
to happen since we clear it at the end
of every frame anyway right
it's really only this one has to get
cleared in that way so what we would
have to do here is we'd have to save
into temporary buffers what those values
are so that we could mix them at the end
or something similar to this right we
can't use our scratch buffers for it so
what we would have to do is say okay you
know temporarily and this is not a smart
way to do this but you know we can again
will optimize this and do a more of a
ping pong buffer thing for it if this
turned out to be what we were going to
do permanently
yeah what I want to do here is just say
okay let's let's keep those around and
then we'll mix them at the end so we can
be sure that we're taking the final
solution of the first one and adding it
to the file solution of the second one
so that we have two like full full
solves and we can control the blend rate
rather than taking the solution and
including it in the distribution step
because that will just probably add all
the noise right back in right so let me
go ahead and do that so in here what I
want to do is something like last emmitt
and last direction
why is that why didn't that breakpoint
set
not that I needed to set yeah and then
what I want to do is when I start I want
to save into their whatever those
whatever those were right so what I'll
do here is say last is valid
I'll come into the render group the
first time through obviously it's not
valid so we'll deal with that in a
second but my last admit I'm going to
take care
before I overwrite in fact you know what
I don't even need to do this let's just
copy it do I have a copy struct I guess
I don't so I'm going to take last event
here or I should say I'll take omit see
zero and I'm going to copy it
oops that's not what I wanted either
average light direction so what I want
to do is just copy these two arrays
again this is not good
but that's okay because we're just doing
this for testing purposes anyway so
we're gonna do that copy there don't ask
me how that got inserted
probably it was trying to hit the buffer
switch key or something like that anyway
uh right in this code base size I was
not capitalized so that will give us a
copy and then we can do our miscibility
or our mixing of those at the very end
so in here where we do where we do the
final sort of averaging of the the
points and all that stuff this is where
we could do our mix so we could do mix
omit c0 which is what we're going to use
we can say omit c0 point index equals
you know alert let's say between the
value that we were last time in the
value that we computed now so we have
our last omit we have our new omit and
we can go some amount of the way there
so let's say we go a quarter of the way
there so four frames it takes four
frames to change the lighting completely
right just making up a value here in
fact you know we can just do it like
this and so the same will be true for
the normal here right we can say all
right the solution last direction will
lurch the new light direction as well
and off we go so now we have we should
have four frames of lag on our lighting
I think and that does look exactly like
what happened and since we don't want to
do this in the case of I want to do a
salute if solution last emit oh sorry
last is valid if this lasts
if we have never taken a light sample
before then I don't want to do that
right like if we've never previously had
any light then I don't want to blend it
in I don't want to blend in zero so I'll
just cause our lighting to fade in for
no reason if we want our lighting to
fade in great we can fade in our light
sources I don't want to have the
lighting solution enforce a fade here so
what I want to do is just again do the
opposite copy so say like oh okay
in fact I don't even need to do a copy I
could just do it like this I could say
last admit people's solution last admit
last Direction equals solution last
direction and then if the if we don't
have a valid lighting solution then what
I can do is say Oh last emit will
actually just be this emit so it'll just
lurk between the value in itself right
which will do nothing so that that will
prevent us from having that fade in so
now when I run it and I do f3 I should
get okay that didn't work at all so I
don't know why because I'm not using
those yukata actually use the variables
you make if you want them to work protip
there we go
oh no that's still why are we getting
that's weird
I don't know what to make of that
that was very strange did you see that
it was like we weren't getting any
lighting on our walls all of a sudden I
must have introduced a little bit of a
bug when I was
when I was doing the last admission
stuff
well you know what so we don't really
know that that's true because we don't
know that these are getting completely
well we do we think they're completely
stable sighs we'll have to see we can
debug it later all right let me so in
theory now we're blending across
multiple frames and it does look like
that right we still get some flicker the
flicker is definitely less we could try
reducing that value and see what happens
here's one that takes ten frames
right
here's one that takes 20 frames
and here's one that takes 100 frames
and you know hopefully what you can see
here is is we can definitely combat that
flicker by just having lag in the
lighting we've done nothing we don't
even have this accelerated so we're not
even taking very many samples compared
to what we could be taking and that's
usable right I mean that's a shippable
lighting scheme sort of in terms of the
just that you know the degree of like
disruption of the game experience it's
very little right so let's say we wanted
this to be something like 20 frames or
even just 10 frames I wonder what we
would have to set the sampling rate up
to and of course we can do better with
our sampling anyway than we're doing now
but let's say I double the sample rate
there
yes oh I mean honestly I think this is
gonna work just fine because we're gonna
get a lot more samples so I think we'll
be able to crank it down pretty low and
what we now know is that if we're
willing to take let's say I wonder 50
frames is sufficient
something is weird about my lighting
startup it's not actually obeying that
last is valid and I don't know why what
am i I did something stupid here what
did I do wrong
you
I'm gonna I want to go step into that
hold on one second is this value not
cleared or something because I thought
they were all cleared but maybe they're
not cleared it could be that that value
is not cleared at startup I should just
go check
okay turning the lighting on now so
that's setting it right and lasted valid
is noun 1
so this loop should always be just two
things that are the same value right
okay that's going to get optimized dad
I'm sure
that's weird so what did I do wrong
there cuz that should have just worked
and those are both the same value so
derping between them should have just
been a straight copy but something about
the startup is busted right you saw that
right it's it's as if it's not doing
that but then once it's done
it's correct like now it's fine so
something about the startup there is
kind of busted and I don't know why cuz
the only two values were persisting
the only two values were persisting were
you know we're just using pointers to
the same ah but average director to
lights version won't be normalized so
it's not quite right yeah so technically
you would have to do that or rather that
would be the smarter thing to do anyway
[Music]
so the emission value is probably fine
but the average direction is not hey
look that fixed it
so what happens what would happen if we
actually put back in our look weird
snake dude this will be the last thing
I'll do today I'm just curious what
would happen if we added that weird
snake dude back in with the light on him
so we still have some kind of weird bugs
going on there like those lights only
seem to work in certain places but as
they go up they don't I wonder if we've
got some like light assignment problems
there you can see the frames of lag are
worse when you have a fast-moving entity
right so this is why we want to reduce
the number of frames of lag there so we
can capture faster moving entities but
look at how there's no light happening
up there so that's a bug but I'm not
sure what that bug is so we definitely
have a light index assignment bug that
we need to debug so that would be our
thing to do for next time right all
right let's do a brief QA and since we
might not do a hand-made here and I say
since it's holiday break I need to make
a note to myself
because we're going to need that
because yeah I'm I'm pretty sure that we
just have some kind of lighting index
aside like that let that was a pretty
hacky thing I just kind of did it
quickly and so we could test with it but
when we go finish that letting in next
time and I'm feeling pretty good about
that I think we're I think we're almost
we're almost there with lighting if we
don't have any questions we can end
early
at tyra dub yesterday someone asked if
it will be beneficial to have more test
scenes for lighting tests and this was
never answered yeah that does sound like
a good idea to me
Arif don't you use the to do that text
in the code Rex Mike does yeah but we
never use it so I wanted to put it right
in the code so I can't miss it
long boolean what is your take on the
use of machine learning to approach
Rosie's I don't have an opinion yet
because I've never tried it probably
it's not as good as people probably say
it is but it's also probably mmm going
to get better so I suspect it like over
time we'll find that machine learning
can generate algorithms for us that we
want to use and you know they will get
better all right I actually go so I'm
gonna I'm gonna do so we don't have a
flood of questions that are on this
topic I'm gonna go ahead and wrap up
early I apologize all right thank you
everyone for joining me for the episode
of hand made here it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along with the series at home you
can always pre-order the game and it
comes with a source code updated nightly
so you can play around with it yourself
we also have a forum site you can go to
if one asked questions a page you can go
to if you want to contribute to the
things like the episode guide and stuff
like that a schedule about that tells
you when we'll be live and the
aforementioned episode guide which has
like all of the old episodes annotated
it's pretty awesome you should check it
out that's it for this week there
probably won't be a show next weekend
because of holiday break but we'll be
back sometime after that to finish the
lighting off it's coming along pretty
nicely I'm pretty happy with it actually
so hopefully you'll come back and join
us in two weeks for that until then have
fun programming have a good holiday
season and see you everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody