hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream we are so yesterday we
did sort of one half of a thing and
tomorrow we're gonna do the today we're
gonna do the other half of the thing in
a sense like the forwards and backwards
versions because what we found yesterday
was we wanted to get our camera frustum
sort of stuff working properly frustums
the wrong word in this case is we're not
really using that we're just trying to
get a rectangle in sort of level space
that corresponds with the camera can see
so we fixed our unprotect call we went
through the math there and fix the
problems with it that we had had because
remember we changed everything around
and we had never really gone back and
made that thing really work right so we
do now so he fixed that part and that
part was important for fixing stuff like
knowing what to query for the lighting
and stuff like that because we need we
need boundary regions for a bunch of
computational stuff that we do in
handmade Hiro and so what we need to
know there right is we need to know the
bounds of what the camera can see so
that we make sure that we never like
don't for example don't compute lighting
for something that the camera can't see
because if we don't compute the
Lighting's in the camera can see it will
show up as an obvious visual glitch so
we fixed that part of it but now today
we do the opposite of that because what
we the other thing that I said I want to
fix in the sort of system to sort of get
things into a more smooth state and I'll
show you what I mean actually right now
as well let me go ahead and do a build
here there we go so the other thing that
I said that I wanna fix is okay we got
the lighting stuff and you can see now
if I you can see the the bounds are nice
and tight to where the camera was and as
we move you can see the lighting
computation move with it so that if
you're here you never really see any
lighting glitches you you always have
everything that's within the camera view
being sent to the lighting solution
which is exactly what we wanted in that
fix is the bug now the other thing that
I want to fix was the camera right now
we have not really gone in and got the
camera working properly now that we kind
of know exactly what we're doing here
there's no excuse for not making the
camera work properly so that's why I
want to do in order to get that working
properly
what we're going to have to do is we're
going have to do the opposite of what we
did yesterday yesterday we were asking
the fundamental question if I take a
given camera position which is where the
camera is right now how much of the
level can I see so I know how much of it
to light that was the question we were
asking right and in addition to lighting
we might want to do other things right
now we're going to be asking the
question is we want the camera to start
working more properly we're going to be
asking the opposite question which is if
I specify a given area of the level like
for example I'm in this hallway or I'm
in this room or that room or somewhere
out here in the dungeon or who knows
what if I decide to do those things and
I want to always know that when I'm in a
particular room I want to be able to see
everything that is in that room
then I put myself in a position where I
need to ask the opposite question and
the opposite question is given a region
of the game that I'm telling you a
prairie I want to see completely how do
I make sure that I pick a camera
location that does see it completely
right so that's what I'm trying to do
effectively is is the opposite thing one
was camera location
give me the region that can be seen so
like this white box right is the region
that the camera can see so we just know
that's what the camera can see for on a
given slice of on a given so I'm looking
for for a given like area so the camera
has a certain distance that we're
looking at and we know that we're
looking at this you know slice of the
world at that distance what is the
rectangle the camera can see was the
question we were asking and that was the
forward question from a camera to a
rectangle and so now we want to ask the
reverse question if I feed in a
rectangle and say at this distance if a
rectangle was this big how far back from
the rectangle would I have to go before
I can see the whole thing right
that's what I need to know now and so
it's not exactly the reverse question
but it's a very similar it's the reverse
question semantically it's just not the
inverse mathematically in any real sense
so it's kind of I'm not sure what you
would call it but it's definitely the
opposite question in terms of semantics
one of the thing that you'll note so you
notice when I hop from here to here to
big room big room to big room you'll
notice how well if for example if I let
the camera settle in here like so and
then I hop out you see how part of the
level just appears first definitely cuz
it's falling out of the simulation
region there really quickly as the
simulation just kind of snaps over one
thing we can do there is we can include
we can force the inclusion of the old
simulation region until the camera move
finishes and that's something that we'll
also want to do again to avoid visual
glitches because we don't really want to
allow we don't want to have anything
that sort of for lack of a better term
breaks the illusion of permanence of the
world you know we know because we wrote
the game that the game only exists right
where you are you know and and well and
we also have the ability to simulate
sort of things on background threads and
stuff like that so but we know that
there's a subset of the actual world
that's ever really being looked at here
and what we want to do as much as
possible when we're making the engine is
limit the degree to which the player
feels that lip that limitation right we
would like them to sort of believe for
the most part like part of the
suspension of disbelief there we would
like them to believe that the entire
game is in existence at all times and so
things like having part of the world
drop out when you switch the simulation
to from room to room isn't easy it's
something we want to have happen and so
what I'd like to do is again like make
sure that that sort of thing is is never
really precede perceptible to the to the
player
now what you can see what you can see
happening is this purple region here
when I move like that the purple region
is just cutting it off right that's
what's happening so we have two choices
there one is we can enlarge the purple
region but not really want to enlarge
the purple region because the larger the
purple region cost us more resources so
rather what I do is what I'd rather do
is say look let's assume that the purple
region from the last room you're in
maybe we assume that that region is
merged with the new region temporarily
while the camera transitions and then
once the camera has successfully
transitioned out you know we will then
drop that region from consideration or
something right another thing we can do
is can do a continuous slide like we can
sort of slide the region slowly away we
do have reasons why we might not want to
do that there's a lot of different
concerns that play here but there's a
lot things we could do so one thing we
could do is merge them so for example a
really simple way and there's some
reasons why we might not want to do this
we can get in those reasons later and
I'll put it through in there to look at
it but just really quickly I can show
you what I mean is we can take we
because we know where the camera is
right we can take the camera rectangle
and we can use that as part of the
simulation region automatically to make
sure that it's always in right so if we
take a look here when we're doing our
our simulation region determination we
have this info information here like
camera bounds and meters and and world
camera rectum and that kind of junk
there so when we produce the sim bounds
like we do here what we can do is merge
the camera rec in so what I could do is
say sim bounds equals you know the union
of these two rectangles like the world
camera rect and the simulation bounds I
can Union those two together and that
was sure that I always have at least
that part there so now what you can see
is even the the world itself kind of
still continues to be in play at that
point and so now what you can see is as
I move around you you no longer get
same glitch where everything drops out
now we probably need a little bit of a
safety apron there I'm not sure I'm not
seeing any glitching at there it is you
see do you see that glitching right if
the thing that's because again the
bounds are sort of like an inner out
thing and an entity has a bigger radius
than the bounds so really in here you
know you would want to enlarge the sim
bounce slightly in two to account for
that apron so you know if we wanted to
we could do also this in fact I suppose
the the world camera rect here could
have an ADD radius to applied to it and
so inside radius to here we could just
say look let's say we add you know you
know five meters on on either side of
that just to give it a little bit of
extra coverage there or something and
then once we have that then I think we
would know for certain that we would not
see that glitch because now we've got a
little bit of a safety apron and now we
would know that we would never allow
stuff to drop kind of out of the
simulation region if the camera can see
it right so it's just an extra let left
like added level of protection there
that's just good for for it's just good
for business there right and so now you
can see if I hop around here you can see
that as we slide around you can see that
safety apron making sure that the purple
region never contracts too early and
that keeps that glitch from happening so
you know like I said that's an easy fix
for now there's reasons why we may not
want to do it and and I'll just put
briefly in here
so one of the things that we did was we
have these sort of notions of collected
entities right that we call brains which
are when you have entities that maybe
want to be made up of multiple parts so
for example let's suppose that we have
one of our little snake entities is
going around one of the problems that
you would get with a sliding simulation
region like that is part of the snake
might be moved out of the simulation
region while another part is still in
and the problem with that that you would
see again is just that it doesn't allow
it doesn't it could lead to bugs where
entities get separated by that window
and then you end up with a snake that's
in two halves for no reason right we did
add some protection for that and I just
again I just want to flag it as saying
cuz that's a fairly complex part of this
system it's the hardest part really I
think that we'll have to get right and
so I just want to be aware of it as we
go forwards to make sure that we don't
have a problem with that but I believe
we did add some protection to that I
think I don't know why we still have
that move entity call we gotta get rid
of some of that but I do think there was
something in here that we did
[Music]
and I just I don't quite remember but I
do remember a sort of I do remember a
sort of like hemming and hawing about
that I just don't remember it's been a
while yes I mean I'm sorry I don't
remember this very well I just I
probably don't really want to go down
this rathole at the moment cuz it's
really just not relevant but hopefully
those of you who watch the show
regularly will remember what I'm talking
about and maybe we didn't do it and I
just am forgetting but I'm pretty sure
we did where we sort of had a thing that
we'd go oh yeah like you know if you
unpacked the brain of this thing then
unpack all of it or stuff like that
there was some kind of thing that tried
to do that
so yeah sorry I mean I'm apologize for
not know exactly where that is we'll
have to go back and look it up again I'm
pretty sure there was something that we
at least tried and maybe we decided that
that just wasn't really something that
we were going to pursue and I deleted it
or something like that but I'm pretty
sure we did something where we tried to
make it so that brains would get a
little bit preferential treatment so
that as entities got packed or unpacked
they tried to pack into the same chunks
even perhaps unnecessarily or weird
things like this and I just don't quite
remember what we did for that I think it
had to do with the fact that if
something was in the apron it would pull
it into the active set Eve so I I don't
really remember
so anyway point being when we go to look
at that code again at some point it's
just something that I wanted to make
sure that we were aware of and you know
that's just neither here nor there
so anyway getting back to what I wanted
the rest of the topic of today to be is
now what I want to do is make sort of a
dynamic camera zoom level if you will if
you remember how we were doing this in
the camera code where we just have a
very basic update bit camera for enemy
movement code what we did here is we
sort of said look we're just gonna hard
code what the target offset Z is unless
we see some kind of an override from
like a camera volume that's that's you
know telling us that we want to focus on
something else so that's a totally
reasonable thing to do and we can sort
of leave that system in place and just
improve it you can see we've got also
room boundary problems here so I don't
know if you can see what's happening
there so what's happening there is we
didn't set our room boundaries up
properly so the hero when he's on the
square in between two rooms it can't
decide which camera to pick right so we
want to fix that as well and that's
pretty easy to fix as well but
separate issue so anyway ignoring that
temporarily just getting back to my
stalking out so what we want to do here
is we want to say all right let's start
making sure that we always have that
camera information so this which is what
we're using before which says how high
up you want to be just to give you an
example what I'm talking about so if I
recompile the game here you can see me
zoom in this is the appropriate level of
zoom for this room perhaps now maybe we
don't ever want to be that close so
maybe there's a minimum that's like here
or something so even though we really
could be closer in that room we won't be
we'll just be this as a minimum this is
the level of zoom that we want for this
room but when we come to this room right
it's not quite sufficient
so we could do one of two things and
again this is really up to us when we're
designing the levels in the generator
it's logic that puts out this room can
make a decision about which one it wants
either we want the camera to scroll
which is something we want to specify
here right or we want it to zoom out but
we want it to do one of those two things
so probably you know what I would want
to do most of time is just zoom out so
the player can see the whole room and so
that requires a zoom level of something
you know quite a bit substantially wider
here like so like something like that
right and so we need the camera to be
able to to understand that when the room
gets bigger it needs the bigger zoom
level right so what we want to do is
really one of two things and I don't
know which one of these two things we
actually want it may be that we really
don't want to go the math route on this
one and the reason I say we might not
want to go the math on this one is it
may just be more about tuning so it may
just be more about the fact that you
know we want to set whatever this value
is and yeah we just want that to be
whatever it is now you can see we got
another thing we want we're going to
want to fix when we do this is
well which is that right now the fog
level is hard-coded so eventually if I
get far enough out like let's say I
wanted to set this as the zoom level
well that it'll everything will fog out
right you can kind of see how everything
is is is beginning to get reduced color
wise and eventually I get far enough out
it'll actually fall out of the clip
plane even right not to mention the fact
that will blow out our lighting buffers
here but that's the sort of separate
issue right so one of the other things
we have to do is if we want to support
zoom levels that are you know more that
allow those those bigger rooms to all be
in view then what we need to be able to
do is we need to be able to set the
fogging so that the fogging correctly
adapts right the fog can't just be at a
hard-coded level the fog has to kind of
be more reasonable now I don't know if
we ever really want this kind of a zoom
level is the other problem so I'm
thinking maybe you know the zoom has to
top out at some point not sure where
that point is so it may be like this is
where the zoom tops out like this is how
far about out we go anyway and what we
may do is just allow scrolling inside
rooms that are this big right and the
normal room is one that just fits in
here right the normal rooms that will be
about this size and then you know and
then we'll go from there
so that's my thinking on this anyway at
in so much as I've I've done it that's
what I'm thinking
oh excuse me all right
so I think what I want to do here is I
think I just want to stick with the with
the hand coded option I think I want to
just go ahead and have a table which is
it like four different kinds of rooms
that my generator generates I want them
to just have something that I specified
where I said specifically this is how
this is how far the camera should be
away a way for a room of this size and I
tuned it manually
to what I wanted because I think it's
just a preference issue and I don't
think the math is gonna help us here
like the math will just give us an
approximate answer that's like whatever
the exact bounds would be that's a an
approximate answer for what a human
might want to see but a human might want
it tuned a little out or a little in
from there or whatever and the math is
not going to tell us that I don't think
so I think it's not really worth doing
that math it's my assumption anyway
don't quote me on that
alright I'll stop marveling at the
profile now ok so what we want to do
here is we want to go ahead and just
actually start looking at the the camera
stuff here you can see the the room
volume information effectively what I
want to do I think is maybe make the
room volume I mean I think what we want
to do is those room volumes want to be
always have the camera offset in them
right because you can see here the only
time that we do take a target offset Z
from the from the data is when there's a
special camera but I don't think we
actually want to do it that way I think
we want to take it from the room always
and then and then have the the special
camera just be additional things that
can be specified but that's about it
so in here where we do type brain room
that probably wants to get that
information directly out of there so so
I'm gonna say we want something more
like this
so just in general whenever there's a
room that room should specify an offset
to Z and that is just a property of the
of the entity itself now we've already
got that in there for special cameras I
believe you see here
don't quote me on that
so I guess we could just use like a
camera offset Z and for that matter I
suppose the X Y could be specified as
well I don't really want to do that part
yet and this may want to get this this
may want to get sort of upgraded a
little bit too but yeah so this okay so
I feel like we've got base of the
building box we need here I'm gonna
start with this one and I think we will
also do is we'll put we can roll all of
this I think together a little bit
better and specify whether we want
whether we want there to be scrolling I
think that could come in here as well so
we'll see we'll see so if I go back in
now to my world the world generator I
mean one of things that should happen
immediately is if I specify this we
should immediately sort of suck directly
in because that'll be set to zero
normally and so we will just go like bra
and it'll just be a nightmare right I'm
guessing so yeah like we're zero away
and I feel like that's a degenerate
condition right so you pretty much never
want this to be set to that what we can
do in the world gen code then is just
make sure we always set it to something
if that's the room gencode actually make
sure we always set it to something and
so in here where we where we do camera
room like this what we want to do is
just specify here cam room camera offset
Z that would set it to 16 is what we had
it before for all rooms right and so now
whenever you move around it'll set it
right but what we want to do now is have
a table that sort of decide
it's based on the dimensions of the room
what's going to happen right and so in
order to do that I'm just gonna sort of
create a little formula here and then
tweak it to my preferences and we'll go
from there so what I want to do is is
say look I know how big we made the room
I've got X count in Y count and those
pretty much tell me and so what I want
to do is I want to here sort of figure
out what the zoom level is so maybe I'll
do something like get off set a get
camera off set Z for dimensions and I'll
pass the X count and the Y count and
I'll just say that this thing has to you
know has to have a way of determining
for a given x and y dimension what
should it actually produce right and so
I sort of said well like maybe 12 is
like the answer in all situations that
aren't handled some other way so like
for example maybe this is just the
default
right and then we adjust things a little
bit depending on what else it is so I
don't know maybe this is like as far out
as we get but then when we come into
something like this maybe we zoom in a
little bit and and so on and so forth
right so I'm not sure about that maybe I
want it a little bit bigger maybe I
don't
again this is something that can be
tweaked all throughout the game design
process and also since I'm not a game
designer I a priori absolve myself for
making any good decisions but point
being architectural II speaking I think
it's the right decision to put it in
here because that way if you one was a
game designer and did have an idea of
what they were doing you would be able
to do it
just fine okay so let's suppose that
we're going to do that here then what we
want to do I think is determine sort of
an X version in a Y version and then
take whichever one is greater because
remember what we're going to do is say
well we've
a certain way we might want to do the
camera based on widths of things in a
certain way we might wanna do the camera
based on heights of things in terms of
rooms with some height or I should say
maybe X&amp;Y dimension in the plane and so
I want to have a formula for each of
those and then I want to take whatever
one wants to be further out because our
preference will always be to go further
out so if you if you'd want to be a
certain distance to see this width and a
certain just see this height well we'll
take whichever one is maximum because
that's the one that would be preferred
right we don't want to if you said you
wanted to be this far out to see one of
these two things we don't want to move
you in closer than that certainly right
so we'll do something like X dist and
widest here right and those will both be
at 0 or maybe we'll make this at the
minimum so I don't know what the minimum
would be maybe the minimum what what is
the minimum that we'd want to be let's
find out it's at like 8 state to close
so you know I don't know maybe it's a
little too close maybe it's more like 10
maybe you know I don't know how much
variability there's gonna be here
exactly but that seems like you know so
this room is what like 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 what is this like that's good
counting Casey 1 2 3 so this is a 13
wide room
I think sent right yeah it's a 13 wide
room so given them that's a 13 that
that's a room that has 13 squares in it
you know for 13 squares I think 10 would
would be good 10 was a good one right so
I'm gonna go ahead and say that like if
the X count is less than 13 I would
leave it at 10 right so basically what
we're talking about if it's greater than
13 that's when we would actually start
to care so looking at this maybe what
I'll say is like okay the x disk tops
out at like 14 or whatever we said that
large amount is going to be somewhere
else
so if the X count is greater than yeah
if the X count is greater than like some
remember we want they're not sure what
that number would be but let's say we
have a couple ones here
so we do something like say well assume
it's ten if for anything over one of
these then we'll then we'll set it to
something more specific I'm not sure
what that has to be but like somewhere
in here we end up getting to a room
that's the biggest we want and after
that it's just working all the way right
so I don't know we set this to something
randomly like that you know this is all
we're kind of talking about here and we
can make a more convenient function for
this later and then at the end we just
say like the result of servers is the
larger those two so what's the y count
it's gonna be quite a bit less I would
say just because of the eccentricity the
difference between those two right so
maybe this is more like this sort of
thing again I'm not really sure oops
so now if I run it you know like in this
room which is sort of the smallest room
I would expect and I think I can even
look right because we we have the Delta
oh no that was the build from sim I
should I should just write out what that
is so for example inside world's mode in
here we've got I specify the Delta from
sim there let me also just specify the
camera offset that we're using and so
that's right here and that kind of tells
us what this room ended up getting set
to right so if I look through here and I
say like okay here's the offset Z it
should be set to ten for the smallest
rooms right and it is that's what that's
approaching there when I move out to a
larger room in theory it should get
larger if it needs to this room still
fits entirely so that it doesn't
actually have to but let's say I go to
the room to the right that room would
probably get bigger right and so there
we've zoomed out now we haven't quite
zoomed out big enough but that's the
maximum sort of that we were saying we
would do right so you know that's why it
didn't is because we don't want to let
it go over 14 and I think that's
reasonable anyway you can see this is
working nice and smooth now right it
just picks the right size for various
rooms the only thing that we have now is
we may want to do something about the
scrolling right so we may want to make
it so that large rooms like this don't
actually zoom out they just stay at 14
and and scroll around slightly depending
on
you know depending on where the player
is inside the room so that's about the
only thing we'd have to do now before I
do that because I would like to do that
but before I do that what I would like
to do is yeah and you know you could see
- do you see it what a nice feeling that
gives the game already right it's really
nice to have that sort of quiet zoom in
it just feels nice when you're doing it
right it's just getting smaller and
bigger just it's again it adds visual
interest to the game and it's just it's
kind of a pleasant right it's just kind
of a pleasant thing so I think that's
great and that's just something that we
want to just keep in mind like little
things like that they make a game the
more of those you have in a game just
it's just a pleasant graphical thing and
that's why people are playing a game
right you know if you if you didn't care
about graphics we didn't care about
audio visual feedback you wouldn't
bother playing a video game you could
just play something pen and paper right
so there's a reason that you're playing
a video game and it's stuff like that
right you want the game designed to be
good obviously but you want that game
designed to be backed up by nice good
feeling audio and visual reinforcement
because that's the whole point of the
game being on a computer right is to
have that sort of thing so let's go
ahead and look at this bug now like I
said I believe this is just because we
need overlap we can't have the rooms
being divided on a boundary we want the
thing to be in between the two we just
need this to be conveyed more accurately
right it's not being calculated properly
right now and so we end up splitting a
tile instead of keeping the tiles in the
rooms themselves right so that's just
it's just wrong so we want to fix that
first before we go any further because
that's where the main part of the bug is
coming from is that this is wrong that's
just not correct
all right so
so if we look at this the problem is
that these are sort of off by a half
right Mint I'll X should be a half
include a half extra because every just
look at what the bounds are here you can
see what I'm talking about it runs right
down the middle and that's you know
correct what we were computing there was
an accurate computation it was computing
the Centers of tiles right and the
problem is that we've got it off
so instead of computing the boundary of
the room what we computed is the center
of the tile that we're on and then the
width of the room correctly but what
that does is it puts us on the center of
the next rooms tile so this whole thing
needs to be shifted back by half a tile
in right in order to get the correct
address there so when we do this we're
producing a correct size that's not
actually the problem size is correct the
problem is the volume that we're
actually producing is offset incorrectly
right so for example when we do this
place entity here and we've got the
chain Center that's the problem that
we're seeing this this is is gonna be
skewed I believe so now we're not really
looking at this we're looking at this
this we're not actually drawing at the
moment we should probably draw this in
fact I guess I can draw that
so this will draw probably way too many
of these things but it should also draw
the room boundary and so there you can
see the room boundary one interesting
thing you can see about that is and this
I believe is also because of the way we
compute the change volume so again all
this stuff is nice to go get right what
you can see is that it's actually
aligned okay on one axis but not on the
other and you might feel like well how
did that happen the answer is because of
the way we computed the chain Center so
all these things are relative of the
chain Center here and here we go into
that code do you see this so what ends
up happening is if the X count is even
you will get it aligned one way and if
it's odd you'll get it aligned the other
way because of the rounding on there
because this integer right um
so what we want to do is just make that
be more rigorous and actually align it
up with where the room actually is but
what we would see is certain rooms will
align differently if I if it had an even
number it would align one axis if it has
an odd number of line I'm if it's an
even number it will align the center of
the odd number aligned to the boundary
or vice versa and quite think of through
which one would be which but that's
exactly what we're seeing is that
difference there and that's why some are
aligned and some are so now our job is
just to go ahead and get those collision
volumes to be lined up correctly and so
that's what we'll go ahead and do here
right okay so when we talk about the
chain Center
so just looking at how this works right
the change rectangle on the chain Center
they're gonna be round into a tile and I
think that's probably what we want so
right like we want to
yeah so so we don't I guess now I think
about it since all of the entities are
created really agnostic of the change
center because that you can see here
everything is done with a place entity
call with an absolute position right so
we're sort of placing all of our
entities correctly either way so really
this change center could do whatever we
want right we we don't really have to
have this being aligned in any
particularly good way it doesn't really
matter right so in a sense this can be
whatever it wants the problem comes when
we come down here to the room placement
what were the problem really is that
we're using the chain Center as where
the room is but that's not where the
room actually is what we need to do is
compute the actual center for real about
where the room really is in reality
right and that has to include if there
is a half tile offset in here that has
to be respected right so we can't the
chain Center has been rounded we don't
want it to be rounded right we don't
want this rounding to be happening that
way so that's the part that we need to
fix is this place entity call has to
take the collision volume for the room
and line it up right and while we're at
it we'd like to fix this one too because
this sort of thing that we'll use for
mapping later I think I'm not sure what
we're gonna do the mapping that's why we
have that ad world room thing in there
is just for that purpose that's that's
the other part of that that we want to
be able to do right so we want that to
be accurate as well it doesn't really
matter if it's accurate but we would
like it to be accurate because why not
right
so yeah
so this size is correct this is off by a
half tile potentially in either
direction and the question is how do we
actually figure out where it is in that
sense right how do we figure out what
the center of it actually is well what I
assume we want to do here is say look we
know whether or not each of these
dimensions was odd or even and so we
sort of know well you know what I would
say maybe we just just compute the
center maybe more directly right so if
we want to these two things are the
these are the two positions of the min
tile and the max tile right so I think
what we could do is say let's just go
ahead and get these two because if we
get these two values the min P and the
Max be here
if we get those two values and I think
this world room this this doesn't really
need to be in here by the way since
we're gonna do the canvas with the
standard what volume stuff if we have
these two values then what I can do is
actually just take their their centroid
and be done with it right so we know
this is the center of the tile and we
want these to really be based on the min
and the max of the tile so what we want
to do here is we want to like map these
in and then also offset them right and
what we could do in fact when we have
chunk position from tile position we can
offset that I don't know if if this
takes an offset it does so when we do
chunk position from tile position there
what we can do is specify negative half
tile offset and positive half tile or
something like that right so we can pull
out to the to the tile dimensions there
in either direction all we want and so
all we need is to know how much half a
tile is and that is something that
should be specified right
[Music]
so the way this actually does it is like
this right and is that's kind of a
little ad hoc with the tile side and
meters thing it kind of feels like
that's something that wants to be more
of a generative situation I'm curious so
yet what you can see here and this is
sort of again starting to clean up
something that always bugged me which is
the tile information so I don't know why
I can't quite do this too in right there
so one of the things that we might want
to do there say look now we can kind of
finally see where that information
should go
so like chunk position from tile
position at this point I would say is
something that should rely on the
generator actually less the world more
of the generator right so I would like
to see this turn into this bizarre there
it is I would like to see this turn into
this and I would like to see this be
something that comes from here because
really our entire world system cares not
all about tiles right nothing cares
about tiles at all the only thing that
cares about tiles is the generator
because it wants to place things in a
grid sometimes right and so when it's
doing that it wants to know about tiles
everybody else doesn't care about tiles
so that's the right place finally after
so much of us playing around we finally
see emergently where tiles should live
they should live there so now this goes
into the world generation code right
where we know that at a startup time
here when we actually go to begin this
that's begin world gym this is where
that gets set like so this information
now the tile sided meters that finally
can get rid of that to do and then the
tile depth and meters again should
always come from the generator so really
these things are making me grumpy
probably my ears are clogged so really
all we want to do here is just say this
also now always comes from the generator
as well
and I think the world would then get
passed in here as something we should
always have oddly enough
over sim region it's there but I I'm
gonna hoist the world out because it's
always going to have one yeah so that
all looks good to me I don't know that
we really want that at the end of the
day we may change how that gets
specified at some point
[Music]
but that's roughly what we want there
and if I take a look at who else was
interested in that then I can start to
yet yeah then I can start to just clean
this coat up and just finally get that
stuff done so let's go ahead and finish
this I know that I want the tile
dimension to be in there I know the
world can come out of the generator
easily could so it's gonna be there I
know that these all need to be calling
Jen instead worlds but that's fine sighs
have that this stuff here again is the
tile dim this is great cuz now this
stuff can go away right that never
happens anymore and this can just be Jen
or this can just be tiled MX talented Y
talboom Z and tile dim can just be
pulled out here
that's the outset and that's all great
and that's Jen Calvin X Y childhood Z
and half tile Jim is now just that and
that's awesome and I love all of that
because that totally now finally answers
the question of where that stuff belongs
it belongs right there and now we can
just say for once and for all we're done
with that right so that's good okay so
now we go back to what we were doing
before which is let's go ahead and try
to make sure these things are aligned
properly so what I was doing first there
trying to make sure that I aligned the
the the a dream call and what you can
see here is I accidentally screwed up we
want to shift it back by the same amount
in both cases and I actually expanded it
by an entire tile so this should not
have been a plus right that was supposed
to be a minus so my bad there but
otherwise I think we had everything
roughly correct and now you can see that
those bounds correctly encompass the
room now what I don't know is how we
want to deal with Z so that's a little
bit confusing like it's in terms of how
far down or up these rooms should extend
that part I don't know I think that's
off and I think the reason that that's
off is because if you look at what
happens inside the world gen chunk thing
there there it is you can see that we do
like an offset automatically on
everything to make sure that it kind of
lines up with how we were thinking about
tiles so I don't know what we want to do
about that
[Music]
so the reason that that was in there is
because the floor information we yeah
like I don't think we really thought it
through very much we kind of just were
always hand wavey a little bit about
that stuff so you know the centers of
things I feel like like I feel like we
just don't really want that to be
happening I feel like we want to treat
all these things uniformly to a certain
degree and you know so you know I'm
tempted to just say oops I'm tempted to
just say we want that and then we want
our rooms to just be aligned however we
want to align them right so when we look
at women's up happening there we want to
just make sure that we align the rooms
properly based on the half table outer
so we would like move everything down
and that in theory would also solve the
other problem I'm not sure about that
and we should probably draw the chunk
boundaries in here as well either way
it's something we want to get correct so
I don't really know how we want to go
about doing that part but now is as good
time as any to make sure that we get
this stuff right let me finish what I
was doing here and then let's go tackle
that alignment problem by drawing the
chunks and figuring out whether we want
this anymore
and figuring out how those are gonna
break down into room boundaries so if we
take this where we have them in room in
the P and the maximum P when we go to
places entity we can create a room
center here and the room center would
just be the difference between these two
right so if you imagine a room center
here
what we
want to do is let's see where we have
well code so we want to do here is take
the difference between these two things
right so we want to say look if we have
the min room P and the max room P and we
took the difference between them that
would tell us how to get from one to the
other so then we can just do look we
just want to map that into one of our
canonical coordinates from the min room
P back and that's it right so that
should give us an actual room center
based on the bounds we actually computed
and furthermore the simple collision
volume here now no longer would have to
do it that way we could just use the
subtract so for example what we could do
here is say rim dimension so there's a
room dimension or you know room
dimension in meters intervention in
meters room dimension in meters you know
I'm saying so the room demand meters in
the room Center now I'll give us that
information that we actually wanted and
in theory that would give us so that the
room in both cases is placed on the same
rectangle in both systems so everyone
knows where everything is the only thing
I don't know is is this ampersand it it
is this takes not a v3 I guess the
collision volume stuff probably is going
to want to get a little bit better soon
too as well as we move forward but now
is not the time to to dive into that
situation oops so I broke something
I'm just not sure what let's take a look
somebody gonna jump into that room Jen
call there and I'm gonna go see what's
up
there's our tyldum which looks fine
here's arm in room P max room P also
looks fine here's our room gym in metres
looks good and what about our own Center
so I guess I don't really know what this
coven does I should probably work
ah okay so yes so some of this stuff is
a little bit borked right you can kind
of see yeah we don't we don't really
want that anyway so this collision
volume is the collision volume really
just a rectangle I'm confused because I
thought we were allowed to have like
multiple pieces of collision or
something like that maybe we deleted
that in that case this is just forget it
like why do we why did I even bother we
know what the room dimension is in
meters so you know in fact we don't even
have to do any of that this this week we
could just avoid the subtract altogether
we could really do is just say something
like this
what was that call
get some relative position we really
should if we call it map into chunks
face this should probably call map into
sim space could be symmetric there and
then when we set the collision volume
for the Senate II since we're placing
manatee at the room center then the
collision volume should just be the
volume from the min to the max right and
that'd be bad so that's what I think we
want this gunfire to look like there we
go
so map into some space I just need the
start creation region his region just
yes it is and in fact when does that get
set
so that's dead code as well alright so
if we know the main room P and the
maximum P here right we could just find
those in in sim space and then just say
that the entity is placed at the chain
Center and then we'd be done right of
course
placing the entity might be important I
don't know if it is or not so that
part's a little bit dicey
I don't know how I feel about that one
way or the other
choose me but point being we can just do
that and then I think it's it would just
be accurate I think let me actually see
here
so now you can see everything lining up
nicely let me go back to the optimized
build and I also don't 100% know if that
fixes our problem or not I think we want
this to not be based on the head we want
it to be based on the body since the
body's the thing that moves discretely
so that's kind of another can see our
near plane is also kind of busted there
so I think really what we want to do now
just focus on the Z because these rooms
are not aligned properly they want to be
up more and so we want to talk about the
tile placement a little bit more
carefully so that has to happen because
otherwise our camera stuff is off right
these need to be offset up and and you
can see - it's it's because it's going
to be placed down at the bottom of the
world here right and that's just wrong
so we've got a lot of issues we got to
address there so we need to focus on the
Z and get that right everything else
seems okay except that when we come to
this the head can can peek right into
the next room over maybe we want that I
don't know to think about that maybe we
want to be able to do that
like maybe that's just kind of nice to
be able to sort of look into the next
room I don't know maybe I'll keep that
for now that's kind of fun it's like
what's in there do I really want to go
in there so maybe if that yeah I don't
know but that would only be if there was
an open door there you know if it's like
a closed door or you got to walk through
it maybe I don't know so I don't know
maybe we really just do want it to be on
the body
ya couldn't tell you if we wanted to be
on the body instead of on the if we
wanted to do it that way
right if we wanted to track it I believe
when we when we set that what the
following entity is we can just choose
to set some other following entity right
so we could if we wanted to just say the
body is what the cameras following and
then it just will follow that so it's
not particularly hard for us to make a
decision either way and if we did that
then it's much clearer and we don't get
the sort of ambiguous hovering the head
over so you know for now let's leave it
like that we may want to play with it a
little bit more later because it was the
idea of peeking into a room is kind of
interesting I don't know it may be
nothing but it's just kind of
interesting and then we've kind of got
rid of that glitch so now I think we
just want to focus on the Z because now
that's clearly wrong now and causing us
some problems so we need to sort of fix
that Z problem and then we can sort of
go from there right
okay the other thing that would be nice
would be to add some lights you know I'm
saying at the moment we sort of have
this idea that the the there's like a
big blocky light thing that follows the
human it follows the play around there
and also I think we've got kind of like
there's the snake thing add add snake
segment thing this guy right and there's
this add piece light it probably would
be good to do a thing that was just like
hey you know here's a lamp and I can
just put a lamp somewhere you know
and maybe with a color I don't know just
making this up as I go but maybe there's
a way to add a lamp and that way we can
sort of have the brooms have lamps in
them like so for example in here you
could just say well you know whatever
the center tile the room is you know
maybe we add a lamp there so we just say
alright let's put a white lamp into the
sim region at you know some location
that's like mint aisle X plus X counter
or to like the center of the room
or maybe we do like the corners of the
room in the center of the room I don't
know but you know just to see if it
works something like this
and just place that in and you know
these things should be up a little bit
probably so you know maybe just place it
towards the top of the thing so it's
just maybe that kind of thing think
that's anyway version from double like
that and then you know there's just like
lamps in the rooms
I guess maybe if I didn't screw that up
which I might have so you can see
there's like a big lamp in every room
now it looks like maybe they're a little
too bright so that's probably not the
best thing in the world to have and I
admit that
so maybe back off on the light level a
little bit but then I could also get rid
of the fact that there's a thing here
around cuz that was like Freddie bugging
and like I don't intend the hero to be
holding a light in any circumstance
other than the circumstance where he is
holding a light for some reason whatever
the light is right so that was you know
not something that was ever supposed to
actually be happening so this this here
like what's just not
it's not half at all right so now at
least we've got those lamps there that
are hanging around we probably want them
to actually be visible like the lamps
should probably actually be actual
objects in the scene eventually at the
moment they're not and that's fine but
you know eventually we want them to be
actual like lamps somewhere placed
somewhere you know and we probably also
don't want them to be quite so bright as
they are that that may have been a
little bit excessive and I admit that so
you know maybe this is something more
like you know half half that brightness
it's a little bit more reasonable you
know
so yeah
all right so if I maybe take that a
little bit further so suppose I don't
really want to white do it that way what
if I just say you know it's gonna be
placed like this
I'm just curious here what's gonna
happen because I kind of accidentally
got myself distracted so again what we
want to do is fix that Z stuff for a
number of reasons but until I do that
let me just kind of mess a little bit
with this light situation and then we'll
fix it later so if I go into room Jen
and look at that add lamp call I want to
make it so that it's maybe more
reasonably sized like a lamp actually it
would be you know and then maybe I want
to place them like in the world as if
they're actual objects right so you know
they they go in to the world in some
reasonable fashion so looking at like
where the lamps will be placed
maybe there's also it prevents things
from being placed at that location so
like maybe there isn't a traversable
there like you can't actually stand on
that square or something like this so if
you imagine maybe that they're like
point four up the tile dim and maybe
there's a couple of them in the corners
of the room so maybe we do something a
little bit different like something like
say this
this is not really how I want to do this
long term so we should probably hold off
on anything like this until until I
actually start writing more real room
generation code but let's say in here we
just said okay you know if the X index
equals 1 and the Y index equals 1 place
a lamp there and then I can say like
okay if x equals 1 and the y and x
equals y count - just putting it in the
corners
so that's all I was thinking then it'll
add a lamp to their and in that case it
will also say like
so in this case we'll always set the
whoops we don't really need to do quite
that I guess so what we would say is
just if not on lamp because I don't want
you to walk where the lamp is I guess
so that's just kind of super crappy and
random but that's just what we're going
with at the moment again I just wanted
to kind of put some lights in there for
fun and we'll try to make that work okay
so now I actually just instead of all of
this I just used the actual position
there we go
yeah and then we should be good to go
I need to when we add the lamp I need to
sort of offset it so that it is the
correct distance off the ground I
suppose for now I'll bake that into this
maybe I don't
again really we kind of want to get the
Z under control now it's not really sure
what I want to do here I kind of need to
like think it through and get a little
bit more serious about it before we go
much further so anyway it's trying to
place these for now as temporary things
in the world that will be usable
[Music]
probably want to be a little higher
all right so now we've got lights at the
corners of rooms so when we walk around
we should see yeah and we do kind of
always have lights there again they're
not very good in this case because
they're kind of too low to the ground so
I think we want them to be a little bit
higher ups even still than they are
there we go
and so now we just need to fix that Z so
that's really all I wanted was yet there
we go we got our kind of lamps in there
and ideally there'd be other sort of
some lamps around the room as well maybe
some lamps in in the actual in the
center
all right so now let's figure out what's
going on with our Z we have a lot of
annoying Z stuff in here that we really
should just now take the time to clean
up because like as we're going through
cleaning up everything it's just it's
important to like once you know how
things work to actually go in and kind
of make them more systemic right and and
try to get try to actually have
everything be working properly there so
yeah all of that looks fine oh you know
what else I should do sorry to keep
tweaking there one thing we probably
should do is just add some randomization
there
and yeah I don't remember what the
random Sirius was entropy say let's
pretend it's entropy hey it is alright
so then there should be a little
variability of the light color I'll be
honest I don't see any
because I would have expected to see
some I don't know if are we not using
that we are there we go now we're
getting it
now maybe we don't really want that and
again we don't have exposure control so
it's yeah I mean until we have a little
bit more in terms of the lighting output
it maybe is not sensible to have that
variability in there but I figured I'd
put it in anyway just ring it for a
little bit so you can see a little bit
of difference between the lights right
you can see that one's a little bit
cooler that one's a little bit warmer
right so that seems pretty good
all right um so now I want to take a
look at the Z stuff how much time do I
have left I've got I don't know how much
time I've got left
let's ask because in Tabata knows oh
four minutes into the Q&amp;A I don't think
that's true I'm not sure about that
maybe in sohbats wrong about that I'm I
should add a time part to this I never
really use it so I never really think to
do so yeah I'm not sure anyway we'll
just let that tell us when it's done but
I want to just get the Z stuff working
now because the cameras in the wrong
place at the moment and so I want to fix
that right and I'd like to make it so
that the cameras in the wrong place
pacifically because the center of the
room is down here and that's what it's
focusing on it should not be focusing on
that right it should be focusing on the
this area of the floor and so this needs
to be shifted up by a half and the
problem that I have is I don't really
know why right so we kind of played it
fast and loose with a number of Z things
as we were going through there because
we didn't really know how things really
going on but now that we actually are
making everything lockdown and concrete
one of the problems we get is now we
need to make these policies be correct
now we already made a really nice big
step forwards already by figuring out
where the tile information supposed to
go and that was great because that's
finally it kind of the end of a of a
long time of not really knowing exactly
where that should go but now if we look
at what we're dealing with here when
we're creating these tile things and
creating the span of the room I think we
now need to think about this a little
bit more in terms of where
everything is the first thing that I
think is pretty crappy and that we're
gonna have to immediately fix and I'll
just start with it because I know it I
don't like it
is we asymmetrically treat the sizes of
cubes right and that's just bad so you
can see it here and it says it right in
the to do so let's just do it
we're in Z correction mode let's stop
that nonsense it's just just no just bad
right
incorrect false wrong no don't do not do
right so when we push a cube let's just
force everyone to update we're just
gonna pass the v3 radius for the cube
and now it's like that's what you have
to do so just do it and shut up
right now that'll break everyone's code
so now we're in happy code land copy
code code Ville code Ness happy and so
we just have to now follow those changes
out and fix them all right so fix
everywhere that was you know it was
doing this wrong we want to fix all of
that so let's go ahead and do that first
thing here is I guess when we call push
cube what are we complaining about do we
have a push cube lofted out somewhere
pv3
radius radius
be three radius so what are you
complaining about nanotubes Kruger types
could be push cube V 3 V 3 while trying
to match the argument render group
loaded bitmap V 3 V 3 F 32 lighting
point state
so that's this one right here and it
does do that doesn't it
what am I missing
this does group bitmapped PE radius ah I
forgot to lead height sorry there we go
so now in this one this was already
correcting for that you can see it doing
it right here right it was correcting
for the fact that it wasn't symmetric so
now we can just get rid of that and make
sure that it is right passing it's
symmetric so that's great and so now all
we have to do is just V 3fi this so when
we're just passing the Dimension X but
here we can pass
no sure I was passing the dimension why
is the emission okay that's you one way
to do it that's packing that in there
clever mr. mr. clever man I don't really
want to do that anymore
so let's go ahead and not do that let's
go ahead and do that properly so I
snuggled this in there for the entity
visible piece I put in that in that
dimension there I was putting for the
light I was because you know there's two
values for gym in there I was sort of
cheating and putting the emission level
in there for whatever reason now why I
would do that I have absolutely no idea
because if it's a light then it doesn't
have a color alpha anyway so the right
place to put that would have been here
so who knows what I was thinking at that
time probably I just wasn't but you know
some days you've got it some days you
don't in programming right and that day
I probably didn't so yeah when we come
through here and do an ad piece like all
I think AB piece light is not that this
is not right that should do something
like this and then
[Music]
that I think unless I'm missing
something so yeah then we push the light
down this here what we really want to do
is just make that be the radius of the
light in general and then I think we're
fine the push cube call it now needs to
be able to specify a dimension in a more
sort of sane way the problem here that
we have is that again we don't specify
more than one of those that's okay
because we know that this is what we
meant anyway in this case of the
encoding we should probably just upgrade
that to just be a regular
three-dimensional shape though so that's
kind of a separate situation so anyway
now what you can see is everything is a
little bit off because since we changed
the way the Z is encoded now everyone
was used to specify height they're
actually specifying a radius now right
and so since we're specify radius
numbers are now twice as large as they
should be because pre before the height
only everything else was still specified
as radius so we want to probably go
ahead and correct that now granted it's
kind of nice with the super high walls
it's it's a little bit fun it makes it
feel more like a real room actually so
who knows maybe it's actually a good
idea I don't know all I might just leave
it that way for now but regardless of
all of that we still want to do the one
important part that we were talking
about before which is now we need
everything to be centered around the
actual tile area a little bit more
correctly right because we're still
totally borked in terms of where this
stuff is supposed to be and there's two
things you want to line up with one is
we want to line up with the chunk
boundaries properly so we're aren't
constantly processing more entities than
we need to inside the pull loop and then
the other thing that we want to do is we
want to make sure that we're a little
bit more sane about how it lines up with
just the room boundaries in general
right so everything these kind of shift
downward so why is that happening well
first of all I think that's happening
partially because you know change the
hiding code
means that everybody need to sort of
think about what their height should be
relative differently than they used to
so for example inside room Jen where
we're adding these pieces and we're
specifying offsets and dimensions and
these sorts of things a lot of these
things are now offset in a way that
wouldn't necessarily be appropriate
right so like the when we add like floor
tiles for example and and we're in here
adding adding this piece type cube we
add the height again that that's a if
that's the height right it should be
half of the height and then we've got
sort of the radius level here when we
pick what the center should be if that's
the point if zero zero zero the tile
location is supposed to be the top of
the thing then we would need to subtract
this away right so it actually needs to
go down by that amount
for the actual point for the traversable
to line up right there now I'm not
saying that's what we want it to be
necessarily I'm just saying if we want
it to actually do the thing it was doing
before
that's the offset we would have to apply
right so now you can see it reverted to
the old way it used to be lined up which
again is still wrong for a separate
reason but it's now not it now doesn't
have the additional bug introduced by
the Z encoding right so now we've
restored things back to the way they
used to be and now we just need to ask
ourselves what's going on in terms of
the Z and code here right so let's talk
about that and one other thing we should
do by the way is then we want to also
look at the chunk boundaries and make
sure our rooms are aligned to the trunk
boundaries in Z properly there's no way
to get them to the line the next
properly that's not gonna happen because
since we have variable size rooms there
are no there's no meaning to that right
x and y doesn't happen on a regular grid
in any meaningful way that we care about
in terms of reducing and identity
processing so that's really just
irrelevant but the part that is relevant
to us is that floors in general in the
game are always relatively consistent
and so we want to make sure that that
part is you know we is not forcing the
system that gathers entities to do more
work than it should strictly for that
reason right and so that's kind of nice
well it's kind of nice if we do that
right all right so what we want to do
here is go we know that a tile that the
tile Z is like a stack that's like
pretty large right it's the height of a
floor and what we're trying to do is
align the world to that in some sort of
smart way now what we want is we want
the entities to generally extend no
further than the bottom of the floor and
then we want them to end probably
somewhere in the middle right so if we
look at how this is actually positioned
what we end up getting is this shame
center here where we're placing or
rather the tile location that replacing
right at that zero zero we really want
probably the room boundaries and the
world chunks to be offset like probably
a half from that so in much the same way
that we were sort of doing this half
tile dim offset here right where we
offset we probably want just trying to
think of how this is going to go
so I just want to try something real
quick here so if we don't offset the Z
at all when we correct for the alignment
here's what we get right and the reason
that we get that is again because we
extend downward and upward from a single
Z tile right the same amount so we sort
of pre-baked that notion in and so as a
result actually I should say that
differently
when we look back at this code here what
we're saying is we know that we want
zero zero zero
Chung said mrs. right we know that we
pre stated that we want zero zero zero
relative to the position of the entity
to be where the traversable czar placed
so this is the floor is that zero zero
zero relative to the entity we then said
the entity right is the wall height up
from the bottom in this line of code
right so we pre we basically pre said
that however high this thing is the
bottom of it will always be at the
bottom of the grid and the middle of it
therefore will be right roughly in the
middle so unlike the rest of the system
we don't want to offset the room
position at that point because we've
already sort of said that we weren't
going to go below there we didn't if we
had centered everything right at that
then we'd want to do that same offset
but we didn't do that right so I think
not offsetting by the half tile is what
we would want there I think
and when we do our chunk space mapping I
think we don't really want to do this
offset baked into it for any particular
reason
because I think it will still line up
correctly now I don't know because we
haven't done this in a while so the only
way I can really be sure is to draw the
chunk locations explicitly now I think
we had code to do that at one point but
I think we've long since gotten rid of
it we don't draw a chunk boundaries
anywhere here I don't think yeah so you
know let's say that we did draw a chunk
boundaries I so let's say that I want to
push a volume outline and I want to just
say like chunk boundary and I'm gonna
set that to some kind of a saucy
rectangle and then I can compute the
chunk boundary quite easily right once I
know for example where my simulation
center is going to be or really any
world position that we've got so like
for example this the cameras location or
something doesn't matter which one
anyone at all
that will have one bound I can use and
then I can create another bound I can
use out of that right so for example if
I want to create the chunk boundary here
what I could do is say all right here's
the world camera P so this is like min
chunk P and the max junk P is just the
min chunk P
with the plus right so if I go in here
to look at the world position not that
this so if I just add one to each chunk
position and furthermore I zero the
offset I've effectively created a one
chunk rectangle out of two of these
things right so if I then map those into
sim space I can then make exactly that
thing that I wanted by doing a rectum in
max-width map into some space and be
done
where's my sim region
and I think that's all we would really
need to draw it that would just show us
how big one chunk would be and so when
you look out here right now you can see
where the chunk boundaries are so
there's a chunk boundary and what I
trying to say is I want that to line up
with a floor so that the entities fit
properly within it so like I said I
think now the correct way to do that you
can see it's not lined up the floor is
to get rid of the offsetting that's
going on there so that when we create
the world it's lined up properly and so
now you can see that it does line up so
now that offsets gone and everything's
fine and we're just done with a series
as well so you know so now if I turn
everything off here and get to sort of a
more reasonable situation so now I think
everything is pretty reasonable
[Music]
you know we're hopping around we've got
our lights we've got our rooms there's
not a lot of glitching our camera is not
does not have a good interpolator and
that's something that we're gonna want
to do the camera has doesn't have a real
interpolator at the moment it's kind of
busted but now we can sort of hop around
didn't have some lights and have
whatever and and you know this now feels
like a proper I'm going around exploring
game so the next things that we need to
do are to the camera and maybe we'll do
those a little bit before doing the art
maybe we'll do this on next Saturday and
we'll start the art on Sunday or
something but what I'd like to do there
is just add something that allows
scrolling around the larger rooms
because I don't really want to zoom out
further I don't think so add something
that allows scrolling around the larger
rooms and just add a more like Seine
interpolator to
to the mix so that's good for today
let me also turn off our room boundary
coat here you don't need that and we
don't do this and there we go so there's
a happy hero hopping around with
lighting and stuff and no art and the
cameras tracking him nicely and then the
only problem he really has is you get to
a room that's too big so the camera
doesn't want to pull out any further you
can't see the whole room and so that's
where we would want that scrolling and
you can also see that the interpolation
isn't great and so those are the two
things I think that really need fixing
there right and so that all feels pretty
good
is there any particular reason why the
sim region and or lighting region are
based on world space rather than
connected rooms I know that's how it was
originally put together but are there
any benefits its advantages either way
also if you place the lighting boundary
right before a lamp and then move so it
enters the light region doesn't it kind
of pop in a little it's more of a fade
but hopefully you know what I mean
entering the big square room does what I
mean with the lamps at the top um yes so
there's kind of two questions in there
so the there is no particular reason to
use world space rather than connected
rooms we could choose to use Keck dreams
the future I don't have a strong opinion
about it yet so we'll see a little
further on what we want to do there we
may want to do connected rooms and we
may not so we'll see there's advantages
and disadvantages the advantages to
doing connected rooms is that you know
you're using one discrete like chunk of
world that makes semantic sense to the
game design the advance of using world
spaces it's a constant amount no matter
where you are so it doesn't matter how
many rooms how many how big the rooms
connected to you are you aren't like
taking a variable-length hit there so
there's there's some differences but you
know as for placing the lighting
boundary yeah there's different ways you
can do that
so I actually am okay with fade in I
think it's kind of nice actually so I
would probably leave it the way it is
now if you don't want the light to fade
in like that then what you can do is
just enlarge those boundaries right so
make the lighting boundary bigger and
then you just cost more CPU time or GPU
time a friend up using a GPU right so
I'm actually okay with that we may
enlarge it slightly more than it is
right now right so it may be that the
optimal is actually a little bit bigger
and maybe we want the you know one thing
we could do is say the active room
should always be entirely included in
the light boundary right so maybe not
connected rooms but just the active room
and so some of those things we will
address later on as we go and since we
have the ability to specify either in
any way we have the freedom to sort of
tune that I think there were two typos
get camera offset Z for dim had X count
type of tone ii get camera offset z for
gym
[Music]
ah you are right there's one right there
and push later push like cook cubed x ik
see ya that's intentional life think are
you sure it wasn't XXY I think that when
you're talking about maybe intentional
so I think it's the push piece one
probably that you're talking about are
you talking about
this one because that one is intentional
because it only starts a two dimension
it stores just the radius for X&amp;Y the
same so it duplicates that out I really
thought much but are those static light
stimulated if yes would it be good to
make they're letting peacock a to
improve forints but so no I don't want
them to be precomputed because as soon
as we add in we have to do a little bit
of stuff in the pipeline to allow the
moving objects to interact with the
lights just by add that we just need to
add light volumes for them and then
extract the lighting for when we light
the sprites so it won't be static right
when someone moves in front of the light
it'll block the light from getting
passed in that direction
so we don't really want any static
lighting in the game well up facing
sprite cars to effect about lighting
feature yes after we do exactly what I
just said
and in the up facing spray cards bit is
a little bit dicey just because we don't
really have normal maps for the sprites
so we do shadow maps no I don't really
want any hard edges in the game it's
should be like softer so there won't be
any shadow mapping there's just general
light transmission I also don't really
know how you would even do shadow
mapping with sprite cards because you
would need to know what the sprite
looked like from the perspective of the
light which you don't know now I guess
you could just guess like always make
the sprite face the light maybe but I
don't know that that would cast a very
good shadow it might catch some really
wrong looking shadows fairly often so
that part I also don't really want among
other things
I need to make stairwells happen here
because we can't the dungeon is beneath
us and we can't we can't get down there
because the rooms current regenerate
doesn't ever do that
do we have any questions yes so rooms
below us so here's a something that we
will probably want to do I don't ever
want to compute lighting for a bigger
region than I have to
so when you look at something in
perspective things that are lower down
you would have to like light much bigger
areas I don't want to do that so what we
will probably do is I will probably
write the shader such that the fog will
now be computed enough in a frustum that
goes straight down from the light so
this stuff will be outfit out entirely
it's what I'll probably do so I I don't
I definitely don't want to have to
expand the light volume out to size it's
just too much so I anticipate when I get
down to fixing those problems to be much
more conservative and like so that
basically the light volume narrows down
to a point like that and everything
alphas out because I don't want to have
to dump more things into the lighting
routine
Seve Asher I'm cleaning up the color
handling to track down rendering
differences between my OpenGL and metal
backends
[Music]
okay are you talking about liking a
handmade hero
fork or something orange your own
renderer anyway is there a generally
accepted way to past our colors in the
pipeline ie pre convert everything in
the asset Packer to linear or widest
color space the roll generate code is
currently linearizing the srgb color
input so that they can then be
reconverted to srgb by OpenGL during
blending this seems inefficient so I
guess what I would say is it really
depends on what you're doing so when you
store something if you can store it in
srgb you generally want to because it
will be smaller than storing it in
actual linear color space that's the
whole reason why we have srgb right if
we didn't have to worry about storage
space we would just always store
everything it's like a floating-point
number that was in linear light because
why not it just everything works and
then you don't care but generally
speaking you don't want to do that
because like especially for bitmaps
which are very large you want to be able
to store like 8-bit color data and have
that just work and the only way to do
that is in a color space that actually
has a better Gama than that right um so
I guess what I would say is you know you
have to be judicious with it sometimes
you want things in srgb sometimes you
want things in linear anytime you're
doing math on it it needs to be in
linear period you can't do math on srgb
directly and have good results unless
you're really careful and have all kinds
of special stuff in there to make sure
it's right so basically what I would say
is you know make sure you you know make
make sure you think about where in the
pipeline you are doing any kind of math
like even like making something brighter
by multiplying by two or
making it dimmer by multiplying on half
or something right
that's what I would say so in terms of
the way we're doing it I think it's
probably the case that we're mostly
reasonable about where we do it but
there's probably some places where maybe
we should just keep things in srgb
because we don't really need to modify
them much but generally speaking I don't
know that there's that many of the
places that we're actually doing that I
think we're probably doing it roughly
right there maybe one or two places
where we could just leave something as
srgb and save some space but otherwise I
think we're doing it mostly right so we
change the code of the hero's fate
depend on the surrounding like he looks
too bright in the darker but well yes
the sprite the sprites will actually be
added to the lighting solution when we
go back to do the final lighting point
placement stuff so they will actually
get lit properly if that makes sense
but yeah so it's kind of weird how your
brain kind of ignores most of it and it
kind of looks okay anyway but it in
general yeah we want the sprites to be
lit so that will actually happen when we
when we actually finish the lighting
pipeline stuff because remember we've
got more work to do there
Jackson Benin is that a question doesn't
look like one it has a cute cone in
front of it but it's not really a
question shouldn't lights behave as
other entities in regard to the sim
region mm-hmm what do you mean by that
behave in what sense
yeah what do you mean by behave in that
sentence
I thought they are visible when outside
well let me just go ahead and show you
what's going on and then you can tell me
what's happening so here is the
simulation region right everything
that's drawn here is the simulation
region now obviously there's a lot more
stuff in the game but this is the only
part that's in the simulation region
right now so if we hop to the next area
right you can see the simulation region
shift over time to now be here right and
that's the only part that's getting
simulated now right now the lights they
get pulled in because they're normal
entities just like anything else they
get pulled in as far as the simulation
region is concerned but they don't
participate in the lighting solution
until they're actually in the lighting
bound and the reason for that is because
lighting is very expensive right it's
the most expensive thing that you can do
is lighting typically unless you've got
some crazy physics happening uh and so
we just don't actually allow them to do
anything besides just sit there until
they actually come in and hopefully that
just give hopefully that explains what's
happening there but maybe not hopefully
you you sort of can see now what what
those two regions are and again the
reason for that I would be happy to run
the lighting on everything in the sim
Region that'd be great I just don't know
that we're ever gonna get the lighting
up to a level of performance where that
would be feasible because lighting is
one of those things that just wants as
much horsepower as you can throw at it
so even if we can do if we could do the
whole sim region lighting wise the
lighting solution would be worse quality
than if we just did a smaller region
because we could spend that same amount
of flops producing better lighting
solutions for a smaller region that we
actually can see so I want to make sure
we only ever light the part that's
actually going to give us
useful visual effects right so all right
don't know what that was complaining
about all right - will you call them
lighting bugs that's a very good idea
all right thank you for joining me for
the episode of handmade hear out
sometimes recording with you as always
we will be back here next week when we
will go ahead and add a few more touches
to the camera and then we'll start
working on art stuff because again I
want to get the lighting kind of squared
away before we go too much further into
world generation stuff because I want
the lighting in the world Jen to work
together closely and be good so I really
want the to have some art in there so we
can see how the lighting affects the
artwork and vice versa so we'll just be
working on that a little bit so that's
what's coming up next weekend hope see
here for that until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see you
all on the Internet
take it easy everybody