hello everybody welcome to handmade Hero
show Rico to complete-game live on
stream we have a bunch of work to do now
one of the problems with with sort of
getting down to the Nitty Gritty here is
we have so many things we can now start
polishing up and actually finishing and
getting proper because we've got the art
importing working and we have editing
facilities as well so now like all of
the stuff that we you know maybe have
loose ends on is all up is all up for
for work if that makes sense so we've
got it's a lot of stuff we can start
working on now and I we should probably
try to button up our attachment point
stuff maybe as the most direct thing we
can do because we were in the middle of
it and so we might as well get it kind
of finished to the amount that we think
we can but like if I actually so so if I
now want to go edit things in the world
I actually can edit things I can
actually edit attachment points now in
the world for reals so for example if I
come on here and select this cat for
example I can adjust where the cat is
where the attachment point is on the on
this cat and furthermore I can add more
attachment points so for example if I
add the head attachment point which we
call basis neck I can put that like
where the base of the neck is and
furthermore on the art asset for the
head I can also adjust where that
attachment point is and they snap
together right you can see them snapping
now like the green and red snap together
exactly as they should so we basically
now have the complete snapping system in
place we can edit it we can even pick
different pieces out here like you know
and so so on so we really do now have
the ability to fully work through our
art assets and get all that stuff
we need one more major feature well two
I think really before we call it done
one is we have to decide how the scale
stuff works right now we're just
ignoring it and we don't want to ignore
it so work out working out how scale
works that's a big one and the other big
one is implementing the save feature the
revert feature already works so we can
already go back to the thing beforehand
or undo and redo all works like you can
see it working right and again that's
really cool like if you if you look at
how little time it actually took us
through the editing side of things it's
pretty good right like you know it's not
a professional grade edit or anything
but in terms of something you throw in a
game we've got undo we've got redo we've
got you know multiple panels and
everything we've got the ability to
interact with all these things and add
stuff trivially we've you know it came
out pretty well I think and again that's
just a testament to keeping it simple
don't add huge object hierarchies don't
add all this like you know ridiculous
cruft don't go the QT route just keep it
small simple fast and we can get almost
all the functionality we need and we
could make this more pretty and more
usable too by just spending a little
more time polishing the actual UI side
of it but again you know you hit
diminishing returns somewhere there
especially if you're not going to be
reusing the engine necessarily so anyway
I think that came out really nicely but
again we do need to now actually think
about how we're gonna do save so I think
if I'm not mistaken sizing and saving
are the two things we really want to do
we want to actually go work on and I
think that's the end of what we would
need in terms of support for alignment
you know I like I can't think of
anything else that we're missing
I think I think we did everything you
know I think we did all the stuff yeah I
mean I really can't think of anything so
I think if we just maybe we'll do those
on this stream you know let's get those
buttoned up and you know it may even
take two streams because the save
feature we want to save to text I think
as well to have a permanent backing
store just saving the HHA is not gonna
be very hard
that'll be quick I think but saving to
the text file is gonna mean we need an
input parser and we got to like validate
that they come out the same and all that
sort of stuff right so we kind of want
to look at that a little bit more
carefully and we'll we'll see what we
can do there now when we finished that
though we're then gonna have to start
working a lot more on everything that
that exposes because at that point you
know we're kind of in wide-open
territory at that point we you know and
I should probably also make these snap
the corners because they drive me insane
the fact that they don't but other than
that at that point we've got so much
stuff we can work on we've got the
lighting can be improved we've got
ground cover we can add we can fix the
camera and do the final camera code now
we can look at how we're gonna do the Z
bias offsetting you can see that these
are wrong right now like you see how
there's a gap you have the reasons that
because they're on the same plane so we
want stuff like be biasing the head
forwards you know the things that are
attached to be biased forwards there's
just all this stuff we can now do as we
look to make the game look professional
right so there's all this polished work
that this opens up now how do we want to
actually get these lights in there you
know all of that tuning becomes becomes
available because we finally know
exactly what we want and I think it's
looking pretty good like this looks like
roughly what I wanted the game to look
like and so it's really just a question
of polishing everything up now and you
know I don't want giant light cubes
sitting in the environment and I want
the light to spread a little bit better
and more evenly and you know I want to
get rid of those sorting artifacts and I
mean the z-buffer artifacts and stuff
like that right so there's a bunch of
stuff I want to do there but otherwise
you know it's like yeah this is this is
starting to get good and and so I want
to go ahead and and and push towards
that also I would like to emphasize just
how good the lighting makes things look
if you look at what this looks like over
here you can just see how uninteresting
that is whereas if we look at the lit
region just having that color spread is
just really good so you know I do think
having lighting in this game is a good
idea and I think we do want to push
forward on that I think we can do a much
better job that we're doing now but just
lighting is hard so you know it's always
an ongoing process so I think that's
where we're at
um don't we have another cat too didn't
we put another wasn't there a cat maybe
in the LARP in the upper room here you
forget with the cats oh it's in there
it's another bedroom yeah so we have
another cat here if this was Fred and so
just we could as further testing if I
set the base of head there and then I
set the alignment point for the head
there again seems pretty good also
that's roughly I guess where the catch
it's it so again yeah you can just see
like now that we've got that it's really
trivial to just snap things together and
make him work right and like I said it
just now it just exposes all of the
things that we're not doing right like
getting the you know figuring out how we
want to handle the sea bias you can see
this as the parts talking about
yesterday where we got to figure out how
we want to stop them from clipping some
of the stuffs easier than others
obviously the fact that like the head
wants to be offset a little that's a
really easy fix
compared to the other ones so anyway
yeah I think we're good
so I think what I want to do is just
let's finish off the alignment editing
stuff now and I think that's probably
the the easiest or best thing for us to
be doing yeah I think that's about it
the other thing we might want to do here
and I don't really know is if you look
at what happens when you're editing
alignment points that go to the parent
you because changing the values counter
rotates like you see how like if I
change the value this way it means that
the alignment points moving down but
since the alignment points determining
where I am it actually it's kind of
going the wrong way in a sense so what
we could do to there is when it's that
way we we could actually reverse the we
could reverse the movement meaning we
could make it so that when you I don't
know that I don't know that this is a
good idea right but inside the editor
when we do let's see in here right so
when we do like edit align point and you
can see us changing like the P percent
here what we could do there is because
we know the difference between the two P
percent we could like swap them here and
I mean we could we could change the
direction that the P percent is actually
being dragged again I don't know that we
actually want to do that but we totally
could do that and it would just be one
if statement here I feel like if it's to
parent do this thing I guess I don't
care
all right so I'm gonna get started I'm
gonna try and get saving working back to
the HHA first and well actually you know
what let's do the harder problem first
instead of saving let's work on sizing
because I think there's some stuff that
we are gonna need to do there that's
kind of a a little bit full-throated so
in here here's the thing that I'm
thinking we probably need so when we
actually have a bitmap you can see that
we have to do in here that says the
original size should probably go in here
for computation purposes and so what
happens when we import one of these
bitmaps is we don't actually know how
big it was originally because we scale
it down to fit inside our texture size
which means we've effectively lost the
actual size when we go to draw it on the
screen we probably want to draw it
proportional to how big the artist made
it originally and then subject to the
sizing information that's placed in the
actual like aligned points themselves
right so if a thing says you know here's
how I should be scaled in this
circumstance then it will use that scale
now when we look at you know what's
stored here I've got a place set up to
store that information I even said to do
it seems like maybe we just should store
or rigged in here basically and then
when we draw things they can all be
drawn as a proportion like that amount
we can use that as that times the size
is the size of your pair on the screen
so that you always take into account how
big the thing was originally and that
helps maintain sizes relative to things
when the artist kept the sizes
consistent right right now we wouldn't
be we aren't doing that furthermore it
would change how we were actually in you
know imp
boarding things here so if we go and
look at how we were so like we import
the images into the HHA here
automatically and we call this down
sampler and one of the things you can
see here is when we're doing like
extraction of a particular image the way
that it works is in the two cases where
we've got single tile or plates we just
get the down sample for the fit and here
we don't do that we do the down sample
fit before we ever find the thing we're
using and the reason for that is because
we've wanted we didn't want to scale
different pieces differently but now we
just could right now we can just shrink
things down only as much as they need in
order to fit into our texture tiles and
then after we do that we can once we
actually have that done we can always
use the maximum amount of texture area
that we have in that tile to represent
the image regardless of how big it
regionally was because we know we will
preserve the size difference using the
original dim parameter right and so I do
think that's a valuable change and I
think that's how I would like to do size
and so yeah I think that's the primary
difference there now the only other
thing that we need to think about is in
terms of size is just where the actual
size stuff takes place relative to the
size of entities themselves and again
that difference was mostly about the
simple case of is a cat art assets you
know a quarter the size of a human's art
assets in terms of their align point
size settings right or does the entity
of a cat get set to that lower size
and and the align points are just set to
1.0 or something right so I don't really
know the answer to that question and so
I think what I would say there is we'll
probably just I think we'll probably
start with the default behavior being
that things are set to a size based on
their real-world size and that sizes in
the entity itself and then the align
point information is only there for
fixing errors that then occur from that
I think that makes the most sense to me
out of what we could do so I think
that's what we're gonna go with okay so
if we assume that that's how we're doing
things then that leads to what I think
is the final change I want to make to
our age at J's I don't know if there's
any other important changes we need to
make to finalize the file format for
version 2 but that's one of them and
yeah like I can't think of anything that
we're really doing that needs to get
fixed beyond that like it seems like
everything else is pretty good so far
the way we've got it I mean I can't
think of anything if anyone else can
then I'm happy to do that too but I'm
not thinking of anything right now and I
think I think we pretty much got what we
want in here it seems pretty good
alright so I'm gonna go ahead and do
that what I want to do first is in the
HHA editor obviously if I want to have
that I rigged dim stuff in there then
what I'm gonna do is any time we read a
v-0 file the the dim there is is
actually direct meaning the ORAC dim and
the actual dim are actually
equivalent and so there's no change that
needs to happen there
right you know another way to say it
would be that that these are always
equal because we didn't ever do any down
sampling of that data before so it's
always gonna be proper and look like
that so in terms of updating the
importer for the old v0 assets that's
all that would have to happen to import
a v0 asset and you should just work
right because there's nothing like
there's nothing else that really happens
there so the only place that the code
actually needs to be more meticulous is
inside this code and so in here we're
we're actually writing out an image to
an HHA file this because this source
image is now not sufficient to tell us
the information we needed what we want
to do is say what that original size was
before we down sampled it that now needs
to get passed so in here we want a
separate thing I don't know if we've got
V to use in here
oh right we got type smile so we've got
no such thing it looks like oh whoops we
only have just the real 32 ones we don't
have the ability to specify to like a
dimension like that unfortunately which
is really too bad but it looks like
that's just the way it goes sometimes so
as a result we would not be able to just
call you a v2 you there I could just be
saucy about it and actually just make
one of those so that we have one meaning
it would just be this right it's the
exact same code the only difference is
it's named a little differently right so
it looks like this probably you and I
mean and so v2 use are usually addressed
this way I would say probably you would
want something like this going on though
because W can be confusing if you throw
that in there right you get confusion
with the X Y Z W it's unfortunate that X
Y Z W happens to be a thing but it kind
of is so you know off you go with that
so anyway I can pass in here and or a
dim value and then when we do a write
image to H I'd say when we come through
here and set these I can you know also
put them in here where we want to put
our rig Jim zero equals you 16 or a gym
width and Jim height like so and those
are like the sum total of what would
need to get updated right so here if we
were to write this asset back like for
example here
No where is it where do we actually
flush the asset data back
so this writes the error streams this
writes the asset data but where does the
asset get written
interesting so do I just flush them in
bulk or something it's funny that I
asked that but I just don't remember
like where do we actually save that out
so the right modifications to HHA is
what handles it I don't know where we
set it as dirty I guess it's just any
time we called that hmm all right I mean
that's fine with me
but let's see here so that just gathers
up all the things it needs to write and
just does the safe right and and that's
the end of it I guess all right it's
fine yeah
all right so that's all well and good so
now we just need to make sure we always
pass that a rig width and height there
and and off we go I'm getting those
winter sneezies so inside here you can
kind of see when we do this extract
image the source image width and height
is actually the original
you know we know exactly what it is so
it's pretty straightforward in this case
to just set that right so we would know
what the width and height are and we can
now pass that when we write the image
because regardless of how you down
sample it it's still that that is still
the original
because it doesn't do any like subtile
plucking basically so yeah and I don't
remember what's the difference between
these two it's just it's just a size
difference I guess it's all it is so I
don't even know why we do that I guess
acet max play tim is just a guard
against doing anything too large um so
that's the same thing would happen here
right and so in both these cases all we
really have to do is just pass before
the image right we just passed that
original dimension down and that's
that's all there is to it so it's really
only the multi tile case that's at all
interesting because that's the one that
actually changes the sizes of things
because it's plucking out actual
rectangular pieces inside the tiles as
far as emptiness is concerned if we look
through here we can see that happening
we produce an extraction here by you
know by doing this tile image bit so
what that means is the tile image will
have the dimensions we actually wanted
so the original dimensions here are just
a tile image width and the tile image
height right because that's the part we
extracted so I think that's it
and now that will always get preserved
properly so if we now went and put into
our code something that uses that
information when it goes to actually do
any rendering work meaning when it tries
to compute the size of things it's going
to actually use that information
potentially
we really just need to know the height
and we need to know the Heights
proportion to some universal idea of
what we're gonna call height in this
case right and again the only reason we
need to do this is just to adjust the
fact that sometimes things are plucked
out of smaller rectangular areas we
don't really know how big they were
supposed to be in the first place
in addition to this I'm gonna go ahead
and say now because we know that piece
of information the downsample account
can actually be called every time and so
instead of having the science test
nonsense
occurring here we can instead say
anytime that we're going to go do one of
these let's actually do it only the
minimum amount necessary which means
that smaller things won't get rish Runk
down below the size that they would need
to be they can still say you know the
source images are like 1k by 1k I think
if you only had a little bit of that
occupied when we go to shrink it down to
fit it inside like a 256 by 256 tile if
it was already 256 by 26 we won't shrink
it right we'll leave it so that it'll
fit in there and use the maximum amount
of area we won't keep shrinking it down
just because we're trying to obey a
general idea of how much each thing in
the entire file should have shrunk so
that's what I want to do there right um
so I think that's all good if we now
were to use that somewhere so let's say
I go into the actual entity renderer
where is this is where I would probably
be using this sort of thing if when I
look at the bitmap information in
question I actually try to take that
into account for the height so you know
inside here we know that this world
radius you can see a select computing
stuff this is going to get cleaned up
considerably now as we start to shrink
this down a bit but if we look inside
like the UPS it's not what I wanted to
do if we sort of look inside how this is
actually
getting scaled and you can see here the
world radius why stuff or the piece the
dim dot why right so when you see how
this like world type thing is being used
here if I wanted to then I could say I
want to take whatever the dimension Y
scaling value is that I've been given
and multiply it by the height ratio here
which let's say is going to be you know
something along the lines of how big was
this thing relative to a tile in terms
of the input dimensions for something
like that it doesn't matter what it is
just it has to be some constant ratio so
if I say you know the bitmap infos
original dimension in Y is going to be
turned into a ratio and then that ratio
is going to be used to set the sizes of
things that would equalize all of them
to the correct size now obviously if I
run it now I'm not going to see anything
and the reason I'm not going to see
anything is because we haven't set any
of those ratios or all those are or
exams right so I come in here I see no
cat why is there no cat I can even
select the cat potentially but I just
can't see it right so if I come in here
and pick that you know why can't I see
the cat and even it's even here right I
can pick it in here and I can't why
can't I see the cat again I rigged dim
is zero because we haven't run rerun the
import so none of that stuff was
actually saved the same would be true of
any other bitmaps that came from the
import process now everybody who's not
using that kind of a scale so like the
font code for example the cubes any of
that stuff totally fine because it's not
using that or a dim value so it doesn't
have to worry about that stuff at all
okay so if I now want to go ahead and
and make that work then what I can do
first of all I you know I really just
don't care about the origam values in
these v-0 things so I don't even need
know that I really care about rerunning
the import we can at some point if we
want to what I really want to do is just
make sure I rerun the import on the
action
new stuff that we're actually using so
like this local HHA file here for
example I want to get rid of that that
should go away and then I'm going to use
HHA edit to create a new one of those so
that it will force the game to notice it
and do the bulk update so now it will go
in and look at all of those pngs rien
port all of them and in theory it should
set those origin values to be something
valid right and so well ready we can
start to see that there is a difference
the fist now is a different size why is
it a different size because now we are
accounting for its actual size relative
to the total size of the tile could have
been and again it's just a normalization
function and it kind of is nice because
you can even see our fist doesn't before
it was looking bigger in the case where
in what in one of them than in the other
and I think the reason for that was it
just happened to be scaled differently
inside the thing so this actually now
properly obeys that scaling a little bit
better and I think that's you know
obviously a good thing and so now our
cat also has that aspect of it as well
too again doesn't really matter a super
super much at the immediate moment but I
think it'll pay off pay some dividends a
little bit later on right and so looking
here I'm gonna go ahead and and make
sure that the rest of this stuff still
works if I don't see why it wouldn't if
I go into the alignment point editor I
should be able to do the same thing that
I was doing before where I snap a base
of neck on there let me zoom in so I can
see that where I snapped the base of
neck on there and also in here change
the alignment point there and off we go
right so now we can see the cat's eyes
you know and you know that honestly
that's probably more what a normal cat's
eyes should be again continuing to
expose new things we need to work on
though you can see that the cat doesn't
really look that good scale down that
far why doesn't it look that good scale
down that far well it's because we're
not using MIT Maps which we're going to
want to turn on sometime soon as well so
that'll be an interesting thing we can
do to improve image quality further in
addition so again
we continue to have it we're getting the
point where we're opening up huge
amounts of things we can work on that
actually make obvious like serious
improvements to the way the game looks
and that's where we want to be in terms
of getting our art and visuals a little
bit more finalized okay so that's all
well and good don't think there's too
much more we really need to think about
there I think that's all we really need
for the sizes so now let's focus on that
saving value and on the the scaling
values that were actually getting
applied here in addition so if we want
to respect the scaling values in the
Edit side of things it's actually not
that bad because we have all the
information we actually need so what we
can do here is just say well you know
let's first of all let's let's clean up
how we've got we got too many dimensions
running around here and so if we look at
this world radius thing where we grabbed
a piece dim out of there
and then we do all this garbage here
what we could do is is let's let's
actually consolidate on that world
radius stuff because now we sort of know
what this actually should be and so when
we call the world dim for world height
function and we have that that height
ratio thing there that's something that
I think we want to be more specific
about now
so what I would like to do is grab in
here I'm gonna put this stuff inside
here I want to set the world radius
actually according to this value here so
when we get the world dim back I'm gonna
put it like so so when we set this
information up we get that that now
newly corrected dimension values coming
back here then what I'd like to do is
take that height ratio I want the height
ratio to be multiplied by the combined
ratio of what the parent wants to do for
scaling and what the child wants to do
for scaling so what that really suggests
to me is I kind of want to come back
here get that set up ahead of time once
we get the child aligned in
information back I want to say okay the
child aligned size multiplies is the
height ratio like so and then I also
want the the parent align size to
multiply the height ratio so that both
of those inform the total size that the
thing should be at the end of the day so
again moving back into the edit mode
here if I go you know what our cat may
be slightly larger than I had hoped
I'm just gonna go out on a limb here and
say that now the reason for that was
just me being kind of dumb obviously we
have to unpack it why it didn't give me
a conversion error there oh because it
does fit entirely in a float I apologize
for making a huge cat that could have
destroyed the entire world I will try to
keep that to a minimum and let's try
that one more time and and now let's try
and play with that part of it right yeah
pick that
so let's see now if I want to set the
size of this thing
I should be able to write um so this
lets me put in an adjustment value right
so I can change if I want its size to be
different again that's not the entity
size that's just the size of the
attachment point in this case one of the
problems that I see here is I can't seem
to get to the other the other piece
doesn't seem to be available like I
don't know where the head is we probably
should have the other pieces available
in this case oh well and you know the
reason for that is because it's not
attachable I suppose now that I think
about it right gotta work on this pick
the ability to pick those things and
center around them so yeah if I add the
base of neck that should be the thing
that allows the head to show up now that
I think about it because there it is now
yeah so looking at this right now if I
want to I should be able to I probably
want to be able to turn off that
highlight as well that highlight there
we need to start making a list of all
the things I'd like to do but you can
see I can change the scale there right
of the head as its attachment point and
if I I'm on the body I can also change
it so the attachment can change it on
either side which is what I wanted and
if I change this one it only changes me
not my children I don't know if we want
that or not
that's kind of a tough one
so what I will say about that is like
I'm not really sure why I would have
thought that that should have cascaded
and the reason that I would have thought
that it would cascaded is because when
we actually go through doing this we
save the scaled x and y axis and that's
what we actually used to reinterpret the
sprite size later so if you were to put
in a higher value here which is f what
we're doing I would have thought that
that would have caused the children o so
it properly scales the location it just
doesn't scale their individual size so
not exactly what I would expect it so I
don't know which one of those we want to
do my guess is we want it the way it is
now you know like my guess is we want it
to be my guess is we don't want it to
scale the children because these are
adjustments for bitmap size differences
and so I don't think we want to do it
it's really easy for us to do it what we
can do is we just have another rake here
that's just like scales you know and we
just save off the the scaling ratio as
necessary I don't think we want that
though
so I think that maybe the only thing I
really want to do there yeah I think
that's that's probably about it so one
of the things that we may want to
consider while we're editing this stuff
is if I go into the at like us like I
said well we're trying to figure out
what the final file format is inside
here I don't know to what extent we may
want to add one more thing which is a Z
bias value you know what I mean
like just thinking it through I feel
like I want to have like the ability to
say that this thing should be biased
behind or in front of the parent piece
but maybe that doesn't really need to be
specified here
I'm kind of torn on that because there's
really two places you can put that and
one of them is inside here but the other
one is inside the entity and so inside
the visible piece here we could have
that piece of information
oops no no where did the little nub
thing go there's a little earpiece thing
that that sticks this thing in your ear
and it like came off of my headphone and
now I don't have any idea where it went
where did that go this is gonna be like
impossible to find oh there it is wow
that got flung far my goodness I never
had that happen on stream before or not
on stream before I guess I suppose uh so
yeah I would I guess what I would say
there is I guess we'll just not specify
that in the art assets at this at this
point because it's not super art asset
esque I guess especially because like
any animation that would happen wouldn't
be specified in there and you could see
the animation wanting to move behind and
in front of things potentially so I
guess I'm gonna go ahead and say it is
what it is at the moment and we really
don't need another element of it that's
what I'm gonna say alright so taking a
look a little bit further down in this
process now we need to have some way of
actually going and writing this stuff
out writing it back to the HHA I think
is actually
totally trivial because all it is is
calling the he's like calling the dirty
flag I think that's really it so like
when you hit save all it really needs to
do is when you do that dirty flag then
you just yeah then you just go ahead and
set it so I think what we would do is
say all right if you're gonna write out
to an HHA then we just run through what
you've edited and we see which hij files
would need to be modified and then we
write back to them I think that's really
it now granted I don't know if you're
allowed to edit multiple HHA files at a
time I don't really remember what we
required as far as that's as far as that
goes
it looks like allow editing would be the
thing and so I suppose we can just say
we'll set the modified flag anytime that
we actually touch one of these things
and go from there now we could be a
little bit more careful about that and
we probably should be so so here's the
thing if we just inside editor like you
know when we do an edit change if all we
did was say set the modified flag any
time we touch a particular HHA that's
not fantastic because what that would do
is it will make it so that our it will
effectively make it so that our hhas
will be set to dirty whether or not undo
has undone the changes to them so a
potentially more useful way to do it or
powerful if you will for the user would
be to actually spin through the undo
buffer and see
there's anything in it and if there is
for each thing that's in the undo buffer
mark the HHA file at that point you had
I mean
I think that would do it now there's one
thing that we can't really do
there's one thing that we can't really
avoid which is that since these edits
kind of happen directly into the memory
that we're using if the user wants to
update an HHA they kind of have to save
it well I guess they could just not save
it though but they would still be
written to so I guess I'm gonna say
we're just we're not gonna support the
following thing if you make changes to a
file if you make changes in the editor
you are not allowed to update the art
assets using the import pass without
also agreeing to save your old changes
make sense so basically like the update
flag the the Save button has to be like
there's two things there's save and
there's you know import and save but
there is no import without saving like
that's just not allowed I think that's
where we're at we could change the
importer to facilitate an import that
doesn't do that I just don't know that
we want to go quite that far what that
would entail is instead of us writing
the data out to the actual HHA we would
just write it out to a buffer in memory
that doesn't get committed back to the
HHA until you hit save right
and I don't necessarily see anything
wrong with that so I don't know maybe we
should just do that maybe everything
should be going through that path I just
don't know if it's worth it
I'm kind of conflicted about that but
you know in order just to give you an
idea of what I mean
so right now inside right asset stream
and and string and data right so we've
got we've got this right asset data
thing and I think almost everything is
like it's like bumped up in there right
so everything funnels down to write a
Sat data and here it is so what you
would do is you would take this here
this write a Sat data function and
rather than calling platform write data
to file you would actually just allocate
a buffer you would stick the data into
the buffer and you would chain it on to
a linked list that's at off the end of
the asset structure that basically said
here's all the rights I would do if I
was going to actually save the HHA file
right
does anyone have any real opinions about
this does anyone does anyone care does
anyone care at all I don't know my
friends I don't know so I guess what
I'll say there is I think it's six of
one half dozen of the other
and I'm not like super concerned about
it so I think I'll just say look let's
do this
for the moment in here where we've got
our check for art changes thing let's go
ahead and and save that is actually
going to be bound to an in-game editor
feature so you know in here we
effectively have we've got the save key
and we've also got another key which is
like import and save something like that
right and that one is always available
because you can always look to see if
there's stuff stuff there to do so then
what we would say is you know any time
that's gonna happen we would we would go
to check for art changes and actually
call that and it would you know kind of
do its thing and we would need the save
feature to actually be available here so
like we would need to then do elect if
you know should save we put that in here
and that's up to us anytime we want to
actually implement it which will be
coming up shortly
we put true in there you know I mean and
so that means we would be able to have
either of those two things call it also
means we could avoid doing that on
startup so in here we have an important
import and save feature that we can
access any time we want and you know we
don't have to use it if we don't want to
right so I think that's all well and
good looking at the way this codes gonna
play out I think I'm fine with that
so that means that inside the asset
system when we actually do our our check
for our changes there this can go away
right so we don't need to do it on
startup anymore you can just if you
wanted to pull in art assets you could
you know what I mean
and you we could even make a thing
that's like force update so if we want
we can even make a button that's like
update everything even if it doesn't
look dirty I'm telling you right now to
pretend that it is so for sorry import'
of this stuff right so I think that
would do it and that would that would
basically be it so you know if we then
went in here and said well you know
we've got this local HHA file here and
we delete it you know what I mean
then when I run the game in theory I
come in here and you know we've got you
know no art assets right if I create one
of those as a dummy file and leave it
there then the game opens in edit mode
and you know I still can't actually see
anything as you can see and let like you
know nothing's here but if I go into the
editor and now say look do an import
would probably be nice we added a
progress bar but you know beggars can't
be choosers
it'll import everything and then return
us to the game and we can call that any
time we want so we can you know call the
import and save anytime we want to
update art assets so you know in theory
that means if we you know we go in here
and
say well you know we want to update some
of our art work now so we've got like
one of these stone floors that we're on
right now I think we're on a stone floor
yeah so we've got one of these stone
floors you know we go in to edit it or
whatever and well you know I guess let
me do it this way
load up the bring out the
okay so if we want to write in I just
want to like do some change so I save
out the PNG there it goes if I then was
in here and said well rien port that
please in theory it should write like at
least I think it should so it doesn't
look like it should it doesn't look like
it did mm-hmm
not sure why we should see why it didn't
decide it it didn't want to update that
I did save it didn't I yeah so I'm not
sure why that oh here's another question
we don't flush our textures currently do
we so I bet it did update and we just
don't flush the textures so that's
another thing we can do today is for us
flushing on textures so I assume it
probably did update and now if you look
yeah right so it would be nice if we
force flush the textures that were in
question there I don't know how specific
we want to be about that but if we force
flush the textures then what we would
want to do is in the game assets we
would just want to make sure everything
got resent down to the to the graphics
card doing so would require yeah we want
just some kind of a full flush feature
so we just say look really there's been
an update go ahead and and flush
everything so in order to do that what
we would want to do is it's basically
have a bunch of free free asset calls
right like we'd want to write in here we
would want to go ahead and and make sure
there was some way we could
[Music]
we could do that we've never had to do
that because currently the only thing
time we ever evict is in the case where
we the only time we ever evicted
textures is when we actually need to put
a new one in there so we do want some
way of doing that and I'm not sure how
we would really do that probably
something where yeah some of the stuff
kind of needs to get rewritten anyway so
you can see it here where it will do its
reclamation there right it's looking for
extra bitmap space
so you know looking at this you can kind
of see why we you know why we probably
want to update this code anyway right
because since we have actual texture
stores now whereas before we always like
loaded and process the memory directly
from the asset system which is more
efficient that way it seems like
probably what we would want to do here
right is we want to be able to just load
it directly into the texture store
probably but you can see how we're doing
it like we've got this remove asset
header from list right and you can see
us doing like merges and stuff like that
you can you can see us doing that all in
here under the acquire asset memory
banner but really none of that's
necessary in to a large extent
especially not for textures for audio
we'd have to kind of think about how we
want that to work because audio might
want something there but in terms of
textures again we don't really need that
because we don't need to store our
textures in memory ever because they
always have to be on the GPU anyway or
in the case of the renderer for the game
the software renderer they would want to
be in the software renderers memory so I
don't really know what I want to do
there
I really couldn't say
what I would like to do is make it so
that what happens is our asynchronous
loading code is really just code that
uses a temporary transfer buffer moves
the data into the transfer buffer
generates the MIT Maps and then uploads
it to the graphics card never actually
tries to allocate any permanent storage
because that's just not what it would be
used for right
yeah I just don't know I really just
don't know what what to what to make of
it I think there's a lot of things we
could do I don't know if it's worth our
time to do that right now but at the
same time like why I don't really want
to spend time updating this code because
we really just don't need it anymore
you know it's kind of just dead code and
you know the audio system could be
similarly merged to work with flat
buffer sizes and then you'd always have
just a nice kind of round round robin
scheme of using buffers upload buffers
and everything would be nice and cleaned
so that seems a lot more sensible than
doing it the way we're doing it here
which was made to be a lot more flexible
than it needs to be and so therefore is
a lot more complicated I guess that's
what I would say about that if we go
look at how texture apps work at the
moment so inside the the handmade
renderer you got these texture apps here
and the texture app update and we should
have this texture app list here I think
generally speaking what you would do is
you would want to have a limited number
of those which is however many texture
uploads you want to have in flight at
once and then you just leave those
allocated and every time you need to do
a load you load into whatever texture
apps you have available if you don't
have a texture off available you just
don't issue the load and that's the
entirety of what you do you know what I
mean and then the asset system doesn't
actually have any memory at all for
textures it only has memory for it only
has memory for audio
and that's it so that seems good
and I have I have no no I have no beef
about that
yeah I think that seems pretty good it
does make the texture up texture op list
texture op update stuff it does make
that a little bit maybe want to be more
on the app side than it currently is so
I'm not really sure that that doesn't
need to get pulled out further so rather
than looking like this so much it's kind
of more of a it's kind of more of a
thing that you allocate and then you
just pass in the list which I think we
kind of flirted with but you know I
think now we can kind of see how that
really should probably work on the other
hand you could make the argument that
you want that to be something that is
mapped in video card memory and then you
do the transfer that way so I don't know
it's it's a hard it's a hard call to
make and I'm not really sure exactly how
you want that to play out so we'll have
to see there as well well that's kind of
just a long way of saying I'm not sure
how I really feel about that update pass
and I feel like it really wants to be
merged with a like when we're doing that
I would like that to be merged with the
thing that works here for doing
on-demand reloading I'm gonna back out
these changes here and then overwrite
this back to its original form uh and
then I guess maybe I'll just try this
rewrite now I don't know if that's a
good idea or not but I just explore it
and see how much of an investment I
think that's gonna be so looking at how
we do our loading work you can see here
you know when it goes to do finalization
you can see it effectively adding a op
to this texture op queue here right so
it's like saying all right I got an OP
I'm gonna add it to the queue if you
look at what that actually does
so here's add up
if you look at what that does you can
see here that it tries as well as it can
to actually get an OP to do the transfer
and if it can't then it just kind of
hard crashes right and again I don't
think that's a particularly good way to
do this because I think what you would
rather do is not actually start an
operation that you can't finish so
probably what you want to do is when you
actually go to load like a bitmap in
this case then one of the things that
you need to do is begin a task that
actually has a texture op transfer
associated with it and if you cannot get
one of those then you simply don't run
you know what I mean
so so that's really more what I want to
do there and we know ahead of time
exactly how much memory we need for that
transfer so it shouldn't be particularly
hard for us to guarantee that that's the
case and the renderer should be able to
satisfy that request for us pretty
easily you know given that we can
guarantee that we're always using a
fixed set of these things
um yes so that all seems good I'm gonna
look at begin tasks with memory I also
don't know why it actually needs the
memory in this case it's just the memory
for that is the only thing it actually
needs I mean these tasks already have
memory associated with them and I assume
that that memory gets freed when the
task is done so honestly we could just
lean on that at the moment and pretty
much be done with it because that could
allocate the space and then that task
could just be actually considered done
only when the OP actually gets retired I
want to see how many of these we planned
on having I'm again I'm not really sure
I actually want to do that but
if we look at where that's actually
happening here it is in here you can see
it's looking through a set of tasks that
it created to actually be able to handle
that that load right and in terms of how
those were originally seated there's
only four of those outstanding at any
given time right
yeah it really just feels to me like the
right thing to do would be to have a
block and call that you use to upload a
texture because in some circumstances in
a on a platform when you where you can
upload textures asynchronously there's
no reason to wait around to upload them
asynchronously and to upload them
synchronously but we have to do that in
OpenGL because OpenGL doesn't really
understand threading properly just tough
calls tough calls this is probably the
most intricate part of how things
usually go right when you've got like
background loading that wants to do
something with the GPU that's like the
worst possible case because you have to
asynchronous things happening together
so yeah I'm just not sure how I want to
how I really want to make that happen
but what I can say is let's say at the
very least here if I wanted to look at
this task stuff here when this actually
happens I could back off and say well
you know if I don't get the if I try to
get the texture up and can't then I just
won't try to do any of this you know
what I mean
I also don't know if immediate like
let's let's see who actually calls
immediate is it nobody
who actually uses that that is not use
there that is not use there it is not
used anywhere it doesn't look like so we
may just not care about that part at all
anyway
so literally no one ever used the
immediate thing anymore it used to be
used for I think background compositing
or something like that but it's not used
anymore
so that's kind of good because it means
we don't have to handle that case anyway
but what I was sort of saying here is
like we could also you know wrap this so
you know this looks like this we could
wrap this part here you know like did we
get a texture up and if we didn't get a
texture up then don't bother trying to
you know actually make this part work at
all because we won't be able to transfer
the thing that we load so it doesn't
matter right so we just need space like
and the texture ops again are not
actually you know we can have as many of
them as we can fit assuming that we need
something like 256 times to do six times
four times you know like let's say two
because if there's gonna be a machine in
there it's gonna be something like that
it's a half megabyte per texture op
right so if we were to say you know we
would if we we could have like up to 128
outstanding and still only use like 64
Meg's right so on the main CPUs we've
just got so much memory these days we
can't afford to make that pipeline kind
of as big as we want and we really
wouldn't have to worry too much about it
so it seems like that's not a bad idea
because we can always get more buffer
memory if we just need to make that
pipeline deeper and deeper and deeper
you know so I think what we want to do
here is say all right look give me a
texture up
something if we got a texture up then we
actually proceed with the transfer if in
here we try and fail to do it then we do
let cancel texture up so that it knows
that it's not actually gonna be used you
know what I mean and then assuming that
it actually does get a texture up then
what we would need to do is I guess in
here we also need to say kind of like
how big we want this thing to be like
here's how big the transfer its gonna be
in this case so we would say something
like okay you know we know what the
width and height is of the texture
transfer that's going to occur so we can
give you that information and we were
assumed that you give us a texture out
back that's the suitable version of that
looking through here in the asset memory
side at that point you would say well we
don't actually need to acquire any asset
memory other than the asset memory
necessary to store the actual thing you
load out of the file and I don't think
we have any of that right like I don't
think we actually need that for anything
because all assets that exist at all
already have a slot reserved for them
which has the data that we actually care
about so if you look at what happens in
here we already have that information
available so I don't think we actually
need to load anything so the asset
memory head our pointer can just be 0 it
doesn't need to be set to anything at
all you know what I mean um so really
what we would have in here instead of an
asset memory header which is this thing
here the loaded bitmap would go away we
wouldn't have any of this right this
stuff would just not be there and we
would just inside here say look there is
a you know
there is going to be like the
information we need to get out of the
asset and you know maybe that should be
in place of that there right there is
gonna be the stuff we're gonna get out
of in place of the asset which is gonna
be like the the you know texture handle
and in the case of audio maybe there's
an audio handle that's here as well
right so the asset system just
responsible for providing that piece of
information back to us but the asset
header in terms of us acquiring any of
this stuff well we don't actually need
any of it because none of this stuff is
relevant to us because the only thing
that we're gonna save is the texture
handle we don't need to save anything
else at all right so this actually goes
away like all of that is gone and all of
this information here I want to say even
the texture handle itself could have
probably been allocated out here but
yeah so we don't need this
this actually does need a free list this
part here
and so we will actually need to
implement that
but that all looks good otherwise
okay so looking through this we've got
all this stuff actually is just fine
everything looks looks just fine so it's
really just all we would be doing is
this man off you go
right I mean that's that's all there is
to it so we do begin texture op cancel
texture up there and like a complete
texture off up here or something like
that so in this case you know we don't
do loaded bitmap right that's not what
would be getting here we just want the
texture operation itself and so inside
the work structure we would need to
store whatever the texture was that we
actually used so inside here we would
have worked texture op equals texture op
which you know that one whatever the one
is that we got and so inside the what is
it
load asset work right here we would have
renderer texture op texture up and that
would be something that we get filled
out there right I think that's it so is
it just called texture out yeah
so the finalization would just be inside
this piece of code where we know that
we're done we would just say well okay
then we would say complete texture up
and we would just pass the texture off
and that would you know add it to the
queue and I just want to change the
phrase from add up because it's a little
bit ambiguous than what's going on so I
want to actually say okay you know we're
actually saying complete as opposed to
cancel because those two things are
different and I think that's it
yeah I mean I think that's it so in here
when we actually do when we actually do
the complete texture up that would not
have this there we would presumably at
the time when we actually know now what
handle we're using we would actually
place that in here so inside the texture
up it would actually be this and sorry
it would actually be this and that would
be that in addition the texture ops
themselves they don't really have
anything now so you know when we do this
smush down I think you would want that
to be the case so that you're really
just looking at hmm there is only one
kind of texture up it's basically saying
that this data will overwrite what's in
this texture handle everything else is
pretty much is what it is and I think
that's it right so that would be just a
lot better like everything about that is
just a lot better than it was and so
then we would just set that texture off
like so so we you know we get one back
after doing this I can I can provide the
Optio in question here so that that all
flows nicely we can also if we cancel we
can also provide the cue so that's
always available to to be used at the
free list so that all flows properly
when we actually go to finish it we do
this and then we never actually call
that allocation right what that means is
now anytime we were going to update an
asset we can actually just clear its
texture handle and be done with it right
so if we clear its texture handle out
then we know that texture is not valid I
believe there is a test for that
I hope there is a test for that I don't
really remember if there's a yeah
so we don't really have that but that's
okay what I can do is say all right
let's see
internal be 32 is valid renderer texture
texture and then I can just say be 30
results what is the texture handle
comprised of consists of rather texture
there it is so yeah if we want to we can
also just reorganize this like so so
that we also have the ability to just
refer to this as a packed value and in
that case we just say like the packed
value equals 0 or since we want is valid
in this case we just say it's not 0 so
if we come in here and say look what you
know is this true or false you know is
this a valid one or not well we just do
it that way and so then when we actually
go to access a bitmap it's a lot more
straightforward we just look to see
whether or not it's got a texture handle
and if it doesn't have a texture handle
then off we go we could even do a lot
more saucy things now we could probably
even get rid of some of the locking the
lock would only have to be around the
allocation of the texture handle itself
it wouldn't actually have yeah I mean
there's just a lot of we can clean up so
much code now it's kind of scary because
we could all we would really have to
lock is the free list for the texture
handles so that we make sure that when
we pull one of those you know someone
isn't in the process of actually using
that list still so you know we
we could clean up a lot of code but
anyway point being now we could say is
when you go to do a load bitmap call
here when you go to do this sort of
thing we don't really need to we don't
really need to do anymore of the fancy
footwork really we can just we can in
here just assume oh you know what we
have loaded as well so I guess I don't
even since we have the loaded flag I
guess we don't even really need to know
that so yeah okay nevermind since we
have the since we have the state flag I
don't even really need to check to see
whether the texture handles valid now
that I think about it so that's probably
a waste of my time but um so now we can
do is say alright when you're actually
going to do one of these things let's
see if we know how do we know when it's
actually loaded first the get a set call
this gets the asset back but how do we
know if it's loaded so you see here
right it's using that header pointer and
the header pointer it looks to see
whether or not the thing's loaded you
know I mean
so every time we use it we take an asset
lock here because we want to be able to
see which asset was the least recently
used asset and I don't know to what
extent that's a smart thing because it
sort of implies that we it sort of
implies that we have to constantly be
shuffling that list around and I can't
help but wonder if the more efficient
thing to do is just when we need to do
like I I don't know if it's maybe easier
to just do like a pass to see when the
last time someone's thing was used when
we go to do like a flush
because really the problem that I'm
having is just like now we we could
really be very efficient here but the
thing that I don't know is how to keep
track of who should get evicted and what
we're doing right now is kind of
wasteful because every time we go to use
somebody we like to cycle them up to
keep them in a bubbled list of who
should get evicted on that frame who
should get evicted first so we keep that
list the sorted order in the order in
which that they were used but really you
almost want to do it as a separate pass
maybe
yes so I'm gonna go ahead and say I
think we should even change how we're
doing this so what I'm going to say here
is every time we use an asset in this
case I think what we want to do is
update essentially a dirtiness level for
that asset that just says when you know
when the last time was that we accessed
it right and so essentially the asset
system would have you know a counter
here you know somewhere in here so
inside game assets right there's some
kind of a like an asset counter where we
just say like this and every time we get
one of these things we would never
really call get we would we'd never call
that we would only really ever call this
right so we would say okay you know get
the asset here so here's the asset for
the bitmap in question so it's like that
and then what we would do is say you
know we probably want to assert that it
you know that it even is a bitmap so
inside here we would say like the asset
you know whatever equals HHA asset type
you know like that because people
shouldn't be asking for something as a
bitmap but it's not actually a bitmap
obviously I can't remember what this is
called but I can look it just called a
JJ so once we do that then we would just
say all right you know that asset it's
last used generation is whatever the
asset system says the
used generation is right now what I
called that thing do six generation so
we're just stamping it
we're just saying hey yeah like don't
forget right and so then what we could
do is say all we're gonna keep a list of
is just who's loaded that's all we're
gonna keep a list of and then when we go
to do a purge we'll just say look
through the list of loaded assets for
the oldest one and use that one and we
can do that as we can do those purges in
waves so we could kind of say look
anything that you know I want you to
find the oldest one because we're gonna
purge that one regardless but I also
want you to purge anyone who's over a
certain age to avoid us having to do
purges too frequently you know what I
mean
so that way on any given frame we're
only gonna purge occasion we're only
gonna maybe purge once for frame we're
not gonna run purges lots of times if
lots of people need to allocate we're
gonna be you know more judicious than
that you know what I mean so that seems
like a lot better to me than what we
were doing that just seems a lot better
and so the operation lock that we're
doing on the assets there would be for
only I'm trying to think if there are
other lists that we need it may be such
that we won't need an operation lock at
all anymore for the most part at least
not for the mainline code maybe that
that can all be sort of kicked off as a
separate thing and so the only real
thing we would need is like the lock
would be only really on the texture up
side of things and the asset system
wouldn't really have any if that makes
sense because we know that there aren't
multiple people calling this code this
code on this side is only called by one
by the game which is single threaded so
the asset system on the other side where
the asynchronous loading people are
working on it if we got rid of their
ability to ever touch you know any of
the things in question here that are
that are possibly being used by the
mainline code that would sort of get rid
of any need to do that um and that's
pretty good too right that's pretty good
too so it really would just be the audio
system that we would have to worry about
there and
and the bit mass would be pretty much
done I like that all right so let's see
we were gonna do that I'll go ahead and
move this up here because it's kind of
in line to get removed then so we just
have like these pieces of code here I'm
gonna get rid of these in lines we don't
really need in lines anymore I should
just get rid of them from the code
entirely but you know they're kind of a
still remains at this point so I'm
pretty sure that's what I want to do so
let's try to make that happen
and that will also that will give us the
ability to purge our textures as we
wanted to on a hop reload but it'll also
just make our system a lot more
efficient because it doesn't have to be
doing all the stuff that it was doing
before
that's pretty inefficient so yeah just
go ahead and uniform make that one more
uniform all right so how do we want to
proceed here so what I'd like to do is
just say all right the last use
generation thing is going to be on an
asset so every time you have one of
these you also have a last used
generation and in the case of a sound so
I'm loading it a sound in rather than
something else that's something that we
just need like a different type of
handle for write faults I'm torn on
because I don't know that I really want
fonts to be dynamically loaded anyway I
mean the bitmaps of fonts are always on
activated so it's really just the glyph
information that where that finalization
happens I don't know I'm a check I just
want to check to see what we're actually
doing there because I don't really know
so I'm gonna look at load font
yeah and so if you kind of see here
where you're doing load font and you
load in the glyph data I might go ahead
and say that since that data is
relatively small we just don't have very
many thoughts and we don't need to have
lots of fonts in the game we might want
to just load all of the font data I mean
I guess the only reason not to do that
would be if there's too many fonts
because of localization concerns but
like that glyph size is just not that
concerning right like if you look at the
size of the fonts themselves there you
can see so inside a given font you've
got horizontal advances which are floats
and you've got code points which are the
font glyphs so those are like you know
you 32 to you 32 values select 64 so
it's like an array of 32 is an array of
64 so the horizontal advance is a bit
big so I guess I would say maybe that is
concerning because that's actually an N
squared table so if you looked at
something where I don't know you needed
like 2000 of these that becomes pretty
substantial when you think about it so
that's like 16 megabytes just for one
font if it had like lots of glyphs in it
certainly that you know so I'm thinking
like you know the Japanese or Chinese
language font obviously for for any
language is written in Roman script it's
you know it's meaningless because there
just wouldn't be very many glyphs to
begin with
but if we look at how that's making sure
it's from like you know do I want to a
load that I don't know we certainly
could just load it and never free its
memory you know what I mean so I'd be
okay with that because it's like look
you're going to be running in
whatever language you're running in and
I would probably be okay with with the
fonts just using whatever memory they're
using and not have to worry about
getting that from some kind of a
reusable pool if that makes sense so I
think as far as fonts are concerned that
could be just a synchronous font load
that wouldn't really matter because
again it's just one really simple really
quick load of some data and you don't
really have to care about it from there
so I think I would be okay with that and
that would just simplify that process
and so it would just be audio data which
would need their own audio pool and that
would be pretty straightforward because
then what I could do is you know we
already have the idea that you can
stream audio data and so I would be able
to just really easily make it so that we
have a fixed set of fixed size audio
buffers and all the audio streams
through there right so I think that's
pretty clean and that's what I would
what I would do so I think I'm just
gonna go ahead and do that right and so
what we would end up with if that if the
scheme looked like that is asset memory
header which is the part that I didn't
like and was really annoying and ugly I
think we just get rid of that now asset
type which is the header thing again
don't need and so we would just be left
with only the state and and like a
handle here and similarly in this case
we'd have texture I mean the audio
buffer index and that would just be
round-robin that would not even really
need to be ever dealt with in any way
because since we know that audio plays
and it plays overtime it's always
whoever was the last person loaded the
the furthest whichever buffer is oldest
is the buffer we could just get rid of
right in almost all cases now we could
try to be a little bit cleaner about
that but I don't know to what extent I
you know I mean I really don't know if
we need to be that advanced about it at
all
right so we would just have a you know
an asset audio buffer and it would just
be some fixed number of samples so we
would just you know we would just have
something like and and you'll forgive me
for not remembering what kind of audio
stuff we actually do there but like it's
been so long since we bothered doing
anything there it's just f-16s right so
we just say something like okay you know
here's the data and in here we would say
you know this this size here is sort of
like a fixed maximum you know what I
mean
meaning the total total number that you
get in here is some fixed maximum and so
all sounds will always be broken up into
like however many chunks it would take
right so in here I would just say look
this is the the maximum sound length and
so it would just be like based on
something like yeah let's say that I
want to have like them broken up into a
half second or something like that so
you know it's gonna be something like
this many samples and so we would just
have buffers that were that big and we
would just have some number of them
sitting around in a chain that we
manipulate right so here we would just
say yeah if it's loaded it's in this
audio buffer if it's not loaded that
it's not in the audio buffer and that's
basically at the end of that and all of
our sounds when we bring them in are
broken up into those chunks and you know
you if you need to use multiple chunks
you can
right so the audio buffer index in this
case is just saying and you know what we
could even just say how many of the
audio buffers you need although we
actually know that information so we
could just call this the first audio
buffer index and so that would just
store those and again now that's just
completely deterministic and it doesn't
matter right so we could do something
like that whether we want to do
something fancier or not I'm not sure
but it would seems pretty simple simple
and honestly if we always did them in a
round-robin scheme so we just always
just roll through the buffer which again
could be stupid I don't know because it
may be that you just then you end up
kind of thrashing because there's some
things like sounds like I hit the guy
that always remain in there and you
don't want to have to do that on the
other hand you could just say we're
always continuously streaming sound and
so it doesn't matter like it's like look
we always prefetch and we always
continuously streams so that's how
that's gonna work you know I don't know
which of those is the right decision
there it's tough to say
[Music]
I kind of want to say if you did a round
robin scheme there's an additional
pretty interesting thing you could do
there which is you don't actually have
to have a back size anymore right you
could just say I have a giant buffer you
know how much button buffer memory do I
want for sound I'll you know I allocated
64 megabytes every time I go to load a
sound I just load it into the buffer
wherever I am and that overwrites
whoever you know whoever was in that
location and then if they can then
determine that they've been overwritten
they just will reload themselves later
the next time they need to get used here
what I mean that sounds kind of dumb but
at the same time I like it I mean I
don't know it just sounds interesting
never heard of that before but it kind
of feels like it would just work
I'm gonna try it this may be really dumb
and I apologize if it is but like so
let's say right Kari you just say like
this is where we loaded the sound at
this particular sample index in our like
sample buffer right and if it's loaded
it's loaded there and and there we go
when you move through and someone else
needs to load then everybody who gets
you know all the sounds that were in
that that who's loaded that sample index
Kotik lipst have to then be sort of have
to be marked as unloaded and I guess
that's the hard part
I mean I guess that's the thing it like
I'm not sure exactly how you tell that
somebody has been unloaded versus not
oh man although if you just had a 64-bit
value that was the loaded it sample
index then you would know oh man so you
could just do this now you just say look
I imagine that I have an infinitely long
buffer and every time I load in a sound
I load it at a 64-bit imaginary giant
address when I look at where my current
loaded in window is it just slides
upwards in that imaginary you 64 address
by like every time I load new things on
I slide it upwards that's kind of nuts
but I like it a lot I mean that's just
plain bizarre oh man and that lets you
do that lets you do another really cool
thing this is awesome so that lets you
do another awesome thing which is that
if you want you can have two halves of
the buffer and go if I'm in the back
half of the buffer and I get played
don't reload me just copy me from the
back half of the buffer into the front
half of the buffer that's actually empty
so as you slide the window up if people
who are used frequently would be in
danger of falling out you can move them
up before they actually got unloaded at
all
this may be really stupid but I'm going
for it
sorry like that's just too crazy like
that's just hilarious and I love it so
then you just have a thing here which is
like yeah okay so here's my like sample
base like sample buffer base index and
and then I've got you know the actual
like sample buffer here and and I've
also got like a sample buffer count like
how many samples there are in the sample
buffer and like everything just happens
in here so we essentially have like a
sample buffer base index and then we
have a load index which probably is off
of the base index because it doesn't
that actually doesn't need to be 64
there it could be but it can't be that
big
so that just increases when it hits the
sample buffer count it goes back to zero
and the thing slides upward right and
then we would do that in halves like I
said so we wouldn't flush it's confusing
it's a little confusing but I think it
would work
all right I'm not gonna have nearly
enough time to make all of these things
the same let's see yeah so so I got a
ton of work that I'm gonna have to do so
I may like pause this and we'll start on
it next stream I do kind of want to be
able to still ask if things are valid
there so we'll put that in there anyway
but um so yeah so I've got a bunch of
stuff that I need to do now I need to do
both the textures the only thing that I
didn't really sketch out there is how
the fonts would work and like I said I'm
not sure how I want the fonts to work
exactly because I'm not sure if I want
to try and be more more fancy with those
what this does mean is like a lot of
this stuff would go away so like all of
this stuff I think is actually now not
necessary so we just we'd need just the
thing for loading in the actual original
files I think is all we would actually
need so this stuff I think would
actually disappear I'm not sure what is
the gamestate doing it for us here I
guess it's just for just for the tasks
so yeah I don't really know yeah I don't
really know to what extent that needs to
be happening at all but anyway um sooo
so yeah I mean I think this would
simplify itself quite a bit and the non
restored memory would just be any time
if you actually do want to load a font
the font just gets loaded into the into
the non restored memory there that seems
pretty easy to abide by and we probably
would just bite a direct load there so
like you know when you want to load a
font we was we just call the font load
immediately and so we like we like don't
queue those right so you know when we
would say load font load font is just
immediate so none of this stuff would
actually happen and so we would get rid
of all of this information here and well
I mean we would still need to do the
actual atomic set it just wouldn't be
atomic anymore like we wouldn't actually
need to be atomic we would just say look
it's if the asset state equals asset
state unloaded then we set it to loaded
and we go from there right and you know
we probably don't even need to do that
we can probably just assert because you
probably should never get here in that
case so we should just say like look
it's got a not you know don't do that
right and so then here when we would do
this part we would say look get rid of
all of this and the finalization you
know none of this stuff should really be
happening here so we would just say do
the load immediately like right here
rather than doing the asset work and so
for finalizing the font it's this
sure
I don't really know what we were doing
with that I guess we just wanted to
remap all the glyphs conveniently so we
could load them out of here so that's
still got to happen right so really all
we need is inside where we you know when
we're in that low priority queue doing
the the load s at work stuff
when we would get rid of the the delayed
read so rather than calling this in an
asynchronous fashion here this piece of
information comes sort of out and gets
called directly so onload font when this
happens we would just say look you know
I need the the file handle here so go
ahead and get me that I don't know what
that actually is called a look at the
load asset work function up here and so
that's going to be called platform file
handle so if they were going to say look
read the data from the file we've got
the offset which is this we've got the
size which is this and the destination
is this
so here's where that stuff all gets
mapped out and we want to probably make
sure that's laid out similarly in but
just in different memory right assuming
that this actually works here then what
we'll do is we will I I mean I guess I
don't really know what we would do in
the case where it fails to completely
honest with you that's kind of a tough
one because I don't know that we can
really come back from that we could try
to load it again but that's about it
so in this case if we like failed the
load you know all we could really do is
just just we we could give the memory
back but that's that's all we could
really do here so what we would want to
do is assert that we can you know load
this thing figure out how much we
actually want memory wise for it instead
of a set header here so we don't want
that so in other words this goes away
and all we're really doing is saying
here's the the memory that we're gonna
use and so inside here we need acquire
some permanent asset memory so if this
call is gonna get modified a little bit
but basically this is the same thing the
ID top value and the asset type font
that would go away so we just be calling
this and then when we come through here
we would say all right let's get the
loaded font information out of here we
do whatever nonsense we're doing here
that means that inside the asset system
this is still presumably beneficial
because it tells us all the information
we need to actually work with this thing
so let me put that down here so that's
actually valid and so the only thing we
really don't know about here is is this
loaded at sample index I don't know
I'm pretty sure all that's available
from the HHA right so you know we don't
really need that it doesn't need to be
there it's it's right here so those are
just blind copy outs so loaded that is
gone right that's no good
this is gone and so really it's only
this one this is the only type this
that's the only actual state that that
remains out of our original ones the
rest of them are now gone so I think all
of that is it's pretty good
and I think we still do need this the
you know I guess even I don't really
even know that but I think we still do
need the the u32 here for what the state
of the asset is we may not even need
that if we actually chose to retire
things on a frame boundary we could
avoid even that and again we would just
only need a lock for this one place in
the code and that maybe is better I
don't know like so we'll see how that
goes as we sort of push a little bit
forwards on it but like I said hopefully
this simplifies this quite a bit coming
down here then for the you know just to
finish off the load for the load font
stuff so as we acquire asset memory
therefore this memory then what we would
do here is say yeah like this here is
just that this stuff is gonna start at
the font
iving at the memory pointer now and then
all the rest of this stuff stays the
same you know I mean
I don't know if there's anything else
none of that has to happen the finalized
asset nonsense up here doesn't have to
happen either because the only thing
that would go on at that point is a nun
or bitmap so the font goes away so we
really only have these two what do you
need to do a complete texture wrap thing
or don't you in theory we could even get
rid of that and just say look if there
was a texture up it needs to be complete
it and if there wasn't there wasn't
so in some sense that can even be made
more straightforward as well because the
only thing that could actually happen
here is
that's not true the only thing that
would really happen here is this I think
pretty sure and so that would get rid of
this as well like if these are set to
zero then they're just not used I think
that's the end of it I also don't know
its final state ever set to anything
else loaded loaded so that's always
asset state loaded so I think that can
get simplified down to like so and again
we maybe even we may even be able to get
rid of that load asset work directly is
presumably oh interesting
Oh interesting so we had a fallback here
I see we were considering having a
fallback that was for probably immediate
where we would just if we couldn't load
it done demand we would try to load it
right away I don't think we want that so
I think again the other thing we can do
here is just say all right look that's
just going to be this right so we can
just kind of get rid of that makes it a
little bit more some simplified there
all right so moving on like we got yeah
there's a ton of work to do here but I
think we can just simplify a lot of this
stuff quite a bit and just you know
really remove so now all of this stuff
can go away completely so we would never
need any of this asset header nonsense
and we would never need a variable sized
asset store which you know just really
it's ugly and I didn't like it so all of
that stuff would be pretty easy to do as
far as getting bit PAP is concerned
where you return a loaded bitmap again
that really would now just be returning
a texture handle so you know get bitmap
in this case is just going to return a
renderer texture and it would return the
renderer texture directly out of here so
presumably the way that would work is it
would just say well you know we'll we'll
give you back whatever the handle was
and if it's not loaded we would try to
load it I would think and then you would
just use his valid here to determine
whether or not you actually wanted to do
it I don't know why we weren't checking
the status field because that seems like
the more appropriate thing to be
checking here in other words it seems
like this should have been saying asset
state equals asset you know loaded or
whatever but maybe we don't even want to
do that maybe we wanted to say look you
can just render with it whatever it is
so the asset like texture handle in this
case the results going to come back as
that and when we unload a texture we'll
just romp over that with zero and that's
how that's gonna go
you know that's totally plausible I
think yeah and so inside get info again
totally same code no difference there
inside here where we do loaded sounds
again loaded sounds not really gonna be
a thing that you get back per se so you
would be expected to actually access the
sound info for
information you wanted so get sounds
gonna actually have to be let get sound
samples right and get sound samples
gonna have to return the next s
sixteenth pointer but that pointer will
always be valid which is kind of nice so
because we're all you would always be
aligned to the correct you 64 boundaries
so if this is a little bit
we gotta actually do that but you know
worst case scenarios you play the wrong
sound if it's like that far off in the
streaming but you'll play the right
sound or you'll get zero back pretty
much all the time so in here when you
call get font again same thing I guess
in this case no change their asset
memory header is not necessary so I
think all of these things that call that
now can just call get asset right
we can also assert on the type in this
case so again we weren't actually doing
that here so I think I will just
continue to do that here and then that
way we can make sure that's consistent
and then we can say that that always
comes off of the asset pointer again
that's just better right so you can get
that bitmap or the info for the bitmap
we may want to just return you the
actual bitmap itself and then you can
get whichever one you want but I don't
know we'll see how we want to play
around that a little bit later again
same thing would happen here when we axe
the value we would say you know is that
is it the sound you know we you know
what's going on there and we would
assert that we'd get that back properly
same thing would happen in this case we
would want to make sure it's actually a
sound before we give you back something
that it's not actually a sound and then
in the font case
same thing we would just always say look
it's the asset font in this case if we
got an asset if it's loaded I guess is
the only real difference here so yeah I
don't really know how that one should go
that's a that one's a little bit more
questionable like should we just
initialize that font to zero everywhere
and and it knows the difference I don't
know so if I look more at how that would
end up end up being initialized yeah I
think that just wants to be allotted so
I think that wants to be like a you know
an asset state equals asset state loaded
I think we just want to do that
because unlike the other ones which can
always be computed properly this one
can't be it's a bunch of pointers and so
we have to verify that it has in fact
been fully loaded before we can do
anything with it
right so I think that's all fine and
we'll put one last one in here where we
look at the asset pointer for that
and then I think we're good to go and
most of that stuff right so then in
stuff like this we would no longer ever
have loaded bitmaps anywhere right you
would just be doing two extra handles so
really you know this would get passed
directly in here and when people call
the bitmap they would they would
literally just be getting back just the
texture handle and you wouldn't be
passing bitmaps around ever right so
these are render a texture texture
handle and this stuff goes away you know
what I'm saying
[Music]
and again these are just like steps in
condensing the code like now that we've
figured out how all this stuff has to
work we can just start to eliminate
stuff that isn't necessary and that's
slowing us down and we're just getting
rid of unnecessary intermediate
structures right you know C++
programming normally a brainy program is
all about adding all of these crufty
intermediate structures that don't do
anything I don't like that kind of
coding I like to when we figure out that
we don't need stuff I want it to go away
because that always improves like the
quality of the code in my opinion it
makes it easier to maintain it makes it
faster to compile and to run it's just
it's just better
okay so yeah I'm still in the mood here
what time is it what is it like a 3:30
our cat should probably wrap it up so
I'm gonna maybe I might do another
stream later I don't know I'm in a
streaming mood certainly this this
season so I think we will wrap it up
there and then we will come back and
spend another maybe you know either
today or tomorrow going through here and
actually making it so that we you know
so that we can implement all of this
stuff properly and that'll give us the
reloading that we wanted which was the
main impetus for actually going through
the work here but it will also let us
just have a much more simplified code
base which would be nice so here's my
texture handle I'm gonna do in is valid
on that so you knew I wanted that and if
it's not valid well then we would load
it right and so that code still works
properly exactly how we would want yeah
and and we would just keep pushing
through here so this would be like text
your handle render protector um so I'll
go to a brief Q&amp;A you can start queuing
your questions now if you've got them
yeah and I will answer those in a second
all right and so now you can see like
pretty much most of the stuff is exactly
where we would expect it to be in terms
of stuff we're gonna have to fix so you
know it's just all in the asset system
basically right and then the the audio
part of things so I might just ping
through here and just say yeah like
while we're at it let me just change
this one as well because that's the only
one in another file their renderer
texture texture handle and we'd get that
out of here and then say is valid so if
we're actually gonna be able to render
it and let me just go ahead and find out
where the other errors would have been
in the entity system because there
aren't many right so that would just be
the texture handle and the texture
handle right and so then we're just down
and even the devil you I one I can
probably fix to so we just down to asset
system in audio which is what I would
want so when you know in here it's just
text your handle
and let's see what else we got is that
it well I got one more debug system
all right so I think that is everything
except for the two systems that we
actually wanted to change which is audio
system and the asset so that should
leave us exactly where we want to be for
next stream start yeah I don't know when
the next team will leave but some time
could you elaborate more on what you
were talking about with more
intermediate data structures in
object-oriented programming I just mean
to say that
so in object-oriented programming and as
the word itself implies the idea is not
really to focus on the algorithm its to
focus on the objects because that is I
mean it's right in the name right and so
it's considered a virtue to have extra
things in there that are representing
something and it's not considered a main
goal of your programming to keep the
number of objects as low as physically
possible right but I consider that a
good thing right like I like the code to
have as few of objects or things that
look like them as possible and I like
things as much as possible to be just
algorithms you can read so it's the
procedures that are important objects
are irrelevant and I don't care about
how you draw the boundaries around them
I think that's all erroneous things to
focus on right and so I like it when we
remove layers of abstraction and bind
things more tightly together whereas
object-oriented programming is the
opposite it likes to separate things and
add layers of abstraction in between
them
you're the start of the stream I think
you mentioned focusing and making the
game look more professional can you
recap what that entails and does that
mean making some artistic decisions on
the stream uh no I just mean like so at
some point you make a leap from the game
looking like a prototype to looking like
an actual game and it's sort of going in
that direction now right so let me give
you some examples first of all we will
probably turn this off by default and
only put it on when you hit a key right
second there's like empty space here so
we'll start making our levels Oh ease
like the camera will never go outside of
where there's actual stuff so we'll have
you know something out here like you
know grounds of the orphanage and stuff
like that will remove placeholder style
things like these light cubes you know
we'll have a real story about how lights
are attached to objects and they'll be
invisible we will no longer have stuff
like weird cat heads that show up as a
particle system test right and as you
start to go through each thing and clean
it up and polish it it then starts
feeling like an actual game world and it
looks more professional right and you
haven't really done anything specific
per se but you have crossed some
threshold of cruft that just you haven't
been paying attention to and now that
you've paid attention to it it looks
much more polished right and it starts
to look like an actual game that you
might buy and less like something that
you're working on and so I'm just saying
we're kind of at that point where we're
starting to try and cross over into that
and so that there's a lot of things on
that threshold that we want to look at
you know what I mean
I've read the sequel happy compass
laughs to you as well Krampus laughs
happy crumb for self I don't know how
you celebrate it other than by
programming I'm putting a bit off topic
if I remember correctly you said that
during the kron4 South streams you may
do some other things like hammer a ray
will be the next thing to do with
handmade ray the next thing we would do
with handmade raised it doesn't have a
reflectance function in there right now
so basically everything is like just a
chalk like a blend between chalk and
mirror I think or something it doesn't
have like any doesn't try to actually
compute any real light kind of
information and so that's that's what we
would do probably and then after that be
some like important sampling so all
right I'm gonna wrap it up
thank your for joining me for the upside
handmade here it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow my series at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade here
org it comes to the source code so you
can follow along with it I'll be back
here for another Krampus Lau stream
fairly soon I'm not sure exactly when
we'll see but I would like to go take a
look at that asset system so we'll see
when that happens that's about it
have fun programming on your own and
I'll see you when we return take it easy
everybody