start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero show recode a
complete game live on stream we are in
the middle of trying to figure out how
our entities get sort of handled as
groups when necessary and yeah we sort
of started on that a little bit
yesterday but I thought about it after
having started down a certain path
yesterday and I was thinking I kind of
thought of a different idea that I
hadn't considered and I wasn't sure
exactly what I do and don't want to do
in terms of trying stuff out there so I
wanted to briefly go over kind of what
my thinking was and why I was thinking
it with you so that you'll know where
I'm coming from because I think I may
reverse course slightly from what we did
yesterday okay so here's the essential
problem that we have that is that let's
say that we have two entities such as
with our hero where we've got kind of
the you know the torso piece or I guess
right now we're kind of cut we've been
calling that the body and then we've got
the head and these are actually separate
entities and in theory during parts of
the game they may even detach if you
have like some kind of magic spell or
something who knows right so they're
capable of acting separately but they're
also capable of acting together and this
is like a case that I want to start
working out a little bit more to try and
make sure that it's handled cleanly
because I think we're going to need this
in more cases as well and so one of the
examples that I think is worth noting
for for this right is let's say we
wanted a snake like boss monster or just
not even boss monster but just a monster
and you know maybe that thing kind of
looks you know like a little like snaky
sort of thing where it's got sort of a
headpiece you know with like antennae or
whatever and then little you know body
pieces here that that it kind of has
maybe I don't know if they've got legs
or what's going on and it can occupy you
know many squares right and when the
headpiece moves you know the body pieces
I move with it right and obviously you
know you'd want to make it so that if
you attack and kill this piece then it
becomes sort of severed but maybe like
this part still walks around and this
part does too so it's like it you know
it breaks into two pieces and then keeps
moving right and so you know we I feel
like we're gonna have multiple different
places where this sort of thing comes in
yet another example might be you know
let's suppose that I've got some enemy
creature like boss monster kind of a
thing that's like you know some piece
that's sitting across a couple squares
or whatever but then it also has you
know like little like arm things that
come out to try and get you or whatever
and maybe those are you know somehow
attached or maybe it's got a little
floating piece that goes around with it
that like kind of circles it or whatever
and again like you know in a lot of
these cases you sort of end up in this
situation where the it's very similar to
the way the entity system was sort of
does
I was conceptualizing having that work
in terms of just having sort of this
collection of properties and things
without having to really define what it
is so that it can sort of amorphous lee
shift between different sort of ways of
being the same has started true for
these things like you know if there's
two or three arms to the guy and a body
or whatever then they should be
controlled as such if one of the arms
gets detached and needs to go off and be
a separate entity for some reason and
isn't controlled by the main entity or
something that should be fine you know
you kind of want this flexibility to
sort of mix and match these entities at
will and not really have to worry about
their controllers being something you
create up front you kind of want them to
be able to sort of have these
controllers be more dynamic than that
right that's kind of tricky so what I
was thinking is rather than go down the
route that we were going down yesterday
where we sort of have this notion that
entities kind of know about who they're
paired with and it's this mutual
direction kind of a thing
I'm concerned about that because I just
don't feel like that is the natural
way to write the code and like you saw
me struggle with it a bit and I mean
struggles a weird word because I guess
it wasn't like it wasn't working but you
saw me have to do a bunch of things to
like figure out well where does the code
for the head go where does the code for
the body go right and we kind of it was
kind of
you kinda just want to have a head body
controller that does both of them right
and then if there's a separate
controller that only does bodies that's
fine or maybe just have some if code but
spreading the code out to two different
things is not so good right we'd rather
have the code in one place and then it
just does well if there isn't a head
then just don't do the head part maybe
but you know it's not like we want to
write this code in isolation of knowing
about both entities and so forcing it
into a concept that every entity
simulates itself it's like I'm falling
into the trap that I would never have
fallen into in regular code right I
would always tell someone not to be an
OOP programmer right I would say why are
you writing this code that's that's like
focused on breaking up the code amongst
objects when the natural place to write
it is across the objects right and the
same thing is true in the entity system
like why would we break up the
controller for a head in a body when the
more natural way to write that is a head
body controller that just checks to see
whether the head is there or not and
then does one thing or another
right and so what I'd rather do is step
back from that sort of OOP
like stupidity and go into something
that's again more focused on the
algorithm and how can we get the entity
system to work in this way that works
across objects and so I thought of a way
to actually do that which is kind of
interesting I hadn't really concerned
this before and so I think this is what
I'd rather try and again I don't have a
lot of examples yet so I'm just trying
it I'm trying to figure out what might
work for this guy and then we could
maybe write another one for something
like you know maybe that's snake dude
and and so I could make like a snake
creature and then we could see like does
it hold up or doesn't it hold up because
we have one use case and we can figure
out something that works for that but
then you know maybe writing another use
case would be a good way to validate it
and make sure that oh it's it's not just
like something that only works for this
one case it works across more than that
right so here's what I thought of and
it's a little weird but I feel like it's
interesting so the way that we have
things work now is right we've got this
sort of sim region concept right and
when we unpack things we sort of have
all these chunks in the world and they
get unpacked into the sim region right
and then we have actual entities and so
during that unpacking process we see all
these entities come through and we put
them into the hash table so that we know
what their IDs are and we can look them
up a by ID if we happen to have an
entity that wants to like you know chase
another entity and so the idea of an
entity reference in that case still
makes a fair bit of sense to me and I
don't think it necessarily needs to get
removed because that still seems
reasonable meaning a couple there's some
entity reference things that still make
sense which are not things you know if
it's not something I'm talking about
controlling if it's something that I'm
actually talking about I'm looking at
this guy or I'm attacking this guy that
I think can stay the way we had it where
there's just this notion of an entity
reference and an ende can reference
other entity in that way that seems fine
what doesn't seem fine was the thing
about entities coming together to form a
coherent operating unit and so that's
the part that I wanted to focus on
fixing so what I thought I would do is
say okay what if in addition to the hash
table we also have a thing that's like
controller templates and I don't mean
templates like the C++ guy in that that
suck i mean--can templates like in a
literal sense like we have sort of like
ideas of what a controller can be and so
one example of a controller template
might be the hero controller that we've
talked about and that has a slot for the
body and it has a slot for the head
right okay now any entity in our system
when it's packed into the chunk can have
a thing in it and they all I guess what
probably have one well no I guess only
entities that can have controllers
active on them would have this I suppose
would have what's called a controller
tag on them or something like this
some name of that type and what that
would have is the template type and an
instance ID right now the instance ideas
can come from the same place as our
entity ideas ideas come from just a
monotonic increasing thing and the
template type is what kind of controller
it's currently expecting to have right
furthermore we add one more thing in
here which is the slot now these things
and I suspect this slot will be like a
slot no it's all right it's just a slot
and so this is you know this could just
be an index we'll have to see how we
want to store it all right the template
types are all the different controllers
that we might have just any controller
that we might have so the hero
controller the snake controller that
whatever blah blah blah right so all of
our things get a controller and they get
an instance ID which says what group is
this actually associated with so if I
create a hero each of the pieces of that
hero would have a template type that was
the hero controller right it's one of
these and it would have an instance ID
that's just some instance ID that's
picked that all of them share right when
they get unpacked we have a separate
hash table for instance IDs we look up
in the instance ID to see if we already
have a controller at that instance ID
and if we do we insert this entity into
its corresponding slot body or head or
whatever now if this slot is an array
type slot then it can have multiple in
there right you can stick a bunch of
them in there and if it doesn't then it
can only have one right and we have to
decide how we deal with conflicts and
maybe the way we deal with is you could
always have more than one in there and
it's the controller's responsibility to
do so
think smart if it's got multiple of them
who knows right I'm not sure how exactly
that would work okay so this way
the way things work is at any time we
can just take any entity right and make
it into its own thing by just assigning
it a new template type which is whatever
controller we want to have in a new
instance ID right and what slot it goes
in in there we can group entities
together by just giving them the same
Endocyte so if some guy wants to like
pick up something and stick it on and
use it as his arm we just take its
template type and assign it to whatever
his controller is you take its instance
ID in a science or whatever his instance
ideas and we take its lot and assign it
to arm now that thing just has a new arm
right and they're all gathered together
based on whenever the sim region is you
know gathers the things up anything that
happens to be in that room is controlled
by that thing and this word would work
in ridiculous scenarios if I batch this
guy's arm off right and now I'm carrying
the arm for this creature around with me
somehow right if I walk off the screen
and carry it up over and drop it
somewhere if that guy comes walking over
and can get to his arm right he still
knows when he walks into the region that
that's his arm and his controller will
still see it in the arm slot and go oh
that thing was part of me right so it
can do all of the things that you would
normally do if you created some kind of
super structure but it's entirely on
demand so it can be broken and streamed
apart and doesn't have any sort of clean
up or or deletion associated with if
there's no maintenance it's all stored
eats per entity and assembled at same
time so there's no overhead essentially
to doing it and there's no restrictions
on doing it you don't have to keep these
things live or worry about what happens
if it thinks there's a head there and
there isn't during those thing because
they're all always assembled each time
you go to do a sim
I don't know so maybe there's something
I'm not thinking of but it feels really
right to me and it gets rid of that
object-oriented nastiness that's what
makes things so ugly and bad in regular
code I don't want that inherited into
our entity system in just another form
and so I think this gets us around that
and allows us to write the code in a
natural way so I'm just going to go and
do that and see what happens
okay so first things first I don't know
why I'm Solinsky Trey because I'm oh I'm
in the wrong place well it doesn't
matter I guess I can just when I load it
we'll fix it
so to go to hand-made project do a
little bill Deepu then really to be
honest probably what I do here is I just
revert yesterday's changes to I don't
think I even want them but we didn't
change very much so I probably won't
bother going through that actual I don't
know what I'm trying to think of what
I'm actually oh yeah I probably won't
actually bother going through that but
really what we did yesterday we just
don't need because we're never going to
stream out array storage at least not of
references that I can think of so we
really just don't need to do that it's
it's simply not necessary by the way I
don't know if Allen's watching he was
wondering how to encounter that bug let
me see if I can do it again this was a
bug Allen was asking me about and I was
just able to make it happen so I've
loaded the hand-made here a project I go
let me switch to a buffer roll my CP and
if I hit X I'm locked up so all I have
to do is open a buffer hit X and the
first time I do that it looks like it
locks up then as soon as I switch that
buffer to something else I'm back in
here and it never happens again
so it must be something with the first
time you create something in a panel
like that yeah and it has to do with I
think it's like we were looking at my
for code or custom it does have
something to with my for code or custom
because I think we had nerfs and things
when we were working on it originally
that weren't implemented yet in for code
or weren't working it for coder so it
may be just that but that's how you
reproduce the bug if that helps so load
a buffer hit X to spawn the new window
that windows locked but as soon as you
change buffers it unlocks and then it's
never a problem again as far as I can
tell so it's only it has to be like an
empty panel and you have to X you know
use the X command to move into it I
guess seems like it and I don't know if
that happens if I delete stuff down to
an empty panel I know how to get back to
an empty panel I don't know how to get
back to an empty panel so I'm not sure
how to see if it ever happens outside of
that yeah let's see and it looks like I
guess maybe doesn't have to be empty it
looks like the compilation buffer was
enough but it's very clear that after I
get out of that it doesn't happen again
like Here I am kidding X all day long
and no no big deal right so so I have no
idea but it just must be something
peculiar all right so anyway sorry for
that diversion I just know that was a
bug Alan wanted to fix and so I wanted
to make sure I got that repo in there
like I said it may just be something
with my four code or custom but that's a
yeah now we know all right so anyway
inside sim region and entity I have to
repair a little bit of the damage I did
and simply say that now we're not
probably going to store relationships
anymore we're just going to have the
entity references the way that they used
to be
right Crips like so and these
relationships are not gonna be there
anymore right that's just not going to
be a thing anymore
and let's see entity references valid
that's gonna be not having to check the
relationship stuff so I don't even know
yeah this doesn't really need to be
there anymore what is happening this
doesn't need to be there anymore and
this doesn't need to be there anymore
either
yeah so it's something like this okay
so hmm what we would be replacing this
with again is I kind of want this notion
of the template of thing this goes away
and so in here I essentially want you
know a thing that's like entity
controller type and this is like a
controller you know none controller hero
and you know let's be optimistic and say
we're gonna have a snake controller as
well right if that makes sense
okay so these controllers are the things
that'll kind of assemble up the
creatures and so in here I would have
something that would say okay I've got
the entity controller type and that's
the type of the controller template that
I want to use right and this can just be
set to none if it's just an MD that
doesn't have that type of controller and
then it has like an entity controller
slot and I don't really know that I want
that to be anything like I said we'll
write the code for it you know in I
don't know I'll call it writing the
usage code first because I kind of just
have this imaginary thing in my head so
we're just gonna have to kind of play
with it and see by writing a hero
controller but at the moment but until
we actually have some more code that I
can actually look at I'm thinking this
is just a thing that's like literally an
index right and there so there's just
you know some number of slots on this
controller and you can pick which one
you go in so I can have the controller
type I can't have a controller slot and
I can have a controller instance ID
right and that can just be an entity ID
I don't know that we need it to be
separate and I'm just so I'm not sure
but again at the moment I'm going to
keep them separate and this is just to
make sure that I don't accidentally
conflate them right
and so so this would essentially be what
would be necessary to assemble those
sort of meta entities right you can kind
of think of this as you know the the
entity kind of that's built out of this
set of entity pieces if you will and you
know there's a couple things about it
that I'm not quite sure about yet
like whether the itself needs additional
storage and if it itself needs
additional storage there are some things
we could do and that's why I like I said
I don't know if this is a separate ID
like if the if the superstructure also
has data then this would have to be one
of these where it's like this is my sort
of meta entity that that I'm that builds
you know out of me essentially but I
don't know if we need that or if we
don't and for them I don't know if we
want that or we don't like I think we
might want to make it more that the
properties of the meta anity are
determined by its sub entities because
that's kind of what makes the organic
Ness whereas if it just sort of has
inherent properties I don't know like
you know I feel like you want the brain
of the thing to be based on what it has
on it and so like if the thing gets its
head chopped off I don't want it to
still necessarily know a bunch of
settings that we magically set it should
become an auto stupid arm that has like
let's just derived from whatever it's
derived from so I don't really know that
part yet so for the moment I was gonna
say that these are separate and you
can't use like an entity controller ID
anywhere else like it's just literally
for this one hashing operation and it's
a totally separate table from the entity
ID table that's just my thinking at the
moment so we'll see and technically
since this is something we're playing
with here I feel like these should kind
of go down here right and so this kind
of replaces the notion of the entity
type because now the entity itself never
has a type
it just has whatever is controlling
at this time because that's the only
thing that's actually unique meaning
only one thing is allowed to control me
it's either the players controller or a
thing or whatever so rather than saying
this is a hero we're never gonna say
that again we're just gonna say it has a
hero controller on it but whatever it is
is defined by other things right and
then if for some reason some part of it
gets broken off that part can just be
picked up by another controller and it
just off it goes and it it's type it has
nothing to do with that right it may be
a glove it's type is not glove right it
just happens to be part of the hero
controller in the glove slot if it
breaks off later it can become a piece
of something else and you know that's
kind of the way that I want it to work
right so that's why I'm trying to get
away from the notion that an entity
itself has an intrinsic type and more
that that is a diffused piece of
information sort in many places so
instead of type determining who your
controller is and how you're drawn will
do something each one of those should be
defined by other things and so we want
to break that entity type into multiple
things that can that could be different
right again so that's just kind of I
kind of explained that yesterday by just
trying to continue to say why I'm
pushing towards this rather than just
having one universities because I'm
trying to find where that other I'm
trying to get to this other place right
that I feel like is there in my head but
I don't really know which is kind of the
nature of architecture right okay so
that's what I actually want to do we now
no longer really have any sort of me and
it kind of a thing like I don't have an
actual entity reference anymore that
actually needs to happen but you know I
should probably you know like I said we
do want entity reference I'm not getting
rid of entity reference it's just not
actually a thing anymore that it that is
in any of the creatures we have it will
be I think target like who I'm targeting
when I'm attacking or stuff like that
will be an entity reference so I think
there will be any references it's just
now the controller aggregation replaces
pairing so pointers back and forth to
people they're gone
right okay so in here we have an entity
hash right which is one of these guys
but we're also going to
have a controller hash and I don't know
why I call it an entity controller
because it's not like we have other
controllers oh well
and you know what controller might be a
weird word because controller sounds
like game controller so maybe before I
get too far next we could call it brain
maybe cuz that's like you know what's
the brain type it's not maybe the most
descriptive but it's gonna be unique you
know what I mean so let's try that let's
just say we have like these sort of
slots and it's just its brain right
brain so I'm gonna go ahead and make
each of those make each of Em's 50/50 to
do two two and then in here I'll with a
brain hash which sounds like some kind
of a bad atom like an after-school
special or something so this would be a
pointer to one of our brain things and
in here we would have a brain ID which
is the ID which is the ID right why this
is index so seems the same same right
that's probably too many right there's
not many of these so it's probably more
like a you know that sort of thing
since mobs are cheap I don't know that
power of two is such a good idea I feel
like in the future we probably want to
make that a prime number and deal with
the mod but you know again minutiae we
can work out anytime we want really
so these frame hashes right are just
things where we can kind of look up and
say okay let's see if we've got one of
these wait a second how does this deal
with duplicates
is this an internally chained hash this
must be an internally chained hash huh
oh yeah it is okay well that makes sense
all right so anyway Jimmy so anyway this
is supposed in that case to our entity
hash we might as well to store the
entities directly in there probably I
don't know if that would be bad for cash
reasons because you'd lose a bit more of
the hash testing but I do kind of wonder
if we should just have this the entity
do you know what I'm saying but that's
it that's that's a story for another
time all right so we've got our brains
our brains will get assembled as we sort
of you know wish these things up and
yeah I feel like I guess I don't so I
don't really know what this value should
be you know I don't really have any idea
but the again these have a cost to them
and the cost is the clearing right so
there is an upfront cost for figuring
out essentially there is an upfront cost
to having this be arbitrarily sized
because we have to do it every frame we
can do incremental clears and other
sorts of stuff like that in the future
but it's definitely the kind of thing
that you know it's probably gonna be you
know could be a pressure point who knows
so anyway we have our brain hash as
entities come in and we see controller
IDs for them we'll add in the brain hash
obviously we would have our controller
ID of zero be reserved for no controller
and a core controller type at least we
have a reserved no controller sort of a
thing for that so that's easy enough and
I think I think that's about it it's
true that since controller ID can be 0
it's possible that brain type actually
doesn't have to
null so I'm gonna stick it like that for
now and say that you actually don't need
one here because if your controller ID
just isn't set to anything then if your
color ID is set to zero then your
controller type right doesn't have to it
doesn't have to have a zero element not
that that matters to anyone ever but
it's fine
all right so during this this simulation
step what we want to do here is when we
call identity right
which I guess is this situation here I
guess I don't know add into the raw I
don't even think anyone's calling this
anymore are they I guess I got a stub
that out for the moment all right moving
on what is going on there we go
moving on I'm gonna have to sort of
clean up the damage I did yesterday like
I sang so in order to do that we've got
PAC at any reference array really isn't
a thing anymore so traversable reference
and PAC entity reference how can any
reference is really just going to be
what it was before I guess so
we just have this and I believe that the
entirety of that code was was just
saying if the ref had a pointer
right basically that if the reference
was a pointer then the ref ID where is
it index what it's called here yeah so
if we have a pointer set then we're
going to go ahead and set the the index
equal to the pointer is ID like so and
if we didn't what we want to do here is
say well we'll either clear it or leave
it the same if the if the element is not
in the hash table right so if if the if
this sim region doesn't have one of
these guys in there then we we would
assume you know that that we'd get rid
of it
the other thing true that I think is
true is during this pack we'd probably
want to check if it's deleted right so
we'd probably say like if deleted or
something like this right
something like this
so in here this is kind of temporary for
the way we're doing the packing because
we don't actually pack it down we leave
the same but we still need to do the
operation of packing to make sure that
the index season pointers stay in sync
so we want to do something here where we
base to say okay if this reference is
set to something valid if it's a deleted
entity if it's entity that no longer you
know got marked as being removed from
the set of entities that there are in
the world then you know we can we would
want to get rid of it right we'd want to
say like okay you know don't don't
consider this as a dude anymore
don't you know don't think that you're
following this guy or whatever because
he's gone otherwise we would take its ID
and say that's the new thing to store if
we don't have a pointer then clearing
the index is only valid if this thing is
it is in the table so like it you know
is in hash table excuse me we would want
to say
something like this or what is it called
stem region the reason for this is well
let's say that I'm referencing somebody
and that somebody walks out of the
simulation region they're just gone
well I'm a swan I still remember that
right so I want to look and go oh okay
if my pointer is zero that means that
this guy is no longer visible to me now
but I may want to store the index still
so what I want to do there is say okay
did I set this value to zero meaning I'm
trying to clear it or did the guy just
go out of the sim region is no longer
here and that's why the pointer didn't
get loaded this time around right and so
in that case I just want to see well is
it in the hash table if it's in the hash
table then I said it that some of us
have set it to zero and they're trying
to clear out this reference so let me do
that up when I pack it let me get rid of
it right that's basically all I'm saying
okay so I don't know like I said it's a
little janky I'm not sure about this yet
but that's basically the way it works
the problem here is when we're doing our
packing we don't always have a sim
region when we're doing our packing and
the example there is we don't have a sim
region during the pack if like say we're
doing world creation at that time you
know what I mean so I don't really know
exactly how to approach this again it's
something that we're gonna have to work
on as we go forward but I would say it's
probably something like okay you pass
some region if you don't pass this image
and then the pack doesn't do this so if
there's no sim region or it's in the
hash table and I guess I'll take a look
at instant region and see exactly how
that query ends up happening load entity
reference here does get hash from ID
this situation and
I think that's really all I have to do
so if I say get hash from ID sim region
ref index I don't know why insisted on
putting that as an dot it's not a dot
all right so I come in here and I say
well is this thing deleted and that's a
query that we're gonna have to do like
later we don't really ever delete
entities at the moment but we're gonna
start right so we say if it's deleted I
don't want to start reference to it
otherwise I do want to store the
reference to it if there's no sim region
at the moment so it's world creation
time or I'm trying to get the hash from
the ID here and I see if anything came
back if something does come back then I
want to clear it because that means it
should have been there so someone must
have actually tried to be getting rid of
it but if if I don't then I leave it be
because it's just somebody who walked
out the region it still wants to be
there right so again in here so we kind
of have this thing where we're we're
we're doing the sim region is passed
through again and here we've got the
same sort of things in regions in region
and I would say this is probably yeah
all of this stuff just passes it through
and like I said I'm still not 100%
certain about that it definitely like
there's definitely some jenkki 'no stare
and so it's a question of whether i can
think of something smarter to do there
and maybe I can maybe I can't I'm not
sure we'll find out okay
ah let's keep going here so is deleted
would be something on the entity and at
the moment I guess we have this entity
flag deleted so you know it's gonna be
basically a thing that's like is deleted
is just it takes an entity and returns
like eflags and any flag deleted right
and that's really all it is but it looks
like I've got an is set here so I guess
this is really just is set entity any
flag deleted right
so moving along this is dot value get
hash from ID is not sound really - ID
so if you say get entity by ID and it
can't refer to it here this this I feel
like this wants to be this doesn't it I
mean get entity by ID should be doing
the same check right and this is
essentially this so I don't really know
why those two were different
probably just vestigial remains we have
made a lot of changes here at some point
we should probably kind of go through ok
so sorry back to what I was doing before
so get hash from ID I could actually
have this just you get entity by ID and
have this be a free you know a function
that's sort of pre callable but I don't
know I'm gonna actually just do it like
this all right so let's see
no operator right you are sir pack
entity into chunk so pack entity into
Chuck doesn't take three arguments and
that is actually true
it takes a sim region now let's see sim
region have so these have to be entity
hash now you've got multiple hashes
check entity into world so these are
just taking zero because they do not
have a sim region same here
is that true all right no so this does
have some reason yeah these are not
necessary anymore so these these are
just they just don't exist anymore right
those are all gone but we will sort of
want to do a thing here where we say
like okay allocate another entity ID
right and we want to sort of make a
brain ID for it
right so we'd say let's get a brain
let's let's let's add a brain and all
that's going to do is give us an ID it
doesn't actually to create anything it
just gives us a token that we can use
and then we would say all right the the
brain ID so we just come back to entity
here and all of these fields like
controller type controller slot these
are all going to be set here
now how I want to do brain slot I'm not
sure that's something that we're going
to have to play with a little bit and
we'll kind of see why I say that in a
second there's gonna be a little bit of
touching this there because we want that
to be something that works nice and
clean and there's gonna be a little bit
of work in us getting that to happen but
you know at the moment let's say that it
worked like this even though this is not
how it's actually going to work so these
are basically both the same in all
respects except for what slot they go
into right so they both have the same
controller one of them that goes into
slot 0 what I'm going to slap one right
and the reason I say that I don't really
want to do it that way is cuz I don't
want to have to remember a bunch of
indices like the ped goes in slot 0 and
the brain you know blah blah blah I want
that to be cleaner so we don't have to
constantly be remembering a bunch of
indices or creating the ton of
enumerators or something like this so
we'll want to kind of make that be a
little bit more straightforward as we go
we're then that we're okay so here is
something to add a brain all this is
going to do is exactly the same thing
that we do up here where we do last huge
storage index right that's that we're
just going to grab exactly that same
thing so we're just gonna say ok there's
a brain ID oops the brain ID just equals
whatever the current storage situation
is and then we can like sort of lock
this guy up to be here with the the
other dudes alright so in here I think
we called this index map it's not value
there we go
and then this sort of pure identity
thing so this is now gonna be quite a
bit different and the way this is going
to work and
and I'm kind of really excited like I
said I'm pretty excited about this I'm I
have a good feeling about the way this
is going and here's why
right so what do we want to do right how
do we want this code to normally work
well if we were just writing it without
all this crazy permutations that we want
to support you know probably we just
write some code that's like for each
player move your guy in the direction
you want them to go and then simulate
everything right like and that's sort of
what we had here for our code like we
had these controllers and then we had to
put the controller stuff into things and
then we came back here and we were like
picking up we were like finding what
controller you were associated with and
like picking that back up again right
and crap like this and so now I think
what we can do is we can make like we
can make this work exactly that way but
in an organic like real fashion for
that's uniform across everything and
doesn't have that like right and pick
back up it can like do the thing that it
wants to do and then later you know and
then not have that that weird like
constant I have to pass things through
this dance Larry structure if that makes
sense so yeah so up at the top here what
we'd be doing is we'd be saying like hey
I need to loop through all of the brains
that are in here right and I don't
really remember to completely honest
with you I don't really remember how the
sim region went about organizing this I
guess it's just a maxim D count entities
sort of a situation and then we've got
the hash table that internally chains
into there so I'm assuming that we would
do the same thing here right and just
have a max brain count frame count and
brains
so in here before anything else happens
we just have our brain indices we'd go
over each one of these which is whatever
so it's the sim region brain cap
we go over the brain index and then in
here we would have you know brain star
brain equals sin region brains but brain
index and then here's where we would do
the actual logic for whatever those
things are
so in our bringing obviously we'd have
whatever the brain type is and we'd have
the brain Kiro code in here and we'd
have the brain snake code in here which
we haven't written yet and I guess we
also have a brain familiar we sort of
had although that's I don't know that we
really that a brain familiar that's more
of a behavior type and we probably will
have yet another thing later down the
road which is like what behavior
something is doing at the moment which
will sort of be a separate issue but
yeah okay so we've got brain here oh
brain snake and then we have like an
invalid default case here no if we have
yeah we do you know where things
wouldn't work so we come through here
and in this case you know if we've got a
controller that's involved we would
sample the controller and presumably
that's actually this code here we could
lock that up into there and that's
actually what I probably would like to
do but we'll hold on that off on that
for a second and then we've got sort of
this code down here which is the stuff
for the the hero head and the hero body
and the hero head and body now don't
really have to be controlled in this way
anymore they could we can do these
things together right but I guess I'll
hold off on that for one second till we
get our compiler errors cleaned up okay
so let's go into some region here and
I've got this brain stuff these will
probably get pulled out to their own
file in a minute but not yet and then
we've got to just kind of deal with with
some of these these other things here
yeah okay so these parity count things
all of this stuff is really
like I said let's let's just if this is
your if zero these things out here for a
second
yeah cuz these these we don't really
want at the moment so I'm just gonna
take care of them briefly doo doo doo
doo and this guy has to actually return
this result all right so I got to clean
some stuff up so this will still work
but that's I just don't want to leave us
in like a bogus day because this is
going to take us a while like we're
gonna it's going to take us you know on
Monday we're gonna have to do some of
this as well all right
so Pat Kennedy reference oh so in this
case I guess we have to check to see to
make sure that the index is not already
zero because obviously that we don't
need to do any more processing on so if
it's already zero we don't have to
decide whether to clear it it's already
clear right so that's pretty
straightforward okay so here we are with
you know our sort of our disabled
controllers if you will and so now what
we need to do is figure out how we want
to write these cleanly right so I want
to again sort of ping back to the usage
code and try to figure out how I would
want these two to be written given the
best possible circumstances and see if I
can reverse engineer back into that
right okay so let's start with this kind
of ugly controller code here and let's
grab that no this is not okay so I'm
gonna grab all the hero head code which
is all this and I'm gonna bring that up
into let's see here brain hero there's a
lot of code so inside brain hero you
know sort of got this notion of
controlled hero and controlled hero like
all that really is is sort of the the
was the you know we were sort of looking
over these controlled heroes to find
whichever one it was that we were
looking at and obviously that's
something we could probably optimize a
little bit better because there's really
no like we could have it so that these
line up it could be that your ID like
your controller ID is just lines up with
the like with the actual physical
controller 0 0 1 2 3 or whatever so I
feel like we could do this a little bit
better but I guess for the moment that
it's fine doesn't really matter we can
just have it you know that there's a
brain ID and that brain ID is what's in
the test hero if that makes sense so I'm
gonna do that first and foremost but
then I'm also gonna go down here and
grab the body stuff so this this stuff
doesn't really have to happen
let's go ahead and get this up here so
here's the body code I don't know what
that bug is I've been noticing that for
a coder bug happen
weird stuff just turns bright white and
it later willed stop being bright white
but like you got to do something to it
yeah there you go so like it gets
confused about the syntax highlighting
in some kind of way that I'm not super
confident how it you can reproduce it
but anyway so now this code just
literally needs to do a thing where it's
like all right I've got this brain I've
got head and body and both both of these
are things that could may or may not be
there right so you know what this is
what hard to do is and then as we go
through here we can basically say like
okay there is no longer sort of a
concept of a you know entity
quote-unquote that's primal it's more
like okay this is you know is this the
head or just the body right so this is
code that only happens on the head
branch all the rest of this code is code
that just happens in general okay well
so here's some more head style code in
there
yeah where else is entity referenced I
guess I could just compile because
entity won't be a thing there we go so
yeah so in here like this is obviously
like our brain ID is going to equal the
brain ID of the hero
and let's see rains obviously would also
presumably always have their ID I don't
know why we're still storing these in
the hash I guess to just make comparison
faster but I'm going to put you in here
again so I'm that's like an optimization
really of laughing that out but we don't
actually know that that's a win to do
that so it seems kind of stupid to have
that be a thing in there so I would say
that that that's like a premature
optimization and we would want to
actually look at and see if there is a
real reason why we were doing it before
just doing it this is not Nike all right
so hand made that H has those controller
those controlled heroes and so in here
these are going to be brain like what
brain ID I go with but again that's like
something that we may want to just we
can probably just do the reverse lookup
now but we'll we'll leave it like that
for the time being so yeah bringing ID
is not wait what value is not a member
of brain ID it's not when did it not
when did it cease to become if it's
index that's no good
all right so get closest reversible on
this entity so when we do this was doing
the closest one on the head so I guess
this entire thing
I guess this debug spawn code is really
just debug code but we could say that
you know this is this is only happens if
the head is here DT is that something
that is not constructed till later yeah
let's see con hero consort Andi facing
direction this is again the head and we
need to clean up this code a lot like a
lot a lot so that's kind of a separate
issue let's see where's my head code
down here and so I guess GDP yeah again
these are sort of things that are only
going to be used in in a second here but
we'll see we just have we have way more
this is the kind of code cleanup that's
really hard to do in a handmade hero
context because normally I'd spend you
know four hours going through all this
stuff and making it right but it like I
literally can't which is troublesome but
anyway so this is the head again and in
here I guess we'd sort of be saying when
we you know we obviously also only ever
do this stuff if we have the head and
we're probably gonna want to coalesce
these out into chunks that are like
here's the part if we're both the head
and body here's a part for only a body
here's a part for only a head kind of a
thing so these we already have all of
right and these are talking about that
what the body's going to do
and let's see we've got our head Delta
stuff here here if we have a head as
well we figured that out and that's all
good and off we go
I don't remember how delete entity works
did we actually to be actually implement
that we did so I would like you to be
able to call the lead on anything even
if it doesn't exist so I'm gonna leave
that like this and I'm assuming that we
actually implemented that yeah we did
there we go
okay and so one thing we could do here
too is we could say like these things to
do fillies in for the brain to do Casey
check that they're not deleted and we do
let's start being more conscientious of
that aspect of it
brain ID is now nothing and brain ID
value and so this is brain ID and so now
again this little kind of lines up
relatively nicely because we have
everything slot in properly right this
is going to return that brain ID that it
generated and now the controller is
attached to that and you can kind of see
that this is starting to make more sense
now too because before when we did add
player well we we sort of arbitrarily
said that the player was the head and
now we don't really have to say that
anymore we just say we created this
notion that there is a group a loose
collection of things that comprises the
player it's this if you are playing that
player anything that has that tag is
under your control right and so if we
created more things that would sort of
glom onto you that's just how that would
work and they
self-assemble right it's kind of a
bottom-up parsing sort of a situation
okay so I'm gonna end there and go to
Q&amp;A but we have to we've got a bunch of
we got one more pass over before we're
actually done so we haven't done this
yet we only did the the initial part but
I'll go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
and that's good so next we can just
basically brain week right like next
week we can find figure this out see if
we can make clean a nice clean set of
controller code for the body pull that
out into a set of files like our brains
file make the snake see if the snake
works and then you know that will tell
us is this was this a good idea it's a
bad idea
right and and there you go
questions and answers questions and
answers questions answers no questions
so there are no answers
well this is going to be quick maybe
though I must have missed the bit about
the snake
what is that so a snake is I was just
saying like so I was trying to think of
examples of creatures that aggregate
potentially multiple entities and don't
necessarily have like a fixed idea of
what comprises them so you know we have
our hero and the hero is comprised of
like the head you know and the body but
I was thinking another obvious one to
try
that's just like a standard kind of game
enemy that would be easy case to
practice on in terms of seeing whether
this architecture works right is you
know a snake creature so you know it
starts off and it's kind of got a little
head right and then it's got like a you
know body parts here and here and then
maybe like a little tail right and so
these could a great up to be a single
controller as well which can think about
what it wants to do so it doesn't just
have to like oh each one of these guys
just knows to follow the person in front
of them we can make something more cop
kid like oh we can decide to like swing
his tail around or do whatever right so
that's what I was thinking of more and
yes someone said it's more of a
millipede and yeah I mean like I guess I
really mean more like centipede like the
game centipede right it's much closer
sort of the creature had mind
how long do you hope this will go on for
do you see some yourself doing some
doing a different game once this is
finished no this will be like the only
game that I do on a stream because it'll
take a long time like I think I
estimated 600 days and based on where we
are that might be correct or it might
not be I don't know there might be too
much gameplay in here so it might be
that the 600 because remember a day is
only one hour so it's 600 hours it's not
very many hours to make a game in you
know it's it's 14 weeks or something
like that
12 weeks I don't know 14 how many weeks
is that if you were working 40 hours a
week it's 15 weeks 15 weeks is just not
very long to make a game from scratch
you know if you're making a game and
some completely pre-built engine and all
you're doing is like setting some entity
flags or something then you know short
but if your since we're eight everything
that's just not very much time and so
you know I don't know if if that'll be
accurate or not because there might be
too much gameplay in this game to get it
all in that but you mentioned you'd
spend four hours cleaning code why not
have a hand made hero day once every
other month or so and deal with problems
with that yeah we could I just don't
know how useful that is because like you
can't choose when that happens really I
mean like I could try it's difficult you
know it's something I would consider as
we get further along potentially easy
sigh about the one entity per grid
spot-checking how will you handle
leaving a spot just before a monster
lands there right now it's binary do you
plan to add a fuzziness as you step out
the square onto another one and a
monster lands on your spot we will see
how it goes at the moment the answer is
that in general I think that you're
probably thinking of it slightly
differently which is to say that
the case is more about you hopping on to
a monster slot coz a monster is never
gonna hop on to your spot unless it's
attacking you and intact doesn't have to
give up the square that it's on probably
my guess but it's probably more like if
a monster was hopping off of this slot
and you're about to hop on to it what
happens right and I still think it is
it's just when you're here everything up
to this point you're still on this
Square and if you want to cross that
center line this guy's got to be
vacating right this guy's got to be
vacating a square and when we do that I
think we'll probably be like earliest
option to vacate or something
so monsters will probably vacate
immediately if they can they'll look
look at this is they'll vacate right
here and then jump off so you'll be able
to jump in but either way like this is
just how the game design works so there
may be some janky nough Swit goes like
that may not be the smoothest feeling
thing but tough right the game design
requires that you can always be on a
particular square and so that's just how
that'll be
guitar someday I will have to ask you
about how to think when representing
dating the program I understand struck
seems a raisin such but what regulates
when to use which well I mean basically
if you've been watching handmade hero
you can see the process it's not there
isn't a rule about when to use which
it's about having gone through enough
architecture to know how to experiment
and figure out right because you'll
notice like anytime I'm at something
where I I don't have a prefab solution
in my head where I'm like this is how I
like to do X it's like something I've
never done before or it's something
where I want to try a new way of doing
it than what I used to do I go through
some permutations right I don't just sit
down and go here's the answer because
we're not far enough along in
programming as an art form or a science
to know the answer to have a structure a
program only very very simple programs
have that right have a known best answer
and usually you know what you are
writing is not unknown thing so the
answer is rarely how do you know which
is when what's use and here are the
rules it's more like you need to do the
things I do on handmade hero right you
need to go through and do architecture
many times different kinds of
architecture and practice seeing how
they come out and then your brain will
start to train up on knowing how to do
that path finding right and I don't
think there's a substitute for that
people who think that they can draw like
UML diagrams or that here's this method
of drawing things on index cards
whatever it's like no it's like that is
not work the thing that works is
practice and in learning to do it it's
like you know no one can tell you how to
hit a golf ball or kick a soccer ball or
whatever it's like they can coach you
and you can see you do it and go oh
you're not thinking about these
correctly whatever they can give you
advice to guide you as you get better at
this thing and watching someone who
knows how to do it helps you get better
at that thing but there is no do these
rules and outcomes the thing we're not
anywhere close to that programming is
way more like
a sport or an art or anything else then
it is a series of steps you just wrote
apply because our understanding of it
just isn't at that point yet and we
don't even know if it ever be but
assuming that someday it would be we're
just not there yet so I would think of
it more as like practice practice
practice practice do lots of
architectures try lots of different ways
of approaching the same problem write
down why they succeeded and why they
failed write down what you think was
better about one than the other how much
code did they take how many bugs did you
have right start to internalize all of
those things because that's really the
the key to understood to getting good
enough to stop having problems working
throughout architecture right and even
if you are very experienced at it and
have done it a lot even at that point
you were still the reason you are good
at it is not because you sit down and
immediately know the answer it's because
you know the process that you can use to
iterate to get to the answer right or to
get to the answer and answer that is
good enough because there isn't a the
answer there's many ways it could happen
right so yeah practice observe and if
you could find someone to give you
advice like a like a mentor to give you
advice about what you may or may not
have done wrong in a program
architecture that's another good thing
to write just like you know in the
sports analogy having a good coach helps
they can't tell you how to do the thing
but they can give you pointers that help
guide your practice of like ah yeah
that's right you know maybe I'm dropping
my shoulder when I'm pitching this you
know pitch and it goes a little wild and
they told me like keep the shoulder up
and oh yeah there we go right that can
help it in programming too right
long brilliant so the idea is to have
the entity system both be able to
support groups of entities that change
from one into another like a monster
that mimics other objects and entities
that when separated from the group can
take action on their own like a
necromancer resurrecting a ripped off
arm yeah I mean the idea is simply to be
able to form to be able to form without
limitation sections that act on their
own right so you know normally we might
say each entity can think and it does a
thing but I want to be able to have
algorithms operate across entities
because that was becoming a problem and
I didn't like what that was going so the
idea here is just to make it simple you
know it's very simple with our MV system
now I believe and going forward so we'll
get better and better
it'll be very simple to do things like I
want this thing to be more cursed or
mote you know or to have a curse on it
or do whatever right I think you know
the way we're working on the ending
system it'll be easy to just add stuff
that you want but what it wasn't easy to
do with the way that we had it was have
multiple things have a piece of code
that thinks across several of them at
once and we were we were butting up
against that and so that's the reason
this entity system I think wanted this
sort of layer the brain layer that I
wanted to try adding it so that I could
write code that thinks across multiple
entities and make that be clean and easy
so they left topic on average how many
hours a day do you work on 1935
well I'm at work from about 9:00 to 4:00
and you know there's maybe like an hour
of lunch in there so so what is that
like six hours or something yeah it's
usually like six hours of of 1935 it's
you know two hours roughly on handmade
here or an hour and a half and then
there's usually like an hour to of
programming on web stuff or whatever the
latest thing is like having to implement
a mailing with system because whatever a
bit
Piggin heart on the note of UML how much
or often would you say you deal with
that at work if at all I've I've
literally never seen anyone draw a UML
diagram in my entire history of the game
industry under any circumstances ever
guitar 87 good answer I understand what
you mean just do it enough and you'll
see what works experience thanks yes yes
Elysium have you thought about using
Vulcan so I think I've covered that
before like I looked at the design of
Vulcan and I don't like it so we we will
almost certainly not use it on streem
like the only reason we use it if for
some reason we had to all right I'm
gonna wrap it up here
all right ooh
as I dropped my water bottom glad these
things are sealed well didn't spill at
all thank you very much for joining me
for a notice of hand right here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with source code at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero
organ it comes with a source code so
that you can sort of do experience with
it and so on we also have a forum site
you can go to if you would like to ask
questions we have a patreon page you can
use to support the video series if you
like what you see and want to show your
appreciation it's always much
appreciated on our and certainly we also
have a schedule bot which tweets the
schedule for the live stream so if you
want to know when they're gonna be you
can take a look at that or follow it on
Twitter and it will tell you and then we
also have a episode guide maintained by
the king of annotation midlow himself
and that got even cooler recently so
there is now like a thing I don't really
know how to get to it but I'll show you
Andrew
well his name is Andrew Johnson but he's
Andrew he's like Andrew JDR up here it
is he's like Andrew JDR on like a
usually on like his handle that gone on
a chats and stuff like that but he made
this new thing so if you are someone who
has pre-ordered the game you can use
your github access like the send owl
download page when you when you peer to
the game you get like a little send out
down you could download source and stuff
there's a thing on there that's like
github access and if you haven't done
that yet you can use that you can go
grab that key and you can put it in and
authorize it's got instructions there it
could authorize yourself for github
access on the github
Andrew junior created this repository
that's pretty cool
you should check it out if you're if you
try to follow along with the series at
home because it's basically got this
HTML directory which is just every file
as it currently is in the game but
instead of these file being a CPP or an
H file it's actually just an HTML file
of the source code but in line with the
source code I actually don't know how
you wait oh sorry
never mind it's the MD for some reason
even though there's an HTML directory
github
use it so you can download it and do
that but get up can't play it if you go
to the MB directory it can display
directly so if you click on one of those
it will show you the source code and
every line of the source code has what
episodes I like worked on that what that
area of the code right so you can like
jump to like oh you know when was this
thing talked about like Oh episode 131
and you just click click on it and you
get to a thing where you know it's got
the the when I worked on that right so
that can be kind of handy if you're
trying to like go back through things so
that's a new thing again that was done
by Andrew Johnson which is pretty great
and so I would highly recommend checking
that out if you are interested in it
that's about it I will I will catch you
guys back here next week check the
schedule bot for the schedule I'll post
it this weekend take it easy everyone