so ideally with something like this
where we started off with more questions
than we were going to be able to answer
we would not add questions to the list
but since folks came up and asked
questions we now have more questions
than we ended the previous session with
so on to our best a pretty good
multi-part question that got asked
actually just in the break that that I
thought was pretty interesting and I
kind of wanted hear what people had to
say about it was oftentimes we in you
know in the game industry we will pull
research from other places so you know
when you're working on something or
implementing something especially in
graphics but also in sort of other areas
we go get research from places that you
know isn't necessarily game industry so
it could be you know SIGGRAPH was a
common one back before games sort of did
a lot of the original research that's
into graph like that sort of stuff but
even today it's still very common but
then there's certainly obviously tons of
stuff like AI all those sorts of things
there's tons of publications and you
know oftentimes the games pull from
those so the two-part question I'll say
what both parts are but we're gonna take
them both separately the first part is
you know these papers oftentimes
regardless of whether the thing they're
talking about is you know going to be
useful or not are oftentimes kind of
they have a bit of a math wall in them
right or a Naumann klaich or wall where
you know if you might be a very good
programmer but you're you know coming to
this paper and you're looking at it and
you're like I do not know what I'm
looking at here right and so the
question is how do you start getting
past this pair here like how do you know
what do you need to do how do you need
to like start practicing to like be able
to start reading these papers and more
fluently and then the second part of the
question was assuming that you kind of
gotten to the point where you can start
using papers effectively you know how do
you find and evaluate them so just going
back to the first part to the math wall
part does anyone want to kind of start
on one I don't know I can I can probably
answer it sound really stupid but when I
look at those and I see a symbol I don't
recognize I try to find it on Wikipedia
and then figure out what the symbol is
and that's where yeah well Google's
really good at like what is the math
sign that is like this is an example
they go weird like half II kind of thing
and it'll come up with it'll show you a
picture and then yeah yeah so Google but
that's only gonna get you that only gets
you a little bit yes well I don't I
don't read a lot of papers either so my
wife is a biostatistician and so I
actually get to read some of her papers
and I know that there's a huge math gap
like she's way more advanced than me so
I do have a resource that helps me cheat
but I would say the first thing is like
the density of papers tends to be very
much higher than most of the reading you
do on the Internet
and so you're probably used to skimming
like this is what I do right mostly
internet reading I'm doing is skimming
even for programming stuff because it's
like yeah yeah yeah okay there's the
meat that's the line of code or that's
the the core function that I need when
you read science papers boy you really
have to just slow down a lot in your
reading and really like if you don't
understand the terminology you have to
go and read something else like go to
Google and get the terminology and and
then it's much more likely you can
actually use the results of those papers
so so about about the math wall I don't
find that that tends to happen to me in
terms of notation but it does happen in
terms of like concepts okay like do you
understand that you know I don't know
differential geometry has a certain set
of results and what that implies and
whatever and if you do you can follow a
thing and if you don't but but usually I
don't try to follow things that much
anyway I'm very impatient when it comes
to papers I'm like yeah yeah I don't
care I don't really care why this works
right now I just want to type the thing
that works and if that's promising then
I'll come back and build
understanding in fact that's even going
way back that's how I learned software
texture mapping which by current day
standards that's actually very simple
mathematics right but I would like read
Mike's articles and like Chris's
articles and like Mike's especially
right I would read those several times I
still didn't really understand I didn't
know what the one over Z thing was for
and like whatever right because I didn't
even at that time have experience with
like projection right all the experience
with projection that you have now from
decades of making games I didn't even
have like I literally sat down and
wanted to make games that didn't know
any of that so but I just kind of
started trying to understand a little
bit of it right like okay I'm just gonna
get a triangle on the screen with no
texture and then by the time I've done
that I actually have more context so the
thing actually this applies to my
approach to everything is just I'm
willing to let myself just be pretty
dumb for a while and not care because
human brains are really good at pattern
matching and learning and improving and
it doesn't need so much for you to
consciously try that hard right if you
immerse yourself in something for a
while you'll just kind of get it and
then you come back and if you really
need to read it again later and
understand it you know it's not like
you're gonna automatically understand it
but you're in a more privileged position
in the second time around right but my
second thing to say is I've been burned
so many times by papers that I think
most of them I don't go to papers as a
like if I see a paper that claims some
result like oh this algorithm does
something fast or I don't believe it my
default stance my default stance is that
this is not even toilet paper because
I've so many times I've put in the
effort to do something and then it turns
out well okay it may be 10% but they
haven't done the real work right and
that I may be a little bit over I've
over corrected in that direction more
cynical than I should be but really most
papers are not very good but some of
them are tremendously good right some of
them will change your understanding in
such a way that you are just on a
different level now in terms of being
able to approach a certain class of
problem and so it's it's very important
to like
keep an eye on stuff yeah but I don't
know how you know which is the right
stuff
I mean sometimes I guess you can kind of
get that from the word of mouth on a
particular paper and then you know
people I trust have been finding this to
be useful but it's really actually not
so even that's kind of saying where it's
hard to tell I suppose I was gonna say
something about the math wall sort of
separate from that that's that's very
much related to what Pat said which is
just I think that most of the time if
I'm looking at a paper and I don't
really know what's actually going on in
the paper like it's obviously you kind
of read the abstract and the textual
part and you're kind of like okay well
obviously anyone who reads this is gonna
kind of vaguely know what's going on the
paper like some papers are maybe so sort
of far afield that you wouldn't even
have any idea what they're even talking
about but most of the time especially we
were talking about so you might be
reading for you know graphics for
example is the least a picture so yeah
you're not completely out too much so
you know typically the math wall part
usually comes in when they start doing
things it's like oh okay you know here's
some equation lines that aren't really
quite worked through all the way and
then they say some stuff and then
there's another one here and they don't
really quite relate exactly the way that
you might be obvious in blah blah blah
so you're kind of starting to go like
wait what about what's going on and I
find that when I actually do need to
understand those pretty much I just have
to redo the math myself on a separate
piece of paper
always so either the math was so obvious
when I looked at it that it was like you
know high school algebra and anyone
could read it or it's pretty much I have
to flick I have to work it out it's rare
that I actually can read it just read it
and so I feel like the slowing down part
is like really important it's just like
okay I want understand this I'm just
gonna take my time I'm gonna like start
writing out the equations every you know
try to work them through myself but you
know maybe get confused about how they
got something and work it through and
then I usually find when I've actually
finally made the mental decisions that
I'm actually gonna take the time to
understand it then I can write whereas
before that it was just kind of like I'm
just moving around my eyes around the
page hoping that for some reason I
eventually start knowing what the math
did which
ever works right or or certainly hasn't
previously so let's move on to the
second part of that question which i
think is you kind of just brought up
which is like okay so how do you find
research and how do you know if that
research is good so you know maybe
you're working on some kind of a problem
and you think that this problem is
probably something that people have
studied it's probably not totally new
what's the process of collect is anyone
have any kind of experience stuff from
that where they'd be like here's how I
you know here's an example of how I
might look for for research on something
just even if it tends to be kind of a
crappy solution like what does that look
like dead
you know the web search will get you a
little of the way so for the witness
this didn't end up in the shipping game
but when we were initially building the
island for the game we even know if it
was gonna be you know a parameterised
surface right or if it was gonna be hand
constructed we ended up with hand
constructed in a modeler but for the
first few years of game it was like
moved some control points around and we
like you know interpolate the surface
and I had some requirements on that that
meant that it couldn't be like the
standard spline sheathing that you would
think of it had to be a different thing
and I just like searched for like you
know terms like an interpolation of
unstructured control points or something
and usually you don't really find the
right thing that way but if you spend
like literally a day doing that like of
eight hours of trying you will probably
find something if it exists usually well
how might I describe this in a way that
I could see a paper yeah yeah and then
sometimes you'll find things that aren't
the right thing but they might refer
like you start learning about the
subject space of like okay this is not
what I want but it's in some field and
I'm seeing the field a little bit better
which might teach me more about the
keywords to look yes yeah so that worked
in that instance that was good Wow I
think some of it is the conclusions the
paper draws like and look if you run
this code then we can simulate thousands
of objects on a computer
that's the evaluation part right look
what you've already found it it's like
when you look at that time that table of
timings that they're proud of and you're
like oh you right because the maximum
number is like way below what you know
you could actually use in a game so
you're like well okay so I have a answer
to this one which is that I actually
typically do it almost exactly the same
way every time which maybe is good maybe
as bad so what I typically do is I first
go through the publication's that I know
of that correspond to this thing so for
like for SIGGRAPH I usually will
manually step through like SIGGRAPH in
reverse chronological order right and go
in that bucket because I don't know if
you ever seen half SIGGRAPH proceedings
are laid out they like bucket them by
group and I'm like for the group that I
care about here what are the five papers
that that are in that group and I just
look to see if the sort of thing that
I'm interested in has had anything in
the SIGGRAPH recently because typically
I find that's a really good way to kind
of like jump up to date on something
that I may have let slide because you
know I don't do that much graphics
programming anymore so I I'm not like
really in the know about what's going on
there so that's usually a good way to
catch a few things the next thing I'll
typically do is take whatever those were
that I found and just resource crawl
them I mean I reference crawl them so in
that you know the thing where it's like
the bibliography
I'll just go like okay let's just grab
all of what those papers are and also by
professor so if I fly if I get any kind
of pull from that at all I'll look at
who the professor was that's on that
paper or any co-authors that are on that
paper because they the professor that
oftentimes students I suppose who are
writing the paper but whoever is writing
the paper because they usually have
websites and those websites are usually
categorized by sort of what they've been
working on recently and they'll
typically be like oh here's some things
and oh that paper was actually the
lead-up to the thesis that I wrote and I
got bingo like I've got the thesis now
and so on and so I find that if I
actually kind of do this manual spider
process if I can just get one good pull
I can get the whole like nets worth of
dolphin slash tuna in that like you know
in that process if that makes sense so I
don't know maybe I'm the only one who
finds that useful but that's that's been
typically my go-to for a long time the
only time that it becomes really hard is
if you can't find any place to get an
initial poll so like if you're in a
thing we're like I literally have no
idea if there even is a publication
somewhere that even talks about this
thing at all or if it did it's the kind
of thing that's almost impenetrable to
search so it's like they don't have
online indexes or anything so I just I
can't even get it most of the time I
think in reality that's very rare I feel
like it especially these days but that's
actually not the hard problem the hard
problem is is again the I don't know
what I don't know problem right yes so
like going back to to the earlier days
right like Ken shumake had his famous
quaternion paper that was like here's
how you could rotate 3d objects right
which was a very important paper because
part of that everybody was doing like
janky Euler ankle stuff not even game
people but like computer graphics didn't
know how to rotate objects correctly
right and that was not a new research
paper that was like no the guys who do
spaceships like know how to do this yeah
I'm gonna communicate it to a different
audience yeah right and so the fact that
that exists like how many of those
papers have not been written because
somebody didn't have the idea that this
other community might be interested in
this thing it's got to be like of
relevancy to games it's got to be
hundreds right well probably there's a
two-stage process there to a certain
degree as well which is that like the
only reason that paper was able to be
written is because somebody in the
spaceship field had read math stuff on
patterns because otherwise they wouldn't
have known to apply quaternion math to
astrophysics anyway right so yeah can I
have that sort of thing probably just in
general although I suppose since
quaternions kind of came from physics in
the first place that's probably kind of
a I mean yeah but he was trying to
describe rotations in 3d space so it
wasn't yeah it wasn't like this thing
that we didn't really think about and
then it came down but you know let's
imagine other mathematical concepts
which were not created to do anything
that had anything to do with computer
stuff pulling those in in the first
place takes one step of somebody going
hey this thing that I happen to do when
I was working on some abstract NASA I
think I could use that here for a
practical problem and then there's the
like oh what other practical problems
could it actually applied to and that's
like a second step that night neither of
which may happen in which case you're
kind of just sitting there going we'll
never know we're still waiting for your
paper by the way on using Taylor series
expansion for estimating the division
coordinate for quaternions because we
stole that well you know you told us
about that idea for guild wars in 2004
something like that right that's a great
idea okay but I never used the Taylor
series expansion for it oh well it was a
different expansion then it was maybe a
it was an estimation of the lower term
of the division term so I think what
that was is just that it's it's actually
a trick I want to say that I saw from
maybe Carmack or something there was not
for quaternions at all but it's
basically just like if you want to
renormalize something so you have
something that you're going to you know
take that was normal before and you do
something you want to renormalize it
right it's just a really simple first
order approximation of how to
renormalize something if you know that
original length was what close to one
you could get it back there so I'm
pretty sure I don't need to write a
paper there's a point at the original
that's like the kind of instruction that
shipped in 3d now and whatever whatever
and so I think I might be able to to
magically point to that paper without
actually do it because yeah that I stole
that that I totally stole I just put it
on quaternions because it was on just
regular vectors like that so I spent
roughly like I'd written the animation
system for Cold War's and spent about a
month trying to optimize quaternions to
use less CPU and like you know so
approximating like a 1 over square root
of sine or something like that
slurp yeah and it's it's nasty and like
so I did all these approximations and I
never would be like these weird 3d
models that would animate like you know
a bunch of points that are obviously
supposed to like look like a character
look like a mess and you came along with
your solution and it just looked for his
tweet stream this to point this out
up there but I knew I stole that I knew
I stole that from because people had to
renormalize you know vectors all the
time just just standard
three-dimensional vectors and since
quaternions are based they're just the
same you could just apply it so I I
think we probably even had been using
that in the characterization system
probably just for regular vectors and I
just like I'll just four elements just
as easy or something like that I just I
just wanted to say it's what lets the
hand go on the doorknob
so if I if it hadn't have been like over
a decade since this happened I could
probably read arrived it but I'm pretty
sure I won't remember how to do it is
the problem it's basically yeah I'll ask
a question and see if I can do it on
notebook and then I could show it's
really simple
but I just yeah since I wasn't the
person who figured it out originally -
it's more of a thing that I just
remember someone telling me how to do
whereas you know if you actually work
something out yourself oftentimes it
kind of sticks a little bit better at
least for me all right so let's let's
ask the last part of that question just
in case there's anything we didn't
actually cover which is for a cigarette
paper or for you know any kind of math
paper that's in this in that range how
do you evaluate one to know if it's good
and it sounds like your answer is it's
the answer is it's not sir you don't
evaluate no I mean there's a there's a
small probability that you know there's
some curve but it's very steep where the
really good papers are clustered at the
end and then but most most of them are
like something a guy wrote cuz he had to
publish a bunch of things like and it's
really it varies by discipline you know
but in computer science it's pretty bad
it's not a good situation the ratio is
not good yeah I guess you were saying
one way is to look at just the
conclusion right you're just looking at
kind of like when they showed the
results what does that section look like
I guess basically like how how much
confidence do you place and if it
doesn't have any results listed at all
I'm assuming the answer she stowed yeah
usually I read the abstract to find that
I'm in the right paper and and everybody
conclusion to see what the results were
and then the sieve that warrants reading
the rest of the papers so it's like the
middle gets gets pigeon if the two ends
look good basically there's also like
some authors are reliable so like if
Catan is on a paper okay it's probably a
good paper okay it's just that most
people are not kaha or whoever okay so
that's the problem well so the basic
going by author is one way as well
potential yeah but then you're not going
to hit most fields or sub headers right
yeah all right so let's go off of that
to that
topic was surprisingly silent I guess
that kind of means maybe we don't use
research as much as we think we do I
don't know I feel like I use it maybe
not we used to more in the in the older
days yeah like back when like now it's
most of our bottlenecks are just getting
everything done which like if I could
read a couple bucks that helps with that
that would be great but it's it's not
like I have a lot of you know I don't I
don't perceive technology barriers
between me and what I'm trying to do
these days all right let me pick another
one here so this one kind of applies to
what we talked about yesterday and it's
kind of a it's kind of an interesting
question because I feel like it gets it
gets brought up a lot it got brought up
at Hamid Khan 2015 as well and it comes
from a poo from India who actually also
makes the papaya which i think is a
network actually it's like a open source
image editor when creating an engine or
shipping a game what do you look for in
a file format for asset data how do you
balance compression versus speed versus
readability etc and sort of like
separate from that is is there a
particular best file format you've
worked with in some case where you're
like this kind of does things right you
know more often than it does wrong
thoughts on that I always get bit by the
byte order stuff oh really
yeah I always do so I try to avoid that
stuff so you have only one byte value
yeah just 0 to 55 and everything
you know it's one of those things that I
think I don't have to worry a whole lot
about storage and load speed but I have
really gravitated towards file formats
that are asking at some level it aren't
a lot of binary stuff and I mean clearly
that does not work in a lot of a lot of
games for what I do I just kind of I
just kind of enjoy that because they can
also just pull up the file in a text
editor and see what else is going on
here yeah so I've I've kind of
gravitated towards kind of a you know a
very dense version of stuff so if you
take for example you were talking about
building a tool that allows you to
layout a room in Fenway Park that's
typically going to save out to some kind
of an ASCII file which generally people
aren't going to edit I guess but it is
actually gonna ask a description of it
yeah yeah I mean there are you know
using a big GUI tool and there there is
a point we're just going into an editor
and just going copy and then paste 50
times it's just a lot faster I've been
going through a GUI tool and I I kind of
like that kind of backdoor into that
data so I tend to tend to favor ASCII
stuff I have actually kind of an
interesting one so again this is the
model exporter for a girl were so we're
using 3ds Max's our animation and model
editing tool and 3ds max is notoriously
difficult to get data out of because you
can't read its file format that's not
documented in so I wrote a plugin that
would like live inside it and you'd
press a button and it would like go and
ask all the API is like here and then we
give vertex data and pull all stuff
together and what I would do is I'd
write a really simple file format it was
it was a chunked file format but like
the data was more or less exactly as it
came from max with no processing and
then I would run a second pass and then
I'd like converted into model format
data that was had to be super tightly
packed because Guild Wars was like
really early in the online game space
and we needed to download the whole game
I mean every single file so make them
small and tight and what that enabled me
to do is then in the build process like
I go you know I have a better way to
compress the animation data and so
instead of having to like you know take
this data which was like hideously
compressed and then reverse it which is
potentially lossy I congest should go
back to the source data and reprocess it
and get a new
junk out of that so that worked really
well and that was so that you wouldn't
basically have to have something that
load max back up and reran the like
export process or something yeah was
like yeah got spurred games to this
trick I forget to the engineer was who
showed it to me but they had the system
where they would automate 3ds Max and
they'd say like okay just you know max
load up this file reprocess it and write
the results and they've just run for
hours and hours and hours this they
changed their model file format and so
that's like a different take on them you
know the problem of like recompressing
your data a different way it also seems
like it would keep you out of the
business
oh like max got upgraded and can't read
this sold file format currently so then
now that has to be artist intervention
for this process for some reason and
it's like we can just avoid that because
as long as we saved the original export
we can always sort of Remus the data
without having to actually go back yeah
I mean I use ASCII stuff for like config
files but for me stuff like when I
integrated flash when I integrated a
spine as a spline I don't remember it's
the one that everybody uses but they
didn't have an a non ASCII format they
just had JSON files which was really
irritating because I want to be able to
just load in a big chunk of data and
just do stuff with it like like what I
do with the SWF file format I just chunk
done and what I save out for levels is
the same it's just a chunk file format
just as small as I could possibly get it
for you know levels or anything so and
the difference there you're saying you
don't want to have to start parsing
things yeah yeah well yeah I well I had
to write a JSON parser which was fun but
I didn't I didn't want to have to do
that I wanted to just load in a thing
and just have all my things but yeah so
to speak yeah so for me it's more about
can like it's more about just what is
documented and what I can use and then
like with with spine they had
you know there are two formats and I was
forced to use this one because they
didn't have documentation for the other
one so they wanted me to use their
library to do all that stuff right now
so yeah it for me it really doesn't
matter well and I think what Pat said is
sort of the direction that most larger
games have gravitated toward and I think
it it reveals a little bit of an
assumption in the question which is that
there's a file format right okay I think
what there really is is there's things
that you need to happen at various
stages right either like when the
release game is going to load something
that needs to have certain
characteristics right our tool pipeline
needs different characteristics and so
you might have two different file
formats again for example for the mesh
at both of those stages right and then
that lets you not just make different
decisions about you know automatically
reprocessing to regenerate that second
format but now that second format can be
different on different platforms right
because what what is a mesh right like a
visual mash has different precision
requirements than a collision mesh and
if you're tight on memory you know you
might use half floats for water together
or whatever right so and that happens
all over the place so even you know
something like entities right we have
two different formats for entities
they're they're the same we meaning into
the witness yeah right there's not
everybody but no and and so and that was
kind of driven by a little bit by a
desire for readability in fact the
original format was just text because it
was expected to be a small amount of
data of course when you have thirty to
forty thousand entities it becomes more
data right but but really you know you
also want to start the game up real fast
and load all those things and not you
know whatever you know use memory on it
as well or anything but we also had the
constraint that entities were one of the
main things that goes into and out of
source control so that's a binary file
format then you're in
because the second you have a merge
conflict you have to throw one or the
other version away you can't
well you can't merge it all really here
it would be kind of crazy right so so
there are reasons you have a text format
and reason to have a reason readable
format and reasons to have a binary
format and they're at different places
in different times and you just lay out
that architecture and decide what level
of complexity you're willing to adopt to
get the performance that you want and
then you do that right so I mean I don't
know like like I'm sure if Chris butcher
had done a survey of how many different
file formats have in the Bungie asset
system like that would have been a
two-hour talk at least like right there
right I assume I don't actually know but
it's just it's it's not that there's a
way to store data right there's Mike
Acton would say right you right they
either side of the data well I don't
know I mean I guess I guess that's a
little meta Acton right because he's
always about he's always about you know
me program to the data but when you can
also determine the data that will make
the best program they write that right
so so I don't know if that that sounds
like you're basically saying you don't
really look for something specific in
file formats so much as you say look I I
know what it needs to do on either side
of it well II so whatever I look for in
it is just what are the things that make
those parts work well or is that yeah
yeah and it's contextual so if something
is a small amount of data were more
likely to be text only so like the
variables that you said to control like
gravity or whatever we don't ever ever
have ballistic things in the witness
anymore but there's still a grab gravity
variable
you know player friction or whatever
right that's like you know there's
probably a hundred variables or
something and those are just in a text
file
and there's no reason to do it another
way it's not a freakin JSON file great
because that stuff drives me bananas
because the the promise of like oh we
have this general file format and all
the tools will make it amazing to work
with that's never true right it's always
easier to just go like search for the
line that says player acceleration and
change that to whatever and then because
it's our own format we can do small
things so I don't know if you hinted us
at this or somebody did but like anytime
that we have a floating point value for
example in one of these files we put the
human readable value and then like
semicolon and then the hex value right
so that if it hasn't been edited you
load the hex value and you get exact
reproducible reproducibility of your
float value won't wander if Yuri save
the file or whatever right through bit
errors but if you want to edit it you
just delete the hex value in just thing
and then it's human editable right so
that's a weird hybrid thing that's a
little bit of a machine format a little
bit of a human format and we just
decided on that as being the best thing
for us at the time right so I like to
keep the text formats very small and
simple how do you know I am almost
certain so much you can you might even
Charles it could have been Charles so I
feel like that's an odd world it could
be how do you know do you just assume
that one bit errors are close enough
because if you can't reproduce the
original float from the ASCII how do you
know if it's been edited you just assume
it fits well it's way worse if you
printf in Windows you're not down to one
bit error half the time I don't think
they might have fixed that right so I
can start saying how do you know that
the whether the user has the reason that
the hex and the float don't agree is
because the user edited them or because
the precision is just off actually let
me correct you do it I said let me
correct that even if it's a one bit
error right that's one bit per load
andrey saves right and received that
like correct 500 times i don't know
where that numbers gonna go right that's
not usually how it works usually it'll
it'll get into its local max because
it'll save the same well if it's a
scalar right so now you've got a vector
and it's normalized or you know I don't
even like there's just it's it's
not that simple right and I don't know
yeah either way I was just curious
so I sleep better at night when the hex
number is there when you actually
implement this Oh the other issue
actually is if that number wanders then
it's gonna generate spurious source
control check-ins and did write which is
a whole different thing thing which we
wanted a minimum we did a lot of tactics
in our file formats actually so there's
a little bit of a different topic but
like okay I've got energy data yes and
I've got all these different types that
the fields could bees there's float
types there's maybe vector types if you
decide that's a high level thing there's
string types and there's like an array
of the IDS of other things because you
want to know like oh this is a container
and here's what's in the container or
whatever right we made the choice to not
put those in the file format but because
it would generate dips and conflicts
like we don't necessarily care what
order things all right word but
subversion doesn't know that so so
because of that we said that kind of
thing is not in our file format and
anytime you have a collection of
entities it works backwards where the
entity knows who it's in right and then
startup time which is a little bit of
overhead but it's small right and that's
just to illustrate this is not an
isolated file format issue at all right
it's like a list of the things that I
connect with is a totally reasonable
thing to have in a file format and yet
for our requirements it was causing
problems every family different way to
do it so okay I just want to ask the
original question there cuz I don't
understand it
so I print out a floating point value
yeah I print out the hex version of a
floating point value right and
presumably the reason I'm doing this is
because the print out routine for the
floating point value and the scan
routine that loads the floating point
value back in is no guarantee you never
did the work to make those River people
have since right right I mean nobody we
didn't nobody done this the C runtime
library that I'm calling let's say I
didn't write it sure no it's just I'm
calling this function and I know that it
won't be reversible yeah so
now I go to load the file in and I load
the file in and I see that the two
numbers are not the same how do I know
whether the reason that they're not the
same is because the user edited it or
the reason they're not the same because
when the user I mean give me where I'm
wrong here but when the user edits the
floating point value you delete the hex
value okay we might have also measured
the magnitude of the difference as well
like if it's a if it's a significant
difference you you can do it just just
as a way to like okay maybe they forgot
to delete that part or whatever but I
think I think we just delete the value
so basically the user goes in the text
file they change the floating point
value they need to remember get rid of
the hex load because otherwise we're
just gonna overwrite your floating point
value next time you say this thing yeah
and this is interesting too because what
we're saying right now only applies to
the entity files right which are rarely
edited by anyway and those get saved out
all the time when you save stuff in the
editor for stuff like the variables that
I was talking about before the computer
doesn't ever write or you know we ended
up writing sometime later I guess but
the main ones are read-only and so we
don't care about this right right and so
we don't then we don't have that
potential mistake of forgetting to
delete the X float as well all right but
but you know it's it's hard to cuz you
put it it's like one space away from the
number so you see it just totally spaced
yeah all right so I don't know why I
really wanted to do so many things are
pretty cool I'm just like wait so okay I
kind of wanted to ask a little bit about
that
reverse storage part there because I
think that's kind of interesting thing
just in general which is that anytime
that you're storing information
you obviously have a choice you know if
it's information that involves sort of a
variable length list or something like
this you can either store something like
a list in the actual data format meaning
I can say okay this is gonna be a
variably sized thing in here that just
enumerates all the things that are
members of it or whatever or you can do
what you were talking about there which
is you can transform that into saying
everyone has a sort of back pointer that
says which
- my a member of right and what's
interesting about that is like so I'm us
you know benefits of that are like you
were saying it means that now it's
doesn't mess with an entity's data every
time maybe that list order changes or
anytime like something like this happens
that isn't really something that you
cared about but it does mean stuff like
okay any you know things can only be in
one list now right for example or now we
need to start having multiple ones of
these and the reason I bring that up is
I think that actually happens in the
witness there were these times when you
had to have stuff like reference one
reference to because sometimes thing
would have that was that was more you
know like you've got like a marker in
any title and what it wants to do is
based on some string tag like says what
like open a door if a person walks into
this marker or whatever and just you
whenever you do that you have different
numbers of things that any of those
handlers will care about those are just
slots for that okay so we never ran into
the specific problem of oh my god we
can't I mean we sort of wanted to put
things in more than one group but it was
never a such a burning desire that it
became a problem and we could have just
said blood group two or whatever right
okay so but but you know in a different
game that might be more or the problem
yeah it's but but it's like I'm saying
it's contextual you solve the problem
that you have as opposed to everybody's
alright let's see here we are down we're
actually making reasonable progress here
this one comes from and and I think this
was basically someone who submitted a
question because they wanted to finally
give me names that I would have no
trouble pronouncing my cue from
Amsterdam asks if you could go back in
time and give yourself only one piece of
advice at the beginning of your career
what would it be
I think I've got one if anybody ever
tells you anything that's ready to
finance or honestly though let's say
that's all I'm thinking of is like maybe
maybe spend the money on lawyers maybe
don't be afraid of them you know I think
I think I would have told myself to be a
lawyer of the panel says talk to a
lawyer is the advice they would have
given us us at the beginning of their
programming career good advice probably
John wanna either say make it 75% of the
panel or do a different one yeah I'm
having a hard time with that one if you
restrict it to programming right if it
has to be a programming piece of advice
you know that I would give myself that's
I mean I don't know that I can really
think of one actually I think the thing
that I mean you hear this a lot that I
probably struggled with a little bit
early is just don't be afraid to fail
you know just just try stuff no matter
what and if it doesn't work just keep
trying
you know I think very early on in my
career I was a little bit you know
dejected by failures where well now I
just I don't care about some level
is that the sort of thing that basically
like you know seeing this this maybe
kind of relates back to the imposter
syndrome part of things that we were
talking about earlier is it's a sort of
thing that kind of is like well if
you've if you experience failure and
then have some successes then you can
sort of start to put it in context where
it's like Oh failures are those things
that happen on the way to success but
maybe it's like you haven't had a
success yet so all you're sort of seeing
as the failures or is this something
that's more like no no I've had
successes already at that point I just
for some reason was still afraid of
failure as a reason to not go do
something or try something well I think
I think a lot of it and maybe he doesn't
go back to that imposter soon another
thing is it's watching people I have an
immense amount of respect for fail and
and it is it's one of the reasons I
enjoy watching your Twitter feed right
you are one of you know the best
programmers that I know and I watch you
on that feed struggle with stuff and I
go well if Casey is struggling with this
stuff it's okay for me to struggle with
this stuff - whispers you know before so
watch it
but but I think I think that's the kind
of thing that you know over time you
realize oh it's not me it's not just me
that's failing
everybody's failing and it makes you it
makes it okay that does seem to me to be
like a pretty big part of it too because
I feel like I don't even know if I still
internalize that part of it meaning I
think I still generally think that I
like in even though if I cognate link of
it I don't think it this way but when
I'm just subconsciously think about it I
don't think of other programmers that I
respect as making mistakes mmm like it
just isn't in there it's like when I
think of somebody else doing this
program I just don't think of them
making the mistakes now I know they must
make them it's not that if you asked me
to then think about it would I would I
not but I think it is kind of the case
that it's hard to actually remind
yourself in practice no really they're
all making mistakes that's just how it
works
I'm gonna start with a design one
because that's the problem I actually
had but then it's got a programming
equivalent right which is just you know
usually usually you have a voice
somewhere telling you what the problem
is with what you're doing and you
usually choose to ignore it
so the first professional game I did was
a you know as a science fiction
hovertank war game and they had yes it
had some gameplay problems that made it
you know not that fun like the the
combat situations would always devolve
into like a mess in a small area of the
map and it was because of decisions that
from a high level I had decided were
important like oh you could place a unit
anywhere because that gives you the
maximum player freedom or whatever but
what that really does is it you know it
makes most it makes terrain a lot less
important or whatever right so but I had
lots of reasons in my head why it was a
good game and it was pretty good in some
areas but it had some fatal flaws to it
right and I I knew what they were right
but I cognitive dissonance myself out of
understanding them and acting on them
you didn't want that to be true so you
just yeah or you know there's always
enough things to think about and deal
with when especially when it's your own
software company that you just find
other things it's like oh you know this
doesn't feel the way I want but you know
we'll figure it out eventually it's not
gonna it's not going to be these
decisions that I made that were the
problem deal with it later
right I mean and the programming version
of that is just you know you're building
some system that you think is gonna
solve a problem and gonna be really
great and it's got plenty of drawbacks
and downsides and you probably know some
of them you probably don't know cuz you
haven't hit the wall but some of them
you know you really do yeah but you're
just choosing not to pay attention to
that voice in your head so it's just
like listen to that and pay attention
to that I learned that or probably in
programming before I learned it in
design but I didn't know that either at
the beginning right I would say kind of
similar or along those same lines one of
the pieces of advice that I will simply
throw in here that's actually from Jeff
Roberts who was in the opening session
at this this handmade one of the things
that he said that I found to be totally
true is he said that like actually
finished pieces of code before moving on
to new pieces of code which is an odd
thing to say because it sounds like well
obviously that has to be true
but actually when you're doing a fairly
large project or you're at the point you
know in your programming career where
you're doing you know a broad spectrum
of things you know it's often the case
that you're like you'll get something up
to just the point where it sort of works
a little bit and then you'll move on to
a new thing right and one of the things
that happens at least to me there is if
I don't actually stop and go wait have I
actually done all of the programming
necessary to to finish sort of fleshing
this out completely it doesn't mean I
have to like optimize it all the way
down or it doesn't mean I have to like
have it in its shippable state it's just
have I actually finished it to the point
where I don't think I will have to come
back to this for some ancillary reason I
find that a lot of times I just won't do
that if I don't stop and like hear
Jeff's voice in my head saying this
right because a lot of times you just
kind of want to get everything working
and now this thing just kind of works
and okay I'm aware of these things that
it's not doing it all but I'll just I'll
do those eventually or something right
and the reason that I find that it
actually becomes important to do that is
just that the amount of mental context
that you build up when you're working on
a piece of code doesn't come back
immediately at least it doesn't for me
if that code is at all complicated so
like when I'm actually writing it for
the first time or even you know whenever
I'm opening up a piece of code in like
working on this system or something my
brain is the lot sharper at working on
that system after I've been doing that
for several days then if I pop back to
it and now it's day one again of working
on that system and so I find that
actually I if I
don't follow that advice I burn a lot of
time INRI getting all of my context back
if the changes that I have to make are
at all non-trivial so nowadays much more
than I used to I definitely tried to
kind of like finish this code to the
point where I don't think I need the
mental context anymore and if it's just
stuff that I can just go look if I pop
back in here it's brutally obvious what
I've been doing I need to optimize this
loop there's no conceptual optimizations
it's just some assembly language stuff
really I'll put Cindy is't or something
like this that's no problem right but if
it's not that if it's like something
where it's like no no there's conceptual
optimizations that I probably need to
make in order to make this thing run I
now do them there if I know that I have
to do them because otherwise I find I
just burn all this time on otherwise
that might not be what other people find
but just the way I program it seems like
it really is true that it ends up saving
time in the end throw that out there
fortunately I have one thing to add on
there actually since nobody else jumped
in there's a secondary reason to do that
that relates to a topic we had earlier
which is just you know we all we all
make stuff and we feel like it's crappy
a lot of the time right and a lot of the
reason we feel like it's crappy is
because we took all these shortcuts get
it go I mean that's my programming
philosophy right is like get it running
as quickly as possible so I will very
deliberately take a large number of
shortcuts where you could like it looks
like a wall but you can kick through it
because it's paper right yeah and you
know that you have to come back and do
that later and at some point that
affects your picture of what you're
making right because in the beginning
it's like oh I'm gonna make an amazing
thing that's gonna do all this right and
then after a while it's like oh I've
been making this crappy thing of all
these shortcuts that don't really do and
and they pile up and eventually at least
for me and I think for a lot of people
your morale changes like oh this thing
I'm working on it's not that good right
and then combined with all the factors
we were talking about before about how
it just can be so hard to just keep
going right that this becomes a barrier
at least for me and so for example with
the compiler I've taken a great deal of
joy and just like stopping and like you
know what okay cool I've done a lot of
good work
to this point I'm gonna go back now and
you know refine these couple of areas to
a much greater degree than I need to
like I'm just gonna do it really I'm
gonna go chase all the corners of this
yeah and I'm gonna be really proud of
what I did and I'll use the demos to do
that like okay I'm gonna demo in a week
everything I do from now till then I can
already demo right right but I'm just
gonna harden all that stuff right and at
the end of that I feel really good about
what I did yes because it's quality now
yes it's not you know it's not just a
thing that's gonna collapse as soon as I
turn that way yeah so and and then that
helps me keep going yeah so I should
have said that earlier well but it's
it's an interesting sort of trade-off -
because it's like overdoing things is
definitely a problem in programming as
well so you're constantly in the stand
of like am I going to am i over building
a system and so I think it's important
to eventually riu know learn that
there's a difference between adding
stuff to a system and making the system
good like they're totally unrelated
right it's like adding features or
thinking that it's gonna do more do
whatever is a separate part and that's
the thing you want to kind of limit like
only do the things you actually you know
need to do but then the like quality
part is like a separate access and you
kind of do want to go down that one more
than oftentimes I think you might but we
have different styles - right so like if
I if I were doing handmade hero right I
would not do the environment I don't do
this on handmade here yeah between what
we do like you you went and did like I'm
building the technical infrastructure
for the game because I want to build a
what I would do in that case is I would
have gone and you know just done the
lowest effort things possible to get
things on the screen and then elaborated
them right so those are two different
approaches and I'm not I see I see what
you work on and I'm like I would have
done that later
right but you know it's not to say that
one is better than the other or like
it's even you know it's down to your
personality as a programmer you have to
do the best thing for you but what's the
best thing for you also changes with
time and winning the project it is so
like the stop and work hard and make a
piece of it high quality is almost the
exact opposite advice of like don't
rathole writings
and but both of those are correct advice
at different times in different contexts
and part of being a really good
programmer is knowing when to swap in
one piece of advice for another or you
do a blend of like thirty percent this
advice to 70 percent this advice your
face makes and that's why new people can
get really confused I I still don't feel
like it's the kind of thing that I'll
probably ever not mess up or at least
not know if I'm messing up right like
you know maybe this system shouldn't
have been done this way or at this time
or whatever so I I don't know
necessarily if it ever gets perfected in
terms of allowing your experience to
inform those things but you know unless
you're literally working on something
that you've you totally have done before
and just know this is exactly the order
to do it in or something like that one
other thing that's funny
is this also happens in design where
like I have a lot of ideas about how
what's a good game design for me or for
a particular game right but then there's
other ideas that come into play at
different contexts in different times so
like someone on the team will be asking
me how something should be and I'll be
like you know most of the time I'll say
this one thing and then one day I'll
like say a completely opposite thing
because now the situation is and I feel
you know like there's this stereotype of
like the flaky designer who just says
random crap that nobody you know
pre-madonna just like has ideas out of
nowhere and expects you to do them but
it's actually it's if they're a good
designer was actually something very
similar at play where you cross some
invisible boundary where before one
thing was appropriate and now a
different thing is appropriate and we
don't know exactly when that was crossed
but it has had
and now what we're doing is different in
this one piece right so it's just you
know if someone asks you how do you
design a game you have to actually plug
them into the matrix and do the thing
because it's not it's not that simple to
say how to do it right as you have to
give them the BSP tree of all these
weird lines where you cross this one and
now this other thing and it's a
multi-dimensional space and whatever and
mine doesn't agree with anyone elses
model anyway okay so you're basically
just saying like yeah okay I've got this
complex set of internal sort of trade
offs I can move the as the design moves
around the actual practical thing I'm
going to tell somebody needs to get done
that the game is gonna change sometimes
I just cross that some boundary where
it's like okay this thing I told you and
was very serious about yesterday needing
to be in this game Tilly doesn't need to
be in this game this other thing does
now I realize that sounds nuts but yeah
trust me there is a very sane logical
process that occurred internally that I
just can't describe and I don't do that
too often
right I've done it simulator yeah so
that so then the last thing to make that
make more sense is like the technical
version of that does exist right and so
in the large like the Chris butcher
asset system thing which was like the
technical version of that but played out
at a much longer time scale where you
can see the reason right like oh we were
doing this thing but had these drawbacks
that we didn't anticipate and because of
that reason the right decision is now
diff different right so it's the same
thing it's just a lot harder to see cuz
it's subjective right with game design
being something that you can't say is
absolutely why are there 15 mega tasks
is not a game design but but then you
know as it becomes more subjective in
the technical realm to like how how
should the handmade hero Engine be right
well a lot of things and you might
change your mind tomorrow about
something
right okay so I don't know how we're
doing on time here we have 15 minutes
left I think I'm gonna not talk for the
rest of the 15 minute that's it okay all
right so these questions cannot be
directed at John anyway this one's for
Pat it said regarding the prevention of
cheating how much is it I figured we
were little heavy there in our in our
sort of psycho psychology psychology for
a second there so this is totally
concrete regarding the prevention of
cheating how much of a difference does
encrypting gameplay network traffic
realistically make I often hear it as
important but it seems to me it would
only catch the lowest hanging fruit so
first I'd say that the thing you're
doing for encryption is you're actually
preventing people's personal data from
being stolen if they're playing in a
cafe is the primary motivation for
everything if you want to cheat in games
there's lots of ways to do it so I mean
first I'm going to separate like console
games from PC games so a console games
it's much harder to cheat because it's
hard to inject code into the console I
mean some really smart people have
managed to figure out exploits for Xbox
and Playstation but by-and-large really
tough and then the risk is if you do
that and get caught then your Xbox gets
bricked and you can't play anymore and
your accounts wiped out so encryption
you know it can be useful for console
games but for PC games it's actually not
really good anti cheat mechanism because
what happens is the game client is
already running in an on trust for the
environment and all I need to do is
break open my create remote thread
inject some code into the process space
and like discover where the network code
is and start sending messages you know
as if I was the game client so
encryption doesn't save you at all so I
would say that you should do it but it's
for a different reason
so basically Krypton is for keeping the
stuff that the user knows themselves
from being snooped in route but other
than that it does nothing so here is a
question for everybody I guess except
John because he has opted out of a
further question witness
I could ask one so this question is when
debugging your code are there obvious
shortcomings in the debugger as you use
and are there any uh you sure you don't
want to talk with this
are there any obvious things that
debuggers should do to make debugging
easier this is a question that is
apparently everyone thinks immediately
tons of people will have tons of answers
for based on the laughter so I apologize
out there the people who write debuggers
yeah so what calm 10-point Oh back in
the DOS 4gw days actually was really
powerful and you could run like a short
script so that like breakpoint a would
hit and it would run a script and look
at some stuff and then set breakpoint B
so you could catch League these really
esoteric bugs that only happened in
certain states and I'm still waiting for
a visual studio to do something to make
that process easy yeah I don't think
they have any way to script a break
point do they have scripts yeah you can
write code to do that like sort of
aftermarket and set debug registers and
things but it's like you're gonna have
this bug that I'm currently trying to
track down and I know there are ways
around this but it's a bug that only
happens when the game is running in
full-screen mode and that becomes very
difficult to debug because I can't
actually step through my code I can't
look at stuff because we're in
full-screen mode so you
[Laughter]
so literally some way to just overlay
the text on the screen but some yeah I
feel like for laptop work that would
make a lot of sense in general reminder
what yeah when you're working on a
laptop and you're doing stuff it's very
difficult to to debug in full-screen
mode
so lens Minds very quick and it might be
a thing but I haven't really looked into
it too much you know data breakpoints
now come in the watch window I can't
right click and hit watch watch the data
right there why can't I do that why do I
have to copy it and paste it and then
kill all the stuff that's also in the
watch row to make the data breakpoint
it's so irritating like why isn't that a
thing
I used like for things in Visual Studio
and that's the one thing I want yeah you
used to at least be able to drag a break
point from line to line you can yeah
don't don't expect a new function no no
I I I copy and paste it's fine we could
re-request
old so this one I think is a possibly a
little tough because I'm not sure I
guess I have addressed to everyone and
the question is what are the costs and
benefits of shipping a mod API or level
editor with a game I guess well you know
what actually no Warcraft at all we're
doing that yeah we're crafting mr. craft
had love letters yeah okay so I don't
know like you know people make these
trivial little add-ons like dota
I'm sorry watch which add-on so did you
want to say the cost/benefit yeah well I
mean you know it's funny because like
clearly other companies have benefited
hugely right like valve and and Riot
Games have made big hey on making new
versions of that game but but also
Warcraft 3 probably got a lot of users
that were playing extensively for really
long periods of time because of the
extended play value of the game because
people were coming up with new ideas all
the time and certainly you know valve
has made a really successful game
business out of like taking the mods
that people have created in and like
really seeing them which is kind of
funny because back in I don't know maybe
2002 or something like that there was a
bunch of us playing CS Kirk beta we're
like now you know everybody who wants to
play this game has probably already
downloaded it nobody's ever gonna pay
money to valve to release this game and
you know I turned it to be totally wrong
on that one so so I think there's huge
value in doing level editors if you have
the time you're in your development
schedule I guess one thing I would ask
about that is is that really level
editor or does that have to go all the
way to mod because I'm just thinking
about the the things because he sort of
said mod or level editor and that
they're kind of grouped together there
but I'm just thinking in terms of finer
detail it seems like a lot of that value
that you're talking about like for
example that valve gets out of the you
know pulling mods into into there you
know sort of business model or whatever
or the you know Warcraft spawning sort
of these other lineages those seem to be
mostly if you can actually change what
the game is right which is not really
quite the same as level editor so I
wonder is perhaps there a big difference
between the value in doing full mod
support versus just level editor and
maybe like level editor isn't so useful
but mod support definitely is or you
know I'm saying like I wonder if there's
actually a pretty big difference between
going all the way and only going part of
the way in terms of allowing the game to
sort of be customized in that way yeah
well in as much as Warcraft who didn't
really spawn any
derivative games because yeah
Warcraft 3 did because it was a yeah you
know like I guess you could argue that
mods are a better strategy Tommy do you
have super meatboy at the PC ship 12 in
ship with it but which is which is the
the mistake is don't promise stuff after
because you're not gonna want to do it
so so but I think more than you know are
mods more valuable than level letters
based on the like the context of the
game so with meatboy when we did when
when I did the editor and I put the
editor out there people made seventy
four hundred levels and that just had
people just constantly playing the game
which you know just had constant
attention there were weekly levels that
people were making and I can't say if I
actually made any money off of that but
what it did is it did get a whole bunch
of people excited about creating for the
game so I think in that way for meatboy
it works is just a love letter I don't
think I needed to go deeper into mods
like make it so Meat Boy has a gun and
you can like make an entire different
game I don't think it would have really
added much to the game because you know
with meatboy a lot of what made it great
is the stuff that you couldn't do so you
know you couldn't make weird little
slopey levels that you know have all
these rolling hills and stuff because it
was just tiles and what people did is
they took that and they creatively found
ways to make new kinds of levels and
stuff and I think I think in that way
that you know that added some sort of
something that engaged people to the
game so mod or no just kind of context
so I guess question about that
it did say costs and benefits kind of
thing obviously benefit to that doesn't
have to be monetary right in a sense it
could be just like I wanted to have
those extra people make those maps I
mean yeah I wanted in the you know as my
vision for what this is so the benefit
doesn't necessarily have to matter could
be anything I suppose yeah I just wanted
us about the cost part because that's
something that people haven't really
talked about yet in the answer it's just
that
okay so let's say we do have this
benefit that we want or that we're
thinking of what about the cost part of
shipping that right because you kind of
touched a little bit there it's like I
promised it now yeah they're written so
it's a it's a big undertaking
potentially or I mean I'm just depending
on what it was like the the reason it
was a big undertaking for meatboy wasn't
in like technical complexity or anything
it was literally I don't want to work on
this anymore and now I have to make it
look pretty and I have to fix all the
bugs in it that II didn't just he didn't
place it there you know he didn't place
that there but now I have to make it so
people can place this thing here and it
doesn't crash so and then after the
crazy development cycle it was like well
live life now I don't want to keep
working on the stupid thing so yeah I I
think though I mean having said that the
games that I'm working on now that I
want to put out I do want to put out the
level editor at launch because if for no
other reason I enjoyed seeing everything
that everybody made I thought it was
pretty cool yes and I think it helps
with just a community in general because
you know media is kind of garbage you
know Twitter is kind of garbage you know
you you want people to just play and be
excited about your game and the way they
can do that some of them at least is by
making more of it so so this would get
to a question that was asked during the
break actually because it kind of
touched on it there just incidentally
the question was actually about
something but jamun said earlier which
means you may have to talk briefly just
just I'm talking about like just a
little bit yes or no or you can kind of
blink it out John had said something
earlier that was about like okay I had
you know done something in particular
and I was really burnt out from this and
you know for doing things a certain way
for too long or whatever and get really
burnt out and he used I was at 20% and
then what you know etc and the person
asked a very interesting question which
was how do you know what that even means
in your head like ignore trying to
quantify the 20
thank us obviously like what you know
you can't but how do you know what it is
to be you know I'm at my normal
productivity or I'm like really close to
bottom productivity you're like what
quick how do you what what does that
even mean is that just an experience
thing or is that something that that
look almost look if you were gonna say
something I think is probably the number
of times per hour then I open up Twitter
yeah so we could quantify exactly really
quantify yeah like three times an hour
that's a good day yeah yeah yeah alright
so number of Twitter checks per hour
metric what is a number that would be
good productivity how often would you
check Twitter I mean literally was with
Twitter right I have two factor
authentication turned on and so I will
in the morning I will log out of Twitter
because it is such a pain to log back
into Twitter because I have to get my
cell phone out and or some crazy number
and all those other stuff that that's
kind of you know how I keep myself
productive during the day is lock myself
basically what you're saying is
two-factor authentication is not a
security I guess though if you were view
if you follow me on Twitter and you
don't hear from me during the day you
know I'm the same way if you're not
feeling it you're not gonna log out of
Twitter so you can be logged into it and
continue to be on Twitter so if you're
if you're not feeling very productive
like that morning when you're logging
out of Twitter yeah so would you even go
so far as to say that we could get
productivity gains by moving to three
all right Pat yeah I guess it's for me
it's email right cuz it's like ooh
there's fun stuff I can go and respond
to people like I actually turn off email
toast when I
programming doesn't pop up it's like Oh
a distraction that looks cool yeah and
so in general you would know if you were
kind of burned out if you're just kind
of like spending all your time an email
or that's ultimately if I don't really
have any I wouldn't do what I'm doing
you know let me hit Google again and
again surely some of you have solved
this problem before okay so basically
searching for other people's answers
rather than writing the answer yourself
is a good sign that like you're not well
and I suppose too because it's like that
means you're not that excited about
solving it yourself because you just
want it to kind of be done and move on
exactly how are we doing on time we got
three minutes left alright so here is
here is kind of I guess we'll do this on
the the closing question because I think
it's the only one that I can ask that
would in no way require John to talk the
question is what old school books
did you like back when people still read
books about programming or tech things
in general and I guess we'll just go
down I don't know if you've got any
wrong well I mean I think my favorite
tech book ever was just that big fat
Commodore 64 manual that you know showed
all the cool pecan poke locations and
stuff it's just like come with no yeah
ordered separately
you didn't come with a ordered it
separately and I just you talked about
every aspect of the Machine and where
all the memory values were and stuff and
I think I mean I don't I don't really
read a lot of stuff me even before the
internet I didn't you know it was mostly
just conversations with people but that
one book so the good book was actually
an AI programming book that I got when I
was in college and it sort of
demystified the whole idea of how a
program like server the basics of
depth-first and breadth-first searches
and things I'm like because before then
it's like I don't know you make the
computer think
and yeah it was really valuable to sort
of demystify the whole process because I
was still learning cooking then and the
one that actually it was the reverse
that was the KN RC book because it's
like you know jumps into like print
death and pointers and stuff it's like
this isn't really helpful how do I do
useful stuff without pointers right
because you know coming from like a very
beginning Pascal knowledge it's like
there's all this weirdness in the
language I don't know you just want to
do something interesting first so I
didn't find it to be very helpful book
so the K in R was just like it was too
focused on just like specific language
these things they were doing they didn't
really take the time to go like look
here's sort of how you start doing
things and see I didn't really read many
programming books I had my one cue basic
book but that was it it was it was on
the Panasonic computer I had that was a
laptop that was about 35 pounds Wow yeah
it was really cool I had like a green
screen and a built-in printer two things
and it had a keyboard that went over and
you would carry it and well you wouldn't
carry it had a roll case because it was
too heavy yeah that was like my first
computer and it had a Q basic book and
that's no it was kind of the only one I
read can you just say the way I got into
programming there was some books that
came like in RadioShack the trs-80 color
computer there was I just remember there
were two books that like started with
really simple exercises and you would go
through I don't know if they were
particularly good it was just like how I
did it so and and you wouldn't use those
to learn today no well maybe learn how
to program the trs-80 all right well I
think we're just about out of time so
thanks so much for coming back and
talking with us again this year
[Applause]