hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream I yesterday did some code
that can load and dump our asset files
and I want to also make something today
which allows us to rewrite them so that
anytime you want change versions or how
they're laid out or optimize them or
remove things or do anything we really
want it's not a huge deal we can just do
it and that's just kind of a nice thing
I felt like it was worth showing how to
do that because it's not that hard as
you've seen it only takes a couple hours
to build something like that if you
remember correctly that's our HHA edit
program which is this program right here
and at the end of yesterday's stream we
were taking a look at the dumps there
and I was using tab you for that but you
can really use anything you want to view
those things where it up with that in
the bonus pack
so here's tab view right and if I go
ahead and and take a look at some of the
file dumps that we had you can sort of
see where we were going with that
here is the day directory here's the
test fonts for example here's a dump of
the test fonts HHA file and what you can
see here is you know we've got a bunch
of glyph it maps in here you can see
them fairly straightforward right
everything you would expect and you know
it's also got the font information
things like the descender is what the
tags were for the font and all that sort
of stuff so that gives us good
confidence the main reason I wanted that
was that just gives us some nice
confidence that we're loading everything
properly and now if I want to resave
this file using the same code it should
be fairly straightforward to do so right
because now we know we've got this
loaded HHA here that has imported all of
the data from the v-0 file which means
that now it's pretty easy for us to
write out a different kind of file
because we just iterate over this and
then it doesn't matter whether we loaded
a v-0 or v1 file right it doesn't matter
which kind we did
so if I then take a look here at the
right HHA you can see here we got the
read HHA and the right HHA so if I just
make a thing here that allows me to
write out the version of the file
HHA v1 let's say like that and I pass it
a test file what I need to do here is
pass it something to take as the source
and of course we already did the
command-line necessary to like load that
in I think we've got a rewrite command
right that that we you know definitely
do anything right now but we yeah you
can see we like make the calls right it
just doesn't do anything so if we take a
look at right HHA here you can see that
you know we're all set up to go we've
opened a file for writing so the only
thing we really need to do now is
actually write something that does this
output of the loaded HHA out into
destination file writing it sequentially
and so that's that's all we need to do
again not particularly difficult all
right so really all we need to do to
write one of these HHA files is place
the header information you know we know
exactly how big the headers going to be
because it's a fixed size once we know
our asset count in our tag count both of
which we know so if we just leave the
space for the header and this is the
same thing we did when we originally
wrote HSA files if we just leave space
for the header all we have to do is loop
over everything we've got dump it all
out into a big old mush and as we go
every time we write out a piece of
flexibly sized data all we have to do is
just remember where we wrote it by
putting it into our version of the
header that we're going to save then at
the very end when we're all done we just
write out that header and we've
completed reading the file that's really
all there is to it it's pretty basic now
it's not always so easy to write
something like that for the simple
reason that it's a lot of
finicky byte manipulation kind of stuff
right so all of our byte offsets that we
write to tell you where things are have
to be correct so you know maybe we can
get some of those wrong or something
like this but usually if you're careful
it's really not a particularly big deal
to verify them eventually right okay so
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna start by
just doing the basics I'm going to say
all right we've got a desk file pointer
and I want to first move that pointer to
a place where I can start writing my
like my data smite my data information
write my my my what's the word I'm
looking for my I I want to be writing my
flexible data store like the parts that
come from bitmaps and strings and things
that are just flexibly sized that are
not like those even chunks right that's
what I want to do I want to be able to
just write those out and one of the
things that I honestly cannot quite
remember is I don't recall how we were
doing appending can we quickly look at
that how did we do that oh right we did
that because these are relocatable so we
just relocate them yeah all right so
basically yeah we don't really have to
think about anything other than what I
just said it's really pretty
straightforward so this should be pretty
simple so let's go ahead and open up the
file formats we've got here so here's
the header file I'm sorry the header
data so I'm gonna first clear it because
we want to get rid of we want to make
sure all the reserved fields are set to
zero so that if we want to in the future
we can look for optional things that we
add there so for example let's say in
the future you want to add a new array a
fool array we want to put a zero in
there for all existing files to make
sure that we know there is no flu or
in those files that way we don't have to
bump the version number to add new
things we only have to bump the version
lever if we change the layout so it just
makes it a little bit easier to maintain
a binary file format right it's sort of
like a little bit of a half way so you
know if you're gonna have a binary file
format you even have a text file format
the bonus of a binary file format very
easy to load it's quick there's no fuss
etc but because there is no parser it's
hard to insert new things into it
because nobody's checking for anything
right you just load and go so in a text
file format the opposites true it's very
slow laborious very error-prone but
you've got this parser there doing all
this parsing it's easy to throw new
things into it because you can just look
for a new symbol if you see it you
process it if you don't you don't write
well zeros are a way of kind of
inserting half-and-half into like a
binary file format inserting a zero
point like a bunch of unused zero
pointers is kind of like saying there's
a bunch of symbols we could use here in
a text parser right it's a bunch of
options you're leaving for your future
self to use so it's kind of a nice
little half way it's like it doesn't
suffer all the drawbacks of moving to a
fully text file format which you know
would then have lots of options but it
also doesn't lock you down like a
completely specified binary file format
would where you can't add anything at
all without breaking something
right so it's you know there's degrees
it's a continuum between binary and text
and you can kind of float to a position
that makes you happy in that sense right
so I'm gonna go ahead and specify the
magic value I'm gonna specify the
version that we're writing here and then
I need to specify the other things we've
got like the tag count in the asset
count and these of course are known to
us because when we loaded we remember
all these things so we can easily do
them here we then have three things we
don't know where they are at a tag array
asset array in the annotations array so
you know at the moment we don't really
want to deal
that yet so I'm just not going to write
like I'm not going to do that however I
am gonna do some things to prepare so
I'm gonna get ready to have written
these things so what I want to do is I
want to first make the desk tags I want
to make the desk assets and I want to
make the desk annotations and what I'm
doing here is to just preparing space
because I know I'm gonna write these
things and rather than do them after I
write all the flexible data I want the
arrays around first because those are
rays are what I'm going to use to store
where I wrote everything right so yeah
that's just how that goes so what I'm
going to do here is I'm just gonna
malloc space for each of these things
and what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
compute their sizes ahead of time right
so I'm gonna say desk tags size desk
assets sighs and just annotations oops
annotations size like so so I'm gonna
figure out how big each of these should
be and of course that's really simple to
do because we kind of know already
exactly how it's going to go we know
that each of these arrays stores
something of this size and we know how
many of each there are so we know that
we're gonna be using the tag count maybe
I'll do it this way instead we know that
we're going to be doing the tag count
for the tags and we know that the assets
and annotations
those are both going to come from
however many assets are because there's
one annotation per asset assuming that
that array is present which in the
future we can actually do a thing where
we don't put that array in if we want to
strip it out I
we're just saying that's possible if we
wanted to save space about I don't
I think it's ever gonna matter but you
could write okay so assuming that you've
got this set up now what we can do is
just pass these sizes in so we know that
that's how many we have like so and once
we've got those file once we've got
those arrays ready we know that we can
now store all our information in them so
when we do our for I loops here over the
tags and the assets we can you know do
exactly what we want to do there which
is stored where we wrote everything and
other stuff like this but then when we
get to the end now is when we would
finally write them out now how am I
gonna write them out well one of the
things that I think is important to
remember is all of the things that we're
writing kind of take the same form they
are something that has a particular size
so we're we know we're going to write
out a block and then somebody somewhere
wants to know where we wrote it so for
example when we write out the death tags
array we know that the header wants to
put those tags into the array right and
so what we're going to do is we're going
to put where we voted into here that
naturally informs what the API should
look like for writing this file because
we know that what we're gonna do is
something that looks like this right we
know we've got desc tag size here we
know that we've got the pointer to it we
know we've got the assets here
oops tests sighs just assets and we know
they got the annotations tests
annotations sighs yes annotations and
like I said this is optional so if we
wanted to we could do something like
include annotations equals true and
tests like this and so this actually is
pretty easy for us to do now obviously
it can't write to a file without knowing
what the file is it's that dest file
there so I can do this if I want
- and just complete the API it's gonna
be pretty clear what it would be like so
right and so if I just used this right
block function it should be pretty
straightforward for me to complete
everything that I wanted to do okay
so similarly now if I'm up here with my
4i loops I can just finish everything
off let's suppose that I want to write
all of the tags first so here's the tag
index I'm going to loop over all of the
tags and what I'm going to do is take
the desk tag and I now also want the
source tag and once I have these two I
know that I'm just gonna copy the desk
tag from I'm just gonna take the source
tag and copy it into the desk tag now we
know there's nothing else to do it's
just too flat values so this is pretty
straightforward it's that's basically it
it doesn't need to write any blocks it
doesn't need to allocating space so this
array is very simple right now if the
tag structure got more complicated we
would put the logic in here but it at
the moment it isn't so it just stays
simple so all of our logic basically
comes in the form of the asset
processing so in here as a loop over the
asset indices what I want to do is
gather all the information that I might
need so the first thing I need is the
source asset I also need the annotation
and I really need I guess this
and then finally I need the destination
asset and destination annotation that
I'm writing right so I got the two
sources now I have the two destinations
right uh this is not what I meant to do
that's what I meant to do there we go so
this sets us up to start writing the
assets but now we have to actually
figure out how we're actually going to
do that so if we look down here here's
our HHA asset we know we can copy this
directly and some of the things will
work all of this stuff is correct that's
right these are right these two things
are not right well I guess the size is
the offset is going to change right
because it could be in a different
location in this file than it was in the
original file especially if we start
doing things like merges or whatever and
we may need to support a little bit more
like if we did emerge one thing that
you'll notice here is for example when
we have this data store pointer all of
this stuff is off of the data store
pointer and that doesn't really help so
you know one thing we could do here is
change sort of the way we're doing this
data store a little bit to make it more
flexible now I'm not going to do that
yet
I'm just gonna kind of leave that for a
moment but that is this is something
that I think we can come back to and
make better than it is right now and we
can sort of see how we might do that a
little later on right okay
but at the moment for just rewriting the
files when we load this stuff in here we
can still use the distort as it is so
the way that we need to use the
datastore is that's how we can figure
out what the asset data actually
consists of right so what we want to do
here is say okay
let's write out this block we know we've
got a source asset we know we've got a
desk asset we can start by copying all
the fields over because we know that
most of them apply but then we have to
kind of ping back and take a look okay
so the data assets sorry the data offset
is going to be wrong so we can take the
data offset and say well we know that
the data offset for this file is going
to be whatever the result of the right
block is when we write this out so what
we could say is all right when we write
this block out go ahead and say whatever
the the the best asset data sizes
whatever that size is that's how much
we're gonna write out we know that the
Deaf's annotations sorry the we know
that the location of it is going to be
that data store so the source data store
plus whatever the old original offset
was right because that's telling us
where it was in the data store so the
source assets data offset offset from
the data store that's where the original
block of data was and then we can just
append that to our file so that copies
the data out of the in memory block we
loaded when we loaded the file out into
the new file so now it's been written
and we store where it was written that's
really all we need to do for the asset
it's the annotations that create more of
a problem those are fairly extensive
here and so we need to do a lot more
work to write those out so here we have
our deaths annotation that we need to
fill out so effectively what we're
looking at is some a big kind of giant
just go ahead and prep this a big sort
of thing that looks like this
we don't need oops to set the zeros on
these reserves because what we could do
is just zero the entire array like
that's what we should do
let me do a bit here now well that's
actually already gonna happen now I
think about it so it's really only the
annotation we need so I can just do this
clear the whole annotation out and then
we just set the parts that we actually
care about it's a little overzealous
there so in here we know that we've got
kind of a number of different sorts of
things restoring so let's take a look
first of all we know that a bunch of
them just come from the source
annotation sooo for the ones that come
from the source annotation we've got a
pretty easy job right those just get
copied directly in so things like the
sprite sheet and the source file date
like that sort of stuff right
oops source file date source file
checksum oh you know what I guess these
reserves kind of have to be copied as
well right so never mind I guess we will
actually do those I didn't really think
of it that way I should have thought of
it that way because we want to copy
reserves over even if we don't know what
they are we want to preserve them right
probably I don't know that we
necessarily can it may be a fool's
errand to bother so it may be that we
actually want a strip and then I think
about it we probably just want to strip
them out
yeah we probably just want to strip them
out because assuming that they referred
to something that was like an offset in
the file or something
we can't preserve that there's no way to
preserve that information so that yeah
that that doesn't actually work so never
mind we won't be doing that so what we
want to do now is actually write these
in for the information here about the
file rights of base name is base name
where where is the base name count
source file base name count we
accidentally deleted that and I
apologize so there it is
so there we go so basically what this
boils down to is a series of us writing
these things out like so right so we
copy these things like this and then we
effectively have to write some strings
out that come from actual like C string
style stuff we've got here so again we
pretty much just know what these are
though so it's not particularly hard for
us to do and furthermore we can probably
just make this a bit of a utility here
we could say something like write string
and then include the count field as an
address for it to fill out so this can
be something that's fairly that's fairly
automated for us we just say look source
file base name is a string right the
strings thick the count in here and
that's you know have a little party
right like so so that that's something
we could easily do and probably should
and you know and and did now yeah this
is a little bit kind of annoying to copy
but let's do it anyway so let's do that
that that here we go and now I just have
to change these
to be the correct things so I want to do
author name offset here author name
author name count and this one is asset
description offset asset description
asset description account and you know
we could make utility for this like we
could make a bundle that's what a string
is in the file and do some stuff but
it's you want them inter lead it's it's
a long story I don't think we really
want to go down that road it's good
enough as it is so it's fine so anyway
this will write those strings out so
soon we have right block and right
string that will take care of the
annotations for us and really at that
point we've you know we're pretty much
done I think I mean that's that's
basically all there is to it
so once we've written all of this stuff
out all that really remains is to take
care of the header so the first thing we
need to do is respect the fact that the
header can't be written till we know all
the information so what we probably want
to do is leave space for it first
so we've got the header size we know
that it's the size of whatever the
header or struct is so what we can do
first is just F seek our pointer for the
Deaf's file forward by the header size
so that it starts out with a header size
chunk missing from the beginning of the
file and we'll just rewrite that later
on so we start there we do all of our
rights after the fact and then finally
at the end we can just F seek back to
the beginning of the file like so and
then write out the header block by
saying look you remember that header we
filled out we would like you to write it
and by the way we can also double check
here check header location we can do an
assertion that makes sure that the
header got written to block 0 because
that's where it has to go like if it
doesn't start at zero the game won't
find it and that will
be very useful but that's basically it
that writes the file out I think with
all of the data I don't think there's
anything particularly fancy going on
there otherwise they don't know if I've
forgotten anything we'll have to
double-check but then we can just go
ahead here and say all right here's the
the right string that's the string -
right
there's the destination count and the
destination file like so and then of
course we also have the right block
that's got the size so yeah I think I
should make these all be 32 now that I
think about it just because we I don't
think we support 30 64-bit sizes really
anywhere currently everything's got to
be 32-bit sizes you can have more than
60 you can have like lots of 4 gigabyte
chunks in the file so it could be way
bigger than 4 gigabytes but nothing
individually can be bigger than 4
gigabytes currently so I think we're
really looking at some more like that
which is fine so there's the data and
there's the desk file now these are
really trivial for us to to write
obviously the location in the file can
be given to us by FTL which will say
where it is
so if I just want to find out where we
are in the file that will tell me where
we are in the file that's where we are
going to write we can then do our F
right we can pass the destination file
the data the size write it out and then
we can use that function to implement
our string right as well so we don't
have to write it twice right everything
can go through the same path so when we
want to write a block well we know the
size of the string that's just whatever
the count was we know the data from the
string it's whatever the data was and so
what we need to do is fill in desc count
first with the size of the string
so that that'll get written to the
header properly and then we're done
right okay uh let's see so yeah these
have to be you thirty twos the moment
when we write the block outs we need to
pass the desk file which we didn't do
let's see here that is a type vote
this that way so the author name is not
in there
it's just author that's why what so it's
yeah it's not names all right so that's
supposed to write a file we could test
it by using rewrite but we would have a
problem which is that we'd have no idea
if it rewrote it correctly
the reason for that is that we don't
load HH once currently so really the
last thing we have to do now is make
something that actually loads HH 1 HH a
version 1 files this should be
relatively straightforward because all
of the stuff is in the right format so
it should just be a case of literally
just pointing to things
yeah and that's about it so you know
when we load the file the data store has
already been loaded so in here if we
just look at the data store of the file
as a header we should be able to just
put everything together so for example
let's see here
where's my HHA edit I just need to fill
out all this stuff and make it be set
correctly so actually let me swap those
two okay so my head's not in the way so
if I want to figure out for example if
this thing has annotations
I can just say header annotations equals
true inside an if statement the if
statement
oops sorry hij the if statement would
just be whether the annotation array had
an offset right so if the annotations
that's that's in this header here this
thing if this was nonzero then it has
them otherwise it doesn't right we know
this is said already magic value and
source version should also be set if I'm
not mistaken those are set by the
calling code right so the code where
does the load read hhj code happen so
you can see that gets set here right so
the file and the magic value and the
version number of those get read so we
don't really have to worry about those
it's the rest of the stuff that we have
to actually do so let's go ahead and and
fill those in now again it's pretty
straightforward the tag count the tags
the asset count and the assets we don't
have to load anything now because it's
just flat memory we can point to and
it's all correct because it's the it
does it's not doing an import it's
actually just it's the correct stuff you
know it's it's the file is right so we
can go ahead and just cast these dupes
we can just go ahead and cast the data
store to those pieces of information and
they're right so let's suppose I just
look here and say well here's the oops
header there's the tag count and we know
that the tags offset from the datastore
I'm just going to call that D let's say
off of the data store that's the value
we want same is true for the assets
right and then the only thing we really
have to process now is those annotations
because everything else is now right
like the assets and everything are
correct so the only thing that we have
to do now is actually allocate space for
the annotations array and actually
process that correctly so if this thing
has annotations then what we need to do
is say that we've got an HHA annotation
that's a source annotation and that's
going to be pointed to by whatever the
header annotations pointer is right and
we can do a for loop over them like so
why did I do I keep getting confused
between HHA and header there we go so I
want to make two of these now I want to
make a loaded HH annotation that I'm
going to write into and I have a source
8hh annotation right and so what I want
to do here is I want to go ahead and
load these in where I say all right each
one of these things is going to be based
off of one of these so I can say look
annotation index get the one that we're
reading from and then loaded HHA
annotation test annotations that's just
going to be the annotations plus
annotation index and then I just have to
load them in so we know exactly what
we're loading in it's this set of things
so we can just say jest annotation
source validate your source annotation
source file date and the same is true of
the checksum same is true the
spritesheet
and so that copies those things in and
then we need to load our strings out and
again that's going to be pretty simple
I'm gonna make a little utility function
for it that basically passes the base
pointer and then passes the two pieces
of information we need for the string so
that is the source file base name count
and the source file face name offset
okay um know which is the best like that
so here we just load the strings in
and think we're done so we just need
this function to do our string D code
for us and it's not really particularly
interesting right all we're doing here
is saying well we have a data store
pointer I guess we'll just keep calling
it D we have a count and we have an
offset and all we're trying to do is
construct the new string from that so
what we want to do is say well the count
of the string is just the count that
we're told and the data for the string
is just going to be going to be the
offset off of the data store and that's
it right so now we load it we're loading
everything
HHA Asset count but we don't actually
set our annotations up at all so we need
to allocate those here
and that's all we need to do for that so
that Malik's an array for us to put our
loaded annotations in and it also tells
us you know hey we we've got some
annotations now I think that's it for
reading v1 files I don't know that
there's anything else particularly much
in there but now we you know we've got
bugs or whatever so we're gonna have to
go in there and figure out anything we
messed up let's go ahead and just try
the basics we can go ahead and look at
what happens if we try to rewrite one of
our existing files for example so test
one dot H H a let's just look at what
that was originally right so here's our
tab view and here's our test 1 h h a so
you can see like what it thinks it has
like some facing directions and some
assets in here oh whoops this we didn't
jump that one with the latest version of
HHA edit it looks like let's try that
again
what am I missing shouldn't that give us
a new shouldn't that tell us like what's
contained in the assets I wanted to step
in and see what's wrong there
so we're not producing a dump file what
did I mess up like did you notice it's
not producing the dump file so
something's busted Oh
oh whoops so that's not how dump works
we got to update our stuff here so
really this should be we got a yeah the
little switch parser probably would have
been good so we need to do a thing here
that's like print usage equals false and
something like this because we got to
make sure we know when we mess up the
command line right like I don't want to
be sitting there like that scratching my
head going wait what happened so we want
something like this it's like hey you
messed up like that's not how you do a
dump you do a dump like this so that's
what I wanted and now we should be able
to see all of the information right all
right so let's launch another tab view
here and let's do some stuff so let's
assume well we should debug this first
because we may just crash we don't know
if it'll work at all right but so let's
take test one dot H H a and do tests one
V one
HHA right and well it didn't crash so
that's good so it rewrote the file and
here's the rewritten file and it's
slightly bigger than the original file
which is actually okay because remember
we added annotation to it right we graft
on those strings so it should be a
little bigger even if it's working
correctly so that's not really a cause
for concern that's actually totally fine
so let's go to the tab view here and
lunch it okay there we go
let's go ahead and take a look at the
other dump file and see if we can see
ha what we got right so you produce a
test 1v1 that HHA now I'm gonna go ahead
and dump that one and I did it again
well I should just I just make the dump
work that way because I obviously want
it to right so here's another dump file
I it's only 5k but I guess the original
was only 5k doesn't this look like more
than 5k of data
I guess just because it's all spread out
with the indentations it looks bigger
than it actually is
all right so here we go so the first
thing we'll notice is these things have
changed they should have changed so
that's okay the magic value is the same
in both cases but the version has
changed that's what we wanted let's take
a look at the assets so you notice we
now have these descriptions from the
file fees were added before now they're
from the file and they match which is
good
that's what I want right and it looks
like
so we lost the asset name somehow so
we're not we do have at least one bug is
the asset name most of the rest of the
things look right to me
the only so really the thing that I'm
not seeing here is the asset name the
author's right the description is right
[Music]
this the base file names right so really
to me it just looks like we messed up we
messed up the asset name somehow so
that's the only thing I see wrong at the
moment is that the asset name is is
busted
so when we're loading it in and we do a
rough string we look at the asset name
count asset name offset that and we
assign the asset name that seems roughly
correct right so I wouldn't imagine
there'd be a lot of issue there so let's
take a look at the writer did the writer
mess that up yeah okay so we did the
author twice is the problem rather than
the asset name so that's I think the
only bug that's pretty good if that's
really the only bug we did all that and
we only had one mess up that's pretty
good so let's just fix that so here
we're trying to say that the asset name
off set is is that right and let's run
the same thing again now and see whether
or not we've got it correctly sussed out
so here we'll we'll rewrite that oh
we've got protection in there for not
deleting something which is kind of nice
so okay we've done it now let's dump
and now we should be able to look and
see if we've got that asset name
properly restored so it looks like we
did right
we've got head cape and torso right head
cape torso uh so that's pretty good to
go yeah so that's all pretty good I
think so the thing that we now we're now
stuck we're now left with with a sort of
we're left in sort of a weird position
we might as well finish up making these
things completely backwards compatible
the thing that we have to do is right
now we would no longer have a way to
query anything by what type it was
because we're effectively stripping out
that type field right so now finally
what we'd have to do is do like tag like
type index or something or like basic
type basic category or something right
but whatever that thing was before and
the basic category is like just whatever
these things were you know what I mean
so we could do something like you know I
don't remember what this is called and
so if we want to we can basically do
like a tag welding operation here which
does stick a new tag and everything and
would allow us to still retain 100%
backwards compatibility right so let's
just do it and that's that'll finish up
the day and then I think at that point
we're free to just go hog-wild and do
whatever we want right we can go back in
to the asset system now we can use the
data storage in the in the HSA file to
actually record information about where
things came from so we can go ahead and
make that system be pretty sweet now I
think
all right so if I want I now have the
ability to sort of specify what that
property would be so that when these get
imported to the type array stuff they
can be set up properly so that just
means that each of these things is going
to have an additional tag grafted on to
them which means that this stuff here
has to continue to work properly and
this stuff here has to be offset so like
our tag importing has to be beefed up a
bit right
not sure exactly how I want to do this I
do want to do one thing though
I would like to truncate this before the
extension so if you pass a string I
would like to do something where we
check and we get rid of any of the stuff
that comes after the last period so
pretty straightforward
if we see a period we just set the new
count and that's it so basically we look
for the last period we could also do a
thing here where we check for slashes so
if we want to support file names the
path and them basically what you could
also do is say something like so
basically you can't truncate if there's
a period in in the file the you know if
a slash comes after a period then forget
those earlier periods you know what I
mean so I just wanted that in there
because I would like to get rid of
mistake and I admit that probably should
do this
so that way when I do those conversions
like when I do the rewrite here and do
the dump
then I should see in the name it's just
no dot HHA right it's just the base name
because that's what we've been going on
at the moment right all right so that's
pretty simple yeah we could also
truncate it could also truncate
pathnames here so you know we can have
both of these
I wonder why should call us maybe like
truncate maybe let's call this remove
extension and remove path
so if we find one of these things then
what we want to do is say well okay the
the new count value gonna say zero cost
a new start so if we encounter one of
these then we know that the start is
going to be the index that index plus
one so then what we're gonna have to do
is say all right the file name count
minus equals the new start position and
the file name data plus equals the new
start position she was basically
advancing to the path part and so that
way we can say like alright yeah
remove the path and remove the extension
of this thing and then what I should be
able to do is say well okay so even if I
was to do something like this where I
said oh yeah like go back a directory
and then forwards a directory hopefully
I would still get a path parse there oh
well I've got to actually do it this way
like that right
and so then if I dump that hopefully
will still get test one even though
that's not what would have come in on
the command line yeah
so that just just cleans it up and
produces just the name which is what we
kind of said we were going with why well
you know it's what we said we were gonna
do so we did it uh so I think all of
that is now good and I just want to add
the I just want to add that tag back in
so that we could still use the old files
and so before we decide on a completely
new set of tags and what we want to put
in there we can still load the old tags
just to verify that everything's working
it's just nice because it doesn't cost
me that much to add it here it's not a
lot of work so I might as well do it
right so we know we're gonna add one new
one each time here so we know we're
gonna have a lot more tags than than we
used to so we're adding the asset count
in then what we need to do as we loop
over these here is now we actually have
to copy the tags out so this this is not
gonna cut it any more at all so we got
elected ooh the copy for each of our
assets here where we loop through and
process the asset that is where we have
to process the tag so what we need to do
is say for each tag that we would have
copied so this is like asset tag index
basically what we want to do here well I
guess now I guess we can still do it as
tag index so what we need to do here is
say well we've got the assets its source
asset we know that the first tag index
is this we know that the one passed last
tag index tells us what to loop to right
so we loop over all those tags we know
the source tag is here so the only
question is where is the death tag well
the death tag is just going to be
something probably that we do this with
right and then finally after we've added
all of those tags you know
and I guess I should probably just do
this right after we've added all of
those tags we have to add one additional
tag which is no ID and value so what we
want to do here is add this stuff in so
basically you know we know what the
original type ID was - think that's
we're gonna say that's the value of this
and we're gonna say like tag basic
category is the tag ID so we added that
category in that gives us the tag set
for this asset correctly and so then
what we need to do is set this up so it
pretty easy right we know the first tag
index is just whatever the tag index was
that we started with and then we know
the last tag index is just whatever the
tag was that we finished with so pretty
straightforward to set up right so the
only thing we really have to do is just
remember where the desk
tags are right so it's just a JJ tags I
probably just should have done a JJ tags
right so all I really have to do here is
just say alright the desk tag index
starts at 1 and goes up from there and
this should reserve the space for that
because the tag out in the file includes
the 0 so it should just work going
forward I think so that all seems fine
yeah I don't know if I'm missing
something there but I think that's
everything that we would have had to do
so let me delete that file let's rewrite
it and then dump it and see if it
actually did that at all
so if we look at the tags here you can
see what we've got it looks actually
correct
I that looks a little odd there's
another one
but maybe it's right we'll find out I'm
not sure we'll have to look into that we
now need to update the array again this
is one of those things where I say
C++ is awful because we shouldn't have
to do this this should have been
automated right and it's trivial like
every programming language except C++
automates that tributing so anyway we
get these unknowns here if I rerun it
now that we've added that entry those
should say basic category and they do
we've got an extra one here so that
feels like just to screw up so I should
go look and see
we must be allocating one too many tags
and oh and we are the reason that we are
is because of the phantom zero asset the
gift that keeps on giving
so we only need the asset count minus
one right because we don't need an extra
tag for the zero asset
it doesn't get any tags at all all right
so now if we go ahead delete rewrite and
dump we've got all of that information
in there and all the tags look good
everything looks good so this allows us
now if we want you to be able to load
version 1 in the game so let's go ahead
and try that so here's how we would do
this you can see we've got all of these
hhas in here so what I'm gonna do is we
could delete all this stuff out of here
- till we have just the hhas involved so
here I'll just make a v-0 directory and
I just I don't want that so I'm just
gonna move that out there as well test
that out I don't remember what this
thing was oops cuz you can't drag and
drop why can't why is 4 code or not a
drop tar
it should have drop files set or
something right hmm all right so I'm
gonna delete these dumps get them out of
there
delete this test and delete the import
test as well now we've got this test out
file I just want to know what it is it
was something we had done for testing
purposes so I don't know what that's for
and I don't care so that's gonna go away
so now we've got these and I want to
import them all to the new file format
so what I'm going to do is I'm just
going to use HH edit to rewrite them all
so again hopefully we're doing this
correctly don't really know well the
only real way to know is you know beyond
what we've already tried to validate is
to actually go and try them in the game
so that's why I want to do it
so now we have v1 versions of each of
those and I can just store these in v-0
there's our v1 versions of everything
and I should be able to dump all of
those so if I want to look at one of
these you know intro art v1
[Music]
here's the dump of that file and if I
bring up my tab views I should be able
to walk through it pretty easy
well tags look good there's the assets
they're all opening cutscenes and you
know everything seems kosher okay so
that seems good to me if we pop back
over to the game now of course that's
the unsaved change I don't know what the
unsane Jam was oh it was the test that
out probably I don't know anyway if I
pop back over to the game now though the
game wouldn't work right because it
doesn't know how to load those files
anymore so the game would break because
it's it it's expecting to load things
with a very specific structure and it
can't load them anymore right so now our
goal is just to bring the game up to the
new file format and we can just proceed
from there so doing that is the first
step is to make like eliminate there is
a part of the code remember where we
tried to put in the shim so this was
just saying like hey we don't want to
port to the new file format yet so
here's the thing that forces it to live
the old file format we want to get rid
of this so we want to go ahead and
compile that and now we should get
compile errors everywhere that we don't
that we we will get compile errors
everywhere that we need to update the
file format to do like something new
with it right so the the asset type here
oops is not really an asset type right
it's actually just a thing see it there
yeah
it's just a thing that we pass in its
it's really not where's my where these
defined here layered see there it is so
you can see here that all of these are
just set to asset opening cutscene
except for this one that's set to asset
none so really all that is is it's just
the thing that tells us which one of
those things we're looking for for the
old compatibility stuff so we can if we
want to in handmade NH just include the
old like handmade file formats 0h right
and as long as we make sure that v-0
always has that ID appended to it then
we can make sure that only the only
people who ever use it are people who
actually really want to write and it
because it'll still work just fine okay
super entity visible piece here again
like these are just old compatibility
ways of doing this but they're fine
right they will just get looked up
slightly differently at the moment
and then like I said the big thing we're
gonna have to do is figure out how we
want to actually look these things up
because that's probably going to change
a little bit now so I do think we're
going to want to pull this eventually
you know at some point
alright so the first thing to recognize
is the file header asset type count the
asset type count is not relevant anymore
we got rid of that so we just have
assets and we don't have to think about
it we don't have to think about that
part anymore right so that's kind of
nice it simplifies our loading too so
that's gonna be nice let's see here what
do we got this is just remember writing
the modifications app so if we're
writing the modifications out we would
still have to write out the so although
this is it necessary we still do we have
an additional one here we've got like
this stuff the annotations want to be
kept want to be preserved here as well
right trying to think like I kind of
feel like we almost want to have that
code shared that like the code for
loading and rewriting the annotations
feels like we just kind of want to share
that code
I mean there's two ways we can go with
it right one is we could weld the
annotations directly to the assets and
they're always just written with the
assets and the other is we just rewrite
the array thinking about it
rewriting the array does seem reasonable
because rewriting because you can just
yeah there's really no reason not to
just rewrite the array I guess because
the array references strings that we're
still there so you don't really have to
worry too much about that aspect of it
so I think it's fine the way it is I
think it's fine the way it is I'm gonna
I'm gonna nerf this temporarily and then
I'm gonna come back and add the
annotations to it because I think we can
just preserve those trivially and we
should because why not and that and
that's when we're gonna be able to weld
in the part about the checksums and
testing for the date as well which we do
want to do all right so asset type
arrays going away this right here
not a thing right so that's just gone
and this we kind of still do want to do
right like we want to do the annotation
or asset count annotations so we do you
know we do still want to be able to
retract the watermark in that way the
asset type counts here we don't need to
loop over this this way anymore we can
just loop over the asset index indices
directly and that is what we want to do
right so what we want to do here is like
nerf this part we want to grab this
yeah so this is just reading the data
from the file and then unpacking it
right that's all we're doing so we
really want to do this we don't have any
way to really handle this especially so
we kind of want to do that right and put
that in here so if the type is a if it's
a font glyph type then we need to be
able to set the bitmap ID offset why was
that stored in the file
what is that doing
what is that do it
but what so why would that have anything
to do with whether or not it was a font
like why isn't that just always I mean
that value that does not make any sense
at all so the bitmap IDs in the font are
going to be relative to the file right
so what I do not understand why why was
that just not always set like why did it
have to check to see if it was a font
glyph you know I'm saying like when you
come through on a file and you load the
file why isn't that just why isn't that
just the setting because you want to
know what the asset count was and you
want to subtract away
whatever the
yeah I don't and so like why aren't the
font bitmaps just like why isn't it just
this like why were we doing it any other
way than that I mean shouldn't if that
shouldn't that be the way that it's done
and I mean if you didn't do it this way
then it would just be wrong like the
file you couldn't have more than one
font per file right this just seems
really messed up to me and I don't know
why we would have done that that's super
spooky like if we and that's what I
wanted so if we dump that file out
oops no bad wrong stop that's gonna go
forever as window windows is super slow
at building those tab views so if you if
you handed a lot of data windows just
dies trying to populate the tree view
you know I'm saying they can't do it all
right so I'm just curious so if these
are the assets here right like like
there's two fonts in this file
aren't there maybe there aren't I mean I
thought there were I thought these are
two fonts right
these numbers don't make any sense I can
tell you that
we should maybe dump the glyph
information here so we can actually see
what it is cuz I do not I do not
fundamentally don't understand what's
going on there I'm just confused it
doesn't make sense to me why it would be
the way that it is it should just be a
file relative index for the glyph
full-stop and so all you should have to
know you shouldn't even need to know
font bitmap ID offset like you should
just have a thing that's like asset base
right like there's tag base there should
just be asset base and then all you do
is you add the glyph index to the font
to the asset base I mean that's all that
it should have done and I do not
understand why I didn't do that
maybe there was like a historical reason
why or something so I yeah I don't I
don't know man I think that should be
acid base I don't think it should be
font bitmap ID offset because the
bitmaps should all just be relative to
the file and so whatever file the font
is in it should just use the asset base
of that file that's what I claimed and
that's what I'm doing and I will just
make it work because that's the only
thing that makes any sense to me
so how does the tag
bass gets set up here
so yeah a lot of this stuff just doesn't
make sense me so the tag base is set up
oh wait no that that makes Ferguson
right I thought that was getting it out
of the header so yeah that's good
so as we do our asset camp here right
the base for loading these is whatever
the asset count or the tag count is
right so that's exactly what we want and
then we go ahead and add in the ones the
new ones here we don't bother with the
zero value honestly so now we know for
every file it has an asset base and a
tag base which is what we want right and
that's I feel like that's what it should
have been so it didn't really like the
fact that it wasn't that it was lame
right so anyway moving along so we've
got this very bad spelling
this is how you spell exercise just
guessing I was wondering do know why
swelled it that way
so anyway exercise for the reader can
still remain but everything else all
right so so I just that I don't know I'm
just gonna go ahead and claim that that
was because maybe we like because of the
way we came at it we originally were
only loading one kind of file and then
we added multiple files and I don't like
I was gonna claim that that was just
like vestigial remain kind of stuff
because I'm I mean obviously when you
output a file and you put bitmaps in it
all of the bitmap IDs in that file would
just be relative to the file so if you
know where the file got loaded in the
asset indices it's just a given like
it's it it shouldn't be any more
complicated than that so I feel like
that was just a mistake and so I'm just
not gonna yeah I'm just gonna say that
that's not the way that goes right so
when we load in our Rho J's here I think
we could do the same thing we were doing
before with the tags so I'm just gonna
say look if there were assets in here
then we're gonna load them in
I guess we don't use we do we ever
because we need these to be kind of
expanded I guess so there's no point in
us loading it off of the base value so I
guess now think about it we don't really
care too much about that specifically so
I suppose that's okay
this right here is now known it's the
file asset base so we don't need that
this we also don't need because we know
that it's all the assets in the file so
we're gonna load you know all of them so
it's really just like file asset counts
and that's just the file header asset
count minus one so we can just do if
file header count off we go and this is
already looking much better so that's
nice we can start the temporary memory
here and do our load into the temporary
memory which is what we do we've got the
file asset count and make a temporary
array for it we read that out this is
just just one write we skip the null we
load that many and we then loop over
them like so and we go through each
asset that we loaded grafting it on to
the assets that we already have right
yeah that's really all there is to
that's I think so all of this stuff
should be right
yeah everything else seems right
so that should load all the assets in
and off you go so we now know that the
asset type ID in this this kind of asset
type ID that we're talking about here is
actually not the that this piece of
information actually isn't like the font
or whatever this is actually now a tag
right it's a tag in that's in the actual
tag array so in order to figure out
what's going on there we need a we need
to look it up in the tag itself right so
we actually have a thing here that's
like you know ask that type ID v-0 type
ID equals asset type what was it so all
right so we're gonna load this we need
here and say okay we now know what the
type ID for this thing is if we don't
find a tag which is it's nothing if we
do find a tag in the tag array and I
guess I we're gonna search the tag right
here that has that then that's the tag
that we use for it so we can loop over
the tiger right here HHA asset first tag
index
I guess I actually want to just do it
this way if that's where the tags are so
now when I loop through these I can just
look and say well whatever the tag is
for this if the ID of that tag is the
basic category then the type ID equals
that tags value and that's it
so asset index and file is always gonna
be bat
oops
and I'll forget all right so we've now
recompiled the game for loading the one
asset files and what we want to do now
is just take a look to see whether any
of it works at all right we're already
compiled in debug mode
I believe so we should be able to step
through this code pretty easily so let's
just see what happens when we do we end
up with an asset set that's got you know
whatever in it it's got a bunch of files
let's take a look at what they are it
says six so I'm gonna go ahead and look
at see what the six files are if I go
and actually view how many files there
are in here I see there's one two three
four five files which is you know not
six so I believe that's because we just
leave files 0 as an on file right that's
the like I don't have a file file ok
empty slot so we start with file 1 we
say ok that starts at 1 1 there's the
watermark which is where the data can be
appended we've got the header here's the
tags and the assets in there it says
that this thing whatever this file was
and I don't remember what it was
actually it had 203 201 so I'm assuming
that must have been the fonts isn't that
the only thing well it could have any
inch of art suppose yeah it was probably
in short there's probably that many
bitmaps in there so you know seems
alright everything looks ok there I
guess
seems alright again yeah alright
so it seems reasonable coming through
here we load in the tag array let's make
sure the file could read that okay
where's the no errors there it is no
where's one look at the asset count just
200 of them seems reasonable we're gonna
go ahead and load that we have an end
temp remember yeah we do
everything seems pretty good here
seems pretty good
all right I mean it seems all right
let's see if we get any errors here so
we are able to load the whole thing
[Music]
which is good so look successful the
tags are operating properly the search
is operating properly so that imported
everything correctly as far as I can
tell right so off we go right so that's
good so I think that really does leave
us I I can do some more work today I can
put 15 minutes into cleaning up the
rewrite part let's let's make sure also
that we are running at a reasonable
speed and that there isn't something
weird going on with the debug builds
well I mean with the release build but I
assume that was just the debug build
there yeah so everything looks good
there the one thing that I do think we
need to bug you could see that the fonts
are messed up right so that offsets we
got to go find out what's the deal with
that offset something weird is going on
with that offset right and I do not know
because I was just totally confused as
to why it's even doing what it's doing I
need
I need some to go refresh my memory as
to what was even going on there with the
fonts so if you look for example what's
happening here you can see that we're
only off by one I think because if you
look at what these values are showing us
you can see the the letters NT and if
you think about was supposed to go there
was milliseconds M s so if M s was what
was supposed to go there and n T is what
is there it means that we are seeing a
font glyph that is one away from what we
actually wanted so that offset is pretty
straight forward it's just off by one it
seems right
so this when we're coming through here
to load these out and we use that asset
base the asset base tells us where the
offs that would be but I guess if we
think about it it doesn't include the
fact that there was a zero right so if
so you need there to be the asset base
says I loaded here but I didn't load my
array I actually loaded one off from
there
right so technically like the asset base
is not really the asset count it's
really the asset count minus one because
everything you would have loaded is what
you slid over by the fact that we
removed the zero so I think that was
probably the only problem and yes I'm
correct
so I think we're all good
and our frame display is looking bad
our OpenGL renderer commands this is
sucking
is just like inaccurate or something cuz
it doesn't seem right when I look here
like I guess because these are getting
summed up is why but you can see that
like most of our time is spent waiting
around for open jail at the moment
yeah anyway so yeah moving on we are
completely upgraded to our new file
format now and that means we can at this
point change this file format around
however we want to and you know decide
on what we're gonna have for our v1 file
format and just do the conversion and be
done with it now I so what I want to do
now is just finish up what we were
trying to do with the asset importing
when we import now we have the ability
to store those annotations that means
that I think and I could be wrong about
this but I think if I want to I can
actually drive the asset source file
stuff here this can actually just be
driven off of the this can be driven off
of what comes out of the HHA right and
so what that means is that all of the
stuff like the asset index stuff all of
this stuff can when we load and act
assets out of the file if it has the
annotation array we can populate our
asset source file information directly
out of the HHA which means we wouldn't
have to store any longer we won't you
destroy any sideband information which
is pretty awesome because it means like
if you get an HH a from somebody if you
just pass around in HH a then you're
done you don't need you you don't need
to pass around like a text file that
also says like where the stuff come from
I think it's all kind of embedded in
there which seems good so I don't know
how much time I got left here I guess I
got 10 minutes left
[Music]
so I'm not really sure what I want to do
I might just want to go to QA because I
think the next thing we're going to want
to do is probably gonna be
more involved than something we're going
to do in ten minutes because basically
the next thing we want to do is we want
to we want to make the writing in the
annotation stuff work but we kind of
want to then go we're gonna want to do
that which take the thing a while and
then we're gonna want to start figuring
out how to do the tag like we need to
start creating some stuff and figure out
how we want these tags to work because
like we need to start going like okay
let's let's try to put all the art
assets into the game and how what is the
way that we want to specify that
information right and we're gonna have
to spend some time iterating over that
and like figuring out like okay what's
the most like what is the most robust
way of saying stuff like okay that you
know trying to create a floor tile in
the room generator how do i articulate
to the game asset system what I want
this floor tile to look like right and
there's a huge continuum to like a very
vague set of things like it's sort of
indoors and it's supposed to be wooden
and it's but you know right and it fuzz
aliy matches on that all the way to like
I want it to be bitmap 37 right and in
finding that middle ground is now we
because we need now we need it we have
art assets we've got to finally say
here's how they get looked up so we got
to consolidate the tag system and figure
out exactly how that works
so they're going to see that for next
weekend
and and we can go from there so I'll go
to the Q&amp;A now because I just don't feel
like starting on something I can't
finish or at least get some reasonable
amount of the way through
I will answer question I see from the
restream there it said have you tried LD
be I use that at work and it seems to be
stable I've not I probably should
because gdb is just awful it crashes a
lot like one out of every three runs for
me or so on a totally vanilla system
doesn't even have a GPU
it's an Intel integrated graphics so
it's not even using any proprietary
drivers
it's just vanilla Ubuntu and like geni
be like just doesn't even work it
crashes all the time and and it's not an
oh and I should mention it's a command
line app like I was debugging a Camille
and it doesn't open a window doesn't
talk to X Windows at all right it was
just like a C runtime library simple
application it opens some sockets and it
calls malloc like that's it gdb crashed
all the time to be fair I guess it links
with curl and curl is probably a big
sprawl so maybe there but I mean curl
doesn't open a window right so how come
the shader debug window with the grass
makes transparent pictures around the
main character white because we use
depth peeling and we only have a few def
peels so when you start to put debug
overlays on top it takes up the depth
peel that you would have used there that
that's what's happening
why is that there is no file file there
if it's in the way all the time it's so
that you can use file index zero to say
that you didn't come from a file or that
you're not talking about a file if you
need to run a bunch of Redick
substitutions on huge chunks of your
codebase how do you go about it I don't
I'd never do that I agree it would be
nice to be able to do that sometimes but
you know I've never really the problem
is just that you really don't want to do
code base wide substitutions
automatically with something that
doesn't understand code and we don't
have that right now like they're you
know if I say I want to change the
global variable that's named this to
this that's a really easy change that
should just be make that should just
work but because text editors only know
text and this is code it doesn't work
right so I tend to just since I don't
often have to do what you're talking
about I just do them manually when they
come up so that I can inspect every file
and I go through the changes to make
sure that's nothing screwy happened and
I wish that were not the case but like
that is currently the way I do it and
and you know there's there's been
refactoring tools and stuff that people
have created and like you know IDE
plug-ins for this sort of thing my
experience with those is they're always
more trouble than they're worth again
because I do this sort of sync thing so
infrequently those tools tend to be kind
of crappy and then now this is another
thing got to maintain and the versions
get off and it doesn't work or doesn't
support something I'm doing or it gets
confused by a macro or you know it's
just people have tried to make things to
do those sorts of joys that they often
just aren't good enough if I guess what
I would say
to be what they don't save more time
than they waste because I just don't
have to do that very often so
and by the way you don't need to put Q
colon in front of things you can put at
handmade hero that actually does work
it's just the Q colons a lot more
convenient so the the thing does the
thing grabs Q :
and at handmade hero it will grab I
think it all it also grabs at senior
Tori so it basically like if you try to
address a question to me using the
traditional trick - which way it will
work it's just a lot more typing for you
for no reason
compared to Q : if you're on a tool that
doesn't use autocomplete right oh yes
thank you
somebody took my name for mentioning
that the glyph didn't it seem am I the
only person who felt like the glyph
stuff printed out wrong or if it didn't
print out wrong then something's weird
about it anyway where did we print that
out here it is okay so yeah it was just
backwards so that's at least reassuring
that was just a simple typo
viii till VTL MKS not really a question
but why efi what problem did they make
up to have efi solve are you referring
to the bio standard I just wanna make
sure I don't answer a question that's
not the one you had like are you
referring to
I referring to this stuff yeah so
where to start as with most things I
don't think if I was making up a problem
to solve I think it was solving a
problem right
pretty much everything standards wise
that we make is in is in response to a
real problem however like many things
rather than solve the problem that it
was in response to what they actually do
is just create a lot of problems you
know and so most of the time standards
are just a mixed bag in that way if you
take a look at the bias that was
originally before EFI it was pretty good
right it was really easy to say here's
how you do a disk i/o here's how you
switch the mode of the graphics card
right it's easy to read it's easy to
program for it was really kind of
enjoyable right and easy but hey I do
you want to know if there's a USB device
connected do you want to boot off the
USB device right that's something that
we do all the time now is boot off of a
USB Drive for example right well that's
not in the original BIOS stuff there
wasn't USB when the BIOS original IBM
BIOS stuff was specified right and so at
some point because remember the IBM PC
specification was originally created by
IBM that's why it was called IBM PC and
it was created at a time when there were
very very few things
- for the computer to do and so those
were the things that were in there you
know was there was a fixed keyboard kind
of interface a fixed Mouse if any you
know that I don't even think the mouse
made the mask may have not even been
there in the original ones you know and
so there were just a lot of things that
were really pretty under specified in
that original spec and so at some point
you know somebody has to say here's how
we're going to handle all these new
things and so EFI was necessary and UEFI
were necessary to address those missing
features as PC hardware started having
more and more things that needed to
happen at buy us time because you know
you can have drivers and stuff and do
things that way once the operating
system is actually booted but where does
the operating system come from right the
BIOS has to be able to bootstrap things
together and if you fundamentally don't
have a BIOS that understands a bunch of
things that happen in a modern PC then
that doesn't work so I totally
understand why you might think efi is
bad it's isn't good but that doesn't
mean that the thing that was before it
was sufficient it wasn't so really what
we would say is we wish they had made
you a UEFI better than it was but I
don't think you want to go back to the
time before it because then you'd be
giving up most of the things you can do
with your computer today you know you
would have to use a floppy drive to boot
and stuff right um well not really you
could boot off a hard drive but how
would you have installed the stuff on
the hard drive you would have had to
boot off a floppy and that floppy would
have to have contained drivers for your
USB stack which you then could plug a
drive into I'm not exaggerating that's
really what would have to have
the other thing you could have done was
they could have had a legacy mode that
if you that had a USB port that if you
plug to drive into it it had a driver
for the USB specifically on a by us on
that port that then made it look like an
old like 80 hard drives that worked with
the by us you know so you know you could
get around since but you see how janky
it is right like so it's not
unreasonable that they wanted to come up
with something new it's just that we you
know do would it be nice it'd have been
better sure not the same thing as saying
that it was superfluous darks bright
it's been even off time a question I
found you talk about gjk and implemented
it for my project but now I don't know
what to do to resolve collisions when I
detect them what should I tell I don't
know what do you want to do in your game
when things collide
I am NOT I'm not sure how to answer that
question
there are ways of extending gjk to find
the time of intersection which may help
you
you can add the motion vector into the
gjk solve and then back out of the gjk
solve and figure out which face you left
through there's there's some stuff you
can do there but
can you give advice for someone who
wants to drop out of college and just
finally get a programming job or is it a
big no-no nowadays to do so I so what I
can only tell you secondhand information
because I don't work with large hiring
organizations or anything like that
here's what I'll tell you from what I
have seen almost no interviewers or
hiring managers at software companies
care if you have a cs degree so it is
true that you'd probably don't need to
finish your CS degree to pass that part
if you are good but here is the rub in
order to get to that stage right you
would have had to go through some kind
of screening process through human
resources or however that company
screens their applicants if that company
screens their applicants based on
whether they have CS degrees you'll
never get the interview right so I think
you have to first sit back and ask
yourself where am I going to try and get
a job and what do I think the chances
are that I can ever get a foot in the
door there without a CS degree right
because remember there's a lot of things
that a CS degree gets you that have
nothing to do with programming
connections with you know that your
professor might have to get you a job
access to job fairs where people recruit
at your college campus just the fact
that you have a CS degree means you
might be able to apply for immigration
lotteries right like in the u.s. if you
have a degree and you're from outside
the US you are more likely I think to
get a limitation visas for working here
I don't know if that's still true but
it was true at the time there's there's
all kinds of reasons why a CS degree may
be important to your future that have
nothing to do with whether you learned
anything while you were there right so
you can't just think of the degree sadly
you know we think of college as a place
you go to learn stuff it's not only that
it's the first part of a filtering
process that other companies use to
determine who they're gonna hire and you
have to be aware of that just because
that seems unfair or unnecessary doesn't
matter because all that matters is that
it's true right right so you have to be
realistic when you're weighing your
options about that it may be true that C
s degree is a waste of time it may be
that you aren't going to learn anything
useful there I'm not saying that's true
I'm just saying let maybe that is true
but if that is true those are not the
that is not dispositive that does it
tell you therefore there's no reason to
stick it out and finish that's not true
there are a number of reasons why that
CS degree as simply a piece of paper may
be important to you so be sure you
understand those trade-offs before you
drop out of college or believe that your
CS degree is not going to be valuable to
you because it's not just what you learn
it's also what other people have put in
place as barriers that CS degrees allow
you to bypass so just keep that in mind
the second part of the question is how
do I get a programming job with that or
without the CS degree I think to a large
extent it depends on where you're what
kind of jobs are applying for
demonstrating that you have skills he's
a good way to go why should I hire you
there's tons of people out there who
program computers most of them are lousy
and I
want to hire them so my question is why
should I hire you right what makes me
think that you are going to be the kind
of person worth spending time on to
bring onto my team teach how to do what
we're doing and like that you will start
contributing if I can go to a webpage
like if you've got a blog or something
and I can see you have posted write-ups
about stuff that seems like you've done
investigation to things that you've
explored things that you know how to
program that you've made some
interesting programs that you understand
how they work right that can be a big
plus
I think programming is more like art in
that way in some cases that other people
think if I can see a portfolio of a
programmer I am much more likely to want
to talk to that programmer and ask them
questions and see if they're good then
if I just you know you just say I worked
here or I went to school here you know I
want to see some stuff you know and you
know at the pro level you can see the
like dream version of this like go look
at Fabien G's ins blog right let's say
you didn't know who he was and and his
resume comes across your desk it's not
going to because you know there's a line
a mile long of people who would want to
hire him if he ever left his current job
so not relevant but you get a look at
his blog and it's just entry after entry
of really detailed tactical analysis of
things you just know that person is
gonna be someone you're gonna want to
interview you know now there could still
be reasons why maybe a person with a
blog like that isn't someone you want to
hire maybe it turns out they don't do
work very much they just do blog entries
and stuff so they explore all these
topics but they don't never get anything
done right that could be true but you at
least know that person is worth your
time to interview so when you see
someone who's like here's all this stuff
I've got
check it out like I care a lot about
tech I do a lot of work programming I'm
really interested in learning new things
and figuring stuff out please talk to me
if if I can see that you've done stuff
I'm like ah right like good now I feel
comfortable saying let's spend an hour
talking to this person because I don't
any longer have to guess about whether
they might be the kind of person who
could you know who has the intellectual
curiosity necessary to be a contributing
member of a tech team so that's what I
would say first understand whether you
need to see us degree or not I'm not in
a position to be able to tell you that
because I think it's highly context
dependent you may need one you may not
and then second figure out why you are
different from every other person who's
applying for a programming job if you
can't answer that question fairly
definitively then you had better stay
with your cs2 tree right because if you
if you are not the point yet where you
could demonstrate why you are an
important person interview then you need
all the help you can get right you are
not in a position to drop out and try to
get a programming job if you're just
gonna look like everybody else so figure
that out figure out how you're gonna get
my attention and when I say that I mean
hrs or hiring managers attention not me
because I'm not gonna hire you obviously
but you know whoever it is that you're
trying to get a job from long boolean a
bit confused by our answer because I
have booted from USP on pre UEFI systems
I'm missing something I believe those
were exactly the kind as I described so
pre UEFI I believe the way that it
worked was the thing that I literally
said they had a certain USB port that if
you plugged the USB Drive into that port
it would make a if it had you know a
standard fat32 filesystem monitor
something
it would allow you to make it look like
a drive to legacy by us
and I'm pretty sure that's the only
reason that stuff worked it would like
basically make it if they basically
implemented us a USB Drive protocol for
a limited set of USB Drive scenarios on
to a port so if they just looked for
that when you plugged it in and went so
they basically what they had done is a
non-standard Yui
UEFI style boot right they because
there's nothing to stop a system
manufacturer from making their own bias
that does all this crazy stuff but that
no one can access so it just makes
everything kind of look like it used to
oh you plug in a USB mouse well we wired
that up to look like a ps2 Mouse right
they can do all that stuff and BIOSes
did but it's all non-standard and you
can't write anything like a Linux boot
loader that uses it or Windows can't
take advantage of that to help you
install the system and blah blah blah
right so it's it's just about
standardizing that so people can work
with it instead of just making entirely
custom to one bias and it can only do
the things that they decided to
implement in the way they decided to
implement them period right can you give
an overview how you've structured your
web programming and see I've heard you
mention it in some stream on how you
made certain components behind the
handmade here website in C or at least
more sanely program than most web
frameworks it really interests me could
you give me some ore info well I mean
sort of basically we have a a/c system
that generates all of the website that's
static so everything that doesn't and
static is a loose term here obviously
it's all updatable but static meaning it
doesn't change like minute to minute it
changes like day to day right so for
example the handmade hero's schedule
make change frequently or wet whether or
not I'm online streaming might change
frequently whereas the content of our
website might only change once a week
like when we post a blog or something so
there's a C system that just generates
all of the everything for the website
that doesn't change more frequently than
once a day or every day or two right or
you know week a month greater than day
granularity and all that stuff just gets
uploaded to a CDN just as a giant bulk
it's just like blah right here's the
whole site everything is generated so
that basically takes you know all of the
pieces and welds them together into
static pages so they can be served
quickly you know because obviously you
know the button bar at the top of 30
pages is the same but you don't want to
be pulling that in dynamically because
that just wastes time and it's a slower
page experience so that happens all that
stuff gets pushed the CDN then there's a
separate server for handling dynamic
stuff running a C program that basically
answers queries as just a simple Apache
cgi-bin I would like it to not be that
but I just haven't gone the extra mile
yet and made my own web server I
probably will someday because Apache is
a piece of crap and I hate it and the
configuration is ridiculous the way it
works and cgi-bin is garbage so I don't
like that either I don't like anything
about it I could split the difference in
make an Apache module but I really don't
kind of want to go down that route so at
some point I'll probably make something
that just sits on the ssl port and
watches for packets and responds to them
appropriately but at the moment i'm not
doing that at the moment I just run
Apache with a CGI bin what that does is
it just provides any dynamic stuff
it's a C program it knows when it gets a
request those requests are usually sent
as URL encodes pretty much exclusively
so the only communication into that is a
URL basically right it just it hits it
with URL it decodes the URL and figures
out the parameters are based on that it
then sends a JSON file back the reason
it sends a JSON files that seemed like
the most compatible thing like the web
browser just has a JSON parser in it so
you can don't have to add any additional
JavaScript code to parse something you
can just run the jace json parser so
again keeping it's all about keeping the
page size small for me so that seemed
like the simplest way so it sends a tiny
little json packet back with the
information that was requested and
that's it that's the entire web
architecture and by the way we have the
fastest page i've ever used like i go to
our web site on a mobile phone and i'm
like clicking the thing and it's so fast
and responsive and i then switch to like
twitter and it's nuts it takes like
seven years and i'm looking what is
going on right so i don't know what web
devs are ostensibly doing other than
sucking like it's just like the web
should be instant I can prove that
because ours is and I do not know why
nothing should be slower than our
website right I have no idea why
everything's so slow you go and you look
and it's nuts even the things that if
the things that we don't make on our
website are super slow YouTube we have
some embedded YouTube videos super slow
send owls purchase button super slow it
takes longer to push the send a purchase
button than it does to load our entire
page like eight times longer right
it's it's embarrassing
how about luring some online curses at
Python or something I have no idea what
that means you talked about people they
need to see the supposed to be hard for
angels did you mean
oopsie puss fuss with compile times
linked to lunch breaks do you think you
would need to bone up on nurses to do so
try yeah kind of I mean I think that any
project that takes longer than a few
seconds to compile is messed up right
like a ten-second compile is already a
bit too long and so if you're you know
if you can't compile your product in ten
seconds you got a big problem so I think
these soups evil ESCO bases are
ridiculous
right I think they're just wrong I think
they're just wrongheaded the way they're
designed but what me thinking they're
wrongheaded and that there are jobs to
work on them are two totally different
things
there are tons and tons and tons of code
bases like that out there that are
accused sprawling oop messes tons of
templates all over the place they take
forever to compile it's nuts there are
many many many jobs working on them so
if you are looking for a job and you're
not like some amazing superstar
programmer that everyone wants to hire
so you can just you know pick the three
places that don't have weird code bases
like that and be you know picky then you
need to know that stuff right because if
you don't know that stuff then you know
you you're not really qualified to work
there now you may still pass the
interview right so maybe you can learn
that stuff on the job right I don't know
but it's entirely possible that they
include sort of some at least basic OOP
C++ template nonsense in their
interviews or in their programming
problems they give you those and so I
don't think you really want to go into a
job interview not knowing that stuff
right I mean maybe this wasn't clear but
I actually know a ton about the original
C++ programming I mean I
written templatized math libraries I
wrote crazy I've done templatized
callback
funky doll that back in the day I just
thought it was bad so I stopped right so
saying that that's not the way I think
you should be programming because I feel
like it leads to bad results is
different from saying you can just not
learn it because unless you always
program it by yourself or you happen to
be lucky enough to be hired by a team
who's sensible which there aren't that
many of it's gonna it's gonna be
relevant you know it's gonna be relevant
and you have to be aware of that that's
why it's a job that's why you get paid
to do it right if it was always your way
all the time that's not a job anymore
right that's that's just recreational so
you know one of the ways that you earn
your money is by programming some stuff
you don't want to do right and you just
have to think of that is that way how
can you create an interesting portfolio
for back-end developers I can't make
fancy sites because I know nothing about
design well let's let's take a look
suppose on my back-end developer because
hey I was I did the backend for Molly
rocket comm right here's one of our
sites so suppose you don't know how to
make any of this stuff and you're like I
don't know I want to show my back-end
development skills whatever well here's
the people we tried to use for our
mailing list originally don't ever use
them for mailing lists they literally
are completely incompetent in all
possible ways I don't even want to go
into how many things are broken about
their service it's nuts it's really
really really bad and you won't know
that it's broken until you start
actually auditing it and figure out that
half of the people who try to sign up
for your mailing list don't actually get
signed up it's it's really bad there
they are really really bad all right so
let's take a look and see if they have a
demonstration
on here I just want to see if they've
got something where I can do like male
jet demo site like can we try one
unfortunately I'm I'm guessing that I
can't come on folks
you must have a demo site somewhere
right
I need to find a place where I can need
to find a place where I could sign up
for this for like a mailing list right
don't you have a mailing list somewhere
actually don't they have a mailing list
shouldn't a mailing list company have a
mailing list I can sign up for here it
is all right so let's suppose I want to
sign up for this mailing list right like
hey I want to sell it for the mint for
the mail jet newsletter right one two
done right so now we know like how long
that thing takes to two to go I suppose
I should have did that poorly
I'm trying to think if there's some way
I can make this trigger automatically
all right here we go so let's see where
we actually hit this button right trying
to see if there's a good click somewhere
here right there I think here it is user
verify right all right so we started
clicking somewhere in here see if I can
get a better
that's the reCAPTCHA
so it's something my count was about
right seems like maybe hard to say
transform time I need to get a good I
want to have a good way of measuring how
the performance is of this thing to
control II assume control eat stops it
to let's see
ready it doesn't
I really really want to get a good
performance thing of this here right
there should be a way that says profile
on click you know I'm Santa like I'm
gonna click please record this control
he just jumps up there so you have to
have the it looks like you have to have
the focus in here which is not great so
that's mostly it like we've mostly got
it here right now so you can see here
that's about the two seconds that I
thought right and you can see like
everything that's going on there right
I'm not sure why how long it takes for
the recapture to work there is there any
kind of event thing that I can look
interactions there we go mouse down so
you can see here it's it's roughly the
two seconds that I thought that's
perfect that's what I wanted there's the
mouse down right and then we know that
we get it right about there right so
that's where we actually start so we can
drag back to the mouse down which i
think was right here
and this is the performance for there
for you know for their website stuff now
what's interesting about this is you
notice it doesn't really work so that's
the first thing I can show you like so
now now that I've said that so there's
an example of a mailing list site and
you could go to MailChimp as well or
some other sites into it so there's an
example of a mailing with service you'll
notice it didn't even tell me that I was
already subscribed right so it didn't
tell me any information or anything when
I put my my email address in there so it
really was just two seconds and then
nothing happened like I don't even get
confirmation other than just that I
subscribed but that's not true because
obviously the second time I didn't also
subscribe right so it's a bit weird but
anyway so it's not great it took two
seconds so then you know let's go over
here two hours or whatever and let's
just see how we compare right what do we
do a good enough job to replace whatever
the other thing was so here's Casey moly
rocket comm record subscribe there we go
so let's see how our performance was
right where's our mouse down those are
all Mouse moves there's the mouse down
right here alright
now let's take a look at where it was
right there
looks like the mousedown was right about
there you can see this that's right
button laid up
maybe Mouse down
looks like it's right there right so
here's our actual time slider you can
see it's maybe about 300 milliseconds I
think a little hard to say uh so we are
we're not quite ten times faster but
we're over five times faster then their
website is and we actually know what
happened right
so we also tell you there's a back-end
demo right record that show people put
this on a blog here we timed how long it
takes for the user response common sites
take two three four seconds maybe more
we take 200 milliseconds because our
back-end is awesome and we don't run 50
million lines of PHP code right plus we
tell you our back-end knows what's
happening theirs doesn't right I don't
know so I think you can make arguments
that again and just to be clear you
don't even have to necessarily be better
like the fact that we're way faster them
I think is cool because I like being
better than people who aren't good at
things but the point is just that you
look into it like you've demonstrated
that you can analyze the performance of
something you know how long something
could take you have some ideas about why
it you know why something did or didn't
work right you know how to investigate
problems whatever right like showing
that you know how to dig into the
technical details of something that you
understand the difference between your
product and competitors products you
know how to take assessments of
different aspects of the package to see
whether they're working these things are
things you can show you know how to do
you don't need a flashy website I mean
I'm not really a front-end developer
either right you know you can make flash
your websites than this to be sure right
but the
the point is just for the thing that
you're working on show you know how to
investigate it improve it understand
what's involved show how to analyze
other people's and yours and why are
yours better or different right or even
just this the same but you knew to look
at those features look we are comparable
to male Jets blah right does that make
sense
have you read out of tar pit no I have
not
have you checked out cor dot IO
webserver written in C I have not Apache
is also written in C is it not I use I
do use a C I use a a C based web server
internally for testing
it's called Mongoose lid micro HTTP D is
pretty good if far as I can tell okay
I ought to check it out do you have any
advice for putting are having trouble to
adjust to it OOP way of thinking on the
job and how to cope with or handle
patterns not really just I mean just
understand what they are they're
people's ways of applying boilerplate
code to a problem right so you just have
to understand you know it's the same as
speaking a foreign language right you
know if you go to France you have to
speak in French when you're in a new
code base you have to understand their
way of speaking you don't have to think
it's a good language but you do have to
understand how to speak it what kind of
products would be interesting for
recruiters to look at for example at the
moment I work on 3d rasterizer and x86
assembly using mode 13 with a DOS
emulator yeah again the project is
probably not the interesting thing
because unless you're so good that
you're gonna make something that like no
one else has ever made before in which
case you know obviously you're gonna get
a job it's not the project type that's
important it's the what you show about
what you knew and did right put up some
blog posts about you analyze it if
you're doing an x86 assembly mode 13
rasterizer show talk about the assembly
why did you make certain choices show
that you time different ways of doing it
what turned out to be fast what turned
out to be slow
under DOSBox you know do do something
that lets me know that you didn't just
copy it out of Michael Abrash his book
right but that's that's all you know you
just need to show that you were
intellectually curious you investigate
things you understand you don't just
cotton copy copy and paste you're not
just searching Stack Exchange right just
give me the what I need to understand
that you know what you are doing when
you come to a problem and you spend time
on it you come away with an
understanding of how it works and if you
approach it logically and intelligently
that's just really all you need to show
because most programmers don't anymore
not anymore you know
Upland cooter that's not technically a
data breach because it does not tell you
anything about whether that person
actually subscribed right they can't
necessarily tell you if the person
confirmed the thing right so I suppose
that's true right but it's not a data
breach because all it says is whether a
particular email address is on or off
the list which you can add one yourself
so you have no idea who added it right
but I agree that since mail jet does a
thing where you're not considered on the
list until you confirm the address
I suppose that is a data breach because
basically you're telling them whether
they confirmed or not sort of I mean I
don't know how what to think about that
right
I'm pretty sure we are GDP are compliant
I read it very carefully and it says as
long as the person has shown interest
then you can mail them and if you mail
them they have to be able to instantly
unsubscribe which they can right you do
not need to add an unchecked by default
checkbox
I challenge you to show me the place in
the gdpr where it said that I found no
such such thing and there's all you also
I did not find anything that said double
verification emails right because you're
gonna get one email either way so the
actual number of emails you send is not
different I do agree that maybe we
should not tell you if the person has
unsubscribed because unsubscribe
is an action that the person takes that
is verifiable to them like if you
unsubscribe you had to have received an
email at the address that has been
entered so that is tactically
information probably so we should
probably only say whether the email
address has ever been entered into the
form so for example if you unsubscribe I
don't know I don't know if there's a I
can't think of an address that's
unsubscribed at the moment but if you
unsubscribe from the mailing list we
probably shouldn't tell anyone else that
of course then I'm not sure how that
person here's a gdpr puzzle for you
how would that person ever get back on
the mailing list because once they tell
you that they don't want your email
anymore
you can't email them so if you don't
tell them on the website how would they
ever actually get back on the mailing
list
that's a little puzzle that's a little
puzzle European Union
what's the answer to that question I'm
really interested to know now does
anyone know because like what we do is
if you enter the email address it would
tell you that's unsubscribe so you have
to email us to say right but technically
now I think about we shouldn't do that
we should turn that off because it is
telling you whether somebody
unsubscribed if somebody unsubscribed we
can't mail them so if they put their
address in here to try to re-subscribe
we can tree subscribe them can we
because they told us never to email them
it just seems like you know yeah because
and that would be bad too because then
other people could just spam their email
address in there and they said they
didn't want to hear from us right so I
wouldn't really be comfortable doing
that
see what it says
let's see
[Music]
this link doesn't really say my guess is
like many things in the GDP are it's
under specified
I don't know maybe we should write a
blog post about it and then send it to
the EU be like hey what do you do here
right
if you unsubscribe from a mailing list
so you have a mailing list and you don't
want it to send any unnecessary emails
so you type in an email address you hit
subscribe the only thing the person will
receive is a mailing this email with an
unsubscribe button on it right you don't
want to say whether that person has ever
accepted any emails from you right
because that would leak data as pointed
out before so you just say whether an
email address has ever been entered into
the form because that's meaningless
anyone can enter anyone's email address
into the form you're not telling anyone
anything right but someone unsubscribes
from an email now you know that that
person actually unsubscribe because that
like we the unsubscribe link has a
unique cookie on it so that no one can
unsubscribe you other than you right if
someone hits that unsubscribe button we
can't send the emails anymore but we
also can't tell them that on the website
potentially because then someone else
could enter their email address and find
out that they are unsubscribed which I
don't know maybe that's not a gdpr
violation but it certainly is at least a
slight data leakage so what would the
gdpr prefer you do right and I don't
know I mean this is one of the problems
with government regulations they
oftentimes aren't actually practically
useful because the people who wrote them
don't really know very much about what
they're regulating a lot of the time and
they haven't thought it all the way
through so I don't know they probably
don't know but maybe they do know and if
they do know they could tell us and then
we could comply with it
whatever the opinion actually is maybe
the answer is it should be exact like it
is now because hey knowing that someone
else unsubscribed from an email address
really doesn't tell you anything right
if you have not previously unsubscribed
wait what that wasn't on the link was
right see that on the link you see here
oops wrong keyboard
yeah that's not in there anywhere
if he unsubscribes he has to accept the
terms again a checkbox when he enters
the email address and wants to subscribe
again yeah but okay so here's my opinion
on that like I disagree with that now
maybe the gdpr is just poorly
constructed but I think that's a really
bad policy if that's true
because anybody can fill out a form and
check that box right so if you don't
have a one-click permanent unsubscribe a
griefer can just sit there Ries absque
reiben you all day long and you'll just
keep getting confirmation emails right a
confirmation email is still an email
right that this is one of the thing I
think a lot of like regulations don't
understand a confirmation you must still
an email is an emailing didn't want
right so I feel like once somebody
subscribes to something or is subscribe
to something whether they did it or not
a pushing up there should be a button
you can push that blocks you from ever
getting email from that people again
right that are found that is what we
have but if someone's trying to
subscribe and they are not getting it
they may have forgotten that they on
subscribed or something and so I wanted
them to have some way of it telling you
here email us you know
you know what here's what we could do
maybe this is the best solution may be
the right solution is just to make the
email make the response to any email
address that has already been put on the
list or unsubscribed the same because
then you're not leaking any data then
all you're saying is at some point in
the past somebody put this email address
into this field but you have no idea
whether it was actually the person who
did it and you have no idea whether
they're so subscribed maybe it just says
this email address was already entered
into our system please email us if you
would like to make changes that doesn't
leak any data right I like that uh you
know I like that better I'm gonna change
it to that you know regardless I don't
really care whether that's required by
the GDP it's just better it's better to
not leak information so I'm just gonna
say that that is what it is because
that's the minimal that's the minimum
amount of information leakage I could
think of that still works and doesn't
ever allow confirmation emails to just
pile up by look at griefer
so at that's that's what I'm that's I'm
claiming that's the best solution
alright I'm done for the day
close it up
okay thank you for joining us from
episode of hand made here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with
series at home you can always go to
handmade hero org and pre-order the game
it comes with the source code so that
you can play around with it yourself and
you can try things and and you know do
some experiments we also have obviously
have a mailing list you can sign up for
which we just showed demo if you want to
sign up for our mailing list it's right
there we also have a handmade hero
that's our handmade community fund you
could check out that's something that
funds various things like our anti
episode guide or the handmade Network
forum stuff like that and it also comes
with some fun stuff if you sign up for
that like that tab you app that I was
using today and a bunch of other things
old source code by me from the from the
good old days so check out that button
it's a pretty interesting thing to check
there's a little video on it as well
also got a watch page which is the thing
where you can watch the series it's got
a twitch viewer on it but it also has a
thing that shows the schedule so you
know went up when streams are going to
be coming and it's got a episode guide
on it which allows you to search the old
episodes which is pretty awesome you can
quickly get to old episodes so that's
pretty great too if you're trying to
watch old verses this series and you
only want to look at things that pertain
to a subject matter your particulars to
did finally click on the handmade hero
ahead if you want to check out some of
our other stuff
malee rocket we got other cool products
in the works for you to explore that's
it for this weekend I'll be back next
weekend where are we gonna have to
finally wrestle with the tagging problem
we're gonna have to decide how we're
gonna do that hopefully it's not that
bad hopefully we're just like hey this
looks good this is how we want to do it
convenient it lets us get our assets
into the game quickly happy birthday
maybe it'll be more of a struggle and we
you'll have to really fight tooth and
nail to find something that we think
works well and satisfies our other
constraints only one way to find out
come back here next week and we will see
until then thanks for joining me
everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet