hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are trying streaming
from the new office location so it's a
little bit tricky I'm not sure whether
or not this is going to work exactly we
tried streaming for a while before
before starting the stream here it was a
little bit dicey initially I thought it
wasn't going to work but then it turned
out that it was just Comcast was gating
our speed in a weird way that they
weren't supposed to below what it was
supposed to be but rebooting the cable
modem seems to fix it and so it maybe
it's working ok now I don't really know
it's a little bit suspicious and it's
one of those things we're probably going
to have to give them a call and find out
because I'm afraid that it's something
that may be happening periodically in
which case we're going to constantly
have to struggle with it but we're going
to give it a shot and we'll see what we
can do we'll see if we can get some
programming out of it and and who knows
so anyway here's a 403 we'll do the best
we can if it turns out the recording
here locally as far as we know works
just fine obviously so if something
happens to the stream partway through I
do apologize we'll just assume that we
you can catch the video on demand when
it's posted up on YouTube right so let's
go ahead and get started today is day
403 I'm going to go ahead and open up
the code base here it's been a while I
don't know why this keeps okay um there
we go
didn't really want that window hanging
around for the entire time we were going
to be programming so it's good that we
were able to get rid of that little
thing anyway so let's go ahead and run
it we were in the middle of playing with
lighting and at the moment we are in a
reasonably good position with lighting
the problem is we just need to start
working out how we're going to propagate
light in
a reasonably high quality way so at the
moment we've kind of got this little
lighting test that you're running
entirely on the CPU side now so it's not
particularly good in terms of speed but
we're just trying to get to a point
where we can verify that the quality is
roughly what we want it to be and and
that's going to require us doing a
little more thinking about how we're
transferring light you can kind of see
that at the moment it is at least
working to a certain extent it's not a
great lighting solution but we are at
least get you know what we're looking at
here is just just sort of block lighting
in fact I can show you the actual lights
here in a second let's see here here we
go this is actually what we're
simulating here just these little sort
of light reflectors and what we don't
really know at the moment is exactly how
we want to transfer light between them
we've sort of done a few things this
right now is using a sort of stochastic
like a ray casting technique this just
looks at different reflectors versus
each other sees how much each reflector
can see each other reflector is in a
sort of like randomized fashion and then
propagates the light around and as you
can see some of that stuff works pretty
well actually and at the speed that it's
running now probably we would actually
even be able to once this is running GPU
side that's probably actually fine as
weird as that seems so you know speed
wise we don't even really have that much
of a problem at the moment I don't think
but what we do want to do before we go
any further down that road is just try
to do something with the quality so
there's two ways we can sort of go about
looking at the quality at the moment or
rather I shouldn't say two ways perhaps
the right way to say it would be there's
two things we need to look at in terms
of quality at the moment and one of them
is just the fact that we are not really
taking
care in how we're transferring light
around and obviously that's something we
can sort of start to improve by
tightening down the equations and doing
a more sensible approach to how we move
the light but the other thing that's
particularly interesting here is we have
not yet put in anything that operates in
a multi resolution fashion and we're
going to want to do that as well even
just for quality and so let me go to the
blackboard assuming that the blackboard
is working here I assume I reset up the
pen properly don't actually know that I
did but we hope that I did
okay it looks not gonna do it so today
is day four a three is that correct man
so it isn't it's so interesting we we
really need to checked on that Milton
bug it's like when Milton loses like
when that thing pops up in front of
Milton it loses the ability to access
the tablet I have no idea why and it's
not repeatable either right like there
it is here we go and there it is still
so you know it wasn't a problem that
time you know anyway so let's let's just
talk about
let's just talk about multi-resolution
and quality in terms of lighting so what
we have right now is we've got you know
if I was going to look top down here you
know we've got some stuff that looks
kind of like this we've got these little
reflectors and what we're seeing is
we've got these reflectors that are sort
of passing rays out to see what they
could hit right and obviously the
quality of the light transfer is you
know besides the equation that tells us
how much light we want to transfer when
we actually see another reflector we
obviously have a number of issues there
which are just related to how many of
these rays we shoot and in what
direction will materially affect the
quality of our solution because you know
no matter we're not going to be able to
shoot out like a million rays right the
number is not going to be high it's
going to be like you know 8 or 16 or at
best on the GPU something like 256 if we
got really obsessive but whatever it is
you have to remember it's trying to
encompass an entire hemisphere right and
a hemisphere is an entire
three-dimensional shape and you know 16
samples even 32 samples just isn't a
very dense sampling of the hemisphere
when you start to think about just how
wide of a net it has to cast and to give
you something understanding exactly how
ridiculous it is I mean imagine if you
were not going to have any kind of
intelligent handling of casting through
to clean and you wanted to have a
situation where you were just going to
simulate let's say sunlight or something
right
well if even in 2d right if the Sun is
you know this sort of thing way way off
in the distance then if you just cast
even just a little bit to either side of
it right you would miss because the Sun
is so tiny and it's so far away the
chances that you'll aim directly at it
with a random sample are actually very
low and so no matter how many samples
you take unless that that number is in
the astronomical up to an astronomical
level you're never going to hit it and
that is why different techniques are
used for sampling light sources and
things like this that have a low
probability of being hit often times
what you'll do is you'll intentionally
aim blue tuned right at the light source
so when you're picking which directions
to send rays oftentimes you'll send one
directly at the light source
intentionally and that's like one of the
cheats that you do it's one of the
things that allows that to happen
however one of the problems here is that
that only works when you know ahead of
time what a light source actually is and
so that helps you for emitters but what
about secondary emitters right it
doesn't help you at all for those so
what happens is if I have like a really
bright light source over here and it's
shining in this direction yes it may
help me to grab it by knowing that it's
an emitter I can always check to see if
I see the admit err and waste array on
that all the time but at that point this
guy who can't see the emitter back here
he is going to try to look around his
scene and he doesn't have any special
knowledge that this is a place where a
lot of lights going to be coming from
because it's the thing that has the
primary bounce from this light source
which may be where most of the lights
coming from so that again is a problem
where you don't necessarily know where
you should be focusing your attention
and this becomes a more significant
problem as you try to do more sort of
global illumination schemes that involve
those secondary bounces because you
never know where you should be looking
to find out now sometimes you can use
hybrid approaches that are like forward
schemes and that may be
thing that we will do what what that
basically entails is saying well okay
let's say that we take the light source
let's cast outward from the light source
instead of backwards from the reflectors
and let's just tag anything we hit so
when we come out here we'll just tag
like a bunch of things that we hit you
know and those will now become our
secondary light sources right that
allows us to know sort of a set of
places where we should probably be
concentrating our efforts in terms of
looking for light and that's a good
strategy and like I said we may use some
like that but there's another strategy
that we probably need to use and that is
the multi resolution approach and the
multi resolution approach is just saying
that well look we know that when we
start to cast these rays out when we're
very close to the surface we probably
have a really good sampling if there's a
light right up here we know that most of
our rays are going to hit it so we don't
have to worry about sampling the
hemisphere very densely because most of
those rays are very close together when
you've only gotten say a foot away from
the reflector surface or an inch away or
something like this right the closer the
better for keeping the hemisphere nicely
sampled but what happens and the part
that we're most concerned about and you
can see it here in 2d is as I send rays
out further right
what may be a very dense sampling in
here becomes a fairly sparse sampling
out here and when I get you know far
enough out it becomes a massively sparse
sampling so you know there's joy ganthet
gaps in the sampling as you get further
away and that's just the nature of a
radial distribution a uniform sampling
of an angular space just produces
coarser and coarser samplers samples as
you expand the radius of the sampling
surface that's just you know you can see
that very intuitively there's not a lot
of mystery to it that's just the way it
goes so what that means and the reason
why I bring up multi-resolution
is that no matter what you do it really
doesn't matter what you do even if you
have sort of a forward scheme like I was
talking about the light sources before
or if you send out a ton of samples it
doesn't matter at all you will not get a
good result for faraway things unless
you have some kind of strategy that
takes into account the fact that when
you get out here you want to use a more
coarse representation of the world so
you can find out what's probably going
on right and what I mean by that is if I
have a you know some reflectors out here
like this sort of thing and I'm casting
out into them what I really want to know
is I don't really want to just miss
these like so right or maybe only hit
this one and never hit these other ones
by all these three rays what I really
want to do is form an aggregate
reflector that's fairly large that just
says how much these generally would
reflect from how far away they are and
that way all of these samples will get
it right and in the best possible world
you have roughly a one-to-one
correspondence of what you're saying the
Rays you're sampling and how you've
compressed your geometry so that each
sample does a maximal amount of work but
you know anywhere close is probably fine
so when you look at that hopefully what
that you know sort of indicates is
that sort of an LOD scheme right a level
of detail scheme like we normally would
do where we are collapsing nearby things
that are similar together is exactly
what we actually want for lighting as
well because when we are looking off in
the distance to say how much light is
coming from a relatively far away piece
of geometry we don't really need the
exact answer for diffuse lighting for
specular lighting we might want the
exact answer because if for a mirror or
something we want to know exactly what
we hit right but for diffuse lighting
that's not we want we just want to know
the general amount of light and sort of
what color it is from that direction we
don't need to know specifically what's
going on so what we actually want again
is something that operates very much
like a cone right that collects all the
things in this area and a cone is
relatively hard to deal with so
preferably what we would like to do is
be able to sample just say a line in a
direction and that line instead
who-who's what I'm so Yanni lately I'm
not sure why I guess I happen to get
enough sleep I don't know I think it's
more that my schedule got shifted up
because it's brutally hot here in
Seattle like not maybe necessarily by
the standards of other parts of the
world that are more tropical but in
Seattle it's usually relatively cool and
I you know we don't have a hundred
degree day weather days here that's not
a thing not it's not like you know
Phoenix Arizona or something like this
and what we've been getting lately is
sort of a heat wave where the
temperature is up above 90 every day and
supposedly it will be up above 100 even
occasionally and it's just it's awful I
don't know how anyone ever gets any work
done with these come temperatures it's
just oh gotta buy an air conditioner now
most places in Seattle don't have air
conditioning specifically because you
didn't really need it so people's homes
typically are built without any kind of
center
air conditioning because it just wasn't
necessary and apartment buildings often
don't have it but they're starting to
build them in now because the the
temperatures are getting so much hotter
anyway so what I would like to explore
in terms of the multi-resolution stuff
is I would like to figure out a way to
maybe take reflectors that are nearby
and pointing in a similar direction I
would like to figure out a way to sort
of condense them down a bit if possible
now it's always kind of a dicey
proposition to do these sorts of things
because when you're talking about coarse
approximation so things like reflectors
you run the risk of producing erroneous
lighting results as well so it's kind of
a little bit tricky and I don't
necessarily pretend that it's going to
be a straightforward process
but in general we do need to do
something so I want to kind of look at
what our options might be now what I'm
trying to say here again is that what I
want to do is I want to be able to cast
rays out from say a reflector and be
able to treat these three for example as
one reflector and just get the sort of
aggregate lighting back right that's
what I would like to do and that
requires sort of a some kind of a tree
or a hierarchy of these reflectors where
I can sort of go in and say how they are
related to each other how like smaller
ones relate to bigger ones and that's
going to be a take a bit of doing and
again the primary problem here is just
figuring out how to make these
reflectors behave in ways that will not
produce highly erroneous results when
sampled in the multi-resolution context
meaning we want something that will sort
of approximate what the what those
reflectors would actually have done if
sampled more densely from the place
where we're casting I and I don't
we know again exactly how hard that's
going to be slipping back to the running
version of the program you can kind of
see that since all of our stuff is
rectangular and we generally know that
that's how it works it does sort of mean
that we we could I suspect if we decided
to switch we kind of use a disk
approximation for reflectors now since
most of our stuff is actual rectangles
we could decide to switch to actual
rectangular reflectors if we did that it
is true that we could probably merge
things fairly cleanly like if you look
at how these things are are currently
laid out you know you could easily
imagine taking you know this entire blue
wall and replacing it with one reflector
this entire white floor place it with
one reflector the you know sort of the
the degree to which these things can be
merged up is probably relatively sane
there's not a lot of of oddity to it
there but if we remain at with disks
that may be more difficult and the
reason that it would be more difficult
remaining with disks is because a lot of
the things here like for walls and such
are not really capable of stretching in
both directions symmetrically like that
if you imagine for example trying to fit
a disc to this these blue wall here
right and I guess I can make it even
more obvious if I go down to where is it
that's not what I wanted no no no render
lighting show reflectors so if I come
here and you just kind of look at what
we've got if you imagine trying to make
a single reflector that encompassed
these three you know it would have to be
this big thing it gets a lot higher and
a lot lower it you know it produces a
much bigger span in Z than we ever would
have wanted it to and so that's kind of
an issue that we wouldn't have if we had
something that could be eccentric you
know we could stay
this they would just have to be ellipses
but it seems like at some point you just
have to ask yourself well if you're
going to be starting with mostly quads
why not stay with quads which is a very
reasonable thing to say and it's also
worth noting that quads are pretty easy
to quickly test for it's not that hard
to do Ranger sections with quads it's
just three three or four edge tests for
triangles or quads right once you find a
point in the plane you can then see
whether or not you're inside the edges
of the quad with just a few edge sets
like you would normally do now one of
the interesting things about that is
there's also a lot of ways that people
have found to accelerate those sorts of
things there are actually ways of doing
faster testing than testing the point
you know actually doing the full point
test in that way but I guess what I
would say is you know we don't probably
have to care too much about that stuff
at the moment so we can just treat it
like we would be treating any other sort
of point in quad kind of scenario so I
think that's everything I have to say
about that and so what I would like to
do is maybe go all right
let's try to think of a structure that
we can use to do some ray casting that
will be multi-resolution
and I don't really know exactly how we
want to structure that hierarchy but I
guess what I would say is I probably
want something where I at least have two
discrete levels of detail I don't know
if we need three but I'm thinking of a
very straightforward and relatively
simple system here where if you imagine
that the world you know is in some kind
of a gridded layout which we've already
thought we're going to need for other
things anyway so a lot of this stuff
maybe event
it can be collapsed into one sort of
spatial structure for a lot of different
purposes if we're lucky who knows but if
we take a look at the world and we say
well okay you know maybe if a reflector
is going to be evaluated it evaluates
like its local neighborhood of four
regions using actually the real
reflectors that are there and then it
evaluates the rest of the region right
the rest of the world using the higher
resolution reflectors right and if we
were going to do that then you know we
there are still issues that we have to
address if we do something that way so
it may be that that's not necessarily
the best way to do it check now that I
think about that's probably not a great
way to do it now I think about the
reason that's not such a good way if you
think about it's going to happen here if
we start to create larger aggregate
occluders those occluders will perhaps
encompass some of the things we've
already checked and then we'll sort of
be double counting them in these weird
ways so I don't know that might not be
so good so it might be better to just
build aggregate build them in sort of a
more tree fashion kind of like the the
paper that we looked at initially was
sort of doing where it says all right
there is one reflector right and that
encompasses everything in the world and
then it breaks down into you know some
set of smaller reflectors and those
break down to some set of smaller
reflectors and maybe each one of these
has a bounding box or something right
maybe each one of these stores the
bounds of all of the things that were
sucked up into it right and so then what
we do is we just start at the top and we
say okay we've got the boundary of this
thing we test
me whether or not you know what's the
how far away are we from this boundary
right however far away we are from the
boundary if we're far enough away we
just use that if we're - if we're not
far enough away we descend one level
right that seems relatively safe to me I
oh that seems that seems pretty good and
I mean there's no reason that can't
operate on the GPU relatively
effectively there are one of the
problems with hierarchical things on the
GPU is that the warps get out of phase
so for example if we're going to cast
multiple arrays at a time or who knows
how will actually be implemented with
GPU or even if you're inputting a CPU
for that matter you end up in a
situation where you want to be able to
cast raise together but different ones
of those rays are coming potentially are
going to hit different things in the
world and be at different levels of
resolution so you end up with different
data structure levels that you're
accessing which can be ugly so it's a
little bit hard to say right now what
degree of you know how problematic this
is going to be for us the other thing we
could do here is we could go again with
a more octree like approach so the other
option is to say let's not merge
reflectors or think of reflectors in
that way let's instead think of the
world is more of a voxel if-- structure
and again that was more if we want to do
tracing out into the world as ways of
sampling ways of sampling the lighting
as a voxel right the reason that is
useful to us is because if we assume
that something is vocalized
just using the top-down version here
which would be a quadtree you can
imagine something that looks like this
if I am a reflector here and I'm trying
to calculate
my lighting is when I cast out
like so what I can do is I can take
samples into the octree at various
levels and when I take those samples
what I will find is I will get if I if I
change the level of resolution I sample
at as I go further out in distance then
I will naturally sample a coarser
lighting solution when I'm farther away
right sampling at the the first
subdivision level here second
subdivision level here third here forth
here fifth here right the problem with
that is again I don't really know to
what degree we can really rely on a box
alized lighting solution for the world
in that way it's it's pretty tricky to
to really think through how you're going
to make that work efficiently where is
something that is more straightforwardly
based on actual flat surfaces tends to
admit itself a little more cleanly to
doing sort of radiosity solutions like
this so I don't know about that
but this seems like a reasonable thing
to do so if we wanted to be able to do
that all we really have to do at that
point is have a way of collapsing these
things up into some kind of uniform
structure now one of the things that
we're suffering from at the moment and
something that I would like to fix and
probably the first thing we'll do today
or perhaps the only thing we'll do today
I don't know how much time we'll have
we're sort once you have an hour and a
half one of the things I'd like to do
today is fix a problem that we have been
having and that is that if you take a
look at this for example if you know
we're still running this lighting
solution in real time but it's not a
real time letting solution right now
right it's getting a hundred and thirty
frames a second or something like this
right that's just not usable and it's
preventing us from trying things that
might be even more expensive
because it just wouldn't even run right
so what I need to be able to do or what
I would like to be able to do is I'd
like to be able to turn this into what
is essentially an offline learning
solution meaning I would like to be able
to just you know kit a key run the
length solution if that letting solution
takes 30 seconds that's fine it then
saves that lighting solution and allows
us to inspect it the reason I want to do
that is because I don't want to keep
fighting the time budget to get
something usable because what we're
trying to do here is experiment and
maybe I want to see what happens if we
cast out an absurd number of rays but
for example if I want to do that right
now and this will be hopefully a good
motivating example if I want to do that
right now I don't remember where
lighting test is there it is we know how
many of these Ray's samples were we're
sending out here right we've got that
where is that here here it is right we
said we've got that here we cast up 16
rays let's say I wanted to cast that 64
Ray's just to see how much better the
lighting solution would get or what the
result would be of the lighting solution
right well it's almost impossible to use
right it's so slow at that point and
then if I keep going further to the
thing that I said originally which is
256 rays it gets pretty much completely
unworkable and it's just you know it's
just not usable right I mean look the
thing doesn't even get like two frames
into it
so I think what we want to do is
something very different than this right
what we want to do is something that
allows us to run this lighting solution
and it doesn't matter if it takes 5
seconds 10 seconds 30 seconds it doesn't
matter it will then just cache the
lighting solution and show it for us
later
right that's what I want to actually do
so what I'd like to do yeah like I said
is figure out a way to make that work
and I think we can figure out a way to
make that work because you know as just
a simple test thing that's inserted in
here we should be able to cache what we
were going to output as the lighting
solution and output it on top of
whatever was going to happen for so
something like you know if we compute
lighting then you do this and then
another if here which is like display
lighting and we would put in whatever
the code is that we need to put in here
and what I want to do is just take this
platform stuff that we're sending down
for video let's see here
here we go we know we've got this game
render commands struct and we know that
we could save the contents of it and put
them back in later right so if we wanted
to we could create a place for saving
this stuff and then we could go ahead
and push it forward so I think all I
would have to do and again this when we
get the render group here we are capable
of extracting this information so for
example if we just keep this out here
well actually you know what now I think
about - I guess I don't even really want
to do that I guess I can do this sort of
as something that well trying to think
of how I want to do this you know I
think it I think is even easier is to
not even bother doing quite that much
work now I think about it
all we really have to do is we were
already copying the lighting out into
this push buffer why don't we just not
do that and instead why don't we just
save these lighting elements then what
we can do is instead of actually
rendering the world we'll just render
the lighting elements and we'll just
make that be an option that seems a lot
more straightforward and doesn't require
us to do any of that other work so yeah
that seems easier so let me just go
ahead and put the lighting elements in
here for now and we'll just make a thing
called lighting solution that happens to
have all these lighting elements in it
like so and I guess since we are going
to be dynamically allocating this in
general I suppose we could also make it
so that this lighting elements things
well
actually I guess we don't even you do
that doesn't matter so what I could
probably say is all right let's take
lighting elements elements to a solution
elements and we know we're going to have
as many elements as there are quads so
I'm just going to store that value in
here something like this and so what
this will do now is this will basically
this will basically store the lighting
test into a you know a permanent buffer
and then what we can do is only we only
have to run that lighting test when we
actually want to recompute it so for
example right here we can call if
lighting test and then here we can do
another thing where we do an if as to
whether or not we want to output it in
that outputting then where we do copy
lighting out here that can become a
separate function that does not have to
include computing the lighting so
outputting the lighting in computing the
lighting can be totally different right
so then what I would want to do is I'd
want to say all right this whole
situation here where we're doing
simulation and any of these other sorts
of things right that should all pretty
much just be predicated on whether we
actually want to yeah like we whether we
actually want to do any new work and
instead what we would do is
we didn't want to do any of that new
work is we would do the output lighting
instead so something like this so that
way we can have like a key or something
that we push it will then you know
recompute the lighting based on whether
or not you press that key and then the
output lighting will be a state that we
can put ourselves in where we're just
viewing the lighting and off we go I
think that's pretty good so what we need
to do here is we want to essentially
transform you know what we were doing
before is sort of hijacking the quads
and putting those in there so you know
we were we were taking the quads that we
had before and we were going to write
the lighting on top of them we pretty
much want to step back from that and we
want to be able to make something here
which we may want to save enough
information to reconstruct the full
state of the quads as well and I mean
that's and that's not too hard to do but
we want something here which will
recreate them from whole cloth basically
so you know it's going to be something
that's just doing push quads and writing
out those quads directly so in the
render group we're going to want to
essentially do this I think where we
just call this directly and we do the
push quad for each one of our lighting
elements right
[Music]
so really at this point we want to loop
over our elements and we want to get
each one of these elements in turn for
each of those elements we're going to
want to do a push quad for the element
and what you can see here is we don't
store in the element right now enough to
reconstruct exactly what the thing was
that came in and that is not necessarily
a problem because if we only wanted to
show just the lighting itself then we
wouldn't have a problem but if we want
to see the lighting on target meaning
with the bitmaps and everything else
we're going to need to have that as well
so we want to do is store those things
down here I think in addition something
like this
and then what we want here four colors
we probably have most of these already
created the emission we don't care about
because emission is not currently used
by the render it's only used by the
lighting solution so obviously we don't
need to worry about that right now
however the
so this is what our lighting would
actually be course I really kind of want
both of these things so I suppose we're
probably going to need to keep most of
this right so really this stuff probably
just wants to stay in place for the most
part it's and this can kind of go away
all right let's get to the other I don't
want to have my head in the way so if I
take a look at what's going on I know
that I want to do this this push here I
know that we can get the bitmap out of
the element because we're going to store
that I know the UVs we can preserve so
then the real question is how do I
produce the rest of these things we
already have code that we wrote before
that essentially does that and so what I
want to do here is I want to just
convert to actually using that so yeah
we basically got we've got two different
ways we could be grabbing say the
positional data so I'm going to store
again basically the entire information
about the quad here that makes sense
in fact now I think about it why don't I
just save the quad itself it's a very
good question and I don't know but for
example write this this textured vertex
why don't I just save those exactly as
they were and I don't know because that
does seem like that would save me the
trouble so let's just do this
that seems a little more sane alright so
from there we can you know like I said
we've got a bunch of options here but
essentially what we need to do is be
pushing quad on which will have these
properties and we need to set these
properties somehow now we know that
we're not going to modify the UV ever
the UV is going to be what the UV is so
these generally should just look like
this and I guess since these are always
vert you know the vert going to get the
referenced here I guess I don't really
need to do it quite that way I can do it
like this and the rest of these values
will get set by these these code paths
another thing I could do is call this
the original vertices to make that more
clear which seems nice just so nobody's
oops so nobody's confused about that
so all this stuff mostly works the same
way right we're just doing the standard
thing we're doing here I don't think any
of this stuff really needs to change at
all the bitmap is going to switch so I
guess we do want to do loaded bitmap fit
map here and we probably want to do that
as element for a bitmap like so and then
we'll set the bitmap differently if it
turns out we don't want to use the
original bitmap okay and then like I
said in here rather than setting these
we're going to need to store these
somewhere as the P as the P values that
will then get used right so here we are
setting these then we want to set the W
values
I'm not sure why this quad does not take
unnormal I guess it's because it just
recomputes the normal so I guess we
don't really need to worry about the
normal yet I guess kind of a waste of
time but whatever alright so then we get
front emit that should all be fine and
then when we set these colors that Alex
front a bit so basically we just need
our color values here so and then I need
to actually define those up top alright
so that's just going to look something
like this and now we'll see where we're
at so we need also somewhere for these
to be stored I suppose we don't need to
do with that just yet
let's grab out that command structure
because we do want to be able to get
that bitmap
there we go and now we really just need
a way to drive this more sensibly so
we've got this a game mode world here if
we want to we can put in a lighting
solution and we just need that learning
solution to be defined somewhere it
should be since it is right here well I
guess it doesn't really matter where we
define this but point being we need some
way of triggering these things but once
we do then we're fine because then we
can just get them out of we can get the
solution out of the world mode and we
can do all the rest of the operations
that we wanted to do and that gives you
enough oops I call it test later
so now we just need some way of setting
these values and we kind of need like a
debug key or something to that effect in
order to make this work and I'll have to
wire one of those up but other than that
I think we're more or less okay the one
thing we did not do that we will need to
do is when we are extracting the
lighting so here where we create four
for each one of these
we're we create one of these elements we
need to store the original values that
we need to reconstruct because we're
using those now so that becomes
important and I don't know that we
actually here don't actually know
don't actually know where we're storing
that you keep on up to push quad
yeah
so then I'll just allow us to extract
that bitmap array as well so when we
loop over this and we get the bitmaps
out we should now be able to when we
store those maybe ELPS do that we should
be able to keep those billet to the
clean what is abstract we should now
have those bitmap stored and so now all
we need to do is is store the original
vertices so widget you know org v-0 is
just going to be four zero and each one
of these will get stored and turn and I
think that's it so now we're just down
to how we actually want to make this run
and you know we need some kind of switch
that says whether we're looking at the
lighting or whether we're looking at
something else and so I need to add some
debug stuff there what I feel like I
might as well do because I can't think
of a reason not to is maybe we'll just
go ahead and inside our I assume this is
inside the thing that says whether or
not it was down before yeah what I might
do is just go ahead and add a little
thing here that gives me the F keys as
debug keys or maybe just the number keys
you know like basically like something
that allows me to send some debug keys
through to the application so that they
could be used and quickly hit to trigger
something
so what I might do here say all right
let's say that I'm just looking at it
here and let's say that in here where
we've got let's see in here where we've
got sort of the catch-all let's go ahead
and say but it's a VK code it's greater
than equal to V KF 1 and the VK code is
less than or equal to v k f 12 then what
I'll do is I'll put into the platform
input something that allows us to just
set the input so that it knows that you
know some kind of special F key went
down right and so if I look in here
we're getting a game controller input
for the keyboard controller but we're
not able to do
[Music]
we're not able to do the access the F
key right here which is kind of annoying
so if I look at win32 processed ending
messages which happens here what I'd
really like to be able to do is I'd like
to be able to access the whole new input
structure right and so I'd like to be
able to you know pass it new input here
which I think shouldn't be a problem and
so I think all I should have to do is
just access off of that and we should be
done ok there's anything to answer to it
so where is that if you pressed sorry
and I do want that to also be cleared so
when we're actually doing that and doing
the process pending messages I do want
to clear those out so in here I want to
basically say like so once we have that
I think inside world mode I should be
able to then use that information to do
my own sort of toggling here or
processing however I want so I can do a
thing like show lighting like so and
what I probably will do here is just say
well if the world mode says that we're
going to show lighting and I guess I
kind of got a reverse these two then
we're just going to output whatever our
lighting solution actually was and if
we're going to compute a new lighting
test then I will say that show lighting
gets turned on like so the other thing I
want to do here is just say like okay
well I if we're in the mode where we're
showing lighting if the input F key
pressed let's say it's going to be a
little confusing I guess now I think
about it I probably should have made the
F keys line up with themselves better
that way we could just say oh is the f1
key right just makes it a little clearer
rather than making it quite so tortured
so if we want to do something like that
then what we can do is say well alright
if we're in the show lighting mode if
the F key was pressed then we're going
to get out of the shear loading mode
right and if we're not then the opposite
is true so if you press the f1 key now
you'll go into the show lighting mode
and I don't know if this will work but
we'll find out
[Music]
p0 ah yes I agree that that is a good
catch
I would like to initialize those here
alright so in theory and I guess I don't
know but in theory we should just start
off with a yeah a purely unlit world
which it does look like is what we're
doing at the moment uh because it's just
putting out pure colors there which i
think is what we should expect to see
with no lighting if I f1 it should
pause for a second which it did and then
go in here all right so we've got some
problem with our lighting output however
and it looks like the problem is that
current quads has not been started so we
need to start the render group here and
we didn't do that I guess that was our
problem so we're going to have to go
ahead yet and and I guess make sure that
happens
all right so if we want to make sure
that the the render group actually is
sort of operational at that time
although let me actually go back here
just really briefly
so doing actually we set up the render
transform do we not or do we not yeah we
call set camera transform so the camera
is set up and ready to go so I'm not
sure why exactly that push quad didn't
work but I believe we should find the
answer here let's take a look here so
I'm imagining that it's because this
needs to be called I take a look at get
current clogs yeah so it looks like we
need to to call get current quads first
before we before we do that process so
let me go ahead and modify output
lighting to do that so we know at the
moment so we don't need that we know at
the moment that we need the quad count
to be however many elements there are
right now we only create one quad for
element so that should be sufficient now
let's see what happens well that is
certainly amusing although not really
what I had in mind for honest
yeah not great not great how we only got
one of those I am Not sure but anyway at
least we know the process working
properly so now we just have to debug
this which hopefully will not be too
onerous for us so let's take a look here
I am out of water which is never good
going to have to get two things of water
it's hot enough here that you just need
you need like infinite waters so I'll
plan that infinite waters that's maybe
too much waters but yes how much time do
I have left I feel like I can ask this
bought this question okay 58 minutes so
this should be easily debuggable in 58
minutes famous last words
so the first question I have is why are
we only seeing one element
oh well that's an easy one the bitmap
looks wrong as well and I'm not sure
that maybe due to the fact that we're
not requesting that that bitmap be
cached so there is that but that's
probably a separate yeah
so let's maybe step in and look at the
bitmap part of things here and just see
what's going on there because that might
illuminate this a little bit because I
don't really know
quad bitmap stuff commands oh yeah this
is not right at all I thought was just
meat cutting and pasting stupidly uh
it's really that right
so it looks like we're not clearing out
that keypress properly but other than
that it looks like we're good to go so
we're almost there so let's take a quick
look if we're showing the lighting
output the lighting and if you press the
F key we stop showing the lighting on
the other hand when you come through
here if the F key was pressed you do the
lighting test and set your lighting to
true that should all be fine
in 32 handmade that's you pressed so I
think that should be clearing it hmm but
I'm not 100% certain let me just verify
this ah
what is input by itself ah there you go
well that was that problem as well good
so let's see how we do now so there is
our lighting solution computed and as
you can see now we're nicely able to
rotate around it in in real-time because
it essentially is caused I can unplug it
at any time move to a different setup
hit it and go right so that's much
better because now I am free to do
things which are very expensive which we
could not possibly do in real time as
tests and still I can inspect them
relatively well and that's pretty
important right so that's that's a very
good thing that is a plus so let's go
ahead and and you can see kind of I'm
already a little bit miffed here you can
kind of see like we just have a lot of
bad we just have a lot of erroneous
thing is happening which I think will be
nice to kind of start to work on like
you know why is this square completely
dark right
and why are these not bright blue
is that just a bug in how they're
getting copied out or something that
really doesn't make very much sense does
it
it's pretty interesting
so anyway I think that's roughly correct
but again I'm not sure if we introduced
any bugs in the copy out because
sometimes can be hard to tell especially
when we don't have a working lighting
solution yet we don't necessarily know
if we ruin something or if we're just
seeing artifacts of our previous
lighting solution one thing I can do
here is I could just go ahead and set
all of the lighting equal to one to make
sure that it's actually working so for
example here when we're doing compute
lighting and we go through this this
process what I could do instead is you
know just set front m8c equal to one
right I could just say
you
so now when I hit f1 I should see
essentially the same screen right and I
do so that's good and that's just my way
of trying to ensure that I don't have a
bug in the copy out and copy back and so
at least that part I know is working
properly and so there may still be some
bugs in the other parts of it but at
least that part is somewhat saying okay
what I really need right now is some
water I should probably get some so in
fact you know I think I will get some
I'll be right back
all right
so we've got output lighting here and
now we can start to look at this just to
make sure that there's nothing strange
going on I don't think there is it looks
relatively fine and yeah so I suspect I
suspect that we mostly have a problem
with our lighting and we probably you
know and let me say that let's say I go
ahead and switch it to a Trey's yeah so
I think we just have some bugs in our in
our lighting there as we expected
because it doesn't show any of those
bugs when we do less rays so it's
probably just doing something stupid
like accumulating and not averaging or
something like this in fact how does
that work right now
[Music]
for each ray we take the hit and we see
whether we have hit or not and then we
accumulate that in
yeah so this doesn't really yeah so we
have a lot of work to do here because
this is this this is a problem when you
just do lighting in little like two-hour
chunks right the lighting is a very
complicated thing and this is just kind
of a mess as we've just been trying
things we don't have enough time to
really write out full stuff so what you
can see here as well is we're not really
we don't really have any kind of
sensible idea of how we're actually
transmitting this light we get a bunch
of light in here and we accumulate the
light each time through we multiply like
visibility type TOC and add that in we
end up with a accumulation of light here
that as far as I can tell
I mean as far as I can tell this is just
only using one of the Rays right I mean
it's supposed to be that eye right there
we go
and hey our lighting solution is a lot
better too huh
as you might expect so yeah that that
was funny
not sure how no one caught that besides
me not that it's anyone's job to catch
it besides me but you know what can you
say so this is kind of nice at this
point it's actually starting to look
kind of nice the lighting solution there
now that we don't have an obvious error
in that you can kind of see that the
things are starting to propagate a
little more nicely but obviously we
still have issues some of those issues
are understandable and it kind of
suggests we're going to want to switch
away from discs so if you take a look at
these reflectors here you can kind of
see oh this is weird I guess our order
of stuff that we push on here is wrong
at the moment let's let's fix that shall
we
so in output lighting I'm guessing that
this p 0 P 1 P 2 P 3 that we were doing
here is is wrong now and we will want to
actually go in the correct winding order
because we're using push quad which will
we reorder them for us so what we want
to do here is say well let's start with
let's say if we want it to go
counterclockwise to start with positive
X we'll go to positive Y then we'll go
to negative x negative Y that should
give us a proper disc oops
doot go and there now we can kind of see
those those disks anyway what I was
trying to say before I had to debug that
minor inconvenience is the fact that
these reflectors don't line up with the
actual world is going to be more and
more of a problem which is why I think
maybe we want to just go ahead and test
them properly because if you look at
what happens here you know there's just
a lot of holes in the geometry as a
result of this and we can use a larger
version of the disks but then they'll be
over-inclusive
of the blocking region and you'll end up
with a bunch of shadows in places that
there shouldn't have been shadows and
bla bla bla bla bla so we may want to
kind of you know we may we may want to
to do something a little bit more
sensible there where we are consuming
where we are
where we are actually using the real
quad structures themselves as reflectors
since we have a few of them that may be
sufficient it will complicate our rate
testing obviously but otherwise would
probably be fine so as I look through
this here you can kind of see now all
the stuff I was complaining about before
not I fix that code to be a plus instead
of an equals you can see the stuff has
complained about the floor has been
fixed as well so I'm now getting that
bounce that I wanted on on ground
elements to a certain degree which is
nice like in here you get that the red
tinge twinges happening and things like
this this little yellow dude needs to go
there we go so like some of that bleed
that I was hoping for is actually
properly there now which is good so
we've got that was that was a pretty
stupid bug we had in there and I'm glad
that that's gone but again we still have
a ways to go before this code is
actually doing a reasonable lighting
transfer and there's a couple things
that we need to talk about a is the
multi resolution thing which I want to
do and now that I have the ability to do
it offline we can play around with
techniques for collapsing them but the
other thing that I kind of want to do
here is I switch from using disks are
using probably you know probably to
using quads it just seems like the right
thing to do
yeah
so there's so there's that and is there
anything else I want to look at right
now
I'm not 100% sure
I think that's mostly it getting the
actual light transport better is
something we'll want to do but it's
probably not the thing to do just yet
because we're still at the point where
we need to sort of work on how we're
moving that light around and so probably
the easiest thing to focus on right now
is just switching to quad and then
having some multi-resolution happen
that's my guess anyway so I think that's
probably what we wanted to and we can
give that I'm not sure which of those to
start with I guess probably switching to
quads is the most logical one because
before I switched a quad if I went and
did the both resolution stuff now we
would end up in a situation where we
built the motors up for discs and we
really don't want to produce anyway so
it seems like maybe switching that to
quads
first would be the most sensible thing
to do
all right so let's now try I'm going to
go try increasing the rate count as well
I'm just interested to see now that we
can do an extremely slow one I'm just
interested to see what the difference is
there
yeah so I think I guess this is
something I should probably do
short-term the other thing you can see
there this is what I thought was going
to happen is we don't take into account
how many things we are looking at for
inbound light so we're not really if we
cast more rays we get higher light
values right which is never the right
way to go so we also need to sort of
think about averaging how many samples
were taking so the number of of rays
cast right has to be a divisor in here
at the very least because if we don't
then we just the more rays we cast the
more light we get which is not a sane
way to perform the solution right
because each one of the Rays weak-ass
needs to basically count for a certain
amount of incoming light and if we don't
see anything in that direction like how
whatever light we see in that direction
has to be multiplied by the amount of
hemisphere that it's supposedly
representing that that ray is supposedly
representing and so it needs to be a
divisor on on the total right so yeah so
anyway just looking at how that would
work what that really means is that when
we come down here and we look at this
sort of addition here front emit see
global render iteration count
essentially what we have here is this is
actually the ray count times the
iteration count
and now I think if I'm not mistaken we
should get a solution that stable across
the number of race so depending on how
many Ray's you want to put in you can
get different solutions in terms of
perhaps quality but you will not get a
difference in terms of total amount of
light and that does seem to be the case
so there's you know eight let's
recompile here
so there's 16 there's 32 there's 64 and
here's like our predict goes one two two
six and you know it seems it seems
reasonable
right I mean that seems like a pretty
reasonable lighting solution and
I'm not seeing too much in the way of
obvious artifact in here
it seems pretty good
all right um so there is one other thing
I thought about and maybe this is
something we should address sooner
rather than later actually now to think
about it and that is that we also need a
way of smoothing out the light solution
and we haven't really talked about that
yet either smoothing out the light
solution just means that if you look at
what's happening here
we're only computing the lighting for
reflectors on a per face basis what this
means is that the lighting would always
be very blocky and wouldn't have a lot
of gradation to it and you can probably
understand why that's maybe not the best
possible circumstance for us here and
it's unclear what we necessarily want to
do about that right so the question
becomes how are we actually going to
deal with reconstructing and end
lighting state from one of these
lighting computations meaning once we
computed what the lighting is supposed
to be how do we then actually have the
pixels in the game look up into that
lighting solution to produce some kind
of a smooth result if you imagine this
scene right here what we'd want to do is
for this to be a sort of this should
sort of be a radial gradient looking
like thing and of course at the moment
it definitely isn't it's just you know
all we've got is sort of a way to
reproduce sort of the blocky version of
that so there's a couple different ways
we could imagine attacking this problem
and it's not immediately clear anyway
what the best way to do it would be so
one way to do it would be to actually
try per pixel to have some kind of a
lighting query that looks up into the
world and uses their computed lighting
on the reflectors to figure out what the
lighting at the pixel is I don't really
know how effective that would be
maybe it's theoretically possible that
that would just work meaning if there
was some kind of a multi-resolution
query where it just kind of looked up
the reflectors in its immediate vicinity
and did some kind of a blend between the
nearby ones based on its normal ah maybe
I could see that working I have to admit
it's a little bit scary sounding like I
don't know for sure that that would
actually work so that's a little bit
dicey the other way we could imagine
doing it is we could just be computing
these add a little bit of a higher
sampling density so instead of just
using one reflector per quod we could
use one reflector per vertex per quod
which would at least give us a little
more leg fidelity like a little bit more
so you get imagine dicing this caught up
into essentially four quads and setting
the lighting based on which you know
this vertex is letting based on disk
lectors incoming radians right um I'm
not sure what to say about that
it has some attractive qualities namely
that there's no per pixel cost
associated with the lighting it's a more
flat cost and it just has an obvious way
in which you get the lighting from the
light solution down to the actual
drawing the problem with it is that any
lighting that's based on per vertex is
always going to fall victim to the
sampling density that you use so it does
seem like it's probably not going to be
a particularly high quality method of
reproducing the lighting and we probably
could do something better given the
information that we have so again I
would say it's a tricky situation and I
don't really know what the easiest way
to try to make that work would be a per
pixel lookup for color information
ooh uber a per pixel lookup for color
information
I guess now that I think about it it's
not entirely out of the question that
that could work like maybe it just would
hmm so this is a bit of a quandary I
really don't know but but I think that
the saving grace here is that once we
have this information we can put it in a
spatially coherent structure so for
example once we know what once we've
done the reflectivity we could put it
into some kind of a voxel or any other
sort of lookup structure we want and
then every pixel could just interpolate
the lighting based on what it found in
the neighborhood of itself right
it's really tough this is always the
problem with anything where you're
trying to reconstruct lighting with less
than per pixel accurate results you end
up in the situation you see people try
to do a lot of clever stuff like with
temporal anti-aliasing or screen space
ambient occlusion or screen space
reflections and all these sorts of
things you always end up in the same
sorts of predicaments where you're just
like well you know we've got this
problem where we are trying to
reconstruct things at pixels but we
don't have the actual data of what
happened at the pixels we just have data
about what happened in some other kind
of sparse way and we're trying to
reconstruct something that's going to be
good enough and it always has bugs and
edge cases and whatever and I think this
is one of those one of those kind of
things so I just I just don't know I
really don't know I mean here's what I
would say it wouldn't be too hard for us
to try doing this per vertex so for
example if I wanted to what I could do
here is say well for each one of these
I'll create one of the I'll create one
of these letting elements per vertex and
then when I come back through when I do
the output lighting I could actually
take the color per vertex and put it in
here so we could actually test per
vertex lighting not - it would not be
too difficult to test per vertex
lighting and again the problem that I
see with that is just that per vertex
lighting doesn't really produce the
kinds of results that you want for
lighting the changes within a quad it
can only do kind of a constant gradient
wash maybe that's good enough I don't
know I
fact it will probably have some obvious
artifacts but we you know we could test
it pretty easily so you know I guess we
could we could kind of do a test here
where we do that
I guess maybe let's just see what
happens if I break this up into multiple
routines so extract lighting from quads
extract or respect reflectors I should
say so we do is extract the selectors
from quads and extract reflectors from
verts and so if I wanted to be able to
do either of those two things close pic
index I don't really care about any more
there you go so when we do lighting copy
in let's go ahead and grab this out
here's the quad version and let's go and
grab
sparked here
okay so if we imagine that we want two
of these one that would be per quod and
one that would be per vertex I then
extract reflectors from quads is going
to do the same path that we were doing
before presumably we can just make that
compile fairly directly and then what we
need to do consuming it make sure that
all the rest of these things can operate
in either fashion
yeah so now really it's just a question
of we have to make sure that we call one
of these first to get the information
don't think debug light P is used
anymore just camera P with you so that
should be good so what we want to be
able to do now is say well okay we want
to be able to do an extraction from the
vertices if we do an extraction from the
vertices the tricky part is just going
to be that when we output the lighting
it's going to be kind of confusing right
because it's it's it's going to have to
do sort of an integration here where it
takes for reflectors and packs them
separately into one output quad right
eye so that's going to be kind of the
more the nastier part of it but we'll
ignore that for the temporary moment and
just focus on extracting since that's
going to have to happen as well so
here's the extraction code and that's
operating currently if we wanted to make
this extract per vertex then as we come
through here and we are about to output
a lighting element really what we want
to do is output for lighting elements
right so this quad count here is going
to be four times so and the lighting
element is going to have to be something
that
happens four times right so here's our
loop I guess let index on the next left
+ 4 + left element index and I think
what we want to do here is you say well
alright so instead of half of the span
really I guess what we're going to do
here is it's going to be a quarter of
the span is is going to be the actual
length or I guess I should say since
we're over sampling you know a third of
the span and the location is going to be
one of the vertices right so it's going
to be whichever one of these we're
currently on I guess that means we sort
of have to do this as an array because
I'm going to want to do something like
this yeah
not pretty
admittedly so yeah that should do it and
then if I just say we've got vert P 4
here we get all this and then we can
compute them thusly so if we take each
of those you can now grab the center out
properly the radius is just always going
to be the radius we can just it's the
same radius for everybody so that's not
really relevant it's the same color for
everyone as well that's just uniform
computation oh no actually it's not we
can do better than that now because we
can actually just get the color for that
particular vertex same would be true of
the normal so all of these can actually
access those directly now all of this
stuff seems relatively straightforward
again the emission same thing here and
then the only problem is these values
are not really accurate anymore right
but otherwise I think we're good there
so now we should be able to do this
although we may need to make that array
bigger but if we want to
just look at reflectors we should now in
theory be able to do that I think of
course the other thing I probably should
do is set that value down from 256 since
we don't really need to see that at the
moment but so here is what it says the
legislation is that doesn't really make
much sense it doesn't look like we've
got one at every vertex at the moment or
well actually maybe it kind of does but
they don't look large enough what's
going on here and also I guess I do have
to do an offset now that I think about
it this is going to be a little more
complicated if I actually want to plate
this properly so
you just make sure we can run this
relatively quickly should be pretty
cheap forgot we are not set up to do
that yet
so yeah it kind of looks more to me like
we're not really distributing these at
the vertices at all I'm not sure what's
going on there so let's take a look at
what the problem is so we're getting the
vert P values this looks reasonable to
me
and then we're accessing out of the vert
P for whatever element index were on up
so have that snuck outside the brace so
we were in fact not creating four of
those try that one more time there we go
alright so at least now we're creating
for them we're not creating them
correctly however for a number of
different reasons so I still think yeah
we've still got a bunch of bugs in there
alright so let's take a look at this so
we're going through the elements zero to
four we're picking out and and perhaps
instead of element index that's really
not right it's the vertex that we're
talking about here right the position
should be correct because we're not even
trying to move that to center it about
the face yet so how that's wrong I don't
know but it kind of looks like it was
wrong so that's a bit strange but oh
well so position and radius of the
reflector none of this stuff should
matter at all nor should any of this
stuff because we're not using it so it's
really just these two things and I'm not
sure how that's managing to be so
incorrect
so just to give you a little bit of an
understanding of what I'm thinking about
here so if we imagine
I mean I guess I could convince myself
that was correct
I can't really
I mean I guess I could imagine that that
was correct so if we take a look at this
as one here here's all the vertex we do
have the different reflectors pointing
in the various directions okay you know
what maybe I can convince myself that's
correct let's let's let myself
temporarily believe that that could be
true and then what I'll do is I'll do
the code for actually offsetting these
and we'll see what happens
so if you look at what's got to happen
here we've got four vertices that we're
setting and really the positions of
those vertices are are pretty different
what I probably didn't need to do this
in hindsight because I'm going to have
to do each of these mainly although we
could we yeah we still probably could
come up with a different an algorithm
for setting them actually but you know
we'll see anyway so if we imagine each
one of these vertices like so if we're
imagining this is a quad then we know
what our bases are right we know that we
have if I remember correctly we've set
these up they're coming out in Tri strip
oh we've done it we've untried stripped
them it looks like here right so we do
zero one three two
so we've got presumably this
and so we did 0 1 3 2 to return to a
standard kind of ordering here so what
we want to do is we want to create a set
of reflectors that represent this face
and we want to distribute them across
the surface evenly right so what we want
to do is say okay the you know the
vertex reflector for vertex zero wants
to be like right here and the vertex
reflector for vertex 2 wants to be right
here which means that one quarter of the
span from 0 to 2 should be added in and
1/4 of the span from 0 to 1 should be
added in for the verts our reflector
right does that make sense so they can
all be based off of vert 0 if we want
right they can all be like vert 0 and
then we just want to do ok whatever the
span is and don't ask me why I called
these that way usually I name them from
to-and-from but that's alright it's time
so if i want to do that i need to add in
a quarter of the span from 1 to 0 and a
quarter of the span from 2 to 0 but well
like I said we remembered these so
actually it's 3 right and what we need
to do here is each of these is going to
be a different span amount right so and
if we wanted to we could base them we
could we could make all of these be 25%
by using the span in in question so if
we redraw this with the things actually
remembered the way we remember them so 0
1 2 3 then the 1 version is going to
want to go well I guess we technically
never compute that span
but we can use the span from zero to
three instead right so it's going to
want to go 25% along that one but it's
going to want to go the negative 25%
along the one zero span to put it like
right here for element 2 which is this
one it's going to want to go a negative
on both of those and for three it's
going to want to go a positive on the
one zero span but a negative on the
three zero span
all right so let's take a look at that
so as you can see that did produce a
fairly regular tiling so I guess I can
convince myself that I didn't have the
bug and so you can see now how this
produces potentially a better lighting
solution because now we at each vertex
could get some lighting that was
potentially more accurate so let's see
if we can do that now when we do output
lighting you could see us going through
the elements here and what we really
want to do is say well instead of going
through the elements one at a time like
that what we actually want to do is we
want to go through the elements by fours
because we're only going to output one
element per we're going to we're only
going to output one quad per element
right that's effectively what we're
saying so what we want to do here is
kind of wonky but you know what can I
say just the way it is
so what we're going to want to do here
is we're going to want to say that in
this path right
in fact I guess maybe we have to get
kind of a light computation thing
happening here where you can kind of see
that we've got this I guess one of
things I think we always want to write a
separate routine how we had output
lighting you know output quad lighting
and output vert lighting basically
like so and then what I can do is just
pick which one of those I'm doing so if
I wanted to have the one that does
vertices the one that does the vertices
is going to do the element count divided
by four as it goes through and what
we're going to do here is just say we
don't care about show visibility anymore
and we don't care about your reflectors
anymore
because we calling the other path if you
were doing that we do if so reflectors
then go to the cloud path otherwise go
to the word pad okay so the verb path
needs to be able to do this and what we
want to do here is we want to
effectively access in fact you know what
we probably want to do it like this so
we grab out one of the elements and most
of this code is actually will still work
but what we want to do is instead of
doing the Hadamard product with just one
front of it we actually need to grab all
the different front omits right so we
need to be able to do element zero one
two three zero one two three
and we're kind of relying on the
duplicated data because inside each of
those they store all the original
vertices just in a fattie way they store
them all so we can just rely on it and
so what we can do here is do a thing
where we say like okay let's grab out
each of the front commision values and
then we can pack the vertices with
different Hadamard products on each one
and I think that might be all we
actually need to do not sure so here's
the reflector computation I here's the
lighting computation without the
reflectors not so good
oh I suppose also haha plus equals zero
that was good I suppose we also want to
say but you're going to be divided by
four because we're only outputting a
quad every four elements now so if I go
into the render let's try this now sure
reflectors false so you can kind of see
it gets a little better but you can also
see some of the problems with that I
mean we don't necessarily know there
might be some bugs in there but you can
see sort of those banding artifacts from
the vertex based lighting that was
exactly the kind of thing that I would
be afraid of let me just move the
lighting over here so you can kind of
see and that's just because again you
know if you take a look at the
reflectors the reflectors generally have
some pattern of what's dark and what's
light and then they're just going to get
interpolated in a straight linear
fashion right and so that's when you get
that kind of ugly vertex based banding
so basically what happens there is
you're almost good I mean it almost
looks good right so it's not like the
worst thing in the world it in like in
some cases like that when the vertices
happen to line up with a sampling it
actually looks quite nice like this
right here looks great you know ship it
but when you get those problems such as
in this example you really get some
nasty banding in there so I think we
would want to come up with solution to
fix that anyway if that makes sense
all right so let's go ahead and go to
the Q&amp;A for now we've done everything
that I wanted to do today tomorrow we
can maybe look at what we want to do
about the banding or we can move on to
the multi resolution stuff that I'd like
to do either or
you can triangle order the verts for the
banding issue oh I think I know what
your suggest well I guess I don't know
I'm going to try and guess what that
means do you mean that if since you can
pick which one of these two you want to
do if you have you know if you look at
the four vertices and want to know and
have an opinion about which way would
produce the least ugly result you pick
between these two is that what you're
saying and I mean I agree it might help
a little I don't think that's going to
get us all the way there it's hard to
say like I mean if I look at what's
happening say here you know no matter
which way you pick it you're probably
going to get something relatively ugly
it just feels like so I don't know that
that's really attacking enough of the
problem like I think you would get a but
if you swap the order of this triangle
for example you just get a bright band
with a dark edge instead of a dark band
with a bright edge so I don't I don't
really think that's going to solve the
problem much the problem is understand
is that it's understand fell'd not that
it just happens to have one of the
rotations
I have brand the hard the hardware
render is running right now it's just
the lighting is happening in software
Carrie Johansson so I had the idea of
maintaining all geometry in a
geometrically determined hash table
computing the trajectory of the
reflections and looking up where the
resulting geometry is that's something
that would be workable or am I missing
something um so I don't necessarily know
if you're missing something or not just
from the question it depends on how
you're thinking about it let me just
give you some food for thought there and
then you can decide for yourself whether
you're missing something a geometrically
determined hash table is a hash table
that basically takes some kind of an
input position like say X Y Z and hashes
it to a particular value you know some
32-bit value or something so that you
can then look it up in a hash table and
see whether there's anything else that
matches this XYZ right so the problem
with this is that it's very good for if
you just have points and you want to
know whether you've seen a particular
point before that can be pretty handy
right but with something like lighting
what you're typically doing is looking
at volume through space like lines
through space or or cones through space
right and this makes geometric hashing a
lot harder the reason it makes geometric
hashing a lot harder is because how do
you define a line through space right
well a line through space is going to
have to be parametrized somehow so one
way you could do it is is parameterize
based on just a normal but if you think
about it that's really not enough
because just the normal doesn't tell you
that that only gives you the lines
through space that happen from the
origin you really need a point plus a
normal to define a raycast right
but if you want all of the things that
lie along this line in space then what
you need to do is come up with a
canonicalized way of representing P and
can just be the normal that you're
looking for but P would have to be some
canonical representation now that's not
so hard right you could probably figure
out a way to canonicalize P so that any
line in space could then be represented
in this way
right that's not that hard we could
figure out ways to do that so I agree
that we could get a hash table that was
like px py PZ and x and y and z and
really I really this is overdetermined
really you only need two of these so to
be a little more explicit here if you
imagine what we're doing here if you
take the origin and we'll just do it in
2d because it's easier for you to
visualize so let's suppose we were just
doing this in 2d so here's the 2d grid
and I take a particular normal that goes
in a direction right here's the normal
that goes in a direction and what I want
to do is I want to say well okay from
the origin all I would need is a normal
X normal Y all I would need is that and
really even that's over determined I
could just use a theta I could use one
value that would tell me what the angle
was and I'd be done but now the question
is what if I wanted to represents a line
through space that started here right
this line through space cannot be
represented by any value that we've just
put here so what I need to do in 2d is I
need to introduce one more variable
which is the amount of slide relative to
the perpendicular to that right so the
perp of N going in the opposite
direction that's the direction
perpendicular direction I need to
introduce a displacement along that so
that if I wanted to represent this I
would start with this which I can
represent and then produce D
this to bring it to here right so I
definitely can produce those things so
that gives me something I could look up
into my hash table so that for every
line through space I can get a hash on
that line in space now here comes the
problem the problem is well what do you
put into that hash table what do you put
into it suppose that I have a thing that
I would like to hit and so I want any
line through space to have that you know
to have this be in that hash well
there's an infinite number of lines that
hit that thing so I can't very well hash
this way right so that I think
immediately disqualifies you from doing
any kind of hashing based around the
actual lookup you're doing so that means
you would then have to go and say all
right the kind of hash I'm going to do
instead is a hash based on say some kind
of spatial occupancy so if the thing
that I'm talking about happens to be in
this region I will hash it with this
point so it's like a discreet hash right
it's basically a sparse voxel at that
point that's all your hash table is and
again the problem is now how do you cast
against it
well if I'm going to cast against it I
now have to cast through a sparse voxel
if it's a hash table I don't even have
any structure to the farc sparse voxel
so I'm going to have to cast you every
voxel point looking up along the way the
query as I go right looking to see if
there's anything in there and again I
would say why not just use a sparse lock
tree right why not just use something
with more structure so that you can move
your ray along faster or something right
so I guess what I would say is I don't
know does that give you does that cover
the ways you were thinking about it and
do you still think that that would be
productive or not if the answer is that
doesn't cover the way you're thinking
about it tell me what's that way was and
I'll take a look at that if it does
comes where you're thinking about it and
you don't think that
means that it wouldn't be a very good
way to do it then you have answered your
question that no you are not missing
something if however you now no longer
think it's a good idea then I guess the
answer was you were missing something I
guess
[Music]
why is my chat not updating oh man
scientist connectives again my hex chat
has been really not working like really
not working it used to work just fine
and now it doesn't work hardly at all I
don't know what happened but it like
constantly disconnects and I miss
messages now
just so I'm sorry if you asked the
question after Gary Johansson's I have
not seen it because text/chat decided to
not talk to the server anymore because
why not
yeah this is a Linux machine so I can
definitely switch to WeChat if it works
well I could try that I would be happy
to try and do when context chat has been
really unreliable and there's nothing in
particular that I like about it I mean
I'm just using it to view the chat so I
don't need like as I just need something
that will be reliable it doesn't have to
be fancy
criminate er one one seven yeah those
vertex banding patterns that you see are
very distinct and they are just that is
what happens when you just interpolate
along points in space linearly and don't
do any recomputation inside is you get
these linear bands because that's what
should happen it's correct unfortunately
it's not pleasing and so if you're
relying on that to generate some kind of
nice results for you a lot of times it
won't it's why Phong shading is better
than Goro shading for example
derp circular would it be possible to
write a transpiler so that we could take
the C code and run it on the GPU
trivially after debugging on the CPU yes
and no so the primary problem and the
reason why I want to do it on the GPU on
the CPU rather in the first place is
that the kinds of things that run fast
on GPUs are not the same as the things
that run fast on CPU is necessarily or
maybe I should say that the other way
around so because typically if you do
have something that runs fast on a GPU
it will run fast on a CPU as well what
I'm more meant to say was CPUs can do a
lot of things GPUs can't write GPUs are
set up very specifically for low clock
rate narrow cache like highly memory
coherent workloads that are wide Sindhi
very wide right and I don't want to have
to think about how to make the lighting
code work properly i under those
constraints yet so it's not that we
couldn't make exactly what we write run
on the GPU because GPUs are pretty
general-purpose these days so we could
we could get that to work the problem is
we wouldn't want to write the problem is
what we want to do is get the lighting
solution working nicely here then do a
pass where we rewrite it to be efficient
and streamed properly for a GPU setting
and so yeah I wish there was a way that
that could automatically happen but it's
it's not really something that can be
automated at this point
chaos calm in your lighting formula you
use negative spans like negatives span 1
0 what if if everything is supposed to
be displaced when I 0 shouldn't you have
plus 0.75 at some point instead of
something night and said something
negative yes but remember I didn't base
it off of vertex zero I ended up basing
it off of whatever vertex we were
actually trying to put ourselves on
right that's why if I had based it off
of vertex zero than yeah they would be
0.75 and so on
you're using a square so why not filter
by linearly along the square axes rather
than interpolating over the triangles
that should avoid the diagonal seems not
oh oh okay I think I see what you're
saying so you're basically saying do a
UV interpolation style like that like a
what's the word I'm looking for so if
I'm catching you correctly you're asking
could we do something like this so right
now what's happening is the graphics
card is drawing these like so so what
it's doing is this turbo its
interpolating you know here to here here
to here and here to here right so
basically like as it walks down this
line it's just interpolating down to
this value right what you're asking is
would it improve matters if instead we
did a bilinear where first we produce
the blend between these two and then we
produce the blend between here right if
I think that's what you're asking and
the answer there is it might it might
improve things and unfortunately I'm not
sure exactly how to test that quickly
because we are sort of forced to go
through the standard rendering pipeline
here I guess I think we would have to do
is sort of in our pixel shader we'd have
to output these four values in to the
pixel shader per per vertex so that when
it was interpolating them
pixel shader could have said do the
interpolation right like I said I don't
think it's a bad idea I just we can't
really test it right now right but I do
think it's a reasonable idea I you know
maybe we could try tomorrow so
and yeah Capcom it's true that light
doesn't behave linearly but remember we
only really care about whether it looks
okay
we don't care how accurate it is we just
care that it looks like it's behaving
light like so if we get a good enough
result in terms of visual quality it's
okay if it's not really all that related
to what the real lighting solution
should be so I'm certainly willing to
try if we could make a different
interpolation mechanism that you know
eliminated the banding and just produce
relatively nice results then that would
be a win I think it doesn't you know
maybe this particular one won't work but
that doesn't mean that something
wouldn't work right like and so it is an
area that's worth examining
to say the least all right I'm going to
go ahead and wrap it up actually I
should close some of these down goodbye
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for an upstart of hand made here at
San pecheur coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always peer to the game on hand
made here at Oregon comes with the
source code so you can test out things
for yourself
we also forum site and go to class
questions the patreon page you want
support the video series a schedule bot
that tweets the schedule at you an
episode guide that you can use to catch
up on past episodes and of course a
little button that you can use to view
the show it's not live now it will be
live as i refresh the page will be live
in 20 hours and that is true we will be
back tomorrow for some more light coding
hopefully everything worked fine from
the news stream you set up I didn't hear
anyone say the stream went down so that
seems pretty good but that's yeah that's
about it until then have fun programming
and I'll see everyone on the Internet
take it easy everybody
you