hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we code a complete game
live on stream no engines no libraries
except we did give you the option in the
asset Packer of using STB if you wanted
to we've got an f0 in there so you do
actually have the option in handmade
heroes asset Packer of using one library
otherwise you get a flop you can extract
the font from windows of course but I
feel like people probably would prefer
to use the library because SDB libraries
are so darn good and Windows is not that
it's the opposite of that
but yeah the mainline game handmade
Heroes no library is still no engines
still that's kind of still rules that's
just the way it goes people and so
that's where we're at right now to be
honest with you I don't know exactly
what we're gonna do today but I think
that what we probably should be doing as
it's been a couple days off well we
probably should be doing is going
through the font code now and figuring
out how to do actual construction of
sentences paragraphs that kind of thing
with our font because all we really did
with our font last week was show how to
extract the font using either Sean
parrots libraries or Windows directly
and that was just for asset packing so
all it did was just put that in our
asset files but our game really just
loads them and uses them exactly like
bitmaps in right now there's absolutely
no data stored with those bitmaps so
there's no way for the game to actually
reconstruct those into anything that
would normally be considered a font you
can't construct even a basic word with
them because we don't even know stuff
like you know that the letter O is short
and like rests on the bottom of the base
line whereas the the letter G like goes
below it or something right so when we
would actually put these if we tried to
put these characters together to make a
string we would end up with something
that totally doesn't look like what what
the font was supposed to look like so
that's probably what we should do I do
have a bug however that's the other
thing that I
to address that someone brought up on
the forums I think they're absolutely
correct I introduced a bug kind of late
in the asset processing system and so I
wonder if maybe what we should do
instead before we go back to the font
thing is just fixed that bug because
it's a relatively important bug and you
know like I said before if I can I
always like to fix a bug immediately
upon knowing about it and sometimes like
I can't really do that on handmade hero
because we're right in the middle of
something and and you know it's hard for
educational purposes if I'm just jumping
around all the time totally randomly so
I try to keep myself a more constrained
where it's in my real day-to-day work I
would absolutely stop right there and go
fix it and then come back to what I was
doing and so I feel like probably what
we should do is fix the bug because we
do have the opportunity to do so we
already just had a few days off so it's
not like we're we're right in the middle
of something and the next thing that we
were gonna do with fonts was really to
start you know pushing sort of the
metadata aspect of the fonts like what
goes in there to tell you how to
reconstruct stuff and so that's really
different from the font glyph extraction
anyways so I think that's what I'd like
to do today is definitely a coding day
so day 165 if you want to follow along
at home with today's coding you will
want to unpack day 164 source code if
you have pre-ordered the game on a major
org that zip that you can download
actually there's two zips the ones for
the old first 100 days and the one for
the current block of 100 days you want
that current zip should have a day 164
source code in it that you can unpack
into a directory and that's what I'm
starting with right now so let me take a
second to explain what the bug is and
you'll probably if you if you're with me
if you watched when we implemented the
asset loading and streaming system you
should be actually pretty familiar with
the stuff what I'm about to say because
we actually talked about it already
cuz the bug was one that I specifically
intentionally have put in protection for
and then for some reason in that way
that I guess when you're programming you
do or maybe it's just because when
you're streaming programming it's even
more likely to happen
I suppose this computer now - I removed
the production that we had and so now we
don't have that protection and it's a
bug that's very unlikely
to occur so having removed the
protection we probably will never see
the bug except for a baby in some rare
circumstance and that's exactly the kind
of bug that you don't want to have in
your code because you will never find it
and you know that is obviously a reason
to take a look at it so let me explain
what it is if you remember when I said
let's go ahead and do our own memory
management you'll remember we had this
acquire asset memory function and what I
did was in the middle of implementing
acquire asset memory I decided that
rather than doing this as a sequential
step I would do it
whenever the asset actually needed to be
acquired we would free any memory that
we needed to free and so if you remember
that is happening that is happening in
this actual loop so if we can find space
for the asset we go ahead and and use
that space but if we cannot find space
for the asset we start to free things
and we free things until we can now the
problem with that is that when we go to
free things like we are doing here that
activity could easily free something
that we were already depending on having
this frame which would lead to us
drawing a bunch of garbage on the screen
not necessarily a catastrophic thing to
have happen but certainly not a pleasant
thing to have happen to our frame right
so the question is how do we how is that
you know how is it happening and how do
we fix it right well it's happening
because we build up a list of assets
well we build up a list of render
instructions right that's our render
group it's this thing right we build up
one of these that's all of the things
that we need to render for a frame and
then we kick it off to our multiple
render threads which then do a bunch of
rendering on it and that's all fine
right the problem is when we actually do
that
it means that these bitmaps that are
used in the render instructions can
never be freed until after the rendering
is completed and in fact we did some
work
to prevent that from happening with
multi-threaded rendering that is where
our asset locking comes in and all that
stuff and so we kind of all knew about
that and what I did to protect against
that as I made it so that assets could
only be evicted at a very specific time
right I had a thing called evict assets
as necessary or something like that and
we would call that and that's where we
do our eviction and I specifically said
why I was doing at that time I was like
so that we don't free things that are
currently in flight like this but then
what did I do when we implemented this
function it's like oh I'd rather do it
here and then I did it here and that
totally reintroduces the bug that I was
trying to avoid now assuming that we
have enough memory so that we're never
rendering close to our memory limit in
terms of the number of things used on a
frame which is pretty much certain to be
the case we'll never actually hit this
bug and so that's kind of good so in
some sense we could just leave it in
there and cross our fingers right that's
something we could do but I don't know
about that right I mean doesn't sound
like a particularly robust thing to do
and I think it should raise a question
can we do something better and so what
I'm wondering is do I now want to start
you know maybe looking do I want to
potentially look at doing something a
little fancier is there something I
could do that would actually allow me to
mark assets definitively as being used
or not used in some specific way right
and the reason that I was thinking about
this was till I was like I would like to
be able to keep freeing stuff here I
think that's a more efficient way to do
it so that we only actually free when we
know we actually need to free stuff that
seems like a good idea and furthermore
the other thing I was thinking of is in
our asset system this locked nonsense it
just complicates things right there's
this notion that assets can be locked
and if assets can be locked it means
that they cannot be you know evicted
well if we're gonna have that
complication wouldn't it be nice to just
have something that was a little bit
more flexible and worked a little bit
better right
if we already have to have that for the
background threads you know is that that
lock thing is kind of a relatively
crappy way of implementing that too
because it means that if you remember if
those assets can never be paged out even
if the background processes aren't using
them at this time right those assets get
locked when the background tasks use
them and never get unlocked right they
have to stay in memory forever and
that's not nearly as efficient as it
could be especially if we end up having
lots and lots of background art
composition assets or something like
this right so that's just I mean that's
that's basically that's basically what
we're dealing with that was the thing
that I had written down and so I'm gonna
just brainstorm for a second I'm just
gonna kind of talk about the problem a
little bit and see if I can arrive at a
solution that would solve both of those
problems in a way that maybe I would
feel a little bit more comfortable about
going forward so that's what we're gonna
try to do today we will see if we can
succeed so here is day 165 and this is
going to be like asset or I should say
in-flight asset protection and in-flight
asset protection the word in-flight
often is used in programming parlance to
mean something that is being used in a
system in a way that like matters to
other systems right it's like if
something's in flight then it means that
like you know for example with the
bitmaps if it Maps I'm saving this but
in flight I mean that some system is
currently in the process of using it and
if somebody else comes in there and
mucks with it during that process that
could be very deleterious to this other
system right so an in-flight asset is
one that's like going through the
process of being used which may take a
while and so what we want to do is
figure out a way of protecting our
assets so that while they're being used
in these rendering different rendering
scenarios we don't evict them from the
set of in-memory assets to replace them
with some other asset
right that might be used and so what
we'd like to do is figure out a way to
do that right so if we think about the
usage pattern for this right if we have
an asset we then have render groups and
there are multiple render groups in the
system these render groups use the asset
right so we have a render group for
example this might be a ground tile
render group and this might be an actual
game frame right this might be a frame
of the actual game and they both might
be using this asset and what we know is
they begin using the asset at some time
right in their existence and then there
when they are done when the render group
is completely committed and has finished
if they no longer need the asset so
there's basically an interval right
there's sort of a usage interval right
that we can talk about in regards to
when this asset becomes used and when it
is released right so it's kind of got an
acquire release sort of semantics to it
right like a reference counting sort of
semantics to it where you say I'm using
this thing now and now I am not using
this thing anymore right and so yeah so
what we would like to know is if we were
going to replace a given asset because
remember this is not garbage collection
right this isn't saying that once an
asset is no longer used anymore we want
to get rid of it that's not true
when an assets not used anymore we
typically keep it we only want to get
rid of the asset once we need space for
it for it once we need it space for a
different asset right so what we're
trying to do here is not so much keep
sort of keep track of what it's used to
get rid of it we're trying to do is keep
track - use to prevent sort of arts or
other sort of thing which in some sense
you could think of as the garbage
collection over there it's not garbage
so it's it's virtual memory paging
basically write our paging system from
ever paging it out
when it is actively in use
so obviously we could introduce literal
acquire release semantics right if we
wanted to we could literally have
acquire and release
we could have an integer on an asset
that's like its usage count right and
every time a one of these render groups
uses it we increment the usage count and
every time one of these things you know
finishes using it it decrements the
usage count now here's the problem with
that approach because that'd be
relatively easy right it would have to
be atomic cuz these can happen from
multiple threads but we could use an
atomic increment or an atomic decrement
we absolutely could use those but
there's a problem we don't really know
when we're done with them right so right
now what happens as we go through the
render group and we do all the rendering
acquiring is easy we know exactly where
that happens but right now we don't ever
step through and figure out what all the
things are we need to release so in
order to actually execute that release
in order to execute the decrement step
to figure out if something's use count
was zero right in order to increment the
decrement step we'd have to run through
the render groups contents a second time
looking at all of the bitmaps in the
render group and decrementing them so it
introduces this whole other big old
nasty piece of code that has to go
through again I mean it's not like it's
that complicated but you know it's
totally extraneous superfluous work that
is there for no reason other than to
release these bitmaps and if that was
the only alternative I might say leave
the bug in there it's way more efficient
to not do that it's potentially a lot
less error-prone to not do that because
we know the cost of our current bug is
just we draw some garbage on the screen
once in a while and probably it will
actually never happen if we have enough
memory will probably never actually have
that happen because the chances of you
evicting an asset you just used are
extremely low you're much more likely to
evict an asset that was used like two
frames ago and that hasn't been used in
a frame or two right that's what the
least recently used thing eviction
scheme does for us so before I would
introduce that complexity which has a
really bad failure case right the
failure case they
is the plus plus if you don't
symmetrically subtract from one of the
plus pluses you would end up
incrementing your assets without ever
decorating them properly and you just
end up at with asset build up until you
get flooding the entire system with
assets that can't be evicted and then
then the game can't run anymore right
you wouldn't be able to load any new
assets so you'd just only be able to see
parts of the world you already saw and
you wouldn't be able to see any new ones
right so that's a problem so I feel like
that is not a good option now what might
be a more interesting option would be to
use a sort of an ID sweep right or I
guess I don't know if there's a good
word for this I feel like generation
index might be the best way to describe
it but what you could imagine instead is
instead of talking about assets as
having a increment or decrement involved
in them right what we could do instead
is have some notion of the render groups
as being a series and then using that
series to lock our assets right so for
example let's say that every time we
create a new render group right it gets
an ID and that ID is some kind of
monotonically increasing thing right so
the first render group gets zero the
next render group right gets one and so
on and these are all atomic so I do an
atomic increment on a number and
whatever I get back is my render group
ID so I know that even on in a multi
threading scenario no to render groups
have the same number right okay so if we
were to do that then what we could do is
every time we use an asset instead of
incrementing in usage count what we
could do is we could write in the
generation index into the asset right so
every time we write it into the asset
right so if the you know if a writer
group goes and uses one
does it right sit in there and
furthermore we could do a scheme where
we always keep the latest one right so
basically you know we read out of the
thing we read we read out unate AMA CLE
so we just read whatever's in there we
take our render group and it and we
produce the maximum of those two and
then we do an atomic compare exchange
for the one we read out and ours and
that way if someone else has come in and
replaced it right it won't
we won't replace we'll just sit in a
little loop and try to replace it but if
it is we'll replace it with the higher
number right something that always
basically replaces with a higher number
and that would be pretty trivial to do
okay so we could try to do something
like this now if we did something like
this what that means is that now an
asset has you know basically a tag in
the corner right it has a generation
index and what that index tells us is
that in until the render group with that
number finishes and all prior render
groups as well we cannot guarantee that
the asset can be evicted so wait until
then and do it so then all we need to do
is we need to make sure that we can
actually retire these render groups in a
way that lets us know what generation
index has actually completed right and
that's actually not that hard to do it's
a little annoying but it's not that hard
to do and not super expensive and so
once we do that we can then just compare
our assets to the current renderer
generation index and assuming that the
asset compares below it we know that it
could be evicted if it compares equal to
or above it we know that it couldn't be
right something like this and that would
be one way of us knowing that we would
never evac tassets you know that we see
me I'm tired today
it isn't a sleepy program dad don't mind
telling you I fall asleep at work anyway
so that is one thing we could do now
there's a little bit of wonkiness there
in that we do have a problem where we
kind of need to watch out for rapping
like when we get up to you aunt max
right the maximum of a 32-bit integer we
have to be aware of overflow right we'd
have to design it so that when we check
the asset we actually check for some
kind of assigned distance between it and
whatever the the this generation index
is so that we don't have the bug where
when we wrap around everything kind of
freaks out right because you know if we
are rendering at 60 frames a second
right just to give you some perspective
here at 60 frames a second right the you
know if we were to take sort of that
that integer maximum 1024 1024 10-4
that's what an unsigned integer can hold
if that was our our count at 60 frames a
second right it's gonna be that many
seconds that's that many minutes that's
that many hours right all right maybe
that's not quite right let's try that
one more time like I said please sleepy
day maximum value 60 frames a second
right 60 seconds in a minute 60 minutes
in an hour right 24 hours in a day and
so yeah so you know rendering cersei
frames a second
that would be 2.2 years the game could
run for without wrapping of course it's
generating ground chunks in the
background so figure you know at most 4
or 5 times out of frame so you know I
mean 6 months if you left the game
running for 6 months you might wrap
just something to think about
so do we need to cover that okay maybe
we don't I don't know it depends how you
feel about it but I'm just saying that
it's something to be sort of aware of is
it likely to happen no most people
aren't going to run the game for more
than a couple days at a time at most but
you know it's worth at least thinking
about to say the least so I don't know
that that seems to me like the most
likely thing to work
I don't think I don't know if I have any
better ideas you made just because I'm
sleepy maybe there's a better idea that
I'm just not seeing that is there but
that seems kind of like the most likely
thing so the tricky part if we were to
implement this is going to be something
along the following lines we have render
groups right that are completing their
completing multi-threaded and as these
render groups complete they obviously
have you know their numbers in them
right three five nine or something and
what's gonna happen you know is nine
might complete first right and then
three and then five so we certainly
can't write when a when a rotor group
completes if we wanted to know what the
current number was of like the
completion status we certainly can't
write nine you know to the like
completed status area because three is
still happening
if nine completes first we can't write
nine because we gotta wait for three
right and so what we really need is we
need a number that's like the last known
thing that was completed which would be
in this case like two or something right
the last known thing completed would be
like two and so if the thing that
completes is not one after this thing
then we don't increment the number so we
look to see if the number is you know is
the next number and if it is then we
then we bump it up right so once three
completes were good but now the problem
is right and in fact I probably should
have done this in a more straightforward
way that shows it a little bit clearer
that the other problems that we're gonna
have so let me do that so let's say we
have three four five right five
completes first with em three then four
right so we look at five you know and to
is is the current number
and we want this to monotonically
increase as things complete so 5 is the
is completed it looks at 2 it goes I'm
not going to Inc that because it's not
the next one it looks at 3 it is so it
crosses it goes to 3 it looks at 4
that's correct it goes to 4 and now it
will stay it for forever because 5
already completed a long time ago right
so what we kind of need to do is we need
to buffer these up right we need to
store the fact that 5 completed and
we're just waiting around you know we're
just kind of waiting around for that to
happen so as soon as it hits 4 it goes
oh and also by the way I already saw 5
being completed so let's increment this
thing right and that's a little tricky
normally you try to not have to do this
right it's a little annoying but yeah
what are you gonna do if we really want
to have completely asynchronous stuff
you kind of got to do it there's not a
whole lot else that you can do so yeah
so probably what we'd have to do is do
some kind of buffering scheme normally
what you do is you try to avoid this
situation and what you try to do is have
just countable x' so you just try to say
like oh I three things and I need to
know when they're all done so you have
to have a counter and when that counter
hits three you know that these all
finished right that's what you typically
want to do but in our case we actually
want to know more granularly because we
want to be able to start freeing assets
so if four finishes or if three finished
first we'd want to know that and start
freeing those assets right so it doesn't
you know using a countable situation
doesn't really help us in this case so
yeah so that's gonna be a little bit
janky that that code is not going to be
fabulous I'm not a fan of that but I
can't think of anything better again off
the top of my head so let's take a quick
look at our current situation and see
how likely it is for
us too you know to be able to implement
this alright and so pretty much get
bitmap and get sound are what we're
talking about here right so when we come
in here to get bitmap or to get sound
what we would want to do is we would
want to do that that sort of asset lock
right here right we want to be able to
say now is the time to do the increment
and off we go so I'm not sure exactly
how you would want to do that off think
about that because we need to make sure
that the thing is loaded and so I'm
wondering if we need something a little
bit fancier there so here's what I'm
thinking here's what I'm thinking we
would do right so let's say we went into
handmade asset here right and we've got
this stuff we could get rid of locking
because that's not going to happen
anymore right so we have asset State
I've got unloaded queued and loaded
right and then we would if we didn't
care about wrapping we would then have
like our generation index or a
generation zero right something like
this so if we wanted to do that then
what we could do is we could say alright
get this get the thing out you know
something like this get the state of
this asset right and this is an asset
state state get the state of the asset
assuming that the asset is is greater
than asset loaded then we're going to
rewrite it with whatever our generation
ID is right so it'd just be like assets
you know generation ID we desert
probably the
that is always greater than equal to
assets Tate loaded and we'd say okay you
know this would be a compare exchange
right I wish I forget what we ended up
calling bull go look it up this would be
a compare exchange and what we do is
we'd say we want to see whatever this
Steve was assuming we do we want to
replace it with this right that's what
we would want to do and so then we would
do you know we'd make an assumption here
we'd probably do something like this
while that state is it's correct in fact
I guess we would maybe do it possibly
even just like this okay I'm inside sort
of the standard multi-threading pattern
where you just kind of have to try
things right we get the state assuming
that it's it's possible we try to do the
compare exchange otherwise we break out
of the loop and it's done like we didn't
find anything right we do the compare
exchange and assuming that we are able
to do that generation ID swap then we go
ahead and move the header to the front
right now
part of the problem with that again is
this move header to front what would be
nice about this too is if we could sort
of get some notion because now you know
the other thing about this is that
generation ID also tells us how recently
used the asset was right so it's like
the move header to front thing doesn't
super need to happen right it just
doesn't it's not something that really
needs to happen so I don't know and
furthermore multi-threaded wise we don't
really want multiple people hitting this
move header to the front so yeah
it's a bit tricky it's a bit tricky but
anyway we would do this compare exchange
and then assuming that we were able to
do the comparison
we would then do the sort of asset
header bitmap thing and and off we would
go so I guess I guess that would
basically be it except for the problem
of now how do we keep our assets sort of
you know sifted in a way sorted in a way
that's actually useful to us because you
know when we do that sort of compare
exchange that's that change it's kind of
a little bit annoying like what would we
act you know we want to be able to do
something like one of those asset
reorganizations but that's pretty hard
to do multi-threaded because if you do
it multi-threaded you're gonna have to
take some kind of a lock doubly linked
lists are like kind of annoying I mean
you don't have take a lock per se but
you know if you did it lock freed it's
it's a huge nightmare it's not a good W
linked lists are not fantastic in terms
of lock free sorts of stuff that's
that's not fun
and I say but that's basically what I
would want to do right and it seems like
there should be something fairly clever
that we could do here because once we
have that generation ID like IRA saying
that generation ID actually also tells
us how old this particular asset is so
it would let us know which ones we
should free in addition to that it's
just we would need some way of more
quickly accessing you know one of them
and in order to quickly access them
we're going to need to keep them sorted
in some way like with the heap or
something and in order to do that we'd
have the problem again of the
multi-threaded heap you know is that's
just kind of ugly and you could take a
lock but then it's like okay you know if
I take a lock then everybody who's
trying to do rendering stalls up on get
bitmap so it would it'd be kind of nice
if we could figure out a way to not have
to do that right
but I'm not thinking of it I am not at
the moment thinking of that and so you
know there's things we could do right we
could have it so that only the main
thread actually does the move to front
and that would solve that problem the
problem is that then means that you know
assets might get shoved to the back that
we're just being used that they are
actually frequently being used but just
for ground chunks and never for anything
else which is highly likely right hmm so
this is a puzzler this is a nasty one
this is a nasty one I'm not sure I'm not
sure what to do about it
I would like something cleverer here
than anything that I'm thinking of
this is where it would be helpful to
have another programmer I would like to
chat about this but you don't always
have another programmer it's a bummer
it's true but you can see what the
problem is right so what I've got what
we sort of we're saying is that okay
we've got you know some thing in this
case it happens to be a doubly linked
list but we've got a doubly linked list
of assets so here's acid a here's a set
B here's asset C right and we're gonna
come we're parachuting in here we're
gonna like use this asset and what we
were saying is well this thing is kept
in sorted order right now so that the
thing that was used the most recently
gets moved to the front right so that we
always know how to find the who most
recently used elements but if there's
two threads that could be coming in here
and visiting this guy you really don't
want this thread to be in the middle of
updating these pointers when this thread
then goes and tries to update them as
well because they'll just end up with
garbage and it could be really bad right
so this is a frowny-face right and what
we need is some way of figuring out you
know how to get the frowny face out of
there we need a way of reliably keeping
our usage thing set up sorted without
work you know the restriction that only
one thread at a time could could access
it right we'd like as many threads as we
want to be able to access it right
so I guess one thing we could do is just
queue those right which is kind of
absurd but we could do that right we
could just introduce some scratch face
and every time we touch an asset we
write it into a queue right just into a
nutty McCue like a stack right well it
probably would be it would probably
actually would be a FIFO right so we
just write in there and we just write in
every time we use something right you'd
write it in there and then what you do
is you'd have just one thread come
through and do these things in order so
that you know that it would do all the
moves two fronts in particular order
right I don't love it do I have a better
suggestion yet no but you know that's
one thing you can do right because it's
easy to do to turn that into into such a
thing
what am I not thinking of what else
could I try I guess they're so of the
ways that we're looking through the
assets themselves I feel like there's
nothing particularly smart to be done
there I guess we could try to see if a
lock free heap was too difficult to do
right like how much complexity and how
difficult do we think it would be to do
a lock free heap if the answer is not
too bad then we could turn this into a
heap sort of a structure in which case
we could then update it from multiple
threads without having to worry too much
about it right and you know I mean it's
not out of the question that that could
happen it's not entirely implausible
I guess there's one more thing that'd be
kind of oh wait
well I did just have an odd idea so
humor me for a second and let's think
about this
well no you know that's gonna be the
same problem I'll talk it through still
just so that I say what I was thinking
but then I realized the problem is I
won't be able to figure out how to
remove the links so doesn't actually
help I don't think but anyway so you
could imagine you could imagine if I
were to take the render groups
themselves right so like enter groups
BCD right these sort of things if I were
to have each render group and in those
render groups I was to actually just
link off the assets that were used right
in those render groups
then that would effectively give me my
generation index thing right so you know
each one of these guys would have a
generation index in them when you go to
use an asset if the asset has a lower
generation index currently than the one
that you that you are you move him into
your list right and then you tag him
with the new asset index and that way
you know that he's always in the linked
list of you know the the red roofs of
the go and then when red roofs get
retired you basically take whatever is
in their list and move it to whatever
the next render group in the sequence is
you you give the list to them and then
you know whenever you want to free
something you just use whatever's on the
front of that list what I realized is as
I was saying that it doesn't actually
help at all because in order to remove a
an asset from one of these things I was
thinking just in terms of adding and a
singly linked list is trivial to do
addition to a singly linked list is
trivial to do lock-free it's just the
exchange just a pointer exchange but
that doesn't actually help because in
order to get one of these moved to move
it you would need it to be doubly linked
again right and once we're back to W
length then forget it
it's the same as what we've got now
right
so the minimum thing is still too much
it's still it's still too much of a deal
so I guess another thing we could do is
we could just sort all of these guys
separately because I guess now that I
think about it
sorting is not really doesn't really
have to be done in a multi-threaded
sense right like even if the sort went
wrong that's probably okay maybe it's
not okay so what I'm thinking is let's
say we've got all our assets in a table
right and we've got their numbers right
here's their generation index indices
and we want to just sort these guys
right so like here's the generation
index here's the number and I wanted to
sort these guys if these numbers are
changing during the sort then the worst
thing that would happen I was thinking
was that the sort just doesn't quite
sort quite right right I mean that's
that's all that happens it's not really
the end of the world because we're just
using it to figure out what asked that
we probably should get rid of but the
problem is thinking is it might mean
that the sort wouldn't terminate I think
and that would be significantly worse
whoo I'm so tired I tell you this is not
the kind of problem that you want to
tackle when you're tired but I got 12
minutes left to the end of the stream so
even though my brain is completely shot
might as well look at it for 12 more
minutes we're sick in a pizzazz you
don't think of anything so yeah so I
guess what I'm thinking of here is like
right if we were to do a sort then could
we do a sort where we knew that we would
never get into a condition where the
sort would never terminate like where
people kept changing these values on
other threads while the sort was
happening is there a way we could
guarantee that wouldn't be a problem and
it feels to me like the answer is yes
because if we pick something like a
merge sort or something like that which
doesn't loop per se it more just like
divides and conquers then if one of
those divide and conquer' steps is wrong
because the generation index that gets
used is the old one instead of the new
one
presumably that's okay it just means
that your sort ends up being wrong at
the end and maybe we don't care if the
sort is wrong at the end furthermore it
seems like we could make it we might be
able to sort of design the sort a little
bit around that notion and make it so
that just because the sword is wrong it
doesn't actually matter too much like
that we still get a relatively correct
result right
and I suppose yet another thing we could
do is we could just build this sort out
of band man that seems like it's too
expensive I mean you got to figure you
know we may have like five thousand
assets or something and so we would like
to do is we would like to sort these
guys we'd like to keep these guys sorted
if we could because that number is gonna
be real big so we really want this to be
like a heap I don't know man
I don't know all the top of my head I
don't know how bad a multi-threaded heap
is I don't know I don't know how nasty
that is let's see let's see how bad it
looks just you know just get that do
that little spot check I like look at
the paper and go should I be terrified
or shouldn't I be right let's see let's
see the logarithm is based on the
sequential skip let's data structure we
randomized and has a problem realization
has promised with technical ecstasy of O
log n randomized is not something I
typically like to hear all that much but
you know what are you gonna do so that's
not too bad right I mean I have not I'm
not reading this paper because it's not
really something you can do on stream
but you know that's not that's not awful
right that's not too bad and you know
it's got delete right it's got insert mm
you know does that look great no you
know there's a lot of complexity in
there right a lot of things that could
go wrong but if it was the only thing
that wouldn't you know wouldn't kill me
I wouldn't be like oh my god no maybe
we'd read a little bit test code for it
right
so yeah we could do that but the other
question then is like well you know also
we don't really know very much about how
that thing behaved so would it actually
just be better to just take a lock
quickly do the move and then release the
lock because you know uncontained in
locks are mostly free and so it's not
like we would pay very much most of the
time because most the time both
processors would certainly not be taking
the lock at the same time so it starts
to kind of seem like you know if you
looked at something like that that maybe
you do just want to take that lock you
want to like do the lock do the
operation and come back I don't know I
really don't but you know what would
that look like
if we were gonna do that probably
something like this right we'd say okay
there's like you know asset state
operating or something like this and
what we would do here is we'd say okay
we're gonna do we're gonna do a compare
exchange assuming the compare exchange
exceeds we do our operation and then we
write we write in just I guess we want
rights forfeiture rights we do our
little operation and then we would write
out the state - to be something else
so our asset state would would turn into
something else our asset state would
become whatever our generation index is
right so we do some kind of compare
exchange where we compare exchange in
some value that was like the operating
value right yeah
fact we might even do that well yeah I
don't know exactly what we would do
we'll think about that in a second
probably and this is really hard to say
but yeah what we would do here is we go
all right we need to operate on this and
we want to be the only person who's
operating on it right so we're already
in a loop because we know that we're
basically going to always do our
operation there's no way we won't do our
operation we just have to wait to make
sure that no other threads are in here
so it's basically just air traffic
control right so we need to do our
compare exchange here's our exchange
right here we go there we go atomic
compare exchange you in 32 we need to
take our asset state and we actually
need to modify it right we need to
modify it by passing in whatever we want
it to be which would be the new
generation ID for the you know for I
guess we probably actually want to pass
that in here at probably not quite that
right so it's some it's something that
we're actually going to be tracking now
we're the render group has to give
notice essentially as to what it's going
to actually do here so this would be a
value that would probably get put in
here we did the italic variance change
we'd say we want to set it to our
generation ID and what we expected it to
be I'm sorry that's not true yet we want
to set it to that operating value
basically that runway clearing value
right and what we expect it to be is
whatever it was before right and so in
order for us to even attempt this we
want to make sure that state is is
greater than equal to asset loaded and
state is I guess in here right if state
is not equal to asset state operating
then we do it right and what that means
to is we'd really wouldn't have to worry
about sort of the thing I was saying
where we just all do it in one step if
we were going to take a lock of that
nature you wouldn't have to do this
anymore
inside the asset you would just probably
have the generation ID right or you
could also do it inside the header gear
right in fact that's the better place to
put it
for certain because then you're not
using space in the asset right so yeah
so in this case and you know what really
this asset state thing probably could
could be fussed with a little bit
because we also have the fact that now
we point to a memory header if that
memory header is zero we know you are
unloaded so we probably could actually
streamline this a little bit in fact
I'll put a little to do here to do Kacie
streamline this by using header pointer
as an indicator of unloaded status but
yes so assuming that we were going to do
that we would do that atomic compare
exchange to make sure that we you know
could move it to an operating State and
then assume that we could again now what
we could do here is just say we assume
that it has to be equal to loading right
loaded is the only time that you get to
use this thing
because if it's not loaded you know
obviously you can't use it and so then
what we would do here is say oh okay if
state is not equal to acid op so that's
that state operating then you break so
in other words if it's loaded we will
try to do our work on it if it's not
loaded then just double check to make
sure that it's not just momentarily
blocked by somebody else who's trying to
stuff with it if it is then just go
ahead and loop again and try again if it
but on the you know on the chant on the
off chance that that is the case loop
again otherwise it's like either
unloaded or queued which means we can't
use it right now so just just flub it
forget it
it's not gonna happen right so we go
ahead and say assets they loaded that we
do generation ID we don't need to check
that anymore so then we come in here we
set it to operating ourselves and we
want to make sure that it actually does
what we think it does which is that it's
you know again during to kind of be that
sort of thing right in fact in fact we
know that it's or always asset state
loaded so we can almost just say we
could even just do it this way and say
okay we know that this always has to be
asset state loaded so it had always
better be a state loaded when we then
come in here and do our little monkey
business we then just reset the state
back to asset state loaded when we are
done with it
and now we can do whatever we want
because we know that nobody else will
try to do this right so that's fine
that's not the best thing in the world
you know it's it's is it fabulous no but
if we are doing it that way we avoid any
possibility of you know stepping on our
own stepping on our own toes here with
move header to front so then at that
point yeah it's pretty easy to update
the generation ID because we know that
nobody else can update the generation ID
because we just took a lock which means
that all we have to do with a generation
ID is make sure that if our generation
ID is higher than its generation ID that
we would set it right and so what we
want to do here is say if the asset
header generation ID is less than our
generation ID then we would want to
reset that all right so like so
I don't know is that that weird bug
where it yeah it is some reason
sometimes Emacs thinks when you type
this that you're starting a template
decoration and it won't get out of it
and you have to go delete it and put it
back that's why that these were just
momentarily indented a weird bug so yeah
so that would get us out of the locking
business we could also get out of the
get state business and the state masking
business and all that nonsense which
would be nice to say the least and then
we would just sort of look at the asset
state a little more directly and and
yeah and that would all be good so we
need to introduce that generation ID
thing other than that I think it's all
good in this case I suppose we want to
look we don't want to reread this really
so I suppose we do kind of want this to
be read out just so we can do the test
on the same value right so and off we go
right and that would preserve the state
as well I don't really know that we care
about that but there we go so that is
all she wrote I guess we could also just
make that at u-32 I don't think there's
anything else particularly much to it it
would be nice to share this piece of
code so that it doesn't have to be
duplicated since it is going to get
relatively complex in here as you can
see it would be nice to basically you
know do this thing they're exactly the
same piece of code even down to the part
where if you take a look
both the bitmap and the sound or
actually in the exact same place so
these things do literally exactly the
same thing so what we would want to do
here is we want to just probably just do
a thing where we return the asset header
right we'd want to do a thing where we
do like you know asset memory header you
know basically get assets and we would
want this thing to just do you know an
asset index right something like that
we could get rid of the must be lock
nonsense and then this thing would just
do its thing right it would just say
like alright I've got an asset memory
header here and instead of all the stuff
I'm just gonna use just the asset memory
header because there's no reason that I
couldn't do that I go through doing
everything that way and then when I get
down to the place where I would actually
take that snap that result instead of
trying to do the bitmap part of it I
just grab the header so that I'll return
that and then these guys can all just do
something really straightforward such as
asset memory header write equals get
asset assets
you got value if header right or I don't
have to do that or just do this load a
bitmap result is like header header
bitmap otherwise nothing and that'd be
like it right and then loaded sound
would do exactly the same thing so it's
just a question of getting the types
right for C's type checking there but
otherwise exactly the same code it's
even returning the exact same pointer
because these two would be at the exact
same address inside this thing 99% of
the time if there wasn't some kind of
alignment change but anyway so that is
mostly that think if borrowing the
generation ID stuff that's totally fine
right right am i right
I don't know if I'm right hopefully I'm
right get rid of all this locking stuff
final states equals that's loaded I'm
just gonna light I never liked this lock
stuff it was such a hack
did not like it and I don't like it now
didn't like it then don't like it now so
that's good that's all fine and so now
all we really need to address is sort of
that generation ID stuff right and so
the generation ID stuff is the part that
I talked about today and what we can
really do at the moment right is we
could start to try and get this code
working by just going like all right
forget about it like nobody cares let's
let's try to make the rest of the code
work first so we'll just say ok the new
plus key lock that's gone goodbye
recompile don't you just not take 3 that
is correct
assets should be locked it needs to go
away as well
assets should be locked let's fix all
this nonsense
yes it should be locked actually want
doo doo doo functions not take two
arguments so then we just have to take
our load bitmap which it looks like must
have got inspect here yeah there it is
and get rid of those so yeah I'm not
quite there yet right but working to
some degree and I don't know if the code
works at all code does not work at all
yeah so that's fine oh right probably
want to exit that for loop at some point
forgot about that little that little
detail we need to actually exit in the
case where we worked right can't can't
keep trying forever yeah so you know
working so that's good we didn't break
anything
but we haven't yet fixed the boat
because the bug is that we still need to
implement that generation ID so I think
you know I feel like I talked through it
reasonably well to the point where I'm
relatively happy that you know taking a
lock here isn't a huge deal because it's
not a very hard lock it's a forward
progress style lock this function this
will effectively be free ninety-nine
percent of the time because all its
gonna do is actually do that compare
exchange and be done and people aren't
probably gonna hit this almost ever
right so I think that should probably be
okay these are just there's almost
nothing happening it's only this move
header to front that's ever happening
there and so I feel like that's probably
fine and the other thing that we can do
is move header to front if we want to
kind of clean this up a little bit if I
take a look at what that's actually
doing you know is that is that doing
much it's it's not right it's it's
pretty straightforward so I think that
it would only be like a few cycles in
there hopefully you know less than a
thousand cycles or something that that
would ever be hitting even in the worst
case hopefully I don't know if that
might not be true we'd have to take a
look at a little more cleanly but so
that would do it and that would get our
generation ID stuff per spekt properly
so that then we could just use the
generation ID as a guard against
eviction which would finish sort of
getting rid of that bug and also getting
us out of the business of locking our
assets which is kind of a double win in
my opinion because we fixed the bug and
we get rid of the stupid thing that was
really janky in there and I think that's
a plus so let's go ahead and go to the
QA like I said I'm very sleepy today so
I apologize my answers are kind of just
random but if you have questions about
the sleepy stuff that I was doing today
you are welcome to ask me them now put Q
:
in front of it and I will answer the
question
oh I did not get enough sleep last night
sure luck 93 hit Casey can you do a
two-minute recap of everything done
today yeah I mean basically what I had
to do today was I wanted to look at some
code that wasn't right it was kind of a
little busted and basically what I had
done is I moved a function to a location
that would make it you know that would
introduce a bug that I didn't have
before I'd moved that function with and
what it was was we were evicting the
assets inside our function that
allocates new memory for the assets and
that function was called any time you
might try to go and load an asset right
and since we might be trying to load
assets in the middle of doing rendering
and stuff that means that we we'd end up
in in a situation where we could evict
an asset we were depending on being
there in a future render kick off right
because we like build up all the render
things we want to do and those point to
the bitmaps that they need and then we
kick it off if those bitmaps get evicted
in the middle of the render before it
has a chance to finish we just draw a
bunch of garbage to screen and that's
nobody likes that right that's ugly and
unprofessional so in order to fix that
what I wanted to do was come up with
some scheme where I could mark when
things were used and so what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna use this generation I
need to do that but while we were doing
that I also wanted to fix the locking
concept which is what we were previously
doing to make sure that a thread that
was using rendered assets didn't have to
worry about the fact they might get
evicted by the main thread but it was
always a little janky because the way
that worked is it would just keep assets
loaded forever that the background
threads used it so that was kind of
nasty and stupid
so we also fixed that but in order to
fix those what I had to do was consider
how the locking profile would work for
these things so when you go to get an
asset there's things that we need to do
and those things can really only be done
from one thought at a time so what I did
was I said all right what I'm going to
do is I'm going to try to take an
optimistic lock by setting the state
field to this asset operating value
if it succeeds it'll do the stuff if it
fails it'll just try again
and it'll keep retrying forever because
I know that only so many threads are
ever gonna try this and they'll all
complete eventually right I mean
technically if you've got you could get
insufficient if you had some code where
they were all just calling this
repeatedly and doing nothing else maybe
that wouldn't happen but but really
that's not super possible so
how often do you actually implement
something from a paper uh not that often
not that often these days I think it it
largely depends on the discipline in
which you're programming like you know
if you're doing graphics work like 3d
graphics work you tend to read a lot of
papers because there's just a lot of
stuff and a lot of people doing research
on a lot of areas of it and so the
chances that you're going to find useful
information in a paper and and you know
you may not implement the paper exactly
but you'll get good information from the
paper right you know 2d game doesn't
happen that often not really right
because you know there's not that many
people doing research on 2d games and so
it's a little harder what would be the
worst case scenario if you had multiple
threads trying to remove an asset
couldn't you just wait till no thread
was trying to remove the asset well that
is kind of what we're doing right I mean
I'm not sure what you mean by trying to
remove the asset because removing the
asset is not really the problem it's
using the asset that's the problem and
what we're trying to do is implement a
scheme where we know definitively that
nobody is going to use that asset
pseudonym 73 one way to avoid the lock
is to split the least recently used list
into two parts keep the most recent 25%
of it in one partition and the least
recent in 75 percent in another only
move an asset to the head of the list if
it's in the least recent part how does
that help avoid the lock though don't
you still have to take the lock because
how are you keeping it partitioned into
those two pieces in order to keep it
partitioned into the two pieces you have
to take the lock at some point at the
boundary right
so if I understand correctly says James
Whitman our problem is that least
recently used in this context means
lease recently stopped being used in all
threads and we can't really know that
for certain without having some form of
inter thread communication is that
correct yes I mean I don't know that I
would have necessarily said it the way
you said it but I don't think that's an
incorrect way of saying it what I would
say is that we have a notion of lease
recently used that notion is just this
move header to front so that linked list
that we're keeping is always in
perfectly sorted order right if we just
wanted to be Bros about it right and you
want to be like you know bro I just
benched 375 of the gym yo right it's
like you know meathead protein powder
action right if you're just gonna go
that route with it then you would just
say that's fine we know the list is in
sorted order we know we will have enough
memory in the system so that we will
never be counting on using an asset in
the back you know 50% of the LRU list so
it's always fine to free what's in the
back of that list right we could do that
right now I would argue that even if we
did that we should still have introduced
this atomic compare exchange because
what we want to do when we do that is we
want to make sure that if you're going
to go delete an asset you're not
deleting one that another thread was
just about to move to front right
because you could have a race condition
there so you still want this I think but
in general this would totally solve the
problem the code that we just wrote
would be like fine
I mean bar in fact we should probably
step through and look for vibes and
stuff because I've just typed it in but
you know assuming that was working the
way that I wanted it to work and
debugged then yes
but the problem with it is if we wanted
to guard against the possibility of
evicting an asset that was still being
used because we're in some really tight
memory pressure scenario or who knows
what's going on where there's hardly any
memory for assets or something and so
it's possible to actually be using
everything in the lr in the in the whole
bank at once and so you shouldn't even
free the last guy in the list or if you
have a situation where one thread just
took a really long time and somehow it's
stuff is at the end of the list even
though it was like least recently used
you know because we're only doing it on
the move to on the the part where you
actually start using it not on the part
where you end using it right then we
don't have protection against that and
so generation ID was just a way of
adding that insurance so so that's you
know my description of it I think your
description of it is fine it sounds
correct to me as well
suitum 73 you don't take the lock on hot
assets most of the time well we don't
take the lock on assets at most the time
anyway right because there's no lock to
take really like all you're doing is
doing one at Gotama comparing exchange
right doing like you know ten mobs or
something and then setting the state so
the chance is that that lock ever
actually executes like meaning that
someone actually gets locked out by it
which is the only time it cost you
anything is I feel like going to be
really low but I could be wrong about
that not to mention the fact that the
assets used by the background threats
are often not the same assets that are
used by the foreground feds so I feel
like that lock is just never contended
probably ever like it's probably like
you know once in a blue moon kind of
thing right I haven't seen you drink any
milk in this stream is that where you're
retired it could be it could very well
be
easy fool says you can avoid the
generation ID gap checking list by
keeping min Max CNT render group done
IDs and freeing all assets max when C
and T equals max minus min then reset
min equals max I'm sorry I don't know
what you're talking about but I don't
think that would help us whatever it is
because why would keeping the minimum
the maximum help you and first of all
the problem is how do you even know what
the minimum is that's the whole problem
all you ever need is the minimum right I
mean the only thing you need to know is
the minimum then you could do everything
perfectly the problem is how do you know
what the minimum is their whole reason
you need to keep the checking list is to
search you know what the actual minimum
is right so keeping more stuff doesn't
really help you do that unless I'm
missing what you're trying to suggest
and also like I said we're not trying to
free the assets all we're trying to do
is prevent the assets from being freed
so if someone who looks at the LRU list
goes I need to free some asset space now
we just need a way of saying check the
generation ID and go no wait don't free
that
right
I see no more cue cones
easy fool you know the men render group
that completed but like you mentioned at
the start if they complete out of order
the men isn't isn't what
sorry I'm not sure if it like cut off
that or something they don't know all I
got was you know the min Ren render
group that completed but like you
mentioned at the start if they complete
out of order the min isn't and then I
don't see anything else
oh isn't correct when a cap Icarus we
need to track the interval and jump
ahead when it fills but maybe I'm just
misunderstanding situation no that's
correct that's what I'm saying that's
why you need to keep the list because
the only way to like fill up the to like
cross the gap is you need to know if all
of the numbers in the gap actually
happened right and so in the worst case
scenario you need to know exactly which
ones did that because otherwise you have
no idea right like it the thing that
you're talking about would just be like
an optimization to jump ahead in the
case where it happened that they all
completed but you don't care about that
case very much you care about knowing
how far to go in the normal case where
does just a couple missing right how far
forward can you go
I'm at the de 19 video improving audio
sync in order to get time begin period
to work I had to call it twice do you
have any idea why
do I have any idea why not off the top
of my head
I don't know I'm not sure why you would
have to call that twice are you sure
that's actually what happened are you
sure that you didn't just think that
that's what happened and maybe there was
some other thing that made it appear
like that was happening I mean it's
totally possible did that happen but
that is not something I would have a
guess about off the top of my head
any update and what algorithms who used
to do laundry these days I just keep
them in the laundry baskets like I did
when I the thing I described on the
podcast you're talking about is is
totally what I use I haven't really
upgraded it since
alright that it for qqs it's good
because I'm sleepy
he's a fool never mind my keyboard and
my internet seems to be dying away -
uh-oh
yikes that's too bad things to have died
on you at the same time
Sherlock 93 I think we should do it
detour and make a simple ray tracer we
should just yeah like eventually we'll
do like a handmade hero that's just all
retraced clearly of course I don't know
who's gonna make all the 3d art assets
that we would need if you wanted to do
that but a ray traced handmade hero
would be awesome
all right let's wind it down cuz I am
too sleepy to do any coding anyway I was
too sleepy to do the coding I actually
did on the stream let's be honest about
it that's just the way it was probably
was all really obvious stuff that I just
like was not thinking of anyway I made
it harder than it had to be anyway
ladies and gentlemen thank you for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's an a pleasure coding
with you as always if you if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always pee order the game on handmade
hero or get come to the source code and
you can download it every night after I
finished programming I upload our latest
changes we also have forums we can go to
ask questions get an anti episode guide
ports to Mac and Linux all sorts of good
things that the community helpfully
maintains for you out of the goodness of
their heart we also have a patreon page
you could subscribe to to help support
the video series and tweet bot that
tweets the schedule at you so if you
want to know when the streams gonna be
live that's the place to go I am in the
middle right now of testing and like
getting the UNIX NISS happening properly
to have github authorizations occur so
hopefully in the not too distant future
you will be able to start getting
handmade hero from github if you have
pre-order the game so stay tuned for
that I will be explaining how to do it
as soon as I am confident that the
system is working reliably enough to
have anyone actually you try it yeah so
until then tomorrow I will be back here
at 8 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
hopefully I will be more awake than I
was this evening for these late-night
streams and I hope to see you there
until then take it easy everyone and I
will see you guys on the Internet