hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we just got done patching
the stupid call that does the stupid
query - stupid twitch to see if the
stream is live which they changed the
API for no frickin reason so we had to
go do that and so now in theory the
watch page is working again because now
it's using the new API exactly the same
as the old API but they changed the
words so that was great let's go ahead
and and jump into what we're doing today
we are trying to work on our lighting
algorithm here there's the little curl
hanging around from that twitch
extravaganza there let me go ahead and
load up a run of the program here so you
can see where we were at last stream we
got blending working in a rudimentary
way and the voxel stabilized so that as
we hop around and go between things as
you can see now the lighting is very
stable and does smooth blending as you
go and I don't know there may be some
errors in it we don't really know we
just kind of barely did that we do have
a couple things we probably need to work
on like for example you can kind of see
we don't for whatever reason we've got
some we've got some issues with how we
pull things into the active said you can
see the way I'm looking at it here when
you have a large room like this and we
grab a room off the other end you can
see there's there's a chance you just
won't grab enough stuff so we do have a
little bit of an issue with the way
we're doing our bounds I'm not going to
worry too much about that right now
those are the sorts of things that we
can probably clean up later on in the
pipe so I'm not really worried about
those but I'm just trying to see to what
extent we we have stability here you can
see there I'm not thrilled about what's
going on there I think though that that
made I don't really know that may just
be about who's finding which light
sources and when so I'm not going to
worry about those exactly yet either
because the voxel seems very stable that
seems to just be maybe a light switch so
most of these things I'm going to say at
the moment we can hold off on until
we're doing sort of different debugging
in in a situate
it doesn't have a hacky like light
source choosing in there because we're
about to get rid of that um so I'm gonna
say that's really pretty stable for our
purposes and that we can move on to the
next step which is the full lighting
solution again the main problem we're
gonna have now is once we engage the
full lighting solution we're going to be
inter plating a single light field
that's probably not really what we're
going to want to do and and so moving up
to the multi light field is probably
really going to be where the problem
comes in for us all right so that's what
we're going to have to take a look at
but for right now we're just gonna focus
on getting the multi bounce in there so
that we're not in flashlight mode but
it's getting pretty close right okay so
let's go ahead and and load up the part
of the code that we haven't finished yet
that we need to finish for today's work
and so if I jump over to the lighting
code here hopefully what you can see if
I jump down to the the voxel lighting
sample which is this code right here it
should just have a nothing in it yeah
right see and so we've got it to do here
this is the thing we want to fill in and
what has to happen this is basically you
know there's there's nothing actually
different that we're gonna do here it's
just because we have part of the
lighting down on the CPU side part of
letting down the GPU side and that's
because we don't really want to require
you know video RTX part or something
we're doing the Ray casting on the CPU
side so what that means is that when the
when the CPU needs to compute lighting
at a point using last frames theta it's
gonna have to do that using a using
information that would normally be
something you'd sample in the pixel
shader so if for example we go to the Z
bias program here that we're actually
using for pretty much all of the the
things that we draw you can see here
that we have a thing called sunlight and
sunlight is literally like the code we
need right so if you take a look at
what's supposed to happen care literally
the thing that's supposed to happen is
this right so the pixel shader is is
already the code that we need so we know
the code that we need
it's literally this and we just need to
figure out how to do that
in our code because our code doesn't
have it doesn't run pixel shaders right
the pixel shader is code we wrote that
runs on the GPU but if we look at it
because we already did some work to help
ourselves out because we sort of knew
this was the case we wanted to keep
these code paths similar what you can
see is that we actually wrote our pixel
shader to use exactly the same syntax as
our regular code and we did that of
course for those of you don't remember
we did that by putting in a bunch of
pound affiance which effectively turned
pixel shader syntax into our syntax for
the most part so if we were to just
paste this in here with the exception of
maybe the fact that they that you know I
don't know why that I'm surprised it
accepted that 2.0 F I don't think it's
supposed to allow that I should probably
get rid of that that must be just being
accepted by the shader because we're
using a later shader model or something
but earlier shader models wouldn't have
liked that I don't think but anyway with
the exception of a few things like the
fact that these should be F listed or
whatever they're ripe effectively when
we're doing the lighting you know what
we want to do is basically this now we
don't necessarily want to do exactly
this there's going to be some changes to
it probably and we probably want just
pure diffuse reflection and and so on
and so forth
but for the most part what we want to do
is almost exactly the same thing that we
were doing in the pixel shader so very
very similar and if you look at what
that means for us really this is the
problem so it's really just these
texture lookups those are the things
that we don't really know right and so
we want some way of emulating what the
texture Union on the ground scar is
doing in our CPU code and that's we have
to write today
all right so what we want to do is focus
on this and start here we know we want a
sample this normal and we want to sample
this position right so we're trying to
find the incoming radiance at that point
we know that we can do some of these
things the same but some of them we
don't really want to do so if you look
at what's happening here right this is
part of doing reflection for things that
might have specularity or like a
reflective component to them that has to
do with the angle of view since we're
moving light around a scene at the
moment I don't know that we really want
that maybe we do I mean you could argue
that that is kind of how it should be
working that we should still be taking
this into account in terms of specular
reflections so you know maybe that's
true and maybe we want to leave that in
there I don't know if that's the case
though what we need to know when we do
compute voxel radiance is we don't
really want world P - camera P that is
saying what light is going to be
reflected back to the viewer and
remember that's fine for computing what
the visible pixels color should be what
we're looking at it but what we would
want to do if we wanted to simulate
specularity in a bounce like this is we
want to know what the query rate is so
effectively what we want here is like an
input you know an eye parameter there
right that's going to give us that
information back and arguably what we
probably should have done here is sent
that in and the reason that I say that
is because if you look at the the get
irradiance sorry the compute voxel
function here this maybe should have got
passed into this anyway because you know
maybe you want to sample it from more
than one direction for some reason or
something you know but anyway so we have
like in incidence here which is like the
out you know the outgoing direction or
whatever and it's really the incoming
direction you can see it's world P -
camera P so it's the it's the you know
in pointing direction so this is like
the incidence I guess we'll call it and
so if we want to do that what we need is
is we just need someone to pass that in
to us and tell us like what direction
were you trying to stamp
right but once we have that then we have
all the same information that we needed
here so we can pretty much do everything
that we needed it to right we compute
that our value this stuff is what we'll
have to change a little bit just to make
sure that we're computing the voxel
information in the same way but
basically that is what we want we're
then going to ask the light sampler to
give us back this information and since
we know that we're not sampling fours we
can actually just change this to be
effectively sampling threes everywhere
because we don't have this this isn't
encoded right so we don't actually have
to do that either we can just sort of do
this in a simpler way okay so we can do
this this would sample all of the things
that we have there and then when we
compute the light data here
that's the outgoing light data that
we're going to sample we could pretty
much just capture all of that
information as we go right so if we do
that all we would have to do is you know
emulate now they get irradiance call it
would be past the light information and
the reflectance here so that information
would come out here and you can see it's
gonna do literally just exactly this
call about this code rather the only
difference is the light value here can
actually be the light color directly so
that information doesn't have to be sort
of I don't the word you want to use is
decoded I guess like it does have to be
in the pixel shader so if that light
color here this stuff doesn't have to
happen because we just have the actual
light unencoded so this would work
directly and the rest of this would not
have to be you know nothing special
would have to happen here so basically
this exact code path should actually be
fine
and what we want to do now is just kind
of work through it and get it
implemented exactly now you can see here
that the world normal is not present
here that's because that was coming in
as a global effectively in the pixel
shader right and so this sample end that
we have here is actually the information
that we need for that so we kind of need
to do something more along these lines
where we're going to pass that in as
another parameter that wasn't getting
passed here so that value is it's
varying now and
we have to make sure that that gets
taken care of here but other than that I
think we're good so there's the sampling
code for that irradiance there and then
we're just working on this part so world
P we know it's just sample P right and
so really the the majority of the
problem now it just comes down to this
piece of code here that we don't really
know it oh and also this is really just
result now right ok so now we have a
sketch of the routine and what you can
see is that really like I said pretty
much everything translates almost
exactly so we don't really have to do
anything to to modify the math it's it's
almost exact right we just had to wire
up the parameter coming from the
function parameter rather than from sort
of a global in the shader because the
shader is sort of its own function that
gets called if you will and global
variables are really just parameters to
it in that context so what we want to do
now is say well the compute voxel
irradiance add function just now had the
work that we don't have is we need a way
to sample the voxel using the same kind
of trilinear filtering that the game
itself would use right and so if i want
to do something like that what i need to
do is just take like the texture call
here and implement the same thing that
the graphics card would have done and
what you can see is it's a little bit
Squinkie because we sort of have the
light voxel is not stored as a separate
thing right but that's actually good in
our case because we don't really want to
belabor the point here so what we
probably want to do is make these just
get sampled directly in here as
something that can be done from the the
you know the neighboring voxels so if i
look at how we've got our voxels stored
there in one of these light computation
sorry lightbox will sell this this
doesn't exist anymore analyze what's the
best digital remain so this light voxel
cell here if we look at the way that
it's laid out what we can see is we've
got all the information that we need
right here so we really just need our
eight voxel
you know our eight voxel cells right
that's what we would need here and we
need a way of grabbing those cells sort
of getting the getting the ones that
surround a particular location so we
know that we can find an exact location
right but what we don't know is how to
get the things around an exact location
right so if you look at get voxel index
for example you can see here right this
this call right here tells us you know
the first piece of information that we
need know why that there we go so we
know part of it right we know that if we
did this this world peak here were three
pass their sample page this gives us our
voxel index here right so if we do know
why like typo King this morning there we
go so this right here would give us the
voxel index that the sample P itself
lies in and then of course we need to
know ones that are sort of on one away
in each case for this right and the key
thing here the thing that's that's a
problem for us is we need to know we
need to be able to clamp right so we
need to be able to say like look if
we're gonna we don't want to fetch
outside this voxel so when we're doing
the fetching we need to be able to clamp
our fetches so that they all end up
inside I'm gonna put that in a sort of
simple function for now and you know we
probably have to speed this routine up
this is probably gonna be the slowest
part of our code is doing this lighting
sample here that'd be my guess anyway
and so we're probably gonna have to do
work to make this cleaner and not do it
the way that I'm doing it here but just
so you're clear on it I'm gonna do the
simple version first and then we're
gonna worry about the speed part after
everything is working so in here what
we'll do is first do the the light box
will sell and I'm just going to go ahead
and take a sort of the literal version
of this you know we've got you know of
eight eight cell region we've got two by
two by two we're trying to get basically
the the things that we would need to
interpolate between
when we get the voxel index here we're
gonna assume that we adjust this
downward so for example normally when we
get in box Linux we just want to know
which voxel index you're in but in this
case we're going to need to do something
where we say okay if you were on one
side of the voxel you would do a
different thing than if you're on the
other side of the voxel right so I'm
gonna assume that we handle that first
and we're gonna sort of deal with with
that flooring and it in a different way
in fact like what I could do here is
literally just put this code in here
because we're gonna need to work with it
a second so this is where we need to
start off right and before we do or
after I guess maybe a week I should say
after we do this floor this F work here
we're going to produce the uvw score
this thing by subtracting these right so
after we've done the floor where we are
inside the voxel that we're actually in
that information well and you know what
I guess the other thing we could say is
we kind of need to know relative to the
voxel Center as well so there's a bunch
of information we need to do here
actually so if we take this F chord what
you can see here is we're producing the
vox of so we're in by doing this but
what we really want to know is the voxel
that we would be in I'm so much to
explain this I think we just need a
diagram I know what I want but I'm not
able to say the words that's that's
going to make it clear so we're just
going to take that as a sign that we
need the diagram so here's
here's our voxel sample so what we want
to do here is we want to say alright we
know that we're trying to produce
effectively this
right we have like this voxel we know
that it's going to be a little cube and
it's divided up such that we have eight
little cells right and we know that if
we imagine you know are sort of X Y Z
here that like this is the minimum
corner right and this is the maximum
corner in terms of coordinates and so
what we want to do is we want to produce
this minimum corner value and then we
want to do like plus one in every
dimension and every combination of
dimension to produce our eight cell
indices now to produce this the thing
that I wanted to point out and I'll draw
the diagram in a simpler form over here
we'll just do a 2d cross-section because
it works the same in any number of
dimensions we have the center of a voxel
cell and that is where we're assuming
these values exist which honestly may
have been a mistake maybe we should have
assumed if they work at the vertices
because would have worked a lot better
if we've done that uh so there's that
but again you know there's yeah we'll
see we can adjust it later if we need to
so what we want to do here is just say
look we know that this is where our
voxel information is stored and so if
you know you imagine this is 0.5 0.5 a
long you know from say the the corner of
this voxel which would be here right if
this is 0.5 0.5 along what that means is
that if you were below point 5 so if you
were only like point 2 above this line
you would actually want your minimum
corner to be this voxel and the reason
is because the things you're going to be
blending between are actually these four
whereas if you were up here and you
considered this you would use these four
right so what we want to do here is
include that 0.5 0.5 bias when we
compute the actual value so in here
where we do this had a marred product
right then we do the inverse Vox will
sell them to figure out basically where
we're at what we need to do is we need
to then say let's shift those let's
shift that value downward
by the point five point five so that we
get a different glamping than we
otherwise would right
so in this right here once we've done
this you know moved it into voxel space
what we want to do is basically shift
over by a a bias factor to move us into
the previous voxel if that was where we
should have been then when we do the
floor we're producing the value we
actually wanted and we can now do the
subtraction off of that value should
give us the proper UVW for blending
whereas before it would not have done
that because we were in a shifted space
relative to where we want it to be I
believe that's my assertion anyway so in
order to get the fractional part here I
can actually just do the opposite I can
take the vox cell dim and multiply it
here so I can do the opposite Hadamard
basically so like this right so this
will give me my UV W's and so now I know
like relatively where I am and that
should always be well behaved right now
the problem that we're gonna have here
is where we this voxel index is
potentially out of bounds as well right
so we need to make sure that that gets
clamped properly but I think other than
that I think we should be okay right the
clamping will happen in here so this UV
W gives us the UV W blend that we need
and so then what we can do is we don't
need this anymore because this code is
what we just implemented up here but for
our scheme right and perhaps we should
also put this down here because that's
something that has to do the lighting
and we maybe don't want to make it look
like that's part of the box so lookup
information that's not so what we're
going to do then is we're gonna get our
voxel light cells here so we'll just
grab a pointer to each of those and say
all right where are those and this will
be like a you know look up voxel lamped
or something like that and we're gonna
say here's the voxel index X
in XY voxel index Z like this and that
way we can say alright look up each of
these things and we're going to get
these out in the order that we would
expect them right so first we would say
X then we would say X plus 1 right for
each of these like so and then we would
say okay then it's going to be y plus 1
potentially
I do one
there we go I only need eight of them
and then finally the Z plus one on the
outside right and so as you can see all
I'm doing here is taking every possible
combination if I space these out you
could see maybe a little bit better what
I'm talking about but we're just
incrementing we're just doing every
permutation of X you know down the line
you know plus 0 plus 1 plus 0 plus 1
plus 0 plus 1 then we're doing a you
know the half cadence on Y and then the
half again cadence on Z and you can kind
of see that that just gives us all the
permutations of plus 0 and plus 1 for
each of these so that would get us all
the voxels and some of these may be the
same voxel if they had to clamp but
we're gonna let the clamping function do
that and then once we have that we
should be able to produce all of these
by just basic lips right so we have a
lab function here it is and so all we
need to do is loop our values I believe
we have a Lib for both types yeah so we
have we can do our b3s as well so we can
just say look I'm gonna loop this stuff
and the way we're going to do this is
we're gonna go between different cells
right so we know we've got cells
something and then we want to take you
know maybe the light n value 0 or
something right and then we would lurk
that with cells something in that end
value and that's how we would produce
like the end 0 right so that's all we
really have to do and this is going to
be the same for all of these it's just
gonna change well the only thing that's
gonna change is what we actually lurk
right and which parameter we actually
use to loop it well I guess you know
it's it's not lerp that's that's
incorrect you shouldn't say that it's
actually like a cubic thing so we
probably need to do our own thing here
something like that I guess
and I'll just make a macro probably that
expands this out
in fact that's almost certainly what
I'll do so what I probably wanted to do
here this was probably a premature
probably didn't need to do it this way I
can probably do just a macro to expand
that out and just say what the what
parameter we're doing right so I can
probably just do this and then I just
need something that will do this
properly right okay so what that looked
like well for a trailer of you know some
field and I guess we didn't even really
need this because since we're defying
the macro of locally we could just say
look that doesn't matter so if we're
fine
we're trying this we know that we can do
it with the cell look up here and to be
fair I guess we didn't really need to do
it we probably could have made these
lookup box a clamped things actually
just be you know cell zero zero zero
cells or what you know we didn't need it
to be an array that may just make it
harder to read so I apologize for that
maybe we'll change that later but for
now so we need to do a trailer for a
particular field what we have to do is
first compute the lerp for each of our
so we first need to do bilinear
interpolation on each of our you know to
two halves of the of the voxel and then
we need to do the linear between them
right so it's basically like a series of
linear blends so the first thing that I
would say is well alright you know if
you take a look at that diagram that I
had before like here so now what we're
effectively saying is look we're sort of
going to break it down and I guess we'll
probably big it down in Z so we'd
probably do it this way
you
so we're pretty much doing is saying all
right the first thing we're gonna do is
take four linear blends to produce
basically these blend points so blend
these this this and this right that
gives us these four will then blend
those to get these and it'll blend those
right so we're just making you know a
series of blends there and so in order
to do that you know first what we would
do like I said is well lerp on X so
we're gonna use that first at in order
to do that what we need is whatever the
field was so we need the cells you know
for that field it'll look like this
right
we need to lurk between the X's of all
possible combinations right so we're
gonna have something that looks
effectively like this where we say look
we're gonna go from 0 to 1 I guess I
should have put that in there first
we're gonna do from 0 to 1 on each X
every X that we have right and so we're
gonna have to do like that I guess right
and so like I said before there's four
of these so I don't know why I was so
over zealous there there's four of these
and that just corresponds to the
different combinations that I could have
done in the other dimensions right and
we're gonna lurk between those so
there's our four loops that we start
with right and like I said that produces
those so now we need to do is lure long
Y so for each Y variance right and you
know what I guess this is the wrong way
round
it should probably be this way right
there yeah so for each y variant I need
to now lerp that right so now you can
kind of see how that's going
[Applause]
so we produce the combinations for the
X's first and then we're gonna lurk
those in Y and then finally there's just
one big lerp at the very end that does
the Z combined and so that's a trilinear
and it's trilinear because it's three
linear blends you first do your blends
in one that's the first blend then you
do your blends in the other dimension
then you do your blends in third
dimension so it's you know three linear
blends in a row all right so that's I
think all we actually need to do and now
it's just a question of getting rid of
compilers and debugging so for here
again we have world P but it's its
sample P in ours so that's the long word
and then we need look up the box of
clamp to be an actual thing now to do
look up box of clamp this is pretty
trivial all we're doing is we're just
going to return the light voxel cell
that is at whatever location we are
asked about so so we basically have an X
the Y and the Z and all we're doing it
going to do is literally just do this
take whatever the words are voxel
I guess so we're gonna take whatever the
cells are here and we're just gonna
return the address of the ZYX
cell and off we go
and if we never we're gonna fetch out of
bounds that would literally be the
entire team but we know that this can
produce out-of-bounds results because we
may be sampling somewhere where it's at
the off the end of the voxel and so we
want to do first is just make sure that
all of our values are clamped so I
believe we have a clamp or these we do
so really this is all we need to do we
just need to feed these values through
the clamp first so we know that we want
to clamp ourselves to large light box'll
or light large voxel dim and maybe we
want to do it to the hot voxel I don't
think we do though because I think will
allow sampling outside to old light
values probably I mean maybe that's dumb
but we'll see I'll put it to doing about
that but either way you know maybe we do
maybe we don't but either way all its
gonna do is change the clamp here to be
a different range so it would be you
know different parameters here in here
but otherwise it'd be the same and so
what we do is we just clamp all those
values and then we do the lookup and
that's it right and so once we have that
I think we there look like there's maybe
a little bit more errors there though
oops that's that's that's all we should
need to do that will get us clamped
values then we'll be able to look these
up I don't know why these are semicolons
you know again it was bad morning for
typos so kind of to be expected who
knows so many typos are creeping into
our code right now and it looks like
maybe this is not quite balanced in the
comma in two places actually
all right what else we got alright uh
it's so it looks like we are missing
something there compute solar
radiance that's what are we missing
oh yes the incidence angle so the
incidence angle here is just how the
light ray is coming in and so the probes
sample n is basically what that is
that's the direction the lights coming
in it's just going the wrong way
so oh no it's not sorry Peart not that
sampled the Ray dirrection there we go
so the Ray Direction right we know we
hit by going in that direction so I
think all we need to do is just pass
that down so right the Ray direction
here is what we actually need
unfortunately that ray Direction is
actually a bundle right it's for Ray
directions in one and so when we're
doing that voxel and by the way it
brings up the fact that this voxel
sampling could probably be done wide
which we may want to do but you know so
we probably want to do this wide and
move it out into here and like basically
pass in like these should all be fours
right so we can just pass these things
directly but for now we're actually
doing an iteration so the raid erection
itself is something that kind of has to
be unpacked right so unpacking that ray
direction what we would need to do is
say all right ray Direction 1 equals get
component where oh well it's sample D
out there actually so it's it's
literally just this right
but again we would like to avoid doing
that so we're probably hoping that Mesa
basically we can just widen this path
for the most part and then only the
thing that actually does the memory
lookups on the voxels would have to be
done sort of not wide so all right
that's how the voxel irradiance would be
going and now we can effectively run
this light transport routine if we want
to the only thing that we don't really
know what to do with now is like the
spamming of the voxels right we're just
gonna go ahead and just call it right
and do the best we can so you know we're
gonna go ahead and stop doing the test
casts I think at this point and start
trying to do actual light convection
it's gonna go terribly we're gonna have
a crap ton of debugging work we're not
going to finish by the end of today but
we're at least gonna get that sort of
going and in order to do that it's
pretty pretty simple we've got our test
cast or like what is it test cast from
probes right so test cast from probes it
just does like a fake lighting solution
right and compute light propagation is
like the real light light solution and
so if you look at the way this is
working what we really want to do is say
all right this transfer here this part
here that we're actually doing that we
want to keep and test cast from probes
is something we actually don't want to
keep anymore and so what we want to do
is say all right let's make this a
switch that can either do the real light
propagation or it can do the test cast
from probes right so if I do this we
will now call call the real routine and
you know it's fail spectacularly or
whatever but that's just the way we want
things to go now if I go look at compute
light provocation you can see that that
doesn't actually pass that this is not
real I don't know why that was still
going through there that was like old
code but you can see that now we're
gonna call this thing and it's gonna
distribute the work out and this is the
the multi work case we can also call the
single work case while we're too buggin
but you know now we're now we're
actually in party zone right so now what
we need to do is start figuring out what
the
is going on and so we're gonna switch
the debug mode because you know if we
got crashes and we gotta like fix all
this stuff
we should also switch to single threaded
probably so if I just you know do that
we'll be in single threaded mode and now
when I do our compilation in debug we
should be able to like step through the
code and see what the heck is going on
so on alright uh looking in here so our
lighting work has changed a little bit
let me just go in and make that work so
yeah like let's see solution first light
probe one pass last first light probe
index one pass light probe index that's
gonna be like probe count so it's
basically that and I think that should
do it
probably didn't we call this compute
light per application work or something
like that yeah we did so what's the
function call for that platform or Q
callback does that not look like that so
platform work you call back looks like
this it takes the work queue and the
data so I guess we're just supposed to
pass the lighting view in here
all right so now what we got to do is
again just figure out what's going on
with our routine and so hopefully we'll
get some information here all right so
to start with this is not really a real
crash this is just we haven't quite
finished writing this routine it looks
like so we have the like and closest
lights bit here so we just never
actually did that so we should probably
do that but for right now we're gonna do
is probably not do and closest lights
we're just gonna call like the get one
closest light feature and or because we
only really need one at the moment right
so instead of any of this stuff you know
we're we're gonna maybe get rid of this
and just say all right
letting box bias toward light is going
to be like what's that get lightly 4p or
whatever the crap it was so this right
and we just need a p-value of where
we're going to actually look for it and
so since we know the point that we're
going to be sampling the light probe
position all we should have to do is
just pass that down and then we'll get
back like the light that is you know Nam
not really closest to us but is near to
us or whatever right a a light that is
near to us um so we could start there
and then we can see what this code is
actually doing and see if it you know we
can actually get it working at all
now we're actually running and so
hopefully like if I compile in release
mode we can see but presumably what our
problems gonna be is we're just gonna
remain black there's not going to be any
actual light because of bugs in the in
the box of sampler or who knows what
else right
all right so here's where we're at you
can see that game is running right and
you know the hero is actually hopping
around but you can't see it I can sort
of see the faint little lines in here so
what we need to do now is figure out why
we're not getting any light back right
and so we're gonna want to do is step
through our you know our lighting
function here and see what's going on
but you know basically we got to figure
out how this you know makes this routine
work properly and also you know it
should be at least injecting some
transfer some light transfer in here so
I think we maybe just have some basic
issues
and you know this doesn't have to happen
in Murr because this happens at the end
you
I would think
yeah so anyway I'm gonna step through
this cuz I don't really know what's
wrong with it
right so I want to see what's going on
and we'll go from there so I'm gonna
start by saying look we should have the
bias towards light path we should hit
something sometimes right and the more
interesting thing to to me actually is
that if we didn't hit anything so like
let's see go in this path we should be
injecting some moon color even if we
didn't hit anything so the fact that
this isn't working is really weird I'm
just gonna actually jump to here really
quickly and see what our what our status
is for like light P light C and light
fall-off oops did I not recompile
so here's our information if I look at
the light color there is light coming
back so that's a bit weird and we're
going to spam the voxel so
[Music]
you
so the fact that the light fall-off
I think that's the wrong way to go for
the moonlight right so light fall-off
gets multiplied in here I think yes
times the light oh no but that should so
the lighting should be adding something
here shouldn't it
ah I know what's going on
so one thing we did and we shouldn't
have done it this way because it was
misleading is in the test cast from
probes we welded the part here that does
the updating of the voxel into the test
cast but we need that to actually happen
inside the lighting always right that
needs to happen here effectively right
so we were never we were accumulating
stuff but that we were never actually
doing anything with the accumulated
version okay so that that makes sense
that that didn't work so we should
because we should even if our ray Kassar
is totally busted we should be seeing
some moonlight because that's what
happens when you don't find any light
sources you're supposed to just get a
little bit of moonlight right um so this
looks totally crazy right now I have no
idea what's going on there but that's
actually better at least than it was
because now at least we sort of are
seeing something right all right so
let's run this in full speed and see
what the heck we're looking at here and
then we'll sort of start to try and
figure out what the heck what's going on
with our with our code right alright so
that was just some crazy I don't know
what that was about but anyway so we are
seeing some light so we can get started
here so let's take a look inside compute
light propagation again we're doing this
single threaded so we shouldn't have to
worry about any weird like threading
things that are happening now and if we
look down here where we're doing our
light updating right here's where we're
spending our voxels you know and this
should be clearing those out right so we
should be seeing some something stable
like you know what's a little bit weird
is why did it go to black like why did
we not
why didn't don't we see just a stable
light there I'm not 100% sure there
might be some like Manning or something
like that going on in here but um so you
know this code path in fact one thing I
could do too is just maybe we just start
with just trying to debug just the moon
the moon light itself so if I literally
just nuke the path that ever actually
does anything right
say we're always gonna just do moonlight
transfer it sounds like some kind of bad
70s band if we just do moonlight
transfer like what happens there and one
thing you can see from the moonlight
transfer at the moment is it's a little
nonsensical the results that we're
getting I especially don't understand
why moving in here changes I don't
understand why that gets darker when we
move in Oh possibly because we are the
closer light than that one was or
something like that and maybe that's not
that understandable but anyway so I'm
curious like about this now like let's
try and figure out why you know the
ambient light looks way too bright you
know why is that and I'm not sure so if
we take a look at how this is being
spamed out here
you
I'm not sure about the Ray wait either
is that
so we're not using the railway either so
we also don't this is totally busted as
well and this is not six anymore
[Music]
you
yeah so if we look at what's happening
here the REA bundle count is how many of
these were going to do right and so the
weight of each one of these would be 1
over the rate bundle count I'm not sure
that that's even necessary though
because we're doing a power sum here in
fact you can see us doing the power sum
and then we're normalizing by the total
power after so I'm pretty sure that
actually this just doesn't need to be
here anymore
when we span the voxel we could just
probably just looking at this
average light location the average light
fall-off and then the light color the
light color is never normalized for some
reason
about this so we're summing the light
color every time but we never normalize
that and we probably should so I guess
maybe I spoke too soon there
you
so this is gonna do one over the Rabin
del count times the raise per bundle
right so it's it's actually times four
and so the Rey wait down here
wouldn't you be used to normalize this
right so I do think that needed to
happen because these are two this was
way too bright and I think that was why
cuz the color was never adjusted
properly and so that should be down
there but the problem is you know are
the way that our color encoding works is
we actually sort of color encode a few
steps down black is is below like the
actual color of no light is moved
upwards by the fact that we're doing
sort of that clamping of the light that
shifting of the light value to get the
interpolation and so it's hard to say we
kind of need to work that out a little
bit more but for now we'll boost our
light files eventually we're gonna have
to go through and work out exactly the
exact math on that to get it just right
but basically what that means is like
yeah this has to be sort of shifted into
a range that actually produces some
visible light there once we do that
truncation and I'm not sure what that
value would necessarily be but we can
play with it and figure out what it
should be back in here
just need to figure out roughly where we
think that that ambient should be at
so that's somewhere right in there looks
like
you
so one thing that's really kind of
strange though is I'm not quite sure why
we're getting different values depending
on where you are I mean this is an
ambient light it should be added into
everybody right and so I guess I'm not
sure where that's coming from that seems
concerning like why would my location
ever change that information because
we're not actually doing anything with
like we're not we if zero it out the
case that actually happens when you hit
a light source so in you know it doesn't
really make a lot of sense is a mission
direction so I guess
I guess that bias does come in
[Music]
you
yeah I'm not sure what we want to do
about that what we would need to do here
for admission directions so a couple
things about this if you look like that
is one place where that thing would have
needed to be normalized and currently
it's not so if we actually look at
what's going on with that initial ray
Direction here
that's not normalized and pretty much
does need to be right so that's a bit of
an issue
yeah that's a bit of an issue so what we
would want to do here I guess let me
just take a look at what we've got here
proxy nose so I'm gonna do a raid
director you know I'm gonna do an
approximate on it and that would
normalize it so that we wouldn't be
getting wildly different results for
rays that are you know pointing directly
upwards towards one oops versus ones
that aren't so I'm assuming that would
allow us to deal with this now more
stable II but again there may be some
other bugs in here
you
right so to me that looks pretty moon
lady you know again I'm not really sure
exactly what's going on with some of
this stuff it looks like there's still
some weirdness in terms of what's going
like why is that I guess that might be
just because things that haven't been
pulled in yet take a while to relight at
that slow of speed
which I guess is going to be a problem
for us but
you
right
so I'm not sure I think we still have
some bugs in there but I'm gonna just
push forward again I know this is gonna
be a long process so as much as it is
annoying I'm just gonna go ahead and say
all right let's try and get as far as we
can
this should blow up now in theory
because like we know something is crazy
about it and the way that those are kind
of flashing like that I believe that
means we're getting some kind of madness
in there like I think we're getting some
invalid values somehow somebody is
returning garbage or like f32 max right
or something so you know maybe that's
you know maybe that's this right I don't
know but anyway so somehow I think we're
getting some garbage values in there I'm
not sure exactly how
I'm not sure why that would be exactly
you
and I don't think there's anything weird
like uninitialized or anything so I'm
not sure why we would be getting weird
values here because you would think that
this all should have been reasonable and
looking at like so you know we're
getting the probe sample out of this
we're getting the normal here we're
getting the color out here and the
emission value so you know I guess just
looking at this I'm just gonna say like
maybe the easiest thing to do is to just
try and say well the only stuff that
really comes out of here
that's particularly strange I mean I
guess light pee
you
what happens with light P probe sample P
so probe sample P is moon P and then in
here we would compute it as get combined
so bright alright so basically like this
is the only stuff we actually ever see
so probe sample P transfer PB s and this
light fall-off this light fall-off is
0.5 here and 0 here so like the chances
that that's causing a significant Manesh
kind of problem or like 0 unless we were
dividing by this light fall-off which we
know we're not and also that's the case
that works right so I think we're
looking at transfer PPS and light P must
have bugs in them somehow so let's take
a look at them and say like you know if
inbounds or looks fishy right I'm gonna
just make this function called looks
fishy and I'm gonna pass these two
things to it like give myself a way to
get a break point in to see if some of
these values are weird and so what I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna make a
function called looks fishy and again
this is just a aid debugging here right
so basically what that's gonna do is
it's going to return if you pass it in
some kind of a vector it's going to
return a result that like if this vector
looks kind of fishy it's gonna say true
so what I'm going to say here is looks
fishy
X
[Applause]
and I'm just gonna make it looks fishy
for scalar and then that's all I really
need right and I'm going to say this
this scalar looks fishy I you know if if
a dot X I want it to kind of be inbounds
right so I want a to X to be greater
than equal to like negative something
large and a 2x a right so I just want to
you know have some way of testing this
thing and finding out like roughly
whether these values are in bounds at
all
and I'm gonna change this to debug mode
and I'm hoping what'll happen is we'll
just get a breakpoint there and we'll be
able to see that some of our values are
just getting you know in just totally
busted that's the hope so let's see so
here we are and we know that we're you
know the folks we're looking at here now
let me look at transfer PPS and light
key
so here's those values transfer PPS
looks fine light P I mean is that really
possible
I mean technically that value is not
ridiculous but it does seem like that
would be kind of weird that the light
position could really be that far away
so I'm what kind of wondering is light P
actually valid so light P in this case
oh that's the summation though it's it's
sorry so it shouldn't be light p its
probperly going re we're looking at the
wrong value there is nothing wrong with
that
so let's let it run a little more here
and see if anything looks fishy we're
hoping it does
you
okay good so we're getting a looks fishy
here let's see what the actual things we
get are so that I mean Oh again look
into throwing one say that's ridiculous
so yeah like it looks like I guess
there's no immediate like nanning
involved but it does look like our light
are feeding back on themselves
like we're putting light into the system
and it's just like driving out - it's
just getting like an infinite amount of
light like way too much light like we're
not properly averaging in the amount
that should be average dinner or
something like this right
so something weird is happening when
we're actually producing when we're
doing the spam voxels like this stuff is
not computing something stabili or
something the transfer PPS is just way
too high and so normally what what's
happening here I guess is is we're doing
that by taking the sample ref color I'm
assuming that's coming from here because
presumably sample ref color should
should never really be particularly high
I mean maybe it is coming back badly but
I would like to see so let's set a
breakpoint in here where we actually got
a hit and see about how much light we're
sending back so let's see we've got a
probe oh sorry we've got voxel
irradiance here here's our trail in here
filtering
so I light in zero weight in one all
right
c0 yeah so this would just produce no
light at all it does and so
first this looks like it's working okay
I guess we don't really know like if
this was going to be something that
actually hit a light source and the
emission value came back then we're
going to actually put something in there
right
you
but again I don't really see that being
particularly bad let me take a look in
here I I don't remember what we're doing
inside spam box well I'm not seeing
anything really all that suspicious yet
which is not good the more subtle it is
the worse right so if we go in here and
take a look at what's happening this is
just filling in the light field
you
and this is kind of yeah so this is kind
of broken so spam voxel slice yeah is
is already accounting for the intensity
range of the light source here so that
is not actually the way we would want to
do it so spam voxel slice probably has
to be changed a little bit
[Music]
and that fall-off has to be more of and
like this this needs to be about the
actual fall off because the emission
rate has already been put in there and
so the light a actually should just be
going like you know between like zero
and one really so so that's not it's not
really what we wanted right
so let me fix that first let's just
let's just try and fix that one part and
we'll see what happens so if this
actually was not going to do that and we
were just gonna use the light DF instead
so this would just do a fall if it
wouldn't do the light intensity boosting
like it was doing there before hmm I'm
just curious what we end up with now
again I think it's still broken I don't
think this will actually fix it but I'm
just curious if we can now sort of
isolate a different portion of the code
is being busted as opposed to just that
which was feeding back like very large
values
you
again not really sure what's going on
here
you
still pretty weird right like I just
don't even know exactly how we're
getting that because since these voxels
are supposed to be kind of smoothed over
time it's like those must be really huge
values that are like coming in and out
of there right so we're still in like
real bizarro and just producing like
fully crazy values and I guess we don't
really know whether it's you know it
could be crazy in in multiple ways it
could be crazy because the normal is
really weird
or it could be crazy because the color
is really weird and one thing we
probably do want to do is normalize our
normals the fact that our normals aren't
normal is a little weird so like for
example when we're doing like the
spamming of the voxels and then we do
you know we accumulate the normals
accumulating the normals shouldn't
actually renormalize them using the
normal value it should renormalize them
using normalization because you want to
your normals to be normal you don't want
them to just be an average because that
could produce pretty much anything
really so I suppose we also should
probably do an end lighting computation
where we do this what we should probably
do is say yeah this part
[Music]
you
where you blend these two together after
that you want to actually do a
normalization right so here you'd want
to do this and again I don't really
think that has much to do with anything
at the moment but it just occurred to me
that like we want our normals to always
be normal we don't want them to be
averages and so off we go now in theory
if the normals are always normal in
theory that would mean that the color
values are the thing that's wrong right
now because we know that they're always
normal really hard to say when we're
looking at this here I also wonder to
what extent we need to do clamping like
so when we output the voxel and we do
light c0 output here how is that getting
encoded
so these don't look like they're maybe
being clamped correctly either so when
the light I value comes in it could be
between zero and whatever right
[Music]
you
and I guess I don't know so but it looks
like it's taking the maximum value so
whatever the highest value is and then
it's like normalizing these down right
so it seems like in theory that should
mean that these are always reasonably
behaved you know what I mean because
whatever the highest value is I mean I
guess you know they could be if somehow
they got to be negative which would be
pretty ridiculous because we're only
ever adding values in but no matter what
the highest value actually is I would
think it should be okay
because this will always knock it back
down
right
so I don't really see any way that could
really overflow so I'm not sure again
I'm not sure where the flickering could
possibly come from let's go ahead and do
some testing so when I do the transfer
suppose that I was to stop transferring
the normals altogether and I just said
look you know the normal is always going
to be the same or something right
so when we actually do the words that go
so down here when we actually pack the
by normal to normal here and we do you
know the packing of these things down
what if I just said like look it's
always just like Z or something right so
so now like I've taken that out of the
equation
and when we run this we should always
have stable normals like always right
and so there's what our result looks
like and then similarly like what if I
leave the normal is the same and always
output the same color so like okay the
color value is just always going to be
like krei or something or maybe it
remember this is sort of a weird
irradiance pack thing oh right I have to
do in a radiance pack on it this let's
suppose I just put in some kind of
stable value here that's always going to
be the same and I don't know what that
value would be but it's like you know
let's say that grey
and now if I just tweak with those what
do I get so all right we're irradiance
packing some values here I don't
actually know what these need to be this
is probably part of the encoding stuff
that we now have to go start working out
more directly to because you know we now
have problems all over the place it's
like pretty hard for us to know exactly
what is what here so how high does this
have to be to actually produce visible I
don't know I don't remember what our max
light intensity is here why don't we
have two of those okay there we go
so that's really bizarre to write so
like that's is that from the normals so
if I now pack a normal in back away so
there is weirdness coming in from both
places basically right so if I pack the
actual normal it's weird too
you
like somehow the normal to the light
that's getting computed for all of these
probes is like I guess downward or
something something that's creating a
pure black they're like I don't know
right like but you can see that that's
purely coming from the normal so I
suppose we can kind of break this into
two separate problems one is that we're
out putting weird information for the
color and one is that we're out putting
weird information for the normal
it would seem
right
you
so I'm not sure how to proceed now we've
got a lot of stuff to debug I'm not sure
what the best way to do it would be but
there we see very you know clearly that
we're getting kind of weird values
coming in so presumably like here where
we're spamming this information and we
sort of have what the light position is
that stuff is coming from you know that
that value is getting set to something
very weird by the rate caster and we
don't really know why that's happening
you know I also realized - we're gonna
have to do a little bit of work when we
multi-thread this because we can't just
sum into a voxel because we don't know
who is doing which part at which voxel
so we're gonna have to break it up
instead of by light probes we're gonna
have to break it up by voxel region
which is a little bit of a pain in the
butt but that's just how it is
you
so there's another thing that I think
that maybe we should be doing here
which is that when we do our spamming I
wonder if we should really be doing that
a little bit differently to which is to
say that we may want our light probes to
not quite do that right we may want our
light probes to
I think this probably doesn't want to do
what it's doing I think we probably just
want to spam just the voxel that we're
in and then we want to just do like a
flood fill probably on the voxel later
so this is probably bad too so let's
take this one step at a time I'm gonna
say that maybe we want spam voxel slice
to actually just be the only thing we
call so I'm going to say like maybe we
don't do this and we'll add a flood fill
to flood fill outward so maybe it would
look more like this
you
and I think we want to probably take it
one step at a time
but I do think like yeah so the you know
the the flood filling to fill in what we
probably want to do is make sure we have
enough light probes that we don't have
any problem with filling in data in the
general case and then when we get to the
edges we can flood fill our voxel for
people who didn't get any samples we can
just flood fill our voxel from there
right but I do think we want to like get
away from having to do all that spamming
right I think that's probably a bad idea
all right so moving on it's weird like
it's getting close to being good right
but yeah so I think we do want to fix
that one part and let's also while we're
at it let's fix the test case now as
well so I'm gonna go to the test cast
the column again test cast from probes
so in test cast from probes I'm gonna go
ahead and test cast from probes I'm
going to enable that again and we have
to fix the light intensity there we have
to output a different light intensity
because the light intensity were
outputting won't be sufficient right so
if we do test cast from probes so here's
the test cast from probes version not
using the flood fill right
and actually there's surprisingly few
things that actually fail when you're
not when you're not doing that and see a
couple right but they're surprisingly
few
so it does look like we have a dense
enough sampling of light probes to not
have too many artifacts at the immediate
moment
so that's all right
you
hmm
I say alright so the fact that that is
doing what it's doing there right if we
go down and look at the you know that
that was always packing in a fixed color
but packing in a normal here so I guess
you know yeah and maybe I should fix
this part first too so let me go ahead
and put in a switch for this so we can
do either one that nurse the color value
and so if I want to now I can just like
switch between those two and say all
right let's not nerf the color value
let's actually look at what the test
case was outputting for the color value
because that maybe that's why it looked
like it was okay it's cuz the color
value was getting stuffed right oh and
that so I'm going to try that and just
see what happens there too because I
think we'll see more gaps now in theory
but maybe not we'll see yeah okay so
also now the intensity is wrong as I
thought it should be okay good good good
so let's go test out some probes and
increase the light intensity so this
right here you know I don't know what
the light intensity should be so we'll
make something up at the moment there we
go
so it does seem like that light fall-off
there is pretty steep right and you can
see that it shifts around to follow me
and I don't know is that just because of
the intensity I'm not sure but let's
find out I'm just going to increase the
intensity here and see what happens
so we'll reload the code there is an
increased intensity so let's fall off
so you know I'm just I'm just seeing a
lot of stuff that that seems
questionable right you know some of it
makes perfect sense some of the stuff
that you see there is just because we're
only casting to that one light source so
you know a fairer test would be instead
of doing this we should probably always
just be testing with that because
otherwise it just doesn't really mean
anything
so this let's just go to testing casting
from just a single light source and now
we know where it is right but if we look
at what's happening there I'm still not
sure it makes really any sense what I'm
seeing I mean maybe it does but I don't
know so if we take a look at at how
that's shifting now I guess that does I
guess that does look okay because inside
you know there's no there's the voxels
up here get nothing because we're not
flood filling them right so you only get
whatever you can see from this light
source and probably you know maybe
that's a little bit laggy on the light
source so you know maybe let's suppose
we change the light preservation to
something like about twice as fast
still maybe a little bit much I guess
that would sway more than twice as fast
now that I think about it there was many
times faster so this is about ten times
faster and that seems better right
all right so I think I want to maybe
because I think like we're gonna need
another weekend of debugging for sure
I'd like to take a look at flood filling
the voxel perhaps and maybe doing some
things with the encoding how much time
do I have a half an hour because our
encoding was pretty ad-hoc maybe we need
to like tighten that up a little bit and
then get the flood filling into the
correct place cuz I feel like there's
too many variables right now and so
trying to debug you know any particular
one of them seems you know sort of not
possible right so let's suppose we move
to a direct voxel fill like we're doing
here and then we flood fill to get our
edges proper right so that the fall-off
around the edges where light stops in
the voxel looks okay okay
and that again can just be done like
sort of with a filter I think after the
fact I hope that's my that's my hope
anyway and in theory we should be okay
all right so the first thing I think we
want to do is try and get the encoding
into a good state and and what I mean by
that is like right now like the normal
encoding is pretty simple it's just a
directional field right so we don't
really have to think too hard about that
we don't really know how to blend them
because we don't know how to produce
more than one like if we only have one
light source then it's pretty simple but
assuming we have like hundreds of light
sources and we want to simulate those
hundreds by projecting down into four
light fields how we do that I'm not
exactly sure
right because you kind of have a K
clusters problem at that point and it's
not clear how you do an incremental K
clusters on this sort of thing you know
maybe it turns out to be simple I don't
know if look at it but we're talking
about the colors there is an encoding
issue there and the encoding issue is
just how do we want to reproduce sort of
the stuff where we get beyond zero right
so really what I'm talking about is this
right here so encoding so that that
works properly requires you to have
effectively like negative light value so
when your light fall-off would end and
you're going like path
that you need to still have those you
need to still have real values they're
right you can't just clamp to zero
that's not going to cut it so what we
need for the interpolation we need the
coding that has effectively like you
know you've heard of Headroom and audio
recording well this is the opposite this
is tail room right we effectively need
something where where we do our
irradiance pack on here what we kind of
need to do is figure out effectively
sort of how we want to shift this light
information around such that it actually
has you know for lack of the term tail
room and the way I think we would
probably want to do that is to let our
light values go to negative so that in
the actual
in the actual code pass in on a CPU side
we know that zero means no light and
that negative means that we're extending
our understanding of light into sort of
regions where there's no light but we
want to capture how the fall-off would
have gone and so I think what we want to
do is create a definition here where
that's going to be valid right so I
think what I'd do is I'd say when the
light value comes in I would then say
that we need to clamp these values and
when we do the irradiance pack on them
we want to first scale ourselves up a
little bit to allow for a little bit of
negative light so if I go to the Z bias
program here and we look at how that's
you know playing out you can see where
we do the light unpack it's here right
and this is not what we want right
that's a perfect halfway split point so
that's basically saying we're going to
bisect the range and have you know
intensity on one side be about the same
as intensity on the other so that the
dark areas get as much as the light
areas and I don't think we want that so
I think what we want instead is
something like this we would say first
of all let's take the light and boost it
by our floor value right so like we
would have like a light floor or
something right and this light floor
value is just going to be like how much
you know it's it's a vector that says
how much light exactly we have to work
with in this case so
how much light we have underneath black
underneath no light and again that's
just for keeping the interpolation
working we need values down there so the
light floor value in this case you know
is gonna be something like this and I
don't know what we should call that
light floor value is not the greatest
name but suppose we did something like
that right so we were just like look you
know Oh point one point one point one or
something is how much room we have there
maybe we do something that's trying to
be a little bit more power of TUI right
and so you have some range but most of
your range is the visible light and then
only a little bit is the dark light
because we're just going to assume that
the fall-off rate is not such that we
need to capture these huge values as we
step out into the voxels we don't need
it to be that precise of an
interpolation so we're just not gonna
assume we need that much tail room there
so when the light comes in the first
thing we would do is shift it up by the
floor value so that we have basically as
much as we can in the actual visible
space and then we would just do like a
clamp and I don't know if that we can
clamp a vector it looks like we can yes
so we wouldn't really want to clamp zero
to one necessarily but we would want to
do that a little later on so I guess
then what we would do is we take the
maximum all of these things I guess we
do really want to clamp it here though
so I'm going to do a clamp
of the MaxLite intensity value year
right
I guess all we really need to do is just
clamp the zero end actually so I think
all we really need to do here is say
look I think that's all we really need
to do I don't think we need to clamp in
the other direction so we just need to
clamp things that are so negative that
they would be underneath the light floor
right so we first shift up by the light
floor value then we clamp to make sure
that we're within that range we now know
that nothing can be negative we take the
maximum value and we normalize out by
that if it was greater than the maximum
intensity that's okay this will take
care of it this clamp right here and
then we encode the light so then in the
pixel shader when we actually need to
deconstruct this then we're not actually
doing this anymore so what we're doing
instead is we're saying well we have an
a value that we use to encode the light
for maximum intensity so we're going to
multiply that out first so here we would
say this clamp doesn't need to happen I
think so I think what we want to do here
is say all right we're going to take the
max light intensity multiplied by the
actual intensity of the light that we
encoded and then multiply that by the
actual light for the actual lighting
values and then that gives us back the
value that we actually encoded in the
first place
but we know that that's been shifted up
slightly by the light floor value so
then we need to do is like remove that
light floor value and that will shift us
back down into the negative range then
we just color things as we normally
would right
so then the light floor value actually
does have to be in there somewhere and
so when we actually output the pound
Defiance for this thing we're probably
gonna have to put that in there
right so we're gonna have to do like you
know our light for value has to get put
in here and that's just something that's
going to come in fact I guess we don't
even have to quite do it that way it
would really just be like this
have to make a string out of that
somehow
you
you know what I can do is I can do right
then the light floor value is the thing
that we can put in here as a percent F
just like we do everything else and so
then when we do all of this stuff we can
just say like light floor value goes
there right and then inside the shader
when we actually need to produce that
light floor value we can just put the
subtraction in right here now I still
don't really know if that's the best way
to do that but something like that and
then we would put the light floor value
pound to fine over with max light
intensity so it ends up you know making
some sense there and then hopefully that
sort of works so that's now a different
encoding of the lighting and hopefully
that makes it easier for us to work with
this stuff so it won't be so ridiculous
all the time now I don't actually know
but hopefully that will help right
because now it's just it's just saying
it's more sane right what we're looking
at okay so looking at the test here it
looks like it roughly works you can see
that when we do the encoding you get
values that kind of shift I assume
because we're just don't have enough
precision in the light information
itself we get a lot of flickering from
that and it's kind of an unfortunate
source of flickering it would be nice if
we didn't have that so I do wonder if
that means we want these values to be
more work we just need more resolution
right we just need more resolution in
the in the light intensity valued right
and so in order to - oh that looks nice
kind of to look kind of nice um
and so I think we also kind of have a
separate problem here that maybe we
should fix this just like the encoding
isn't enough bits right like the the
encoding needs to be like 16 bits or
something or we need to encode the you
know we can encode the RGB one way but
include you know like maybe like a y UV
or something where we have 16 bits for
the Alpha for the intensity value and
then just like two things for the color
or something like that right so we could
try to do something like that like you
know use a different lighting space like
loggia V or something like that I don't
want to do that yet because I think that
again introduces yet more parameters
into the system that we have to then
wrestle with so I think what I'd rather
do is figure out if we can get a cheap
way here to make to me make this maybe
be 16 bits so you know maybe I don't
know but if we were to look at how the
opengl how the texture was being sent
down there if we look here right you can
see we've got some of the like look up
stuff
that's the normal so here's the light
data here you can see it's RGB eight and
it's submitting an unsigned byte and so
I just wonder like you know suppose we
we kick that up to like an unsigned
short you know and did the encoding that
way we could also use like half float or
something like that but I wonder do we
have those defines we have to copy those
defines in but if we have those defines
we could then potentially yeah we do
we could start submitting these as
unsigned shorts and if we put them in as
unsigned shorts then maybe we can get a
little bit more out of that so looking
at the light voxel information that
we're submitting there right so when we
actually go to do the irradiance pack
here instead of doing a BG are a pack
four by eight we would actually
producing like a 64-bit value and
putting that out as a result right and
if we looked at how that would go just
going down to the where the light stuff
actually gets set up if we were to do a
64 pack it would look something like
this it would be the exact same call
right so it's it's really really simple
but when we're doing this rounding and
we produce these values what we would
want to do here is this would explain
the 65535 and this would be packing a
64-bit value instead of a a set of a
32-bit value so 16 32 48 right
um so it's pretty easy for us to do
something like that and then we just
have to actually like record that that
packing what's it complaining about
conversion from you 64 to you 32 sorry
yeah and so now all we have to do is
actually allocate that storage as a
different kind of storage so now like
the light see that information that's
going to be 64-bit coming down and all
we're doing here is increasing the bit
depth a little bit just to see to what
extent we're getting a problem with just
bit depth information there right and so
you can see here light voxel C needs to
be expanded so what we're getting there
is like this information right needs to
be 64 s right
and like j2c is the same so that's just
that so again nothing really interesting
happening there I just wanted to
increase the Biff depth a little bit to
see whether that flickering was coming
from it or not and I don't know that is
not what I expected even a little bit so
what did I screw up there did I I not
Oh haha yeah so actually we said short
on the initial one but we didn't say
short on this one
oops
you
my bad
okay so here's one that has more light
bits and I just want to see if that has
anything to do with it
so I would say it's you know I can't
even really tell if there's maybe even
more there so you know I'm just going to
say forget it we're just gonna send this
down regular and we'll figure out the
encoding later right so I'm gonna do it
to do figure out the encoding for these
later and because I don't really want to
have to wrestle with that anymore
because you know what that could be the
normal as well so I'll switch both of
these now we can play with them but I'm
just gonna like I'm gonna let these be
encoded exactly as they are as just
floats and just say look we're gonna
we'll figure out the encoding later when
we actually care but that's what we're
gonna do okay
so the lightbox will see in the in the
platform layer here so light box let's
see here we're gonna change that to be
VIII's right and then we're just not
gonna pack the values at all we're just
going to leave them exactly as they are
so these light C values here instead of
calling a radiance pack on those we're
not going to we're just going to do that
right and this is just me saying look
that was pretty mature we want to see
the actual values we're computing so
that we know that the the art of any
artifacts that we see are not from our
quantization and then later when we're
trying to optimize things then we'll
quantize so that was just me being lazy
because I didn't want to have to like
add a float path there but that's not
what we want to do and so here where we
set up the the light C's we'll do those
this way and we won't pack and then when
we do our sampling in the pixel shader
we just we'll just use it exactly as it
is right we won't touch it
we won't change the value in any way so
that we know like packing or clamping or
anything right and then so yeah the Z
bias program where this thing gets you
know
we used I'm not I'm gonna like nerf out
this bit here and just say that whatever
the light for that you know whatever
that light see came back as
you
yeah we're just going to use so I'm
gonna say oops I'm gonna say the lights
color equals the light the RGB and used
that's it no modification for the light
floor no modification for anything so
then in the OpenGL code when we submit
our textures down we're just gonna
submit floats for both of them and
that's all that's going to happen so the
the sixteen there this this one this is
going to come down as float just like
before when we ask for how it's going to
be stored I'm gonna ask for a float
there as well so I'm gonna see if we can
just get that in both cases so not
encoded in any kind of shifty way there
right and so when we do the normal I
don't know if we unpacked that here's
the light normal
you
so light and ink right also got unpacked
I'm not gonna do that so when I have
that go in the same way as well so
basically all of this will just stay
exactly as it was so we get floats there
we get floats here and then I guess we
also just need to make sure that we're
those are actually submitted their float
but I think we already did that yep
all right so I think that's what we
needed and now everything should be
kosher when we actually packed these we
would just be assigning them directly as
well so inside the letting call when we
actually surface the voxel there what
I'd like to do is just make that make
that packing code not actually use sorry
where does that radience the by normal
to normal thing we don't want to do
anymore right so we want to just assign
these directly so these should be like
this and off we go
and so let's try to get this working
before we end for the day so just now
passing everything that is floats so we
know that like look it's piggy there's
probably no reason for it but at least
we can start to eliminate like any
suspicion we have about the artifacts
coming from quantization and so I think
my suspicion was well-founded
so like looking at it now it's not
sparkly anymore at all right but you can
tell that it's a bad idea right just
looking at it currently it's very slow
by comparison to the old one so you can
see like those texture samplers really
do cost you right it's not free now we
can speed it back up again it doesn't
have to be slow I'm assuming that's the
graphs right I guess I don't really know
so I should be careful there but inside
our actual Z bias program we can sample
less of those right at the moment we're
not using a bunch of them so if we
wanted to we could just say like yeah
don't actually do any of this right just
sample one of them and use that and that
should in theory get us you know that
speed back if it is the graphics card
that's the actual problem right which I
think it was I don't see because it
slowed down only when I'm out here
right and so now when we look at this
right and now it's perfectly fast again
and so I do think you know you could I
wasn't wrong that we need to do some
encoding to keep that stuff fast but it
does have a cost right and it looks like
the cost may have been mostly in the
encoding of the normals not in the
encoding of the colors which is pretty
interesting but you know that's just
something that's worth looking at right
and so we may be able to go ahead and
make color values be much much less
resolute but we may need to make our
normals be 64-bit encoded or maybe we
change to an encoding that's like an X
and a Y and then a bit for Z or
something like that right just so we can
get more data out in there so we
definitely have an encoding problem we
could choose to like work on the
encoding is a little bit more because
now we have we know exactly like we have
a case where we can demonstrate that
it's perfect no no freckling and so we
just would need some way of going wait a
minute
what kind of encoding can we do here
that would that would make that work so
I'm going to go ahead and say that's it
for today next week and me what we'll do
is get the encoding working correctly
but we're almost there on that and then
we can go back to the ray casting and
get that working so you know again
getting pretty close you know it's and
you can see here we've got issues to
like so do you see how we're centering
the simulation region is centered over
there right now for some reason I don't
really know why that's the case
you
so if we look at exactly what's going on
there the simulation center is it's
really very far this way even though
this room is not
not actually the center
yeah but anyway point B you can see how
the lighting voxel probably doesn't want
to be simulation center based we
probably want it to be more camera based
when we move that voxel around so that's
another thing we got to do we got plenty
of stuff to do
you
um so yeah maybe I'm also gonna start
here like a little list because there's
a lot of stuff here so if we go to
lighting I'm gonna put a little thing in
that right so that's one that we can
just do next weekend that's one we could
just do get that working get our
encoding so it's nice and smooth and
then we just don't have to think about
that as a possible source of error
anymore
right so you could do that or we could
do that later but either way we can do
that and figure that out right number
two would be flood filled the voxel so
that portions that didn't get sampled
get filled in from nearby samples so
basically you have filter pass so I'll
do that's just to fill in the edges
there and then what we want to do I
think is fix the voxel centering so that
a lighting hot region is always nearby
to the camera so we don't see
so I think those are some small - dues
that way I just want to remember them
all because they all have to happen
separate from going now than fixing the
light transport to be working properly
because it's kind of busted at the
moment so we'll work on the light
transport but we also have these three
and we want to do those separate so
that's what we're looking at heading
into next weekend
all right let's go ahead and go to QA
oops miss type that there
[Music]
where is my discord
yeah okay
you
- why you pound to find internal -
static so you know I've kind of had a
slight change of mind on that that
there's now like other reasons to do it
than the one that I originally did and I
probably wouldn't have chosen the name
internal so you know six of one half
dozen together but I don't like the word
the keyword static in C and C++ I think
it was a really bad idea it is the basis
of it the reason is because it's used
for two totally different purposes so
you can't really grep very effectively
for things like I don't ever need to
grep for whether I have functions that
are defined static because all my
functions usually can be defined static
I definitely want to know if there's any
variables defined static like that's
really important to know so the keywords
what I would have done if it were up to
me is I would have had the following B
keywords I would have had them be
function and external function and these
would have mapped to static and you know
nothing right and you would have had to
have put these in front of everything so
whenever you defined a function you
would say function void through and you
would go right and that would default to
internal linkage only so only in the
same compilation module and then if you
wanted something exported you would have
said that now I don't care what these
are you know maybe you don't want to
type that much so it's just func and you
know e funk or something right I don't
care but but that's what I wanted to
keywords to be static and nothing not
cool right that is just not what should
be there and especially because in in if
you want to make lightweight text
Cicero's for example that look at C code
or something the fact that it's just a
type name that starts a function is also
terrible right because it means you have
to have global awareness of the entire
set of things that happen in the program
in order just to even know if
something's a function half the time
right but anyway so I would have done
that and any other thing I would have
done is I would have had keywords for
like global variable or something and
local persistent variable right and
those would have mapped both to what the
see currently defines a static and and
basically you know and you would have
had to have said which one of these you
were talking about right and again maybe
you just want them to be like you know X
glob and you know blob and local
position right so they can be terse if
you want I don't care but they should
have been keywords and they should have
had a different one for each case so I
think that makes sense right
you
is there a way to suggest or home the
processor that a branch is likely or not
likely to be taken goal is to help with
branch prediction
mmm well so yeah I want to see the
answer is currently No
you
I want to say the answer is currently No
don't quote me on that because I'd have
to go look it up but I think the answer
is currently no there isn't there has
been many times many ways as they say in
the Merry Christmas song so there used
to be things where like the branch
predictor would initialize to assume
that like backward branches were taken
and forward branches weren't so you
could always structure your code so that
the positive side of an if statement was
the most likely case and the else was
the least likely and loops were always
biased that way right that was a thing
that used to happen on certain CPUs if I
remember correctly there was branch
prediction bits so there were ways you
could actually put it into the assembly
language or the machine code into the
jump instructions on certain CPUs where
things were say a hint as to whether
this is commonly taken or commonly not I
remember at least to those two things I
want to say that none of those are true
anymore
I could be wrong because I not up to
date on some of these things I haven't
looked at branch prediction in a while
but I want to say that currently the
Intel and AMD branch prediction
architectures are their own thing that
just I don't know that they really have
the ability to be hinted at anymore
maybe there is I don't know you would
have to go look but I don't know of a
way to do it anymore so I'm sorry you're
gonna have to go read the docs I think
is the real answer
what's your owner stream we said
something along the lines of I've never
worked on a commercial compiler so have
you ever worked on a non-commercial
compiler yes I have worked on
non-commercial compilers meaning like
internal things that do compilation
stuff some of them are more like text
translators like a trad I wrote some
text translators that we used which
Fabien always had the dubious honour of
having to turn into real compilers later
because then one of the weird things
that always happens it seems if you ever
make something that's just a simple text
translator people will start using it
and they'll end up wanting it to
eventually be a cool compiler that's
just what it that's it's it's just I
don't know why that's just what happens
so stuff has a way of sticking around a
lot longer than it was supposed to
that's just what happens but yeah and
then internally I've done some more real
compiler work at Mali rocket for just
stuff we use internally and that stuff's
more of real compiler stuff the stuff I
did it rad was not really although I did
do one thing that was sort of real can
probably be optimizing back-end that I
did for Xbox 360 as a test that one was
fairly real but we didn't end up using
it because we ended up changing the way
we were doing stuff on that platform
anyway
you
what see us first
do you remember recommend for a beginner
I don't have any recommendations for
that sorry
what's your guess on how much faster GPU
trilling your sampling is compared to
CPU side also could you not bounce the
light on GPU side and be faster even an
onyx cards what are the reasons against
doing that is that just to keep
complexity at HMH scope I don't actually
that the reason is mostly that no I
don't think we can so basically what
we're gonna have to do I think is we're
gonna have some lighting we're gonna
have to have some lighting quality
controls and I'm guessing that we will
do very simplistic lighting output on
sort of lower end stuff and so while
maybe the card that's in my machine now
it might this this machine might have a
1080 in it in which case sure we could
do ray tracing on the card side and it
would probably be faster than the than
the CPU but that's not necessarily going
to be the minimum specs we're shooting
for I mean if we try to port handmade
hero to Raspberry Pi right we need a way
of doing some lighting somewhere and
then outputting it in a way that could
be used right and so I just don't want
to take the full leap of going this game
requires GPU ray tracing because that
just really limits what you can run on
right
we just write some CPU stuff that we use
that's like a much simpler version of
this that we run on lower end stuff and
furthermore on machines with like Intel
i GPUs and stuff I would wager that you
could still do like the full ray tracing
because it might be a very good this de
CPU might be great right but the GPU
would never be able to do a good job of
ray tracing right so I think it's just
you have to respect the heterogeneity
there so if we can if we can make the
CPU do the Ray casting fast enough we
probably should because it's not going
to be used for anything else in this
game we don't have it we don't have any
physics sim or stuff like that that
we're really using it for so I think we
want to take advantage of that so that
we can run on on crappy GPUs basically
you
it seems unlikely that enzyme D would
change behavior
branch lick and concerning things like
pgo and GCC building specs severe oh
they did like the AMD branch predictor
predictor in Rison - is totally
different than the branch predictor
predictor even in Rison one but
certainly than in bulldozer it's totally
different
so it changes completely from
architecture to architecture so trust me
it's totally different
have you considered the fact that if you
just said handmade hero had an AI based
lighting solution you could say it was
done now
you
I understand you're doing a unity
building handmade here what's the
meaning of internalist scenario well
again it just if you don't put it then
the C compiler thinks everything needs
to be external
and that costs you extra linking time
because you output it a bunch of data
you didn't need to output so even when
you're doing a unity build you still
want to say all of this stuff is within
this compilation unit so don't do any
extra work right you need to tell the
compiler that cuz it doesn't know that's
what you're doing then through the is hi
guy content by to company to work as a C
programmer one job on the numerical
repeating dia but as I stood aside one
of the cryptography they also wrote to
me that they have a hard time in finding
people who are in a little programming
do you think it is because majority
people use Python just for high level
languages I guess there's always a job
as someone could you see in a bit of
assembly yeah I mean this is exactly
what I said before
there's almost nobody knows how to do
this kind of programming any more
programmers who know anything about how
to do low-level programming are very
valuable everywhere because they're the
only people who know how to like
actually make things run smoothly or
fast right so yes I mean it's there's
always a job for you if you know how to
do the sorts of stuff we do on handmade
hero cuz nobody does
it's not that there's like millions of
jobs for it it's just that there's
nobody you can do it so it's just it's
just a supply issue right when running
visual studio with my executable has an
argument I can't find the project
properties properties window in which
you set the pound defines dude I don't I
don't know about Visual Studio like
you
like Visual Studio is the pilot crap go
get remedy that's my advice
just catching up on the show again what
do we have left other than lighting an
actual gameplay so not really anything
but the gameplay stuff will be kind of
slow at first I think because we'll want
to there's two things I think want to be
tightened up there one is we need the
collision detector to be back in there
for like projectiles so that'll probably
get tuned a little bit because that
really never got done that we're just
kind of sitting in there but the other
thing that I would want to the other
thing that I think we're gonna want to
do is the tag based matching sucks right
now and so what I want to do is like
write some gameplay code and do the
snuffleupagus thing stuff let the
snuffle epistle into programming where
we just go okay now that we're actually
running real gameplay play code what do
we want to type in here to say like how
these things should have their graphics
assigned and then go fix the tag code to
work that way so that wants to happen to
that can happen with the gameplay code
though it doesn't have to be a separate
step but yeah but I would say the
collision detector needs to be fixed and
like get that part of the code like
correct again again we can do that while
we're doing getting played programming
that we don't like doesn't need a
separate phase but we know new gameplay
room like okay how do we want push next
to work here like let's go but clean
that up and make that robust right I
don't think there's really anything else
I mean there's a lot of cleanup work we
can do so you know cleaning things up we
could spend a few weeks on just getting
like stuff kind of organized now that we
have everything done for the engine but
I don't know that we we could probably
just do some gameplay stuff first before
we do that just to make sure we validate
everything out first
so I would probably say we'd start the
gameplay first then take a break from
the gameplay once we have some basic
gameplay in there and say okay this is
basically what it's supposed to play
like you know like I look up you know
first level kind of thing then clean
everything up then push forward
that seems saying
which features a c-list do you think our
conductive orchids are conducive to
performance oriented programming and
which do you think are detrimental and
should be avoided I noticed that you use
default argument sometimes for example
um I would say C++ you really doesn't
have almost anything in it that you want
the only things I would use are operator
overloading default parameters well I
think C us has that now and declare
anywhere which C also has now
constructor destructor pairs are
sometimes useful for automatic things
like count block so constructor
destructor pairs for structs maybe but I
don't really care you don't really have
to use it it's just a convenience a mild
convenience that I can easily live
without so yeah
when adding the normals together doesn't
immediately normalizing after each ad
make the result dependent on the order
of the vectors yes it does but we're not
doing that at least not that I remember
so if you look when we actually do our
normal accumulation step so you can see
we do not normalize during our normal
accumulation step right so there's the
accumulation step right there and it
does not normalize right
so you know that's that's that we
probably should normalize this sample
down here but that's another story so
the place that you might be thinking of
is the place where we update the voxel
for the frame but that one's fine
because that's just doing one update per
frame right so this right here is just
saying look we've now produced the new
result for the for the frame so let's
normalize it and we always want to start
with the normalized normal right so that
that doesn't does that does that help
hope
you
all right we're good all right just few
questions and we're on topic questions
so let's go ahead and close this out
all right Oh
someone once said as you remember we
talked about valve a CEO shader
compilers replacing LLVM I heard that it
reduces the shadow compile time
significantly they said that it is great
for the open source graphics driver on
Linux okay I mean that that seems good I
had not looked at it yet though also I
don't program on Linux but
did we track light energy so we do but
at the moment it's kind of an abstract
value so we don't make an attempt to try
and have the light energy correspond to
an actual real value like we're not
trying to actually measure flux in like
real physical units so we kind of have
an abstract value that we claim to
convict around which is photons per
second by some scale which is just how
we're thinking of it and the the reason
it's not really physical is because that
scale value is arbitrary we're not
saying what it is we're just saying look
this is a measure of the number of
photons per second that pass through
this point they Begley right and so
we're not really trying to to measure
that how is the radiance different from
radiance well they're not really
different it's just trying to it's
trying to talk about whether something's
coming in or going out right so like
radiance is what comes out and
irradiance is what comes in right so if
you look
they get this is this is so so this is
the value eight more right so irradiance
is the radiant flux received by a
surface per unit area right so
irradiance coming in
whereas radiance I believe is going out
typically right yeah in radiometry
radiance is the radiant flux emitted
right or you know reflected basically
coming out right and it looks like maybe
you could have used that for received as
well so I don't know I'm not sure about
the terminology exactly there but the
point is when you say irradiance you
specifically mean that it's what's
entering the surface at that point like
what's entering the equation from the
outside not stuff that's going that
you're sending back into the environment
from the system right so I think really
the only reason we use that term
irradiance is just to make it clear that
we're talking about stuff that's coming
in right and and radiance is talking
about what's going out that's usually
how I think about them anyway
you
and why mmm zero I don't think radiance
and irradiance are measured differently
though I don't think when you say
irradiance you're talking about
different measure than radiance meaning
I think irradiance is still per service
area and Prasad angle right meaning it
does not change it's just talking about
the fact that it's incoming right it's
not it's not that it's measured in a
different measure is it so I don't I
don't think that's true might be though
so they are different units alright so I
guess they're different units as well so
when you talk about the outgoing your
you actually change the units apparently
you
that part I don't know I usually have to
go study that stuff pretty carefully
when I go to write anything that
actually does tries to do a lighting
reflectance I find it pretty confusing
to remember it all at some point I
should probably sit down and work it out
myself in a way that I like to think
about it so that it would stick
either way the point is simply that
irradiance is what's coming in so that's
why I use that term instead of just
saying radians I'm not trying to talk
about any specific units at all I'm just
trying to talk about the fact that if I
say your radiance IRR as opposed to
radiance with just an R I'm just trying
to say it's coming in right
have you read Sean Barrett's post on
anti-aliasing I don't think so
you
uhh
I remember this when he was working on
it
but
I
but I think I do yeah I don't remember
reading this though I don't think I've
ever seen this actual post
all right
you
let's go ahead and close it down thank
you everyone for tuning in for an
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with the
series at home you can always print the
game on hand made here at organic house
the source code so you can follow along
with me as we code it also in theory the
watch page is working again now because
I went and updated the server to use the
the new twitch API so in theory now you
come here you should get the old
behavior where you know it's me talking
like this whenever the show is live and
whenever the show is not live it should
revert back to having just the the
schedule posted there so that's about it
I'll be back here next week for us to
sort of start working through some of
those lighting to do's until then have
fun programming everyone and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody