hello everybody and welcome to handmade
here I'll show a recode a complete game
live on stream we have to do a little
bookkeeping before we start today
because I as you know last weekend's
sunday stream my Masai I posted a bunch
of art to dues to the github it's the
first time we're doing this but now that
we sort of have we're kind of building
out the world and we're gonna start
really kind of trying to pull the game
together as a game again not really my
strong suit not a game designer so you
know take it with a grain of salt but
just doing the engine part of let's
let's build a nice world that part I can
do because that's that's just engine
programming um so at this point we're
gonna start hitting art bugs right we
try to put something in and that the you
know it's not right or we decide that we
need to shuffle the way that we're doing
this like how we're building the our
nests the first place so we're gonna
have art bugs and those need to get
fixed by the artists it's just Anna on
this product but if you imagine like a
bigger project if you round like a
triple-a game there's a whole art team
and our director in an art process right
and so you have to kind of send reports
back that are like hey we're doing this
programming we're putting this stuff in
and it didn't work the way it's supposed
to or we're changing something we need
the art team to change stuff with us so
what i did is i'm just using because we
already have it i'm using the github
issue system to just mark art things and
i set up anna's computer to have a way
for her to list those and she went
through and made the changes that we
asked for you can see for example these
are commented by her there's a done on
on these so what i did was i grab the
files from her and put them here this is
the updated art files so the first thing
i want to do is just merge these updated
art files with our existing art files so
that we can get those updates a lot of
them aren't changed because there wasn't
anything wrong with them
but some of them
have been right and like so she did some
stuff to after I told her because
remember we made this change after I
told her about how we were doing scenery
now she went through and like built you
know various things for the scenery
files and whatnot right does that have a
pink that's got a like a pink thing that
wasn't that's still there or something I
should I should well again this is why
we have an art bug list so we when we go
through these and actually put them in
we can see whether or not they're
correct or not right so anyway what we
want to do now is we would like to start
to incorporate these into the game and
we would like to basically take any old
files that we have and delete them if
they don't like correspond anymore I
don't know what the easiest way to do
this is because normally on my machine I
use a commercial program called beyond
compare that I'll usually use for stuff
like this it's a pretty good program
actually it's similar to Reaper in the
beginning of the stream I was ranting
about how bad software is and I was
trying to point to if someone's there
actually good Reaper was one of them
beyond compare it's actually one to it's
pretty good I haven't had a lot of
problems with it and I've been using it
for a long time so if we go ahead I
think meld is on here which is a similar
tool to beyond compare and I like I said
I try to use things that are free or
cheap really cheap on the stream because
I don't know you know people especially
people who are you know young don't
maybe have any money I don't want to be
using stuff on the stream that costs a
billion dollars to use right but anyway
so if I do a directory comparison here I
should be able to say hey if we go to
this export directory and pick that and
then I go to the directory inside
handmade hero that has the base game
assets
I should here be able to have this do a
diff on them to see
which of these things are the same and
which of them are different now I don't
know to what extent it can actually
provide me a diff of these things
because these are binary files and
having double clicked on that and having
it go away forever suggests to me that
it's going to try to do the diff in text
which is not great so you know this is
something again if you like I should
point out beyond compare it's really it
is a good tool and if people have a
little bit of money it's not that
expensive and and I bought I think I
bought multiple licenses for it actually
why I don't know I'm just me but so the
this this tool here beyond compare it's
how much is it it's you know so it's
it's 60 bucks it's not cheap right I
don't know what the difference is
between the pro and the standard edition
so you know there is a thirty dollar one
but I use this Pro Edition the for 60
bucks if you are someone with an actual
programming job right 60 bucks is not a
huge deal so I do recommend that tool
it's it's pretty good and you can see
this is just gone completely like it's
forget it right so we can do one of the
things we want to do which is just tell
us which things changed it can't really
apparently do any dips of them that's
fine let me just try doing it without
doing any diffs and we'll do the merge
that way and that's good enough for us
right let me go ahead and in here say w
handmade sources base game art open so
if I do the compare here what I can see
is you know we've got sort of these
these underscore files using since we're
now following art bugs I don't really
think I need to keep those anymore
so I'm just going to delete those two
out of here
this hero body and the hero head those
we had raided a bug on those because
they were
if you remember the the facing direction
was wrong so the Kiros like face and
body were going like the wrong
directions compared to what we were
supposed to wind the mass so I want to
take those and copy them over right so
that we now have the new versions in our
art file again obstacles forest we
deleted on purpose I'm going to leave
those and same with the templates we
move those so I'm going to leave those
the way they are you can see here we've
got these particle flowers large splotch
stones those you can see that Anna sort
of made her own which is what we want
this was just me experimenting with
these things we want the artists to make
whatever sets they want here she also
made us some other things like stars and
fire and stuff that we can play with for
particles that are specifically
particles and off we go she also used
the word particles not particle and
there's a couple philosophies on this
right like one is we could go rate a bug
and say hey it's supposed to be particle
not particles that is tempting to do and
let me just give you a little
perspective on why I'm not going to do
it
the reason it's tempting to do is not
having too much variability can be a
good thing being specific about having
sort of work is good however you have to
remember when you're working with
artists their job is to be artists they
make art for a living that's what they
do right they are not meticulous in the
way that programmers have to be
meticulous they don't think about things
like case sensitivity or exact syntax
right why because that's not what they
do
like day-to-day they draw pictures okay
it doesn't ever matter when you're
drawing a picture what if you named the
layer with the with a capital letter or
a lowercase letter right it doesn't have
any effect on their workflow these
things so when we need them to conform
to certain things that our programmer e
because they have to flow into an engine
pipeline and we need certain information
right um having that be as permissive as
possible just smooth things over so I
don't recommend being really procrustean
about it I would say loosen up there
don't do what you would do with a normal
parser which is report errors for
everything and force them to be exact
which is what you want to do in a
programming language it's not what you
want to do in an arc situation so what
I'd like to do here is say all right
we're gonna we're gonna take that cue
the fact that Ana named it particles
instead of particle is just a good
indication that an artist who isn't
necessarily thinking about it when
they're going to export will often add
an S on the end of that that's all we
need to know right it's probably because
we talked about making like particle
stars and that was probably made before
we did this and we probably decided on
particles there and then on particle
here right so just let them both happen
there's no reason for them not to happen
so I'm going to copy these over and
delete these the scenery here you can
see this like scenery chair what's going
on I thought we did make a chair oh why
we need Orphanage chair so I don't care
about that Orphanage lamp labeling
either so I'm gonna delete those just
fine and then also these and then I'm
just gonna bulk copy all the stuff she
made the way she made it now title
screen got moved so again don't care
about that so just looking at the expert
directory now I think we're good like I
think we've updated all of these changes
now some of these are gonna have
consequences so let's go take care of
those consequences and I can also just
no we don't need that anymore so let's
go ahead and open up handmade hero oops
and what I want to do is twofold first
any import layer there's a place where
we search for particles and as you can
see what we're doing is saying it has to
be exactly that
let's just not oh wait never mind
that's irrelevant we don't care about
that it's only in the hht I don't know
why I thought that that was the case
right because this this is not necessary
anymore this is just this is just for
our block but the actual the actual
place where this is specified in here
just specifies the name directly so if I
go look at particle you can see that it
lists the names here so all it is is
these PNG s would have particles right
so this is a trivial fix for us all
right so what we want to do now is say
look all of this stuff like the particle
flowers and grass large and grass watch
and all that stuff these have different
names now so we want to go through and
change these to more accurately reflect
what's actually in the directory and I
think all of this stuff remains the same
there were no updates to this part of
the code so what I'm going to do at the
moment is I'm just gonna sort of you
know comment these out really really
quickly here and say alright these are
gone as things let's go look at what
we've actually got now and insert those
in so looking at the directory if we go
to handmade sources base in here where
we've got the art input if I was to do
particle star it would list all the
particles that we have and I can just
put those in directly right so if I just
copy these and say here's what we're
talking about these are the particle
files that we now have we've got three
grass types some puffs rocks and stars
the puffs if you're wondering are like
if we want to do smoke or something I
asked Anna just give us a sampling of
some generic particles and the reason
for that is we'd like to put in the
particle systems we have particles of
some code we don't use it for anything
right now
and so we'd like to experiment with that
at some point so here's some example of
like some little puffs like if we want
like smoke puffs or something like that
right
if we want some like fire puffs you know
if we want some stars for like when
someone gets punched or something I
don't want to throw some stars out there
you know I'm saying so we've got a lot
of situations where we we might want to
do some stuff with these and that to me
is is why I wanted some generic stuff
but before we even really know what kind
of particles we need just something to
play with so we can get that system off
the ground now coming back in here I'm
gonna go ahead and make this define I'm
just gonna say okay each of these should
look like this so maybe this and then we
just want to go ahead and grab it so
that's what we're looking at and these
are gonna have to be tagged with
something
each of these which we kind of think
about what that's going to be a lot of
these are kind of self-explanatory like
fire or grass or whatever so we should
probably go look at the files this is
pretty basic though this is just like
fire and probably it should be tagged
with particle actual particle because
it's not just something that is used as
a splotch it's actually specifically
used as a particle so I think we
probably want to do something like that
where we say like cover you know like
we've got different things here the
thing about that is I don't know that
could also be something that's a base
type meaning we could make that be
something that's that sort of specified
elsewhere but at the moment it really
doesn't I don't know whether we want
that in the tags or whether we want that
elsewhere I'm not sure right but you can
see that this is really what this sort
of boils down to you
it would look like that these things are
things that are used as ground cover not
really particles and these things are
actually used as literal particles and
we probably want to distinguish between
those two
I'm guessing again whether or not that
should be out here I'm not sure maybe it
should and I don't know we're gonna
leave it like that for now all right so
those are our particles and we're gonna
have to tag them with something useful
we've then got our sceneries and between
the particles and the sceneries I think
that's everything I don't think there's
anything else that was new so I should
be able to do this and get all those so
here are those and if I go ahead and cut
and paste those in here I should be able
to do similarly so if I just do this
well actually I should get rid of this
first I really have to finish up my new
for coder well I guess it's not really
technically 4-footer anymore because
I've ended up writing a whole new thing
but the editor put that way okay so this
is what we're looking at for scenery and
the same thing applies we're gonna have
to there we go we're gonna have to do
some tagging here because we don't
really know what any of this stuff
contains or how its differentiated
really you know I'm saying so looking at
these let me see
so you know the only thing I would say
is I'm not sure why like these this
scenery chair Oh - in scenery chair oh
three seem like they're just equivalent
right like this those are just variants
in the same chair like I I can't think
of well maybe not now this is a rocking
chair and that's not maybe that's good
enough of a difference a reason to make
that different I don't know anyway so
yeah like it's hard to say some of the
stuff is complicated because it's like
who knows like that that maybe is a
longer ish table than this so I don't
know that we'd want to pick those
equivalently either anyway so a lot of
this stuff now has to get tagged because
we have no idea what the tags actually
are gonna be unless this stuff so we got
to start there I think let's take a look
at particle grass so the first one
particle grass 0 1 which is this looking
at that I don't know what we're gonna do
for differentiation there so I think
that's just the size probably so I think
we can just use what we were using
before here as far as tags to
differentiate those I think we could say
alright the o2 is the large one and oh
one is the small one I'm half water
already
so grass oh three is flowers right so
that's actually this
particle puffs I'm gonna go ahead and
call that smoke I'm gonna call this
rocks because I think we've already got
that right our stones stone yes stone
stars are just stars I think and off we
go
so inside our tags we need to add those
because we don't have some of those
we're gonna need stars right we're gonna
need smoke we're gonna need cover
we're gonna need particle we're gonna
need to not have an extra semicolon we
need fire and
[Music]
like that's it right eat those zones we
added so let's move on to the scenery
now we've got a bunch of chairs here
we've got a bunch of lamps we've got a
rug
we've got a table we've got all these
trees all of this stuff needs to be
labeled I'm gonna go ahead and drop
these into the to the list of tags here
so yeah I'm missing some parentheses
there there we go no incorrect
so we've got that table covered now we
need to come look at these again I'm
going to go ahead and look at what we
already did here because we kind of
worked out what probably most of this
stuff is and so the the orphanage chair
I'm assuming Molly went to get her
dinner I don't know when I don't know if
and when she left well I know if she
left cuz she's not there anymore but I
could I just heard her like automated
feeder go off so that is that it's Meal
Time so if we take a look here at like
the chair stuff all of this stuff for
scenery is all orphanage scenery so I
think these are all gonna be like you
know this sort of thing now in order to
differentiate between these we may need
some additional tags to the extent that
we actually care which one of these
we're picking when we look at the chair
like these two are kind of a matching
set so I'm a kind of call these sofa
right that's chair of four I may say
that that's size one and this is size of
five or something like that you and I'm
saying to you these two I don't think we
care about so I think those are
literally just chair I don't know that
we care about rocking or otherwise I'm
not sure again we can add more of that
as we go scenery lamp
we've got really sizes on those I think
again so I think this is just going to
be a size of five lamp
this is gonna be like a size one lamp
kind of a thing the rug I don't know
that we need anything other than the
word rug and the table I don't know that
we need anything other than the word
table for now going by the rest of this
here just trying to think in here I
don't think we have table right and I
don't think we have rug
we should have chair right and we have
like orphan right we have all that stuff
we've got lamp
we don't have sofa I think that's all we
need for the stuff we added there so
again just adding those into the list
because C++ is a giant steaming pile and
makes you do everything yourself job
security people think of it that way the
C++ committee has your back they will
never let the computer do anything
because the C++ committee wants to make
sure that C programmers still have
plenty of hours a day of typing to do so
that it looks like they're busy so
scenery tree we've got a set of those
here and it looks like the evergreen
verse is not is not something Anna
wanted to differentiate on it looks like
it's more like stumped or not and then
like more like the season I guess maybe
and then this I think was I asked her
what these were I think she was saying
these are more for spooky like graveyard
areas or something like that so I don't
really know
they weren't damaged like I thought that
was what they might be for but that's
not what they're gonna be for I guess so
that's just worth noting so evergreen is
not actually on the table as a tag this
is
probably a deprecated tag for now oh
hello miss kitty did you have a good
dinner well it's really lunch isn't it
how are you doing how are you doing
mm-hmm that's a good puss that's a good
place it's raining out did you know that
did you look at the rain yet do you want
to look do you want to look oh yeah how
are you doing okay
that's my oh that's my headphones that's
my headphones okay all right let's just
maybe we can get the headphones kind of
um out from underneath the cat and that
would help that's a good kitty do you
want to help us program do you want to
help us do some programming mm-hmm what
do you want to do we can do whatever you
want we can do whatever you want do you
want a program we can program if you
just want to sit here we can sit here
that's that's good too
everyone loves it when you're on stream
everyone does yes of course they do
okay if we can convince Molly to not
attack the headphones then we can
probably do some more coding here maybe
maybe not
we'll see she may demand more attention
and then the programming is obviously
not possible okay okay
all right what's she doing okay now
you're all tangled up what's it gonna be
what do you want to do do you want to go
into your Cassatt or do you want to want
to go to the cat the the cat I don't
know what you call that it's not really
a cat tree because it's not really a
tree it's like half a cat tree I'm gonna
go into you're half a cat tree okay
okay okay all right you know what we're
gonna go to the cat tree now because now
you're starting to bite and get rowdy oh
okay come on I'm sick all right I need
to take this off you totally tangle it
up what are you doing there you go
you're gonna be okay all right
you wanna how about you look out how
about your little look at the rain for a
while how's that sound okay I don't
really want to get bit right now that's
not that wouldn't be that's not my
favorite thing to do right now okay yeah
yeah there's there's probably birds out
there did you look
did you look and see yeah okay all right
we don't know what Molly's gonna do
she's a wild card in this and we'll see
but yeah we don't know whether the
headphones will last
she likes to chew through cables and
stuff that's like just something she
will do anyway so we're gonna deprecate
the Evergreen for now because we don't
actually know if that's gonna be
something that that happens I'm gonna
leave the damage tag because that
probably will be something happens I
think there's a thing called dark that
we had and I may say that maybe dark is
the thing that won't label those sort of
like spooky trees with because I mean
why not right so let's see here if we
look at scenery tree what we were
labeling those with before was like this
kind of thing right and so if we come in
here and label these with like this sort
of stuff we know evergreen isn't there
and we know damaged isn't there but like
winter would be there and dark would be
there
and I guess fall would be there do we
have that we did and fall so we kind of
have like this sort of thing and I guess
you know damaged we could use for the
stump maybe it's a little bit of a
stretch but maybe we could say that was
true
so maybe scenery tree OH - is like
damaged or something I don't know seems
possible anyway so in here we've got the
fall trees and here we've got the spring
trees so I guess we would say that oh
three is the fall trees oh four is the
dark trees
and oh five is the winter trees and just
that's good enough for now
right so I think that's everything that
we've got and and then we can delete
these I don't want to keep the alignment
points because they may not be the same
there's a couple of these that we
aligned but that's not going to be
accurate anymore so I'm just going to
delete those now and then we're gonna
call it a day so I think that's
everything if I rebuild we will now have
different tags there the evergreen tag
has been deprecated because I don't
really think we're gonna it doesn't look
like Anna wants to differentiate maybe
in the future if she does we'll undec
ate it but for now I'm just gonna say
don't use that so like here I'm gonna
say don't use that we could add the
other ones in here so what did we say
fall damaged winter and there's one
other thing
dark so if we add these sort of like
random tagging things tag dark isn't
undeclared identifier but it's right
here could be not too clear that oh it's
dark energy my bad
so maybe dark energy isn't quite the
best thing for that maybe we should have
another one I don't know what it would
be like spooky or something I'm not sure
let's go ahead and run remedy here and
see where we're at
I'm gonna load up the handmade hero code
I'm gonna run it it's gonna have to do
some importing here because we changed a
ton of stuff uh if I look at the errors
it looks like we didn't have any oddly
enough
which is kind of somewhat surprising
what I will point out is already some of
our bugs have been fixed I can tell the
hero now faces the right direction so
that was a bug that we had recorded
right so that's pretty exciting and we
can actually now say that that you know
because that was annoying the whole time
so now that that's fixed that's great so
we can fix this or rather mark this as
fixed and let's see I don't know what
else we have to Marcus fix but we'll see
in a second so here's a bunch of stuff
these things need their sizes and
alignments modified I would note that
this doesn't seem to really be picking
particularly fairly which I'm not sure
why that would be that we should
probably look to see oh so here's one
thing that that yeah
so we should probably raid an art bug
about on this because I noticed this
before and I don't think I ever told
Anna about this so it's not clear and
one way we could do it is we could go
back in and change the parser to look at
this but I think there's some negative
consequences to doing that so I would
really rather not
and specifically wait I thought I'd just
closed that oh that was the body ones so
this one these are both closed now these
are fixed as well this is fixed as well
so really this one turned out to be our
fault as well
yeah I don't know to do about this let
me explain you what the problem is then
we can sort of decide what you want to
do so if you look at files that have
variants in them this is not really what
we want what we want for variants is we
want there to be like this variant
should actually be over here because
since variant goes zero point two five
point five seven five or what it lower
bulb no I guess it goes like you know
evenly spaced throughout if you pick a
random number between zero and one then
you're way more often gonna pick this
and you're almost never gonna pick this
because you have like a three-quarters
chance of hitting this one and only a
1/4 chance of hitting this one so
basically three out of four times you're
gonna get this guy which is not what you
want it you wanted a 50% spread right so
I think we want to just call that an art
update because what we want to do is we
track which label which cell these
things come from
so we want to keep them in the same cell
like once you put something somewhere we
want to keep it there so that when you
re import it doesn't reinforce
more things than necessary and you know
stuff like that just easier to track so
I think we want to actually ask the
artists to put things separated that way
if they're not going to draw all four
now we could do in a different way where
we could just detect how many of them we
have and then spread it out among those
but I don't really think so so I'm gonna
just call that a bug
and you know the only thing about that
is now that I think as I'm saying it
though I realized that this creates
really just annoying stuff for the
artist so that means for particles you
would put one in the top one in here and
I'd have to pin it so you know what no I
think we're gonna have to do the work of
spreading those out ourselves
yeah that it just seems to me that we're
gonna have to do it deal with that
ourselves so maybe that's what we do
today maybe we've got a we've got to
make that happen
trying to change the way we were doing
things a little bit to make sure that
when we're doing things like parsing
variants the variants come out as a
count and then distribute along the
count that that may be what we have to
do
the reason that's super annoying is it
means that we don't have we can't really
have templates for our sprite sheets
anymore because those templates change
depending on how many things you filled
up right I'm trying to think if there's
any other way we could really do it
I mean I suppose one thing we could do
is we could do some kind of an auto
variant thing where variant tags are
added at the end based on how many
things were seen
that's probably the most expeditious way
to do it but it may prove kind of
complicated and error-prone to do it
that way so I don't know
let's also by the way this got finished
a long time ago didn't it all right
so I think that's probably what we're
gonna have to do because just looking at
it's like yeah I could tell Anna to do
it that way but it's just annoying and
like if you think about what this file
would have to look like it would have to
look like fill this one this would be
like a diagonal almost but slightly
different because we got five it's just
that's not something artists should have
to be dealing with that's like not good
so we need some way of assigning the
variant number automatically and it
needs to be spread out along the 0 to 1
range you know very specifically and so
I think what we want to do there is
let's let's actually let's let's
actually try to attack that problem a
little more head-on so all right
other than that I think we were okay
like it looks like we're pretty good
otherwise you know what we may also want
to do while we're at it I'm gonna maybe
I'll maybe file a bug for that
so I'm calling that an issue and I'm
calling it a programming issue because
we should probably fix that what I was
gonna say is I do wonder if we could
test the particle stuff what could have
put the particles back in like for
example maybe I want to spawn some puffs
when I hop on the ground we could we
could play with that a little bit and
just see what's going on I think that
might be fun to do right and then we've
got the furniture in the ground cover so
we've got tons of stuff to work on but I
do think we want to go ahead and make
sure we can actually do the the variant
stuff correctly first because that's
just that that's gonna throw a wrench in
any time we try to do randomized picking
right
looks like our lamps are working okay as
well so that's good yeah all right so
let's go ahead and figure out what we're
doing here we'll look maybe we go play
with with that particle thing get that
Rhian abled because we haven't done that
in a while let's let's do that and then
if we have time after that we'll also go
take a look at the variant computation
in the particle system I don't really
remember why it was called spawn fire
because it wasn't actually fire but I
think that's just because that was what
we called our test code so if you look
in here a lot of the stuff sift out and
there's just weird stuff going on
now might be a good time to go ahead and
you know put put this stuff to work I
think we want to just start by
probably putting these things back in I
don't know why there if zero doubt
exactly but the compiler should tell us
pretty much immediately why we it if
zero those out right okay so here you
can see we don't actually have the world
mode getting passed to us so that's a
pretty obvious reason why particle sells
so this is like doing a hybrid
oh this was like if we were doing hybrid
like like hybrid sim like Lagrangian
illyrian combined like I think what do
they call them nowadays it's called a
different thing they call them they had
they have a they have a different name
for these things what do you call what
do you call it now when you do a
Lagrangian I read like Lagrangian or
Larian thing like
do they do they maybe they don't have
another name so I don't I don't know if
if they have another name maybe that
maybe calling them or hybrid like
Lagrangian or Larian methods is what
it's called so maybe there is no other
name for it maybe that's why I can't
think of it anyway we were doing a
little bit of that kind of thing here I
don't know that we really want to be
doing that I think we just can use just
regular particles here so I guess this
if zero actually is a real if zero look
we don't actually need that in there so
this code yeah like it looks fine for
doing the rendering looks good so why
aren't we getting this did we inside the
world code actually like if zero that
out is that what happened so we've got
to do here for render re-enabled
particles but we do have that if one in
here to the update and render particles
and and it's supposed to be calling
update and render fire but it doesn't
actually render anything so why not
right if we were actually jumping in
here what's what's not happening in
there because the F zero is that around
anything important I don't think it is
anymore
yeah so I fit feels like this should be
okay system bitmap ID I don't know to
what extent that's maybe not able to
find anything I'm not sure so it could
be that this is just failing but I'm not
I'm not certain so what I'd like to do
is maybe step in here and see what's
going on I don't know where we call init
particle cache but it looks like that is
getting set up properly so the particle
cache is getting initialized so most of
this stuff does seem like it actually is
still getting called so the question is
why aren't we actually seeing anything
you know what I'm saying
and we should go find out why that's the
case the other thing I guess is well if
we never spawned any that might do it so
it could be that we're just never like
maybe we're never spawning anything okay
so it might be more like this is the
problem
there we go
so now we just need that's like the
that's the first head in the list
I guess so now we just need to instead
of having heads in there but maybe even
put the puffs in there so to do that we
would just need to query that particle
right so in here we would go to the hht
where would we query the particle for
puffs its particle smoke so I guess we
would say we want particle smoke and
just see if that loads that in properly
and then we've got to actually go you
know I don't think we left the particle
systems we just kind of sketch them in
there I don't think we left them in a
particularly useful state so for some
reason that doesn't seem to actually be
picking anything which doesn't make a
whole lot of sense because it should be
right particle smoke we should be
getting particle puffs so one I think
and then we get this back we should be
getting that bitmap ID looking at
looking at that asset match oh that's
why it's looking in the wrong category
alright so there's the little puffs
right and what we want to do so you can
see there's actually some bugs in there
to where we're in terms of the movement
right you see how it's moving wrong at
the transition point that's because we
haven't gone in and made sure that the
particle system displacement was updated
when we did the final camera right our
camera is now basically what it would
ship as I don't think we really have to
do much else to it so when the camera
itself is transitioning the particles go
in the wrong way
you can see how they're going totally
wrong so we need to go in and make sure
that the camera properly tells particles
how to adjust so that they align with
the world because particles are just in
screen space they don't really exist in
the world per se so it's a little bit I
shouldn't say screen space it's really
since pace right and so we want to be
able to do that and we also kind of need
to adjust these particles so if they
make a little bit more sense like they
should be smaller and things like that
right but otherwise that's what we
wanted so let's go ahead and try to make
that make some of those changes make
sense in here so first of all these are
too big and so if you look at what's
happening in here right we were doing
this push bitmap we want these particles
probably to be smaller than they are and
so when we look at how the particle
system is set up you can see here that
for some reason we didn't include a size
right and I don't know why we didn't
normally you've got a size in there and
so it's a little bit weird and we
probably should have one so if you look
at what's happening with say the color
and the DDC right we probably want the
same thing to happen with the size and
if you look
I think that we just have to be
completely separate parameter I'm not
sure where else we would really go to do
something like that so yeah like looking
in here this parameter right here where
it's like how big did you want this
thing to be that value should really be
coming from our code and furthermore we
could actually support stretching in
there and stuff like that but at the
moment I don't see a lot of ways to do
that um the floors e and the chunk Z and
that stuff do we really need that like
cuz we're full 3d now so this stuff
should just work right like do we even
use this anymore
good so this is really all the particle
has now and you can see here we've got
like four four X versions of these
things because they're wide right we're
doing sim D so we can do four particles
at a time and so what we would want to
do here is for any place where we were
gonna do like we want to be able to do
an f32 4x4 the size right so this is the
size of the particle and so in here when
we initialize one of these spawn fires
we want to do something like size equals
mm set expression 1.0 right last we can
adjust that and then in here when we
render this thing we want to actually
render it properly now when it's doing
the particle updating which is this
garbage here we could also have a size
change I'm not going to do that yet but
we very easily could right so in here
though what I want to do is grab that
size out to actually get for any
individual one of these to do this I
need to be able to get the sub index
which I believe works like this that's
how we do the extraction what the heck
is M like just pound to find m
what is that actually doing so this is
bad by the way I probably just did this
because it's you know was expedient if
you're gonna extract one of these things
you actually want to you usually want to
use the actual extraction so there's
actually an mm extract PS that you can
do and that's probably what we want to
do that actually does an instruction to
instruct extract the floating-point
value I think that'll be defined here I
cannot convert argument one from 4x to
m28 how do I actually access the VEX P
so if I just say hey man I can just do
that like this
should-should get me the actual Cindy
register and say hey change that to I
they're right mm okay so the problem
with that is it's inside a for loop that
the compiler is not able to unroll in
that way so I don't know if you can see
what's going on here we want this to
issue an instruction to unpack that set
of four values into one value can
actually pass to somebody you know
saying we want to extract that directly
but in order to do that we would need
this loop to be unrolled because the
instruction takes an immediate not of
variable so we don't really have any way
of unpacking these directly without that
looping unrolled so I guess for now I'll
leave it the way it is but we probably
want to unroll that at some point
because you don't want to do that so I'm
just gonna say to do here Casey we
probably want to unroll the loops and
make these macros use mm extracts but
anyway other than that caveat which we
will attack right now the size now
should be specifiable per particle
system which is what we want so if we
don't like those sizes right we should
be able to now inside the spawn when
we're actually making one of these
things I should be able to adjust the
size down to something smaller and then
when we hop around the particles should
be tinier right in theory so there they
are it is updated the executable and so
that's like more like what we would
expect right for some puff-puff sizes
some puff daddy's
so we want to make a particle system for
Puffs specifically and so I'd like to do
that as well but in at the immediate
moment what I'd rather we do just really
quickly here is fix the displacement so
I'd like to fix the bug where we're
getting this sort of nonsense happening
right that that sort of garbage there so
in order to do that I need to go look at
how we're doing the displacement because
basically what happens is the particles
are just bulk displaced you can see them
in here this is just a thing that's like
we expect you to tell us how to do the
camera offset for any given frame please
so make that happen right like where we
are not gonna worry about it we're
expecting you to do it for us
so when we call update and render fire
update and render well I guess it's
actually a big minute of particle
systems here this is actually the thing
that is going to be the problem for us
right this value needs to be correct and
at the moment it probably isn't correct
how do we make it so so the frame to
frame camera delta p has to tell us look
I don't know what that last p thing is
or even okay so we snap we snap the
camera I don't know whether this to do
is still relevant we snap where the
camera thinks it is here we let it
update right and then we look at the
difference of where it says the camera
is now I'm gonna go out on a limb and
say that that doesn't really help
probably because the camera was set
beforehand anyway so I'm not sure that
that method of doing things is really
gonna work anyway I could be
long about that and I often am but it
does seem
[Music]
yeah like that could be an issue the
other thing I would like to do is the
debug light P here that should probably
go away eventually sometime at some
point as well where is the debug light
this is the different way because we
probably want to actually start putting
correct lighting in as we go further
down that road as well so right I mean
we we don't want the hero to be carrying
around too light anymore as we get more
towards correct lighting the hero should
only be lit when the heroes actually lit
all right so anyway what we want to do
here is figure out what the correct plan
is for how this update works so if I
look at update camera for enemy movement
just gonna look at what happens here so
what does it actually update here's the
interpolation for the camera that you
can see and it looks like what it does
is it says okay we're going to take the
camera position here and
it looks like the camera position and
the target position there are just
continually mapped into camera P so I
mean I think
I think that's just completely
irrelevant to what we're doing because
these are all going to be relative to
the center the sim Center right which is
the region origin it's this thing so
what we really want to know is just
where is that right look where is that
happening
so in here like with this simulate call
and we you know this world sim dot sim
region that's actually the thing we want
to know how that shifted I believe from
frame to frame that's sort of my story
and I'm sticking to it
alright so I'm gonna try that I don't
actually know if that'll work but if you
look in here and you see right game
camera we've got this world position P
that's not being used anymore what I
think I want to do here is say well you
know we've got this simulation center
nonsense here you can see that happening
here and I think that that is where you
know whatever the world mode camera
simulation center whatever that says I
think that's the thing we want to track
the updates on so I'm guessing that what
we want is to say that this is actually
where what the coordinate system is
based around we will look at what that
is after we're done here we'll actually
look at the difference in simulation
centers for the camera and that I think
would be what the actual coordinate
change is now I have to go look to see
when it actually changes the simulation
center because I don't know but I'm
assuming that it changes it in here
so inside update entity for camera
movement we've got the simulation center
yeah you can see that when it moves from
room to room that's when that actually
gets updated and that's the thing we
actually used in the center of our
coordinate system right here so I think
that's the thing we would actually need
to offset the particles by right and it
looks like it's almost right but it has
a right at the changeover point it looks
like we get some issues
so I believe all I think it's probably
only a one frame issue and the reason
for that is because the simulation
center this time around is still using
the old one so my assumption is all we
really need to do is because of that one
frame we're changing the simulation
center for the next time around what we
probably want to do is just say hey when
we're actually applying that
displacement that displacements going to
get this applied afterward right so in
other words this whole thing where we do
the frame displacement this right here
this offset really needs to be done
after the particle has been pushed so
it's really this part is really not
supposed to happen yet this should
happen and then the particle should
happen so like
so I think that would eliminate the one
frame glitch that we would have because
what was happening there is we're
applying the frame displacement and then
rendering the particles but the frame
displacement won't happen till next
frame because we're already set up to
send this frame right and so I think
that's what we would need to prevent
that and there you know that there you
go right that fixed it so now our
particles are nice and stable and they
track the world properly as you can see
they're not very good particles yet they
don't do what we would want them to do
but you know we can play with that a
little bit later I think the main thing
that I noticed there's the the alpha
fade needs to be like way faster this
right here should be more like a bat or
something right
oops so yeah like when we're actually
spawning those particles here
I want to zoom in there a little bit and
just see what's going on
so that's a little better right now one
of the weird things is that I do think
the Alpha fading is is not is not
perceptually linear probably because
it's happening and everything is gamma
correct gamma correct fading is not
perceptual fading I know that sounds a
little bit weird but it does seem like
they fade a little fast you know what I
mean
not that the speed is too fast but
rather they it's not it it feels
nonlinear the fading it feels like it
accelerates towards the end which is not
exactly what I think we would want there
does that make sense so I am curious
like you know if you were for example to
take the Alpha level of this thing here
right and say that you squared that or
something right so you know if you did
something like this or square root of it
I just wanted I just want to play with
those two and see
I guess we're not clamping
so there's what squared alpha press
square root alpha and again I'm just
playing with it here I just want to see
if any of these looks perceptually more
reasonable to me
so squared alpha actually looks
perceptually better to me let's try quad
alpha just curious
so I would say squared alpha looks like
a more reasonable fade to me that's my
favorite of the over the three just
looking at it it just feels a little
better the way that fades out I would
also say and again this was supposed to
be spawn fire it's not fire it's puffs
right now so we probably want to change
that but when we're actually doing the
the spawning of the particles here when
we look at the the DP I also want these
to kind of poot outward more than they
are right now
so I think we want like more of a you
know sort of a strong outward force in
terms of when you splat down and then I
think we're good
still seems kind of weak which doesn't
make a whole lot of sense I guess you
know this is not guaranteed to produce
motion because it could still pick
things in the middle but it may be one
of those things where we need to like
ensure a certain amount I just I don't
really want to do a cosign there on
spawn so here's what I will say this it
should probably where you place it is
probably also where it should go so I
guess what I would say is this probably
also wants to be whatever this random
between is producing I I probably want
to use it for both right so what I
probably want to do is say like X
displacement or rather I probably wanted
to get that displacement so like or like
a direction you know I mean and just say
look I'm gonna get two Direction values
here and I'm going to use the direction
the same direction value to both place
the puff relative to where the hero is
and to spawn the puff you know to give
it its velocity and and that way
hopefully it makes a little more sense
right except for some reason
Oh oops that's not what I meant to do
that
mm said expression expands that thing
out to put one in each of the lanes so
that was creating four particles that
all were exactly the same which
obviously we don't want to do so let me
just change briefly how that's happening
there you go
so that's what we actually needed to do
there
that way we'll still get four different
particles hmm but obeying the exact same
thing as I was saying before why can we
not do multiply here F 32 for X should
should be able to take a multiplier
right can we just not implement that
looks like we didn't it doesn't really
matter because I can just do this the P
scale and the DP scale can just be made
into their own values here right so I
think that should do it and then we can
get proper particle placement there for
some definition of particle our proper
rather and then you can see now it's
maybe a little bit too much right but
now it seems to be working better right
that's more like what we would expect
we also would probably in the future
want to spawn these kind of opposite the
direction you were hitting so if you
were gonna if your whatever direction
you're going you probably hit the
opposite one and when you stop would
probably go a particular way as well so
we probably want to like tune that but
that's that's more what I was expecting
right for puffs but yet they're probably
too fast now so these this should
probably be something lower but we'll
call that a day so all right our
particles are back in that's good our
Arts in that's good too
so mostly now I don't know we probably
want to go tackle the variant problem
and then probably tomorrow well tomorrow
we might have to debug the variant stuff
because that's gonna be pretty hairy
tomorrow we can maybe start on the
ground cover stuff or we can go do the
entity entity fix up we're still placing
that chair hilariously in the exit which
is not where chairs should be placed but
let me through let me through
inside the room gencode I don't remember
why it's able to place the furniture
into that square
[Music]
I'm gonna say that tile open should not
include the exits and maybe see if that
helps so basically like if it says on
connection so it can't I'm gonna say not
on connection here and just see if we
can patch that for now like creating
some furniture layout code is obviously
a totally separate thing that we want to
do at some point but for right now I
just don't want to be blocked by an
errand chair there we go
so I make sure it can still go down to
the dungeons yeah
all right that all seems right those
guys want some little boots as well
it's at the end
that's not maybe could get down here
further alright um hmm so how much time
do I have left
it's 1400 right now so we started at
what 12:30 right so we have what a half
hour left maybe let's say is that right
I think that's right
so I think we've got about a half hour
left trying to think of whether I should
start down the road to doing the variant
stuff or whether I should do something
else and start the variants first thing
tomorrow what else do we need to do you
know other than like big things like
fixing like finishing the lighting and
stuff like that
it's or a small thing I should be doing
right now that we can do
I could try changing from well no that's
gonna be big too so we went to the
variants run to the entity change that's
pretty big so those I want to do on
their own day what else are we doing now
that would make sense
yeah
I think everything that was on my mind
to do is like a day it's like a day long
thing that probably wants to start the
beginning of the day and there's at
least three of them that I want to do I
want to do the ground cover I want to do
the variant thing I want to do the
changing to not having entity pieces and
just entities and I'm just not not
thinking of of what would happen there
maybe I'll just go play around with
something then so like what's going on
right now with our kind of punchy stupid
punch thing I think I'm just gonna play
around stuff oh also why don't we have
any snakes
we don't ever place any snakes I guess I
don't know why we don't place a snakes
but I'm just curious
when we actually do a punch here
so it looks like there's a thing called
angle attack swipe and it looks like
maybe that punch speed is a bit high for
our current purposes and how high is
that glove
tends to be lowered down possibly
because it becomes disconnected so you
can see it drops down to the floor and
I'm not sure why it's doing that
if you look at what happens when it's
that angle offset here is the code for
angle offset it's angle base and then
it's got like this nonsense going on in
here
and for whatever reason I guess so if
you look this is a fall through case
right it's basically doing this updating
but it's always hitting this and so I
wonder why why would it have that
difference between you can see like the
oh well floating I guess is what it
normally is so I guess in any mode
floating just doesn't do anything right
you can see that it it kind of sets
itself back here and it's got a Z
displacement of 5 so this is just kind
of garbage code right like this angle
base I guess this is really the the only
difference probably
and we'll want to do like this code will
get completely rewritten once we
actually you know are working on combat
but I figured you know since we have
nothing to do right now it's like so
that should keep the fist stable you can
see now hunches at the same height just
make the room that it makes is also a
bit much I also think it should depend
on the facing direction where it's
hovering probably so we should probably
do that as well so you know if you look
at here it's get this angle based thing
so this this hover this piece of hover
information we actually want to know the
body facing direction where it creates
an arm - for that well I guess we're not
no one is but we want to take that body
facing direction and create a
displacement vector so the depending on
which way you're facing the glove should
look to that side so this is not what we
want right what we actually want to do
is say well there should be an arm to
here which says whatever the body's
facing direction is we then go out a
certain you know proportion from that
along a facing direction and that is you
know where we're actually going to place
the glove and so that way when we are
walking around you know it'll it'll pick
a location now if you look at what
happens that puts the glove directly in
front of the hero but we probably want
it to the side of the hero so what we
probably want to do is add right we want
to rotate the facing direction so that
we're actually back 90 degrees wound
backwards from where we're actually four
from what the face from where we're
facing so in other words we want it
pointing you know we our faces rector's
which are pointing the glove is to the
side of that so it's sort of like a
perpendicular right so what I probably
want to here is just say look why don't
you take
a quarter towel off of that before you
do anything and that's to be an F and
that way it'll be rotated backwards from
there so performing that now it feels a
lot more solid right now looking at
where it's actually placed it's it seems
like it might be a little too high
though
just looking you know it's up by his
head it should maybe be down a little
bit more from there so like this this
offset this height offset I don't really
know you know what we want that to be
but like you know temporarily let's say
it's something like that uh so that
allows our glove to be maybe a little
bit more fun and exciting right and at
this point we do have a little bit of an
issue we're like animation wise I'm not
sure how we want to do that eventually
look should it should you can see I kind
of whines a little bit differently where
should it go to the other side of the
hero like should we actually track that
and interesting enough it looks like we
are tracking that for the animation um
so you know so maybe we should so for
example in here the way that's doing it
is I I guess the glove angle current is
what would tell us that piece of
information so I guess the angle current
is the thing that we'd need to come in
here I don't know to what extent that
actually is just an exact angle we could
use so I'm gonna try throwing that in
there because I don't remember what we
set that to
well I guess it is it's exactly it's
exactly the amount of Tao rotated around
so it's on the wrong side there so if we
just add that angle current into where
it's floating then I think it'll return
to the correct side as well so like all
right so yeah I mean there's there's the
glove now I don't know that I can
actually punch people with this glove at
all but it won't be nice to be able to
do so right like I'd like to be able to
hit him I think that feels like about
the right speed for the glove but I'm
not 100% sure look maybe it should be a
little bit slower at least at first you
know again that's hard to say
so because the speed of the glove this
this part will have to be updated as
well because we probably want the speed
of the glove to be a parameter of the
glove you know that can be upgraded and
depending on which glove you're using it
will change and all that sort of stuff
so those will probably be that does feel
too small too slow though so I think
five will probably be where that's at
now if we did want to have some way of
having the glove attack the dude we
would need that you know to to go start
on the collision detection stuff but we
can probably hack something like that
I'm pretty pretty quickly just just for
testing purposes so if we go we sort of
have this notion of hit points we don't
really have a good way to draw them
right now
if we wanted to place the hit points on
the you know on on the characters that
you're fighting i we had like you know
ways of doing that already so if we look
I don't really remember what kind of
monster we're using here let's see so I
think it's this ad snake and just
looking at it it doesn't look like it
has hit points right so it seems like it
probably wants to do this on the add
snake just guessing so the snake has hit
points and then we need a way of drawing
the hit points which we had in there a
long time ago so as a thing I should
probably also put a snake in a starting
room just so we don't have to go down
there every time we want to do because
it takes a while to hop along on the
world for obvious reasons alright so
there's the hit point looks like we
still are German so that's good and we
probably don't want to draw them that
way in you know a limit but you know
that's fine for now we can see them so
we would like to do is just be able to
hit that dude with the glove and have
hip points go down so if we want to do
that
I believe we don't currently have a
collision volume set up for some of
these things we've got
this render volume code here which would
draw yeah like you can kind of see well
actually I don't know why I keep
rebooting so you can see here there's
like one collision volume for like where
the head the leader the leading of the
head is it's totally wrong and not what
we would want anymore
it's kind of old vestigial remains but
we would need one for the glove because
in order for the glove to hit enemies
both the enemy and the glove have to
have one so what we would want to do
there is again the glove is a separate
entity I think is it so the glove is a
separate entity and you can see that
it's set to collides here but nobody
ever gives it a collision volume so it
doesn't actually matter that it's set to
collide it won't help
right so in here we would need something
where we said like look the gloves
collision volume is like some collision
volume you know I mean so you know I
don't really want simple grounded
collision
I really just want this so here we could
just say here's a rectangle Center dim
call I think we just want to say like
the collision volume for the glove you
know is whatever it is which I don't
know what it is but let's say it's
something like that okay that's nice
blue glow so if we create a collision
volume for the glove and assigned it
which is what we're doing here then in
theory we should be able to see one
floating on the glove so if I leave this
and restart like hey look right and that
looks about right it looks like it's
floating too low maybe but I don't
really care at the moment too much about
that so when I'm hopping around there if
I want to if I want to actually hit the
enemy obviously the enemy has to have
one as well so when we create the snake
which I believe was right here we need
this to have a collision volume on it so
it needs to actually have collision and
that collision needs to be at least
somewhat representative of the of the
entity now looking at the way that works
the offset Z here probably should be
zero
and these things I think were relatively
like normal size I don't really know
so if we go run the game and look at
that snake now it should have a
collision volume on it as well so we've
got one on the glove we'll have one on
the snake and then we can do something
when they hit each other but that's code
that we wrote like you know Dave 20 or
something of handmade here way back when
that's gonna need to get polished up
certainly but let's take a look so there
you go you can see the collision volume
there so now we know we will know when
these two things hit each other but we
just won't we just don't do anything to
does this guy go upstairs ever I guess
not but I don't know why did we tell him
not to
hey man can you go upstairs see if I
push him towards it I'll just block him
so he has to go up the stairs no yeah
can you go upstairs yes go up there go
up there he doesn't want to go up there
so I guess they don't go upstairs
they'll go from room to room but they
don't go upstairs I guess it must win it
searches it must do a search that
doesn't allow it to change the height
very much I don't know all right so what
we want to do is know when we hit this
thing and I think I could be wrong about
this but there's still code in there
that moves entities and looks for
collisions right somewhere in here
there's like a move entity call here it
is this code is like totally garbage
it's just kind of hanging around but it
does still work and so I think
technically like you can see here we've
got sort of these handle collision calls
and
I really don't know if they even do
anything anymore but they probably are
still getting called no I'm saying so if
we want something damage oriented if we
go down and look at the move entity you
know move entity is gonna get called and
when it does these tests and it looks at
can collide what's gonna do is say
speculative collide here and then handle
collision here so handle collision does
something it looks like basically no
actual thing takes place though so
whatever we were gonna do on handle
collision just doesn't happen anymore
so you know if we wanted to implement
something where the glove if we wanted
to implement something where the glove
is that here's the other thing is move
entity is that actually every being
called on the glove because the glove
just gets placed this way so we really
just need to check for overlap with the
glove for doing that hit testing but the
actual movement does anyone actually
ever call that
so I'm not really sure
I'm not 100% certain if that actually
ever happens in fact I'm pretty positive
it doesn't because if you look at what's
going on here we fill out like the DP
and stuff but I'm sorry we fill out like
the position but we don't fill out the
DP or anything so it's never gonna
actually think that it needs to to move
this entity in that way and in fact we
know that we really just don't move
entities in that way anymore right
entities don't move that way
so really all we need to do is rather
than having the concept of entities move
is we really just need to do the overlap
test between the entities and see which
one you know I'm saying so I think if
you just if zero this out and just said
move entity is done it's not happening
anymore I don't think anything changes
right I don't think we actually get any
issues do we maybe we I mean we might
you can see that like nothing happens
right everything's fine
so if we want to change this to being
overlapped testing and not based on new
vanity there we can still use the same
code though to do the overlap testing
but we need to be able to see where the
entity was and where the entity is you
know what I mean so we need to kind of
know those two things like where was it
and where is it now so we need to know
like the difference in where the
position is of this thing and then where
the position a you know where it started
the frame and where it ended the frame
so we probably want to do something
where we just like look and see you know
the start P is going to be you know that
and then the end P it's going to be back
and once we know those two things then
we can actually do overlap testing but
the problem is you know again that's not
quite good enough because since each
since all the things are moving and we
want to check pairwise
we probably want to put the collision
detection there so we'll stop that now
because we're at the five-minute warning
and probably don't really want to do
anything more with that but that's where
that's where we would go with that
information right and we'd sort of
change this move entity call into a
thing that just takes all the movement
vectors does the collision detection on
them and reports back to us which ones
hit so that we can do our collision
handling there all right I'm going to go
ahead and go to the QA
we don't know where Molly went we've
lost we've lost the puss the puss is
gone
oh cool someone if you were here on the
pre stream someone asks a question about
amiga Oz and I was explaining the fact
that it used to interrupt to do
scheduling but I didn't know which
interrupt it was using I could remember
I and VT VT l MKS wrote back now that
it's the V blank interrupts so you know
how you had on the old CRTs you know the
the beam would trace left to right and
when it got to the bottom it would go
back to the top that time where it
returns back to the top that was called
the vertical blank and so on the Amiga
there was a piece of hardware I want to
say it was probably like hard like
hardwired into the copper chip I'm
assuming the copper chip was the thing
that did scanline based operations and
so I'm assuming that the copper chip is
the thing that would trigger the V blank
interrupts on the 6800
so you know the 6800 has interrupts and
you know the way a CPU works right is
it's got like pins that come in the
contribute interrupts and stuff I'm
assuming the copper chip was connected
to the 68k in such a way as to be able
to trigger that interrupts when it hit
the V blank that's what I would assume I
don't actually know I don't remember I
don't know that I ever knew the answer
that question really I know that both
the 68k and the copper knew about the
vertical blank but I don't know how they
would talk to each other necessarily but
anyway so that was what the Amiga OS
used for scheduling for pre-emptive
scheduling I didn't know which interrupt
they were using I didn't know if there
was like a separate timer interrupt or
whatever I couldn't remember but it
sounds like what they do is they use the
vertical blank the VTL MKS said default
quantum was 4 so I'm assuming what that
means is you get 4 V blanks or four
sixtieths of a second and then it would
consider swapping you is that is that
what you mean is that what default
quantum was for for V blanks
which on the Amiga would be 62 ii in in
mtsc so probably japan in the US but it
would probably have been for 50th of a
second on PAL because the display
centers were different so the V blank
timing was different
NTSC with 60 fields a second pal was 50
again if I remember correctly
yeah four frames
four fields technically right probably
but those are sort of like frames
but that's pretty cool it's a little
weird it means you're multitasking runs
at different speeds depending on whether
it's pal or ntsc right the number of
instructions you can execute before
being swapped out is different so it it
means that you get finer grained
multitasking but that's probably slower
overall because it's swapping more
frequently which takes more work on the
NTSC amigas and on the PAL amigas you
would get less fine-grained multitasking
but probably faster overall probably
what collisions be solved in a
physically based way or in a hacky way
well collisions are not physically based
or hacky in terms of detecting them
right how you detect collisions can be
hacky or cleaned totally separately of
whether it has any of physics in terms
of resolving the motion we don't really
have any of that that I can think of we
don't have any physically based movement
our movement is all programmatic so
there there isn't like you know free
flying bodies that like will bounce off
walls or something everything is more
specific about how it's supposed to move
like it's supposed to hop from here to
here or something and we don't it's like
hard hard coded gameplay wise that a hop
is an exact thing we don't allow you to
get like interrupted in the middle of a
hop for example and we do that because
we don't want any gameplay bugs which
would obviously occur if you allowed
physics to happen in there because then
you could have like two people who are
both trying to hop to ask where the
squares there we're on get occupied and
now there's nowhere for them to go and
you're just in a bug there's no
resolution because now you've got two
people occupying one square which is not
in the game and all that's rough right
so we don't allow that we have like a
rigorous logic for how things are
allowed to move and physics is not
allowed to intercede because you would
end up in buggy scenarios I mean all
games that are physically based have
bugs all over the place right and that's
fine if your priority is the physical
movement because it's like look we don't
care that we'll get into a bunch of
buggy gameplay scenarios because we're
trying to provide like physics based
gameplay that's the point
right but in our case we don't care
about physics based gameplay like
physics doesn't have anything to this
game it's not an interesting part of it
so we have like specific logic things
that have to occur to that because we
want to prevent being able to get into
any of those gameplay bug scenarios
where you've got things that impossible
configurations that then explode no NTSC
is not 30 FPS it's 60 FPS but the F
stands for fields not frames because it
renders the odd scan lines in 162 second
and then the even scan lines on the
other 62 second and the V blank happens
both times at least that's my
recollection and then I want to say that
pal was 25 and 50 right so it did every
50th of a second it would do even on
fields even odd fields every 50 a second
doing either/or so it was just a little
slower
I assume that has to do with power
standards
I assume like European powers 100 based
and our power is 120 based or something
I'm assuming this I'm gonna do that I
don't know K that has nothing to do with
it
probably has nothing to do with it but
anyway there was probably a reason I
just don't know what that reason was
what was the reason why why wasn't ESC
60 in PAL 50 does anyone know
Wow was I actually right that it was the
power standard that means I've looked
this up before and it did lodge itself
in there and then I forgot
this is due to the fact that mtsc is
journal using countries the utility
frequency of 60 Hertz and Palin
countries with 50 Hertz so I think that
is actually what I was saying like the
power standard is actually more
appropriate for one or the other so I
guess I guess I was right
am I really I don't know
also Anna informed us that this the Hat
flower is is supposed to go on the side
of the head that's why I thought this is
it so this is actually our bad it was
not a bug it was not an art
all right and if we are no questions
then I will call it a day
alright let's wrap it up I should update
to the new remedy as well there's
there's like two new versions of remedy
past the one we're on I think we're on
like two four and they're on two five
yeah I'm sorry two six there George is
on two six now all right thank you for
joining me for an episode of a handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you would like to
follow along series at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
org it comes to the source code if you
want to play around with it tomorrow I'd
like to do the variant stuff and that'll
probably take all day
well not all day but you know you'll
take the time for the episode and get
that fixed in that way that's solid and
we don't have to worry about it anymore
so we'll probably do that we probably
have time for anything else
if we do we'll move on to the cover
ground cover because that's sort of the
next big thing we should probably get
into the system that's about it for
today if you or shouldn't that come back
tomorrow see you here for that until
then have fun programming I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody