hello everybody welcome to handmade Hero
show Rico to complete-game live on
stream for those of you who didn't stick
around past the end of the recording
yesterday one of our viewers who I don't
really remember if they had asked a
question before or not it's Benjamin on
the chat actually was like hey do you
think that the bug was related to not
having the bitmap loaded yet and I was
like I do think that the bug could be
very related to that and we quickly
looked and it totally is so the bug we
were looking for yesterday we think we
know what it is I didn't want to fix it
because I don't ever like to do anything
off stream so basically we just looked
to see if it was probably the case and
it almost certainly is so what I'd like
to do is just just take a quick second
show what the bug actually what we
thought it was and and then we can go
ahead and fix it since we don't really
have a way to repo it exactly we could
force it to repro but since we don't
have a way to really know exactly what
bug we were seeing last time we can't
guarantee that this is it but it seems
very likely so if you look at what was
happening here we do have this
run-through of these piece indexes for
every entity and for each one we store a
pointer to the bitmap that was
responsible for that piece index so
whichever one we end up drawing the
problem that we ended up with is that
that pointer that bitmap info pointer
here that we're getting that actually
only gets set inside the this particular
part of the routine right so you can see
that happening right here this is where
that that array gets filled out and the
problem is that we don't descend into
this part of the code unless the texture
handle we get back is actually valid
that's a huge problem for us because
that means we don't store this piece of
information back now there's no reason
that we can't do that and we should
write in other words this storage here
there's no reason it can't be done here
because this get bitmap info that will
work whether or not the bitmap is loaded
so if instead we were to just say oh
like do this right
get the thing always and write it back
always and then if you have a texture
handle by all means go to town that's
fine
right but what we don't want to do is
not actually process this piece of
information here right now instead of
doing that exactly what I'd like to do I
think is just move this this piece of it
for me this is a check down closer to
the rendering process because the
texture handle actually isn't used for
anything
and so what I'd rather do is say look
all of this stuff should really just
still happen and why don't we just save
this part right where we're actually
looking at the the texture handle here
why don't we only defer the rendering if
we can't get the texture handle because
all of this stuff is about constructing
the world properly right and we'd like
to be able to do that now one of the
problems this world dim from world
plight this takes the test texture
handle here and that's the only thing I
think that takes the texture handle but
I'm pretty sure I mean I could be wrong
but I'm pretty sure this texture width
and I think here there's really no
reason to actually do this this way
because that piece of information
actually is in the bitmap info as well
right so if you were to look at how
restoring our bitmaps you can see here
that we have the dimension information
both the original size that the thing
was
in like when we imported it
so before we like process scale it and
afterwards when we store it both of
those pieces of information are actually
available right so I'm pretty sure that
there's really no need for that texture
handle at all this texture handle could
instead be replaced with the HH a bitmap
pointer and that bitmap pointer would
give us everything we need so I'm gonna
argue that's what we should do because
again this is kind of part of my process
I tend to do this just in general I like
to separate streaming information from
non streaming information pretty
rigorously if I can and say look when a
game starts up it should have all of its
functional information just loaded if it
can and nowadays it's pretty rare for it
to be the case that you can't do that
you know you're usually talking about
something like 256 megabytes even for a
giant giant system for all of the
metadata you might need and so all the
like 30 gigabytes of extra data that you
need is all textures and vertex buffers
and stuff that stuff is all the
streaming stuff just stream that part in
but leave all of the connective tissue
always rezident why because the game can
keep running without it right without
that streaming stuff if it has all the
metadata it can always make the gameplay
happen every frame exactly as it should
and you can just do worse rendering or
you know something just flickers and
doesn't quite appear correctly or
something if your streaming can't keep
up but the game doesn't stutter do a
halt right and so I prefer to like have
it so that the anything that the game
needs to actually make decisions about
where stuff is or how it's doing what
it's doing I try to have that stuff
resident
much guaranteed and then usually all the
stuff that's streaming you can break
that down into stuff that doesn't ever
need to be looked at for decision-making
right most of the time not all the time
but a lot of the time you can and that's
just because there's a huge disparity in
size between the sorts of things that
are used for visuals and the sorts of
things that are used for gameplay just
usually right okay so in here where we
do world dim from world height what I
want to do is just do okay you know
maybe you pass me a bitmap info oh
that's actually an H H bitmap and what
we want to do there is be able to grab
that out and like I said this is
producing this change in sort of size so
we just the only thing we really need
here is the aspect ratio and so that's
what the original dimensions will tell
us it's telling us the aspect ratio of
the original image so the original dip
dimension one is the height right and
here we have info or exam
and the dim zero is gonna be the width
right and so if I redo real dim from
world height that way and say here is
the new function definition for this
thing that in theory should get me out
of the business of using that texture
handle right so now in here where we
were passing the texture handle before
we should be able to pass the bitmap
info instead and that's all we would
need I think okay so if that's actually
the case now my argument is that we have
potentially eliminated the bug that we
were seeing yesterday and in theory we
shouldn't have changed anything else
that's just in theory though we don't
actually know now that allows us to
maybe potentially possibly hopefully and
I guess we'll see in a second
get back to what we were trying to do
before and if you remember what we were
trying to do before was get this stuff
working where we are going to use the
we're gonna use the information about
where our sprites are to try and do some
improved snapping of points two points
right and we talked about that yesterday
so if you're not familiar with what
we're doing you want to watch at least
the beginning of yesterday's stream
where I talk about what we want to do
for alignment if that makes sense
so what I'd like to do now is just take
a look at when we're doing these bright
values for upper right and we we pull in
you know whatever we're doing for us
right here we know that this is centered
about zero zero right now so the min P
is telling us where we would place this
thing if we wanted zero zero to be the
if we wanted zero zero to be the
alignment point right so that's what min
P is basically telling us and then we
also at the same time because we have
gotten the the parent piece here we've
got this initial P this this right here
this initial P tells us the point that
we're trying to align with and this one
will
you know that's that's just accurate in
world space it's just where we want to
snap to right so what we want to do now
is figure out how to compute a location
for this new sprite that will match the
location that we're supposed to be
matching when viewed dead-on from the
camera and you can like I said go back
to yesterday's dream for an explanation
of what I mean by that but essentially
what I'm talking about is if we were to
look at when we start to set these
points now if I open up the point editor
here right you can see me tweaking like
where this this alignment thing is let
me turn off this top that head
attachment there so if you look at where
this zoom on in there we go so if you
look at how these points are distributed
right you can see me moving it around
here what we want to do is say all right
that white point when we draw the white
point we're drawing there is the point
that's being input by the game and
saying this is the point you're supposed
to align to right these colors down here
tell us what the points are that we're
looking at so the red point is point
zero the green point is point one for us
to see and so what we want to do is make
something that snaps this red alignment
point here to this white point here
that's what we want to do and like I
said we want to do that such that if I
were looking at from this camera angle
exactly and you were right in the middle
of the view looking right down at it it
would snap now it's crucial to
understand that I mean only that
particular alignment of the camera and
the entity should we get the snapping
and like I said go back to yesterday's
stream if you want to know why in more
detail but the idea here is I want there
to be perspective shift as the things
move across or up and down on the screen
so I do not want this algorithm to
correct for the perspective shift that
happens around by Reese napping so I'm
intentionally we need our algorithm for
aligning these points to intentionally
only align them from one specific camera
angle and one specific camera angle only
that is where they should appear a line
and then anything off of that camera
angle they should become progressively
more unaligned as the perspective shift
pulls them apart okay so that's at least
what we're trying now that's our goal
right now to see if we can make that
happen
a little more specifically just without
any additional you know we want very
specifically to make sure that we're not
correcting too much and preventing
ourselves from from getting that nice
perspective shift that I want right okay
um so let's see now if I go over here
and look at how this is actually being
lined the game's still running over here
by the way I haven't turned it off or
anything but so if we take a look at how
these sprite values who are coming in
I'm gonna want to work out a diagram so
I'll probably flip over to Milton in a
second but if you look at how these are
working we get this back and what we
want to do is take this bright min P
that we received and we want to adjust
it for the alignment so the entire goal
of this process is to adjust that sprite
min P now there is something a little
confusing about what we're doing and I'm
not sure exactly how we're supposed to
deal with it it's a little bit under
specified right and the part that I'm
talking about is this piece offset here
so there's two choices that we have and
they're both probably wrong and that's
why I say we might need to like upgrade
the way that we're processing that but
the piece offset right now is used for
two separate things one thing it's used
for
offsetting something in space so for
example if we're saying that the head
attached to the body and we want the
head to be like up higher than the body
and Z right it's being used to do that
but then it's also being used to do
something totally separate which is to
provide secondary animation to the head
as it bounces around right and so our
problem is I don't really know exactly
how that should be working with respect
to the alignment what I'm going to say
because it doesn't really matter but
what I'm going to say at the start is
let's say that the piece offset is added
after alignment so you align these two
points and then you offset the piece
from that alignment to its location so
offset can just break all the rules
it can do anything it wants so the
alignment happens first then the offset
happens right so I think that's what we
want to do the reason I think that's
what we want to do is because really
alignment is just for our own art
aesthetic purposes and so I think it's
sufficient to do it this way where we
just align a point and then say what
kind of displacement we want off of the
point I can't think of a reason why we
can't just do it that way although there
might be some reasons I'm not sure that
that that that we don't want to do that
the reason that I don't think it matters
is because let's suppose that we then
find that that's not sufficient and what
we would rather do is split into two
halves one half is there's the offset of
this piece and we want to take that we
want to do that before aligning right
and then the other one is secondary
animation that moves it around and
obviously we want to do that after
alignment it's trivial for us to just
split them right because we can always
just before we start processing mimpi
we can always stuff the align
the pre alignment offset in there do the
alignment exactly however we solved it
do it and then apply the post alignment
so we can it's freedom for us to split
this later and shove one part of it in
earlier the process if we need to so I'm
gonna say right now let's just not worry
about that we'll let this happen at the
end of the process and then we'll look
later on right we can decide whether we
need to change up how that's working so
at the moment what we can see is this is
the part we then have to work with this
right here is sort of the stuff we were
doing that we found worked well for
sorting which is to say using the Y
displacement and this is us preventing
it from sinking down into the floor and
stuff this is the part that we want to
now want to look at more closely and we
need to figure out how we will compute
these values now hopefully this won't be
very complicated hopefully this is a
relatively simple piece of math for us
to do but we have to think about what it
actually should do first so we don't
actually know if it's simpler or not
we're about to find out after we sort of
state what our requirements for this
particular thing are so here's day 5:22
and this is a line for default camera
okay so what we want to do like I said
let's take a look at a side view since
its easiest to understand what's going
on in that case I think let's draw the
canonical wall plus floor right so this
is wall this right here is floor not
flour flour all right it's flour
apparently so it's like a it's a little
like sack of flour and it like poof's
all right it's great let's bake a
biscuit I'm chuffed to bits really I
didn't think I would make it past cake
week but I'm just I'm just
chuffed to bits all right so anyway here
we are in a line for default camera and
what I mean by that is there is some
default camera that's pointing right
down here like I said we're looking at
this from the side here's a wall here's
the flower and what we want to do is
create a sprite here that's going to
have the alignment information that I
want now we know for the first you know
just to start with is it's gonna be
something like the center point of the
floor what I'm going to do is I'm going
to I need right if I were to draw a line
through that point to the camera so I
don't know exactly how the camera is
actually pointing pretty downward right
so I do think it's something like this
but if I were to draw a line down
through that point like that there we go
so what we're talking about with a line
point is we know we have a sprite now
that's got some point on it that we
computed as the align point right and
what we're saying is we want this point
to appear in the same location as that
point right so we're trying to figure
out where to place this sprite so that
this point and that point are on the
same line of the camera now what we were
doing before and this is why things were
sinking into the ground before we
started down the path of let's figure
out how to do the correct placement so
before yesterday or before the I guess
before last Sunday we were just snapping
these points together in world space
right like that or something and that's
not gonna cut it because that's gonna
sink right into the floor right so what
we want to do instead is throughout work
replace this thing so that it will
properly look like we did that but not
sink into the floor so what we want to
do is say okay I want to figure out the
location of this point such that the
lowest point
the thing wherever that was right I want
the lowest point to stay constrained to
this plane but I want this point to end
up on this line right so it's free for
us to do one of those things right one
of those things takes almost no thought
at all we know what the lowest point on
this on this is right would be right
because literally we just have an x and
y axis and we're gonna draw it off of
that wherever we place the thing that's
the lowest point it can't go lower than
that right now
rotation is gonna change this so again
like I said we're gonna have to go
through this as a second pass hopefully
if we get through with this today we'll
start on that second pass right after to
make sure that we do some slightly
different stuff for rotation because
it's a little bit more complicated but
again take rotation out of the equation
for a second we would know what the
lowest point is it's just where we were
gonna draw in the first place right so
that is free to just say look wherever
this thing would have been whatever this
alignment point was we just make sure
that that Z is the same right and then
we know it's that's that's how high it
is so that's really pretty basic to move
this down to here that's fine so the
only real question we have to ask
ourselves is if we were to slide along
of the Z plane right and we don't have
to slide in X because X just works right
X setting the alignment point in X
matching the two alignment points in X
will just work because there is no need
to play with the Z bias there right Y is
the only thing that affects our Z bias X
doesn't because it's lateral on the
screen doesn't change the depth at all
so if we're gonna slide again and this
is in the y axis right because remember
Z is going up here so we're gonna slide
in the y axis here's our camera again
right and let me draw that line coming
down so here's that let's say that's our
line here's our alignment point you know
here's the camera and we want that that
to line up right
so if we were to say alright let's place
this this thing on the ground right and
we know we've got a point somewhere on
this thing that we're gonna align all we
need to know is what would be the point
that we would place it at so this if we
were to make sure that this was on this
line right so we want to slide this
thing such that it ends up looking like
that we want to know this point the
thing that would place it such that the
alignment point will be in the same line
as the alignment point that we're
matching right the child point in the
parent point this is the child point
this is the parent point we need those
to appear in a line right and that's and
that's all right pretty straightforward
okay so there's a number of different
ways that we could imagine solving this
and they kind of correspond to two ways
of looking at this diagram one way of
solving this would be to say well we
know this line because we're making
we're saying that our default camera if
this thing we're placed in the center of
the screen the default camera pointing
up it's actually this is just you know
that's just the z-axis right
that's just the z-axis of the camera
that's what that is that you're pointing
down so we know what this line is we
don't have to solve for it we just have
it it's the z-axis so one thing we could
do is say look let's just say that we
align the alignment point with this
thing so we're gonna construct around
the z-axis how far down the z-axis would
we have to push before this hits the
plane right the other way to do it would
be to say let's place this at the
alignment point and figure out how far
we have to slide this way before we hit
this line now my intuition tells me and
that intuition is not particularly good
but
intuition suggests to me that that
pushing along this line is the easier
way to do it
probably but I would guess that probably
if you worked either one out they
probably come out to basically the same
meaning I don't think either one is
gonna be all that more complex right
that's just a guess
all right so let's again recap if we
assume then that we know what this line
is because we know that it's the it's
the Z coordinate of this alignment point
so we don't have to do much to that
right so if what we want to know is
moving along this z axis where would we
have to put this thing such that this
was correctly at the the horizon now at
the that line well it really shouldn't
be very difficult because we know this
length right we know we know how high up
we actually need this thing to go right
because this point and this point we
already computed so if we subtract there
Z's we get like a height value that's
like how high this thing needs to go
right we also know this camera z-axis
right it's that that's the camera z-axis
so we know it's ratio of movement to its
unit right we know it's unit length this
way we know this right by just it's just
a dot product with the world's axis it's
just and that just gives us here's the z
axis here here's the camera z axis
camera z dot actual z axis right gives
us this and hey when you dot something
with the z axis that's like saying CX x
ZX plus cy x zy plus c z times z z don't
ask me why that Camozzi
right what do we know about the z-axis
it's X is zero its Y is zero and it's Z
is 1 so that is the value right so we
actually know that the Z coordinate of
the cameras z-axis is this amount right
and we know this amount so if we want to
push this thing up until it would be at
the height where it's low point right
would touch the ground they're not
particularly difficult just H over cz
done right so H over cz is the amount we
could call that t let's say is the
amount along this axis that I would have
to push in order you know again along
the camera z-axis to push this thing
from the alignment point to get it to
where it needs to be and so at that
point we're just looking at literally
this T times that camera access this you
know the alignment point you start here
alignment point plus teeth T C gets us
right there and we're done right so I
think this displacement is really all we
needed it's incredibly simple to compute
I didn't even have to solve for anything
it was literally just inspecting the
diagram was sufficient to give me
basically how I would make it I don't
see a lot of problems with that
it seems relatively stable and like I
said before it allows us we could do
whatever we wanted there if we want to
include some kind of a pre displacement
that would move this whole thing off of
the alignment point first we certainly
can right because this term right here
can have anything you want baked into it
so you know you can have alignment point
plus T times C plus offset right and
these things can do whatever they want
in that regard right and so the only
thing you have to do is figure out how
you want to compute H whether you want
it off of the original or off of a
displaced right and that's the only
thing that would change how this thing
would look is that computation of T
right so we should be able to plus with
this however we want and it just doesn't
seem like it's gonna be that big of a
deal you know famous last words but I'm
fairly comfortable with that so when the
sprite values for upright things come
back let's just take a minute to assess
what and I'm gonna move it over here so
my head's not in the way a part of it
let's just take a minute to assess like
what do we actually have there and how
does like a correspond to the diagram
right well this initial P okay that's
good
this initial P here I don't know why I
keep going it there we go I was trying
to highlight that for you but the wiggle
went too far and went over there umm
this initial P right that's that
alignment point of the parent so that's
where we were starting that was this
right so that's where we want to move
out from then we've got the the child
point here we need that to find this
where the alarm point supposed to be we
need to find that height so how high up
off of the ground that's going to be so
how do we do that well this sprite
values for up right that's gonna give us
back a min P that effectively is that
height
so this sprite min P Z before we zeroed
it here that's right min P Z was the
height of the alignment point right
because that was how we computed it see
here the min P is just hey let's step
backwards on the X&amp;Y along the XY axis
for the sprite and let's see where we
end up if we want to do our alignment
right so that means that the min P Z
right that Z displacement that's
actually the value we want now it's
going backwards right cuz it's it's so
that's the the negative essentially of
the height cuz it's gonna be going down
into the ground rather than up but it's
still the value we want it's just the
negative of the value we want right so
if we were to first say what's that H
value right well the H value is just
gonna be this so we already know we
already know what that is right
and again we know that cz this is pissed
me off okay there we go
we know that cz because again it's the
camera z-axis and I believe that's OB as
part of the render group actually I
could be wrong about that but I'm pretty
sure it is well actually you can see it
here we're getting that information like
this right so here's our camera Z so we
can get that trivially that camera
z-axis is just just grab out the value
right so that gives us the two things we
want that height and that's easy now
what's you know what's the the
degenerate condition here because you
know watch what's gonna happen so that T
value I said is H over cz that gives us
that ratio of push well notice that now
we've created a situation where we can
get unstable right as that cz approaches
zero this becomes an undefined value and
it will explode actually right it will
start getting higher and higher and then
and then go to an undefined value but
looking at this right as you can see how
its constructed the math usually doesn't
introduce synthetic things those are
usually real things that you're seeing
so what is the real thing that we're
seeing here well if you come back to the
diagram we're asking this to push this
thing up right to account for this much
height so that we don't interpenetrate
the ground right well if the camera was
all the way down here looking sideways
right there is then it would have to
push along this line and there is no
elevation so it could push along this
line for infinitely long and never get
any higher right make sense so that is
the math is telling us there's a
degenerate case and that's exactly
correct right now that degenerate case
is fine because our camera can't go down
they're right we don't let the camera do
that but that's exactly what that's
telling us right and we can go ahead and
you know make sure that we sort of
account for this right we can say look
you know we don't we don't even want you
to have entertain any situations that
are even close to this right where is
the actual there it is
so we can say look if the if the camera
is not in a reasonable position then
we're not going to go any further down
this right so the Z has to be you know
it has to be kind of looking down like
this right and we don't allow the user
to move the camera at all but our
cutscene stuff may cut scenes the wrong
word but are like our camera movement
stuff that focuses on things in the
level or whatever it may do some flexing
so we don't want a hard code it we still
do want to look at this value because we
may allow it to vary we just don't ever
want it to get particularly low so it
should it should stay you know up in
that range where this value is gonna be
you know I mean that's probably even
reasonable but you know all right so you
know maybe I'll even leave it there just
to make just to be a real grouse about
it so we want to make sure you're fairly
elevated because that's the only way we
really allow this stuff to line up and
then we say okay let's make sure that
everything else falls into line assuming
that that's the case this is the T value
that we know that we actually needed
that T value is the thing that we would
have to displace to get these things to
line up properly and so now I think we
can actually just apply that alignment
and be done I think so meaning if now I
said look forget about this stuff that
was happening before what we're gonna do
instead is just apply the cameras z axis
on this proportion right pull that to
let it pull out by that amount and then
we're gonna apply whatever the
displacement is right now I'm gonna nerf
that for now oh no that's correct sorry
this is the displacement right
so we're just gonna take whatever the
initial P was that's the alignment point
and we're gonna take that T camera Z and
that's gonna be the min P we're gonna
offset by that much and that should
should push us out I think that's
correct although actually that that is
actually correct but we want to set the
point to be exactly there so we don't
want to add we want to actually make
that work right is that right no that's
not right this was aligned around zero
zero so we still need to conclude that
offset for our alignment point so I
believe this is correct right yeah
so then we would apply this piece offset
I'm just not gonna do that yet right I
don't actually want that to happen yet
so I'm gonna compile this code and see
if this without the offset how we're
doing here right maybe maybe really
terrible we'll see uh so let me take a
look with why is there a second is that
a bug in our okay is that a bug in our
art pipeline if that got added
let me delete that I'm curious if we
have a bug because we never you know we
still have to do a bunch of debugging in
the art pipeline stuff and I'm just
curious if it adds points unnecessarily
there yeah so I'm not sure where that
came from
hmm so anyway here's the base of neck so
well you know what we can start by
looking at the alignment of this so
here's the the motion of this around and
you'll notice I'm getting really good
behavior there's nothing it's not inter
penetrating the ground at all right if I
leave it in a particular place and then
switch to the debug camera so that we
can kind of look in here at those points
that is just right on the money
look at that I mean that's just great
right so now if I go back here and say
let's turn back on the alignment for
this guy for example so here's that
alignment point that I'm just moving
around on me then I'll look at the head
right let me add one of these here right
and then we'll sort of shift it around
okay so you can look and that's just
locked exactly to right so that seems
like resounding success
to me I mean that just seems great right
and yeah I got no complaints there so I
think that's really all we needed I
think that's very good so our only real
issue now is what to do about the
rotation now we have another decision we
can make that's free so we'll go do
rotation now but we have another
decision here that's effectively free
for us and I just don't know which way
we want to make it but effectively what
we need to know is when we apply this
offset when do we want it applied right
so let's suppose that I apply it now so
it just gets added after the fact
what that means is our alignment points
will no longer line up because we lined
them up and then we moved the thing
right so that offset is not taken into
account by the alignment so if we look
how these things are displaced now
whatever that piece offset is and again
that piece offset like I said is kind of
important because I want to you know be
able to have that secondary motion in
there right but that piece offset then
means that if I look at the alignment
points here in theory any amount of
alignment that may have happened there
would make it so that these would not
line up anymore I'm moving the head
around here and looking at that green
alignment point and then looking back at
one of these there we go snap on there I
don't actually see it drawing the red
point anywhere is there a reason for
that
oh do I have to be in debug camera mode
for that I guess I do I don't know why
oh it might have been click no I don't
know why oh well maybe no you know I
have no idea why all right so anyway
there's that red point and there's the
green point do you see how they're not
aligned anymore right before they were
exact and I think we could probably even
make that a little bit clearer right if
I actually compile that down right
there we go so right now those are exact
if I swap back and forth right they're
exactly aligned to each other and if I
put this on assuming that there is an
offset which I guess I don't know they
won't be exact anymore or they shouldn't
be anyway right so if I go back to
alignment points here I have no idea why
that doesn't because the entities not
selected okay we got to do some cleanup
on our UI for this editor it's it's
annoying all right so you actually can
see yes there is a displacement right it
moves a little bit not much but a little
bit and it's whatever that piece offset
amount is right I'm gonna go ahead and
say that I guess we don't really care it
looks fine with it just getting added in
I mean it was barely a difference anyway
even for the amount that we were using
right now so maybe that's just fine I
want to go into like ad player I want to
see how much displacement actually is
there if we look at adding the headpiece
on here you can see that headpiece being
added right here it doesn't really look
like there's very much Z there and maybe
there should be more right because there
maybe should be more exaggeration to the
separation between the two things so one
of the problems I guess that we would
have is we don't really know what kind
of stacking we want there
I don't know so if you assume that's
yeah if you assume that this is in
roughly in meters you know maybe this is
more should be more like that maybe
again kind of hard to say but you know
we need to decide on how far up those
things should be but you know there's
gonna be some number and again what that
number is really gonna determine for our
purposes is how much perspective shift
you get between these two elements right
and I like that perspective shift you
know I want that in there um so I think
that's all we really needed to do it
looks like we've got really good shape
there and you know the sorting seems
basically perfect now so everything's
happy and fine and dandy and so really
what we want to do I think is we'd like
to go back in and get some rotating
elements in there so you know maybe make
the head just spin around for no reason
and then we can go and make sure that
our our rotation works we the body is
doing shearing right now and we're not
getting much of an error from the
shearing but that's because the shearing
doesn't really deform the shape as much
in terms of where the high Z values are
as spinning it all the way around wood
right and so we have to kind of decide
what we think should be happening with
rotation and I don't know so it may be
that because we're aligning the
alignment points now which is good
because I mean they're called alignment
points or a reason because we're
aligning the alignment points I think
what we want to do is say well maybe
rotation can just be made to work
directly with the fact that those are
aligned and maybe it just doesn't matter
right because since they'll the
alignment points will align anyway then
it doesn't matter what rotation you did
it'll just work because we don't care
what the base point is anymore that may
actually be true right so I think if we
look at what happens here this this
value is the only value we probably
would have to change meaning that each
value is
if you imagine the thing is spinning
around that H value is not necessarily
the point that needs to be pulled out of
the ground right and so that's really
the part that I'm not sure what we want
to do with yeah so here's what I'm
thinking I think what we want to do is
maybe make this H value directly
proportional to the sprite height
instead of actually looking at the min
PZ and the reason I say that is because
it for a sprite that spins around we're
gonna need to keep it a consistent
distance from the camera we don't want
it to do this so it may be that we need
to just say look based on the alignment
point we're gonna say that we use a
particular maximum value maybe based on
whatever the whatever the larger of the
two fractions is so if the alignment
point was 25% then we know the most you
could sink into the floor was the 75% if
you'd spun 180 degrees around with
rotation so we use that as the distance
and it's whatis constant so we don't
care how you've rotated cuz again we as
you rotate we don't want to move you
like further you we don't want it to
pulse into the camera because we're
perspective you'll see it right if we
were orthographic you wouldn't be able
to tell how it was moving real it's
camera but what perspective you would
see it enlarge so I think we want to do
is compute a constant value for that and
and I think that would would do the
trick
that seems pretty good to me what I'd
like to do first is just say look let's
get some rotation in there so we can see
you know doing this is gonna be
pointless if we if we don't have some
idea of like what's actually happening
so we need some way to get the entity
spinning around I don't know if we have
anything like that at all I looks like
in the team movement stuff there's some
you know there's some skewing but
there's not it doesn't look to me like
there's any any rotation actually where
are we getting these x axis Y axis is
from actually entity x-axis and a y-axis
where are those getting set though
I don't actually see anyone modifying
them in the movement code so I guess
they're only being set up inside the
brains maybe are they just being cold
set can we do a little who is who set in
those I mean cuz nobody nobody here is
doing anything right and nobody here is
doing anything so where is that
what am I missing folks we must be
setting something because if you look at
what happens to the like we're
definitely warping the axes I mean look
at look at that bottom in fact you know
if I turn off let's say in here
I turn off the alignment points for the
invasive neck right so we're just
looking at this thing
I mean look that's totally setting a
that's totally setting a skew on the on
the axes so someone's setting those axes
right and if it's not in the brain where
is it exactly because I would have
thought it would have been in here
somewhere where we would have set those
axes up or you know back in the nd code
but maybe it's using some kind of a like
convenience function that's not in the
place that I was looking let's see it's
been a while since we ever looked at
this code it's just kind of some I look
that's a good to do right there
I mean I'm not seeing I'm not seeing us
deal with that anywhere in particular
right ah okay so it is sitting the
y-axis it's just not setting the x-axis
my bad
so here it is here's us setting that
x-axis I'm sorry that y-axis that's
what's that head Delta right is that's
what's allowing us to kind of do that
that pointing there so I don't really
know of anybody else who's even touching
this stuff you know oh well all right so
if we wanted to make this thing spin
around we probably could do that by I
don't know how exactly we would want to
do that but I could just have the t-bob
value or something like that or a t-spin
value that was just spending this thing
around I don't have a lot of other ideas
but basically all I'm saying is if
instead of setting it this way we just
had the head kind of do this sort of
thing I don't know the only thing is the
head is not really an entity right now I
mean we sort of have some vestigial
remains in there where it is but it's
actually not being that it's not being
processed as a separate entity that's
not something that's actually happening
right so yeah I do think that probably
we want to fix the way we were doing
this and I just don't know if I want to
do it right now I think I'd rather just
hack it in and then move to it a little
later but what I'm gonna say is the
entity pieces thing I don't think worked
out really well I don't love it I think
probably what we should do instead is
just have the notion that
you snap together so the heads identity
the bodies identity the gloves identity
and they all snap together right I think
that's what we should have done and so I
think I will do that as you know a
separate pass maybe next weekend I just
don't want to do it right now
but anyway what I'd like to do is say
okay let's go ahead and see if we can't
just hack in something spinning here for
no good reason right
so inside like the inside the thing that
draws I'm just gonna hack in like a
hard-coded thing to to spin stuff around
so inside the entity code maybe we'll
just spin and I'll say that you know in
here this entity x-axis entity y-axis
part where we do axis to form I'm just
gonna have these things spinning around
continuously so I don't know like here's
a ridiculous thing this will just be
some angle thing here and we'll put a DT
on it and we'll just say like alright
this is actually right there let's say
so we just accumulate that over time in
here instead of these I'm going to say
all right x-axis equals right something
like this so we're just gonna produce
like these two and actually well do this
there we go so if I just say look give
me the x-axis that's built off of that
angle and then give me the perpendicular
to that that should be sufficient I
think so let me see if I run this now
yeah you can kind of see everything's
just kind of spinning around right all
right so first let's talk about the
thing that I was saying you can actually
see it happening right so what's going
on here well if we go to the debug
camera you can actually see the way
these things are pulsing in and out of
the camera that's exactly what I was
trying to say what happened why it's
because that min P point is going up and
down and up and down so it's not the
lowest point on the sprite anymore right
so that displacement really doesn't help
give us the information that we want
right and so what we'd rather do here is
say all right we need something that's
gonna be a more stable than that more
stable than the min P right and I don't
know again like exactly how we want to
compute that value but what I would say
is let's make it part of the sprite
values right so in here where we've got
like min P and then you know some other
stuff this Z bias here we don't need
this so I'm gonna say that is gonna
become the value right so this is going
to be a Z displacement and
gonna use that as a value that comes out
of here so we're gonna say not being
used min P we're going to use Z
displacement and then when we compute
these we're gonna actually compute that
as a separate value right and the way
that I want to compute that value in
this case is I want to say look we want
to know maybe without using the x and
y-axes here exactly the way that they
were being used before we want to
compute some stable value that's
representative of the alignment point
you know maybe and again I really don't
know what the right way to compute this
is I don't think there is necessarily a
right answer I just want something
that's going to be stable so it doesn't
change as the thing rotates and that
roughly corresponds to aligning it if
you weren't rotating it so if you
weren't rotating it right so if you
assume that this x axis and this Y axis
we're coming in stable right then you
can see what we would have been doing in
that case this is the value we would
want to compute right the align py times
the y axis Z right that's the value we
would want this is not gonna be negative
anymore because we don't need to do a
double negation we're just gonna provide
the D to the Z displacement that we
actually want and then what we want to
do is say okay how would we compute this
value instead of doing it this way right
how would we compute this this value for
non rotation and so if we just use this
in this one by itself that would avoid
doing any rotation that was implied here
so we can do is say well this axis would
have been this prior to rotation so if
all we want is the Z out of it then
that's this
so let's suppose we use that value that
should now give us the same results when
we're not rotating and when we are
rotating we displace it the same amount
right in theory anyway
okay or not how is that how is that
possible the world didn't why the y-axis
H up okay
not sure why I did that it helps if you
actually set the value you said you were
gonna set and not some totally different
value that's actually not at all what
you wanted
all right in theory this should be
stable now and yeah it is right so now
as these things spin around they should
just spin around about their alignment
point and so you know if I go in here
and and I access the alignment point of
one of these things you know like here's
the alignment point of the head if I
move it like that when it rotates it
should rotate about its alignment point
which you can see it doing right you can
see that right that it's it's rotating
about this point and so wherever that
point is on the sprite that's what it
would hate around and I think that's
what we want
again we don't really have much in the
way of animation knowledge in the game
at the moment we could have other things
like separate alignment and pivot points
if we want to it's very easy just a
displacement that happens but at the
moment we don't really have any reason
to believe we would really need that so
I think whatever the alignment point is
for the time being is probably fine if
we wanted a separate point that said
where we would rotate around the way
we'll do that is we'll just add a point
in here and this will add
one of these four pivot right and then
we can have an alignment and a pivot
point that operates separately again
don't care about that at all right now
so I think we're fine so that pretty
much concludes what I wanted to do I
think we crushed it to be honest with
you I think we crushed it that's just
fantastic and everything looks great to
me I'm gonna take out that ridiculous
rotation nonsense because obviously we
don't actually want that to be happening
that was just a test but now we should
be able to go set those alignment points
and get back to just playing with the
artists that's a little bit so if I now
wanted to set the hero properly and we
do have to get an art patch from Anna
actually before the heroes actually
correct because the head directions were
wrong in the art file in fact you can
kind of see that if I create look well
let's go through and actually do them
all I suppose and you can see what I
mean so if I go in here and I select
some of this stuff and actually start to
set the alignment points oh you know
what we could do here too let's actually
make it so that if one of these is off
it doesn't Shh it doesn't do the drawing
right so that that code is
here right no I'll be honest with it I
don't remember where this is here it is
so this thing here where it's like
should draw a lineman point right so
should draw a line point is is what
would cause these things to be drawn
what I'd like to do is should draw a
line point I want to make it so that we
won't descend into this code if should
draw a line point for our alignment
point is wrong so for example this
should draw a line point here I'm gonna
wrap this like this and say we need two
things we need like are we in debug mode
and I don't really know
does anyone know if we have that
there should hit test let's do that kind
of crappy sorry about that
we should probably improve this stuff a
little bit but we'll get there so I mean
here we're where I say look if I should
if I'm in you know edit mode and this
alignment point should be drawn or not
let me just go grab whatever the parent
align not the parent align my alignment
point is what is it child align so child
line child line child align child align
this so this find the line here so that
doesn't tell us which one it actually is
but that's okay because I can obviously
figure it out myself but so the child
align that we're drawing this one it
looks like for some reason we don't
actually have a you know a function for
getting the index of an alignment point
which we should you can see here we
don't actually ever have a thing for
doing that math and we kind of should
because it actually happens already
inside the Jannetty at the end of the
age and yeah so in here right people are
doing that nonsense but we don't
actually have a function for it like
this right well no I guess they're not I
take it back that was doing it on the
entity visible pieces not on the
alignment points it's sorry everyone
not not really no not the case um so all
right I won't chastise myself further
I'll simply say that we do want that and
what I want to do is have a thing that's
like you know get aligned index and we'd
say like here's the bitmap info in
question and here's the aligned point
and it would just do like point - the
line points right so just want something
that's gonna give me back that index
because we need to know what it actually
is in this case so we need to say look
for the alignments on this guy like yeah
are we supposed to draw that or not and
that's just my way of like hacking in
well I'll show you what it's my way of
hacking in but what is the problem there
oh that's mm the word it again so the
problem is you know this doesn't return
the P index and what you can see here is
because this will go ahead and and do
like a synthetic one for you if it
couldn't find it
[Music]
hmm so I really have two choices here
but this shenanigans isn't going to work
[Music]
so if we have you know this then I could
do this I guess that's what I'll do
it's not my favorite solution but it's
good enough for now and probably for
always as well so in this case we would
say all right the point is this the
index is this in this case we would say
oh the index remains zero and we're
going to do that we could set the index
to some kind of like not found value you
know something like
don't know how I feel about that but we
certainly could so at that point we
would actually do say Oh child align
dots index now it's like a thing that we
do and then the people up here who were
doing child align this is actually going
to be a find align result and it will
take with it that piece of information
so then we would be looking at something
like that when you actually use
something out of the child align as you
kind of flow through the process there
right that seems fine anyway there we go
what else we got this one we don't need
to remember so this can just do that and
it doesn't matter I don't know what else
we got yeah so at that point I think we
should be able to successfully turn
things on and off maybe or I broke
everything and it's horrible right so in
here we've got this stuff in here I'm
going to add to parent attachment and
then it shows up if I turn it off it
goes away like so
so the problem there all right this is
not as good as I thought we're still a
little screwed
so the problem there is actually I want
to do it on the parent so actually this
was a lie
by the way it's actually the parent
aligned that I want to mask out right so
I actually want to do should draw a line
point parent a line dot index right
that's actually what I'm supposed to be
turning off so yeah I also probably only
want to do this if this is the entity
I'm actually looking at
and I'll be honest I'm not sure how that
was happening right is that part of the
hit test function so I'm not sure how it
was because this it's this dev ID here
right that's telling you that piece of
information I don't know how we were
doing that magic sauce I just don't
remember to make it so that should draw
a line point on the hit test was only
telling you to draw stuff if you were
selected like I don't know how we were
doing that
if highlighted should be here it's that
all right so this is actually what we
want to do that's better so if we're not
highlighted we always draw if we are and
and let me just double check that that's
for the whole that's for only this piece
and that's not good either really
because we need to check to see whether
our parent align point was turned off of
people downstream for us so we kind of
need to do something like this to say
look something in this stack was
highlighted so that's good enough for
doing this checking right I guess that's
what we would want to do and we also
would have to do something where we
record that the fact that we were
attached to the highlighted person I you
know gosh if we really want to do this
right it's pretty complicated it's
actually this
right and this is gonna get worse too
because the entity itself is actually
the you know in the future we would be
looking up into an entity potentially to
do the snapping so we'd actually need to
look into the entity and say what's that
entity and highlighted and if it was we
need to turn this thing off this is a
this is a rough feature
I have a better idea I think
I'm gonna claim this is a better idea
I'm gonna do all that it's gone it's
over forget it never happened
it's gone
goodbye you didn't see it we're gonna
erase this part of the video so that no
one will ever know right
all of it gone goodbye okay so all
that's gone here's what we're gonna do
in the editor where we actually have
this edit stuff happening and we've got
those alignment point buttons or
whatever right like this nonsense here
like this kind of crap right so this
stuff where we're editing the alignment
points I'm gonna have a thing that's
actually list a button right and inside
the editor we've got you know a button
thing that's like draw a line point
right here this thing I'm gonna have a
like draw children or something or like
yeah I don't know we're gonna have a
draw children button and then what I'm
gonna do is inside mmm
the alignment point thing I don't know
if I need to be in a section here I
guess I do
probably not sure how this stuff works
really all right so in this section
stuff it looks like yeah like right here
I can just do a button I can edit up a
boolean right like this and so I can
just say look give me a boolean I it's a
pointer to the draw children thing in
the editor so that's what I'm editing
that show children button is gonna like
okay is gonna let you toggle this and in
here we can have a thing where you can
say like yeah
the should hit test thing and this
should draw a line point and all that
nonsense so this stuff we can just have
another one of those
that's like wherever they should draw
children or sir draw line point part was
we're gonna put one of those for should
draw children and that's going to do in
the hit test we're gonna have draw
children set there and that's what it's
going to return now at the outset when
we in it this stuff I assume there is an
initialized editor yeah we're gonna set
that to true because I so you want to
draw children by default so then inside
the entity what we can do here's my huge
genius idea it's really smart and you're
gonna love it
so when we actually go to get the bitmap
info for the parents here the parent
bitmap info is used for that alignment
I'm gonna go ahead and say that we have
some kind of a thing that's just like if
you didn't get that or yeah like if that
was set to zero then it just undoes it
or something
or we set something in like the array
that says whether it should be drawn
right like this
and I'm saying so we could just say like
look are we supposed to draw children of
this thing that we're looking at right
now or not and then we'll just remember
that setting for whoever it was you and
I mean I and I guess I don't actually
know oh I could even do this a little
bit better I could even do this a little
bit better if we did it this way dev ID
from you 32s or whatever right so I just
did this and said okay what's the dev
idea of my parent because it's that
right so if that's a parent I could just
say oh it's visible if like should draw
children excuse me for this parent div
ID it's true right that's even better
yeah that's even better so then what I'd
say is okay there's a should draw
children thing on for that guy you're
not right whatever and so we passed the
hip test down and we say look tell us
the visible thing for this if we end up
saying that that it's not visible we
just won't draw it then this draw
children is not that it's five children
for dev ID right
and then what I do is say okay hmm hi
children for detta dev ID is just zero
by default so we don't hide in fact that
that's probably just finally there an
old dev ID I don't know if there is
excuse me I don't even know if I have to
do anything for that so instead of
having that we actually have a dev ID
here and we have a dev ID that's like
you know hide children or dev ID or
something like that well actually no you
know what I'm take it back let's leave
it this way right and so all I guess we
really need to do is here and should
draw children you pass the dev ID of the
parent ID right and then in slide should
draw children we just say the result is
should you draw the children or the hit
test editor highlight ID is not equal to
whatever this was so you're giving me
the person to check and I say if we're
just supposed to draw children anyway
okay don't matter but if we're not
supposed to draw children is this the
person we're highlighting right that
parent and if they are then don't now I
think I have to do an art equal there
cuz cuz that's a there's no overlayer
operator that so I think we just do an
are equal and say look if these two
things are not equal then we're good to
go I think that's what we want let's see
what else we got here dev ID from
pointer drug building can I turn blue
into a void star that's a good point
I agree with that point I think that's
it so now if I draw in theory anyway
and this is only a theory I at least
have some slightly better human factors
on that particular part of it where is
if you're editing the alignment points
in this thing now and you've got your
you know you're looking at something
you're like I can't see anything
in theory we should be able to at this
switch to work now why mmm that was a
little weird so it started off negative
but I'm not sure why did I screw
something up there because it should
have started off positive right oh did I
delete that probably deleted it sorry
let me read that
um so yeah all right so I think this is
now correct it took me a little while to
figure out what the best way to do that
would be I think this is the best way or
at least it's a good way so we set the
piece equal to visible we then say look
if the parent thing that I was supposed
to be talking about here if that thing
should draw its children then I'm
visible otherwise I'm not if I don't
have a parent that I'm just always
visible right I don't have to worry
about it if it's visible I push the
sprite if it's not I don't that's pretty
straightforward and so now all we have
to do is focus on answering this
question properly from from there out so
then we say okay
Who am I highlighting right so should a
line point right um sorry should draw
children I think it's really or is it
one selecting so I'm not sure which one
of these is the one that I actually want
it could be this stuff too right like I
don't know
so let me go remember quickly well
remember is the wrong word let me go
look up who were actually showing in the
editor and that's the person that we
actually want to use so here's that part
of the editor and if we're doing a
bitmap here we do get asset assets asset
index here excuse me so that actually
gets us back a particular asset
unfortunately that doesn't really give
us that's a little harder that doesn't
really give us what we would need to
know for whether or not we would draw
children of that particular dude right
because
because that's just keeping the asset
it's not really saying which which dev
ID was captured there right so this
active asset index let me see where
that's but it looks like the highlight
ID is set to that so it does look like
this is true right
so should drop Children is saying if you
should draw children or these two are
not equal then you're okay
that seems correct to me now of course
it didn't look like it worked so I guess
it's not correct
so now we have to find out why but do
you think that's fine for the way we're
doing the editing there should just work
all right so let's see if I'm selecting
this I don't know what I'm selecting
here actually but all right so I'm
selecting something I can kind of see
what the problem probably is there right
I'm selecting an entity but who knows
which piece I was clicking on right
like that will not change this one this
is just changing the asset index I'm
looking at but it's not gonna change
yeah hmm so I think I can probably still
do this but that's gonna be a little
trickier I think what I would have to do
is say for the asset index do I want to
[Music]
let's take a look at this for the asset
index do I actually want to draw the
children of the asset index and you can
see that happening here right
so you're saying
so sing for each of these when we do the
update and rendered no but that should
still work - I'm I think I'm missing
something here because now that I look
at it you know where it's drawing that
those picah bulls across the top
[Music]
that looked actually fine so here's the
active group asset count and it goes
through there and it's like set active
asset on this editable asset thing here
so there's the dev ID why doesn't that
work
if that's the dev ID and it's the dev ID
that's it's created right
right here I don't know man
probably map step it into that because I
don't have a lot of ideas about whether
we've broken it it seems like this
should produce the same one right
whatever the parent piece is here and
we're just passing the Peace Index here
so that should match right and so when
you're saying parent dev ID in here that
should tell me whether the things
visible or not right and I'm not getting
why that wouldn't be the case so like
all of those dev IDs are tracked as far
as I can tell actually accurately and so
it should just be able to say look did
that parent is that parent the one that
you're focusing on right now and if it
is I only do it if I should draw the
children
so let's we're gonna have to step it and
see I product you compiled a debug mode
I'm not sure because we're gonna want to
look at the actual code there pretty
carefully so if I select one of these
right that should actually be switching
to the actual dev ID it's not just the
asset it actually knows which one it is
and then if I turn off the show children
if that should actually have stopped
showing that particular anyone who was
attached to this parent so the gloves
should remain but the head should have
disappeared right and I'm not I'm not
seeing anything like that happen it's
not it doesn't even register that those
two things it might be different so if I
go to like good draw children just
curious if that's ever even getting
called here
so here's that it's an inline call
again with a disassembly
I'm not sure I'm gonna learn much from
this all right so if we switch to debug
mode and SPECT let's see what's going on
in here so here's the should draw
children call we're stepping in here and
not really going to look at anything too
carefully here because we're not gonna
set up for it yet but if we take a look
at the editor draw children as one as we
would expect the active asset index and
the highlight ID these are not said
anything or shouldn't be right now right
and they're not so this will always be
true and so let's actually you know real
quick just set ourselves up a situation
where those things won't be true so if I
click on this and say let me see the HHA
is on it I'm sorry let me see the
alignment points I click on this and I
turn off the show children part like so
there we go
let me just also make a point for this
guy
so in this case everything should be set
up properly and of course we're not
seeing anything happen if I set a
breakpoint and should draw children what
I want to do now is is take a look at
what when we check this and what the
highlight IDs are versus the ideas being
passed down so first things first I
guess should draw children I want to see
draw children be false it is right so
that's good and then what I want to do
is say or a hit test editor highlight
IDE what is that
versus parent ID right because we've got
two separate things here so looking
through one thing you can see that's
actually kind of amusing here is pardon
I guess is not amusing at all so if you
take a look at these two values what you
can see here is actually these two are
set to the same thing and these pieces
here and I guess the reason for that
well I guess I'm not sure the reason for
that is but these two things are set to
the same value whereas this part here is
set to actually a pointer into I assume
I don't actually know what that's trying
to tell me but oh if those the two
separate u32 values that would break
into so this is set to something I'm not
sure exactly what it is but this is set
to what looks like a pointer right
so you can see the two values here I
mean those look very pointer II right so
I'm assuming these are unions right so
if you take a look at what these are
pointing to yet I don't really know if
we go back and see how they're created
so you've got this entity ID dot value
right and it looks like that's just the
entity number so these are both we're
being we're asking about something
that's in the same entity then the
bitmap piece value I'll be honest not
sure I understand how this is this dev
ID from you thirty twos is it's doing
what it's doing because why would you
have all this noise in there the bitmap
piece is just a single value right like
that parent piece is just zero so I'm
not sure why dev ID from you three twos
is doing something so complicated as
that so I may I may just back up one
second and remind myself what how we
were bundling these so dev ID from you
thirty twos oh okay
so that right there is our culprit we
actually differentiate these by location
in the code and that's really all we
need to know that would do it you know
that's fine I don't mind what that
essentially means is that that dev ID
needs to kind of do this sort of thing
so what we want to do here is say look
we know that we've got this dev ID we
want these to be harmonized types so I'm
just gonna say copy that you know have a
thing that copies types so the same
place that you would do dev ID from you
three twos right this same thing here I
would just say look I need to be able to
copy a type like so and then what it
would do is this part here that's got to
be harmonized between the two because
that was the differentiator for
different types of these things so the
from value comes out there it goes into
the two value and that should do it
I forgot that we differentiate these by
where they come from right and that's
somewhat intentional like we because we
want to be able to stuff random garbage
in there and have it actually work so we
want to be able to differentiate you
know the number zero and one are used as
actual IDs in lots of places we want to
be able to use a file name or
differentiate those two but we won't but
sometimes we want to say oh I'm trying
to refer to the same type as this other
fellow up here make that happen right
okay so I think that's probably all we
were doing wrong because I was like we
weren't doing anything fancy so I was
surprised that it wasn't working that's
why we actually have an additional layer
of differentiation in there that I'd
forgotten about so if I go through here
now and look at these alignment points
I'm thinking this will probably work
better or not I need double check that
this guy actually is using alignment
which I don't actually know if they are
not add this in here
well that was anticlimactic all right so
it's worse than that
I guess so we're copying the type now so
those two things should be the same
right
without a looks reasonable and then
we're asking should have shown yeah
still don't know why that's busted let's
try one more time so if I create the
same scenario again pick one of these
select this guy through here and say
don't draw any of children now I go back
here and set a breakpoint what am I
looking at so here's a parent ID we've
got this address of the string now at
least now we know what we're looking at
there and here's the actual value of the
entity number and the piece index
okay we're looking at the highlighted ID
here to say is this the particular
person who is being highlighted and it
is right so this should actually should
draw children this is zero and this
should fail so this should actually
return false right
aren't those two things equal there's a
dot value zero so those are equal right
exactly the same a dot value one e dot
value one oops maybe I'm wrong
they are slightly different
so how is that possible that those
things could be off by a tiny amount
like that
yep Wow I am just totally out to lunch
today so don't ask me why I thought this
change would persist out of here
it ain't gonna right you would need to
do that slow morning huh we did great
with our displacement code and then it
all kind of went off the rails this
should have taken like 10 seconds and we
totally screwed it up but oh well I'm
gonna say we finally got it this time
right let's just this is go hog-wild
it's compiled release mode and just say
it's gonna work right I have a good
feeling about this it says on solo so
anyway take a look here there we go
that's all we really wanted right and so
that's that's exactly right
great okay while we're on that subject
since we don't have a whole lot of time
right I want to fix this certainly
that's nonsense that's going on here so
when we have the camera motion it counts
as a pic and I want to turn that off
right so I'd like to have the camera
motion be something that's kind of like
where it understands that the camera
when you're doing stuff with the camera
that you're not supposed to do stuff
with the editor it can be a happy thing
I don't mind if it's hockey
it just has to not annoy me right and so
in here if we look at what's going on
you can see like the mouse up mouse down
transition index crap I think what I'd
like to do here is say look just don't
process this with the alt keys down
because that means I'm using the camera
right so what I might do here is say
okay this transition stuff let's just
let's just nerf it
if the alts down and that way the camera
code can just do its own thing we don't
have to worry about it right again this
is just improving the usability of it
for my purposes now doesn't have to be
professional or anything it just needs
to be usable for me and so like looking
at something like this what I want to do
is be able to like go into the camera
mode here and now it's good right so now
we're not having any of that spurious
nonsense happen
we're staying locked into the Edit that
we wanted to do right
all right so that's a much better
improve to last thing is this stuff also
sucks and we have like we've got the
ability to use the F keys now I think we
should just use them right so you know
we could just make it so that you know
there's nothing there's the camera stuff
there's the the h of TS and and and that
and then this should just the alignment
point at it right if I hit f5 so we
should just like put put that at the
bottom of this and get rid of that one
and then this can just be its own thing
right I think that's better right so
let's try and make that happen again and
that's just getting rid of just some
annoyances things that are just you know
making it more cumbersome to work with
than it should be I think we're almost
out of time anyway so this is a good
time to just do a little bit of just a
little bit of clean-up on that front so
if I look through here
[Music]
this stuff is this stuff is for section
begin right you can see this section
info section bitmap editing yeah so I
think the section thing I just will get
rid of right and then we'll just have a
couple different ones of this so maybe
it would just do like HHA editor or
something like you know that and
everything that was gonna go on in here
I'm just gonna move out of there so the
section thing is not is not a thing
right like maybe that section should
just be an experiment that goes away so
this can now just be eliminated this
will be the info part and that can just
go I think at the bottom so I'm I'm
happy with that actually just going down
here right
it'll just append when whatever you're
looking at it'll just tell you I think
that's better so that will go away and
then this can just be deleted as well
right I think that's all we would need
so then inside the asset editor we just
have to know that there's now an
additional type which is like the HHA
edit part of things as opposed to just
the asset edit or not right and so that
was there was like a switch statement
for that where we were just saying like
what kind of thing are we editing in
here you see it here it's
like re-editing assets or ridding the
camera so I guess what I'd say here is
like that
and then I just need to you know look at
where that stuff is actually happening
so if I go to yeah it looks like that
stuff is here for the debug state and
here for the rest of it so that would
probably be like camera assets something
like that I guess
so looking at how that's actually
working here's where the f key press
stuff happens so in here we just say
like editing HHA I guess
almost done all right
I think that gives us everything we need
there evening and this is just to make
it so I don't have to fuss around with
it so much we can just get right into
what we want so that's nothing as f1 f2
gives us the camera information f3 gives
us
whatever you know we're looking at here
right we can get rid of these now and
then f4 was supposed to give us the HHA
but instead of switches to profile that
seems like a mistake
that's why
I think that's everything the only thing
I want to do is I want to get rid of
that section picker I don't like it and
it just gets in the way now because now
I can just do everything with the F keys
which is much better so I don't really
remember exactly where that was
happening but I suppose it's in here
somewhere
looks like there so let's just get rid
of that so now I think we're just in a
better place that should pretty much
give us something reasonable that we can
work with quickly yeah so here's our hht
stuff here's our asset edit so you know
we can now quickly get in there and pick
everything that we want here's our
camera which we don't really need that
like cameras pretty solid right now so
we don't really use that but you know we
might want to play with us again in the
future
add something more there but that seems
pretty good yeah it feels like these
probably should be only if you're in the
asset editor I mean they don't need to
be there for other things probably but I
don't know I'll leave them for now I
guess that's it
so now we would really be back to just
let's play with the art system a little
bit and let's get this stuff together so
you know I would want to first of all
take a minute to get the hero looking
roughly correct other than the fact that
the head in the actual assets is wrong
but it should be pretty straightforward
right so we know that we've got this
part here if I pick for example this I
need to add two things to it right I've
got the one for the worlds and you know
just looking at where that should be
I don't know it probably would be like
something like that
just about like where it where it is
standing in the world I don't know it's
pretty hard it's pretty close to 5050
actually where it probably is standing
and then where the head is just looking
at that I'd say it's probably gonna
attach like I know right there would be
where the base of the neck is right I
think that's about right
looking at the the head piece now that's
really only got this part we should get
hats in here soon there's some actually
in the file there right oops that's
two-parent and so yeah looking at where
that should be aligned it's probably
something like that I'm guessing right
it seems about right
so then again yeah looking in here if I
go ahead and add one of these on here I
don't know where that should be exactly
but it's probably something like that
and then looking at where the head is
attached it's probably somewhere like
there right looking at this particular
piece again this is gonna have to be
edited a little bit but it's probably
because it's facing the wrong direction
should be facing leftward but the art
asset files have it flipped but it's
probably something like that right and
so if I keep going through here looking
at that switch you can see it's a little
bit off probably so if I if I
not sure who is more correct I'm not
sure who is more correct there but you
can see it going a little bit off oops
that's the wrong one it probably should
be more like that it seems pretty dialed
let's take a look at this one so that's
not the right frame is it oh it is yeah
turn off that that's show children thing
is very important I'm glad we added that
so yeah not sure where that should line
up exactly but something like that
so probably something like that if I
turn on the head point there that's like
yeah probably then something like that
those green points are really far field
though which is a little weird
oh I forgot I have undo keep thinking
hey this is cool we made ourselves a
partisan heaven do it does so I'm
guessing it's more like that that looks
about right
and let's take a look at this guy
that's about right this one is basic
neck that's probably something like that
right all right
so now I want this to just have a two
parent on there so I don't know where
that would attach exactly but yeah
probably somewhere like there and then
four here yeah like more like that would
be where the neck would be I guess and
here
and so I think that's all the alignment
for that it's now correct so if I ask it
to save that I hopefully that's right
now you know again bunch of work so now
we want to see you know does this
actually work I have no idea if it does
so if I load it now are all those
remembered and they are all right so
that's good we're getting there
so that's pretty good you can see it
looks like we're getting a little bit of
an of an inter penetration there so we
may have to take a look at that
alignment for when like that that
shearing because we're using a fixed
distance like I was saying before that
interpenetration for the shearing may be
a problem so you probably look at that
as we go otherwise you have looking
pretty good right we can put heads on
some of these fellows too now
I don't know why I can't is the reason
I'm not seeing in alignment point there
oh right because it only shows up in
debug
all right so the cat probably sits on
its base something like that
you know it's gonna be honest haunches
sort of right like this sort of thing
the base of neck is gonna be like there
it's got a really pronounced location
for that so that's pretty easy let's go
back to show children let's get the cat
head on there so that's gonna be like
their ish right and off we go
so our cat has a nice little set up now
I don't know what this dude is doing I
can't remember his name
it's like layered I think although the
bodies are generic now we don't actually
this is the body that originally went
with layered I think but we don't
actually we're letting heads and bodies
be freely interchangeable now so it
doesn't actually matter whose body this
was originally um so there's the base of
neck and that's not weird
so case in point let's let's get that
set up properly I'm going to turn off
show children right there's our bases
neck they're back again let's figure out
where that head goes add that there and
put that to basically the right place
probably should keep it at this camera
angle when we're doing this looking here
yeah that's in the right place this is
not quite so it should be more like that
and I think that's right now
so you can see how much distance there
is movement there and it looks like it's
too much like it gets a little too
displaced from the body in that case now
we could there's a couple different ways
we could look at that but I think that
just means that there's too much
displacement as far as the orphans are
concerned with how much off of the body
they are right and the player I guess in
this case same thing right maybe I went
a little bit too overboard on that cuz
you can kind of see for the head that's
case now part of that might just because
the heads are too small on these right
like that head looks too small compared
to like the politicize the player head
so it could be that we want those heads
to be bigger or maybe the bodies need to
be bigger as well right like it's hard
to say but again that's the kind of
thing that we can tweak with now we got
a kind of side but like you can imagine
if we made that head bigger right it
might be different or if the attachment
point was placed a little bit
differently right like if it's um more
like that so yeah let me see what ends
up happening there yeah it's just if the
displacement looks like it's gonna be a
little bit too much so I think that's
probably will something we'll have to
get into next time and I think that I
probably do next time but it is it's
getting really good I mean it's getting
pretty close to right what that
displacement is just a little too it too
much too pronounced so have to tone it
down just a little bit just give it a
little less Z Delta right and then I
think we're fine
all right QA
0l PBM says shouldn't body pieces
displacement be a function of camera
distance and maybe angle distance no
angle yes and it is currently a function
of the angle that's actually exactly how
we implemented it right but I am not
sure why the distance of the camera
would change how you want us place it I
there's really no reason why the far
onus of the camera should change the way
one's place it right
um we can't really do the gloves yet
because we need to actually put in code
for how the gloves are gonna float right
and so we kind of want to do that as a
separate thing no I'm saying we do want
to do hats because there actually are
some hats in there right now and so we
should add hats as another thing to test
the alignment stuff right
but again that's kind of more of
something for a different day maybe
turned out letting quality bug mr.
Vivaan reinvest your skin I think we're
actually gonna do is just fix the
lighting sometime soon what cracks a few
guys does Hammond here he is right now
it just uses OpenGL it's the only one
that use this right now
and that was done because that was like
the most cross-platform thing I could
use at the time so I thought it would
help people be able to like there's
people who try to follow along i like
mac and linux and stuff and it was you
know the easiest thing for I think
everyone to be able to use a little bit
of at least
no I think this is what the final final
lighting will look like roughly I think
I'll just be faster right because it
looks like what I want right you know
that is roughly what I want the only
thing we're not doing right now is we
don't like the sprites and when I do the
improved lighting pass we will light the
sprites with the same lights we're
lighting the same lighting we're using
for the world I'll probably be able to
take some more of the flicker out of it
- in the final pass like hopefully but
other than that no it's that's what it
looks like
I thought I'd respiratory I followed 15
of your videos and I'm in a game dev
studio that's pretty quick which 15 nice
work
have you tried a Vulcan on any project
yet not I just don't think it's useful
so I have not put any more time to it
other than when I initially looked at it
to determine that it wasn't good so I
probably will never look at it again I'm
guessing because like I said I don't see
I don't see it having a reason to exist
at the immediate moment well cause of
the flickering in the lighting well it's
because we can't sample all of the rays
so we basically have to just sample a
subset of how the lighting is is being
translated around and so that subset
that we're picking changes every frame
and that's what leads to the flickering
the skewing when moving on why is only
applied to the body should the head also
be modified um I don't know again that's
sort of something we can play with like
a little later on down the road when
we're doing some more work with
animation sorts of things for right now
it seems fine to me
as it is I would like the head to be
bobbing which it's not at the moment so
we'd probably add that but yeah
it's like that's a bit using Monte Carlo
integration yes in a sense it's using a
kind of a couple different things it's
based on randomized sampling but it's
it's highly stratified like so it's not
really Monte Carlo in the pure sense of
the word I mean anything that that does
randomize sampling is kind of in the
Monte Carlo camp
but we're fairly regularize there and
the other thing is we also smooth over
time so we're also kind of not just a
straight you know you could write a
straight Monte Carlo lighting thing that
didn't do any of those things so we
don't do that
but but we are fundamentally doing that
yes
if they're a good article on camera in
the computer graphics field or video
games I'm really or I'm ready to learn
in detail about the camera
you know there might be
you're looking for this sort of stuff
right
[Music]
this is not particularly introductory so
I guess you know there's gonna be I
would chase around references in here
[Music]
you know Mitchell Hanrahan Oh Don
Mitchell in fact who is a friend of mine
he's the guy who taught me rate racing
actually I mean advance rate racing
let's look let's look at what he had to
say and Pat Hanrahan obviously everyone
knows who that hanhan is or I hope you
know who Batman is so this is a nice old
one realistic camera model for computer
graphics
this is looking good
this is looking good this this might be
a good place to start they've got a lot
of stuff in here right so here you can
see them talking about like how the lens
aperture how the lights going through it
right and what it's doing and that's
really what we want to know right the
thin lens approximation is like kind of
the old-school way right the thick lens
approximation
well thin lens is still better than
pinhole camera but thick lenses
approximation is like talking about
lenses that actually have some light
behavior inside them and so this might
be a good place to start I don't know I
can only skim it from here but this
might be a good place to start
I also don't know if like
for some reason I thought this book
was like made available for free
somewhere recently maybe I'm worried
about that
this is what I'm talking about you could
try this
here we go here's the thin lens model do
they get too thick lens
I hear ya
so this might be another place you could
try right here PB are booked org 320
teen slash camera models that HTML
camera under square miles a tional you
know your mileage may vary depends on
who you like to read right I find this
book I find isn't written it's in that
like literate programming style where
the code in the book are together I find
it really not great but it does have
like all the information kind of
collected in one place so I find it a
little hard to read but if you can get
past that nonsense that that might be
something to think about
right I don't know if that helps my
regarding volcn I wonder why you don't
think it's relevant well I think I've
said this like a billion times though
it's not relevant because nobody's
platforms making it their priority
rendering system other than Android
right games are shipped on PC primarily
and that's d3 d12 or D 3 D 11
that's what Microsoft pushes they don't
push Vulcan right so that's the platform
renderer there Mac I said nobody gets to
do anything it's all metal right like
everything's on top of metal and forget
the rest of you right so they're not
putting resources into Vulcan people
just have to make Vulcan work on Mac as
best they can
right just like OpenGL or something so
it's metal is the thing that Apple said
is what we're doing right PlayStation 4
not Vulcan at all
has nothing to do with Vulcan right it's
you know the you know the ambi it sort
of more I mean it's vaguely related in
the SEC's fact that it's like the Andy
style stuff but it's it's the custom ps4
one the Xbox one definitely not right
that's d3 d12 style and then I guess
you're left with a Nintendo switch I
don't know what people tend to use on
that
but they have their own API obviously so
it's just like really for the types of
games we talk about its ps4 Xbox one
maybe Nintendo switch maybe not
depending on how high horsepower you're
shooting and then PC and Mac Vulcan is
like nowhere to be found it's a
secondary like on top of compatibility
layer kind of thing at best so I have no
idea why you would use it right you're
you're not gonna ship that native on
whit on iOS or Mac you're gonna ship a
metal driver version and so why would
your second driver version be Vulcan
when it could just be d3 d12 and you'd
be on Microsoft's native path right I
mean just it doesn't make any sense so I
really don't see Vulcan serves like no
purpose I don't know what you would use
it for it's it's just that it's just
clogging up the works right if vendors
decided that they're gonna get together
and that's good the primary API that
you're gonna use on these platforms is
going to be Vulcan great but that's not
what happened the OS vendors decided
that they're that they're api's are the
ones are gonna get used so that's what
happened if in the future people discard
those and they say we're not gonna use
metal anymore we're gonna switch to
Vulcan then it becomes then it makes
sense right but that's just not nobody
did that right we're going to compose
specific particle effects of the editor
I don't know we could put parameters for
particles in there we haven't played
with particles much other than to make
sure that we could do them so we
probably do have to do that at some
point right whether or not we bother
making any editable things in there I'm
not sure but we might
all right we all done we all done here
think rel about here
to us which is kind of pushing Vulcan
isn't it which is I guess kind of
similar to mobile programming yeah I
don't know what they're gonna do with
that like I said it's entirely possible
that in the future people could decide
to switch to it if like Microsoft
decided they don't want to maintain a
separate API anymore and they switched
to it or something right then it becomes
a compelling use case at the moment it's
just I just don't see the point you know
what you're doing with the graphics API
is you're trying to minimize the amount
of compatibility headaches that you have
and really the only way to minimize the
compatibility headaches that you have is
to use the OS vendors preferred API like
you just don't really have another
choice and so it's fine you something
like OpenGL or Vulcan for
experimentation or development purposes
or even on handmade hero we could have
decided to use it because it's an
educational stream but when you're
actually talking about what do you need
to do to ship the game you absolutely
don't want to use a different API
shipping a game on OpenGL is like
fraught with peril
you really want to not do that right you
want to ship it on d3d and metal and the
same will be true a Vulcan i 100%
guarantee you you can do it it's just
you're creating a huge amount of extra
work for yourself for no real reason
right and so that's what I would say now
if in the future like I said if people
maybe get on board with it and so people
say okay we're gonna like support this
API as our platform native API that
would be great
I wish Vulcan were a better API so we
could Center it as someone that wasn't
crappy but like hey at least at that
point it's fine because you know that
the compatibility headaches will go away
right
that's my opinion on anyway what it's
about say struck name who's member name
equals AB yeah that's a good that's a
good point that's a very very good point
yeah I would see a sue looking ahead to
the future - I would say that the most
likely scenario might actually be if
Microsoft were to adopt Wilkin they have
kind of been like more into the open
source and this sort of things lately
you know
so amusingly they may actually I could
see them doing it before um before Apple
these days which is kind of funny
because it used to be the other way
around right but I could see them doing
that saying like why are we maintaining
this separate API like when we're kind
of open source e these days and so that
could happen I don't know
Mac like Apple seems really dedicated to
doing their own thing so I don't know
what's gonna happen there
I really don't it's it's a mystery what
I can tell you is it sucks and we have
so many api's now we've got open jail
Vulcan metal D 3d custom ones on the
platforms and stuff right so yeah it's
dicey so a support really matter that
much seems like actually GPU driver
vendors who have to curate yeah OS
support matters tremendously it matters
tremendously the the problem is that the
the operating system plays a huge role
in how those systems interact with
everything whether it's like you know
even things as basic as whether alt-tab
is working properly right and so you
really just don't want a position where
the OS vendor doesn't care about Vulcan
they care about their own API and so
like multi-monitor doesn't suddenly work
properly with Vulcan right or you know
all these other sorts of things right
and so you just really you really want
the OS vendor to to care about the the
graphics API that you choose to use you
really want that to be true
and you know I just I don't have a
crystal ball so I just don't know what's
gonna happen hasn't this have to use the
platform so VAP I think always been the
case for multi-platform console games
yeah I mean it's nothing new for game
development right it's nothing new I'm
just saying that's why just don't get
the point you know but that could change
and then it would become more
interesting API to to put time into
right as soon as a major platform vendor
actually said this is you know gonna be
our API now and maybe Microsoft could do
that then it becomes possible I it'll
still suck but at least there's a reason
to use the thing that sucks instead of
just because well I don't know why
the next people care a lot about vogue
if that means thing it doesn't because
Linux like no one plays games on Linux
or I should say no one buys games on
Linux and they always say they do right
but then when you ship a Linux version
of your game literally nobody buys it so
there just isn't a reason to care like
Linux could be on anything the next
could could be on any API they wanted it
would not affect games at all right
which is unfortunate and it has not made
a dent
like literally nobody literally nobody
has ever been like oh wow that shipping
the Linux version of our game actually
paid enough money to be worth the
porting cost never happened right people
say it over and over and over again
every game studio that ever does that
they're like wasn't worth it so that's
just the way it is and again that too
could change in any time but it just
hasn't so there you go and yeah like
people are saying even Mackeson whereas
most it's totally true Matt Goss is
really worth it to Matt Goss is less of
a concern though because iOS is often
worth it for you depending on what
you're doing and so porting to metal
makes some sense because you have to do
that for iOS anyway so it's you know you
know it's kind of a different thing but
alright I'm gonna close it up
all right thanks everyone for joining
beforehand my here it's my pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to following stories at home you
can always prepare the game at hand made
here org and it comes with a source code
so you can port it to Vulcan if you want
to actually you think some people have
already that's about it for today we
accomplish basically what we want - it
looks like the idea of using a fixed
distance isn't quite right because when
we do that skew you could see that we
were still interpenetrating to the
ground there so I don't know exactly
what we're gonna do - to fix that
problem we may have to still use an
adaptive motion which has some issues
for rotation and I'm not sure exactly
what we should take away from that but
we'll take a look at it but mostly we're
pretty much out of the woods on that
because we're getting some pretty nice
sorting in there now that's really only
for those skew vectors that we're really
having a problem so next week we won't
do any here oh we're doing a for code
Jam next week to finish up the for coder
mods so hopefully you'll stop by for
that that's not really a stream that's
just kind of like an all-day thing that
people come and go for so if you're
interested in that that'll be happening
next weekend then after that we come
back the weekend after that's when we'll
be doing probably some just looking
through like okay how do we finish
getting items in to the a suppressor put
some sound input in there since now we
have a good place to list them that sort
of stuff so we can just want to go
through and and make a list of sort of
where we're going now because we're
getting pretty close to everything being
done it's got to take a look at what's
not in there right and at some point
we've got to decide to spend another few
weeks on lighting to get that really
straightened out and hammered out so
that's it we'll be back for some
pathfinding two weeks from now
pathfinding for the project not
pathfinding like AI and hope see some of
you for a fur coat of jam this coming
weekend should be fun until then have
fun programming I'll see everyone on the
internet tikkis everybody