hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show where I code a complete game
live on stream we ended in a very
fortuitous place yesterday actually we
kind of I don't know we we just had a
good day I guess you would say
the both things I wanted to look at and
try to do just kind of worked it seemed
like right right off the bat and maybe
we've got some lurking bugs in there
because we haven't really gone through
it with a fine-tooth comb but it was
pretty great and so if you take a look
at where we ended up we put in some some
testing that we were going to we
returned all the reflectors red so we
could tell the difference between direct
light and indirect light for example but
if you take a look at where we left off
we have some nice ways of looking at now
what's going on with the lighting and it
really has improved rather dramatically
in a number of ways there are still some
things that we want to start looking at
now but it's it's it's quite nice with
the way that it's actually purpose or
tough permeating the world right and you
can kind of see when we take a look at
how much more solid the localized
lighting is it doesn't leak through
walls it doesn't really leak through the
floor like you still get some lighting
here just from interpolation but you can
see that the actual light probes don't
pick up lighting through solid objects
anymore like they used to just because
of the way that the blending was working
so we've we've really got a pretty solid
version of the lighting now and mostly
our problem at the moment is just how do
we now start to improve the quality
level of the light solution so that we
actually kind of more know what these
values actually are and we can have sort
of a
an idea that we're actually producing
stable results because even with our our
upgrades from yesterday we haven't
addressed like feedback problems so do
you see you can see here there's like
these weird feedback problems that occur
as as I'm moving there's lag right in
the lighting as you know there's there's
some lag in in the light and as I spread
the light out it kind of has like a
feedback effect right we're lighting
that's left in the world is is obviously
not always converging towards a stable
state it can sometimes feedback on
itself and produce more lighting and the
red that you see here like I said is the
secondary lighting it's lighting that's
being picked up from reflectors and you
can see how there's just a big
difference depending on how I do things
here's the lighting when I stopped in
this room but you saw how red that it
got before when I was just moving
through it and so that's really I think
the last big thing that we want to
tackle there are a bunch of clean up
things that we want to do once we're
pretty happy with how the lighting
solutions actually working but in terms
of getting to that point where we're
really happy with it that feedback is
just a little bit it's just a little bit
of a problem right and so what we'd like
to do is figure out some way because you
saw I mean hopefully if you've if you've
seen the past couple episodes hopefully
you saw just how important and powerful
it was to draw everything that we wanted
to look at because when we are you know
when we're trying to debug things we're
looking for insight and what we're
trying to improve things we're looking
for insight into how the system's
working and how it might work better and
every time we introduce some kind of a
visualization like this where we can see
what the lighting is actually producing
it's really pretty dramatic in terms of
how much insight that can give
and so the problem that I think we have
right now is the you know this
visualization allowed us to really
effectively attack the problems of the
light leaking through various places and
and other problems of that nature so
what I think we need to figure out now
is how do we create a system that shows
us something about the energy
propagation so we can actually start to
think about how that has to work and one
of the things that I think we need to do
is we need to now that we know that this
is pretty much our final scheme we need
to produce some idea of what the actual
physical quantities are of the light so
I would say going forwards primarily
what we need to do is figure out some
way of visualizing the energy levels and
how they are what they mean and how
they're balanced and then the other
thing that we want to do is then start
to look at the render side so probably
you know looking at this interpolation
it's a little bit too square you know
and I think we probably will can do
things that will make it more diffuse
that'll spread it out more and that'll
hide some of the artifacting that you
get because we're sampling on a regular
grid for example right
and so what we want to be able to do
here is we want to be able to progress
towards that letting quality goal using
some visualizations that will let us see
what's going on there
and these are pretty good visualizations
for showing things like the fluctuation
of power and the lighting and so it's
not that we don't have like something
right like this this shows us something
that we that we can look at and we
probably need to clamp it down a little
bit because you know if you take a look
how strong these directions are they
just they grow a little bit too too much
right so probably we would want to in
here if I just load up the hand-made
here a lighting system here there we go
when we render our octahedral maps we
probably want something that will scale
these values in maybe like a clamped
fashion probably so you can see here
we've got a scale and I don't know
there's there's different ways we can
draw it but we could actually even not
use the intensity for that we could just
draw the color right so another way of
looking at this would be we could just
do that right we could say you know
we're we're just always going to draw a
little ball and we don't actually make
them longer
we just make them change color and so
then what you can do is you can look at
these little like you know that these
little balls here and I like that
because it never gets out of hand but I
do think maybe we want just a little bit
of of a hint there so I think what we
might want to do is is just have a clamp
0 1 of the intensity so you know imagine
something more like let's say we do this
so this way we are taking a little bit
of that intensity into account so as
those lighting values get larger we will
you know produce a increased length so
we can see a little bit just to provide
like a spatial visualization component
to it but this way they'll never grow
like without bound right and I think
that's you know more what we want what I
will say is it's a little weird that
they flash to me right I can't say that
I understand why that's happening and
it's a little bit disquieting because
when you look at how that that when you
look at how that pattern is is occurring
oh you know what that's just the Alpha
is what that is
if I do this that or not yeah okay so as
we move around the world as you can see
here we can now kind of more cleanly see
the directional components of these
things they don't grow without bound and
that's good again this doesn't really
help us with the power thing but it just
keeps this visualization working a
little more smoothly and if you want to
look at any particular part of it you
can still go in there and it does sort
of have a fairly clean directional
component to it and you can also still
see the low colors because they never
get too small right but you can see
where that light is coming from and
so now if we start to move on to the
next part of of what we sort of need to
do there's a couple things we could
start to talk about so one of them is if
you take a look at at how this you know
this room is set up here so let me it's
actually kind of hard to control that
way I could be right right about there I
don't know if that's the rough center of
the room um yeah so if you take a look
at that you know I'm just curious to
what extent we're getting accurate
bounce lighting and if I look at its
like it you know it seems somewhat
plausible right like I'm not seeing a
lot of of weirdness there it seems seems
fairly reasonable and so so I just don't
think there's much left to debug in just
that one in this that one aspect of it
so I think we do want to now move on to
just like let's take a look at the power
distributions here
and how those are working we also
there's some things we could do to
reduce the flicker and I think we
probably want to do them but it's it's
kind of it's a little bit weird I
thought of a pretty obvious way that you
could substantially reduce the flicker
and I just don't know if it's good or
not so that's another thing that we
could choose to do I don't know if we
really want to do that yet though it
seems like the flicker is fine for now
because the flicker is not really it's
not interfering with my ability to see
what's going on it's just like a
constant level of noise that's
superimposed on top of the data and
because there's really no harm in that I
think I'll leave the denoising which I
actually think I have a pretty good idea
of how I want to do
and I'll leave that for later
so right now let's talk about how we
manage the power level in these things
so I think what we want to do is I want
to talk about lights as having a
particular amount of a flow coming out
of them and this is the way that I liked
to think about it before in terms of how
I can go about creating a stable system
or hope to create a stable system I'd
like to think about lights as having a
particular amount of like you know power
that they're putting out into the world
and what I want to do is I want to make
it so that amount of power can bounce
around the world without generating more
so when you look at a particular place
in the world it should be the case that
you can never have any surface with more
lights than the total power of the
lights that are directly hitting it
right and just to give some perspective
on what that means and where I think
we're kind of going wrong I'll do a
little diagram here
fundamentally what we'd like to do with
this system is say well we know there
are some lights in the world and we're
going to say that each of these lights
has a particular power associated with
it or maybe for our purposes at the
moment I'm just going to call that the
amount of flow like how much flow is
coming out of these so we might have an
f0 and an f1 that's the amount of like
flow that's coming out of the lights and
this is in RG and B so they can be
colored lights but I don't actually care
about that right now because as far as
I'm concerned each RG and B are
basically separate light channels so
weak it's sufficient to talk about any
one of them we could just talk about the
red channel and that's sufficient so if
you think about what's gonna happen a
surface in the world that's reflecting
light if two light sources are both
incident on this surface directly so
this surface can hit both light sources
I want to have no more than f0 + f1
reflected off okay so this should be the
maximum possible if this surface is
somehow set to 1.0 reflectivity a mirror
basically the perfect mirror it should
never be able to achieve a value
fundamentally higher than that zooming
and so what we need to do is figure out
how to ensure that through all of our
light sampling this cannot be violated
and right now we basically know that it
can be so what we're seeing right now is
something like this we have a light
reflector and then maybe we have I don't
know say another reflector over here and
what we're seeing is that somehow you
know we reflect light in this way so we
have two light sources they're both
incident from this and incident on this
and somehow this then gathers from here
even more light
so maybe this guy is is reflecting f0
plus f1 at first and this one is
reflecting f0 plus one at first but then
it's like additive so it's it's taking
this light and it's becoming now even
this other thing where we're actually
adding another term in here and we're
getting brighter than our light sources
and so what we need to do is go through
how our light is being propagated and
stop doing that
what we need to do is look at the
lighting that's incident on a surface
and produce answers for say our lighting
probes that make it impossible for you
to generate more light than you were
previously having since the way we
currently do things is all we're doing
is taking samples of what light is out
in the world and averaging them I think
I have a pretty good idea about where
we're going wrong and where we're going
wrong I think is in our diffuse blur so
I think what's happening is that
currently here in the diffuse wait Maps
the problem that we have is we're taking
a speck like a spectral light source and
you can see here that we're summing
basically like a over a hemisphere how
much light is in coming and we're pre
creating an energy value here right and
the problem that we have is this is
completely wrong this is basically
saying look if I have to and you know
what I don't know why I put the
blackboard away I guess I just wanted to
go to this real quick but we should talk
about this on the actual blackboard so
if you think about what this is doing we
have an octahedral map which you know is
basically a way of encoding the lighting
on the sphere and so we're saying that
for a particular location right we've
got the sphere and we happen to be
encoding it an octahedral map but that's
really incidental it doesn't matter how
we're encoding at the point is we have a
collection of light samples on the
sphere and what we're doing is we're
saying well
we produced specific samples in our
specular encoding so we have a specular
map and the specular map is what we
actually encode so if we have a
direction here in a direction here we
know the lighting at these two
directions but then what's happening is
we're producing a diffuse map and the
diffuse map is saying what yeah you know
we don't really need a diffuse map for
anything if there is an optimization we
don't want to have to sample lots and
lots and lots of points on the specular
map to produce our lighting we want to
just do one right and so what we want to
do here is say look the diffuse map
needs to produce what you would get if
you actually summed the specular answers
right and the problem that we have here
is we didn't normalize our blend I think
that's really all it is
so we're taking these and we're adding
them together and we're just multiplying
by some stupid coefficient I don't know
why we did this doesn't make any sense
it's not energy preserving if you want
to know how much light you would get
during the diffuse sample well each of
those samples that you would have taken
weighted by the cosine of them you can't
just add them together because you're
trying to produce a sampling of all the
different light rays you could have cast
and so they're not necessarily going to
sum together right that's that's not
that's not realistic of how a surface
works a surface when light bounces off
it if it's going to bounce light in many
directions it has to be able to bounce
that light in the many directions I'm
not trying to say this so suppose we
have ten photons
hitting our surface right so we know
that incoming there are ten photons if
we want to say that this surface is
diffuse then fundamentally what we are
saying is that it radiates light out in
all directions when a light hits it from
any direction so there are cosine
weightings there that have to do with
how the surface incidence affects how
much flow there can be but fundamentally
that's what we're saying and so if you
look at the problem that you have here
if ten photons hit the surface and you
scatter ten photons in each of these
directions well then what you've done is
you've multiplied the total number of
photons hitting in this case by four X
right so when we're doing that diffuse
plan what we're effectively doing is
taking an accurate representation of how
many photons were hitting our our our
probe or we're passing through our probe
in that case and we're multiplying them
because the diffuse blur is effectively
summing them without any waiting so what
we actually need to do is say something
closer to this if ten photons hit our
surface and we want to scatter those
photons in five directions we need to
send two photons out of each of those
directions now probably the way we need
to do this is actually do the scattering
weighted by the cosine like I said so
you probably want to do something more
like this where one photon scatter is
out on either side and those two photons
get added here so it's more like a
four-to-one kind of a weighting right so
we probably do want to wait by the
incidence to capture that cosine curve
which happens when light incident light
hits a surface so we may want to do
something like that to to try and get a
cosine term in there and one way or the
other but what we definitely don't want
to do is take a certain amount of power
of light coming in and scatter it out in
a way that multiplies its intensity so
I'm pretty sure although I don't know
I'm pretty sure
that's actually the source of our
problems so what I'd like to do is take
a look at this routine and figure out
where we went wrong because I mean well
we know how we went wrong how we went
wrong is we didn't even discuss this
talk about it or even think about it
when we wrote this routine we literally
just smeared the map right that's all we
did so we weren't even trying to do a
good job here and so really all we need
to do I think now is actually try so
when you take a look at what's going on
you can see that there are two texels
that are in play at any given time and
what we're doing here is we're stepping
through the destination so this is the
diffuse this is where we're producing
that blur and what we're doing is we're
taking the specular map and we're
smearing that specular map out into the
diffuse map so here's where we are going
to here's what we're going to write to
the T X T y location of the diffuse map
and then the inner loop is just summing
over all of the all of the specular
texels right so it's basically just
picking specular texels writing them to
diffuse and we did throw in a weight
here and you can see we have it to do so
it's not like we didn't know we were
doing a bad job we did it's just knowing
you did a bad job is the same as doing a
bad job so now we need to fix it when we
look at how our weighting is distributed
you can see that we're using a cosine
fall-off to weight the difference
between the incoming and outgoing
directions whether that's the best way
to represent the physical behavior of
light in this particular scenario for
the performance constraints we have I'm
not sure so we may want to eventually
take a look at how to change how that
weighting is working but what I will say
is let's just leave that for now and say
suppose that is the weighting we need
because we know we will have some
weighting that we want there suppose
that is the weighting we want
how would we then go about and ensure
that the power that we then distribute
doesn't produce some kind of doesn't
multiply the total power that that we
that we would have right and so the
typical way we would do this is we would
say well what if we just produce all of
the weights that we're going to have and
we then just normalize you know do a one
normalization to say well now we want to
make sure that this sums to the same
amount of power that we had beforehand
so we just take all the weights and we
and we normalize them the problem that
we're gonna have here is we never really
produce all of the weights so it's not
as simple as just summing them up
because we don't actually know what they
even are right but we do know for any
given txt Y we do know the opposite
thing right we have produced all the
weights that would sum into it we just
don't know what would some out of it but
if we looked at the same slot right so
if we looked at the same slot each time
and summed up all of those weight so if
we looked at you know here's the diffuse
weight map right you can see it writing
into the diffuse weight map here if we
looked at the same slot in the diffuse
weight map and just looked across all
txt Y when we built it if we summed up
those same slots that would give us the
total amount of weight being pulled from
that particular spec Texel and if we
normalized that that should give us the
correct energy distribution right
because that would mean that we were
spreading that particular energy source
in such a way that it never summed to
more than it was originally worth
right so I think what that means is that
in theory anyway I mean I think because
I can't think of any reason why it
wouldn't work let's suppose that we
moved this out going into here I think
if we just reorganize our loop because
who cares it doesn't matter which order
we do the loops in if the loop was in
this order it should in theory mean that
we can do the entire set of weights for
one sy SX pair remember them and then
normalize after the fact I think right
so in theory what we should be able to
do here is just some the weights like so
and do one more loop afterward you know
through to just to renormalize so we
first loop over all of the destination
texels affected by this source Texel we
fill in what the weight there should be
and off we go now we don't need to write
the weight in this particular case we
just need to sum right and we could even
sort of pre compute this value because
one of the things you can see is that
well it doesn't matter
we're putting the whole thing so I don't
even know why it would go down that road
right so again pretty straightforward
how this would work we would then just
say all right we go through here and we
we do the same loop twice first time we
just sum how much total weight we're
going to have and I want us
this value should probably I mean it
might vary but this it almost seems like
this would be the same for everybody
right because it's sort of the same
weight octahedral map each way I might
put the thing in here that just says but
since I don't really know if the
octahedral map actually has that
property I'm just not going to do it
because I don't want to introduce that
in here and we don't care because this
only runs at startup anyway so when we
go and now produce the actual final
values all we would do is say well we'll
just divide by the W total now so
instead of writing out the weight by
itself we write out the weight divided
by the total weight for that particular
Texel and now in theory we should have
oops I didn't realize that was still
running
we should have a table that preserves
the power of the original light that
it's sampled rather than having a
feedback loop right so now when we move
around what we should see is like a lot
less light than we were seeing which is
totally fine because we don't have any
idea of what these light powers actually
are so the fact that they would be less
is totally fine with us and we don't
really know like what these light powers
should really even represent so let's
start adding some more light to the
world at this point and we may like I
said have to kind of think about how
much light what the actual total amount
of light would want to be so I'm going
to go in here and put back in some of
these lamps which
like so okay and now what we need to do
is Wow they don't even really bounce
hardly any light which I guess is kind
of good all right so now what we have to
do is start to work on our scale and see
I mean unless I introduce some kind of a
really bad bug which I may have right
but it doesn't look like it because you
can see that this looks like a sanely
behaved lighting source at that point so
what I'd like to do now is just crank up
the intensity of these lights to see
what happens if we map them in a
slightly different way and we have to
start thinking about what we want our
power curve to look like for lights
anyway all right so now we've got again
our light sources here and I don't know
if that's a same amount of light or an
insane amount of light looking at them
and I'm just going to keep cranking up
the power to see what happens because
like I said we have no idea where on
this curve we even are so for all we
know this is like exactly correct
lighting all of a sudden or something
like this who knows so you can see at
that point we kind of have a weird not
sure what happens when we crank it up to
that level of light and I'm not sure why
exactly we would be getting that so it
looks like we still have a bug because
in theory it should still stay stable no
matter what we crank the light up to I
would think I could be wrong about that
though
right so no matter what I cranked the
light levels up to we should have been
seeing fairly stable light and we're
totally not right so I'm guessing that
that I still kind of have there's
there's bugs in the propagation here
that that are making it do kind of weird
things right and
it looks like I mean there's a couple of
things that you have to remember first
of all there's no ceilings which creates
a incorrect light propagation so we
should probably add those in as well
before we start looking at light quality
but on the whole I want to try and hop
down here to the to the underground as
well because there are ceilings here now
right so if we take a look at just how
the light propagation is working that
just looks like it's not really
propagating properly you know what I
mean
so I feel like we've got some bugs in
there that we're gonna have to to look
at and it's not always obvious though
why like because if you take a look at
how the if you take a look at how the
how some of the lighting probes look
they look fairly reasonable though so
it's it is at least kind of confusing
right I kind of want to look at the spec
map first let me take a look at this
routine I wrote and make sure that it's
not stupid I mean I think it's really
straightforward right you're just saying
I want to produce a blurred version of
this map that doesn't introduce any
additional power and so you know I've
put that in here the I guess I don't
know if we really want the outgoing
incoming part of this that parts a
little bit a little bit harder to to
determine because it may actually be
that this doesn't make a whole lot of
sense because if you think about it when
you're sampling the light I'm not sure
yeah I'm not sure how much that that
cosine fall-off makes sense but if you
assume that it does make sense then one
of the thing that we probably also have
to consider is that when we do like the
raycast and we compute the outgoing
values one of the weird things about it
is that I feel like this probably
doesn't make a whole lot of sense
because you're you're kind of double
counting it so I kind of feel like this
this maybe is not a good thing right if
we do leave it in there now again I
don't really know to what extent that
that has any effect I don't expect it
would account for much right yeah like
it kind of still looks roughly the same
but I do think that like if we're going
to have our probe itself include that
then it seems like you wouldn't want to
include it twice because if you're
already doing cosine fall-off of the
transmission in the diffuse map then you
wouldn't
that when you sample the map again right
I mean that doesn't make a whole lot of
sense to me yeah so as to why we're just
not getting very good
as to why we're not getting very good
transmission there I really don't know
and the no ceiling part of it here seems
like it makes sense obviously but but
when we go down I should probably just
stick a roof on the orphanage so that we
can have a ceiling but oh crap I know
why I mean I don't know why but I did
forget one very important thing the grid
ray caster we have not quite fully
enabled yet so one thing I forgot is
that we don't do termination sampling
anymore and we're probably gonna have to
so what we want to do here is probably
turn termination sampling back on and
debug that first so that was all without
termination sampling and we need
termination sampling so we probably need
to do that right so okay so let's let's
take a look at this and and restart the
debugging process with the grid ray
caster actually yeah yep so that was the
problem
right so now let's take a look and see
because I don't know what the what the
total lighting values would have to be
here in order to to make this work but
they shouldn't have to be particularly
high once you actually have transmission
going there right so okay now the the
the cube ray caster will propagate the
light and in terms of how bright you
need the lights to be we can't
necessarily determine that there's a
feedback loop without without doing a
power visualization so there may or may
not be feedback loops in it currently
and we kind of have to find out so if
you take a look at how this lighting is
looking actually actually looking
freaking great I'm I'm really liking
this so what we now need to do is write
some kind of visualization for the power
because for example when it over braided
there because we have 50 times we had a
50 times powerful
/ color light it could have just been
the correct lighting right it would look
ultimately bright right so I'm very
curious to know essentially like what
the total level of light ends up being
in in terms of situations where a sample
now one thing that I'm noticing is that
when we when we use that termination
based sampling though it does look like
we're getting light leaking again right
can see light leaking out here and I
don't I don't care for that so we have
to take a look at why we're getting that
it could be that our termination
sampling is is just a problem right but
at least unless I'm misunderstanding
when I when I was looking in here right
it was able to get outside pretty easily
like you see that so we have some issues
in terms of how the light leaking is
working we're gonna have to study why
that's occurring but anyway you can see
that the feedback loops are not nearly
is it's not obvious that we even have
them right so that's also kind of a good
thing all right so let's make the debug
light very powerful and remove these
lights and start to work on specific
cases now so that we can take a look so
if I go into the world mode and I look
at the push light call what I'm going to
do is just increase the power of this
debug light which I believe just
requires me doing something like this
right like I can't oops that's not good
look I can just jack up the power of
this light here and I can in theory just
have my light be a super-bright light
right and so now when I move around I
will have a light that's this that's you
know powerful enough to do bounces and
you can kind of see that happening here
right now the light again it
we're artificially constraining bounce
light to be
redlight and non bounce light to be
white light
so here's with a light that's fairly
powerful you can kind of see it being
powerful and let's see what happens so
you can see this is an example of the
light leaking right and you can see that
these are getting light now whereas they
weren't getting light before and so I
think what we need to do is take a look
at how we're doing our termination when
we do a T terminate I think the problem
that we're having is we're sampling that
probably the incorrect direction that's
my guess or or the point is not quite at
the right place because if you remember
when we call compute voxel irradiance
what we're doing is we're saying hey
don't allow sampling from any probes
that are on the wrong side of whatever
it is that we quote-unquote hit right
and I'm assuming that the problem that
we're going to have now is that when you
early terminate a grid raycast it's
probably not correctly ignoring some of
the light probes right so we I mean I'm
guessing that's what it is because
that's the only thing we changed right
if you take a look at what's going on
here you can see that there's really
only two cases where we error out one is
we err out on the apron and the other is
that we have started not err out early
out is we we stopped on the apron
because we didn't hit anything and the
other is that we did an early terminate
the cost metric now one thing I might do
here is actually put this path back in
real quick with a sort of a fake thing
in fact I guess I don't really need to
put the path back in per se what I can
do is just make a special if here and
what I want to do is make sure that
we're looking at only one case so inside
here where we look at the spatial the
node dot start index spatial grid node
Terminator at that bit here what I want
to do is put in a like debug do not some
or something right or debug zero and
we'll make that be false and what I want
to do is I want to take this and just
say debug zero equals that so if we
happen to hit the Terminator and I don't
mean Arnold Schwarzenegger if we happen
to hit the Terminator I don't want to
use the the result of that in the light
spreading so when I run this now what I
want to see is is it the apron or is it
the Terminator that produces this
problem and you know I can it seems like
I can demonstrate pretty clearly here
that it doesn't require the Terminator
right because I think I turned that off
and you can still see lighting coming
from here so let's try the other way
around so in here I'm going to set it to
do when we hit the cost metric so now
we're gonna do is we will allow the
apron to transmit the light but we won't
allow early outs to transmit the light
and now again I just want to see if I
can spread light outside the boundary in
that in that case right and so before it
seems like I was able to do it here and
I'm not
so that seems to me that our early
termination code is not producing
satisfactory results and so we need to
figure out what we're passing
incorrectly there right because
something's busted and we need to figure
out what that something is so that we
can so that we can fix it all right so
let's go ahead and take a look we now
know what the specific case is that
we're looking at and that specific case
right here is you can see how we're
generating this you can see that we're
taking the t terminate and the Ray
direction and that's how we're producing
what we're going to sample so you can
see that we're sampling you know the
emission direction and the radius single
law stuff I don't believe in Mission
directions actually getting used I could
be wrong about that yeah so even though
in the future we may want to start using
that we're not using it now so we're
really just talking about these two
things and you can see how they're used
in here we use the sample P and the
sample n to produce this table that
prevents us from sampling from anything
that's on the other side of the sample
head now the probe ends single it's a
little it's a little hard to know
exactly what that should be pointing
back in the direction of the Ray does
seem totally fine but we have to be
careful about what location we pick here
so my assumption is that our t terminate
value is not good
if you look at how it works when we take
a step we also accept the new t
terminate value so if you look at
computing the walk table the T terminate
value that we write in has already taken
its step forward and I would suspect
that's probably the problem we're
probably marching into the next grid
Square and then taking the sample but
what we want to do is stay in the
previous grid square because if we're
not going to process the grid square
ahead of us we don't want to use that to
terminate so I think we want this right
we want something that only writes the T
terminate for the previous step so that
we'll never sample ahead of where we
actually collision detected now I don't
know that that was the problem but you
know I would suspect it would be a
problem it doesn't look like it really
helped because like a look at that right
yeah we're still obviously wrong here
yeah I'm saying and you know there's
there's ways we could be creating this
problem pretty easily the fact that this
isn't sealed you know it could be
bouncing up here and then bouncing down
so I don't necessarily know that we have
a bug there in fact I suppose that's
something that we probably need to
figure out how to look we probably want
the light occluders to be much higher
than the walls right so let's just try
that just to see so when we do a push
occluder in the entity code
this particular part of you know of the
code here I I feel like we need to have
two pieces of information when we push
the cubes there so if we look at if you
look at entity pieces so I feel like I
feel like this code needs to have like
an occluder size as well you know so you
know we've got bitmap pieces and we've
got you know we've got various things I
feel like we need like an occluder size
right and I guess that's a little bit
easier said than done because at the
moment you know it might just be that we
should just add a clue to zazz pieces I
think that might just be a better idea
so it might be a better idea to just say
look there's occluders that oops that's
a flag
why are those flags I guess we just we
just roll the yeah all right who knows
these don't need to be flex with our
energy system is not really something
yet right it's kind of just a zygote or
something um and so maybe we just have
occluders in there so we would do
something like this
um and then what we can do is say yeah
that stuff just doesn't it's not how
that works right we're gonna push
occluders on here as a separate pass and
so you know if we actually ran the code
now we would literally have nothing to
affect the lighting the lighting would
be completely random because there'd be
no walls whatsoever and then what we'll
do is we'll actually when we create
these whoa oops sorry about that typo so
now we just we won't have anything right
so the light can just spread wherever it
wants to spread right and it won't be
affected by walls whatsoever and so now
what I want to do is actually put
occluders in there and I'm gonna draw
the occluders for now so you can see
I've pushed a volume outline in there
and what I'm going to do is I'm going to
go into the room gencode and I'm just
going to look at how this is working
so you can see where like for example
this adds a light to something so I
don't really know how we want this code
to work overall but like for example
whenever we place walls in here you can
kind of see we've added a thing you know
we add we add tags to this where do we
actually create that entity it's right
here so we've added an entity and at
some point I guess we must add pieces to
the entity right yeah so you can see us
adding pieces here and what we want to
do now is we just add in addition to
that piece we'd want to also add like
the occluder so we'd say you know
whatever this thing is we'd add we'd
want one that didn't that didn't use the
asset category stuff so much so much
like the ad peace light call we'd want
like an ad piece occluder and this would
just be like wouldn't have a mission
this would just be like a you would have
a dimension here probably something like
this offset dimension color you know and
it would just say here's the dimension
here's the offset here's the color and
it's an occluder so that would allow me
to do like add peace occluder anywhere i
wanted to and you don't really need the
return values you wouldn't really modify
it and all you'd be doing is saying
here's the radius in the center and
there's the color sorry it's just be
three and so at that point I think we
then would be able to you know make the
we would be able to make it a taller
larger bounds right and so is it v3 from
how do you create a v3 from o that you
don't even need to it's just that I
don't know why I was thinking I'm just
out to lunch so at that point we should
be able to now see like occluders around
right and so there's all of our our
actual blocks and
I kind of forgot that we don't actually
put any geometry out here which is fine
we don't actually need any at the moment
but what I'd like to do now is start to
add occluders to that that go up to the
actual total height right so I want
these things to be taller so in order to
do that what I would need in this case
is I'd need some way of of knowing the
top bound of the area in question and
you can see here getting a volume we
have this sort of tile concept and it
can tell me that so what I'd like to do
is look at those calls because I think
we already sort of had an understanding
of how these things worked and we have
like a bunch of functions we can
actually use so if you look at like you
know these get room volumes get grid all
this stuff get volume from minimum Z is
basically saying like look if you passed
a height in here
what would you you know and you looked
at the the min or max Z or whatever
right if we said get total volume of the
tile that might be more what we want for
cases where we're actually adding a wall
right so I don't really know when we
choose to add walls but it looks like we
just have an on wall right so what we
could do is say well there's an occluder
and that's just gonna be the total
volume of this tile right
so whatever the tile is it's it's you
know it's that and then if we want to we
can say if we're not on a wall then we
can just say well you know we could even
do this right so this just allows us to
produce you know different occlusion
geometry from what we draw because we
want to draw walls at like half height
so the player can see but we want the
occluders to be larger which it looks
like we sort of did but the problem is
is it looks like it's not quite aligned
properly so when we get the total volume
here we're like producing an odd a
fairly odd version of what's going on so
let's take a look at why oh right we
would have to do a make relative okay
because right we need it to be relative
to whatever the position we're saying
the entity is okay so there we go and
now we've got actual blockers in place
and it does look to me like now we've
we've correctly like cracked down on
that light leakage problem right and
we'll see but yeah it does look like
that's significantly less now we're
still getting a little bit right and
again we kind of want to know where
that's coming from so I would like to
still kind of hunt that down it could be
coming from stuff that's you know even
further up and I suppose we could test
that I don't know to what extent that's
likely but we definitely could test that
just by putting caps putting a cap on
on the room as well right I really like
the idea of having the include errs be
totally separate because that allows me
to create real geometry for the lighting
which is what's happening here while
still creating fake geometry for
rendering because you typically don't
want to draw a completely sealed room
because the player can't see it and so
at the very least you need to do like
wall cutaways or something which you
could do with a render pass but you know
it's oftentimes just better to let it be
an artistic decision so that has some
pretty bad leaking there right so I
think that would be something we want to
take a look at and you know what this is
a good indication that we have a problem
because this is totally sealed right and
we're still getting samples so
something's up and I'm not sure what
like how is that getting samples
so let's take a look does that happen
right out of the gate it does right so
now let's go in and and see what happens
if we turn off the various parts of the
grid right caster so again I'm just
going to go down and do the same thing I
did before
so I guess I'm not sure exactly where I
want to do this but I think I just want
to do it right here is probably the
easiest place right so that would zero
it out and then I can look at what
happens in the various cases so this is
apron still flickering let's try an on
apron and then I'll just try it both
okay so that's proof positive that I'm
still screwing something up with the
termination right and you know that's
just a really weird I don't really even
know how that's possible something's
really busted there and the reason that
I say that is just because those those
cells that are getting light are not
even casting like where they would
terminate would be casts going downward
so how the heck right so something is
really busted for example with how we're
doing the probe probe sample piece
single something's just messed up right
and so when we fall out of this and and
we're going to hit this case you can see
us doing the sample here
I guess the reflect color foo
so the hit ref color in this case is
what exactly because we haven't hit
anything so the hit ref color is just
Fulbright it's just transmission
the emission level would be based on hit
emission which is nothing and that's
good so it's really strange so it seems
like this probe sample piece single must
be wrong maybe that one's really
interesting but you can see that you
know something's up here so T terminate
starts zero so in theory it just should
not it should not ever move you forward
in that way I think we're gonna have to
draw this because I'm not thinking of
I'm not thinking of how that's wrong
yeah that's a tricky one I just can't
figure out how you're getting samples
when you should never be hitting that
case unless you're casting away from
where the light is so how are you
picking up any light you know
like you can see that it's not picking
up any light without the you know when
it's when it's doing bucket-brigade
carrying and then if you take that out
it's definitely getting light you know
and what's more is it's getting light
from like below like it's getting light
from like down here right how there's
nothing down there to hit and none of
these things well I suppose it could be
a feedback where someone down here casts
upwards yeah so that's what could be
happening summoned down here casts
upwards there the termination sampling
is broken it samples something from up
here and that's and it picks up some of
that light so it could still be that
this that this is is just incorrect
so another thing well another thing I
suppose we could do is I guess when
you're looking in this direction so you
would start at the center of a cell and
you take one step forward and if you
didn't really terminate you take another
step and you would move from where you
were to the edge of the other cell and
no matter what your angle is I don't see
how that would ever possibly leak light
at that point I mean maybe it could but
it would seem pretty tough right I mean
it just doesn't it just doesn't seem
likely
I guess one thing we could do is let's
try to look at one of those that's the
only thing I can think to do at this
point I I'm sorry I just I don't have
any other ideas at the moment using the
debug zeroing we know that something's
wrong and so the question is just what
is it
okay so what I want to try and do here
is look for that particular look for
something that's down there so if I
that's gonna be a much lower value I
assumed should probably just cold set
this thing gonna take me forever to like
we don't have we don't have debug value
inputs here
so I'm gonna I'm gonna cold set that
value quite a bit lower so I'm gonna set
this down to like I don't know some much
lower number hmm I don't actually know
where we want to be for that lower grid
tier
all right so it's not horrible but it
looks like we're sort of a little too
low at that point
so I think that's still one too low for
looking at those oops alright so
hopefully this will give us something
where we can kind of take a look I don't
actually know should probably make a
better tester for this it's been enough
times of having to go through stuff that
would be nice to be able to just like
click on it and have it like compute
that which voxel we're talking about so
that looks good
we're basically right in there now
so this is an example of someone who's
getting that light and you can kind of
see I mean it looks about right in terms
of debug output right it's stopping on
this and it's it's doing that the point
back there so if I just scan through the
Rays here you can see like how they're
doing
I suppose what we kind of need to do is
say what it actually retrieved you know
or why that would be a thing I want to
probably I'll lock these in so it's 13
to 586 and 335 as an example I'd also
probably like to draw a little bit lower
so I'm gonna have like the debug dimmed
minzy I'm just gonna drop that oops
sorry
I'm gonna take the debug dim Z and just
add 2 to it so I get a I get a taller
stack
I might actually say let's add quite a
bit more to it just so we get like a
nice stack to look at there yeah I don't
care about that
all right yeah how is this thing working
[Music]
I don't know what this is suppose this
go this is terrible like what that's not
what you want so no no no this is right
so you have the total dimension right
and you subtract away the amount that
you were going to show right and this
leaves how much was left what you want
to do is go up by half of that right
that's how you'd actually Center what
you were doing I don't know what I know
what the heck we were writing there that
was that was some nonsense code if ever
I did see some all right so if if now we
run it what we should get is a taller
stack right so at least we can kind of
see like what's going on and you can
kind of see like all of these are
pointing down let's just get the
complete stack so this will just give us
like the whole thing that is we don't
run out of of debug lines first yeah we
need better we need better support for
our debug lines fine for sake of
argument we'll start this the voxel at
zero for now
okay so here's what we're looking at and
really it just it just doesn't make any
sense I don't understand right
I'm also not sure how the heck if that's
the minimum
I see it's because that's the minimum
that we would sample from but we can
still cast outside of it right to pick
up light sources I guess what was the
idea behind that
you know I don't think that makes any
sense to be completely honest with you
if if we think that through why would we
cast outs why did the voxel being wider
why would that ever help us because we
can't actually pick up anything other
than like pure light sources I guess we
just wanted to be able to transmit light
sources if we're gonna do that though we
don't need very much larger because
since we can't convict any light around
who the heck cares like you you it would
only work if there was an actual
physical light source there you it's not
gonna actually give you any bounce
lighting because we don't actually store
any any bounce lighting outside of it so
why the voxel itself is larger I don't
know it doesn't doesn't really make any
sense anyway fortunately though this
does tell me what I needed to know which
is you can see who's getting lighting
like and it does look like what's
happening is sort of what I feared
some folks down here who are casting
back up at the surface are casting up
and able to pick up a lighting sample
right so if we take a look at say this
person we should be able to see where
they're getting their light sample from
so let's take a look at that that's
literally on the ground floor so it
should be pretty easy to isolate
and in the meantime I should just shrink
that grid what's the point I have no
idea why I did that I think I didn't
think that through because like this
just doesn't it just doesn't make a lot
of sense I mean a very tiny apron is
probably fine but I don't know I don't
really think that makes a difference I'm
gonna get rid of that because I think
that's just a fool's a fool's errand you
pretty much have to have your your atlas
or it won't work so alright so what I'd
like to do is start to take a look at
that specifically and so I'm gonna go
ahead and grab the the debug slider here
and just try to pick that one out which
somehow I'm not seeing which doesn't
really make any sense cuz I should be
right
oh wait I'm still in the apron right so
I gotta get off the apron and then we'll
we should get right on there there we go
okay so this is someone who is getting
light from above somehow right and we
don't really know exactly what direction
we're getting laid from but we are
getting some and so I'm gonna just take
a look at at some ray indexes here to
see if I can
aha well that's an actual hit though
so that should pretty solidly eliminate
any sampling that comes from above it
I'm trying to figure out which direction
this is actually coming from right it
looks like it's kind of coming from that
direction right somehow and so
I guess yeah something like something
like that
so it looks like it's coming from over
there and I don't actually know how
that's happening like maybe it's coming
for their is that roughly the center
area or not now it's it's probably a
little bit more
so that's probably pretty close right I
mean it may not be the exact one but
that looks you know at least roughly
like
I think that's pretty sane right so
we're somehow getting light transmitted
from up here and I mean there's a couple
of different ways that could be
happening one is we could actually be
getting secondary bounce from this so it
could be that something up here actually
is creating light that's flowing through
so I guess we should probably look at
that this is what 7 1 7 5 3 1 and so
what I assume I want to do is just take
a look and see well okay so if that's
the actual cast back to here like where
is it what what is it actually picking
up over there so what I might do is is
lock the vox start x and y 2 also be in
the corner right and just see what
happens there cuz i I can't tell what
lighting is in that is in that area
right so if I move this stack I guess I
just want to move it over in X a little
bit so maybe I'll do something more like
this
and probably watched a little more than
that
oops that was the wrong way and so now I
should be able to look to see what are
the lighting values over there that it's
sampling from like is somebody in that
region creating light and is that who we
need to debug or is somehow this bug
yeah I mean you can sort of see that it
is actually these folks are getting
light from above them right
right you can see like that but I have
no idea how right because how the heck
are they getting through here right
again it's kind of a mystery now it's
true that there's no floor here so they
are free to cast straight up through
here and that's totally fine right but
again I want to know why right how are
all of these folks getting light when I
just don't see where that would really
be coming from right are they are they
I'm also very curious what that is
happening there so we're gonna have to
see what's up with that there's also
sort of a separate issue here that I'm
not sure I'm internalizing correctly I'm
not sure I always have these directions
proper like I think part of the problem
is when you're sampling in a direction
like that it's almost like I feel like
we have the normal backwards in a way
when you're sampling a surface that you
hit you sample in a different direction
right like then if you're sampling for
transmission and so I think I also think
I need this like I think we need two
separate things and when you're bouncing
off the surface they're the same but
when you're terminating they're
different
I don't know if that makes sense right
so basically like probably should have
used search and replaced there but it's
fine
I hate capslock with a passion
I want my editor just ignore it
anyway I think what we want here is we
want to say when we do a computer a
daeun sat in all of these circumstances
you know we're we're going to do probe
sample n signal and single and we're
going to pass the emission direction
here and those need to be different so
they'll be the same in
in some cases and they'll be different
in others so I think in this case where
you're bouncing off its emission
direction is not what it is it's the
occlusion direction right so in some
cases they're the same so in instead of
emission direction we're going to call
this occlusion and what we're gonna do
here is say that when we do a sample we
will sample in the direction we're
heading but we'll occlude in the reverse
direction right and then when we
actually hit something that one will be
slightly different so when we actually
hit something we will say that the
occlusion Direction is the same right we
want them both to be the same and then
an ABB raycast won't really matter which
one we do because we're probably gonna
get rid of this path eventually anyway
but that's the deal and so here we
passed the occlusion D and I think
that's important because before we were
sampling we were transmitting in a
bounce which is bad and I could see that
creating a lot of issues for us right so
let's take a quick look now at what's
happening down here yeah so do you see
how much quieter that is now they're
still probably some bugs in it but like
it's not doing a it's not irradiating
between terminators and I think that's
really important because that was
basically creating fake reflection but
didn't really exist and now we're not
we're just using transmission yeah look
at look at how much better that is right
that was crucial so so okay yeah that
was clearly a problem
so that seems quite good by comparison
to what it was right much much much much
better so yeah so I think we've got a
couple of things we're going to need an
exposure curve in here pretty soon
because we're you know in terms of
actually bouncing light around you can't
really use linear 0 to 1
lighting expect anything to happen I'm
gonna try doing some light over
floodings stuff and then we'll save the
the power curve stuff for for next time
around alright so if I go ahead and do
let's let's go ahead and jump to where
we're pushing that debug light on I
think then we're just about done for
today anyway and I'm gonna massively
over bright that light
and I just want to see what happens so
we still get a little light leaking
there right you can see some light
leaking happening it's actually fairly
stable but it's it's it's not great
let's see if I push it up to 30 I just
want to see where our breaking point is
now and this is just a good way of
testing like you can see like we're
getting some weird results so I think we
we can probably I think we've still got
some bugs in there like possibly that
that that may not be algorithm artifacts
that made that may just be bugs right so
we should probably do some testing for
just like to see if we can if we can use
like light over flooding to find any
more artifacts there right and and we'll
just we'll see at the moment however you
know not bad so I'm gonna go I'm going
to really quickly just restore this to
normal and just see what's up if I put
things back the way they were sort of
working before I'm just curious where
we're at because we're getting there but
we got to put in a curve now we got to
put in a power curve and then we got to
kind of find some debug there all right
so looking at the lighting from a high
level now I think the biggest problem we
have is just the actual power conserving
transmission doesn't spread the light as
far as I would like again I think power
curve may solve that problem so we'll
have to take a look at that
but starting to get some some promising
results right it's it's getting much
close much closer but but yeah again we
have to start we have to start looking
very carefully at power and trying to
figure out exactly how that should go
right because we're not getting enough
oh you know what else we should do while
we're at it since we can now let's add a
clue ders to two trees when we place a
tree because like there's a there was an
outside sort of thing we were doing that
wasn't very good and if we go over to
and actually know how we were even doing
this
I don't know where we were putting these
in this code is always so kind of weird
like we didn't haven't really ever made
this code good so I don't know where
we're putting tree here so place tree I
guess so
I think all I really want is to just
take that occluder code so this thing
here
if we're gonna place a tree I guess I
just make a larger occluder there right
so maybe it's just this I'm not sure if
that's all I need to do but it might be
and so if I head over here now to a tree
area I don't actually know but yeah so
like you can see the occluders are now
actually including like the light
doesn't spread outside there right so we
probably don't want as much occlusion
from trees so we probably don't want to
do you know this what what I literally
did so probably not going to quite do
that but what I might want to do is
something more like this
so if we are going to place a tree here
then what I would do is maybe make a
little tree ball thing and just say well
alright so the you know the tree ball is
going to be I don't know like the
original volume maybe with an add radius
to I guess I don't really want to start
with the original volume so I probably
want to do this
and then I probably want to do an ad
radius too I think I probably actually
also want to do a Minzy here to not have
it overflowed but I want to shrink this
in right so I kind of want to say well
the tree volume is is going to be you
know less by something right so you know
like we're just gonna shrink it down and
I you know I don't know well we'll we
actually need to go make our generator
code generate worlds that we actually
care about you know that's that's a game
play thing but I should probably still
be drawing those occluders too because I
have no idea what I've just created but
we want something that allows light to
kind of flow through there's a little
bit more so let me just let me just go
ahead and put in the the volume
outlining so that way we can at least
just see
all right so that didn't work at all ah
that's because I didn't actually use the
results all right so there we go that
thins out the trees a little but there's
still way too tall and also probably
still too fat so we probably want to do
this we probably want to tree Vall max Z
equals I don't even know so in terms of
in terms of like how we can ask about
these when we do the from Minzy thing
like what is
so it looks like get volume from Minzy
is like produces something from the
bottom of the tile up to a particular
place which doesn't really help us in
this case and like looking here like how
do we know where this thing actually
starts is that p00
is like where it actually is I have no
idea write this code sort of sucks and
it just makes it hard to create things
so let's do this maybe for now and we'll
like worry about creating actual tree
occluders that that aren't terrible and
when we actually do the room code and
that could probably stand to be a little
more yet okay so probably just call that
a day and we can go to QA is there a
reason why that doesn't seem to be
shrinking much in Z because that should
be a quite large Z contraction but I'm
not seeing that right is it just that Z
is much larger and so it doesn't look
like as much difficult action by
comparison or what's going on there yeah
I guess that was so there's some trees
maybe all right
so if we take a look now we should be
able to also get some bounce lighting
from trees I mean in theory right so
which now we do right and you can kind
of see that before we were getting
complete occlusion there and no bounce
but now we're actually getting some
bounce lighting so we're getting there
slowly but surely and so now I think our
biggest problem is just like we're not
getting as much light convection as we
would hope and so I kind of want to know
what's up with that right and we got to
start to analyze that it's especially
kind of strange because I think again
power curve is really the issue here
because you can kind of see like in fact
if I just go into the shader and turn
off the way that we were doing the light
flooring just for interpolation purposes
you can kind of see in here where is
that so you can see here where we do our
light floor value
right so the light floor value here if I
just turn off that which I don't
actually know if anyone's properly using
it in lighting yeah so we're not we're
not even using the light floor pack at
the moment like we're supposed to be but
we don't so if we just went to the light
floor value and we just set the light
floor value at the moment to be zero we
would see a lot more light in there as
well right because right now we're using
the light floor in the shader but not in
the actual lighting code right so here's
the lighting when you don't floor and
you can see there's a lot more light
right so you know it's just better right
and again that's just when I say we got
power curve issues we have to work out
that's what I mean
so we're really pretty close I think
we're we're getting we're getting we're
getting pretty darn close here because
we're also quite quite speedy at this
point we have a lot of debug drawing
happening in here but the actual amount
of light computation work is pretty
manageable at this point so I think if
we went ahead and and stopped doing all
of our debug drawing and and went from
there I think I think we're in pretty
good shape here it's looking really nice
and if I go ahead and turn off those
occluders again so me let me just turn
off the volume outlines and maybe we'll
turn off the debug draw octahedral
values as well so we can just kind of
look at the lighting as a sort of a
rough a rough state should probably get
rid of the drawing of light and bounds
as well it's it's really pretty darn
close so I don't think we've got I don't
think we've got far to go before we're
before we're basically like and I mean
it's really kind of cool too because you
can see as I hop in front of the doorway
so I move this light there you can
actually see the light starts to go out
into the outer area and when I'm behind
it it doesn't right so you get really
pretty cool lighting effects happening
now and so as we sort of dial in on the
final version we're really getting some
pretty good good results I don't know
these guys don't have their lights still
attached
we should probably centralize some of
this debug code into like a lighting
panel that we can turn on various debug
things without me have to go through the
code and constantly do all this crap but
you know so I thought there should be
lights on those guys and there are they
were just really dark so you know let's
add actual lights on those guys just for
fun and and I think now we can get sort
of a sense of after we do the the final
set of finishing work this is also
without any ambient at the moment
yeah so so I think we're gonna be really
pretty pretty darn good lighting I mean
we're only a few sessions away from
smoothing out some of these other rough
edges here adapting the power curve
getting the spreading a little better
and reducing the noise and then this is
going to be some really pretty freakin
baller lighting I mean zero
pre-computation I think it'll run at
60fps certainly on newer machines in
this one it definitely will doesn't even
use a GPU and we could move it to the
GPU at some point too I just don't know
how sensible that is because in terms of
which platforms we can run on and which
ones we can't I'm not sure we want to
stress the GPU even more because you
know we already want that for drawing
you know high res and such so I'm not
sure it makes sense to do that but yeah
all right any questions
in the diffuse map weighting divided
could you get a divide by zero no you
can't because there is no because you're
always summing over all the possible
light directions for the input and the
output
we know that the weights will always be
at least somewhere non zero so there's
no way you can have all of the
transmission so between every Texel
every speck Texel and every diffuse
Texel sorry for a particular speck Texel
we know that there cannot be literally
zero transfer from that speck Texel to
all the diffuse texels a speck Texel
will you know always do a speck Texel
will always have to affect some diffuse
texels
with this isn't a curry we do more
physically based rendering looking to
the light um so I'm not sure exactly
what you mean by that as far as
physically based rendering is concerned
there really isn't a plausible way to do
something like that with what we're
doing because we don't even have 3d
geometry for most of our stuff right and
we certainly don't have any material
parameters for it because it's just a
bitmap that an artist painted so there
isn't really a path towards physically
based rendering from here it there just
isn't right we just don't have we
fundamentally don't have the source data
to explore anything like that so we can
only really look at artistically based
lighting things like conserving the
power like I did in that diffuse map
spread that's an example of of using a
PBR style of of coding and I do think
you want that so you want to do some you
know sort of physical things like
conservation of energy and that's simply
for making the system well-behaved
but beyond that I don't really think
there's very much we can do
I just don't think there's much you can
do when you're just talking about flat
sprites you know that really have had no
they're just not constructed for this
does the fuse bounce use the albedo of
the materials yeah it already does
we don't actually look up into the
materials because that would be very
expensive so what we do is you just
state what you want the occluders bounce
to be so on things that are made of you
know reddish material you can set them
red or if you you know so it's it's
artistically controllable but we don't
actually sample the texture but yeah so
to give an example of that if you wanted
to write when we add the those occluders
let me just go ahead and do it
so in the code where we are is it at
peace occluder actually I guess I don't
really remember at peace occluder so
what we can do is in these sort of
different places here like let's suppose
you wanted and this is not correct but
let's suppose you wanted for some reason
trees to bounce green light right and
everything else to bounce blue light and
like I don't know why you would want
this but let's suppose that's what you
were doing what we can do is just change
which occluders we're adding there and
then what you can see hopefully is that
all of the secondary bounce lighting now
has a blue tinge to it and you can kind
of see it you know pretty pretty clearly
like in here and in here right and then
all of the trees would not like they'll
have an extra green bounce to them right
so you know I mean because our bounce
lighting is really muted right now it's
harder to see but that's you know that's
what that is
maybe I should make it red since
everything is green out there I'm not
sure you could really see the fact that
it was green but you get the idea I'll
make it yellow so we do use it but
because the diffuses are a lot more
muted than we would like you just don't
see it as much right and that's that's
why we need to start getting the light
power curve under control so you'd
actually get some of those effects and I
still can't really see much bounce
lighting which is sort of a problem out
here which is you know which is a bit of
an issue but obviously these will all
still be blue and you can see that they
are
but the bounce waiting it for these guys
I just don't see right it I like just
don't see it at all so I'm not sure
what's up with that we may just have to
look at it a little more carefully let
me try with read one of the problems
everything in that area is green so it's
kind of hard it's like already kind of
not something that bounces yet so you
can so you can sort of see it now right
you can see the red tinge so we are
using it it's just that because direct
lighting is so much brighter than our
indirect lighting right now which is
again I think because we're not we need
to start working on like the
transmission exposure levels I think
that one the problems we're gonna have
is just that until we do that you don't
see you really just don't see the bounce
something as much as you should
can you compare with the older raycast I
suppose we might be able to obviously
there are some issues with the older
raycast in terms of how it convex light
but we certainly can let me try the
older ray cast has ambient lighting and
we haven't put that into the new ray
cast yet so it would have a slightly
different effect
although you know what no it doesn't
because we turned it off so I guess
that's fine so no it doesn't
so yeah so in terms of actual light cost
we also can't really we haven't pulled
the debug code out of our grid rate
caster so we actually can't tell how
fast the grid rate caster is at the
moment either which is another thing so
it's hard to necessarily compare these
two and we also haven't tuned the grid
rate caster so it's a little premature
to do the comparison but there's
certainly nothing wrong with this rate
caster like it's fine I just don't think
at the end of the day we'll be able to
quite get it up as fast as I need it to
be whereas I think the other one I will
be able to
after the shader modification it appears
the light is still leaking why is that
so actually even before we were messing
with the shader at all we still have
some light leakage that I I demonstrated
early in this stream and if you remember
so we know it's there and we have to
look and see whether it's a natural
artifact of of what's going on or not
some light leakage well I guess this has
a ton of light leakage this is the wrong
caster hello again I'm not sure why
there's that much in there but yeah I'm
not sure about I'm not sure what was
going on there but if you take a look at
what's happening here there's actually
or at least there was and I'm pretty
sure Cecilia's let me just try and make
it happen again
some more obvious light leakage so I
can't make it happen just at the
immediate moment there was some obvious
light leakage happening earlier that I
wanted to take a closer look at it's
it's not happening now like that looks
it's quite solid actually so so I'm not
totally sure I think there's some still
light leakage thing we want looked at
for whatever reason I'm not able to
actually make it happen again so I don't
know maybe we accidentally fixed it
completely but I don't think we did so I
was going to look at at some more light
leakage issues later at the moment I
can't seem to get it to do any light
leakage at all which is great
I mean hey it's nice that I can't make
it do that but but I'm not sure why so
yeah
you know there's that yeah and I don't
know why I'm not seeing the light
leakage anymore I guess we fixed it hard
more than I thought we did because I
thought there was still some flickery
problems with certain folks about kind
of in the distance there so I don't know
at the very least when we did light
flooding so I mean at the very least
when we do light flooding we can see
that it eventually does bounce around I
thought unless I'm just misremembering
so if I go in and do a push light here
and I just like really over flood the
lighting I I think this leaks out right
and that was that was a fairly
conclusive see so eventually it does get
outside right
if you push enough power through it so
it's not perfectly sealed which again
there is no ceiling on this thing so
technically that could actually be
correct it could be the light that
strong in our system should propagate
outside because there is no sealed
ceiling if we actually put a sealed
ceiling on then obviously that shouldn't
happen so I don't really know and and
you know maybe one thing that we should
do is actually create that scene that
although our room Jen needs to be like
actually written hardcore so we can make
things easily with it and we're pretty
freaking far from that right now it
probably isn't the worst idea for me to
try and put occluders in on non wall
sections that are just the ceiling I
probably should do that so if we were
going to do that I guess what I would
need to do is say if there was into room
well I don't know exactly how we would
do this but it's probably something like
taking the max Z of the wall so like if
we're not on a wall
but we are inside I don't know what that
means
like how do we know if we're inside or
not so it's spec outdoors so I guess we
would say like if we're not on a wall
and we're not outdoors then we need to
add a ceiling tile right so we would say
like okay
like give me give me a ceiling and we
just need to know how do we create that
ceiling and so to to do this we would
need to presumably just take the whole
tile and then I guess we just say like
look the minzy equals the max Z and then
we just create a thickness you know
so minus some some very thin thing
so in terms of like trying to seal right
do you see what I did there so there
there's like this you know a set of
ceiling tiles now so that the light is
is inside only and you know at that
point I should be able to over dial that
light and it shouldn't be able to get
outside now I don't know if that will
actually happen
because I think we do have some light
leaking bugs still but that's now at
least we know that it's sealed inside
there right so now when you really like
push that light level you can see what
ends up happening and you can see that
it still does get out right so there is
some way that light eventually can get
out and again with an inexact algorithm
like this where we're trying to save a
lot of computation time by not doing a
whole slew of things that may be
unavoidable so I'm not really concerned
about that but I do want to do it as
testing if that makes sense
so that in the future we know
definitively whether there's additional
bug who's causing light leaking or
whether it's just an artifact of the
approximations of the algorithm that
makes the light leak either way I'm
happy that now we really don't have much
light leaking in the game proper right
like if you just look at the normal way
this would be played there's no light
leaking so it's mostly just quality
concerns that I want to increase the
just want to denoise and blur is
basically all we really need to do at
this point I think right but but it's
looking really nice so let me see what
other questions
is it possible to smooth out the
lighting oh yeah I mean I will smooth it
out I'm I probably will be able to get
it to where it's perfectly smooth would
be my guess I kind of have some ideas on
how I want to do that but but I'm just
not interested in that right now because
we still have like accuracy issues I can
look at a noisy solution and go is that
actually producing the crack solution I
can already sort of tell that we need a
power curve in there and we need to like
work on that transmission of stuff a
little bit better so we've we've got
things we need to do first before we
work on denoise from what I've perceived
watching handmade heroes lighting has
taken up a pretty sizable chunk of the
episodes is lighting inherently complex
yes lighting is by far the most
difficult thing you can do in graphics
period there's nothing even close to as
hard as lighting that I know of
literally anything you want to do in
graphics is easier than lighting photons
are the fastest moving things in the
known universe and they are the most
plentiful things in the known universe
so you are inherently simulating the
very hardest thing you possibly can
there's nothing as bad as lighting for
fixing the square interpolation that's
just because our samples are on a grid
so what we want to do there is just in
the shader where we sample it we just
want to blur those out right so really
it's just a sampling issue so it's the
question of what's the fastest that we
can do right
we'll be topics which we spend as much
time as light no there's there's nothing
as hard as lighting there I don't think
there's anything you can pick that would
take as much time as lighting
even fluid simulations such as plasma
yes so fluid simulation is significantly
easier than lighting much much easier
than lighting and the reason for that is
fluid simulation has so inherently all
physical phenomena have a propagation
rate is the way to think about it
so all physical phenomena that we saw
that we simulate in games are inherently
three-dimensional or you could think of
them as four-dimensional depending on
how you want to look at it right but
everything we simulate in games is
three-dimensional we sometimes make
two-dimensional versions of things or
whatever right but inherently everything
is a three-dimensional phenomena from
the real world that we're trying to do
in sight a game right and each one of
those physical phenomena have
propagation rates which determine how
much of the system they can affect and
how quickly lighting has the fastest
propagation rate it propagates bright
photons which are the fastest moving
things in the known universe there is no
phenomenon harder than that fluid
simulation usually can only propagate at
the speed of sound or worse so sound is
much slower than light and because all
physical phenomenon tend to happen at
the speed of sound not the speed of
light it's always easier the the region
you're trying to affect on every frame
of update is inherently contracted
dramatically whereas lighting could
literally affect the entire world pretty
much in one frame so
like game worlds are basically the size
that a photon could span in like one
frame right so so yeah fluid dynamics
much much easier than lighting now
neither are easy and the reason for that
is that it has the same sorts of
problems meaning that we can't possibly
hope to simulate the behavior of all of
these molecules so you know
networking is trivial compared to
lighting I wouldn't consider networking
even remotely in the same class of
problem difficulty as lighting to me I
mean they're they're not even there
they're not even a little bit scary to
me right so
hmm it seems like when you walk you drag
the light behind you with inertia more
like a liquid is that in purpose or an
effective combination no that's that's
specifically because there's no way for
us to do it fast enough right if we move
to a GPU if you know if we were saying
this is an RT X 2080 game always or
something we could have it be instant
and that's because our geometry is very
simple you know a triple a 3d game has
just dramatically more geometric
complexity than we do so they always
still have to have a few frames a few
frames of latency with their indirect
lighting there's nothing they can really
do about that but because we have such a
simplistic set of geometry if we wanted
to require very high-end 3d hardware for
this game we could make the lighting
instant probably so you wouldn't see
that lag but it is 100% an artifact of
of what I just said which is that
lighting is like the hardest thing and
you can't really do it right it's not
possible
so yeah I don't really want to argue
with people on the chat you're welcome
to think whatever you want is complex
I've been a programmer for almost so 35
years I know what is complex and what
it's not and what is difficult than what
it's not networking is it's it's not
trivial but compared to lighting it's
cakewalk period I mean and you're
welcome to disagree with me but I don't
really care because what you think is
hard you may think lots of things are
hard that I don't find hard right so you
know not really super relevant to me if
you have a hard prime programming game
networking then you know fine but I
don't so it's it's it's not something
that scares me right lighting scares me
a lot and the reason for that is because
it's so complex and so difficult to
approximate well and no one's ever done
it tons of people have network games
that work well tons of people have
network games will work poorly but tons
of people have things that work poorly
all the time
so you know lighting is a problem that
literally no one's ever shipped a good
solution for in history in real time
whereas tons of games have good
networking right just because some games
have really terrible networking doesn't
mean anything right people write crappy
stuff all the time but but literally no
one's ever shipped real time indirect
lighting ever in anything that actually
worked right doesn't doesn't happen so
we're always a few frames behind right
we're always doing weird approximations
and it's always kind of wrong so and
that's just that's just the way it is
right
what is so special in RTX well there's
nothing special in RTX it's just that
when you have hardware that can do
dramatically more ray casts per second
then it becomes much easier to do fast
lighting updates right because all of
our slowness that we don't really know
how to work around there's some the
diffuse blur we can work around and make
much faster probably then we're done we
have at the moment but the other half of
things is the ray casting and we'd
really just don't have ways of making
that dramatically faster than what we're
currently doing at least not that I know
of and so we're kind of always gated on
that whereas if you have special purpose
hardware that can do it way way more ray
casts way way faster which an RT X would
do that's just a really big deal right
is the difficulty of global illumination
part of the reason why you're doing it
sure I mean it's just it's mostly just
because you know it's something that if
you want to do a professional quality
engine you need to reckon with at some
point right so I feel like it's
something we should at least cover and
do a reasonable job of because it gives
you some perspective and just how hard
this problem is right so and maybe
someday and video will save us right you
know once you throw enough simulation
hardware at the problem you know maybe
we can just go away you know but at the
moment we're just kind of screwed right
yeah the r-tx version of Minecraft might
have noticeable light lag in it but
remember again they've probably got way
more geometry to worry about than we do
because even though we sort of look a
little minecraft II because we've got
like blocky things we're only looking
top-down at like a room minecraft you're
like looking out you know at the world
and there's just so much more geometry
there that like you know it's the ray
casting cost is proportional to the
geometric density of the scene right and
we have the ability to limit that
geometric density a lot more than a game
like Minecraft has the first-person
perspective so I guess that's what I
would say
if someone were making a different game
with much sparser scenes containing more
complex geometry well wait which are
they are they sparser or more complex I
guess they're sparse but complex we do
have an alternative prescription could
the probes be arranged in a sparse grid
or in-camera frustum space rather than
world space so a sparse arrangement of
probes would be difficult and the reason
is difficult
not because computation on it would be
much more difficult but because the
shader in the GPU used to look up the
lighting samples would be more expensive
and I'm not sure how far you want to go
down that route before it becomes
prohibitively expensive right arranging
them in a grid that isn't world space so
like I said camera for us in space that
seems more doable because as long as you
have some affine mapping from pixels to
whatever this space is I think that
would you know that would certainly be
feasible I don't know to what extent
people have tried that one of the
problems that you're going to often have
is that there's two things you're trying
to do here one is you like you correctly
identified you're trying to make sure
that you spend the most amount of time
computing lighting on things that are
that you can see on the screen so you
want things that are close to the camera
to have more time spent on them
certainly the things for our way the
problem is that light needs to be
simulated and it may be that a lot of
simulation time may be necessary to move
the light from something distant into a
way that just makes something distant
look brighter than it you know so that
you can see it so even though that's a
very small thing on the screen figuring
out that it should be lit is might cost
a lot because you needed to do a bunch
of crazy balance letting out that that's
why lighting is so hard
it doesn't really yield to those kind of
approximations as well as you would hope
which is why we introduced all these
other artistic approximations because at
the end of the day accurate lighting is
just sort of impossible and probably
always will be
so what we're going for is never
accurate lighting it's just approximate
lighting and when I say maybe in video
save us it's approximate lighting that
they'll be giving us but fast
approximate lighting accurate letting
forget it it's not possible when you
tested secondary bounces with red light
it seemed like it only worked in the
left and down directions so if it could
be the case that we have a bug there and
I'm not really sure if we do or don't
like I said we're still in the process
of kind trying to kind of like fix
everything in the lighting system and
make sure it all works well but I don't
actually know whether we've gotten to
that point yet because we're doing a lot
of crazy stuff like sampling the voxels
using occlusion it's entirely possible
that a bug in that inclusion code so for
example this code here if this code here
were broken that would be a pretty easy
way to get directional bias in how light
was spreading right because when you go
to sample a voxel it would be sampling
the voxel only in like a it would be
knocking out people who shouldn't have
been knocked out based on the occlusion
normal or something based on like an
error in this code right
I don't know one question I do have here
is did we ever stop to look to see
whether this is correct so this is
saying like isn't this the wrong way
round kind of like did we do we actually
look at this so um that's the point that
we're sampling from so we're basically
saying from the corner to the point
we're sampling from and then we're
looking at the normal so this is like
what direction we want it to be able to
go we're basically trying to say that
those need to be same sided we should
just really quickly make sure that's
true I suspect it probably would have
shown up as a very obvious error
especially with the light leaking but I
don't know let's just check so if you
imagine we have this and we're talking
about a particular uvw point here so if
we want to sample a particular direction
so let's say the particular direction
we're sampling in this case is this way
then what we want to do is we want to
imagine that there is a plane passing
through here and these will then be
disqualified from sampling because they
can't possibly have hit this and then
gone in that direction right so what we
would like to do is say is the direction
the same and it looks like it is looks
like we did do it correctly right so
we're subtracting UVW we're doing uvw
minus the corner and that is what we
want so yeah just just wanted to
reassure myself that that wasn't
obviously busted again I think it would
have shown up but you know somehow make
sure
how does an RTX occur to actually
perform a rate racing is it similar to
what the ps5 can provide which is
hardware to work on a BVH structure to
perform rate racing or is that different
so I guess what I would say is I don't
actually know much about what's on an RT
X card because I don't know that they've
ever told anyone I mean maybe they have
but I haven't followed it very closely
in general the I can I can tell you more
the reason why these hardware solutions
can get you better results than a CPU
the reason is because the primary work
involved in tracing array is actually
very simple there's not a lot to it as
you know testing whether a ray hits a
triangle doesn't really require a lot of
work the problem is that you're trying
to do lots of these tests and you know
usually you like you said use a bounding
volume hierarchy and what happens is as
you traverse you that bounding volume
hierarchy you're typically basically
creating completely unpredictable code
so every step the better you're bounding
volume hierarchy is the the more random
the walks through it will be because
each time each ray will be classified
very cleanly into the stuff that can and
can't hit and that just creates an
incredibly unpredictable path with
unpredictable cache usage through this
memory that you then have to upon and
modern CPUs are low core count
generally speaking high predictability
optimizing machines they really like
doing highly predictable things in a
small number of cores that's what they
tend to do and that's the exact opposite
of what a bounding volume hierarchy
traversal is so what custom hardware
does for graphics processing is they
typically kind of take an opposite
approach they will basically crank the
number of micro DH of I guess we call
them hyper threads on the CPU side but
basically what they'll do is they'll say
look let's just accept the fact that we
have no frickin clue how this thing is
going to want to walk through this
memory and what we'll do instead is
we'll just launch like a tremendous
number of rays at a time through the
system so while one ray is unpredictably
trying to fetch the stuff in the
bounding volume hierarchy that it's
going to need next we always have more
Ray's in the pipeline who can have
computations done on them so typically
what happens on a GPU that's very
different from a CPU is whereas a CPU
maybe has two hyper threads per core at
maximum a GPU might have dozens right it
might like just have tons and tons and
tons and tons of Ray bundles stacked up
waiting to flow through this pipeline so
even though you have no idea what memory
you're going to use next and it might
take you a while to go and fetch it
there's always somebody else ready to
use the hardware and so what ends up
happening is they can just stamp down
lots of units that have lots of hyper
threads and then just worry about
feeding those with tremendous amount of
memory bandwidth and even though they're
doing computations any individual
floating-point operation on say an
NVIDIA GPU is probably much slower than
a CPU it doesn't matter because the
actual total throughput is much much
higher right so they have more units
running more hyper threads and so even
though they are clocked lower typically
they can just get way way more
throughput for something like ray
tracing I don't know much about the PS 5
so I can't tell you if there's anything
special going on there but generally
speaking I would
fact that RTX or at PS 5 or anything
else I don't think there's any
particular secret sauce to it I think
it's mostly just look tons and tons of
hyper threads on lots and lots of little
micro cores is how you get good rate
racing performance and CPUs aren't that
are the pros in the wall still getting
cleared to zero
yes they well no I don't know that they
get cleared to zero they just aren't
allowed to cast
yeah and just to be clear so what I was
talking about was not Rea incoherence
actually so Rea incoherence is a
different phenomenon Rea incoherence is
when you're trying to trace a bundle of
say sixteen rays at a time because
you're using a wide vector unit to do
the computations what what the problem
you have there is that if you're rays if
one ray hits very early but another ray
takes quite a bit more computation to
generate the hit that it will produce
you end up spending as much time on all
the rays as the most expensive ray in
that bundle and that's just an artifact
of any sim D computation so obviously
there's a whole separate set of work
that goes into trying to limit that
extra cost but that's not the same as
the unpredictable walk problem which
even if you're only doing one ray still
occurs right the fact that you don't
know what part of the bounding volume
hierarchy you will need to load until
after you've already done your
computation makes cashing cash streaming
suck right
it makes the memory streaming suck and
so you can't walk through that bounding
volume hierarchy at anything close to
the same speed as you can actually
compute what to do so maybe it takes you
only a few cycles to determine which
side of the bounding volume hierarchy to
traverse it doesn't matter because you
can't possibly load it fast enough right
modern CPUs rely on so in order for a
modern CPU to get good performance it
has to be able to predict what memory
you will use before you use it if it
can't then your performance will be
horrible period that's just the end of
the story and the problem with the thing
like a bounding volume hierarchy is the
whole point of the bounding volume
Harkey is you don't know what part of it
you're going to end up in if you did you
wouldn't need the bounding
hierarchy so fundamentally speaking when
you're talking about something like
ray-tracing very geometrically dense
scenes the problem that you have and
have to surmount is that you need a
completely unpredictable traversal
through a bounding volume hierarchy but
you know that that is very slow so
typically what they will do like I said
to solve this problem is accept that
that will be slow and just do a ton of
them together so as one piece of memory
comes into the system we do the ops for
it we issue the fetch to get the next
part of the bounding value our key and
then we immediately switch to a new set
of rays you know I'm saying so basically
we can keep we just make that pipeline
deep enough that the memory that's
coming in even though it takes a
tremendous amount of latency to get that
memory it doesn't matter because we're
issuing so many different memory fetches
that one of them is always coming back
as we finish the computation for another
one right so we always keep it fed and
that's what I was talking about when I
was saying there unpredictability ray
incoherence is not that ray incoherence
is different and it has to do with
packing they're called warps in GPU
parlance but they're just seemed
elaine's it's when you pack multiple
rays because you need to be able to do
them together
and like I said there's other ways that
in our system we actually don't do that
right now what we do is multiple volumes
against one ray and you can you can pick
which one you're doing right
all right I think we're vet into the
questions
sounds like alright thank you everyone
for joining me from the episode of hand
made here it's been a pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along theories at home you can
know is head over to hand made here org
and peer to the game it comes to the
source code so you can follow along with
it at home I will be back here next week
I believe is that true yes I'll be back
here next weekend to take a look at
improving the lighting quality I think
we've done some pretty good work here
but we now have to kind of smooth out
those rough edges we have to look at the
power curve of the lighting and we have
to look at the that interpolation
smoothing so there's a couple different
things you want to do that can really
you know dramatically improve how good
the lighting appears to be without
really even improving any of the
underlying like Ray casting or sampling
so that's what we're going to start
moving into over the next few weeks as
we go so hope see you back here for that
until then have fun program everyone and
I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody