stop recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show where
we could a complete-game live on stream
yesterday we organized some stuff into a
hierarchy because we wanted to draw it
hierarchically and so today we're gonna
do exactly that we're gonna draw it
higher ARCA CLE H AI R a RC H Ali Lee
it's a very hard word to spell scholars
have been debating how to spell it for
generations and no one's really ever
figured it out
it's kind of like William Shakespeare
his last name there's debate there's
vigorous debate about how it was felled
and so the important part for us is that
we don't really have to learn how to
spell it we just have learn how to
implement and that's we're gonna do
today so if you or someone would like to
follow along with the programming today
is day 195 you will want to unpack day
194 source code that is what I'm
starting with today
right and here we go let's do this let's
get this going
let us get it going let us run it so
what we did was we sort of took all our
debug variables the ones who are coming
up in the radial menu and we wanted to
kind of put them over here so we
organized them and we did the work
yesterday to make it so that that would
be possible to do but we have not
actually done the thing that draws them
so what I'd like to do now is just do
exactly that I just like to go implement
it so I can see that on the little side
of the screen that is what I want to
have happen that is what I'm going to
make happen
and you honestly I really can't stop me
I'm doing it I'm just doing it so here
we go we have obviously a function that
already does this you can see it here
right and you can see here that I'm
iterating over the the variables right
and what I don't necessarily know at
this point now that what I'm like
looking at this you know I don't really
necessarily want to cut and paste this
code because both you know when I look
at this I'm like this is looking kind of
complicated and so if I go and write
something that you know this is this is
the code that saves our variable
if I couldn't paste this now I've got
two copies of this you know it's not too
crazy but it's a little bit intricate
and it involves like an inorder walk of
the tree right and the thing that's a
little bit confusing to me it's like
okay you know maybe I could just pull
that out into an iterate or something
and use that you know so don't have to
do it once but the problem with that is
every little piece here where I might
have done something probably will do
something slightly different in the
actual hierarchy the the hierarchical
printout so I feel like although I don't
really want to cut and paste it I'm
going to cut and paste it first right
the code that I actually want the way
that I want it and then I'm going to set
it again take that sort of compression
oriented approach where I say I'm going
to wait till I see both of them and then
when I see both of them I will then make
the call about whether they can be
condensed into a utility function or
whether I think it's better that they
are separate because they really sort of
represent two different things okay
so if I was to do that I guess I've got
your debug main menu it's right here in
fact so what I'll do is I'll just go
ahead and like I said we're doing
essentially the same thing here so I
should be able to just cut and paste
this in here and now write a thing that
actually displays the menu in our game
rather than writes it to a file which is
what we were doing with it before right
so I guess the the most straightforward
thing here again is to sort of just go
alright we don't really need to yeah I
guess we don't really need to do
anything too fancy we're just going to
print out some debug text so if I want
to I should be able to just use like you
know like this debug text out thing for
example to print whatever it is I'm
going to print out and presumably I
should be able to do something like this
where you know I have a little
that I use I just filled that buffer
with whatever the thing is that I want
to fill it with right so if it's a
boolean if it's a group or whatever I
can just print it out and so again I
want to use the same routine for
everything because like I said I want to
replace the dependency on the C runtime
library at some point perhaps even
relatively soon and so I want everything
to call through one function so I only
have to like replace one function I
don't have to write like 50 million
different like printf Saur other weird
things like this so yeah so if I'm going
to do that it looks something like this
and then what I want to do is I want to
just print out the name of the variable
like so so I would say here's the name
and then I guess based on the value I'll
either print true or false so if the
value is set to pop to some you know
thing that would be nonzero then I'll
print out true if it's if it said
something else I'll print out false
that's how I'll do my text then in here
I've got groups groups like are only the
name that's all they have and so again
I'll just print that out and you know
oops and so once I've got that it's
pretty trivial for me to say okay print
out whatever was in the buffer I know
I've got you know sort of color that I
want it to be and let's say so I can
keep that concept will just make it
white for now but you know we can change
something else later based on you know
what it is or what state it's in or
other fun things like that and then when
we come down through here and I do the
walk you know things happen right so the
the biggest change here is this
operation where I descend to the child
that is going to be dependent on whether
or not this group is collapsed I think
because if if we remember I want a
hierarchal list so I want to be able to
expand and collapse it like a tree view
or something like that
so I don't want this to happen if the
group is supposed to be collapsed I
guess I won't worry about that first
because I suppose would be a little bit
better first to make sure that we have
everything else working so we'll go
ahead and do that first and just get a
some stuff up on the screen but then I
think what I want to do is like go ahead
and handle that collapse tough alright
so now let's see let's start things off
by taking I think we have in here some
information about where things should go
right we've got left edge and this sort
of stuff right so if I want to
initialize things I've got that left
edge and that app why there it is
so I want something like this where I'm
going to do this sort of thing right
start here and I think we just need some
like that font info where is that guy
that font in for something that we have
cached if I remember correctly yeah in
fact now that we have the debug font
info cached this stuff this is this is
just something we should have collapsed
a long time ago that should have just
been that right yeah so anyway this will
start us at the top corner of the screen
so there we have our edx we know already
that this is the left edge and what we
should probably do as well is subtract
two times this because we have a line
there already although maybe we just
stopped printing that line it might be
the other way to go because we have like
a debug text at bank text fine for
compiling yeah so maybe what we do is we
do something a little fancier than that
so in here we would do like we'll just
always call our debug drop menu for
right now and maybe we'll let that
advance the app why so these things will
start at the bottom
so I'll just I'll actually just take the
debug States
at why we'll do that and then at the end
I'll set them equal because we probably
will get rid of that concept in it in a
bit here anyway all right so now I just
need to know where this text actually is
going to be and I don't know that I need
the text bounds necessarily for this
process because I think I want to start
at the corridor anyway because we're
starting at the left edge so that should
actually be fine for now so at the
moment I think we can just do something
where we say okay we have the text be
the text be is just the add X that why
there's nothing to it really we can just
go ahead and use that so if I do that I
can I'm not really sure like I just kind
of like hacking this out there oh right
and of course we will need to actually
advance after we do this we will need to
move the @ y forward by whatever that
that height the the like you know the
baseline to baseline height is of the
font right so at y plus equals should we
have another one of those somewhere key
bug text where are you keep up text up
so you can see it in here should I
should be able to advance it at Y right
there it is get line advance for like I
know we have it I just don't remember
what it was I'm too old to remember
stuff I only do for an hour a night it's
true long past the point where I'm too
old to remember those things so what I
want to do is after we print out every
single one of these right I want to go
ahead and move forwards by that much
and there we go and again we already
have font info so I don't need to read
get that just all there into
and so that should give me I think a
list of all the variables and and there
they are right and that all looks fine
so what I want to do now is I guess
indent things based on how far in they
are great how how deep down the tree
they are which is pretty easy because we
already were tracking the depth before
so it's pretty free for me to just go
like I don't know how much I want maybe
I can say that we've got the line
advance is a thing because I find that
sometimes a handy thing to do to keep
your stuff working well with any font is
to take how big a line is and use that
as the indent amount because that tends
to look about right and it will scale
properly with whatever the font is so
I'm just gonna go like four line
advances in and see how that goes oops
that's not good got to actually multiply
it by the depth and maybe maybe four was
a little too much we'll try to yeah
so now we've got a horrorcore printout
right you can see that we've got the
printout here we've got all of our
variables that we previously were using
in the radial menu they're all printed
out here and they all look like they're
doing the correct thing so what I'd like
to do now is make it so that I can
interact with these in some way and like
I said maybe expand and collapse them do
that sort of a thing like you would see
in a tree view you know like a Windows
tree viewer or an outliner or something
like that so if I wanna do that again
pretty trivial what I need to do is I
need to have some way of figuring out
whether you know I can interact with
this thing and so this is where again
that get text bounds would be kind of
handy because if i text bounce there it
is it's trying to help me and I'm not
letting it if I know what the text
bounds are I could see whether or not
the mouse is inside it and then do
something with that right so I can do
something where I say like okay you know
I'm gonna get these text bounds for the
text that I've produced and then I'm
gonna check to see whether or not I'm
inside those text bounds and if I am
inside those text bounds
then I'm going to consider I'm gonna
consider it clickable you know there
should be it inside or is in rectangle
there we go
so if I go ahead and pull that out here
I can just say like alright if I am
inside the rectangle and this would be
again another place where I could then
lean on that item color I could just say
well if I'm inside the text bounds with
the mouse P which I'm already getting
cuz I'm the menu then I'm gonna set the
mouse I'm sorry because that the item
color to yellow just so I can see if I'm
detecting the hit location correctly and
I guess the other thing here is the text
bounce also is not offset by the text P
so I also need to do something like this
right to get the actual rectangle that I
want and so here you can see that the
hit detection is is now working
correctly so that's all good and what I
can also do now is I can just say well
alright let's do you know let's do
whatever we were gonna do when the mouse
got clicked so I will need something
like a you know some kind of an
interactive ear I guess we could just do
something like clicked for now but well
you know what I'm gonna I want to make
it a little more I'm gonna make it a
little fancier than that because we
probably want to probably want to do
something a little more I'm gonna use
the word perspicacious but that's not
the probably correct word but I wanted
to use that word and I figured that
since you're gonna see what I'm gonna do
anyway the fact that I used a word that
was not the proper word for the
circumstance shouldn't actually pose a
significant problem at the end of the
day alright so I pull out here and we go
into something where we're looking kind
of at what our interaction code was this
is gonna start to get into some more
like serious interaction stuff so I
guess problem you know honestly probably
what I would rather do here for a second
is say it just does write handmade can
Figg do the compile automatically it
does okay so what I want to do here is I
want to make it so that this will you
know maybe I can I can do use that use
kind of the same logic here but I'm
always gonna draw the debug menu instead
of only when the right mouse button does
its thing and then instead of the
previous checks I was doing I'm gonna
use like if the left mouse button was
clicked for right now and then I'm gonna
sort of talk a little bit more about
this in a second so this is a sort of a
stopgap thing just so we can test our
code but we're gonna probably do a
little bit different stuff in a second
okay so if the left mouse button was
clicked then what I'd like to do is say
this hot menu index thing that we used
to be using that's gone okay because not
many way next was just something that we
were using temporarily but now we have
this formal notion of a debug variable
and once I have that I can now say that
there is a concept of like a hot
variable right it's the variable that
I'm actually interacting with at the
time potentially well that's not
actually what it will probably
eventually be but for right now that's
all it is
so if I come in here I can say all right
if the debug state has a hot variable
set then what I will do is I will use
that thing to do something now remember
a variable can be anything that it wants
to be right it could be whatever so
whatever the variable is we probably
want to look for us to see what the type
is right so I'd want to say debug state
a hot variable type and I guess you know
what I'll probably pull it out into a
local here so we'd have to keep typing
all that so something like this they'll
say okay you know you've got the
variable type it's all good we know
we've got two of them at the moment we
might have a boolean yeah we might have
a group either one of those could be
true and then we're gonna have some kind
of some kind of a notion of what's gonna
happen in the circumstance yeah so
looking at the the variable itself
assuming that it was a boolean we just
want to take that boolean
and we want to negate it like we were
doing before but if it was a group then
we want to take the group's expanded
state and they gave that right because
again a group is not really a brilliant
has more data in it so we just want to
make sure that we're treating those
things separately for now and these will
kind of increase probably in the numbers
and types of operations that we have you
know all right so assuming that we
actually did interact with a variable at
all then we'll rewrite the config but we
don't actually need to we read the
config if we didn't interact with a
variable to say the least so once you've
got that done now we would just have to
set that debug hot variable right we
have to set that to something and so in
this case I think all we really want to
do is just say that at the start the
debug state hot variable is going to
equal zero and then at the end the debug
hot variable will be set any time we
were in the rectangle something like
this so now we know if there is a hot
variable like we've hit tested it and we
found it and it's and once we've done
that we now you know we could even
really indicate here for a group for
example we could even do something like
this where we go var group expanded we
could say like if it's expanded we'll do
a minus and if it's not we'll do a plus
right just so we can see so cures are
you know here's our sort of stuff in
theory I should be able to do a particle
test I should be able to set one oh I'm
release that's a that's a mistake that
is a missed take when I saw a bug we're
gonna have to fix there too it's kind of
interesting so yeah so in here I I'm
only checking to see whether the left
mouse button went through a transition
so what I really want to do is make sure
it went through a
mission and didn't end down so it
actually went it was released it's
probably or well-pressed maybe I don't
know don't we have code for this feel
like we have code for this I feel like
we have code for this right here so I'm
just going to say that instead of all
this cuz that's what I mean there we go
so that should be fine oops that should
be an else yeah or maybe not what did I
do now that should that's that's correct
just need an extra parenthesis what's
the problem okay and so now we're good
except we do have well you know what one
other thing I should do is say we only
need to write the config if we actually
changed a variable that we care about
probably well yeah that might not be
true we might want to serialize the
group's expansion states as well or
things like that so let's leave it that
way for now all right so if I want to
change something like whether or not we
use the debug camera I can set that
right and it toggles like so but we have
a bug here which is that these strings
are are stored in the DLL which means
that when we reload it if they move we
would have a problem and I think yeah
there you go
so you see this up this changed what
strings were in the executable so it
means that all of our string pointers
are totally wrong now does that make
sense at least I believe that's what's
happening I guess I don't technically
now so I feel like what we want to do
there is we want to make sure that when
we build our debug variable table we
actually build the debug variable table
to be to copy the the strings out right
so it has a copy of them so when we do
let me see if we've got debug variables
you here it is so when we've got our
debug variables in here we want to go
ahead and do when we add the variable
this name should actually get pushed on
to the stack as its own thing so they
it's saved we keep a copy of it not
relying on the DLL itself you know
and I feel like the probably the easiest
way to do that would be to do like a
push copy sort of a thing because we
have a copy right we have this and so if
we have that we should be able to do a
thing where there is a push copy which
takes the arena the size and the source
and then does some stuff right probably
what it does is it close copy actually
this is a little tricky this is a little
a little bit tricky how to make sure
that the macro returns the right thing
and still supports the varargs
the varves that's a little nasty it's a
little bit nasty I suppose you would do
something like this to make your life a
little easier because you are just that
kind of a person that because what I
want to do here right is I want to push
a copy so that this thing can return at
the copy but that means that the thing
inside the copy wouldn't have gotten
returned out to the top of the macro
right it has to kind of it have to
evaluate to that so I'm just going ahead
and saying well let's make copy return
its destination and then we'd be home
free right cuz then we can just do this
and everyone wins or something
right that that would then do what I
want so now we can just say push copy
you know string-length name name or
something like this
and now we should be good to go
of course I don't know if I actually
have a string-length thought we did I've
really thought we had some kind of a
string like thing is that not true is
that something that like we only did in
test asset builder where where is it
I swore we wrote this it's right there
oh wait no that's the one I wanted never
mind I'm like it's right there it's like
no it's not there it is hello come on
out come on out to play
so yes unfortunately this would have to
be in platform because it's actually
used by the platform layer as well but
that's not the end of the world we could
have a little utility section here that
we start to work on right this is just
like shared utils or something like that
something like this I don't know seems
plausible to me it's probably you right
because it can't be negative all right
so this should in theory now do our push
copy for us so I think that at least our
string should be preserved let's see
about that
I'm not sure why we're getting
that's a little weird
so we're preserving our strings properly
but there's a bit of a hit test bug here
I'm not sure so we've got we've got ones
we got some other bug happening that
doesn't look like it has anything to do
with that particular part of the
situation so what is going on I set my
hot variable and I set it if we are in
if the mouse is in the rectangle of the
text which I would think should have
been correct but even before we reload
you can see that it's wrong right like
it thinks that it thinks that that is
somehow inside that that's actually like
that that's the mouse is hovering over
both of these at once how is that
possible how I asked you it seems a
little nonsensical to me but there must
be a bug because it's not working if it
was working we might be able to make the
argument there wasn't a bug but because
it's not working it would be pretty hard
to make that argument so we set the item
color every time as well
we print out the stuff that's all well
and good I should probably also put in a
legal default case here so we know that
we have not processed that thing in the
case of some other weird variable flow
oh and of course yeah when we rewrote
them we had some garbage strings in
there as well I'm assuming that that was
just because we had that screw up with
the strings the first time but I'm
actually now so we should like verify
that that's not a bug that's still in
there after we fixed the string problem
so that would have rewritten it all
right so we have another bug oh oh man
it's it's amateur day today I can tell
exactly what that is that's just I when
I did my push size thing I should have I
needed to copy the null Terminator onto
the end of the string never use ask easy
strings kids this is why I really don't
like them very much
you don't have much of a choice when you
work when you at least are working
partially with the C runtime library
because it always uses them and a lot of
times even like windows forces you to
use ASCII strings you just don't have a
choice you can see here I'm push copy
string length will only return the
length of the string which is usually
what I actually want 99% of time when
I'm programming but anytime you're going
to call any time any time you've set up
your stuff to work with sort of the the
standard windows or C things they always
use a null terminator so you have to do
that route as well right and so all of
our stuff in hand made hero still does
know terminators which is not really
what you would do we don't really use
that may string so it's not the end of
the world but you just it's kind of
janky point being so I think we're in
good good shape here now it looks like
everything is working nicely
yeah pretty good I'm happy with that
yeah so now the only thing we have left
to do before we finish like our basic
stated goal is you know when I when I
click on these things here they don't
actually change right so you can see the
little plus is changing to a minus so we
are able to expand and collapse them in
the sense that they're variable changes
but since we don't use that variable the
actual tree view itself the
implementation is not yet correct right
because it doesn't actually obey it in
any way so we want to do to obey it is
just prevent we don't want to go down
any further into the tree in the case
that the group was not actually expanded
right so what we would do here is we'd
say this is the case right where we
descend we would just say we're not
gonna do that unless it's also we're not
going to entertain that unless it's also
expanded like so right fact I guess I
could just read about that so don't
bother descending to children in the
case where something is not expanded and
notice this is the wrong routine so you
know you could also just do that totally
wrong if you want to steps fine it's
totally fine let's we save that there
don't actually want to change it so yeah
so now that we've got that I just need
to come down here and do that in the
actual place that I actually was
supposed to do it like so and and there
we go so now we won't descend unless the
thing is actually expanded and you can
see already that it's you know doing
something differently right now we've
just got these compressed guys up here
and I can you know expand them and so on
and the nested stuff works as well and
it
remember you know wherever it was or
blah blah blah right so that's all good
and I think that pretty much gives us
what we wanted what would be nice to do
now I guess time is it got like 30
minutes left 30 minutes left
so we got quite a bit of time so
probably what we would want to do here
is add other sorts of stuff to this and
maybe try to get enough things in there
that we would have to allow it to scroll
I mean that seems like the next most
logical thing to do so that we could
have you know this this would get big
enough I don't know where we're gonna
get all the things we just insert dummy
things at this point I guess maybe I
don't know who knows so if I want to do
that if I want to add other sorts of
variables to the mix then I can
literally just come in through here and
kind of set what those things are gonna
be right so really I probably wanted to
call that bool 32 right and this can be
in 32 and this could be unit 32 right
and I can just sort of say that we've
got some stuff and why not we might as
well throw in for good measure v 3s or
b2 and b3 s V fours you know that seems
that seems reasonable so now I can print
out whatever you know we get throw
rectangles in there as well but just
like you know whatever our base whatever
our base types are we can throw them in
there
right so if we did that then we would
just all we'd have to do is just
implement the switches where we actually
care about this in the config again it's
just you know gonna be pretty much the
exact same thing this is gonna become a
pool 32 and this is going to come in 32
or something like this and it's going to
print out just the exact same stuff but
it's going to print out as an in 32
again we don't really need to do that
one for the most part to be honest we
really don't have to do those but I'm
doing them anyway and I mean you could
actually say that honestly you just do
this because these are pretty
straightforward right those are both
going to do that same same exact path so
the UN path is a little different but
only a little what's gonna happen there
and again we know these are in the same
place so it's all good
what's gonna happen there is we're just
gonna print it out as an unsigned but
everything else stays the same same is
true for the real 32 real thirty twos
are just gonna be printed out as floats
but otherwise everything is the same and
that's pretty much it
but what you can sort of see here you
know if you start to look at this you
can start to see that we're gonna have a
problem so let's take a look at the
compression or inside of this like I was
sort of saying before if we take a look
at what's going on here you can see that
I'm pretty soon gonna write exactly the
same code here right more or less so I'm
gonna have to do this sort of thing
where I you know we had this one but
then we would also have exact same thing
that I did over here happen
where the UN 32 case is only different
because it's got this I guess I can't do
that cuz that's true or false
yeah and this guy getting exact same
code but he's printing out to you
instead and then finally the r32 is just
float but again it's really kind of
wrote you can see that there's a lot of
a lot of similar to there a lot of
duplication that sort of thing but
that's what it would be so let's start
with that and then let's see what we
could do about compressing that down to
something a little more manageable in
the meantime I'm gonna have to actually
add some of these because we can't
really very much test with them unless I
have you know something to actually test
and so I'm gonna go ahead and make a way
to add things that are not boolean I
wanted to for example I can add other
types of variables here like like the
maybe in our 32 what's a real 32 and
that will set its value except
so now if I wanted to add some real 30
twos in here I could the only kind of
confusing thing is we don't actually
have any of those sorts of variables but
I could certainly make one so one way I
would make one is in the in where we're
actually doing a configure whatever I
could just say like maybe there's gonna
be you know something in here that's a
debug UI debug camera I think I even
said this one debug camera distance and
I don't know you know what I should also
do now I think about it I just typed
that F in there is I should also when I
print it out
print out the F yeah in that top line so
you know I look at that and I'm like
okay Divac camera distance we could make
that a thing because we said that was
going to be a thing and I think I even
mentioned it in here right at distance
for debug camera so if I wanted to I
could go into the render group and when
it does the debug debug camera I guess I
don't even move what's called a bug
camera instead of just adding 50 it
would add like whatever we actually did
here right so that's one thing we could
do and if I do that then I can add in a
float variable here which is what I
wanted so I can say here that we've got
oh we've got a debug UI debug camera
distance like so so that seems pretty
reasonable and now we've got a we've got
at least one floating-point value in
there and so if I open it up now let's
take a look at what it actually shows
there's that 50 which is what we set it
to and if we turn on debug camera it's
using it but we don't really have any
way to interact with it yet in fact we
interact with it we will go ahead and
hit our assertion which just says like
hey you asked me to interact with the
variables I don't know how to interact
with and so what we'd like to do there
right is we'd like to potentially make a
way to like tweak that variable
potentially because again we've sort of
done all the work that's
sorry to do whatever in here so we might
as well do something that lets you tweak
it so if we want to do that and I guess
that's so you only have 20 minutes left
maybe that's what I'll focus on doing
instead of going down there's two other
paths we could go down right this is a
bunch of things that kind of opens up
for us now but let me just go ahead and
start talking about the UI side of
things because the UI side of things is
really well you know what no let's start
tomorrow by talking about the UI side of
things so I'll let that 50 just just
ride the 50 is just gonna ride let's do
the compression side of stuff first and
clean that up a little bit and just see
what happens there because I'd rather
start tomorrow fresh talking about the
UI side of things cuz it's actually
relatively broad topic and I think
that'd be a little more interesting
okay so in this case right I feel like
for the most part you can see what's you
can I can kind of see what's what's
happening here where I've definitely got
a in terms of how things are getting
print it out I've definitely got
something that I could tease out of that
I could use the true and the false that
that could be symmetric in both cases
and if I look it's really this part
right here the percent s with the value
after it that's actually the part that's
changing the percent desk :
this part is exactly the same in both
cases
and so this it's also true over here you
can see that I've kind of got you know a
preamble but then I do exactly the same
stuff I would have done here so it's
like preamble post amble and then the
value is like in the middle now there is
one of them that is not the same and
that is this part right here so that F
is actually different
so you know it's like I'm trying to
think of what the best way to pull that
one piece out is and I suspect you know
I I suspect that probably the right
thing to do is to just make it so that
you can kind of sort of pull these pull
those things out having been printed in
some kind of a in some kind of a
parametric ways so we basically pass in
a flag that told us how we want it
formatted which would stick F on the end
if it was you know being printed in one
way and not in another or something like
this right and in fact I guess you know
now that I think about it we could
actually make it so that it all kind of
flows through one path let's see what
that looks like because that maybe is
kind of interesting I don't actually
know but I'm gonna I'm gonna see so if
we were to do something where we just
did like variable two texts right
something like this and we just made it
kind of do all the things that we needed
to do so it's gonna do something like
this where we have like the buffer size
and the buffer we have the debug
variable and then we have like some
flags or something like this then we
would just have something where we've
got okay we've got the buffer size
passed twice I've got the buffer of past
ones we don't really have to worry too
much about this but we could actually
have that be pass through and so this is
like character is used or something so
that if someone does want to jay-z chain
these together they totes could that's
kiss do they say so if I do something
like this and I guess you know now I
think about it we do kind of care about
that a little bit because we're gonna
probably use that here in a second right
I
thing yeah yeah we could actually use
that so what we do is we set up our at
here to be the buffer and then we'd
actually do we do exactly what we are
doing here in fact I take it back we do
exactly this and so I just need the
buffer pointer and probably the end
pointer like we were doing before app
becomes the buffer pointer it does
exactly what it was doing before with
the advancement so that we can do the
change things together and then at the
end we just return and minus at so that
we can I'm not in minus at at my buffer
so that it knows how many there were
right so do somebody it used so if I do
that then I should be able to well you
know what since that's exactly the same
I'm just gonna go ahead and copy that
out here we go okay oops missed the same
okay that's what I actually wanted
so now that I've got this my job is to
take this block of code and this block
of code oops here and harmonize these
two so the first things first we've got
to handle this part right so we've got
to have something that basically says
you know if you want to prefix it with
this we actually will prefix it with
that you know this has to be a bat
format as well there we go there we go
okay so if I grab one of these guys and
I'm going to print this out then what I
would do say okay I got to print out the
the debug define bit so we did show that
on there we print out the name off we go
right otherwise we might also have a
flag which does the exact same thing but
it only prints that just just the name
part we could even have that be like
this is a prefix and then we don't even
print out the name so you pass them both
or something like that I don't know just
just making stuff up here and so we
could do something like flags if the
flags and you but you know debug bar to
text underscore or add debug UI and we
could also do one that's like add name
something like that then in here all we
would actually print out is just the
value like so
something like this and that I think
gives us the basis of routine we want
there's still a couple other things in
here that we would want to do but that's
basically it right so then we have one
more down for just a float which is like
do we want to post pad that float
something like this
or I guess it's just star at plus plus
equals F all right and that's like float
suffix so now we've kind of got a
parametric way of like dumping these
things out you know and we could also
say whether we wanted to cure it to turn
on the end and that could apply to
everybody so something like this turn
and or line feed and like this and I put
that in here then we've just got you
know debug variable detects flag and
then all these guys just get some kind
of flag value okay
where's my last guy there it is okay so
now we have one routine that does all of
that printing so now I should be able to
just use that routine right so instead
of doing a switch on the variable type
here I can just use this debug variable
to text I can just use it here so I can
say okay I'm going to increment at by
whatever it takes to do this thing I
already can use the exact same thing
that I normally use here where I just do
like okay here is that here's end and I
know what the variable is and then for
the flags which ones I want I don't want
the debug UI I do
oh sorry I do want the debug UI I do
want the name yeah I don't want the
foot's of suffix I do want the line feed
end I think it's roughly the set of
fram's parameters I want for that then
all this just goes away right so now we
don't have that anymore this is the
entirety of the routine which is now
looking much nicer and then up here we
can do exactly the same thing so instead
of doing all of this again we would just
do the same thing we did here where we
just do okay please you know we don't
actually care about that please o null
terminator let's not make the same
mistake twice we also want to make sure
your spittle null terminator in there
yeah
that way the for people who are one want
it and they'll terminated aren't grading
alternates themselves yeah that'll do
that as well
okay so yeah this guy now we've got sort
of this this name prefix here it doesn't
have a colon in front of it though so
that's a little wonky but it will have a
space in front of it so we could do
something like this where we say alright
if the flag say with a colon then we put
one otherwise we don't something like
that okay wow that was yeah okay so if
we do that now I can also just print out
this thing in one fell swoop as well
which is also kind of cool and that
would take the form
I don't want debug UI I do want the name
I don't know why Flags got added in
there that's just a mistake okay I don't
want a debug UI I do want the name I do
want the float suffix I do want the null
Terminator and the colon and that is how
I want that prepared past the text of
that and I think that's it oops and end
is just going to be however big text is
so this is actually gonna return a size
T basically right here we go and I'm not
sure missing semicolon what is the
problem before debug vertex it's not a
memory you int that's not what we called
it that member you it was what we called
it what is it complaining about what are
you unhappy about my friend reindex okay
so I think that's all good
debug very able to text that wants to
take the buffer the end the variable and
the flags that looks like the right
number of parameters to me what am I
missing
1 2 3 4 1 2 3 4 does not take 3
arguments you're correct it doesn't oh
yeah as a weird order to print those
arrows out in so now in theory
everything should now be working but
everything is kind of a little bit more
compressed there so let's take a look to
see if that that was also working let's
see if it wrote out properly oh it's not
not as good not good is not good that is
ugly print out so my carriage return is
not happening we can kind of see why
it's because I decided to put an s on
the end of it said I like copied this
and didn't actually change it and well
that looks like that might actually be
it to be honest so I think
although the value why am I not seeing
the value right so in there is one thing
we want to do here which is we don't
want to print out groups and right now
we are still printing out groups right
so in this one we that's okay we also
probably should get rid of get rid of
this stuff here in this one we don't
want to print out groups so we want to
say - you know it in the case where the
thing was a group we don't print it out
and in fact I guess we already start by
checking that so we just only do it in
here so assuming the thing isn't a group
then we would actually do this right and
of course now we have that nasty problem
this is kind of a nasty thing I think
it's probably saying we probably would
have to fix is our R if we have a bug in
our debug code our printout is kind of
toasted right you know what I mean and
you can imagine this being being pretty
bad if we had like a huge number of
these you can mitigate it by because you
have source code control you could
always restore it or whatever but it's
still just a bad that's not a good
that's not a good situation you don't
want to you don't want that to be the
case we can avoid it so that probably
means that yeah like we want a way of
rewriting this or of making sure that
that sort of thing doesn't actually
become a problem like maybe by saving a
backup of the file and gets mean to
restore or by changing the way we're
doing it slightly yeah so anyway
show lighting samples what the Schiller
example say invalid
integer constant expression so it looks
like these is after my correct in
thinking that that's that they cannot be
true and false because it actually not
legal to do that I would have thought
but it could be the macro preprocessor
doesn't allow true and false for testing
let's see it does look that way do you
back camera distance has the F on the
end okay so the other thing that I want
to do there though
again I'm just about a lot of time but I
just want to clean up one more thing so
the other thing that I want to do there
though is when I am printing out those
trues and falses then that means I
should also only do only do that
assuming that a particular variable is
set right so what I would want to do is
have two different versions of this I'd
want to have flags and debug var to text
pretty true or pretty bools something
like that and so if we do pretty fools
will do that if we vote we just do this
so and print out the actual value and so
then we've got that out of control we
know that we don't want pretty Bulls
here we do want pretty Bulls here
all right so if I run that I see here
getting a little closer getting some
cool I don't know why there's a coal in
the beginning I should double-check
what's going on there all right so now
that seems to be working properly again
and let's see how the right out goes
there's a config file okay and that's
back to like being reasonable again so
that's all good and I guess we when we
were doing this guy here - we may have
wanted to fix because we have this colon
thing right where we're printing out the
colon
Oh awesome we're printing out the colon
before the name that's just a typo
supposed to look like that right so
that's better okay
TiVo camera distance and that looks like
I'm still not that means I have still
not printing out that F on the end of it
float suffix so does that mean yeah I
just wasn't passing that flag so we want
the float suffix on there and I actually
don't want the float suffix on here I
don't know why I was doing that okay so
we're getting a little closer a little
bit a little beat let's see here so we
can open these guys up that all works
fine
we could change these guys now and
that's good too but now we need to do a
few more things just to get us back to
parity and have all this stuff bundled
in one routine
okay so this all looks fine
but what we would want to do here is we
probably want to do some drawing for
when these things or groups to do like
sort of like something reasonable with
sort of group connectors or I'm not sure
what and then the other thing that we
want to probably do here is we wanted to
add in we had those little things where
we would put in a comment field and in
the case of the group so I actually
don't want to make it so that you don't
see them at all I probably do want to
actually make it so that you can see
groups and yeah so so it seems like
since it's already gonna put out the
group name this shouldn't be here right
groups don't print anything at the
moment and the only thing I would need
to do to fix the the other part where I
print out commas is instead of making it
so that I don't protect anything in this
case I would always print something out
and I would just print out a comma
before it right so I'd do something
where I do like this printf I would just
go ahead and put something in there you
know that looked like this write
something like that
so I'm gonna go ahead and do that in the
case where it is a group and then we
will always print it out I think that
should be that should be just about it
let me see see where we're at so that
all looks pretty good let's take a look
at what the big biopsy looks like yeah
all right all right so that's pretty
good now we've kind of got it down to a
thing where we just have our sort of
like configuration in line and the only
reason I want to do it that way is
because now when I add these in here
it's a lot faster so for example if I
wanted to add a vector type I just think
that now that I've kind of condensed it
in that way it makes it a lot easier so
if I want to add these guys in here I
don't have to do very much right I can
just kind of do the most minimal thing
and it works so for example if I am to
take one of those it would just be like
this right and and whatever that
actually is let's see here so that would
be like could we actually put money in
we could not so it'd be like v2
something like that and we could
actually have those in here now there's
a little bit of a caveat there which is
that we do have a problem still even so
we're printing out the brackets is is
kind of going to be annoying because it
probably normally needs to look like
that right I guess we could just leave
it like that
and if we do that then we can actually
just create everything for all of them
like so okay
that's about it I think but now you know
like I said it just makes it a little
bit easier on me if I want to add types
I don't have to worry about adding them
all over the place
all the time I do have some things that
I probably want to do take it a little
bit further just in terms of being able
to edit like be for us and be threes and
stuff like that but now we again have
the ability to have like extra types in
there and that's kind of nice and I
could add one if I wanted to I don't
really know where I would add one but I
could add a v2 in here somehow somewhere
I'd I guess I would literally just do
make up a fanciful one debug UI o v4 and
that would just be you know something
like this maybe and then in here we just
say like oh yeah we've got so before as
a variable or something and so yeah so
that's about it I think and we just need
some way of actually adding one of those
which is you know again really really
really trivial oops
yeah I think that's all there is
am I still doing debug camera distance
right no that's that's correct
oh so it's the it's the v4 that makes it
do that it's not sure which one of those
is arguing conversion from float to be
32 possible loss of data oh I
accidentally vaporized the one that I
wanted
keep sorry guys
but yeah so I think that gives us the
other types now too so like there's our
there's our v4 as well so that sets us
up pretty nicely to you know have you
know what we want for debug UI for the
most part but there's a couple janky
things so I think we probably want to
like tweak a little bit about how we're
doing that but I might focus on the UI
part of it tomorrow because again like
really the Genki part there is just that
I don't the the the trying doing the
thing where you like automatically
recompile is pretty cool but like we
sort of did that test and it doesn't
seem like we really get that much from
it and because we recompile on every
time it means that the your ability to
modify things it's too slow you know
would be nice it was it was faster it
should be faster because there's but you
know just the nature of MS PC is it's
very slow to compile things and so you
know we'll probably want to want to
address that part of this because we
probably realistically will want
something that's gonna be faster like
that should be instantaneous but it's
too slow right now and there's nothing
you know that we can do about that right
there's nothing we're not gonna be able
to speed that up that's Visual Studio
right we can't we can't fix it right
so with that in mind let's go ahead and
go to the Q&amp;A if you have questions
about we did into this dream please put
a Q :
and then asked
and a Z that was pretty Bulls man yes
pretty fools fools shocked 93 in case we
heard cutlery maybe skip Q&amp;A and eat
well I don't know if it's dinner's ready
yet normally I put in dinner before I
start the stream but I didn't get home
in time today to do it so I don't know
what is happening for dinner to be
honest why aren't the plus and minus
signs sharing the great labels because
we didn't put those in into the little
print out thing yet we can you know we
can put them back in if you just want to
throw them back in at the moment right
because we got our sort of weird printer
outer thing and basically that would
just be like okay you know expansion
tags or something and you'd put it in
here but I want to I don't want to use a
character for it I what I want to do is
actually make that be a thing that
happens in here in a more graphical way
that maybe draws a line like you'd see
in a real tree of you so I may do
something a little fancier there or I
might not do it at all I don't know it's
not super important but that's yeah
that's why I'm out there
instead of Manitoba values the power to
for our debug text items can't we just
use one shift of one one shift of two
etc yes you can
although start with one shifted up zero
and that one shifted up one obviously
cuber Caleb so is this what you mean by
I am GUI mm no I mean this this would
qualify us and I am GUI because it is
immediate mode at the moment but I am
GUI is really more about the interface
so there's a this is one of eight this
this is one of a family of things that I
would consider I am GUI
besides that colored text option for v4
is representing colors yeah you totally
could among other things insofar as we
may extreme type debug variables maybe
for things like save for location keep
buying et cetera no I don't think so
because we won't really have I don't
think we'll have much in the way of
string parameters the save folder
location is mandated by Windows as far
as I know so you can't change it Elvan
why can't we use LLVM in Windows that
way we use the same compiler for our
major platforms you
you can't output debug information for
visual studio from LLVM yet as far as I
know so that's the primary reason but
you know the I I my understanding has
they've been working on that and I don't
know where they're at in terms of
getting it working but once they got
that working we we totally could for
sure
Prine difficult road library we must
implement string formatting to the
stream isn't based on a lie well
actually so right we even said at the
outset though we won't remove the C
runtime library till the end because
that's not the only thing that calls
into the way C works like we don't even
have control over the things that the
that are being called from the C runtime
library without doing a bunch of extra
work which I didn't really want to show
people quite at the outset so if we were
to turn on no default Lib so like maybe
in here or something like this if I did
no default Lib or whatever it is I'm not
sure what the don't remember what the
what the thing is for it I think it's
after the link line there it is I think
it might just be no default Lib so if
you take a look at what happens here
some of them are the ones that you know
you are the ones we actually call which
are not very many
it's these right here but then we've got
these that we don't we don't call like
float used security cookie gs handler
check right and I didn't really want to
quite get into that yet so we need to
remove the C runtime runtime library
eventually or we don't need to I would
like to remove the C runtime eventually
but technically I don't actually
consider that a priority because the
compiler expects it to be there so it's
not really like a library that you
choose to bring into your project it's a
library that tab has to be in your
project and as you'll see when we go to
remove it you actually have to do a fair
number of ridiculous weird gyrations to
get it out of there even if you don't
call it so not calling these you know
for functions or whatever isn't going to
help us we will have to replace those
and then have to do a bunch of crazy
stuff to make the compiler stop relying
on its library because the compiler is
not made it they basically assume
than anyone building with their compiler
builds with their runtime library it's
an assumption unlike all the other
things that like when I say we don't use
libraries I mean we don't pull any
libraries in so we don't choose to use
any libraries but the compiler voice
that went on us we will be able to get
rid of it it's possible it's just it's
not as simple as not calling anything
from it insofar as if you had to do an
encryption system would you use a
library or write it from scratch
yourself actually I do have an
encryption system at work and I did read
it myself
cruza how long after getting gives her a
number should you call text them I don't
know I never picked someone up at a bar
so I sauce the kid are you planning on
doing user text input no Elven you
missed my question twice in the pre
stream looks like it's not appearing is
there a math question like that you
filter out well heck's chat might have
one I don't but hex chat might you can
debug LVM things using the visual studio
in UI what is that link you're pointing
to Microsoft mi engine I'm not sure what
that is I also look at that later wooden
vessel to compile all possible
combinations debug virus the separate
binaries but then only use the one that
matches the chosen debug virus for
faster switching is this a stupid
question it is not a stupid question but
I would divide you to consider how many
binaries that would be so I'll give you
a simple example how many binaries would
it take to just do the rudimentary ones
we have put in here for testing right
what has happened here why isn't my game
frozen something bad has happened
oops that's not what I wanted
ok so we have some kind of a hang here
hold on a second where what is happening
tell me where my thread is it's in GD I
what what what did we do wrong here
we're hanging but we're hanging in oh is
it just because I was doing this I don't
think so why would that be the case why
are we hanging in GD I I don't know
what's going on that was really weird
well anyway just take the values we have
here boolean values 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
how many executables would it take to
have all the combinations of those 11
variables and if you watch a mate here
regularly you should know the answer to
this because just imagine each of those
were a flag we often make our flag
fields right so each bit imagine of a
number each bit can either be on or off
ground chunk outlines that's bit 0
ground chunk checkerboards that's bit 1
recompute ground chunks on exchange
that's pit 3 I'm sorry with 2 3 4 or 5
right so we would have 2 to the 11
different combinations right however
many we have there that would be how
many bits are in the number that says
how how many executables we have right
because you can kind of think of it as
like these are the flags that we have
we've got 11 of them
or something right that all can be set
right and any one of them could be set
you know this one could be set to you
know on or off on off on off and this
one would be like okay off off on on
right off off this one would be like off
off off off on on right it becomes
essentially a it's exactly like a number
each bit can be set to one or zero and
you have every combination of all the
bits so if you have eleven bits you will
have two to the eleven possible binary
x' right now you all know what two to
the eighth is probably right it's 256
yeah so two to the ninth is 512 to the
tenth 1024 right which means that the
number of binary is you would have to
compile just to do the basic debug
switches we have right now is 2048 it's
not probably the number of binaries you
want to recompile every time makes sense
so that's why that's not practical it's
because it's a combinatorial complexity
problem and scales you know very poorly
what is the end goal for the DWI like at
what point will we say this is done I
have no idea probably what I'm just
satisfied that you know we can look at
our performance and we can look at
values and some diagrams relatively well
you know he's add stuff to it later in
case the debug variables header is
messed up can we check easily if the
debug variable is not defined it set
some default value we could I'm thinking
I probably need to do something else
there though because it's just kind of
janky I'm not sure what I'm gonna do but
we'll figure something out how would you
implement your own string without having
them be null terminated bundle the care
start with a count variable yeah usually
what I do is I do int count and care
star pointer that's what I usually do
all right let's see somebody said here
is the priest in question question I was
thinking more about the handmade sort of
case and subject that was brought up
yesterday and I think it would be pretty
cool for it to happen because the
knowledge gained by somebody who
followed study and understood the
strangers were valuable in my opinion
the neighboring class a hammie degree
could mean more than a college degree
you would also draw our people to the
show the tricky part is that it
organized it make it happen a couple of
things occurred to me zero it's not
feasible to everybody but a paper exam
somewhere near Seattle or one online
oral test via Skype calls tests could
take an hour at first case who does it
ask you question many areas conversation
gets credit uh yeah I mean like I said
it just doesn't interest me very much
like I don't want really wanna be in
some kind of position of like certifying
people as like knowing or not knowing
something my goal is just to put this
information out there and then you know
I'm putting out like some information on
a way to program that's effective and it
does some things that are useful and to
demonstrate this effective because I
like I'm able to get things done in the
short amount of time on stream or
whatever right but I don't really want
to be in some kind of a policing
capacity or in some kind of a like III I
don't think it need to be any more
formal than that like if people want to
learn from it and they learn something
good from it then that's great but I
don't think it needs to be you know done
this or that I don't think it's
something that should be like rigorous
sized nor do I necessarily know how you
would do that even if you went through
the links that you're talking about I
think it would be still pretty tough
difficult to do but yeah anyway oh maybe
that's all that was happening maybe I
was just clicking on something and then
so it was just it was just getting
having trouble showing the assertion
that said hey we don't have an
interactive for that that could have
been anyway thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of
handmade he wrote us recorded with you
as always if you would like to follow
along the source code at home you can
always pre-order the game on handmade
hero org and it comes with the source
code so you can play around and
experiment
a patreon page you can subscribe to if
you want support the video series it's
always very appreciated we have a forum
site you can go to to ask questions and
take a look at an annotated episode
guide we have a tweet bot the tweets the
schedule at you if you're trying to get
to series live and we even now have an
upcoming conference if you type handmade
comm org into your browser it will show
you the most up-to-date post about it we
just only announced it and there will be
more information about it coming pretty
soon and this speakers for it are gonna
be pretty awesome it's looking like so
I'm pretty excited about that we'll be
announcing that in a week or two
probably so definitely check that out
when you get a chance I'll be back here
to tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Standard
Time or Daylight Time I guess Pacific
Daylight Time
until then have fun programming and I'll
see you guys on the Internet
take these everyone