hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show where we code a complete game
live on stream we are gonna do movement
modes today a little bit more formally
we sort of have them working already but
we it's kind of a little fast and loose
and there's I think enough slop in there
that I wouldn't really want to leave it
as arbitrary disease right now because
it's pretty close to being something
that I think could be relatively
reliable and work a little more cleanly
so I think that's what I would like to
do and so that's what we're gonna do
since we now have brains working
relatively solidly and we tested that
out we built like some interesting
creatures yesterday and so I'd like to
take a look at that movement mode stuff
and kind of clean that up a bit and I
think that would probably get us to the
point where I'm relatively comfortable
with how we're doing sort of all of the
you know behavioral stuff in the you
know in code because it seems like we're
able to write relatively directly what
we want at this point and I'm not I
don't have a whole lot of architectural
concerns about it I would like to like I
said address the movement mode stuff and
then we're gonna probably have to take a
look at how we're doing world
construction because right now it's a
little bit overly verbose and like how
you pass things around and with the
world chunks and so on and we've got the
spatial query stuff as well which we
kind of want to handle so there's a
bunch of things like that that we would
like to figure out and that's what we
will be dealing with over the next
couple days so let's take a look
today is day 293 I am going to go ahead
and jump right in so if you want to
follow along at home unzip day 292
source code into a directory and that is
what I'm starting with right now so you
can see kind of where we left off back
yesterday we've got a bunch of things
running we've got this little snake dude
here
just kind of snakes around and we have
monster who hops around randomly and
we've got a familiar who just kind of
randomly pushes towards the player but
we haven't really done anything with
with that yet either and one of the
things that you'll notice is that
although our hopping movement mode right
the hopping movement mode is the one
currently being used by almost all the
entities on the screen the snake uses
the hopping movement mode the mana star
uses the hopping movement mode the hero
uses the the hopping movement Road but
actually the the familiar who has flown
off the screen doesn't use the hopping
movement mode because obviously it's
just this kind of floating head and one
thing you'll notice about that and I
could go find that familiar I suppose I
don't know where he went probably up
here somewhere well there's a different
familiar so that's fine one thing you'll
notice about the familiar is that it
does not actually occupy any square
other than the one that it started on Oh
back over here you can see it's still
technically occupying this square right
and that's because it doesn't really
have a movement mode of its own it's
just kind of being moved around by the
brain arbitrarily and that's essentially
equivalent to what's happening with the
head of of the hero here right this head
and that you know we want to probably
change a little bit the way the hero's
head is moving as well but we definitely
want the the familiar to not work that
way because it basically is just totally
bogus what we want to have happen is we
want a movement mode for floating where
as you float around you try to occupy
the square that you are going to be most
underneath and if that square is not
available you should be stopped from
going there right you should not be
allowed to actually enter a square
that's occupied just because you are
floating right and right now we wouldn't
you know we cannot like anything that's
in the hopping movement mode right it
cannot enter there so you know I'm
clearly moving over here and we don't
try to stop the head so I can just keep
on going but the body will never try to
do the hop right it's like completely
stuck there right which is exactly what
we want
so yeah so we need that same logic to
happen inside floating entities because
unlike something like a projectile which
perhaps is would just be allowed to
float around and when it hits something
it just does damage to that something or
who knows what else we want to have
happen unlike a projectile and a
floating entity is still gonna be
considered an entity most of the time
and you know we can always turn that off
we don't want it but we certainly want
the ability of for floating entities to
be considered occupiers of squares so
that other people can't move in there
and so they cannot move on top of other
squares and so that's what I kind of
want to take a look at today as we
improve this movement mode code to be a
little bit more formal and to have you
no real alternative movement modes
instead of just the one hopping versus
planted which is currently the only
thing that's actually in there so if I
take a look at the entity you can see
that the entity has a movement mode
enumerator and that amudha
movement mode enumerator only has two
things which is planted and hopping most
things are in a planted mode by default
hopping mode is what they engage when
they when they hop from one Square to
another which certainly a number of
enemies will and the hero will certainly
be using but we will probably have
floating or just we probably don't have
to call it floating we could call it
like sliding right because we don't
really care whether the thing is
technically floating or technically
walking from one squared the other the
point is that it's not a hop it's a
smooth you know sort of linear movement
from one place to another is really the
only part we actually care about
so we could say movement mode sliding
and that would be enough information I
think for basically most things that
we're gonna move in that way and I don't
know how many more of these there would
be and I'll be completely honest with
you it's possible that the movement mode
stuff really I don't even know maybe we
only need one movement mode and that the
fact the hopping part is really just
of dressing and maybe entity movement
mode is you know is more about a look
than anything else I don't know but for
right now I think we're just gonna say
all right there's a planted there's a
hopping and there's a sliding and so
when we see sliding we're gonna you know
sort of move someone from one square to
another in in a more continuous fashion
or something like this that seems that
seems pretty reasonable to me
yeah because planted movement mode
implies that you are fixed at the
location and that's relatively important
I think because if you are fixed on
you're occupying location that means
when it moves you would move as well and
so I think sliding perhaps also
indicates another thing which is that
you're moving of your own volition
separate from the motion of the point
that you might be standing on if that
makes sense and you know now I think
about it that may be a good reason why
we would distinguish floating from other
things I suppose that means we might
actually want floating because when you
are floating you would not if if the
points that you're occupying arm cells
moving a floating entity doesn't move
with them right that that seems right to
me
yeah so anyway let's take a look at that
and see what we want to do here and
there's one possibility there's another
possibility too which is that it's
possible that movement mode floating is
actually redundant with movement mode
planting and we'll find that out as
we've started cleaning up the code and
that really like there's just two things
there's you know they're both the same
because you're always talking about a
displacement relative to one of the
points and you can accomplish that by
sort of adjusting your displacement
relative to your home point or something
like this so I don't know yeah that's
basically it okay so let's take a look
at that and we'll see where we're at
I'm not 100% certain how this is going
to play out so I just want to kind of
play with it for a little bit and see
alright so here we are in our world mode
which is where the movement stuff takes
place you can kind of see here we've got
the code for planted versus hopping and
this is where we're doing sort of that
simulated bounce effect that we were
using before and we really don't do any
other physics besides whatever that sort
of faux hopping is and then this move
entity call which is really something
we're going to replace pretty soon
because it's way more complicated than
it needs to be for any particular
purpose in this game and we never really
wrote it right to begin with we were
just kind of playing around with
collision detection and I was sort of
showing some stuff about it when we
wrote it but it's you know it's not
really appropriate anymore for what
we're doing it's you know you can't
grind up against walls and stuff in this
game because you hop specifically from a
square to another Square and stuff like
that so the kinds of stuff that we were
having it handle are not super important
to handle anyway for this particular
game so anyway what we would like to do
I think is we'd like to say that you
know when I have something like the
familiar and that's in brain dot cpp
here when I have something like the
familiar what I'm doing right now is I'm
saying I want him to move in a
particular direction so I'm stuffing his
DDP right which is his you know
acceleration that he wants to have I'm
stuffing his DDP with the acceleration I
would like to give him and the problem
here is that when I stuff that
acceleration it's just going to apply it
directly to the object and again it
doesn't matter it doesn't think at all
about what Square I might be on or what
square to square I might be trying to
move to or any of those things and so
that's why we don't update we never
update our occupy because normally the
the updating the occupying would be here
in the brain code and you know now it's
not going to be so again try to think
through how we want this
be handled and I don't really know we've
got this sort of concept that we could
do it sort of similar to the way the
hopping works which is everything is
handled over in the brain that thinks
about where you're going to be occupying
and where you're going to move to and
that sort of stuff the other way is that
it's handled were in the entity code as
part of the movement modes and like I
said I'm not really sure which one of
those we want to do similarly because
I'm sort of saying that the movement
mode concept is in question right now
and I'm just sort of trying to think
about where we draw the delineation
architectural speaking between who does
what you could also imagine that in here
we could sort of we could say that stuff
like where I'm trying to move to is not
maybe handled directly in the brain code
you know maybe only requests for
movement or handle in the brain code I
don't know but my suspicion and this is
just it comes from having built the
snake right it was very easy to make
that snake I mean the amount of code we
needed to make the snake is like so tiny
and if you think about how complicated a
motion movement that really is it's kind
of awesome that it was this easy to make
a snake that works completely perfectly
and can never get into any state where
it's like occupying its own region or
any other those sorts of things it's
completely robust that was pretty cool
and one of the main reasons we were able
to do that code was because the brain
issues the transactional occupy
instructions right inside itself and so
that's kind of a thing where you know it
feels like we want these sorts of things
to be kept at the brain level and and
you know insofar as there might be ways
for resolving them we would want to at
least you know if I am gonna push it
down a level because we want it to be
sort of solved simultaneously or other
things like this I think we still want
to look to the snake as an example of
how easy this was to write and I think
we want to make sure we don't destroy
that ability by making it you know
too complicated to be able to write such
a simple piece of code to do such a
complex motion right so yeah so that's
the tricky part in my mind so let me
think about this for a second here and
let's just start writing a little bit of
code so that I can get my head around
exactly how this stuff has to work so if
I take a look at what happens with the
familiar I'm stuffing the DVP here and
what I probably want to know is I want
to know if I can keep accelerating in
that direction or not right and I
probably want to do a spring back to my
home square as well if it sort of
critically keeps me from getting into
the next square if it's not something I
can occupy so I feel like I could
implement this particular particular
thing relatively simply by just saying
well you know we've got that kind of get
closest traversable bit here right we've
got this notion where are we here here's
great I'm familiar I've got this notion
that I could say well you know you know
what I should probably also say that
this whole thing since the familiar is
just ahead we don't really need to do
anything if we don't have a head so I
don't really need to keep checking so
you know we've got this head and we're
gonna find out what the closest
traversable is to it
and we want to know if that closest
traversal becomes a traversable other
than the one that we are occupying and
if it is a one other than occupy we want
to take that new square right so we want
to say something like and we'll just do
it this way you know if I think we have
a traversable like check right we have
the ability to see if they're equal like
this so we can say something like okay
you know if if these guys are equal if
the closest traversable is is the same
as the one we're occupying we don't have
to do
work if it's not then we're gonna want
to do that that that's swap right so
then we want to do a transactional
occupy and again just bringing up that
code here so we can take a look at that
there's transactional occupy we're
saying that the head has a desk ref
which is our occupying ref right that's
the place we were and there's a place
we're going to go to and that's this
traversable right so if we can
transactionally occupy the square that's
good for us if we can't we need to know
that because we're gonna have to not
continue to accelerate in that direction
right
but for now I'm not going to do anything
else I'm just gonna verify that that
allows the head to float around and
occupy whatever the closest Square is to
it and you can see that it's happening
now right so now at least I couldn't
move into the same Square as this guy
right and so you know I have to hop over
whatever his occupy square is but as you
can see he's still free to float
anywhere so the fact that he is
occupying the right square is good but
we want him to have to stop if there was
something in his way right and so
clearly after we do this transactional
occupy in here we probably want to do
something where we say if the
transactional occupy doesn't succeed or
rather if we are not hovering generally
over our closest traversable then we
have to spring back to that traversable
and that's just a rule or something
right so you know we'll have a thing
that's like blocked equals false or
something and what we'll say is when we
do get closest traversal or you know
what let's assume that block is true and
then what we'll say is well if we get
the kosis traversable right we can say
are they equal and if they're equal then
we'll say that we're
blocked because that means we're
floating over the place we're supposed
to be floating and if we were able to
transactionally occupy the new square
then that would also mean that we aren't
blocked right but any other case we are
blocked and so then we can say well you
know if we're blocked we do one thing
right and if we're not blocked we do
another thing and really we don't need
to do this checking cure at all and
we're gonna get rid of that because I
guess that's just true from now on so
we're gonna go ahead and grab this guy
out here I'm gonna put inside this this
loop I'm gonna put this thing because we
don't need to search for someone to
follow if we're blocked because if we're
blocked we have to return to our square
first right so we don't want to do that
at all so if we're blocked we want to
apply a spring back to the traversable
location and so we'd want to do
something like you know whatever the
whatever the traversable position is
that we actually are on so it's head
occupying and I think we want to do a
get sim space P of that I believe if you
remember we can ask the simulation where
a particular traversable is so sim get
some space reversible right
so we can say that this is our target
now and really I guess now that I think
about it we could apply this logic
always
probably right we could apply this logic
always and I could just say that if
we're not blocked we look to see if
there's a different target but if we are
blocked then we'll just use this this
logic here right so I'll say the target
is the sim space traversable for our
occupying point and we just update that
target equals closest hero P in the case
where we have a different a different
place we could go right meaning we're
not blocked and we found somebody to
follow right so yeah so the problem with
that in some sense so we're using the
closest hero distance squared so I'm
gonna I'm gonna get rid of the fanciness
here a little bit and I'm just gonna say
like we've got our acceleration x times
this distance I'm not gonna probably
play with any other aspects of it I'm
just gonna leave that the way or that it
was okay let's see what else we got
alright so that's a little uncompelled
target because if we're not blocked and
blocked is assumed to be true if we get
the closest reversible and it's equal to
what we're on block becomes false
transactional occupy of the thing then
black would also become false if we
can't get the closest traversable to our
P then we'd be so that all seems fine
but finally occupying P for the target
that all seems reasonable yes that all
seems reasonable so I want to step in
there and see why that's not moving why
am I not moving all right I should
probably move those in here as well
since they're not really relevant that's
interesting so the traversable and the
heads occupying location are not the
same that's a little peculiar wouldn't
you say I wonder why that's true
the traversable at the moment I would
like to see what it is
head occupying and first of all so by
default we're on index zero of vicinity
here right and when we get the closest
one that sure looks the same to me
and of these are the same the indices
are the same
references are equal
this is the
I see
so we have a valid entity pointer in
both cases but we don't have a valid in
the index in both cases meaning when we
initially set it well I'll be honest I'm
not sure why that would be the case I'm
not sure about that so that's saying
that the traversable that we retrieved
did not have a valid index for some
reason but since it must have had a
valid index originally do we just not
set it in there I'm sort of confused
about that let's let me let me look at
that I think that's a little weird
so where's get closest traversable but
get closest traversable
aha so we never set this and I think we
should because that way if we're trying
to have both of these things work we can
always guarantee that they're set
properly all right so that was just a
bug and get closest reversible okay so
now we are at least only accelerating
this guy when he believes himself to be
able to go into a square and if he
doesn't leave and go to square he'll
he'll accelerate back to his current one
unfortunately he has enough momentum
that it's easy for him to overshoot
right so this is our our spring
situation again you can see his behavior
there like he's he will eventually come
to rest in a correct fashion but without
any damping he's just gonna oscillate
forever so we need to sort of give him
something more like the the head spring
has on the on the main hero so that
that's you know so that he has a little
more restitution there and you can kind
of see you know we use sort of the
standard proportional derivative
controller style PD C or you know
basically a spring proportional
derivative controller is I don't
remember if I gave that definition on
the stream but basically like if I flip
over to Milton I can I can just say that
one more time
in case I forgot to say it originally
here on what day to 93
so there's proportional derivative
controller and this is oftentimes
abbreviated PDC and there's also
similarly this can actually be an
integral as well so there's proportional
derivative controllers which are PD CS
and porch proportional integral
controllers or P I see the formula for a
proportional derivative controller we
already went over right it's that the
acceleration of this thing whatever it
is of and it's usually like the
acceleration given some particular
position right I'll actually write it
this way so the acceleration of this
thing is going to be equal to something
on you know it's not a good day for math
let's do it this way so the second
derivative of my location my position is
going to be equal to some kind of a
constant a constant on you know like the
zeroeth order constant or whatever some
tuning value for my spring the strength
of the spring if you will times the
difference between where I am and where
I want to be right so it's basically
some target value for my for my position
minus the position I'm actually at
that's going to determine how much
acceleration I have and similarly I'm
going to add in a term for the velocity
here so I'm going to add in some other
coefficient and that coefficient is
going to make it so that my velocity
target - my current velocity also has a
coefficient on it and so basically what
this is is it's trying to drive these
assuming that these coefficients
are are both gonna be positive right
meaning I'm trying to drive towards
these target values I'm always going to
be accelerating in a way that tries to
make these things zero so that tries to
bring these things together right
because only when I have a 0 here and a
0 here will this actually become zero
right and so my the reason it's called a
proportional derivative controller is
because hey there's a derivative in it
and it's proportional I don't think
there's really much more to it than that
I guess to be honest I don't really know
where this part comes from I guess if I
had to say the proportional derivative
controller part I'm not sure if it lines
up property properly with the
proportional integral controller because
I'll just think out loud here this thing
I really probably would have called
Delta and the reason I would have called
it a proportional delta controller is
because it's really not about the
derivative it's about the Delta between
two things right and it doesn't really
matter what they are and the fact that I
have a zeroth order and a first order is
hardly a good reason to call it
derivative and the reason I say that
makes more sense is because the other
kind which is a proportional integral
controller what that does is it
accumulates this value over time so
basically what happens is every time
step I sum up how far I have been off so
that the terms get stronger and stronger
the longer I am off as opposed to only
being about the instantaneous difference
and so Delta feels a little bit better
to me instead of derivative but you know
I mean who knows I you know I'm not a
mathematician so maybe maybe this is
fine
anyway so that's again we went over
those in some detail when I first
introduced the concept so I'm not going
to belabor the point here your point
being is we need some additional terms
in here we probably need this to be a
pretty stiff spring and we probably need
to go ahead and say that we want I guess
I'll just bake the the negative in there
because we're basically doing a
you know zero velocity - my current
velocity kind of a thing right but so I
can just take the negative in there and
not bother with that so we want some
negative coefficient on here I don't
know what it should be let's say it's
negative 4.0 for now I don't know and
then we'll tune it and we'll see what it
actually should be so now we can kind of
see that that our little friend here is
a little bit he's he doesn't move in a
very satisfying fashion right but he's
moving fairly correctly now right and
one thing I could do here is I could
make it so that now we don't do this
this closest here Oh a d squared part
anymore I could take that out of there
as well so he's always kind of following
us but he's just the reason he stops is
cuz he gets to like that halfway point
right and you know he's a little clingy
it's true he's a little bit clinging and
you'll notice see I can't enter his
square which is what we wanted and he
won't enter mine which is good too but
it's still not it's not quite it's not
quite what we want and there's a couple
of things there there's a couple of
reasons it might not be I don't know but
we can see right you can see oscillates
kind of back and forth there and the
reason he's asked letting there is not
because of the spring the reason he's
oscillating there is because of this
notion of blocked this blocked notion
oscillates as well right
so in some sense what we have here and I
think this is kind of a problem that we
want to solve more fully as well is we
don't have any way currently for people
who are moving to think about where
they're going to be they only know once
they get there so really what we would
prefer for our little dude here is we'd
prefer for him to just stop on that
square if he knows he can't move into
the next square right but instead what
he does is he tries to move into the
next
where and when he finds that he would be
in the next square he sees it's occupied
so then he springs back to the previous
one as soon as he moves over the
previous square he finds he's okay again
so then he tries to move towards a hero
and that's when you get that oscillation
happening right so I think what we want
to do is probably introduce another
concept here and I think we're gonna
want to use this for the hero as well
when we sort of tune this head control
what I think we want to do is I think we
want to have some way of saying what
would the next traversable be if I went
in this direction right so you know if I
was to go in the direction that I am
planning on going what would the next
traversable be and if that traversable
is already occupied I won't try to go
there until I see that it isn't occupied
right okay so basically you know this
code here where we're doing block this
can probably stay in as sort of a
fail-safe for when somebody moves into a
square that we were trying to go to but
what we want to do here is say well the
target P being are occupying we actually
want that to be true even if we're not
blocked if we see that the next square
would have been blocked right so after
we do this and we look at what the
target P would be we don't want to
accept that target P unless we can get
there safely so I'm gonna go ahead and
say let's pretend let's just try this
again here and then I think we've gotten
to the point at least I'm fairly
confident know that now would be a time
to maybe start pulling some this code
out into helper functions so that
they're easier to use for constructing
brains think we're gonna want to do this
sort of stuff a lot okay so when we find
the closest hero this is the line we're
going to execute and instead what we
want to do is like say that there's a
target traversable and will get that
target reversal by saying what's the
head P you know Plus maybe a uniform
step in this direction or something
right
so this is the Delta that we're trying
to go we've got that closest hero P and
we've got the head P and I'm just going
to go ahead and say let's like normalize
or zero that I think we've got a nas
function so we've got that Delta that's
the direction we're going in and what
I'd like to do here is just take that
say in if I were to move a certain
distance forward in that Delta what
would the next Traverse will be that I
would be in right and we have a there's
a little bit baked in here and I guess
I'd say this like you know default
distance or something we've got there's
a little bit of hand waving this in
there that we need to sort of
systematize I'll talk about in a second
but for now let's just say we're going
to move one unit in that direction right
so if I was to move one unit in that
direction I'm gonna get this target
traversable and I just want to see like
is it occupied so if it's not occupied
then I'm going to try to go there right
and that's it that's all I wanted to do
so ah he's occupied I'm assuming we
already know how to do but I guess I
just never made anything for it you can
see I guess here yeah that that we never
really did and anything that was is this
thing occupied I guess that just wasn't
it wasn't a thing it looks like now it's
it's a trivial thing it's just it
doesn't have an occupier but I'd rather
be able to just write is occupied and
not have to worry about how these things
were implemented right because you know
maybe we change it further down the road
and maybe I forget or whatever so since
I just want to be able to say hey is it
occupied and you know know that I'm
gonna get something back so here's the
riff and I believe all we have to do
is-is-is this I think I will see I
really should probably just define to be
32x
destr F undeclared identifier that's
true so let's see if that is any better
and oh dear all right
so yeah not great and I think that's
probably just because it's not asking to
move far enough
well but that looks like the opposite is
happening is occupied
if the occupier is zero
oh just had the sense of it wrong much
better
Oh texture download yes so it clearly
needs to be able to do it slightly
further than one unit and that's the
part I was talking about before now let
me explain that before I fix it just so
you can see so what I'm want to do here
is we're currently set up in a regular
grid but there's actually no reason why
we have to be in a regular grid right in
fact just to prove this point sort of
for people who might be confused about
that because I realized that we haven't
spent much time really talking about it
hardly at all but if you take a look at
that standard room here you'll notice
that I'm adding these you know these
entities in here with whatever the
traversable x' and stuff like this and
I'm adding them at particular locations
and blah blah blah so here's like this p
with the world position and and all that
stuff right if I wanted to I could add
Delta's to these so for example well I
could say that the there's an offset Oh
in fact I've already kind of got one
right you can see it right here I was
setting the Z offset but I could you
know make there be an X offset I could
make that be a random bilateral on the
series and I could do an offset Y that's
a random bilateral in the series and you
know I don't know how far you could go
on these exactly but let's say you can
go a quarter unit and now when I create
the room you can oh well that was not
what I was expecting I admit that
it looks like I may have been a little
bit overzealous there in my in my
changing of what the offsets were her my
goodness that should not have had that
effect I don't understand why that
wasn't just a very very small
modification right that should not have
oh right sorry
I didn't mean to override it completely
my bad all right so let's make these now
I can go back to what I thought was
gonna be reasonable value and it was I
was actually overwriting the thing I for
some reason didn't make it a plus so you
can see in this case right there's
really no reason why they have to be a
grid right we we have not written the
code such that a grid is required
everybody pretty much is just able to
function on completely arbitrary Maps
the only rule is that only one person is
allowed to occupy one of these things at
a time right and I don't know that we're
ever going to make use of this
particular feature but since I don't
actually know that we won't this might
be the easiest way to say it I want to
make sure that we can right and so we're
still at the point where I'm not willing
to give that up and I think I'm never
probably going to because I think we're
gonna want to make some maps that have
two apologies that are a little bit
different so just you know keep that in
mind
so what that means is there's no way for
the familiar to know something like what
is the next Square over right there's no
way for it to to ask that question
semantically because there is no logical
definition of next Square over there's
only a geometric definition of the next
Square over which is like if you gave me
a direction what would be the time when
I hit a point
next that was we came closer than the
point I'm currently on or something
right so we can make geometric
definitions and you know those
definitions we could make one that sort
of coincides with our intuition the
intuition that we expect to have here
right
but we can't do something like uh you
know have some sort there isn't I guess
all I'm saying is there isn't some hard
and fast notion of what points to the
left so what I need to do is I need to
basically cast across so I need to take
these these little fellows right and I
need them to kind of go like oh where
would I be what would I be going to if I
looked a certain distance to the left
hello Monstar so if I looked a certain
distance to the left or to the right or
whatever I if I'm doing that casting I
need to make sure that I look far enough
that I'm going to get the next one but
not so far that I pick up one after it
right and so really I don't really want
a query that's like get closest point
what I really want is get point in
direction but rather than write that at
the moment we should be able to just use
the fact that these are relatively
regulars spaced to sort of not address
that particular query right now but when
we do spatial queries we will probably
want to do that right so what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna say okay we've got the
sim region get closest traversable I'm
gonna pretend that we've got another one
that does get you know the thing in this
direction but then you know I'm not
gonna implement it right now but I think
that's better so that we can only see
who's what sort of look for that way we
can at least see see who's using it when
we have to go andrey implement it right
so instead of get closest reversible
here we're just going to use basis the
same logic so I'm going to say get
closest reversible a long ray and so
what we'll do here is we'll just say
alright in this sim region that we're
talking about if I start from this P and
I go in this direction
what was the traversable that I will
first hit right and so I'm again not
really going to do anything smart here
I'm going to just call our existing
function and it's slow and crappy but
that's just what's going to happen and
like I said we can always speed all of
these up later so it's no big deal so
what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna
start by me you know sort of pulsing out
along this line and I I'm going to sort
of take sample points and see what when
I get to another one
first now there's a problem here right
which is that when we're doing this
traversal along array we don't we want
to skip the one that we're currently on
and so we kind of have this other
slightly nasty thing we got to do here
which we got to say like oh you know
skip the this one because we don't want
to return the one that we're next to or
whatever right something like that so
I'm not sure exactly how we want to do
that but I think that's roughly what I
want to do okay so over here we would
say get closest reversible along ray
we'd have the sim region we'd say here's
the head P here's the Delta direction
then I would say well I don't want the
one that I'm on right and I want you to
just return to me whatever the target is
and I'm not gonna I don't want you to
look only for things that aren't
occupied because I want to know if it's
occupied that's the whole reason I'm
doing this so what I'm going to do here
is say alright let's do
for I loop you know probe index equals
zero probe index is less than 10 I don't
know plus plus probe index maybe that's
too many we'll just say five and so then
what I'm going to say here is alright
we're going to take sample points out
along the sky as we do sort of our
sampling and we'll say that like the
sample P is going to be equal to
wherever we started plus you know the
the probe index whatever that is we're
going to multiply that by our sample
sort of distance which we'll say is one
unit and maybe we'll even say it's point
five units we'll take closer samples as
we step out or whatever so we're going
to take that times the direction that
will move us out to a new sample point
and then we'll just call get closest
traversable right we'll call get closest
reversible and we'll see if it returns
true we pass the same stuff we were
passing before but now we're going to
pass that sample point and we're going
to pass the results here so we'll grab
whatever it comes back in to that result
if we got it closest traversable then
all we need to do is say well is the
closest Tercel oh you know what i should
pass the flag - is that closest
traversable that it's giving me back is
that one the one that we were told to
skip or not so I can say like what is it
is equal if the skipped one is equal to
the result one then we haven't found a
match but if they're not equal then we
have and so then I would say the result
or for found equals true and we would
break out of the loop at that point
right so that's really all we need to do
there to modify the routine to work out
along the Ray and now you can see that
this guy is a lot more stable now that
he's working that way and he he properly
he doesn't have that weird halting
behavior except when he's close to me
and has to stop
right
let's move up and get some more of these
guys
ah yeah let's see and I you know what I
would like to be able to do I would like
to be able to see when these guys think
they're blocked and not in that sort of
thing
it's kind of funny to leave these guys
around mm-hmm so another thing I kind of
want to do right now because we're
almost out of time so I don't know how
much more stuff I'm gonna have time to
do here in our profile I did want to do
one thing which is I'm interested to
know how much time we're spending in
these functions right and since we made
a bunch of tools for these I don't
remember what they are if it's like
count function or something like this
and so I wanna I just want to see what
the profile is there so let's go to sim
region dot CPP and just see what it is
it's time function because I suspect
that we spend a ton of time in these
spatial queries there they're really
really slow and they iterate over lots
of things and so I just wanted to see
how much time we were actually spending
in them and if my intuition was correct
that that's where all our time was being
spent but I don't actually know so yeah
there is 15 percent of the time and get
closest traversable
although inside begins sim we are still
spending a lot of time in there which
I'm not really sure why probably because
we're still copying giant introduced
trucks around right I'm guessing but I'm
actually know that that's true either
yes you can you can really see that get
closest reversible just taking a ton of
time right and so that's what we want I
mean that's good
because that is very specifically
something that's easy for us to optimize
quite a bit right we can get that down
to probably taking like very almost no
percent of the time and that'll free up
a huge amount of our cycle count which
is good I would like to know a little
bit more about begin soon because I want
to make sure I kind of understand where
that time is being spent and I and I
don't necessarily know so I would also
like to kind of go in here and just see
so inside begins Tim if we have this
whole thing timed we've got the triple
loop and then we're unpacking in the
blocks I'm assuming that mostly like
that time is just spent in that
unpacking process right because this is
just a lot of copying I would think so
we'll see
I will also double check quickly just to
see what happens to this when we do a
build in release mode we go
yeah and so so in release mode even even
now that stuff is just irrelevant though
I guess so
I guess it's mostly just a lot of
checking and inefficiencies and them in
the way it would be copying those
entities trucks and stuff like that
because we still get a solid 60 Hertz
like pretty much no sweat even with that
completely ridiculous junk going on
which again I think bodes really well
for this entity system because this
isn't even a fast machine this is a
pretty slow machine it's from six years
ago this machine so if we're all I mean
look at all this junk that's already
happening on the screen if that's not
and we're not doing anything yet to try
and copy those entities in any sort of
efficient way I think we'd be fine
went you know I I don't think we're
gonna have a lot of trouble because
remember all these trees or entities all
these points or entities we have a ton
of entities and it's just chewing
through them like it was nothing and we
have done zero to help it so yeah I'm
thinking that we've got so much
processing power to spare you know that
that just I think means this is going to
be the right decision for this game how
we're doing it let's go ahead and zoom
out just to see what the world looks
like in this fashion I'm not super sure
why those aren't simulating I guess it's
just because this guy locked himself up
it looks like the snake trapped this guy
pretty great uh so anyway yeah I think
that's good for now I'm trying to think
if there's anything else I want to do
quickly I just wanted to get a I just
wanted to get a sort of baseline on that
but yeah like I said it is it's it's a
it's a pretty old machine trying to
think if I should do anything else here
if I should just call it there I don't
want to start something that I can't
finish but yeah I guess what I could do
is maybe I could pull out something here
so let's take a look at at some of this
code and see so here's the thing that's
like get closest entity with a brain
with a particular brain type right and
that's probably going to be a pretty
common function right that's probably
going to be something fairly common as
well
so that might want to be pulled out in
addition I'm guessing also these sort of
springy functions are very common and I
feel like those are gonna want to get
pulled out yeah so you know maybe let's
do in the sim region maybe in here just
so we're sort of building up a little
rogues gallery of stuff that is spatial
queries that probably need to be
accelerated you know I could say that
this thing is a get closest entity with
brain or something
and that could be here as a point and
here's the sim region and I'm gonna tell
you what the brain type is and you're
gonna tell me what the result is right
that seems useful because then this
stuff becomes a lot simpler the other
thing we can do is this thing here is
just say like oh what's the radius and
started out that way so yeah and we
could make this a default parameter so
we could say something like oh yeah you
know we'll we'll do a 20 meter radius or
who knows what as our default and so
when people don't care they just get
that radius and if they do care if they
get a different radius right and
probably what I would do is since we
have to compute it anyway I would do
like closest entity thing and I'd say
like let's just give them all the
information did we find one what was it
and what's the closest what's the
distance squared because they may want
that distance squared to do something
with so I feel like that's a good thing
and and we could also give it the Delta
so like since it's doing a bunch of
computations here we might as well
return those computations so that they
don't get duplicated for no reason right
so here's the closest entity result and
I guess I'll just initialize found to
false and I guess closest here oh well
you know I might as well I guess
initialize
them all for now and we'll initialize
the distance squared to that max radius
then in here we can just say like okay
every time we find one we just say that
our result entity is going to be the
test entity our result distance squared
is going to be the test distance squared
and our result Delta is going to be the
test Delta and I'll compute that test
Delta explicitly here rather than as
part of the expression just so we can
save it in case they want it outside so
there's the test Delta the P is not head
P obviously it's just the P that gets
passed in now there's that brain slap
type and I think that's it really yeah
now we're probably going to need to
expand this notion a little bit to
something a little fancier here and this
is obviously always a bit of an
annoyance with C++ you can't pass things
in very easily like closure testing
there and I don't really want to go down
the lambda wrap now but so you know
you'll notice this is being a bit of an
annoyance but for the most part we
should be okay so there's that results
and just squared okay and so in here
what I'm going to do is say well okay
when we do these spatial queries and I'm
doing this whole bit here instead I'm
just gonna call and I realize I'm a
little over time so we'll stop and just
one second I'm just gonna call this and
say closest or whatever equals get close
to sanity that with brain I'll pass the
sim region I'll pass the head P I'll
pass the brain type but I wanted
and and that'll just work right and then
I can do if the closest found well I
guess I don't need the found I guess
it's just the entity pointer I'll do the
closest entity and everything else
should be fine this is that Delta so I
guess I don't have to compute that I
mean that's that's it right there and
yeah we don't actually need this anymore
either
right cuz that's just not necessary with
the race stamping so really all we need
to do is say we need to normalize this
we've got the head P the head occupied
our traversal or spend closest chair
apiece so really this is the only thing
that we need to modify here so and so
then we just kind of cleaned up that
code a little bit and just have it now
have a nice utility and now you know
anyone can ask what the closest thing is
of a particular brain type and off it
goes right so yeah I think we're good
I'll go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
so if you have any questions ask away
Gary Johansson any thoughts on
multi-threading the energy system well
there's there's two things there one is
it depends what you want to multi thread
one thing oh my god in Sopot that's
amazing sorry in sohbat just said
something awesome in the chat anyway
point being there's two things you might
think about multi-threading wise one is
to multi thread the current entity sim
to make it faster my thought on that is
that just seems dumb because we haven't
optimized anything in it yet we're
running literally thousands of entities
through it at this point I guess maybe
not thousands but we're running I'm
we're running like probably a couple
hundred through it and it's literally
not even touching the profile and
release mode so and it's not a six year
old machine so I'm guessing that like
making the entity sims run faster for us
once in region is probably not it's just
probably not gonna be worth it I mean
we'll see maybe when we get to further
down the line there'll be you know more
stuff that that does that so I don't
think that's relevant if we want to
multi thread the entity updates of other
places in the world that he's already
I think free actually I mean I there
might be a couple things we would have
to do like add brain and stuff like that
there's there's some some things we may
have to make sure call atomic adds
rather than regular adds but otherwise
our sim region stuff takes place
entirely inside the sim region so you
can issue you could have all six worker
threads all run a different sim region
and that's there wouldn't they wouldn't
interfere with each other in any way
so the only thing we have to make sure
that we support is when we add new
things we have to make sure that when we
call like get a new when we get a new ID
or things like that we we do those
atomically that'd be it and so we
already are completely mud multi-thread
compatible I think for getting to first
scaling that way and that's kind of
intentional because I wanted to be able
to scale that way so basically if
there's somebody out if there's like you
know more things happening elsewhere in
the world that are very far from the
player so they wouldn't be getting
sinned I want to be able to run separate
threads to keep them siming and so that
is kind of something I would like to do
and so that's kind of a little bit
somewhat conscious the other thing that
we might have to thread in the future
and I don't know is if we have any kind
of really heavyweight AI thing that
happens for some reason like some very
specific kinds of pathfinding that are
expensive or who knows what maybe that's
a place where we would have to start
thinking about how we're gonna deal with
it but you know at the moment you know
nothing for how many more times will you
hit get hit with the texture of the
issue before you actually fix it and
it's just not appropriate to fix it now
right like I said on stream I don't have
the luxury of fixing things when that
are broken when they happen because if
we're in the middle of something I try
to keep it so that the things are
relatively coherent so since it doesn't
cause us any actual problem you know you
just close and and start it again I it
won't be till we go work on the renderer
again
Rome do you have a Mack Sennett account
at the sim region on the debug display
we don't at the moment inside sim region
when we are done so so when we when we
do begin sim in here we should be able
to at the end of the whole thing we
should be able to say edit account and
like I don't know what that value would
be but let's find out so its 740 at the
moment let's walk out to a place where
we'll hit more stuff so 1121 like I said
it's crazy how fast machines are these
days the fact that that in in the in the
release build the fact that that
literally didn't even show up on the
profile in any like it wasn't even 10%
to do 1100 entities at 16 frames a
second is crazy considering all of the
pack unpack we're doing is not a pack
unpack at the moment it's a block copy
but that's just computers are crazy fast
it's why I'm always so annoyed at how
slow the web is because it's ridiculous
how fast computers are you wouldn't
think so if you you know went to use
Gmail but computers are actually very
very very fast
I see no more coding questions
I heard of topic Milton seems to be
treating Wacom input as mouse input
restart Milton will look into it
how are you able to tell this but sure
close Milton
is this better
it sure seems it
all right I think there are no more
program in question so I will go ahead
and close things down or try to close
things there we go
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of handmade hero it's
what a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home you can pre-order the game at
handmade hero Organic come to the source
code even as we speak so you can play
around at home with the game we also
have a forum site if you have questions
about the series and you would like to
talk about mm-hmm set questions we have
a patreon page if you'd like to support
the video series we have a schedule bot
if you want know when we're gonna be
live and we have an episode guide if
you're trying to catch up with past
episodes that is it for today I will be
back for the last stream of this week
tomorrow Friday until then have fun
programming and I will see you guys on
the Internet take it easy everyone