start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero this is the
show where we code a complete game live
on stream and we unfortunately we
finished what we were doing yesterday
which is always it's good to finish
things but it means that we don't really
know what we're doing today right we do
not know what is the most appropriate
thing for us to come back and do so I
don't know what's gonna happen here and
so I'm gonna have to see I'm gonna have
to look at the list and see what we feel
like doing because we have plenty of
options there's plenty of things to do
it's not like we're done by any stretch
of the imagination
but there is a question of what do we
actually want to do here so we we did
some of these things we got rid of the
even scanline notation and we got put in
the sorting which for some reason was
not actually in here it looks like and
so the question is how we want to
proceed
this is our list of kind of everything
we could do right like this is the list
of like everything that could be done in
the game I mean it's not it's not
complete I'm sure but it just was us
listing stuff as we thought of it like
hey we wanted to do this and we need to
do that and so we have a bunch of
different things we could do one thing
we can do is we can go back and finish
our debug code because I'd like to get
that finished at some point we've got
some small things here like debugging
some audio stuff flushes thread that
sort of stuff and I really don't know
what I want to do so I think you know I
I do wonder if it may be time for us to
try to get things into sort of a more
shippable state just in terms of like
being able to clean up because there's
not that much left to do before we're
gonna be basically game like before
we're just making game stuff right most
of all these things are just game you
know right in the actual game and we're
gonna be wanting to play around with the
actual game all through all through
everything that's basically on the other
out of this right and so one thing that
I do wonder is maybe if now is a time to
just bite the bullet go into the win32
platform layer add OpenGL support so
that we can finally go through some
compositing layer that Windows will
actually get us a vsync on so that we
know that we're running at 60 frames a
second or 30 frames a second our choice
and won't have to worry about timing and
accuracy and stuff like that we can
actually get a locked framerate because
I don't really want to be in a position
where I'm gonna be like making things in
the game and testing them out and having
to deal with a non locked framerate now
that also probably means at some point
here I should stop streaming off of this
computer and start streaming off of a
different computer which because I do
have an HDMI capture card because we
bought one to use with handmade con and
so at that point that would be a nice
thing to do too because then we could
actually be testing on a system that
didn't have OBS jumping in and stealing
stuff so I don't know I feel like maybe
win32 platform layer cleanup and having
kind of a thing there that we could say
we could send this to somebody and it
would reasonably play the game so like
clean up the audio code a little clean
up the video code so it's at least going
through OpenGL for just at least the
final compositing if not the the whole
renderer like we don't have to actually
make the whole renderer go that way if
we don't want to do that right now but
at least getting it so that we have a
vsync that maybe seems like a good idea
to me
I don't know uh so I may just I just I
may just do that I mean I may say that
that's what we want to do that just
seems like an idea to me so anyway if we
want to do that here we are back in our
win32 and we wrote kind of some of the
stuff that we might want here I like the
threading is still on there of course we
actually did that I guess we don't ever
update our to-do lists we just do stuff
off them and you know there we go
and so this one right here which is
hardware acceleration I'm basically
saying like you know let's go ahead
and move these guys up here and and
start take a look at those I'm trying to
see if there's anything else here that's
relevant I don't know if asset loading
path I think we might consider that done
too because we're not really gonna do
anything more with that than what we
already did probably I feel like so yeah
maybe that's right anyway so yeah I'm
saying maybe we do some of this here I
just thought so let me give you a little
bit of a background over sir just so you
can kind of understand what I would be
about to do since I think that's what
I'm leaning towards doing so see if you
can cast your mind back if you will to
the olden days when we were just 250
hours of programming back in the past
when we sat down to get ourselves
something we could work with on win32 so
that we could write all the stuff we did
like the renderer is an audio system the
asset loading and all that stuff that
we've written in between then and now
and you'll remember we get called in
this function called win main this is
where our program starts up and if you
remember what we do at some point after
we kind of get ourselves set up here and
we did a thing with fading in and out
but we create a window in that window is
what we use to draw right so you know
we've kind of got this weird fade thing
happening now mm-hmm
I believe this was mid blows fault he
was like I want I want to fade in and
out from the Windows desktop I don't
know why you wanted to we just wanted to
so we've got this thing where you like
fade in and out like that and and I
think you can even escape out yeah so it
fades in and out it does both directions
right so that's you know that's sort of
a little extra sauce on top that we did
but in general the only important part
is so we have I guess the reason I
mention that because we have a window
that basically does the the in-and-out
fade for us that's a separate window
that we use to just black out the screen
but the actual window we care about is
this window right here we create this
window
and we then make it fullscreen right so
we make it the size of the whole screen
it's not set to visible so it's
invisible it takes it all scream that's
not visible later we switch it to
visible and then we start doing blitz to
it and that's how we display our game
okay so what we need to do if we want to
use OpenGL or direct3d for that matter
but either way we have additional work
that we need to do now we need to be
able to set up our window in a way that
tells windows we're going to be using
the 3d hardware right and the first part
of this is actually pretty simple and
that's just linking to remember we did
this thing here we listed here are the
windows services that we call right so
remember what these these guys were
these are not the kinds of libraries
that you normally think of where that
the functions are actually in the
libraries these are called import
libraries and what they do is they allow
us to call through to the Windows
operating system services that we need
so user 32 dot Lib has the stuff like
create window so we need to a separate
system for a window that's in there
GDI 32 has like the graphics things like
get device caps and that sort of stuff
would be in there for example and we mmm
had what we needed that for one specific
thing which was setting the clock that
the timer resolution the for the for the
for the window scheduler right so so far
that's all we've needed to use and
you'll notice nothing in there or I
should say nothing in those three import
libraries connects us with the part of
the operating system that talks to 3d
graphics hardware now we're on top of
Windows so there's no way we can hand
code this we can't talk to the graphics
ourself Windows is the guy who's got the
access to the hardware we have to go
through it and so what we need to do is
add one import library that's going to
give it that to us now we could add
DirectX we could add OpenGL I'm gonna
add OpenGL because it's the more
cross-platform version of the two so
what we learn here on how to start it up
in Windows is not gonna help you
anywhere else but what if we actually do
our rendering through it everything that
we
do their will apply on every platform
that OpenGL works you know like so you
can apply this on Mac and I'm Linux
which i think is a lot better for an
instructional series that seems like a
much smarter way to go because it's
something you could use no matter what
platform you're on not just this one so
the as you might have guessed from the
sort of naming convention here other
than win mmm live OpenGL 32 dot lib is
actually the name of the library that
you need if you want to link it to call
the 3d graphics hardware through OpenGL
if we compile with this we'll see that
we just get linked nothing happens right
nothing actually occurs of note yet
because we haven't actually done
anything and so if I run the game you
know everything's still the same the
only difference like I saying before
literally the only difference there is
now we have the ability to call the
operating system functions that OpenGL
has and similarly like we had to do this
to bring in these things like direct
sound the next input and so on we have
to include an OpenGL header and in this
case I believe it's gah
and there you go so what that does is
that brings in all the opengl functions
that we might need so now we can talk to
opengl just like we had to include
things like windows h2 call the other
platform AP is an x input that age to
call the X input api's now there's
obviously more than one way we could
call it if you remember 4x input and
direct sound the way that we actually
called those at least I believe direct
sound is that true for direct sound yeah
4x input in direct sound you'll notice
we did late binding here so what we did
is instead of linking to those import
libraries directly we manually called
get proc address right and there's a
very good reason for that with X input
for example it may not be on the machine
so if we were to cold link to X input as
a library like a dot Lib when our
executable loads if X input was not
installed in that machine we would fail
to load and we don't want to do that
OpenGL on the other hand has the
nice property of having shipped with
Windows since the beginning like Windows
NT three five one
the oldest branch back you can go for
this strain of Windows remember we're on
the empty branch we're not on the
windows 95 windows 3-1 we're not on that
branch around the windows 1.0 branch
that died with Windows ME that was the
last version of that type of Windows
that shipped so all the way back to the
very first version windows 3 5 one had
OpenGL support in it so it's totally
safe to link with OpenGL and use the
basic OpenGL functions now you can't
guarantee that all of the opengl
functions in the most modern OpenGL will
be there because that depends on how new
the graphics card and how new the
drivers are so it doesn't mean you can
just call any old thing in OpenGL that
you want because there are lots of
extensions to open jill's over the years
there's OpenGL 1.0 2.0 3.0 4.0 sr 4.3
whatever right so when I say that it's
been there through the beginning I mean
the basic OpenGL 1 point to support
probably or might have been one point
one support I don't remember the first
version was might even be just one point
now I don't know but the basic stuff is
all in there so the stuff that we need
to do to set up OpenGL in its in its
limited form for example just to do like
a blitt to the screen which is all we
will probably do it first that stuff we
can always just call other things and
you'll see this if we decide to move the
renderer over a sooner rather than later
other things require a more sensitive
approach if we want to call the more
advanced features OpenGL we have to take
a more approach that is a lot more like
the dynamic loading approach that we
took with these other ones here so
alright so there's our GLH and now what
we need to do is we need to get us into
a position where we can actually use the
opengl stuff on our window so if you
remember how we did direct sound
right I don't know if you recall how we
did that when we do direct sound like
there's this sort of initialization
process right we had to load the library
I'm saying we don't need to do that for
OpenGL it's okay to hard bind to it
because like user 32 and that sort of
stuff it's something that will always be
there so when our executables loaded and
it looks for the Opera in system
services they will always be there it's
just a question of which version but
they'll always be there and then we had
to do this stuff like direct sound
create a sec rapido level this exact
thing if you're you remember how we did
that where we had to kind of go through
these steps and that's exactly what we
have to do to initialize OpenGL now the
process is so janky that I am probably
not going to remember how to do it
correctly now you've seen me program
windows on the stream a lot and I am
remarkably successful in this series at
not having messed up too many things in
the Windows layer right which is odd
like normally you have to go digging
through lots of people's tutorial code
and I haven't had to do that yet I think
that's just because we're importing
waited so long I will be shocked shocked
I tell you if I can get through the full
initialization of open jail even vanilla
without having to resort to looking at
some sample code I'll be shocked but who
knows and it's not because there's that
many steps it's just because the steps
are bizarre alright so we're gonna
follow exactly that thing that we had
before just just exactly like this where
we have essentially a win32 init opengl
right I'm just gonna make a function
here and I'm just I'm not gonna think
too hard about it like this I'm just
gonna put them in here cuz we've got a
lot of stuff in this file I don't want
it to mush it into anything and get lost
in it so I'm just gonna just start by
saying all right we've got a window and
I need this window to to have an open
jail thing attached to it alright so
let's talk a little bit about the OpenGL
model so before I start that and have to
deal with the pain and suffering of
trying to remember exactly how it goes
let's just talk about OpenGL
on Windows okay so OpenGL is a graphics
API it was defined as a attempt to make
a public spectacle I receive I believe
is the case of it or is it i Rick's GL
basically there was just a thing called
essentially GL was all it was called
from a company called Silicon Graphics
now if you don't know what Silicon
Graphics was you could be forgiven they
don't really exist anymore but what they
were was way back before anyone really
was ever talking about even the concept
that a personal computer a home computer
would have 3d graphics acceleration
because that's just a fanciful dream
back in the 80s let's say right Silicon
Graphics was a company that specialized
in building hardware accelerated 3d
graphics so what they did is they
produced workstations high-end
workstations very very expensive that
had 3d acceleration Hardware in them and
this Hardware could do remarkable
amazing never-before stuff that you
could ever have dreamt on a PC like
filling a triangle with a solid color
and yet if you set yourself back that
far you know there were about people
Evans &amp; Sutherland these people making
hardware that did stuff like filling
solid triangles at a fast rate remember
these are the old days that was
remarkable and difficult and then as
time progressed they did more more
stupid texture mapping hardware and
that's our stuff and really all of what
we now think of as stuff that you plug
into the GPU you know the extension slot
that basically is only used for GPU now
right the PCI Express whatever all of
that stuff Nvidia and went back when we
have 3d effects and all that stuff most
of it came out of this most of it is is
because of these guys in fact Nvidia and
3d effects the old 3d effects one of the
first you know the one of the first
add-on cards for PC the first was
actually by selling graphics that I know
about but what was my 3d effects and
NVIDIA
all X SGI guys write Silicon Graphics
was SGI Silicon Graphics Incorporated I
think is what it was but and so they
really basically what they did is people
at these that this company you know they
saw that the future was probably going
to be 3d on the PC because it was
getting cheap enough now to do and they
left looking graphics and they started
making add-on cards and hey this company
eventually went away because the add-on
cards for PC became so powerful there
was never now there was no need to ever
buy us dedicated workstation because
these things were just as good and
eventually better right so anyway what
OpenGL was was it was their graphics API
they had a graphics API that you used to
talk to the silicon graphics hardware at
the workstations it was called GL I
believe I can't quite remember
and I think iris GL was just a name that
you would oftentimes used to it because
they the iris was the name of one of
their product lines I believe right
there were different names there's the
onyx the iris there were different names
of the workstations and so what happened
was Silicon Graphics eventually and I
don't really know why don't I I'm not
really familiar with the politics of
this company I don't know very much
about what happened in those days you'd
have to ask someone who worked there but
they wanted to make a more open standard
so that people would program to this
graphics language and then you know that
would be good for them because that
meant that any programs that were
written to that if you compiled them and
ran the last lemongrass bean they'd run
really fast right because they have
hardware acceleration for all the stuff
that's in this geo and so what GL was
was a way of talking essentially to
graphics hardware back then and really
all it was meant to do was draw like
lines and felt solid triangles and
eventually some texture mapping that was
it there was absolutely no concept of
shaders or compute or any of that stuff
that's all new stuff that was never in
the original the original was just very
very basic stuff okay so what happened
with OpenGL is it bifurcated into two
sort of halves and for obvious reasons
when this becomes OpenGL and they create
a committee for maintaining the standard
and they make it a stain
obviously now Silicon Graphics machines
are not the only machines running GL
what that means is there needs to be
sort of two halves to OpenGL few will
write the platform-specific part and the
platform-independent part right and when
you refer to OpenGL really this is the
part you're talking about and that's
things like if you've ever seen stuff
like a call to GL vertex 3f or something
like this or GL clear right
the platform-independent part is the
part that's all the calls that you're
used to seeing when you if you've ever
read anything about OpenGL if you
haven't that's okay you don't need to
know it I'm gonna be telling you
anything that you need to know about it
but if you've seen it before that's what
the platform different independent
artists the platform specific part is
how you get opengl like up and running
on your platform and the reason this
can't be automated is because who knows
what you're trying to do with it how
many windows do you have in your app
that need OpenGL support are you trying
to blit to one of them or the other one
of them does this platform even have the
concept of a window who knows right so
that's very specific to the platform so
what they decide to do here is just not
specify it right so when you say OpenGL
you're really never talking about this
because they never bothered to spec any
of it it's just left up to the
implementation on any given platform to
decide how you want to handle that right
and the OpenGL committee does have sort
of a way of issuing standards for
different platforms for the platform
specific part if you want and that does
sort of happen in a separate way but for
the most part the OpenGL part is this
part and this part is really up to the
platform people how they end up specking
it out how it tends to go right all
right so this the non OpenGL part if you
will is the part we actually care about
today and the way that that works on
Windows is they have a set of API
that are prefixed with wgl for Windows
GL and there's a bunch of functions like
w GL swap buffers I think is one of them
is it GL swap buffers RW yeah it's w GL
swap buffers right hello so no it's not
they did not prefixes that's why I was I
was trying to remember and I was gonna I
was gonna say it looks wrong to me it's
like I don't think it's there and and I
guess it's not there
so swap buffers isn't thought that way I
take it back
so it's more like a better example would
be wiggle make current that one I am
sure of they did prefix I'm pretty sure
almost all the time it's actually
prefixed but swap buffers is just
anomalistic so there you go that's an
example of one right okay so that's the
part that we care about here all right
so you remember it we'll hope you
remember from our windows programming
there's a thing called a DC right a
device context and a device context is
just like a handle basically or I
shouldn't say handle it's a notion in
Windows of the state of the graphics at
that time so it's storage stuff like oh
you know what's the coordinate transform
of the stuff I'm drawing now what's the
active pen color you know mode stuff
like that right and so we have things
called HD C's which are handles to a DC
to one of these and we would always pass
those around right remember we'd say
like oh we got address something we
gotta get a handle to the DC that we're
gonna draw into then we use it and then
we release the handle right we had a
bunch of stuff like that
well OpenGL has a very equivalent
compact concept it's called it OpenGL
it's an OpenGL RC I believe Open GL RC
let me let me
yeah it's I can't remember what that
stands for is it a rendering colors yet
okay so there it is rendering context
I'm just like I remembered it was our se
but remember there's OpenGL RC and
basically what happens is this OpenGL RC
sort of sits on top of this not
implementation wise inside windows
because who knows right I've never been
privy to that code but I mean
conceptually to the user so what has to
happen is once you have a device context
you need to piggyback an OpenGL
rendering context on top of that and
once you have an OpenGL rendering
context then you can issue your OpenGL
calls now there's a caveat there's a
caveat in Windows and I can just sort of
show you this example here let's take
Phil rect right it's how we might clear
a rectangle in in Windows GDI right
you'll notice Phil rec takes as a first
parameter a handle to the device context
that you are trying to clear right you
can see that it's right there so what I
want to clear something in Windows I say
okay Phil rect
with a particular HTC write whatever you
know my DC or something right and
whatever I want to do and then it knows
whatever this is targeting that's what
gets filled so that's on some window
somewhere and so it knows if there's two
windows on the screen and they both
belong to me and I say Phil rekt my DC
it knows that whichever one my DC points
to that's the window where the filling
takes place right but what you will
notice very quickly when you look at
OpenGL if we were to look at say for
example GL clear which is the thing that
clears a buffer in OpenGL again don't
need to know this it will get to it all
later when it becomes relevant you will
notice that it takes no such thing the
only thing that you pass to GL clear is
a bit field that says what you want
cleared the color buffer the depth
buffer the accumulation buffer the
stencil buffer so if you have two
windows or two buffers how do you know
what to clear
and the answer is that the whole state
of the GL is actually implicit to your
thread so you remember we had threads
right in Windows there are the things
that we lack securing all at the same
time right if we have multiple cores
each one can be operating different
thread so like for example we had our
background rendering or our background
loading those are on different threads
right and then we have the main thread
which is doing most of the work so a
thread is a single unit of execution
right that's happening on some core
somewhere or it's suspended who knows
but it's you know it's a state right
each thread has implicit to it in OpenGL
RC so anytime a thread issues in OpenGL
call it must have previously established
which OpenGL RC it is talking about and
in fact I already mentioned the call
that does that
wiggle make current basically what
wiggle make current does is it sets what
the OpenGL RC is for your thread so what
we need to do in order to get our opengl
up and running even just in a
rudimentary sense or our first goal will
be to just like clear the screen with
opengl right that'll that's all we're
gonna try to do will clear the screen to
some hideous pink so we don't worked so
in order to do that with opengl what we
need to be able to do is we need to be
able to create one of these OpenGL
rendering contexts and then after we do
that we need to be able to establish
that it is the one for the thread
whichever thread in the system we want
it's the one for that thread that will
display it to the screen so whoever's
doing the OpenGL calls that thread has
to establish it as its context so
hopefully that makes some sense again
not too complicated it's basically
setting a bacterial system we have
Windows as DC idea and now we're
essentially putting something on top of
that which is this OpenGL RC okay so
yeah
we start out as you might expect with
wiggle create context is a call that
will allow us to make one of these
OpenGL rendering context and you can
kind of see there so HD LRC is Windows
term for an OpenGL rendering context
handle right handle to a GL RC and so
that's exactly what we need
so this is our opengl RC we need to do a
rittle create context and then you can
see right here that we have to pass it
that HDC that weeks that were that you
know it's it's sitting on top of right
so we need to do a get DC from the
window potentially that we're calling to
we need to get that TC and I believe I
can release the DC I don't think we ever
need to hold on to it we just need it
temporarily so it can be associated with
the window I believe that's true
we'll find out in a second look I said
hard to remember all these things but so
we get that EC we create a context off
of that DC and then we would need to
make it so that this thread actually has
that context sort of active right so we
do a wiggle make current and again that
wiggle make current is just to associate
it with the thread because just the act
of creating it it doesn't know whether
you actually want to use that one or if
you just try to create one to have it
and maybe you're creating multiple or
something right so that takes the DC and
the RC ok so this obviously has a
boolean that it returns so we expect
this to be true if it's not we might
want to go ahead and do a diagnostic
here but it's probably never going to
fail but we could the very least right
now say like invalid code path right so
I'm gonna compile that and at this point
this would be you know success in theory
now there's a there's a caveat here
right because that looks way too simple
right it's like Oh Casey you said this
tunic op kadia there's no way you were
ever gonna get it right and yet there
it's that's so trivial what could be
easier than what you've just typed in
well I'm gonna go ahead and go a little
further maybe just so we can maybe test
this guy or whatever and show you that
this doesn't work because there's a
bunch of stuff we actually have to do to
make this work so I wish it were that
easy it's not that easy this call
basically won't actually do what we want
it to do and we'll get into why that is
a little bit later so let me just finish
up this quickly and then you'll see but
if you're if you're thinking in your
head right now what was he talking about
trust me it it gets worse it sounds
alright so if we call win thirty
thirty-two in it open jail then we will
have an open GL context now what we need
to do here is we need to actually do
something where we'd actually be able to
see it working and so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to take where we do all
the rest of our stuff like our swap
buffers sort of our stuff where we like
present so I believe we have our stretch
we have like a stretch di bits win32
display buffering window this thing
right this win32 display buffering
window right now is taking that off
screen buffer the cat draw and it's
going ahead and it's putting it out to
the screen I'm gonna go ahead and
disable all of that right now and so
what happens if I run this is we should
get you know our game should disappear
so we should have our fade and there's
just garbage or whatever blackness who
knows what is there right so then I'm
going to insert some OpenGL in here now
this is very simple the basis of the
really easy part about this I'm just
going to set some things and again you
don't have to pay too much attention to
these but I'll kind of go through it
each of their art and we'll cover them
in more detail later when we actually do
a render path with OpenGL but I'm just
going to sort of show you the three
steps we need to show something on the
screen so first of all we have GL clear
color and what GL clear color does is it
establishes what color will be used for
clearing the screen and basically we
just pass it it's it's exactly like
you've seen before all the
the stuff we've done it just passes a
floating point value for red green blue
and alpha that's the destination alpha
Channel so in the in the frame buffer
remember we had in our frame buffer we
had a 32-bit frame buffer with 8 bits
for alpha red green blue right and we
often times talked about them and
operate them on floats but then we
converted them down to eight but the
exact same thing is true for OpenGL in
the clear color we can set what colors
we want in a floating point sense so we
can say oh I want to set it to like
purple right or something like that
right
Mississippi alpha zero so I'll set it to
like a bright ugly a nice ugly bright
purple or something and what that'll do
is it says that's the color we're going
to be clearing with and then when I go
to clear it will automatically one of
the things about OpenGL is it's a little
bit higher level it's not that low level
of a graphics API I mean it is a little
level but it's not that low level it's
not like mantle or something where it's
you know trying to target a sort of a
specific graphics card format right so
OpenGL does some things for you so for
example when we do GL clear it doesn't
matter what format the back buffer
actually is that you're clearing it'll
automatically convert the color down to
whatever that is and then fill it with
that right so GL does do some stuff for
you if that makes sense
and that's some of the things it does so
that's that's that and then we have the
GL clear call we just say what we want
to clear now I would like to clear
everything oops that's not what I wanted
to click but the only thing we actually
care about at the moment is the color
buffer because we're not really using
any other buffers we're not using any of
these other buffers so I can just say
hey it's the GL color buffer bit
that just means clear the color buffer
if you have other buffers we haven't
talked about any of these are so you
don't care and neither do I at this
point but these are other buffers like
this the depth buffer is a Z buffer what
we call Z buffer right the accumulation
buffer is an old opengl thing that you
don't even use anymore and the stencil
buffer is a thing for a very specific
raster ops there's tons of reasons why I
exist and we won't even go into him I
don't even know if we'll ever even
talk about them hammer here but point
being color buffer is the actual
displayed colors that we want to show on
the screen and so here's some OpenGL
that makes that happen
okay so we have GL clear color that sets
the clear color we have GL clear which
says the the buffer bit that does much
like we do drawing to a off-screen
buffer so it's going to do those
operations potentially on some memory
that we can't actually see and the way
that you bring that into the to actually
display that to the window is you call
swap buffers which says hey go ahead and
display whatever it was you were
displaying but in order to that I
believe we have to give it a the the DC
that we're trying to swap with I think
yeah that's it
and so then we just say ok display that
now again there's a little more business
we probably want to do here just to make
sure things are just a little more a
little more correct and that is there's
also a notion in OpenGL of what region
of the screen that you're drawing to
write and that is done with this
function called GL viewport and what GL
viewport does is it just defines the
boundaries of what you're trying to
render right and so really we just want
to clear the whole screen so we would
just say hey you know what guys we're
just gonna go from zero zero to width
height and that's it but that right
there is roughly the correct GL for pick
a region of the screen to render set
what color I want to clear it to clear
it and we'll call that done for now
display it on the screen okay now give
me I'm going into too much detail but
exactly what happens with those but
that's the basic idea
alright so now every time we go to
display something instead of doing the
stuff we're routing before it'll do that
however unless I'm very much mistaken
this will not show us a pink screen so
you can see that we have no such pink
screen to speak up why is that well this
is where it starts getting into the
stuff for hours like yeah it's not
as easy as you might like first of all
well I guess that's not fair we should
have we have to at least call the
function so let me call the function and
then we'll still won't draw a pink and
and then I can say what I just said so
let's go down to where we want to put
this once we create the window obviously
then we'd be ready to to initialize up a
jail on it so let's go ahead and do that
okay perfect even better so we don't
even get past the initialization presume
lis that's because we couldn't create
the RCD yes so that's great that that
illustrates it even better than not
seeing pink you can just see that it
didn't work
so why didn't it work wouldn't it be
great if it worked yes but why didn't
work well the reason it didn't work is
because for reasons which nowadays I
would say are very legacy back in the
old days there was a lot more
optimization around things regarding
graphics in terms of like the format of
what was on screen and what was stored
because memory was very expensive you
didn't have infinity of it like you did
now memory bandwidth was very expensive
you couldn't just go around having
everything be 32-bit color all the time
and all this stuff and so in the old
days you used to have stuff like Windows
could run in a palletized graphics mode
for example right like Windows could run
in an 8-bit color mode where there was a
color table and each pixel was only
eight bits of data and it could go and
like look in a color table to see what
color that 8 bits referred to right so
it's a palette 'add you know like a pet
like a color palette I mean heck it used
to run in a 16 color mode right and so
when you were actually hooking these up
in the old days it was important to tell
windows before you actually tried to do
OpenGL rendering to a window what kind
of display you were actually trying to
accomplish what kind of pixels you were
actually thinking you were gonna a store
in the back buffer for OpenGL and B
display in the actual like
the actual window itself and so what you
have to do is a thing called set pixel
format now if I remember correctly we
started about 15 minutes late so I've
got about 20 minutes we might be able to
get this done
we might not so I think it's called set
DC pixel for ya there it is
so what you have to do here is you have
to go through a ridiculous dance to
figure out what quote-unquote pixel
format you are going to set your DC to
for OpenGL to use it for rendering and
you can see by this descriptor that it
is not a fun thing to do basically what
you're trying to do is set up all of the
possible information you might need now
do if you remember from when we did
bitmaps remember like green shift red
shift that sort of stuff
where we were talking about where like
what the mask was for where the bits
were and what the shift was well this is
that times 10 right now you've got the
RGB x' and you got the accumulation
buffer and the depth and stencil buffers
these other buffers that I said we don't
even really care about right now all of
that stuff has to be specified right but
yes it would be straightforward if all
we had to do is fill one of these out
because then we just fill out whatever
we wanted we'd say here's where we want
the red here's to run three here so the
blue go nuts but that's not what this is
what this is is actually a way of
selecting from the format's that OpenGL
and and GDI currently support okay so
you have to imagine this more as like a
negotiation process where we have
something we want which is a 32-bit RGB
a buffer right an OpenGL the graphics
library and the card that it's that's
it's running on can only support certain
ways of dealing with pixels because it's
hardware it's graphics hardware it's not
completely arbitrary
right mm-hmm so it's actually a
negotiation so we actually don't make
one of these what we do instead is we
try to find one of these right and in
order to find one of these we need to
use these other functions here right and
so what these are choose and describe
right is describe pixel format will if
we go through all of the pixel formats
right describe pixel format allows us to
pass an index and say what is pixel
format 0mr operating system and it will
come back and say oh here is the pixel
format descriptor for that thing right
this giant mess of nightmare okay and
furthermore then we'd go okay what's
pixel format 1 what's - what's 3 right
and we ask until I believe I don't even
know if we can get how many there are I
think we just keep asking until there's
no more left right until it says I can't
give you one is that true yeah I'm
pretty sure that's true so basically we
just keep asking until it tells us that
we couldn't get one so we just ask ask
ask ask ask ask ask and we would get all
the pixel formats that are there and
we'd see whether there was one that that
fit what we what we wanted right that's
one way we could do it the other way we
can do it is to ask the operating system
to try to find the pixel format it has
that most closely matches something we
pass in right and that's the one that
I'm gonna choose because I seem to
recall that that works fairly reliably
right and so what we do is we fill out
some small part of this we ask it to
pick the closest thing it can find and
then we hope it comes back with a with a
yes that it found one
all right you can see why I say that
this is easy to forget how to do it
right so here is one of these things
these pixel format descriptors what we
need to do is we need to first set our
DC to that so here it is a pixel format
descriptor right and we're just going to
have this is our pixel format this is
our desired pixel format let's say we
initialize it to 0 we now have to set up
the ones that it says that we need
so here's choose pixel format and here's
what how we have to set it up the N size
is obviously the size of the data
structure this is that stupid thing that
Windows does that's absolutely useless
that has literally never helped them a
single time which is that you have to
say how big the struct is so that you
know in case it gets like extended later
or something like that right then we
have an inversion which this is the the
version number because in case that
wasn't enough and of course there's only
ever been one version and it's that one
right there we go we then have the flags
and for the flags these we do need to
set appropriately because we need to ask
it to support OpenGL rendering and here
is that flag right there as you can see
like I said this was built into windows
open jail with despite the fact that
direct3d is there like thing that they
push on every one OpenGL was the
original graphics API built into Windows
3d graphics API direct3d was a much
later edition so we need that right we
need to be able to do OpenGL rendering
and we also need to be able to draw to a
window because we are not just
compositing some back buffer that we're
gonna read like this you can imagine
starting up OpenGL or an HDC that was
just for like rendering into a bitmap
that you were gonna like save to a file
or something and you never display it to
a window right but we actually need that
to happen right and furthermore we want
double buffering we want our window to
be able to draw to a back buffer and
then present to the front buffer right
so I believe we also want that specified
okay
so that's what we need our if it smart
to be see color bits is zero greater we
want to have 32-bit color right that's
what we're trying to display here so we
want 32 color bits and then I think
let's see not use not news to your
Creator so then we have alpha bits oh so
I guess not
color bits is probably not inclusive of
alphabets so this is probably just 24
and then we want our alpha bits to be 8
we don't care about any of the rest of
these we don't need an accumulation
buffer a depth of or sample buffer or an
auxilary buffer at all we don't need any
of the layer values this is for doing
stuff like overlays which they supported
in the old days back when hardware was
slower and they needed to do like
overlays it at Hardware time it's like
this that that's not a relevant at all
so we're just saying that we're just the
main plain that the main graphics that's
being displayed that's completely
meaningless value at this point and that
I think is what we need according to
that piece of documentation anyway is
what it wants us to do right so we do
our choose pixel format like so and
choose pixel format takes the HDC and
the pixel format descriptor that we're
trying to match and it returns us an
integer that's which pixel format right
so this is the like suggested pixel
format index that it's going to give us
back that's what it thinks we should use
and so again we guess I should put this
up here because we need our DC so it's
the window DC and we gotta pass the
address LexA format that in theory picks
one for us and then we have to set it up
so we have to then say all right set
pixel format on the DC the one that we
got back right we need to set so we say
okay here's the window DC I would like
you to take the one that you told me you
were gonna that you wanted to use I need
you to use that one but unfortunately as
you can see we also have to point it the
pixel to the pixel format specification
now here's the problem we don't know
what the pixel format specification is
right we don't know it told us back in
session 1 it might have nothing to do
with when we pass in we have no idea
we just hope it had 24 and eight in it
right but we never gave it we don't even
have a fully formed one of these we just
have the half filled out one that it
told us to pass it for this so what we
need to do in addition is to make
another pixel format descriptor here
that's like the suggested pixel format
and that is one that we will get from
Windows itself and say hey that thing
you just told me was the right one to
use could you actually go ahead and
describe it for me
right and that's what describe pixel
format does so we pass in the DC that
we're talking about we take the integer
that's the that represents which picks
for - cuz again these just indexed in
the operating system for this particular
instantiation of OpenGL and and and I'm
that gel of GDI so we just need to go
ahead and say okay that one that you
told us whichever one that is that's the
one I want to hear about we've got n
bytes and that says how big the the
thing that we're pointing at here is
right and it won't write past that and
so then we just say like okay obviously
it's it's whatever the size of that opes
it's whatever the size of this was is
how much you're allowed to write in
there and there you go
so we asked if the pics the pixel format
that matches this for the most part we
asked it to describe the one that depict
we then just turn around and hand that
directly back to it and say hey want to
go ahead and do that all right
so that actually sets us up to be able
to open to do OpenGL rendering if that
makes sense
oops got my ampersand and like I said I
probably just I'm not remembering all
the things that I have to do so that may
not be enough but hey that's some magic
stuff you had to know by being a Windows
programmer how would you know that
because you just know the magic of
Windows so here we go let's go ahead
step through this so you can kind of see
because I know that was just a bunch of
randomness that I had to tell you just
then and there's really not a lot of
rhyme or reason for it so here's our
desired pixel form I can see that we
didn't set anything up in fact we want
24-bit color plus an 8-bit alpha Channel
right there
and we have the version and the flag set
and then the size of the structure is 40
we then go ahead and say hey why don't
you pick one for us and that's going to
give us back the suggested pixel format
at the moment it's just gonna say index
2 but as soon as we call describe pixel
format it should fill out this struct
with whatever that paper format was so
there it is so the one we got has a
bunch of random Flags don't know what
they are we could try to test for them
if you want to don't really care the
color bits is 32 so that suggests to me
that maybe the alpha-bits is actually is
included in here so I'm gonna go ahead
and say that we actually should pass a
32 to that then and is it documented
maybe it's docked let's just
double-check does this say number
Culbertson use prefer to be the close of
the color buffer excluding the Alpha bit
planes so do they just straight up not
follow their own documentation it kind
of looks like that doesn't it it says
excluding
I don't know what to make of that it
says right in it that it's excluding
well anyway I'm gonna go ahead and say
to do okay see hey Raymond Chen what's
the deal here is see color bits actually
supposed to exclude the alphabets like
the docs like MSDN says or not because
it's pretty clearly not doing that when
we come back in here so I don't know but
anyway you can see that what happened
when we actually did this is that we got
back a 32-bit color thing which is what
we wanted
it's got our G B and a like we wanted
but you'll notice that it also decided
to just give us some free buffers it
gave us a 24-bit depth buffer and an
8-bit stencil buffer it just gave them
to us
and that's presumably because this
Hardware only knows how to do that I
guess I don't know who knows why that's
what it shows so that's what we got so
we got extra buffers we don't care we
won't use them but we have them ok so
then we say set pixel format oops
no we don't because I've actually added
some code there alright so then we'd say
say pixel set pixel format which which
sets our window up to use it and then we
say we will make current and hey it
actually works now so that we actually
have an OpenGL context right and hey so
I guess when I said that I was never
gonna get it right I guess I actually
did get it right that was pure luck
it's been a long time since I've written
any OpenGL startup code but I guess we
lucked out today so anyway that's OpenGL
startup in a nutshell that is basically
all you really need to know about it but
there is one
potential problem here that I guess I'm
not sure if it's a problem or not
we could kind of see if it is or if it
isn't I guess I don't know I'm guessing
that the fade in yet so the fade in does
not work anymore and that's not that
surprising to me because OpenGL I think
kind of just isn't gonna listen to the
on top window stuff necessarily as much
would be my guess
let me see yeah so all the like overlay
window stuff just stops working as soon
as OpenGL is in the mix right so yeah
that fade in fade out stuff we will
probably have to put the fade in if
midlow is still adamant about having the
fade in part that's gonna have to be in
the game proper which is not a big deal
but just so you know that's that's what
that's that's how that's gonna have to
roll but that's it that's how you start
up OpenGL and so once you've got that
you can now actually do just any OpenGL
you want there is one caveat which is if
you want to access opengl 3.0 or 4.0 you
have to do an extended context creation
call so after you do create context you
then have to do a wiggle create context
a trib call which maybe we'll do a
little later on if we decide we want to
do OpenGL rendering but that's the
basics of getting it working and once
you do that you can make any OpenGL
calls that you want so let's go ahead
and go to the Q&amp;A
funny the pink didn't show up on the
stream OBS problem yeah I guess it can't
capture up in jail
Connor rents we all just saw a black
screen out of pink screen uh so I guess
what I'll do is I'll switch over to
using the capture card it's probably
what I'll do and and we'll just go from
there
Cubert Caleb according to this you
should use 32 for the color bit yeah I
mean so as far as I can it looked pretty
clear to me that the docks are just
wrong because we looked at what came
back and it came back we passed 24 it
came back 32 so there ain't no such
thing and it was it was 32 with 8 bits
of alpha and and there no graphics card
is gonna prefer 32 bits of color plus 8
bits of alpha for a 30 for a 40 bit
color buffer that's not a thing I mean
it's not that you couldn't do it but
it's not gonna be the thing that's going
to default to right so I'm pretty sure
that those docks are just wrong
pretty sure
gary johansson curious at the CPU or the
GPU actually communicates the
information to the screen I feel you
mentioned this I forgot so I'm not sure
to mean by information to the screen
I don't exactly what that means in your
mind but what I will say is that what's
happening at the moment is that what's
the CPU is packaging up a buffer
essentially of commands and those
commands are then transferred to the GPU
over the PCI bus where it executes them
within a reasonable amount of slop
that's what's going on
so the clearing does not happen on the
CPU the clear to pink actually happens
on the GPU but telling it the CPU like
packages up the commands to tell it to
clear to pink and then the GPU executes
that right is roughly what's happening 1
2 1 3 I see what are your thoughts about
Vulcan not a fan but can't talk about it
specifically because it's not out yet I
don't think I have to wait till I can
actually talk about it SSS McGrath if
you're ever in the mood to do a
straight-up unrelated tutorial stream IO
completion ports would be great because
I ain't reading about that star star
star presumably that was a four-letter
word that was removed yeah I mean I got
so much stuff to stream that I don't
know that that's gonna happen but
they're a good API you should read about
them it's the one API in Windows that's
actually good what do you think of
NVIDIA GeForce just what do you think of
NVIDIA GeForce does not clear memory no
idea what that means
Elvin came in late do we have our own GL
function pointers loaded now no not yet
because we are only using at the moment
OpenGL one point X basically because all
we had to do all we have to do is start
rendering OpenGL is just use the ones
that's actually built directly in
windows for always but but at some point
if we do just putting our bitmap on the
screen will not require any function
pointers for up in jail but if we want
to take advantage of like open jail 4.0
stuff or something we would need or 3.0
stuff we would need function pointers
insofar as Tricolore other than pink OBS
might treat that as transparent I think
it's not gonna capture I think I could
set it to capture I'd have to set it to
OpenGL capture or something but I'm not
gonna put through a capture card so we
don't have to care anymore
that'll also get us out of the business
of having this nonsense where there's
always an 11% load on the CPU like all
the time or whatever
/ AC do you know why they deprecated GL
underscore alpha what are what are you
referring to what what GL alpha are you
referring to what API are you talking
about no VIN you don't need to describe
pixel format call since when you use
choose pixel format it modifies your
desired pixel format with the correct
stuff oh just is that true all right I
did not remember that at all so you're
saying that when I do this it will just
open wait why did it not wanna why was
it not saying my breakpoint there we go
so you're saying when I do this it will
overwrite this for me nope that is not
what it does you can you can see that
that is not true right because there
there it is and it ain't overwritten
Cubert Caleb's since we have a depth
buffer does the Z sort really matter
anymore yes absolutely for two reasons
one for transparency you have to sort if
you want transparent things to work
properly and two because it'll be faster
because we can draw front to back and
use like an early Z or things like that
we can actually get speed improvement
from that if we want so there's there's
two reasons why you might want to sort
even if you use the Z buffer we probably
won't ever use the Z buffer also you
save a bunch of bandwidth if you don't
use the Z buffer then it doesn't have to
read or write from the Z buffer which is
it's a good savings to but you know we
we may turn the Z buffer on to get the
early occlusions they were for DZ buffer
which we would still sort for blah blah
blah no even my bad looks like the
OpenGL Doc's are lying to me again yeah
well they do appear to be pretty
inaccurate we just found that out more
than once I guess icarus going to be
doing multiple GL versions or just the
minimum for general win XP machines what
versions are most of them on even on
anyway um I don't really know uh not my
feeling on that is that like my feeling
on that is that we should probably only
do like what we should just pick a
reasonable version of OpenGL and use it
because we're a 2-d game we don't need a
lot of extended stuff I mean we could
even just get by with OpenGL 2.0 I think
probably in a lot of cases
so we'll see we'll try to keep it as
minimal as possible
because I just don't think we need very
much snow Vinh 92 would there be any
benefit of using the new vs. OpenGL for
a game like handmade hero yeah I mean
we're gonna have to we will probably
want some shape shaders right so we
probably want at a at a minimum some
shaders probably I mean we could get by
without them but you know we may want
some effects in there
mad equ a is there a difference when
calling a function like GL clear on the
OpenGL 32 lib versus the one on the
graphics driver DLL they're the same
thing they're exactly the same thing so
trying to underscore this
so when you see dot lib it can mean one
of two things okay it can either be an
import library or it can actually be a
code library right so when you think
about like oh I'm I'm linking the Z Lib
or something right well that's a code
library that's like a bunch of code that
somebody wrote that's like Z you know
it's like compression code and I'm gonna
link it into my game right OpenGL 32 dot
Lib is not that kind of a Lib OpenGL 32
dot Lib is an import library it's like
user 32 or something like that so what's
in there are just bind points to the
operating system so when you link to
OpenGL 32 at lib what you're actually
calling through to is just the is just
the OpenGL I CD that's loaded at that
time that's what it's gonna link you to
now sometimes there's an operating step
in operation step in between but that's
necessary like it's it's Windows needs
to intercept the call and do something
first before it dispatches to the driver
right but that's all this is so all
OpenGL 32 Lib does is it gives you the
bind points that call into the operating
system services you need to either jump
directly to the the driver if it wants
to do that or if it wants to go through
Windows first first to Windows then to
the driver because Windows needs to like
do some checking or ring transition or
who knows what it wants to do whatever
wants to do
quit scuttle since we are using OpenGL
will you be modifying our 2.5 genius or
keeping code as is the code will be the
same it's just we'll have a hardware
path at some point as well question 4
choose pixel format were we not supposed
to specify eye pixel type and set it to
PFD type RGB a that could be we could
have missed that one let's let's double
check yours choose pixel format oh yeah
no you're totally right we probably just
lucked out there because that may be
that might actually just be 0 or it
might be that it just defaults to that
if you don't let's see yep we just
lucked out it happens to be 0
hmm well we could just keep relying on
that but it seems like a little cleaner
to just put it in there so let's just
put it in there thanks for catching that
like I said it's actually I guess
technically correct just not to do that
because 0 is the one we want so this
clear will always get us the thing but
it's just it's a little nicer just to
show that we actually were obeying it
the spec properly
Angus holder so by linking against open
jail to reach out Lib we don't need to
use get proc address at all with OpenGL
no unfortunately that is not true and
the reason like I sort of alluded to at
the beginning is that the version of
OpenGL that was built into Windows
directly in the old days was too old and
so if we were only gonna use OpenGL one
point X then yes we would never have to
call get proc address because just like
user 32 just like we didn't have to call
get proc address for create window right
and I mean I'll just we covered all this
before ball just say it one more time so
in your code right when you when you are
talking about hmm
what's gonna happen in the code you've
got two different types of things that
might happen there's like I'm gonna call
you know my well I'm gonna call my
function right or that I'm gonna call
you know create window okay this one is
in the operating system this one is I
defined it in myself when I link my
program it produced executable this goes
away this that this is gone right
there's never even remembrance unless I
save like debug information there's
never even a remembrance that there was
something called my function all that
happens is it directly puts into the
compiled executable a call to the
relative address that this function was
compiled act like we're in the code it
was so my function goes away and it
becomes call something right but that is
not what happens with create window what
happens with great window and there's
two different ways that this can
actually work depending on how you set
up the linker made money even be bored
in two ways but there's at least two
ways what happens the create window is
slightly different yes it does change
into a call with a address here
but that call to an address actually
goes to a location with nothing in it
it's like empty and this location is
stored in a table it's it's stored in
like a relocation table or I guess we
call it let's let's call a dynamic
linked table that's probably the best
word for it there's a dynamic linked
table and this is part of your
executable right that says at this
location I was trying to call create
window and everywhere you call create
window right it all gets replaced with
calls to that one location and then what
happens is that an amp level goes and
romps over that location with the actual
address of where the operating systems
create window call is mapped in your
process space which it does when you
load so when you load it grabs all this
stuff right not this because this it
doesn't care about anymore it loads that
you know it obviously loads this the
executable it knows where the dynamic
link table is and it loads it but it
doesn't care about that so much it loads
this stuff right into memory so here's
my whole executable here is like that
place that here's here's this location
and executable it loads us into memory
it has a dynamic link table but it
doesn't have to store it it just has to
apply it once so it knows about this but
it hasn't cared about it yet it then
goes ahead and maps other things up in
here right it maps like create window
the actual code for create window gets
mapped into your process space it then
reads through your dynamic link table
and goes ok where were these oh right
here was a call to create window update
that call to call into here so it romps
over the code that the nothing but like
no ops that were there before and it
puts them out to create window that's
how that works
and I don't know the specifics I haven't
looked at it in a long time it might be
that they're smart and they store like
the dynamic link tables actually sort of
built into this so that it stores it I
know you can do a thing called delay
load which will also put the code into
here that actually loads the library
that it needs so that you don't load
libraries that you haven't called yet
there's a whole bunch of stuff like that
too so this is a you know this is an
approximation of what happens it's not
exactly what happens and I'd have to go
reread the specifics to remember for
this particular operating system for
Windows how that works but that's what
happens
so get proc address is just us doing
that manually and the reason that we do
this manually well there's some other
reasons we might do it manually but the
main reason we've done on Hamid here is
because we don't know that that this
thing might exist so for create window
we can always let the dynamic link table
handle it because create winners always
there you can't possibly run on a
Windows machine doesn't have great
window you could very easily run on a
Windows machine that doesn't have X
input so I choose to call get proc
address for X input because if it's not
there I don't want to fail it's just
gamepad support you can play with the
keyboard so I don't want my app to not
run just because X input isn't there I
know that's the trend nowadays is to
just ship a giant redistributable and
the game doesn't run on half machines
and who cares and run em SVC readest and
on stuff I don't want use that to do
that I want you to be able just run the
extrude 1 it works and so what I try to
do is anything that I think might not be
there that's when we call get proc
address now for OpenGL if we only wanted
to use one point X we wouldn't have to
use get proc address because everything
is just in there but if we want to call
the functions that were added after open
jail so to point OpenGL 2.0 and up which
is most of the stuff that's in OpenGL
nowadays we do have to call get proc
address HS you don't call get proc
address you called the OpenGL equivalent
which is wiggle get proc address and
that is the mechanism by which you you
query extensions to the windows binding
part
and then I believe there's also GL get
proc address which is how you query
platform nonspecific extensions and
these two we probably will have to use
one two one three
l AC since you are complaining about
Windows pretty often why don't use
another operating system I don't know
how many times gonna have to do this I
guess it never gets old let's see here
hmm the reason is that if you are a game
programmer you have to use Windows 95
percent of all the games are on Windows
and there's really nothing you're gonna
be able do about it
so until these numbers get up to like 70
or something combined you're gonna be on
Windows mr. slick 10:15 do you think the
OS export you will need a wrapper
written in objective-c to get use OpenGL
and make a window yeah I I don't think
it even has anything to do with OpenGL I
think nowadays if you want to properly
behaved app I think you have to write
the the startup in Objective C I think
but I don't do a lot of Mac programming
so it's been a long time since I've I
programmed on a Mac
Guerry Johansson this is probably done
but what about offloading much of the
computing we are doing onto the GPU
using OpenCL then not use OpenGL and
keep things mostly as is I'm not sure
exactly what you're proposing are you
saying running our software renderer
through OpenCL the reason is because
that really just won't work
you can't Oh GPUs run general-purpose
code much much slower than CPUs do so
you have to you can't just like give
something to open steal expects to go
any faster you have to have organized
the code so that it takes it basically
takes warping seriously it's got to be
based on doing 32 wide operations and
very and severely parallelizable and
stuff we could do that I mean we could
do the work because we've already got
our things broken up into a tiled
rendering kind of a thing so we could do
some of that but that's not a good idea
because we just be making a bunch of
work for ourselves
that same amount of work we could just
call up and jail to do the rendering as
a separate pipe which is what you know
makes more sense for us certainly to
actually use OpenGL rendering services
cubic y over the break I wrote a program
that generates opengl function point
decorations an initialization by
scanning CPP H files to determine what
needs to be added do you plan on doing
something similar for HMH or you keep it
simple we'll be keeping it simple on a
handmade Hiro certainly but that is the
sort of thing that I do normally yes how
bad is an if statement is shader depends
on whether all pixels take the branch or
not
and obviously on the graphics card
that's that's gross that's a good story
to eat have you ever programmed for a
console yes but they were older consoles
well I guess I plug him for the
PlayStation 4 for a week this past this
past November
but like the time that I was doing more
crops boring was like the Xbox
Playstation 2 days and the Gamecube as
well
Linux has Windows Vista beat I think
you're right
so fifth point 15% Windows Vista 64 32
so 0.4 or 5% is Windows Vista nope
Linux can't quite do it you can't quite
do it
no single skew of Windows of Linux I
guess can quite beat it
wait but what's going on that doesn't
add up to the same number I don't know
what I'm I don't even know what this is
saying I guess there's a bunch that
aren't in here but yeah if you count all
links is it does beat out Vista so
that's good you are correct let's see
let's see
alright well that's about it for
handmade hero for this evening so I'm
gonna go ahead and wind it down alright
everyone thank you for joining me for
another episode of handmade hariya
there's been a pleasure coding with you
as always now we've got open jail
running who knows what will happen next
that was smoother I think that I
probably expected it but sometimes you
get lucky if you would like to follow
along with our OpenGL exploits you can
always pure to the game on handmade hero
org and it comes to the source code so
you can follow along we also have a
forum site you can go to ask questions
we have a patreon page where you can go
to support the video series and a tweet
bot where you can find out when we're
gonna be live and the next time we're
gonna be live it's 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Standard Time tomorrow when we are gonna
go ahead and I guess display our frames
through up in jail and then we can have
vsync which I wanted before we do that
I'm gonna have to remember so that you
don't take the roof road I'm gonna have
to remember to start going through a
video capture card so I got to find out
where the video capture card even is so
I'm gonna go do that I hope the rest of
you have a pleasant evening I'll see you
back here tomorrow till then have fun
programming I'll see you guys on the
Internet techies everyone