there we go so hello everyone welcome to
handmade hero
the show where we coat an entire game
from scratch live on twitch no engine no
libraries just straight-up every last
little bit we code ourselves both our
educational purposes and just because
it's fun and because it's just kind of
cool sometimes one of the things that's
true and we kind of saw this happen with
the with the looped live code editing
that we did earlier and you know I will
see couple more things like that when
you actually write everything from
scratch you also tend to find places
where you can do things better than
people have done them before and that's
kind of compelling too if you never get
down there and start writing the stuff
that you kind of use in an engine or use
in libraries you don't ever find the
ways to do it better than what they do
and I always like trying to find better
ways to do things because I think that's
kind of the most interesting thing about
programming it's kind of coming up with
new ways to do stuff that people haven't
done before so since we're starting to
late let's jump right into it if you
have pre-ordered the game you can
download the source code you should have
got a link in your email and that link
has a zip file that you can download and
we are here if I'm not mistaken on day
47 I believe that's correct
47 let's double check that's true where
are we I don't even know I don't even
know anymore yes we're on day 47 so if
you unzip this the zip file for day 46
then that is a source code that I am
starting with here on day 47 and you
will be exactly where I am right now now
if you remember correctly yesterday we
just took a little bit of time to fix
well a bug but basically in fixing that
bug we decided to kind of add a feature
which is multiple people controlling
multiple entities on the screen and so
we basically had the ability for people
to kind of drop in if I have a game I
got a gamepad here I can add another guy
right and and he's there hanging out now
we started basically pulling out the
code for for the sprite control for that
hero character
into its own function and he is kind of
he's kind of doing his thing right but
what we had interrupted to do that
yesterday because I want to take care of
that right
what we interrupted is we interrupted
fixing our walls sticking problem which
we had discussed and we were in the
process of writing code for now I want
to talk about that a little bit but one
thing I did want to do too is while
we're at it at the beginning of the
stream here I want to clean up one more
thing because now that we actually have
the the you know now that we actually
have multiple little heroes on here we
and we're supporting the analog stick
now I want to go in there and deal with
some stuff that we didn't deal with on
the analog stick in terms of the motion
of the actual player so just quickly if
you recall we had not really learned
vectors yet when we first visited see
here when we first visited this code
right here so what we were doing
originally is we basically just did a
little hack which said that if both of
your if both of you were when when the
user is controlling the hero we had just
hacked into things so that when he tries
to move diagonally he wouldn't move
faster than he moved when he was moving
in cardinal directions right and this is
something that we did before we learned
vectors so basically we had a situation
where we had something that looks like
this we have him moving in this
direction and we would set this to be
one Y and 0 X so this is the vector 0 1
right or we would be moving this way and
this would be the vector 1 0 or or we
would moving this way up sorry that's
actually negative 1 and that's 0 1
because remember Y goes up that's
positive x positive Y and and this is
negative 1 right these are the vectors
that the d-pad could be creating by
pushing in the cardinal directions but
when you push in two directions at once
we were ending up the vector like 1 1
right which is longer if you remember by
root 2 we went through all this so jump
back to the is if you're not sure I'm
talking about I'm not going to go over
all again today but we would basically
end up with this and that's moving
faster than either of these its its root
2 long instead of one long right
so what we decided to do is we decided
to solve you know we actually solved
Pythagorean theorem to figure out how
long it should be so that would be the
same length it would still be one long
but just in that direction right but now
we have a different problem if the
analog stick is being used then really
inside this unit circle right you could
imagine the analog stick pushing in any
direction and it can be pushing
proportionally so it doesn't have to be
just one of these Cardinal one of these
carbon directions or the diagonal right
so all we really want to do is we want
to make sure that that vector that comes
back to the analog stick we just want to
use that as his acceleration directly
unless for some reason the value we get
back tries to exceed the length of one
right tries to exceed the length of one
so that it would be accelerating beyond
the maximum acceleration that we wanted
it to have right and well we don't
necessarily know if that will ever
happen because it could be that the
analog stick always returns values that
are perfectly inside that unit circle
unit circle you could imagine if there
was some game pad that had more of a
square range of motion so that when you
pushed it up into the corner here it was
actually kind of more at negative I'm
sorry
negative one one you know or something
like that or negative one negative one
down here instead of sort of being more
at that unit circle range then we would
have this thing where people could sort
of cheat by moving the player faster
than they should be able to on those
joysticks right so we want to make sure
that no matter what we get back from the
operating system as our joystick values
we always want to make sure they are
capped so that the that that motion that
acceleration vector that we're taking
from the joystick is not greater than
one now we showed how to implement the
length of a vector right we already
showed how to say if we've got some
acceleration vector here we showed how
to say well we can take the length of
that vector right and if you remember
that was just the components of it right
squared right so we had this the length
squared was equal to this squared and
getting that's just that Pythagorean
theorem theorem a squared plus B squared
equals C squared that's what we did
right and if we wanted to actually find
out the actual length we could just
square root this right so we'd square
root both sides and we've
get this right x squared plus ay Y
squared like that so we have this
ability and we actually implemented that
in our math library if you remember
correctly we went and did length squared
and we implemented that by just taking
the inner product of the vector with
itself which again basically computes
exactly that thing ax times a X a Y
times a Y because remember our passing a
in both cases which is exactly that
Pythagorean theorem that selects of the
vector so now we do know at least how to
directly ask the question whatever comes
back is our acceleration vector how long
is that vector right because I could go
into this code and I can ask what the
length square it is right I can say what
is the length squared of this value so
if I say DDP length I can compute it
right and that'll get me a value that I
know is gonna tell me how long the the
requested acceleration for this player
is and I can then go ahead and say well
all right
however long that acceleration vector is
well I'm gonna get it squared value back
now I could square root it if I wanted
to but I don't really have to just do my
check right because if you look at the
value of square root right if we looked
at what what square root was going to do
and maybe I'll do this in a sort of kind
of oh you know what I wonder if we can
do this I wonder if we can do this this
way Square or like Wolfram Alpha or
something I don't know if it's I don't
know if it's got this sort of stuff but
let's see here square root I just want
someone to give us a little graph and I
figured it'd be easier than me drawing
it out but I don't actually know if that
would do it so there it is good so this
is a graph right of the square root
function and I guess the one we probably
want more oops that's no good would
actually be from zero to one I don't
know if we can can we we're gonna have
we got to have some kind of Pro thing
God Wolfram Alpha what what is what
don't know go away thank you
alright good so I guess we'll use this
one here what I really want is just the
up to one but it's it's fine so if you
look at this here you can see that the
interesting thing about square root
right is the square root of one is one
it's right that's the one value where a
square the square root of the number
equals itself it's the identity for
square root right so if I take the
square root of one I actually get one
back right and so I could just say well
since I actually want to just check to
see if this thing would be one if I took
its actual length of square root of it
well I could just say whatever that
length is that I want you know max
acceleration right I could just say
whatever the square of that is I'll
compare against that so if the if the
length that we get back is greater than
the square of the max duration then I'll
do it but of course I know in this case
the maxillary should here is just 1 and
I know that the square of that is 1 so I
can basically just check if it's greater
than 1 and save everyone the trouble ok
now you may ask why is the maxillary
agen 1 it's because we're not actually
producing the max acceleration here what
we're doing is producing the direction
and the amount of the max solutions that
we will apply and you'll see that in one
second so I need to do here is just
check to see ok is the length of the
thing that we were supposed to be using
he is that going to be greater than 1
and if it is greater than 1 I need to
cap it at length 1 okay so I need to
figure out some way that now I need to
do something to DDP here right I need to
do something to DDP such that I can
change its length to 1 without changing
its direction right so I need to
construct a kind of diagram that again
should be familiar to you from your high
school math right I have a vector oops I
have a vector here right there's my
vector and you can imagine in fact I
should give myself a little more room to
draw so let's say it's big there's my
vector right and it has its components x
and y here's the component of the
original vector we'll call that vector a
here are the components right and this
is my vector
now what I want to do is I want to
construct another vector and I want to
point in exactly the same direction as a
but I want its length to be 1 so this
length here should be 1 this length here
is some other length it's the length of
a right makes sense okay now if you
remember again like I said from from
your convenient your convenient sort of
grade school or high school math you
know that if you have right triangles
like this that share all the angles are
the same right you've got all the angles
are the same on this diagram then you
know that they are similar triangles and
what similar triangles mean is that the
sides are actually proportional in
length to each other so the ratio of one
of the sides of this triangle to one of
the sides of this other triangle is the
same ratio no matter which side I pick
right so if I want to know how big this
is relative to this or if I want to know
how big this is relative to this all I
have to know is the relative ratio of
one of the sides now of course I have
that because I know how long a is right
and I know that I want it to be 1 right
so I basically know that if I take the
ratio of 1 which is this what I want
here right to a which is the actual
length that gives me the coefficient
that gives me the ratio that I would
want you know I can even I can write it
out as an actual ratio expression the
ratio of the you know the thing I want
versus the thing that I have I can then
pick any other part of it like the ax
that I might want to get and if I want
to get that new that new X right
whatever that new a prime X is so a
prime X would be down here right this
length right so if I want to try and
figure out what that is I can just use I
can just use this exact this exact
formula right and the thing that I want
to solve for is this so multiplying out
you get just doing the cross multiply
again this is where I'm shocked I
made a serious math error on the stream
this may be the day but we'll find out
yeah so anyway
the thing I want software is this this
right here this this a prime X the new
the new you know this value because I
know that value and I want to get this
value so if I want to solve for that I
just have to go ahead and isolate that
term which just means dividing by this
and of course that gives me a prime x
equals ax over length a right and this
turns into basically the the sort of the
canonical version of changing the length
of a vector so let's say I want to do it
a little more sort of aggressively let's
say I wanted to do a prime so I just
have some new length here length of a
prime whatever that length is right so I
want to basically say no matter what the
length is what would I do here well now
cross multiplying right I get that
length of a prime here right so ax times
that right cross multiply here if that's
this term cross multiply there that's
this term they're equal to each other
and so then when I actually do this
right I get one additional term instead
of just having ax over a on this side I
actually have the length of a prime
times ax over a right because I'm taking
this and dividing by this and this right
here is the canonical form for how you
change the length of a vector without
changing its direction it's this a prime
over a right so length of a prime over a
length of a so the lengths that I want
my vector to be over the length that it
is right is that term right there times
the component that I want right ax is
the existing value for my x coordinate
of that vector so that gives me the new
a prime the new the new a prime X and if
I want to do it with Y again this would
be the exact same equation there just be
wise here so all the same math carries
through so a prime Y is just the exact
same thing coefficient times a Y right
so what that get gets for us is just
this really really simple way to take a
vector and change its length all we have
to do is multiply the components of the
vector
by that ratio a prime over a now we know
that we want the length the the a prime
there that length is just 1.0 and so now
we just need to know what this value is
here right what that is
now unfortunately ratios do not work
through squaring if that makes sense
so basically if I have this a prime over
a and this is the coefficient I want to
compute
I cannot compute a prime squared over a
squared I can't do that right I wish
that were true but I don't believe
there's any real way you could you can
yeah I'm trying to think if there's a
good way to do that
basically I can't think of any way to
really do that simpler than just
actually after you do the square root
right so that means we do have to do a
square root here but hey square roots
aren't as expensive as they used to be I
don't know if we actually ever put one
into our math let's see here I into our
math library oops
where is intrinsics square root no we
didn't so we want to put in a square
root here again this is going to be
something that should be generated
directly by the compiler hopefully at
least inverse square root usually is
square root usually is as well anyway
we'll see let's take a look so square
root of some value that comes in that's
going to be equal to the square root of
the value that comes in return that as a
result yeah and so all we really need to
do here is just do the what that length
we had take that square root and that
will will essentially do that operation
that we just said right multiply all the
components of our of our vector of our
acceleration vector by whatever would
make its length equal to 1 right and
we're not going to do that if it's less
than 1 already because that's fine that
just means the person is pushing just a
little bit on the stick and now we can
get rid of this right so hopefully that
will what is the problem do we not have
an F squirt first oh do we need there we
go sorry for some reason it's F
but squirt f don't ask me why that
happened because I have no idea but
that's just the way it goes
alright so now in theory we should have
more ability to control this guy a
little smoother there's not really going
to be a whole lot of difference there
but that's just getting that's just
getting rid of that kind of crufty code
that only worked for the d-pad so now
it'll work for the analog stick as well
and we're all good right and you can see
now you can move just a little bit right
and we don't get any kind of weirdness
in there or any kind of non proportional
stuff so yeah so that's good so that's
all I really wanted to take care of was
just that yeah
and hopefully that made some sense it's
pretty straightforward now as I said
before if you want to know why we are
making it length one it's because
basically anything that's length one is
easy to then transform out into some
other length right because if I know
something is already length one and I
want to make it some other length later
I just multiply it by the length that I
want right because you have to remember
this this equation that I just said
where it's the new length right over the
the old length if I wanted to make
something a new length and I already
knew its old length was one well that
means this square root here would just
already be one and so it would just be a
new length over one or new length so
that would be the equation right for
changing it to some new length if I knew
its if its current length was already
one and so the reason I'm constructing a
length one vector here is because now I
just have basically the generic vector
that points in the direction that the
person goes or a vector that's something
less than one and if it's something less
than one then all it will do is when I
multiply it by something later it will
be proportionally less which is exactly
what I would want with the analog stick
right I'd want a proportion less than
whatever I'm going to do if it was
pushed all the way out and so then we do
exactly what I just said we take that
vector and we multiply it by however
fast we wanted the player to actually
accelerate in meters per second squared
and that basically gives us a new vector
that's the correct length now for
acceleration to use and then we proceed
as normal so nothing nothing weird
happens there so that's it I mean
there's nothing there's nothing really
fancy going on there just want to make
sure everyone kind understood what was
going on and so they'd hey there he goes
and he's good so now we have to do is
concentrate on this problem right where
we're not grinding along the wall
because we don't allow movement when we
just when we when we detect a collision
right and so what you want to do is
allow movement when we detect collision
now and clean that up ok so what we need
to do for that I thought about this
quite a bit and I talked about on a
previous stream I was talking about
whether we should do search and P or
certainty and we like I kind of talked
about how to implement both methods and
I the more I thought think about it the
less I want to do search and P I was
kind of like really on the fence if you
remember I wasn't sure and I thought
about it over the weekend and that's
like you know what I don't think it's a
good idea and the reason I don't think
it's a good idea is because I feel like
it's gonna introduce a lot of complexity
into the code for us for not a lot of
benefit because really in this game
we're not gonna be grinding against
walls a lot it's not like a walking
simulator kind of a game and I feel like
the benefit that we'd get from having
search and P which I like better for
collision detection in the in some case
sense it's just gonna cost too much in
terms of the code complexity so I think
since we really never actually bothered
to implement it I'm just gonna say let's
not bother and let's go with the more
traditional version which I was going to
show how to implement anyway let's just
do that method because I think that
method makes more sense because it's
just it's cheaper is the thing and and I
feel like the cheapness is gonna be
important for us that's all and I don't
think we're gonna get much benefit out
of the other way so basically all we
really needed to do was come up with a
better way of actually detecting when we
were hitting stuff so what all we were
doing before is when we actually go in
you know somewhere we say we're here and
over a time step we want to go here but
there's something in our way all we were
doing before is checking checking that
ending location we were checking that
ending location to see whether we could
stand there and if we could we just took
accepted the move if we couldn't we
denied the move that was it and so we
need to do something better than that
and in order to do something better than
that the first thing we have to do is
figure out what we actually hit and
where we hit it so we need to do
something where we're going to look at
what you know what we could collide with
and we have to go ahead and say all
right when we collide with something
let's figure out where we collided and
when we figure out where we collided we
will put the player there right we will
update his velocity vector which is what
we were doing before to basically not
have any of the component that was going
into the thing that he collided against
and then we will try again to move him
now we will try a few times we will
basically do this in a loop that tries a
few times to get him to where he should
be and if it fails to get him to where
he should be
you know if it shouldn't say where he
should be it'll try a few times to move
him the total amount that it should have
moved him right because when we go here
you know we'll find the velocity vector
still is has there still a delta T right
because we moved to here and we know
that he would have gotten there if this
was the entire time step we know that we
would have gotten to here in less than
that so there's some smaller thing here
delta T 2 or something right that's a
smaller thing and we want to then use
the remainder that delta T remainder we
want to still try to move him by that
much and so hopefully delta T that the
amount that's remaining goes down to
zero and we know that we've done a
complete move but if we find that we
just can't resolve it because there's
all these crazy walls in there and he's
bouncing around or whatever we'll just
cut our losses and say you know after
four iterations or something we're just
gonna consider that good enough and
we'll stop because we don't want to have
something where we're gonna do an
unbounded number of iterations that's
just a very bad idea for something
that's performance oriented and again
this whole thing is very tiny we're
talking about something that happens
over a xxx or a sixtieth of a second so
these are like microscopic movements
that we're talking about here so how
many bounces we support is not
particularly relevant in terms of what
the player can actually experience as
long as it's like you know two or three
I think we should be fine so what I need
to do is figure out how to compute that
right I need to figure out how to
compute that and we'll start by
computing it for the simplest case that
we possibly could
we'll start by compete computing it with
point vs. line essentially right so what
we want to do is say all right we need
to we're going to have some kind of line
right and we're going to have to have
some representation for our guy
and some concept of direction is going
and we need to figure out when he hits
that that sort of whatever that is that
line that that blocker so we're gonna
start with that as the simplest case and
we'll kind of work up from there because
I think I don't know how much time we
got left got about a half hour left so
that'll be it's quite that'll be quite a
bit for us to actually go through in
such a short amount of time actually so
let's you know focus on doing that and
then we will go ahead and see when we
get when we get done with that we'll
probably maybe tomorrow talk about how
to do some more complicates complicated
stuff okay so if we're just doing that
simple case what we need to start
thinking about is how to solve equations
with these vectors right because
typically when you have something like
this you know if I've got if I have
something like that where I've got some
kind of a line segment right like so and
I have some kind of a vector that's
going in that direction I now need to
figure out how to do solves because in
order to figure out when if I was going
along this line when I go here we're
essentially talking about something
that's going to be some function of time
right as time progresses I'm moving and
I want to know when this function of
time that tells me like a location of
the player when it equals some
particular criteria right I've got you
know some some some value that I want to
satisfy here and I need to know when
that becomes equal to something right
and so if I want to do that we're
starting to talk about actually solving
some equations and so the first question
is well what is the equations what is
the first equation that were or what is
the first part of the question that
we're going to use how do we represent
this part how do we represent there's a
player and he's at a location and he's
moving right well this the most simple
thing to do here right is to say well I
started a place we'll call that p0 right
and then I move along some vector that's
like a distance right I move in a
direction so I know that I've got some
you know p0 which is which is this point
here and I know I've got some
we'll call that D and I'm moving along
it in you know some amount so if you
remember we did that thing where we
talked about the linear blend right and
we said oh well if we want to if you
want to have a linear blend between two
points a and B right you can think of it
as the Delta between them right B minus
a you can think of that Delta between
them you can think of starting at a and
adding some port B a percentage of that
difference between them right and this
was the standard linear blend function
and I said it comes up all the time
right
remember I said everything we do is
gonna have this in it well guess what
it's gonna happen here too
I've got a place I'm going to I've got a
place I'm coming from right and I want
to move between them
classic linear blend right so I'm going
to talk about this as if I have this
vector so we're gonna say that I have
that that that Delta vector there right
and I'm like I said I'm gonna call that
D so I'm gonna call this this difference
cream T and so I'm just talking about
that p 0 which is this I'm tearing that
p 0 plus T times D right that will tell
me where my guy is at any time T right
so if he starts from here I can plug in
any time I want and he will move along
that line and just keep going right now
if I want to I can do different things
here I can phrase this in a couple
different ways I can say that D is the
full distance that he moves so it's like
B minus a if in this case here or like
this is the p1 he's going to so in this
case it would be p 1 minus p 0 i could
say that and what that would mean is
that t is normalized it means that t
ranges from 0 to 1 right and when he
gets to 1 he's done moving for this
that's as far as he can go right i could
on the other hand also take d and say
that D has length 1 the length of D is 1
right that would be normalizing the D
vector and then T would range from 0 to
whatever the actual amount is that would
get him along that vector to the
location right it would be his his
motion amount so we have different ways
we could phrase this we could have tea
range from 0 to some value or we can
have it range from 0 to 1 and it depends
on what we want our properties to be of
these vectors do we want this to be
normalized do we care stuff like that so
just keeping in mind that this could
actually be phrased a couple different
ways the p0 is kind of unambiguous it's
where we started at the beginning of
time step where the player is standing
right now the D is somewhat ambiguous in
the somewhat unambiguous and that we
know it's pointing in the direction of
motion but in terms of the T and the
length of D they are kind of
interchangeable we can we can move
between different schemes there
depending on how we want it to work
right ok so let's start with the
simplest possible case we could we could
imagine right the simplest possible case
would be if we just know that we have
like say a vertical wall right we just
want to know when this guy hits a
vertical wall that extends let's say
infinitely for now so this is just an
infinite vertical war he cannot go past
it ever he'll never get past that wall
whether he goes up down any other way
well what do we know about a vertical
wall we know a vertical wall has an
x-coordinate of something and a
y-coordinate of everything right any y
coordinate that you want is on that wall
but it only has one x-coordinate right
so this can be anything but this would
have to be a specific value and that
would basically be like our wall X right
or something so we'll call that wall X
so if we want to we could now imagine
how we would directly solve this
equation to see when a guy walking in
that direction right would hit this wall
we would say we want to know when the X
component of this so PT x which is p 0 x
plus t DX remember because this is a
vector equation and I can always look at
its scalar parts by just looking at the
X particular X component of it if I have
this equation all I need to do is say
whenever that equals the wall X right so
this right here is the equation I would
solve to tell
when I would hit that in T so if I want
to actually solve it right I can just
solve for T I get T DX equals W X minus
p0 X right I subtract this over to this
side
so that goes over here and then I
divided by DX to get rid of the DX right
so get rid of that and put it under here
divided by DX okay so this is the time
at which I would hit that wall simple
enough right
not particularly complicated but there's
a catch here I now have a well you know
what I should I should probably be sly
err about that does anyone know what the
catch is here maybe you guys already
know there's a catch here and I haven't
mentioned it yet we'll kind of see if
anyone will give you a chance to think
about it a little bit but I want to
point it out I wish I had more tea
but I'm regretfully out of tea all right
so the catch is right here when you
divide by DX
you may remember from your high school
math classes someone would always say
you know the teacher would always say
subject to DX not equal to zero right
they would say I'm gonna write it in in
our form not math forum right D s can't
be zero
I guess the math form is more typically
that way right and they say that because
D X can't be 0 because dividing by zero
is undefined behavior in math you don't
know what it is
at least it's undefined behavior in some
math the math we're doing it's undefined
and since that's the case since you
can't divide by zero you know that your
solution to this equation depends on DX
having been set to some value that isn't
zero now you may have always wondered I
don't care about that what is that for
it's just lame stupid I don't care when
you were in high school math that's it's
just annoying right but it's not
annoying when you actually get to start
using math for real you realize it's
very important and it's interesting what
does that mean well what it means is
think about this vector this is the
vector D what are its components it is d
is DX dy right
that's the components we're talking
about this the x-coordinate of the
vector that's which how far it is like
this so you know if I have my vector
here you know here's my vector D we're
talking about DX it's down here and
here's dy well
if DX was zero that means that the
vector is pointing in either up or down
straight up or down it's not pointing to
left or right at all right or it's not
pointing anywhere it's just zero but if
that were true if this is pointing
straight up or straight down well guess
what it's parallel to this line so there
is no solution to when he will hit this
line when the person walking along that
will hit it there's no solution because
he'll never hit it you walk as long as
he wants he can walk to the end of time
and he'll never hit that wall right so
what was stupid in math class rightfully
so is actually quite nice in game
programming it is information and that
information has real meaning and that's
one of the most satisfying things about
math is when you actually start to use
it you realize that all the stupid crap
actually mean stuff and you use it right
so when we're gonna implement this we
have to look and say oh okay
if that if that if the x-coordinate is
very close to zero this is becoming an
undefined equation we don't we just
assume that you can't hit the wall at
that point right and we don't have to
check against this wall at all because
they'll never hit it so what's the rest
of this mean this T value that comes
back assuming that he can hit the wall
so it's got some X component well the T
that was either gonna be positive which
means he goes some direction and hits it
or it's gonna be negative which means
that like he was actually walking in the
opposite direction of the wall and he
would have hit it if he'd walked
backwards some amount of time so this
solution actually gives us how far it
would take him to reach the wall go
walking forwards or backwards and it
tells us which one of them it would have
been right so that's kind of cool
but we can when this comes back we can
go oh we're just gonna say we only care
about stuff that's T greater than equal
to zero because we actually don't care
about Kim walking backwards into the
wall we're only checking the forwards
right so that would be a pretty simple
thing for us to test and to see what
happens when he walks into vertical or
of course horizontal walls would be the
same we just change this to W X the W X
and the PX and DX would all change to
right so we now have that that's sort of
oh you know what I'm gonna try I'm gonna
try it you guys ready for this I'm gonna
try it
scrolling over check it out man that's
cool
all right so this is the equation the T
equals W X minus p0 x over DX right
that's the equation that we would use to
solve for an x wall and similarly if you
wanna solve for y wall right we would
say same thing but in Y right so that's
how we solve for vertical or horizontal
walls now with that we can actually go
implement mostly our top map collision
and maybe we should do that maybe that
is what we'll do and then tomorrow we'll
talk about how to do more arbitrary
stuff so if you think about this well
you think about this we go okay when we
do these collision detection right
excuse me we would be collide against
infinite walls so we have stuff in our
game where we've got these walls that
have like holes in them and stuff that
would work right because if we will
start at kalitta colliding against this
wall here where you know here's the
walls right and the hero's trying to go
through this door he'd never be able to
get through there because the wall is
infinitely high right it's just it goes
up and down and covers everything
because it's an infinitely long wall
it's just testing against one thing but
obviously if we wanted to we could fix
that pretty easily right because when we
find out where this would actually be
like where do we find out what the
actual collision time is right we could
then say well use that T value because
we have this function here right use
plug that T value back into the walking
equation find out where the guy is
standing at that time right so do p 0
plus and let's call this like our solved
for T or something plus T solve right
times D this right here will give us
this this solved for time P that will
give us this when he walks that will
give us this location when he
it's the wall right when he hits the
wall we can check the y-coordinate to
see what its ranges and if that range is
not in between the two locations that we
know of the wall to be right we could
just not do it so for every wall for
every tile block that's solid we could
basically check for different collisions
right one for each side of the block and
just check the range of the collision to
make sure it's actually in between there
if it's not we don't count it as a
collision we just move on and so that's
a pretty easy way right that we could do
this so let's go ahead and implement
that since this may be very new to a lot
of people I figure like we shouldn't
really jump ahead at all that makes
sense so that makes sense
hopefully that makes sense and again so
so this is the yeah well there you go I
need to I need to get my so there you go
okay so moving along let's just go ahead
and implement this code it's pretty
trivial right so if we go ahead and
implement this code this was our old
code up above here that we were just
that we were using pretty
straightforwardly
and so now we're gonna have to write
some actual collision detection code
here and so what we need to do here well
I guess I can keep some of that actually
this is this is actually really
important what we need to do is loop
over all of the tiles that are around us
right all the tiles that are that we
could be hitting taking a look at them
and seeing if they are solid if we can't
stand in them then we need to go ahead
and see whether or not we would hit them
by walking into them right if that makes
sense yeah so first things first we need
to map into some common location and so
let's just assume that the player is
like going to be at zero zero right that
seems pretty straightforward so let's go
ahead and say well actually it's we
don't even have to do that we can just
go ahead and say we have our tile map
difference we're going to subtract the
player position for the tile position
that gets us the relative position of
the
of the player I guess in that tile that
seems yeah I guess that seems fair
enough yeah that's totally fine and then
all we have to do in here is actually
implement whatever the check is that we
actually want to do okay
so let's set up this loop I guess this
we have not yet initialized so the first
thing we need to figure out is which
tiles do we actually want to check right
like what are the tiles that actually
need to be checked and so that's
actually another discussion we kind of
have to have there's a lot involved here
I got explaining a lot of stuff we may
not get through all this tonight all
right so if you imagine what's happening
here collision detection is complicated
why can't I oh I'm just cuz I got some
stuff selected so many things I have to
do prerequisite wise all right so if you
imagine that I have my tile map then we
have to ask the question what are the
things that I actually have to collide
with if like my guy is say here and the
time step would move him to here right
well the answer is I need to check all
of the tiles that he could have gone
through so I need to check like the tile
that I'm standing on I need to check the
tile that that he would end up in and
all the tiles in between right and so if
you think about what that means it's
basically just a min max such a
situation right it's the minimum tile
lie and the maximum tile lie and the
minimum tile acts the maximum tile acts
of the two locations where he is and
where he's going because if he was going
to go like that or something like this
we'd want to check this whole rectangle
right because we want to check all of
these things for collision now really if
we want it to be that's a that's not
that's a conservative check right a
conservative check means it checks
perhaps more than enough things right a
conservative check is basically one that
that doesn't necessarily check the
fewest number of things but it
definitely checks all the things that
has to right we could do better in the
cases where we had something like this
by actually saying well okay the the
line the player moved
doesn't actually pass through these guys
here right it only passes through this
one this one this one in this one so we
don't have to do the full rectangle
right and that's definitely something to
think about when we're actually
implementing the engine for reals
because that could save time but again
these aren't gonna be very there's
really no way to pass through that of
any tiles unless you're moving extremely
quickly but yet just something to think
about so all we really need to do is a
conservative check at this point which
will basically say ok as long as we get
all the tiles we might check will be
fine doesn't matter if we check some of
the ones that we actually shouldn't have
have checked because that's just like
some waste of time and that's like stuff
to worry about in the optimization phase
of things so we don't actually care
about that for now so we want to do is
basically say ok the two places place
we're coming from the place we're going
to we want to take the min and Max tile
values of those and to know which tiles
to check so the min tile X is just going
to be the minimum I don't know if we'd
ever actually did did we actually ever
do minimum and maximum macros I don't
know if we did hand-made platform bed
age did we do yeah we didn't so there is
a C++ feature that someone was
mentioning that actually well okay we
don't actually need to use that for this
but I was reminded of something just now
that yeah that may be good to do in
future but anyway so if we go in here we
can define a min and Max basically if we
want to do a minimum or a maximum of two
things so I've got two values whatever
they are it's pretty easy to do that
check right we can just say if a is less
than B then the thing you wanted was a
right and if not the thing you wanted
was be pretty simple right and the same
is true for the maximum if a was greater
than B rank then you'd want a otherwise
you want B that's pretty much all I'm
talking about here very very
straightforward really nothing to it but
what I would like to do now is say okay
so I've got the old player P and I've
got the new player P so let's take
whatever his abs tile whichever one of
those is a is a greater I'm sorry is a
smaller for that one and greater
absolute tile index oops there we go and
then what I have to do is I have to add
one because I want one past the maximum
tile and again the reason I'm doing that
is to make sure that wrapping works
properly that makes sense so there we go
next I'll let's get that Y in there and
then this one will be there we go so
basically I just got to get that minimum
tile I got to get that back some tile
and then I'm gonna loop and add one to
it so I'm one passed it and then I loop
over those tiles making sure that I I
stop when I get to that that maximum one
right and again I had to use not equals
not less than because I want to support
wrapping and you can't support wrapping
with the less than because if I went if
I under flow here and the min tile was
less than then that would be no good all
right
so hmm what I need to do now say okay we
we're only checking things in our tile Z
so that the tile Z is not really
relevant at this point we then are going
to say we're gonna figure out where the
best place is to leave the player and
that's going to be again since I'm
checking against all of these I need to
check against multiple of these guys
right I have an equation that'll tell me
when I hit a wall like that but what I
haven't done is figured out well okay if
I have tons of walls what would I do
right and the answer is just well okay
if you've got tons of walls that you're
checking against so you're checking
against like this wall and this wall and
so on right then that puts you in a
situation where I've you know I've got
here
and I'm doing this sort of thing and I
test like you know this wall first and I
say oh okay you know he hit it here and
so that would be some tea that's like
some tea that I solved for is look all
that tea far right but there was
actually later on I find that I I test
this wall and there's another tea right
this the tea became he called the team
near when I did this equation right and
I need some way of figuring out well
which one do they actually stop at right
which one should I use when I loop
through all these walls and find all
these collision points how do I know
which one's the actual collision point I
should use well obviously we want the
closest one so we just want whichever
one let gave us the least value of T
right so really what we can do here is
say okay we've got a tea that we're
solving for and there's some best tea
which is really just the closest tea
right the key that was the the you know
the lowest right if that makes sense we
could also call that tea lowest or
something or team in right and then what
we want to do is say okay the minimum
value of T that we want to start with
meaning we don't want to entertain
anything further than that is just
whatever the value would be if we what
if we allowed the whole time step to go
forwards right so basically if I was
going to do the full difference between
the new player P and the old player P
that's what I would do right and so
basically that's just that's just
whatever the the player Delta is that
this that's this right here right
and so that player Delta is is basically
the vector that would move us between
them so if I take its length right if I
take its squared length
maybe I'll just I'll leave T min as a
squared but I'm gonna actually solve for
the actual T so we could also make T be
equal to one if that you know what let's
just say that T is equal to one let's do
it this way so I I made this decision
based on this thing I was talking about
back here right remember how I said T
and D are kind of fungible they have to
multiply together when when get when
they get to their maximum values they
have to multiply out to be wherever the
guy would end up at the end of the time
step but what I realized just now
because I saying like how much what am I
going to do it's gonna be better if I
just make the length of D be equal to
the total movement right right so that's
the total movement he should do and then
T will be equal to one and that way I
can just straight up set it at the
beginning and I don't have to really do
any other work so that'll be fine I can
straight up set to one that's the
maximum it should ever be so any
collisions that you find had better be
lower than that otherwise there were
collision that would have happened after
the time step would already be finished
somewhere out here like you know after
he would walk much further or something
like that so okay so assuming that that
is set up properly now now I just have
to go through
and if the tile is is not empty I have
to test all of the walls and see if they
need to update my my my team in right
and I really don't need this best player
P anymore because I just afterwards I
can reconstruct where I should be by
looking at the team in right so that's
pretty easy so all I need to do here is
say all right hmm I need to solve my
team in so what I'm going to do is going
to test each of the walls of of the of
the guy so I need to do like a test wall
if that makes sense
and so I've got the relative position of
the player I'll put that in a up with
that in our rel vector here so real new
player P I don't remember what we call
this like we said we're going to change
it to a 3d vector once we had them but
we didn't quite yet DXY oh I actually
can just use that directly there we go
so I could even do yeah they're mine
anyway so I've got my relative my
relative movement here that is going to
multiply by T obviously to give us the
the motion that we want so T min times
this relative vector would move me from
the players current position to wherever
oh sorry
yeah that's not that's not correct at
all what am I talking about that's
that's the real that's his position
relative to the tile my bad
the it's it's the player Delta is the
thing I was thinking of their player
Delta is the function is the vector
that's going to move us from our current
location times you know times T to be
wherever the the point is that we would
end up right so what we need to do now
is we need to actually compute this
equation that I said we were going to
compute for each wall and so we've got
it here right we said that it was TS
equals W X minus p 0 X the whole thing
right over DX right and again DX is just
that player Delta right so that's that
player Delta X and then the p 0 X that
was where we started from
and so we know what that is that's real
new player pee right that's that's where
the player is relative to the tile
that's his starting location and we're
doing all this relative to where the
tile is and then we've got that wall X
which is the the the actual point that
we want to test right so we've got the
wall X there so what we want to do here
is we want to make this into something
that we can call and this is again going
to be the the T result value we want to
make this into something that we can
call four times with four different
values so we can do test wall with like
the the rail player X and one of the
wall X's right so you know like the min
corner the minimum corner of the of the
tiles X value for example we want to say
that and then we can mm-hmm say what its
bounds are in Y so it's its min corner Y
and Max corner y so basically this is
the location of the wall these are the
bounds where the wall is and then we've
got our R value that we're actually oh
no that's sad the stream is over we're
so close to well I guess test well we'll
have to wait till tomorrow what are you
gonna do all I was going to say is all
right so the test well function right it
it takes the wall information and then
you know it takes the player the real
new player whatever the yeah I'm so
deflated right now can you see how
deflated I am
well some days go better than others you
know you can't always have the Q&amp;A start
at just the right time and I have to
admit we were on a streak I think we had
two days we had one day yes yes
yesterday
and then one day I think maybe was
Thursday where the Q&amp;A started like
exactly when I was done so you know what
are you gonna do I guess we'll finish it
tomorrow we're mostly there we just have
to figure out a way to phrase this so
that we can test each wall so we'll just
say to do test all four walls and take
the minimum see so that's really all we
needed to do so what are you gonna do
alright okay
I will go to the QA deflated as I am of
not being able to finish the code I
always hate it when we get to a piece of
code and I can't finish writing it that
something doesn't really happen much in
real life right because you just program
a little longer but when you've got a
schedule to skip to yeah you don't get
that opportunity so we're still
compiling cuz we're still using the
other branch of the code so we don't
have to worry about that the code that
we post tonight will still compile just
fine but we just won't have turned on
our actual collision detection yet which
we'd like to do and so tomorrow we'll go
ahead and do that all right so please
post questions now with Q :
in front of them so I can see them and
please keep the questions and stuff
we've done on today's stream as
deflating as it was and and if you want
to ask things that are or anything for
today's dream or previous dreams if you
want to ask questions about stuff that's
off topic you can do that on the pre
stream so come 15 minutes early tomorrow
to the stream and I'll be on answering
questions that are off topic but please
try to keep the ones in the official Q&amp;A
here to the actual stuff we coded today
are on previous days
so deflating stopping programming in the
middle of stuff of something is so
unsatisfying yeah that's all I can
really say about that she's very very
unsatisfying
yeah
I missed when you changed from F P 2 ft
when why did you decide to switch so
basically I can explain that in a little
more detail here so basically the reason
that I decided to go with F of T and you
remember I was kind of hemming and
hawing about it on Friday I couldn't
decide which one I wanted to do and so
on and so here's the reasoning behind it
so f of P right all right I should say F
of P is what I call it search in P
versus certainty right so search and P
has some nice properties right search
and P has is is bounded in in iterations
right where a certainty is unbounded in
iterations to produce the correct answer
right search in P allows sort of
smoothly ignoring geometry bugs
whereas this gets stuck right geometry
bugs right so these are like pluses for
search and P and minuses for this but
search in P has a pretty big negative
that search and T has is positive and
there's there's really two positives one
of which I don't think we care about
much but one of which we really do so
search in P one of the huge negatives is
you have to be able to search MP right
where a search and T doesn't have to do
that so you never need to know you never
need to know need to form the search
space the space right the P space and
what that means is like with search and
P right if you imagine I'm I've got some
crazy collision geometry here in order
to search for the closest point to
something like here which is what search
and P is doing it's got to be able to
actually know how to look through the
space and figure out what that closest
point is search and T never does that
sir
he just tries to drive in a straight
line if it hit something it changes
direction that's it so it never even
knows really necessarily what the space
looks like and that can be much more
efficient right so this is definitely
the more efficient algorithm in the
normal case right the other problem is
this is handles like bounciness better
right and this doesn't and that's
because with search and P you don't
really know how many times you would
have collided with a wall to get where
you are and stuff like that so this is a
little bit better if you want bouncy
things this is better usually if you get
basically this is a plus up until the
point where you want things to bounce a
lot and then this becomes a plus right
and so really search and tea with fixing
this unbounded in iterations problem so
just full-on saying will produce the
wrong result by bounding it arbitrarily
just is going to be way more efficient
than this is and so I just kind of
decided this is you know just not gonna
be a good algorithm for us to choose
because we don't really care that much
about this and we just give up too much
because we have to do all this extra
work to produce the space in the witness
we have to produce the space anyway for
other reasons and so that's why I chose
to well I even choose to do this this
actually just turned out to be the most
efficient algorithm in the witness
because of the way we were doing things
but this is gonna be way more efficient
for a Mahiro I think because we never
build these spaces so hopefully that
makes some sense
how does the aim handle the state of the
two separate players when they are on
different floors
well the collision detector just works
right because it's it's using the the
tile Z of wherever the entity that is
that it's colliding so that's just
that's doesn't matter it's really the
rendering that we have to worry about
because we don't know what we're going
to do when people go off screen what we
may do is just say that only the main
character determines where the screen is
and the secondary character can't go
can't leave the screen we might just
make that rule so that we don't have to
have like split screen or something
that's going to be weird
why is the code complexity for piece art
so much greater than T search so the
reason is because of that of that
process of searching so basically i've
already told you you know 25 percent or
50 percent of the code necessary like
this is not that far from the complete
code that we're actually going to need
to implement certainty
it's just iterating doing this a bunch
of times right and we're basically all
we're gonna do when we move to a better
collision detection than what we're
doing with them then just point verses
infinite wall when we move to like
circle or ellipse versus sort of
arbitrary shape or something right all
we're gonna do is have a fancier set of
equations here like a slightly fancier
set right that's all that's gonna happen
but the algorithm is the same it's still
just like okay drive along the line see
where you when you hit something change
the direction you're driving drive
Samora see if you hit something that's
all that's it that's all that happens
it's nothing else going on and so given
that that's the case it's just really
simple code complexity wise to implement
this it's just the simplest darn thing
and if you want to do search in P it's
much harder search and P is basically a
closest point problem it says take all
the geometry that you've got whatever it
is that the person's walking through
take a point and I want to know the
closest point on where you know to that
point and so what you have to do is you
then have to know how to be able to
search firstly it's in two things you
have to be able to search all along the
edge of all the geometry to see what the
closest point actually would be which is
very complicated and you have to do that
for another shape right because whatever
the shape the player is it's not just
really closest point it's closest
extruded point so it's like it's the
closest center of some collision shape
right so in the case of a player who's
represented by an ellipse or something
it's the closest place and ellipse could
be that's close to that point or
something right and so you have to like
minkowski your geometry
or do other kind of stuff there it's
complicated whereas we will just be able
to bake that right into these when we do
them you'll see so that's complicated
but what's also complicated is the fact
you have to know whether the player
could have gotten there so you still
have to end up doing a passing thing to
see whether the player could get there
because you don't want them to be able
to tunnel through walls with this system
right and so depending on what you
actually have this is either very
expensive or free in the case of the
witness it was free to do this but in
the case of this game it would be very
expensive and this is going to be much
cheaper
why not treat the map as a matrix and
validate objects and its collisions
through coordinates what problems can
appear with this mindset I'm not really
sure what you mean by that if the map
itself was a matrix that's really no
different than what we have now which is
just a tile map and the problem is that
when you look to see you need to know
between two points you need to know if
you hit anything in between and so you
still have to write this collision code
for the matrix thing but really remember
we're gonna be doing something better
than a tile map so we're just using the
tile map right now because that's all we
actually have is a world representation
but we're actually gonna be allowing all
kinds of crazy stuff for closing section
like we're gonna be allowing arbitrary
geometries for close detection so we
don't a matrix really wouldn't be able
to store the world anyway
so your towels are the 6:17 by ten
blocks I'm fuzzy on collision detection
as the player moves from tile to tile I
get lost on the world coordinate tiles
coordinate and screen coordinates still
I guess well I mean we've kind of gone
over this a bunch of times so I'm not
sure how to elaborate on it on anyway
other than how we already have basically
our tiles you can just think of the
tiles as a giant 4 billion by 4 billion
array right so we've got ABS tile X and
ABS tile Y for a person's location and
ABS tiles II just think of these as a
giant 4 billion by you know by 4 billion
by 4 billion world ok so it's a giant
cube made up of tiny cubes that's 4
billion by 4 billion by 4 billion right
you know let's let's go over here
okay so this is our world right this is
four billion long this is 4 billion long
this is for a billion long in tiles so
each tile is this tiny little thing
right and then at any given time we take
out a little slice of that world right
that's seventeen by ten or whatever we
said it was seventeen by nine something
like that seventeen by ten who knows I
can't remember what we're drawing
something like that we take out a little
slice from somewhere in there and we
draw it on the screen as the tile map
right that's all we're doing now we have
a sparse storage mechanism that breaks
up this cube since we can't store for a
billion by four billion by four billion
that that basically just stores the
places where there's actually part world
data in them and so we have these tile
chunks that are pieces that are just a
storage thing but you don't have to
think about those where you think about
collision detection because Visnic
doesn't care it doesn't care where that
data is coming from it's just going to
do the iteration of the absolute tile
and disease right and so for the
collision detection all that happens is
we just pull out those tile use and go
okay take where the player was and take
where he's going and let's check all of
the tiles that he could that are around
there to see if any of them are solid
and if they are figure out where he
would hit them and and stop his motion
there and that's what we were trying to
write right now can this week's time to
3d collision yes the equations are the
same in 2d and 3d
could you check collisions by looking at
the players position and seeing if it's
in the inner side of the vectors along
the walls like it's up from the bottom
well vector it's to the right of the
left ball vector yes as an optimization
you can definitely do that
so one optimization that you can do and
we'll kind of we'll probably get to some
of these well it's kind of hard to say
which exactly ones we'll end up doing as
depends how we do things but if you
imagine that you've got a guy here's our
p0 and here's our D so there's our
direction and we're going along here and
we want to know when we get this thing
so we're gonna check against these walls
right here are all the collision points
we would find right here's when he hits
this wall here's when he hits this wall
here's where he hits this wall and
here's where he hits this wall now these
two collisions would get thrown out
immediately because they're outside the
bounds that we allowed for the wall so
we would throw those out right but these
two collisions are both valid and then
we would take the closest one which is
this one and what you were talking about
is can we use the information about
where the player is to maybe do less
work here at least I think that's what
you were saying and the answer is yes we
could what we could do is since we know
that these walls basically have a
sightedness to them right we basically
know that in here you cannot stand and
so the walls kind of have a direction
they kind of point outwards if you will
right what we could do is see which
direction the player is moving or which
direction he is which direction we could
see where the player is relative to the
thing and only take those walls that are
pointing towards him because we know he
can't ever point he can't ever hit a
wall facing away from him because he hit
some other wall first so we could just
flat-out reject these two because they
are not pointing towards him only these
are pointing towards him and how would
you compute that well it's our old
friend the inner product a transpose V
we'll compute that
how will it compute that well you
remember it maps one vector onto another
it is a B cosine theta and what does
facing someone
well if we took the sort of direction
from the the tile to the guy right
we know that it's this direction we want
vectors that are not pointing backwards
from that vector right we want these
vectors not these vectors so what we can
do is say all right the angle between
those guys the theta between this and
this and this and this right has to be
less than 90 degrees right if the angle
between them was greater than 90 degrees
you'd be in trouble what do we know
about cosine theta well cosine theta
right if cosine if that angle if theta
is less than 90 degrees right then
cosine is positive but if it's greater
than 90 degrees right then it's negative
until it flips back around again right
so we compute that dot product we could
actually just use the sine of a
transpose B to tell us which of these
would actually be in play so you
absolutely could do what you were saying
it's just an optimization but it'd be a
nice optimization right so again we'll
look at stuff like that a little later
on
what's your point on zero length vector
normalization and what behavior does
your code have so we haven't really
quite gotten to that yet but yeah if you
notice here we don't have any
normalization happening when things are
zero because we're only looking at one
point oh right we're only looking at
things that are greater than 1.0 so we
we would never divide by zero here
because we'd be fine but if you were
trying to do something normalization
wise then yes you have to worry about
that
so hmm I guess I deleted that because I
hadn't thought of my infinite swirl yet
so basically if you think about what
happens when we do that that canonical
equation where I said we had the new
length we want for a vector divided by
the old length we want write times the
vector itself gives us a new vector
that's that's a different length with
this length right when I said that
obviously it's it's also again that
thing of length of a equals it cannot be
equal to zero right because it's the
same as before where I saying it you
can't divide by zero value now we didn't
actually ever that cuz condition can't
happen here so I was not bringing it up
yet but when we get to that we'll talk
about it a little bit more basically
what happens is before you do anything
with a vector to change the vectors
length you have to be sure that its
length currently isn't zero because if
it's length were zero that would means
that it has no direction it's just here
it doesn't it doesn't point anywhere
it's so you can't change its length
there's no way to know what it's like
would have been and so that's something
that you have to handle on a
case-by-case basis you need to know what
was the purpose that you were doing you
know what were you trying to accomplish
when you did this and when you and when
you know what the purpose is you know
how to handle the zero case you know
what you should do in that case right
how can sometimes players enter
glitching lis through the corners of
walls or fall through them is that an
art mistake or programming the answer is
it can actually be either so basically
you can have two you can have two
conditions happen there
one is that the collision geometry is
just wrong
right and so one case is I've got a
thing and it looks like that right the
collision geometry looks like this and
the player is only that big and he fits
between them and then he can glitch
through it so even though maybe it's
drawn like a solid thing the collision
geometry is wrong and he can glitch
through it another one's a programming
bug the programming bug happens when the
collision resolution the collision
resolve is not robust in the face of
twiki situations right so let's say like
I'm jamming into a corner here you know
in that corner basically has you know a
couple of different things of budding in
it like this you know something like
that and maybe this is empty here and
set to here and so these two things kind
of abut and I've got this thing where I
can glitch through there because I'd I'm
not conservative about how I'm checking
for the collision with my guys somehow
right that could certainly occur
it occurs in cases I mean I'd have to
know the specific code to know why the
glitch was occurring right but you can
certainly have just things that are
numerical precision problems and people
not thinking through how to do the
collision right or whatever so it may
not be art can we look at our dropped
frames it's been quite choppy so it
looks a little dropping but not too much
I don't know I don't know we're people
on the stream in general having a
problem
let's see
I don't know if anyone yeah can anyone
tell me if we were having choppiness
problems I don't know if we're having
chopping his problems or not yeah so
we're almost done here I think I'm day
47 we've got what have we got about ten
minutes left okay so I think kuru I
think that was just you who was dropping
the frame sorry don't blame my isp yet
it's not their fault this time alright
so that it for questions so we can end
early
yeah I don't see any more questions so I
think I'm a I don't know how to I I feel
like we've now gotten too huge for for I
want to kind of delete this so we're not
taking up so much space there we go
I'm afraid that that krita's gonna run
out of room for us here all right so
we'll put that back like that for next
time
there we go okay so I think that's it I
don't see any more questions I'm
surprised that the new timer code
actually worked that's kind of
surprising to me I was expecting it to
roll over and die and really we only had
one problem which is that it I didn't
actually have the thing
stop telling us when the stream was
already started but that's okay so
that's good the stream now supports
fractional our boundaries just quite
robust
all right so yeah this was a bit
disappointing today because I hope to
get to that and I guess you know a large
part of the problem was I decided to
talk about vector lengths which you know
takes up some time but what are you
gonna do what are you gonna do
storm buzzes do you need to do the math
when doing solid walls and objects or is
that just basic program arithmetics well
you need to do the math regardless of
what the thing is are I'm not sure you
mean by solid walls aren't all walls
solid yeah I'm sorry I don't quite
understand the question if you want to
rephrase it though I can answer it
so yeah it doesn't look like any
questions so I think we are done we can
call it and everyone can you know go
program get program on their own I
actually wanted to go fix something in
the witness just now I'm Mei she wrote
me back about a thing that I was doing
wrong that was that about iterating over
collision geometry that I was like I'm
not sure how to I don't actually know
how to tell what this material is
because I don't know the engine very
well and so now that I know that I'd
like to go do that so maybe I will go do
that if that makes sense
and of them I think he means graphically
walls maybe hollow inside so doing the
math of the whole object or just the
outer collidable parts oh so well it if
you think about it though it doesn't
matter right because if a thing if an
object is solid right so if I have a
solid object and I have a hollow object
but that stills got you know it's got
walls right there's no difference
between these two things as far as the
collision detection is concerned if a
guy is walking into this thing he still
stops here regardless right so the
equations are the same whether he's in a
solid thing or a hollow thing it doesn't
matter if just all that matters is the
first wall he could run into and they're
the same in both cases
right you only for collision detection
you only care about the boundary of the
thing you don't care what's inside it
because you can never get inside it
that's the whole point the closed
reduction is to prevent that right all
right so I think that's it
I will go ahead and call it for now we
will close this down hello awesome I
kind of like it when he pops up I can't
wait to do his animation controller his
animation controller is gonna be so much
fun
and that's what we'll do it right after
we finish the collision detection but
like getting him hopping along is gonna
be the most fun thing to do and it will
also be the thing that most motivates us
to go do the renderer because once we do
the hopping we'll really want to be able
to bend his body like to emphasize the
hop but of course we can't with our draw
a bitmap code that we have right now and
so that'll be like the perfect thing to
make us want to go do like a nice
renderer that can do like bending of
stuff right so yeah anyway okay so I'm
gonna go ahead and close this down and
come to me there we go
let's see
okay so thank you very much for joining
me this evening I'm sorry that we didn't
quite get to finish the thing that I
wanted to finish so we will try to do
that tomorrow and then we can move on to
doing some more animation sorts of stuff
although we may actually want to do a
little more collision detection because
now that we've got two guys in there we
probably want to throw like a monster in
there and and collide against the
monster and move it have different
moving things colliding so well well
well sort of probably we probably will
have to do maybe the rest of this week
on collision because we'll want to do
all that stuff and get out to doing a
nice rounded volume for the player and
so on so we've realistically speaking we
probably have a fair bit more collision
detection to do but I didn't want to
finish just the simple wall case the
simple vertical horizontal wall case
today so we could get on another stuff
so sorry about that but we'll finish it
up tomorrow and then we'll move on to
sort of the more complex law cases to
sort of see how to build a more
interesting closure detector that
doesn't work things that are better
better for the field the game so thank
you very much for joining me is been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to pre-order the game and
get the source code you can do that at
handmade hero org and you can download
the source code every night I upload it
every night you'll get a link in your
email and you can use that link over and
over and over again to download the
source code every night you just save
the link that comes and you can always
go back there and download the latest
source so if you want to do that you can
do that a hammer here or if you want to
just support the video series you can
subscribe to our patreon as well which
we have which is right here and then if
you want to study the series more in
depth we also have a news and forum site
that's got a bunch of stuff on it that
you might want to use it's got the
schedule for the week in case you want
to know when we're broadcasting each
week it's got an episode guide so you
can catch up on previous episodes that's
really great it's got time coded videos
and all this stuff it's pretty awesome
we've got coding resources which is like
ports to Mac OSX and Linux and stuff so
if you're trying to run out in from
platform you can check that out and we
also have a code discussion board so if
you want to ask questions or sort of
talk more about a particular episode
that is the place to do it and hey let
the timer even still worked check that
out alright so thank you very much for
joining me I will be back tomorrow 8
p.m. Pacific Standard Time tomorrow our
standard time slot since John is not
doing to power Denver tomorrow and so I
certainly hope see you
there and have a wonderful Monday I'm
sorry Wednesday either way
take it easy everyone