hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream I apologize I was sick
this week so my voice is a little
gravelly today and but I'm feeling okay
I'm not feeling too bad so I'm assuming
that will be okay here we'll see how it
goes we don't have anything to
ridiculous plan for today so I'm
assuming it'll be fine um what we
stopped on last week was actually kind
of promising I had kind of anticipated
things being a little more difficult
than they were which is always a
surprise in programming because you know
a lot of times in programming where you
were more focused on the backwards
surprise where you're like I thought
this was gonna be easy or I thought this
wouldn't take that long but then it did
right because of unforeseen complexities
that you know you didn't anticipate and
so you know now you're you're having to
do more work or spend more time on
something than you thought but sometimes
you get the opposite and it turned out
we ended up getting the opposite here we
were playing around with our sprites and
saying I saying okay I got it for how to
do the sorting now on these guys but it
turned out actually that editing the
y-values just as a direct slide
proportional to the alignment as we did
last Sunday turned out to give us
basically perfect results like it's
exactly what I wanted and I haven't seen
any problems with it like it does
exactly what I want pretty much all the
time and so all we really needed to do
today before saying all right great is
we just have to do a little bit more
formalization of that to make sure that
we've got it
where we want it now just to explain
there's two parts of the formalization
that need to happen
and you know they're they're both a
little bit different so if I
like let me let me try to create a
circumstance that's a little bit clearer
here so you know let's suppose we've got
the hero on here well you can already
see right so we haven't set the
alignment points for the hero and now we
made this nice debug camera by the way I
know for the folks who haven't been
watching the past couple episodes you
may have missed it our debug camera is
pretty great now so yeah we were just in
the middle of doing that stuff so we
probably should finished up some of that
do it looks like we've got a weirdness
there though as I'm saying it's great
I'm noticing that we were using the
wrong axes there for sliding oh yeah we
are we're not using the debug axes
actually we're using the game axes for
sliding we should change that in fact
let me just change that right now before
I even say what I was gonna say did you
notice that I don't know if anyone
noticed that but me probably if no-one
played around with with the debug camera
they wouldn't noticed it but anyway we
did some really cool stuff video camera
you can now switch for game camera debug
camera which is pretty cool we solved
for the you know it's not I've
complicated solve but it's just fun to
get stuff like a little stuff like that
right we solved for the trig to place
the orbit camera at the same place as a
game camera so you get a seamless switch
when you switch into debug camera mode
which is really nice I like that but
anyway yeah I noticed just now when I
was sliding around we're using the wrong
axis and that's true you can see here we
get the camera x y and z-axes here and
we use those right we process the the
input here and then we go in here and do
the use debug camera and here's those
processing that transform right so the
axes that we want are actually in here
they're part of this debug camera oh
right that's that's what's actually what
we would want and so we actually need
some way of pulling that part out in
order to properly build the debug camera
right
so if you look at what happens one thing
that's kind of nice about it is debug
camera pan is actually used later on so
if I wanted to I actually could do this
and split these two out right that's
totally possible and so what I can do is
I can actually say oh alright if I just
grab this part and move it down here
then what will happen is well and you
know we may even not quite want to do
that because we may want to to use as
much as we can on the input so for
example if we want to use the rotation
stuff we can the only thing that we
would be wrong about would be right here
the camera pan part so what I can do I
can even go a little bit further and say
oh actually you know what I should do is
say here we are in you know using the
debug camera and whatever let me
actually do a second pass on the input
here so I'm just gonna say look this
input just as we were doing before I'm
just gonna grab out the part where we do
the panning and that way we still can
update everything on the same frame
right because I could have I need the
axes that I'm computing here but those
axes are dependent on the input because
you might be rotating around but then I
want to update the position based on
those axes so I I could store them for
the next frame that seems like bad to
introduce a frame of lag so instead I'm
just gonna do the partial update here
and then after I know what this
orientation is I can go ahead here and
and snap these these axes to use right
so that allows me to say look if we're
using the debug camera and I can
actually roll that into this code
because this input only needs to happen
in that case so we can actually put it
right here in fact so if you know we're
using debug camera and the input is
valid so we're actually doing input
we're not just you know doing some kind
of processing that doesn't involve any
input then all I need to do is just
check to see if this part is down here
right if the middle mouse button is down
if the middle mouse button is down then
your doing that panning right so I can
just say look if the middle mouse button
is down do the pant we need to make sure
that the alt button is not down though
because if the alt was down we would do
the other one so we need to also say
look don't let the alt be down but
that's about it and so then when we do
this this update of the debug camera pan
then that will flow into here properly
so the only other thing we would then
need is we just need to do debug camera
engines and debug camera why and then
what we do is when we flow through this
code we just need to say look if we're
using debug camera so we've built the
orientation matrix for the debug camera
then what I can do is just get that I
can get the axes out of there
now these things need to persist down to
here right because I need to be able to
use them I need to be able to use both
of those so I'm gonna go ahead and put
them up I could also just always compute
them if I want to write you know this
this isn't something that's super
computation intensive so if I want to I
can actually do it like this where I'm
always going to compute that right
that's totally fine as well so if I want
to I can make it look a little bit more
like this
and as this sort of falls out we could
probably simplify this code a little bit
too but you get the idea all right
so assuming that that actually happens I
guess that makes it even less necessary
to do this because actually these can
just happen in here where they would
actually be used so right here we could
just do that where we just do get column
and so what I'm gonna do is take the
orientation matrix and as we've gone
over many many many times column of the
orientation matrix tell me the axes of
the object that we would be using that
we would place using that orientation
matrix
so I'm just going to go ahead and pull
out the x and y-axes of that matrix to
get my debug camera and debug camera Y
now at that point we don't really need
these thing around anymore
but you know whatever I'm just gonna
leave them that way because it seems
fine to do so so I'm gonna go ahead and
build here and let me just take a look d
Mouse what's going on there
ah so D Mouse pee is actually just the
difference that happens here so I think
that's actually something that we could
again preserve so you know there's no
issue with doing that because if we
didn't have input then there's just no
no Delta Mouse which is exactly what we
expect right all right so that minor
patch there now should give us proper
movement everywhere and you can see that
it does so now we properly do the debug
camera before again we were just we were
doing proper camera relative motion we
were just doing it relative to the game
camera and that doesn't really help us
right because we're only viewing from
the game camera when we're not in debug
mode so why would that you know why
would we ever want to do that alright so
hopefully that made sense to everybody
now back to our story so let me switch
back to game camera here for a second
what I was trying to say before is all
right so you know if you take a look at
one of these sprites and you know I mean
there's the hero if I switch into debug
camera mode I can go in here and inspect
what's going on right I can I can look
at how we're actually rendering the
world you can see if they're right how
it sort of stacks up so what I wanted to
be able to do here was have a coherent
idea of how alignment points were to
actually be working with the system that
allows the sprites to to show up in Z
properly right and we did a great job of
that I was really surprised that the
slide and Y was as simple as it was
let that be a lesson but now we have to
talk about actually setting these
alignment points permanently and a
couple things that we need to do in
order to make all this work properly so
first of all even if we were to just do
what we already did which is slide the
alignment points and why the current
algorithm that we have is not quite
sufficient the reason that the algorithm
isn't quite sufficient is because if you
imagine what would happen with rotate
rotating one of these so imagine that it
was spinning around we don't currently
take into account tilting of the x and y
axes in order to figure out where we
would slide so when we rotate something
we need to have an idea about what that
rotation means in this sort of slanted
space that keeps the sorting accurate
right and so I'm gonna probably go throw
in like maybe we'll just make the the
fist rotate continuously or the head
rotate continuously so you can see what
I mean so that's the first thing you
have to address these are in no
particular order X reasons a first thing
that's one thing after dress and the
second thing we have to address is that
if you look at how these things are
being aligned right now we have this
notion of alignment points so if I go in
to the editor here and I just say look
I'm gonna pick one of these things like
I don't know I want to pick the the
alignment of this base piece here right
here's a list of all those alignment
points and you can actually see white
strip to the side right because we were
playing with that the alignment points
there and when so you know this right
here was shifted to the side that it
should really be more about halfway
right so you can kind of see where that
alignment point is there and the
alignment points obviously actually I
need to make it so that if the Alt key
is down we don't process clicks should
do that for ease of use but anyway if we
go back here and take a look at what it
looks like from the game camera right
turn the sky off here you can see that
the alignment points not in the right
place so the actual place the alignment
point needs to be is like you know
probably like right there right that's
like where it looks like it's more
correctly anchored into the ground like
at the point that it's supposed to be
right so it's probably something like
that and then this point which is where
the head anchors on probably is like
maybe there I you know I don't know
exactly right but it's something like
that and so then if you take a look at
what that looks like and maybe I'll keep
it turned off for now if we go into the
debug camera mode right yeah I really
got to fix that because otherwise it's
gonna keep deselecting every time I
rotate around but if you look at sort of
where those points are right there they
don't really they are drawn in the
correct location for the object that
they're on right because we compute what
the axes are to render that object and
then we move the those points to the
right locations what I don't remember if
we did is something that would do the
right thing for the person we're
attaching meaning I don't know if we
take into account both sets of axes or
if we assume that those axes are gonna
actually be the same so what I don't
know and this is the other part we have
to look at is once you actually snap one
of these things on there so we've got
this base of neck thing right are those
points now snap together properly do
they line up correctly you know what I
mean and so if we take a look at at
where the different points are so this
is those are the two points for the body
I'm gonna grab the head here those are
the two points for the body there's the
point for the head that's supposed to
align with it let's say add one on here
right so if I were to create an
arbitrary ups that supposed to be two
parents all right
if I was to create an arbitrator's
placement would that still align two to
the right place you know and if you look
at it it seems like clearly that's not
because that's the point that we're
supposed to be aligning to right but
here's the point that we're saying we're
aligning and it doesn't line up right
they don't so they're not you know
they're supposed to be snapping together
they're not snapping together and again
that's because we're changing those axes
and I don't think we actually did the
work to say make sure that these two
points in these two coordinate systems
actually end up in the same apparent
visual like location to the viewer at
least if not in world space in their
entirety right so that's another thing
that we have to deal with and we want to
make sure that that's correct as well so
those are the two things that we have to
do but fortunately they're quite easy
meaning there's nothing unknown about
that process now again any time we're
dealing with 3d math there's a lot of
stuff involved and so it might take us a
little while to work through it and get
it right and get it to bugged so it's
not like it's easy as in quick but it is
easy from the standpoint of we're not
going into uncharted territory like we
were before when it has like I don't
really know what the best way to create
these sprites in a way that sorts them
into this real 3d environment you know
you know given that we're doing so many
things that normal 2d 3d games don't do
like with real perspective shifts and
stuff like that a lot of times I try to
be more isometric to avoid a lot of
these problems so we really wanted our
territories there we came out the other
end in fabulous forum which I'm you know
luck was with us so that was pretty good
you know you persevere sometimes luck is
with you so this is not as hard that's
what I thought we were gonna have to do
which is going to be much more
exploration --all
all right so let's just start looking at
the VAT code and let's try to bring that
code in line with what we need it to do
based on those things that I said so
here's the entity code and we really
have I'm going to move it to their
window so my head's not in the way so
here's the entity code and we really
have you know a pretty straightforward
thing we're doing here it's just there's
a lot of bookkeeping involved so it's a
little bit complicated all the stuff
that goes in right so what you can see
here is we've got these piece index
things right that's a particular entity
can have any number of these pieces and
what you can see here is those pieces
they kind of come together and you say
all right I've got these piece indexes
I've got a particular visible piece it's
got you know some kind of deformations
that I might want to put on it right
like these axis deform stuff those are
things for some of that procedural
animation that we're doing Bob is the
same right all the sort of stuff floor
displacement all these things so we're
computing some animation quantities
those will probably get a little more
complicated and a little bit more
well-defined over time as we push more
down the animation side of things but
basically we've got those coming in to
it and then what we want to know is all
right
let's go ahead and get our this part is
for picking and stuff that we use the
dev IDs and stuff that's for the for
doing like you know the editor and stuff
like that so we have to worry about that
too much but then assuming that this
thing isn't a light or a cube because
lights and cubes are actually 3d so we
don't have to do any like mojo you know
we don't have to do extra work to make
sure that those things place themselves
into the environment properly we can
just hand those to the render and
because they're actual 3d shapes it just
works
through the pipeline right so really
what we're worried about now is just
this one case here where we're saying
this is an entity
peace this is a piece of an enemy that's
got just a sprite you know it's got a
bitmap that sticks on to a plane right
so here we are with that and we get the
bitmap back and we take a look at what
the parent piece is gonna be so when we
do that parent piece thing what that's
telling us is who we're supposed to snap
to right so you know we create one of
these sprites we say maybe that's the
body and then we say maybe it's got a
head and we stick the head on to the
body or something like this right so
then when we do that we say alright
let's find the alignment that's whatever
you said we needed to use to stick these
two together so we're just we're getting
for any given piece we say what
alignment point on its parent did you
want it to stick to you know what are we
supposed to stick it to right and
where's the alignment point on this
thing that we want to use SiC right so
this one is the one that says this one
is the one that gets the one that we're
you know that's on us the you know the
snap point on us and this one is the one
that gets the snap point on our parent
now since there isn't always a parents
that's why we pre select the ground
point of the entity where the entity is
standing because if we don't have any
other information if we don't have
someone to stick our stick us to we'll
stick to the ground right all right so
after we do all of this right we've got
all of that information ready then we
say okay now it's time to actually do
this computation so here is where we
need to actually produce the the final
results so this is the part you know all
of that stuff really doesn't affect us
it's just getting all of the bookkeeping
in place even if all that stuff were
wrong it's okay that's debugging for a
different day the part where we come out
with two points now we've got them so
the question is stick them together and
that's our job today
stick those two points together right
[Music]
okay so the first thing you can see here
is we're taking the initial placement
point and that initial placement point
is the you know is this alignment point
here and the thing that you can see kind
of right off the bat is this world P
from a line P that's assuming that it
can produce a world point from a
particular alignment point in one of the
parent sprites now I'm skeptical that
it's actually doing that correctly at
this point and so I want to see if
that's actually true so you can see the
sprite values here and you can see the
alignment point here and you can see the
scaled x axis scaled y axis see it you
can see these alignment values right
being what they are now just looking at
that you can kind of see that will be
correct if and only if the values min P
that we recorded takes into account the
Y bias that we were talking about before
okay so here's our sprite values for up
right call this is the one we were
talking about here and what you can see
is this this part right here where the
min P gets gets created although I was
skeptical that we were doing correctly
it does look like we did right
we took the aligned P and we said all
right whatever the alignment point is
that we're using we're gonna interpret
it out this way and you know that's
where it's gonna be drawn right that's
what the Mindi so it really does sort of
correctly represent that minimum base
point using the slid out why that we
were talking about before
who knew
so that's a good first step it means
that we're already in a good shape for
creating exactly what we need to create
right now this isn't handling the
rotation like we wanted to but again
like I said the rotation part will come
in later and the reason that this isn't
handling the rotation part properly is
again because this alignment Y slide has
to take into account when these axes
start to shift the actual points how
they should be moved out in Y need to be
considered individually so this part is
going to get more complicated but before
we start comp making it more complicated
I want to get it correct for the non
rotating case for obvious reasons right
like let's start with a simpler case
first alright so that actually seems
pretty reasonable and then so the
question is well what about the scaled x
axis scaled y axis part of things and
this aline p part right here so that
world p from a line p that's happening
there when that uses those scaled axes
again that seems like that should be
correct because those axes that we're
recording here are actually the ones
that are being used you know with the
with the lie down taken into account so
that point should slide along the
slanted plane exactly the way that we
think it should right so all of that
seems pretty good to me
and I'm not seeing any real reason why
that part shouldn't produce correct
answers now let's just take a quick
second to make sure that what we see on
the screen reflects that and and there
isn't some other you know indication
that that's not actually happening so if
I go ahead back to the game here and I
select one of these you know and I
select one of these guys like the person
we were working with before what I want
to see now is if I go it went in here
and I slid this point around maybe the
easiest way to do it would be to get
right in there and looking at the plane
almost slide on
right and so if I select this now and I
go to the those alignment points this
green point is this one here let's just
make sure it actually slides along that
plane properly right and it really does
look like it's correct like if I go all
the way up to the upper corner of that
plane there right
and then I I come back here and I take a
look at it a little bit more closely so
let me grab that again you know it's
right where it should be so I would say
that our initial attempt to sort of get
those values out I'm relatively
comfortable that doesn't look like
there's a lot of surprises there so
that's good alright so now let's talk
about the part where we try to actually
align to that snapped point because
since we've seen that it doesn't seem to
work but these points look correct that
suggests that at least for the
non-rotating rotated case we aren't
doing the work we need to do in this
next part of the algorithm here right
because if we're producing the alignment
point on our parent correctly but we're
not snapping to that point the way we
think we should that kind of only leaves
one place for the bug at least in the
obvious sense alright so here we are
getting the world dimensions of this
piece that we're going to be putting
down and here's us asking for the sprite
values for upright part of things so
that gets us back into this routine and
what we're doing is we're passing the x
and y axis of rotation that we want
imagining that we were in the plane
eventually so this is just giving us
regular 2d axes that we want for us
right and that alignment point is the
one that we've computed here right oh no
I'm sorry
initial P is the point we're aligning to
a line P is the percentage in our space
where the point we're trying to align
you know where that would would would
occur right look where that snapping
point should be and so now we kind of
have to figure out okay how is that go
to work now this gets again more
complicated because we have to remember
that these planes we maybe that when we
snap these things together we're not
necessarily snapping them together in Z
right we're snapping them together only
from the perspective of the person
looking and I can't really think oh well
you know what let me just show you it in
the games like I get draw a diagram but
then I'm like you know what just showing
you in the game is probably easier so if
you look at what's going on here
these two sprites are intentionally
separated in Z and the reason that
they're separated in Z and you know they
don't really need to be separated that
as much as they are necessarily but the
reason if they're separated in Z like
that is specifically because we don't
want to stack them right on top of each
other in the plane because if we stacked
them right on top of each other in the
plane then there's two things that don't
work properly one is that we wouldn't
necessarily get the proper perspective
shifting that we might want from things
that are supposed to be a little bit
tall but the other thing that we
wouldn't get is we wouldn't leave
sufficient room for the z-buffer to
resolve properly if they're right in the
same plane you would get potentially
z-fighting because since you know
there's limited precision arithmetic
going on and it's not an infinitely
precise plane you get those little
sparkly artifacts that you see sometimes
in games when things it's called Z
fighting when things are trying to write
to the Z buffer and they don't precisely
calculate the plane equation correctly
so you get some pixels that show through
in some pixels that don't show through
from underlying objects so we do want
there to be some separation there as
well
all right so we have to kind of define
what it means to snap together in this
way we have to kind of come up with some
rules about what we actually expect to
be true and this is somewhat complicated
because there ways that we might want
them to be true
differ in terms of what we would
consider a correct result so one thing
that we could say is true is we could
say that from the perspective of the
camera we always want the alignment
points to appear as if they're on top of
each other right even though when we
then zoom rotate around like that we
will see that they are not in fact in
the same place in 3d when we rotate back
to here we would see that they come into
alignment so from our perspective they
would be right now that would be the
correct thing to do if we were concerned
only with the concept of an alignment
point in the abstract sense we want to
align these two points but there may be
reasons why we don't actually want that
to happen and it's again this is
actually an aesthetic decision it has
nothing to do with 3d math or anything
else it's a it's an actually an artistic
decision and what I'm gonna do is going
to show you what I mean here in the
hallway by selecting this particular
fellow here I guess let me go ahead and
go into debug cam so I can pick him yeah
let's let's say let's say that we shrink
the head down I know it's gonna be a
little bit weird right let's say we
shrink the head down like that and then
let me go back to the game camera and
let's let's go back here right so as I
move across the screen I want you to pay
attention to the location of the head
relative to the body and what you can
see is you actually get a sense of
perspective even though these are not 3d
they're 2d sprites and they're aligned
to the camera to a certain degree but
because we have allowed some of the 3d
to affect the sprites and we allow the
full 3d to affect their pin we allow
their position to be fully effective in
3d and we allow the slanting of them
into full 3d to be partially true right
we partially orient to the camera
and we partially orient to the world but
because we have enough of the 3d coming
through what you can see is the
perspective shift on the head is
actually fairly pronounced you can sort
it sort of feels a little bit more 3d as
the character moves from side to side
because you actually see him tip as if
he was a real 3d object right so what we
don't necessarily want to do because I
think that's a fairly compelling
artistic result that we can make use of
as we actually build our sprites and
align things what I don't think we want
to do is make a rule that says let's
actually pin these two points together
using the cameras perspective because
what that would do is that would
actually eliminate some of that 3d
motion by using the cameras actual 3d
location to adjust the location of the
head in the body right it would
essentially be fighting the natural 3d
motion by introducing this synthetic
constraint that doesn't have anything to
do with well it does have something to
do with but that isn't as close as just
the normal result would be to the 3d
tilting of that stack of sprites so I
think we want the to the 3d tilting of
that stack of sprites to occur and so
what I might propose is the best way to
talk about our alignment is to say let's
suppose that we were right in line with
the camera so we're going to presuppose
that the camera cannot be off access
when we're doing alignment and let's say
that the alignment point should line up
there okay so we will try to do the
correct math that forces these points
into alignment when you're right down
the barrel of the gun so to speak right
but when you get to the sides we will
continue to apply that same alignment as
if the camera was over there so that we
let the natural 3d display
meant to the side do the work it would
have done right so I think that is
probably how we want to do it that way
when we're authoring the points there's
a natural way of talking about them they
snap together when we're looking
directly at them you know like this they
will snap together but when you move to
the side you'll get that sort of tilting
of the stack that gives you again that
extra feeling of real like tangibility
that you don't get with sprites normally
because when they move across the screen
no you get no parallax in a 2-d game
right so I think that's what I would
like that alignment idea to reflect and
when we look at how that's going to work
what you can see here is when we call
sprite values for upright we're passing
an initial P that is the information
that we would need to start with for
where we're trying to match so we're
giving it a proper world space location
that's actually on the plane of the
parent and that is the actual target
point that we're trying to snap to so I
would say that we've done our due
diligence and we don't really have to
worry about that point anymore at least
not till we start addressing the
rotation case which is the second part
of it if I come over here to sprite
values for upright and see what we're
doing with that however because again
remember them the only other thing we
really give ourselves is the Xbox mu
line P if we look at what we're doing
with that you know we've got that you
know so we've got that base P on there
um well I mean I guess I should I should
be more specific because it's actually
little upstream via that they probably
curse know what I said is not entirely
correct this piece offset here has
actually displaced right the snap to
point in three dimensions before we've
ever actually had a chance to snap to it
right so in a sense what I said was a
lie the part that I actually need to
talk about here is this part right here
and it has
happened before we we passed it just
right values for up right so that is
actually the thing we're gonna have to
deal with why here's why
so sprite values for up right we get a
base P in here and what you can see is
that base piece serves as the offset for
how we are going to construct the
location of our plane you can see it
happening in here right you can see the
align px shifting us on the axis and the
align py shifting us out in along the
worldwide there right and what you can
see happening here is that when we're
actually doing those computations we
have no knowledge actually of where
we're actually trying to snap to anymore
because this was the the point we were
trying to snap to but we already offset
it by something we never tell this
routine about so there's no way that
sprite values for up right can possibly
align this thing because it has no idea
right it just has no idea you know where
it should put it now we have a couple of
choices here sprite values for up right
doesn't have to be the thing that does
that alignment though so we don't
necessarily have to think about this way
what we could do instead is for example
this base P is only used for this offset
what we could do is get rid of that base
P so what we could do is say sprite
values for upright gives you the
alignment as if you were just going to
align yourself to world 0 and then
outside here maybe this is where we
actually do the snapping right it could
be um I'm somewhat can I find that
somewhat compelling right that that
seems pretty interesting so I think I
may start us off by going down that
direction now we're probably going to
get rid of Z bias it looks like we'll be
able to accomplish the job that we need
without Z bias and that will simplify
our back-end pipeline because we will no
longer
have to pass down four wide vertices or
if we do want to keep passing down four
wide vertices we can put something else
into the W component instead of having
to rely on instead of having to use it
for biasing the z-buffer
so actually that all is I think going to
be quite nice now that we've found that
we can just use the Y displacement to
make this work but so if I go ahead and
get rid of that then what I could do is
say all right so the align P align X
thing all that sort of stuff if I just
now start saying let's get rid of that
base P offset so when you actually try
to get sprite values we're just gonna
give you them a line to the world and
then what you need to do is on the
outside you need to come up with how
you're going to do your alignment
separately right and that seems kind of
compelling to me because whoops because
that would allow us to do a little bit
more that would allow us to take it into
a more contextual setting rather than
over here where we're just producing
these these sprite sort of these sort of
values that are isolated to the sprite
otherwise so if we wanted to reproduce
the exact situation we have now it's not
particularly difficult we know that the
min P that comes out of here is just not
getting offset by this thing right so
literally all we would have to do is say
well whatever comes out of there why am
I not give up there we go
whatever comes out of there I know that
I can just displace it by initial P and
that's going to reproduce the exact
results I had so it's pretty easy for me
to not actually bother you know to not
disturb anything that we had going on
currently or or not what did I oh yeah
sorry I accidentally deleted the minus
there as well you can see that those are
supposed to be minus alignments right
because the align peas inside it so
hopefully now yeah you can see we didn't
change the alignment at all so you know
we go in and look and it's exactly
stacked the way that we had it before
and everything
right so now if we think about how this
is working we now have the alignment
points in both of our spaces and now the
question is how do we make those two
alignment points appear to line up to
the camera right because that's what we
actually want to do and that allows us
to say oh well if we look at what goes
on in here so you see where we're do you
know where we're looking at this stuff
if I look at initial P you can see that
I don't really use it anywhere else
right it's only used for that what that
means is I can stop doing this piece off
set this thing here I can stop doing I
can do these as two separate steps right
and again that will give me the exact
same result that we already have because
all I'm doing there is is applying the
offset in two steps instead of one step
right so I get the same thing so now
what that means is I do actually know
the exact alignment point I'm trying to
align to it's this right that's the
parent point I know the offset that we
want to have in world space right so I
have an actual displacement that I'm
supposed to get because this piece is is
this piece right and I furthermore know
what I want I furthermore know the point
that on me that I'm trying to snap you
know to my parent because that's
actually coming out here the sprite min
P is the point in on this sprite before
I adjust it at all
that's the offset in me that I'm trying
to snap to right that that point I said
that a little bit wrong this is the
basis sprite min P is the basis point
you would draw the sprite around zero
zero zero is in this in this sprite
space is the point we would snap to
right we had zero B the point you would
snap to so we know that if we just
aligned if we just figure out how to
move this thing from being centered
around zero zero zero as the snap point
if we just move zero zero to the place
you want to be snap to we would be done
right
now let's verify that to ourselves a
little bit suppose I get rid of the
piece offset right so now we don't have
that additional offset that we're asking
for here we want to get rid of that and
let's see if now we snap directly
because we should snap directly one two
one
so if I look at what's going on now what
I should see and actually its I'm a
little bit weirded out why don't I see
anything there so I'm glad I did this
because I should have seen that much
more like I'm not sure where the Z
offset would be coming from
that's the offset look pretty
significant didn't it so I'm not okay
all right I take it back I'm a little
confused so there's something else we
need to account for here if we don't add
in the piece offset this is supposed to
Center us about zero zero zero right
well okay so no there is one more piece
of it if you look at what's going on
here the y-axis part has not actually
put us at the location that we would
need to be because the y-axis you can
see actually isn't taken into account
here at all
so that that I guess pretty much gives
us what we would need to know so I think
we still want to continue down the road
that I'm going down though I want this
to come out being centered around zero
zero zero because that gives us a
prepared piece that we can then do what
we want to do with so if you look at
what's happening here we will be
correctly centered around X because we
are moving backwards along the x axis
we're going to use for drawing by our
alignment point that keeps it aligned
properly we then move in Y backwards
along the world dim we don't use the y
axis part at all right what we want to
do now is say if we're doing that sort
of tilt right if that is what we're
doing we want zeros we still want to
Center this thing around zero zero zero
right and then presumably it's it's the
job of whoever's on the outside to
figure out how that alignments going to
work right so I realize that's a little
janky
let me draw this out for you because it
at least I think makes sense in my head
but I don't know other than a diagram a
good way to sort of show it to you and
and let you know what I'm thinking so
for doing alignment and again this is
really this is really a very simple case
all I'm trying to say with this is I
want away is there's the oh right okay
all I'm really trying to say is I want a
way for us to is there like a
full-screen yeah okay sorry
okay distracted what I'm trying to say
is I want a good way of telling the
exterior code which i think is the place
that the alignment should happen and you
know can use utility function to do the
alignment but it should work on these
two sprite things I want them to both
have concrete knowledge of the worlds
base points they're trying to align
right and so if I create this you know
the the sprite values for up right what
they're essentially doing is they're
saying okay you're giving me some point
like here and what I was doing is I say
well all right let's walk out about this
far right depending on the height of the
sprite and then we'll tilt it backwards
like that right so assuming that the
camera is looking from here you know and
that's gonna be the sprite points so I'm
gonna return min pees down here oops you
know and this part is the y-axis since
we're looking from the side here right
and you know if we wanted to draw it out
more completely it would be like okay if
we were looking from the cameras
perspective you give this point it walks
a little bit towards us in a little bit
out right we get sort of this we lie it
back a little bit and a little bit up
like that right we output this corner
point as min P we output these axes
right that's the y-axis this is the
x-axis and these are scaled right so it
includes that height value in there
that's what we're giving back now when
we do that when we get back them you
know these these coordinates what we
were doing before is we were passing in
the alignment point which was this thing
and then we were actually giving back to
world space like here's exactly where to
draw it I took out that alignment point
and so now what I want to do is have
zero zero zero be the alignment point so
the coordinates you get back are just
implicitly aligned around zero zero zero
so if you were to look at the sprite
itself like from the side on again
whatever the alignment point was that
you were trying to align to like say
this should actually be at zero zero
zero relative to where you're trying to
align right that means this whole thing
needs to get shifted down to line up
properly with that alignment point and
put it in the correct space okay so that
means I actually don't want that shift
the Y shifting that was happening here I
don't really want that to be happening
in the interior I want it to happen in
the exterior code okay and that's the
part I was trying to get to so the
reason I wanted in the exterior code is
because the exterior code needs to think
about it in order to figure out exactly
how it should snap the points together
right and so I just wanted to make sure
that was you know clearer in your head
as I do these next few things so that
means this code here right which I do
want to remember because it's good it's
the thing that actually worked right so
we like that but I don't actually want
to do it here what I want to do instead
is I want to retain exactly this piece
of information the thing that we were
doing before where we just create the
alignment I want to do that still okay
so even though this is gonna bring us
back to our old crappy
bad way of sorting that isn't good right
that's okay cuz it's temporary yeah
alright so now we should get exactly
aligned and we do right so Ennis and if
I go in here and switch to switch to a
debug mode where I look at those points
again if I add a point on here the two
parent matching point right whatever it
is so that's that red point there if I
look in here and I set the green point
the green point and the red point should
always agree right and they do right so
they're directly snapped one to the
other and that's what I want it so if I
start from that and now say okay how do
i construct that exterior code to snap
these two things together in a way that
makes sense right
well excuse me I apologize for blowing
my nose one of the consequences of
having too thick all right so if we take
a look at what's happening here what
were we sort of doing before where we
were just testing that code well all we
were really doing was saying look
instead of actually producing the
alignment point let's just tilt this
thing let's just push it outward and why
so that we still stay on the same z
plane as we were right just stay on the
same z plane well it's pretty easy for
me to make sure that we stay on the same
z plane as wherever I'm gonna align to
all I would have to do is look at what
the sprites outcoming Z values were form
in P and shift it back up right so if I
want to do essentially the same thing
that we were doing here I can I can just
do that myself on the outside right so
right here exactly this operation that
we were doing before where I say look I
want to shift this out I can do right
like this and if you look at what's
happening with the y axis there this
alignment would have been modifying the
Y in
some way right it definitely would have
modified the why of the alignment and if
we don't want the Y alignment to have
been modified you know look if we if we
don't want the Z or the Y or whatever to
have changed we can always also just
cold set those right so maybe we want
our Z to just always be like we don't
want our z axis to have been altered we
want to base it exactly on where it was
right we can also do anything we want to
do in that regard trivially right so on
the outside we can always fuss with what
comes back before we actually do any
additional work don't what is this bug
by the way we saw this before I wish we
had it in a debug build
it's asking to find an alignment and the
align points for a bitmap info let's
actually take a look at it
we saw it once before I'd like to know
what it is so we can fix it of course
the variable is optimized away I'm gonna
look at the disassembly really quickly
what
you I mean of course you can show me the
disassembly just show me where are you I
mean that's weird like just show me
where the code broke not that hard
alright anyway uh so just looking here
what are we actually trying to access so
it looks like we're loading off of RSI
it thinks that was the parent bitmap
info that was put into RSI it's looking
six off of RSI and then trying to access
it so if we actually look at the source
code there at this inline frame so the
align points P index I guess we don't
necessarily know what P index is but
maybe we can tell that from the
disassembly as well this is kind of a
pain in the butt to have to go back and
forth this way so in the disassembly
here we're doing a loop right so we're
testing clcl
updating render entities we jump back to
where is the actual loop here
whatever say we're comping can I can I
see you know what here's what I'm
wondering can I like see this at the
same time is that is that gonna be
possible
can we
so all I really want to do is I want to
see this routine source code and then I
want to look at this
disassembly at the same time but that
apparently is like way past what you
might want it to bugger to do apparently
can I do this okay anyways so I just
want to look and see if I can
deconstruct what's actually going on in
here just to give it a little bit more
so I can sort of see exactly what's
happening even the debugger won't tell
me so if we take a look at here what
we're looking at we got a P index it's
looping from zero to a known number
which is like twelve or something and
remember how many there are of this
right but that's all it's doing so if we
take a look at at if we try to reverse
engineer what the assem you know which
assembly language goes with this thing
since the debugger doesn't know but we
can probably figure it out if you look
at what's going on in here you can
actually see right there that's a comp
instruction that's compare this register
with this constant value and if we take
a look right at what that is that's oxo
C in for some reason assembly has the
convention of writing H at the end of
hexadecimal numbers whereas the C its Oh
X but there's the 12 right which if I
remember correctly is exactly how many a
line points there are right
um know how to actually get I'll just
look at it myself what's this an H H a
bitmap I guess yeah so you can see there
that that's that's the 12 so I'm just
using that right you can see how I'm
doing this just trying to explain how
you reverse engineer the assembly so
when they come when the debugger is a
piece of junk um because it always is so
you know trying to deconstruct where we
are on this loop you can see that comp
with 12 that's probably going to be this
loop condition because we were trying to
go from 0 to 12 so that strongly
suggests that this is the thing that's
doing that loop right let me go and see
if we go to 12
so when we do that that comp and we see
whether it's 12 or not that gives us an
indication that that's this piece of
code
it suggests that r9d right that is the
register that would be holding the P
index and what I wanted to know is I
wanted to know what the P index was I'm
assuming it's zero but I just wanted to
verify that fact for myself right so if
we look at what's going on here we're
gonna do an Inc r9d and we're gonna see
if we get it so that pretty much tells
me that that's the loop
let's take a look it is zero so it's our
first time through this loop that's all
I wanted to know because I assumed it
was but didn't want to you know be wrong
okay so then we're coming to this line
and the question is if we're looking at
the zero with one of this right then
presumably this bitmap info structure is
bogus it's not a valid value right so
what's going on there are si appears to
be where that was loaded
I guess because this looks like the
thing that was loading the bitmap info
in right
probably that seems to me to be the case
so in theory if I do Aris eye on this oh
and I'm apparently very wrong
oh okay I'm sorry I totally read that
wrong as sometimes I get confused
because in the debugger they do stuff
like this which isn't that's not
assembly language like there's no you
know there's no variables in it so
sometimes I get confused when I look at
stuff like that and I'm like thinking
it's doing something it's not this is
actually loading off of that pointer so
it's it's loading something off of the
parent bitmap info if that's even
accurate which we don't know what that
is but so the thing they're loading is
some number that's in there
my guess is actually that maybe because
there's nothing in particular you would
load out of there and you know adding
six to it right what is that trying to
do yeah I'm not sure so let's keep
trying to parse this apart here and see
what we're doing this right here is a
clear so it's putting zero into
something so this must be like in the
preamble code here we must be looking at
some part do go to source on this there
we go
you must be looking at something out
here I would guess
but I'll be honest I'm not sure what
let's get that one more time
well
so I'm not exactly sure what it's doing
here
it's doing a comparison against r15 D
and I'm not sure let's take a look and
see it's doing a comparison against
three that may be the thing that's
testing the type right so what it could
be doing is saying look RSI
okay I wasn't wrong
so RSI is the offset that it's trying to
load from it probably just had a zero
pointer to start with right and this
right here was trying to get that it was
trying to get that portion of the value
right so I'm assuming if we look at
alignment point that it's six up for the
type right so right you can see it doing
its ad six here where's that coming from
so I think what it's doing is it loads
the base pointer which just thinks it's
pointing to the beginning of alignment
point it's got two bytes for the first
one p % two bytes for the next one to
exercise that's six bytes up and there's
the type so this right here is saying
alright let's let's load RSI out of this
so it's got this what this load right
here this load failed so there was a
zero in here it then looked six up and
tried to get the type out right right
here where it actually I don't know what
I accidentally just clicked right here
where it tried to load that type it is
where it crashed so that's why it was
six so RSI was the pointer I wasn't
wrong before I was just not thinking all
right so the question is why is bitmap
info being passed as a zero there right
so if we unwind one level in the stack
we can see that that parent bitmap info
was supposed to come from here so you
know whatever this bitmap info array has
in it we were coming in here and asking
for one that we don't have right it does
not exist and so how does this happen
right how has this happened to us can we
access that array
yes we can I where is that array defined
entity max piece count so there's a
couple of years right who knows how many
they're all probably zero yeah right
so we're just wait a minute no that's
wrong too
that's just garbage that's not telling
me what I wanted at all that's what I
was trying to say um so we look at these
bitmap infos in the array there's
nothing in the array right it's just
it's empty and it gets up to I don't
know how many years I think you'd have
four so here's where the array ends I
remember what this value is but so I
think you're allowed to have four of
those so this is the array nothing has
been filled into the right yet and so
what's happening is there's a zero
meaning right we're tying its to we're
asking it to look up one of these things
but we must be on 0 because otherwise we
would have written them back I would
think so when we're going to access
these like this we must be getting a
parent aligned type that's nonzero on
the first person right
I mean that's fundamentally what's
happening
and I'm not sure why we're getting that
it seems like some kind of a bug in went
you know an entity we've constructed
somehow we've constructed an entity with
as its first thing something that attach
unfortunately I don't know how to really
look into it in more detail than that
see who was responsible looking at it
it's a great a be cat so this is Molly
beans fault Molly is causing causing the
problem right but I'm not 100% sure how
because the pieces of Molly should not
have had that property we can guard
against this kind of a crash really
easily and probably should but before I
do that I would like to understand how
we got a piece that did this in the
first place so I'm looking here at the
bitmap and you can actually see that
it's parent line type is very clearly 0
so the bitmap piece in question when we
did get this bitmap info should have
given us back a parent a line type
it should have given it fact it's not
even we're not even talking about this
we're talking about this right here
right
so I don't understand how we were ever
able to get inside that if statement I'd
like to go back to the disassembly so we
know that there should have been a test
to make sure that this value was not
zero right and because that's
specifically not here we don't care
about this
here's that source code here's this if
statement right bitmap P stop parent a
line type we should not be able to get
into this code if that was not true
right so you can see here that the last
thing we tested was CL on CL right we
were like CL equal to CL that was the
last thing we tested right or I should
say we asked the processor to compute
the difference between CL CL which will
set a bunch of flags that say you know
it's greater than or it's whatever right
we then did a jump to this effective
address a 5a which is way down here we
then jumped all the way down here if
based on the test so what what is this
probably doing for techs mmm
I mean that certainly could be
consistent with this spent a lot of chef
PS and unpacking going on here so yeah I
think that's right because all of this
shut this shuffling and unpacking is
probably taking the 16-bit values and
turning them into floats which you would
need to do so I I can believe that this
is actually doing that test so the cl-cl
test is probably this right so what is
CL CL is zero that's what we would
expect it to be to not enter this
routine right where did we load that
from let me try to get further
confirmation that I'm looking at the
right test here where did we get it
yeah why am I not seeing that you can
imagine debuggers that were actually
cool right you just like say where was
CL loaded in it would just tell you it
knows right it can just look back I mean
across jumps I guess it can't because it
doesn't necessarily know if they were
taken or not but it could still tell you
where the possible places it was nearby
so CL is just ECX though now I think
about so CL is just a quick way of
saying yeah I'm bad with some of those
quick ratios so actually it's not that
hard because that's just gonna be this
register extended register it's just
it's just testing only the bottom part
of it right so if you do just to make
this a little clearer and that's a
little bit weird
it's the Intel naming thing is the same
I don't program enough Intel assembly to
have it like quick in my head but
basically like these registers right
they started out being just you know 16
bits probably I'm guessing so they
started out being like that big and then
they went to being you know that big and
then they went to being that big and you
can still refer to the sub portions of
them so if you say are a you know RCX
you're talking about the whole 64 bits
if you say ECX you're only talking about
the 32-bit value on the bottom and if
you just say like CL I guess I don't
know so I don't remember how that works
if CL is only part of the register even
further but if you say that you're
talking about the non e non r version
then you're talking about just the
bottom so this is actually the part that
we're looking at this is the register
that we're looking at here I believe and
you can see that again not being
referred to as our CX but it's being
referred to as EC X here it's trying to
load this as just the bottom 32 bits of
that whatever's at that location right
so in theory RSP because that I believe
would be the stack there right am I
wrong about that that shouldn't have
changed so no one probably touched
on our way down here so RSP I would
assume we can just look and see what's
at that location to see what actually
got loaded in you know into ECX at this
point and then and then it just gets
tested so I think this is the location
we're looking for maybe right so that's
the actual place that we're looking for
and we loaded a 32-bit value out of it
but we're only testing the bottom part
of that anyway which makes sense because
the thing we were trying to test is only
supposed to be 16 bits long so if that
was an unsigned short pointer what would
it be so it's saying that that was 259
did I do that correctly
you sure I did that cuz that shouldn't
be right right because if we didn't
touch ECX since then although just test
here's the thing I don't remember what
tests effect on its register actually is
again just don't do nearly enough
assembly programming to remember stuff
like that I almost always ignore those
kind of things we're so far down the
rabbit hole at this point that I
actually just want to know though so I'm
gonna go ahead and do it how do I get I
just want to get back to the desktop
here so let's take a look I'm gonna go
ahead and pop over the architecture
reference man it's never too late to
learn assembly language folks don't let
anyone tell you otherwise um so you know
we've got the complete reference let's
just find it in fact I guess I can just
click on it in here it's usually the way
I do it so if we just scroll down here
and take a look that's the oh I opened
the wrong one that starts with B I need
a little bit back there we go I'm
through you so if I scroll through here
and find the test instruction
so I don't see anything that would
suggest that it would right back to the
sources I mean I don't know do you
so if you look at here you can see the
pseudocode for what intel is saying the
test instruction would do it says hey
we're going to compute the and of the
two things we you know we gave you and
then we're gonna set some flags right
based on that and it doesn't suggest at
least as far as I can see that source 1
in source 2 would ever get touched right
it should leave the value unadulterated
right so unless I'm reading that wrong
then I'm just confused when we're doing
the test cl-cl it seems like that should
leave it now what I don't know is maybe
because it's referred to as CL it's
clears part of the register because it
the top part is not referred to as part
of the CEO cuz like let's suppose we
took a look at this right of course even
if that were true you'd still see 3
there so what I don't understand is if
this is actually the assembly that
occurred what am I doing wrong we did a
mob oh well okay so I guess mob Z X we
should double-check what that does maybe
there's something special about that
that I'm forgetting but if this is the
last time we touched it I suppose our BP
and rst could point to the same thing
and this overrode it I mean that's the
only other thing it could be right
neither of those two things has been
touched right
ah nope here's the problem you see it so
ECX did get reloaded so when we tested
CL versus CL it obviously wasn't zero
and what we're getting here is it's just
it got overwritten by this so this may
be correct right this may actually be
what was in that location and it could
be that what was in that location was
actually 103 right was actually 259 and
that 259 would cause us to enter this
loop so the question is how the heck is
259 what's in there right why are we
getting something where the first thing
has a 259 in it so if we again look at
the hexadecimal for that what would is
to be nine even a valid value like
doesn't make sense right and so if you
look at what should be in an aligned
point type but because that's we're
looking at parent aligned type here
right you expect it to be something like
eight zero zero and then you know maybe
the three like one two three it could be
right base of neck could be totally
something that would be in there right I
don't think it should be but you know 0
1 2 3 that could be a value this bit
getting set we should never have done
that right there's no valid alignment
point that has a 1 in that location so
this looks very suspicious but again
unless I'm mistaken the actual
disassembly that we're seeing there how
do I actually go to area
that disassembly that we're seeing sure
looks like that's what was in there so
again let's do our due diligence and
just say if this was what we moved in
there and this code right here is the
only thing that could have interceded as
far as I can tell because and nothing
else actually did anything let's just
make sure that our SP and our VP aren't
pointing anywhere near each other I
don't see why they would be but let's
just see they're not gonna make it easy
on us are they so it turns out that our
SP and our BP are actually are actually
like right next to each other okay the
plot thickens if you ever wanted to see
having to dig through some assembly
language code to figure out where your
bug comes from well you're getting a
treat today because they're making it
hard on us I always like doing this
because it's educational for me like I
said I just I never did any x64 assembly
language programming I and so it's all
always educational right and little
things that you learn to do like oh
right you know remember to look for the
different versions of the register that
you wouldn't be used to doing on other
architectures necessarily every time you
get burned by something like that it's
like sticks in your head better so
you'll be quicker next time around right
so I don't know I I always find it to be
educational to do I mean it would be
great if you didn't have to do it
because the debugger actually could show
you this stuff in release mode but you
know if if wishes were unicorns we'd all
join the circus as they say so anyway
back to our story
let's see if we actually did we have a
problem with over writing here where it
may have obscured the actual value that
was originally in there because that one
you're just eating right isn't actually
super far away so that's a bit of an
issue these are the two locations that
we're talking about here let's look at
what they actually are so we have our SP
plus o X 59 and we have our BP - o X 60
those are the two locations that we're
looking at this mod is moving XM m 1 and
XM m 1 is just a 128-bit value right XM
m 1 is one of the cindy registers and
exactly this in analogous fashion to the
way the processor got added to the XM m
ones are the ones that were 128 bits
wide the ym m ones are when your tube do
6 and then the ZM m ones are one year I
don't really remember they're not on
here but so if you want to talk about
the lower part of one of these registers
128 bits part you call it XM m 0 if you
want to talk about the full width it's
ym 0 or if you're on a B X 512
I think it's zmm 0 to do the fab I'll
have exit I don't have a B X 512 on this
machine this chip doesn't the core i7
770 hon 7700 Kate didn't have avx-512 if
I remember correctly so we need so
that's why it came even turning on in
here alright so back to our story so
we're writing a 128-bit value that's 16
bytes right we're writing 16 bytes to
this location right here our BP - 6 th
and so I'm wondering with that even
interfered with what's here right that's
that's all I wanted to know and so if we
look back at this watch window what we
could say is well our BP minus 60 plus
16 would be here and reading out of here
those addresses are close but they don't
overlap right there's plenty of distance
between them you can see this you know
well yeah I can't even do this for you
here's that pointer here's this one so
you can see that they're actually
separated by quite a few bytes right
there's like there's there's a
significant distance between the two of
them and so we're not really gonna have
you know anything close just a sixth a
syllable 16 byte right is not going to
create a problem all right
so again bringing us back to what we
were talking about here again this is
the part of the code that we're looking
at so we loaded it here
we did a write from a register to a part
that was close by but not overlapping as
far as I can tell because we don't touch
either our SP or our BP anywhere down
through here that I can see make sure
that's right
because RSP this is why I city of
circumcision RSI and RSP are not the
same registers it's not a nominal Eicher
thing like the other ones right yeah so
those are not interfering being
interfered with at all
let's do here first I can see anyway
yeah so that means that unless I'm
mistaken
2:59 somehow got in there right we
somehow got a 259 into that bitmap piece
and I just don't understand where that
would have come from this value right
here is 259 and so you know do we have
some kind of a of a of a bug with the
way that we're doing these VIP map
pieces where we're like you know maybe
there's a weird bug somewhere that
actually writes 259 to that thing and
I'm not sure where you know it's loaded
out of here obviously but yeah I just
don't know I don't know where that would
have come from it makes me want to put
some guarding in here to look at these
particular things and see if we can
catch it a little earlier on to see
where that's coming from right so like
to get some idea of when 2:59 got stuck
into the bitmap piece in the first place
because where did it come from what
makes it even more confusing is remember
this actually isn't part of the art
stuff this is actually just where we
create those snap-together pieces that's
the only place that we set that
information up so for example let's say
actually I said I'm going to close that
down but let's suppose we go back to
where that sort of stuff happens right
and I don't know
that gets in here right so when we
actually create this stuff when we
create these pieces we've got this
connect piece call and then a connected
piece call like set some stuff up right
it says oh you know truncate this stuff
down and stuff it in here like this or
whatever right alright so looking at
that actually now those are 8-bit values
that's particularly justing to so CL was
really just loading the 8-bit value now
look at that alright so actually 209
isn't weird I'm sorry
203 what was it 103 hex was fine that
actually means that someone just set the
low thing to be in this parent line type
it was setting it right because it was
loading what we were actually seeing
there was it loading the next thing in
memory right and it wouldn't have loaded
that because well it wouldn't have used
that because it was testing CL 2 CL so
it would have only used a low 8 bits
I believe so that means it's not
necessarily garbage it's a totally valid
value in the totally wrong place right
so that's interesting so now the
question becomes how did that end up
right I mean let's let me just reset
that one more time so no there's a lot
going on there
so we reset that one more time in parent
a line type which is set in here how did
we end up having the first thing the
first piece in the entity say that it
was supposed to have a parent a line
type non zero how did it happen
right that's the question
so
one possibility is but we're not
clearing them properly we thought they
would all be zeros at the start but they
weren't or something that things that
likely and the reason that that seems
unlikely is there are only three valid
values that that thing could have taken
on and it was one of the valid values if
it wasn't if it was a non cleared memory
problem
you would expect it to be one of the 252
other things it could have been randomly
you would have thought it would have
been one of those more likely right so
it's a low probability thing we should
check it but it's low probability more
possible if somebody is calling connect
peace weirdly or something strange is
happening there now if we're right that
it was the tabie I mean if it was right
if it's Molly's fault then here in in
add cat this is where the problem would
have been so this add piece here where
we add the body in the head somehow
somehow this code was producing
something erroneous okay
now when we call add piece look here
what are we doing each time well we
assert that we haven't overflowed the
number of pieces we didn't hit that
assert and we assume that the assert
would have fired so we have entity
pieces plus entity piece count plus plus
right so we grab a piece out of this
array it pretty much I have to go in
order right I mean how could they not so
the body will come before the head the
body speed zero heads piece one when we
call connect piece to world just down
here
we're doing an HHA align nun as the
parent piece of line type not sure why
we don't just set it to zero so that's a
little odd
but let's I mean I'll double-check it
but that's pretty much not a problem for
us right because that's always gonna be
zero so I mean even if it wasn't cleared
this call should have done the work
right there shouldn't have been any way
for that to of this would have
overwritten whatever was there with a
zero they guess safe truncate to you
eight is literally just going to you
eight cast this value the value is 0 so
this bitmap parent a line type would
also be 0 and the entity as a result
should just be what it is right
it's a place cat no it's odd cat oh
right I can't jump to it because of the
parser doesn't understand the kind of
yeah long story on that one no matches
for add cat
so I'm still thoroughly stumped how is
it possible that we add body is zero
head as one we connect a piece to the
world which should have cleared this and
then we've got this connect piece here
that's operating on the head let's make
sure that connect piece doesn't do
something weird there I guess
so here's connect piece there's only one
version of it but I can see in here we
say we're gonna look at the child bitmap
so we're looking at the one that's off
of the head so we're not even touching
this body would hear.i we grab the
parent piece again doesn't that's not
gonna make any difference because it's
not the one we're not writing this back
to the one in question which is the zero
width you know the 0th entry so who even
cares how this function works we just do
not care even a little bit
I I literally can't see ya anyway that
that would have affected it so somehow
although I don't see any way for to
actually happen we are getting an
alignment value that is nonzero into the
first piece in our entity unless our
debugging of the assembly code was way
off base and the value we're getting we
actually know what the value was - right
it was one so it was
HHA aligned default was the parent
alignment so it's like it wrote the one
like if we if I had to make up a bug
that doesn't look like it's actually
there it looks like it wrote the parent
a line type HS a line none
instead it wrote the child type into the
parent a line type right like if it
wrote if these two lines had been
swapped that would be the bug right I
mean that's what the but that would have
been the bug but they're not swapped so
so I don't really know
I guess because I don't have any better
ideas should we go ahead and look at the
ad cat disassembly in release mode to
see what it actually does in case maybe
there's something we're just not
thinking about so here's the disassembly
I don't know why it's not sure which one
I want there but whatever so here's a
disassembly of that call right of
add cat eye and if I just look through
it here where I'm sort of stepping you
know let's take a look at the place
where we add those pieces I guess so
what I will say is I don't see any calls
in here right so there is a little bit
of a concern in my head now because I'm
like alright so it decided to inline the
call to connect peace to world and the
call to connect peace it inlined both of
those right and in fact also I guess it
in lines the call to add peace as well
right
here's it doing in fact if we take a
look back here
here's add peace right so px4 so here's
it doing the assertion right here we're
this right here I believe is it just
filling in let me try to show you here
filling in this right I believe
yeah so it's running on our registers I
think to pass these so it's putting them
on the stack cuz they're structs right
I think don't quote me on this it might
actually fling in default primers to I
don't know so we're going through here
though pretty straightforward right
we're just checking the assertions
I mean I yeah you know I mean I'm not
gonna follow this all the way through or
take a while here's the second ad piece
call and now we're down into the
connector calls right in theory so yeah
all right
looking at this a little bit more
closely here let's see what are we doing
here
so it looks like
so it looks like this test here was
probably this assertion I'm guessing
yeah you can see the assertion here
would have written to the zero address
to cause the crash right so remember our
assertion just writes to the zero page
so it halts the process immediately if
it happens so that here we were saying
alright let's go ahead and write the
rest of this stuff out so it's this is
where we would be doing that I would
assume assuming this actually didn't get
rearranged too much but let's take a
look
so our 11w
we go our 11 w and then 1 are the two
things that it's writing out if we look
at the structure of these bitmap pieces
in entity visible piece here's where
those are created the reserved value is
obviously 0 the parent piece in our case
is also going to be 0 out here or one in
the other as far as the other one and
the parent line type child the line type
that's the sort of thing that we're
looking at here how that's actually
getting added in there but yeah so if
you look at this it looks like the way
that that's working in here is it sort
of knows exactly what it wants to write
into this part of the struct I don't
know if we've got of course not
the ability to inspect it much here's AD
cat yeah it doesn't know anything no
entity does so if we take a look at the
pieces here here's them getting
structured so if we take a look inside
the pieces here and we look at the
bitmap part of this right so the first
one is supposed to get set to zero here
zero here and zero here but one should
get set right here and if you look at
the disassembly that looks like exactly
what's going to happen where do I get
that one go back here it is this is
setting the first part to zero so that's
setting these parts to zero here I
believe and then this part right here is
putting that one in place so I think
when we step over this that should go
yeah right so that set it up exactly as
we think that it should which is great
I mean quote unquote right now looking
for weird bugs that might be in this
code I guess so
are 11w I mean I don't know where the
last time that got set was
here's one place
I guess I couldn't tell you man like
where is that getting set this just
clears it right
but I guess now I think about it it can
only ever be zero so I guess that's just
fine that would always be correct right
so as long as our 11 doesn't get changed
again that would be fine do we ever
touch it again and we don't we we do a
mob here which is interesting
this is writing 0 to 0 this is writing 0
to hear which but that just might
because it happened to know it had a
zero so it used it for clearing
I don't know man so that seems like it
would pretty reliably write out exactly
what we think it should right I don't
have a lot of explanation for that
so that looks fine I guess I should
double-check again though before we say
that all looks fine that you know what
happens after that so here you know when
we're going through to figure out the
next part of it we've got the connect
piece call if we can I get that to go to
the source code yeah so here it needs to
do right this subtraction where it's got
to figure out what index this thing is
actually lining up for the parent piece
it doesn't really matter right it's
doing a shift to figure that out because
it knows that this happens to be 16
bytes long right so that's how it's
doing the divide there again I don't
think any of this matters because it's
not going to write to the person who we
care about anyway it's doing a jump here
this is the assertion again that it left
in which is fine and then it's yeah
looks like it's just again let me just I
don't know why it keeps moving us away
from that source I wanted to see this
source there we go so in here we're
looking at this bitmap parent piece it's
just looking to make sure I guess we
didn't yeah when we're doing that
connection we're saying make sure that
the thing we're connecting to is earlier
than we are
which again seems fine so I don't know
this is a real nasty bug somewhere
because I don't actually see where the
bug is coming from here
we can't repro it right meaning we only
get it once in a while and we don't
really know why we're getting it does it
have something to do with code reloading
like does it happen when I do this or
something so I don't know uh I guess you
know that was a sufficient looking into
of it right we didn't cheese out we
looked for it pretty hard so I think
what we're gonna have to do is possibly
add some more code to help us look for
it I guess in the future or hope we get
a lucky break and get an easier to debug
case down the line but I don't see
anything amiss in there and I don't
understand how that thing could have
happened exactly we can guard against it
pretty easily meaning inside the actual
entity code all we would have to do here
is just make sure that we don't actually
ever do this like you know we could even
move this code up above this line and
then we'd be fine right because we would
just look at our own bitmap info and
that would you know would crash right
but it's still wrong you know what I
mean like it's unclear to me I'd like to
figure out why we're ever getting this
because this should never be able to
actually happen we can certainly make
the bug occur a little bit further
upstream but not enough to actually
matter that I can think of anyway which
is to say that when we do this parent a
line type bit here when we get in here
could just say hey just so we know let's
make sure we never do this on a piece
index that's zero right so I don't know
right I don't really know what to make
of it
it's it's pretty weird but that's it and
I don't know I don't know how to track
it down further well go ahead and go to
the QA and I guess we'll finish up what
we were doing today we'll finish that up
tomorrow I'm glad we took a look into
that to see if there was anything
obviously but I didn't that
investigation turned up really not much
and so if anyone has any while that was
happening obviously you guys were
watching if you had any particular
Avenue you think I missed tell me you
know tell me what it was because I'd be
interested to know if there was anything
that I didn't pursue there that looked
like it could have been fruitful I don't
I don't have anything off the top of my
head that I think we could have done
that would have helped us in release
mode you know the debugger doesn't give
you much help so you're pretty much
reading on your own yeah I got nothing
so how do you like the progress of HH so
far um I like everything except the
lighting I'd like to do a pass and
lighting and fix that but I like I
really like where we ended up I like how
everything works now it's pretty good
it's the first time I've ever tried a
mix mode game I don't you know it's not
something I do I don't do like 2d 3d
stuff I usually just do 3d or straight
2d so it was really interesting going
through all of that and I feel like what
we ended up with is pretty novel I've
never seen anything that quite does
exactly what we do
and so I feel like we found some pretty
cool stuff I don't know I really like
the way it looks and seems like a pretty
solid engine so far it suffers from the
fact that not very much time has been
put into it you know engine work is it's
hard work it's long hours and it's like
you're a lot of stuff you have to do and
so it's pretty truncated compared to
what I would like to spend on the engine
you know I'd like to spend at least four
times as much time as we've spent on
stream for the same amount of code that
we've had just refining things making
them more robust and cleaning them up
and all that sort of stuff that I would
normally have plenty of time to do for
an engine of this complexity which is
not that high
but you know given the limitations of
the series and what I can do with the
way that we set it up
I think it's delightful I would like to
I would like to fix the lighting though
the lighting is not where it needs to be
it looks cool it's too slow and so I
think that's the last thing that we
I have some ideas about it that's the
last thing that I'm like yeah that's not
really solved right everything else
looks and feels great terms the
architecture and the things that we have
to do or more just like straight to do
items I don't see a lot of unknowns in
there but the lighting needs needs to be
improved
well you have 3d printers as collision
proxies we already have them you've
mentioned the past your climate for
exercise have you seen free soil yet I
have yes that stuff is nuts
now earlier the problem with handle it
some people assembly do you have a
chance to look at the burst compiler
demo from unities GDC 2019 keynote no I
mean you know unity just doesn't isn't
something I need to follow because I
don't use it so I don't really care what
they're doing most of the time so I
don't follow it I certainly don't care
about the birth compiler because well I
mean why would I care about the bris
compiler I think it's good though
because for people who have to use unity
which is a lot of people I think it's
good that they are trying to provide
ways of giving you access to actual
speed focused code right because it will
enable I would think it will enable
people who are programming in unity to
do things they couldn't have done that
are like custom to their game you know
that they really couldn't have done
before without like making a plug-in
right where they have to go right like
the C++ code themselves but just you
know the whole point of unity is that
you're not having to do that like the
whole point is that you don't have to go
do all the standard game development
stuff you can just use the stuff they've
already built but you know there are
specific things that you need to do in
your game that are specific to your game
and you don't want to have this
handcuffs on you where you can't get
reasonable for it sighs so I think the
best compiler is very good and I hope it
is successful at like Oh giving people
the ability to stay in the like the
confines of unity so they don't have to
learn a whole new environment and
programming language and all these other
sorts of things but still learn they can
learn a few things about how could
and how to do things quickly and then
access that power through a standard
unity you know interface so I think that
is just fundamentally good and will have
a positive impact on this you know the
the types of games you can make in unity
that maybe in the past would you know
you wouldn't really have been able to
make certain kinds of games because the
performance would have been a limiting
factor now you you know now you can
maybe consider those games whatever that
sort of space looks like right may blow
a couple of days late but now that we're
hopping in Z how about adding water so
the hero can go swimming I'm not averse
to it
but you know I'll be honest the thing is
I don't know that we really want to take
the time to do water rendering because
water rendering is kind of its own whole
thing and just based on like time
constraints right like you know I don't
know that we want to go down that road
so I would say that might be more left
as an exercise for the reader you know
it seems to me somewhat straightforward
how you would go about adding something
like that so I think most people would
be able to do it on their own and the
really big challenge is how do you draw
it right because you want the water to
look nice you want to look like water
and the question is how do you make it
respond you know when the when the hero
like jumps on in you know and do you do
some water simulation try to make it
look like it's rippling out and you know
those sorts of things and then what do
you do about you know do you want to try
and reflect things in it you know so
it's a pretty you know water is a bad
thing to add to a game if you don't want
to go down kind of a pretty big
rendering rathole because it's a tone
its its whole own thing now you could if
you just want cheap water that's not so
hard right it's just a trans loose
and plane you stick in there and that's
not so bad
so you know we could do really lousy
water but you know I'd probably rather
just not do water
not a question now Casey a Monday I'm
starting my first day of work at a
medium-sized game studio after working
for Microsoft for a few years just want
to say thanks to you among others for
the inspiration education that made this
career change possibly awesome yes
second person today who said that it's
good to see so many people or you know
finding new directions
Thanks just you know some increased
exposure to low-level programming stuff
like it was a good demo on about how a
bug can mess up the schedule and get you
2 hours of info but sadly nothing yeah I
mean that's and I guess the other thing
that I would say is that's why I think
debuggers are really underrated I mean a
lot of that time that we spent there was
time that a machine could have answered
the questions right look I wasn't doing
anything superhuman related not
superhuman buts
that was super related to humans
most of the enquiries that I performed
are ones that a machine could have
performed with very limited direction
right and so better debuggers would save
a lot of time for low-level programmers
debuggers right now we're just really
lousy and so improving debuggers and
making it so that you don't have to
spend very much time to debug release
mode code which is where a lot of bugs
happen would be a pretty major
improvement and like most of the two
hours of today well not two hours
because we spent an hour before it doing
that so it was a nap but an hour a good
hour was spent mostly doing things that
could have been automated right and so I
feel like you know I would really like
to emphasize just how bad the debugging
situation is we weren't doing things
that really needed to be done by a
person those were things that could have
been done by a computer but that we just
have to do manually for no real reason
just poor debuggers right
so there's a lot of questions here and
not sure how many we really want to get
into but we'll start with first one from
Bulma nadir hey Casey the way you think
teach how to think about maybe she's
helped me understand the transmission
pipe out a lot better but there's one
thing I think I'm missing at one point
you put the camera coordinates into clip
space I was wondering how you scale
world units to make sure things aren't
huge on screen so I guess I'm not really
sure how to answer that question
in order to give you a really good
complete answer I think it probably
would help I guess if I actually brought
the matrix up so this is the perspective
projection call that we're that we're
actually using in handmade Hiro right
and if you look at the way that this
matrix is structured what you can see is
this scale is given by two fundamental
values a times C and B times C right and
you can see them right here right in our
case we fix a at one point O which means
that we're sort of I don't know how to
put it but like x coordinate primal like
we're basically saying we're going to
adjust the scale in Y of the clip
transform to account for the aspect
ratio right because we're creating a
unit cube for our clip space and we're
choosing we have to either compress X or
compress Y differently to make sure that
we have the same aspirations our screen
right so hopefully a and B makes sense
they're neither of those two is scaling
anything right
a is 1.0 so it doesn't scale anything at
all and B is only applying a scale such
that our unit cube properly captures the
fact that the final height of the screen
the final height that we want to see of
the world you know that slice through
the world is wider than it is tall
right and you can see that it's a little
bit paradoxical its width over height
that we're putting in there right
instead of height over width which is
what you would expect if you were doing
the other way around but remember it's
because this is the compression not the
expansion so we're going the opposite
direction as we would if we were trying
to we're not trying to compute the
height from the width because if we were
would be the other way around
instead what we're trying to do is
compress the height into the same space
as the width right so that's why the
ratio is flipped from what you might
intuitively think okay so these two
values do not scale the world at all
they're just trying to make sure that we
end up with a cube that matches so we
don't get warping right that matches the
display because after this transfer
maccer x' we're going to multiply the
outcoming values by the number of pixels
in X&amp;Y and those numbers are different
so this is accounting for that
difference in scale on the other side
might be another way to think of it
right hopefully okay so what that leaves
you with is the C value this right here
and that C value is the thing that does
all of the scaling that's the focal
length of the lens right and that C
value is precisely the thing that gives
you the scaling that you're talking
about so the focal length of a lens and
this is not exactly true because
obviously we're not really simulating a
lens per se this is a kind of idealized
like pinhole camera kind of a thing
right but it is precisely that focal
length of the pinhole camera lens that
determines how big the world appears on
the cameras film back so that
is what that is right so that's the
thing to answer your question that right
there
that focal length value is what
determines how big or small the world
appears on the picture of it that you
are taking right I don't know if there's
any really better way to put it than
that
does that make any sense it might not
have but
and again it may seem a little bit that
may not have been a complete enough
explanation so you know it's an
important question that you're asking
this is a this is an important question
most you know 99% of all programmers
who've ever used a perspective
projection matrix don't know how it
works so it's good that you're asking
this question because most people don't
ask this question and and they just you
know never understand what's going on so
hmm just to be a little bit more
concrete and maybe this diagram will
help a little bit so in a normal camera
right you've got a thing called the lens
assembly and the lens assembly is some
nonsense that's got like all these
different lenses and crap in it right
and so the world is out here somewhere
you know what I mean that we're looking
at and what's actually happening with
those lenses is all kinds of light
bouncing around is happening in here and
then eventually it gets to a film back
and you know it exposes some part of the
film back or the CCD in the case of a
digital camera nowadays and that's how
we get the image right and so normally
when we talk about things like the
effective focal length of a lens we're
talking about something like this and
like okay we're not doing that so the
word focal length here is not really
talking about any kind of real-world
analog of a real lens assembly but it's
not that far off because what we are
actually talking about is the following
thing for a pinhole camera here is my
pinhole camera right and here is some
crap in the world
okay so let's suppose that I take
something in the world like this ball
and you are asking the question how
large is this ball going to appear in my
game because there's a world with 3d
coordinates and all this other stuff in
it but then I'm looking at a screen so
what you know how do those two things
correlate together ones like a flat 2d
display surface where things have an
actual size I can take a ruler out and
measure it on my actual screen it has a
real size in the real world reviewing it
in but there's also this fake world in
the game and we're saying stuff like one
unit is one meter how you know what I
don't understand right what you're
saying like I don't get how these things
are related and so the answer there is
that well okay the focal length of the
lens in this case what we're seeing is
how far from the aperture right the
thing that the light is passing through
how far back are we going to get to the
actual you know to the actual film back
right and you know so the place where
the light crosses and inverts there's
two ways that you can measure that I
don't actually remember the kind of
things that I'm too old they flick out
of my head I know on the days when I
write the code for this stuff because I
go relook it up and make sure I've got
it right so I'm not naming things
improperly in my actual code but then
you know I'm sorry so this is gonna be
slightly wrong in a real camera right
there's an aperture that light comes
through because you're getting more than
a pinhole right it's not a pinhole and
then there's a place where the light
crosses so that you know you've got a
single emanation point light is coming
out to the lens it's getting redirected
by the lens it's crossing and then it
hits right the film back and you know
like my brains never remembers do you is
that the focal length or is that the
focal length right it's probably that
one I don't remember it doesn't matter
for our cases because these aren't real
values we're not submitting a real
camera but if you were you'd better get
it right cuz you're gonna be off by two
right it's you mean 2x you're twice as
large or half as big depending on which
way you got it wrong you know what I
mean
so you do need to know what that
actually means if you're doing a real
camera we're not so the point is this
distance whether you measure it by half
or by whole this distance is what
determines how big the world will look
in a sense right because when we
actually project this thing through here
the pinhole is actually the place where
these things would flip around right
onto here and the further back we move
this thing right the further they would
diverge does that make sense so it's not
an accident that we called that the
focal length it's essentially measuring
how far back you're putting that camera
plate in the imaginary camera that we've
created to photograph this world with
right but you know
I don't know if that helps you picture a
little bit more what's going on in there
with that that focal length value so
yeah um trying to think if that makes
any sense
it's still not a very good explanation
because the intuition there was like
okay so I move this thing back further
but you know this thing gets bigger as
well so maybe I can draw this diagram a
little bit better I don't know if any of
this is helping it's probably not so
let's suppose that we're talking about a
nice 90 degree F over here and let's say
the camera is pointing this way okay so
here are the bounds of the camera when
I'm looking out right and so I'm
creating a film back here and then I'm
also going to create another film back
here it's further back right and then
I'm gonna create something that's that
big and I'm gonna pass it through as
delicately as I can
all right so let's say it's about that
big okay um so yeah like if we look at
what actually happens here when we've
got these sort of things and you know
like I said it's unfortunately not the
best but you know I if we try to imagine
what's happening here with if we
literally just made these as as our I'm
not sure what the right way to say this
would be if you just imagine these
things continuing to kind of extend out
as far as you can
I just need a better I need a better way
to draw these diagrams cuz this is just
I'm trying to show that those triangles
end up being
right okay so as best as I can actually
do this right these are going to be
similar triangles right so each one of
these the ratio should be the same right
I guess it's what I was trying to say so
the reason I was saying like this is not
a completely compelling way to actually
view the focal length effect is because
the diagram doesn't include the actual
part that makes this not produce the
exact same result right
whereas this diagram does include the
thing that makes it not produce the
exact same results which is the fact
that the aperture size is the same but
the focal length part is changing well
that's not a particularly useful way to
say it I guess but yeah not sure what
else to put on there so really really
what you have to imagine happening is
this pinhole mm has collapsed two parts
of this camera down into one part of the
camera so this part is actually changing
independently from this part and I don't
know how to draw that in a way that
makes better sense than what I've what
I've drawn if I was to draw the real
version of it I think it becomes a
little bit clearer right because you can
see what I mean by I have an aperture
that lets light in right I have a point
in the world that I'm projecting right
and you know maybe I've got if I've got
two of those points or something right
and they're both kind of doing something
that looks a little bit like this and
they're getting redirected from here
through a focus
right and there's the focus point from
there the film back gets moved forwards
or backwards right this point doesn't
change so the further back you move this
fixed size thing right the more you can
see how this would change size so the
right way to do it on this diagram would
be enforce a fixed size maybe this is
the way I should have drawn dat first
right so assume this fixed size here
right because it is gonna be a fixed
size right the thing that we produce
that unit cube is the unit cube that's
how big it is right so maybe this is the
best way to draw the diagram I don't
know it's like I think about it in these
terms nowadays because I'm used to
having to simulate real camera effects
so when you go to a pinhole camera I'm
not sure the best way to like visualize
what's going on in my head I think of it
like this diagram but we don't have that
part of this diagram so maybe a better
way to think it would be if this is a
fixed size the reason that we call it
focal length is because you can imagine
moving this fixed size plate backwards
and as you move that fixed size plate
backwards right this is going to take up
more room on the back of the plate and
get bigger right does that make sense so
as the focal length gets further back
this will get bigger so that's why when
you look on here these clips space for
dances that come out the focal length is
just a straight up scale and it's a
scale because it's effectively just
taking these and pushing them outwards
as the focal length gets bigger they
will
get larger right I don't know if that
makes any sense
um and so that's like effectively what
you're doing in a compressed pinhole
camera so that these things don't
actually really exist but you can think
of the you know you can still think of
this as the negative one positive one
bounds of the clip space right and so
that focal length is effectively
changing where this one one plane is
likes lit up versus your your camera
boundary there right versus the well not
for us our camera body versus the world
that you're looking into right so you're
you're changing how this fixed divide
because remember the divide doesn't
change right the divide is happening in
you know proportional to the near far
clip playing stuff for the Z coordinate
and just press relative to W directly
for the actual values that come out
right so as far as the projection is
concerned you can see it doesn't care
it's not even looking right at those
values so it really is just this is
fixed and you're just figuring out where
that focal length film back is placed
does that make sense so again I have a
really hard time explaining it and I'm
apologize for that because I just don't
think in terms of pinhole cameras much
anymore but that might be the best way
to say it right is that you're
effectively sliding the film back closer
to the pinhole or further from the
pinhole by adjusting that focal length
parameter sorry to take so long to get
there
0l PBM says I think in a pinhole camera
the focal length is zero and the focal
point is the actual pinhole itself
yeah that sounds about right
you've like moved those two things to be
coincidence yeah so you know what that
this phrase here it's really you know
that value is really the distance of the
film back from the pinhole I write do
you know what I mean and so I feel like
we just named that poorly we went
through lots of iterations of this and
we probably just kept this value called
focal length maybe it was the focal
length at one point it's definitely not
now but a better way to think of it it's
like that's the distance the film back
has moved from the pinhole which would
be the point
the focal point I guess it's the place
where all the light beams cross right
and invert
going the perspective question so
mathematically you were recreating the
space bounded by the near and far clip
frame in a space defined by the lens the
focal length so if you could imagine one
pixel as being a vector from the lens to
some point you are literally just doing
a magnitude scale if that's the case how
do you handle the fact that you're
mapping a curved surface onto a plane
you mean hmm what do you mean by a
curved surface G because remember we
don't really project curved surfaces in
the 3d pipeline hardly ever if there are
some things that we could talk about
that like if you're projecting NURBS
into from if you're going to project
things that actually themselves have the
ability to project there's a whole other
set of things you have to talk about but
we only really project points so we we
usually convert curved surfaces to fixed
points and we just use lots of them to
approximate the curved surface right so
we don't ever have to ask the question
how does a curved surface in the world
project onto a into a curved surface on
the film back right but maybe that's not
what you're asking
what you may send me since I think again
it thank you very much I'm gonna mess
around with it get things Cub yeah sorry
it took me so long get there like I said
one of the problems with the pinhole
camera thing is I've kind of forgotten
how to think about it very efficiently
there's just you know human brains
aren't great including mine and so I
forget a lot of stuff you know you work
through it and then you just you page it
out and you remember how to get back to
it if you need to but takes it sometime
so yeah how much do curve monitors
complicate this um they you know they
don't really complicate it much at all
if you wanted to take a curve monitor
into account you certainly can in your
projection the problem that you actually
get with curved monitors is that
piecewise linear approximations don't
actually work on curved monitors because
the monitor is curved so if you really
actually want to do proper rendering for
a curved monitor you actually need to
change the 3d pipeline to support proper
what's called perspective rasterization
that's actually not that hard
but it doesn't you can't do it on modern
hardware it doesn't support it because
the rasterizer is fixed to be more sin
fat what I'm talking about so if we
wanted to extend our projection
equations to work properly on a curve
monitor it's not that hard all we have
to do is say oh when we go ahead and
project these things then when we're
projecting instead of just forcing
things through a matrix and saying that
we're done we just need to go oh this
this back here that we're projecting
onto right is is curved so the distance
that things go when they come through
here is not going to be the same it's
not that hard to work out the math for
that because you know based on the
direction of the thing being projected
what that distance is for the curve
monitor right so it's not that bad if
you had to work that out but the problem
is then you're going to get specific
discrete answers for like points of a
polygon and then when you rasterize
you're going to interpolate between that
directly and that's not what you
actually want you want the whole you
want every pixel to to properly have
taken into account that perspective work
right but like I said that's it's
actually not that hard you could we
could have built all 3d Hardware to do
this it's just we didn't because
and by the way curved monitors isn't the
most interesting case it's actually lens
I optic that are usually the interesting
case but they have another problem which
is RGB gets shifted differently through
a lens it's really a long story but
like where
[Music]
um so I have a particular paper that I
want to reference right now and I'm
having a really hard time thinking of
what its name is so I can't find it
there it is I think yes um so this paper
is literally about this exact topic and
I highly recommend reading it if you
just want an interesting read it is
useful to no one at all at this point
because you can't do it in hardware as
far as I know but you know you could
have done it so at least I think am I
wrong about this
I don't remember if they came up with
like a way to hack it
I don't remember if they try to make a
way to hack it into a current GPU
pipeline or not I'm sorry I just don't
remember but the point is ignore whether
a GPU can do it or not you could make a
GPU do it because it actually works the
exact same way as current GPU
rasterization works it just takes the
bounds of what could be the projected
area of a particular triangle and then
when it actually computes the values at
the pixel coordinates it just does the
correct full 3d homogeneous computation
of what they should be through the
curved projection right so this does
literally the exact right thing for
curved projections and it's pretty cool
I that's I guess what I would say right
and like I said it's really just about
changing your idea of what the bounds of
the projected triangle are and then when
you compute what pixels are in or out
and what the values are they're pixels
you just use the homogeneous coordinates
still to make sure that you're actually
doing the full curve projection at each
point it just works the pits the same
pixel shaders will just work at that
point right so it's really just about
the rasterizer how it's doing the those
how it's feeding that right
I imagine the true surface as being an
arc with radius equals focal length oh
okay mmm-hmm so I maybe understand what
you're asking about with the curb
services now this is jumping back to the
previous question let me try to I give
you you a more clear impression here so
again with any camera right so we'll try
to get out of the pinhole versus regular
there is some point where this stuff is
inverting right and so for our pinhole
camera you know light from the world is
going through the pinhole and inverting
at the pinhole with our wide aperture
camera it's going through the aperture
right so it's like actually all of the
light is going across this entire
surface and then there's a pinhole like
this it's not pinhole there's a point
where the same location that goes
through two sides of the lens will
invert and project right so stuff like
this right if the focal length is set to
that you get here if you take these two
going through the same point so let's
say you took them both going through
here where they would cross is probably
the equivalent of the pinhole so
ignoring all that we have a point
somewhere where the light beams crossed
and we don't know how we got there right
when those beams cross even if this
surface is curved right versus straight
we don't care the film back just needs
to be the shape of the display so if
it's a photograph it's flat if it's a
monitor it's flat at the monitors flat
it would be curbed the monitor was
curved the actual projection on here
we're trying to ask where it hits a flat
surface we're not trying to ask how far
this went
we're not asking how long this ray is
we're waiting until the ray hits our
collector so it doesn't produce for a
flat collector it doesn't produce an
ideal function looks
that it's actually producing a
projection that is flat on the flat
surface and then we stick it on a flat
surface and we're done right so no there
isn't a curve induced by the fact that
these rays are traveling different
distances it's okay that they are right
that's okay because we're making a flat
collector of rays that are hitting it
and they were putting it onto a flat
surface we don't need to think about the
curvature at all there hopefully that
helps a little bit
all right I think I have definitely
talked enough today for my poor voice I
can't remember what questions we skipped
I hope they weren't super important
really quickly
so there's only one it looks like we
missed which was if I wanted to create
seamless terrains starting from a cube
like tile map what algorithm should I
look into so that's a little bit too
open-ended and it also was a little
under specified so I'd say I'm probably
not gonna take that one I apologize I'm
serious I was thinking that you'd want
to solve the problem that you'd get a
differential zooming but it seems like
this not too much an issue okay well as
long as alright so hopefully we've
addressed all the questions again sorry
I took me a while to get around to it to
a good diagram for what was happening in
the camera land it's confusing stuff
right and it's because there's so many
pieces that are interacting at that
point you know there's the concept that
we're shrinking it down into the clip
space so you know you're inherently
thinking of this like negative one one
space and then you're like well what
does that mean exactly because we're
also multiplying by this focal length
value why are we doing that and what's
that doing to the values and and then
there's the aspect ratio coming in as
well and there's a divide by Z and so
you know thinking all through all that
stuff you can see what it does
mathematically very easily by just
looking at the numbers and where they go
but it's hard to come up with an
intuitive picture so I tend to like the
film back distance way that's why I
usually went there but it was hard for
me to kind of get to the point where
it's like oh the right way to think
about that in this face is to say the
film back is a fixed size so as you move
it back it doesn't widen with those
projection lines it's the same size so
you're collecting more or less of that
as you change where you're at and that's
what scales the world effectively I
think that's a good way to think about
it intuitively there's a lot of ways you
could Intuit it I find that to be a good
way because I feel like it helps you
take the next step which is to start
thinking in terms of real lens assembly
sim which is where you have to go
eventually right once you start doing a
harder core 3d engine
you need to be able to think about
things like bokeh and lens aberration
and these sorts of things that just
don't happen with a pinhole camera and
so if you try to use just just a similar
triangles projection and it's the only
thing you ever thought about you can't
get there so it helps to have your
intuition think more about an actual
physical assembly I think that's a good
habit to get into cuz it'll shorten the
length that the it shortens the gap you
have to cross to start getting into more
advanced rendering techniques later we
don't do those on handmade Hiro but you
know if you're someone who goes into the
graphics running you're gonna have to do
that you're gonna have to think about
those later alright let's see here I'm
gonna go ahead and close things down
here
alright thanks everyone for joining me
for the episode of handmade Hiro it's
what a pleasure coating with you as
always if you want to follow along the
series at home you can always go to
handmade hero not org and pre-order the
game it comes with a source code so you
can play around with stuff like the
focal length perimeter and see what it
actually does that's it for tomorrow
I'm just gonna pick up where we left off
today we weren't able to find that bug
we're gonna have to see if we can cut it
down some other way it's a pretty
elusive one and I'm not really sure
where it's coming from
so it's gonna be a bit tricky but
hopefully we'll get it we'll try to pay
close attention let me see it next time
that's it I hope see you back here
tomorrow same time same place until then
have fun program everyone and I'll see
everybody on the Internet take it easy
everybody