hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we tried a complete game
live on stream before I get started
today I just wanted to mention that
after today's normal programming stream
we will be doing a special Sunday stream
where we're gonna head over to Jonathan
blows channel on Twitch and we'll
probably do like a squad stream so you
can easily switch back and forth between
feeds or something I don't exactly know
how we'll get that working optimally but
we're gonna go talk to Jonathan Blow
about whatever we whatever we end up
talking about really it'll be it'll
won't be a constrained conversation but
we're gonna start talking about some
parser stuff and really it's just an
excuse to get together and talk about
some programming things because well
streaming gets a little bit boring after
a while and it helps if you can talk to
other programmers about stuff so I'm
looking forward to it
hopefully the video feed stuff will work
well enough and won't be too much of an
issue but will we make in the best of
the kovat 19 situation and and trying to
do a little Sunday programming stream
where we can hang out and learn some
cool stuff from John about you know
basically like compiler implementation
stuff at first and then if we if we end
up on other topics we end up in other
topics but that's the idea so I'm
looking forward to it so stick around
for that and you can you know either
watch this channel or John's channel is
twitch.tv slash naysayer 88 na y sa Y e
r88
so if you you know want to catch that
stream you can come to either channel
and we'll we'll figure it out so it's
it's this dream right here so that's
what's going on today and that's all
that's the only public service
announcement I had there so let's go
ahead and get started programming on
yesterday's stream I basically wanted to
kind of clean up the way the full cast
code was working and that went pretty
well it's at a point now where we have
our our input like sampling information
is now well aligned to what we're
actually trying to do and so we're
correctly like sampling our octahedral
Maps I think now with a good stochastic
sampling the guarantees that we sample
one octahedral pixel one ray out of each
octahedral pixel every frame and that we
jitter those pixels in a way that like
uniformly covers the sphere over time
pretty well and on any given frame so
I'm pretty excited about that and I I
think that worked pretty well and if you
look at the way the lighting is working
now I think it's going pretty good so
really what I want to do is try to
accelerate the Ray casting now just take
a look at where we're slow maybe why
we're slow what are our options for
maybe speeding things up and then we
have to move on to a lighting quality
pass so basically like get the
performance of the ray caster going well
because that's gonna pretty much be
unrelated to the quality well the more
ways you can cast the better quality
obviously so it's not completely
unrelated to the quality but what I mean
to say is our decisions about how to
compute the lighting equations are not
going to be particularly relevant to how
we traced Ray's quickly we know that we
need to trace our rays
quickly and accurately in order to
produce good lighting results but we
don't really have those two systems are
not tied together so we should be able
to optimize our ray tracer without any
fear of causing problems for optimum
improving the lighting equation
computations which is sort of a separate
issue and our lighting is already
looking pretty good the main thing I'm
worried about is doing a little bit of
smoothing so you don't see voxel edges
as much which is thing one and then the
other thing is well some tone mapping
but also figuring out why we're getting
some of the lighting feedback like for
example down here you can kind of see
that simple lights tend to really flood
out the rooms down here and again like
some of this is I think has to do with
also how we're constructing the room so
there's a lot of lighting quality things
I want to look at as we go and you know
like I said III I don't think that will
be a huge problem for us to get going
but it's a separate problem so I want to
leave it
now all right so if we take a look I
guess I probably shouldn't close that if
we take a look at the lighting debug
information so here's sort of a heads-up
display if you will of what's going on
our raise / probe is now locked 64 which
is exactly what I want and so we're
casting out a 64 a 64 points fear if you
will and that sphere like rotates
through over time so that we get more
coverage and that corresponds exactly
the octahedral map so every pixel of the
octahedral map gets one cast out of it
and the reason I wanted to do it that
way is just because I felt like that's
the cleanest way to write it out it may
not be the best coverage way to do
things and we could consider changing
how that done in the future but I kind
of wanted to start with that streamline
process so we could get any code gunk
there out of the way you can then take a
look at what we're doing here you can
see that in general we visit about five
leaves per cast what that means assuming
that we're still collecting those
statistics properly which we'll have to
do a little bit of a verification to
make sure we don't have any errant stuff
we missed but what these statistics tell
us is that we're generally testing about
five cubes for every cast now that's a
pretty reasonable number there I'm not
too worried about that number and you
can also see like how many partitions we
visited per leaves cast but this number
is a little more troubling this 24
partitions for cast
I believe that means we go down 24
checks before we actually get to do an
actual test right so we're spending a
lot of time navigating our bounding
hierarchy and you know that that might
not be so good right and there's
probably things we'll want to do to make
that work better right it's hard to say
but you know we we have some issues here
so we kind of need to look at how we can
get these numbers to look a little bit
better because generally speaking I
would assume and we can try to we can
try to make you know a little bit
we can try to prove this a little bit
more to ourselves as we investigate the
code but trying to initiate about a
hundred thousand casts into the system a
hundred thousand Kasper frame spread
over like at least six processors is not
that many castes right so if you take a
look at what we're asking the computer
to do here and we come in and we say all
right we've got you know somewhere
around a hundred thousand casts we're
splitting that out across six processors
so we're asking for you know 20 grand 15
grand in terms of the number of casts
and if we assume that the processor is
is gonna be you know somewhere north of
2 gigahertz always sometimes as high as
3 gigahertz you know if we did want that
to be at you know at a reasonable 60
frames a second let's say and we're just
looking at what that's going to imply so
you know we're talking about a about 33
million right you know somewhere in the
30 million cycles range for how many
each of those has so if we're talking
about you know if we're basically
talking about something where 2,000 ops
per ray is what we would need at 60
frames a second it's not the end of the
world as you can see it's not as fluffy
as you would want right again these
numbers they multiply out in in ways
that are kind of non-intuitive when you
think about how fast a modern processor
is it sounds really fast but once you
talk about having to do something at 60
frames a second suddenly it whittles
down quite a bit
right and we were talking about
something like ray tracing where you
have a lot of rays that you're trying to
cast right and so you've got just a
tremendous amount of work involved there
you kind of have to to be very judicious
about it
so when you think about the fact that
you know if I if I did that back of the
envelope math right and we should
probably do a more serious investigation
of it where I actually double-check and
make sure I've got it right a little bit
later on but if we take a look in here
as to how our full cast is actually
working so you can see what the routine
looks like you can sort of see that you
know everything that we care about for
the most part that's probably going to
be slow happens inside this raycast
call right so this think here if this
routine here that does for wide raycast
at a time that's gonna be the thing that
really ends up being you know this is
where all the times gonna be spent and
so if we look at what's going on in this
function you can kind of start to see
why we're getting this problem if you
look at what happens inside the
raycasting you can kind of see that
although we have a relatively
straightforward piece of code I mean the
number of ops here is actually pretty
small the problem is we've got a fairly
weighty set of things going on around it
so this stack traversal here and these
you know sort of the child ops situation
going on here we're just you know we're
getting a lot of box data right like
we're basically pulling a lot of box
data out here and we are suffering for
the fact that you know when we're doing
these when we're doing this we've got to
push a lot of things onto the stack pop
things off the stack and so on right so
the fundamental way that this thing
works and by the way this is probably
bad sticking and if in here is not a
good thing in fact it's a very bad thing
so we probably want to do something
different than this right like
this is probably not code you really
want to have you don't want any kind of
ifs in that aren't essential inside your
your main loop so I'm gonna I'm gonna go
ahead and just nerf these real quick I
don't think that would affect our
runtime much but I just want to make
sure that that we're getting those out
of there so anyway all of that is what's
happening in here and we're getting you
know a total time here that's
represented by this line so pretty much
all the work we're doing that we care
abouts in here and this work here for
compute light propagation we already
optimized a bit so it's already kind of
down in the lower end of things but it
could start to become significant as
full cast becomes optimized so we really
have to optimization targets and they're
the two top things here everything else
underneath is not really relevant to us
and I also don't know to what extent
we're doing a vsync here I think we're
not let me see what happens if I turn
that on I don't see really any
difference so I don't know if we're
actually getting I don't know to what
extent we're V syncing and what extent
we're not like I don't know if we're
getting held up much by the processor
here or not the fact that frame displays
stays the same take a look here it's a
little bit hard to say so so I don't
really know exactly what's going on
there I don't know what we're what we're
seeing here so that's that's that's
something we maybe have to look at a
little bit later but either way it
doesn't matter the point is in this case
we're gonna try and be working on this
top line number and I don't really know
that there's much we can do about this
value here so this six one four four for
the full cast I mean there are some
things we could do right
if we wanted to we could do some kind of
an inter leave where we only did every
other one of our lights of our light
foxholes I mean thinking it through that
top line number which is how many times
we call full cast we could use some kind
of a stipple pattern where we basically
say look we're gonna do like even and
odds in like a checkerboard pattern or
something and we just won't actually
update anything that's outside the
checkerboard pattern so and we flipped
the checkerboard pattern on every frame
right so we could do something like that
and that would also improve the lighting
speed by enough to get us to 60 frames a
second potentially I just don't know
what it would look like exactly but yeah
I mean I'm kind of curious let's take a
look at what that would entail so you
know I don't think we have really
anything like that in the code at the
moment but if you imagine what what
would you know what that would look like
so let me let me get the test sphere and
move that down I don't want that in the
way there I'm gonna put that over here
all right so if we take a look at what's
happening in full cast you can see here
that for each one of these full casts it
calls it on a particular textured tile
so it's like I need you to update this
tile right now so that full cast
function could just be could just be
done like with a stipple pattern right
so basically we could just say inside
here the Z and Y that we're doing will
just take and will compute whether or
not we do this particular one based on a
checkerboard pattern that alternates
either frame right
so if so for example if we did you know
an X and one write a y and one and a Z
and one write that basically tells us
like which one's of these if you think
about like the checkerboard pattern if
the X is X and one says is it odd right
and Y and one says is it odd so
basically if we said that we wanted the
well I guess I'll do y&amp;z because those
are in here so if we basically check to
see what the status was of Y and one and
Z and one and said look we want them to
be not equal right we want to have if if
the X is odd we don't want the Z to be
odd and vice versa
presumably that would produce a
checkerboard pattern that was you know
uniform through the space and I'll leave
the X out of it for now because that's
something we want to compute the headend
since we're doing a single X sheet here
but I could do something like this where
we basically said all right we're going
to have a should compute in here and
then we'll just do it if should compute
and we would go ahead and put the
checkerboard pattern in like so and we
probably don't care much about the
entropy sourcing at the moment although
in the future we're gonna probably want
to fix that to be different but anyway
if we stick a checkerboard pattern in
there right then what we should see when
we run the game is we should see like a
checkerboard pattern emerge in the code
where we're only actually seeing
lighting on the checkerboard although
oddly enough I am not seeing that what's
going on there why end one not equal to
Z and
shouldn't I only get checkerboards out
of that let me go ahead and and draw
just make sure I'm producing a
checkerboard here let me go ahead into
our OpenGL renderer and I'm just gonna
go to the end frame code and I'm going
to force it to draw the actual like you
know light maps in here okay
so I want to go ahead and see I guess
one thing is they will get copied so I
need to start by not copying I guess
just to see if we actually produce the
checkerboard pattern and I should
probably also zoom out and turn off the
smoothing so let's take a look at what
that would be in the yeah hmm so in our
visa man news man I'm not sure exactly
what I want to look at here I guess I'll
just widen it a little bit so I guess
I'll just say alright the visa man here
will just be I don't know
0.25 right and we'll just take a look at
what what the visa man is so there's the
visa fan and if you look at at what's
happening here you can see we're sort of
getting a you know an obvious drop out
of each of the Y of each of the zeros
and but it doesn't necessarily look like
it doesn't necessarily look like it's
alternating the Y Rose did I do this
wrong
if the Z if the Y and one so if I mean
it seems like that's correct right
just checking the lower bit which would
go on off on off on off on off right
across the voxel I only want to compute
it if they're equal yeah I don't really
see what would be weird about that you
know I'm saying that seems like that
should be correct I guess the only thing
though is X's aren't parodied so
actually that may be fine because of the
section we're looking at yeah okay so
that might act that SS probably actually
right I'm just probably not looking at
it cuz X X X Y is the checkerboard
you're gonna see Z is this way so I
suppose yeah I suppose that's okay let's
go ahead and introduce X then so that
each sheet flips polarity so basically
we need something here that's like you
know looking X odd right where we go
ahead and check that so what we'd want
to do here is say like I guess if X odd
isn't it's not equal to those so we can
flip it each time you know this should
be just something we can X or shouldn't
it if they're both the same it would
flip I feel like that would give me what
I want
this is complaining or was let me just
see that seems checkerboard like to me
there we go so now I'm getting a
checkerboard I would just forgot that
well X isn't involved so that's why you
got a singular row there so if this is
the checkerboard pattern you can see now
that like the checker boards it updates
the checkerboard doesn't update anything
else which is what I wanted and so what
we can do here is just like on either
frame we can just do the checkerboard on
the frame index as well so finally we
would do like an X odd here with you
know some kind of a thing that comes in
from
the actual work itself or from the
solution right which is a frame odd
value right and inside handmade lighting
I just say okay there's like you know
frame odd value here and the frame odd
value just goes 0 or 1 0 or 1 0 1 right
so every time we go into every time we
finish pushing a lighting frame we just
say like frame odd equals frame odd
sorry solution frame odd and we just XOR
that with with 1 right I guess I'll I'll
write this is o X 1 front well now so
basically what we're doing here is just
saying look just flip that bit flip that
bottom bit whatever it was I guess I
shouldn't even have to do this right
that'll just flip the bottom bit by
itself all right
so I'm just curious about this so you
can see at that point we actually saved
quite a bit of time right now it's down
at at about 20 milliseconds per frame
consistently between 19 and 20 which is
almost enough to get us a clean 60 right
and you know I don't know not
immediately obvious that you would care
that much about that so that seems like
another good option for us because that
way you know we're just computing less
obviously the easiest way to optimize is
just to not run code you know I mean
because that's gonna there's really
nothing you can do that is it
there's no optimization you can do
that's faster than not running something
right so yeah so let me go ahead and
turn off that debug draw there and then
we can start to look at you know is
there a way to speed up the actual
raycasting at all because any
improvement we could make to the
raycasting code would be huge for us in
terms of being able to improve the speed
of the lighting so as it is you know it
seems pretty reasonable right like it's
it seems like it's working pretty well
but you know like I said I I'd like to
get it up to 60 or more if I can not
that OBS can capture that it drops
frames all over the place but alright oh
and by the way chat know it doesn't make
propagation any slower at all right
because actually like the I mean I
shouldn't say that it does make
propagation slower in one sense but not
in another because you see the updates
for a given light transmission for
however far away it is on the same frame
so you can also if you want to
blend in faster and in theory you might
be okay there too so it does make the it
how do I say it
propagation is the same speed but
blending is slower might be the way to
say it in other words it doesn't reduce
the amount of time it takes from light
to get from one side of the screen to
the other which is still instant what it
does do is make the blending half as
fast right so the amount of time it
takes you to get up to a certain blend
level is is less lessened I don't know
if that makes sense
all right anyway moving on let's see
what we can do with our full cast so I'm
gonna go ahead and take a look at this
code and uh you know just just see what
I can do inside the raycast function so
when we look at what's happening here
you can see sort of the way that we're
going about things is we're doing sort
of a traversal of our of our box this
year and we're pushing on the first one
right so we make a little box stack and
we go ahead and push a box on the box
stack we go ahead and look to see out of
its children you know which ones we want
to look at we loop through those and we
continue now one of the things that one
of the things that I'm immediately kind
of concerned about here is I don't
so I don't really know to be completely
honest with you that this is a smart way
to set this up and I guess I do feel
like generally speaking people trace ray
bundles at a time but to be honest I
guess I'm wondering why they trace ray
bundles at a time
so this is kind of a little confusing
and I suppose I should think this
through a little bit more when I'm
looking at this I'm thinking to myself I
do believe that most of the time when
people do rate racers like this they
trace bundles of rays at a time which i
think is usually the way it's done but I
guess I don't know why they don't just
trace one ray at a time and instead test
against a bundle of boxes
and I guess I just have no idea why I
mean that's the kind of thing I should
probably go read up on and take a look
at what the latest research is on that
but I guess I just don't know why we
don't just always do a tree that's got
four wide it's always four wide so we
always build a hierarchy of four wide
boxes and then store a four wide box
that we intersect with do you know what
I'm saying so I'm just I'm not sure why
we didn't just do that and I even
remember us thinking that we would do
that so I don't think we did it out of
hand but again I don't really know so I
do feel like rather than have
it seems like maybe that's just a
mistake I feel like why don't you want
to test against four boxes at the same
time because that way when you load you
always load four wide so the boxes would
already be set up for you to do a four
wide load on the boxes
so you'd combine your X's your Y's your
Z's four four boxes at a time and then
what you do is you would cast against
one Ray that way you would always
traverse the exact right hierarchy for
that Ray and that just seems like it
would be way better I'm gonna go out on
a limb here and say that maybe the
reason people don't normally do that is
because they are trying to go much wider
than for meaning you probably wouldn't
want a spatial hierarchy that was fanned
out on 16s and like that's more what a
GPU has to do so it could be that like
four is a good number like two and four
are reasonable numbers 16 and 32 and 64
aren't so it may be that the reason that
you normally don't do it that way is
because you're normally targeting
something that's much wider than four
that's all I really have but that really
tempts me to want to try rewriting this
the other way round because I would like
to see what the speed comparison is so
what I might say is like I might say
what if you know could we could be
basically like imagine what would this
routine look like if it was operating
the other way around
so like instead of the raycast taking
the Ray origin and the rady this way it
would take you know box wise raycast or
something and whereas the other ones the
Ray wise ray cast right so it would take
a single ray origin in a single ray D
and it would cast that against the Box
hierarchy more you know by going along
the same as the Box by loading the boxes
instead and if you look at what that
would do I'm gonna go ahead and and
leave the debug code in here for now as
well if you look at what that would do
if we imagine that if we load up things
instead when we look at lighting box we
would have a thing that was like a
lighting box for X basically right so
you know every time we push something on
the stack it's four boxes and when we
check against it we would check against
four boxes right so there wouldn't be a
loop here the loop would not exist you
would check against like a four x box
and you just do it right and again the
reason I like that is cuz it gets rid of
that loop which I don't particularly
care for
so you'd pop a box for X out and then
you would just go ahead and start
working with that box so rather than
doing a loft here which is what we're
doing we would instead just grab these
out as actual for X wide like these are
already four
right so we would yeah does the box P
get used here anywhere we use the center
probably what to do the radius yeah
so I'll leave that like this for now but
I think this is a little suspect these
should probably just be loaded directly
and computed out of hand so and so I
think we probably want to fix that
because I don't think this is set up
quite properly also if we look at box
radius right it's really yeah like this
code is not doing what we would want so
I think what you probably want to do is
you just want to store like these values
and use them after the fact probably I
don't know we'll we'll take a look at
that later but I just want to look at
the effects of doing effectively the
same calculation but I think there's
work to be done there all right so
assuming that we get this stuff like ice
you know what I'm saying here is that we
have a Rea origin and a rady and this is
like gonna be lofted so these are the
things that will actually become loft it
up from singles single ones to packs so
now those are four wide clones
effectively of themselves right
and so I think that makes more sense
anyway and the tough part at that point
is just going in will be at the end when
you want to extract stuff out of here
you only want to extract the one that is
the best right so you - but to a certain
extent that is kind of what you want
right because we know because of the
limitations of the SSE instruction set
we know that we can't do voxel
irradiance wide right because the
lookups like fetching memory which is
most of what's happening in there is
something that can only happen in
straight line code we can't do it wide
because the SSE instruction set doesn't
have scattered either in it if we were
85 12 we could no there are no parts
really of that unless you've got an
ice-like laptop or something well that's
not true maybe X 512 those is in some of
the I 9s - but anyway so this might yeah
I think this might be worth exploring so
maybe this week today and next weekend
we can just play around with this and
see what's going on there so if we
imagine we're actually doing this code
the same exact way I don't think any of
this changes right so all of this is
exactly the same the only difference is
we take a look to see when we try to
figure out whether or not we hit
something we just need to know whether
or not we just need to know which one of
our which sub box to like descend down
right so we need to be able to push
boxes on the stack depending on which
one we hit like we need to push a
different box four onto the stack
depending on which one we hit and we
would have to push like up to four boxes
you know I'm saying so in order to do
that I
that part is a little bit tricky because
if you when you need to actually descend
that parts a little bit a little bit
iffy right I don't know that we need a
box child count here per se but what we
do need is we need I guess we do need I
mean child counts fine I suppose we just
need some way of saying whether or not
we push something on the stack or record
the hit right
so yeah I'm not sure exactly how to do
that cleanly that's a little bit tricky
what we sexually need to do is just an a
mask extract and then we need to push on
the parts of the mass like what for
whichever one we need to like push on
the correct values onto our stack right
and it's just a little bit iffy because
try I'm trying to figure out how you
would do that without too many s that's
the thing that really I feel like is
difficult there because if you if you
need to push on like you need something
looks like this because you tested for
box Oh although we could do something
even more ridiculous than that hmm so
there's another thing we could do and
that is really weird and probably not a
good idea we could do a thing that
basically was there's only one dissent
now that doesn't make sense but anyway
point being if we have four boxes here
we need to do something that looks like
this where we pushed four boxes on and
we need to push them on based on whether
or not we hit them the reason that
that's troubling is because I'm not sure
exactly how you would do that in a way
that doesn't become ugly pretty quickly
right you can imagine doing like
conditional moves for all of this I
suppose so just like Seema Seema Seema
Seema Seema Seema Seema and I suppose
that's not that bad because it doesn't
change what code is actually being
executed I don't know that I would
really have all that much luck in
compiler to generate that
but you know what I don't want is
something that looks like this because
that's just a horrible pipeline flushing
nightmare at that point because you know
there's no way it's gonna predict that
stuff correctly at all so yeah that's
that's pretty nasty
that's pretty best pretty ugly anyway so
if we take a look at what's happening in
here
and we look at what this branch does
yeah this would have to be a kind of
conditional move thing where you know I
don't know what would would make the
compiler do the right thing here but
imagine something like this maybe so it
would do something like look if the mask
and foo then do the assignment right
that kind of thing and same with the
depth so you could do a thing like this
where you just kind of walk through it
and say like okay you know can see if
you can get the compiler to do C moves
for each of these things and then you
have like a mask that's like okay form
for the box that we're looking at we've
got our sub box and we just do something
like this right and so you have like if
the mask and like you know whatever the
the thing is that you're testing against
when you extract the mask you would do
something like this
by the way that's probably not what the
mask will actually extract - but you
know separate issue it's probably more
like well I'll be honest I'm not sure
exactly what it would be but I when we
extract the mask would probably bite
wise so we'd probably be like you know
bit 1 bit for bit 8 bit 12 kind of a
thing you know I'm saying but we'll look
at that in a second so anyway the point
is yeah you know it would be something
like this probably so that way it's just
like a big serial dependency chain that
can get thrown off to the process or and
then the processor can just loop and
start computing crap right
and the downside there is that because
of the way we wrote the this being depth
first it means that it has to wait on
this thing which is not great right
because that dependency chains so
terrible
none of this feels good I'll be honest
with you
so now I'm trying to think okay is there
some other thing that I'm missing here
that's just like look there's a better
way to traverse this thing because what
I really I just want something where it
can stay relatively streaming right
where it relatively most the time it's
just loading boxes and testing buttons
boxes because the closer we can have it
to just I load box I test box repeat the
faster it's going to run and the more
you have to sit around fussing with
stuff like what am i testing and where
it's just gonna go really slowly
so here's another way to think about it
I'd guess maybe another way to think
about it is what if we instead turn this
into more of just like in a codex style
problem so what if we just said how
about we write the thing that we can
actually do and then we try to make a
thing that encodes a hierarchy in a way
that we can actually do it and we just
live with those limitations like it
sounds stupid what I'm saying it but
it's like I mean that's something right
and so just trying to think it through
imagine I guess if we just said all
right you are doing
you're doing boxes you're producing a
mask the mask then tells you what to
load into what to load into the thing to
do next and I guess maybe you can do
that yeah I don't know so maybe this is
this is part of the reason perhaps why
doing it the other way is better
although this the other way we did it
does sort of still have the problem like
if you look at what's actually happening
in the other ray caster you still sort
of have the problem where's my other red
caster there it is you sort of still do
have the problem of the depth push
happens and then you immediately have to
use it right
[Music]
I guess one thing that's worth noting is
you don't actually need to push things
onto the stack in the case where you are
like if you actually put everything onto
the stack instead you could change the
way this loop worked a little bit so for
example you could if you wanted to
change it so the source index actually
happens in here right then that doesn't
seem like a very good idea because that
just seems like probably a waste of time
so I wouldn't really recommend it but
yeah and we have you know we can change
the hierarchy every want so I'm not
trying to work with this heart
particularly I'm just trying to think of
how we would actually keep the hierarchy
how we would write any hierarchy that
allows us to stream boxes cleanly so
that we could test against multiple
boxes at once just because that seems a
little bit better and maybe that's not
true but it feels like it would be
hmm so we do know that those four boxes
can put things fairly continuously for
themselves
Oh actually I just got an idea I just
got an idea so actually maybe not maybe
what you actually want to do
[Music]
hmm I say so what if instead we had a
lightbox stack and tree and in that we
stored which box we were going to look
at but also the mask that we got for
that box and maybe I want that aligned
so if you think about it then what you
would do is say alright we got this box
stock garbage here and what we're gonna
do is we're going to say we get one of
these boxes and we put it in here and
then we also put in a mask and the mask
is just whatever the heck the mask is
right and then what we do is we always
load four-wide out of the boxes but we
only when we do our test we mask the
test against the mask we put on so
rather than ever having to do this crap
it's still just this
right so when we need to go down another
level of the hierarchy we can just say
like okay let's process this box and do
this mask right
yeah yeah yeah yeah so that seems good
because then when you let out the mask
you yeah you could just you could just
say we're loading up the things out of
this box and we can just mask the
results of that thing against what we're
looking at here now that's not quite
correct correct because yeah like
there's four of these rights you test
against you're gonna load up four
separate pieces but those four separate
pieces can be the things that are sort
of contiguous right so when you load up
here you you would still do root box
right and you would still do a loop over
the four pieces you just and yeah and
when you push each of those on yeah you
then do do the test four times or you
push for things not sure which of those
you want but again the nice part about
that is you just say yeah look the when
we push this on we just pushed the mask
on and then that way we know at a time
which ones were doing
I suppose that now I'm thinking about to
like though it's like alright is that
really any better I mean we could have
done it just push all four onto that we
could always push all four on to the
stack and then just zero out the pointer
and just check the pointer right so and
I don't know maybe that's not so hot
still not sure yeah
so yeah um
I'm just not thinking of anything clever
here
maybe it's the fools earned but yeah I
mean I do kind of feel like I want to be
able to do as many of these as possible
right and just looking at it like yeah
and like my dream world right it's you
know it's gonna be something like this
and we would just I want it to look as
close as possible just doing all of
these things just in a tight loop with
no nothing else right so like the best
possible case cuz it looks something
like this right
and you can just loop over this in
process as fast as possible you know I
mean so that's like what you would want
to do and so the question is how do you
get this part as efficient as possible
the part where you just push on four
boxes that you're doing
hmm and so
you
yeah so looking at this right here I
mean essentially there's a few ways we
can go with this right we could try some
pretty ridiculous stuff where we where
we mask out ones that aren't in the set
right we let these selects run so we
could do like a child mask right that we
load out of the box for and I mean I
guess another way to look at it too
would be since we know whether things
are children or not do we really even
need to write the loop that way all
right
I'm gonna delete this for now I I got to
think about this I think I want to like
just let it rot in the back of my brain
for a little bit but just having looked
at that that now begs the question here
so I feel like maybe we want this box to
tell us what it's children are right so
if you imagine doing an if here
basically where we would not have to do
the if on the inside of this thing I
feel like that might make a little bit
more sense as well so like when we pull
off the root box we would then loop over
the children of the root box in a
tighter loop if we know that they're
actual things we can hit if that makes
sense so you know if you imagine pulling
the if the child count if out to some
other things so let's suppose I did like
okay
root box you know is leaf container or
something so we just say sometimes we
know this you know we sorry as we know
this thing's a leaf sometimes we know
it's not right and then we just
specialize these two things so in one
case we say all right like give me the
you know give me the version of this
that operates one way and then give me
the version of this the operates the
other way so in the case where we know
that this thing is a leaf container then
we know that we're always testing leaves
when we're inside it and as we plow
through those we would say that we never
look at this case here right we just
want to know if we're in any closer case
and if we are then we're going to do
this thing otherwise we won't right and
we could get rid we could make this be
more streamlined with less ifs I don't
know that we actually want to do that
because there's a fair number of
computations actually happening in here
but it does mean that like this code
goes away right so you know we only need
any any closer
right and yeah and we could even just
say look if we if we stop doing this
stuff and we just look at what happens
with the if any true here we could also
say look maybe that's enough to just
just run the thing right
all right
so you know again just looking at this
like trying to get this down and we'd
say look this is what we're gonna do for
all of the boxes that we're actually
testing against and so that we don't
have to yeah so that we don't have to
like worry about it and we can do it in
a in a more condensed loop then the
other question is like all right when
we're on the other kind so now we're
doing partitions instead of leaves right
in that case we could also say look we
know how many there are because there's
always two or something like that I want
to say there's like only a certain
number of boxes and that's enough like
fixing that aspect of the hierarchy
might be another thing we should
probably do at some point but yeah so
you know taking a look at this loop here
we would leave this loop the same except
for now this part goes away right and
this goes away so it's mostly just that
and right and so now we just have two
sides of the thing and we can look at
them separately again I'm not sure it
makes sense to bother with this because
you've got another one down here so you
know maybe we do that and it just
simplifies that code as slightly we
could maybe turn this into a conditional
move or try to although I don't think
it's really gonna work but there would
be like a push or should push right and
then here we would just say all right
box
stack depth equals should push box stack
depth and will sign box back to it if we
want to actually we don't even really
need well block stack that way you can
see it's conditional move and then depth
equal should push depth plus one so
again we can start to turn these into
flatter things we don't really know that
we want to do that yet but I'm just this
is strictly for my benefit like I'm just
trying to read this and see what I think
of it right and so at that point all we
would really need to know is in that
lighting box nonsense we would need to
know if something was a leaf right so in
here where we've got like you know is
light or whatever we would just have I
guess it just be other flags right so in
addition to is light it would be like
you know is light you know is
yeah I guess it would just be is light
and is can his leaf container right and
then anyone who actually pushes one of
these things on you know instead of this
sort of thing they would actually be
just when they like pushing an occluder
or something like that right they would
just be you know setting that to zero
when you're pushing on a light you would
be setting leaf container to you know
equal like you know some flag that
equals that something like this and so
if we look at where the lending box is
defined there just be you know maybe
I'll do it like this doesn't really
matter but something like that so you
know we would set whether or not it's a
light based on that and then here we
would just say all right is light is
leaf container if it you know ends with
that way it doesn't add any more space
something like that this part here I'm
gonna go ahead and say we don't really
need this anymore anyway so I'm going to
take this out and not we're not really
gonna use that I don't think so
all right so let's go ahead and get this
working now because I'm curious to know
oh by the way also since we're not
casting here how fast is this so kind of
weirdly flickery there of timing it's a
little bit hard to tell what's going on
there
but alright
so anyway in terms of knowing what to
actually test there what we have to do
is we have to actually set that
container flag so when we're doing split
box in here whenever we create one of
these boxes that we need to split don't
really know what the if one is here for
it to be completely honest with you I
guess we were looking at some kind of
non split case or something like that
but I get rid of that now so if we
actually look at how we're splitting up
this hierarchy here which again is
another thing we can look at improving
because our hierarchy could probably be
a lot better but when we and you know
what this is also the case of something
we could do where if we just actually
since this KT tree like here we could
just start doing it as a KD tree so that
we didn't actually do a box test now
that we'd split the loops out right but
anyway so when we come through here and
we say we're gonna split this box and we
put the children into the box I guess
you can see like it's setting the child
count here I think all we would have to
do is remember whether or not we needed
to split any of the children right so I
think it's just saying look loop over
the split plains here if the count a and
count B are both you know it's if we
actually did a split then we start just
with the children right and so in that
case I guess we just need to know
so I guess I'm not sure so when that
into that builds the entire Harkey just
within that one loop right you can kind
of see it so I guess what happens is if
the source count is greater than four it
actually tries to do it if the source
count
isn't it just stuffs it in here right so
I guess all we need to do is find out if
we actually did split the boxes and if
we change the source count there right
so we just need to know if we did this
because if we did this then there's
other split boxes beneath us but if we
didn't then there aren't right so I
think that that's all we really need to
do so you know I guess we would just do
something like this so then here we just
do look if we actually split then we're
not a leaf container if we did we are
does that seem right
apparently not it's kind of an
interesting effect I'm not sure what's
actually happening there so it looks
like that's not quite correct although I
don't actually know it may actually be
correct and it's just the actual test
that's not correct but yeah so in here
where we add bucks references and we
stuff those in here right and we're
going ahead and doing is is lightest
leaf container and we order that in I
believe so if we come through here and
we've actually split then the boxes in
question are going to be tested against
for actual they're arguing this for
actual question because they they
themselves might have children I guess
you know maybe what we have to do though
is verify that the box did get split so
although no because because it's always
going to be a parent box right so that's
that's not true it's creating these
boxes here right I guess another way to
look at it is I guess we don't even
really have to do this we know that
anybody who had like I don't know I
think that's right so I don't know that
seems right to me does it not seem right
to you that feels right to me I'm not
sure why we're getting not sure why that
wouldn't it worked so I guess we'll have
to take a look at at the code more
carefully to figure out what I screwed
up but it seems like
you
it seems like that should be doing the
right thing what are the stats again on
that total cast initiated till the
partitions tested total leaves used to
the leaves tested wait what oh I've got
it backwards did I get it backwards no
no I didn't so for each one of these
were doing total ease tested for each
one of these we're doing total
partitions tested so yeah I mean
shouldn't that work I don't get it we
should have been seeing something come
through here right so you're telling me
that that the is leaf container and you
know is the container there is always
set so actually split is false if you
come through here actually split is true
so at that point this is true you would
not pour this in right so we should be
getting to this case how are we not
what am I missing there because I'm
obviously missing something since total
partitions tested is never getting hit
so let's go ahead and step in here I'm
gonna set this to debug mode because I I
don't have an idea of why that's failing
and that's in raycast so inside raycast
here I should probably also set us to
single thread I don't know if you can
freeze threads I think like single
thread stepping was something that that
was supposed to be added at some point
but I don't actually know how to do it
and it may or may not be in here so I'm
gonna go ahead and turn off all the
threading for a second so I don't have
to deal with it
so right here I'm just gonna say look go
ahead and do the work that way we only
have one thing to look at
so in the raycast what I just want to do
is see what am I not understanding about
what's happening here because we should
hit that case at least sometimes but we
don't so let me see like what does this
box look like what are these root box
look like are they just totally not
correct so this is just zero even at the
root weight but that's correct so we
should hit this and there's total
partitions tested what the hey so if
total partitions tested is getting
incremented how am I not seeing it are
we reporting those numbers wrong there
is total partitions tested did I miss
something is that does that not say what
I thought it said
yeah total partitions test at zero hmm
so if that's coming back is zero and yet
I just watched it get added there must
be some kind of a thing where it's not
actually tracking it properly although
in this case I suppose no I don't know
what because here it is right we loop
over this we put in a bunch of ads right
caste initiated partitions tested leaves
uses leaves used and I mean there there
it is printed out so like what the heck
is happening there
so let's do another step in the debating
to find out how we're getting the wrong
values because that doesn't really make
any sense does it so I'm curious about
this here's the call so I'm going to run
through to that call specifically right
and then what I want to do is I want to
look at work to see like there's total
partitions tested 41 880 right so then
we're gonna come through here and the
work count you know is whatever the work
count is we're then going to look at
each one in turn
there's televisions tested so we're
gonna add that to this there we go so we
just like overflowing this variable
somehow no so that's one one nine seven
104 is what we're supposed to be sending
out to the debug system
but now it is zero what so the first
time through it is correct the next time
through it's not okay is it not testing
the next time through so is the lighting
hierarchy wrong after a frame
okay so we must not be clearing those I
guess
so the two places I know that we can do
it is on the push occluder and push
light there's really two things that we
can push as far as I know when we
actually do our oh so maybe this just
doesn't clear anything I guess it's
possible that split box actually is
trying to be efficient and just never
sets that value so I guess what we would
actually need to do there is set this
explicitly so maybe it really needs to
do something more like this I guess okay
I mean I guess that's efficient we were
trying to be efficient here we didn't
clear you know we weren't in a sort of
defensive programming clear everything
mode because we didn't want to spend
that time so I guess that's fine all
right now let's see if this thing is
actually producing correct numbers that
was cool I mean it was bad but it was
cool
so that seems pretty good Wow
that's running at 50 milliseconds that's
single-threaded
how is that running so much faster all
of a sudden hold on a second
so what happens when I turn on threading
now
um so that seems pretty cool actually
right it actually seems like that makes
a substantial difference in the speed to
be completely honest right because that
also that's a bit weird that the frame
time doesn't go down by a factor of six
since these should be independent I
wonder if that means we got some memory
boundness happening here the heck is
this what's happening out here
hmm HM hmm all right so we're starting
to get somewhere here honestly looking
at that frame time it's starting to look
pretty small actually the lighting is
not really occupying as much time now
and I'm a little concerned as to why
it's showing up as high on the profile
I guess this sixty is because it's
looking at it across six threads so I
think that means the cast is now the
same cost as this and the frame display
right so I think that actually was
pretty cool
I guess it's hard to say but I mean yeah
like it looks like we're actually in the
point where we're gonna have to start
fixing the renderer which is fine but
look at that because at this point I
think that clocks is summed so I'm I
think in other words let me just just to
try and put this in perspective so full
cast is threaded so I think if we
actually stopped timing full cast and
just timed the lighting update outside
the threads that would be a fairer test
I don't know if that makes sense but if
we effectively said look I'm at time and
lighting which is is there and only that
now you can see a fairer estimate of
what's happening right so now we're like
evenly split CPU GPU waiting around
right so I think I would just miss like
miss counting that sort of how fast we
actually were we're actually quite fast
and I wonder what would happen if I
enable the checkerboard or just stop
doing the checkerboard now right I'm
wondering what that effect has on the
frame time
cuz yeah that's just like we're not even
number one on the board anymore half the
time so let's go ahead and take a look
and see if we turn off the
checkerboarding so just get rid of that
I'm curious
so without checkerboarding we do end up
a little bit worse right you can see now
we're where's consistently on top so
it's still not optimal right it's not
great but we're still hitting 30 just
fine
now without checkerboard right so that's
pretty cool actually
and I wonder what happens if we turn off
the diffuse copy I'm also curious about
that because that's very expensive I
want to see how expensive that actually
is at the moment so when we actually do
our diffuse lighting here
so we could actually also make a
substantial difference there right by
optimizing that code so by optimizing
that copy so that is now like
significantly bad I would say
all right so
so I guess I have a few more questions
as well so if I go now and I say all
right why don't you try building the
hierarchy a little bit differently so
like if I go to split box and I just say
look for how about instead of four we
say it's a
how about it's too
how about its four so it's interesting
like it's not even sensitive
particularly much to us how we're
building that hierarchy either so yeah I
think we're onto something here
I think basically like our raycast is
now pretty much substantially better
than it was interesting interesting
interesting
so I'm also wondering what happens if we
cast more Ray's like how much do these
rays actually cost now I'm actually
somewhat confused about that cost a
little bit and and I wonder if you know
if we changed the way we were doing this
now I wonder if we could even do
something a little bit different where
we said instead let's cast for Ray's out
of the same lock octagonal slot and do
four times higher lighter lighting
quality that way because it's looks like
actually that traversal is yeah like
fairly yeah mmm-hmm cuz the yeah I mean
it's really kind of wild at this point
looking at what we could dig in pretty
deep into this I think because it looks
like we're we're actually doing pretty
well and looking at the performance here
we're gonna need a more accurate way to
measure this I feel like
because it it seems like almost not that
it's it's really hard to look at the
difference I'm a just and you see like
what's happening here with these slots
to it's just we're just not having a
particularly stable timing here
I mean it's almost like it doesn't
really care what I'm doing it's it's
it's surprising how a little of
different some of these things make but
anyway so I'm not sure like that we're
doing the best job how were distributing
to raise the moment as a result of what
we're seeing so because it may be that
if we cast rays that are closer together
will get better traversal and end up
getting like lighting of similar at a
similar cost but that's actually much
better right
and furthermore like yeah if you take a
look at the blending and our there's a
bunch of other things we can sort of
tweak here right but if we look at
what's happening blend wise
what I'm trying to do now is figure out
what an estimate it would be for if we
wanted it to be quite stable what we
would have to do I don't know that I
really want it stable I kind of want it
to be flickery because I like that
effect but I could I suppose I can get
that by just flickering the lights so we
may want to do some better sampling
integration too because it may be that
like you know we can do a better job
using the samples we have than we're
doing right now but it looks like if we
were to do twice as many samples it
wouldn't look that much different but if
we were to do four times as many samples
it would look like this with the same
algorithm and this is considerably
smoother right and there wouldn't be any
lag because we'd be doing four times the
samples so I would be interested to know
if maybe that's a if that's a smart way
to go you see a little bit of on really
distant stuff you see a little bit of
flicker still but otherwise it would be
quite stable right and like I said I
think we may be able to change that by
perhaps looking at the total
contribution that something's making and
picking the T update blend based on that
you know what I mean
[Music]
just basically doing some importance
like some measure of like importance
sampling there to reintegrate those over
time yeah so gosh
yeah I'm not sure what to do next it
does look like 8 over 60 is plenty so if
we had four times the samples which we
could do we would basically get mostly
flicker free lighting at that point it
looks like and it would be pretty much
indistinguishable in terms of updates
because you can see like I don't really
see any lag at this speed and so if we
have the quality of the previous one
with the speed of this that's what we
would have if we were doing four raise
per octal instead of one in theory look
I'm not sure that's a perfect test but
it's something like that interesting
[Music]
and I guess I also don't know that our
entropy is working particularly well
here either but I guess that's sort of a
separate point but yet like so if you
imagine like if you imagine just doing
this for X so like imagine you just did
this four times right so and it would be
faster because we'd be doing it that
means the rays would be in a pretty
tight bundle but if so if you imagine
just doing like where we're calling the
raycast
so here right where we're grabbing out
the sampling sphere and we have the
entropy index I mean I guess I could
even just do this in the work load but
if we throw on an over sampling pass
here right like so and we effectively
say alright the entropy index you know
is gonna be like plus equals something
at the end of this so if we add a 4x
over sampling there we can sort of see
it wouldn't it won't it will be slow but
we did presumably see what we'd actually
get that looks like
so that doesn't actually look better
which is interesting that suggests maybe
our sampling is just bad and that's why
we're slow that's why we're flickery but
so let me just see what's going on here
I guess at that point I should probably
also do like
there we go
so yeah you know it would look something
like this I don't know how much faster
than this it would be though you can see
here the cost goes up sort of
prohibitively for that but yeah it could
be yeah do we have time to try this ten
minutes so the reason that I don't know
that I can test it in a short amount of
time but yeah it does you know that's
kind of interesting as is all the reason
I I don't know if I can test in a short
amount of time is just because if you
look at what's happening here where you
look at the spec Texel the way that the
raycast is working is the raycast writes
out you know it does four pixels at a
time and it wouldn't want to do that
anymore
so changing this is kind of expensive
because you really have to make a
decision about which one you are doing
and I suppose I could make an if here
that you know you know didn't do that
but yeah if you take a look at what's
going on here you I suppose you could do
it this way you'd say look here's an f0
and what we're gonna do is instead of
what was happening here instead of you
know writing these out we're actually
gonna write them out because we didn't
cast enough of these right
mmm yeah so we're just gonna sum this
part here we're just gonna sum up what
the answer actually is and so like I
said it's a little bit hairy to actually
do that and then when we do this we
would have to do like a load and then we
would when we would write it out we
would leave the the back value the same
so we wouldn't blend in that one I mean
that's what we would do I'm kind of
tempted to try it just to see what
happens it's too much for right now it's
too much for it we'll save that for next
time let's get let's do the QA now so
that we can be on time for switching
over to John stream I'm gonna leave it
like that I'll leave it like that for
now
all right
did you notice the instability and
timing was connected to the hovering
text and debugger okay no I didn't
notice that one of the problems that we
have and we probably will have to fix it
eventually is that our debug UI is too
expensive and you know for profiling
work so we probably need some way of
isolating that you know this is why
oftentimes it's better to use a separate
machine for profiling
it's why things like rads telemetry
program they're like a separate server
that you run and you just send packets
to it so you do have to pay the cost of
sending the packet but you don't pay the
cost of anything else and that's a good
way to do it because again when you're
trying to look for performance things
it's really too difficult sometimes to
make it go
integrated into the app like that
it's for coder miss editor
so the flickering in the lighting is
because it's undersampled so rather than
doing sort of a fake lighting where we
just slap a sphere around the character
like you would normally see in 2d games
we're actually doing full indirect light
transport like entirely right so it's
like a full ray tracer in there
computing the lighting and because ray
tracing is very expensive and currently
we just do it on the cpu we've
considered many of the GPU but if we
move it to the GPU then you basically
are only gonna be able to use it on like
an RT X card or something right
because we already use the GPU to do
compositing and stuff and we use a lot
of cycles if we want high res anti-alias
free and so on so because of that we
don't have very many samples to send out
and so the flicker comes from the fact
that the light from eat the samples that
you send out through each Texel of the
light map you only sometimes hit the
light sources and sometimes don't and so
you're trying to do an integration over
a whole like region there right and
doing it sarcastically like that adds
noise to your system so what you're
seeing is the noise of the sampling and
more specifically if you wanted to
imagine I could draw you a diagram that
that maybe helps understand a little
more intuitively what's happening there
so like if you look at here
so if you look at what it is seen if you
will from a particular Texel
so from a particular Texel you have to
imagine like you know okay we've got a
light map right and there's some data in
it or whatever right in fact let me go
ahead and grab a grid there so you know
we're computing a light map and we're
basically saying each one of these
texels is a light source and we're
saying that that mapped to a sphere
right and we're saying that like you
know so for example this quadrant of the
upper hemisphere of the sphere maps to
you know this part of the light map
right or whatever
so what we're effectively asking is what
is the total for one of these texels
like let's say this Texel right here and
maybe it maps to like right there right
we're effectively asking for that shaft
of light so for the shaft of light
that's going out of a particular Texel
right we're asking what is the total
amount of light that's coming in through
that shaft that's effectively a camera
rendering problem right you're
effectively asking what do you see when
you look out through that Texel as a
window so if you're shooting rays out
there to find out what you end up with
is something that if we now imagine here
is the Texel and we're looking outward
so we're looking out through this Texel
we're shooting rays and we're just
seeing what comes back right now when we
get an answer when we see what the light
is that comes back what we get is
something that's a crude approximation
of the light in that area so maybe
there's a light source here right let's
say and maybe there's a wall that's a
fairly bright reflector here right as
we're taking these samples we're
starting to get a better picture of
what's there and if it was static after
a while we just have a fairly complete
picture of what was there because we'd
have so many samples that we can
basically say we've reconstructed what
the incoming light is because we need
just the average right all we need is
the average but since these things are
moving over time like the lights like
moving this way whatever we can't just
take a long-running average
we have to fade out old samples over
time so that as things move we stop
counting them so as a result at anytime
we're really only looking at like you
know maybe 16 samples worth and we have
to reconstruct this exact picture from
just those 16 samples as we get more or
less samples that fall inside or outside
of a bright light source that's where
you see the flicker make sense so what
we can do going forwards like I said is
be a little bit smarter about how we're
integrating those samples don't always
use constant waiting use waiting based
on what we see and how much it
contributes to the particular Texel and
so on so we can probably do some kind of
importance based weighting of our
results that would be better than what
I'm doing now the reason I didn't throw
that in already is I'm not a sampling
Theory person so I don't really know
offhand what we would do so I need to
think about that and and like maybe I
may need to go read a little bit up
papers on it
to see what we should be doing there
right
as previously mentioned in chat both is
light and is the content of x1 Oh No how
did that not cause a bug for us I guess
you just wouldn't see it hmm oops oh
well you know what I guess the reason
that I guess now that I think about it
that can never happen anyway we
shouldn't have even bothered with this
this it should just be is light or is
leaf container yeah that was those dumb
talking about character movement will we
implement a transaction system something
like John's we already did so that's how
our character movement works
it's a transactional movement system
that's why in fact I was one one of the
people the person advocating to John
very often specifically that I was like
I love transactional systems you should
do one we've talked about it a bunch of
times and he was there's reasons to and
not to do them and he's been on the
fence about it
he eventually just committed to the
transactional system because I think he
just felt like there's no way to really
get a puzzle based game working properly
that way which is also my opinion for
ours ours is an action game so maybe
that's not true but I just feel like
transactional based systems don't have
the same kind of game play bugs that non
transactional systems do so I prefer
them so we've always been transactional
ever since the early days of when we
started doing the hopping mechanic
because once we had the hot mechanic I'm
like alright I want this to be
transactional because people are either
on a square or they're not and I'm never
gonna allow two people to be on the same
square so it's got to be transactional
let me see take another question or two
here I think I told John 2:30 but I
don't know he may be ready now
so in fact let me just check and see
what John status is if I can check to
see what John status is all right he
said 2:30 on Twitter so I guess I'll
just do two until 2:15 for the questions
and then at 2:15 I'll switch to trying
to get John to to hook up on video chat
just trying to because I'm sure we'll
need at least 15 minutes to make sure
that the like video chat works properly
and is streamable so and then we'll just
play us right at 2:30
is this already the best lit - but 3d
game in the whole history of camping I
don't know no I don't think so
we might be by the time we finished some
of our quality passes but no we're using
a diffusion heat model to average the
texture samples over space and time no
we don't diffuse over space at all the
reason we don't diffuse over space is
because lighting doesn't diffuse through
space I mean that's just just doesn't
right light is transmitted in lines
because photons travel in straight lines
that's just how it works so we don't do
that we do average texture samples over
time but the way that we do that is we
we bias towards more recent samples
because we want the lighting to be
responsive now like I saying before I
think we will want to change a few
things about how we're doing that
averaging so I don't think what we're
doing right now is particularly good I
don't know that a heat model is anything
we particularly want to use but we
probably will have some more importance
based integration happening to try and
make for better use of our samples and
also to try and and denoise so one of
the things that you know we probably can
do is try to figure out a little bit
more specifically what's happening in
terms of when we cast and potentially
save more information than a more saving
now here's a crude example
suppose we sample the specular lighting
and I don't think we can do this the
thing is too expensive but suppose we
sample the specular lighting at 60 for
us are 16 times the resolution of the
diffuse so rather than storing one texel
we store a grid of 4x4 texels for every
specular slot but we only store it then
what happens is every time we cast out
array we overwrite one of those slots
completely then to produce the diffuse
lighting we average that 4x4 down and
use that result now why is that useful
it's useful because that takes our
sampling jitter out of the solution
because rather than integrating over
space over multiple frames I should say
space over directions every frame we are
only integrating we're integrating over
all directions every frame every time
right so it doesn't have a lag to it so
that way if you hit the light source in
one direction you didn't hit it in
another direction then currently that
introduces flicker but in this system it
wouldn't because you wouldn't be
overwriting the bright sample you just
be overriding a direction that
previously had a dark sample anyway so
the average of those every frame would
still come out to the same thing so
that's why I say it's possible that we
can do something much smarter in terms
of how we're storing or integrating our
values that would make it so that we
would eliminate that flicker without
casting more rays I didn't explain that
well but
I do think there's ways we can do it
that don't that don't have the
directional variance because if you
remembered more about what directions
you'd looked you wouldn't have that
variance and so that suggests to me that
we can do a better job with the
information we have just and it could
because we know that if we stored that
extra information we could without
casting more raids same Ray's just more
storage right instead Oh key to use some
features from later versions of C++ I
may find useful for example lambdas or
templates I guess what I would say is
it's always okay to use anything you
want to use as long as you've done the
due diligence to determine that it's
actually saving you development time
that's that's really the key thing to
remember so I don't find C++ as features
save time in the long run they may make
you think you're saving time but when
you add up all the other costs bad error
messages longer compile times worst code
generation blah blah blah blah blah I
typically find that pretty much anything
you use from C++ ends up hurting you in
the long run not because it has to do
but just because they always do a bad
job right all of the things that C++
could have been done as good features
they just weren't so the reason I don't
use them is because I think they're
actually a bad trade-off that doesn't
mean that you have to think they're a
bad trade-off
you can go assess that yourself and so
the only thing that I urge people to do
is actually seriously assess it C++
programmers almost universally in my
experience do not actually assess it
they claim that something is better and
they don't actually verify that right
obviously the secret sauce committee
doesn't verify it but I mean people who
then use those features in their code
base
and when I say verify I mean you have to
verify it across everything all cost the
total cost of development not just that
you saved a few lines of code somewhere
by using this template or whatever right
um but if you've actually done that work
then you should not only feel free to
use the feature if you've found that it
actually can be verifiably better but
you shouldn't need to ask me about it at
that point obviously because you've done
the work you've proven that for the way
you're programming and then the code
base you're working in it is more
effective and that's what you need to
know it doesn't matter what I think and
it also doesn't matter what I think
about my code base because your code
base will differ and your development
processes will differ from mine and so
that's what you need to verify and as
long as you've done that verification I
would say feel comfortable using
anything you want feel comfortable using
JavaScript through end script and
through a rust translator that outputs
Java bytecode if you've verified it
actually saves you total development
time for the same end project if you've
actually done that work then you have
nothing to worry about the thing that
people have to worry about is making
these choices without any analysis right
that's the only thing to worry about
because computers are discrete and
analyzable you can tell whether or not
you're producing quality code and you
can tell how fast you're producing it
because you've got a calendar right so
you can measure these things at least to
a first approximation and if you have
measured them you should feel
comfortable if you haven't measured them
you shouldn't feel comfortable just
doing what I'm doing either right you
should learn those skills and when
you're a beginner it's okay to just say
well I'm just gonna program the way
Casey does because I know it can't be
that bad
since he's obviously able to do it right
that's fine but as you get better and
you become more of an expert then that's
not okay anymore it's not okay to just
say program make Casey does cuz he must
know because he doesn't
right he's not working in your system he
doesn't have the same brain as you
there's not the same teammates that you
do he doesn't have the same end goals
that you do necessarily so the
trade-offs that Casey makes and the
trade-offs that you make are not going
to be the same trade-offs necessarily
right so as you come more of an expert I
expect you to analyze those yourself and
if you happen to come the same
conclusions than I do totally fine but
you don't want to count on the fact that
I made exactly the right decisions for
your code and that goes for everyone
anyone who sits around telling you that
they have the right way for you to
program is wrong they may accidentally
be correct about the conclusion but they
are wrong about the claim that they knew
it was right because they can't
would you - link transactional inverses
what I'm sure so transactional movement
systems or transactional gameplay
systems in general something I've worked
with for a really long time and in fact
the witness' collision detector even was
this kind of system as well although
since it doesn't have multiple people
the transactional part doesn't have to
do much but the idea is broader than any
real specific implementation it's just
about saying look there's two ways that
we can express the core gameplay of any
given game one way is a chaotic system
that just has a bunch of floating-point
simulation code and whatever comes out
the end of that is the game okay
and this is a Unity game or an Unreal
Engine game like anything made in those
systems is this way it works by saying I
throw a bunch of entities into a system
there's some kind of a physics system
tying it together the things like move
around and they bump into each other or
whatever and then just whatever happens
when the collision gets resolved I have
like vent that fires and it does
something right and the game is created
organically from those things and the
the game designer piles enough rules on
top to make the game that they're making
right now the problem with these kind of
systems is bugs are everywhere people
are accidentally getting shot through
the world or you know people get clones
of treasures or they're able to like run
up the side of the wall or whatever and
that's because it was just a paintbrush
model of painting rules and events on
until it sort of looked like it was the
game right a transactional model is the
opposite of that that's saying we're
gonna approach this like a traditional
game like chess or something where the
rules are 100% explicitly written if
this is the situation this is the
outcome and all of the outcomes have
been
pree analyzed right now this has pluses
and minuses the pluses are the design is
explicit you know exactly what it is and
you know all of the possible outcomes
from that design right because you can
literally look at them like a chess tree
and maybe you can't quite look at the
entire analysis because you haven't you
can't afford enough AWS time to actually
search the entire tree or something
right but at least you know like on
chess you know the space of all like
roughly possible things that can happen
more or less right however the cost of
it is that that chaos isn't there right
you now have a much more pre-conceived
overtly designed system and the things
that will happen in it are more
deliberate so if you're trying to have
some ridiculous thing like that happens
in grand theft auto where it was
considered a bonus that somebody
accidentally like shoved dynamite into
the shark which it caused the tail to
explode off at a very high rate which
you know kind of caused this bug where a
ship flipped around 180 degrees which is
never supposed to be able to do but that
was great and everyone loved it right
that's a feature you know sandbox games
want lunacy they don't they're not
trying to make a deliberate controlled
experience they're trying to let things
get out of control right and so you know
you that that's that's what's happening
there so
I think I'm gonna go ahead and and stop
the recording now I'll keep the stream
running but I'm gonna have to quit now
and we're gonna try and switch over to
John and see if we can get a video
uplink working so