hello everyone in Wilkin handmade here
oh sure we could a complete game live on
stream we sketched out a routine
yesterday that we want to code today and
I don't know why I'm still wearing my
headset that was for playing slipways in
the pre stream if you haven't played
slipways yet I highly recommend it you
can go to slipways net and you know you
can you can get your slipways on this is
actually for the PC version that's
coming the Piko 8 Edition is the one I'm
playing because the PC version isn't
here yet but this thing is awesome it's
like my favorite game I've played in
quite some time
and quite a respite from playing some
Animal Crossing which is like absolutely
the most tedious game that you can
imagine now so check out slipways I am
going today to be doing the routine the
grid-based raycast and routine that we
sketched out yesterday because I wanted
to test that because we want to sort of
circle the wagons and finish up the
raycasting part of the lighting system
which you know works fine as it is
currently but is not up to the speed
that I would prefer so basically what we
need to do is make that run fast enough
and if you take a look right now at you
know how it's running in game you can
see oh wait you know what that's running
the wrong the wrong um or out there grid
grid based raycast do we have like
raycast or grid raycast grid raycast
that's it so if we want to we can switch
this back on by saying use for arrays
and if we take a look at the lighting
there's two things that we're basically
working on right now so we roughly have
the effects we want from our lighting
system CPU side right now but there's
two things I want to do one is reduce
the noise in the sampling and the other
is to just speed it up now it does run
30 frames a second pretty saw
right now but the problem is I'd rather
a trance IXY frames/second because we're
gonna have more complex geometry in here
and so I don't want something that
already can't hit 60 when we're not
really using the full geometry and yeah
we could just do this GPU side and that
would probably get us our frame rate
back but you know I want to do a cpu
side one at least first and prove that
that's feasible because I don't really
know how much ray-tracing support on
cards we're gonna be able to count on
like it'd be nice to have a fallback
plan for if you're running on an iPad or
something who knows what you want to do
obviously I refuse to use Apple hardware
now because of their like ridiculous
policies on not letting programmers
distribute programs they're basically
like Richard Stallman's arch-enemy or
something for no real reason even if he
does occasionally eat something from his
foot that is not a reason to not allow
people to distribute software on your
platform that's just basically
antisocial and weird anyway let's go
ahead and take a look at the routine
that I sketched out and how it would
need to work so in order to start using
this grid raycast routine we need to do
three things first we need to actually
like implement the routine correctly
like there's a couple things in here
that are just sketched out and we need
to like fill those in we can do that now
then we need to do to set up phase
things one is we need to produce the
look-up tables for the directions the
rays go and that's not that hard but it
is a little finicky so we'll have to
write that routine and then the other
one is we need to actually grid up our
geometry so we've got three steps to
produce here so I'm gonna go ahead and
comment in the routine we sketched out
and we'll start by trying to make this
work sensibly so if you look at what's
going on the first thing you'll notice
is we don't have a walk table here and
so what we need to do here is in the
the same way where we're actually doing
the the Ray casts here where we pass the
Ray in we need to know what our walk
table is and I think that's probably
going to be something that comes from
the outer code because my guess is that
yeah like if you look at what this is
gonna do the people who look up the Ray
or the people who know what the walk
table is so it's probably gonna look
something like walk out and we know that
this is also a small value I don't know
if we actually need to specify that here
but it's something that would need to
that might affect like it could be
relevant to the optimizer so I'm just
gonna tell it that it's a tiny value and
I don't know sometimes that's actually
worse this is one of those ways that C
is just terrible like there's no way to
tell it things like this is an 8-bit
value that never overflows like that's
the actual information I need to give it
and of course you can't give it because
the C++ standard community is like too
busy you know going on vacations to
theory land without actually ever making
the language work so anyway I'm gonna
give the walk table a little set up here
and we're gonna assume that this
actually this part doesn't actually need
to happen right so what's actually gonna
happen here is when we look up the walk
table we're just gonna look it up like
this we're gonna say like the grid index
equals the walk table walk index and
this is the grid index here and so those
are both driven off of this well not
both that is driven off of the walk
index so we run through that array in
the way that you would expect and we
pull out the individual grid squares
that we think that we're gonna need we
pull those spatial grid nodes out of
this out of whatever the storage is
going to be for those and we expect each
time we get one of those to see a start
in a one pass last right now these are
probably just going to be copied
directly out because all they are is two
16-bit integers which
is just totally like it's a 32-bit value
right so we don't really want to do
anything where we we actually used
pointers or anything on this so I'm just
gonna copy this out and access it this
way that just lets the compiler know
that it's not alias like it just
simplifies things for the optimizer so
now when we go in here we're gonna be
loading these leaves out and each leaf
is gonna have to have the information
that we require we have the hit ref
color and the hit emission and those
need to come from somewhere
mostly I think we're just doing this and
if we look at what's happening here this
is kind of busted actually so so my
streaming machine right now just popped
up a thing that says we've turned on
storage sense to optimize storage usage
we've turned on storage sense for you
that is a terrifying statement so I'm
just gonna go over to this machine and
see what that means I think that means
we're low on disk space so I'm gonna go
ahead and make that not happen because
that is very bad whatever it's doing I
don't trust it like if Windows 10 thinks
it's doing something it should stop it
will never be good it's just a bad
situation so I'm gonna go ahead and
delete some of these recordings here
that were on this machine and like free
up some disk space that way so that we
do not have this problem and I'm gonna
turn off storage sense cuz storage sense
is giving me the creeps Windows 10 is
like the worst thing ever
I really wish I think John often says
the phrase they need an adult to
supervise it and I totally agree
I don't think Windows has had an adult
on the team in like I mean at least in
management for an incredibly long time
they may have forgotten what an adult
looks like they're like Oh an adult
that's the thing in diapers that like
waves a rattle around right and you're
like no that's not an adult
that's the opposite of an adult actually
so okay
I have cleaned up this particular
problem here and now we can go back to
actual programming which is what I
wanted to do before Windows interrupted
me so okay so going back to actual
programming what I want to do here is I
want to make sure that we're actually
picking these things properly and if
we're loading these things up four at a
time so this is testing four leaves at
once and you know one of the other
things about this is is these are all
for wide so these leaves are for boxes
packed together but it's fine
we want to be able to load in for ref
colors at the same time and we also want
to load in for his emissions at the same
time so these need to be loaded this way
now these are a little bit piggy they're
bigger than they need to be but it's
okay for now because we haven't done
storage optimization on this yet we're
gonna have to to make sure that we
actually get the most performance out of
it because we don't really want to be
moving a bunch of crap around that
doesn't need to get moved right it's
just worse for the cache and takes more
instructions and etc etc so the more
things we can load up into one the
better and so if you looked at like this
for example so you know you've got like
the min the max color of the emission
you know there's so many things that we
could start doing here to optimize the
way that these things flew through the
pipe and so eventually we may like do
some of that right that's all as I'm
saying so I think that's all we really
need here this loads everything out that
we needed to we know that these are 16s
as well like I said all of these are
small right and so we can just leave
that be and we can look to see what the
compiler is actually generating and we
may need to do other things there it
depends right so in
we now have a question if I compile that
what I can do too is sketch out what
these look like as well because I might
as well do that too
so we would know that if we were gonna
implement this routine the grid nodes we
now know what they would look like
they're a start index and a one past
last index and we also know what the
leaves look like so we know what this
looks like yeah we know that this is a
box men a box Max and a ref color and
emission so this is for emissions pact
this is for ref colors pax this is for
box mins and this is for box maxes and
those can all get load up load load opt
here and these get loaded in and
processed here so that seems totally
fine to me and doesn't super-scary mean
so if we go into the lighting solution
and we look at what we're doing here so
we can also say like okay in the same
way that we were just gonna like have
all these different things flat on top
of each other I can go ahead and grab a
an array for each of these and say these
are gonna go in here and I don't
actually know like what they're gonna
look like yet and I don't care but we
know that we're gonna be loading these
off like this and actually that's
spatial grid node spatial grid leaves so
that's the whole collision detector like
basically this is the Ray caster now and
you can see why I wanted to try it out
this way because when I was thinking
about it in my head I'm like this can be
so much more straightforward all it's
doing is doing an index based load off
of these leaves right so it loads
indices in order and loads leaves off of
those indices so it's dependent load but
it's there's nothing to predict right
there's no ifs
at all in this entire thing so you're
only paying the only thing you're paying
for during the raycast is one branch
that is only happening at the end so
this is predictable the whole time
through until you end right and then
you've got this one so this is the only
like issue is the branch for this loop
otherwise it's just a straight streaming
process or right now there's issues with
it I don't necessarily know that's going
to be placing lis fast but you can see
why I wanted this because if you compare
this to how complicated like the K treat
gate KD tree or a bee tree walks were is
there's just a lot more decision-making
going on and the more decision-making
there is the harder it is to make the
routine operate in a streamlined fashion
right because it's not just a straight
stream process that that CPU can chug
through right and so I don't know what
else to do to predict its performance
unfortunately so we're just implementing
it but that's the idea that's why I want
to test this one so I think that's
everything for the loop so mostly now
it's the support of the loop that is the
issue now exiting the loop we have more
work to do because before we
fundamentally have two ways we can
raycast
in this version of the raycasting and
this is another reason that I like it
but again it could end up being a bad
idea but the other reason I like it is
instead of casting for raise at a time
it cast one rate at a time and normally
you think of that as a bad idea but the
problem is with a rain caster when you
cast for a raise at a time they're
incoherent so you don't necessarily know
that they have to both that that all
four rays go down the same parts of your
spatial partition so if you if you're
doing it that way it means every time
through your loop you're testing one
leaf at a time against four rays you
would rather be testing one Regan's four
leaves if you can figure out a way to
make that fast enough and in this case I
think maybe we have I don't actually
know the problem we're gonna run into is
if you don't have very many leaves that
are actually filled with you know
actually four
if a lot of the leaves are filled with
only two or one that becomes a problem
because then you're spending a lot of
time doing operations that you don't use
much like in the other version you're
spending a lot of time walking down tree
branches that aren't necessarily useful
for a particular array so you can either
push into the spatial partition side of
things or you can push into the leaf
side of things that inefficiency and the
question is which one's smarter now
there are ways you can actually fill
holes so if you look at what's going on
here there's another way we could write
this routine and again it may be the
better way to write this routine so
we're gonna have to write it both ways
to see which one's faster probably and
the other way to write this routine is
to pack on demand so if instead of doing
the inner leaf here what we actually did
was the inner leaf in a pre walk which
is the way I first like what sort of
sketching it out and I said well let's
try this way first if you actually do
the inner leave in a pre walk then you
know you are only paying the absolute
minimum wastage because you only waste
the very end it could be that that's
just a fundamentally smarter way to do
it so basically you load you have a pre
walk that goes through loading in
interleaving as many things as the Rae
actually touches and again I really
don't know which of those two would be
more efficient so you're gonna have to
figure that out yourself and I'm gonna
have to figure that out myself as we go
so that part is is tough and you know
I'll slap you in here in case just so
everyone remembers
and so it's hard to say now it's worth
noting that this one is still fine when
there's nothing so if there are no
actual members it will just skip right
so it's we're not wasting computation in
cases where you don't so we're not gonna
we're not wasting computation in cases
where there's nothing to do we're just
wasting computation where there's not a
multiple of four things to do because
whatever the modulus is whatever the
wastage is on that if there was only two
things in it but we compute four then
we're wasting two lanes of our Sindhi in
much the same way that if you went down
a branch of a tree
that you didn't need for one of the
raise in or two of the raise in your
lanes but the other two did need that
branch then you're wasting half of your
lanes in that case right so the wastage
is very similar in both cases because
when you mask out you're gonna end up
like masking out something and you don't
actually need to do it or whatever right
so it's just it's it's this thing that
happens with Cindy it's why Cindy is
inefficient you do it because you can
tell the cpu to do a lot of things at
once and that turns out to be a big
benefit but it's just it's inefficient
because you can't always come up with
enough work to do without going through
a lot of gyrations especially in things
like this where you've got where you
trying to call all right so now if we
take a look and we look at the outside
of the gene when we fall out and we just
have to figure out which way were
actually take taking the fastest way to
do this would be using SC 4 sorry 3
ssse3 and use them in Posie PU which is
this right here
and the way that we would do this this
is basically gonna tell us it would come
it would put into the min test it would
actually put in there who was the
minimum act the actual minimum value and
that's a much faster way to do this than
actually doing any kind of sets of
swizzles the question is do we want to
use ssse3 we looked it up and there is
no nothing like nobody on Steam doesn't
have it so it's probably pretty safe to
use three more or less across the board
so we could probably use min pause EPU
and if we did that then if you take a
look at what that actually does here so
you can see in the insulin in transit
sky min pause EPU so if you look at the
way this behaves it's basically a
horizontal compare it takes four cycles
to do you can see why it's ssse3 it's
only in skylake and forward cores so if
you have the old ones it's not there I
guess now sometimes the intelligence
guide is wrong I mean how could it be
right it's only made by the people who
make the chips so sometimes you want to
go look at a third party for that so I
don't actually know the same hardware
survey is really the thing but let's
take a look at whatever that is and
what's that instruction it's that so if
we turn on as this e we can look here
and see what it actually thinks it's on
so in this case it's just registered to
register we don't care about registered
in memory here it is and you can see
that it's in sky lake ice lake cable a
coffee like and okay so basically the
Intel intrinsics guide is full of it
this is totally wrong I mean here it is
like it's on everything like so I don't
know where they were getting that from
like Sandy Bridge ivory bridge has well
Broadwell everybody has it way before
sky lake so I don't know what I I don't
why that's the case so we can do that
it's a latency for instruction so to be
honest I'm not 100% certain we actually
need it because if you take a look at
how long it takes us to do it the other
way around it's also going to be for
probably latency for I mean it's more
like latency five to do it the other so
I'm gonna go ahead and say this is just
stupid like if it's a latency for
instruction but it only took us five
instructions probably to do this I'm not
sure we actually need to do that
I mean I guess the benefit is this brick
this gives us something better to work
with I mean I guess the benefit of it is
this latency for but it puts the right
thing in there and I didn't really have
a good strategy for putting the right
thing in there like we needed to use a
shuffle table to pick up what the answer
was and so I suppose that the argument
there is like look it's latency for but
it puts exactly the right thing in for
us I believe because if we take a look
at what the actual result is of that you
can see that you get in 0-2 like right
here in the zero two bits you get the
index of of who was the minimum right so
it looks at all the 16-bit integers of
which there should be eight right it
fills the the bottom three bits with
that information although I think is the
min
where do those go oh I'm like I'm like
what the heck it's just using those as
temporary variables for some reason so
it's storing the minimum the value that
was actually the minimum it's storing it
in 0 through 15 and then in 16 through
18 so in the next 16-bit up it's storing
the index right so if we actually wanted
to use a byte shuffle we'd have to do
like a replicate that like you know that
broadcasts this thing across the entire
across the entire selection and that's
fine so if you look at where this is
being placed it's kind of a little bit
inconvenience so we would need to do a
shift first to move it down so it would
be something like this
like you'd do a shift or well if you
could do a shuffle as well so you would
do a 32-bit shift or I don't know to
actually do they have a 32-bit shift
they may not know they do I was like I
couldn't remember if 32-bit shift got
added the first time or where the 32-bit
shifts were added later so we can do a
shift right and I want that one so we
can do a shift right by 16 so it'd be
like a like a ester a epi32 right and
what we would want to do here is just
say like okay we want to shift this
thing after we get it we want to shift
this thing right by 16 to put it in the
bottom and then we want to do so that
produces a new whole ball of wax there
then we want to do now that we have that
we want to do an mm shuffle to broadcast
it right and you can see so this avoids
actually loading in a table and which
again this this might be faster I mean
just looking at it I'm wondering cuz I
don't know how long
move masks takes I don't know how long
move mistakes it's not long right
so yeah I mean it may just be that it
just isn't worth it you just move just
move masks and load out of shuffle table
I mean seems like it so even though we
could use that and what's the what's
shuffle epi8 as sse3 so if we want to
use that we do have to use sse3 as well
so we don't actually get that for free
if I look at you ops info what speech f
be listed as in terms of architectures
here if I go to just a standard register
register shuffle
so again are they sure I don't know I
don't always know if this thing is right
anyway it doesn't really matter point
being that's probably fine because
there's not going to be again like the I
think min pause and shuffle are both
fine so it's really hard
I mean P chef P Chef be not regular chef
PS regular stuff PS goes back even
further that's like to the first that
was in the first SSU release like SSE
one so I don't actually know what to do
here I do not know which of these would
be smarter but it does seem like you'd
be doing a lot too once you actually got
the min out there and you wanted then
produce a shuffle that corresponds in
order to shuffle any shuffle you can do
that's gonna have an input is gonna be
ssse3 anyway so you're already kind of
out of luck because the inputs I don't
think you can there's nothing you can do
there's nothing you can do that takes a
that doesn't use an immediate right so
basically the first time like pea chef B
is the first time you can actually get
something out like as far as I know I
don't think there's any other way
besides pea chef B to have something
that's in the register and actually do
something with it right everything else
that shuffles is immediate shuffle
that's that's what I recall anyway so
yeah so having to do all that work it
seems like maybe you just load the
shuffle table and call it a day and that
way you don't really care about min pose
because it just seems like it's more
trouble than it's worth
to get that out now we could use instead
of doing it this way we could still use
min pose epu and say look we do the mole
we do the min pause and then we're just
gonna actually like move that 32-bit
value out so we'll just extract the
32-bit value and then still use a
shuffle table
and that may still be faster than doing
all of these it's latency for but it
might work maybe again it builds up a
huge dependency chain off of here so I'm
not sure but yeah so if we did a min
pause here and then we said look just
move that value out so you know maybe
you do maybe you do the shift so that
now you've cleared it and then you do an
mm oops
mm convert and we just extract the value
so in fact actually we may be able to do
that in one go
actually we can so what we could do is
not do that we could just say alright do
an mm extract epi16 and then just say
look we need the second one bro right so
like get us that particular one out so
this here is what whatever the actual
lookup in the shuffle table is so this
is the like shuffle index here we would
just say all right that's the extraction
that we actually wanted and now we just
say look that up in the shuffle table
and off we go so once we have that that
just loads a shuffle table for 0 1 2 or
3 right whichever one it's going to be
and then we shuffle epp chef B I don't
know why they insist on always having
different names for the intrinsics
versus the instructions it's maddening
just call it something if it's shuffle
call it shuffle if it's pea chef be
caught Keisha feed just like this nobody
wants this I do not know why anyone
wants this I should just make a giant
pound to find thing that like but you
can't even do that because they force
you to pass these different I hate this
just make it look like sembly language
it is assembly language huh so
frustrating and the typing like the MM
128 versus once we I hate that stuff so
annoying anyway so what we want to
here is we want to go in and make this
code path now be correct so we want to
shuffle everything so that we load up a
shuffle table we shuffle each time to
produce a output that has only the one
Rea we care about right now because we
like there's no reason for us to drop
the scaler here even though we only care
about the thing that's in the zero
column because we so actually we don't
need to do this either this can be an mm
like load one now that I think about it
so we can't actually just load a single
value I don't know what they call that
in oops or as my so if I want to load
just one thing you're gonna let me do
that you're not I feel like there's a
way to do a load one PS of a float so
shouldn't there be a way to do a load 1
of an int right but if I remember
correctly this there's some really weird
thing we're loading one integer actually
just doesn't work and you the intrinsic
slike don't work on they only work on
Windows or something it's I don't
remember the specifics it's absolutely
nuts it's again just more stupidity but
like I want to say there was a thing
that like you can do was it in
conversion it's also frustrating so yeah
it's like
I don't know where it is
I do not know where it is there's there
was a way to like cast from an inch to
one of these things yes set one so I
want to say that there was some really
weird stuff where when you do a set one
like epi16 or whatever it like doesn't
work like on intel or some weird thing
like this
I really cannot remember the specifics
but it's like I'm it doesn't work on
Linux rather there was some ridiculous
like getting the VP broadcast W like
didn't happen or something
I just cannot remember so what we want
to do is this basically we want to do a
VP broadcast D and we want to do a VP
broadcast D of 0 1 2 3 right so we would
load that up and we would we would put
that in there so it just goes 0 1 2 3 0
1 2 3 0 1 2 3 but it's not actually 0 1
2 3 it's whatever the it's whatever the
action the C's are so it might be four
five six seven four five six seven four
six seven four seven it's just pulling
the correct bytes so that everyone
shuffles into the lower Lane that's all
we're trying to do here right so I don't
know if I can actually use this on Linux
I just don't remember I remembered there
being some weird thing like I shipped a
version of meow hash with this in it and
people were like it doesn't compile on
Linux and they were right it didn't and
it was like what the heck you know what
I can test it here cuz I don't really
want to go the like the slash the Stack
Exchange route and have someone tell me
something wrong so let's just test it
here here's GCC I'm gonna shove this in
here and just see what it says if I
include the the intrinsics file so in
here if I set the options I'm gonna use
clang because I don't really actually
know how to use you see I'm used in a
really long time
I assume the switches are the same they
usually are but I don't actually
so if I go to clang here and I say
alright like go ahead and include like
what is it in trend on H or something
like this in trend on H is not correct
see this it might be that I'm gonna go
ahead and look at me on hash cuz I don't
ever remember what the heck the fact
that these are different include files
on different platforms is also amazing
to me everything about the way these
intrinsics were handled is amazing to me
it's like the biggest cluster of stuff
for no reason like at all
like everything should have been done
cleanly here and none of it was alright
so if I do that it does not like that
now maybe that's because what's the
architecture switch on this thing so I'm
gonna give it like a boost and say look
use all the extensions and all that
stuff do you know this instruction so
yeah so unless I'm missing something
oh no it's fine so it just didn't I just
because I didn't give it a memory all
right so it looks like I can use Sethi
pi32 on clang so I'm gonna go ahead and
say just something else I was thinking
of and we're okay I just want to make
sure that I wasn't gonna set a little
booby trap for folks compounding on
another platform there so set one epi32
should work and that does a broadcast
correct like I'll verify that it
actually does a broadcast but then I'm
gonna say that that's the way we'll just
load out of our table so let me look at
the V broadcast oops the key broadcast
right
where's the broadcast instruction what
so what is this actually doing you
notice it doesn't actually mention what
does it actually do why does it it
normally it has the instruction that
it's going to use and in here it does
not which no here it is so VP broadcast
EVP Brooke SW and so on so why was I not
able to search for these is there a
reason for that
is that because of like I don't have
something contract that I need to okay
so those were in a V X so if that
intrinsic might it says it's an SS
either so I wonder what it what will it
generate only in SSE what would actually
use would be my question right like if I
use that if it's if it's not gonna do a
VP broadcast what is it gonna do you
know what I mean like cuz I don't really
know what that will actually generate so
I guess one way to do it is just to look
and see what it generates so if I do a
set one EP a-- epi32 let's just see
because I don't again I I'm just nervous
that's all I'm just nervous about this
but if I do a set one epi32 offer the
shuffle table like so that's what I
actually want to have happen here and if
we do a nerfing of the rest of the
routine like this and I don't know
transfer PPS it's nothing
let me just go ahead and make sure this
does something
first and this needs a convert so if I'm
gonna do a convert here I need to do a
so yeah again if I do this EP u16 this
is a little bit gnarly because if I do a
convert here to go from float to 16 I
have to then pack and after I pack the
index of which six teens to grab is
slightly off
well no it's still correct because it's
still zero one two three four yeah so
okay it's fine
so after I do my mol this puts it into
the range so then I just need to do an
mm convert and I'm going to do this in
action of multiple steps then I'm gonna
do this here where I'm gonna do like you
know in tier a integer basically so I'm
gonna do like a Mull and then I'm gonna
do a mm convert EP IPs right so this
will basically turn these floating-point
numbers into integers which is what I
want so once we have them as integers
then I'll do the comparison on them now
one thing so actually I don't need to do
the multiplication do I
I mean you sort of do because we're
gonna truncate them so I guess we do I
was gonna be like you can just compare
them directly because the minimum like a
floating-point value if you compared the
floating-point value if you can poured
the floating-point value as if it were
an integer that would work right meaning
a floating point values layout is such
that it will compare as if it was a
signed integer is that not true because
the sign bit is still the first bit
meaning much like two's complement if
the high bit of the value point number
is set its negative if it's 0 it's not
then you have the exponent and the
exponent works exactly the same way it
gets larger as it get as the number gets
larger and then you have the mantissa
which is just an integer basically in
the exact same way it just gets larger
as it gets larger so I think that I mean
I'm assuming if they were smart when
they did I Triple E which they were if I
remember correctly they were very good
they wouldn't have wanted to make 2
comparison circuits they would have
wanted to be able to feed the I Triple E
floating point value directly into their
normal comparison circuit and have that
do the comparison right
they wouldn't have wanted to have made a
completely separate comparison circuit
just for a trick just for a
floating-point number when when you
wouldn't normally need to anyone out
there in I Triple E expert who wants to
confirm that that sounds right to me
we probably don't have any I Triple E
jockeys on the stream right now but
that sounds right to me because it seems
like they laid it out exactly such that
you could have done that but I'm just
not sure about the exponent part because
when the number is negative of course
our numbers are never going to be
negative so in our case even if they
didn't do that part I know I'm right for
us because in our case we're never
negative so we don't actually care what
they do with the exponent or if there's
something special I can confirm that I
am NOT a nitro player
fair enough in this case we could I'm
pretty positive we could because so we
don't actually need this convert EP IPS
at all I don't think so
you know we don't really need to do this
but the reason that I'm going to is
because since I have to pack down 216
that part might break if you truncate
the end of the mantissa I'm assuming
that after the multiply truncating the
end of the mantissa would do what you
would do anyway if you were doing the
conversion so I want to say I want to
say that that that basically like
there's two things you could do here so
there's like a when we do them in pause
EPU 16 there's like the horizontal
compare right so this is our H comp
vector and so there's two ways we could
do this one is we can actually convert
this to an integer right and then we can
say build this by doing a pack
and these are unsigned we know that
they're not negative because you can't
have t raise and be negative so if we
pack tear a int like so where we just
pack on sign 16s as a down convert I
think that's the correct that's what
they normally call this instruction
right fact convert taxes and reduce a
bit know so it's pack it's the it's
actually the pack 30 to 1 but where is
that one
okay I want ones that just have PAC in
the title please I don't actually want
you to search the description but thank
you
so here's PAC s I guess you can't pack
unsigned again I don't care because this
number is the same no matter how you
interpret it so it's PAC s epi32 and
that'll pack these two down to 16s and
then we can run the age comp on this
right so this is one way to do it and if
we were to look at it step by step we
would and we need to do the multiply
either way so I could do this and say
alright there's an m1 28 which is like
tier a scaled and this happens right so
if we do tier a scaled and scale to the
16-bit range and then I do a tea the
tier a scaled convert if I do the
conversion here you know and I guess I
shouldn't say I don't know maybe this
doesn't happen in both cases in fact
maybe it doesn't so this would be the
steps you scale it you convert the scale
up to 32 bits you pack the 32 bit value
down to 16 and then you compare the 16s
right the other way to do it is to just
say screw it I do not fundamentally care
about that at all and you then literally
just do a cast think so you need to do a
cast and you need to do a cast in an and
to knock out the 16-bit values you don't
care about right so you do trying to
think if there's any other way like I
want it to
I wanted to do just an extract
so let me just take a look and see what
a nun pack would do here because a nun
pack might be what we want right so in
here if we have like unpacks unpack hi
unpack low so if I just take the upper
part of these unpack and interleave so
she finished in the high half so yeah
it's not quite what I want because I
would want something that that actually
just zeroed out so there may be no way
to finesse this like that like that may
just be fine it's only three
instructions because I can't think of it
because although you could do like you
could literally just compare the bits
without you can let min pause compare
the bits I don't know how to put it into
a structure that gets rid of the cruft
at the bottom so I need to compare just
the high sixteen bits of each 32 so like
packing the high 30 bits the high bits
there I guess is a shuffle what a
shuffle do that for me oh those are
interested in the low 64 bits of a yeah
and that's not what I want
so I don't actually see so we could do a
pea chef be right a pea chef B would do
it and so you know you could do this you
could do like a
you could do this where you say take
tier a shuffle it according to my
specifications and then we have the bits
arranged that we actually want to
compare right so it would be like that
you know I'm saying so I think that
would be it
what's the problem Oh P yeah 28 I wait
what are you saying here cannot give our
argument one for mentoring - no you
define okay so is this actually the
other way around I never remember which
way they write these yeah okay so yeah
so this probably is wrong to them this
is probably the wrong way around right
this is probably convert PS epi32 yeah
so here's the two ways we could do it
one is one instruction it's this
instruction one is three instructions so
this is just better all the way around I
think it's just one instruction to do
everything I think and this is a load up
so this would not actually be an
instruction it would just use the
address it via it be a pea chef be from
memory I think
I don't know if my analysis is 100%
correct there but I'm pretty sure that
if you just compare the top 16 bits of
to floating-point numbers that's the
same as first scaling them to the best
possible range for the comparison which
is what we were going to do and then
comparing them as doing a conversion
because the bottom bits of the
floating-point number are bits that you
only get to if all the previous bits
were the same if any of the previous
bits differ you would have already known
because either the exponent was
different in which case the number is
higher or like we already know which
one's higher or the earlier bits in the
mantissa were higher so scaling the
number there's no way they could produce
something else you know what I'm saying
you know I'm saying to you you know
anyone anyway this is where you need
some I Triple E jockeys on stream but
I'm just saying I think you can just do
this I think you can just do that and
and you're pretty much done and you're
this here the H comp shuffler is just a
predefined value that we need to do
right and so in this case it's just it's
a u8 pattern that we define for loading
stuff and in here we just pretend that
it's an m1 28 I even though it's not
right so we just say look this is an H
comp shuffler we need this to be deco
spec aligned because the compiler is
stupid and sucks and well it's not
actually that it's actually not the
class it's that Intel was stupid and
sucks because they made it fault on an
unaligned memory operand if you don't
put a V prefix in front of the
instruction for no reason I don't know
why they did that this very bad idea
maybe there was a good ship reason but I
seriously doubt it anyway so in in here
we're gonna base to say look we've got a
H comp shuffler and what we need to do
is we need to put the things into 16-bit
values as necessary so what we want to
do is we want these to go
in the correct order so like zero this
is that's a null shuffle right so this
is a thing that would take a register
one SSE register
16 wide bytes right and it would shuffle
it to be itself because it puts the zero
byte at zero the one byte at one the 2
by 2 to the 3 by 2 3 the 4 by 2 4 right
so what I want to do is I want to take
the high 16 bits of each 32-bit value
and I want to put them into 0 1 2 3 and
then everything else I want to be 0
right so if we just look at you know
what that would look like if we actually
try to do it you're manually moving
these things around what that's going to
look like is first of all all right so
the high of a 32-bit is 2 3 right so I
want to put the 2 3 first right so I
want to put the 2 in the 3 here then the
4 and the 5 again are not what I want I
want the 6 and the 7 the 8 and the 9 or
not what I want
I wanted the 10 and the 11 and then the
12 and 13 or not what I want I want the
14 - 15 right so that would take the
high bits of the first d-word the high
bits of the second d-word the high bits
of the third d-word in the high bits of
the fourth D word impact them 0 1 2 3 in
terms of 16-bit values up here we end up
with stuff that we do not want to
compare against this we don't want any
of this to ever be the highest value
right so what I want to do there is I
want to say ok we do have a special out
condition which is that you can see here
if any of the bits like if I you can see
here when we do the the shuffle assuming
that the index itself is from is from
zero to sixteen then it will actually do
a move of that element but if instead
you set the high bit right so the
seventh bit of the value if that's set
then you pack a zero so what we can do
is just like say alright there's gonna
be just like clearing that happens so
that we will in one instruction
literally one instruction we will both
move all the comparison data to the
right location we will zero out
everything that's above us and then we
will be prepared to do our min pause so
one instruction does everything right
and that's better than three
instructions it's not always better than
three instructions you'd have to see
what those instructions take but I
happen to know that those instructions
don't execute in less than one cycle
altogether so right um so anyway if we
look at what happens here I think that's
the complete version of the compare and
the only question I have here is this
the right number of things it is this is
actually a looks like a full-on
reinterpret cast for some reason and the
rest I think we're good so now we do it
min pause then we extract and that gives
us the index we actually need why is
this complaining in 216 okay fine you're
saying this is an INT that you're giving
me back that's fine and then we have the
shuffle table here so now we just need
our actual shuffle table and then we can
have the correct shuffler so the shuffle
table is just going to be this thing
again and when this comes out the thing
that I don't want to have happen is what
if all of the raise all hit something at
zero
I shouldn't say all of the Rays what if
all of the leaves all somehow hit
something at zero so everything is zero
I don't know what this will pick right
oh and you know what that's not quite
right making those all zero means
they'll always get picked so I actually
need some way of making these be greater
which is tough so it can't do it all in
one instruction because we need to fill
those values with well we can still do
it in one instruction yeah we can we can
well we can sort of do in less pressure
depends on how we want to build or two
so we can still do into one instruction
by saying look we're just going to
repeat so zero one two three we will
simply PAB the end of this thing with
zeros I mean with a element zero so that
way we know if we just Pat it out right
so we have let's say 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 so
if we just Pat it out with 2 3 2 3 2 3 2
3 then if 0 is the minimum value we'll
get back 0 because it's never gonna
compare against itself assuming this
returns the lowest value we know if they
do anything else if it doesn't we have
to add our some things to our table in
case it picks the later values now I
don't know what it's defined to do so
let's take a look what's going on
how are you not finding that I thought
that was sse3 all right it's just to see
4.1 now thought it was ssse3 I guess
it's not so yeah this is so again it's a
little bit more expensive because we
don't actually know what our steam
hardware survey would be or outside the
same hardware server we don't really
know whether this is good or not right
why am I not know Wow alright um so
again we don't really know and that's
why I say like we may want to do an
alternate path for this we'll see but we
may just want to say look by the time
handmade hero ships because you know at
one weekend it's worth of like at four
hours a week yeah I mean come on SSC 4
will be I don't know we could say that
I'm not sure um anyway point being if we
take a look at what this does I don't
actually know which one it picks so if
multiple of these are the same I'm not
sure which one it picks if you look at
the way that they literally wrote this
then that would mean that it would pick
an earlier value meaning it's saying
less than not less than or equal to so
if if you pick a min value at 0 and then
a later one is less is equal to that one
it won't overwrite it because it's not
going to be less than it's just going to
be equal to so we would assume that that
would be fine and the shuffle index can
look like this cannot ever be greater
than 4 it has to be one of those first
four because it just repeats itself from
then on right so that's what the docs
say but we may have to test to make sure
that that's like actually true because
who knows right so assuming we actually
have this right though our shuffle table
then produces what
ever it is that we actually want here
and if we do a set one epi32 on it it
means that we then have another one of
these here right which is our shuffle
table and the shuffle table just needs
to have the correct values to pick out
those bytes so if we imagine that what
we're doing here is is picking out the
right bytes that go hmm
depending on which one of these we want
we kind of know that hey it's just
replicated each bite is just replicated
you know what I mean so I need a few
more of these here right so if zero was
the lowest value then we would know that
we would pick the if zero was the lowest
value then we would just pick all zeros
so we don't really have to do anything
for our shuffle table there because it's
just going to just replicate all zeros
right oh wait no I take that back
that's not true it needs to replicate 0
1 2 3 so as to be 0 1 2 3 0 1 2 3 0 1 2
3 right so it would have to be across
the byte here it would have to be like 0
so it would be 0 1 2 3 like that right
because it's gonna load this up it's
gonna replicate it for wide and then
it's going to use it so if that's gonna
pull the load D word out of everything
now if I wanted to pull the next D word
out then it's 4 5 6 7 if I want to pull
the next D word out it's 8 9 10 11 and
if I want to pull the final D word out
it's 12 13 14 15 right
so I think literally all we're doing
here is just loading you yeah we're mean
it's it is what it it's just whatever
right and we don't have to use a
broadcast we could use a direct load
here but I'm not sure that we need to do
that like we'll see what it generates
all right so compiling this code yeah
this needs to pass some stuff to it and
at the moment we don't really know what
that stuff is going to be so we're gonna
stub that out temporarily in fact we'll
just do this and then we'll worry about
it later so what I wanted to do here is
it probably compiled this out so I
probably can't actually look at it this
way but I wanted to see what instruction
it generates or tries to generate from
that API set oh and you know what I
could have done there actually I had
that god bolts going I could totally use
the god bolt for that so what did you
generate mr. man so let's suppose I
wanted to know what this value was and
like guy returned it or something oops
what's what's the deal
look what do you do so for the set one
epi32 it looks like there is no
instruction for that right you turn this
off because this is more what I'm
interested in just basic SSE so assuming
that I do a set one epi32 it looks like
what it's gonna do here is to mob D's in
a PN pack and that's not what we want at
all maybe it does something smarter in a
303 forget oh three
let's do o2 so what it actually did
there is it actually went ahead and
generated the correct table that we
would have used and it did a DQ a mauve
so that pretty much tells me what I need
to know which is that don't do what I
did right so what I actually want to do
here is I actually just want to do the
table like the full table so instead of
doing that set one where did that go
so instead of this we actually do want
the shuffle table to be like you know
four of sixteen it's like a Borg index
and we just want to do like we just want
to build this table so that we've
manually replicated it and I know wives
did that and that way we can just do
this in one load it looks like that's
the preferable way to do it and so I
guess that's how we're going to do it
because if that's what the compiler
wanted to do anyway and looking at that
there's no instruction for it so it
seems fine actually want a little more
spacing between those just so I could
see them a little loops for that very
reason okay
I could also line these up a little
better just you can see what the table
looks like
so what I want to do here is just again
have this be pre-loaded so that that way
there's no set API and that way getting
the shuffler is just a case of like
loading up whatever one of these you're
actually looking for and I don't know
how to tell this thing to align the base
of the table but I'm hoping that we'll
do it again see kind of just always just
well C++ it just kind of sucks so I want
the shuffle table here to just produce
one of those values for me and I
basically just want it to turn it into
something that I can use there and that
should do it so I think that's
everything for getting the min test done
and so like I said it's really nice and
simple it's one operation to get the H
comp value one operation to comp it one
operation to extract it and then one
operation to load it and so that's a
pretty efficient conversion from four
values to one there's probably an even
better way if I thought about it longer
but that's not terrible like I'm not
gonna lose sleep over that especially
since this only happens after you've
done all these leaf tests which should
in theory be way more expensive so
hopefully this will be so efficient as
to not be something we actually care
about because that already should be
more than enough to keep it under the
radar if this turns out to be a good
routine so off we go
and now in here where we've got the
actual processing that has to knock on
from that so I think that basically we
just do the same stuff we were doing
so the only difference is first we just
like make sure that the zero layer so
when we come through here right what
we're doing is we're saying alright put
into the zero level like so in lane zero
of our floats we want to put the value
that actually was the hit so the whole
point of this shuffler was just to get
us something that moves everything to
the zero lane so that we actually can
use that right and it doesn't actually
matter when we do that we can either do
it to the input or we can do it to the
output and the question of course is
when is the most efficient way to
actually do that right and I have no
idea actually yes I do also that's
that's a uhm I think we can do this even
better so actually if we just let it
compute all four so so riddle me this
Batman once we get here we know who
we're gonna extract right if we know who
we're going to extract we only have to
shuffle the actual people who we care
about extracting and the people that we
care about extracting are the emission
the ref color and the tier a right and
the hit normal so we could
we could in theory defer this down to
something else let's take a look
so in here if we have hitbox men and
hitbox max if we look for where those
are used you can see that they're only
used here to compute the radius in the
center so actually like we just don't
need to do any of this probably right
like you could probably just do that so
you do this computation exactly the way
that you were doing it before or
whatever right this doesn't need to be
cleared so we come through here I don't
even know if we're gonna need to do this
this may not actually happen I mean we
need this shuffle table eventually but I
don't know
so we have the shuffler if we need it
but let's just see if we actually need
it so all of this can just happen and
then the question is well we've got
scaled D and we want to pick which one
of those like we want a particular one
of those which is based on whatever the
shuffle index is and we could shuffle
scale D at that point mm-hmm but let's
just identify identify the places that
we need it so Rea origin plus R ad in v3
we only need the T ray to have been
shuffled at that point right and
furthermore we actually only really need
it to be extracted so we could do a
shuffle extract cuz I don't think you
can do there's no way for me to do an
extract on a on a on an actual like non
immediate right I thought we verified
that and I'm pretty sure that's true
right so there's no way to get when we
get an actual value out of here there's
no way to say here's the value I wanted
and it's in a register right that
doesn't happen so you would have to
distort it and pull it out
yourself somehow right and I don't know
which is faster whether it's to store it
and read it or whether it's to pull it
out using the using the shuffler you
know I'm saying but we'll use the
shuffler for now just to see so if we
want to pull out the tear a so this is
the tear a scaler if I want to pull out
the tear a scaler that's just gonna be
an mm extract epi you know PS we're just
going to use an MMS truck PS and we're
gonna extract the zero value and the mm
shuffle epi8 of tear a and the shuffler
right so this would get us whatever the
scaler is that's the tear a you know and
I'm saying so basically like this would
get us the scalar value of tear a so
tear a scaler oops not equal to F 32 max
in this case what you can see here is
the transfer PPS when you didn't hit all
of this stuff doesn't have to happen if
you can't use it right so really this
whole nonsense here can also move inside
because if you didn't hit something you
don't need to do that so since we
already know we have to do and if or we
think we do anyway to fill in a base
color here that means we could save a
ton of work in the cases where the Rays
don't hit and that's not something we
could have done before because we were
dealing with more than one ray that's
kind of compelling as well right it's a
bonus of this routine so you can see
that that's what we would do here
unfortunately just stacks up behind the
branch which is not the best possible
thing but you know oh well and then in
here we're gonna do a bunch of stuff
these can all just happen the way that
they were happening and so then the only
question is how does this stuff happen
if we look here we've already extracted
tier a scalar so this can happen just
fine right the probe sample N and
honestly this stuff we don't even really
need the extract because this stuff yeah
it's a long story we can talk about all
this when we actually look at the
routine we're getting ahead of ourselves
there's a micro optimization that could
be happening in here for sure right
okay so for sample ref color we now have
a problem which is that the sample ref
colors came from a pack a packed set
right but but if we actually look at how
these are loaded there's no reason they
had to be loaded that way right so what
we could have done is done RGB emission
RGB emission and actually loaded them
out without the Select I think right I
mean with the Select but selecting for a
different thing I'm not explaining this
well
yeah I don't know I'm gonna leave that
for now and we'll talk about that again
also later so this is fine this part is
the part that now we would have to deal
with which is how the hit normal gets
done here and so we can just say that
this is like probe sample n right and
get rid of this so we can see that a
little more curly this is something we
can just compute it's like that's just
something we know how to do right
because it's the origin is in scalar
radius scalar this is scalar everything
is in the scalar nothing is packed right
I should say single not scalar
everything's in single not packed there
so really what we're talking about is
these amiss emission if we want to get
the emission that's gonna be the same
routine here right so in getting the
emission is just gonna be doing that one
shuffle so that's pretty easy to get as
well because it's just a single value
and then all the rest of this stuff can
just do what it does right so I think
mostly what we're looking at is this
piece of code here is the piece of code
that we actually need to do like that we
actually need to make good what did I
screw up here oh great so I'm gonna go
ahead and assume there's no way to do a
shuffle epi8 that has the right stupid
casting I absolutely hate these
intrinsic s-- they're so terrible yeah
so basically like this is that we want
to call a pea chef B and we don't want
it to be yeah it's whatever I'm gonna
make a in our cindy code I'm gonna make
a routine for this because that's gonna
drive me nuts
so in here I'm gonna do one and it's
gonna be one that that can shuffle
either way right so it's like we're
gonna do one that's that's a I guess we
could use our I guess we don't have the
inversion but I'm just gonna call it
like this for now and we'll we'll figure
how we want to deal with this a little
bit later but I'm gonna call this like
pshh FB and it's gonna take an M 128 is
the shuffle and the M mm 128 that's the
value and it's gonna do the ridiculous
dance that you have to do to shuffle
it's so nuts where do you see this so
it's one assembly instruction it's just
pshh FB register register that's all you
would type in assembly and link C is
supposed to be like a higher-level
language and C++ must be like a
higher-level language right
what is higher-level about this
ridiculous crap that I'm about to have
to type right so in this case this is
the wrong way around like I just want
this but I had to type all of that right
that's not tear a that's value and
pattern okay mm-hmm so the higher-level
language of C++ that's doing such
helpful type checking here for me and
saving me all of these wonderful errors
I have no idea what they could possibly
be because all the errors you get when
you do this sort of thing are about Lane
swizzle patterns and things that you
don't understand it's never because you
accidentally treated a floating-point
value as a 32-bit value when you're
programming in sse that's absurd right
but here is the like time savings that I
got from C++ instead of typing this this
is what I would have typed in assembly
language this is what you had to
remember to type in C and C++ right it's
absolutely insane like they constantly
say that these things are high-level in
languages but they're not they actually
make work for you if you're actually
trying cuz like what they're supposed to
do what a high-level language is
supposed to do
is provide a more convenient way for you
to generate the assembly language you
were trying to generate right like it
shouldn't be easier to type the assembly
language than it is to type the
higher-level language because at the
very least the higher-level language
should have just let me type the
assembly language if that was the case
and of course I can't because MS PC
doesn't even support inline assembler so
I can't even do that if I'd wanted to
but the point is it should have been as
simple as just typing pfb parentheses
the two inputs right like that should
have been the hilar this was a save me
time it doesn't save your time these
higher-level languages they just they're
so bad that they just waste your time
instead of saving you time it's so nuts
it's it's just so stupid anyway so let
me actually get this working here so I
can actually type P chef be the way that
I want to this is coming about something
cannot give everyone from F 32x so yeah
in this case maybe I'll just do this
here and I'll return this here same way
right so we'll do f3 2 for X results and
this will be I think I do this right
that's a value dot P okay and so we can
down to our pfb and this will come back
I don't know if we have an extract like
extract zero extract one kind of thing
we should probably add one of those to
our little tool here so we can do em
right but I guess I don't really like
that so I'm gonna do this
I'm gonna have a thing for F 32 for X to
get the F credit F 32 out that's just
like extract zero right and you do the
value here and that will just do the MM
extract PS of value dot P
so that is how will extract stuff so
we'll do like a extract zero like so I
think that's all we really need what is
the complaint here extract PS version
from int to what warning the
initialisation conversions from int to
f/32 my doing something odd oh well
that's not good
but that's separate mmm extract PS
should extract am I thinking something
Oh weird it returns an integer even
though we are extracting a float okay
I'm gonna do it this way I feel like
that's probably fine to do it this way I
don't actually know it may be that you
want to do it this way just to tell the
compiler what's actually going on but I
think I'm gonna do the store I think I'm
gonna do this so so we're gonna do it
this way like so and that way we'll just
say look store this thing here and
hopefully the compiler is smart enough
to know what that is you know I'm saying
okay so at that point let's see so we
have this is this there's actually a
scalar array Direction here so there's a
radius Kahler I'm gonna call this radius
scalar or a radius single I guess and
then we'll call this tier a single
because I realize it's kind of just just
calling its thing scalar is wrong
because they're scalar everywhere it's
not what I really mean all right so
we've got our singles there and I think
that's everything
what's the Rey origin so the Rey origin
we also need the single version of so
I'm gonna go ahead and and have that
come in that way too as Rey origin
single and I'm gonna do the same
replication process we did on it before
so I'm gonna say you know ray origin
goes b3 for x-ray origin single
so yeah so I'm not sure what we want to
do now but basically this part here
where we generate the where we generate
like the normals and stuff like that is
mostly what we need now as far as
extraction is concerned again I'm not
exactly sure how we want to do this but
do this pea chef be here so there's
definitely some open questions there let
me see so we need to diffuse Atlas here
which we forgot to pass I deleted it
because thinking that we weren't gonna
use it but we are gonna use it because
we need that for sampling so let's drop
that bad boy in here all right so we're
real close to being done with how this
routine actually walks and if we look
through this part all we really have to
think about now is how we're actually
gonna I don't know we're done scaled
diga we got rid of unskilled D
accidentally it's it's just the it's the
probe sample P subtracting from the
center but yeah so if we look at this
the other thing I'm thinking is now
maybe I'm wrong maybe origin single and
tier a single maybe I'm sorry and and
this stuff maybe we don't actually care
about that at all and actually we can
just do this whole thing without
converting down because if we look where
this will actually use its in unscaled D
that's the only place we would use it
and so we don't actually need to shuffle
any of those I don't think so if we
wanted to we could do something here
where tier a just equals
pshhh FB tear a Schaeffler right so now
we know that T ray is correct the whole
way around and then if you did this
this probe sample P is now fine for all
of this well okay but you still have to
extract it here right so you do still
have to extract it either way so I'm not
sure how I feel about it to be extract
first retracts second
it's tough call folks it is a tough call
so there's a riff-off times the hannam
our product down here
let's here's what I want to do let's
work backwards from what's being
computed lighting wise here to get a
little bit of a better feeling for how
this is actually getting used because I
want this to be as efficient as possible
now that it's actually able to choose
because it's not as enough to do for
wide it's actually able to choose when
it steps down so let's suppose we missed
right if we missed then really all we
need is the emission direction to figure
out how much moonlight would shine onto
this like we need the cosine attenuation
on the moonlight but that's it right so
and furthermore if we don't actually
need to do that work because we know
what that value would be its
the attenuation on the moonlight from
well actually wait but this is also
wrong I mean I guess it's not wrong
because we are pretending there's a moon
that's shining down and we're just like
losing some of the light as we Bend away
from it so I guess that's fine no so it
is the emission direction times the moon
light I guess as it comes this way you'd
be hitting it less so this is just a
crappy way of saying do you hit the moon
or the atmosphere right so I suppose
that's all fine and yeah this could just
be pre computed as well so like this is
just true for like this whole equation
is just a known thing that you just
always know for a given R a direction so
you could even pull this up out of like
that scaler could just you could just be
pulled directly out so it doesn't even
need to be there I'm gonna actually
change the way this works a little bit
and say look let's just do let's just do
this as like an input value kind of a
thing and maybe what we say here is
maybe we say something like that this
updates the transfer PPS value or
something so like you know maybe it
looks a little bit more like this so the
moon color and Moon derp are not in here
and this value that the transfer PPS
value that we initialized to I think
what we want to do is say that that
comes from externally right because that
makes a lot more sense and so in here
maybe what we do is we do something like
this
and we say all right so we've got a
transfer PPS of four and actually these
are just going to be things that are
like return values of the thing right
I'm sorry our output parameters of the
thing and we will initialize them to
what we want in the case of of you
didn't hit something we're gonna say
what you should get if you didn't hit
something which might be nothing or it
might be the moon right and then I'm
going to say okay moon contribs goes in
here for now or something like that
right and then we overwrite it the grid
raycast does if it wants to so basically
it's more like a conditional move that
just like overrides things that's
necessary so it's like here's the you
know transfer PPS the value that's gonna
right so when it comes through here it's
gonna say look I'm a write that value
and that's where we actually do anything
otherwise we just don't touch it right
and we're not gonna we're not going to
return anything at all okay so that
seems sane so that means like this is
what we're looking at here so what we
have to figure out is what are we
actually doing in terms of omission and
all this sort of stuff right so when we
compute the voxel irradiance at a
particular location and that's like
where we actually hit the question is do
we actually want to do this is very
expensive
oops and since we only have to do it for
one like we're only doing one ray at a
time across multiple stuff here
presumably what we would want to do is
actually just test to see whether this
thing is emissive or not and if it's
emissive because it its emissive it
presumably doesn't also reflect light
but maybe the answer is it does maybe
it's reflective Animus is like we want
to have both so I don't know but let's
say that was the case so let's say
emission is in here and you can see like
as the emission gets higher the
probe gets lower which doesn't make any
sense because emission should just be
added right like I don't know that we
actually want that either
I guess the problem that we have is the
way that we do the system if lights
reflected light back from the things
when they hit the problem is we're gonna
have that the lights will feed back on
themselves right because you it doesn't
know that the lighting from the probe
directly under the light source was
actually just getting all of its light
from the light source so I guess what we
need to do here is actually we probably
just want these things to either be
emissive or not like I don't I don't
feel like the way we're doing our
lighting would allow us to do a surface
that was partially emissive and
partially reflect reflective I could
just be not thinking about it correctly
but that seems to be true
so I guess what you could do though is
instead of adding the emissions together
you could just min the emissions or max
the emissions rather
so I guess that's what you would do you
would allow lights to reflect light but
you would also at the same time you
would make sure that in addition to the
emission value and the reflected value
rather than adding them together you
just take whichever one is maximum of
each Channel and that would allow you to
put light into the system and also
reflect light at the same time without
feeding back on yourself because at most
you'll always ever contribute up to your
maximum that seems right so I think what
we would want here is if this thing is
saying look here's the emission level of
this thing then what you want to do is
say what's the actual emission that you
would then what's the actual emission
that you're actually building right so
you're building emission times your
sample ref color right and then that's
the channel that you have right so you
have your emission color is your
emission times your ref color right and
then your sample right is this is your
reflect color so you're reflecting this
and you're emitting this and then you
just want those two things to be like
min you know you want to take the
maximum of each one of those right
yeah
so I think that's good and this here
where we have the clamp that ref
fall-off is still there so this value is
just you know it's really just reflect
color x equals reflect fall-off right so
you you build up your emission color
this way your reflection color this way
you figure out the fall-off is and you
modulate by the fall-off now you take
the actual transfer PPS and this
so there we go okay so the emission is
off the ref color the reflect fall off
comes on here too we probably could do
something where this actually gets
handled a little bit cleaner but let's
suppose it looks like that for now and
then the transfer PPS is just going to
be like an r g b max right so this is
going to be like something like this so
i think that's what we want right I
think that's what we want
that all seems good to me so that'll
write to the transfer PPS RG and B and
it'll write out whatever the maximum is
we want to make sure this is actually
going to use a max PS instruction and
not if so we're gonna have to do like
you know as we you know as we go through
here roll as we clean up the assembly
that the compiler generates we're gonna
have to make sure we like to give it the
right
foof to do that but everything else
seems fine the ref color extraction now
so this part here is a part we actually
care about if we look at sample ref
color up sorry get component rather
that's not particularly compelling so we
probably don't want to do it that way we
probably want to do it the way we were
doing it before so we'd basically do
like this and this is probably not the
best way to do it we'll have to think
about that but I think for now that's
what we've got to work with right
okay so these are all still not done yet
we get down here the ref this is the
wrong thing it's just called ref color
or I get I guess this is the hit hit
this is the hit color the surface color
I don't know what we call that really
and so then we just really need to focus
on how we're gonna get like the normal
out of this thing which is again pretty
tough I don't know what max is talking
about here so those are VIII's so maybe
maximum is what we need there but we
really just want so if you look at max
here I guess that's actually the routine
we want right
the v3 for X I mean f3 32 for X there's
a max on that right somewhere in here I
assume yeah so this is the routine we
actually want we want to do the max PSS
on these things but I guess we can't do
that right now because you don't really
have a way of actually telling it look
please do that for us again we could
just keep all of these this an f32 X the
entire way through and then you just
don't do the extract
I suppose that's fine let's just try
that so if we did hit color here so we
did v3 for X then what we would do is we
would just say okay just store the P
chef of this thing
right and we could also make a pea chef
be that DP chefs this whole thing but
that's fine the way we're doing it here
so we'd pea chef B to make sure the RGB
now in zero is the one we actually want
although as I'm saying that now I think
about it you don't even have to do that
why did I do that I don't know why I did
that we literally don't care about that
that's just dumb
so hit ref color is actually just all
you need to do so you just do okay the
emission color is the hit ref color
times the emission the reflection color
comes back here
and you would just load up that up out
into four X is the emission you'd leave
right so that's just hit emission
actually and then when you come through
here and you want to build the emission
color it's just the hit emission times
the hit ref color right so you don't
actually have to extract you come down
here and we need to do the reflect part
but then when you get to here you just
say look when we're going to return the
transfer PBS the transfer of PBS is just
one color value what we want to do is
take the maximum value and then extract
just the bottom so this would just be
like you know emission color reflect
color
so there's the transfer color and then
we would just do the pea chef beyond
transfer color right so you you wouldn't
bother ever extract anything because you
don't get anything from that so you just
do it at the latest possible time that
you that you could that seems to be the
same thing so this would be an extract
zero all the way down on the pea chef be
of transfer color right so that way I
think this just does everything you
needed to do and the only problem you
have is that reflect color at that point
is not wide so if you made it wide and
we then say okay the reflect color
although it looks like so you're gonna
have to do this in single because probe
sample and already had to be extracted
so you don't really care about that so
once you get reflect fall-off reflect
color how to mark you might as well just
wait and do it here right so you might
as well just do like this
and I think that's what we need okay so
what else this is just with shuffler and
then I think we're back to what I said
before so hit color in this case okay so
the Hadamard product here has to be done
after right because the hit color is
never extracted so we would want that to
be had a Martin in there now the hit ref
color so we could we could actually do
that at the end though so we don't
because the hit ref color gets
multiplied in either case whether it's
emission or otherwise
I think you could just save that
Hadamard product to the end
right so if you take hit Rhett color and
look at where you know the two places
would be used is here in here you know I
mean if you did that at the end so you
actually said that you don't do this you
do it here then what you'd be doing is
you'd actually be just taking the
emission so you could just so if I'm
right about this so you could do all of
this I think and just do the Hat of our
product at the end so it'd just be the
multiplies like you could just do it by
only actually extracting just the
emission
I think that's right I'm not entirely
sure let's take a look
so in emission color here we do hit
emission times hit ref color so what I
would need to do is say look the
emission value is actually just going to
be a value that we do a max width to to
max against the reflect color right and
it feels like you could just do this
like if we loaded this in a packed value
we could do this directly right so let's
suppose that you imagined that the
reflect color was actually came back as
like
suppose we did something where the
reflect color we actually packed up so
we did at f/32 Forex of this thing and
we packed up foo
so we imagined we grabbed that as a
reflect color right then we imagine we
take the emission color or reflect level
and emission level we generate this just
from the extract zero of the emission so
we extract zero the emission and we
replicate it now actually we don't
extract it we just pfb it right because
if we P Chef be the hit emission with
shuffler it's now got emission in all
four so this is the RGB bla the RGB
blank and this is the emission emission
emission we can then do one max on those
right yeah yep yep yep so let's say we
need to reflect fall-off here and we do
reflect color foo x equals reflect fall
off like so then we do the load up then
we do the max here
and then we just know how much we're
transmitting with our hit ref color so
then we say our a that's the
transmission level for RGB now we just
extract zero one two and go although I
don't know if we should try to do
something different there with a hit ref
color maybe we just do that it's in the
wrong lanes is the problem there right
so yeah you can't really you can do the
max efficiently but you can't really do
you can't cheat and do what I'm doing
here you'd have to do like a replicate
out right so that that does not actually
help you so we don't care about that we
don't care about this we don't care
about that this is our actual
transmission level here and so then you
just do like extract zero of this one -
I think that's it
all right so you have one extraction
that you have to do for each color
channel the RG and the B and then you
have to figure out how to get the normal
and the position out and so I think that
means this does look like this right
probably although I don't know because
this also has to happen that way so I'm
not sure it may be that you extract that
out I don't know so that's that's kind
of an open question those are kind of an
open question but I think this stuff is
now correct so if I go to extract zero
and I just make a couple of these
I'm not sure how to actually ask this
thing to store later values because like
I said it for whatever reason doesn't
seem to want to store anything other
than oh wait this is not this is not
what we want so store one's actually a
replicating store which is not at all
what I want
I just want to convert I just want to
take a float out of this thing
here it is this is what I actually want
I won't convert s sf32 that's what I
actually want now like I said I'm not
sure about this one because I don't know
how to get anything else out of this
thing and it may be that there is no
real efficient way to actually do that
we could look but I doubt it right
because that's like looks like the only
one that you get right so I could
extract an int so because there was the
extract with an immediate that was out
here so we could extract an integer from
it and convert that back to a float
because you can see that it's it's it's
not doing conversion so it's actually
just giving you the float back it just
doesn't return an f32 for some reason
and i have no idea what the reason is
until you want to tell me what the
reason is do you have an explanation for
that I don't know what their explanation
is for that but so this so doing a
convert SS convert as 32 to pull
something out of there I'm not sure
exactly how we would do that for the
other values
fish as efficiently as possible it might
be that what you want to do is the
extract if we did that it would look
like this and then we would do this so
we're just like forcing it to do what we
want I don't actually know if that'll
work but but we'll see so I would say
the reasonable progress this is a pretty
tricky thing to get right because we've
got sort of scalar and non-scalar mixed
together it's always that point like it
when you up shift to packed and then
down shift to scaler it's those are
always the hardest parts of your
routines so I think all we really need
to do now is to finish that part off I
can if zero this out for now and do a QA
and next weekend we'll focus on
finishing that part testing and then
we'll move on oh and this can this is no
longer relevant because I actually did
make sure the max happens there again
it's starting to look very clean now and
I I don't know like but except for this
which is very expensive obviously I feel
like we're able to trim a lot of the fat
out of here and the downshift is still a
little janky but at least it's like it's
not as wearable as it could be these
don't need to be here
and this is just kind of placeholder for
now but it's these um yeah nope okay so
in terms of what we need to pass the
rate grid grid cast I think that's the
end to just tie this off it's work its
diffuse Atlas rare urge and single what
is the REA origin code here is that a
thing that we know it's not so we would
have to do it get component on that as
well boy I hope this works out if this
actually turns out to be a good way to
raycast it's gonna be so nice because so
much code will go away we can just
delete like the most of all this stuff
that we've been using to try and figure
out what would be the efficient way to
do it and when we actually hit upon one
it's gonna feel pretty nice to clean
everything up this doesn't return a
value anymore all right let's do brief
Q&amp;A
John said you had opinions on signed and
unsigned he said you said maybe it's the
wrong complication to have yeah I mean I
mmm
my problem with almost all high level
languages is that rather than making
decisions that always save you time they
tend to make decisions that only save
you time if you happen to program
exactly this one way and any other way
you might try to program it just falls
apart which you know is the nature of
compressing things down for sure but it
seems like it's unnecessary in a lot of
cases so the example in this case would
be that signed and unsigned arithmetic
is exactly the same in most places if
you add two numbers together your CPU
just adds them together it doesn't care
whether they're signed or unsigned so
calling things signed or unsigned it's
not a type what it is is a default so I
would prefer if what you said was hmm
32-bit integer and I'm not going to tell
you whether it's signed or unsigned that
all that would do is generate code where
any time you did something that actually
did need to know it said please specify
which operation you want right so if you
then did something like a shift you
could say do you want an arithmetic or a
logical shift normally what happens is
it uses the signed type to tell it which
one to do I don't want that most of the
time I want to tell you which shift to
do because just cuz the value is signed
or unsigned that doesn't not that's like
suggesting that that there's not values
that take on both characteristics and
that's wrong when you're actually
programming their dere fungible I might
do something in a way that it appears
like the values signed for three
instructions and then change to unsigned
sorry certain things later so it's just
signed it on sign is not right it's not
a property of a piece of data signed and
unsigned is a property of an operation
and so I think the abstraction that's
made in all high-level languages is
wrong i I don't think they did it
properly
are you familiar with home assistant no
I am NOT are there alternatives to
inline assembly other than intrinsics
just external assembly right you write
these you write you a function like we
could write this grid raycast function
in assembly language and then link it in
and that is what you do if you fail like
what you normally do is you try to get
the compiler to do something not stupid
with your code when you're optimizing a
routine and if you fail like if you just
can't get the compiler to emit what you
want then you just write it an assembly
and link it in that's what you do most
of the time you can like you know sort
of fuss with the phrasing and get the
compiler to eventually do it but if you
can't then you do it assembly episode 3
introduced you mentioned that OpenGL is
much closer to a good graph see if you
had that something like Vulcan I was
wondering if other developers you know
agree with you on this and if so then
why would something like Vulcan get
support who exactly makes the design
adoption decisions for these
technologies do developer 70 say so
first of all I guess what I would say is
Vulcan doesn't have much support like
it's just not very popular right so I
wouldn't say people are supporting
Vulcan but in terms of people who do
support Vulcan the reason is because
what else are they gonna use right
opengl 4.5 isn't well supported at all
right so it's more about a decision of
what the ihds choose to give us and they
chose to give us Vulcan it's a pile of
crap and it's unfortunate but that's
what you get so when you program on
Windows you get two choices dx12 or
Vulcan personally I had picked dx12 if
you want to pick Vulcan go right ahead
right who gets the designer adoption is
mostly the IH fees it's mostly what the
yhv is choose right
so basically like IH V's have - IH V's
are basically who determines everything
more or less and platform holders can
force their hands sometimes so Apple for
example can just demand that metal is
the thing now and then the IH fees have
to live with it but short of that IH v
is determine what we get and they have a
fantastically poor track record at
producing api's that are a good stable
and long-term there is very bad at that
so
why is this loop for the CPU to do
horizontal assembly operations so the
reason is because of the way that
arithmetic logic units are designed for
high speeds and I guess what I would say
is it's not slow slow is the wrong term
to use it's latent horizontal operations
aren't slow
they're just latent meaning you don't
get the results back for a while they
might be very fast meaning you can do
lots of them because you can start many
of them so it's usually very good idea
to be specific so slow you know what
does this mean well there's two things
you could mean by slow slow could mean
takes a long time to take input and
produce corresponding output
and I prefer not to use that term
because it could also mean does few opps
per second like per unit time right and
slow could be either of these and the
reason that I don't like using the term
slow or if I do use the term slow I
usually mean this slow is because this
slow I can usually program around so I
prefer to say high latency in this case
potentially because it's not necessarily
slow because you may be able if you have
many independent ones to do you might be
able to run them at exactly the same
speed as something else right and so I
would say that that's what horizontal
ops are so horizontal equals high
latency it does not mean slow in a can't
do many of these per second you can they
just take awhile to get the results out
for any individual um but you can
overlap many of them right so why are
they high latency well they're high
latency because this is the way in an
arithmetic logic unit normally works an
arithmetic logic unit normally looks
like this the input comes in in four
wide lanes right the circuit for doing
the operation takes a clock right so it
comes in here and I've got wiring for
each of these operations and the clock
does an operation on eat you know in one
cycle I'm gonna do an operation on each
of the lanes and those lanes are gonna
feed forward into the next operation
right so if I have something like a
comparison that I need to do right then
what's going to happen is when this
input comes in
the first thing that's going to happen
is the inputs gonna have to merge
crosswise so the OP that I actually have
is going to have to take input from two
sources right and so income my lanes the
first thing is going to be like a
feed-forward thing that produces you
know an OP like this or something
so like I do something and I forward
that result to some other lane right and
then I do something and I forward that
result to some other lane again right
and so what ends up happening is if the
if you're thinking about it coming in in
this fashion then if you want something
that can be answered across all four
lanes you have to pay the price of the
furthest cascade so if I need a result
from three to propagate all the way to
result from one which is what I need if
I'm gonna compare all four lanes
well how many hops does it take right
here's one cycle here's one cycle here's
one cycle here's one cycle it is one two
three and then the fourth operation
gives me my answer right I mean I should
write this a little bit differently it
should be like the cycle is here right
the cycle is what moves the thing to the
next phase right so and you could also
count it as like the input step as a
cycle I mean I don't I'm not a hardware
designer so I don't know what the right
way to write this diagram is but point
being something comes in on three it has
to move to two something's on two it has
to move to one sometimes on one ask to
move to zero and then it moves to the
output that's you know for Cascades and
so when you look up horizontal
operations usually the cycle counts
match that cascade pattern really well
so like for example if I come up on here
and I say well what's the actual answer
gonna be for doing something like the
menu PS mm-hmm sorry I'm in Posie PU 16
it's like hey it's latency for exactly
what you would expect right what happens
if I do the horizontal ad for dot
products with the H ad right so if you
do the horizontal ad you can see that
what these do is they do
horizontal ads if they only do one step
of the ad and you can see the latency is
basically like a little less because it
doesn't actually have to do all four
it's not a propagation it just has to
propagate once and then ad once and then
out right so again you get down to
latency three because it doesn't
actually do the whole ad if you do two
of them to ad the whole way
yeah and you can see like basically all
of these kind of line up that way so
again take that diagram with a grain of
salt I'm not a chip engineer so like
that's probably not a very good
explanation of what actually happens but
it's sort of it's vaguely right so the
point of Cindy is that you have this
circuitry that doesn't have crosstalk
and that's why it's fast it knows it can
just do multiplies in lanes and they're
all just stamped copies of scalar
multipliers as soon as you start
crosstalking with the lanes that whole
structure breaks down and you need to
have like a bucket brigade that like
moves crap around the chip to get it all
the way over and that's what costs does
that make sense
hmm
wouldn't use Vulcan for cross-platform
no it's terrible for cross-platform like
why would you use Vulcan for
cross-platform you know that it's not an
API you can actually use to write to
graphics cards on Mac and what else do
you have for your platforms you don't
have Vulcan on like you know the Xbox
it's it's not a thing right I mean maybe
they do support Vulcan for X the new
Xbox I don't know scarlet or something I
have no idea but it's not cross-platform
like like Apple requires that metal is
the driver layer so if you're running
Vulcan on that it's going through a
translation that's the opposite of what
you were trying to do when you wrote to
Vulcan right fokin supposed to be a bare
metal API anything and on Windows it's
like well r8 so if I'm gonna be writing
metal on Mac I might as well write dx12
on Windows I ain't gonna write Vulcan
unlike the PS 5 and Xbox whatever they
call scarlet xbox 1 X s 12 or whatever
the next one is it just doesn't really
make sense
it's a Vulcan it's like an API that just
has no point in existing I don't even
understand why they bothered maybe for
Linux I don't know
alright looks like the end of the
questions alright do-do-do-do-do alright
thank you everyone for joining me for
this to the hand-made here that's my
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow on the series
at home you can always peer to the game
on hand menhir org and it comes to the
source code maybe you can go finish the
grid base lighting this week while you
wait and that'd be good practice because
I've sketched out all the routines so
the question is just getting them
working right so you could give that a
shot until then we are doing this is the
last week of our Kickstarter if you want
on now the infinite comic your very own
you can always just click on this banner
that'll take you right there and we hit
basically all of our stretch goals I
guess I don't know there's one more for
coloring book that but it looks like
it'll hit that one too so you get a
whole bunch of cool stuff with it
definitely check it out if you're into
comics or space or cats that's it for
this weekend I don't know if I'll scream
some more slipways I feel like I don't
want to put the pressure on John to like
learn to get good at slipways because
you know I watched his stream last night
playing slipways and as like looked a
lot like naysay looked like a lot like
kingdoms and castles or it was just a
really depressing Kingdom that no one
wanted to live in and so like I'm afraid
that his galactic empires probably will
be that way as well so you know maybe
it's best you just not put the pressure
on and leave it there that's fine too
but you know if if we do want to give
some demonstrations about how
intergalactic routing is best done then
maybe I'll stream some of that later I
don't know we'll see that's it for today
I'll see everyone back here next week
it's very least and I'll go check now to
see if John is streaming right now and
if so we'll rate them that's it take it
easy everybody