hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream today we are going to be
looking at debugging our situation with
the lighting which we kind of put in
some nice checks for yesterday that I'm
interested in sort of using to improve
the quality of the lighting solution
because we know we got some bugs in
there and I think we can we can get to
some pretty good results by just kind of
pushing through and fixing some of the
problems what I do want to mention
before we started yesterday I talked
about the patreon situation the
beginning of the stream so hopefully
everyone's kind of aware of what went
down there I wanted to say that I did
spend some time yesterday putting up an
alternative so we can close down the
patreon as I suggested by Monday you'll
notice now if you refresh the hand-made
here a website actually here the patreon
button has been replaced with a
contribute button that has some patreon
alternative options on it this page is
just using send owl the same thing that
you use to preorder the source code
which has worked really well from us and
we really haven't had pretty much any
complaints from people using it
unlike patreon and basically it's just a
site that I took a look at what the
common donation styles were on patreon
because send-out doesn't support
variable donation amounts you have to
you have to have fixed ones and I just
put a stack of them on here that are all
the kinds of contributions that people
were typically making on patreon
plus some aggregated yearly ones because
I noticed some people giving a dollar a
month I thought it might be less fees
for them credit card wise and stuff like
that to just give 12 or 24 dollars a
year rather than one or two dollars a
month would probably save a bunch of
money for them so I put those on there
too I tested it out a couple of people
have it seems to working pretty well I
haven't done a blast out on patreon yet
because cendol seems to be a little bit
having a little trouble sending out the
subscription management links they
they're timed links and they come a
little bit late and you have to ask for
them to be recent so we're kind of
working with them to get that process
straightened out everything else seems
that we're working well so I think by
tomorrow
be pretty much set to just get rid of
patreon and anyone who wants to make
pledges can just move their pledge
straight from patreon here and never
deal with patreon again so we should be
on track to close the page tomorrow just
as we had suggested and everything seems
to be working cleanly thanks again to
send owl for running such a great
service hopefully they'll be able to
help us iron out the the last little
details but really that's about it and
yeah and so that was easier than I
thought it was going to be in order to
encourage people to to make the switch I
know it's a pain in the butt to have to
go to patreon and like cancel your
pledge and then go over here and make a
new pledge or whatever I also decided
that now that I could on send a lit was
pretty easy to do I am gonna be
including a little digital bonus pack
with the with anyone who pledges and
basically this is just a little zip file
of goodies from me just to say thank you
for taking the time to move your pledge
over and it's something that I may
update from time to time with new little
goodies in it and those are always
accessible to anyone who still has an
active pledge so once you you know sign
up for one of these recurring
contributions no matter what level
there's no diff you know difference it's
it's not graded by tea or anything like
this
anyone who contributes there's just a
thank you zip file that gets updated
periodically as I put some things in it
and you'll always be able to kind of
download it download it
the latest one just like you can with
like the handmade hero source code so
that's up please if you have any trouble
with it or you know see anything that's
amiss here are just like I said I rushed
it together to address the patreon
situation as it rapidly deteriorated and
to make sure that these kind of projects
that I'm really grateful for people in
community for having done can still get
funding so you know I tested as best I
could but what it really needs this you
folks out there who are it should and
pledging to try it and send me feedback
tell me if it works we can send this
feedback to send out as well hopefully
they can help us streamline the process
I know this is not exactly what they
were set up to do but it seems to work
pretty well for it so hopefully we can
them to spend a little time improving
the process as well so when you when you
go through the experience if you want to
send me email or post on the handmade
hero forums or anything else or even
just send support sundale send alikom a
direct email you can do that too but
just anything that you want to do to
help make the process better would be
great because we just started this and
we don't have a lot of insight into
whether people are able to navigate it
successfully whether you've got the
options that you want here do you want
different options than these and I've
already asked send Al for the ability to
customize so hopefully someday we can
replace this with just a very simple do
you want yearly or monthly contribution
or one-time yearly or monthly and how
much so that you can just completely
customize whatever whatever you want to
donate and then we will just take that
money and give it out to the projects
that are currently trying to make
resources such as these or other ones we
find that we think are doing a great job
making things for people who like ham a
hero that people like that would be
interested in so thanks for checking
that out and hopefully for those of you
who donate on patreon this will be a
nice solution you can move to that won't
have any of the negative associations
with patreon and that'll work nice and
reliably like the source code stuff we
use on sundial that we've never really
had any problem with and send owl also
takes no cut at all so they do its only
credit card fees that you're paying and
tax and it's only the government and the
credit card companies that take money
from you when you pledge here Sindel
actually takes no cut they are just a
subscription service that I pay to use
every month so the the same thing that
I'm paying for for being able to
distribute the source code fight and
take pre-orders is already paying for
this as well so so it's even the 5% take
that patreon was taking is now also gone
so we were even able to give a little
more of your contributions out to people
doing good stuff because of this move so
again really big thanks to send a low
for being such a great service I think
that once we iron out any kinks that
might still be in here I think
this will be just better all-around than
what people were doing on the patreon
anyway so just wanted to get that out
there again I'll send a blast out to the
patreon list tomorrow after I've at
least had 24 hours with people using it
and letting me know if there's anything
critically broken or any problems that
they're having just so I can make sure
we don't have too many people using it
before we we know that it's that no
one's having trouble we have had people
pledged with it and it seems to be
working ok other than email delay
problem so as far as I know it's one
thing that we need to really look at and
that was not a show stopper you can
always just hit resend me my link and it
works so presumably that's not shows our
bug and I'd like to try and get some of
that stuff iron out if there's any other
problems please bring them to my
attention Casey at Molly rocket comm you
can always email me it's on my Twitter
as well if you if you need to contact me
directly or support at send alikom if
you want to contact them directly or of
course you can ask me something in the
Q&amp;A as well ok
that's about it for the preamble let's
get started with the coding today is day
414 and I am going to be debugging that
lighting code you can for those of you
maybe weren't with us yesterday we can
give a brief recap and just get everyone
in the in the mood in the context of
what's going on here so what we did is
we sort of drew the raw lighting
iterations such that we can kind of come
in here and if we if we run a lighting
simulation right you can see that we're
drawing the reflectors here but we added
the ability to turn off the lighting
right so I don't know where that was
disabled right there and of course we
probably should always turn off the
lighting for the text when we turn on
the lighting it's actually lighting the
text too because we just haven't we
didn't put a thing in the renderer to
know the difference between those two
that's like we hey we don't want
lighting on text guys but we also did a
thing where in here we can we could show
the iteration camp what that means is we
can kind of go through here and
look at what happens if we run the
lighting iteration at a single iteration
right like so we can see what happens to
the light as we iterate forwards that's
the initial lighting solution when no
bouncing has happened and you can see
what we've got here is just the the one
light that we have then after we do a
single iteration we're taking that light
and you can see that that light gets
spread out to various services here
right you can see that that light gets
moved to various services we update
again do the lighting a second time this
is after the next bounce and you can
already start to see there's a couple
different things that you can already
see just with this that our buggy right
and what you can see is that we don't
have any notion with the way this light
is being transferred we don't have any
notion of what really should be
happening to these surfaces
we're just randomly spreading light
around like for example you can see
there's or it's already made a mistake
where this was the light this was the
light source here and it's had one of
these lights distribute light to one of
its cells and it overwrote the light
that was already there and obviously
that's not what we want right like this
the new lighting solution should not be
that this is blue light right we so this
is just kind of like showing us the bugs
in our sort of simplistic light
distribution we had started with so what
we want to do today I think because this
is a critical step of the process is
that lighting bounce I think what we
want to do today is try to figure out
how to rewrite this routine in a way
that makes more sense
and we kind of have to think it through
a little bit because again lighting is
very complicated this is the one of the
hardest things in games is lighting it's
one of the things that's really still
not solved you if you look at you know
the major engines out there frostbite
unreal unity whatever none of them have
a coherent lighting solution it's all
like lots of combinations of different
sort of hacks there's a lot of
pre-computation involved in a lot of
cases there's all these sorts of things
it's like it's one of those things that
just not
that clean even today because it's just
a really nasty complex problem and so we
got to think it through and we got to
try and figure out a good way to get a
nice solution that's not that does
enough of what we need without being too
expensive to implement so let's take a
look at what's going on here and let's
work it through on the whiteboard and
then we'll try to improve what we've got
there to not be so sort of a hacky your
ad hoc or whatever you want to say it's
a very simple routine right just this
little routine right here oh we're all
we're talking about is improving this
guy right here so oh shoot Oh big yard
so what you can see we're doing this
compute like propagation here is that
what we're doing is we're stepping over
for for however many iterations of
bounces we said we wanted we're stepping
over actually the emitters right so
we're looking at each one of the
lighting elements of the scene and we're
looking to see what kind which one's of
those emit light right and already I
think this is probably a stupid idea
right I don't really know why I was
thinking of it that way but it's
probably a stupid idea
I don't know because it sort of implies
right that like we're going from emitter
out which maybe I don't know you know
what let me not call it stupid yet
there's reasons why we might want to do
it so let me let me just finished
explaining it first then we can talk
about so we're looping over all of these
the the lighting elements in our in our
solution we're looking to see whether or
not any of those elements have emissive
an emissive amount of light to give away
at the moment right and if they do then
what we're gonna do is shoot out some
number of rays and right now that number
of rays is set to eight we're just gonna
pick eight random directions and we're
gonna spread that light out right so
then what we do is we say okay we now
that we've spread this light out we're
gonna go say you know if we hit somebody
we're gonna see what the angle is that
that it was hitting it at
and we're going to attenuate the light
by that amount right and we record a
weight of how many of these things
shined on the surface and then at the
end we normalized that weight so we
basically bounce the light out record
how many of them we did so that we get
average after right now I as you can see
there's sort of a really bad problem
with this right and that is that we
overwrite on any given step we actually
overwrite the emission that we're going
to use on the next step with the thing
that we calculated what that means is
that a light source only has the first
time it's got light to give it away
right that just doesn't make a lot of
sense like I'm not sure why we did that
exactly it's just kind of weird right
and so if you think about this we
probably need to like really kind of
think through how we want to deal with
what what we're actually trying to do
energy distribution wise and we probably
want to make that work in a smarter way
because lights are lights and every time
we process a light it should probably be
emitting however much it's emitting each
step of the iteration maybe I mean or I
don't know or maybe we wanted to think
of it as there's a certain amount of
photons that they bounce around I'm not
sure how we really want to approach that
problem but it's a bit weird right and
it means things that our emitters are
gonna be bouncing light and they're even
going to bounce light that's not their
color which is not really what would
happen in the real world probably I mean
[Music]
you know especially because of the low
sampling amount I'm just gonna draw for
you an example of something that could
happen here that I think is a pretty
good indication of
be why this is bad right so if we take a
look at what could happen here let's
suppose we have a light source right so
maybe this is already bitter here and
then we've got like a little reflector
here and a reflector here so let's say
this is white this is white but this is
red right well remember we don't have an
infinite number of samples we're not
throwing around billions of photons like
the real world is so well it might be a
fine thing in the real world to say
let's just shoot photons out of here and
let them bounce around and if they
bounce back and hit us again we'll let
them bounce again and fine and whatever
it just works right with billions of
photons you converge on the right
lighting solution in our case we're only
sending out a few rays so it may be
entirely possible that when we send out
the a trays for this guy right we send
that one and we hit this red surface
right now this surface becomes black
because it has not received any lighting
incoming to it right this surface is
black as well
right but it reflects white and so does
this right so now in the next iteration
this is red so it's going to bounce
exclusively red light out and let's say
now it bounces right well I'll say let's
say it bounces light to here right now
this will become red and potentially
bounce light to here and instead of this
being mostly white from this guy's
bounce it will actually be mostly red
because this surface has now been
overwritten with red but we know
intuitively that if this thing is right
next to the light source it should be
mostly getting the light from the light
source right so it doesn't really make
sense to be overwriting overriding
surfaces like that it's just not a
particularly sensible
I think approach to that problem where
we're looking at at how surfaces evolve
over time
right so I guess the question is just
what do we want to do you know to
address this problem and I I'm not sure
right one thing I would say that I'm
kind of interested in in trying just off
the bat and again there's a lot of stuff
we want to try here but I'm interested
in reducing the ray count progressively
so I would be interested to know what
would happen for example if we started
out casting 256 rays but each time
through we divided by two or something
like that maybe that's a little
aggressive let's say it was 64 rays or
something like that but each time
through we divided by 2 right so
basically like at first we spread those
initial light sources out very heavily
you know I'm saying but then on the next
one the secondary bounces is less and
then the tertiary bounces is less and so
on right I don't know I'm just gonna I
just I'm just curious really honestly to
see what that does because I'm not sure
let me turn the lighting off and look at
what what that will do renderer
[Music]
okay so if we take a look at what
happens with the lighting here after our
iteration count after each or iteration
counts so here's after our first
iteration count and what you can see is
that we cover a lot more a lot more of
the surfaces can see us which is good
because of that increased bounce rate
right we're getting a lot more of them
here now for whatever reason and maybe
this is just because of poor sampling
I'm not sure what but you can also see
some weirdness here and again this maybe
is just about us being better about the
debugging but it's really weird that no
rays hit here right it's pretty strange
that nothing was able to hit this at all
and my guess and I could be very wrong
about this but my guess is that's
because we're not really shooting out of
the hemisphere correctly and so maybe
like we're getting something where the
cone you can shoot out in in general
tends to be like that here and like that
here and this is a gap where it's very
likely that the random generator the
random perturbation just never hits
that's my guess don't quote me on that
but that is my guess so I think we've
got some work to do there but let's keep
going so after the second bounce right
now this is a bounce that takes less
it's going to do 32 bounces that you can
see that bouncing around here and it
looks pretty reasonable how it bounced I
don't know about this that looks a
little suspicious to me to be honest
that that seems a bit odd so I'm not
sure how we've got a blue light going
over there probably a bug then we
bounced one more time and again it
continues to sort of spread that laid
out a little bit and then the last time
of our four iterations now we've got you
know what is the the sort of final
spread lighting solution if we take a
look at what that actually looks like
lighting wise I'm not sure
[Music]
how to actually did we make a way that
we could actually see yeah so one of the
things that I'm not totally sure about
is if you take a look at what happens
here this is supposedly the result of
the final gather it doesn't really seem
to reflect pun intended oh I know why
it's because that's the reflectors
that's the actual thing
so anyway maybe that's a little bit more
accurate but even so that doesn't seem
to really reflect very well pun intended
what the lighting solution actually said
was going on so I'm not sure if our
final gather is maybe not so good as
well or it may just be that that's
because since we have no ambient light
here
it's just that hey a lot of the Rays
kind of go up and out and so they're
just not gonna hit anything they're just
gonna hit a skylight which is actually
accurate right that's not wrong but it
is just a little bit weird when you kind
of look at the interpolation here I
think part of that again is that because
the voxels maybe don't have enough
contributions in them just due to the
reflect where the reflectors are it's
hard to say like if you take a look at
how big each of these reflectors are it
could be that the voxels are just
they're not we spread them out too much
with the way that we ended up doing our
voxels right you remember in platformer
dot H here we've got sort of our light
lookup levels right and previously you
know we were using a much more sort of
condensed voxel the elements of the
voxel were quite a bit larger which
allows more blending to happen inside
each of them and so you know it could be
that that's just mostly what's going on
there but I'm not entirely sure right
you can see how it gets much smoother as
we sort of allow
wider net to be cast in the voxel in
terms of blending so yeah you know
that's sort of a separate issue that we
have to deal with but but that does look
it does look somewhat reasonable let me
see how we're doing here
I mean it's actually again it's really
not looking that bad I am again
interested to know so in here where
we've got that sort of like I'm pushing
light to things this part is tough
because we can't do light propagation
yet should probably also talk about how
do you light propagation from the
skylight that's another reason why
pushing from emitters is not great in my
opinion
because again that's we're starting to
get to something that's pretty usable as
a lighting solution and it actually has
a lot of nice sort of like bounced
lighting happening so I think we're
actually not that far from being good
here I think we really just have a few
issues to address and then I think we're
gonna be okay I'm liking the way this is
looking actually right I mean that
really does give you a nice feel of
where the light is and so I think if we
just fix some of these problems yeah
it's not that far from a reasonable
solution I think actually all right so I
think part of the problem is that maybe
this to past situation is just kind of
dumb right so let's let's think about
this a little bit more let's let's let
me work through this because I've never
really done an algorithm that does like
this sort of like loose light
propagation kind of a radiosity is sort
of algorithm right let's think about
this a little bit more in terms of
where's my Milton at I have a mouse mat
here and I need to there we go Dave for
so if you think about what happens with
a raytracer for example which I
understand better and have written more
of right we've got sort of where we're
looking from and we have surfaces out in
the world and we randomly perturb rays
that come out from the eye through a
particular pixel right
and those of you watch hand read read
know about this we sum up a number of
samples that bounce through the world
and see what they hit
right maybe this one hits the light
source here right and so how we
determine how much light comes along
this ray is really based on that process
of full chain discovery the reason that
works really well is because each chain
is like a uniquely satisfiable path of
light from an emitter whose value is
known through a series of bounces whose
values are known right the problem with
it is that it wastes a lot of
computation potentially because for a
particular surface right I may know a
lot about the lighting coming on the
surface because many pixel rays may have
hit this surface from various angles and
may have bounced out in various angles
and found different light sources right
so I may be wasting a lot of
computational time with this path
sampling by not reusing the knowledge
that I already have about the surface
what we're fundamentally trying to do in
our algorithm inside handmade hero is
sort of generate that knowledge meaning
instead of ever thinking about an eye
calculation we want to do a series of
bounces that just tell us generally what
is the incident light at each of these
surfaces right
and I believe generally this has a name
I believe it's called an irradiance
cache let me see if I'm right about that
it's been a long time since I've worked
with this sort of stuff don't suppose
we're gonna have a Wikipedia page or
anything there do we
let's take a look
well this is more of a
[Music]
yes so you can see this is basically
what I'm talking about right
compute on an as-needed basis the
irradiance at particular points and then
just interpolate them right so you can
kind of see here I mean this is this is
exactly what we're doing right
and you can kind of see what they're
doing is they're just rendering out a
hemisphere from a particular point and
then they're just like you know using
those values
so what I'm not seeing
when I'm not seeing as the part that I
was kind of more interested in is just
how to render the irradiance cache using
the irradiance cache right but that's
the part that I you know anyway I got
the answer I wanted which is is this
called the irradiance cache yes
basically that is exactly what we're
doing right so we're trying to make
inner radiance cache here and what we
want to do because we're really
concerned about the performance here
what we're sort of trying to do is build
an irradiance cache using the existing
irradiance cache right what we want to
do is say all right at every step of the
evaluation try to refine an irradiance
cache using its self so that we don't
have to keep computing for every surface
a complete view of the scene you know
from that surface and this is just a
natural thing that you're gonna have to
deal with anyway right because if you're
asking the question how do we speed up a
Monte Carlo ray tracer and the answer is
irradiance cache but in order to
generate three readings cached you have
to run a monte carlo ray tracer from a
bunch of points in the scene
the obvious answer will be well can we
speed up those with an irradiance cache
right so you want to be able to have
this sort of way of understanding what
you're actually representing that allows
you to iterate over it and right now as
you saw we don't the way we're storing
it as just a single omission value I
think may not be sufficient as something
we can use to both compute the lighting
and bounce the lighting because it's
just
it may not be I'm not trying to put this
but it may not be a sufficiently rich
representation to understand what to do
in both those cases and so what do I
mean by that well so if we treated this
strictly as a photon tracing problem for
something like
that then we're more or less doing it
correctly right I mean we there's some
things we probably want to do
differently but the way a photon tracer
would work right is you've got the the
light and it just sends out some number
of rays and those are light
you basically say how much power was
there in it right you send out that much
light in the form of individual rays
that each have a certain amount of light
power they're going to distribute and
whenever one of those hits a surface it
just writes that power in so it's like a
plus of that power and specifically one
thing we would not be doing for example
is normalizing so that's not really an
accurate part of this process if it was
photon tracing this next emission weight
for example would not be there what we
would have instead is just hey the next
emit C is is it adds whatever the light
C is right and this would have some
notion of the power associated with it
that is based on however many rays we
were sending out from that light source
probably right so we would probably say
okay one over the Ray counts right
is how much power is getting dis is
getting put out but to this particular
element right and and off we go
then inside here when we go to normalize
we would no longer do that so the next
emission weight would not occur right we
would just take whatever the Hadamard
product was and we would use the
reflectance of the surface to modify it
right so yeah all we would be doing is
just just this part and that's that's
all there is to it and then the next
emission W part just isn't relevant now
again I don't know that we I really want
to do this in a photon tracing way but
you could kind of see why that wasn't
right that we were waiting those because
we're just talking about spreading the
light power out here so there really
should not have been that waiting right
um and even with just that change you
can kind of see that it looks a little
more correct to what we would have
expected like the light is kind of more
localized and bright where it is which
is what we should be seeing right like
that actually gives a better result than
what we had in a lot of ways right I
think and that's the more straight
photon tracing method in fact that looks
really good like that's that looks a lot
better than what we had before let's
turn off the ambient light I want to see
what those bounces look like
so there's there's the light and that
really does feel a lot better without
that normalization that feels more like
what I would have expected to have
happen however I do think we probably
have we're not really getting much in
the way of bounced light there I feel
like so I would like to take a quick
look at that let me let me see what's
going on here renderer I also don't know
about that
those that light emit W part and it W
what does this say should we switch to
an integer here no we should just delete
it
oh that's why it's because there was a
greater than zero there all right so
this is more of a straight photon
distribution right we're starting with a
light source we scatter its photons out
those photons are now gone from that so
it becomes black until it gets a what's
the right before it until it receives
light again right and so let's take a
look at how those bounces work out let's
see here
so let's drop it down to zero so there
we can see that first bounce I mean that
first initial seed which is what we
expect here's our first bounce so here's
where all of the light went from the
initial light source and you can see
like I said that light source is now
black which is what we what it should be
because it has distributed all of its
photons to other people right it is sent
them away
now let's update that bounce one more
time and see what we get
and so what you can see now is the a lot
of that light has now been dissipated
out and you know this is the thing about
this is that that is kind of what you
would expect to happen because we have
no absorption right now meaning we're
not accounting for any light that may be
sent back to the viewer right so
basically we're just scattering photons
around and eventually probably this
exact what happens they all end up just
flying off into space right because it's
not a closed system and so you can kind
of see that eventually yeah we just we
dissipate all of our photons but this
actually seems like a more sane set of
bounces to me it seems like it's working
a little better so now the question is
well what do we do about remembering
what the photons at each individual
location actually you know saw or
actually could emit back and that's a
good question
I don't know how we want to really
record that piece of information every
time we strike array with the surface
we're sort of saying that light did get
here at some point and when the photons
bounce around it's hard to say like how
much of them should stay one way of
thinking of it is like hey let's keep
half and send half or something I I
don't know like I'm not a photon tracing
expert so I'm
not sure what the most logical thing is
to do there but you can imagine going
like hey let's just get rid of the final
gather lighting all together right like
what if we just said don't bother right
instead here all we do is say all right
well you know when when we have
something what we'll say is here's what
our emission would have been let's take
what the let's take for the incident
light and the average direction to light
I guess that average direction to light
parts a little bit tricky to do that was
the nice part about the final gather as
we kind of had an idea about where it
was coming from we could just deposit
some of that light in here right into
the incident light and say we're gonna
keep some of the photons to bounce back
out I don't know it doesn't seem wise
I mean another thing we could do is sort
of say that we only add light to
services so it just keeps getting
brighter I'm kind of at a loss here
folks I'm kind of at a loss I mean like
for example there's that which is just
adds light to the system I feel like I
need to do a better job though figuring
out how I'm really gonna do this because
I it's kind of a little bit loose for me
what did I it what happened there Oh
so if we just allow it to keep getting
brighter than this is what we get I
don't remember what our light is
currently set to in terms of its
brightness something's a little wacky
here though because that should be white
it's not right because if we're always
adding to the admit see that should have
like this should stay white shouldn't it
so something's weird there we go through
all of the emitters we push out based on
the emit seed then we're just gonna add
to the admit see some more light that's
the light be received
oh no I take it back
since the final gather just looks
outward it would not do that
so that's correct what are we doing is
this what level of lighting is this is
this a 1.0 light I don't remember yeah
so this is a 1.0 light sitting up above
us there right in our face see what
happens here
I tried going like Heinsohn this stuff
here
it does seem to work somewhat okay but
it's a little odd like I'm not sure why
we don't get much light thrown to
further away it seems to be very
localized but I'm not sure why I don't
know if we have a distance attenuation
term in there that's too aggressive or
something like this something's up
oh I guess that's because the giant
sprite cards um I'm kind of interested
to know if maybe this should be it would
be nice if we could disable those to a
certain extent for the time being cuz I
don't really want those in there anyway
like we probably don't want the hero to
be an actual giant and he won't be once
we get his sprite clipped a little bit
more but he's not really supposed to be
such a giant thing that's just because
the bitmap wasn't was never properly
conditioned for him it's just a giant
BMP that was stuck in a directory right
so he cuts out a lot more light than he
should I wonder if we should really
quick just take him out of here
all right so now that I've got an actual
block that I can push around here that's
the light I'm interested to see what
kinds to throw light around I still
think I still think for some reason yeah
not for some reason I guess I still
think we have a pretty steep distance
based attenuation there that might be
just because of the way we're doing the
Ray casting I mean basically the ray
casting itself is what provides the
distance attenuation because Ray's
spread out so they're less likely to hit
things when they get further away right
so if I take a look here compute final
lighting
I'm sorry compute light propagation when
we're doing our sampling in our
hemisphere here you know we don't do a
distance basic to attenuation but yeah I
think just that the fact that the Rays
tend to diminish quite a bit is largely
what would end up making that happen so
the lights just are able a lot more of
the light samples hit things that are
close by which is what makes it brighter
I think
yeah so there's thing I'd be interested
to see is if we were to decide for
example to not do things this way let's
suppose we did something more like this
you just said all right we're not going
to do a final gather pass the average
direction to ladies always the normal
for whatever reason right and the
incident light is always the emit
whatever the final limit round said it
was you know I mean I'm kind of
interested to know what happens in that
case right so here's the case where we
just say look light is gonna be bounced
around photon wise and we're not going
to do a final gather for it
that's just not happening this is what
we end up with now I don't really know
quite what to make of that but it
actually looks quite a bit better right
you get a lot more light thrown out it
feels like that is just able to take
into account a lot more of the light
information that we have just looking at
it right so we may want to do something
that just does the photons and then
calls it a day it skips the final gather
so maybe we should concentrate on
schemes that do it in one pass where
they're just passing the light around
now one problem is we don't really know
where the lights coming from as much but
we could start tracking that - right the
we could we could track the incident
direction so let's just go ahead and try
this
we could track the incident direction by
just tracking the photons that come in
right that's not that hard to do
suing here when we create for whatever
it is when we create the incident light
in fact I guess what we do is we still
could do this now I think about it in
the final gather where drink here isn't
really a final gather it's just a thing
that like bakes the average is down so
really this sort of thing would still
occur
the average direction the light would
just be the normalized version of
whatever the incident Direction was
which will just store in here as an
accumulator right and the incident light
is just whatever the emitter color was
right so the average direction to light
we would just say okay every time we get
one of these hits we just say like the
average direction of the light is just
going to be equal to let's take the
power value that we were using here and
we'll just say the average direction to
the light is modified by that but we
really should take how strong the light
was in fact I guess we just can let's
just take the length of the color right
so however much power there is behind
that
so we'll do wait times the the direction
out to where the hit was from because we
know what that was right we have the
emitters location and we have our
location so normal an emit D
so the omit D is the direction we went
in right so the direction to the light
is just going to be the negative of that
right the emitter direction is the
direction we had to go to get to the
thing so it's the it's coming back the
other way is the direction to the light
because we're spreading the light out
yeah so that should tell us the
direction to the light in theory right
yep so so that gives us that information
ooh what is happening I don't know why
that just happened so that lighting is
starting to look reasonable I mean I
would be pretty happy with that
right I think our voxel scheme is a
little janky right now it needs to get
fixed
just the way it that's interpolating
isn't fabulous like you can kind of see
a lot of it poking through and I don't
know how good that's going to be once we
actually transfer this to something that
runs on the GPU right because we're once
this runs in real time we've got we will
see artifacts that we're not seeing now
from the voxel interpolation I strongly
suspect
and I think our hemisphere sampling is
also pretty bad like I feel like we're
getting artifact because of that so I
feel like we should also improve our
hemisphere sampling but yeah so I would
say yeah the couple things we need to do
first of all we should probably try to
to improve that hemisphere sampling
second thing we should probably do is we
need to start addressing the sprite
cards issue because although the sprite
cards want to be drawn as sprites for
purposes of the lighting solution they
should probably be upright blocks right
because they want to catch the light as
if they were a little like blocks
standing there probably at least that's
my assumption so we probably want to do
something like that where everything is
probably a going to be a little bright
rectangular prism that we send down for
the lighting solution and then you know
yeah when we go to actually render it we
draw it as the sprite card with with the
lighting being with the lighting coming
from the computed samples right so we
kind of have some work to do there but I
think we're getting closer I think we're
getting closer there so the other thing
that we'd have to do is we don't have
any skylight rays right now just things
that kind of come in to propagate the
light inward and that's why I wonder if
we really want to do this backwards
right going from the light source
definitely has advantages in that it
sort of concentrates things where where
it's probably most important to do them
but you know because the skylight should
be illuminating everything I don't know
how exactly we want to account for that
we could allow the final gather to occur
or just have a separate sky lighting
pass right in other words we could say
like okay you know
do a bunch of raycast as a final thing
that we do is like the last step of the
process and that's you know that's
strictly there to sort of like wait the
skylight in I don't know how smart that
is that might just be dumb but what we
could do is say yeah right you know like
maybe just at each pass through this we
also do a little bit of skylight here so
we do something like okay when we're
raycasting we do something like this so
sample the hemisphere do a ray cast to
see what is it called hit index or done
I'd yeah if that I equals solution
element count so it's not if we don't
hit anything
then add the skylight right so that's
some power that comes from the sky that
has to be specified
and it should probably based on the sky
right account and the iterations so
whatever this is so that's gonna
diminish whatever the sky power is in
the sky power is something we can just
set right so then we could say it's like
alright if we want to add in some
skylight here then we could just say
take that sky color take the average
direction to light bit and maybe we
don't alter that maybe we let that not
be recorded I don't know how we want to
do that exactly but either way we would
just say like okay the next emit C
equals sky power kind of color I and
then we could still do this part if we
wanted to
all right like that and I don't know
that's pretty ad-hoc I admit that but
I'm just kind of playing with it all
right so let's see what happens if I put
that in there not much honestly
that did not really do anything I don't
know if that's because the sky power is
too weak oh I didn't actually do that
many and again this isn't really
necessary if we were to just sample
outward from services because we just
have that in line with with catching the
light sources or whatever but I I think
we may need to have since bimodal where
we do out from light sources and back
from services separately and I'm not
sure which should go where or how many
of each to do so we kind of need to like
feel around there a little bit and just
see like what's going on so we'll find
out I think we may also be double
counting the color here so if you take a
look at this emissions it's getting the
emission itself gets modified by it gets
multiplied by the reflection color we
don't really want that probably for our
light that we end up recording so that's
probably wrong as well we probably need
to record both of these two things
so we probably need for example the
incident light here probably we need to
be recorded here and it would probably
need to be that the incident light we
add without multiplying so the emission
amount we multiply by that ref C but the
other one we don't know we could store
those both is the same value because we
just multiplied by the reflection color
when we go to transmit the light so if
we decide on this scheme that's what we
would do I think probably that'd be my
guess anyway so there now we've got our
skylight in place and that's looking
pretty nice actually and again I think
there's a lot of bugs there with
hemisphere sampling that I don't love
but
and you can see that slower now probably
largely because of that all the services
or light sources now so you you know we
are we don't do rate casting out
services outward the outward iteration
on services that aren't light sources so
I think what I might want to do is
instead of having to split this idea
that we had before between like bouncing
the light and gathering the light I
think what I might want to do is
actually make those two just different
ways of iterating so there's a forward
iteration we can do that spreads light
out from emitters and there's a backward
iteration we can do that gathers light
from the protective services and so
maybe we just do one or two quick
forward iterations of the light to take
our light sources and scatter those out
to everything that they touch and then
everything else is a gather based update
from that on seems plausible to me maybe
sort of a little bit that seems like
something that could in theory be
something in theory that maybe happen
sometimes to someone somewhere right
let's try to go over here and see what
the lighting solution is it's kind of
weird
what's going on there
if I set this let me see what what I did
there when I when I move the incident
light in and it seems like I'm not sure
exactly what's happening there just
incident oh I know what it is incident
light is probably never cleared yeah so
in here where we extract reflectors from
quads we never clear that so that's that
was all that was that's gonna say that's
a bit weird skylight all right it's my
mistake
so now if I move over here hopefully I
should see the highlight move yeah so
that looks much more correct
so I think that that's working pretty
well
again needs some work but we're getting
there slowly but surely I mean from
where we started we're now at a pretty
good
we're in a pretty good place I would say
actually so let's maybe take a look at
just breaking this now down into the
ability to do a forward iteration and
something that does a backward iteration
and that way we can in prince who and
maybe let's look at sampling the
hemisphere better because right now we
definitely don't do that well right fast
generation of hemispherical samples
let's take a look what is this code it
now what what is this because this this
was the top hit on a previous search we
just did for irradiance cache as well is
this somebody who does a bunch of ray
tracing work I don't know
you can does anyone know who this is I
don't know who this is
there should be looking about button
somewhere there isn't Rory hello Rory
well I don't know it's someone named
Rory and there's the irradiance caching
that's a lot of transcendentals and that
one here's stratified sampling which is
probably what we want to do too which is
basically just like sampling in ways
that you think are probably more
reasonable for reconstructing the
function you're trying to sample let's
see here
so basically what's going on here right
is this generates points on a disk and
then puts them up on the hemisphere
where they should be
which basically samples sort of it it
spreads out the samples proportional to
the cosine of theta so what you could do
is you could then take the cosine of
theta out of your waiting term because
you know that you're just not sampling
as much in that direction and that
becomes the weight itself right
unfortunately yeah just a lot of
transcendentals there which you know is
not fantastic doing a cosine and a sine
just to generate one of those seems bad
to me but anyway so I'm going to take a
look at what we got here what does this
say
you
same problem right all those cosines and
sines here just stack overflow where you
think they say about it I do like the
rejection method that's basically like
one where you just kind of generate and
then repeat until you find one that
satisfies that ease inside a disk so
rather than using cosine sign you just
randomly pick one in a square and then
if it's tested against the circle
sooo
I guess one thing that I hadn't thought
of here's an interesting thought so
rather than trying to generate a random
hemispherical distribution right if we
did just generate a random spherical
distribution we could then dot product
with the normal and if it was pointing
in the opposite direction as the normal
we could just flip it and then it would
be in the hemisphere right so for
example this function here what we could
say is get rid of the 0.5 and the N plus
right just normalize your zero this that
would give us a random point on a sphere
now how its arranged I'm not sure but I
think it should be roughly randomly
distributed it's hard to say because it
might be that it bunches up some a bit
because you're projecting down onto the
sphere so it may not be perfectly
uniform I'd have to think about that but
then once you have one of these you
could then say like alright if the inner
you know do this if the inner product of
the result and the normal is less than
zero then the result just equals oops
the negative result that would give you
a hemisphere sample that covers the
entire hemisphere and that yeah I think
just works right
no transcendentals no cosines and sines
involved which is nice so that seems
kind of good right
so feel like that's a nice addition and
I don't know to what extent that
necessarily fixes anything for us but I
think that would get rid of the sort of
nasty sort of bias we had there with the
hemisphere sampling holes I'm not sure
why we get these breaks in the middle
here I don't know if that's just because
of the two sides of the light source
being a little bit odd or if that's more
just because this is where the two
elements are spread apart I don't know
if there's like a voxel boundary there
is something this is again where we kind
of want to it would be nice if we had a
way to sort of measure or show things a
little better we could use better
visualization here for sure also we may
want our skylight to
to only work if it actually hits someone
facing upwards right so or make our
skylight be proportional to the
direction it is right so we could do
something like hey the skylight gets
kind of less like maybe the skylight has
more of a color wash to it right so it
it's like we take the inner product of
the REA direction and like up we don't
which we don't even need to do that it's
just it's just whatever the Z coordinate
is right you know we could even sort of
make us sunlight is sort of a thing if
we wanted to there no think about it so
let's try that so let's say we've got a
Sun color which is just gonna be like I
don't know let's be ever I don't think I
ever installed color cop on this machine
I did not
but color cop is good
let's grab a little color cop
all right and
let's go ahead and pick some colors here
so if I wanted like a some kind of color
here
maybe it's something like that looks a
little bit too green
okay there's our quote-unquote Sun and
now let's do a sky
and the power level of these of course
should be related so what I might do is
I might make these f4 kind of things
here
I guess I'll still call that sky power
and I might do something here where we
say like okay so this is sky power but
there's a lot like the Sun is like much
more powerful right so maybe you know
this maybe the sky color is like point
two five and this is like ten or
something I don't know and so what we
could do there is say like okay so let's
suppose that we take some blend between
these two so we could say we we do that
sort of same thing where we've got the
the power is represented by the Alpha
and so then we can just say ok here is
our power value and off we go
so then we just have to have a blend
between these two right so we can lurk
between the Sun color and the sky color
argus sky color sun color and we just
need a T value that would give us like
how close to the Sun you're pointing so
maybe we've got like a Sun Direction in
here right
maybe the Sun Direction is just that and
so then I can take the inner product of
the raid erection and the Sun Direction
and that gives me the cosine between the
two of those right and maybe I just want
to clamp that like I want to map that
I don't remember what that math function
was called but it's like plant
normalized map to range or something
like that
where we do like min and Max with a T
value or whatever so I think that's what
we want so we can say hey that inner
products gonna be a full range of things
we want something that's really just
pointed very close to the Sun only to be
sunlight and whatnot and so what we're
gonna do there is say like yeah the
clamp 0 1 map to range is gonna go
between like 0.9 and 1.0 right and
that's the T value for the Sun or
something I'm totally just randomly
screwing around here I admit that
thank you color Cup but that was just
designed to sort of like have there be
some kind of a notion of like Sun
Direction versus a non Sun Direction in
the sky versus like a sky color versus
the Sun color I'm gonna take the let's
see if I can make that work I'm going to
take the current push light out just for
a second well I fuss with that a little
bit of course what I probably should
just put a sunlight up in there but
sometimes you want to handle things like
infinitely far directional light sources
like that in a special way all right
so here we've got our lighting and I'll
be honest I have no idea what that is
right there does anybody else I have no
idea what that's coming from which is
not great right not a good sign
unless that's people who happen to point
towards the sunlight right but we want
to start seeing is we want to see like a
brighter area in a darker area here
based on whether you're pointing towards
the Sun or not pointing towards the Sun
right and the Sun since it's one one one
should be kind of like up in this
direction right and you know we do have
a little bit of shadowing in here that
would seem to suggest that slightly but
again it's not it's not fabulous so I'll
play this a little bit here and to see
so since we're sort of slow since our
lighting solution is sort of slow anyway
let's maybe see here about doing like oh
I don't know maybe we could do some more
of these rays and let's make the Sun
look way more powerful
and one of the things that's you know
kind of wrong about this who my goodness
well we definitely got a more powerful
Sun so let's see so the Sun so we are
actually getting a bit of a Sun
Direction suggestion in there because
this is dark in here and this is very
bright right and it is coming from that
direction but it's still a little bit
wonky let me let me go ahead and calm
that down a little bit that may have
been overzealous
so yeah like if we take a look at what's
going on there I feel like there's a
certain degree of maybe the Sun is just
a little bit too easy to hit I mean
that's a pretty wide angle there and one
of the problems that we have is what we
really want to do is just see if you can
see the Sun right and actually this is
this lighting here as well is not using
the cosine attenuation which it should
be using so we kind of need to like
again make this a little bit more
standardized I feel like so it's
understandable what kind of light you're
hitting in what cases but yeah in this
case we would still also need to do here
when we compute the power look that used
color a we probably won't use color a to
be multiplied by the inner product of
the reference normal and the Ray
direction right again we probably just
want a sample in a biased fashion so
that we're already weighting them by
that amount but yeah this is one of
those things where we kind of have to go
through here with a fine-tooth comb and
make sure all of it's correct it's
actually pretty difficult to make sure
that you do
but otherwise I think that's okay
otherwise I think that's okay so yeah
and and like I said this parts a little
tricky cuz in general when you're
casting raise out words to find things
you typically intentionally sample the
sunlight Direction specifically to see
whether you you hit it or not and so
that's also something we should probably
do so the skylight really you don't need
to do this lip thing what you do
typically is is you just sample the Sun
Direction once and see whether you hit
it or not right and so probably that's
more what should happen here we should
probably just sample the Sun Direction
at some point and see whether or not we
hit it so for example you would do
something more like this
it would not be inside the loop you just
say like hey if there's only one
direction that can see the Sun like so
assuming that you can see it then the
color that you're going to use here it's
going to be the Sun color I will just go
ahead and do all of the summation here
for you and in this case then we don't
really have to do this anymore it's just
like use color equals sky color and what
we could do is like pull out those two
sample maybe like make a little thing
that like some samples for us which
would be nice
so that we can just easily call you know
something that does this sample for us
and so again I think part of the problem
here is that everyone can really see the
Sun we're kind of whiteout we're out in
the open here a little bit too much and
and of course in this case where we do
that that Sun power should not have the
the sky ray count included in it so here
for that we've actually got we actually
want to have something more like
so yeah so we've got about 15 minutes
left I think that's what I'll do I'll
just try and start to make this a little
bit more rigorous so we can start to
converge on a good lighting solution
what I think I'll probably do is pull
out that code that does a lighting
accumulation sample into something
saying and try to make that work a
little bit better right so this is
looking better here you can kind of see
you're starting to get a little bit more
of that sunlight feel in there right
like things in here but you can really
see the Sun easily or nice and bright
and things that can't aren't getting
darker there right which is nice again
we haven't really constructed a scene
that lends itself particularly well to
this because there's just not a lot of
blockades here and probably what we
would want to do is these trees like I
said we need to do something probably
what we should do next weekend is make
it so we now actually send down
something coherent for the lighting
where things like trees are represented
by little blocks so that they're not
just these cards right look UV and that
is probably what we would want to do
yeah so let me pull out that piece of
code and that can be the last thing that
we do today essentially this code here
kind of wants to just be a thing I think
or maybe like sample lights something
like this and so what we do there is we
would pass the lighting solution we
would pass the Ray well you know do we
want to call the ray cast or not well
let's do this in two phases
so let's try it this way
let's say that we have a lighting
element and what we're gonna do is we're
going to take light and the light has a
light color and a light power right and
it's got a direction maybe normal to
light something like that and then what
we could do is say well we know what
happens here right
we are currently saying we're going to
use the cosine fall-off law so what we
would say is the power equals the light
power times the inner products of the
normal to the light times the elements
normal it's the cosine fall-off term or
just the angular follow
and then in here we say alright we know
that the next emission color therefore
needs to be the power times the light
color and then the weight for summing
the light direction is going to be
whatever the length of the light color
is times the power and that will be the
normal to light weighting factor right
and so this is how you accumulate
samples of lighting yeah so in here
let's just double check that this is
what we think it should be so this power
value is always constant so we can just
compute it up here the angular fall-off
needs to be clamped so but other than
that this all looks correct so I think
then what we can do is say yeah all
right so let's do a cumulate sample we
know that we're accumulating sample into
this particular hit we know the color of
the light is the emitters emit color we
know the light power is the constant
light power value that we have there and
we know that the normal to the light is
going to be the emitter directions
inverse right because that was we went
from that direction from the emitter to
go so we'd go the other direction to go
back right so that is a one hit one
accumulation
for these other one here we would do
okay we want to accumulate a sample we
want to accumulate it into the reference
the reflector that were looming on that
reference the reflector that we're on we
want the sky color and the sky power
which in this case is just the sky color
alpha value and we know the direction is
whatever the direction is we looked at
for the Sun we know same thing it's the
Sun color RGB and the Sun color a and
then it's whatever the Sun Direction is
where it was that seems right to me
and of course the Sun is a bit bright
but you know Suns are bright that
something Suns do so yeah let's take a
look at what happens if we get rid of
the sunlight
so that's removing the sunlight don't
ask me why close the game down I don't
know
so there's just the diffused ilight and
that looks pretty good as well so I
think both of those are reasonable right
so that's fine I think now we could also
get rid of the incident light value
because the incident light value is just
the same as the emit value we just don't
have a marred by the reflected color
right so what we could do instead is
never actually do that instead just have
emit C is always the thing and up here
where we go to transfer color instead of
emit see here we do the Hadamard product
here of the emitter ref color so-called
ref C we could also just do like emit C
here
so we grab the emitter we compute it
this way so we know that's the emitted
light is whatever it's emit value is
modified by will how it transmits it we
would then look at that to test whether
that meets the minimum criteria assuming
it does we then use that as the color
all the way through then here we don't
bother with this ever right we just sum
up what the next emission is going to be
and that means we can just get rid of
the incident light bit entirely
and I think that's just done so then in
the final lighting gather we don't have
to do anything cept normalize and then
we can just go ahead and get rid of the
incident light oops
because we just don't care about it
anymore and so now the emit C is always
the value that we use there aren't two
values in the lighting propagation which
is good just because we're gonna have to
move this to the GP eventually so we
don't really want an orgy of you know
data flying around the more concise we
can make it the more simple we can make
it the better it will be for making sure
that it can work on like a small set of
subsets of textures or something like
this right so there we go
let's put back in our regular light and
take out our skylight and sunlight there
just to make sure that's all still
working
yeah so I take this out I should now
have no light at all and now if I go
into world mode and look for the push
light
I should be back to having my light
sources I can move around all right
slowly but surely
I don't know man that's starting to look
kind of nice I think we're getting
somewhere
all right I'm gonna leave it there and I
think the next thing like I said we want
to do is we probably have to change the
way we're sending things down because we
want to start sending things down that
are proper for the lighting solution
which means not giant weird cards that
aren't sized properly even though
eventually they will be sized properly
so that we can actually have those
lighting elements be a little bit more
sensible right all right so let's go
ahead and go to a QA here
why is there a dark horizontal band on
the red/blue voxels approximate the
height of the bottom of the push light
box note possibly fixed at the end of
the stream render so I don't know yet we
have I've mentioned that was we were
looking at it I'm pretty sure that we've
still got plenty of bugs in here so it's
probably just because hey yeah we have
to work on how we're interpolating those
samples better but I do think there's
some some issues there now it may be
because of the fact that that actually
is somewhat representative of this
angular emitter you know not being able
to shine the light as uniformly because
of that but it's probably not because if
you look at the way it's shaped this
should be kidding out here just fine
with regular throw samples I mean I
could try moving into well I can't
really move into the tree unfortunately
I need to turn off the collision
detection so I can move this light
anywhere I want but anyway I suspect if
that has more to do with the voxel
interpolation and problems with that
because we still haven't quite cleaned
that up to the point where it's really
what we need it's sort of really
sensitive to the boundaries of the voxel
like I mean you know we want some scheme
where it's not so sensitive to for
example
if I'd go into this and make my voxels
you know twice as dense in each
direction I want the scheme to still
work right and you know it doesn't right
because now the the samples are too
isolated so they don't blur with each
other properly and so what we're gonna
have to do is we're gonna and this is
what we should be doing anyway is when
you look at how we're subdividing up our
lighting samples what we want to do is
probably subdivide the lighting samples
based on voxel boundaries more so
instead of just blindly subdividing here
when we maybe don't even need to we
would want to do something where we look
at where the voxel boundaries are and
make sure that we've got lighting
samples spaced nicely throughout those
voxel boundaries so that they blend well
right
so what I would assume and we could take
a look but what I would assume is
there's actually a voxel boundary here
that's not interpolating properly or
something like this that is more the
cause of that then any than anything
with the actual lighting solution itself
I don't know if that makes sense but I
believe that's what's actually happening
is there a good tutorial for using
modern OpenGL in CAD like applications
where you need to draw many sharp and
precise lines and filled planes mostly
in 2d
I don't think so yeah I mean I've
pointed to this on the stream before and
I do think it's a good place to start
but
I've referenced this paper before on the
stream and it's probably a good place to
get started right what it is is just a
collection of shaders that show you how
to draw shapes that you might want to
draw right in a modern context with nice
quality filtering built into the shader
and I don't know if that's the kind of
thing you're looking for but you know if
you zoom in here you can kind of see
that these are all kind of a little bit
anti-aliased and everything and you know
that might be a good place for you to
start in terms of figuring out like oh
here are some ways that I can try to
improve the drawing quality of my
program using modern stuff but I don't
know that might not be what you mean but
has anyone tried to give you an actual
3d model of a cartoon spruce by now
uh-huh no but we don't use any 3d models
in the game anyway so I remember you
mentioning you didn't go to college how
did you learn see I'm actually there in
C long before I would have been able to
go to college anyway I was little when I
learned C I don't really remember how I
learned it
my dad taught me basic on the deck
rainbow and I think he may have taught
me Pascal after that or sori just gave
me like books on it or whatever so I
don't really remember but see I learned
I think mostly on my own probably out of
the Kernighan and Ritchie book because
once you kind of know like Pascal or
another language like that I mean any of
the languages c-sharp Java any of like
the C family of languages Pascal is sort
of really a close neighbor as well it's
really not hard to pick it up but I I
knew Pascal before I learned C
and how much time did you learn Game Dev
well I've been programming the first
program I wrote when I was 7 was a game
it was like a really crappy like basic
printf like it wasn't printed just print
and basic where you I think you could
enter a number and it did something and
so I've been programming games I'm 41
now so I've been programming games for
what is that 38 years
no sorry 30 so it's three before so 34
years and I still don't really know game
development I I'm constantly like I mean
you see what we do with the lighting
right that's game development like like
there's so many aspects of game
development that are just aren't done
well yet that nobody has learned it yet
right we're all still figuring it out
like it's it's really just that much of
an expansive space that I feel like I'm
constantly learning every day and so I
don't know the answer is somewhere over
thirty four years is how long it takes
to learn game development what's the
most poops I may have deleted the
database thing you have seen well
probably the one that I can remember in
most recent memory is I went to try to
risk to to update a backup drive and
when I plugged in the backup drive
windows decided spontaneously to
overwrite the master boot table of both
the backup drive and the drive I was
trying to back up
that's just what disk partition the disk
management thing decided to do which
knocked me down to only one
drive that still had the date on it I'll
uh I totally lost it I was so freaked
out but I was able to generate it back
from that but that was terrifying
anonymous to C++ 17 bring anything you
like not know I mean C++ is a way lost
cause forget about C++ right like it's
good to learn to program C I think
everyone should probably learn to
program and C in assembly language
because they teach you how to program
actual programs not things that are high
level constructs that maybe someday
eventually make a CPU do something right
but C++ is a waste of time I mean it
just it's it is it's a it's a lousy
language it's poorly designed everything
in it is broken it will not last like
C++ will not be the thing that games are
programmed in in the future there will
be a replacement language it will
probably retain a bunch of C thing like
things but I strongly suspect that if
all of the things that C++ does will be
jettisoned and they'll be replaced by
much better constructs that are sane and
designed by people who knew what they
were doing
so nocebo suppose 17 well I haven't read
up on much of it yet I'm sure it's an
epic disaster because literally every
time the C++ community tries to do
something they designed the worst
possible version of that thing and I do
not know how they are so consistently
that bad I really don't I think that's
just probably designed by committee
because you know that not everyone there
is an idiot I mean it that just can't be
true so it's like something about the
process or the tone of C++ just makes it
so that somehow they constantly make the
worst language decisions you can make I
don't know how I really don't you think
eventually they accidentally do
something right but they never do so I
don't know it's a
sneaky blahblah what's your favorite
game from your youth mule on the Atari
8-bit for me 100% agreed mule is
probably my favorite game from my youth
I it's probably one of the best games
ever made and certainly one of the very
few games from that era that you can
boot up right now and have a great time
with a lot of the other games i remember
playing as a child if i when i went back
to play them now they're just not very
good they were good for the time and
they were good for what we had and what
the machines could do and whatever but
mule was actually a legitimately great
game and one of the only ones from that
time period that really you can look
back on and go this design still is
fantastic look at this little been
coding games for scratches visual studio
and your opinion a good start thanks
yeah visual studio is fine I don't love
the editor so I use an external editor
but you know I use the compiler from
visual studio and it's fine the debugger
is decent there aren't really very many
good debuggers for windows so it's like
you know it's one of the better ones for
Windows the community editions available
for free so you can use it so that's
good if you're on Linux obviously LLVM
and clang right it's a good way to go
gdb is kind of but but it works and for
your editor well I don't know you know
there's lots of editors you can use like
QT creator it's an integrated idea as
well if you want did you have any input
on jii well John will often bring up
programming things related to ji with me
and discussed them when he wants to talk
through like an issue or something he's
trying to design so in that sense I
suppose I have some input on it but it's
really just that it's really most mostly
like as a sounding board for John is the
the extent to which I've had input on J
I don't participate in the design of it
really at all or and think that but
occasionally and this is true of a lot
of people John knows you know
he will just be like working on some
part of it he's not really sure exactly
what he thinks the right solution is so
he'll talk it out be like let's talk
about this you know how do you normally
do this when you're programming or what
do you think about this solution right
and so I've definitely done that several
times over the course of his work on J I
but but that's but that's all so it's I
would say it's less input and more just
as a sounding board for John which a lot
of programmers that he knows have you
know he does that to kind of get you
know some some additional perspective on
issues that he's not you know sure what
he thinks is the exact right solution
yet you know if he already knows exactly
what he thinks it should be then you
know yeah I think he just does that but
you know cases where he feels like it's
a little more ambiguous he'll kind of go
try to feel out what other people might
do in general and then he'll go back and
think about what language decisions
would you know comport with that nicely
every language in mind replaceable s not
particularly
you know ji is a great initiative that
John's doing and I'm excited to see what
ends up happening with it I think it's
the kind of thing that I will probably
work on in the future as well we already
have an internal language at Mali rocket
for stuff and I would probably consider
building that out more after our first
game you know at the very least I can
tell you I will not be programming C++
for very long like I am actively
programming less and less of it every
day and moving things over to different
ways of doing things and you know
because it's a it's a bum language it's
bad it's holding the industry back and
it's lousy and you know unfortunately
it's hard for us as an industry to
switch to other languages because most
other languages don't have performance
as a concern and don't allow access to
the kinds of things we need access to
you know you can't write a game in
Python unless you have a game engine
written in C underneath it right and
that's just because those foreigners
don't prioritize you know the important
things like direct memory management
really good ways of generating concise
performant code from you know kind of
just slightly above the assembly
language level things like that those
are never those languages priorities and
so only a few languages are really
capable of taking up the mantle of
high-performance programming like that
jei is targeting there but so maybe is
rust I think potentially targeting there
there's only a few language that are
doing it so a lot of the language is
that other people can switch for for
other purposes where performance is less
of a concern for them we just don't have
the option so that we've been saddled
with C++ for a long time because of that
and typically what we have to do in
games is write most of the important
stuff in C you're in C++ and then the
like less important code like scripts
can be written in other languages like
Java or Python or whatever
right if you want to if you feel like
those languages are an improvement but I
think that can change in the future like
I think if we just have a little bit
more of a concerted effort I think we
can make a new language for games that
would retain all of the low-level access
that C provides and good memory direct
memory management things like that but
that starts to layer on high the kinds
of high level constructs we'd like to
have without sacrificing that ability
right because that's what it's all about
it's basically like getting getting that
ability to high-level extend things and
mix things and edit things at a higher
level while still be able to drill down
to the real minutiae that's the key and
I think we can get there eventually I
don't have any experience with the cocoa
API I see you switch to for coder from
you max how do you like for code or
compared to you max I
it's basically for coder has a few
features from Emacs that it hasn't
implemented yet like keyboard macro
macro recording that I miss also jump to
function with autocomplete I missed
those two everything else it now does
and it does it so much better than Emacs
that when I have gone back to Emacs to
use a keyboard macro to do an edit that
was that I needed that for or something
it is so painful switching back to Emacs
now so for coder basically just like
flattened Emacs it's it's not even a
remotely close competition anymore for
coder is lightyears ahead of you max and
the only thing that holds for coder
backed by relation at all is a few
features that it doesn't quite have yet
but they are features that's on Allen's
roadmap so by the time he gets to those
I think Emacs is a complete non-issue Oh
anonymous do you agree with those who
say source code is text or do you think
we should push for more structure where
and centers and tools source code is
definitely not text it's a holdover from
the old days and it definitely holds us
back
Kri NSA B what will come next afterward
deflating probably some gameplay stuff
I'd like to get it more into game
situations so probably try to get art in
there upgrade our art path and get art
in there and make the game like easy to
move around and get controls good so
ever gonna be a hand made compiler no
I'm not really a compiler expert so I
don't know that I would ever make a
handmade compiler John said he would do
something like that but he has not yet
probably because he's too busy making
his own actual compiler so he hasn't
wanted to probably do a tutorial stream
of making a simple compiler you can
understand that all right I think that's
all the cue Colin's alrighty let's close
this down thank you everyone for joining
me for this sort of handmade here it's a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with
series at home you can always pee order
the game and it comes with the source
code so you can do your own
experimentation with it we also have a
forum site you can go to ask questions a
new replacement for patreon because
patreon imploded we now have our own way
of making pledges that can be used to
support community projects like the
annotated episode guide and the forums
and stuff that are maintained by
community members on a mostly volunteer
basis we try to get the money for their
efforts so you can contribute now using
not patreon using just basic sundial
subscription which is kind of nice and a
lot cleaner actually we have a schedule
bot that tells you when we're going to
be live and an episode guide where we
sort of have this fantastic annotated
thing that may blow is done where you
can kind of go through and search for
topics you want to learn more about and
it'll jump you right to the episodes
where those things occur so definitely
check all that out the contribution page
is is something I put up just this
weekend so it's still kind of in beta if
you have any trouble with it please let
me know so I can fix it
and make it smoother for people again
it's a replacement for patreon so that
people don't have to use patreon anymore
since the consensus was that it had kind
of imploded all right that's it I will
be back next week for some more lighting
coding until then everyone thanks for
joining me and I will see y'all on the
Internet
take it easy everybody