hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we have a off-topic
stream today by way of apology I
realized I did an off topic stream
yesterday because I wanted to talk a
little bit about broken shaders in unity
games and for pixel art and how you
would fix them if you were making unity
game for example and had access to the
shaders
we tried maybe to go actually fix them
ourselves but we found that Nvidia is n
site tool actually doesn't let us edit
compiled shaders so we aren't really
able to inject our shaders without doing
a little more craziness which we didn't
really want to get into so but that's
what we did yesterday and I realized
that that was pretty rude to do and I
apologize because we had had a standing
request for zr i zi on the chat about
doing an explanation of how skin
domesticating works they'd been asking
for that for a while and i was like when
we get a break we'll do it and then i
went and did something that i wanted to
talk about without even thinking about
that so I apologize I don't think 0zi is
with us today but I'm sure he'll watch
the vodkas he's been asking for this so
we will cover skin meshes today and then
we'll go back to regular or handmade
hero programming next time so first let
me say that this is kind of a nice
change which is to say that this is
actually a topic that I have a ton of
professional experience with you know
there's only so many things in in a game
programming career that you've really
spent like you know months of time
working on particular problems and other
things you maybe have experience with
but they're not necessarily a specialty
as far as skinned meshes are concerned I
mean I spent I guess four to five years
at rad game tools literally just doing
skinned mesh character animation
technology both the export side and the
run
side so it's something that I have a lot
of experience doing and so I am happy to
go into how it all works because I feel
like unlike some topics where I have to
give a disclaimer where I'm like I don't
really know that much about this we
should probably go take a look at an
expert's thing in this case I think I
can probably give you a pretty complete
explanation of at least the initial set
now one of the things that you have to
remember about 3d mesh getting is it's
kind of there's a set of core things
that you have to understand about it and
that's what we'll go over today and then
there's a lot of things on top of it
that you may or may not want to be aware
of depending on what your goals are and
what you're actually trying to
accomplish with it you know are you
Pixar are you trying to give character
or animators a lot of stuff to work with
that has to do with pose and new
traditional animation techniques that
sort of thing
do you have an infinite amount of time
well not infinite my time but do you
have a substantial amount of time to
render a given frame so you're thinking
about things beyond just you know the
the things that can happen at 60 frames
a second so we'll try to mention what
some of those technologies are with the
caveat that they are changing all the
time
so every year I mean this is what
SIGGRAPH and stuff and euro graphics
oftentimes are focused on in there you
know animation character animation mesh
getting papers they are new advances
trying to make better tools for doing
this sort of stuff and so we will cover
today thus all the core stuff that you
will need to know to get yourself
started on character animation with mesh
skinning and then you will have to
decide where you want to go from there
because there's no way to give a
complete description of all the rest of
it because not only is it changing all
the time but there are many different
paths you might go down so as you might
expect this is going to be a very
blackboard heavy
the episode so let's just dive in and
talk about it so here we are this is
introduction to mesh skinning and I'm
gonna talk primarily about 3d mesh
beginning but 3d mesh gaming is sort of
a superset of 2d sprite skinning and so
if you know how to do 3d mesh getting
you also know how to do 2d sprite
skinning so if you are someone who wants
to learn how to make like bone based
models for 2d graphics that allow them
to warp around you can also use all the
same things I'm talking about here for
that by just eliminating Z literally
there isn't really anything else to it
there are some specific things you care
about when you're doing 2d mesh skinning
but maybe you don't need to know as much
about for for 3d mesh getting that are
like specific to how things may be like
overlap in sprite space because you know
if you're not doing real 3d you might
not know some of those things but for
the most part all of the math is the
same alright so let's start with the
basis for 3d graphics that everyone has
learned or should have learned before
they come to this introduction because
I've got to start somewhere so if we're
talking about introduction in mesh
canang I'm assuming that you understand
a basic transform okay now a basic
transform is something that's like intro
in any 3d thing we've covered it on
handmade hero so you can go look at it
if you want to know about it by using
the search tools on handmade hero dot
org slash watch and so I expect you'll
know what I'm talking about when I draw
like a coordinate frame like this oops
so you going up there when I draw a
coordinate frame like this and say that
we can write a transform that takes a
basic coordinate system like this one
from some orientation that is considered
a like a rest pose or a neutral modeling
pose around which we build something
some kind of
aybe right built out of vertices and
triangles or really whatever you want as
long as there are points involved that
we can talk about in this space I expect
that you'll understand what I mean when
we say we have a transform that can go
from here this coordinate system to this
coordinate system right and so you
expect to be able to transform the
coordinate system and have all of the
points go with it and we've done this on
handmade here oh and again we typically
write these as matrices so you might see
me right oftentimes on handmade here oh
that like a new point right which is a
point in this face is equal to whatever
the point was in this space times some
matrix which is in the way right this
matrix T transforms these points in this
order to you know the new points that
you're going to use and you see us do
this on handmade here all the time and
again there's nothing magical about a
matrix and I just want to underscore
that again
they're not magical you don't have to
treat them like a black box in fact
there's an entire episode I'm sorry
there's a higher lecture on my website
how to open a black box that talks about
why you don't have to think of matrices
as a black box
but these matrices are just vector
components or you know they're numbers
we understand if you look at a matrix
right typically they're four by four and
if you look at a matrix you can read off
the components by breaking them into
some structured things the ones we
typically look at they typically look
like this and what you'll see is the
first three components going down right
in the first column of the matrix this
is the new x-axis so this vector here
goes here this vector here goes here and
this vector here goes here
okay the location of the origin so where
the vectors emanate from which is
normally 0 0 0 in the resting position
you know I will often refer to this as
the rest
position because we need something to
differentiate this origin from the one
that we're actually drawing so we have
the rest position and then sort of like
the drawing position sometimes this is
called like world's face right where I'm
trying to put the thing but it doesn't
have to be world space it could be
anything we're doing we have some sort
of source which is the rest and then we
have some destination which is whatever
we're actually generating anyway this
point in space goes here and then the
bottom is zero zero zero one now if you
don't understand why this is again it's
a very simple homogeneous transform the
ink I shouldn't put P there this is like
the the origin so let me just put like o
or something for origin high because I
was using P for the point so I apologize
I'm dad with math naming I I never
picked good letters and again a simple
just review of how matrices work if in
here we're talking about some kind of
transform and I have some source point
which I'm calling P here I have a px py
PZ and then a traditionally we put a one
in here that's for using what are called
homogeneous coordinates or 4x4 matrices
where you're encoding only three
dimensions that extra dimension is to
allow you to do that affine movement to
allow you to move things around again
outside the scope of this I just want to
make sure you understand all this if you
don't understand anything any particular
part of this doesn't ring a bell to you
you should go back to some of the
episodes in Hammond here where we talk
about it or go to look at your favorite
introductory 3d textbook they will cover
this this is just the basic stuff so
this is all stuff you need to or you be
familiar with but anyway point being
when points come in here the way they
multiply these out is very
straightforward if you do the matrix
math you will see that PX multiplies the
x coordinate so you end up with PX x
plus py multiplies the why do i PZ
multiplies the Z Z and the origin just
gets added on because it multiplies this
right so this is the I don't know
position of the origin I need to give it
some name that stands out I don't know
it's bad to say P uh I I don't know what
to tell you we'll figure out some better
names later you should
understand this basic transform it's
very very simple the elements of the
vector multiply the elements in the
matrix such that they pull through these
axes right XY and Z and you can see
exactly what this is doing I'm going px
along the x axis I'm doing py along the
y axis I'm doing PZ along the z axis and
so wherever I had worked myself out to
before in the rest position I am working
myself out to the same exact position
just in a new coordinate frame that's
been placed somewhere in the world very
very straightforward when you think
about it in terms of these components
get yourself comfortable with this by
either reading up on it or watching old
episodes of handmade hero because that
is the one major part of what we need to
talk about today so you need to be
comfortable with it get comfortable with
it now the other thing you need to be
comfortable with is the linear blend and
I said on the handmade hero I think I
said at some point go with the box there
I think I said it Hammond here at one
point they're sort of like this concept
of of desert island code like you know
they always say like you gonna stuck on
a desert island like which which three
albums do you take with you to listen to
because you got a pick like the three
you're gonna really rely on so if you
had to take three you know pieces of
code with you to a desert island or
something I don't know
these pieces of math let's say the
linear blend is kind of one that I think
should make the top three for any game
programmer because it's such a
cornerstone operation matrix transform
for points is probably another one so
you're talking about two of the big ones
here they are heavily leaned on to do
mesh Kinning so linear blend you've got
to be comfortable with it what is it
well a linear blend is just a way of
saying one of two ways of thinking about
it and I'll show you both of them
they're very simple the one we typically
encounter most often is the concept of a
ramp between two values essentially and
so for example I might have a T
parameter
right which is the blend amount and it
ranges from zero to one inclusive so it
can be zero it can be one or it can be
any floating-point number in between
those two and then we write the equation
1 minus T times some value plus T times
some other value equals the blended
version right and so you know this is
maybe a point or something whatever
we're blending I don't know what these
are they could be anything literally
anything that admits a linear
combination so points matrices pixels
whatever you want this equation is a
thing that goes from A to B as T goes
from 0 to 1 so if these were points in
space and this was a and this was B then
if T is equal to 0 you have 1 minus T
which is 1 times a so that's just a plus
0 times B which means I have no I've
gone nowhere I've just stayed at a if I
put one into the equation I have 1 minus
1 which is 0 right so no a plus 1 times
B which is just B so at at one I'm at B
and anywhere in between I am a
combination of the two so point five
point five you know if T is 0.5 I get
point five here and point five here I'm
right in the middle if T is 0.25 I get
point seven five here which means I'm
about that close to a 0.25 here right so
by setting T to some proportion I get a
linear movement between these two points
or to anything colors doesn't matter all
right so these two fundamental concepts
to graphics programming in general the
basic transform of things in 3d space by
using 4x4 matrices or if you didn't want
to use matrices even just this equation
the idea that we have three axes x y&amp;z
that describe an orientation in space
and then some basis to put them around
like a point in space that forms the new
origin
and then we're taking input points in a
some source space and reinterpreting
them to move them this equation and this
equation are core now I said there's two
ways to think about this and this is by
by moving to the second way of thinking
of a linear blend that's how we'll sort
of start ourselves into our mesh canang
topic ok
so another way to think of a linear
blend is to think of it as something
that doesn't just involve a single
scalar value that moves me between two
things ok so what I'd like to introduce
today is the notion of convex linear
blending now what I mean by convex
linear blending is I mean to say that
rather than thinking about a T value
that ranges from 0 to 1 and that gives
us a way of moving between two points a
and B I'd like to talk about the concept
that for any collection of things we can
create an equation that always gives us
something that that will result in a
answer a blend that is inside the set of
inputs we give it right so if you think
about that original linear blend 1 minus
T times a plus T times B and we think
about what these points are and maybe
you know let me start to write this a
little more formally so that we can kind
of get I can try to rectify my problem
from earlier so I'm at where I always
named things poorly let's say that we've
got p 0 1 minus T times B 0 and then I
want to add P 1 and then I want to get
my p prime which is the resulting point
let's actually start to talk about the
math try to be a little bit more
specific about it because this is
supposed to be giving you the
fundamental basis you can use to
understand these things this is the same
equation we wrote before if I drew it
out I would have p 0 here right I would
have P 1 here and then this line between
them is everywhere that P Prime
could appear by setting T equal to
something between zero and one right now
it's crucial to understand that this
already creates a convex linear blend we
have created a convex region we have
created an enclosed region it happens to
have no area but it is a line and no
matter what we do we will never move
outside of it T zero to one will always
four disappoint that's inside of it now
we can and oftentimes again we will call
this interpolation right you hear that
interpolated interpolation why because
we are inside the two sample points that
we're given we're given p 0 and P 1 we
are interpolating right now we could
extrapolate right this is totally
possible how would we do it like this
that's the worst infinity sign I've ever
drawn no it's not probably doing the
worst one by letting T range from
negative infinity to infinity right
giving it the entire range it can do
anything it wants we would start to move
beyond these two points but still along
the line so rather than a convex linear
blend or an interpolated linear blend we
are creating something that allows us to
go outside of our sample point right we
are creating something that is not
contained within the shape originally
implied in this case a line segment
between our points right so if for
example I set it to negative 1 I would
end up with something that was out here
at negative like whatever this vector is
that you want to call P 1 minus p 0 I
would end up with the negative version
of that vector taking me out to the
blend if I call it let's give this a
name let's call this our f of T right
our F of negative 1 is all the way out
here at the negative of that vector
because if one moves me to here negative
1 moves me to here because it is linear
motion so we expect it to
always move the same distance for any
size of T that is equal if I move it
plus two I expect it to move the same
distance as negative two right if I go
from 0.5 to one that should be the same
distance as 0 to 0.5 because as long as
I go the same distance in T I should go
the same distance in space and that is
why we say linear blending right that's
the linear in linear blending if this
were nonlinear if there were squared
terms in here if T appeared as a power
other than just linear right just to the
first then would be a nonlinear blend
right it would be a blend that does not
move the same amount for a linear change
in T linear changes in T produce linear
changes in space nonlinear changes in T
would produce nonlinear changes in space
but that we wouldn't call that nonlinear
blending really because again we're just
the blend is still linear we're non
linearly changing T right but just to
point out there is such a thing as
nonlinear blending and that is when
these values appear squared 4 cubed or
any other power in the blend equation
itself because then a linear change in T
translates into a nonlinear change in
space hopefully that makes some clear
sense to you ok so what I'd like to do
is introduce the concept of the convex
linear blend as a more general form of
this equation and that will get us into
mesh skinning if I wanted to look at
this more broadly I could say well you
know what is this actually doing where
did I get this notion of 1 minus T plus
T and could I think of that more broadly
and the answer obviously is yes if I
just start to think of this as a sum of
terms where those terms have certain
constraints I can start to form a more
Universal way of thinking of a convex
linear blend where I can get more
interesting results more interest more
power out of the same I
gyah without doing any more work okay so
what is this actually amount to let me
rewrite this equation as c0 which is
going to be equal to one minus T and c1
which is going to be equal to T what
does that make this equation well one
minus T is just c0 so that's times p0
plus T is just c1 so I have P one here
and then I get my result right c0 p 0
plus C 1 P 1 equals P Prime
okay same exact equation all I have done
is replace these terms with different
names I just named them something else I
said C 0 is 1 minus T C 1 is T same
equation does the same thing I input
some value T I produce these two results
and I get my blend now why would I want
to do that
well hopefully you can see the obvious
step coming next what if I just said
well forget this let's just talk about
arbitrary numbers I can multiply by p 0
and P 1 to equal P Prime suppose I
didn't know about 1 minus T and T in the
first place right suppose I didn't know
well if I said I wanted to produce some
kind of equation where C 0 and C 1
multiplied p 0 and P 1 in such a way
that they produced a point like I was
doing and I didn't know about 1 minus T
and T as being the magic way to set them
so that I always got things in between
them right so P prime here's p 0 here's
P 1 right what would I have done to
figure that out right like how would I
have figured out that that's what I
wanted to do right what was it that was
guiding me to produce this T 1 minus T
thing in the first place and if we
understood that deeper idea would we be
able to produce something more powerful
than the simple version that just moves
us between the two points right and so
the answer is that
these these right here actually come
from a more systemic way of looking at
these components in a summed vector
equation like this it comes specifically
from a thing called norms which I've
talked about on handmade hero before and
what norms are is there a way of looking
at a series of parameters such that you
get certain results out of them when or
it's certain ways of measuring them and
certain ways of unifying them with those
measurements right and so let's talk
about one you actually know probably
intuitively already and then one you
might not actually know you've probably
seen it before but maybe you haven't
thought about it on handmade hero if
you've watched the whole thing then you
do know about these because I've already
talked about them but we'll what kind of
ease into it because people probably
will watch this stream stand alone as
opposed to as part of the series okay so
let's talk about Euclidean norms so what
we've got when we talk about vectors in
space right in a standard coordinate
system that's Euclidean which is pretty
much all we use in basic graphics right
3d 2d when you're not talking about
solves or rotations and stuff like that
you're typically talking about Euclidean
spaces for points in 3d space what we
tend to do is we tend to always just
have known from when we started the
concept that you know we've got some
vectors you know like I've got a vector
here and you know I've got some point or
something so I've got a vector say V and
that vector will actually you know what
let's just let's call something else
I've got a vector a and that vector in
space goes from the origin to some
location typically is what we think of
as a displacement or something but we
also can talk about the vector as itself
pretty simply by saying things like it
has a length right like my vector a
actually has a length which is typically
written like this and that length is the
distance along the line you would have
to go if you were walking in that
direction and you wanted to go from the
origin to the end point
right there's like a distance here right
and this length is equal to that
distance okay now we think of those as
distance the length of the vector that
sort of thing but it's really actually
computed you know obviously by the
Pythagorean theorem which you all know
which is ax squared plus ay Y squared
Square rooted right is going to be equal
to this distance right the D and why is
that the case well it's the Pythagorean
theorem right here
we know that ax is this we know that a Y
is this
we know the Pythagorean theorem says
that ax squared plus ay Y squared oops
equals what every one cost length of a
squared yeah so if I want to know my
length of a let me write that as length
of a if I want to know my length of a we
square root this term here and we get
the foot familiar equation that everyone
knows for the length of a vector but
this length of a vector even though I
don't know that Pythagoras probably knew
about it because he was sort of blazing
a trail so I feel like norms kind of got
introduced afterward the Euclidean to
norm is actually this this equation here
the ax squared plus ay Y squared Square
rooted it's actually something called
the Euclidean to norm to norm is what we
call it when we square each term and
then square root it the two is the
square and square root and I can write
the concept of a norm more directly as
saying that my norm of the power I don't
know I don't want to use P norm of it's
gonna be a theme I'm bad at naming them
norm of and let's say well that's even
worse god I hate naming things norm of
gee I don't know norm of G so the
Euclidean norm for some number is just
equal to the
some of all of your terms in the vector
so however long it is right if I've
2-dimensional it's - its equal to the
gia througt of each of those raised to
the g power and this goes on for however
many terms the vector you have if I have
a x a y AZ aw blah blah blah blah blah
right these would all appear here to the
G power summed G rooted okay
the two norm is the one we're most
familiar with intuitively because it is
the length of the vector and what the
two norm does is it tells you how long
the vector is if you went along it the
hypotenuse of this triangle
but there's another norm there's in fact
an infinite number of norms anything you
plug in here so norm two is the length
of the vector but norm one what is that
well we know how to produce it right
norm one is a one throat which is
nothing right that just goes away and
then everything to the 1 power first
power and that goes away so if I take ax
to the 1 plus ay Y to the 1 1 rooted
what do I get
well I just get ax plus ay Y right and
that's it now if you were a math pendant
which I'm not I wish I was it's handy to
know a lot of math you would probably
know whether or not these are
traditionally absolute valued or not I
want to say that they are so I want to
say that traditionally the norm is
written like this so the 1 power removes
the sign but I don't really know that
that's true so I'm not gonna state that
strongly here one way or the other
that's for math people to know so I'm
gonna say that they aren't right now
because the 1 power itself doesn't
necessarily imply that so let's just say
for now that the one norm doesn't do
that but
I would encourage you to talk to a more
math person I would talk to you I would
encourage you to go look up the math
there if you want to know the actual
real answer for our purposes it won't
matter because we want to just be able
to understand both whichever one we want
that makes okay
so coming back to what we wanted to know
here well we've got ax plus ay Y is the
Euclidean 1 norm we know that the 2 norm
tells us this right the length of a what
does the 1 norm tell us well what is ax
plus ay why it's walking out this far
and then walking out this far it's the
route along the outside of the triangle
formed right so the 2 norm gives us this
the 1 norm gives us this entire distance
it's the Manhattan distance as we
sometimes call it of the vector right so
you know we've got this is as the crow
flies you could say if I have to write
norm of 1 is the Manhattan distance norm
of 2 is the crow distance right so using
these two norms we can actually think in
a more systemic way about which of these
things we want to talk about we can
calculate the the crows 5 distance by
doing norm - we can do the Manhattan
distance by doing norm 1 which is the
sum of the sides right if that makes
sense ok so why did I want to go down
that digression well it wasn't a
digression it was how we explained this
in order to produce the original 1 minus
TT blend equation what we were trying to
do here right is we were trying to make
it so that we always produced
values that lie between p0 and p1 and by
taking the Euclidean 1 norm of the
weights if you will of the of the
coefficients on p0 and p1 we were
essentially trying to say how do we
produce a coherent equation that allows
us to always produce a convex blood
between them and let me show you how
that works so if you want to make sure
that your Manhattan distance is 1 right
if I want to make sure that I've always
got a distance of 1 when I go along the
length of my vector again we all have
learned how to do this from working on
our our 3d stuff we know that if we take
the crows fly's distance right if we
take the length of the vector we can
always divide the vector by that value
and get a unit vector right we know this
we do it all the time why does that work
because this has a length of whatever
the length is right this has a length of
the length of a this is the length of a
if I divide something with the length of
a by the length of a I get a length of 1
right it's because vector math
distributes to its components so if each
of the components get multiplied by
something that's exactly how much less
you get in the in the the squared sum
right so normalization to the two norm
we know what will happen the two norm
dividing by the two norm produces a 2
norm of one because what a surprise you
divide the components by whatever the
two norm value is you get a two norm of
one out the other end the same is true
of dividing by the one norm a over the
two norm I'll write that like this norm
two of a so I can pass a n so norm 2 of
a ranked over a this equals a unit
vector but a over the one norm right
that equals a sum of one
it's just this before was Pythagorean
theorem some to one right it rooted
equals one this year is just the term
sum to one so this means ax plus ay Y
dot that dot however many you have I
guess equals one right
it allows me to make all of these things
sum to one and how do I do that well
exactly the same way I did it here right
I compute the norm and then I divide the
components of a by that norm again super
simple it means I take a and divide it
by ax plus ay y plus however many of
that components it has right so this is
just a long-winded mathematical way of
introducing you to all of these concepts
that are helpful to kind of know where
they come from but it comes back down to
understanding where this basic idea came
from it was the one norm how did I get
this let's look at it now and start to
pull it apart okay so I am wondering how
one might arrive at these well if I was
to just say that I have a vector right
of these a vector C and its components
are C 0 and C 1 so I'm talking about the
two weights I'm gonna use in the
equation here oops so I'm talking about
this where I've got you know Caesar and
C 1 and I want to know what would I do
you know if I wanted to produce a
version of this equation that's always
going to give me something in between p0
and p1 right so it should always lie
along this line okay well if I was to
take the 1 norm of C 0 and C 1 right if
I was to take the 1 norm of this vector
so norm 1 of C what would I get right I
would get C 0 plus C 1 right that's the
winner so if I just had any two values
that I placed in here you know who knows
what they were there was something I
don't know what they were there were any
values you gave me for C 0 and C 1 and I
wanted to turn it into something that
fell into the comics one let's do a one
normalization on it right let's do the
one normalization on it that means I
divide C by the one norm this is the one
norm I'm dividing C by the one norm what
will I get
well I'll get C zero over C 0 plus C one
right and C one over C 0 plus C 1 I mean
that's the new vector right and what do
I know about this new vector I know that
it always has to sum to 1 you can see
this trivially by inspection if I add
these two terms together not knowing
what their components are or anything
else about them you can see that they
both have the same denominator so they
would add directly on top and C 0 plus C
1 over C 0 plus C 1 is 1 right so we
know that that actually happens ok so
now what we could say is look if we
wanted to simplify these equations down
a little bit and say how would we write
1 in terms of the other all right we've
got a we've got a post situation
Molly beam Molly no no we're right in
the middle we're right in the middle of
a of a blackboard session baby you got
to wait a little bit all right I think
the post wants to play but we're gonna
have to finish what we're doing here
first ok so if we know that these things
sum to 1 right and by the way if we look
at what what happens here if we look at
what we were talking about with our
original blend equation what's the 1
norm of these well 1 minus T plus T
right is just 1 minus T plus T the T is
cancel and you get 1 right so you can
see already that that 1 minus T and T
satisfy the 1 norm equation already
right they are a simplified version of
that but if we wanted to try and get
these values more simplified let's see
how we might do it and again I'm always
a little weak on the mass Oh
you'll have to forgive me if I if I felt
a little bit no matter how much I work
with this stuff I've it always falls out
a little bit but anyway so c0 over C 0
plus C 1 and C 1 plus C 0 over C so
let's say I wanted to create some new
equations here that are just based on
B's c0 over c0 plus c1 c1 over C 0 plus
C 1 right so if we took a look at these
equations here right and we were to say
alright I'm trying to make some new
versions and what I want to do is I want
to rewrite this so that it's only in
terms of 1 you know one variable right I
want to create something that satisfies
these properties but such that I won't
ever actually have to put in two random
values and then do the simplification
right so if I was to do some
multiplication out on these guys here
actually I don't know if this is really
gonna work I may skip that part because
I probably would have to think about how
to do the substitution and I don't want
to get bogged down in that yet so
suffice to say if I was more on top of
my math game right now I would probably
be able to show you how you easily do
the substitutions that reproduce the 1
minus TT here to get to here as opposed
to just pointing out the fact that
obviously this is the simplification of
these equations that produce one
variable which can all twich always
result in something pre set up for
normalizing to the 1 norm right but you
can see that behavior in the 1 minus TT
and that is the crucial property of
these equations that actually make it
always stay inside where it actually
started the p 0 p 1 it is specifically
the norm one of these C values it is the
fact that they are normalized to the one
norm that keeps them inside between p0
and p1 now why does that happen
like what is it that makes that what is
it makes the one norm special as far as
summing things together well if you
think of
out a slight change of basis I can give
you a more intuitive understanding of
why that works let's suppose that the
origin was here right so p0 is that
vector and p1 is that vector and the
origin is right in the middle right well
what do I know about the space that I
can span using these two displacements
right well if I was to assign any
particular values to c0 and c1 what I
know is that they always have to sum to
1 right so I can never get a value
I could never get a vector larger than
say this or this because I can never
make more than 1 multiplied by 0 p1
right so I have in this direction I can
only ever get out to p0 because I can't
set it greater to 1 or I'd violate the 1
norm just with p0 right and when I'm
heading out in this direction I can
never I could never set P ones
coefficient anything higher than 1
because I violated the one norm there as
well right and again I should say I'm
talking a little bit more about the
absolute value version of the one norm
because technically I could set the
weights on c0 to something negative
which would offset the amount of p1 and
so on right so let's you know I don't
really want to talk about weights that
are negative just yet so let's keep for
our intuition these are just positive
coefficients right now but we can talk
about negative ones a little bit later
all right
so I can't really ever get out of this
cage right from where I start because I
can never get further away now you may
ask well what if the origin was over
here right and so p0 was there like and
p1 is here why can't I get you know why
can't I get somewhere that's that's you
know closer in why does it always stay
on this line right and the answer is
because every time I try to detract to
get backwards from p1 I have to add the
equivalent extra amount of p0 into some
to one which means that I'm always
gradually getting closer to p0 as I go
since I know this is a linear equation
it can't bow in because that would be a
curve so the only way
to go directly from p0 to p1 if the
weights can never dip below one as a sum
and I know that one puts me here for c0
and c1 of one puts me here right there's
no other route it can take a linear
equation can't take another route
because it's linear so I can't curve and
so the only thing that makes me smoothly
go between those two if I force the
weights to sum to one has to be a line
so I know that I'm stuck between my two
points I can't get inside I can't get
outside specifically because I have
constrained these two values to always
sum to one and that is the constraint of
the one norm this is the simplified
version of the equation but I can just
use this equation where I just do the
I'm sorry this equation where I just put
in any two values I want and then I
normalize them by their sum okay all
right hopefully that made some sense I
never know what I'm talking if I'm
making any sense to anybody because
these are just the way I think about
things they may not be ways that make
sense to you so I apologize so now let's
talk about the multi point blend this is
the foundation of Nets mesh jimang mesh
skinning so hopefully you will
understand why I had to motivate it by
talking about all of these sort of one
norms blends blah blah right multi point
blending is the idea that I may want a
lot more points p0 p1 p2 p3 what am i
doing going clockwise who goes clockwise
let's go counterclockwise all right
if I was to set up some arbitrary number
of points in this case I've done a
Pentagon but it could be any number of
points if I want to create a multi-point
blend and I want to know that it is a
convex multi-point blend meaning I stay
within the boundaries that I am provided
right I can apply the same thing we just
did for two points to any number of
points right and all the same thing
applies so if I want to extend my notion
of those coefficients out to five I just
have five values in my coefficient
vector for my five points right I have C
0 p 0 plus C 1 P 1 thought the dot C 4 p
4 right and all I have to do to ensure
that I stay inside you know where I'm
going here is to make sure that these
values sum to 1 because the exact same
thing applies no matter where the origin
is if I equal 1 on any of these points
I'm at the point right I know that
because everybody else has to be 0
that's the requirement of sum to 1 so if
I'm if I'm doing this right if I've
divided all of my weights by their sum
by their 1 norm right if I've divided
all the weights by the 1 norm I know
that if any one of these values is 1 the
rest have to be 0 so I'm gonna
definitely be at one of my points and
any minut change has to increase my
motion towards one of the other points
because if I was to ever decrease my
contribution to P Zero I must put that
contribution towards some other point
right it has to go towards it
because I can't drop any of these values
negative like I sing for him I'm
enforcing absolute value here not
absolute diamond I'm forcing greater
than zero here for purposes of our
discussion so I have to move towards say
p1 or I have to move towards p3 or a
combination of P 3 and P 2 right but I
can't ever regress away from the shape
that I've created everything I do must
stay inside it hopefully that makes some
intuitive sense to you now after we've
looked at it a little bit more so this
means we can now form our general blend
equation which is very simple very very
simple now you've seen the underlying
parts of it all we really have to do is
say that we have some set of
coefficients that we're gonna multiply
some set of inputs by and that is pretty
much the end of the story right so let's
write this out in the way that we tend
to do it in Mexican Aang and then I can
show you the mesh getting equations so
typically what we do is we say we have a
weight vector now coefficient I think is
better I would probably prefer to have
you see for this like I did above I
think it makes more sense with the math
and it also unifies it a little bit more
with b-spline blending and stuff like
that where typically you think of the
knot weights as being a vector of C but
just to give you some familiarity with
how they're often written in the
literature and how often we talk about
them game programming I will say that a
weight vector which is our C vector from
before is oftentimes written as double
use and you saw me kind of introduced
that briefly up above so I don't care
which letter you use I'll start using W
now we used C before I'm gonna use those
interchangeably because you kind of want
to know both us if you're in spline land
and doing non linear interpolation you
see this if you're in matrix multiply
linear waiting land you tend to see W
you need to just know both of them are
used for weights there's not a lot of
science to it
just what happens alright so you can
either think of it oops as C equals C 0
C 1 C 2 C 3 about the BA or you can
think of it as W equals W 0 W 1 W 2 W 3
they're just two names for the same
thing a vector of coefficients we're
going to use for a blend some kind right
so what we have in the basic
introduction blending equations is just
our final point is always equal to w0
times p0 plus w1 times P oops p1 plus
dot dot plus W n times P n for any
number of inputs that gives us a set of
P's right so we have our set of points
that's our P P n equals our set of
points right and we have WN equals our
set of weights these are the fundamental
concepts of blending extremely safe
straightforward a set of scalar numbers
0.5 0.2 0.2 whatever 0.1 and a set of
input points these input points can
represent anything linearly combine
about they can be vectors points colors
I don't care anything right anything
that emits a linear combination as
written here where I can multiply them
by a value and then some
so F mad right a floating point multiply
addition if you can do that with this
thing then we're in business okay and
this is the fundamental equation for
blending you should always be familiar
with and always mapping things back to
in your head as we talked about mesh
Kinning which is gonna be really
anti-climatic now because we've
basically covered the entire thing I
know it sounds a little bit weird that's
actually it if you understand this and
you understand the Euclidean 1 norm
normalization that allows us to produce
a
UN that is always convex you pretty much
know mesh canang and I'm not gonna have
to tell you very much
going forwards so what is mesh giving
well mush skinning was an attempt to
solve a problem and the problem is what
do you do if you don't want your objects
to be disjoint when you transform them
all right so let's suppose I wanted to
make an arm and I want an elbow and I
want it to bend well in early computer
graphics all we could do right and I'll
draw this in 2d but it works the same 3d
is something like this
here's the upper arm here's the forearm
and you know the hand would be out here
somewhere and this is the elbow joint
now it's 3d graphics I already sent the
beginning should be comfortable the
basic transform we know what these basic
transforms are right we can create a
bone structure and basically say hey
there's a coordinate system right here
there's another coordinate system right
here and we just transform the upper arm
geometry by this transform we'll call
that T 0 and we multiply this one
actually let's call it B for bone we'll
call this B 0 right and we'll call this
no I'm gonna call T 0 we'll call this T
0 right transform it and we'll call this
t1 right well transform the forearm by
that and that's our final shape right
it's the non mesh skinning version it's
the non Myshkin inversion and there's a
big old gap that forms at the elbow
because these are two disjoint shapes as
they get transformed they separate even
if at the beginning I modeled them
together right like this then when this
rotates up you can see that a gap forms
here and
interpenetration forms here right so
what I wanted to have happen back in the
old days when this was a problem what
you wanted to have happen was to have
the mesh be continuous through that
elbow joint right so what I wanted to do
was when I was doing this what I wanted
to do was just have this be one mesh
right I didn't want there to be a
separation here I wanted these vertices
to be shared right so what I could do at
the start is something a little bit
simpler than mesh skinning what I could
do is say well I don't really have to
separate these geometrically I could
just assign these two vertices as part
of the upper arm and just reuse the
vertices I'm sorry as part of the lower
arm or upper arm my choice really but I
could reuse them in both sides so when I
draw the upper arm geometry and the
lower arm geometry right I can just
share these vertices and then what will
happen is there's no gap when this
starts to bend upward like this
I just whichever one I assigned it to
let's say I assigned it here right
here's where they would have transformed
under each transform let's say I picked
this one right so these are both there
and there I now just draw this as my
mesh right easy peasy
that prevents the gap from forming but
if you look at what happens here this as
this arm straightens out collapses
entirely right so my mesh now gets this
super super collapsed arm right can you
see what I'm talking about here because
if we just map this to one or the other
as I start here right let's look at the
two cases so one case is I get that
right
so my mesh now becomes this right
there's my elbow not a very good looking
elbow right
that's if I assigned them to the upper
arm or the lower arm rather sorry and if
I do the opposite if I assign them this
way then I get this
right still really really bad so I get
the same pinch I just decide where it
goes not really acceptable for animation
purposes right okay so there are two
ways of addressing this problem and they
both are actually equivalent there's
actually an infinite number of ways to
address this problem but there are two
core ways that end up addressing this
problem from the basic set of equations
okay what we want is some way of
producing a more subtle blend between
these two because if we were to look at
the two super positions here or rather
if we were to look at a superposition of
these two sets right and let me try is
gonna be a little bit difficult let me
try to draw the overlay for you of the
two of these here is my coordinate
system here is my bone structure here is
one of my meshes that I could have here
is the other one I could have right then
if we were to look at what we have
produced after our blend we know after
our transforming of all of the points in
all of the systems right we know we've
got this part of the mesh covered we
know we've got this part of the mesh
covered so the question is just how do
we produce two points here that aren't
awful this is not good and this is not
good either but what about some
combination of these and the answer is
if we were to maybe take this right
maybe we could produce something that
wasn't quite so bad right this ends up
being a pretty reasonable elbow it blows
in a little bit right more than we might
want but so does your elbow who to a
certain extent
um not really the the fat kind I usually
built is out here but that is much
better than that which was almost
collapsed or equivalently the other
version which was at right
I may have connected those wrong but
point being this is a more preferable
result it's still not perfect and we'll
talk about what would be perfect later
on when we talk about sort of the next
steps after basic mesh skinning that
would be nice right it would be
acceptable and usable as opposed to the
other one which is not can you see from
the diagram where I'm going with this
what is this line here between these two
right does it look familiar does it look
like something we maybe just talked
about
it sure does right it looks a heck of a
lot like this original equation doesn't
it where these are constrained to be
normalized to the one norm right that's
that line right I mean you can see it
you can see it coming out can't you
before I even show you I mean you can
see that that's where we're going so
let's do it
what do we need to do to make that
happen well previously right when we
transform stuff in computer graphics I
told you this at the beginning of the
stream right we've got some transform
that we're gonna transfer on these
things by it's that's not a P one that's
a P Prime to produce our point and we're
inputting the point right so that's what
we you know we normally do that's how we
would have produced these positions and
that's how we would have produced these
positions with just normal regular or
old-school computer graphics where you
just have one transform that moves all
your points right and specifically in
this case we have sort of two P Prime's
we were talking about potentially having
depending on where we assigned our
points did we assign two points the
upper arm we sign the lower arm so we
have a P Prime it's a P Prime
let's say upper arm right and that's the
transform of the upper arm times p0 but
we could also do an equivalent transform
for the lower arm P Prime lower and
that's just going to be the lower
transform times p0 right not not
particularly complicated I lower arm
probably bad let's call it forearm
because you can't tell it was between 1
and L right so these two transforms and
transforms we already know we already
know how to transform some point let's
say p0 in our example here you know was
this point here right so we're talking
about it transforming to either here or
here
depending on which one we assign it to
if we assign it to the transform upper
arm it's gonna be here right so this is
transform upper arm times p0 if we
assign it to the lower arm it's going to
be here so this is transform lower our
sorry forearm equal p0 right so you know
we we know we can produce these two
points there just the basic transforms
we would have gotten if we treat
everything as rigid right make sense so
if you look at these two equations what
do you think I'm gonna do right well I
just said look at that line in between
them doesn't it look like this and the
answer is let's just use that equation
let's take our P R to transform points
right which are here and here and let's
just produce a blend between them let's
just blend between them let's just do W
0 times P Prime you write plus W 1 times
P prime F that's our new final P Prime
this right here gives us two control
levers to dial to give us any point that
we want and if we don't want it
wandering all around in here right so if
I want to know if I don't want it out
there or
here right I want it to be right there
let's say in the middle then I know I
can just enforce the Euclidian 1 norm on
these two and I will get something on
this line if I literally use point five
that it would be 0.5 and 0.5 because
that's what sums to 1 and I will
literally get that center point that I
drew that is what I wanted
that's mesh skinning end of story
actually that's pretty much all there is
to it to be completely honest with you
it really doesn't get much more
complicated than that
now there's a ton of advanced topics we
can go into which we will in a second I
just want to cement this home but this
is my skinning that's all it is all it
is is weights that multiply transforms
of things that get transformed in the
space of more than one transform so
you're taking the same point in your
input you're transforming it by more
than one of your bones inside the
character and then you're just
performing a weighted convex blend and
we're gonna talk about non convex lenss
in a second but a weighted convex blend
between the two let's make this a little
bit more concrete by talking about the
entire process as it traditionally
occurs traditionally what happens is you
you know create some humanoid shape
some kind of gingerbread man right we
call this the rest pose somebody models
this in like 3d studio or Maya or
something right and they then create a
skeleton we call it and that is nothing
more than a series of transforms that
line up with where you would typically
put you know the bones or the joints of
a human right guy should have some
longer legs probably right this skeleton
is a set of transforms right each one of
these is a transform and we compute what
those transforms are the way we would
compute any other transforms in 3d
graphics they are not they have nothing
to do with mesh Kinning right so they
are just a series of T 0 T 1 T 2 dot the
top T n each of these T 0 T 1 T 2
whatever right we have a skeleton which
is a series of transforms and then we
have a mesh and that's this sole thing
right and that's how we model a
character actually this is the input
it's the rest pose of both the bones and
the mesh and then what we assign in
addition to the vertices so obviously
all through here all the p0 p1 p2 dot
the dot right so all the vertices all
over the place here those are our points
so then what we want to do is we want to
produce a new version of this for run
time animation that we you know in our
game that we want to draw the character
dancing around or doing whatever
what we want to be able to do is change
these transforms exactly the way we
would if it were just like a robotic
skeleton so they're you know no mesh
canang we just wanted to produce say a
rotation of this thing so it can rotate
upwards you know like this right so it
can bend the elbow like I was doing up
there and what we want is this mesh to
come with it right that's what we want
now the equation is actually just this
at its base but there's an extra element
that has to come in and this may be why
people sometimes get confused I know
back in the day when we were first
working out this math I often
encountered people who didn't understand
this step and there are some really
crazy things that they used to do to get
around it but you you just if you
understand this step you don't have to
do anything crazy it's very simplistic
all you have to do now is you just have
to understand that you need to put
things into the space of the skeleton
first before you take them out of the
space of the skeleton I know that sounds
weird but I'll explain what I mean and
we'll use our elbow example so it's
something you're familiar with right
okay let me say one more thing first
before I swing that so this is the rest
pose this is the input to the system the
output right in the game is an actual
pose right it's something that we want
to render in our game the character
animating the doing something right and
so what we want is we wanted to go from
our rest pose to some other pose you
know of the dude you know running or
something right and we want this whole
mesh to go with it
right so though as this guy's skeleton
runs through the world which is a
separate problem that's like animation
that's a totally different topic right
but as this skeleton animates through
the world mesh skinning is the problem
of how do we make the geometry for the
guy follow the skeleton right that's
what we're doing and so what we want to
do is figure out how do we go from
understanding that this allows us to do
this sort of blended smoother version of
the deformation that occurs if we just
were to assign points directly to bones
right how do we go from that to doing
this exact operation that's what we want
right and so there's only one trick
there's only one thing but you would
have that you have to do to make this
work
that's not obvious from what I just
wrote because otherwise you just do this
literally you just do this right okay so
what's the non obvious part well I said
before we start with the understanding
that let's suppose we just assign
everybody to one particular bone right
that's the non skinned mesh case and if
we assigned every vertex to a particular
bone what do we know about how we would
store that vertex right what do we know
about that well what we know is what I
wrote before this is our fundamental
equation what does it do well it starts
in a rest space right and it transforms
this is the rest face here so maybe at
this point right it transforms one of
our points by whatever the transform
implies right that's this transform
whatever the transfer implies I get the
new point in whatever space
is now in so if I want to take a
skeleton for example if I want to take a
transform that is in rest space in the
pose face of the guy what everyone to
call up the rest space is what I'm gonna
use the rest face that was modeled in
and I want to transform it
I want transform that point out to the
game to the world's face right where I'm
gonna actually draw it well what I know
is that T times peak gives me that if
and only if he was already stored local
to this transform right cuz that's how
we normally did it in graphics we made
our cube or whatever it is centered
around that original transforms point
that original you know zero zero zero
this was zero zero zero this was just
the x y&amp;z world axes right and then when
we applied this T transform we can move
it out from being around the origin of
the world to being somewhere else in the
world and spun right and so if we
assigned every point in our original
mesh to one of these bones what we could
have done what we could have done is
when we wrote this skeleton out when we
took it from the 3d art package and put
it into our data file format is we could
take the inverse of the rest pose right
because remember now we've got a
slightly more complex case here is the
actual origin of our guy it's down here
right here is a point p0 here is a bone
t0 it's transform looks like that in
rest space what can you see immediately
when you look at this diagram it isn't
this equation because P is not stored
relative to this transform P is we want
P to be relative to t0 Eady
it's relative to the rest space the
whatever the space is the modeling space
of this of this mesh right but if we
assigned P zero to one and only one
transform as we used to in the early
days right we can fix this what do we do
we take the inverse of T zero multiply P
Zero by that and store that as our new P
Zero right so what we actually have is
like a PA in T zero space okay this is a
trivial process we can do it on export
we take each individual point in our
mesh we say which of the transforms
which of our bones in the skeleton did
the artist wanted assigned to and we
just do the inverse transform to produce
PT zero once we have that then this
works now at runtime we just do the
actual current T zero times our PT 0
that does give us the correct point and
that does do this operation right
because now we're using a point that is
stored in the original space hopefully
that makes sense again that's nothing
new that's just what you do during
exporting some character if you weren't
doing mesh skinning so forget character
it's just the wheel of a car let's say
right no character involved it's rigid
we don't do any mesh skinning here's the
axis system we need to rotate the wheel
of the car what would we do well we'd
make all of the points of the wheel be
relative to wherever this center of the
wheel is there'd be some transform there
and then we'd spin the transform and the
wheel would spin you all know this if
you know none
skinned meshes right so this is what we
would do for non skinned meshes and we'd
just store everything relative to the
transform that it up that it was
controlled by it's controlling transform
but the problem we get with mesh getting
and the only subtlety the only one is
that we don't have just one bone because
what's
to happen here inside the art tool the
artist is going to sort of paint or
adjust or use envelopes which are sort
of ways of assigning using fields
they're going to generate these right
w0w one right they're gonna generate
these and the problem is if they're
generating these weights w0 w1 we now
need to play those back at run time okay
and what does that look like at run time
we're not gonna be doing that we're not
going to doing that we're gonna be doing
this right we're gonna be doing that
base equation as many times as there are
bones for a particular vertex so if a
vertex was assigned to some weight on
the bone to 0 and some weight on bone t1
we have to do both of these transforms
right well this creates a really nasty
storage problem for us it means that for
every bone we wanted to use and for some
things in like this area of this area or
the face especially there might be two
three four five six even bones blended
together to get a final result it starts
to get a little ugly four bones is not
in a typical number to use as your max
number for example in Mexican Aang even
back in my day in 1999 when we were
doing this stuff it was already four
wasn't not a typical number to use right
so this massively explodes our mesh
storage right because now for every
point we restoring for our mesh before
we have to store four points which is
the transform of that point in the
inverse space of each bone so this thing
we were doing before we do for each
phone if this was T 0 T 1 T 2 and T 3
waited right so we know this point is
weighted to four different bones because
that's what the artist painted then we
have to store inverse of each of these
matrices times the point in question
right we have to store four things for
one input and that's exactly what people
used to do because they didn't think of
anything better right but that's not the
way to do it and you wouldn't do it that
way today cuz you know we know better
and and I knew better at the time too so
I never did that but you know there were
a bunch of people skinning systems that
worked that way in the early days
because they just didn't think of
something better so what's the better
solution there's a much much better
solution much better solution to this
problem and the much better solution is
to not store P transformed at all just
store the points the way they're
originally modeled don't transform them
so don't do the thing we would have done
with the wheel just don't do that
anymore forget it
peas are always stored in the rest post
space completely so it's stored like
this not relative to T zero but relative
to the total origin relative to the same
space in which T zero was was modeled
right so the skeleton and the mesh are
modeled in the same space and stored in
the same space no pre transforms okay
then what we do is we compute the
rebasing at runtime and we can do this
almost for free why can we do it almost
for free well look at what this equation
is actually computing PT zero
what was it well it was W 0 times T zero
the new T zero right and I need to start
differentiating these if I wrote this
out a little bit you know let me let me
just write it out in the full form first
so you can see exactly what I'm talking
about we need to specify our different
things so we need different spaces for
these guys so I'm going to get a gets
nominate or heavy or poor notation heavy
but it's simple in code you just have
different arrays for them right it's not
math gets ugly but code stays simple in
that sense all right so I have
zero in the rest pose okay what is that
that's here is the origin of my
coordinate system here is T zero in the
rest pose okay so that's T zero R I need
to produce a different T 0 T 0 in world
space right and that's just whatever it
has to be if I'm rotating my shoulder if
this was coming up right then T 0 has
rotated upwards but it stayed in one
place if the shoulder is sliding out a
little bit right then it's gonna do that
if it's moving because the guy is moving
then it's gonna do that so I have a rest
pose T art this is what the modeler made
this is what the art staff this is what
the art staff made okay exactly what
they made and this is what's in the game
that we're trying to produce okay and
what I was saying before is the old way
we were doing this right was to say if I
need to store a p0 p0 in our right and I
need to produce p0 in world okay so I'm
gonna start talking about p0 in world
and p0 in our as well
then what I did is I stored an
intermediate value right I store it ap
let's call that P intermediate of 0 and
what I did is I stored the inverse of
the rest matrix this guy times that
input P right so p p0 and the rest pose
times T zeroes in the rest poses inverse
gives me this interim value pti right
and there's we called other things maybe
you could call it PT local I don't know
but I'm gonna call PT I basically PT
interim because we don't actually care
about it and then I was saying well what
we were doing at run time to reproduce
it is saying let's take the T 0 in world
space right and we want to multiply that
by our interim and
that's what's gonna get our p0 in world
space right and this was the equation we
used well what you actually want to do
instead of storing a bunch of these once
you need to do multiple of them is just
look at what this actually computed
right what this actually computed was t0
W sub in this term it equals that we
just said so right it's T rest pose
inverse times p0 are okay now look what
happens when we do the full sub okay we
said before what I wanted to do was
extend to this value so p0 in world
space is going to equal a weight right
some wait times t0 in world space times
p0 internal plus some other thing right
some other weight times some other bone
in world space times its internal
storage right dot doc and what we would
see if we transfer if we substituted all
of the pies with what they actually were
equal to that we just said they were
equal to right is actually whatever the
particular bone you were talking about
whatever its inverse was times the
original PR in rest space same thing
will happen here when I substitute in
now what do you see right you see that
my p0 r is the same P in the whole
equation this eliminates the multi
storage problem right we just stored w's
which is what we would have stored
anyway to say what the weight is we
store the p0 r once not four times four
four bones and then at runtime what we
do is we look at this internal term that
internal term is the T in world space of
any of our of our bones right doesn't
matter which one times the inverse rest
pose of any of our bones this right here
is what I call the composite
a tricks I don't know if it has a real
name right or a composite transform that
right there is the fundamental transform
of any mesh getting operation okay and
what it is it's just the transform that
takes the rest posed location of
something and puts it into the world
posed location of something relative to
a specific bone and I can pick any bone
I want and I never have to store any
additional information right so what we
typically do in a mesh getting pipeline
and this is absolutely crucial to
understand is we prepare the TW set so
this is like an array we do key world
space of 0 T world space 1 T world space
to dot that the dot right we prepare
that as the output from the character
animation system or the skeletal
animation system so this is our skeletal
animation system a topic we're not
covering because that's animation
nothing to do with mesh getting our
skeletal animation system outputs this
array it is the world space location of
the skeleton that's where the skeleton
needs to go right our our asset pipeline
when we exported the model right outputs
a separate array this is just constant
never changes this is the inverse rest
pose of all of the bones right so we
know this because it's in our file we
load it up and we just have it because
it's the inverse precomputed of these
values we know this value because we
just generated from our skeleton
animation system this times this is the
transform right t0w times TR negative TR
0 inverse
right is the final transform or a
composite transform as I call it
oops put it there of any bone so we end
up with our rendering array and that is
t0 W times T 0 R 1 T 1 W times T 1 R
inverse a little block right this is the
final goal of a mesh skinning skeleton
pipeline it is the output of the
skeletal animation system times the
asset pipelines inverse rest pose stored
array that produces a final transform
that is just 2 matrices times each other
for each slot that is our rendering
array once we have this rendering array
we arrive at the final operation of a
mesh gating system and that is the skin
output and it is trivial if we call this
again we just say it's t 0 see the like
composite transform all it is is just a
straight readout of the points P 0 for
any transform we want I sorry for any
point we want is no more than the weight
of matrix 0 times matrix zeroes
composite times the original point in
arrests both rest pose right we sum as
many terms of these as we want we can
support as many bones as we want and do
no more work other than the 1 term right
and we just go out as far as we want
this is mesh skinning this right here is
literally the points that you draw and
that's the end of it so before our even
our 2 hours is up
we're done that's it that's the system
you don't even have to know where these
w0 and w1 s come from honestly because
they come from the art tool the art tool
tells you the weights so the Euclidian
one-arm stuff that I explained before is
just so you understand how this equation
works but you don't even have to know
how to make it because the art too tells
you the W's they tell you the weights
those are the vertex weights of each
vertex now there's a slight complication
in here that's a purely practical we
don't want all cuz I mean there could be
200 bones easily there could easily be
200 bones in a modern game character no
one would bat an eyelash at that we have
the horsepower for it you do not want to
some 200 of these terms in a vertex
shader which is where this is typically
going on for a text assembly typically
goes in a virgin shader why because you
typically want to send the mesh down to
the card and store it local to the card
you don't want to send the points down
each time so you send down the points
with their weights and you then just
send down the bones each frame right
okay so what does this look like well we
don't want to actually do 200 of these
matrix multiplies because what's this
going to be it's a W times the t times
the P right this is an entire matrix
transform that's an entire 4x4 transform
times an actual scaler a lot of F mats
we want to minimize it so typically what
we do is we say look we know that any
given vertex is only going to be
affected by a few bones at most so we
typically say let's give the artist some
fixed number of bones let's say for
right we then store the indices with the
vertex so a vertex typically consists of
its position right its rest position you
know a normal or a tangent frame
whatever we don't care about these color
no throw out those and then finally we
have like something like a u8 or a u 16
depending on how many bones you have
right let's say we have a u 8 which is
just you know an 8-bit value that is the
index and we have four of those and then
typically we'd also have like a you
eight or something very small that is
the weight for right and so then what we
do is we
use these four weights and these four
indices to pull out which bones we want
so we have a constant store in our
vertex shader that has the T C's in it
right
I keep written it wrong right and we
just use these vertex indices we say
take the first index grab whatever
location that says maybe it's this one
multiply it by the first weight we
probably encoded it as like a u8 that's
just like whatever this weight is over
to 55 right and that produces our 0 to 1
value or something right you know who
knows we probably don't need to store
them all because we probably know they
sum to 1 if we want to we can just or
three of them blah blah blah right
there's all kind of stuff you could do
here that's that's minutia ok and that's
all we do we just compute some number of
terms here let's say for we use an index
to say which transforms we want that's
which bones it picks out we use the
weights that the artist specified for
those bones and off we go if the artist
specified more than four bones and we
want to truncate what do we do we get
rid of the lowest weight bones because
they're the ones the artist will notice
missing the least because there's the
least effect on the vertex and then we
renormalize using the Euclidean 1 norm
why that prevents us from ever getting
things that fall outside of the
transform of those points individually
as we saw right everyone cool with that
hopefully hopefully that's all clear
there that is fundamentally how much
skating works that's the end of it right
so I don't think there's really anything
else you need to know to implement mesh
skinning that's it right that's the end
of the story for misgiving but as we
know it's never really the end of the
story right it's never quite the end of
story now why isn't it quite the end of
the story well the reason it's not quite
the end of story is because for all of
the for all of the games that this
concept enabled right it still sucks
[Laughter]
go back to my original diagram I picked
elbows for a reason it's because they
always look crappy as I said Myshkin
gives us something that is better than
we would have had otherwise
it gives us this point oops sorry and
this point which is better than any of
these points okay so it's better but is
it good I mean it's better a lot of game
shift on it
90% of all 3d games probably shift on it
right it's better but is it good okay
and the answer is no it's not very good
right that's not what an elbow looks
like when it bends at all so let's talk
a little bit about what I guess I would
call exercise for the reader which is to
say if you understood everything that I
said so far you're in a good position to
go implement your first mesh skinning
system congratulations do it it's a very
good learning experience and you should
be able to do something where you can
maybe look at an existing file format to
get you started I think likes there's
some file formats that are somewhat open
that have skinning data I think maybe
the film box format that Autodesk pushes
might be kind of open and there's like
an
okay for reading it or something there's
probably other ones out there I don't
know so you know you can go take a look
at that right you can go take a look at
that
but understanding where these techniques
fall short and what we have developed as
more advanced techniques it's very
important because that's the only way
you can really take the next steps
towards really high quality character
animation which games have already done
for certain circumstances in certain
engines and which film definitely does
always alright what we need to recognize
here is that fundamentally speaking
giving the artist control over where
this point lies in between two points
that are transformed as part of the
skeleton is fundamentally just an
approximate artistic process for what
they would actually like to do and what
would they actually like to do well what
are they gonna do when you give them
this what the artist is gonna do is
they're gonna bend the arm around and
they're gonna try and paint the weight
value which again only really gives them
the ability to go between these two
things they're gonna try and adjust the
weight value so that it looks the least
bad as they're gonna do right but they
can never get something that they
actually want which is an arbitrary
placement what they'd like to do is just
move the elbow and then move the point
somewhere where should it go well it
should go there right and this is
especially true with things like you
know ZBrush or Mudbox or whatever
sculpting tools people use today where
you can just paint like sculpt vertices
into position what I'd rather do is just
bend the arm sculpt it and then know
that as I move the arm joint around
you'll just play back the sculpts that I
did right I mean that's what the artist
wants they don't want they don't want to
have to just pick a point on that line I
mean what does that have to do with
anything and furthermore it doesn't
model the problem at all either skin is
wrapped around it first of all skin is
it
self somewhat elastic but it's wrapped
around fat which you know slides and
deforms muscle which grows larger
actually right if you tense a muscle it
will expand and then only that internal
bone itself the actual physical bone you
have really stays for our purposes rigid
everything else is very deformable and
so it doesn't make a lot of sense to
tell the artist pick some rigid line
that's going to transform in between
these two effective transforms that
would only really correctly model a
literal skeleton like a literal series
of bones it would work just fine but it
would not work at all
for the fat the skin and so on and so
there are two camps two fundamental
camps that these fall into and one is
just I'll guess I'll call this double
down right there's the double down camp
and there's the simulation camp and I
should say that they're not much like
all of the linear blending they're not
mutually exclusive you can be somewhere
in the middle I'll tell you what both of
them are we to take simulation first
because it's the least interesting from
a game perspective because you really
just don't do it very much the
simulation perspective is oh well
instead of doing mesh healing at all
let's actually have some really complex
set of things that model surfaces and
we'll attach the points to those right
so the simulation approach says alright
I'm gonna actually pretend there's a
real bone it's like for reals made of
like marrow and stuff right
and and then I'm going to actually say
that there's like muscle fiber like
wrapped around it like for realsies
right and then I'm gonna say that
there's a fat layer
and then I'm gonna say there's actual
skin like I'm literally going to do all
of that crap right and then when I move
this joint I'm gonna actually do finite
element solves you know or something to
figure out how this skin will
interpenetrate how the fat will bulge
together how the muscles will contract
I'm going to simulate if I pull it this
way that the bicep is gonna bulge here
right blah blah blah blah blah
fundamentally speaking this is the route
you want to take if what you're trying
to do is put as much programming in as
possible
and the least art right what you may
want to do depending on your goals you
may want to go a programming or heavy
route and that is simulation just like
everything else the more simulation you
do the less art you need kind of like
how physics remove some of the need for
animation because you can just simulate
what you're trying to do right but it
removes the art from the process it's
not very artistic it's not very
controllable because it's a simulation
under the hood just like physics makes
it pretty hard to produce animations you
actually want you have to sit there and
fuss with them a lot and we spend a lot
of time figuring out how to move them
more towards the artistic side of things
right so it has some drawbacks but it
has some strengths and the biggest
strength it has is maybe it can produce
use once you do it once maybe it can
produce a lot of useful animation
results for you without an artist having
to be there to adjust them now the
double down camp is to say let's go the
artist route they were already modeling
everything using tools they already
built the skeleton themselves using
tools so let's just give them tools to
do more work here and so what they do in
the DoubleDown camp is exactly what I
just said let's have the artist sculpt
more right artists sculpt more you know
I'm saying so basically what we do there
is we say all right the artist is going
to give us a rest pose yes that's like
whatever the arm looks like what it's
just out but then you know what else
they're going to do
they're gonna pose the arm in like an
arm up position and they're gonna model
the bicep bulge right and then they're
gonna rotate the arm over and they're
gonna model that okay and so what these
what these with this camp what doubling
down on art input does is it said let's
have the artist give us lots of examples
and then what our jobs gonna do going to
be is to change those blending equations
to be able to reproduce as closely as
possible all of the examples that our
artist gave us by driving which samples
we use off of the position of the
underlying skeleton and any other
parameters they want to give us for
example we could have a stress parameter
that you specify for each bone that is
how taut the muscle is right and so the
artist can crank up the stress is the is
the dude like really you know flexing
his arm or is he the slack right because
I can I can do that with my arm or I can
do that with my arm right and you can
see that the bicep you know totally
changes its shape even though the
skeleton hasn't changed right and that's
how much stress you know it's being put
through there so we extend the parameter
space of the skeleton to include both
bone positions and rotations as before
but we also include in that set we also
include sort of scaler or I shouldn't
say scaler but oh there are parameters
right they could be anything the artist
wants and what we do when we look at
these systems is we take an input mesh
plus the set of bone positions and
parameters that the artist said it
correlated to and we typically use what
is known well and this is maybe my term
but we use a reduction process or a
fitting process to take a large number
of examples and produce smaller blending
equations that still look almost exactly
like the ones I already
just with more terms that we can compute
at runtime given a set of these to
produce an output set okay reading more
about this I would highly recommend the
paper pose space deformation by
industrial light magic it is probably
the easiest one to understand and it was
an early one in the field so it's pretty
basic and obviously we've done way more
complicated stuff since then but I would
recommend that one to give you a link
this is it maybe isn't it all right
maybe it wasn't by Industrial Light and
Magic I don't know what's entropolis is
why did I think this was pose
um all right well I have no idea what's
entropolis is so nevermind I thought it
was Industrial Light man I'm wrong I
guess it's this alright I apologize and
trap list or misattribution anyway I
think that's probably the easiest paper
it does involve some matrix fitting
which we haven't covered here and is
kind of a topic for a different time
it's its own topic and so I'm gonna end
it here where we perfectly fit this into
our into our window which is pretty
crazy but I think I've covered pretty
much everything you need to know to get
started on my skinning if there's
anything I left out I'm sure we can
cover it here in the Q&amp;A so hopefully
that pretty much is that I'm gonna pop
the Q&amp;A here and see if anyone has any
questions on topic to this please let me
know
for what version of grainy had I worked
I did all of the versions up through 2.7
maybe 2.5 pausing
okay so I did all of the versions prior
to 2.4 it's where what I did
yeah so I think all of the versions so
2.3 was my last full version I did and
somewhere in between 2.3 and 2.4 I think
was when I handed it off to Tom and I
did all of the previous versions
starting from Oh 7b which was the first
release all the way through
are the bone transform inverses stored
relative to the mesh Center yes
generally speaking the idea is that you
want to pick a single space in which you
store all of your source data so you
store the entire mesh and all of the
inverse transforms you store those all
relative to the original single model Oh
Molly's asleep right now but I'll let
her look out the window later sorry what
file format would you recommend for
beginners and for someone not willing to
use a Lib so obj files are the easiest
files because they're just a text file
that's obvious what the stuff is but my
my problem with them is I don't know if
if most art tools will export a weight
section for you or not so if you can get
a art tool to output an obj file that
has vertex weights that would be a good
way to start but I just don't know so my
problem is I'm not sure what file format
would be best to start in because I
don't know which ones have weights when
I started granny there were no exports
with weights granny has its own exporter
that you run inside the art tool to
extract the information it doesn't use
an existing file format would busy a
curve work for the fatty part of the arm
probably be terrible um busy curves
don't work well but they have been tried
there was a package called
I think it was called characters this so
there is a there is a plugin for the
original 3d studio max at the very first
version of 3d studio max which isn't the
first thread in the 3d studio because 3d
studio actually went up through version
for at least possibly 5 in Dass so when
they ported it from das to Windows and
made 3d studio max there was a thing
called character studio which was done
by like mmm was I don't know who did it
originally I don't remember but
character studio featured a thing called
biped which is a little like intelligent
skeleton that did some things
automatically for you kind of crappy but
it was better than most things at the
time and then physique which was a mesh
skinning tool and the way that physique
worked was it actually threaded up as a
a curve through the bones it doesn't
really help much it's not great but it's
it's something you can look to if you
want to know how that works I wouldn't
recommend it how often would composite
bone matrices usually be updated per
frame
yes per frame so every frame what you do
is you compute the results of your
animation that gives you a new world
space transform for each of your bones
you multiply in the inverse that you
store it in the file and every frame you
do that combination to give you your
final world transform
how do quaternions fit into this they
don't so quaternions really have nothing
to do with any of the stuff that I've
talked about they're quatrain Ian's are
traditionally used in animation to
represent the rotations of bones but
that's purely a storage format or it's
not many stories right a manipulation
format they can get you some benefits
right there are things called there is a
thing called dual quaternion skinning
and that is basically a sort of a
separate technique for skinning that you
know I haven't implemented this
personally it came out much much well
after I was done with with working on
granny at all you can take a look at
this if you're interested but it it's
really I don't know how I don't have a
strong opinion about it because I've
never myself I don't know how much you
would really care I think it's kind of
something that's not probably
particularly necessary because you want
sculpted results
you're really not trying to fix
artifacts like this in the real world
you tend to just add more artistic
sculpting to the process but that's one
place you can have quaternions involved
directly in the skinning process but
that's a special case and isn't really
necessarily a general idea about mesh
getting that makes sense
what kind of skinning to be used for
handmade here oh we don't really do
skinning in handmade here oh we covered
this just because I wanted to cover
because people had asked how do you
recommend to go about learning a new
language or technology that's not a
little off topic for this stream you
probably asked on different one if you
miss live chartreuse no Roman you did
not I have not played Chrono Trigger yet
I'm kind of waiting for it to be on sale
and my chartreuse is almost still almost
full maybe this week we'll do some
chartreuse gaming it might not be Chrono
Trigger cuz I said I was kind of waiting
for it to go on sale I have a wish list
but if you send a lot of data to the GPU
it doesn't have that much memory is
there some sort of virtual memory that
it will be used or will it crash
so typically speaking that depends a lot
on what APR you're using and also the
answer is generally yes nowadays there
is some sorts of virtual memory
happening there but even in the old days
there was not kind of some virtual
memory in the sense that the driver
would actually manage it for you so you
kind of didn't know but behind your back
it was swapping memory out so that's a
topic I don't really want to cover on
this because it doesn't really have
anything to do with mesh skinning but
the answer is to certain extent yes to a
certain scent no and that it depends on
which card which driver you're talking
about
so the lerp versus slurp is in the
animation system and not on the skinning
system that is correct the skinning
system does not fundamentally care how
you are producing the points
it's the skinning system is just that
inverse transform and then a weighted
blend how you're producing the actual
transforms forward in space is
completely up to you so the skeletal
animation system is the part that cares
about looping versus slurping the
skinned mesh getting never needs to do
anything with slurping that's just
unnecessary as far as I'm concerned not
to say you couldn't engineer one that
did it and that dual quaternions
skinning is kind of an example of
someone saying maybe we should be doing
more rotational things inside our inside
our skinning system but the basic
skinning systems that form the
foundation of most games even today just
fundamentally don't do they don't use
things like quaternions to produce the
final blend weights to produce the final
blend points typically you're using
quaternions to produce the interim
transforms that you use to then do the
blend equation and again with the caveat
that things like dual quaternions
getting to exist so some people do go
kind of a different direction with it
there's not like a right answer
you
all right I think we've pretty much got
all the questions I don't see any more
in there I think we could say if they
wrap it up quick quick check does anyone
have any questions that are about mesh
getting before we close up
roman asks coordinates you've drawn
Xia's up while opengl is deep so this is
kind of an interesting i'll quickly say
this briefly since we don't have any
questions that are totally on topic and
this is somewhat on topic i will just go
ahead and do this so it's worth noting
that saying that opengl has z is up
while opengl z is deep is kind of a
misnomer and let me tell you why i think
if this is similar to the mirror in
algae a lot of people are like why do
mirrors reverse things left to right
instead of up and down and the answer is
they don't they reverse them period and
whether you think of it as reversing
them upside up and down or whether you
think of them as reversing it left to
right is really because of how it's
happening in your head not because of
how it's happening in the world the same
is true here so in your head what you're
thinking is well my computer monitor is
obviously situated like this I hung it
you know on a monitor stand or something
and I am a human who looks forward at
this monitor
therefore when I'm using OpenGL because
it's coordinate system aligns this way
that's that's the Z right and that's the
X and that's the Y we go in OpenGL Z is
this is it's it's looking backwards
basically not quite forwards it's
actually the backwards vector right and
that's because you applied a whole bunch
of human specific stuff to your thinking
about it right how you tend to put a
monitor up right what you expect that
monitor
to show how you expect to sit in front
of the monitor but in reality I could
put the monitor anywhere I could put the
monitor like this and I could have a
chair with the sling in it and I'm
hanging over the monitor like this with
my arms out like Superman looking down
at the monitor right and the monitor is
sitting on the floor at that point what
is open jails coordinate system I asked
you right well let me try 100 percent
correctly to the diagram it's that and
that is ease up right Z is up it points
upwards so really all you have to do if
you want Z to be up and x and y to be
the world plane but you can if you want
to it's up to you you know who knows if
you want Y is up Z is up to your choice
it's just say what when I start out what
am I looking at am I looking at
something you know do I expect my
startup to be an FPS or an RTS if it's
an RTS I start out looking down at the
world that is Z is up right if it's an
FPS then I started out looking out at
the world and that is why is up right in
OpenGL native coordinates you know I'm
saying so I just choose the arts yes
paradigm I choose when I turn on my
monitor that I'm looking down at the
world right like an RTS instead of
looking up at the world we're looking
out at the world like an FPS does that
help all Roman
else faceless says the ligament seems to
have a bearing on the arm movement also
the pivot of the arm knee shoulder seem
to be on the outside and not the center
which makes me think we are thinking
about the problem naively who knows no
you're correct in your observations and
a lot of times artists will do that so
if you look at where they you know place
the bone even in a naive mesh skinning
system they will often put it like up
towards the outside so that when it
bends it produces a better result so
you're not wrong and artists will do
that for sure
and that's just about getting a better
base result before you ever sculpt
anything the Roman says he said Redmond
if you want to use that chartreuse turn
the chartreuse is for me trying to play
Chrono Trigger well I'm a little bit
tipsy Brian Griese I've been going
through the multi-threaded code memory
what up so you're talking about loading
the asset files and chunks okay that's
kind of off topic so let's let's do that
for what scream that that's that let's
do that on a regular stream following on
from what you've explained about
coordinate systems in OpenGL and how we
choose it what do we need to do to set
up Z up instead again trying to just
underscore this it already is it's just
what you it's just what your mind thinks
of the default camera position right if
you want Z to be up all you have to do
is think that in a non rotated camera
points down that's it now Z is up it's
just a change in thinking there's you
don't do anything else
you have to do anything it's just how
are you thinking about your camera
that's it
your electrodes from that yesterday made
national headlines yeah it did alright
I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it up
because we're done with our stream today
thank you everyone for joining me for
the upside of handmade heroes with a
pleasure
black boarding with you as always I hope
that gave you a pretty intuitive
understanding of all of the components
of the mesh skinning pipeline if it
didn't
I apologize hopefully you can look to
some secondary resources or drop by
handmade hero sometime handmade hero or
you can always go to the watch page and
when it's not live it will have a
schedule on there saying when it is live
so you can always stop by and ask
questions and we can cover anything that
you might not have understood about this
introduction to mesh getting I always
take questions during both the pre
stream before we start and also the post
stream Q&amp;A so you can come by and ask
those questions that's it for today I'll
be back here either sometime this week
if I'm feeling saucy or next weekend
with more handmade hero where we will be
putting our new lighting sampling
spheres into effect that hopefully
you'll join me for until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see you on
the Internet
take it easy everybody