hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show Rico to complete game live
on stream a couple things for I get
started today obviously we have a
discord now there is a button for it if
you would like to chat offline as well
as online you can always go over there
it's discord for all Molly rocket things
including handmade hero and there's
pretty much people chatting at all hours
of the day on there so head over there
there's a technical area to ask tech
questions or talk about tech stuff
there's also a general place there's an
art place there there's even a place for
food people have been doing so much
handmade cooking there's like a food
channel on there now so head over there
if you want to check that out I also
have a public service announcement the
watch page is broken a parent I
mentioned this the other day I
double-checked it
twitch went ahead and changed their API
out from under everyone as they love to
do and so I'm gonna have to go like
reimplemented asks twitch whether the
stream is live because of course you
know it was too much to ask for them to
have the question about the stream being
live be something that they could
support in multiple versions that was
just way beyond anyone's technical
capabilities twitch they just couldn't
imagine how that something like that
would occur and so you know I get to go
rewrite that part of the code and so
that'll be a lot of fun thanks twitch
for that moving on
today we've got some debugging to do we
left yesterday we had done a bunch of
work to set ourselves up for doing like
prep calculations and sampling from my
probes inside the actual game proper I'd
like to get to that but before we do we
have a bug that we want to solve which
is that I mean I guess we don't really
know it's a bug but my assertions that I
put in the code are triggering and so
unless those assertions themselves are
somehow wrong which I don't think they
are but I don't know we'll have to
double track unless those assertions
themselves are somehow wrong we have a
bug in the system that assigns
light probe IDs to light probe entities
and the reason that we have this at all
because you know you might be like
asking why do we care
it's a legitimate question the reason we
care is because in lighting we do not
have the luxury of largesse basically
when we are processing lighting it is
going to be very difficult and
performance critical it's going to be
hard for us to optimize it to a speed
that we are going to be happy with
because lighting is just very expensive
so why they're shipping graphics cards
that specially accelerate ray tracing
right lighting is hard lighting is the
hardest thing you can possibly do in
computer graphics
well alright maybe it's not the hardest
thing you can do you know maybe we could
argue that motion blur is actually the
hardest thing you can do if you want to
get it right but you know let's just say
that short of accurate motion blur
lighting is like the hardest thing and
let's be frank if you were going to have
to do accurate motion blur you would
need to light the motion blur accurately
and then we're back to lighting anyway
it's one of the hardest things you can
possibly do let's say that and so we
don't want to have large numbers of
extra light probes sitting around in the
light probe system getting calculated
wasting CPU cycles we don't really want
to have that we want a nice tight
compact array of only light probes we
actually are going to work with in the
minimal amount of space so that says
cash friendly as possible taking up the
least amount of bandwidth to the
graphics card bla bla bla bla bla
we basically want everything to be set
up as well as possible to make our lives
as easy as possible because we kind of
know it's not one of those things that
we're just going to wait for it to be
slow we know it slow we know it will be
this is one where you don't have to
wonder whether you're doing premature
optimization because guess what it's
slow no matter what you do and so you
have to kind of go into it with the
mentality of making sure you set
yourself up for success and in this
particular case we are trying to assign
lighting values so that we can put any
kind of pre-filter we want at the head
end and assign lighting values based on
you
a separate criteria that maybe doesn't
have anything to do with whether or not
the enemy's active it might be more
about whether the entity is like within
a certain region specific to lighting
that we even enabled or who knows right
and so what we need to do now is we need
to go ahead and make sure that that
assignment scheme is relatively safe and
robust we implemented one version of the
scheme and it doesn't work and then we
were out of time and so what we need to
do today is go look at that code and
find out why so today is a debugging day
that's what we're going to do and if I
run the application as it stands you can
see us hitting the case here and like I
said we we don't observe any bugs per se
we're not really at the point yet where
we would observe an actual bug because
these lighting probe indices aren't used
we were about to use them in the
lighting system to figure out how to
send down light information to the
graphics card which we now created room
for but we do have assertions in here
that tell us whether we think things are
working properly and the place where we
actually hit the assertion is in our
call which is supposed to be taking an
entity that has no light probe index
assigned and it's going to assign one
potentially if it's a light probe it
will assign a light probe index to that
empty what we're seeing is that for some
reason the entity already has a light
probe index assigned so you can see if I
open up the entity structure here we're
in assigned indices which means it's
supposed to check to see if it's light
probe and then assign it index if it is
what we're seeing is that it already has
a light probe index and we have no idea
where that came from
right now we know which leg probe index
it is it's 101 and that brings up an
interesting question which is like okay
if I run the game again
is it still number 101 it would be great
if it was and it is so what that tells
me is perhaps the way to start looking
at this problem is to find out why light
probe index 101 got assigned in the
first place and why it never got
unassigned right how are we calling this
thing multiple times so one thing we can
see is where is it calling it from right
you can see in here that ensure region
is unpacked what we're doing is we're
unpacking a world chunk so we're taking
this world chunk we're removing it from
the system we're unpacking the entities
and then we're adding it to the free or
list right so it can go deal with that
right that's how we're actually working
with this system now the problem is when
we actually unpack an entity right we're
unpacking it into a region you can see
right here we're unpacking that aquire
you know that unquiet unpacked entity
slot right this right here we're getting
back what should be empty entity data as
far as the light probe index is
concerned why do I say that because
everywhere we were giving up a slot in
the past which I believe is only here
right so anytime we were doing remove
from unpacked we thought and obviously
we're wrong we thought we were getting
rid of the of the light probe index
attached to that entity so we're giving
up slots here and you can see when we
get to this where we say like is deleted
remove entities whatever you can see it
says removed from unpacked here and
remove from unpacked here these are the
only two places as far as we know that
we can remove entities during the normal
game loop and pack entity as well as
[Music]
remove indices will both remove the
indices so pack entity calls remove
indices on the entity right and you can
see remove ennis remove indices getting
called explicitly in the case where the
entity is just getting thrown away so in
both cases
it should be the case that the indices
got removed from the entity right now
the only other place we know of where we
can actually get rid of an enmity is
where we clear the entire thing and
there again we're calling pac entity
which we'll call remove indices so I'm
just not sure is there some other place
right where this is happening is did we
miss a case it's a very complicated
piece of coach one of the most
complicated parts we have in the system
certainly so okay like I can understand
that there might be bugs in it it's it's
intricate and it has a lot of complexity
to it but I just can't think of at the
moment where we would be having that
problem come from right so what I'd like
to do to start is since I have a little
bit of a clue here right I know
something I'm not completely blind about
the problem since I know that 101 is the
specific index that's getting assigned
what I would like to do is I'd like to
see when that first gets assigned so
what I would like to do here is
basically take and be able to set a
breakpoint on this line of code when we
have the MD light probe index come back
as 101 right
and similarly I'd like to do that here
as well I'd like to be able to know if
we ever undo that one just so I can kind
of see what's happening right and one
answer could be you know and I don't
know but one answer could be that is
light probe for all I know if we were
calling remove and indices at some time
when the entity had been otherwise
- destroyed so for example if we were
calling it like let's say that here I
don't know if we ever set if we even
have any time when things get deleted at
the moment looks like here is the only
place right so in delete entity
that's the only place so someone has to
call delete entity and I don't know to
what extent that's happening let's take
a look so here we delete these two
entities right these are getting okay
well that would probably do it right but
these aren't light probes right there's
no light probes on these so the fact
that these are getting deleted and then
having their brain ID value set to zero
shouldn't really change anything because
again they're not actually ever gonna
probe lighting far as I know right
um but yeah so delete entity maybe
should be the thing that removes the
indices I don't know that's hard to say
but you know it certainly could hard to
say
anyway looking at that it just doesn't
seem likely it doesn't seem like that's
the source of the bug so anyway moving
back here what I'd like to do is set a
breakpoint assigned indices temporarily
here I just want to go in and in here I
want to set a breakpoint on this line
and I want to set a breakpoint on this
line so I just want to see what happens
when light probe index 101 is assigned
and so if we look at this entity here
what I would expect to see is type 6
should be a light probe I don't actually
know if it is or not so we should
probably take that and look and see if
it really is this would be 0 1 2 3 4 or
5 6 so it does look like that's actually
true meaning that that brain light probe
does seem to actually be correctly set
on this so it does suggest that would
have gone into this routine actually
assigned 101 to it and now we have an an
entity that is you know the entity in
question I can look at value 8 11 that's
kind of interesting to probably I should
look and see if that's consistent as
well but we'll move on from there
all right so what you can see is
actually this is probably a pretty good
sign so the first time light probe index
101 gets assigned
entity eight eleven when that happens we
never call remove indices on it right so
you saw it like it was obvious right I
come through here I assign 101 is it
still in eighteen eighty 11 let's see so
that's a stable value as well so we
assign that index and we assigned it as
normal during the unpack right and then
the question is just like okay what
happened
right how did we then end up assigning
it again do we exit this successfully
yes we do so we unpacked everybody and
then we're apparently happy about that
and where are we on here so this is
during editing it looks like right so
you know we're kind of doing our edits
here and whatever right so at some point
as we kind of come out of here let's see
we we would expect right at some point I
mean can we just let me see if I can I
want to see if we get to this point so
when we go to clear unpacked nd cache
I'm gonna set a breakpoint there do we
get there so we don't so we're getting
more and more and more information here
right what that suggests to me is when
we go back out here so this bug is
happening entirely inside the world
generation so we're never even getting
to the part where we would we're never
even getting to the part where we would
run the game again that's actually
encouraging that means that in less
cases to debug because now we're just
talking about the edit pass so we're
starting to narrow it down a little bit
and that makes me happy right I don't
want to see this sprawling thing where
we have to get 30 frames into the game
before the bug appears right because it
every time you add latency in a bug it
becomes harder to debug the less stuff
that's going on to create the bug the
better because I just have any
time tracking it down it's that simple
right so that was good I'm encouraged by
the fact that we saw that but again I'm
not sure how that's happening right I
don't quite understand how we're ending
up with something getting called in
assign indices twice and I think it was
getting a call in assign indices twice
in the same place as well I'm not 100%
sure about that but I think that's
actually true and so one thing I have to
start thinking about is well what are
the ways in which these entities can
really be touched in that sense and also
maybe I need to start looking at just
figuring out like am I am I like
reducing the size of this array ever in
in some sense you know I do this packing
we're never calling this by the time the
bug hits so I don't know
so it's something in this loop I guess
but again it's pretty hard to say when
you look at what's going on here when we
decide that we're going to remove an
entity you can see us packing here we
we romp the entire entity and that does
seem fine I'm gonna let's see here so we
have only a couple places where we romp
entities I'm just gonna say look when
you romp this entity because you're
about to overwrite it
let me just assert that the light probe
index is zero there and I assume that
should fire but I guess I don't know and
I'm interested to know if it does or if
it doesn't right and I have no idea so
here's us assigning light probe index
101 to entity 8 11 and here we are back
getting assigned indices called again on
a different entity which is 15 and again
it's got light primp index 101 on it
right and what you can see here like if
we do this again twice we're assigning
this one five one nine oh seven eight
and so can I write that pointer value if
I am to copy that pointer value and just
kind of paste it in here right so we've
got the entity in question when I hit
the bug you'll notice it's the same
pointer right so it is 100% a case of
reusing a slot without ever calling this
part of the function right and so we are
at least the manifestation of the bug is
exactly what we think is happening
meaning we've got an entity slot it gets
reused without ever calling remove
indices so we're literally just looking
for how that slots getting reused and so
the other thing that I would like to
know is how are we doing like our create
NV call right and if I look when we do
create entity like we're calling a choir
unpacked entity slot right and when we
do a choir unpacked entity slot that's
another place like in here when I get
one of these entities that's another
place I could assert right and as you
can see all I'm really doing is I'm just
trying to move the bug backward
until I can find it right so I'm just
trying to look for where these things
that where these things might be
happening so I can try to fix it and
you'll see me keep doing that as we go
it's not leave this result and so all
I'm doing right is bubbling that
bubbling the problem up to try and get
closer to the source of the error and so
we changed lines so these have to kind
of get reset there we go so here we are
again on nd should be 8:11 yeah and it
is 101 it is and now I want to see if we
get it and we do right so now we can see
clearly like we're acquiring an unpacked
entity slot here and the way that we do
that is always the same we take the
unpacked entity count and we take
whatever that last entity was right so
we're taking that and we're going
forwards with it right so it's exactly
what we thought and we're we're doing
this acquire unpacked entity slot here
you can see that we're going to do it
and we're about to go into the part
where you fill it out you can see that
somehow we ended up with a slot that
even though we think right we think that
every time we put one back it had the
light probe index equal to 0 if that's
what we thought right got it all right
so I think we've found the bug and what
you can see happening here is the bug
these don't get swapped that's the bug
right so what's happening here is in
fact kind of a wider bug and in fact we
probably want to just fix this more
dramatically I think
yeah I think we do so if you look at
what's happening here when we acquire
unpacked entity slot we're taking
whatever the end of the array is and
we're using that but what we did not do
right is when we actually copy this guy
back we don't clear whatever is in that
slot so the old entity is just sitting
there still the whole thing now that's
actually fine when we do our unpack
because we're op over the data with what
we actually decompress as the entity but
the problem with that is it doesn't
actually help us clear out the space for
the part that we actually need anew if
we go to create entity and we look at
what happens there you can see us
zeroing out the struct because we're
creating a new one that zeros out the
entire struct which is exactly what we
want however when we unpack an entity it
is insufficient to simply copy just that
part in we also need to zero the end of
it which is the part that was not saved
right so when we go to fill unpacked
entity right here that needs to have it
taken care of so what we actually need
to do is something more like this right
take the destination pointer add the
packed entity size to it right and we
want to clear the entire entity -
whatever the pack size is that we you
know actually put in there we want to
clear that overhang right and so that
will finally get us back to 0 where we
know that we've we haven't had left
stuff lying around in that other portion
right so I believe that was probably the
bug now I don't know but that was
probably it looks like I'm wrong oh well
I'm not wrong because that zero happens
after it so that aquire unpacked mb slot
actually can't do that so let's go ahead
over here wire unpack any slot so in
here we can't do that just yet because
we haven't actually cleared it yet and
we don't necessarily want to because two
different people want to clear two
different amounts of things creating an
entity wants to clear the whole thing
whereas you know just the regular wants
to clear just the end right okay so now
we've solved that bug which was kind of
tricky right we were thinking of
entities as permanent things they aren't
they're kind of recycled in a way there
and so you can kind of see that we're
now back to where we wanted to be which
is we've got light probes they're
getting assigned numbers and yeah I
think we're all good now what I can do
as well is I can play around this little
bit just to make sure that what we're
seeing makes sense we have a get debug
color call you know here it is and what
I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead
and take the part of the code that
renders the entities where it renders
the light probe index where it renders
the light probe sorry and instead of
doing a V 4 V 4 V 4 I'm actually gonna
do a thing here where we do color equals
this that's what we're actually gonna do
normally but I'm gonna do one of these
here I'm gonna use the light probe index
and then I'm gonna delete this so this
way now we can see that each one of
these things is assigned a color I'm
assigning two index and we can also see
if it's stable right we could we could
get some sense of whether it is a stable
value by whether or not these things are
flashing and what we should see is
although if we went away from something
and came back the color should have
changed
we should never see the colors flash so
while we are looking at a light probe it
should never lose its index right and
that is what I'm seeing so that's a good
sign like I'm not getting any indication
at all really anywhere in here that
we're losing the stability of these
indices so that's good because that
means these are stable indexes that's
what I want and now what I need to do is
I need to go and actually start
performing some lighting computations
with these indices with these light
probes as we go right so that's where
we're at
all right so that's all good let's go
ahead and take a look now at how I would
how I'm gonna actually go about doing
that we have some things we need to
address such as the light probe clearing
and things like that all right so here's
our situation we now want to I guess you
just gonna see here where I'm pushing
this cube on right
we know while these light probes are in
specific locations and we need some way
of articulating to the lighting system
just what locations those are right
somebody needs to do that and we set
ourselves up for success for some
definition of success in the renderer by
having when we output everything a
location where we can record the
information about the light probes right
so you can see in here we've got a max
light prep count a light probe count a
light primer radians right and the
problem that we have here is that this
is sort of designed as you can see as
some kind of a sort of streaming system
or something like that and it's not
quite right there's some issues with it
blah blah blah so what we would rather
do here is we would rather have
something where we can store information
about the lighting that's going on by
just recording actual position values
into the lighting position array right
and so unlike other things that want to
be cleared every time this kind of wants
to be something that is stationary right
it wants to be something that just gets
updated incrementally and doesn't really
have that same sort of streaming quality
that these that the vertex rate index
ray do so rather than like a count
that gets reset every time we kind of
want this to be something more like
we're just shifting values in and out
and telling you about things that go in
and out of the working set right so what
I'd like to do is kind of change the way
this works a bit I do need to add an
additional array here which is light
probe position and the light probe
position is just one for every light
probe right but that's all we really
need and then I need ways of setting
these up right so what I need to do here
is I need a call that operates on the
render set that basically announces a
light probe that it is active and which
one it was
so in here we need to say something such
as that I would pass the render group
and then I would say the position of
this light probe is this and that's it
right I'm not going to tell you what the
irradiance is because I'm gonna assume
that you cache that and I'm going to
tell you what the position is because
I'm going to hope that you will allow it
to move right and I'm just promising
that I'm not going to move it without
clearing it very much so if there was a
slow moving probe we maybe wouldn't
clear it we allow it to a ver egde if it
teleports it would be my responsibility
to tell you what that means is we also
have a place to put this value which is
here and we can now undo the lighting
probe clearer so we can say all right
here's the light probe information I'm
telling you if you need to clear the
irradiance cache to zero I'm also
telling you if you need to
move it somewhere else and all that will
be in one nice little simple function
that should allow you to do everything
you need to do render wise right at once
the light probe clear only has to happen
when the thing moves and so yeah I mean
you know what now that I think about it
we could just use a distance metric for
this I'm gonna go ahead and say that we
probably don't need that light probe
clear now that I'm thinking about it
because the only reason that a light
probe can be wrong is if the light probe
moved right so the position of it would
tell us what we need to know right you
know what no I take that back so because
we do everything centered around a local
coordinate system that's not necessarily
true so I'm gonna go ahead and say we're
gonna leave the light probe clear in
there and I'm gonna put a note to that
effect so we don't forget
so I'm just putting that in there is a
little note because it's pretty subtle
and if you didn't know that you might
think that this would have been
sufficient to know whether you should
clear it I don't think it really is
sufficient and so I think that we need
the light probe clear now it's true that
we could optimize this by doing a
positional Delta or rather by using
positional value so we could look at the
entity position that's well know yes we
couldn't so I you know what I'm just
gonna stop talking about that I think
it's right let's just leave it at that
so I think we're doing that right I
think we do what we need to do there and
I don't want to overthink it because you
know I think there's it's I was kind of
try and convince myself of something but
it just wasn't the case so now what I
want to do is in here I would like to
put something that allows us to to
provide information about these light
probes down to the renderer so we know
what it should look like because we
wrote the usage code you happen to know
exactly what we want which is great
and then we can have our clear in here
as well so if you look at what has to
happen now we're gonna be getting the
commands here and what we want to do is
we want to take a look at the commands
that we've got and first of all oh you
know what we forgot one thing though I'm
wanting to send down the light probe
index that was the whole point there we
go so we need that index as this is how
we know where it should go so what I
want to do here is I want to say look if
the commands MaxLite probe count
get the light prep index is less than
that right if it's not we want to
probably assert that because that would
be bad
assuming we can fit it in here what we
want to do is say if the light probe
index is greater than the commands light
probe count hello there we go
or a meanie the right way to write this
just so it's a little clearer is if it's
less right so basically what we want to
do here is say look if the light probe
index is less I'm sorry if the light
probe count is less than a light probe
index plus one right because it's the
count not an index then we want to set
it equal to that right that's like the
new maximum and the reason for that is
as we insert things here we just want to
make sure we have the upper bound of
indices so we know when we go to do our
lighting we do it over all the ones that
we actually got told about and we won't
do it over any ones that have kind of
been shooed out of the set right then
what we need to do is into the light
probe position array we now know that
we're writing into this specific
location we need to put our p value and
then if it turns out that we were
supposed to clear it right we also want
the light probe irradiance to be set to
two nothing right so we want to actually
clear this this light information we
want to clear the light information if
you said that the old cached values are
now stale because this doesn't represent
the same light probe anymore
for whatever reason either you assigned
a new entity to the same index or maybe
in the future we have teleporting
entities and so if you teleport in a
light probe which you know I don't know
if that's I'm really gonna happen but if
it did you would tell us to clear it cuz
it's like hey it's letting
no longer valid even though it's the
same light probe we put it somewhere
else the all bets are off
right so that will announce all of our
light probes to the system and as you
can see if we go back here that's really
all the information we needed right the
lighting system is gonna be responsible
for calculating this and it will
preserve it here and the voxel is
created every time right we're gonna
recreate that voxel every time by
rasterizing our light sources I'm sorry
light probes into it right and so we
pretty much don't really need anything
other than that I don't think right okay
the light occluder streaming already
pretty much done and so pretty much I
think all we need to do now is just
focus on getting this part working and
then when we actually have all of this
working we can pop back to the occluders
side of things and start to do our ray
tracing again which we have most of the
code for but we need to kind of clean it
up and make it work with the new light
probe system all right so I'm pretty
sure that's all we really needed to do
to get those light probes into the
system and so now we should be good as
far as that's concerned what is this
problem here 2 V 3 star ah that's right
this is actually like a 6 wide version
of that isn't it
so this clear actually has to clear all
6 of the light purple radiances so this
is actually more of this
right and that's just because that light
probe irradiance is actually for every
face of the cube so when you put down a
light probe you're putting down a light
probe that actually has six different
faces
you know when I think about that I also
do kind of wonder just a little bit
about how that lighting recombination
there are some things I wonder like you
know I wonder if it's kind of dumb that
we treat the light probes as cubes
instead of just like points and
directions like we were doing before
because I don't actually know that we
couldn't have just done that and then
had them just go in a row I guess it
doesn't really matter I don't know we'll
have to think about that anyway the
light probe will get cleared here in in
you know kind of an obvious way and we
may want to make this be something a
little bit more structured you know like
we could make this be a pointer to a
struct of III s the way we would do that
would be something more like this and
maybe this is just a better idea
something like that and then we could
just say well you know what this is a
light probe a radiance array and it's it
just looks like that right and that does
seem good because then at that point
you're not doing any kind of funny
business you can just say hey let's
clear that out and off we go and that
does seem compelling right I like that
better and here where we're actually
initializing it then you know the OpenGL
layers if we want to change that we just
could and because now where we would be
putting that information where where is
that
yeah win32 up and Jill there no it's
right here
so here we're we're doing like proper
radiance instead of the six times we
just do light probe irradiance and call
it a day
right so that does seem like a better
idea
certainly if we go over to the lighting
system now we can also take a look and
see does this lineup particularly well
if you take a look at the spatial probe
sure you give either the spatial probe
in question which is this right here you
can see that it's just an array of light
indices and it's got the SEL dims right
and the dim Pao - that's just the same
stuff so we should now be able to
convert this over right - instead of
light index being a thing that we
allocate for our like for the lighting
system we can actually just use the
voxel that's actually present now right
so we can make these things work right
on top of each other in exactly the way
that we want and be done with it right
so I think we're in good shape here to
collapse these things down but you know
one thing at a time all right so now if
we run this we shouldn't get any
surprises hopefully all we're doing is
sending that array down now and oh and
I'm wrong oh no not wrong we I literally
said we have to add that to the OpenGL
and then didn't do it so I guess I can't
call that a surprise when I said that we
had to do it and then didn't do it so
the light probe P just has to go in here
and you can see that I'm using parallel
arrays for this and that's just because
I suspect in the future I will need to
do graphics card transmission and I
don't want these things intermixed
because only some of them will get
transmitted light probe P won't like
probe irradiance will or something there
abouts
right so the light probe P that happens
here all we're doing is just assigning
that over so where the light probe
irradiance previously was getting
assigned which is down in here Oh in
fact we're already there we're right on
it right here this code when it sets the
light perm irradiance just has to set
the light for a position array so that
there's actually some place to put those
right and then we should not get any
surprises or shall I say if we get
anything else
it will be a surprise and then we need
to do something we've done all the
plumbing work now we actually have to do
something with it right so that's what
our next step is okay so taking a look
at all of these you can kind of see you
know we've got their colors in there and
and that's all good so what we want to
do now is we need to start actually
sampling from these things somehow we
need to try and figure out a way of
getting the light probes down to the
graphics card and picking out ones that
are close to the pixels that we need and
the way we were going to do that was
with a voxel right we wanted to have
sort of a fairly dense voxel that would
allow specify how we would pull out our
light information and go from there now
when I think about it actually I suppose
we do sort of need to transmit light
probe position sort of but it's not
immediately obvious to me how we're
gonna do that we probably need to send
down
[Music]
I mean just thinking this through right
it would obviously much more efficient
and easy for us if our light probes were
just voxel centered right like the best
possible case for us is light probes
just occur in the middle of the raxil
and that's the end of it and you know
that makes it easier to do the filtering
it makes it easier to do the
transmission source less data but
completely honest I'm not sure how that
would work with a flexible world layout
like ours
so I'm not really sure happy you know we
would be able to get away with something
like that we can pretty trivially use
the voxels to pick what we are going to
bilinear between or trilinear between if
we use all eight cubes of the voxel that
surrounds the player or up the lighting
point but
I just can't quite figure out if I did
that I feel like we just need to store
the position still
so I guess I would say I don't really
have any ideas here this is this is kind
of the ugliest part I'm not really sure
what to do about it we could choose to
use the lookup that didn't quite do it
this way meaning a non voxel but I just
don't know
I don't really see that as being
something that's gonna be any better
yeah I don't I don't really have any
good ideas here I mean basically the
problem is very simple we want to light
with the lighting probe it would be very
easy for us to light with just one
lighting probe finding the closest probe
would be a pretty simple voxel lookup
and we would just light with it and
that's not too bad right
but the problem we're gonna have is that
if we only lit with just the closest
lighting probe then we end up with a
situation where we will see some
lighting pops because where we change
from one probe to another probe you
would see the discontinuous lighting
change as you move between them so the
reason that you typically by linear
blend between lighting probes in at
least some fashion or at least linearly
blend between at least two is because
you're trying to prevent that pop from
occurring and I'm trying to think if
there is some way of blending these
together in such a fashion that would it
would not require you know eight
lighting probes to actually be loaded
and then blended per pixel right I mean
that just seems brutal you know what I
mean
and furthermore after you load those
eight you still don't really know what's
going on because the lighting probes
have different locations so you would
still have to use you know you'd still
have to use basically like some kind of
positional blend
yeah I don't know I don't know this
parts this parts a little troubling and
I don't have a lot of good ideas for it
it's a spatial query to find the light
probes and I'm not sure I have a good
idea about what to do using it voxels
one way to look things up it would work
pretty easily although maybe would be
time-consuming because of all the
texture lookups to just look up the
eight voxels that bound where the
location the pixel is that you're
lighting and then do trilinear to find
what the actual inbound light is you
could certainly do that but the problem
there that I see is how do you do
the trilinear between things with with
arbitrary positions it would actually be
a little bit it would actually be a
little bit difficult to figure out how
you would do that and and maybe so okay
so I guess one answer is even though the
lights are not at the Centers of the
voxel you could just pretend that they
were meaning you don't really care where
a light probe is it's just at the center
of oxal for all intents and purposes
you could do that the problem with that
is if the light probes move then you end
up in a situation where the movement of
the light probes creates its own set of
discontinuities now maybe the answer is
just don't move light probes light
probes have to stay where they are and
that's probably fine
so maybe the answer is light perhaps
have to stay where they are
we don't really end up caring where
light probe is we treat the light probe
as if it's at the center of the voxel
and that's how we do our blending and
that's pretty much it and we try to make
those two things line up as much as
possible
but when they don't we don't care that
way we can sort of just do one divide
well it's not a device to multiply we
can do one multiplied two and then get
take a fractional value which ends up
being the correct amount to blend by
right in terms of T values for the
trilinear blend and I mean I guess we
just try that first it sounds crazy to
me but then again GPUs are incredibly
fast these days so I don't know yeah I
don't know so if you imagine what this
would look like I mean let's just write
it out
so if we take a look super at the Z bias
program what you can see here is that
well we're not we're not gonna have to
change the fragment shader obviously I'm
sorry at the vertex shader that can be
fine
also at this point I think we may have
eliminated the Z bias as well so at some
point we may be able to get rid of that
I don't know but if we didn't look at
the fret the fragment code as we're
doing it right now what you can see is
there's affection some like light thing
happening right and then we've got like
this
sunlight thing happening and and all the
stuff we commented those out because
they're not actually happening anymore
but we need to start putting those back
in you know I'm saying so basically this
right here where we produce a value that
we multiply our surface reflectance by
that needs to reappear and if we want
that to reappear we've got this lighting
disabled thing we just have to on
lighting disabled and it will come back
in right so we would delete that so
lighting is no longer disabled and then
what we would do is in here we have to
replace this lighting some code with
code that actually does the lighting
fetching that we need it to do so if you
imagine what has to happen per probe is
we would need to fetch a probe and the
irradiance there from which is six
irradiance values which you know this is
why I say we really want these things to
be you thirty twos because we don't want
them to be that big but so we
effectively need to fetch this is um
this is you can see why I'm nervous
about this right
so if we have six radiance values that
means if we fetch eight probes times 6
or radiance values per probe times once
they're compressed down that's 4 bytes
we have to fetch 192 bytes of lighting
data for every pixel which is not my
favorite thing in the world
but I think that's just where we're at
so I think we just start with that
and we then will try to figure out how
to optimize it and maybe we go read some
research papers to see what kind of
solutions people have come up with here
because I
yeah I don't know like what exactly we
would do maybe that's not that much
anymore these days I don't know but if
we were to compute the bandwidth there
look at 1980 at 19 that's good
1920 by 1080 which is the number of
pixels we're gonna have to do at a
minimum but we did some work that kind
of gets it down to like you know not too
much above that times 192 that's just
like kind of ugly
that's 398 megabytes of texture
throughput per frame right and so you
know how much text in addition any
texture band if we happen to be using if
we assume the game is trying to run at
60 frames a second we end up with 23
gigabytes of texture bandwidth being
consumed for lighting now granted we
don't consume that much texture
bandwidth for any other textures but you
know if we were to look at
what the texture bandwidth tends to be
which you know it's hard to estimate
because it depends how often it hits the
cache if I was to go to like a you know
modern 1080 or something which is like a
high-end one and we look at what the
gigabyte per second bandwidth this right
so like here's some high-end bandwidth
would be thread and 20 gigabytes per
second in terms of like peak theoretical
and like yeah I mean it's not horrible
but you know go down there and look at
an crappy card and you're like using the
whole thing right so it's basically
using like all of the bandwidth of the
graphics card just to load the lighting
data at that at that bandwidth now again
maybe it's not as dire as I am making it
sound because maybe you hit the cache
just so much because if you think about
what happens all of the pixels in a
given area are gonna be loading like the
same lighting information right so it
could be that just you hit the cache so
much that you just don't actually take
that much bandwidth so I'm willing to
believe that we should just proceed down
this road and see how bad it actually is
and then once we are satisfied that it
is actually super slow and bad then then
worried about it right cuz I don't know
I can't predict how the graphics card
will respond to having to do those those
texture loads
I just don't know and so the fact that
they'll hit the cache all the time
which I guess they really probably would
I just don't have any insight into
whether that means anything you know I
don't know so I'm gonna go ahead with it
for now
and
[Music]
you know if I if I think of something
magically smart that's better than this
we can we can put it in there afterward
right but this is something we may we
may struggle with because I don't have a
particularly good idea of how that would
work all right so if we move along here
what we would need to do is pretty
similar like this fetching some thing is
it's pretty similar to what we need to
do so beforehand where we were doing
this like running something when we do
the fetch and some what we need to do is
be able to pass the difference here is
before we were doing like a positional
contribution distance sort of thing and
we could still do that right like if we
wanted to we could totally still do that
and all that like the difference there
would so I just realized I'm wrong
actually we don't have to do what I just
said
so what I said was erroneous for any
given pixel because we are only looking
in one direction so that pixel has a
normal and the normal is the direction
in which you look at the lighting all we
would actually have to do is look at
which face of the light probe that is
implied by that normal so actually is
not true we don't have to fetch six
lighting values per probe we only have
to fetch one so actually it's only eight
pieces of lighting data that's much
better it's not 8 times 6 times 4 it's 8
times 4 I'm sorry it's yeah it's 8 times
4 times 1920 x 1080 right and that's a
lot more meager 4 gigabytes a second if
total bandwidth if you literally miss
the cache every time suddenly not as
scary is a number and especially because
I do think we will hit the cache a lot
of the time so maybe I'm more optimistic
about this than I that I was previously
maybe now that I'm thinking about it
it's not as fat because if you assume
that you're only looking at the part of
the light probe that you actually need
which I'm not sure why you wouldn't
suddenly uh that just doesn't seem so
bad
okay now one thing that I don't actually
know it may be the case that we want to
separate this out into more samplers
than we have it may be that we want one
light sampler per direction so I don't
know whether the light probe irradiance
is best stored as six separate textures
or if it's best stored as one texture
and we just stride idli access it the
reason I don't know that is because
again since I'm not a GPU person I don't
know if the GPU is particularly good at
doing things like six times an index
plus two right Intel chips make Swiss
cheese of things like this because you
can do little tricks and they have lots
of ways of making you know easy array
indices and stuff like that I don't know
to what extent GPUs like that sort of
thing so what I might suggest and you
know I'm just gonna I'm just going out
on a limb here but what I might suggest
is that we we will actually sort of
stride we will so we will actually have
a sampler per perlite I guess per per
direction
even that I'm not sure like I wish I
knew more about GPUs internals which I
you know it's just not my thing because
I'm just not sure this is this is simply
a case of knowing how GPUs tend to like
things all I really want to know is
what's the most efficient way to sample
this stuff and you know what meat you
actually you know what maybe is the best
way to sample this stuff the best way to
sample this stuff might actually just be
as a 2d texture where one dimension is
the number of light probes and the other
dimension is the direction that seems
pretty good right
I mean yet another way to do it would be
to do it as a cube map right like we
actually have a cube map and we
literally let the graphics cards cube
mapping take the normal and do that work
for us right so that's another thing we
could do and I guess I don't know maybe
that makes some sense as well right the
reason that makes some sense is because
then it's you know on what might be a
faster path because if the graphics card
understands that what we're doing is a
cube map sample it may be more inclined
to give us something optimal you know
let me just take a look here
yes you can see here we could just send
these down as cube maps right and we
would have a special binding for the
cube map then we just need GLSL and here
for cube map samplers let me take a look
where that happens so you can see G
sample cube here for cube map textures I
don't know where they I'm not actually
seeing where they actually specify what
the G OSL format is for sampling from
that cube map obviously let's see no no
no here we go oh no that's just regular
projective textures nevermind let's just
see if you look it up this way
here's the quick reference card enjoy so
here's the texture samplers so you can
see them on here and if we're gonna ask
it to do a cube map for us then you can
see here like there's a special sampler
for this one for cube and one for shadow
map cube I guess but anyway
so if we take a look at the cube sampler
and we do the p-value here that should I
think automate the lookup into which one
of the sides we're actually talking
about I don't really know if we want to
do it this way it could be one texel
large
but I'm just thinking about it and you
know my head I'm thinking well gosh if
we used a cube map yeah I mean I think
we probably don't I mean it's almost
like you think about it you must want to
use a texture array for this so that you
can basically pass the last parameter
and then you more want to use when
you're fetching in there you would more
just want to use like a positional value
that you computed so yeah I'm thinking
that maybe not I do think a texture
array would make a lot of sense but I
think maybe this makes not so much sense
right and so if you look at what's
happening here right where we do a
textile fetch into one of these samplers
if we were assuming that actually what
we're doing is we're sending down a
texture array or a 2d texture or
anything like that that just seems like
it makes more sense because then we just
compute the fetch value we use it and
we're done so I think maybe maybe we
want something more like that where we
have a rectangular texture maybe that we
sample from and we're just pulling data
out of it
when we want to do an actual fetch we
just do a thing that's like light
sampler we say that the light sampler
for our textual fetch is going to be
like the light index and the side index
right something like this so we
basically passed down which light probe
we were asking for and which side of the
light probe we were asking for that
gives us back the exact value the rest
of this stuff we don't care right so
fetching some now kind of becomes a
non-issue and if we wanted to look at
what sunlight would look like I think we
can kind of just get rid of all this
right and do something more like this
so if we imagined this sort of thing
well I guess we do need a v4 because
eventually we will use that for
intensity but basically we'd end up
doing eight Texel fetches from our
indices right and the tough thing there
is that these each index also requires
so it'd be sixteen Texel fetches total
which isn't great right but thankfully
sixteen is a lot less than one I thought
we were going to need because I thought
we were gonna need more like eight plus
eight times six which is so more
than sixteen right uhm so yeah so I
think we're looking at something like
this again it's not great you know I
can't pretend that I'm thinking this is
fantastic here but maybe it's the best
we can do you know I mean so if we were
to fetch our voxel stuff here right and
I don't know that may not be I have to
go look at how we should how we should
fetch into our voxel but if we were to
come up with these values so if we were
to have a way of getting these indices
out of the voxel which we know we can do
we've done it before
then we fetch based off of them and we
get all of the light data right then
it's a simple matter of doing the
trilinear blend and that's actually not
so expensive there isn't a whole lot to
it right so we know that we would have
three fractional blending values and all
we really have to do
is pick an order of how we want to blend
and blend right so what I would say is
maybe we do lips this way so we would
combine these two values right we would
combine we would combined the Z first
you know I'm saying
so we collapse a lot or you know maybe
that's X first I don't care how we want
a number of these it's completely
irrelevant as long as we make sure that
the the T values line up so maybe that's
X so we're gonna collapse the x value
first or the z value first or who cares
and just get that out of it right
so we collapse these down there's the
zero one and you know there might is
there a try am I being stupid is there
already just a try learn your blend here
take these values and expand that to a
trial in your mind I actually think
there is but you know what let's take a
look looks like only just the one
you can do it vector wide but we don't
really want to I don't think because
we're not really loading him strided so
I think I think we're pretty much we get
what we get but anyway you know if we
mix this is always the this is going to
be the T like you know we've got three
places we'll call it the TX value maybe
for now so first we're gonna mix along
the X and that's just producing all four
mixes along the you know the the X lines
of the cube that leaves us with for
residual like remaining values we're
gonna do the same thing again to produce
two values right so now we're blending
along Y oops
like so and then finally we just do the
last blend can you hit the light data
that's actually pushed all together and
that just blends this year on the one by
a dizzy so again not complicated that
part it's really simple so the mixing
yeah I'm feeling better about this as
I'm actually writing it because when I
look at it now that we see how much is
involved here really the sixteen Texel
fetches aren't great by any stretch of
the imagination but the actual work we
then do to light is pretty simple right
so you know this fetching to get smooth
blending in three dimensions that's bad
and you know ouch certainly but at least
it's pretty straightforward at
the end of the day to use it so I'm not
particularly worried at that point about
about what's gonna happen after the fact
right so yeah so something like this is
all we really need and if we go down to
the lighting code here you can see where
we're doing this we don't need to do
this anymore
so that's kind of gone really all we
need to do is when we are in here we
need to have actually compiled this
shader with or without lighting right
and I mean I guess now I think about it
if we always kind of have the lighting
setup so I think you I think we probably
want to compile this with and without
lighting and then we just want to know
if the lighting is enabled we use the
one with lighting and a filling sonmez
what we don't right so I think we want
to deal with that later so that's what
we do in here we call the sunlight
function and we multiply the surface
reflectance by whatever that is that we
get out I think that's all we need and
then we're pretty much done so really
the only thing so it's a it's a but
simple shader so really the hard parts
are just first coming up with which
direction we're supposed to look in
order to do that we need the normal
obviously we have the normal because
that was something that we're going to
be provided so world normal right and
world P we have both of these things and
it's pretty easy for us to figure out
what they should be so what we now need
to do is compute those values and then
sample out of the voxel be
on that piece of information so in here
somewhere we need like a light sample
sampler and we need a light index
sampler and this textile fetch here is
going to be something that uses the
light index sampler to me so we're gonna
say like fetch the light index sampler
at the light index and this is gonna be
it's like a base index and this is going
to be something where it's got like an X
or Y to Z offset right so I guess I
don't know how Tex will fetch likes to
work let me look at how it wants to
because I want to pass integers there
and I don't know if I can bundle
integers together in GLSL it's you know
it's GLSL who who the heck knows so if I
go look at Texel fetch
it's got like int avec so i Veck would
be what we would use so i do think we
could write i do think we could we we
could use an Isaac here so I could say
what is this hi Vic 3 I could say I Vic
3 and I could say that I want it to be
like you know voxel X voxel why voxel Z
or something like this right and then I
just passed that same log value because
we you know we don't have multiple
levels of detail so in theory I can do
something like this and then I can get
all of the all of the values out of the
voxel that I need for blending now of
course like I said in the voxel I don't
know like the way that we're actually
doing this these are probably encoded
backwards ways you know XY and z so it
probably would look like this but again
this is just I don't even know I don't
have any basis not
a GPU person I have no idea what the
more reasonable thing would be here oops
what happened here
what did we how did I mess this up so
badly
we've got like an extra two in there
that was weird
all right anyway so I don't know that
would be what it would be if we actually
had the voxel going this way around
because of course the indices are
usually switched inverted from how its
section stored in memory don't ask me
why
well I guess I know why because usually
in bitmaps you go in X runs in the old
days so that's why that convention
developed but so if we were to do a
textile fetch here we would know what we
need we need a Vox X a Vox Y and a Vox Z
and we also need to compute which side
we're looking out on so basically we're
computing where we are in the voxel from
P and which side of the light we want
with via N and it's pretty easy to know
which side we want based on the world
end but the tricky thing is I don't know
what the most efficient way to do that
is in OpenGL and what we want to do is
take whatever the maximum component is
and then whether or not it was positive
or negative right and so I don't know
what they've got in here like you know
you can see some things they have that
would be relevant there for doing this
especially because this is a kind of
thing that they need for doing cube map
lookups as well right and so I don't
know if there's anything in here that
can help us with that I'm not seeing
anything so we may have to just do it
completely manually which is too bad
right because it's it takes a while to
it takes us several instructions to do
and so I don't actually know if there's
maybe something that they had in here
that would have been an easier way of
producing that integer but I don't see
it right
like I'm just all I see is normal
function normal like regular functions
shouldn't say normal that's a little
confusing all I see is regular functions
in here I don't really see anything
yeah so I don't see anything there so I
might just be missing it and someone in
the chat if there's a GPU person on the
chat maybe they can fill us in if there
is a better way to do that but basically
what we need to do here is compare a
bunch of values and pick out which one
is the highest value and I'm not again
like that's why I say I'm not sure what
the best way to have it I'm not sure
what the right way is to to get the
graphs card to do that series of
operations but basically it's like okay
we just want to know whether or not we
want the sign to be positive or negative
and whether or not we were larger on X Y
or Z so the first thing we could do is
say well alright the result is going to
be the sign of the X component right and
so when we can or I guess it's even
easier than that it's just the
comparison of whether or not it's less
than zero
I think sign yeah I don't actually want
that so we just want like this we just
want something like this right and I
don't know to what extent I can even
write question mark syntax they might
not like that let me see if they have a
ternary operator in here yeah they do
because I think that's what well I don't
know if that's what they're actually
trying to say with that but
particular geocell integer from normal
direction
yeah I'm not sure I'm not sure anyway so
if we take a look at what's going on
here I'm gonna write it out really
poorly first and then we'll try to work
on it from there so then what I would
need to do is in fact maybe I just do
with if so that we don't have any
surprises here it doesn't really matter
it's not gonna be faster one way or the
other so basically what we would do is
say look it's zero and we'll just assume
it's zero if world and X oh and also I
should just use this convention that we
introduced already west east south north
up down right so here are the ways that
we want to do this it's zero positive I
start zero negative zero positive so
that's like X negative x positive so
basically I'd say like look we're going
to assume that's X negative if X is
greater than zero then we'll assume that
it's X positive right then we'll do look
if the Y component is greater than the X
component then it's actually pointing
more in that direction right so then
what we want to do is say okay then we
would say if we'll then I guess we
should say if the absolute value right I
have to say F ABS in G us all by the way
and actually no nope so then we would
say look if the magnitude of the normal
and y direction is bigger than the X
then actually we're going to look into
that cube instead so then we just need
to know which direction is you know what
I could do to I could probably make this
a little bit easier on myself by just
that I don't bother so if the world n is
greater than zero
you know I will I will oh my good this
way so I'm going to also track in
addition to my side i I'm also going to
attract a float
which is the max magnitude right or
largest component and so what I'm gonna
do here is say all right the maximum
component is X right and then what I can
do is just say well if the max component
is less than Y then I'm going to set the
max component to be equal to Y and set
the side-eye equal to 2 right then I'm
gonna say if the absolute value of the
mass component is less than Z then I'm
going to set the max impotant to Z and
set the side-eye equal to 4 right at
that point I now know that the max
component is equal to whatever value was
largest and I also know that the
side-eye is set to 0 2 or 4 to tell me
which axis is actually the larger one so
then I can just do if the max component
is greater than 0 then add 1 to it now I
have a way to distribute that value that
side value very quickly right and so if
I write this a little more compactly
here just so you can kind of see right
what's going on it's really just not
that many operations and these will just
be selection operations right
so it's not that bad to select a side I
that's not too bad and that will allow
us to look up into our texture so then
we just get down to the world position
here and the problem we're gonna have
here is we need to pass down a bunch of
crap we we don't really have a choice we
need to have a quick way of mapping our
world P into our voxel so we're going to
have to specify some constants here that
have to do with the voxel right and what
we want to do there is say okay the way
that the voxel is going to work is that
our world P we're going to subtract like
the voxel mid-corner right and this is
gonna be like voxel relative P right
once we have the voxel relative P we
then need to scale it so that it ends up
being integer values along the voxel
right so we then do a box index P right
that's gonna be the Vox rail P times the
in seldom write the the inverse voxel
Cell dimension that scales us to the
size of the voxel integers are steps of
one voxel along and then we can finally
extract all the values we actually need
so we do need floats for T X py and PZ
and we then you know we also need
integer values to be floored out from
those indices right now I don't know how
to get an IV out of a float that's like
a cast operation basically and OpenGL is
always a pain in the butt for casting so
while I would normally like a function
that's like floor - you know floor to an
integer right it doesn't actually have
that so we have two floor
and then convert right so what we're
gonna do here is we have the floor and
then I think that's the only syntax I
think I don't remember how you do
casting syntax in OpenGL but whatever it
was it was stupid so I think it has to
look like that and so what I want to do
now is just say look extract these
values out as integers and while you're
at it I also need the fractional value
right so I need I need this right I also
need the fractional value because I need
to use that for blending you know what I
mean
so once we compute this I once we
compute the lookup for the textures I
also need you to compute the fractional
blend values because those are the
things that I'm going to use down here
right
I think that's literally the entire
thing right that produces the entire
lighting lookup now at the end we
probably still want to do some work on
the actual lighting itself right
possibly I don't actually know but if
you look at what has to happen there
that's that's basically what we're doing
now the thing that's kind of nasty is
you know I don't know if we want to have
to do a three-way blend here to
reconstruct as the normal kind of spins
around
that's if we want things that are like
kind of rounded and whatnot
but I don't know if we ever actually
need that right we only have flat
sprites we don't have normal maps for
them maybe we do want that rounded value
you know or maybe we just don't care and
it's hard to say but if you look at what
would have to happen if we were going to
get a rounded value then again we end up
with we we end up with more issues
right so what I might do is say we
probably want to be able to try stuff
like that so I suspect what I will want
to do here is something like this if I
go in and I have a fetch you know call
and I can basically do the blend to get
the light data out so here so I can make
a fetch call the fetch call just takes
you know what you were trying to fetch
that would allow us at any time to do
the textile fetch of the actually you
know what this can actually be reused to
write it's only actually that be nice if
there's a way to bundle that together
but I don't know if I want to go to that
far so actually I take it back we
probably want saying that looks more
like this
and what you want to do here is be able
to pass all of these indices which is
kind of a pain in the butt right but you
want to reuse them because you don't
actually want to do the fetching again
to look up what all the lights actually
are here I mean and so yeah at that
point it's kind of a bit of a nasty
situation I don't know if maybe yeah I
don't have a lot of opinions about that
so at that point you want to be able to
fetch more than one side value from your
you know from your text from your
textile fetches and the problem is you
kind of need all of these right so you
need you need to be able to be like this
and actually maybe you just want to do
this you know I'm saying so I don't
actually know at that point you know how
ugly this becomes you can see why I
really would prefer to not have to fetch
a lot of information and I also don't
know if the cube map this is again where
the cube map stuff comes in if you
imagine something like a cube map array
so you said we have an array of cube
maps and we're going to sample the cube
map using this normal and here's the
array index that's exactly what we're
trying to do so if there's accelerated
Hardware anywhere to do that we would
want to take advantage of it and that's
why I'm a little hazy because I just
don't know to what extent that exists
it sounds great doesn't it
ah man that's just slightly different
from what we picked we picked negative
than positive and they pick positive and
negative we should probably switch to
using that same scheme but
so I'm gonna go ahead and say you know
honestly maybe we just should use this
who supports this let's find out let's
see who can do this magic magic thing
tell me it's just me like where are the
ads you know how Google used to have a
lot of ads on here where do the ads go
I'm getting nervous because if I don't
see ads I'm wondering what's happening
because I know that's how they make
money and if they're not showing it to
me I think they must be doing something
else bad like like my level of trust is
low but how bad is this somebody tell me
[Music]
I mean it seems pretty safe
I mean if Intel HD graphics is doing it
can't be that crazy you know I'm saying
76% pretty high
I mean we're already you know
multisample is kind of just assumed to
be possible on anything you were gonna
run a game on and that's only at 78%
right so you know it seems like we're in
pretty good shape there
let's see let's what's something else
that's really
dirigir at this point yeah so you know
if if sRGB is running at 83% that seems
pretty straightforward that you know the
cubemap array is just kind of there so
it kind of feels like maybe that's what
we want it would be lot simpler and then
we get the the sampling so I don't know
if it's if it would blend at that point
though but we could make it blend by
copying the values into so you know if
you imagine we actually make a 3x3 sort
of so we make the size of the texture 3
by 3 and then we stuff the values for
each face of the cube in there maybe
that's the best idea
I mean I want to say that's just what we
should do because then we're on the
faster path for sampling cube Maps I
think I hope
and all of the graphics cards will know
what we're doing you know if I slam this
crap down there it's gonna have no idea
what's going on right
so I don't know so that seems like maybe
something I do want to look into maybe I
want to do something like this where we
look up what the light indices are right
and then when we actually go get the
lighting values that's just gonna be one
thing and we're gonna bake the blend in
there
and that seems like possibly the right
solution I'm gonna say that that's
probably good because again I'm pretty
worried about the expense of all this
and I don't really want to be doing
something super weird so if I can
structure this as a thing that just
samples cube maps then that seems like
we're not really doing anything weird
and we'll be in good shape
so that means side-eye doesn't actually
have to be computed right so this can go
away
and what we would really be doing is
rather than calling Texel fetch we would
call there it is
we would call a sampler cube or a we
would call that and we just call I think
the texture function right and then we
would pass the correct set of values
there so then you know it's this right
and so when we call the it would be G
sampler Q well it'd be sampler we would
want simper cube array right
is that only in four
let's take a look at the floor Wow it's
a bigger car didn't it
so it clearly says cube array in here
for just a regular texture call right
and so I'm because I'm guessing that
basically like we just wouldn't be
allowed to do it here because there
isn't a 3d cube array version at least
not that I'm seeing so I'm guessing that
this was something that got added after
three after up in go3 which is mildly
annoying but if you look like I don't
really see any indication that you're
allowed to do it in actual GL 3 I don't
know how to tell it we want that
extension right I'm not sure how to
actually convince it that that extension
would be a good idea and that we just
wanted if it's there right yeah I mean
you can see it's just not contemplated
in here right you can have a cube
sampler but you can't have a cube array
sampler and that's sort of what we would
need
try to think if there's anything other
anything else fancy
so I suppose there is another way to
look at this problem entirely
and I suppose that maybe we would want
to and the way that I'm thinking we
could look at this instead is if we
thought of the lighting more as a
texture Atlas where we were actually
just gonna provide a 2d texture and then
the value that we pass into the sampler
just does a bilinear sample on that
Atlas that actually seems more sane to
me so bear with me for a second here
while I explain what I mean by this
because I realize that's a little bit
weird
I really need to get a Milton that has
this bug fixed that the the the strokes
look terrible does anyone know what the
status is of that there was like a
really bad regression in Milton that
makes it so that the strokes the
horrible and I don't know how to undo
that anyway
here's all I'm thinking what if we just
have a giant 2d texture the 2d texture
is laid out like this it is five high
it's five texels I mean look at that
it's horrible now Milton just got
totally Milton's just totally messed up
now I should probably try to revert back
to the old version but it's like really
bad so it's five high and then it's
light probe count times three long and
how its set up is little chunks of three
by fives right each three by five oh
wait I can do this
so each three by five
is a unwrapped cube now that's a three
by six alright so if you imagined a cube
like so and we unwrapped it such that it
basically unwrapped these four faces
here I guess now I think about it I
probably gonna need to be a little bit
wider than three but so I've got you
know here here here here so if I twitch
nobody's face like eh eh you know that's
B that's C that's D on there then like
you know E and s or whatever right then
down here would just be like a right B C
D and then a again yeah I'm saying and
maybe this is a little conservative so
maybe it needs to be more than what I
said maybe it needs to be like six by
five might be the right way to do it but
you get the idea right so it's something
like this and if you look at where each
of these faces is then the face is on
either side of a in this case or like F
and E right
and then for B right it's the same it's
F and E
and so you can imagine something where
we can just pick a point and get the
blend of any face of the cube just by
doing figuring out where we would need
to put the point in here
to properly sample it you know I'm
saying I think that would actually work
because no matter where you are in this
on here you should be able to produce
the correct blend here
right and since F and E can't touch each
other if they don't ever need to blend
right and every other pair
I'm sorry every other triple of blending
it should then should be related if they
touch each other right so like for
example I know that if I was to take my
cube well draw this a little bit better
here if I was to take my cube and think
about all of the places I could be on it
right it basically amounts to this
it's essentially a the entire cube has
eight quadrants right they mapped to the
sr8 octants they mapped to each vertex
so each of the whatever normal direction
you're pointing you only really have to
map between the outbound values of three
of the faces right and if you look at
what each of these are right it's going
to in and if I number them the same way
that I numbered them they're right so
we're just looking at the vertices
there's only eight places I can be on
the cube right and those eight places
tell me what my blends are so let's just
walk around them right so there's a EB
as one of them and in fact I'll just
write them over here there's a a B is 1
AE D is another Dec that's DCF that's
BFC that's be a F that is DFA and that
is BCE and that's all the blends that I
could possibly want to do so can I get
an AE B yes it's right there
right so that's fine can I get an AED
out of it yes that's right there can I
get a Dec out of it yes that's right
there can I get a DCF out of it yes
that's right there kind of get a BFC out
of it
yes that's right there can I get a baf
out of it that's right there can I get a
DFA out of it
that's right there can I get a BCE out
of it yeah that's right there right so
it does seem possible to do a blend that
would create what we want here and if
you always made sure you were inside the
triangles you would get the right blends
out now I don't really know how possible
that is because if you think about what
should have happened when you were up in
here right when you're in like you know
one of these sections of this cube
you're trying to smoothly blend between
the lighting that's coming in at eff the
lighting that's coming in at D and the
lighting that's coming in at a and it's
like not I'm trying to think of what
kind of blend that really is right it's
like a triangulated blend but I don't I
don't have a handle on exactly how right
but it's an interesting thing so if you
were to imagine I'm creating this kind
of a layout then what you could do is
take your input Q values translate them
into a UV look up into just this one
texture do the texture look up and
that's the lighting right that's the
lighting period so you only do that just
one time
so that would get the blend
automatically the directional blend
automatically if we wanted to do that I
just don't know I have to think that
through but we're out of time for today
so that's okay
I'm gonna go ahead and just keep
lighting disabled for now then so we
didn't finish yet and yeah we will pick
this back up next weekend or whenever
the next schedule I haven't posted the
schedule yet so whenever the next
scheduled stream is but I'll leave it in
a compiling state so we can get back to
it alright quick questions
would you want to do a debug Milt in a
stream not particularly man never looked
at that codebase before so I feel like
it's pretty obvious what's going on bug
wise like because they had an old
working version and they updated it now
it's broken so it shouldn't be that hard
to vent what the bug is right so I'm
assuming it's pretty simple maybe I'm
wrong about that
no questions
chirp circuit does this still work on XP
so if you compiled in 32-bit mode we
might be able to still get it to run on
XP the problem is we haven't done that
in a while so there's probably parts of
the code right now that we'd have like
casting errors and stuff like that so I
think you would if you wanted to run it
on XP you'd have to go clean some stuff
up first but it probably wouldn't be
impossible if you wanted it to run on XP
because remember Windows XP didn't
really ship a like true 64-bit version
you know what I mean there was a 64-bit
version of XP but it's not really quite
it's not the same as it's not really a
full 64-bit operating system it's more
like a 32-bit operating system with
64-bit extensions you can use and so you
wouldn't be able to run this on XP
without first read without first doing
some 32-bit compiles which requires to
clean up
[Music]
if you had to draw text in Arabic
Chinese Korean etc in a game how would
you do text shaping um I don't know so I
have not done any work with Arabic
Chinese in in particular I don't think
really requires a whole lot of special I
don't get the sense like Chinese
characters kind of could just be typeset
normally I think Arabic would be the one
that would I would think would be more
interesting in terms of like complexity
but I could be wrong anyway I have not
worked on that myself so I don't have
any strong opinions about it I I would
want to at least ship one game in Arabic
first before I had an opinion about it
actually six the big Fox says would it
make sense to store the whole cube the
whole cube of voxels as six 3d textures
one for each direction and then use
Hardware trilinear filtering so the
reason I'm not doing that is because
we're not actually storing color values
in the voxel we could and maybe we
should right but right now what we're
actually doing is storing indexes to
light probes the reason for that is so
the light probes are kind of large right
and so I don't know here's the
difference in practice and we can talk
about I mean you know it's because again
storing lights in a voxel maybe what we
want to do and I mentioned that before
so you know I'm not ruling that out by
any stretch of the imagination but if
you imagine having a 128 by 128 by 2
which is what we have right now you're
talking about going from that to
something that's at least that right um
and it's not that bad right it's not
that bad so I'm totally willing to
believe that we should just do that and
then primarily what we would do I guess
I mean I'm not sure but I think what we
would probably want to do is we would
basically have the voxel Pass be
something where we first render into the
voxel the lighting so you know we we
actually have a like lighting
replacement scheme that we render the
lighting information that we've computed
into the voxels that spams it out and
then we do the Texel fetches right and
maybe that's better right like I don't
know there's just a lot of complexity
here I don't know which ones better we
could certainly try it
we could certainly try it
would you overestimate sight FM the cube
map again really hard to say it depends
a lot on how we want to try and do that
blending and again so like let's say so
for example let's say we do want to go
ahead and use we want to instead of in
directing the cube map that's right in
directing the voxel we want to just put
the lights in the voxel right if we just
put the lights in the voxel then we
still have the problem of after we
sample we need to figure out what we do
with those samples and so we would still
be back to that problem as well it's
it's sort of a separate problem right is
how do you blend the directions together
alright I'm gonna light it down
thank you everyone for joining me for
enough so the hand made here us what a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow series at home
you could always peer to the game at
hand made here org it comes to the
source code so you can play around with
it
we also have a discord if you'd like to
chat about the series offline or while
we're online there's a pound live
channel as well check that out it's
opening right at the moment so get in
while you can
and we'll see you there I will be back
here at some point we haven't posted
schedule for next week and the coming
weeks yet but we'll post it as soon as I
get a chance so check the schedule on
the watch page I check this right here
we'll be updating that soon that's it
for today until next time have fun
programming LC ever around the internet
take use everybody