hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream we are mostly done
actually with doing a memory system
upgrade that I promised I would do and
did does it promise fulfilled where we
basically said okay previously we've
been working with just fixed memory
blocks where we have to sub allocate out
of those blocks and so at the beginning
of the program we have to allocate how
much fun we're going to use then we
subdivide it and that's a perfectly
reasonable way to write something like a
game where you want to maybe guarantee
that you run within a certain memory
footprint especially because you may be
on a platform which doesn't have any
virtual memory for example there were
plenty of console games that you know
we're running on systems as recently as
you know a couple years ago would have
been very standard to not have any real
way to implement virtual memory on these
consoles and even today there are plenty
of platforms you might want to ship a
game on depending on the circumstances
we're implementing something like
transparent virtual memory for your game
is not really an option so knowing at a
time that you're going to allocate a
certain amount of memory and sticking to
it is a valuable thing to know how to do
and to understand how that would happen
but at the same time it's also useful to
be able to do programming where you
don't know how much memory is going to
be used ahead of time and you want to
just let your program use as much memory
as it's going to use because maybe what
the user wants to do is 6 64 gigabytes
of memory in their machine and if your
program is hard-coded to only use two
gigabytes of that and they're like no I
want to make bigger worlds or bigger
things or whatever you want to
gracefully scale up to that and give the
user the option of using all that memory
and you need to allow that dynamic
growth to occur and so what we did is we
changed over our memory system without
really changing much of the usage code
at all so we can still switch back at
any time like we're pretty much in a
place where we don't have to do dynamic
allocation but we do allow dynamic
allocation now so it's really our
prerogative which one we want to do at
any time but we have one more
thing we have to do in order to call our
port complete and that is we have to go
and make it so that our looped live code
editing is able to support dynamically
growing arenas because the way that we
use to support dynam the Russians they
support the way that we used to
implement the loop live code editing was
since we knew that up front we just
allocated you know however much like a
gigabyte of memory or something and ran
the whole game out of it then what we
did to implement loop live coding would
you say well okay good just just write
that two gigabytes of data out right and
that's all you need to do you don't need
to do anything else because if you write
that two gigs that could give io data
out you know the game couldn't have
touched any other memory and so if you
load the two gigs back in you have
restored the state definitively right so
what we would like to do today is we
would like to go ahead and implement the
loop live code editing in a way or i
should say reimplemented perhaps in a
way that will allow us to take advantage
of the dynamic arenas such that not only
will we be supporting the dynamic arenas
correctly but we also will get a bonus
from supporting them that we didn't have
previously because we can do a little
bit of extra fanciness and technically
we probably could have done this
fanciness before but you know now is a
good time to do it as well so we'll get
some fancy nas's in addition they just
left up on the screen face de 343 so if
you want to follow along at home and
you're typing along with me you want to
use de 342 source code as a starting
point that's what i'm using right now
let's go ahead and load up for kodir
here and i'm going to load the handmade
project file and then i'm going to go
ahead and build it and then as I
demonstrated I think at the end of
yesterday's stream or not yesterday
today's Monday so it would've been last
week stream everything's working okay in
the game at the moment in terms of stuff
we can
observe but again if i try to do loop
live coding here I've hit l and then I
hit l again you can see that nothing
happened right we didn't actually get
any loop live coded think I'm still in
control of the game nothing is happening
and if you think about why that's
occurring well it's relatively obvious
why the only thing we were doing when
you push the L key down right is we
would go ahead and say win through win32
begin recording input right and if we
take a look at what happens here you can
kind of see what we were doing is we
have this thing called the replay buffer
right and we copy the game memory block
into that replay buffer at blah blah
blah right here's the the total size of
it and that game memory block used to be
the thing that we put all the memory in
but now there's nothing in it right so
there's literally like nothing in that
game memory block at all so there's
really no way for us to there's really
when we do our loop live coding nothing
is happening right like we're not
actually recording anything because the
game memory block isn't set to anything
so there's no way for it to ever
actually do anything and furthermore I
think when we're doing like our map view
of file and all this other sort of stuff
we come down here and you can see we've
got the total size is set to zero
because you know there's there's no
actual storage or anything so all this
stuff is just like you know all of this
stuff is not is not set up right anymore
as I guess what I would say so the first
thing I want to do is say let's get rid
of some of these to do is because mem
lard pages is not really something you
can count on in Windows I remember some
people recently telling me they tried to
look into it and apparently it's just
not something you can ship in commercial
software at the moment at least not in
games because you have to do a bunch of
you have to be like have the correct
like administrator privileges to even
use it and all these other sorts of
things it's like you just don't want to
do it so we're not going to do that and
the transient storage stuff we don't
have to worry about anymore
because now that we're allowing 2na
maclee growing arenas we don't have to
have that rigorous segmentation if we
don't want to we could just sort of
allow the game to break those things up
as it seems necessary so what we want to
do here you start rethinking a little
bit of how this is working so that we
can do something that's going to allow
us to do our loop live code editing in
the same way that we're doing it before
but with the dynamic arenas so if we
take a look at what a win32 stage
structure has in it you can see that
it's got this idea of a game memory
block and then it's got these replay
buffers now the replay buffers are fine
for the moment because really all they
are is just places to store data and so
the fact that we have these replay
buffers around is fine the problem is
more this part right here where when we
actually go to use one of these replay
buffers the thing that we've got is just
not conducive to anything it's not
useful what's going on there right so
what we'd like to do here again is we'd
like to do something where we can figure
out how to translate what we were doing
which was to say here is the memory
block that the game needs saved and
restored we just need some way of making
that work again with the sort of more
dynamic system where you can allocate as
many buffers as you want from the game
side of things right and that seems a
little bit more complicated at first
it's like what are we going to do about
that but really if you think about it
it's not really all that much more
complicated at at a basic at a basic
level before we were saving out one
memory block now we just have multiple
memory blocks right we know there's been
multiple allocations if we just had some
way of enumerated all the memory blocks
then we could restore all the memory
blocks right so the fact that the game
is not using a single large memory block
doesn't really change the algorithm that
we would need to employ to do loop live
coding which is save the memory blocks
right and then restore them when you
want to hit the loop point that's
actually all we have to do it's just we
now need a way of iterating over
multiple memory blocks instead of just
having one memory block so really what
we want to do here is say something like
you know win32 memory
and we want to make you know a list or
something right I want to say you know
here's the next one you know maybe your
maybe it's a doubly linked list or
whatever and then I've got you know in
here the size of that memory block and
the base of that memory block right and
that would be the arena information
there right now what I can also say
about this is well you know it's
possible that the size well okay Emily
but I mess it I'm going to leave that
was gonna say that so once I have this
information right if I wanted to I could
then say alright we've got you know just
like we did before we've got sort of a
linked list in here we'll put a sentinel
in there which is oops every Sentinel
which would just allow us to iterate
over all the blocks so now if just every
time we allocated a block we sort of had
an additional one of these things in it
that would really be all we would need
and since we're allocating memory
already it's pretty easy for us just to
expand the size of the allocation and
stick this onto the end and then we'd be
good to go right so if I were to do that
where we do our win through to allocate
memory right you can imagine exactly
what this would look like it's really
really trivial all I would do is say
okay there's a win32 memory block that I
want to assign and I want to link that
in here what I do a virtual analog i'm
going to ask for the size plus the size
of a win32 memory block right so the
application asked for some precise I'm
going to ask for a little bit more than
the size right and I'm going to stick my
little secret information in here
because that's just the kind of person I
am and so off we go so when I stick that
little piece of information in there
then what i can do is say the same trick
we did before i can just say oh okay if
you were to take the the result move
forward by the original size now i'm
pointing to the end of the buffer but i
know i added an extra win32 remember
luck beyond that
I now know I have a win32 memory block
worth of space that i can use right so
then i can say well okay now i know i
just have to use my win32 state
structure which I don't know if we made
that global hopefully we did it should
be but I don't know if it is it could be
that we never needed to I don't tend to
make anything global until I actually
needed to be global if that makes sense
and so it's possible that we never
actually do that to be global and so it
wasn't win32 oops to skate it looks like
we always pass that through because
there it is so I'm not sure why we do
that because here it is the top of wind
main and we never created again i'm not
sure why we decided not to make it a
global probably just because like i said
i tend not to make things global if they
don't have to be but you can see that
this probably should have just been a
global there's no reason it can't ever
not be that one there aren't like other
ones that can exist so it's kind of just
wasting time to pass it down if that
makes sense and we don't really want the
application to have to do a call back
there so we certainly could make this
you know global variable like so where
we put the win32 stayed up here i could
say you know this is global variable
global win32 state or something like
that and that's just something that
happens and the people can get at so
that's all well and good we got now we
got to do some replacement stuff here we
could also say that you know these sorts
of things where we're looking at the
wind through to a state or whatever we
could say that these are not going to
take that pointer anymore either those
could could get that pointer directly
off of the global I don't know that we
want to do that because if something is
operating as upon a pass in pointer
there's no reason to like undo that
flexibility I suppose so i'll probably
just let that chill the way it is
although we could consider it redundant
and collapse it at our convenience
certainly so anyway i'm going to take a
look here at the rest of the stuff we've
got and just see what's going on ok here
we go folks do not take three
arguments what are you talking about of
course ritual elek takes four arguments
oh there it is that's the problem what
are you talking about it's like it takes
for argument's doesn't it but yeah there
you go so again let's go ahead and take
a look at what we need to do here if I
want to link in this this block of
memory oops come back there go to it
this of course that's using win32 state
I think what I'm going to do here I
might as well just bought this while I'm
still in there i'm going to call this
just state like we were doing before and
then make that a pointer to win through
to a global 132 state and then i'll
replace like address of wind through to
state in this function with just the
state pointer right and then I think
we're good let's take a look at anywhere
else that that was happening so it looks
like yeah there's a couple of places
where that's been used this we don't
really care about yet but we do want to
make sure we link up that pointer so we
want to do here is we don't really care
about that but we do want to do is we
want to initialize that Sentinel so
right here we want to again you remember
we've done w linked list a couple times
on handmade hero they're really simple
right we want to make sure that state
free evils state and state next equals
state so that it's correctly just a
little circular list right there just to
make sure that when we start looking
things in it works okay that's about it
oops such memories memories Sentinel
there we go so yeah and then I think
probably should actually type that
incorrectly Chris now I'm behind my head
and I can't see that's okay we'll do it
without being able to see you know i'll
switch over here there we go and so now
we just have to actually link that in
right and i guess i should also while
I'm at it well see i didn't want to
touch those yet till we finish
the part that we were working on so
we'll get to these are is they happen to
be higher in the file unfortunately but
we'll just get them for a second and
actually go do the linking or maybe
they're not hard in the file maybe I
just got to a point of no errors down
here yeah that was the problem so when I
get one of these blocks again i want to
set its previous and next pointers to
the correct things I don't really care
where I link this in so we'll just link
it at the end because that seems like
where we would normally link something
so if we have the global win32 state
memory Sentinel I'm going to go ahead
and get a pointer to that so it's a
little easier for me to type it there we
go and all I want to do here is I just
want to link this in so that the
previous person here is whatever the
Sentinels previous person was and the
next one is the Sentinel so this will
add it kind of like to the end of the
list right and then we just do the
standard thing that we do to link up a
linked list once we set the pointers
properly we can just set the previous
person's next pointer to us and the next
vs previous for us and now we are linked
into the list right so that linked up
our links every time one gets allocated
off it goes now in the case where we
virtual free we have the exact same
situation exact same corresponding
situation but we have an additional
problem here I suppose now that I think
about it this is going to be something
that we I don't know exactly how i would
get around it means we might have to put
this thing at the beginning at a
predictable location so you can see the
the conundrum that i run into here which
is that when we allocate something i
won't actually know what the size is so
i won't be able to get back the block
header when we free it right if that
makes sense we could force the person
freeing the memory to pass in how big
the memory is and then we could leave it
at the end but in this case if we put it
at the beginning we wouldn't have to do
that of course if we do put at the
beginning then we mess up the alignment
of the first bite so we would have to
make sure our memory block was probably
like cache line aligned or something
like that like a 64-byte alignment on
that block so that we don't risk messing
up anyone's alignment that's probably
fine to do
rather than forcing people to pass in
the width earning the length that seems
fine so what we could do is like assert
that the size of a win32 memory block
equals 64 which is a cache line size we
could say note Casey ah let's see we
require a memory block headers not to
change the cache line alignment of the
page of a an allocation as you say so I
guess that's okay it was not my first
choice with that I guess is just the way
the cookie crumbles sometimes so what we
would say here is that we're going to
start that's how much we're going to
move it over by and then what we do is
we just say oh okay so really what
happens here is we're going to get a
win32 memory block back from this right
that's the base pointer at this point
now so we call virtual a lock that's
what we've got then what we're going to
do is say well the result is just after
the header right and that's fine so then
once we link it up if we go and what we
can do here is store the information
that we wanted to store we don't need to
store the base pointer anymore because
now we just know the base pointer it's
the memory block so we don't have to
worry so really all restoring is the
size and if we want this thing to be
cache line aligned then what we have to
do is say okay we got 88 for the pointer
eight for this pointer set 16 8 4 the
size right which is I guess technically
for compiling a 32-bit it wouldn't be so
we might have to we might have to really
relax I saw it on 32-bit or change the
padding but after that we just want to
say we have some padding and if we did
one padding here this would be 32 right
it'd be 88 and so if we want 64 we just
need to add more padding so now this
would be padded out to that size and
this of course will check that size so
we make sure that we're using this
function we know that it's the right
size so then I can say all right the
science is whatever the size was of the
allocation right
and honestly I guess we don't really
super need to store that anymore if we
don't want to so we could actually say
you know we could actually say this
where we just have like a bunch of
padding out there really all we need is
the the previous xpress we may
eventually want to store that size
anyway but for now I guess we don't
really have to so that's really it then
when we come here we could say all right
when we get something in that we're
supposed to free take a look at the
memory block for it since we know the
result is going to be moved up one what
we want to do is basically move back one
after we cast right so we're going to
cast it up to a memory block and then
move it back one because you know that's
actually where the memory started and
then we would free it of course before
we free it we want to do the little leap
frog thing to remove ourselves from the
linked list so that this page is no
longer in that list right so we want to
say like okay we've got the block we
know we have a previous the next part of
the pages on either side of us in the
list we want to go to the previous guy
and say hey the next corner for you is
actually the one after me and hey mister
mister person after me the previous guy
is going to be my previous guy and then
we just free ourselves right so we just
point make sure the list crosses us now
and doesn't you know touch us at all and
then and then we're good to go right now
there is sort of a caveat here there's
something relatively important that that
needs to be observed and that is that in
this scheme we have added something to
the allocation that did not previously
happen and that is that if we were going
to be calling these functions from
multiple threads at the same time we
would not be thread-safe anymore and the
reason that we would not be thread-safe
anymore is because this linked list is
being touched in a way that isn't
particularly thread safe right so in
that sense we need to if we want to make
this actually work although virtual a
lock itself has thread protection in it
our ability to use it does not so this
is all thread safe nothing that's
happening here is touching any memory
that someone else might be touching this
is not
right similarly this is thread-safe this
is not so essentially and also we want
to bring the base pointer right I might
also add we probably want to do some
assertions here just going to see what's
going on I so in these in these
scenarios what we need to do here is we
need to like lock these we need to lock
access to this list if we want this to
be thread-safe so the question is do we
want to be said thread-safe memory isn't
allocated that often in our scheme we do
not call this allocator on every
allocation we only call this allocator
under circumstances where we've run out
of space in like a pool of memory and we
need more space for the pool so since
multiple threads may want to call an
allocate memory when they run out there
doesn't seem to be any reason not to
lock it right because it's just not
getting called that often and I don't
think we have to worry particularly much
about any kind of situation where these
locks would slow us down so I think what
we want to do is ticket lock just these
X just just the access where we link
ourselves skin to the list right so what
we're going to do here is say okay our
win32 state structure right our global
in 32 state is going to have a memory
mutex on it and we're going to take and
release the memory mutex to make sure
that no two people are using it at the
same time now normally we'd use that
memory mutex also to do the work of the
memory allocation but of course windows
is already doing that for us and is
already mute xing it for us and there's
no really way to share that mutex with
them normally what we want to do is bury
what this bury this operation inside the
mutex for the virtual Alec because we
would know that they were already taking
one because they have to touch the
memory page and presumably they can't
do that when I'm taking a mutex of some
kind that we could hide behind but we
don't have access to that so that's not
really on the table for us so what we're
going to have to do instead is exactly
what i'm doing here and just have a
mutex we can reuse our existing mutex
there's no reason not to we can reuse
our existing mutex for that and make
sure that we can know that that ring is
not being disrupted in any kind of
fashion that would be bad right ok so
all we need to do now is actually make
one of those new texts and I don't
really remember where that information
was is where that mutex type thing was
at all in the first place but maybe it
was called ticket new techs yep so we'll
just go ahead and say there is a member
a mutex and say note to touch the memory
ring you must take the memory mutex
right ah yeah and that's that's that so
now that we've done that right we now
have a ring that we know tracks all of
the memory that we actually have and so
if you take a look at what we've got
here and here's the part where the size
where we probably want to put the size
in there right because you can kind of
see where this is going where we when we
need to copy when we need to save it the
state that's when we're probably going
to need to know what the size is because
we won't necessarily know what the sizes
anyway if we go ahead and do that we
could see at this point when we go to do
something like copy memory you can see
what we do in the two different cases
for when we're going to record input we
copy memory from the pooja me from the
replay buffer wait does that go the
right way begin recording input it
copies from the replay buffer to the
game memory block this looks backwards
Oh copy memory is a win32 call but we
wrote this a long time ago we didn't
even call our own copy I'm like that
looks backwards and hey it's because
they use the reversed set of parameters
from what we use that's why all right
doesn't matter anyway point being they
copy this copy is the way I thought it
data just it was different parameters so
you just need to know the size the the
memory block that the was storing the
information we want to save and then we
put it into the replay buffer right and
the same is true here where we were
doing the playback we do the opposite
copy and off we go now what the
important part here is when we actually
do the playback what we want to look at
is we want to look at our when we're
accessing these files we want to extend
the notion of this of the memory block
that we're saving to be some number of
memory blocks which means that the first
thing that we're going to have to save
is like how many memory blocks there are
or at least a null terminator that says
this is the end of the memory blocks and
now comes the input or whatever because
you can kind of see what's going on here
where we do likes would through to get
file location or whatever we do some
stuff here where we go all right where
you know where are we actually going to
read from and when we do those reeds and
that sort of stuff we were going to be
reading from places that are we were
previously counting that we just had a
size of the memory block that we could
just save and load from and that's not
going to be true you know anymore so we
need to think this through in a little
bit more of a complete fashion and
furthermore I don't think any we don't
really need any more to use the crazy
weird memory map file stuff that we were
using before because now will only be
saving data that we actually cared about
and so in theory we should be fine to
not do any kind of
any kind of hitting the we shouldn't
really have to do that kind of fancy
footwork if that makes sense it does I
am a little bit confused as to why we're
using memory map file stuff I guess the
reason that we didn't use the memory map
file stuff for anything other than the
memory block was just because we didn't
want to limit how big it could be or
something because you can see here we
just stream in the the input stuff so
it's like we could just do that and I
think we don't and so I don't really
know that we need like you can even see
us doing this stuff here right yeah I
think this can just go away so I think
we can get rid of the map view of file
thing I think we just don't really need
that at least I'm pretty sure we don't
and we could just get we can just say
that's not important right so if we go
down to map view of file and all this
stuff for we're going through these
buffers and creating them for the first
time through where we yeah where we need
to do this this this sort of nonsense
with the file mapping we can probably
just get rid of that so i think i'm
going to go ahead and do that let's go
ahead and get rid of all this stuff
let's not create a file mapping what's
not map you a file will get rid of all
of that stuff and we'll just use the
method we were using before where we
create a single file we stream out to
the file and that's all there is to it
right so in this case where we have
these replay buffers those replay
buffers will not have the file map or
any of that stuff nor will they have a
memory block or any of these things I
guess they'll just have whatever the
file name was of the thing of the file
that you'd be using and we'll go from
there all right so what we would want to
do now we don't care about any
we probably just go ahead and go I guess
what we want to do is say if we had a
because what's interesting is we
actually do create the file right right
here we go to the replay when we create
a file handle and there's the file
handle but what I'm not clear on is why
we have to reopen it here
so I'm inclined to say you know I really
don't know why that is we create two
handles but I don't see why we would
need that one I don't think we do so I
think that's residual as well so i think
really all we need to do is this and i'm
not even sure we really need to do that
the replay buffer filename bit doesn't
seem super useful either i must see so
can we just get rid of all this stuff to
be any of this why is this even here
does anybody know like what happens if i
just get rid of this stuff although yes
I need to leave that in there what is it
even necessary do we even know do we
even care yeah one-third you get replay
buffer I just don't think it's I don't
think we need that I don't think that's
a thing and that's just not a thing
anymore I don't think we need to get a
replay buffer at all I think we just can
go back to the old way we used to do it
where we just say like hey why don't you
tell us where that info file would be if
we had one start recording it and have a
party my friend right i mean just go
nuts seems like that would just work and
then go ahead and do the copy memory
here
right and then when we come in and do
the end recording we just do the clothes
handle which is fine and when we begin
the playback we do the same thing so we
left the structure in from when we did
it originally and it seems pretty good
looks like state input recording index
needs to get set as well like so but I
think that's it and then in here we
could just say same thing get the
location create the file and then to do
stream memory in file and what we could
do here is say like if state playback
handles not equal to about file handle
you know then maybe we record the fact
that that happened kind of things sort
of maybe a little bit if you please just
to have some error checking there in
case for some reason and don't ask me
why type stream there not a thing so if
we don't if we can't open it for some
reason you know who knows why then we
can so something more like that which is
more like we had it originally seems
pretty good replay buffers don't care
not relevant you know and offer you so
let's see so then we've got a few
residual things from our win32 state
days the win32 state thing i think this
was just a pointer here right yeah
undeclared identifier oh no just ate of
course actually don't care about this
right because we just got rid of that we
nuke that
and that's it okay so now we're in good
shape i think because at this point we
can go look at that to do so we get we
need some diagnostics in here right a
lot of to do is there just like we need
some Diagnostics where is our to do
stream Eric file so now what you can see
here is we just have two things we've
got street memory out to the file and
stream memory in from the file so what
we want to do here is we need some way
of actually streaming memory in and out
we don't have any way to do that at the
moment what we were streaming in and out
before is just like input information
right we were just streaming in and out
what we were sending in terms of input
but we now need some way of streaming
memory blocks out in and out right and
so what we could do here is say alright
let's say we've got a structure that's
like struct went through on disk mem
block or whatever she'll be like this or
saved memory block and the save memory
block is just like a size which is how
much is coming after it and in like a
base pointer right so it's like where
this memory should be put where it
should be written to if you will and
where it will be placed and what we
could do is we could just say well keep
reading these in until you can't until
you get a base pointer of 0 and then you
know the next thing you're going to read
will be the input stream right so we'll
just say we in the file we have base
pointer size block of memory base
pointer size block of memory and as soon
as you see a base point of zero size of
0 you know you've hit the null
terminator stop reading and memory
blocks start reading an input right so
if you imagine the stream memory in
situation what that would look like
right is you just say like ok start
loop up reading from the file one of
these things right read in those every
time you read one of those in you just
say okay if the blocks base pointer is
not equal to 0 then you're going to read
it in if it is equal to 0 then you're
just going to break you're just going to
like forget about it right just move on
do something else with your life so yeah
let's put that in here so we're going to
read off the playback handle we're going
to read in the memory blocks here I
should probably say size of block and I
should probably do that now this is
going to be a lot harder than it has to
be unfortunately and let me go look up
the read file dock there so we can pass
the right parameters to it there we go
so we've got each file we got the buffer
pointer right there we've got the size
and yeah so that's the number of bytes
read which we don't care about and then
we got the overlap which we don't care
about all right so that's going to read
in and we're going to have a problem
here in a second that you'll see we're
going to have to make a 4i loop and this
is one thing I really hate about windows
I do not understand why they're there
wasn't a 64-bit value passed for right
file and read file because you can't you
basically can't pass it a 64-bit size if
that makes sense so if we allocate a
block of memory that is bigger than 4
gigabytes which nowadays isn't an
impossibility you know probably on hand
material we could just assert it and say
no one's going to do that but if you're
actually trying to support it for reals
what you would need to do here is your
read write file operation would have to
do a for I loop right it would actually
have to loop over
and like break it up into parts so
anyway so what we want to do here is is
we want to do read files and and just
get the information we need in this case
we have a block we know that we have a
base pointer coming in so just take the
base pointer read into the base pointer
we know we have a size oops so we'll
give it the size and the thing that's
that's a bummer is we have to cast a
size to a u32 and here we can just
assert that the block size is less than
or equal to you 30 to maxvill and like
so eventually we could support this by
putting a 4i loop in here that just a
sequential series of reads to read it
out right now we know we're not going to
have afford any 4 gigabyte stuff so it's
okay but it's just worth noting right
but that's all I'm really talking about
in terms of what I'm saying for reading
in the memory pages right and then for
writing out the memory pages it's the
exact same thing we would just say like
okay we want to do a for I loop and we
want to loop over all of the pages that
we have well how do we know what they
have well that's the work we just did we
have the memory Sentinel so we know that
we can go ahead and say the global win32
state that we loft it up there get that
memory Sentinel out in fact let's go
ahead and just get it this way right
yank the Sentinel and let's just go
ahead and I just like source block like
so let's just go ahead and start with
the first block and go until we hit the
central again and then what we'll do is
we'll write these out we'll take this
the save memory block will say okay the
desk clock base pointer is going to be
equal to whatever this location is that
we're trying to say that so in this case
it's just the source block we know what
the source block resource I should
probably just in here actually have a
thing
so like in line you know avoid star get
base pointer for win32 memory block
because it's literally just that but in
case we change that scheme so we'll just
say like get base pointer there's our
source block and we want to convert that
to a you 64 so we're going to change the
pointer into the you 64 then you're in
the desk block what we want to do is say
let's make sure we save the size of that
thing and that's the part that I sort of
was saying we don't really need I was
wrong right good this is that sort of i
said little earlier i was like uptight I
should have kept the size so that's why
i said we need the science we need to
know how much of memory to write out and
we might be able to call windows for
that I don't really know I don't think I
remember virtual Alec get size of
allocation I don't really remember if
there is a call for doing that because
they probably have to store that
information win32 get size of allocated
page that's the one we're talking about
retrieve information about a range of
page the virtualization of claims
process what's the support on this guy
XP is fine that's good virtual query
memory basic information so there it is
the information is here right so if we
want to we wouldn't actually have to
save that information anywhere we could
just ask windows to give it to us anyway
and that now that i think about it if we
wanted to we could also lean on that to
keep us from having to put the thing at
the beginning we could put it at the end
instead as well because if we wanted to
we could
call this function and just say hey
windows tell me about this this thing
that I've got what's the where are the
base where was the base allocation
address for it and not in and so on so
forth I'm not going to do that right now
just because I might as well show you
how you would do this on a system that
couldn't query it but now you know you
could call virtual query get that I'm
going to save the side circus eh it's
free because we had to pad this thing
out anyway well it's not really free
because like i said i could put
something at the end blah blah blah but
anyway point being i'm just going to
show how to do it without that so I'm
going to say like right we could just
grab that out of the source block which
we're presuming we saved we would then
call right file to sort of put this
block to the disk and that's just going
to write sequentially we're also going
to go ahead and write out its contents
like so save my base pointer fair and
that's it right so that's really all we
need to do and then when we're done we
just need to write out that Mel
terminator like i said before so that
the system knows the person who's
reading knows that we're done so we need
one more at the end right which is just
this sorry actually want this one which
is just a desk block that doesn't have
anything in it right it's just empty
it's zeros and that's it so that's
really all we need to do now we just
need when we do our allocation we do
need to save what the size is so in here
we would need to say like oh ok yeah you
know the size of this allocation is
whatever the size of this allocation is
right so similarly here when we do
result this would be get base pointer of
the block
and I think that's about it yeah so now
we're in much better shape hopefully you
can kind of see what we were doing here
it's not particularly complicated the
code it's exactly the same as what we
were doing like there's there's really
nothing to it it's just now instead of
forcing all of the memory attitude one
block that we write out we just write
out more than one block we read out as
many blocks as we need to write out in
order to capture all of the dynamic
allocations that the application has
done up to this point right and that's
that's the end of that now that should
work I think but you know we might have
bugs obviously so we're going to have to
debug the bugs but after we do that I
think we should be okay let's take a
look what is this is a deallocation call
here is our memory block
so this looks like our block did not get
initialized properly here let's see
let's make sure let's make sure it was
initialized properly there we are so
let's take a look here what do our
blocks look like that start that all
looks lovely that's exactly what I would
have expected that to look like I'm a
fan and now let's get our result pointer
so here is our result pointer if I was
to take the result pointer cast it to a
win32 memory block and subtract one
would I be happy I would be set 64
megabytes looks like this is a 64
megabyte large fellow and let's see okay
so that all seems pretty good what
happens when we come in here
what is block block this block is fine
that seems reasonable and we get our
virtual free yes so let's take a look I
want to take a look at my global win32
state I want to take a look at my memory
Sentinel and see what that looks like so
that seems pretty reasonable right so it
looks like it's not it's not like this
gets messed up every time through
it actually goes for a while before it
had that problem and in fact it didn't
actually have a problem this time right
so we're dealing with a knot we're
dealing with a subtle bug not a
straightforward or you just messed up
something obvious right so that's not
great I don't like a in non reproducible
bug being in there at the moment but I
guess that's okay we do have to earn our
game engine program and keep now and
again but that's just a little bit weird
I'm not sure why we would have had that
in this situation because it doesn't
make a whole lot of sense but is that
something that we can reproduce ever
there we go so let's take a look the
first clue that I have here that things
are a little unusual is that we're
inside the asset loading which suggests
to me that this is a thread problem like
our mutex is insufficient for some
reason like we're not actually getting
that now that actually does remind me
technically we should have ticket locked
are our walk so our right at writing out
and reading in should have been ticket
locked presumably because they actually
walked the list and if anyone was going
to touch them at that time it would have
been problem but we can get that in a
second so the fact that we're having a
problem with something in that sense is
like suggests to me that I must have
either our ticket lock isn't working for
some reason which I don't know why that
would be but I assuming that it is it
means we have some kind of a problem
with our actual like what we decided to
lock because there shouldn't be any way
for multi-threading to affect the fact
you know the the lock should have
prevented anything weird from happening
with with this with the locket with the
linked list update right so I'm trying
to think what would be causing that
especially since as far as I can think
of the only people ever touching this
are these two routines so you can see
when we go to allocate memory we know
exactly what we're doing we're you know
we're calling the virtual a lock we're
getting out the sense at all ah that is
our problem right there so I was a
little too conservative there wasn't I
perhaps one should not be so one should
not be so so so so we can only set to
the sentinel and know that that's
correct and we can always set the size
but as soon as we are accessing a
pointer off the sentinel someone else
might be touching that right so
technically that all has to go inside
the lock because that is updating the
state of the link right
I think that's probably it
so we don't really know for working a
hundred percent yet because that was a
transient bug but I'm pretty sure that
was the bug so I don't know if hopefully
you understand what was happening there
so because win32 allocate memory can be
called from multiple threads at once
what was happening there was just that
because one line that touched the part
of the linked list touched a part of the
linked lists linkage was outside the
mutex what could happen is two people
could have ended up with pointing to the
same previous pointer which would
corrupt the linked list right instead of
actually inserting both people
sequentially it would insert them both
into the same place right which would
then cause the link the list to be
completely worked at that point so
moving that inside the ticket should be
sufficient okay so we finished all of
that but we're out of time so we'll have
to wait till tomorrow to debug the rest
of it presumably it doesn't work yet i'm
not sure but here is like our yeah so
wait how did we crash here Oh inside
colonel base what what does the problem
I am Not sure I see the problem that i'm
not sure i see where we crashed though
we crashed inside Colonel base I should
probably not debug this now but I'm just
curious we want to load one of these we
did a read file with the address of it
and the size of it right I wonder if
actually that's not really optional I
wonder if that's not truly optional and
we have to pass a pointer it's entirely
plausible to me that that is the case
let's find out let's just take a look
and see if that does happen to be the
case I don't see why not I doubt that's
the case but I'm just curious
that sure does seem to be the case well
so how wait a minute how come that
didn't save there it is weird so that
was the case I guess so yeah you do have
to pass by a thread guess what it said
optional it didn't really mean it was
that optional it must be only optional
if you're going to pass the overlapped
right
yep that was the problem all right good
deal so not so optional but what are you
going to do okay so in that case I think
we're basically done here we will have
to verify we will have to go debug like
to get the loop working it looks like we
had some one other bug potentially in
there which I'll try to keep myself into
bugging because I really wanted to bug
it right now but I'm not supposed to
really be doing that because we are
technically out of time so you know
that's just one of those things that
happens when you're out of time and so
yeah because this is just like it's
doing the read file when it reads in one
it should be reading in one that's zero
and then it should break and we do write
out one that's zero here I don't
actually know it might be that right
file also requires us to pass that dummy
pointer let's double check add optional
rich should inform you know only one
thank you okay great nope fantastic it's
great it's fine i'm super happy about
that i love it i love what you've done
with the place bytes written and go
ahead and put it in there just put it in
there bytes written by it's written
bytes written by kitten all right
alright so I'm assuming that where this
is breaking is it's just not mmm okay
wasn't expecting it to be there what's
so I guess it does reload but we're not
quite reloading correctly well that's
better than I would have thought that's
rather grand I suppose so it looks like
we don't have much work to do so
tomorrow we will tomorrow we will finish
debugging that for now let's go ahead
and go to the QA I think we're basically
done with this but we just have a few
more loose ends probably to try up let's
let's take a look
soy sauce the kid could you explain the
padding you use for the memories direct
I believe you said it was for cache line
stuff so you admitted it if your bitted
it but it just resulted more cache line
mrs. or what a crass game so basically
it's more just like a principle of least
surprise thing so generally if I'm
writing something that does memory
allocation and I'm not really obeying
here which I I wish I was but so I'm
much I'm more careful about this sort of
stuff in in our main code base at Molly
but it just it's a lot more finicky when
you start getting into this stuff so I
do sort of a lighter version of it on
handmade hero but basically what I'm
doing memory allocation stuff I
generally don't like to do anything that
would violate the general conception of
what a page is to the system so I try to
provide memory AP is that like the
person who's using this memory subsystem
can know that if they're trying to
allocate something at page granularity
they can so I try to return base
pointers that are at the beginning of
memory pages in release mode in debug
mode I will skew the pages up to catch
overruns or ski or skew them back and
Men protect the previous page to catch
under runs in like randomized settings
but generally speaking I will try to do
that and then any data that i want to
add i will add kind of on a page off the
end of that block so that i don't change
what the person thinks they're doing in
terms of lining things up to a memory
page and that's just I feel like if you
can spend some time to do that it helps
because then people using that memory
system don't have to worry about like oh
I'm trying to I want something cash
aligned and so now i have to like ask
for a certain alignment or whatever and
i can't just assume that when i allocate
memory it's going to be cached a line
because of course it would be normally
reallocated page from the Opera do
system of course the first byte is cash
aligned you know and and other stuff
like this so that's all
how did you get to where you are today
and how do did you do it in terms of
coding knowledge there's actually a pre
complete answer to that nope there it is
this stream right here actually has the
whole answer to that question its pretty
long so if you want to you can go there
and listen to it
toreador it's a bit early to ask but
will there be a handmade con 2017
probably not I think that we will
probably do a handmade con in 2018 and
we'll probably do it earlier in the year
so I we have to figure out a good time
for handmade con and it may be best to
put it at a different time of the year
because based on the place if I think
we're going to probably want to keep
doing it the place that we're doing it
at this year and the problem is that
that place because it also hosts the
Seattle ballet and opera and stuff
christmas time is like a really hard
time to book because they've got all
this stupid stuff like the Nutcracker so
if so ideally we would move to a time of
the year when people aren't going to
these these kinds of shows we could have
a much easier time getting time slots at
the venue so but I don't really want to
do at amby con 2017 and you know may be
cuz we'll only have been like six months
since the last handmade con right so
we'll probably do is instead of doing
six months to the next time icon will do
18 months the next time icon and then we
can go back to doing it eerily assuming
that people want to do it literally
maybe the kind of thing that wants to be
every two years or something like this I
don't know we'll see how it goes we'll
have to see how we will have to see like
how it goes this year and if people
still like it and you know I mean we've
only done it once and we know that it
went really well last year but you know
doing something once you maybe you just
got lucky so let's see if this year is
really good and it's something that that
seems like it should keep going then
yeah I think probably handmade con 2018
would be the next one and it would not
be a full two years from this handmade
con it would be more like a year and a
half
that'd be my guess again don't know yet
that's kind of a remains to be seen sort
of question but there you go would you
recommend any specific resource for
letting C++ so far i've been using the
team the learn cpp website i don't know
i don't have a particular recommendation
no have you ever used a rope to
manipulate strings I like I remember
playing around a little bit with various
string things at one point and I think I
maybe did like a toy implementation of a
rope for strings but I have never used
it since in my recollection I but keep
in mind that I generally don't do pretty
much anything with strings in a
sufficient amount like nothing I do with
strings tends to do enough string
operations in a rope like fashion to
make that be even remotely a thing I
would care about so it's not like I used
ropes and time them and decided they
were a bad idea and then don't use them
it's more like I've never really had a
time when I really needed to evaluate
string manipulation schemes for heavy
restring rearrangement kind of stuff so
I've never had the occasion to use ropes
let's see
aren't you going to read in pages that
have been allocated yes there's two
things that we have to do sort of next
time when we get this working in the
first place because right now you know
we'd correct we'd crash immediately if
we tried to read in the page that Ben
deallocated so I was fairly certain that
isn't a problem that we're looking at at
the moment but what we'll have to do
next time is two things one we're going
to want to protect our pages when we
start recording so that we only write
out pages that are actually that have
actually changed and then the other
thing we're going to want to do is
prevent a deallocation during input
playback and recording so that anybody
who tries to deallocate a page can't do
so right we can if we want to get
fancier that solves the deallocation
problem but it doesn't solve the case
where someone's allocating a page during
that pot doing playback that page would
get orphaned right in a bad way if we
just tried to restore the state and so
I'm not sure what the best way to fix
that is we may have to do something
where we actually are smart about
rewinding the pages where we actually
like flush the whole like we actually go
through and diff the memory list and I'm
not sure right
so I don't know exactly how we'll do
that we have a lot of you know the
problem is very well defined but until
we actually get in there and and type it
in i'm not sure exactly what the best
way will be to make that work we'll see
but yet we should be at a point now
where we're at least nominally working
but we haven't but we're not quite so
we'll have to debug that first once
that's the case then we'll sort of get a
little more fancy with our page system
and yeah off the top of my head I can't
think of how we will we will handle the
allocation stuff meaning if somebody
allocates if so many d allocates a page
during input playback or recording
that's that's real easy because you just
don't do it and it's not a problem but
if somebody allocates a page that's a
problem because every time through it
will allocate that page and so I mean
yeah I I can't I don't really know what
the best way to deal with that would be
I I'm not sure storing tortoise so with
memory systems do you always try to put
extra bits of data at the end to ensure
if they asked remember me from a civic
address and it doesn't ruin their day
yeah i mean just generally speaking i
try to make it so that you know if i if
i can and sometimes i can I try to make
memory subsystems just not do anything
with the memory it's just like give it
back directly as much as possible but if
I am in a situation where I have to mark
these things somehow then I generally
try to do it at the end of the pages
because typically there's room at the
end of the pages anyway the only time
that there isn't is if someone's doing
exactly page boundary based Seth and
then there's nowhere to put it anyway
like know where you put it will be good
it's bad at the beginning it's bad at
the end it's just bad period right but
at least if you put it at the end then
you are still at least giving them back
something aligned to a page for the part
they can actually see and yeah this is
extra page off the end boohoo so yeah I
mean it doesn't mean you can't put it at
the beginning you could put at the
beginning by giving them a page back of
beginning and allocating the page prior
to the allocation and sticking it in
there right so you could do that if you
want to too but you know
alright
so regal let's go ahead and close it
down uh all right thank you everybody
for joining me for another sort of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always we almost
finished up the memory stuff but we've
got some work still to do tomorrow so
hopefully tomorrow we will be able to
sort of like debug everything put the
finishing touch finishing touches on it
and then we can also like I said maybe
look into some of other things with it
that we could do now that we're being a
little bit more sort of hand holy about
like how many memory pages were
allocating and where there's maybe some
other stuff we could do that's fun with
that but so I hope you'll join me for
that for now if you want to follow along
with the series at home of course you
can always pure to the game on handmade
here or get comes with a source code if
you would like to play around with it we
also have a forum site where you can go
to ask questions a patreon page from on
supports video series a schedule bot
that tweets the schedule at you and an
episode guide for catching up on old
episodes I'll be back tomorrow 5pm this
next time we're doing an 85 85 schedule
now so i'll be back 5 p.m. pacific
daylight time is it or we just have we
change the standard time now i don't
know 55 p.m. here in seattle time and so
hopes to you back here for that we'll
finish up the memory stuff until then I
hope you guys have fun programming and
i'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everyone