start recording okay hello everyone and
welcome to handmade year the show where
we code a complete game live on stream
yeah some new stuff today
first things first Sergio I totally
solved our Milton problems from
yesterday so we now have a super good
super full functioning Milton it's
really zippy it's perfect I'm pretty
excited about this actually this is the
best drawing we've had on handmade hero
this feels like really good I think it's
going to be much nicer to work on the
blackboard now so thank you very much
Sergio for fixing that for us it feels
really great now even on the super old
machines it's you know pretty much
perfect the other thing we had is
someone was suggesting on the pre stream
that we maybe try code excels for grabs
debugging because as you know the
graphics card is really old so stuff
like render dock which we tried before I
just don't work and so they were saying
maybe try the old version of code excel
because you know it had to run on these
old cards it's a legacy piece of
software that was for from that time
period so we downloaded node version and
we're going to try it so I'm just going
to go ahead and try it here's we're
going to try on say three days for 88
today so day three t7 source code is
what's sitting on my drive right now so
I'm going to just go ahead and see I've
never used this piece of software before
I assume this is this used to be Grem
ADIZ program right like AMD bought like
remedy or something or bought the gr
debugger from them or whatever something
like that I don't really remember but I
feel like that's what code excel is is
like the the was the latest incantation
at the time of crema DS thing but I
could be really wrong about that I don't
remember that's just my hunch I so we've
got this debug here and I'm just going
to try doing what it says so I've got
create a new product for debugging
and so I'll just say you know handmade
hero it's a local host it's a desktop
application so I'll go and pick one of
those we've got that on here it's not a
mayor to build so we just want win32
handmade and then our working directory
is is not filled with data
I believe so we can load our stuff and
we don't pass any command-line arguments
at the moment so I think that's really
all we need the source file thing I
don't know if they need that or not if
they can get it out of a PDB or what's
going on but you know it just so happens
that all of our code is in this
directory so I'll just give it that in
case that helps I don't know what this
is about really looks just like Oh how
do we determine where a frame is or
isn't swap buffers would be fine for us
we don't have any OpenCL we're only open
GL so that is the area would be fine I
don't know that we really need much in
the way of CPU profiling right now we're
mostly doing debugging so I could
probably turn that off but so I don't
know how to use this tool yet I'm just
going to leave it on defaults on
anything that I don't obviously know
should be changed and so all of that
looks fine so I'm just going to say ok
and and then I'm going to see what
happens if I run this I assume that just
clicking on this this local arrow here
will do the trick
I don't know if I need to say so there's
places to put the logs I'm going to have
it put the logs in our temp directory
here just because why not and and then I
guess I can just leave all of this stuff
basically the same for now so I'm going
to hit the Run button
there's our you know there's handmade
hero running and then I'm going to just
close it see if it did anything I don't
know if I needed to tell it to start
maybe I didn't do that I'm not sure or
maybe that was enough it's a little bit
behind my head here so it's going to put
it in here
so let's see this just looks like basic
stuff like when a context was created in
things like this so I'm guessing that I
probably have to do something to tell it
how to capture a frame or something like
maybe I have to put push one of these
buttons you know
hello what are you what is this output
properties click so sort of functional
history call set locals watch
so it looks like I mean one thing I can
do here is set a breakpoint on something
I'm not sure that that's really what we
want but you know I let's just try
something basic here because we're just
trying to get our feet wet so here we
run the program it's a little weird that
we saw anything on the screen before
calling swap buffers but that might have
been from the last run of the game like
maybe that's just junk that was in the
buffer or something or hard to say but
it did what we asked which is it did
break on swap buffers and so I I guess
I'm just going to kind of walk this back
here so here's a complete history of
what happened so it looks like that
worked pretty well which is kind of nice
so this does look to me like this looks
right I mean you could imagine us using
this to find bugs right this is this is
a pretty nice like just if we were to do
this ourselves you would have had to
write something that logs all of our
OpenGL calls and here is just a thing
that will do that for us so even that is
probably worth it right and again now we
can even see like this is what I was
talking about you can see if we have to
issue a draw call for every triangle
because we have to change textures right
so although I am a little bit confused
as to why it's always saying buying
texture - oh right because that's the
white the white texture that's for the
just the cubes I bet but shouldn't we be
seeing other there should be a bunch of
times when we bind something else
probably now in the first frame though
because we haven't loaded anything yet
we haven't loaded any bitmaps yet so it
probably just skipped those can we go
again to the next frame and not great
I'm guessing I don't need to send that
probably because they're not updating
this version of software anymore so yeah
it's a little iffy right but it did run
once so let's try that one more time and
see if I can run it twice or if it's
going to crash every time we try to run
it twice so basically it can't run twice
let's just hit debug know how to detach
this doesn't look like they have it
attached see I would like to see where
we broken barcodes you know maybe we've
got a bug that's you know causing the
crash that we could fix and then it
wouldn't be a problem but it's hard to
know because it's not going to tell us
where we were getting that crash right
so that's unfortunate so I don't know
that would be helpful it might just not
be because it might be too unstable but
it's a little early to tell right so
let's take a look at the breakpoint
window here I'm going to delete this
let's say we were running so it can run
multiple frames is fine and then I were
to break yeah so that really just looks
like a problem with code Excel and not
us unfortunately right I mean
yeah
not not great so I don't know I couldn't
help maybe uh it's just looking a little
iffy there though is all I think what
probably I should do is at some point I
should update this machine probably just
put it get a new machine honestly the
whole machine is so old it's it's you've
decade old at this point more or less
mister graphics card is so I should
probably you know just update to a new
machine maybe we can find some company
interested in donating machine for us to
run on handmade hero I don't know
but yeah anyway I'm going to go ahead
and switch over to working on the code
regular and we do want to before moving
on we do have the sort of bug report
that came in on the pre stream it's also
on handmade network I'll pull it up now
that folks found which which might help
us out we don't know yet but it could
with what we were playing around with so
we're going to widen this a little bit
so let's go ahead and take a look at
that here so here we go so the problem
here is that when we do resolves
multisample depth test is disabled so
basically the thing is that it's the
assumption is that the disable depth
test is creating other bugs for us and
that's the problem so I'll read this
whole thing out and then we can go take
a look and see what happened
all right so Moxie is high and I believe
it locks is MTX knocks right on the yeah
I think MTS mocks you are mocks on the
forums which are MTS mocks on the chat
right MTS mocks is here I think anyway
I'll let you guys figure that out but I
believe MTS Knox and mock so the same
person
I believe me to probably attempt to do
handli resolve if the desk buffer is
disabled with GL disabled GL depth test
which is true because we we do switch
that off right but this also disables
the depth right and therefore messes up
all the following peels before using the
handmade resolve the blip frame buffer
would fill the depth buffer but now this
should be done manually a good way to
demonstrate the bug is to only appeal
1/4 file sheffster not so anything so a
better way is this I found that that
with trying to improve the manual is off
fader I believe the deaths in max range
would give good results but ran through
the definition while debugging ask the
dustbin max worked okay if I used used
sample count sample can help fraction to
set the Alpha value of the combined
color and a pound to find depth
threshold of and that remember we try to
set that it wasn't working so we kind of
knew something was wrong we couldn't
figure out what this is a good good find
thank you mocks after bit more fidgeting
and actually watching the rest the
episode I saw that you were also using
centroid to get better death result Ixil
with the center I still used some edges
won't get smooth the connection of a
lower block against a higher block but
a-sailing essentially gives weird
results along other edges so I tried
collecting all the samples without
respect for the depth they have and only
setting the GL frog depth to the depth
max of the tested range by commenting
line 31 table the range test I think
this emulates the normal resolve as far
as selecting colors the best but still
the upside of clearly the depth buffer
output that combined with sailing centre
a deficit to get the best result a bit a
key but seems to give nice results so I
guess what I would say is everything
there sounds really good
I totally agree that the GL disabled F
tests I hadn't thought about that
but it is true that they
basically when GL depth test the way
that they do the depth testing thing is
a little weird so GL disables depth test
is really more like saying GL disable
the depth pipeline and if you want depth
right to occur but not depth test you
don't GL disabled GL depth test what you
do is you enable zeal depth test let's
set the depth function to effectively
not test so it's really just more of a
misnomer but it's it's really GL disable
deal depth processing in a sense and so
mocks is completely correct here that GL
depth bunk GL always is the right way to
disable that if we want to
I don't remember thinking about this I
suspect that really what happened is it
just totally flipped my mind as many
open GL state things do it's one of the
problems with the programming with GPU
especially is that because you're not
stepping through the code yourself it's
really hard to remember what you're not
thinking of right because normally when
you write code you can you wrote all the
code in there so you know what he did
and you're not going to be stupid enough
not to write a depth value in somewhere
if you thought you were supposed to
write and you would see it very clear as
you didn't but with GPU code that's not
the case there's all the stuff that's
configured and you're just flipping
switches and if you forget to flip one
of the switches well some whole set of
things might be happening or not
happening that you just assumed were
happening because in your mind that's
what you were trying to do and you never
explicitly write the code for it so you
just have to remember which switches you
have set and which ones you tell in this
case I think that's just completely
flipped my mind
entirely I didn't think I thought about
death rights I think I was only thinking
about depth testing and I never
remembered like oh wait if I turn off
depth testing depth writing will also
turn off and we need to write to the
depth buffer so anyway if nothing else
even if it doesn't work thank you very
much mock's for looking into that I
probably would have just moved on and
never really gone back and revisited it
but now we we will and maybe we can find
something that works in the end
because it would be nice it would be
nice to know that there what if there
was something here that we could work
with I so let's take a look at where we
left this because I we were kinda
messing around with a I only remember
exactly what we were doing at the time
so first of all this def threshold
should be much too high probably
although we probably want to look at
setting this in a different way so
because remember is this the depth range
is nonlinear so probably what we want to
do you know we might want to try to come
up with a way of analyzing our depth
separations in a way that's not going to
vary tremendously as we progress outward
from the camera because things that are
small changes close to the camera and
things that are small changes far from
the camera
could have different meaning in terms of
whether we think they're close enough to
weren't peeling or not peeling and stuff
like that so we don't really know the
behavior of that but we might want to
look into that or at least we want to
mark it so that it's somewhere far in
the future people are looking at this
code and trying to improve it they can
get it you know maybe get a leg up on
the fact that that was something that
never really got investigated you know
that sort of thing okay so in theory
this looks pretty good with there's some
stuff that I would like to do to it
certainly but it looks like it's still
doing roughly what it should be doing
which is combining the colors and and
then setting the depth value it sounded
to me like emptiest max was suggesting
that in playing around with it he found
it was better to just actually sum all
the colors together so you don't you
don't want to only some the ones in the
depth range that's what it sort of
sounded like he was saying is what he
found for the best results so we're
going to start by leaving this the way
it is but then we'll come back here and
and try taking it just boxes advice I -
you know just see whether
returning that to a general sum for the
color side of things and only using the
picking range to pick the depth is
actually an improvement visual quality
wise because it might be so okay so
let's take a look here the reason that I
was assuming that wouldn't be the case
because look that would over contribute
things that were underneath because
they'll get contributed on both depth
peels but you know it's hard to say
right multi sampling is a bit of a hack
with depth feeling right when we're
putting them together like this so it's
not unusual to expect that happy-happy
versions of the resolve might also be
better because we're kind of doing
something a little aqui in the first
place right alright so let's take a look
at that result code that's the compiled
not what I want none of this is what I
want where is my actual result there it
is
so here's resolved multi sample you can
see the disabled death test here and the
reenable in the death tuck here and what
we're basically saying now is that well
we want the depth test on all the time
because it really means that pipeline
what we don't want to do is we don't
want to test against the depth buffer
because we just want to write to it and
so we could clear it here or something
like that potentially but that's just
wasting time since we know we're going
to write to every pixel we just want to
say don't test it right and so if we
just set our GL depth bunk here which I
believe we were setting here you can see
it to Gio less than or equal to what we
can do is just say oh let's just set it
to deal always so it never does an
actual test against it and then when
we're done we'll set it back to less
than or equal to so this is effectively
turning off depth testing but it's going
to leave depth writes on right because
remember depth map controls depth right
and that's that's a true and we're not
touching it here so that was just a dumb
thing on my part again I was kind of
thinking oh I'll just turn off death
testing but
that's not what I was actually doing I
was actually turning off the whole
dipped pipeline which I didn't actually
want right so I believe that was all
that MCS MOX was talking about in the
initial set I'll just verify here that
I'm doing similar thing so that's the
same Jill different always less equal so
that's exactly the same that's all he's
got in the coast of it so I'm assuming
right I'm just assuming that that is
exactly what he tried and he was saying
that was reasonable so then here is his
shader which let's leave this let's live
this alone for a second so that we could
run what we have before messing with the
result shader which we may have to now
do because remember we didn't we were
just trying to play around that we never
really got anywhere probably because our
depth rights are just completely wrong
on the load visual studio or try to and
that's going to take a good long while
probably because now we installed the
stupid code Excel Visual Studio
extension which is probably now ruining
my life yep there it is
so here that is hopefully that doesn't
is that do that every time
no that's not too bad is there like an
auto update feature because if there is
I need to turn that off right away
[Music]
so like a extensions add-in manager nope
what is code Excel if it's not an add-in
extensions and updates'
uh so in a balloon
Persis man and now I'm in meow meow all
right I don't know I'm just going to
assume that I don't care about this so
we'll just pretend this is fine I don't
know if it's fine or not but we'll
pretend that it's fine so the first
thing I'll say is that that is actually
looking much better right because or
wait we don't know you know what we want
the multi sample hint on yet okay we got
rid of those things but it's not on yet
is it yeah I declared victory too early
all right so let's go turn on the multi
sampling by default I'm going to clear
this guy out here God code Excel codec
so why do I install that extension
why did I do it you know why did I do it
how do I disable disabled disabled stop
bad no incorrect
so I uninstall it can I not just just
say no
bad dog bad dog
no let me see if I can get rid of some
of this crap
so that's back to normal so maybe we're
okay there alright so I'm going to go
into win32 handmade I'm going to try a
couple things here much to do a couple
things to put us into a position to
better explore this resolve and just see
what we can do here so the first thing
I'm going to do is I'm going to switch
to half res right so I'm going to switch
to this mode which is 960 by 540 I'm
going to turn on the multi sampling tint
by default and I think is the pixelation
hint I'm just going to look to see where
the pixelation hint gets done here
OpenGL frame buffer filtered on the
results flags
so I think I'm not don't quote me on
this but I think if I set this to true I
[Applause]
should get one-to-one pixels now I hope
I'm not 100% certain of that but that
was my hope so I think you know now I
can actually look and see if I take a
look at the print screen of this I think
I can see one two one
well it's not one to one it's one to two
right
pixels so I just want to see if that's
true one two three four yeah so this is
good so now I'm in a mode where we can
where we can run at full speed right
because the Scribus card does not like
running with multisample at 1920 by 1080
we know that so I can run it in half res
but I can still see every pixel is now
four pixels so I don't introduce any
other blurring because which is what I
don't want right I don't want to
introduce linear smear there which would
make it harder for us to debug on the
other 2x up sample which is what it
would normally do all right
so if I come through here and run this
right like now we pretty much you know
to be honest a lot of this is actually
looking okay but it's clear that our
resolves like it's just it the edges are
so crispy in some places although not in
others which is a little bit odd but we
also get these lines down the middle so
we're still having that problem however
all our artifacts from the peeling are
gone at least most of them are maybe
there's one like right there
so that's actually a big improvement to
again thank you very much too empty as
much for giving us the opportunity to
work on this again by finding that bug
bugs like that a real hard to find
without a debugger that without an
OpenGL debugger obviously you got to
really look for him I probably should
have had some mode where we draw all of
our death buffers because then we would
have seen that it was wrong that's one
thing I can think of it would have
caught that bug other than just you know
straight up inspection of the code more
meticulously and hope that you think of
it so now all we really have to do
assuming than that is working properly
now is see if there is something we
could do with our death stamp like here
and again mps fox is saying maybe just
just use all the samples just use them
directly and don't worry so much about
the death man
so if I were to do that if I base it was
to just get rid of the test there that
would give us this and you know some of
it looks pretty good some of it doesn't
right it's pretty hard to tell exactly
why I can't say I had a lot of theories
so if we take a look at the difference
between multi sampling and not multi
sampling so you know there's crispy
edges everywhere in the non multi
sampling version if I turn multi
sampling on the crispy edges go away
like here but they don't go away
at places where the cubes intersect not
really intersect but a but directly
right so they are for all intents and
purposes intersecting and so the
question is why is that happening right
and you know is there something we can
do about it
it does look you know I would say at
this point it does look just generally
better with multi sampling on which is
more than we could have ever said before
so I think thanks to Moxa's careful look
at the result shader we are in a better
place than we were we're maybe not all
the way home because it would be nice to
clean up those edges but despite not
being all the way home I do feel like
we've made a visual improvement so I do
feel like you'd rather play the game in
this mode than in the other mode so far
when maybe there are some artifacts we
haven't seen yet but you know it does
kind of look like most of the time what
artifacts there are are at least no more
objectionable right so now one question
would be well what if we go start
playing with this shader a little bit
more you know maybe there's something we
can do that improves it even further
right that's going to be an even better
way to way to have it run and so you
know most of what we can do here most of
what we can do here I guess
it just depends on the way that we're
picking that depth range right
and it looks like I've sort of I removed
the operable part of it that was
previously picking the range so this is
just taking the minimum now so if I was
to go
back to doing something more complicated
where we actually did pick a range I
wonder if that might be a better place
to start and I suppose I should defer to
MTS marks on this I assume yeah so it
looks like he also and I think that's
why I remember him saying he went back
to the depth range version of the shader
remember this is how we were doing it
previously before we started playing
with it some more so let's go ahead and
try that out so this is basically
restoring the way it used to work before
when I tried this and it didn't work but
as far as we know that was really mostly
just because we were messing up the
depth buffer rights so let's start back
with this and see what happens and
there's some other stuff we can probably
do there to improve things further so
looking at this I would say it doesn't
really look appreciably better than the
other version in fact if anything I
think it looks a little bit worse than
just picking the minimum you can see
some artifact and going on up here that
I don't remember having much problems
with them in the previous version that
you can see right in there you get kind
of a nasty problem with artifacting
there and and that makes some sense like
that's probably in places where we're
just picking depth values poorly from
this tree at the edge of this tree to
where it sort of intersects where this
tree is being picked or something like
that we're probably just doing something
a little bit stupid in that case so I
don't know exactly what we want to do
here but it does seem like picking the
min is a little bit better in this case
at least as far as I can tell that that
seems like a more sane result right
so I would say mostly just looking at at
the game in that mode you know you're
not seeing those artifacts pop up I feel
like
I'm still seeing there's still some
definite artifacts in right you can see
as we start to peel away you still get
artifacts on the resolve with those
those places where the primitives of but
and it does you know it makes sense as
to why that's the case
certainly
so I don't have to think I have to think
of what else I might want to try here
so
I guess what I would say is going back
to first principles on this the thing
that's so frustrating about it is we
don't even need multi sampling for any
reason right there's nothing actually
happening here that we care about multi
sampling for the only thing we're trying
to do is smooth the edges of our cubes
because our cubes are geometric
primitives not sprites and therefore
they have hard edges now multi sampling
is intended for this purpose certainly
like the goal of multi sampling is very
specifically to smooth the edges of
geometric primitives that's what it does
no question about that but we don't
actually want it to be doing all the
work it's doing it's actually creating
too much work for us
all we really want it to do is to write
proportionally into the pixel it would
have filled based on its coverage of
that pixel that's all we actually want
right we don't want to record multi
sample we want us to produce one depth
value per pixel and then we want it to
if it cuts that pixel right in a alpha
blended color value that does not
actually alpha blame it just writes in
the Alpha role and they're just I just
don't know any way to do it and it's a
little bit frustrating because it's so
simple in concept but it's just there's
I don't know any way to convince the GPU
to actually do it
and we end up in the situation where
we're bending over backwards to try to
produce this this other results I mean I
really feel like we should be able to
reconstruct that basically though right
so you know inside this loop what we
should be able to do is find the depth
pin and we should be able to do this
operation right that should have worked
and I really just don't know why it
doesn't and I feel like I need to maybe
think that through a little more clearly
because I really feel like that should
work I feel like that should generally
produce the results that I wanted right
and I don't quite get why it doesn't and
I think it's a little bit subtle
probably why it does it you know would
be my guess
I'm kind of curious what happens if we
turn off srgb just curious
so it's definitely closer to right and
sRGB is always on in this case right
because we turned off the yeah
so hmm I'm going to draw the settlement
wait for word just so we all know what
we're talking about and so I can just
check my assumptions basically so let's
talk about what I would ideally like to
have happen but that is not happening
right now so we have primitives that are
like these cubes right and what happens
is along the edges of the cubes there's
a you know obviously a change in what's
happening along that geometric edge
right so if we were to take one of these
triangles here like let's say that this
was broken up like that if we were to
take one of those triangles that we're
looking at there are pixels right along
the edge of the triangle for any given
one of those pixels here's what I would
like to see happen right I would like to
see it take the percentage of the pixel
that is covered by that edge and I'd
like it to turn that into a percent
coverage value so I don't know maybe
that's 50 percent or something right so
that would be 0.5 and then what I'd like
to see it do is produce the color value
which is whatever the color value would
have been on this pixel I don't care do
the centroid I don't really even care at
all where you sample it but sample the
color value and then multiply the color
value by this alpha to give the
premultiplied alpha result right
[Applause]
I mean that's fundamentally what I want
to have happen
all right let's keep going here so
fundamentally that's what I want to have
happen and so I want to produce a value
in the buffer I believe and we can go
double-check this but I want to produce
the value in the buffer that is
effectively whatever this color would be
if this is si I want to do 0.5 see in
the RGB channel and point 5 in the alpha
channel so I want a pre multiplied
result here for that pixel and I want
that stored in the peel right and that's
it and I want it depth value whatever
its depth value was stored in it in the
peel there okay so that's what I want
now that should be approximated by what
I'm doing in this shader which is to say
that we've got 8 samples in here right
and if what I do is I sum up the samples
that appear to come from this primitive
which have the same Z value so let's say
you know in this case it's the same
thing I sum up these V values I'd say
sum up the color values that match the Z
which are these ones these ones don't i
sum those together and I should get
effectively the same answer right I
should get that I end up with 0.5 and it
won't be as exact as it would have been
because we only have 8 samples so it's
going to be more granular but it's
basically the same thing I would get 0.5
times the color with 0.5 in the Alpha
Channel now I know I'm going to get
point 5 in the Alpha Channel because I'm
doing in sample count times a combined
color so however many of those we added
up their alpha value is presumably 1 but
then I divide by the total number so if
I only have four of them and I divide by
eight I'll get that point five but now
the question is do I end up with point
five see in the Alpha Channel well I do
end up with point slides here but the
problem is thinking about this where
does the srgb factor come into play and
to answer that question I feel like I
have to look at how we're doing our peel
compositing because I don't really
remember but if you take a look at here
how we're doing it we square the RGB as
it comes in right
so in theory we want to do the alpha
multiplied before doing the srgb right
because if I did it after then this
square would mess it up right this
square undoes this square root and put
me back into the space where I expect to
be so I'm pretty sure is if that is the
correct place to do it now when we come
through here peel 3 obviously was going
to be an essentially it isn't now but we
don't care too much about that because
we're talking mainly about peels 1 &amp; 2
that's our 0 or 1 and maybe two but
probably not so then we take P peel 0
RGB we assume that that's the correct
thing to sum and then we multiply in
whatever the underlying layer is
composited to using the inverse of
whatever the peel alpha is and that
seems like the correct compositing
operation I don't really see what's
wrong with that at the moment what
something must be and I'm guessing that
what must be happening is what will help
to be honest I don't really know I
really just don't know what's happening
I don't understand why I wouldn't come
out to the same value because especially
when you consider the case of the two
triangles touching you know that like
these four over here went to one
triangle like this is triangle a and
these went to triangle B along this line
right or something like this they both
have the same color value right I mean
there's almost no difference between the
color values on either side of this
triangle there isn't really even a
gradient at in play there you know maybe
you look at this one like there's a
gradient there maybe something's wrong
with this how the cut but this is the
same color right so all the samples are
the same color in both of these cases so
they should sum
to the same thing so it suggests to me
that there is an error here that I just
don't understand and I feel like we need
to understand it in order to really say
this is or isn't working because
something's wrong there and the fact
that I can't tell what it is is is bad
right it means that there could be yet
another bug like the one mts NOx found
that you know we may not get lucky you
know no you know sometimes you get lucky
someone finds a bug for you you may not
get lucky so we're the only people who
really have to be responsible for
finding if there's bugs in here because
you know we can't necessarily guarantee
that anyone else is going to look at it
after and find it so yeah looking at
this code you know we're fetching the
depth the same way both times so
presumably there isn't an issue there
and you know we're summing up the color
in squared space which is where we think
we should be doing it and I don't see
any problem with that so you know it
seems like that's pretty basic and we're
checking for equals to the DEF men which
is the value that we're setting the frag
depth to right yeah so here's the frag
depth depth man that's what we're
setting it to and so the next peel will
include all samples that are below that
right I mean that's what's going to
happen I suppose maybe is it possible
that the samples are not predictable
like if the multi sampling sample
locations were different between the two
passes I suppose that could lead to the
problem
because again we know that we're just a
little bit we know that we're very
granular right because we only have
eight shades of alpha to play with with
multi sampling right we only have
between zero zero and eight are the
number of samples that can be covered so
we only have the steps between there one
two three four five six seven and eight
so really there's between zero and one
we're only dealing with seven possible
shades in between which isn't a lot so
it could be something like that and I
you know I mean if it was I guess there
wouldn't be a lot of ways for us to test
other than if there's some way we can
tell the card to always use the same
sample positions just at the test and I
don't really know if we can or not but
that would be one way to do it
[Applause]
you know I really can't say I have a
good idea about that I do not know what
the actual problem is there
I mean blending is disabled so we're not
accidentally like double blending or
anything like that at least as far as I
know and so is I really wish I could say
that I could think of something else
that could be happening there other than
different sample positions but I can't
think of much I mean I guess there's the
precision of the accumulator since we're
dividing by the sample count every time
I guess maybe I could try to make sure
the precision isn't a problem I don't
really think that could be the case it
doesn't seem likely but you know we
could put in sample count at the top and
then add in game sample count times the
color every time but that I don't mean X
if anything could be less accurate so at
ups so yeah and it looks basically the
same which is what you expect um yeah
yeah
well anyone have any ideas I'm curious
to know about where that difference
comes from because I would think that it
would be equivalent especially between
those two tiles and I can't really think
of why it's having a difference there
unless there's something about the
sampling we don't know or you know with
it we don't understand
so here's a question actually now that I
think about it so do we necessarily know
exactly how many samples there are in
the pixel is the same is the Mac multi
sampling value we always have set it to
that right like there's no possibility
that we have an off by one error here
where the number of samples that can be
summed is actually lower I mean if we do
sample index 0 to 7 which is what we're
doing here then that's 8 individual
things that are add together so we would
want to multiply by 1 over 8 I would
think so it's not some case where like
one of these samples doesn't actually
exist or something like we're querying
it and it's not actually there or
there's one additional sample we're not
accounting for or something but I am NOT
I am Not sure
yeah I'm not sure
hmm so I'm going to double check the
depth peel code
so what we do in the deaf peel code is
we fetch from the tech the we do the
textile fetch so
so here's a question do we know that the
frame buffers recording as V values
couldn't be involved in this case as
well like we're using deff component 24
here which is not the same as a floating
point value right it's very specifically
not and so I wonder a little bit look
what if we just said let's make this be
something we can set and some place and
so let's go here and set that to 32 s
because now it's the same it's the exact
same kind of value so whatever we
actually compute in the shader is what
gets stored directly in the frame buffer
and there's no quantization error right
nope
because I was just curious like when
you're dealing with something that what
depth fielding is kind of exact in that
sense and it's like well I don't know if
maybe we're getting something weird
happening there where it's like oops you
threw out you know you quantize the
value which makes it compare wrong
instead of comparing less than it
compares greater than or something
because you just flipped on either side
of it when you were right you know right
on the boundary like you would be when
two triangles abut each other like that
so I feel like you know when you're in a
game of inches like that
you probably want to make sure that
you're not the quantization artifacts
are not sneaking up on you there but
that doesn't look like that has anything
to do with it so
you know let me hear me out for a second
on this because you know just talk about
this for a second
I want to pick out an artifact on the
screen here and just just talk about it
and I think this is probably the best
place to look at it I well you and maybe
not maybe this is
yeah maybe this is so okay this is a
clue and important clue I would say so
let's take a look at the hero here if
you take a look at what's happening to
him what I think you'll find unless I'm
very much mistaken is that we are seeing
through the split in his graphics right
so where the two triangles meet here
it's not a question of an incorrect
summation it's a question of actually
peeling it away so at the boundary for
some reason when we're doing the multi
sample rather than the next depth peel
actually being whatever the whatever the
budding triangle was it actually looks
like it's picking the next thing down
which is kind of what we want if these
were some incorrectly but is not
actually right by what I think the
pipeline should be doing so suggest that
there's something happening uh he
suggests that something weird is
happening with the depth peel where it's
actually being more forgiving with the
depth peel then it should be and I do
not know how that's happening
because you can see here what it's doing
is it's saying whatever the fragment V
is that I was going to write here if
it's less than or equal to the clip step
that I'm not going to write it right but
what we should have seen is that anyone
who wouldn't have passed this test
should have gotten swept up in this
equal statement because if you were
equal to it you would be included in the
summation so how is it that something is
failing this test but succeeding this
one or I should say also failing this I
mean it's not hitting the discard right
because if it was equal to if it was
less than it should have been in a
previous feel one before even the one
we're checking against so in two peels
back right so if it's saying that it's
not in this that it's actually at the
clip step or was before the cliff death
then it how could it possibly not be in
hitting this on a previous step peel how
is that possible that's the part that's
a bit of a mystery right like it doesn't
seem like that should really be possible
to to have that happen you know
I'm not seeing it
because there needs to be some
explanation for why that's happening
even if we don't really care about it
from a perspective of you know even if
we don't think we can really get the
improvement that we want we should be
able to fix at least that or have an
understanding come to understanding of
why it would occur and I can't think of
anything I can't think of any reason why
that would occur because we know we're
writing that into the depth buffer
yeah and I don't see it so
blending remains off the entire time
right yeah so I really do not know what
the deal is there I guess I don't know
4gl multi-sample
being enabled we don't ever have to turn
that off do we like presumably that just
turns on or off based on whether you're
writing to a multi sample surface and
I'm assuming that you don't really have
to enable it or disable it in any more
specific way than just to turn it on and
then you'd only turn it off if for some
reason you didn't want to write multi
sampled right I wonder if there's
anything I'm going to take a look at
core ARB this is me just kind of
daydreaming now because I don't have any
particularly good idea I want to take a
look at coverage here
so I would like to know what sample
coverage value is
multifamily examples a pixel multiple
times is very sensation dependent
subject locations generate anti aliasing
effect multi stamping transparently
anticipated if it is enabled value is
used to construct a temporary mask use
determining which samples will be used
in resolving the final fragment color
this massive dip by banded with the
coverage master narrator from the
multi-tenant computation if the invert
flag is set the temporary mask is
inverted and then the bitwise confutatis
and implications does not have any left
in where's rail orbiters no the
restoration occurs only a single sample
computing a pixels final RGB color
provided and implementation sports play
several buffers and multi-channel
examines the files no derivative
occupying several samples per pixel each
template official diversity performed on
each sample here is a question though
the question is could you do that and
just give me the value back this is
really what I want to know
I love all these crazy pages that are
like basically just the docs from the
open jail thing moved up opengl 4.5
slack let's take a look at the latest
spec if that is wait a sec I don't even
know if it is anymore
that sample coverage coverage
all right the RGB values of the ran
stress governor left unaffected but the
a value is multiplied by a floating
point value in the range 0 to 1 the
describe the fragment stream
crystal-covered wait this is what I
wanted
how do we turn this on
raster addition specify which premium is
converted to a 2-dimensional image bla
bla bla raster Reznick Runa begins by
determining which square as integrated
window yeah that's fine a grid square so
should data of furniture is called a
fragment yeah
fragments div square okay after as
Esther press release pragmatist in
fragments so I'm like we don't care any
that that's a grid squares need on
actually be square and GL fine several
fractions prisons running before
decision points they're given
rasterization only produces fragments
Crosswhite includes in the frame buffer
fragments which would be Bruce class
diction of a infirmary rest which rules
for Evelyn so the Pharaoh not produced
nor they processed primitives right by
enable rasterizer
bridges can be optionally that's carded
before esters become enabled table with
rasterizer discard resorts card
immediately for the restoration stage
okay that's fine we don't need that
considered primitive Pease legacy okay
whatever
Ann Taylor saying their GP values for
apparent let's put a value see what are
you even talking about when you say
anti-aliasing like hello specification
tell me something about when that would
occur but this is what we wanted but I
was not able to get this to happen the
per fragment stage of the GL can be set
up to use the a value to blend the
incoming fragment crystal or and I'd get
that we don't care about that we want to
write the actual value details the
parent players current coverage
Peter different difficult so in general
reason is that hi clients doing may take
into account perceptual issues 12
characters monitor okay so those might
be just mystical document further the
coverage about a commuter for a fragment
of some ready-made the privileged
relationship to a number of grid squares
neighboring the one cross line the
fragment asked right I'm serious thing
okay you're all giving jilted okay fine
we chose to specify the behavior of
exact investing in the prototypical case
that each sleeve is a very square of
your
see the square it's called a fragment
square in the lower left corner XY upper
corner X plus one minus one recognize
that symbol box will dramatically
muscular results because a simple well
defined model at field position we use
other metric a fine
instantly she's ready to return anything
Claudia a routine barber ngl hints but I
need you to make up to speed up but how
do you get it to actually turn on that
is the question like this is all we
actually want we want this section of
the spec to occur and then we could get
rid of multi sample buffers entirely
right that's all we this is all we
actually wanted but we were not able to
get that to occur
yeah anyway
don't pick the care about any of this
is there anything about anti-aliasing
the polygons section polygons
interesting rasterizer polygons by
producing a fragment wherever the
interior the plug on your sex the
fragment square the coverage value is
computed at each such fragment and this
value is saved to be applied to
subscribe in Section 17 one associated
datum is assigned to fragment by
integrating the datums value of the yeah
so why could we not get that to happen
we want that we want to at least try
that the interpretation of polygons
rasterization is controlled using
polygon mode blah blah which we don't
care about no care about polygon offset
either
because the weather polygon interesting
polygon smooth is enabled or disabled
did we ever try turning that on curious
[Music]
yet is that did we do that
maybe we didn't do that
what happened let's just I'm just
curious
so let's say we don't have multi
sampling on right so this is a non multi
sample game running in low resolution at
the moment because why bother setting it
back up we don't really care we just
want to know whether we conclude some
things right okay so now let's go in
here and say okay GL enable GL polygons
smooth start with that first eye
what does that do I don't see any
polygon smoothing at all happening there
so that doesn't seem to do anything
right I guess like a disable multi
sample as well just to make sure we're
not using it at the moment so it
wouldn't matter I still see it I see no
smoothing i GL Kim I think that person
had it there right yeah just in case
[Applause]
can you open or Target has an invalid e
now is that not allowed
[Applause]
still see no smoothing now we're going
to totally wreck our rendering here in a
second unfortunately best I I'm going to
go ahead and do a GL enable GL blend
right and do we ever enable blending
again no so in theory if I enable
blending which should allow it to draw
and then I set the blend funk to one
zero I'm still not getting any smoothing
so it's not because it should just be
writing that alpha value in although I
guess we would have we it doesn't know
to pre multiply the alpha value so let's
just just to see again I just want to
know whether this whether you can ever
coax this into producing a primitive at
all it really doesn't seem like it like
I should see something right and maybe
not but I mean here's an example of
something that's just against the
background I should see some color
variation or something there but I'm not
seeing anything right hmm so I don't
know how do you get
[Applause]
all right
yeah I mean I unless I'm missing
something it does not look like even
though that's specifically stated in the
specification I don't see it turning on
at all but it's supposed to right I mean
it's it like that whole section in the
spec specifically says that you're
supposed to be able to turn on some kind
of anti-aliasing right so I'm I guess
what I don't understand is why that's
not why that doesn't seem to ever
produce it because I really would have
liked to be able to get that but I can't
seem to get so the first is you're in
the location of frame buffer is when
it's just on the drum buffer right yeah
so there test should be fine
so I don't see ya I literally see no
reason why we shouldn't be getting
polygon smoothing they're right
[Applause]
so it looks like basically that part of
the spec is just a word maybe and it's
just like hey yeah sorry about that we
we just don't care about that idea right
well it would have been nice all right
so yeah I mean honestly I don't know I
don't have a lot of ideas as to why as
to why we're not getting an even
summation on there because we're clearly
getting something where it's knocking
out a pixel which I feel like should
then should have belonged to the
subsequent death feel but doesn't appear
to and maybe the problem there is just a
summation from death feel to depth
appeal is incorrect because I suppose
that would do it like if it was under
weighting them in some way that I
suppose could be part of the problem
what I feel like might maybe if there
was some kind of a problem with the
Alpha that was being picked up at that
pixel like the Alpha value was not
correct so it was getting under weighted
like I just I don't understand exactly
how that would be possible but it's just
I'm saying that that's something that
would cause it so for example in you
know in here where we're doing this
summation we're sort of assuming that
the alpha value is one for all the
samples along that border and there's
just a fraction of the samples but I
don't know like is there something
that's creating non one alpha values
there I don't know and you know you
can't imagine us specify
this more stringently by doing something
like this combined color RGB combined
color a plus equals one right so if we
just assume that that well I mean you
know it's probably this that's probably
dumb right just so we don't care what we
fetch out of the buffer even if the
alpha value appears to be something
we're going to set it to one anyway
right um so you know looking at that so
I mean that's just that to me again like
I just do not understand what I'm seeing
then because now I mean you can ignore
all the black stuff here that's what we
would expect right we're taking pixels
that should have an alpha value and
we're treating them like they are solid
but I'm talking about for these
in-between pieces here like now we know
that that's not happening right the
alpha value is full-on and it's still
getting that same error so the summation
here across the boundary is just plain
broken but I have no idea why it's
broken I don't understand how we're not
getting to even size of the sample count
to sum up properly it doesn't make a
whole lot of sense to me
No all right good
that was bugging me I think I ought to
get it now all right so let's turn this
into something where we were looking at
the actual depth layers here's the peels
so here's our pixel right and we're
doing this V fall on the top tip field
these don't so they get moved down to
this depth field
what's going to happen right these still
happen on here but they're already taken
care of so they rejected right and then
there's something down here well what's
going to end up happening is the alpha
value here is point five and the Alpha
value here is point five but this is on
top lemming so what's going to happen is
this point five is going to add with
this point five right and rather than
producing one and not summing this it's
going to do an on top right it's going
to do it's going to turn this into a
point two five and it's going to add
point two five of this which is wrong
and I don't see a lot of ways around
that
I mean I think this is basically why
people use multi sampling in the regular
situation is specifically because you
don't know what the Alpha value is
actually trying to tell you
actively what it means is that when you
have multi sampling you need to track
how many actual samples there were in
the depth range and then you use
so here's a question if we just take the
whole thing what happens if we just take
the whole thing
if I just say give me the maximum give
me the highest give me the first back
right for this back thing sum all the
colors what happens then
what does that look like I'm curious to
know so we get some artifacts
specifically where the tree boundaries
overlap each other but now we don't have
that problem right of the
yet we don't have the problem
where we get those cross-purposes so
we're only talking about the fringes
once we switch that on and then we're
good to go pretty much everywhere else
right so in that situation we're just
back to the old problem that we had
before where and presumably this is
what's happening in the regular resolve
- right because this is the problem we
had when we just used the default
resolve and that problem is just that
when you get out to the fringe edge you
are going to produce an alpha value
that's too low and you're blocking the
other pieces from showing through
but at the end of the day that's really
more of a problem with the fact
that we don't clip out the Alpha when it
gets down to that level because if there
was still something to be contributed
here than the peeling like we're really
just talking about the fact that these
peels are overlapping directly in Z and
so we end up under weighting one of the
other values so I'm interested to know
what would happen if we put in some sort
of an alpha threshold here and just play
with that a little bit I'm curious to
know right so that that sort of wide
apron artifacting is more or less
controllable by the Alpha by the alpha
threshold what happens when we come down
through look at some sparklies though
it's pretty interesting
[Music]
that's pretty interesting so I also
wonder a little bit I want to try one
thing here so for intersecting I don't
know there's much we can do about
intersecting cubes because in that case
the multi sampling is not going to help
right so for intersecting cubes
I would actually need to do something
where we actually record the values
there because the most multi sampling
isn't going to help I'll sink
sounds like if there's a reason if multi
sampling if we were just doing regular
multi sampling would it work you know
without the depth feeling would it be
okay there and I don't think it would be
well no I guess you know to be honest I
guess I don't know exactly why those are
having that problem either meaning along
that boundary I would expect we should
be able to get multi sampling along that
boundary to work properly as well unless
the problem is that the primitive it's
not the primitive edge because it's a
little too fat so it sticks inside of it
and the primitive edge is so it doesn't
turn on multi sampling in that case
because I don't know if it if it uses
the Z testing to check so I wonder if
it's our centroid sampling that is that
that that makes that be the problem
right because our centroid for sampling
have forces all of that to be having the
same value and that prevents you from
getting multi sample they're probably so
if I were to turn off the centroid stuff
I wonder if that would improve that
situation so if I just take centroid out
of here right I guess I didn't need to
do that it's just that
yes so so it's really just a centroid
that ruins that but if you take a look
at what we've got now right where we're
just taking the maximum depth value
that's actually really nice and smooth
and it smoothes those intersections so
really at that point we're just talking
about some of that when we when we sort
of clip out there's there's some
objectionable sparklies in there but
everything else is pretty nice right and
I mean if you compare these two
especially here at this lower resolution
which admittedly is not exactly fair
because well you wouldn't run in the
lower resolution but you know if you
take a look at those two it's really a
lot nicer with multi sampling on you
know I'm saying
hmm
all right so I'm just not willing to
quite give up on this yet so I guess
what I would say is we're going to have
to pull Center it out it's pretty clear
that without centroid you get way better
anti-aliasing on those intersection
points so I'm just saying it's out
sentry is gone goodbye centroid no more
centroid oops
because that looks way nicer to me right
I am a fan I am a fan of this
that looks really nice and smooth and I
don't get a lot of those sparklies I
hate those sparkly is when things move
and you get the spark leaves right so
really we're just talking about those
those artifacts which we mostly can get
rid of with an alpha test which is what
I turned on there and I'd almost be
willing to live with that but there's a
little bit I wonder if we can just do a
little bit better
you can see some of those artifacts
right the edges there right I'm not
quite sure it because the clipping
right you can see right in there I don't
know if you can see it you can see it's
just subtly wrong all the time right at
those edges
ah very close now very very close now
though so the question is just could I
do something in the multi sample resolve
that's a little bit better about how it
processes those multi samples so we know
that if we pick the max depth here I
guess I'm not 100% sure when we're doing
that pick I guess I'm not a hundred
percent sure again and this is probably
just the fact that I always have to work
on it on a weekend and that is a week in
between and maybe my brain just kind of
loses some of the context that's
important in really thinking through a
problem but you don't totally know
what's going on right it's important to
try and get to that understanding
sometimes you need more focus then that
provides but if we take a look at what's
going on there with picking the depth
maximum value which is the farthest away
saying then I guess what I'm not clear
on is right at the edge when it does the
multi sampling if the Alpha value I
guess the problem is that the Alpha
value is very low then you for those
samples what you want to do is you want
to pick up okay so I I do know exactly
what's going on so that's good so the
problem is if when you do your multi
samples right you end up in a
circumstance where you've got one two
three four five six seven eight so if
you end up in this circumstance where
you've got a bunch of samples and you
know you're you're doing something like
this
and so you've got all these samples here
that you want to talk about but their
alpha value is very low
so when you pick all these guys up
you've got you know five samples but the
five samples all have alpha values of
like point one right as a result you're
going to produce the combined you're
producing the combined colors here using
the multi sampling so you're going to
get you know a three that have some
other color here but what you wanted to
do was you wanted to figure out what the
color was on the next depth peeled down
from just these samples right you wanted
to figure out what the def PLU was there
and add that in that's what you're
trying to do but you're not going to do
that because these samples are already
from here so you're actually going to
skip this depth all together and get
down to the next depth field right and
only this amount of contribution came
from this layer which is not what you
wanted so you get way more of this color
than you should get in this peel and
that's incorrect right or vice versa and
so when you pick the minimum color what
you do is you preserve the depth feeling
right when you picked up min you
preserve the depth feeling effect very
nicely what you don't do is you you
don't get drilled down deep enough right
and especially when things are
overlapping you end up in a bit of a
pickle there right now I don't know like
maybe there's simpler things that just
happen to not produce as much of an
error like I don't know you know maybe
maybe if we did the you know depth
equals one and you know we took step
then we grab that here
and I just tracked both and you know we
split the range in half right who knows
I'm making stuff up at this point I so
you know like if we take a look at what
happens there what you know what do we
get if we just split the depth range in
half so if there's oh it's going to be
mostly what it would have been if
they're close together if they're not
close together it'll pick something you
know halfway in between right what does
that look like and well what I would say
is I see a lot less artifacts of the
kind that we were talking about before
and I guess I would be interested to
know just looking at it here I'm not
seeing those artifacts on the top of the
trees for example right and and maybe
right if I also took a look and how we
were doing the threshold maybe that you
know what happens if I if I back off
that threshold again where do the
artifacts look like in this mode with
with no threshold and oddly enough I
don't see any so it doesn't look like
the Alpha threshold actually needs to be
there if you split the range
so right now honestly the only artifacts
I'm seeing so far are mostly in peeling
away like right now in the peeling away
like you can see some flicker unis
they're right
that's mostly all I'm seeing I would
like to know whether at alpha threshold
makes a difference for that I have no
idea let's find out
doesn't appear to
so I guess I would say at the moment and
that's weird that sort of simple
solution happens to be so good but that
really does look pretty shippable I
don't love the the pullthru artifacts
there I don't love the artifacts that
I'm seeing right here but that's really
it in terms of just rendering the scene
that looks real stable and very nice to
me everything is silky smooth there
I'm pretty happy with that so far
any questions and any questions any
questions also
[Applause]
we did that yesterday
I don't know other issues we've got
outstanding here news variable by
mistake
so this is not a bug that's just a
suggestion
two small compiler warnings vs 17p
Lindex has previous different okay first
more seconds looking at the shadow of
fixing the last one civil training set
cursor these are pretty free to change
and they would help if they would help
people compile on via 17 that's time
with me so that's in here the arrow
resource so that's just going to cast
that to the proper value and value for
the compiler to be happy declaration
feeling to touch previous local
decoration that here probably a for I
loop yep
so I'm going to go ahead and change this
one to on keel index since it's a little
more global and I'd like it to be a
little clearer I really wish I need to
figure out a way to make for code or not
stop searching for things because you
scroll all right that's it
well good
[Applause]
yeah uplink coder I I wish there was
some way and I guess conservative
rasterization is the thing that you know
look I talked about the beginning is the
thing that I want and some modern cards
now have added that looks like Nvidia
and Intel
you know both both have that Super Cub
what about the typecast what about what
typecast if this is this was the
typecast right making resource
oh hey and rec yeah game wise this isn't
really much of a game stream if it's a
programming stream so the engine coding
is the point of it if that makes sense
and we're kind of coming to the end of
that so we are going to build the game
on top of it as well just to show how
that part is done but I am NOT a game
designer so that that part will be more
just about like hey so here's you know
how to code the game part of the game in
case you didn't already know how to do
that from all the stuff we've already
sort of shown because a lot of its you
know kind of pretty obvious I think at
this point if people have followed the
whole stream they pretty much know how
to you know make a game on top of it now
because the game code is not
particularly complicated so we will be
doing that part but it it's not really
the point of stream if that makes sense
the game coding will be much less
important than the engine so I guess
that's that's what I would say so it's
not really much of a stream for people
who want to make games as the primary
goal is just to make a game and not
don't care about engine work because the
point the stream is the engine work not
the game that means
there are plenty of oh well I think that
things there are I think there are other
streams available that are more about
making a game and like so they just
glued up unity you know and show you how
to like put entities in or something
like that and so I think there are
streams that cover that kind of stuff
and this is very far from that right we
even wrote our own software rasterizer
for the game at one point which is you
know something you would never do for
any real reason it was just to sort of
educationally show here's how
rasterization works and here's how you
should think about it here's what the
GPU is doing under the hood and let's
implement that ourselves so we can
understand it that sort of stuff so you
know we pretty much are very heavily
focused on learning to program engine
and how they work and we don't really
focus on games or game design and and
again that's because I'm not a game
designer so I feel like that's really
[Music]
someone else's dream to make I wish
there were good ones as is there really
I don't know if there are you know game
good game designers are very hard to
come by there aren't very many of them
in the world
there's a lot of game designers but very
few of them are good and I don't think
any of them that I know of stream I mean
that's not entirely true like Jonathan
Blow does streams and he is a great game
designer but he doesn't do streams on
game design he streams like when he's
programming his compiler or something
like that which is great but not you
know yeah
I guess what I'd says it's it's not
helping anyone who's whose main goal was
to see how a great game designer does
that work
John blow streams aren't going to help
you because he doesn't show that right
key work shows how he does programming
on other things wasn't able as it
appeared to her nearing the end of the
main engine deadly be adding in the
non-mining to three layers to or have
others already done those um so I we
won't do ports till the very end so the
game will be done on one three two and
then we'll do the ports that said yes
other people have already done them if
you pre-ordered the game you can
actually go on the github and people
have ported it to STL which is a
cross-platform like library thing so I
think if you care about that you can go
get one of those and that would allow
you to run it probably in most places to
at least a certain degree because STL
has code for lots of different platforms
however I don't have any experience with
that branch myself I've never looked at
it so I don't know what it does or
doesn't do I will port the game to the
other platforms eventually you know at
least probably Linux Mac and Raspberry
Pi because those are plat open platforms
now one of them may close by the end of
that like Mac maybe completely closed
platform by that time I mean heck
windows maybe a closed platform by that
time I have no idea platforms are
rapidly closing up
but Raspberry Pi will be open so we'll
definitely port to Raspberry Pi right
but what else before - I don't know and
Linux right because that'll death open
so Linux and Raspberry Pi and those are
both similar ports because presumably we
could do a Linux Raspberry Pi port
although it might be more fun to do a
whole cloth Raspberry Pi
work but but yeah
alright looks like we're done with the Q
:
ah so I wouldn't go ahead and I will
wrap it up for the day I'm surprised at
how well that multi sampling suddenly
started working I guess once we fixed
the bug with a custom result it turns
out that just a small change to the
custom resolves produces a very good
result which doesn't make a whole lot of
sense to me why splitting the depth
range in half is suddenly somehow
magically amazing but I guess that's
just like your bisecting the difference
between the two I don't know
- did odd if we're honest or being
honest about it it's a bit weird but
yeah I mean just looking at it now I
feel like most of the bugs are just are
just in that that movement downwards but
in terms of rendering the scene it's
like rock solid I don't see any problems
that I notice rendering the scene it
looks great I mean for not doing any
sprite sorting at all just dumping all
the sprites into the engine and having
it completely resolve it with def peels
plus multi sample that's just kind of
crazy I'm like pretty impressed by how
well that works before we started I
don't think I would have said that that
I mean I had really no idea I'd never
thought about using defiantly for a 2d
engine before I'm kind of surprised at
how well that works
well sometimes you get lucky I guess I
don't know what that is notifications I
love when your developer studio has
notifications alright thank you for
joining me for enough code a handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you would like to
follow along series you can always
secure to the game on hammaker org and
it comes with a source code so you can
play around with it and practice the
stuff that we have talked about on the
stream or in the case of MTS mocks find
bugs for us that were really helpful we
may never have revisited that if you
hadn't to take a look at it or she I
don't actually know MTS mocks personally
although I often see them on the stream
that I remember the MTS mocks um
nickname coming up so thank you very
much for finding that that was great
and it made us go back to it and
actually do something pretty cool so I
think that's a pretty valuable thing
that's about it until next time if you
have questions you can go to the forums
talk to other community folks about it
you can go to a patreon page if you want
support the video series you can check
our schedule box find out what's good is
going to be and you can go to our
episode guide to catch up on old
episodes if there's something that you
missed that's about it for today until
next week yeah have fun programming and
I'll see you on the Internet
take it easy everybody