hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here of the show we code a complete game
live on stream we are doing some
lighting today we are trying to put in a
little bit of a of a light distribution
kind of a system into our renderer but
just as that designed to sort of give
the light a softer more bounced around
look to it and we've just started it we
have to finish the downward path before
we can really start playing with it at
all and so that's what we are going to
be doing today today is day 396 so you
want to start with day 395 source code
if that's something you are going to
follow along with at home that is the
source code you want to be using so
where we left off II was yesterday there
we go so where we left off is we had
just started with the downward iteration
for our sampler and what we've got here
ah let's see so here we go here's our
multiply down so what we've got here is
something which goes through the various
textures that we've got the front emit
back emit and the NP and then looks at a
particular textual surface color and in
it some NP data which is the normal
location of that particular reflector
and it tries to you know do something
with it and right now we don't do
anything in particular it's set up to do
something but we don't actually do
anything with it now one thing that we
haven't done yet is the UV step
parameter is not set to anything in
particular
oh wait no we did we did that so I guess
we've done most of the compulsories then
because we did set the UV step to be the
correct value I believe so let's double
check that we did that because this is
actually and I think I wanted to rename
this as well from UV step step to source
UV step
because it's there's 2uv steps that you
could think about in this particular
situation right there's the UV step of
the destination parameter and there's
the UV step of the source parameters and
since they're at different levels of the
texture they're necessarily different so
let's go ahead just make sure that this
is correct everywhere okay so yeah so I
think we're doing everything correctly
here at least as far as I know in terms
of what we are presenting to the tropics
card now and we just need some actual
code that's going to do something useful
right I and one of the things that might
be good for us to do here is you know at
the moment we don't really need it
because we know what the up textures
look like so we know we're just looking
to down in the future what we might want
to do is when we do handmade internal
rather than using the same textures for
the up and the down use a different set
of textures so that we can compare what
the it looks like before and after doing
the down sampling at the moment though I
just like to take a look at this now
that we have it all in place and to see
what we're doing here and try to figure
out roughly what we need to be roughly
what this needs to look like as we go
forwards so you can see that we've got a
desk front in it and a desk back event
happening here at those two are getting
computed and they're being placed here
one of the things that I need to do is
if you if you remember the lighting
is going to be additive to a large
extent in this case like in other words
we've got a situation where at any given
level of the texture we need to add in
the new lighting that we compute because
we certainly don't want to take out any
lighting that was already at the place
that we're talking about that we knew
about on the way up so we just want to
be adding new lighting in from other
sources and that's very important so if
we take a look at how this is executing
we're putting the desk front and
vacuumed it in here what we want to do
is the desk front emit and the desk
vacuumed it both our raw lighting
computations that we will be doing when
we fill in this transfer light equation
and at the moment even if we assume that
that was happening we're still a little
bit wrong because we have here a
reflection color and we're not using
that reflection color so what we want to
do is we want to take the desk front
emit and the desk back emit and multiply
them by a reflection color because
whatever light we compute as hitting our
surface we want that light we want that
that bit of light to correctly take on
the surface properties now what we
probably want to do you know instead of
doing it right here is if we ever want
to try to do some kind of approximate
specular with this which I don't think
we really can but if we ever did we
would need to have multiple pieces of
information like the specular power and
things like that in here
so what I can do instead is just move
back computation in here since we're
passing the reflected color - they'll
transfer light equation we can take
whatever the emitted light is that we're
just going to be transferring and
multiply it by that ref C and that would
be fine so that's at least one thing we
have to do the other thing we have to do
is make it so this is additive and in
order to make it so that it's additive
what we have to do
is when we actually use the multi like
down in this here in this routine where
we do which apparently I can't find for
some reason where is it there it is so
it's like a cute like transport here
what's going to happen when we use a
program begin multi grated light down is
when it computes these results we're
going to want them to add into the
texture the way we're doing currently so
what that means is we need to do a GL
enable and a GL disabled for blend
because we need it we need the blending
the blend unit to take the output of
this light pass and add it to whatever
was in the texture beforehand so the
blends funk that we want to use here is
going to be GL one GL one in the sense
that we we don't want to modulate any
one by any alpha or anything the values
that were outputting are literally just
the amount of light that's being added
so we want to take 100% of destination
and 100% of source light and combine
them together we don't want any
attenuation of them by anyone's values
at all so I'm pretty sure that's okay
because as far as I know nobody is using
blending anywhere else other than in
front of these old routines that we
don't support at the moment so we should
be able to just let that roll and that
should all be good now what you'll see
here
is that now that I switched it to add
we're getting some kind of odd results
there right which is the oh my that's
really pretty cool that has nothing to
do probably with what we want to be
having happening but it's really neat
anyway this is a little bit surprising
to me and I'm not sure I have an
explanation for it which makes me a
little nervous now that we switch the
blend mode to add we're getting the old
lighting in here as well on top of the
new lighting the reason that that is odd
to me is you'll notice that the whole
screen is yellow but we're seeing a red
and green dot now the reason that that's
weird is because yellow should be fully
1 1 or you know the maximum that bright
yellow is the maximum you could get on
either Channel how adding yellow to
something that's red gives you red still
I have no idea
and just to underscore why that's odd
if you the only way I can think of that
that would be happening legitimately
meaning not because of the bug in our
program is if it's because hey these
lights are set at more than one for
their initial value because if you
remember the feed lighting was that way
so where was that feed looking to see
here the C's lighting has these as as
110 now if I was to drop these down the
problem is we wouldn't be getting that
bright yellow propagated back I assume
you know maybe we would but if we didn't
yeah okay so this is just odd so I think
we need to investigate this a little bit
further because you can see now I'm not
even
getting any values that are over 1 so
how you could have a yellow light
everywhere and still end up with with
what we're seeing I have no idea right
so this is this is just peculiar to me
and again I suppose it could have
something to do with the power of like
I'll drop them down even further so that
I know we're mostly going to be within
the the range that can be directly
converted from float to 8-bit color for
display because I don't know what's
happening in that phase exactly but yeah
you can still see I mean there just
doesn't I just can't see any explanation
for this at all so there's got to be
something buggy about the way we're
doing it and I would like to figure out
what so let's investigate further let's
see how we're getting this this data so
when we take these samples here so
here's the up path which as far as I can
tell isn't doing anything wrong or
anything obviously wrong in the down
path
I'm sampling from the parents and when
I'm doing this that you can see me
adding the the light transfer equations
in here I guess I am blowing out the
range of the float that is true because
I'm adding four things and I'm not
dividing them out by anything and you
know so if we're talking about trying to
just get something that can be
represented in a float that's going to
blow it out now I don't care about
representing them in the float at the
limit because what I'm doing is I'm
summing a bunch of light values can be
arbitrary and at the end we will have a
mapping step that map's that down to
something and we're not doing that at
the moment but you know in the meantime
if I wanted to I can keep this this
stuff at a reasonable level by using the
the number of things some did quartering
them right so looking at that that looks
more like what I would expect
why not quartering them which allows the
float to overflow why that produces the
result it does I really couldn't tell
you I guess it's possible that the way
the mapping works is just by taking the
F mod of the value that would make sense
I guess but even so I don't know so
let's suppose we crank that up you know
over time a little bit just to see
roughly what we get and again I'm just
experimenting here because I don't
understand exactly what I'm seeing and I
want to gain a little bit more insight
into it so you can kind of see that
blending process right it keeps working
around the two points but never really
seems to change what's on the interior
of those light sources and that is just
really perplexing I have no explanation
for that
I really wish I did
but I so totally don't and
and just to be extra clear about what
I'm talking about when you look at these
two dots in the middle here what I'm
expecting to have happen and what it's
not happening is I expect those two
points to be getting brighter themselves
as I transfer more light from the parent
so as I say instead that will double the
power of the light transmitted by the
parent right but as I look there what
you can see is that the area around the
light is having that happen ah you know
what I think I know why that is
that's because of the recipe that's
because of this isn't it so if I was to
take out because the recipe on a light
is zero so there will be no light
transmitted to the light surface so if I
instead was to do this there we go okay
so that was actually just a case of nice
wording myself there right okay now I
can still move the hero around here and
this is some bizarre stuff that's
happening to say the least and you can
kind of see there how our filtering is
going to have to get better because you
can see what's happening with that sort
of bizarre light propagation since it
happens on right now on two by two
boundaries you end up with sort of this
this visible sort of filtering error as
you go but if we clamp that light a
little bit more right so now you can see
me sort of moving it around here
if the clamp that light a little bit
more then you can see that it's still
kind of reasonable at at a level that
doesn't
doesn't feedback on itself and becomes
quite so obvious so anyway so we have a
couple paths we can go down here so if I
do do recipe in here and prevent it from
contributing to a thing that's already
in emitter which I don't know if we want
to do because I don't know if we want to
ask something as an emitter reflector in
the real world I don't know that there's
a whole lot of stuff that's like that
sometimes there is what typically lights
are so bright if you look directly at
the element that you don't super
distinguish like you don't super need to
talk about light that gets reflected off
of necessarily but you know either way
so if we talk about these lights here
I'm going to go ahead and beat the power
up on these lights and I'm going to see
what happens as I sort of change that
since now we've got a Semite stable
situation occurring there just for the
sake seed lighting so I'm going to
return these back to one and one first
[Applause]
now I'm going to go 10:1
and now I'm going to go to 101
and lastly I'm going to go to 1010 or
110 I should say alright so now we've
got our two lights and they have sort of
quite a bit of outside power and you can
see some problems that we're already
going to have to start tackling right
you can see the problems with the
filtering approaches there where when
you line up well for the filtering you
get further you get more bleed than if
you don't and so as we start to work
with these right we're going to have to
try to do a good job with keeping these
things relatively smooth in that way
right and yeah I mean that's just again
a battle but you anytime you discretize
something on a grid you end up in a
situation where you're going to have to
kind of fight that sampling problem so
let's go ahead and say that this is
where I'm going to leave it for right
now again we haven't done any of the
lighting stuff yet we just set up our
filtering and I think what I'd like to
do now
probably because without this I feel
like it's going to be well I don't know
so I have two directions I can go now
either I can go and say all right we've
got this in place we need to go work out
how the lighting works let's before we
do that have a way that we can switch
back and forth between the gain load and
the test mode right in order to do that
we need to go make the ability in the
renderer to specify that a surface is
emissive and that will have to be
something that gets put into the render
passes right
so that's what we want to do and I'm
just trying to think about how we're
going to do that exactly or you know
what the what the way is that we're
going to do that so we need to do that
and the reason that I'm thinking that I
might want to go do that now is because
as we start to progress forward on the
lighting one of the things that we're
not going to know is how good the
lighting is at any particular time right
so you know because this is all going to
be about approximate light transfer
stuff and we've got the system set up
now to sort of play with it
and play around with it one of the
things we're going to want to do once we
get something working is we're going to
want to flip over to the game and see
what does the lighting look like if we
actually try to use it in the game and
right now we can't do that because
there's no way to get the game the game
doesn't specify any lights and we don't
have a transfer from the game to the
lighting system and the lighting system
back to the game so I think that's what
I'd like to do since we haven't I don't
want to get too far down the road
because once we go down the lighting
Road I want to finish it I don't want to
have to ping pong back so I think what
I'm going to do now is just stop it here
and we'll leave that maybe we'll leave
that for next week like writing the
lighting equations because I think what
I want to now is get it so we can see
the results of the lighting creations in
the game and we should already be able
to do that like if we were to look at
something like this in the game we
should see the world lit in this really
unusually weird way right we should see
a blobby red splotch of light and a
green and yellow splotch of light around
the character and that's all we would
see and the rest would be dark right we
would see literally this as the light
mask overlay for the game right so if we
wanted to go down that route let's take
a look at what we would have to do here
right because again this is going to be
pretty complicated okay
so here's the status of the game render
at the moment it is using some lighting
and we're basically going to pull that
lighting out right to a certain degree
and we can pull it out in steps
potentially as well but anyway so what
we want to be able to do here is right
now we only specify one light we specify
a light position and a light position
isn't at all what we want what we want
to be able to do instead is randomly
select any sprite that we want and turn
it into a light source right that's what
we that's what we actually want because
that way we can just have as many lights
as we want in the scene and then they
get rendered in and processed as light
so we don't have to have some fixed
number of lights with some fixed number
of positions they're just sprites can be
illuminated or not right and any sprites
that is Mark is illuminated gets
rendered you know emissive Lea and any
sprite that is any sprite that is not
that is just rendered as a reflector
okay
so that's what we want to do so if you
think about how that's going to have to
happen as we look into this a little bit
further the complexity here a lot of
that complexity comes from the fact that
we've got depth feeling happening so
we've got a situation where we're going
to be rendering these for depth feels
right and you can kind of see where
we've got the multisample def peeling
happening here you can see this this is
the the just feel loop where we set up
our frame buffers for right into the DEF
peels and we have this multi sample
resolve that half of secured snacks
things down after it's after we've sort
of dealt with them and if we take a look
at what we're doing in that resolved
multi sample we use the few words it
in the compiled resolve month a sample
function which we have here you can see
that what we're doing is we do some
textile fetches to determine what the
range is of the depth so we do this and
we go whatever the depth range is split
it in half and we're going to take
everybody who's on the front side of
that is going to be considered in for
the depth that that particular depth
field right so everyone on the downside
of that will get rendered on the next
peel as well whereas everyone on the
front side of it doesn't
I also for whatever reason and I don't
really know what the reason is we
elected not to sort the samples based on
that I don't remember if we tested which
one looked better and determined that it
looked better to average them all or
what happened here so you know honestly
here's a question should we just double
check that while I'm in here we probably
should all right so let's let's take a
look at the light stuff here I'm going
to pull this light stuff out for a
minute
[Applause]
so I'm going to just render the whole
screen the fulbright which there you go
and what I could do is leave directional
on but not distance as well which I
guess would be nice we can see the edges
of those cubes better so if I did
directional instead of distance what I
could do is say like distance camera
distance here let's see here light
distance one over light distance I could
just say light distance equals 1.0 or
something
well actually leg strength are divided
by light distance squared yes so I can
say I think can just do that well
actually now I take that back
because we need to normalize it properly
so I think what I actually need to do is
do that act in fact so we've got light
distance equals like to light then this
normalizes that then here this is the
part we do light strength and we compute
it with the light distance squared what
I want to do there I think is just do
like distance equals 1.0 so that we
won't modify that strength at all right
so there we've got it nice and bright
now so I should be able to see and just
looking at the edges of things I don't
really like the fact that I still get
that let me maybe if I fix the light
position so it doesn't move around would
be the other thing I could do right so I
could say light P equals you know
[Applause]
and so there I can see a lot more
cleanly right because this is more like
the original where the light is is sort
of semi stationary although it's you
know not quite so again just looking at
the artifact in here from the DEF peel
you know you can see some of it you can
see a little bit in there it's hard to
see which because we worked on making it
hard to see but you still can sort of
see it a little bit again I'm just
looking for artifacts there and let's
take a look now if I change the way
we're reproducing the samples here so
the way we've got this is the sample
camp here we run through when we do one
point over the sample count what I want
to do is take the fist feel for Ag depth
here and I basically want to say like if
you are on the positive side of that so
when we come through these samples and
we fetch one the if statement we're
going to want here is for depth being
sort of great I don't remember which
direction depth ever goes in here so
Jeff max is zero depth min is one point
oh so basically if the depth is higher
than the GL frag depth we will take it
right and we'll also introduce sample
div here and use that
instead because we only want to divide
by the number that we actually got right
I guess unsigned integers are now saying
yes oh that's no good that eliminates a
lot of the blending we were getting
there although that's a little bit odd
to me so I'm kind of wondering why
that's so bad
oh because this is backwards never mind
yeah I read that wrong my bad I still
know better though but yeah I believe
because if deaf min is one that means
that we're using less ones for that I
guess we don't really know deaf min deaf
max whether I named those properly
either but we've tested both directions
and these are fun work so I suppose we
know that that's the case either way so
I just wanted to just wanted to double
check that there wasn't something better
we could do there than what we were
doing so we'll leave that as is I'll
take this out
and think we can just leave this as is
alright
so the only goal now that I have is
again trying to figure out how to get
everything into the lighting system
proper now the way that this needs to
happen again is pretty tricky I think
and the reason for that is because of
the depth field if we weren't going to
try and do a sort of actual
three-dimensional lighting this would be
a lot simpler but because we are going
to try and do actual three-dimensional
lighting it's going to be a little bit
more complicated but that's ok
complicated stuff is what we do on
handmade 0 because after all we're
supposed to be teaching programming and
picking things that are incredibly easy
would not be very interesting for that
end even though that might be what you
should do on your game if you don't care
so what we want to do here is we want to
take a look at how we might get this
information out of the renderer depth
field process into some bitmaps that we
can use and what we'll do is we'll
concentrate on the first bitmap but what
we'll do is we'll try to remember that
what we can that we want to eventually
do the lighting on all 4 def fields so
that we can have a deep lighting solve
that actually has some dimension some of
that third dimension to the lighting
bounce ceilings and floors and stuff
like that that wouldn't ordinarily
happen if we just did it in pure screen
space with only one so what I want to do
here is take a look at how the def peel
renders are set up so you can see in the
open GL frame by first thing here we've
got a color handle and a depth handle
that we are normally writing to for each
of our def peels right so you can see on
here we've got a depth field buffer at a
deaf people resolve buffer and there's a
frame buffer for each of those and so
what happens is we resolve the frame
buffer
with the color and depth handle we
resolved that from one that's multi
sampled to one that's not so each of
these def peel and death peel results
here each of those get sort of smacked
together right we render one of them
into the DEF peel buffer than we do a
def peel resolve to the DEF peel resolve
buffer which smacks down the multi
sampling at whatever the multi sampling
was set to down to a single sample which
we then use to the rest of the process
so in order to effectively mimic that
right what we need to do is include
omission in this equation somehow now we
already have an RGB you know value in
there which could serve as our surface
color value and we already know the
depth and the depth of the thing because
the DEF peel buffer gives us that right
so we have the D value and we have the
surface RGB value what we don't have is
front side back side emission and we
don't have the normal right now we can
easily get the normal in the shader but
we don't have anywhere to store it so we
need to have somewhere that we're going
to store the shader going forward we
also need somewhere to store the
emission somehow and we again need to
store that at a high resolution
potentially because we may want that
value to be fairly granular now we could
still store it in 8-bit and up sample at
layer to float because we don't need the
initial lighting values to be that
precise we only need our lighting
computations to store that precise as
they iterate so we could use just 8-bit
color for recording the emitters that
wouldn't be too big of a deal the
regardless of what we do we're going to
need more right bandwidth here which is
a little scary but we're going to need
it because inside these depth
the buffers we're going to have to write
in addition to just the information we
were writing we're going to have to
write more stuff that we can pick up by
the pickup with the lighting system
later all right so let's think about how
we want to do that I think what I might
want to do is these OpenGL frame buffer
things here I think again maybe we won't
really be able to use that as the
utility class so much because it seems
like we constantly have to make things
that are more complicated than that so
in the same way that we have a light
buffer here we may need to end up with a
peel buffer here that has all of this
information in it right and that seems
pretty likely so if we were going to do
that what we would end up with much like
like we have the light buffer there we
would have a peel buffer here which is a
similar thing it would end up with
something like this which is the multi
sample frame buffer handle the multiple
Cohan also multi sample test handle then
it would have the frame reprehend of
color handle depth handle right but now
in addition to these things it's going
to have more color handles right and
what we could do is well I suppose is
instead of just one color handle here I
suppose we could do something like this
right so we could say something like
there's going to be more than one color
handle potentially for an OpenGL frame
buffer
so you could say OpenGL color handle
type and you could say that the color
handles in here was a OpenGL color
surface reflects OpenGL color front
emits dribbler back in man good conceal
color
[Applause]
and P so in a circumstance like that we
would have is each frame buffer would
have a couple different targets to it
and we would pretty much just use
exactly the same process that we use for
everything else it's just we're going to
extend the amount scored by a lot more
values so the emissions there are yeah
all I guess the the emissions they're
just kind of all recorded for us now
what we could say and I guess I don't
know that there's any reason not to say
this it seems like we probably should
just say it
one kind of site is I don't know if
front omit or backing it is I don't know
that it's necessary to save that
information well we probably want to
have stuff like that in the actual well
we want to do stuff that deals with
propagation direction in the actual
solve I don't know that we need to
remember that information on the actual
render and the reason that I say that is
because on the render it seems like a
lot of the times things are only going
to emit out of their front face probably
not necessarily out of their back face
however I don't know that that's true
and I guess more specifically what we
could say is we could just make it so
that things just emit period I don't
know if that's a really tough call
being able to specify the lighting in
either direction of an emitter seems
useful because for example if you were
talking about like a light on the face
of one of the cubes you would not want
it to emit out the back which is what it
would do if it had back emission but at
the same time you want situations where
like if a sprite is supposed to be lit
up in all directions it's
omnidirectional you kind of want some
way of satisfying that as well so in a
sense maybe what I really want here is
more of just a emit value that is like
RGB a where a is the spherical nosov it
I mean for lack of a better term where
is my Milton there it is
I really want someone to figure out why
Milton loses connection to the tablet
all the time it doesn't really make any
sense to me like what even is happening
such that that can occur you know
there's got to be some all right why can
I not open there's got to be some reason
for that I was looking at it the source
before the stream started but I didn't
get far enough in to figure out to come
up with a plausible idea of how that can
happen
because I've never had a program where
that happens before like I've never had
another program like at any art package
ever lose connection to the tablet like
that where it thinks that it's Mouse can
put all of a sudden in instead of tablet
input and so there's got to be some
explanation for it but I don't know what
that explanation would be and I'm very
curious anyway so what I was saying here
is emission specification is what I want
to do here is I want to say okay if I
have a direction so I've got whenever I
render anything on the screen I know
what the direction is of a thing I
rendered right so for example if you
take the hero which is like a sprite
card standing up it's normal it's like
going to be pointing out you know sort
of slightly down and slightly toward the
viewer so if I wanted to say that the
hero was emissive there's most ways I
might want to say that right and so what
I was thinking is if we had RGB is like
the color of the emission but a was like
a term that told us the spread of the
emission so you know if a is zero then
it's just a line of light and if a is
one
it's like 360 degrees or something you
know and point five would be like 180 so
it would just it would like you know
kind of control that then we could sort
of have a specification which only used
one bitmap and four values rather than
having a front
vacuum ition which even that doesn't
really capture very much information
because the front in the back you don't
really know if that would suppose to be
an omni emitter or two fairly straight
emitters pointing it out to directions
right and they're going to have
different lighting qualities and it
doesn't tell you very much about the up
and down emission and so on so I feel
like maybe a a conical sort of
description there that widens out to 360
in some way is maybe a little bit more
of a useful specification and at the
moment we'll just use 0 or 1 to
represent whether it should be all in
the front emitter or a front and back
emitter when we transfer it over that
seems to me to be the most reasonable
thing at the moment and we can always
plus with that term as we get further
down the loading path to figure out
exactly how lighting should be working
in our letting transfer we can then go
back and tween tweak that a parameter to
give us the most control we can get out
of one parameter that does make sense
through the rest of the lighting
pipeline so I feel like that's probably
what I want to do so I would say it's
just like emit so it's kind of like you
know
[Applause]
so in this case we still have the death
buffer so we really don't need the depth
in this case so I don't really know what
we want to store here I suppose what we
could do is just store the N x and y and
that's it
right so maybe this is just like 16-bit
n X 16-bit NY so we use 1 32-bit texture
but we store the normals at higher
resolution right we could do that I
don't know that we really care about the
high resolution we could maybe just use
a 16-bit texture so you know just use it
NX NY and just don't worry about it
because again the depth buffer here has
that information in it so we don't
really need to store the depth in in the
render passes it's already in the depth
buffer we don't need a story
it's just redundant to put it there
again so this is emit RGB and then like
spread at alpha and the surface effect
is just like select RGB so this would
again this would be giving us you know
quite a bit more write bandwidth
requirements which isn't great and when
I say quite a bit more I mean like a lot
more right because essentially we're
multiplying by 2 plus the amount of
write bandwidth we had to do on the
multi sample pass which is the worst
possible pass because that's the one
that could write the most stuff so it's
not good right but we need to get that
information in there somehow and like I
said we're basically multiplying it by 2
plus because we have the surface reflect
RGB and the you know coverage L a rather
that's what we are currently writing so
this doesn't increase it at all because
that's just what we already were writing
but then we have another bitmap of the
same size plus a little extra plus 16
bit extra so it's like two and a half
times the right bandwidth that we're
going to suck down on those def pas am I
not concerned about it no because I mean
at the end of the day you could always
turn lighting off entirely and still
play the game if you were trying to get
it to run on like a Raspberry Pi or
whatever and anyone is running this on a
PC probably has a graphics card that can
eat this whole thing for breakfast 12
times over you know we're not doing
anything even close to as complicated as
you know battlefield 1 or something
probably is so six of one half dozen or
the other you can also drop the
resolution down play at a lower
resolution play at less than 60 frames a
second 30 frames a second half
resolution blah blah blah where the
resolution is going to dramatically
improve that speed because again it's
just right speed we're not doing a whole
lot of ops on these at the moment I so I
say what's back we'll try it right eye
and and we'll see what we get
now the question curious do we need
anything else we've got 2 of these 3 2 v
maps and then we've got this kind of
weird bitmap here again I don't see any
way to really do anything smarter than
that and in terms of storing any other
data you know into this MP bitmap here
we could put more information like
whether there's specular like how
reflective the surfaces or something
like that like a specular power kind of
a thing and so we could say that let's
just say that these are all 32-bit ones
and just say it's 3x the bandwidth and
we have like LP 0 and LP 1 here and
we'll just say to do KC 2 parameters
here that can control the lighting right
so eventually we'll let you specify 2
parameters that up the two parameters of
control the lighting will snuggle them
in with the NX and why in this
NP will call MPL texture and then
hopefully in the future we'll have you
know some degree of of something we can
do with those in the lighting to change
the surface look based on something that
you specify when you create the sprite
information alright so let's go ahead
and plow forward with that
ridiculousness here so when we pass the
flags and stuff here what I want to do
is on create frame buffer I want to
specify how many color buffers it has so
rather than just a has color thing here
I think what I want to do instead is say
that the color flag either we can make a
color flag for each of these but I don't
know that that's super useful I think
what we could do is just pass how many
of them you want right so we could do is
say that we've just got this like so and
then remember doing the color ones what
we'll do is like we'll just say color
buffer count and the color buffer count
will just serve as like a four I loop
essentially where we allocate that many
of these so we'll say let color index
equals zero colored X is less than color
buffer count plus plus color index for
good measure let's assert that the color
buffer count is less than or equal to
the numbers that we expect to have or I
guess we can even just say whatever the
array county is of that place that we're
going to store them which in this case
is the color handle array and so here
we've got you know color index ranging
from here to here so when we put this in
to a storage location we'll just say
okay and the same thing will happen it's
the same thing will happen here we'll
add the color index to the e number
passing and we'll grab the
wrapper color handle out so that would
let us create you know as many of those
as we wanted to so I deleted that I
actually delete the wrong one I guess
not
and they again so this one's going to
have to loop through all of these so
we're going to look at each of the color
handles on clean up and we're just going
to delete any that we're allocated in
that frame buffer the frame of our color
resolve flags is no longer a thing so
we're always going to just assume that
that gets back that's passed down for
anyone who allocates a texture a frame
buffer they're going to have to pass how
many of those they expect to have so
here where we do create frame buffer for
the OpenGL resolve buffer we know that
that once we do our final result we're
only going to have one color buffer so
we can just forget about creating any
any more of them there
similarly here and create frame buffer
for the death field this is the place
where if we wanted to just mimic exactly
the operations that we're currently
doing we'd say one we know we want to go
further than that now and we want to
pass the full color count now we will
use those buffers we'll just create them
and again since we know we also have to
downsample them we'll create both the
downsampled version and the fully multi
sampled version so now when we're using
these color handles anywhere we're going
to have to do binds on them and in order
to do that we're going to have to be a
little bit more careful about where
we're writing things and
how we're going to do that so for the
moment I'm not going to deal with that
at all I'm just going to get things
working the exact way they were by using
color handle zero which should always
work in theory and so now I just want to
make sure that I can actually run this
because we may have introduced a bug
there but it looks like we're all good
so we're still running correctly and
everyone's happy and smiling and doing
all the things that that were just I've
got great fine whatever so now we've got
those extra color handles here we have
to start thinking about what we're going
to do with them and the tricky part here
is just that you can kind of see here in
the light buffer where we do this this
dumb sequence color attachment stuff so
the same thing that we did here where we
have draw buffers we're going to have to
do for our other frame buffer operations
so if we take a look at the frame
buffers that we made and create frame
buffer here where is that here it is
where we specify the color buffer camp
here what we're going to have to do is
we're going to have to call the same
stupid thing here we're going to have to
call that on these to make sure that all
of the color indices that we've set up
and I guess we should also make sure
that all of these that we set up we're
going to have to make sure that they all
are that all of the sequences that we've
set up of color buffers have this dumb
sequence bound so that when we actually
write to them it knows what we were
trying to write to so at the end when we
do this the frame buffer we need to make
sure we call GL draw buffers with
however many color buffers there were
and the dumb sequence which just has
these things like sort of listed out in
them
and I don't know how many of these we
put in there but you know since to avoid
having this more than once maybe what I
should do is just make one of these at
the top right which is like oops so it's
a global variable that's just all color
attachments and in here we would
literally just put everything now we
probably will never use this but now we
know we just have an array of all of
these and we can just use that anytime
we want to do one of these vines
[Applause]
okay so let me delete all that and again
we should be good to go so now what you
can see here is that even though we set
up to draw the multiple buffers we can
still see the game rendering just fine
because you know even though we said we
have multiple fish to draw to it'll just
draw nothing I believe - it'll just draw
garbage - those buffers or zero - those
buffers that we're not throwing - and
since we're never displaying those
buffers are using those buffers for any
purpose whatsoever we really don't have
to worry about them at all so that makes
it now so that we can keep the whole
thing running and slowly get to a point
where we're propagating the information
from these new buffers that we have out
into the out into the the legs system so
in order to do that what we have to do
is when we're drawing we have to have a
way of writing to the actual color
buffers right so what you can see here
is we've got this sort of the Z bias
program this devious program is the the
version that we're using for both the
first step feel and all subsequent def
peels but it gets compiled in two
different ways like one way it does this
textile fetch and clip and another one
it wouldn't do that so what we need to
process here after we do this stuff all
of this lighting information can go away
it can be sort of put into a separate
process and in fact I think I am going
to do that now in preparation for moving
things along so what I'd like to do is
well actually know what I could do I
could have it write the light
information
in to the buffer right here right it's
one thing I could do so let me pull out
this information for the lighting the
way that we were doing it so this whole
thing is lighting right so let's pull
out all of that lighting information and
I'm just going to put it down here with
our lighting code our multi light down
code I'm just going to put that here in
an fzero block so we can put it back
oops so we can put it back in later when
when and if we want it right so now what
we've got is when we're writing we don't
have any lighting that's going to be
written into this buffer in the Deaf
field right so the Deaf feel that it is
so the Deaf feel now doesn't have to
have any of this light stuff happening
in it
let's frag thee okay so that's just set
up there this this could be removed now
because frag Z is not used so if this
could just be that we were playing with
that value before okay so now we don't
have any lighting happening or in theory
we don't and write total light just
needs to get pulled out of that multiply
so instead of multiplying this by
anything we're just going to write the
blank color in like so and now we have
an unlit version of the game that's
writing to the surface reflectance
information which is exactly what I want
right and our goal now is to have
something which will write you know not
you know addition
in addition to that writing the lighting
into buffers as well and so we want to
do is do the same thing we do with FRA
cords here some some folks had said that
we have some frogs there are problems on
more modern cards with frag cord because
it's deprecated so one thing I might
want to do right now while we're here is
if we take a look at the github issues I
believe someone wrote in about this yeah
so so since we switched up our faders
are already on one five oh we don't want
to be using Jill frag data apparently
because of the deprecation problem so
martins who i tend to trust on all
things meticulous because he often
writes in with very specific important
changes for us I feel like he may have
the right idea here which is to just say
since we've said we're going to be using
shader version 1/5 though we could just
switch to using LAN sex which are much
better anyway because layout specs are
things that let you say what the bind
location is for each variable so that
you don't have to bother querying it at
all right so I think that's a pretty
reasonable idea and if we want to do
that I believe all we have to do is use
the location mapping thing for 0
whatever I think all we have to do here
is specify I think all we have to do
here is specify our own name and write
to it as if it was GL frag cord a GL
frag color and I think it will work but
again I'm not entirely certain however
we can certainly just try it and see
what happens and go from there and I'm
sure the folks who have the graphics
cards that these that will complain
about these sort of things will tell us
one way or the other which one happened
so let's take a look at the frag color
situation as it stands
that's alright frag data so here's the
frag data stuff I'll go ahead and switch
the lighting back on for a moment
so here is us writing - whoa why was
that so slow Wow I know I know so slow
so what we can do here is we can verify
that we're still writing to all of these
right and now I'm going to go in and
make that change and verify that the
graphics card is still writing to each
of them so if we want to get rid of frag
data here what we are saying we have to
do is in the place where we've got frag
data we need to sign our own value and
you can see here is a layout location
equal zero out v4 my output bar
essentially what this is doing is
declaring our own version of frag data
and the fact that it's an out value with
location equals zero I guess is how it's
clear to the graphics card what we are
trying to do so we can just say that
this is frag color four and then
eventually when we write this out we
just don't use frag data we use frag
color right in our case we don't have
four we only have two in this one we do
have four in the other one let's try it
one at a time see if that works
looks fine
so let's try same thing
[Applause]
I'm getting some weird like the frame
rate slows way down randomly which I
don't really know why and there it looks
like we're doing okay with our right
still so that looks like it's all good
all right so everything looks pretty
reasonable there to me
and the reason that I want to do that is
because we're about to do that same
thing in all the rest of our shaders
that have to write because they're gonna
have to write to multiple outputs so I
don't want to make like even harder for
folks who are on those other ones on
those other cards so we'll go ahead and
close that issue out and I'm sure
Martins will tell us or the original
commenter slow or cuchara I don't know
which I never know how to address people
properly because a lot of people have
different um a lot of people have
different names than handles and I never
know whether they like to go by their
handle or their name or whatever I
assume since its regards flow I will say
flow so either Martin's or flow will
tell us if that in fact fixed their
problem on the more modern cards that
probably are supposed to complain this
this car probably should be complaining
about frag data wasn't so you know
whatevs
but anyway so if that's the frag data
information there let's see where else
we've got it it looks like just in the
fake speed lighting so I'll again just
kind of propagate this forward a bit
more
into all of our shaders so
in this one here we'll just call that
fried color and then we are good to go
so now I will go ahead and start making
some of these other pieces of code work
with the additional buffers that we have
so what you can see here vertex code
fragment code
this one has a frag color that it's
going to be writing out here called
result color I'm going to change that
from result color to frag color for
consistency well you know what maybe
that's a bad idea because it looks like
we used frag color for the incoming
fragment color there hmm
let me see I would like to have a naming
convention that makes some sense here
that isn't weird here I'm saying
so I'm going to change this here from
frag color to like in color or something
and in UV and then I'm going to change
his vote color to frag color and it's
not perfect but that's just the way it
goes
[Applause]
you know what this is the worst you know
I hate the way these things work I have
to tell you it's so frustrating so
that's not good either because I have to
name it the same thing in the vertex
shader as its named in the fragment
shader because that's the way they get
bound I can't call it what it is in each
of them which is the input and the
output to that shader because you don't
have the option of doing that right so
maybe a result color is the best way to
go and I should just change and I should
change the places where I was using frag
color to actually be result color ugh so
bad because I mean so if you think about
this right this is a separate side so
it's so clear how these are not properly
designed for what they do in terms of
Naumann klaich ER first of all how you
have a void main void being the thing
that's supposed to do this operation
it's like it should be defined as
accepting the parameters that it accepts
and outputting the things that outputs
right so this should be a struct that
has the things in it fitted outputs and
this should be a struct that has things
in it could it takes or something so you
can see the inputs and the outputs of
this thing as a function that would be
what would actually make sense instead
you always have global variables and the
global variables are supposed to line up
with like something else declared global
that is writable in the other one but
readable by you it's just it's not it
like it I don't know it's just a very
strange way and it leads to these sort
of tortured naming conventions like the
thing that I'm having to mess with now
where it's like I I want to name this a
different thing in each function the
input and the output of the function
should be able to be named in
put an output but I can't name it in put
an output because if I did that it
wouldn't line up and it's required to so
you can't call the output of the vertex
shader the output because then in the
fragment shader we called output which
is not right whatever
all right so we pretty much have to have
a naming convention that respects the
fact that each of these things have to
have the same name so that kind of means
we'll have to call it what may be the
stage is so let's adopt the stage naming
convention the input to a thing takes
its name always so in here we've got
vert P vert color vert you defrag you
defrag color right exactly what we want
in here we've got froggy beef right
color result color not we want so what
is result color well result part is the
blend units color right so we'll call
this the blend unit color and then
everywhere we're going to write to that
we'll just call it blend unit color all
right
and then everything that comes into the
fragment shader again should always be
titled frag is going to be a nightmare
to get working again because of all
these name changes and the compiler is
error messages are not fabulous
but whatever will live with it so here
in the fragment code right we've got
information coming in from here smooth
in let's see frag color frag UV that's
what that should be result color is not
supposed to be result color
[Applause]
and we'll just cross our fingers that we
can get this working again all right so
that looks slow right that doesn't so
that actually looks wrong because that's
not blending those two colors so what
was going on there are we writing
incorrectly to those so now we have to
fix the frag color in these ones so
let's take a look at frag color in the Z
bias program that's actually the correct
name for it let's put the outs like that
so there's the ins in the apps there's
Frank color blend unit color and it
looks relatively straightforward here's
a result multisample and that all looks
fine as well
all right so then we've got the final
stretch so the thread use the out fix
for blend unit color that all looks good
too now you're the fake seed lighting
fix you letting look like it's working
correctly however frag color is not the
right name they're frag colors here has
to be blend unit color we go so that's
all good all right
so looking at this where we've got the
blend unit color here in the two so
multi light up for example I versus
multi light down just trying to see what
we can make of this so blend unit color
out the front emit and vacuum it here so
there's the problem that looks like a
bug we always have not one we just
introduced there we go
all right so that all looks fine now and
let's try to figure out how we can get
our our lighting values now written too
now that we have a sensible way of
naming those things and we don't have to
worry about the GL flag data problem
either so if we want to now for compiled
fake feed lighting we can do the same
thing that we were doing compile succeed
lighting in for example like our
resolved multi sample paths or our
compiled D bias program so if we take a
look at compiled D bias program for
example now we could do is where we have
before our blend unit color we can
instead have output to multiple textures
now what we defined when we said what
we're going to do is we would have three
of these there'd be reflect RGB and
coverage a that's the first one the emit
RGB and spread a and then the N X&amp;Y LPL
smell p0 p1 so what we want to do here
is say ok we're only writing the three
things in this particular case and so
when we come up through here and do our
blend unit color what I want to do is is
sort of change up the names of these a
little bit so instead of blend unit
color here this is going to be surface
reflect
[Applause]
so the surface reflectance they're
getting coated in srgb that's fine but
regardless when we get to here now we've
got blend unit color 0 equal surface
reflect blending Claire 1 should be
equal to emit which we haven't done yet
and plenty of color 2 should be equal to
NP L so we want to compute those other
values there and all these values are
only going to be computed if the alpha
threshold is met if we discard we
discards all things we don't want to
bother computing any of this information
when the Alpha drops below it so what we
need to do now is compute the emit and
we need to compute the NPL now we know
the emit is going to be the emit RGB
plus the spread and we know the NPL I
assume you can do in RGB here like I
said we can do like a V 3 plus an a I
don't remember if they allow that or not
this is going to be the N X + y LP 0 LP
1 right which we don't know I could also
just write this out longhand so that's
how we need to pack these values in
order to produce those some of them we
have some of them we don't so you can
see here we've got a world normal that
will allow us to do the NX and wide
directly so what we want to do here is
produce that NX + x + y the LP 0 we're
just going to fill in a bogus values
here
[Applause]
but the n x and y values we can compute
from the world normal end and the world
normal why yeah so what we want to do
there is we want to pack these into an
8-bit value right we don't want to have
to specify floating point frame buffers
just to get this data through to the
lighting system where it will eventually
use floating point computations but we
want to encode it you know in a more
straightforward way so in order to do
that where we've got our world and X&amp;Y
here what we need to do is we need to
take this which we know is in the range
of negative 1 to 1 and we need to put it
in the range of 0 to 1 now I don't
remember they might already have a way
to do that directly obviously it's
trivial for us to write so we'll just
write it but I want to double check that
they don't have a utility function for
that that automatically does this
operation but just be a bias operation
basically let's see if it's in here
okay so here's built-in functions common
[Music]
mod round cross face forward not seeing
much here I don't see it so I'm assuming
we will write it because I don't see it
anywhere would be in here I would think
because it's kind of like you know
smooth stuff and these other ones that
are pretty straightforward little blendy
sorts of things alright so what we want
to do is we want to take this value
that's from negative 1 to 1 and we just
want to pack it down right so we want to
basically take it it's too wide at the
moment right negative 1 to 1 so it's 2
units long we want to compress that down
to one unit long so we divide by 2 right
Oh point 5 and then we got to ship it up
because then it's negative point 5 to
positive point which got shifted up from
0 to 1 so then those can be packed in
here just fine and off we go now we have
to make sure our unpacker also handles
that properly so let's go ahead and
double check that that's true I don't
know where that is no we had it in here
somewhere
here it is
so here you go so here's reconstruct
normal the past BMP what you can see
here is yeah it doesn't really because
this is using these as if they were the
actual values which they are not at the
moment although I guess since that's
floating-point that's probably okay so
yeah we can hold off on that they're
packed in here but when we do the
transfer we'll have to unpack them so
that's fine that's all good and X so
that packs up the NPL vector and so
really all we need here is the emission
vector with the spread so at the moment
I'm going to call the emit spread 1.0
and again to do kc some way of
specifying like emission so what i want
to do here is take the emit RGB and what
i'm going to do is i'm just going to use
the light p here and i'm going to do
essentially what we do with the other
with the fake feed lighting i'm going to
use that temporarily so we're just going
to write one light in just like we were
writing in before only we're going to
write it in here instead of in our fake
food lighting program so in here what
i'm going to do is i'm going to say well
okay we know that we've got a light p -
world p in terms of the distance of the
light source so i'm just going to say
whatever the length is of these things
if the length between the light p and
the world P is less than I don't know
fifth of a meter or something then the
emission value is going to be something
real otherwise it's not so we're going
to assume that the emission is nothing
unless you're at the light source in
which case we'll make the emission be a
bright red light as before and that'll
be the brightest red light you can
possibly have right
okay so now we're going to debug the
shader or not the bug fix and Pilar as
the shader the surface reflects
undeclared identifier that is true
redefinition err omit and I'll just go
ahead and pack these in here so we don't
have more variables than necessary so
that's good alright so that looks all
reasonable there and the surface
reflectance here again gets packed in
and then written out so I think that's
all fine a look at the next compiler
error all right so it looks like we're
good
so now we need to actually get that data
over somehow so we're writing that out
right and now we need to actually do
something with it now what we can do
here if we're feeling particularly saucy
is we can view this directly so whatever
the actual information is this getting
output by one of these fragment shaders
we could grab it and use it in our
lighting computation directly already
because in theory well okay I guess
that's not true
so we need one more step which is we
need to have the multi sample resolve
also take it into account right
so the multi sample resolves
here needs to be able to read from these
other buffers and write them out as well
so in addition to having just that one
color sampler which it's going to fetch
from it needs to sample from the other
two as well so in addition to just the
surface reflectance one it needs to take
the emit and the MPL right so in here
where it's picking up the some of the
samples the same would be true
presumably for the emit in the NPL I you
know again we don't really have a sane
idea for how we would be treating the n
x and y or the lp0 lt1 or whatever when
they get blended together so when you're
at a when you're at a corner pixel a
pixel that's covered by multiple people
we just have to pick something to do
with it in terms of what its emission
spray it in x and y and LP 0 LP 1 r so
we can just blend them together and
cross our fingers because there's no
right answer for that really unless we
computed everything at the multi sample
level which we don't really want to do I
don't think so anyway so here what we're
going to have is we're going to have
multiple color samplers here we're going
to have a color sampler and a mix
sampler and an MPL sampler alright and
when we do these Suches that we've
decided we're not doing anything fancy
there so we're going to take em Jimmy
we're going to take the color fetch and
just duplicate it out like so
[Applause]
so same exact process same exact
everything and then what we want to do
is we want to just sum those together
into the combined commit combined mg/l
so up here we've got a combined pillar a
combined commit and a combined NPL each
of those things starts at zero sums up
and then in the end when we need to
actually write these doubts then we have
to go ahead and do the computation now
this right here is this blend unit color
bit here this is the actual surface
reflect so this is actually right so
this is actually the service reflect
amendment we do the texture that starts
to be right we would if we were
simulating that we would do the power
ourselves there so which I think we
always do currently because we get bugs
if we don't do it currently although in
the future when we change our art asset
format we might be able to get rid of
that and let the card do it so anyway
moving along there we've got our
combined colors now we need for the
other two we need do the same thing so
here what we want to do is we want to
take our blend unit color zero and make
that equal to the surface reflects you
want to take blend unit color one and
make that equal to the emit Linea Clark
to make that equal to the MPL and so in
each of those cases when we're writing
those in we need to take the inverse
sample count multiply them to get that
blending to occur just like we did with
the surface reflect and that's really
about it
so that will blend out the rest of those
we just need now to make sure
that we're grabbing that blends unit
color as definition with the layout
specifier so that we know that it all
goes to the right location so let's take
a look at resolve multi sampled here we
just here we're writing to the blend
unit color we just need to have that be
defined here right and we're only
writing the three of them so now that
should also write to them the only trick
there is we need more samplers now
because we're reading from multiple
textures so this part where we have to
actually write to these we need an amid
sampler and an fel sampler those both
need to get down so that's in the
resolves multi sample program like so so
when we do that resolve those need to
get set up so when color sampler in our
use program begin for resolve multi
sample we need these to all be lined up
somehow
and I guess I'll just do them I guess
preserving the order they used to be in
so the zero and one is for the coding
the depth the Amit and MPL samplers will
come after and so let me do the multi
sample resolve actually you know what
that doesn't really make any sense let's
put the depth sampler first and then all
the colors because then that way the
colors are contiguous that seems more
reasonable to me so when we do is the
multi sample now where is that actual
function
it is so when we do resolve multi-sample
what I want to be able to do here is a
four I loop and so that we can set the
active textures up again now I don't
know why we felt the need to clear the
active texture here to be honest with
you I don't know that that's really
necessary I feel like it shouldn't be
because every time we set all detectors
that we're going to use so it just seems
like active texture is the only thing
that needs to get reset in case people
are not using it somewhere
even though really hopefully they would
be but let's go ahead and do before I
loop here color index equal zero color
index is less than open Jill well I
guess it's a red count in this case now
now it's open jail color count where is
that where to get up with that so
textured 0 is the DEF handle texture 1
plus whatever color index were on is
going to be the color handle in this
case then we will draw and then we will
unbind I'm just going to say that this
is going to work I don't know that it
actually will but hopefully now the
resolve will work properly let's see
under it Amit and undeclared NPL so
let's take a look at why we're getting
those undeclared
that's in here so we've got yeah so this
is supposed to be combined emit and
combined MPL all right so now we've got
that stuff going but we don't know if
it's working properly and the easiest
thing we can do first just to make sure
we didn't you know to get the really bad
bugs on the way first I can switch back
to showing the game render see if we
still get it and surprisingly to me we
do so that's pretty good obviously so we
are able to render the world properly in
the theory we're also rendering the
other buffers at the moment to now when
we do at that point when we do our
lighting view right which is this in
theory now I think I should be able to
take the bottom level of the compute
light transport and get it
from the peel buffers instead so we can
see what we're actually drawing there so
I what we need to do is is actually have
a way of transferring one of the other
at the moment we don't actually have a
way to do that because we have to write
a shader to do it but before we do that
we can in theory view the emission part
of things because that will translate
over properly it's not encoded in any
weird way or anything so if we want to
now what we could say is well when we
when we do our multi light C multi light
down we just need oh it's a transport
light so we need to our compute light
transport right normally we're starting
here at source place light plus index is
going to be
zero and we do these binds here right
the bind textures and that all makes
sense but what I can do is I can say
well if the source light buff index
happens equals zero what I can do is
override what you were going to get the
front emission texture from and say well
instead why don't you get that from the
peel buffer instead right so then we can
say well the depth feel resolve buffer
for just peels zero has the color it
buffers in it right what's this one here
we could go ahead and peel out for
example the emission from there right
and now just that first time we're going
to pick up that depth peel buffer I'm
going to comment out the down phase just
to keep things a little simpler and oops
that's under OpenGL
so again just reaching directly into
that depth field buffer and starting
with that as the source so we can see
what got written to to it at all right
that cannot possibly be true
I do not believe what I'm seeing
so just like both index source type of
index source type of index that the
opening should be zero so what we should
see oh no that's fine so we're not
copying it over so that is actually
correct so it's the next one up that we
would have to look at to see what we
were drawing in and so we see nothing so
that's not a good sign right that means
our first sample up got got nothing out
of the emission there which is not
fabulous not fabulous at all however I
would point out that I don't remember
all of the mojo you have to do to enable
frame buffer output I don't remember if
you have to do GL enable for that so
let's just double check that we don't
have to do some kind of nonsense for
this so when we do begin screen fill
so it doesn't look like we really have
to alright so it doesn't look like we
really have to so let's start by digging
this one slow step at a time
so here's our compiled for the resolved
multi sample so when we do the resolved
multi sample what I'm going to do again
is the same debugging technique I've
done every time here since we don't
really have any GPU debugging on this
machine sadly we've got a blend unit
color that we're writing out zero one
two and what I want to do is verify that
this is actually happening the way that
I think it is so I'm going to go to the
place where we're actually specifying
the debug part here and I'm going to get
rid of that so now I should be able to
see what I what I'm looking at should be
the game right and that's the first
surface reflect thing that gets written
out there so the next thing I'm going to
do is now I know that I'm viewing that
correctly so what I want to do is take
the combined emission value that I'm
outputting and reroute that to be in
place of what was what I was just seeing
so now I can see what I'm writing out of
surface emission right so here's what
I'm supposedly writing out into the
surface emission buffer okay now one
thing you'll notice there is the certain
submission of the background is gray but
we'll have to fix that because we don't
really want that to be happening but we
can fix that later and so already you
can see I've got a problem if I write
the combined emission out there I'm not
seeing any emission I'm not seeing any
written emission in there which is
already a little bit broken because what
I should be seeing instead of that is I
should be seeing a light somewhere so we
have to fix that right that needs to be
set
let me also see what I'm getting for NPL
so oddly enough NPL is looking pretty
reasonable it's not what I would have
expected so it's not quite right but
it's not quite wrong either so a couple
things that are wrong with it yet you
can kind of see we're getting like
yellow for things that should be
pointing upwards so things that should
be pointing upwards should actually be
black and things that are pointing left
and right do look like they're sort of 0
&amp; 1 at the moment in greens or red
channels so that's a little bit better
but it looks kind of slightly wrong
while we're on that subject I think I
might as well go in and and take a look
here at the Z bias program here it is
and if we take a look at this here what
we want to know is why are we getting
weird values for the NX and why here so
the world normals
in this case we're compressing them down
to that range and so what we would
expect to see is that if the normal was
pointing upward in Z we would expect
like so for those cube tops of cubes
world in in world's world an X in world
and why should both be 0 and in that
case what we expect the output to be
would be 0.5 so it should not have been
bright yellow it should have been like
half yellow 128 128 like a mustard right
so it's not super wrong it's it's it's
not super wrong it's
just too bright yeah it would be the
only way to say it right it's too bright
now I don't know whether there's any RGB
conversion happening there I don't think
there should be because I don't want
those to be interpreted as srgb so
hopefully they're not but I don't
actually know that that's true at the
moment so what I do want to do probably
in this case is make sure that they're
not being coded that's RGB and that's
actually pretty easy to do so when we
come through here instead of default
frame buffer texture format in this case
what I can do here is say that for color
buffer 0 maybe that's true sort of color
the next is 0 then it's that otherwise
it's GL r g b a8 which is not NS RGB
format right because i don't want I
don't want any funny business there at
all I just want them encoded in in a
straightforward fashion so let's just
verifies that's the case but I think
that's probably the case yeah so
[Applause]
although they aren't getting encoded in
now that I think about it they will be
getting decoded by swearing so that
could actually be part of it
so those normals may actually not be
wrong so let's hold off on trying to bug
those QA begins now in theory but I want
to keep playing with this just a little
bit so let me just go ahead and in that
resolve there where's the result so
multi sample can't see cuz we find the
dinner so what I want to do here is I
want to take the emission and put that
back in there is that there and I just
want to look here at the thing that's
supposedly writing out the emission and
see why I'm not getting any of that
emission writing happening right so when
I run this like I said I should I expect
to nothing here the blackness that we
saw before and so I want to make sure
that there's nothing trivially going
wrong so I'm just going to write read
yeah so here's the other thing that I
was thinking about we we have to make
sure that blending is off but I'm pretty
sure it is so let's just make sure that
if I write read with zero in the Alpha
channel that it still comes through okay
so I wanted to make sure that that's the
case and that's good however it looks
like it's getting added because what you
can see here is there's actually like
addition looking like it's happening
there which should not be the case so I
want to make sure that you know geo
blends to the extent that it's on I want
to make sure that geo blend is not
occurring in the untoward way
so chill blend is supposed to be
disabled so in theory that blending must
be coming from somewhere else I don't
know about maybe if it's coming from the
multi sample resolution somehow although
I can't say I know how that would be
happening so this is a little suspicious
we may have to do more debugging next
weekend on this
however just taking a look at that as
well we do know that emissions should be
getting written out now so I should be
able just before we finish I should be
able to fix this particular bug with not
having a mission by looking at maybe
what's wrong with our light equation the
length light P minus world P situation
so what I should be able to do is take
the emission here as we were doing it
before with the emission RGB emit spread
that's happening here
I should be able to take this length
light P minus world B that should be
working and I don't know why it's not so
so previously we were definitely using
light P and world P and we were
subtracting the two to determine what
was going on so it does seem kind of
strange but I can't subtract them now
and get what should be basic it's a
circle right
I can widen this out to something very
large and see if that makes any
difference and it does so that's kind of
weird so somehow the length of that
being less than 1 is insufficient oh you
know why because it's above the head so
it's got a it's like a light that's
gotta kind of be I see it's a lightness
of sphere and the sphere was hovering a
little too high okay so at least now
we've got a sphere of life that's
basically just anything that's in that
side that sphere gets set to a lighting
value which is what I wanted okay so now
I should be able to stop cheating stop
moving that over unnecessarily here for
their surface reflect and now we should
be rendering to all of those places and
if I go down and look now when I do come
the transport light here we are when I
do this letting transport if now I will
actually guess I should turn it on first
if now I look at what happens for that
as the input I should be able to see
yeah as I go up I get a blurry version
of the actual light that's coming out
from the
game right as you can see there so now I
should be able to also turn back on the
light transport down like so and now I
should be able to see yeah essentially
like glowy here oh right so yeah like
you can see I'll go to the Q&amp;A now
definitely making a progress here this
is the way graphics programming tends to
go you know when you're working with
GPUs you can I got to go slowly through
it and it takes a while to get things
all sorted out because of the incredible
amount of busy work the programming
paradigm for GPU is just easy good
there's not a lot of other ways you can
say it it requires the programmer to do
a lot of stupid work that's not
necessary and that's just the way it
goes but you know the reward for doing
it is nice because you have all this
extra horsepower all these extra flops
you can take advantage of which is which
is pretty cool right so we're getting
there so what we have to do like I said
as we kind of go further forward here is
we just have to sort of take it one step
at a time and make sure we verify
results from each stage to each stage
when we're done with getting the
transfer over which we mostly done we
just need one more shader which
transfers those game output textures to
inputs for front back surface and NP
Tech by doing the translation over once
we move that over we're in position to
start iterating on our lighting solution
which again is going to take a while
because we kind of need to figure out
how to do a bunch of stuff in there
using a lot of approximated hacks right
but then we're great because we have the
complete conduit going through the
system so now we can get data from the
game into the lighting system which is
what we need and we can do it in an
arbitrary way so we can have any sprites
that we want light up which is nice
right
midlow asks we can set the spread of the
emitter but we can also but can we also
set the direction of the spread yes so
the the idea is that we have two pieces
of information coming out of the render
we have the normal of the sprite like
whichever way the sprite was facing
right we have that piece of information
and right now we are rendering just the
direction the actual sprite is facing
that may not be what we actually want to
save for the direction of the emitter we
may want to be able to specify a false
emitter right so basically like if we
were rendering a sprite and we wanted to
say like yeah the sprite is facing this
way but it's actually emitting that way
we could specify a different normal for
the emission perm right and the way that
we would do this is just by recognizing
that the emission thing the part where
the light is emitting we don't really
care about the reflectance so we can
just render two sprites the emitter
sprite which has a fake normal that we
set and then because I guess the other
part to remember is remember that the
normal is not used for any rendering
operation whatsoever right the normal is
not computed from the actual polygon
it's just an additional value that we
send down so when we render lights we
can render lights with a direction that
is has nothing to do with anything right
this if they're a sprite card with the
light on it that's a particular pattern
we can set what direction that is facing
right and it will work just fine
Valis why not doing a marathon screaming
lighting maybe if doing so will be more
productive as you remember what hack you
have done and maybe forgot the next
weekend yeah we definitely could do that
when we're ready to really hit the
lighting hard so when this whole
pipeline is working properly and we have
some lighting because like next weekend
we'll have actual lighting working in
the sense that it'll be wrong but we'll
see it in the game and playing off of
surfaces and whatever totally wrongly
when we then go to sort of okay now
we've really got to work out you know
experiment with different ways of
transporting this light around and how
we do our iterations and who writes to
what and whether we do you know what are
the values we actually propagate around
do we try to use spherical harmonics for
transfer do we try to do emitter
directions for transfer like we're doing
a blah blah blah as we sort of work on
that part it might make sense to do
longer streams
Napolean 89 don't know if this is the
right place with your assert macro it
could currently cause bugs if you place
it inside and if else that doesn't use
curly braces adding an elf to this macro
could solve this yeah I don't really
allow for lack of a better term
if Elsa's without brackets if there's an
if-else in my code that doesn't have
brackets that's that's a bug in my
opinion right like I would prefer the
compiler just told me like I would
prefer that compiler require brackets I
would turn that on because I don't think
the syntax and see for if-else is very
good and as a result it you know it
produces bad problems of the forum that
you talk about right where you know it's
ambiguous to the compiler they probably
might not be able to figure out what you
were trying to do as for the bug that
you're talking about inside and if else
that doesn't use curly braces then yeah
again you would end up with the
ambiguous the hanging else problem but I
don't allow that in the code so I don't
usually think about that or care about
that that make sense
psycho maniac TV I have been looking
into compression schemes for skeletal
animation data currently I have only
implemented basic quantization but I
would like to add Kerr fitting to the
mix could you give me some pointers on
this if I were to use Catmull ROM
splines what are some methods on
estimating the error of the segment and
finding a good split point how could I
apply this stuff to quaternions you see
if there's any questions on the on the
actual episode first do you plan to
allow sprite to use emit textures that
could for example make eyes glow yeah so
the idea would just be that anytime you
wanted to have emission in the artwork
you
just render an omission sprite with that
pattern and it would glow and cast light
I don't know that that will be achieved
but that's like what we're trying right
and we'll see how well we do
uh who says 42 alternative if-else
syntax uh well the alternative FL syntax
in my opinion just requiring brackets
right
I feel like brackets should be required
for that because they're the only thing
that makes it clear what is the body of
something like I feel like there should
always have been the notion that control
blocks have to take a block not a
statement is what I would have said
right it's two extra characters you know
I don't it doesn't add a significant
amount of typing like I don't like extra
typing certainly so I understand why
people wouldn't want a lot of extra
typing in there but it's two extra
characters I just don't see that as
being saving those two characters and in
return getting this really bad ambiguous
syntax just doesn't seem like a win you
know
now shota says about the NX NY lp0
LP one texture is a 16-bit texture worse
than a 32-bit texture in any way I felt
like you added LP 0 and LP 1 just
because it wouldn't make much of a
difference performance wise is that true
no it's not true performance wise I do
think RGB a and RGB or probably
preferred memory unpack lines but I
suspect RG is fine now as well like I
don't know I've never really played with
that but I would suspect that RG is
faster than RGB or RGB a because it's
just less bandwidth so I don't think
that it's just what I was looking at
that I was like well I could treat these
as for uniform textures that are three
uniform types that are all exactly the
same and when I thought about that I was
like that's got a knife it makes the
code a little bit easier to deal with on
the outside and so what I thought of in
my head was do I think I'll need extra
space or should I bother cuz I don't
want to prematurely clip it down and
then end up going oh wait I actually
needed more perms anyway and so what I
thought was well we're probably going to
want to specify some parameters for
lighting here because for example if we
do have any kind of ability to have
glossy versus diffuse surfaces I'm going
to need at least one more parameter for
that and then if we decided to do some
other kind of encoding like supposing
that we instead of storing the emission
we just stored like they we get rid of
that emission texture and just instead
store either surface reflectance or
immittance and we set another parameter
to say the immittance amount then that
would be to four wide textures which
maybe is the better way to go now I
think about it I don't think about that
ahead of time in fact that seems a lot
smarter
why didn't we do that so I feel like
that's actually a lot smarter if we just
stored NPL here and it was like emission
and specular and I guess we wouldn't
have any place to put the spread amount
but we could say that everything is in
just generally within I don't know I'll
leave it like this for now but I feel
like that so we should think about that
a little bit because we could get rid of
a whole texture at that point because if
we assume that surfaces are just always
one color and then they emit a certain
amount I feel like that is probably the
better way to go because then we don't
have to write to an entire other texture
which probably isn't really necessary
Alex killed the off topic I'm playing
with the debug cycle counters is there a
way to find out how long Windows puts
our process to sleep I'm missing
millions of cycles in my main loop yes
you can figure that out but it is
incredibly incredibly difficult so so if
you search for the worst API ever made
you will get a blog entry by me where I
talk about the way you can get this
information from windows I highly
recommend not doing it the reason I
highly recommend not doing it is because
it is the worst API ever made and so the
chances that you will even get it
working a little bit are is like zero
it's not just a bad API it's not just a
horrible API it's literally so
incredibly terrible that I literally
cannot imagine the thought process that
arrived at it
I cannot even I have no idea how someone
who could create such a thing actually
thinks about programming in their head
it's so foreign to me it's like I just I
can't even buy it's a dumbstruck when I
look at it so unfortunately even though
that data should be incredibly easy to
get the data that you're asking for
should be a trivial one function call to
Windows something like give me my
process sleep history buffer please and
you look at it it is instead literally
hundreds of API calls that are
incredibly obtuse very difficult to get
working require administrator privilege
and are globally required to be set
uniformly across the entire system just
to use it's insane
i wmb oh how do you define a good API
and a bad API or do you have examples of
very good ap is the definition of a good
API versus about API actually isn't as
hard as you would think a good API is an
API which has a number of API calls
proportional to the number of things you
were trying to do generally speaking and
does them efficiently write a bad API is
the opposite of that
in either case right so for example with
event tracing for Windows that API
should be roughly to call long probably
the first call would pass for example an
array or a series of flags ever you
wanted it which are the events that you
wanted to trace so it'd be like
beginning trace here are the flags and
then the second call bien tres here is a
buffer to put them into or end trace
give me a buffer back and then there's
one more API to free it either way right
this would be foolproof you know almost
nobody could mess that up it's trivial
to learn requires almost no
documentation very very straightforward
right instead what they decided to do
was first and you know I one of the
things I did was I show at the top of
this what it should probably look like
right I was like if you were just going
to implement this the dumbest way
possible and you know you weren't trying
to be even remotely clever with the API
you just sat down and did the first
thing that the average programmer should
probably think of this is the code right
and here is the API so I specified what
a good API would look like and again by
good in this case I'm not even saying
exceptionally good I'm just saying this
is just the basic thing that just has
the stuff the programmer does it's like
they begin a trace
they end at race and they get events
from the Tres that's what they do so
that's the ATI right and then I
sissified what some more complicated
versions would look like if you were
trying to do something fancier and then
I also said well if you wanted to have
other retrieval methods so I said let's
get more complicated how complicated
could it get at this point you're kind
of out of ideas like when you're sort of
get to here you're like I don't know how
it would make this any more complicated
this problem is so simple I don't know
how to make it more complicated like it
it's basically mem copy like I think
like they're it's like designing the API
for mem copy yeah you can sort of start
to make it more complicated but how
complicated can you really get with the
mem copy and the answer is they came up
with whole new ways so for example they
came up with a way that in order to get
a trace on Windows you have to create a
thread I'm not kidding you can't get a
trace without creating a separate thread
first how do you get from give me a
buffer of events which is so simple to
us to create a thread right I don't know
they did it they say man they made it
happen right at Microsoft nothing is
impossible they're like we could we can
do it I know we can take an API that's
essentially mem copy and require the
user to make a thread right so I'd
encourage you to look through this and
just see what I'm talking about it's
nuts you know you've got to specify all
these quids in here and you've got to
set all this stuff up you've got to
include a whole ton of header files
right so instead of just including one
header file it's like here's the tracing
functions right you've got a call start
trace and you've got to call this this
start trace thing in some weird way that
I forget what it is you can't do it this
way you have to create a buffer that you
malloc to put the name in I because you
need to name it something and the name
has to be in some kind of permanent I
don't even remember
the name has to be attached to the end
of the struct that you pass in so
instead of passing the struct and the
name separately you have to concatenate
them together first by allocating a
thing copying the name into the offset
buffer which they don't give you any
utility functions for so you have to do
it
you then have to make these control
calls and then copy the name in using a
different thing in a separate place so
it has to be there and it also has to be
here
you then have to open the trace because
starting the trace and opening a trace
or different things you haven't you
could see like all these things are just
building up on top of each other you
have to set a bunch of things in this
structure to like point to callbacks
that are going to happen when it goes
and then you can open it and then you've
got a thread callback where it's going
to calling you back you have to do that
on the on a separate thread because it's
going to then lock up that thread just
sitting there waiting to call this
callback it's going to call this
callback you can't actually get the
callback unless you call process trace
I'm forgetting a bunch of these things
but like that's roughly how they mean at
work and it's just nuts you know what I
mean like it's like it's so far away
from anything that should ever happen in
an organization shipping an API that I
just I can't even imagine how they got
to it it's got to be really special I
love for someone to have done the like
archeology on the series of check-ins
that led up to that being released as an
API because I'd love to see how it grew
to be that thing right because you know
there's got to be a lineage there you
don't just sit down and write that I
hope as your API right like you have
some sort of serious thing but if you
want to try and get that API working and
heaven help you if you do but if you
want to that is the only way at least
that I know of that's how you get the
information out of windows as to when it
put your tasks to sleep so if you're
trying to determine when you got
switched away that is the only way I
know of to do it now if you just want to
know how many total cycles you did you
got slept there maybe some way to do
that I'm not sure like you may be able
to query a performance counter of some
kind that will tell you just that
information and by dipping the two you
could get just the cycles back but you
wouldn't necessarily I don't know if
you'd know which thread that was on so
it might be hard for you to tell who to
attribute it to but you could try to get
that out that way which would be a lot
less painful potentially right
all right
so I think I'm going to close it down
the the question before that was off
topic as well which is about how do you
do compression of animation data I guess
what I say about that is this kind of a
large topic and I sort of gave a talk on
this a long time ago I gave one of the
GBC and one in Korea on the topic I it
was included in sort of a larger topic
that was like on how to do exporting and
I can't really reprise it in a short
amount of time
I mean basically there's a lot of a lot
of aspects to it the one I did for
granny is a least-squares curve fitter
and it kind of uses just some heuristics
to determine where to refine the curves
and you know that is at this point
seventeen year old technology so you can
do a lot better than it now by taking
into account a lot more stuff and you
could have a lot more horsepower too and
I think we understand the problem a lot
better now you know back when we
originally did this it was kind of I
don't want to use the word cutting edge
because it's not really that it's more
just like it wasn't really being done
hardly anywhere when I did it and so I
feel like now we've kind of gotten a lot
more visibility into how that sort of
stuff can work in what ways you can do
it and so I I don't know if if someone
is put out some good information on that
somewhere but it's kind of in depth and
you would want like a whole talk you
know a whole sort of lecture or paper on
it that was sort of a practical one not
a research paper like here are some
theoretical ways we've tried compressing
slides but rather something that's like
here at Naughty Dog you know we store
our slides in this format we can press
them this way or something right like I
feel like somebody should have been
putting out a modern one of that by now
but since I haven't looked for anything
like that myself I don't know I just
feel like it should be there you know
it's it's not a super hard problem but
it does require some elbow grease and it
is a bit subtle and it does take
experience you know you have to have
worked with animation and understand how
things work and what goes on in there
and how you you know what you have to do
with quaternions in this case as well
and and all that stuff but for us we
ninja
speaking of ever thought of releasing
old stalks you've done if you still have
sliced notes and the like laying around
yeah so I I have thought about it a
little bit I don't know how much utility
there is in that exactly but you know I
I do I have thought about maybe trying
to redo the talks you know on stream
sort of a thing and like so that I've
have a recording of them because I don't
have recordings I don't think of a lot
of them but like for example here's the
GDC one that I gave and this has the
information in it it's fact that that
you were that's not you but the person
who was asking about the curve fitting
uh
you can see here so here's like what I
was using in a dennis's this is
basically 17 years ago because I did it
in like 2000 2001 and so this lecture
was 2002 so even the lecture itself is
at this point so you know like I said
it's old information probably not all
how I'd write it today but it's you know
it did ship in lots and lots of games so
it's good enough for that I guess so I
you know you can kind of see that I've
got to outline the algorithm here and I
talked about how you can use linear
quaternion as a linear approximate I can
use real quaternions as an approximation
to orientation quaternions to give you a
result you can actually use but still be
linear and I talked about oversampling
the input to you know to get a Nyquist
thing in your interior solver I talked
about how you sample from the various
things and talk about how you transfer
windpipes Ida I don't know if I've got
the curve getting stuff in here the cria
one might be more in depth that's
probably in the pipeline here yeah so
you can see the curve fitter here in
operation on a 2d curve for example and
you can see that it just starts with a
minimum curve and fits it and it looks
at the error across the curve to each
individual sample and it adds not
progressively until it can sort of fit
to the data and you can sort of figure
out how closely you want it to match and
it'll stop at the part where it needs to
right and there's a lot of reasons why
this isn't the best approach but like I
said it does work
it's just these days I'd probably do
something more heavyweight than that but
anyway I don't know if if I talk yeah I
guess I don't really talk about it
anymore so yeah sorry so I don't know
that I ever really talked about this and
just didn't have any yeah
all right uh let's see I think close
down now let's let's go ahead and wrap
it up all right thank you for joining me
for that sort of handmade here it's my
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with a
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero or going to
come to the source code so you can play
around with it learn from it and do your
own experimentation we also have a forum
site you can go to if you want to ask
questions about stuff we've done the
patreon page go to transport the video
series a schedule bot that tweets the
schedule at you if you want to know when
we're going to be live and an episode
guide for catching up on old episodes
that's it for this week I'll be back
next week I believe I got to check my
calendar but I believe always check the
schedule bot I believe we'll even Act
next week to finish up getting the
lighting working through the pipeline
entirely and then start playing with the
lighting transfer til we get something
that we think is usable for the game
that's about it until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody