hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show recode a complete game live on
stream yesterday we did some rudimentary
float print out stuff because we you
know had replaced printf and we needed
to replace the float printing and I'll
be honest with you I don't really know
what we're gonna do today because that
you know here we are we're on day 3 30
and I I mean I'm sure there's plenty to
do but that was definitely we finished
sort of that that bit of it so we are
currently printing out floats like a
champ they're not it's not a very good
float print out routine but we don't
really need a very good float print out
routine we just needed something that
would print out floats so I don't know
at the moment what we should be doing
I'm going to take a look at the to do
list and also maybe we can take a look I
don't know if we can go to github and
see I think I can sign in here and see
what's going on I we could take a look
at some of our bugs and see if we can
just finish up a few more bugs but the
after that we're have to pick something
new to dive into because at the moment
we don't really have where we finish the
thing that we were working on uh so
let's take a look here I don't know what
this is type punning through pointers
instead of just casting what are we
talking about stereo where value is a
void star this could said be written as
u mm value or you mM value i I don't
care about that at all I don't that's
not a bug why would that I feel like if
you're going to put a bug in it should
be a bug right that you would have you
have to demonstrate that there is some
this is not a bug in any way is it why
is this in here
alright so that's good so let's see here
so we've got a couple other ones here I
for again for clang stuff these and then
we've got a few other things here switch
constant power panning rate Campari okay
so this one I believe we fixed right
infra resting list we're using a rig
count on the temp care pointer this
gives a length size of eight for
everything so this was the one that I
fixed so I believe this was fixed on day
3 29 okay there so I can see see stuff
okay so that's good and let's see what
else we got here so a couple other ones
so these two are the clan compatibility
ones this one I it looks like we've got
a situation where if we can't load if
Pam a close one but debugging fair man
fails to load for the dll in the
function with the d'box Wilk you might
do data but will not be collated okay so
we we basically have a problem of we'd
keep we'd keep gathering debug info
until we run out the buffer and that
would be bad okay well good to know yeah
we could probably fix that and then
what's this it's just a constant power
panning from this forum post this is a
pretty small easy fix and once for the
audio maintain same intensity across the
whole panting field first depending
range of negative one to one needs to be
map to the range of pie for drips of the
panic field and radians then the panning
for the lr channels is calculated oh so
that's just a you're sort of doing a
rotation around so that's expensive that
looks real expensive though right you
have to do a sign cose inside the loop
there
I don't think I like that for this
unless we really had a situation where
we were hearing it be a problem I don't
know if I like that because here's what
they're sort of saying and I don't
disagree with them what they're saying
is that
I I think anyways is that if I have a
source and I move it like this right and
here is the listener it's actually if I
just linearly interpolate it between the
two speakers it's technically getting
closer to me right like the distance
here is obviously less than the distance
here so if the speakers do their job
faithfully then we would expect to hear
it get louder as it passes through and
then software again right which i assume
is what this is talking about but I'm
not one hundred percent sure so what
they're sort of suggesting is you know
you can kind of go and and interpolate
an arc right as you go through here and
that arc would would then make it so
that you're not going to be you're not
going to be getting that that bit there
but I feel like this looks really
expensive to me so i might say are we
sure that that is the the right way to
make that trade-off like you know let's
say we were going to do constant power
panning and maybe we didn't care exactly
about perfectly linear speed in the pan
you could imagine another thing we could
do which is is to renormalize this out
to the arc so do the linear pan and then
just use a reciprocal square root to
normalize back out to the arc so we
wouldn't have to do cosine and sine
right so for example we could imagine
some function that's like okay yeah you
know we have a pan value right and the
pan value is negative 1 to 1 but we want
to make sure that that it gets
interpreted constant power as as we go
through right and so yeah in order to do
that what we could do is sort of say
well I
I guess the problem is we need the
volume yeah trying to think about how we
would do this because what we want to
know right is how loud this point is
going to be in the left channel in the
right channel and I'm not sure exactly
how to map it directly to their but I
don't love this because I just don't
know if I remember correctly let me
double check and make sure that I'm not
miss mistaken maybe I am but I thought
our audio was per sample interpolated
and I don't remember if it's not then
it's not a big deal because you only
have to do that once but I didn't know
if the pan was animated right so do we
have pan at all here let's see output
playing sounds loaded sonic let's get
sound get next on Shane d volume uh
geez vol chunk jump to mix Clemens out
channel index so it looks like we are
actually not really doing panning in
that sense inside the mixer we are just
sort of outputting into the mixer we are
out putting up like a per channel volume
it looks like right let me see here
t volume so we do you can see here that
we do volume per sample so if we're
doing volume per sample then I don't
want to be doing like a sign in a cosine
and a in the middle there right that
just doesn't seem like a good idea at
all to me so I don't know how I feel
about that I would say that probably we
could work out a thing where we you know
where we did some kind of a
approximation to it using only using
only our squirt because that'll be
faster but I don't know that I want sine
and cosine in there I feel like they're
going to be too expensive per sample for
me to really want to do that because
there is no sine and cosine instruction
you have to actually issue a series of
instructions to generate a sine a cosine
and the sine and the cosine they're not
short i I'm just going to randomly pick
someone's here in Kate it's hopefully
there is one I don't know if this is one
here let's see there's a sin in here
that I can just just so I can sort of
point to an example if there is one okay
so here's a sine function right and you
can kind of see what's going on here
right it's it's quite a few instructions
to make this work you know it's it's 20
or 30 instructions or something probably
in here may be hard to say because
you've got to do all of those and then
all of these right probably maybe even
yeah I think 30 instructions are
something like that and 30 instructions
for sample in addition to what we've got
a
you you know um I just don't know I just
don't know if I if I like that let me
verify that we're actually in fact
interpolating the volume yeah we are so
I mean you know it's already we're
already doing what about six
instructions here is something like that
per sample so we we'd be we'd be you
know making our mixer like six times
slower or something like this to add
that feature and we don't really know if
we ever need it so i think i'm going to
say no to that one
so that's going to closed oops so what
else we got here let's see we've got
texture environment being set in the
wrong place that's definitely true so I
believe we just kind of cut and pasted
that code and basically what happens
inside OpenGL is texture environment
stuff why did we not find that where is
Jill whereas our oh because I didn't
open the project file that's why so GL
Texan it looks like we are setting that
for some reason we're setting that here
which we don't need and here yeah those
that is not where that should be set so
text parameters are set on the texture
so those are appropriately going with
the individual texture but GL text em I
is a property of the pipeline it's the
property of like what this what the
current drawing state is going to be so
really that could be set kind of
globally and in fact we never change
that texture environment so we should be
able to set that up just in our in it
and leave it on right so like when we
are originally initializing things we
should be good to go so if we wanted to
we should be able to do that so for
example I think we could probably put
that right here and just leave it there
for now since at the moment we don't do
any multi texturing or anything like
that so that's probably fine right ok
okay and yeah so this one's a little
tricky because I don't know very much
about this so we might have to go look
that up a little bit but Martin's who
probably many of you know from the
forums he answers a lot of people's
questions that they have about things
handmade hero related and otherwise he
was pointing out on the forums that
there is a recommendation from Intel
that if you are going to spin lock I on
a if you're going to spin lock on some
kind of variable like we are doing with
our ticket mutex which I think we used
for like texture updating or something
like this right we got one right here so
when we are putting these operations in
for the textures when we do those ticket
mutexes we're really in there for an
incredibly short period of time right
three three assignments or four
assignments is all we're doing right so
the thing is I don't really know if it
makes sense to issue and mm pause in the
case where there's that few but maybe it
does right maybe it's always better if
even if you're going to only spend like
once on the spin lock maybe it's always
better because the CPU can do something
smarter and I just don't know and since
I've never really used mm pause I'm not
sure what to make of it I don't know
whether it's a good idea to
use it or not but essentially what it is
is inside when if we look at the
implementation of it inside the ticket
mutex basically all you do is inside
this while loop you put the mm pause
bait you know as the essentially
instruction that you're executing and
what it's supposed to do is let the
processor architecture know that you've
got one cpu core waiting on some other
cpu core because then it will do
something smarter in theory now I don't
actually know what it will do and that's
what worries me right I don't really
want it to do anything like downshift
that core power wise or anything like
that so I'm not really sure let's see so
in the software developers mania let's
see what Martin's referenced he says
eight ten to
ok so the pause instruction can improves
alright so they got a little grammar
mistake there that's okay the pause
instruction can improve the performance
of processors supporting hyper-threading
technology when exiting spin wait loops
and other routines where 1 30 secs
tuning shared lock or a simmer for in a
tight pulling loop when extreme spin
wait loop the processor can suffer a
severe performance penalty when exiting
the loop because it detects a possible
memory order violation and flushes the
core processors pipeline the pause
instruction provides a hint of the
processor that the code sequence is a
spin wait loop the processor uses this
hint to avoid the memory order violation
and prevent the pipeline flush in
addition the pause instruction d
pipelines the spin wait loop to prevent
it from consuming execution resources
excessively and consume power needlessly
interesting when it exits the spin wait
loop the processor can suffer a
performance penalty when excellent
because it detects a possible memory
order violation and flushes the core
processors pipeline I guess I don't
understand how the wait the pause
instruction would fix that because it
doesn't know what else you did in that
loop hmm I'm not sure I understand what
how it is that exiting the loop would
cause the flush in one case but not in
the other just based on the presence of
this instruction mmm let's read 8 10 61
until recommends that a pause
instruction be placed in allston way
loops that run until a prosperous
reporting until I prophetic technology
and multi-core processors so froh
teasing you spin lock wait loops include
blood pressure circulation primitives
and I de loop such routines get the
processor core busy x rating a load
compared branch loop law thread waits
for resource to become available
including a positive such loop greatly
improves efficiency the following
routine gives example use the pause
instruction the spin wait loop abuses a
test test and set technique for turning
the ability synchronization let's test
record for a spin like loops because we
really dependent for the files for she
has an opposite rection so it really
doesn't tell us very much about what
this thing does
I am just not sure what to make of that
it seems like based on what it says it
does that it should be strictly a
benefit to put it in there like it does
not sound like it's doing anything fancy
like down powering that core or anything
like that so you know it seems at least
for the documentation that it would be
harmless to add and so if it actually
does give us you know confer upon us
some theoretical benefit in terms of not
flushing the pipeline on it exit from
the loop then that's cool but I you know
how do I know that because I don't feel
like I really understand it you know in
general it's definitely it makes some
sense because you could imagine the
processor looking at the loop and going
okay I'm doing all this loop code I
don't have any idea what I'm going to
exit this loop so my my pipeline just
consists of a ton of compare jump
instructions that I'm looking to try and
do right and so when one of those
finally says no don't keep looping
obviously the entire pipeline is wrong
at that point you know what I'm saying
so I guess if I understand what their
insinuating here it would mean that the
pause instruction is the signal to the
CPU not to undiluted does is it says hey
mr. read ahead like stop reading ahead
like or stops but don't do any
speculative execution like just do this
thing exactly as it is so don't do
speculative execution that way when week
when we do jump out you don't have to
flush anything and hey we know there's
no benefit to speculate execution
because all you're doing is reading from
a line that you don't control anyway so
until someone else let's go with a line
not going to do anything right I mean I
could see that I could see that being
implemented in the processor that makes
some sense to me I wish they gave a more
specific explanation of albeit so that I
could verify that that sort of cursory
understanding that I just sort of said
actually bears some resemblance to
reality because I don't feel like the
documentation here really gives me
enough to go on to understand what
they're actually doing in practice which
is possibly intentional you know a lot
of times they don't want you to know
exactly what their chip is doing and
that's fine but yeah it's a little
confusing so what that would imply is
that you know in here we would put one
of these and presumably that would just
make things work a little bit better and
in theory it shouldn't change the
execution of our program at all it just
gets rid of a little bit of a pipeline
potential pipeline stall during the spin
lock so so there we go
okay uh so let's say that that was okay
um all right so yeah we'll leave that in
there let me go ahead and bracket that
more and yeah and there we go so now
we've got quite a few of these issues
down let's take a last look at some of
these guys here maybe we can do these
two these are clang compat ones which we
were sort of trying to get to these I
thought wrong meters two pixels we did
okay so that this was a we fixed it for
our main code but we still have the same
problem so maybe we should do this to do
as well so that's another one we can do
all right so you should be able to do
this one we should be able do this one
in this one this one I don't know if
we'll do today claimed compatibility
wise I don't know where we're at on this
we have problems with the macros and I
don't know how much I want to deal with
that because as far as I'm concerned on
GCC you know if you can't run the debug
system I'm not sure I care as far as
cross-platform ISCO's there if it means
I gotta deal with more macro nonsense
which is always a pain so I don't know
if anyone's figured out how we can do
our macros the way we want to do our
macros but yeah so let's take a look at
the other ones instead let's take a look
at this usual arithmetic of ridges where
apparently applied to the typography
Eric my code this caused a problem when
clogging the macro air from GCC and
clang let's see here a second order is a
promotable type you ate undefined
behavior because our grits are promoted
to int
okay I guess I see what that saying
where did we do that so I guess what I
don't understand here is are we
essentially saying that there is no way
to read one of these under any
circumstances meaning you cannot ever do
a read bar
because I thought the idea was that the
integer length fields to specify this
but I guess what we're saying is well
hey it's going to get promoted to an int
because the compiler defines all ver arc
functions as promoting their arguments
too if they can so maybe the case is
just that when you do integer length I
where do we actually set that so we
don't support 64-bit integers yet it
looks like either all right well so if
energy length is always four then I
guess what we could do is say you know
in general no matter what you try to
read if it's gonna be promotable to an
int than it will be promoted to an int
if that makes sense and then if you are
actually 64-bit then it'll read that but
I think that that does make sense
because my recollection of how and we
were never calling that code path so
that would have been like a bug but we
just would never see it right so it
probably is better to write it that way
because if you were to pass a care like
a one-bite integer or tube ID integer if
you were to pass those down you would
definitely see those being converted up
two integers right because that's the
definition of it now I assume that care
we did the same way yeah you can see we
did that so I assume that this is
actually this to do could be removed and
that is exactly what it should be so I
think I believe we fixed this on day 2
30 I believe that is the correct thing
to do there okay
I passing v8 list is pointer I'll see
you at lunch at our sex VA lista finds
an array type okay this caused the
problem when passed as a pointer in the
reed ver arg functions she has a similar
complaint so canada function on file
known conversion from built-in vilas
star for a second argument so i don't
know what we want to do about that I
guess what we could do
let's take a look here lead bar are
designed to Jay
I'll be honest I don't super understand
however why we are not able to take the
address of it I guess because it is not
really an actual value on the stack I
guess so i'm not sure what the fix for
that is yes its stack overflow but the
answer is good okay so we essentially
have to wrap it into something
hmm well that seems like a really like
if I may that just seems really stupid
in general because it's like you need to
be able to pass this to utility
functions but okay let me take a look
here at what I think would be the most
expedient way to fix this so we passed
the VA list to for mastering list and
it's going to call read vard float
reverb site integer right it's going to
call these guys here so what I guess is
true is you know I could macro these
guys and that would work I mean you know
I could do something like this
not sure I love this idea
but here you go
so I could do something like that right
where it's a macro now and so since it's
a macro it'll just operate directly on
the VAR glist that it's actually using
does this not get called off it does so
and now I would have to remove the
address of situation here right because
now I just want to pass it I just want
to like use it as the argument to a
macro so I don't you know I don't want
to actually pass it as an address
anymore I want to just use it as is and
in theory that would just work I got to
do the other ones here so pound fine
there we go so this would be another one
these are backwards here just need to do
basically the exact same code
so if the length is 8 then we want to
use the 64-bit read and if the length is
not then we use the 32-bit read okay and
finally exact same thing for this guy
it's just doing the signed version of it
so this guy's a little trickier but
actually I don't know that we need to do
this anymore because I can just
basically copy this code right I can
just say like okay this is pretty
trivial to do here might as well just
copy it one more time and say well
alright let's use assigned value
everywhere for that so in theory I think
that would work and I'll verify that we
didn't break any of our code but we'll
need somebody on GCC to test that out
since we're kind of just shooting in the
dark here trying to help them out okay
in theory we fix this on day 3 30 what
pain in the butt totally unnecessary and
don't like it at all okay so oops I
think we had one more yeah and so I
think the only one the other one I
wanted to do here was the wrong leaders
to pixels one we could try one of those
to this one and this one are kind of
going to remain for a little bit so this
one is just we've got the same meters
two pixels computations going on in the
cutscene code right so here's our
cutscene code meters sit here meters two
pixels so we've got our meters two
pixels code and we've got the to do for
unify the stuff
and like if we go over to world no 2
think you can see the code is the same
over here so you can kind of see we've
got this the same things exactly the
same things being defined multiple loops
multiple times and so the question was
do we want to try and unify that now
that we sort of have a different now
that we fix the equation to be right in
one place and it's wrong in the other
place do we want to try and do something
smarter here and the answer is I don't
really know it seems like probably the
easiest thing to do would be to just
have a thing that that does just this
one piece uh so you know if we want to
share this we could do something like
you know standard camera params or
something like that and we could have
width of monitor meters to pixels focal
length you know and then we could have
like gets standard or you know we could
even do this camera Rams and that could
just return
whatever we think the right values here
would be so we believe lease at the time
being this to be the case so all we
would need is something that passes the
width and then off we would go so yeah I
don't know if focal length gets used
anywhere else it doesn't meters to
pixels it doesn't with the monitor it
doesn't so probably what we can do is
just say all right center camp Rams
camera equals get 200 camera params and
we can pass that draw buffer with to the
function we can keep this comment and
then we could just say all right get rid
of that and grab those out of here
uh so yeah I'm I'm fine with that I feel
like that's pretty reasonable get
standard camp rands driver for width
sanic Arizona cleared identifier that's
because that's not what scholars just
called camera prams so if we were to
then share that you know and I could put
that in the render or something I'm not
really sure where that would be most
appropriate but yeah you know let's say
we just put that in there for now then I
can just go back over the cutscene and
call it the same way and then we can
always adjust the parameters if we need
to buy having some other function that
lets us pass something in there more
specifically potentially but let's go
ahead and start with that and we'll see
what happens and yeah now that may mess
up all of our camera settings right so
we may have to readjust the foot that
focal lengths to make sense for what
we're trying to do here right like you
can see that that's like all of our
scenes are going to be a little bit
wrong so we may have to kind of have a
thing where maybe you maybe you pass the
focal length in because I think all of
these are going to be like a little bit
wrong all of the all of the layouts for
these guys are going to be a little bit
wrong and we're going to have to cut the
other they're going to be too close in
so I think what we want to do there is
just say like okay let's you know we've
got that one we know that the focal
length was three on this one let's
change the focal length to other things
and see what happens until we get
something that's a little bit better for
us
let's see if that's a little more like
what we wanted for our cut seeing stuff
maybe something like that
can we speed up the time step here at
all
we need better sliders but that looks
like a pretty good focal length for what
we're doing
so the question is does that work for
the game as well should we just leave
that focal length for everything no so
I'm just going to make it so that you
can pass the focal length here and then
we'll just pass the one that we actually
want so in cutscene when we call get
standard camera prams will pass 1.25
because that's what we were using for
that adjustment at which point it's kind
of stupid that we're even passing in
there but hey we'll leave it that way
and then we'll pass three for the other
one ah sorry yes we won't pass three
will pass a third okay so i think that's
good now and we can close that guy off
there we go
alright so let's see how are we doing
here we have four issues remaining we've
got a fail-safe in here and we've got
the client compatibility one so I think
that's good for now although I guess
since we've got what we've got 15
minutes left I suppose if we have 15
minutes left we could do this take a
look at this failsafe one this is not
really a bug that we care super much
about because it wouldn't affect end
users but you know like I said we've got
15 minutes we might as well do it so
let's take a look at what it's talking
about it just says that you know when we
do win32 load game code obviously with
3g load game code could fail right
because it's trying to load the game
code but if it can't for some reason
like the games to be recompiled or
whatever so again not really an end user
scenario but it is a developer scenario
when we call win32 load game code and it
can't load the game then what's going to
happen is it can't do debug endframe it
can't call this because it won't be
there right and so I think the idea is
that if it just can't ever reload it at
all then it gets into a bad state where
it is just going to accumulate debug
things forever and it can't ever get
can't ever flush them so I'm not sure
shouldn't there be a global debug table
thing in here I forget it's been a long
time there it is d book too so record
increment i think is the thing that
stops recording from happening if we
wanted to stop recording right in fact
there it is a debug set event recording
enabled that would turn it off so what
we probably could do is we could
probably do something like this and then
you know turn it back on again but it
looks like we're actually doing that
here so when we tried to reload if the
game wasn't valid it should have turned
it off in fact why didn't that happen I
guess it doesn't happen if the first
time through like when is executable
needs to be reloaded so i suppose what
we need to do here is do this at the
outset probably right so when we do
win32 load game code the first time we
probably want to say is like okay set
event recording to whether or not the
game is valid like right off the bat
that's probably the only thing we would
really need to do and we could test that
right by saying like okay game is valid
equals false and we could say game i
debug what is it endframe
so we could nuke it and set set that up
and we can see how it goes
so yeah I think that's probably fine but
I'm not exactly sure because this is not
something that's ever happened to us so
I'm not one hundred percent certain
so I'm not sure so let's take a look at
is valid so it looks like we're also
missing this so that's another problem
there okay okay so that probably does it
but we'll let that be confirmed by
whoever wanted that actually fixed all
right so now we're just down to a clan
compatibility here because this these
two are sort of not code things those
were things for me to do some day on my
own these are the Klang compatibility
ones that are still there and probably
what I would say is I'm going to need
somebody to figure out of this of the
things in here that we haven't fixed I
think we actually fix some of them of
the things in here that we haven't fixed
what actually do you want me to do about
it right so somebody has to come up with
who uses clanging in GCC on a day-to-day
basis oh they can test it figure out
what solves this problem and then I'll
do it but I can't really speculate as to
how to fix their macro processing very
well because I don't am not running with
them so it's pretty hard to do at that
point and these I guess we already did
so all of these are done it's just the
macro debug macros that are a problem
and then I think we could close this
issue so someone if someone wants to do
that send it to me then I'll take a look
at that otherwise I think we're good so
let's go ahead and end it since we don't
have any bugs left right now to we can
look at let's go ahead and end it for
today and go to the Q and a if anyone
has any questions I can
take them now
Casey is there a bug with chun creation
you added a free list up but are not
using it well we could certainly take a
look so let's see to do
so what what makes you say that what
makes you say that tell config could you
could you be more specific about that
perhaps I'm going to look at Martin's
thing he said he'd caught a copy-paste
bug that I did on stream so I'm going to
go fix that while you while you type in
more stuff when doing copypasta you left
f60 forecast in the wrong place
returning operator ah thank you
Thanks Martin's
when you found yourself unable to write
code for something what would you do to
try to find something to do for said
project um well I guess what I would say
about that is there's there's a couple
things so one if you're having if you
get stuck on a problem then there's a
lot of things you could do to get
yourself unstuck on the problem if it's
if it's a if it's the problem that you
can't figure out how to do the code
right you can talk to some other
programmers about it you could post on
the internet about it like a blog post
and get help from people I mean you can
ask about it on handmade hero people do
that often right even you can try
experimenting try like writing some
little side code to try and get more
traction on the problem there's a lot of
things you can do for that on the other
hand if your problem is just that you're
doing a really like sloggi problem that
takes a long time and isn't very
rewarding to work on until like the end
and you're having trouble just staying
motivated doing all the work that's
necessary to get it going you know
sometimes it is just a slog and
sometimes you know you got it you gotta
grind through it and my advice on that
is just don't stop right like sometimes
you're going to be down and you're only
right in two hours or three hours of
code today or something because it's
just such a slog and you're not feeling
good about it but you got to keep
writing code because writing codes the
only way you're going to get yourself
out of it and it's not because you just
need to pile code on top of kotick type
of code it just means you got to keep
trying things and until it clicks until
this stuff works and so the worst thing
you can do is get yourself in a
situation where you stop writing code
because you think you're just going to
have an epiphany and then it's going to
be clear how to write it all it's like
no don't do that that's rarely the right
thing to do yes the code that you may be
slogging through that doesn't seem like
it's right and you're confused and
whatever yes it's probably the wrong
code yes you will probably have to
delete it right but that's not the point
the point is getting the code out there
and trying those things is what will get
you to the Epiphany and if all you do is
just sit there and sit inside your head
all the time you probably won't be able
to get there because if it's a coding
problem like not a math problem you know
then
it's probably too inked intricate for
you to really see the truth in it just
inside your own head and this is the
problem I have with a lot of those kind
of like super formal methodologies like
uml diagrams and all this sort of
nonsense is because they really aren't
any good for things that are complicated
and that's the only time you really need
them right and it's because you actually
need to see how the real code works
because the details are where the
trickiness and the complexity lies not
the abstract bigger picture most usually
the abstract bigger picture is clear
look I just want to do this thing to
this thing or whatever right it's very
simple to state it's all of the minutia
that important and so sometimes you'll
find yourself in a situation where
you're having a lot of trouble I still
have this to this day I often do that
when I'm working on new architectures
like that often often it is not unusual
it's not because you're a bad program or
anything like that something good
programmers can have happen to them
throughout the entire course of their
programming career if they're if they're
continuing to challenge themselves and
and if they don't stagnate you know and
so I would say the most important thing
to do during those times is to be
persistent and force yourself to write a
few hours of code every day never let it
drop to zero right never let a hard
problem stop you from writing some code
to try an experiment or push on the
problem because eventually you will get
it if you are persistent and keep trying
things and so that's real important and
there has been many times in my
programming career where I've gotten
into a state where it was really grim
but I just kept coding a little every
day and eventually i clawed my way out
of it as my brain sort of started to
internalize all the things and I got
enough tries in the area and I saw how
it sort of started me I was like ah ok
now I've got it and then I go right but
you can't get you won't get over that
hump if you stop coding you'll just sit
there and paralysis forever until you
start so never let your coding rate fall
to zero is like probably the biggest
single piece of advice I could have I
can give for people who are tackling
difficult new problems where they don't
know the solution already or they don't
know how to write the code correctly
already that's really the most the
single most important thing to do is
never stop writing code every day
and if you can't think of what to write
that day to help you solve the problem
just pick something random be like I
don't know I'm just going to try
something the first thing that comes to
mind if I have to write even if it's a
long shot even if I know it's a it's a
02 to the end solution to the problem
write it because in writing that thing
you at least learn something and your
brain will see something and that's what
keeps it going and will eventually get
the solution yes that code will be throw
away it won't be what you ship but
that's okay because sometimes coding is
not about writing code you're going to
ship it's about getting your brain to
the state where it can write the code
you're going to ship and a lot of times
that involves code to it involves
throwaway code and that's okay so just
know that and don't spend a lot of time
fussing with that code like don't try to
make it pretty or do any you know
fanciness to it write it as ugly as you
want but just get it out there get it
working and let that push you forwards
towards the better solution looking to
start a career in programming computer
science I'm currently 16 and in grade 12
any tips on what i should do also thanks
to chat for all the help uh well yeah I
mean the best way to start a career in
programming is just to be doing a lot of
programming right the there's so many
resources out there to learn programming
you should just be programming a ton on
your own and if you program a ton on
your own you will get good enough that
you should be able to like you know make
some blog posts or post some things to
start getting people to notice that
you're you know okay what you do that
you're learning and that's usually how
you can sort of start to get you know
meet some people on the internet through
those things that you can do and then
you can start talking to people about
you know like oh can I have an
internship whatever so I don't really
know these days what the easiest route
is but I would say you know the one
thing that I can say is pretty much
always been true throughout all game
programming history is the best way to
get yourself in a position to have a
career in programming kuta sciences to
do a lot of programming every day I've
never known a good programmer who didn't
I know a lot of bad programmers who
don't long billion it has been a while
since we've seen some of the sea time
stats that are being collected if you
have time sure I think we can do that we
have been keeping those right in here no
in here don't remember where I put the
sea time stats
well I don't remember where I put them
so let me take a look handmade sherrod
ctm it's like it'll be in the bill
directory right oh no it's after the pop
d so it'll be in the code directory so I
must have been looking right at it let's
see ctm there we go my stats so here you
go you can see some stats here we have
spent a total of twenty-three minutes
building throughout the life of the
project I for successful builds and nine
minutes for unsuccessful builds we have
tried to build the thing over 1,700
times which is funny you can look at our
averages we tend to spike out in about
three seconds it looks like this is 181
days for bucket that's how many builds
we did did we really do 181 builds in
one day I'm not sure what that's telling
us
oh no it's 4.5 days per bucket okay and
there's one day per bucket so there we
go okay yeah yeah so that's not all
right so yeah there you go is that the
SATs you were looking for let's see what
is the current kind of the stream it
seems that we have been dealing with
bugs for a while sorry I may have missed
the explanation if you provided it a
little while ago we don't do a schedule
for streams we just work on whatever
we're working on day to day till config
when we get the chunk in get world chunk
it seems we always allocate new memory
well when we get the chunks that's in
that's in here so I'm not sure what
you're talking about and get in here you
mean or we're talking about this guy I
guess to the best of my knowledge let me
see to the best of my knowledge I guess
I'm not sure I remember do we ever when
do we actually add chunks to free lists
at all
so we put the whole chunk we do so when
we load it up we put the whole chunk in
the free list so we add the chunk of the
free list there and then later on I
guess when we pack we're going to use a
get call right are we I don't know let's
find out map into chunks pace when do we
actually get the chunk map into chunks
pace pack entity into world get world
chunk yeah I think you're right so it
looks like we aren't actually recycling
that memory properly
I agree with you so in here when we do
get world chunk internal that we're
getting back a you know most the time a
chunk that already exists perhaps but
sometimes if we've deleted that chunk
then there is no chunk there so then we
will find that we need to allocate one
and in that case when we do the
allocation we should be checking the
free list first right we should be doing
something more like you know if let's
take a look here so if results equals
world first fruit chunk and so you know
always take it off of the free list
basically and what we can do it just say
okay if there isn't one on the free list
then we'll push a new one on so then
we'll do the allocation in that in that
case if there is one on the free list
right so after we get it we can just say
that it's equal to the next one on the
free list so let's see next I'm assuming
we use next in hash for chaining but I
could make that a little more explicit
so we could do yeah it does use next
exit hash right so here's what we're
doing we're just saying okay we come
through here if there isn't anything on
the free list then we'll add one to the
free list right and in this case we do
want to do one clearing operation which
is that the first free chunks next in
hashed pointer should be zero so that it
knows that it's only getting one off
then when we actually go to allocate one
here we say okay get the first free
chunk advance the next pointer set it
all up and off we go so I think that
will will properly recycle the free
chunks now
thank you for finding that one
update coder what makes a bad programmer
in your opinion a bad programmer is the
programmer who doesn't get code done
that can be used right you know that
doesn't doesn't write code that can be
shipped you know or tour takes way too
long to write it and there's a lot of
subtlety that goes into it but that's
you know the basic idea
about your build up FL why do you
disable exceptions and warnings
exceptions because we don't use them and
the warnings are we disable ones that I
don't like like they just bother me and
i don't like them looks like
Mabel Oh a related thing mentioned in a
Creative Writing course I did was to
postpone perfection yes I that is a good
that is a good way to think of it my
blow I do think postpone perfection is a
nice a nice way to say don't spend too
much time trying to think of how to do
something perfect just get something and
learn from that and then you know kind
of build on it and try again if you need
to all right i am going to i think are
we in the Q&amp;A right now I think we don't
have any more cues
I wrong about that
I don't know if I'm wrong about that or
not
so it looks like there are no Q Colin's
left so i guess i will wind it down okay
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it has
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on handmade hero org it comes
the source code so you can do your own
experiments and play around with it we
also have a forum site you go to if you
want to ask questions a patreon page you
can use to support the video series
scheduled about that tells you when
we're going to be live and an episode
guide that has all of the old episodes
on it if you're trying to catch up
that's about it for today I'll be back
here tomorrow same time same place until
then have fun programming and I will see
you guys on the internet take it easy
everyone