hello everyone and welcome to handmade
heroes chair we code a complete game
live on stream we are kind of at a point
where we've got a lot of different
things we can't be working on right now
that's a good thing and I think today I
could bounce over to start cleaning up
the lighting or the camera system camera
systems big on my list so I feel like
there's some stuff we want to do there
what I may do is leave that till next
weekend and maybe spend all weekend do
and clean up on that whole like region
base stuff because right now at Mac I'll
show you what I'm talking about I just
you understand what what I'm thinking
about here if you remember when I said
we were kind of gonna go over to the
world gem stuff because I wanted to
start making things I could actually
look at so you can see kind of here we
don't have a stable understanding in the
camera system or anywhere really it we
just don't have it worked out right now
to properly get what are we looking at
what needs to be lit and so on so for
example right here is the camera view we
need something that's going to compute
the area that you're looking at so the
lighting bounds can be correct you see
the lighting bounds are here if that's
too small right the letting bounce
should be outside the screen boundary
and then when you move from room to room
you can see that sometimes the camera
works okay in terms of picking up the
room
but it right now doesn't really have any
ability to look at the size of the room
and focus on the size of the room and
stuff like that so we need some of those
camera routines now because like for
example I hop into this room and it's
just almost getting it right I happen to
this room and now it's totally not
getting it right like it's like the the
lighting is not the right size I can't
see really what's on the other side of
things and so on so it just needs it
just needs us to go in and really kind
of finish up that code into something
usable right and so all of that stuff is
stuff that we want to do and you know
that's all well and good but we need to
we before plugging back to that and
getting started on cleaning that up what
I'd like to do is just do a little bit
more of the generation code because we
just kind of got it the basic stuff
working and I'd like to play around a
little more and also get us to a point
where we can clearly see the limitations
of the system so we know when we come
back to it to start doing the final pass
on generation where we're actually can
generate stuff that we're gonna let me
plan to use permanently where we kind of
know what stuff needs to happen so what
I'd like to do here is I'd like to do
two things one is I'd like to get this
stuff working better so you can kind of
see here we end up with a far clip
playing that you know if I turn on the
debug camera or I can just move around
the far clip playing pretty much Thor
it's us right and there's not much we
can really do there so the far clip
playing it would be nice one thing we
probably should do is have an infinite
for our clip playing projection mode for
example so that's one thing we should do
but short of that I also think we need a
way to view this map a little bit more
sanely as well so some kind of a map
view we can use that shows us if if not
for in game then at least just for
debugging so we can see because one of
the problems that we're gonna have
really soon here even that we sort of
have right now is when we run the
generator we have no idea what we
generated so as soon as we get something
bigger than this little tiny patch here
like we would normally be viewing in the
actual game we can't see what we made
all right
so what I think I wanna do today is do
two things one I want to go ahead and
add some light additional generation
instructions to the generator to try and
have it build out an actual world that's
just placeholder but that's out there
that we can up around and it's got you
know some dungeons or whatever in it
just as a basic sketch of like okay
here's sort of an idea of what's what's
going on out there I'd like to do that
and then I'd also like to make a thing
that let me see what I generated because
what we're gonna find at that point
even just like I said right now is I
can't see anything right this debug
camera was was just here to allow us to
double-check our 3d code and this is
really all it's made for we need to
expand that concept so we need something
that can that can actually let us view
more of the world and in a more
convenient way that's pretty important
so we got to get that something in there
for that can be a hack it's just a debug
camera it doesn't have to be anything
good but we need it to be functional so
that's the the main thing that I'm gonna
be working on today is just getting rid
of a place where okay the world
generation code can now serve as a real
placeholder for something that is you
know it's actually kind of running the
way that we might expect building
something out and we never gonna come
back to it and add a lot of features and
goodness to it but we just now we at
least have something that's like okay
here's a world and then we can bounce
back and get like the lighting camera
stuff working out so that we can hop
around that world in a satisfying way
and see what we're supposed to see and
and it'll look clean right so if I hop
over to the world gencode you put it in
the one that doesn't have my head over
it if I have over to the world gencode
remember what I started saying yesterday
we've got this Nisshin of create
orphanage and this is exactly how I want
my code to look right there is a
function you can call anytime you want
to make an orphanage and it makes the
orphanage right now this is really
important because this gives us a
functional building block we can use to
create pieces of the world anytime we
want an orphanage now there's only gonna
be one in this particular game but
anytime we wanted one we could just call
this to make another one right that is
exactly how we want to go forward with
all the things that will be in the world
right and it'll become much more
important for all of those things that
we'd be able to call them as functions
anytime we want to produce new pieces of
the world that tie up with existing
pieces all right sue maybe I want to
make something that's like a dungeon
call and
don't ask me why % : there I want to be
able to create that to to make a
free-standing dungeon and connect that
dungeon up to some other part of the
world and again you'll note how I did
this I did this very specifically this
way because I kind of in my head had a
notion of how I want to work a priority
these functional elements that create a
standing structure they are sort of
functional right and they're not
functional of functional programming
sense but they are functional in a sense
that they don't really have side effects
beyond their little element they create
so they create a little interconnected
system and then they just return back to
you the notional connection points on
that system for you to connect up and
that's the really crucial part so that's
what's gonna allow me to create lots of
pieces out of generative components and
have an overarching game structure sense
that put those into in regional places
and randomizes their layout and does
stuff like that so it basically allows
us to approach a problem on a sort of a
multi scale way so we can say here is
the overall structure of the world
there should be dungeon here some forest
here or lice world here blah blah blah
right we connect those up that's one
piece of code that sits at the high
level and then inside each of those are
the functions that creating each of
those things so here's what creates a
cemetery here's what creates the forest
area here's which creates a dungeon
right and then each of those can have
things inside them as well here's what
creates you know this little torture
chamber here here's what what creates
this you know dragon lair or whatever
right and so building it out of those
multi-resolution pieces allows us to mix
and match these things very freely and
the thing that ties it all together is
this idea that it is somewhat functional
when you call this thing it just
produces the information that it needs
to encapsulate what it made into like a
little bundle and then you can take that
and throw it in to some other
it's some other part of the of the world
and this the layout system is what's
responsible for then harmonizing all
that at the end right and that was a
really crucial part that I wanted to get
in there so that way all the pieces can
be functional in that way and then at
the end the procedural part the part
that has to have knowledge across
everything he's a one uniform system
that we can then continue to improve to
create better and better layouts out of
the information that we're given but I
really wanted that sort of a feel to it
because I think that's what I'll allow
us to make nice convenient generative
code that still ends up producing good
high quality stuff one of the things
that you risk when you create a
generative world is if you are not very
good at structuring the code and making
smart generative code then it feels like
a generative game right it feels like a
game that did not have thought put into
it and that's not fun
so the most important thing to remember
when you're going through all of this is
you need to have the code be very
flexible and able to express the kinds
of things that a game designer might
want to express because if those things
cannot be expressed in your game just
feels random right and there's a big
difference between a game that feels
random and a game that feels randomly
generated right like random is not good
right just pure random is not good it
feels sloppy and unthought through
randomly generated a good high-quality
game could be randomly generated but it
shouldn't feel random right it should
feel like thought was put into it and
our job when we're inner is to encode
that thought and the system needs the
ability to incorporate those thoughts
right and that's what we're we're trying
to accomplish here um so let's suppose
that we have something here that's gonna
do create dungeon and something else
here that's gonna do you know create
forest right
now I don't really know much about how I
want to do this so I'm just going to go
ahead and start creating some things
here and what we'll see I think really
quickly is we'll see the limitations of
the current layout system and that's
exactly what I want so you know we only
just barely spent a few hours on this
generation system so it's not going to
be what we need we're going to need to
make a lot of upgrades to it but what
we're gonna see here as I sort of start
working on this stuff is we'll hopefully
start to see those issues coming into
play so we can have a better idea we
come back to it what sorts of stuff we
want to do right how we want to kind of
work with that so let's go ahead and do
something that creates a dungeon so for
creating a dungeon I'm just gonna go
ahead and make something that it takes
sort of a fairly standard look to a
dungeon I'm thinking like a dungeon
should be like an easily understandable
sort of room based thing where we just
kind of have a few maybe six or seven
rooms or something and then a passage
down to the next floor so it's basically
like you know one floor say roll down
new floor stairwell down new floor I I
think probably this is the kind of game
that wants to not let you go up and down
between floors so we don't really have
exactly what we need for that just yet I
don't have the concept of a like thing
you can go down but you can't go back up
right now so at some point we'll add
something like that but I think I would
like the dungeons to be more like
Binding of Isaac and less like Zelda in
that sense that like dungeons are things
you work your way down you don't go back
up so when you commit to a dungeon you
must finish the dungeon in order to come
back out I think that's more or less
what I'm looking for there for now I'm
just gonna put in stairwells or or maybe
we can't go down the dungeons yet
because I'll just put a square that it's
like hey look this is supposed to let
you go down you can't go down right now
what we know what it was supposed to be
so what I'm gonna do here is say alright
let's go ahead and create some
interconnected rooms and just make some
basic sort of assumptions about those so
we're gonna do things the same way we
did before and for our gem dungeon we
know because dungeon is kind of a simple
concept actually we more or less know
what it is that's gonna happen here
there's an entrance room and that
entrance room is going to be sort of the
piece that's up above that there's the
one you know sort of place that you
would go down into or walk into and I
don't know exactly how we want that to
be placed it's kind of a difficult thing
to say because I don't really know how
we want that to appear to the player but
I'm assuming that we want it to be
something where probably there's an
entrance to a dungeon that's part of the
other thing in the world so it's
probably the first the entrance room is
probably the first room on the floor
that is all underground I'm guessing
right so we probably have an entrance
room and that's probably all we have for
a dungeon at least at the moment because
like I said you'll fight your way down
the dungeon and then you'll probably
just teleport back out right and that'll
probably be it so there would be
something here eventually you know
probably something like that where
there'd be a room that you can then get
out from but that's it and so when we
create one of these things we're then
gonna make all of our rooms and then
we're going to and you know for now I'll
just say alright there's a dungeon spec
and everything we'll get that for now
and I'm just gonna make rooms that are
connected to each other and this is
gonna be a floor based thing right so
probably what's gonna happen when we
create here we're gonna pass for
hemorrhage these routines create
orphanage we'll even have some we'll see
in a second I'll probably do a little
bit that today potentially but create
dungeon is going to be something that's
going to at the very least
take how many floors we want in that in
the dungeon so we're gonna have a floor
account here not a flower count we're
gonna have a floor account here and the
floor accounts gonna say here's how many
levels the dungeon should have and we're
going to start at the top and work our
way down right as a as a good dungeon
should so we start at floor index zero
we're less than floor count and we just
kind of proceed from there so each time
when we generate a room I at the start
of our dungeon we need to be connected
to the floor above it right it needs to
be connected okay so here we're gonna
have or I don't what would call this
room above maybe so when we first start
out we're gonna take floor entrance room
and we're gonna generate a room and this
is going to be the floor entrance room
and this room is going to either right
depending on whether there is a room
above it's either going to connect to
the room above it using a downward
connection or in the case where this was
the first room it will become the result
entrance room so if there is a room
above it then we need to connect these
two rooms right so we say all right
we've got a floor entrance room the
floor entrance room is going to connect
remember we've got did I not load my
project there we go so if we go here and
we look at what direction we go you know
here are directions we know that the
floor entrance room if you go down from
there you should get up sorry if you go
down from the the room above this one
you should get to the floor entrance
room so just gonna connect those two up
and then what I want to do is I want to
say well in the case where there was no
room above it then rather than make a
connection we know that the person is
good to the connecting is the person out
outside of this routine so when we
return the dungeon
sort of construction back to
and say look here's the dungeons built
we don't know where it goes
that person will take this floor
entrance route which is the first floor
entrance room on the top floor of the
dungeon they'll connect it up right so
if we take this floor entrance room and
we assign it to the thing we were going
to return here so remember this right so
now we pass that back and it can get
connected up outside as we put dungeons
around the world in various places
they'll can sort of connect up right in
that way so then what we want to do is
say all right now we've got these
dungeons connected up what we want to do
is start to create more than just one
floor because this would just create a
stack of rooms that kind of just connect
that's the minimal possible dungeon
right and could be a dungeon that we
might want for some unknown reason like
a sort of a gauntlet thing where you
maybe you fight harder enemies on each
floor as you go down or something so
it's not necessarily bad but most the
time we probably want to done just to
have a little bit more to them than that
so once we create the floor entrance
room we also want to create some other
rooms connected to them you know
whatever right we don't really know what
that is but we want to do something like
that so from there what we're gonna do
is say okay let's go ahead and create
some other sort of branching factor
rooms or whatever here so you know maybe
there's a thing where we generate some
things that this thing has and maybe I
guess the part that I'm not sure about
is how we would necessarily want to go
about figuring out what exists in each
one of these floors because you know if
you follow the standard model you've got
different things that could appear on
any floor but not all of them do a
parent a floor and then oftentimes there
are things that maybe always appear on
the floor so if you took the example of
binding of issac for example you know
that there's almost always a store
there's always an item room there's
always a one of those whatever you call
it the the
with the little Fang doors the sacrifice
room you know so there's a lot of
different things that you can expect to
see on any given floor so I'm gonna go
ahead and say but but I should finish
that thought but there's also things
that don't necessarily occur on every
floor right so there's things like
certain room types only occur on some
floors not others there's other things
that only occurs when you get certain
distance down you know all sorts tough
like that so what I would like to do is
I would like to try to mirror that kind
of a like structure as we go to do the
generation now what I should mention
before we get into that is here we've
got sort of this result our loop is X up
quite nicely in that this room above
that gets set as we go because I get me
knowing I should actually put that here
so on the exit we get that when we are
falling out of the loop after create all
the floors the exit room is gonna be
something that we could either just have
be that final entrance room if we know
that's one of that works or we would
want to set up another room that's
carried over here like for example well
actually know that that is always what
we want because whatever the room is
that you would go to to exit now think
about it it's not this one it's some
other thing here it's the it's the exit
room for this floor right because you
don't go down to the next floor from the
entrance room it's from whatever the
like boss room is on that that floor or
whatever right so yeah so this loop
flows kind of nicely each time we create
an entrance room we create a bunch of
rooms in it in a second here and one of
them is like the final room you go to
and then off you go right so what I
would like to do is is figure out kind
of how we want to place this I don't
really know the best way to do this
because I haven't really thought much
about this kind of code
certainly at the head end so at the part
where we start thinking about the floor
I think we want to do some analysis and
we want to we would want to put some
code here that creates sort of the
boolean x' for the system right whether
this will have a store whether this will
have of this whether the slab of that
right uh so what I sort of expect we
would want to have is probably something
like all right maybe there's some kind
of a thing that says like we're gonna
build a little batch of rooms
where maybe I just like say here's their
rooms that are gonna have to be in the
dungeon and then later as I'm kind of
spidering out to make a dungeon I'm
gonna place them somewhere yeah I don't
know you know is that logical you know I
don't know one of the problems is
dungeon floors tend not to be so big you
know a typical dungeon floor is what
twelve rooms maybe something like that
there's just not a lot of rooms in a
dungeon floor so some kind of typing
that out I'm like well it might have to
be more specific than that right it
might have to be more careful about how
it's thinking things through
so generating a list of things to place
may not be so useful after all just
because of the low number of rooms you
know it's not it doesn't produce a big
sprawling thing with you know 100 rooms
it's supposed to be like fairly
understandable and self-contained so I
guess maybe that's not the faintest
thing to do
so maybe I'll do something a little bit
different maybe I'll say that as we
design this game there's probably gonna
be some idea of how dungeons should be
laid out that we sort of get to but
generally speaking you're trying to work
your way from the entrance to the exit
right so let's make a path from the
entrance to the exit first and go from
there maybe we say something and we've
got a in our generator we've got a
random number generator yeah
do we horrors we don't have fun oh we do
the world has one actually I remember
this we said that random numbers come
from the world they're right here all
right
so this right here it would be nice to
be able to get random numbers a little
easier so I think I would probably
introduce an easy way to pick random
numbers as we go that just come off the
world generator and it'll grab it out of
here as necessary but yeah that's that's
sort of a separate a separate issue well
what I could do to is say look this
points to the this world generator
points to the the world that it gets so
when you create the generator in here
you just set the pointer like that and
so for now I can say some you know
things like this uh so let's let me go
over to our random code right here and
this is what I'll do for now I'll say
that maybe the path gets a little longer
each time so maybe the floor index
divided by two or something so you know
let's say a dungeon had eight levels to
it so the first two floors would have a
certain number the next two floors would
have one more room the next two floors I
have one more room on the path between
the entrance and the exit something like
that right and so what I would say is I
you know the randomization would be
floor index over two so something from
the minimum I don't know what the
minimum be maybe the minimum number of
rooms along the path is like four or
something like that and the maximum
number of rooms along the path is going
to be six at the start and then those
will just go up as you go and maybe I
could do this a little bit differently
so maybe like the maximum number of
rooms could get really egregious
eventually like maybe you just get
really unlucky and you pull a really bad
random and and then you you end up with
some super huge dependency change you
kind of go through I don't know
robee lakes aren't known for being kind
to the player
right but anyway I'm not a game designer
so I'm not responsible for this kind of
stuff that's someone else's fault if
it's wrong don't blame me this is not my
job
anyway some stuff will come in here that
allows us to do a and we will actually
although I say you know I'm not soft
stuff we will do better code for doing
game design based picking than this for
sure I just am NOT promising all ever to
knit correctly because I that's a game
designers job right the game designer is
the one who to tunes and picks those
things
not the engine programmer so that's not
my responsibility but it will be my
responsibility to produce better tools
than this because in the future you can
imagine us wanting to say some very sort
of things such as ok sometimes there can
be a really hard floor but maybe there
should only be one of those per dungeon
right so we want some nice tools some
some code tools we can use to say stuff
like that and not have it be strictly
left to random and again that's why I
say you want games to feel randomly
generated not random random feels crappy
so throwing in random numbers like this
this is not good look we will not be
leaving this in the final version of the
game you want something that takes a
more thoughtful approach to it and we'll
see how to build those as we go that's
not the focus right now but I feel it's
important to mention so I'm just
throwing in some stuff at the moment but
that will not be how it is left as we go
right so this will pick some number of
rooms for the path along the way and
what those will do is they'll just say
ok for each one of these things actually
we know what the preview is is the floor
entrance room right
that's fine too so what we want to do
here is we want to say from this
particular room we want to create a new
room we want to like create another room
that goes somewhere from the existing
room that we picked so we start off at
the floor entrance room and we want to
go somewhere from there so we know that
we can't go down because down has a
special meaning in the dungeon and we
know that we can't go up because up
would also have a special meaning in the
dungeon so what we want to do is pick
from the these four options here right
so what we want to do is pick our
connection direction from one of these
four options and we want to connect we
want to pick from the four options that
do not include the option that we picked
last time right so we want to knock that
one out of the running when we when we
pick now we're going to run into
something here that I think is is going
to be kind of interesting so when we are
placing these rooms we want to be able
to place these rooms probably in a
similar fashion to how we were placing
them before right in that we want to be
able to test to see if there's a room in
this particular area and we want to like
not place the room if that's the case so
what I want to do here is say well
rather than create some special case
code to just help me lay out the dungeon
I'd rather just lean on the code we know
we will be raided writing to handle room
intersection and overlap to do the work
for me
right so what I'd rather do is set the
generation index stuff up now to allow
me to do sub generation placement that
then gets overwritten right now what do
I mean by this well it's important to
remember that when you place rooms down
there under no obligation to stay there
so what we can do is create the dungeon
and place rooms in two particular
locations and then we can see whether or
not we would have hit the any existing
room using the same stuff we were
currently using to check right so we can
actually do stuff here that would would
essentially allow us to do checking on
that layout in the middle of doing sort
of a sub basically a sub layout so that
we know we if we curl around and hit
ourselves we wouldn't put more rooms
there or whatever else right
so I'm having a thought as I say that
hmm so here's what I'm thinking
it occurs to me that that almost wants
to be the kind of thing that is sort of
encoded into the layout itself because
you might want that to be able to run in
the face of other things that get
connected up to here I wonder if there's
a possibility for basically encoding the
fact that a connection is just something
that has to be connected to a family of
rooms
you
that's actually very interesting so so
it does seem like this is the kind of
thing where maybe we can just let the
layout code do this later
I'm gonna go with that so I'm just gonna
say look all we know is there's a cereal
chain here and we know oh wait we
already have this that it's flat so it
can't go up or down and I'm just gonna
say look that's gonna be the generators
job so we know there's a cereal chain
from the entrance to the exit and this
is what it is
right
generation code is gonna have to deal
with it from there on out
okay so we'll upgrade the generator code
to deal with that I think that's just
that's where that should go so that's
what we have to do from there we also
know that the cereal chain will have
rooms hanging off of it occasionally
there are rooms that we want to have in
the dungeon right and
those connections are a little harder to
understand at some level but I think I
want to just push through with it and
see how we go so what I'm going to say
here is
I'm gonna keep track of these and I'm
gonna find out how many of these we've
got right and I'm gonna say that
I'm going to say that however many of
these we end up picking for the path
count I've got my temporary memory
somewhere here yeah so I'm just going to
go ahead and say look actually remember
how this works but let's say it works
like that I'm gonna say we're gonna keep
an array of every room that is in the
path so we start out every time you make
one of these
we record which one it is
and the exit room and the entrance room
are probably special I don't know if we
want to put this into the path probably
not so I would say maybe the exit room
is special as well so maybe floor exit
room is its own Jenna as well so when we
create one of these paths it'll sort of
push a temporary on there that says have
what all the paths are and then at the
end we'll get one of these guys the
connects to the floor exit room there
and then the you know on when we
actually exit we'll keep that one for
the for the final room that all seems
pretty reasonable to me and then when I
have this array here that has all of the
rooms in it what I can do at the end is
then now I can just sort of randomly
place where the other things are going
to be right so I can say all right I
don't know what other things are going
to be in this but let's say we've got a
couple other things
since I don't really care to go down the
rathole of thinking about all the things
that might be in a dungeon right now
that will suffice so what I want to do
is say let's randomly put those off of
something in the chain right so what I'd
like to do is say okay pick a random
number so we'll just say connect one of
the rooms in the path with the shop room
same with the item room now there's a
problem with this style of writing the
code as you can see almost immediately
right and the problem is that if you
wanted to have more than two you would
quickly get to a place where if you
randomly picked the same room every time
to connect them to you'd run out of
walls to connect them too right so what
we want to do here is we want to make
this we probably want to make a utility
for doing exactly this that every time
we connect a room to something it will
remove that room as a choice for future
connections here what I mean
but otherwise and for right now since we
only have two of them there it's fine
now it could still fail in a snake
configuration possibly well not probably
not but it might
it could right so this may still cause
us some problems at the moment depending
on how the dungeon ends up being laid
out but yeah so if we take a look at
this now we've kind of got a sketch of
it this is basically the generation code
for a dungeon right I mean there's not a
lot more to it than that this would
basically produce a typical binding of
issac level the only thing it doesn't do
is allow the dungeon to connect back up
to itself which we might want to do for
the moment I don't really want to do
that because we're gonna want to do more
stuff with dungeons later on and so on
but still so what I'd like to do here
what's this complaining about how is
this ambiguous
ah because they're you thirty twos
all right I assume moving on I gotta
actually put this in the temp memory
this path count come first guess it does
and for the forest code
we're just probably going to have four
exits one for each of the directions and
I think this should probably line up
with these right here right so we
probably want to just have four four X's
of correspond to west east north and
south okay so that's it
and now if I actually wanted to generate
one of these one of the nice things is
we can just not call the orphanage
generator and call only the dungeon
generator temporarily so that it won't
make an orphanage so we don't have to
like hop out of the orphanage to find
the dungeon or something like that right
we can just make a dungeon and place the
character right in the dungeon now one
thing I haven't done yet is I want to
create size of these rooms one of the
things that I did earlier on is there
was a thing I placed in here
that's the required dimensions right I'd
like to first move that into the room
spec because that's really where that
probably belongs right room
specifications should probably be the
thing that says what the dimensions of
the room have to be or can be so I think
I want to do this and then everywhere
that was doing required dimensions
should really be something that's called
on a room spec
that's my story and I'm sticking to it
so when we go to grab one of these
things I'm gonna do Jen room spec spec
equals room spec and then everything
that was room required dim is now gonna
be room spec right
oops no it's not
sorry what I meant to say was anything
that was room require dim is going to be
spec required dim can't see that
don't want to touch those right yet and
here we go for this
so in here what I want to do is for
these and you can see why I want to do
this because that's really what we're
saying
so the bedroom spec is the thing that
determines the size of all of the
bedrooms right and we want those to be
specified uniformly same thing with the
hero save slot probably so actually
these these bedrooms here should not be
bedroom specs they should be save slots
they're a little bit different so this
is just going to say looks up the
bedroom specs size let's see here here a
save slot that's the save slots back
this is the garden spec
a sick law respect
[Music]
this is the hallway spec I guess and the
hallway spec is a little bit different
because you know we're kind of an
in-between point here and normally when
we specify the hallway we wouldn't say
what direction the hallway goes it would
allow the system to probably place the
hallway in either in either orientation
right now we will have to create two
because our system doesn't really handle
that so that's a vertical and horizontal
if you will and so like the front hall
is a vertical hallway and the back hall
is a horizontal hallway if that makes
sense
but eventually I don't think we'll
differentiate we'll just have hallways
and the spec will specify that it can do
that rotation as necessary so here's a
kitchen spec taylor spec main room spec
we go so then here we can just sort of
make this code behave like this although
you know eventually I think we probably
want to make this a little bit more we
want to clean that code up as well at
some point here because this is gonna
have to be a little bit more thoughtful
so if I run this what I should get is
the exact same orphanage and I do write
anyway so the point now is when we're up
in the dungeon code you know the
dungeons are supposed to have a bunch of
rooms that are sized uniformly so we
should only really have to set the size
once here and say the dungeon the
dungeons all use this same one here so
they're all gonna say look the dimension
is always whatever the standard Zelda
size room is or whatever it is I don't
know if that's 17 by 9 something like
that so where it's always gonna look
like this like that's just what a
dungeon looks like and that's the end of
the story right
so if I go ahead and compile that now we
should this should now be functional
because everyone uses unjust facts so
all of these should be reasonable and if
we ask you to create a dungeon we're
almost on our way but we are now getting
into the part of the generation where we
got to upgrade the system a little
because we don't handle arbitrary
connections yet right so when you have a
set of connections that are specified
like that right now we don't handle
selecting one from a set yeah that's not
something that we actually allow so
let's go ahead and start that though so
if I made an if 0 here
and I'm gonna have to do basically both
of these right well I can still create
the orphanage so this will create that
dungeon this will lay out the dungeon
but I probably want to do here is to
have a thing that's like so this would
normally be that right but we're not
gonna do that we're gonna do this
instead temporarily in fact we could
just do it like this where we overwrite
it and then here you know again we've
got sort of this situation going that
would create the dungeon and place us in
the starting room of the dungeon
everyone knows dungeons have seven
floors so there you go
and now if we run this we will probably
get something very bad and the reason is
because we don't have and you can see we
asserted here that we can't place this
because we don't know what to do
remember all our code does now is it
assumes that the direction that you want
to go from a room can only have one
members right so it can only have one
bit set east north south west whatever
right but what you can't do is say any
of the above so the simplest
modification to this that we could make
right is something that tries to place
rooms along the edge in the case where
it just if it has
large set of possibilities it will just
go ahead and pick randomly from them
until it can succeed so if I go to a
place rooms along edge where is placed
rivers along and shears fixtures along
edge so if you take a look at place
rooms along edge it's just gonna place
these rooms and what we could do is we
can look at this generation index here
as being something that maybe should
only be set speculatively right so what
we can do is we could say all right if
we find that the rooms that were placing
can't all be placed we will back up and
undo those placements as necessary right
so we so now we can start to make
something that might actually work
so we can do something like that but
let's just think through how this is
going to work so normally what happens
we come through here we say okay we
found a room and this room needs to be
placed and the room that its antecedent
room has been placed right now when we
get this direction here what we need
expand is to is supporting more than one
direction and to do something about that
so if we were to randomly if we were to
randomly try places up for the room we
could do this with a single room pretty
easily and not even have to back up if
we never got into a failure State so let
me just articulate a little bit how that
would go so first of all in fact you
know what let me actually back up one
step further because I just realized we
have a more powerful routine now than we
had before and we can simplify so let's
suppose that we nerf the dungeon bit for
a second here
so here's the orphanage
now remember we're placing rooms using
this place rooms long edge we don't have
to do that anymore why because we have
testing so instead of place rooms along
edge this can actually be just called
place room along edge and it can say
which room it wants to place right this
can go away now and we can just pass the
connection in right so we can say place
room along edge and say Jen connection
connection and then in here when we go
when we continue down through here this
is not really a dura mask it's actually
just a direction we could pass this
directly if we want to and that would do
it right so if I replace the call to
this place rooms place rooms along edge
with place room along edge right then
what we can do is say oh well the other
room here and this connection that we're
on that's what we're trying to that's
what we're trying to place okay we know
the direction in the generation index
still here
this I believe will now lay out the
orphanage the same way so we don't need
to place rooms along an edge one after
the other because now we just test to
see where they can fit in so we can just
call it per room so once we can call it
per room that also means now when we get
this direction we can try multiple times
right if we aren't able to place this
room so if this call fails to be able to
place the room the room does not get
placed right so when we come through
here rather than asserting this place we
can just say if placed like so
what we can then do is move placed out
as a more primary element here and like
so and then just return that now we
could check the generation index and
know this actually but also it's pretty
convenient to just have it be returned
so then when we can do is say well let's
keep trying all of the directions that
we could potentially go and as we try
those directions we can also probably
just say we don't need to test this
anymore because presumably the outside
code did test that so that might be more
of an assertion really now if that makes
sense so I think we probably want to do
something more like this
right because if somebody called us to
place a room that's already been placed
that's probably a bug in the outside
code and we'd rather know about it
sooner than later because somebody's got
to fix something right so now what I
want to do say all right
well if this place room along edge call
is gonna be a thing that that takes this
connection in and assigns it what I
should be able to do is now say all
right let's move this surface index here
let's move that up right and so to show
you what I mean by that
where's our mask used it's is it only
there yes so what I want to do here is
is elevate that up one so what I want do
is say give me the surface mask right or
yeah give me the surface mask for this
surface index like so so there's no dur
mask anymore like this and then move
this up as the thing that gets passed in
right so now on the outside here what I
want to do is say oops that's the wrong
loop so now what I want to do here is
say okay when we're gonna place this
room into the system here when we
actually take this direction that we do
get dirt mass from room I can also say
get box box surface index direction and
make this adder mask and you can see how
we're collapsing this code further up
into this into the calling code in
preparation for looping over it so now
again run exact same code path but we've
elevated that choice of the direction up
to the calling code which means that now
we are no longer obligated to do it this
way right so now what we could do is try
if the dur mask supports multiple things
we can randomly pull those
out of the we can randomly pick ones to
try from there as we fail so we can try
if adder mask has multiple things set in
it then what we can do is randomly try
things in the der mask as we go right so
what I'm going to do here is I'm gonna
introduce a call that allows me to pick
a random direction from the direction
mask and so we're gonna we're going to
first pull out the direction mask then
I'm going to loop on trying to place
this room we're gonna leave the
assertion in place because right now if
we can't place the room we don't have an
alternate strategy in the future we will
have to have alternate strategies
rip-rip up and replace strategies to
help place rooms when we backed
ourselves into corner
what what do I mean by backed ourselves
into a corner well let's suppose I just
said that I've got a certain number of
rooms connected to each other and I
don't say how they're connected so I've
got eight rooms and they're just
connected in a line right perfectly
valid thing to say so the random
generator starts and it just happens to
pick this right I said eight
well if now this room happened to have
some other room that needs to get placed
as well it can't go anywhere right all
of its places are their stuff there so
what would need to happen here is either
it would need to know that it can move
this over here or something if there's
like information that allows if if it's
not essential that this be connected
here if it has other options for a
connection then that's fine but short of
that what it would have to do is back up
and try a different strategy
so try placing this room first let's say
and then hey this would just work
because it wouldn't pick there to put
that thing so we will have to introduce
other strategies for placement and so
we're going to have more than just what
you see at the moment but at the moment
we're not doing anything fancy so this
assertion should stand because it's not
gonna there's no recovery right so the
assertion lets us know we've outstripped
the capabilities of our current very
limited placement routines so once we
get adder mask what I'd like to do now
is I'd like to loop through I and I'd
like to I'd like to have a way of
picking a random direction for the dur
mask so I'd like to do something like
this
so if I pass a germ a skin and I pass in
a random series so you like the random
generator right and I see look give me a
random Direction out I'm gonna try that
direction and then when I'm done I'm
gonna see whether or not I could
actually go that direction right so when
this thing comes out I'm gonna say
alright if I could place the room along
that thing then I'm done
otherwise I'm I'm not right otherwise I
keep going and in that case I suppose we
can also say what we do we want to do
get surface mask from the index right I
believe that is this thing right here
this surface mask I want to take the
direction and I want to knock out that
direction from it so oops sorry
so I want to take whatever direction I
tried and I don't want to ever try it
again
so as I'm picking random directions I'm
gonna pick that many so what I want to
do here is I want to yeah I just want to
do this this attempts so we've got two
things we might do so if we can place
them along the edge the other one is if
this direction comes back invalid right
or if there's nothing to do so the way
that would work is saying look hey only
try this while there's something in the
der mask to try once we've tried all the
directions we're done and we've
obviously failed so at that point it's
time to raise the assertion and say I
can't figure out where to place this
room and that's you know a problem for a
later day for for a better generator
right to solve not a bear generate a
better layout code specifically so all
we need I think to get this working
properly is that one piece of code this
right here that I'm sitting on that will
take a mask of directions and produce a
random direction there from right and so
I'm gonna do this in a really dumb way
right just a real stupid way and we can
think about this is where those things
where it might be fun to do the bit
twiddle even of it eventually so this is
gonna be a piece of code that honestly
we do not have to optimize I don't think
it will ever be called enough to really
make any difference to anybody but I'm
gonna do it a stupid super stupid way
and I bet just because when you
typically have something like a mass
like this when you have a bit tweedily
kind of situation there's probably a
clever way if we sit down to think about
it there's probably a clever way to do
the thing that produces a random one of
those bits right so I'm gonna do the
stupid version but there's gonna be a
smart version probably and maybe someday
we'll want to find that I don't actually
know that that's true but I'm just just
hypothesizing so we know there are six
directions so all I'm going to do
is I'm just going to go through them and
I'm gonna do the laziest stupidest
possible thing so I'm going to say if
the directional mask that were given
that was awesome I don't know what it
was but it's awesome I am going to I'm
going to basically test each of them and
when I find whichever one ones are set
I'm going to add them to the array and
then I'm just gonna return that that's
it I am gonna say at least at the moment
that this routine is required to have at
least one valid direction when you pass
it because I don't know if I want to
since since box surface index doesn't
have a null value I don't want anyone
asking for one if they can't get a real
one back so I'm just gonna say you have
to test der masks on the way in since
that does have a null value which is
zero so that's your responsibility so
anyone Pat calls us the der mask of zero
there any an assertion right off the bat
that's just how that's going to help
roll for now we'll revisit that later if
I decide I don't like it anyway
I this will produce for us a random
Direction out of the directions and that
should be it I yeah forgot I actually
need to call that code
it's what's well okay but that was good
you know so okay we ran it and we still
are producing the correct orphan step
that's good that means that this code at
least doesn't have an obvious bug in it
so when you give it a set of explicit
directional connections that must be
followed it will follow them so that's
good we wanted to make we want that to
work right and so it is good that I
tested that I didn't mean the test that
I was planning to call the dungeon area
but we should have tested it to make
sure that it's actually that the obvious
case is working so now let's try the
dungeon version just to see to what
extent that will work and it looks like
oh well so that assertion
huh so that's suggesting this room was
called uh uh yes
so that's incorrect we do have a we do
have one thing we have to modify in that
code this code that places the room it
always sets the generation that ice it
should not do that
it should only set the generation index
in the case where the room actually gets
placed so that that is that is correct
if the room cannot be placed in fact I
could put it here if the room cannot be
placed yeah then that's that's erroneous
maybe what I should do is actually make
that be something that gets computed
after the fact that way they both depend
on the same thing so bases say like you
know the results here is based on
whether the room generation index ends
up being equal to our generation index
which means it gets placed maybe that's
a more appropriate way to signal that so
that way there's it's not set twice in
the code and you can't have that problem
right all right so I think based on what
I'm seeing here I think that's this is
good because this means we don't have we
have hit one of any bug yet so what we
need to do here for a place room along
edge we don't currently support up/down
now I guess I should I kind of want to
test the other code first so maybe what
I'll do is I won't put in the up/down
connections yet so when we do floor
count here
maybe I'll nerf the floor account
temporarily so there isn't an up/down
there so that there will be no up-down
connections created so instead of that
what we'll do here is say alright you
know floor account always equals one
just so I can see if the other codes
working into bug that and then what I'll
do is add the up/down code right so
here's our dungeon layout and you can
see it
amusingly created exactly the layout
that I was talking about it did the
whined around don't ask me why but it
did so now I can hop around
the dungeon this is presumably the store
here or the or the item room right and
then I can hop out of here
and and I can ya can just keep on going
through through our dungeon and off we
go right so that's all fine whatever
great so that code is now working at
least moderately well and then what I
want to do is so I'll put the floor code
back in and then what we should see is
when I run this we get the assertion
that you're trying to connect things in
a way that this routine doesn't support
right so I think the tricky thing about
this is I don't really know how I want
this stuff to work just semantically
even I most of the time in video games
that I see there is no such thing as two
downward connections from a single room
that connect to two separate rooms not
in a game like Zelda anyway
but I suppose once you get up to the
versions of Zelda that had long
scrolling rooms then that was true so
like linked to the Past for example you
could probably go down over here and you
walk a long way through a scrolling room
and then there'd be a down over here in
those connect two separate rooms so so
you know that's that's not that's fine
right that's not
yeah that yeah that's that's that's not
a problem so I guess I will I will
endeavor at least at the outset here
because I don't have a better idea I
will endeavor to just make it so that
there really isn't a big difference
between downward connections and upward
connections I guess
so what I might go ahead and do is just
say well you know if you want to create
a downward connection it'll try to do
the exact same thing it does for upward
connections in that you know it'll try
to place the rooms and if it can't place
the rooms it'll try to push them in a
particular direction I you know sliding
along the room or whatever I could
alternatively have two different
routines that are like where one is
special case first doing stacking just
because Z is different you know it's
it's different than the rules we think
of I just kind of feel like they're
different for downward connections and
upward connections than they are for you
know your your run-of-the-mill wall
based doors I mean certainly in the real
world they're just completely different
right
north-south east-west directional things
are doors they're you know they're
anywhere in the wall you open it up you
walk through it whatever that's very
normal I up down connections are very
special they usually require a stairwell
or a ladder they typically are you know
placed anywhere in the 2d plane so they
don't they don't have they don't
constrain to two edges at once you know
a door can't be anywhere on a wall a
door is always connected to the floor
right but opening to above you or below
you can occur anywhere in the plane so I
feel like fundamentally the the logic of
it is a bit different the the degrees of
there's two degrees of freedom and
placement of an up-down connection and
there's only one degree of freedom in
the placement
of a north-south east-west connection so
that's that's kind of suggesting to me
you know that that's that it's a
different thing so you know I may do
something like where we just say
something like this
yeah
so yeah just not really sure about this
I just I feel like I'm gonna need two
pieces of code for this I feel I mean
maybe I find when I get a little further
into it if they can collapse down in
some kind of clever way that involves
something where you just set one of the
access ranges to one thing but I don't
know I'm not gonna go that route at
first if they turns out that they
collapsed later then that's fine
but even looking at this code the door
code is gonna be a little bit different
it'll probably start out with an
intersection yes but then it'll probably
do it'll probably do something where it
collapses both axes down to an aperture
so I'm pretty sure that this just is
gonna be it's gonna be special sauce
right like
yeah so what I'm gonna do now is gonna
say like look if it's an is up/down
connection I'm not even gonna look for
stuff we're just gonna do one test and
it's just like that's it right that's
all we're gonna do so we're gonna say
that we create a test volume here the
test volume is I guess actually you know
what no I could just search the whole 2d
region so we'll search and we'll do like
a yeah well do like a we'll do like a
stampings based search I guess we'll
just we'll just do it
and now that I said after I said all of
that I'm starting to see like oh yeah
hey this probably for me this probably
will end up being something that you can
generalize by just squashing one of the
axes to zero
oops anyway so if it's an is up-down
connection then I'm going to search
along two sets of axes
I don't know what I want to call these
they're like relative X&amp;Y
so I sort of want to do a thing that's
like well real X is less than max real X
or something like that so in here you
know I do my search I got to produce my
test volume
yeah and I guess you know just looking
at it it looks like if you just wrote
one of these you could then just smush
one axis down to zero the outer axis and
then it would be the same so I guess I
take it back we probably can just make
one of these and it just forces on the
other AXI like on the north south east
west it just forces the search so that
there's only one of the other axis that
gets searched and I guess that just
works so I should probably take back
everything I said about wanting two of
these maybe I don't really want two of
these we'll see so anyway moving along
so let's suppose I take a look at these
here if I do is up down then I'm gonna
search a long you know rel x-axis I got
to find the min/max there and oops and I
have got to have my rail y-axis as well
and those are not the X and y-axis there
some other axes whatever they are right
in the case of an actual up/down
connection they are the X and y-axis but
if we generalize this code out then they
will actually be potentially X and Z or
Y &amp; Z depending on which direction that
we're going right so we're gonna search
along one of those at a time and then
search along the other one as well so
then what we can do is say like well
okay when we go to search along this we
start at mineral-y
we go to max rel y and we stop there
again this is not really as inclusive as
we want to be because these ranges right
we probably actually want to start in
the middle and then move to whichever
side looks like it's gonna work and
we'll see how that goes a little bit
later for now we're not going to do that
so anyway we'll just deal with that a
little bit later but this is mostly what
we want here then when we take a look at
how this is being laid out here we want
to do two of these so when we actually
go to create our test volume we want to
be able to set the rel x-axis
to be equal to whatever our rail X is so
as we look along it and then the rail x
axis the max wants to be whatever that
thing was right plus whatever the spec
requires of us along that axis now one
weird thing here yes so anyway so we can
amortize this set so we might as well so
we set the Y at the outset right and
then we set the X every time through and
then we also need some way of setting
whatever the other axis is and you could
see how that was being set here this is
to abut the edges properly on the axis
that's actually being like the one
you're actually going along right so
this is the this is the actual movement
axis not the edge sort of the
perpendicular if you will so the
perpendicular gets set like this
I don't think it ever changes right so
I'm pretty sure you can just set that
here and never care about it again right
so we've got basically the r LZ axis
right and the rel z axis and we need
that sort of which one which direction
we're going but I'm pretty sure this
just sort of works right
so we set up the relative z-axis and say
look that one has to a butt and I
believe this never depends on anything
else so it can actually be lofted all
the way out to the initial portion of
the loop because we know like it's just
it's gotta be a buddy
that's just where it is right so that's
just known you know period and then
these have to be tested right so once we
do test these we know rel Y can get
added to here and what we want to do is
is sort of take this code again and
bring this code up in and I guess I will
just nerf this loop and just use one
loop I'll do exactly what I said
we couldn't do as always when you start
writing the code it becomes very clear
that actually this the shared parts just
jump out at you so you know off we go
uh yeah so I think this this will just
work and we're gonna have to verify that
it actually does and tune all these
constants properly but I think we can
get this down to something fine so what
we need to now do is say well okay when
we do the placement here the placement
that we're talking about is is the real
x-axis placement when the real x axis
placement doesn't work then we need to
move the real x by the Delta that we get
back if we can place it then we're done
so we want to break out of here we need
this to be a while loop based on the
placement function here as well so we
really want to say while the room hasn't
been placed and and the relative Y is
still something we want to test then do
the rest of the loop right so once we
get in here and we look and we say okay
let's try to place the stream we replace
what we do the intersection we find out
along this is going to be the edge
access that we're testing right here
so the edge access in this case is going
to be real X right so that's the thing
that we're probing along I and that rel
x-axis when we when we set the door to
have that if that was actually yeah I
mean that that we then need to do that
for both cases so the y-axis that we're
testing along also has to be shrunk down
to its middle for wherever the
connection was and then the min door and
Max door part of things that's just the
rel z-axis
I believe
so I think that is sufficient that's
what I think that may prove to be very
wrong that's just what I think
sooo coming in here we're gonna have
real x-axis I believe it's the real
z-axis that needs to know whether it's
mint or nuts
[Music]
the ZX is the direction of the
connection so I and that's the one needs
to know whether it's MIT or not so I
think that's fine so r LZ axis oops
this is like the abutments
so the real x-axis real y-axis here so
the x-axis is the edge axis that's going
to be this and so the y-axis is is Z and
doesn't actually matter in the testing
right so the when we go to do this and
we do the min/max here we should only
get we should get like no actual testing
there and we can override some of this a
little bit like like what we could do
for example is make sure our min R L min
and Max r ly are set like up here so
that when rooms end up stacked higher
they won't put doors where you couldn't
get to them we'll have to look at that a
little bit later for right now this will
be fine so in this case it's the same
thing but but the directionality is
different right so that's all fine in
this case we now flip the two so it's
actually like that the y axis is now the
direction of the connection but
otherwise everything's fine and then
similarly here same exact thing that
this becomes a false so now what we can
do is actually just treat our
up-and-downs exactly the way that we
were treating everything else and we can
just actually use literally this exact
layout of axes that actually exist in
the world and then it will just work
right it'll search along the X and y
axes and can
on the z-axis now if we're going up this
is actually backwards so I feel like
these should have been set like that and
that's kind of a mess up so if I come in
here and look you see how we've got like
down and up our set this way I don't
know why they ended up being the other
way here because down is the min version
and should have been that way so
thankfully we did it right in in here
but we did it wrong over here so now
we've got that fixed and that's good so
I think that's the sketch of the routine
I think we've probably got a lot of
typos in there so we're gonna have to
fix that but once we do then I think
we're good to go I think I'm a little
surprised at that know why that was real
x-axis this is just this just adds why
did we have I don't know why we had that
I mean isn't this just this why did we
not do it that way before I'm not sure
anyway
so I think that should do it now I'm
gonna go ahead and switch back to the
floor account version we had before
where I did create dungeon with only one
I'm gonna go ahead and get rid of the
floor account again because I don't want
to deal with those up and downs yet
before I actually determine whether that
coat is working at all so I wanted a
debug I'm gonna first try to debug the
version of this where the I wanted to
bug the version of this hopefully where
the we actually need some rooms
obviously where the connections are
still planar and get that code working
first and then go ahead and do the other
version so I want to that like like I
want to make sure that that part is
properly working and you know what I
instead of doing this I might use the
orphanage since I know that those
connections are hard-coded and I know
which direction they should go that'll
help me as I step through it to make
sure that those are doing what I wanted
them to do and not screwing around again
so here's the orphanage version and
let's go ahead and step into the debug
version of this code so I could test it
so I want to look at the first time it's
we place a room so coming through here I
want to see what we get this is a
northward connection so it says the
x-axis is 0 the y axis is Z so we're
searching a long x that's correct for a
northward connection and the z axis
which is the direction of the of the
connection is going to be the y axis
that's correct and it's on the Mac side
which is correct for north because North
is going up so it's it's
it's connected to the max of the
connecting room so we start
is it the min no it's not so we start by
setting up the base rooms information
here so we're gonna take our test volume
just go ahead and rid of this here we're
gonna look at the base rooms volume
there it is
and we're going to look at the test
volume so here we can kind of see when
we create these volumes what we're
actually looking at so we're starting
with the base room it goes from zero to
four or five right that's just how that
works and it's already placed so now we
need to do is figure out okay what
should the how should the z-axis be set
now it has to a but so what we should
see is we should see this create a for
the z-axis which is the edge axis which
is the y-axis we should see the Y be set
to an abutting connection right and so
what we should see is if the max Y here
is five right we should see six and we
do and off so so that worked that was
correct so now we're gonna go ahead and
figure out what the other testing areas
are here oh and I can already see a
problem that we're gonna have this is
probably bug number one so you can see
our X goes from zero to four
this is our problem this min rel here is
gonna have to go it's gonna have to be a
less than or equal to test because it
may actually be the z-axis where there's
only one high the other one we
intentionally left it out because we're
sliding it across and we knew we
couldn't slide it that far with its low
overlapping this is kind of a it gets at
the thing where I this this is the part
right here that I'm actually talking
about very specifically I'm gonna go
ahead and do this for now that's not
really correct there's more we want to
do there to obey that to do so let's try
that one more time so now we come
through here and you can see are these
values are set correctly however so
that's good and
now we should enter the loop before we
would have skipped out of the loop and
so that was bug number one so now we set
the test volume up as a the first place
to test and you can see here what we're
testing that we're setting that z-axis
we should set this next exact same thing
this is set to and we do and that's
great right that's what we want now
we're going to proceed to test the
x-axis so we set up an x-axis test that
x-axis is 0 to 12 right we see if we can
place it there and we can right then we
put the door in place I'm gonna ignore
doors for now that's another part of
this routine we break out because we've
set the generation index now so we're
good and off we go so let's take a look
at whether that place of these rooms
properly I think it probably did I'll
switch back to an optimized build for
now because at some point we should just
have the lighting turn off in debug mode
because then we could just run debug
mode all we want the lighting is our
only slow code right now so that place
to your fridge just fine so now I'm
gonna kick over to the dungeon again and
see if we can get that Z code working
we're almost out of time but hey that's
the only other thing that I wanted to do
anyway in this set of code that I was
working on right now so if I go ahead
and do the create dungeon call and set
those as the starting rooms then we can
see what happens all right so we're
still getting we're getting a placement
problem here we don't really know what
that placement problem is so I'm gonna
start by creating it the easiest thing
from YouTube ugh I messed up the floor
count equal to 1 see whether we get any
problems on floor 0 we do not so it's
still able to create this simple ring
correctly I'm then going to set it up to
floor 2 and see if we is it the the
downward connection that caused a
problem so it's not and you can see now
we've created a two floor dungeon so I
suspect what we're getting now is just
at some point we create a dungeon that
loops back on itself and cannot be
placed so it looks like our up/down
connection
just work just fine right and so that's
yeah yeah so that's actually probably
okay because that's just something we
have to do later anyway so at some point
we get to a dungeon floor that can't be
laid out using the direct stream with no
rip up it just picks a bad set of things
but you can see our dungeon continued to
grow here so at some point we get to a
floor count that's high enough that one
of the way the snake generates itself
can't get itself out of a jam here you
go right so maybe it's floor for that
does it
who knows yeah so it's floor for that
does it stop before getting to floor
floor floor is zero through three are
all just fine and off we go
so when we are in our debug camera mode
here I would like to do something in
terms of for our clip plane like I say
before I want to be able to have a way
to see this stuff a little bit better so
we fly take a look in the in the code
for the far clip plane but you can see
here that we set it depending on debug
camera what I want to do here is change
this so I want to I want this to be
specific as well so I want us at the far
clip plane to something when we're using
debug camera it's gonna be something
other than what it was before so what I
want to do is I want to set this to
something that's proportional to the
target distance so basically as you zoom
out you get more fart clip plane right
so I want to take like when we when we
have that when we dolly right which is
this bit right here I want to be able to
take that dolly distance and I want to
put that into the mix right so I don't
know what it should be but like as we
dolly out more we will be able to see
more or something like that so I'm just
gonna set this for our clip plane up to
sort of allow us to zoom out better
so as we zoom out
we don't get any clipping basically
right so you can kind of see now we can
view the whole thing right and so that's
good so there's our dungeon being
created now and that's all well and good
I would like now to combine these two
things just so we can verify that the
world generator stuff is working at the
base level that I want to be working at
again without rip up and replace but
that's okay because that's a more
complicated thing that will be sort of
putting in a little bit later on but
then the way to do that here right if I
create the reference create the dungeon
I need the dungeon to be connected to
something I might as well make it the
forest path there because that's where
we exit the orphanage now eventually
I'll want to put the forest in between
those two things but at the moment since
we're pretty much out of time I'm just
gonna connect them up and leave it at
that so if we take a look at the forest
code here I'm sorry at the forest code
the orphanage on the dungeon code I have
the forest entrance I'm gonna go ahead
and take the forest entrance I'm gonna
connect these up so that if I'm going to
say if you go down word box index down
yeah so if we if you can't go downward
from the orphanage forest entrance you
will go directly into the dungeon now
normally you'd go through the forest
love it first but who cares right and so
this will create an orphanage and a
dungeon hopefully together right and
again we sort of have some problems
where like I said the dungeon connection
stuff doesn't quite work right but
hopefully that's all fine so I want to
be able to see out further than that
like I said so I'm gonna go in here and
change that far clip plane now that I
have some special code to change the far
clip plane out so what I'm gonna do here
is I'm maybe gonna say take that camera
dolly distance and just put it up a bit
I'm also gonna start out maybe with a
little bit of a further four clip
playing in debug mode and we'll just
call it a day
so now you can see the world as its
generated with that dungeon so if we
were to come out through here walk out
of the orphanage right like so now we
get into the forest and when we get to
the forest now you can see that we end
up with a room that stacked on top of
each other as it should be
here's the connection between those two
rooms so that's the connection down our
room generation code does not have any
stairway generating code in it so that's
why there's no stairway there but you
can see that it correctly picked up the
fact that that is where you would go
down and then you would get into the
dungeon which correctly stacks exactly
where it should and you can see you know
you would call through there you'd come
down here you'd go out through the
dungeon and everything's fine right so
the world is now sort of starts slowly
becoming an actual world with some stuff
in it and that's probably enough for now
right so I think now that gives us
enough I mainly lair the forest in there
at some point perhaps one thing that
would be nice I don't know what we I
don't really remember what we have in
our renderer for Strings
oh boy been a long time uh so here's our
string printing code so we don't really
have any way to print anything in a non
debug way but I would like to be able to
do that
I'm not gonna tackle this now but soon
when I think I would like to do as well
as have a way to attach our room name so
we look we can look at this thing we can
see what the generator thought it was
making right because right now it's been
pretty straightforward and everything
seems fine well in the future we're
probably gonna situation we're looking
for like what was that like why did that
get put there and what is it and it
would be nice to have a little thing
that says oh that was it was thinking
that the throne-room went there and
you're like why was it putting the
throne-room there so right like for
debugging purposes I feel like we're
gonna need that sort of a thing so yeah
I think that'll be something we'll want
to do a little bit later on for now I
think that's fine for today I'm gonna go
ahead and go to the QA and we'll pick up
next week when I think it's time to now
start picking up the lighting in the
camera code and start cleaning that
stuff up and then we probably want to
put in art because we're gonna need to
decorate these rooms so that they look
different
you
should you those air how do you decide
whether to include a library in your
project or not not that is the decision
tt BJM who builds a dungeon under an
orphanage Charles Dickens
what am i listening to nothing
what's the invalid default finger
shaming so I find that a lot of times
when I have a switch statement I want to
know I want it to handle certain cases
and I only want it to be called with
those cases so typically I put invalid
default case at the bottom which just
says anything else would be invalid so
that's just defined to this so these are
basically just two notes I put in my
code invalid code path means if we get
here something horrible has happened
like it should the values should never
be able to equal what they're equal
we're totally screwed right so that's an
assertion invalid default case is the
same thing but for switch statements it
just says look anything other than the
switches that are handled here or that
should say the cases that are handled
here is invalid so I put that at the
bottom of every switch statement that
doesn't have a default unless I unless I
intentionally don't want to handle the
cases right which maybe sometimes I want
to do are you wearing headphones because
you want to hear the visual studio error
sounds no I'm wearing them because we're
for two reasons one
it's the headset I use as my microphone
but the other reason is because when we
debug game sound I need to hear it right
mr. love pickle how do you keep up the
motivation to continue working on
handmade here oh well you know handmade
hero is is not a very time consuming
thing like I've spent seven or eight
hundred hours on it I think and that's
20 weeks of development now and 20 weeks
of development for a game engine
programmer is nothing I mean 20 weeks
it's not even a year right so I'm used
to projects to take three four five
years of development time to make
because engine code is very complicated
and there's a lot of it so
handmade hero is small potatoes right
it's it's hardly anything I mean that
yet seven eight hundred hours is is
child's play for an engine programmer
right it's it's just it's it's a blink
of an eye because normally you're
working 40 hours a week or something on
an engine for years potentially right I
like for when I worked at rad right I
was working on the character animation
system I mean I worked on that from 1999
to 2004 and that's just the animation
system all day every day right
and so handmade hero is I mean I I don't
love the fact that I'm have to think
about more than one project in my head
at a time you know I have to keep
handmade hero kinda in the back of my
head like how it works you know a little
bit and I prefer to only really
necessary be thinking about one thing at
a time usually so that's a little
annoying but the motivation is pretty
easy because again it's just it'd be
impossible to get burned out on
something that you've only spent 800
hours on if you're a game engine
programmer that's like right it's like
it's it's like you've took a nap and it
went by right long billions so I'm
guessing the layout system still will
not handle cyclical connections nicely
or do you think it could now no it
definitely doesn't write like cyclical
connections that would just we have not
cyclical connections require rip up and
replace for sure and we don't have that
yet
and also probably some more strategic
thinking pith no could you do a brief
overview of all the parts that are
involved in generating the world I lost
the thread sure it's pretty simple right
now actually at least by our standards
on handmade hero it's pretty simple so
what we do is we first do a pass where
we create a series of Jen
and Jen connections that specify how
those rooms are connected so each room
that we want in the final game will have
a gender in created for it and then each
time that two rooms connect to each
other with a door or up up down or
sideways we create a connection that has
the two rooms on either side and a mass
that says how they could be connected
sometimes that's specific like it has to
be in east-west connection right other
times it's nonspecific like well it can
be any connection or any planar
connection so it can't be up-down but it
could be anything else right so that's
the first pass and that pass looks like
this so in the world gencode you know
you've got some of creates an orphanage
it says here's all the rooms in the
orphanage here's all the ways they're
connected to each other right and here's
the size as I want them to be go right
so we have passes that do that they just
create those and you can see us calling
them both here this creates a 7 level
dungeon this creates an orphanage and
then we just connect the two together
and we're good to go we then have a
layout call the layout call is kind of
the code that's slowly starting to take
shape now it's very primitive but it's
getting a little bit better and what
that does at the moment we don't really
need this code anymore
we're not gonna go back to that specific
code at the moment what that code does
is it places the first room sort of
arbitrarily just puts it in the centre
because it's like who cares where it is
right
today's the first room and then it
crawls outward from that room trying to
place rooms connected to it by looking
at what directions those rooms could be
connected based on the direction mask
set in the connection like what's
allowed for this connection and just
trying to place the room if it can place
the room it places a room and then it
continues and it just spiders out from
there placing all the rooms so the
reason I say that it's still pretty
primitive is because it only will work
if that process happens to successfully
complete
in one pass so if it gets to a point
where it has paid itself into a corner
like I talked about before so it wrapped
around itself and now cannot place rooms
it is too dumb to do anything about it
you cannot go back to the start and try
again with a different attempt right and
it also while it is expanding never
looks at anything else that might help
it to expand properly so if it knows for
example that it needs to place two rooms
on this one thing it doesn't even do
anything to attempt to not enclose that
room by looping other rooms around there
anything like that right so it both
cannot restart and cannot try to do
something sensible so when we put enough
stuff in there it will fail right when
we give it something that doesn't just
happen to work so what we have to do is
we have to continue to make this code
more intelligent so that we can lay out
the kind of structures we want which
isn't too much more intelligent probably
because we don't have things there's
nothing in this game that's going to be
more complicated than sort of roughly
the dungeon and orphanage stuff we just
put in there but we do need it to get a
little smarter we probably want some
cycles in there and we also I think need
it to be able to handle the dungeon code
where it has to restart and try a
different path to lay things out right
so we need to get that stuff in there
are you working on other stuff parallel
to him here yeah I I programmed full
time like I actually make game
technology for a living so this is only
done in my spare time scallywag just
caught up and watched a stream for the
first time live today wanted to say
thanks for the amazing learning resource
you've made me a better programmer than
college or university ever could well
that's great thanks so much for saying
so I hope that you continue to find it
useful neat sir have you decided how
many levels the world will have in the
end well there's no such thing as levels
in this where it's all continuous so
it's just a giant forest with dungeons
right so we'll probably try to tune it
so that the biggest it would get is
something that can be finished in a few
hours
like who knows I don't know what we'll
do you know maybe we'll have two modes
you can pick from like maybe you can
pick one that says generate me a 40-hour
we're done 40-hour crawl and it will you
know I mean I don't know I'm a game
designer I don't care
really about that part of it so you know
since the engine will probably be able
to generate you a 40-hour thing maybe if
you want to you could do that but
regardless of any of that it will always
just be one continuous world so there
will not be like levels where there
where you like load a new one it's just
one big world you walk around in and you
know how big it is is what you input to
the generator so when you call the
generator you'll say here's how many
hours this dungeons supposed to be and
we'll probably pass like 0.5 hours for
the first one so it's supposed to be
like a 30 minute thing and then as you
unlock more we'll say like ok now it's 1
hour now it's an hour and a half now
it's 2 hours 3 hours and that maybe
would be as big as we typically do it
right when you unlock everything it's 3
hours but maybe we'll want to just have
a silly mode you if you get to the 3
hour mode where you can also say
generate me an N our dungeon and you can
just set it to whatever you want so it's
like if you want to say generate me a
200 hour like dungeon crawl it will why
you would want to I don't know but you
know we could do it this is a game
that's meant to teach people how to
program so it's not really about making
design decisions it's about programming
and if our code supports you asking for
a 200 done our dungeon and getting one
back then maybe we should just let that
happen
see voucher the current system doesn't
handle adding a rotated or mirrored
orphanage right well you know it doesn't
but it would be really simple to do so
so if we wanted to make a rotated or a
mirrored orphanage we certainly could uh
I don't really want to do that because I
don't want you to when you learn a type
of room I want you to be able to
recognize that room and I want it to be
the same orientation right so I don't
want you to come into rooms that you
would have expected this way and have
them be that way if that makes sense
because I want them to be recognizable
to the player like oh I'm going into the
fountain room now and oh now I'm in a
hall a mirror hallway or whatever so I
kind of want those to be understandable
as themselves so I don't want the system
to randomly - I don't want the system to
ever take something that I specified
this way and be like oh well I'll just
place it rotated over here or something
that's not something I want to have
happen but if you wanted to do it it
wouldn't be very hard right all you'd
have to do is specify the rotation you
wanted and then you would rotate the
derp mask which would just be like a
barrel shift of the bits pretty much
well it's not quite that but it's
similar and then you would swap the the
dimension X&amp;Y right that's it
at the moment that Jen rooms are all
created by hand no they're not so for
example the dungeon is not created by
hand right the dungeon is a for loop
with some random choices baked into it
so you can already see how this plays
out right so even now when we haven't
really even though we haven't really
done much you can see this is completely
procedural right there's no hand off the
ring here at all really it randomly
picks how many there are in a chain from
beginning to end it randomly picks where
it might place the shop in the item room
you can imagine saying putting an if
around these if you don't always want
there to be a shop right so no like
we're already past the point of the hand
authoring like we're already into random
generation and we've only just started
does that make sense
if you're talking about what goes in the
rooms yes that we haven't done anything
with right the rooms right now don't
don't pop inside you're just empty so
that obviously we haven't anything with
but have you worked on procedurally
generated worlds similar to this before
no I have not
I've never really done a tile map be
kind of a game this isn't really a tile
map but you know what I mean like the
only things I've ever worked on before
our continuous 3d really I
I've never really worked on things that
have like a sort of tile based feel to
them like this so it's a little bit new
for me certainly and also most of the
things I've ever had experience with in
the past were not procedurally their
hand authored usually obviously like my
the last preparatory lon the witness is
very hand authored right every last bit
is like fine-tuned by hand
so there's a couple pretty jewel pieces
in there like the grass you know grasses
and foliage just kind of stuff but
that's that's really it
all right
thank you everyone for joining me for
the episode of hand made here up so I
pepper coating with you as always if you
would like to follow along with the
series at home you can always peer out
of the game on hand made here at org and
it comes with a source code so you can
play around with it yourself which would
be a good thing to do this week if you
wanted to try your hand at fixing the
generation code that currently doesn't
know what to do if it can't place rooms
right so we talked about how that needs
to get improved you could try improving
it that'd be a great thing to try over
the week if you are so inclined I'll be
back next week when I think we will not
be addressing that problem directly I am
going to go
I think clean up the camera and lighting
stuff so that it properly frames the
rooms that you're in and does a couple
of things like that that are just some
quality of life things so that we can
hop around our world as it becomes a
little bit more of a real world I don't
really want all the rough edges in there
I want to see what it looks like for
real so that's a relatively
straightforward cleanup stuff we need to
do and we should just do it so that we
can be happy with that so we'll be doing
probably that next weekend
before coming back to the generator
we're gonna do a little bit of a twerk
for sure so that's about it for today
see hope to see you back here next week
until then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet take it
easy everybody