hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we are going to continue with the
lighting stuff we were working on
yesterday we need to essentially do two
things today one is we have to decide
what we're going to be doing about
targeting light sources and then we have
to go ahead and implement something that
allows us to target those light sources
inside our actual ray casting code we
sort of ended on a note yesterday
whereas like well this came up I don't
have a plan for it right now and it's
gonna be fairly complicated so I want to
wait until we have a full episode and
now is that episode let me go ahead and
there we go load up the code here if I
go to handmade lighting dot CPP which is
where this code lives we can take a look
at the part that I'm talking about just
to get you acquainted with it in the
test casting code here what we want to
do is figure out a solution to this
problem right here so what we were
previously doing in the test cast is we
were saying well if we want to cast
towards the light source rather than
just casting completely randomly and I
do think we want the ability to cast
towards the light source stochastically
in the actual caster itself sorry this
is not academic this is something that
we actually are going to need to do to
get our convergence good you know to get
our lighting to be less flickery we want
the ability to specifically target
nearby light sources and gather their
values at higher rates than we would
just randomly hitting them from picking
just arbitrary directions so if you take
a look at what's going on inside the
probing what we want to be able to do
here is say look for a particular
casting location we want it to tell us
with some degree of accuracy what the
nearest light sources are and since
we're a cast bundles at a time one thing
we may want to do is Ray cast those as a
bundle I don't know if that's what we
want to do instead what we may want to
do is just have the closest light source
in each direction and then when we break
our bundles into
affections maybe we have six directional
bundles for example for 24 total ray
casts or something like that maybe we
write over one of each of those with it
so that the raycast have a more coherent
traversal I don't really know and so I
think that's you know honestly the
bundles need to be coherent so I think
that might be a more likely way we're
gonna do that and so when you think
about what's going on there we need some
way of getting like that information we
need something like that and so the
problem is we just at the moment don't
really have any way of knowing what that
that light source would actually be and
we don't really know we don't really
have a plan for getting that information
now what I think we probably are gonna
have to do because I thought about it a
little bit kind of in the back of my
brain as you do after you you know code
something and then you're like well I
got to do this thing next sort of it's
on the its you know it's often the in
your peripheral thinking they're right
what I would like to do is I'd like to
say that we probably need a separate
data structure for this so we probably
want to put our occluders into one thing
and we probably want to put our light
sources into a separate thing now the
light sources also go into the occluders
because we need to like Ray cast against
them but the directional lookup thing
probably needs to be something that's
purpose-built so what I think we want to
do is something where we sort of have a
data structure whose entire goal is just
to figure out when you're casting from a
particular location what are the
directional casts that you want to do
like how what are the light light
sources in this case that you actually
want to use and that's primarily what
we're gonna be working with right and so
the problem is we have to figure out
some way to build that data structure
and it's unclear like exactly what that
data structure would look like and
furthermore it's unclear how accurate we
really need it to be or want it to be
and so on
and in our case the problem that we're
gonna face is we need something that
sort of splits directional lookups in
some way so we can say all right for
this location in space
give me the closest light sources like
up-down left-right
you know north south east west that sort
of thing and so that we can bundle it
with the raycast that we're going to do
and so in order to make that data
structure we would need something that
can sort of take the locations of the
light sources themselves and break them
down into sort of regions that where as
you cross the region boundaries you
would get different answers so that the
the splits between the regions
correspond to times when the closest
light source in a particular direction
changes to something else right and I
don't really know how to do that right I
don't really know what that that thing
would would look look like and so if I
actually go here and sort of draw out
what we're actually talking about I'm
going to go ahead and put de 571 in here
I so like this is the closest light
query right so the things that I've seen
in the past that sort of have this this
type of a structure to them are usually
you know I I can't think of very many
but the one that comes to mind is like
light cuts right and the way light cuts
work is they sort of build a hierarchy
of light sources that looks a little
something like this
so let's suppose that in my system you
know let's take a very simple case
there's you know seven light sources
that get pushed into the system so you
know maybe we've got a top-down view of
just a simple room and there's seven
light sources you know there's one there
there's one here there's one here one
here one here one here and one here
right
and then we want to create life cuts out
of this what is the like cut well like
cut is essentially building up a spatial
model of your light sources by grouping
nearby light sources together into a
tree so we start by saying well okay we
these farm form the leaves of our trees
so we say you know okay here's one two
three four five six seven and those form
the base of our tree so we have one two
three four five six seven and those are
the leaves and then we do is say well
well how close are these things together
right and what we could say is well five
and six are pretty close together right
so those might form sort of this new
light source right which will I'll give
these letters instead of numbers ones
that are not actual light sources this
can be like composite light source a
right so what we would say is these two
light sources we can form together and
maybe we treat them as one light source
who is like here actually right look I'm
in between location or something and
we'll call that light source a which
does not actually exist in the real
world but it's a composite of two of the
light sources that do exist right and
then maybe we say well two and three are
fairly close together as well so maybe
they form light source B right and
that's like here you know right so now
we've got another one and then we have
like some other light sources here and
those light sources you know kind of
can't really form together in any
particularly clean way at the moment you
might say that the easiest thing to do
would like to be extend this out to to
contain light source seven maybe and
again I'm not sure how we would want to
build this tree but I'm just giving an
example so this is not exactly how it
would be done Australia but just example
to form light source see so maybe a and
seven form light source see here and
then maybe that expands to hold this one
which would be what is that light source
for there and so C and for that forms a
new light source which is D and then you
know probably it also grabs this one so
probably these two come up together as
well so one is probably actually
secretly over here right and that forms
e and then these tumors together to form
the final light source half right and so
what you're doing is you're creating
successive
less resolute light sources where
there's less and less light sources as
you go up the tree right and then the
way this actually ends up working in
practice is if you just take a look at
how close you are to the bounding region
of this light source you keep splitting
the light source down until you get
lower and lower into ones that are
sufficiently resolute for how close you
are to them right
the reason they call this light cuts is
because for any particular person who
wants to query them let's say someone
who's like right here and you want to
query them you may find that you know
you want light source five at full
resolution right so your light cut wants
to include light source five as a
particular thing so you know that this
is going to be in right which means that
you've expanded all the way down here so
that means that like you know five and
six this this path through the tree is
probably completely expanded right but
then you know you may say well two and
three really don't need to be right so I
never even went down this branch of the
tree right I just don't even use it at
all and so you may end up with some path
that just goes like okay this is the the
entirety of the expansion's that I got
to do and I'm gonna let light source you
know F if I had to expand it you know B
will stand in for two and three entirely
and I'll just never expand those two e
will get expanded out to one and D D
will get expand up to C in for C will
get expanded out to this one and we'll
end up with a certain you know set of
light sources here right now I don't
remember the exact ways of building
light cut trees that are efficient or
any of these sorts of things so I'm just
kind of saying like you know this is
probably not quite how you do it it
seems like you really want something
that allows you to be more specific
about how these get broken down but just
in general the idea is we build a tree
out of these and we only explain
the tree in the places we actually care
about and we leave the tree on expand
into places that aren't that way right
and so you could imagine us just merging
nearby light sources together in that
way
and if we did that then we could
actually cut down on the number of light
sources that we were choosing to target
and furthermore there's probably in ways
that we can
there's probably ways we can do this
such that it does help us with the fact
that we need our rate traces to be
somewhat coherent in terms of
directionality I'm not sure exactly how
I would do that to think about that a
little bit but if you imagine expanding
the tree in such a way as to figure out
like what's going on in each direction
from us so as we expand those light
sources that are like nearby to us or
whatever we would be keeping track of
which side of us they were on and just
like remembering you know sifting
sitting them out into you know six
different arrays to pick from or
something like this right so I think
that's something we could do I don't
really have a like a solid handle on it
like I say but I think that's more or
less the way that we would want to
approach it so we have some way of
basically just like expanding a separate
light tree so I'm just gonna assume
that's what we want right and I don't
know the shape of it or exactly what the
routines look like but that's okay I
just know that we're going to have some
kind of a separate thing that's gonna be
special purpose for this and so I know
that I don't have to care about about
this gets facial leaf for P thing
anymore like that we can change to just
being one that's specific to light
sources right and so what I'm gonna do
is say let's suppose there's a different
tree in here there's a tree that's
something like yeah like light light
spatial partition or something like this
I don't know we're gonna call it but
like a lighting node or a light
know'd something like that and this
light node would have to have something
like how it expanded out right and if
it's like something like a binary tree
you know maybe it's got two indices or
something like that you know this sort
of thing and then what we would do from
there is for each one of these light
nodes you know and like a binary tree or
we expand it or whatever maybe we just
have a bounds for it so we would just
say like you know key and radius so it
can basically be just treated the same
as our other ones so our Etan the same
it's basically the same as our other
summated spatial partition so we look at
the lighting box here right it's the
same as this but it's gonna have
different information in it so instead
of it's gonna have the P and the radius
and then it's gonna have the emission
value or something baked in here so we
can basically just use these and they
kind of expand as they go and we have
like synthetic ones like I said that
kind of you know they keep going now we
may want to do the exact same thing as
we were doing in here so we may want to
have a thing where we just have these
light nodes or baked in there so you
push light nodes onto the light node set
I don't know exactly how we want to do
this stuff but something like that so we
were getting we would build a tree and
the tree would be sort of separate and
then we would use that tree is something
that we would you know query and then we
would take the light nodes that we found
and we would just sort those light nodes
into which direction they were from us
you know basically which which one of
their when we're looking in the
different directions for things we can
then make those rays more coherent by
sipping these nodes into the correct
location so something like this and what
I'm gonna do now is I'm just gonna do
like some basic work getting that that
code started and then we're gonna use
that to look up the lighting and just
kind of get it working right just get a
basic thing working and then we can
worry about turning the crank on that
once everything is kind of in place and
we start throwing tons of lights in it
start slowing down and stuff like that
then we'll start to worry about okay how
do we start to occupy this code because
they're already not very optimal like
the Ray caster is at least four wide and
doing some good space partition stuff so
the Rhea casters not terrible but this
lighting code is gonna be brand new and
it doesn't really know what it's doing
and so you know that that part's gonna
be slower alright so when we actually do
our build spatial partition for lighting
here what we want to do now is have a
separate pass you can see the pass sort
of starting here we don't actually want
this you know this light box target key
thing anymore we're gonna get rid of
that and instead what we're gonna do is
we're gonna do this pass over the thing
where we say all right for each of these
we're gonna look at the boxes
twice and we can really do this because
it's a separate tree and we don't really
need to know those bounds probably I
would say what we could do is we can
build this the base level of this tree
we can probably build it sort of off the
bat I mean we could build this the same
way we build the other one I suppose
trying to think of like how we want to
do this because when we actually do this
this split box here I feel like we could
do the same exact thing but just for
light sources right so I mean let's if
we did occluder bounds here and we did
lighting light bounds as a separate
thing and we imagine in here saying like
okay there's an if statement that we'll
use and we'll just sort of take two
separate sets of bounds one for things
that are lights because we know that so
for anything that is a light we included
in these bounds and for everything that
exists at all be included in the
occluder bounds so things that you can
hit are both light sources and walls
things that you can treat as a light
source for sampling only go in this this
sort of other box set right and so again
I don't really know what this thing
should look like but presumably
can use a very similar sort of splitting
for it or something like presumably we
can do a pretty similar set of things I
don't really know I don't again really
know exactly how we want this to look
but just in terms of like how far away
light sources are I think that's all we
probably need to know and so we could
sort of do here is is we can probably
run effectively the same code like more
or less the exact same code and then we
could just go ahead and break it down
into a binary tree now I don't again I
really just don't know exactly how we
want to do this but for now maybe we say
we do it exactly the same way so if you
imagine this split box code operating
the same way and I mean honestly I'm you
may even be able to make it and I'm
thinking about it I wonder if we could
just do it with the split boxes
themselves so maybe we just build two
spatial structures and we don't really
care whether they're lights or not and
we just have two of them right so if you
look in here and we say well we've got
sort of a box table that we you know and
lighting boxes here maybe we just have
two of those and you know we just go
ahead and and use yeah like we just used
two of those and we build them
symmetrically and so that when you call
this you know you just use a different
root box right so we'd add one box here
and we'd add another box there and off
we would go so if you imagine what that
would look like I mean it would just
really be something like this right and
instead of the actual box count and this
sort of stuff we would just need like a
separate light count and we would need
those things to be added right so we
would need something like route light
box here and we would put that yeah like
I also don't know by root box okay so
basically it would look like this right
so you would basically say route light
box index which would be sort of a
separate thing because here we've got
the root box index is something we store
or else
there so we would have a route lightbox
index and that would be something that
we would build sort of a separate pass
you know again I don't know if these
will have to be expanded to be 32 bits
or not because kind of like we may end
up having too many nodes I don't know so
you know this may want to be 32 bit
integers at the end of the day and we
can always expand it if we find it's too
little but you know we want our lighting
system solution to run fast so we're
probably gonna try and limit the amount
of things get thrown into it either way
but anyway so if you imagine us doing
this stuff you're exactly the same way
that we were doing it and then we get
the route lightening box by using that
route light box index in here once we
actually get those out we can get the
center of the light bounds instead of
the clear bounds and in here we can get
the radius right of that light bounds
and so that allows us to you know make
this system work for both so we just use
the same building function for each and
the differences one tree has everything
and the other tree only has lights right
now since that needs to know how many
lights there are we end up in a
situation where this part here is not
quite as simple we need something that
has the actual light count in here and
that's gonna start out at zero and in
here I think what we would do is say we
need to count how many of those there
are and each time we actually get one we
would need to load it in here right so
what we would need to do is make it so
that we have you know honestly probably
this right here where we say okay we've
got the route light box index and we're
gonna make that be the first box of our
set and so inside this we assume that
each of these will just come after it
right and so we need a way to add the
lights in here as sort of a separate
thing because you know because these
have to be continuous oh well I guess
they don't
you know yeah so all right so here's the
thing in the in the lighting box here
right so we've got the first child index
and the child count right so when we're
actually partitioning these things into
children then what we're actually going
to see here I guess is those indices
that we're looking at here they go into
this box table which is sort of a doubly
in directed table which honestly is not
great I kind of suspect that that's
probably not the the best way to do this
but because those are going in there I
guess we don't actually need to do
anything particularly fancy there all
that needs to happen is in that box
table index we just like we just need to
add a reference to this thing right so
instead of adding box storage we can
just use box reference and point to the
box in question so like here where we
have the box storage index we can just
say oh well we're just trying to refer
to this box and we just need it to be
contiguous so that the we can split
these indices up right we don't even
really need to store that information in
the actual thing itself it's just we're
going to that's a little bit wasteful
because they're not contiguous and we're
trying to pass them down to a separate
thing
we'll see how we'll see how we do anyway
so we've got this root box index here
that we're now saying okay this thing is
the light we're keeping track of how
many of these there are this doesn't
actually have to be here if we don't
want it to be here but I'm going to do
it this way anyway just so we have an
idea of where this array starts and so
in here we can say well the root light
box is this one this is the the number
of boxes in question and I believe this
is the offset so this just needs to be
like the
one after the the root box let me just
make sure that's true
I'm not oh no that's not true so how do
I tell it oh it's just a source array
okay that makes sense so in order to
tell it where we're actually looking
here that's still a zero but when we
pass the actual source array which is
this thing
I guess that source array for scratch a
has to be set up with that base pointer
being correct so this would be that I
want to say I don't really know how
scratch B works we're gonna have to go
look at this code what is that that's
the destination so I'm not sure how
that's supposed to be working there
what's going on how does this thing do
this partition so it's just writing into
the source there and then the
destination gets flipped I'm not sure I
this is some some pretty crazy code so
the interesting thing here right is you
can see that basically those two arrays
are just used for the splitting and the
writing at the end and so
I want to do a walk through this exactly
and make sure it's okay so when the
source count is not greater than four so
if you have four or less children you do
nothing right so what that means that
what you pass in directly for the source
has to kind of be correct and that's
okay because that is what's happening
here right so effectively what we would
want to do is say all right here's the
route light box and by default you know
I would assume it's children need to be
correct in the cause in case you have
less than four lights going into the
system this would have to be able to
fall out correctly right and so whatever
the child count that goes in would be
the first child index would just be
source count source for adding box
references there and so the source well
okay no it's correct so I guess that
just works
we'll see so I think that once if we go
through and make that a little clearer
and I can I clean up that code so that
and I know that it's working correctly
that will build us to light pounds one
for the route light box and one for the
route occluder box and that's probably
fine and probably most of what we need
right so if I go in here and we make
this sort of Union work correctly by
changing spelling so it's not busted we
now have a way to look up light sources
and so now mainly what we're looking for
here is we need loops why can I not get
back to the first thing here here yeah
mainly what we need here route light box
that's spelled wrong mainly what we need
here is just a way of now using this
light to you know to figure out what's
light we're
and a cast against if you look at how
we're doing it here essentially what
we're doing is we're only casting
against just this one light and you know
what we can do at the moment is we can
just actually just use the route light
box as the thing we cast against and if
we only push one light down then that is
what that would be right because it
would get the correct the correct values
associated with it the only thing that's
not gonna happen here is the route light
box needs to actually be set up properly
to have its value be be an actual
average there because if you look at
what's going on here you know we've got
this split box or whatever that's
happening and normally in here where we
are doing this splitting where we
actually have more of them we can
actually compute some values here even
though these are not computing those
values we do want to actually compute
sort of averaging values here what we
need to do is every time we hit
something that would be a container it
needs to sort of get some aggregate
values associated with it this right
here is effectively doing sort of the
splitting process and so in here what
we're doing is we're saying look if we
have something where we got a valid
split then we're gonna go ahead and
assign some information right and we do
you know this this this sort of sub
sitting this part here kind of needs to
have a way of putting the right bounds
in there so you can see where we do
where we compute the bounds right you
can see here what's happening for each
parent box is that when we create those
two children we create the new children
with the values that we've tracked so
when we do the split we know what the
left and right sides of the slit should
have for their center in radius but we
don't fill in any kind of like
information for them and what we do need
is we need this ref sea value to
actually be valid
is the thing right and so if something
is a light source we know that this is
the emission if it's not we know that
it's the occlusion value those are good
pieces of information to have and we
need them right so what we need here is
we need to be able to say well the ref C
is gonna be used in either of these
cases is going to be like the ref CA
right and the ref C in this case is
going to be the ref CB right and
honestly we should have been doing that
for our occluders anyway because when
you hit one of those occluders you need
it to tell you that information anyway
right you need to know that this thing
is a light or an occluder you need to
know what the color values were of the
occluder just as much as you need to
know what is a light source if you're
gonna stop your traversal and so that
may have also been why we were having
that bug where you were getting black
for the bounces on when you got too far
away because we may have just not been
aggregating our ref CA values or rest EB
and ref CA values so we were just
getting complete knock out of the
lighting source there right so that was
probably a bug separate from this and we
need to fix it for the lighting we we
probably are fixing it for the occluders
as well so that's kind of a nice thing
so here we decide which one of these
we're going to have we can go ahead and
take the color Union here so all I'm
gonna do is say that we have a ref CA
and a ref CD we're gonna sum these
values together and we're gonna produce
a composite color for this thing that's
based on you know that that value and so
the ref C or ref B in this case are just
gonna get oops sorry
the ref CA and the ref CB I don't know
why I had that I wrote them correctly
down here you can see those are just
going to get these values sum together
so the ref C is gonna it's gonna tally
it up and in this case we already have
counts so for each of these we can also
now normalize that so this here
can be multiplied by the inverse so we
can do one over the the total sum so the
total sum and the a side is count a we
can multiply that by the ref to
basically get it back down this is an
average right so we're taking the
average so to rescale it back down to
the appropriate scale so ref CA and ref
CB in this case can both be
automatically normalized am because we
know that they've each got a count on
them otherwise we wouldn't have recorded
it right so I think that gives us all we
really need for the splitting there the
only problem is that the initial one the
top level right doesn't get the value
and that's an issue we need the the
light box the root box itself needs to
know that piece of information in order
to figure out like you know what it's
composite value should be and so for the
particular case of the root we kind of
need a separate summation pass that we
don't actually get this way and so I
think what we may want to do here is we
may just want to say this thing always
has to split try think if there's any
another way they didn't really do this
because since you have to look at them
in order to decide to split you kind of
just want to make sure that that happens
in line yeah I don't know I couldn't
really say I don't really know how they
should go but you can see the problem
like like the root box
in the in this case doesn't get a proper
value and we would have to write a
completely separate routine that just
spun through the children of it to
actually produce that composite value
which seems wrecker real pain in the
butt and so that's kind of annoying and
it would be nice if we didn't have to do
it but on the whole I guess I can't say
I guess I I don't really know how we
would get around that I don't see an
obvious way of tightening this code up
so that I don't have to write that
routine separately because basically it
only actually happens on the split and
we could force it so that it always had
to split the first time around and the
only problem there is like what if you
feed it something that can't be split
like you have one light source period
that can't be split right so I do think
maybe what we kind of need to do here is
just actually bite the bullet and make
sure that we you know right I mean I
hate to do it but I don't know what else
to do right I mean I just I feel like
that just has to happen
so it's annoying and stupid but I don't
know you know it eludes me at least at
the immediate moment not having thought
about it very much but it eludes me at
the immediate moment how to make that
code so that it you know it can both be
efficient and done in line with a split
and then also kind of have a different
pass that lets you do it this way so
yeah I don't know about that anyway if
we want to compute these right so in
terms of like doing the lookup here
where we do a calculate ref see here's
the root box in question what we're
going to need here is a way to sort of
look up and I mean you know let's let's
use the raycast code as a guide because
that's showing exactly how you do the
lookup so you can see here if we wanted
to loop over the children of this thing
we would do it like this that gives us
the the child boxes so for each child
right we're gonna look up the box inside
the source index here and then we're
going to take
Russy value and some sum it up right so
we know the child count we can basically
say like look if there's no child count
then we don't need to do anything
because obviously we can't compute an
average of no things so in the case of
there's no lights or no occluders then
just zero for the ref see is fine
because it can't really exist but in the
other case here so if we did ref c
equals the initial value of zero then
for each one of these and i guess i
don't know if we may have to do that
sort of separately in fact maybe I'll do
it this way let's let's do it this way
so we're gonna start out assuming zero
we're gonna then go ahead and for each
box we'll take the ref C value and we'll
you know sum them up and then at the end
we will just normalize exactly the way
we were doing it before by taking the
root box table count like so and and and
turning that into a floating point value
that can renormalize so there we've
built our trees and we've properly
updated the ref sea values I mean
barring bugs anyway I and and up here we
just needed to clear those and so now
we're building two spatial partitions
one for light sources one for occluders
and we just now you know we haven't
really I don't think we've messed with
the code in any particular way for the
what's the word I'm looking for I don't
think we've messed with a code in any
particular way for the occluders so
those should still in theory be working
fine so the only thing we really have to
do now is change our get space relief
for p function to really be something
that does more of a light source query
for us and i think all this wants to do
at the moment is just kind of do a query
because normally what we would be doing
is actually sort of building an array
and then randomly picking from it
probably right now what we're going to
do for get spatial leave for p
is just actually pick out the location
here so when we do get spatial leaf 4p
I'm gonna call this get lightly 4p this
is not gonna have to happen now because
now what will happen is when we do get
lightly 4p we can just just give us back
the lightbox and then this can get the
information out of that lightbox so this
can be lightbox P and now we can cast
against it right all right sort of
tangentially this also gives us a way to
understand area light sources more than
we could have before possibly there are
some downsides to how we're doing it
it's kind of hard to say but we'll sort
of we'll work towards these things as we
go so anyway now that we've got all of
this stuff wrapped up I'm really just
looking you know the only problem now is
I have to get this function working and
so if we look at get spatial leaf for P
we're sort of gonna be doing the same
thing but instead here it's get lightly
for P right and so here we're going to
be doing the root lightbox index we're
starting with that we're gonna be
walking the children to find whatever
that index is and then we're going to
return it now if we look at how the
result is working now I do want to
return a lighting box and also in here
where we do the light color we could
also make that the ref see but I'm gonna
do that in separate steps because we're
trying to kind of this is the tesco
we're trying to test that this stuff is
working properly
and so now this should give us the light
that is sort of closest I guess to where
we are and that's I guess I would say we
need to update this a little bit and it
actually makes the routine a little
simpler to what we can't actually say
here is we just want the closest one we
don't want you to have to be inside the
light source because that doesn't make
any sense so what we really want to do
here I guess is say look there's a
result we're gonna assume it's the route
light while we are inside the volume of
this thing we can divide it down further
so we just say look while or rather we
know that that's got to be true so we
can just do this and say if this thing
has children I guess you know what
here's the thing that's what we really
want so while we haven't expanded down
to a single light source keep going
and in here we would just say all right
for each one of these things we just
pick whichever one of these is closest
right and we expand the closest one so
instead of doing a is in rectangle I
think we want like a get distance or
like distance to box and I guess we
don't have that which is what we want
that's unfortunate I guess I'll have to
write it but what we effectively want
here is a best distance to rectangle so
we want like a closest distance right
and then we want to do is loop through
the children of this thing and if there
was you know we know there's a child
count because we've said we won't have
descendant if there wasn't and so we
want to do is take the closest distance
for each one of these things we would
say like this distance equals get
distance
to Fox and we would just you know do
this right and we would say if this
distance is a better distance use it
right and so this is just the thing
that's going to go through and like take
the closest Fox whatever the closest box
is to it is to us we will expand it and
take you know that result this is not
actually you know I'm gonna put a note
here right this does not actually
guarantee that that this that you're
gonna get the closest light source and
the reason for that is because you would
need to revisit other parts of the tree
to ensure that there wasn't something
inside a bounding box that was actually
closer even though that bounding box was
further away and the reason for that is
of course when you create bounding boxes
they're approximations to what's inside
them you don't know if there was
actually a light source anywhere near
that boundary that you found was closest
to you and so you're just kind of saying
well this might be something close to me
but it's not necessarily and so we're
not trying in this case to actually find
that exact result and so I just want to
make you know that clear so in terms of
finding the distance to the box I guess
we don't have any functions in our math
library for doing that unfortunately so
that's a little unfortunate right but if
we wanted to have one right and we want
to say get this since the box and we
just said Center you know radius P or
whatever if I wanted to be able to do
this it's actually not that bad really
you probably want to do this off of an
actual rectangle because you kind of
want the min and Max which again I'm not
sure it why we may want to change our
boxes to storing mins and maxes instead
of peas and radii and the reason for
that is just looking at it
I'm not sure that it seems like we want
the min and Max way more often than we
want the center and so you know I might
put that in here as a thing to do it's
just an efficiency concern when we're
all done I'd like to look at that
because you know just want to make sure
you're not doing extra math you don't
have to do so we may want to change that
and we'll leave that for later because
it's strictly an efficiency concern
doesn't affect the math in any way it's
just hey which one of these things
results in less ops to do the same you
know math that we're trying to do so we
want to make sure that we're not doing
extraneous sort of adjustments that
don't need to happen because of our the
way we chose to store it now when we
call get this since the box what we need
to do here is say all right let's figure
out how far away we are from each of
these things and I think really this is
just a series of mins and maxes trying
to think if there's anything
particularly weird about it but I think
you just need to take the minimum
distance from each of the sides of the
box right
[Music]
I think so so I think it's just this I
think we just say the test point that
we're going to create is going to be the
so you know I'm actually going to do
this so if I take the box top min right
and I say look what I want you to do is
create a fictitious point on the box
that is the closest point to us and what
we would do there is say well that point
you know is going to be the minimum of
the box and us right so whichever of
these I'm sorry the maximum of these two
so whichever one of these is kind of
closer they're right and then the
minimum versus the maximum of that right
and so if you look at what happens here
we're basically saying look if you you
know first of all take the the the box's
minimum spent you know the place where
the box starts and us so if we are
further if we're further to the left on
the number line if you will of this
thing we're gonna take the boxes one but
if we're further to the right we're
gonna take us and then we're gonna do
the same thing on the other side but for
the maximum values so if we're less than
the maximum value we're gonna keep
ourselves but if we're further we're
gonna take that so this just clips the
point effectively to inside the box
right and what we want to do we don't
have an element minimum do we or a
minimum that works on vectors I don't
know if we do we know
well we sort of do that we have that one
well but ounce I don't see one for
actuators um so if you take a look at
what this is doing its just producing a
a clipping of our point to the box
itself right and if we do this for each
of our sort of coordinates separately
then what we get is a point that is on
or inside the box that is the closest
point to us by definition right because
it tried to move to be as close to us as
it could be without exceeding the box at
that point I think we just take the
distance and we're done and I'm going to
make this a squared distance because
that felt that means we don't take the
square root which in a lot of cases is
all we would really need so why bother
taking square it you don't need to right
and so what I might do is break this
into two functions one is get closest
point in box and so this actually
returns us that point right so here's
the resulting P and then here where we
do the extra little closest distance now
I would just say like oh okay so closest
you know P that's something we needed to
do anyway oops so we might as well have
allow whoever is calling us to get
either one so they can choose whatever
they want to do here so then we can say
well the closest point you know is it's
here so the distance squared to it is
you know just this standard length
squared call right so I think that's all
we need and yeah I don't see what else
didn't either
what is it complaining about
I don't know what it's actually
complaining about to complete house with
you
what is the rectangle 3 defined to be
min and Max can ocular are from real 32
to vector 3
that closes the max that closes the min
and that's the comma what is the
complaint cannot convert argument 1 in
max so there is a max for that oh ok
nevermind we do it's right here I don't
know why I couldn't find it before I was
just looking it up stupid I guess so
that is exactly what we want we just
want that you know this is the element
min max right so you know this code now
is much easier right it's just Fox Max
min box min P right so that's all we
actually wanted I didn't know we had one
of those but I guess we do right ok so
now that we have that that makes it
easier to do our queries because now we
can just ask those questions about the
box
and that sort of makes me curious as
well like I'm now wondering like do we
have a min thing that happens here but
anywhere else no we don't I'm Sam yeah
anyway that's a typo
yeah so it should be the maximum of the
min and P like whichever one is higher
right and then the minimum of the
maximum and that sorry that was shifted
around all right so now we just need
this thing to actually call that
properly and so since we don't have a
min in the max here again I think that
means we want these boxes to have mins
and maxes in them but yeah so here's the
center half dem construction of that
thing like so and again I think like
just that repeated sort of asking what
the min and Max is it just means we
probably shouldn't be doing it that way
this is unnecessary now and I think now
we will get the lighting out relatively
reliable it will see so this is goodness
is devoxx squared and these are all
squared distances because we can compare
squared distances and never square root
anything in this case so I think that's
what we want so I think that will do
what we need and now we will be able to
get our actual lighting information out
when we do get lightly 4p that'll tell
us where the actual light is and also
what its color is which we can start to
test all right so a bunch of codes fam
doubt there let's get it working and
then we can proceed I think with with
what we need to do so you can see it's
kind of busted right you know just not
obviously completely wrong but also
obviously buggy so now we're gonna have
to start like figuring out what's going
on right so the first thing I would like
to do is just take a look at what the
actual code is returning so for example
like you know in just this part here I
would like to go see I don't know is
this is this release mode because I
probably want to change to debug mode
yeah so in debug mode what I'd like to
do is I'd like to take this lighting
solution here and say what are we
actually getting back in that routine
right so you know for this you can see
it's debug mode now so the framerate
slower I want to go into the lighting
code and just see that what's happening
in that test cast so here's the lighting
code here let me go to that test we
don't
well not that test cast the other test
cast so where is it should be right here
there it is so in this test cast from
probes where we're looking over this
stuff here what I'd like to do is just
have a thing where I take a look at this
and see because I know what the debug
light was actually set to I'd like to
see what this thing tells us right so if
you look inside the solution oops that
will have our debug light P in it
somewhere there it is so we know that
like this is what the light is supposed
to be at like that's where we should get
our results if the push happened
properly so let's see what we actually
get when we go into this light box thing
and and what it actually tells us so
when we go here we're gonna see
something right we've got a child count
which seems good there's two children I
don't know why because when I think
about it it feels like the number of
children should not be that in fact as
as I'm thinking about it what I really
want to do is step into the other part
so I'm assuming there should have only
been one actual light
so when we are builds facial this part
here where we do build face pressures
rear lighting this should have only
produced one child and that is not what
happened so I'm wondering if this actual
ah there you go so that was that was
wrong we were passing the the number of
boxes not the number of lights because
I'm like all right we shouldn't have
seen you know that that what I just saw
was not what we should have seen so you
know not good so now when we step
through here I should see a child kind
of one I'm hoping nope still - all right
never mind let's go just take a look in
there let's see what's going on because
I don't know maybe we're pushing a lot
more lights on there in fact you know
what I just realized we I guess we are
so because we probably are still pushing
on like the lights from the lamps and
stuff so you know maybe I should stop
doing that for testing purposes but yeah
okay so actual light count is eight so
okay - isn't isn't stupid then that's
fine let's go ahead and just run this if
I look at get lightly for pee now child
count of two well that's okay right
No no harm done we're gonna look through
it here try to find the closest one and
I'm hoping that the closest one is still
actually you know let's let's take a
look at what these distance Squared's
are here just in case that that's also
messy
so there's the min and the max that's
quite large so I guess that's hopefully
not a leaf node
I'm not really sure what's going on here
why are all these so similar I guess
maybe they could be right but why would
you need this many nodes just to divide
up eight lights this just seems nuts
something's wrong here so we got the
root light box index this way right
which I assume is the correct way to do
it but we should probably go check that
that's actually correct I mean I don't
really know okay so we should probably
figure that out
we're going in too and in fact I guess I
could look at the raycast to find out
yeah it looks like that so that works so
we're getting that box out we're going
through the children of it which i think
is correct
so we're iterating over the sources here
and then we're just trying to pick out
whatever the next best result is in this
case and I guess the problem is you know
we want the result too if we never found
something closer I guess we just want to
exit right so if the thing we found so
far was the closest thing then we don't
want to keep going but I would assume we
want to always expand down until we get
to something with no children although
maybe we wouldn't always do that but I
think you would look I don't know how
this didn't terminate like basically
right away something's weird there I'm
gonna have to go look at the tree
construction and find out what's going
on that doesn't really make any sense to
me to be honest with you so we can draw
that traversal out which we probably
will have to do and you know we'll
probably you know have to do it for like
one point or something like that I but
yeah like I just don't understand what
exactly is happening there with the
closest light
travursel that that that spatial
partition doesn't really make any sense
to me I'm not I'm not clear on what's
going on there because if you look at
what's happening oh wait this this also
what is this about that's I mean that
doesn't affect anything cuz we overwrite
it but that wasn't shouldn't have been
there either so this should be adding
all of the lightbox indexes here so that
they you know they occur in a row so
that the eight things that happen after
the root box root lightbox index here
right
I guess this should be a plus one so
that itself is not categorized maybe
that's what our problem is there but I
seems like there's probably more
problems than that we'll start there but
I'm really gonna have to step through
that construction and see what the heck
is going on and I also want to draw it
like I'd like to take this right here
and draw what that spatial walk looks
like for some known point so what I
might do is in get spatial or get
lightly for P right what I should
probably do is in here say okay for each
of these boxes that we get like draw the
box if this isn't the test right so
we'll do an is test case here and then
like the push debug box or I don't know
yeah that so push debug box should
probably go on here and in this I should
say for every single one of these you
know draw it right so
I guess we would draw it here let's say
so maybe this like that I don't know if
that's supposed to be a v4 yeah it is
and so what we can do here is say look
for will push down one test case and
we'll draw whatever the result is what
I'll do is rather than trying to
identify what test case we actually want
instead what I'll do is inside test cast
from probes what I'll do is I'll just
make a call here where I say okay at the
start
we'll just take something like maybe the
debug light position itself so we know
that you know debug light P should
always produce itself let's do a get
lightly for peek Hall where we take and
we draw exactly that walk like so and so
we can see if we're querying the actual
point where the light itself exists what
would we actually get right and then
these we just won't draw because it
would produce just a cacophony of cubes
and stuff that we don't you know would
make it hard for us to see what the heck
we were looking at right and so then we
should be able to see how that query
works we have probably have to turn off
lighting because we won't be able to
actually see the boxes themselves in
that walk with without turning off the
lighting but that's that's easy enough
again something I really this entire
time I keep saying I need to make
something that that turns us off a
hotkey and I keep not doing it just
because I'm in the middle of something
else and don't have the time so anyway
if we turn the lightning off and we look
just at what the actual box query
produces so you can see the box where
you happy
over here you can also see that it's
like totally wrong it's not even
including the the point we're at
ourselves so to me that seems to suggest
that our box metric is wrong like maybe
that function I did for like get closest
point for example is wrong because we're
drawing the same things that are in the
region so you know presumably it would
work properly at least the the picking
of the mass I don't actually know but
let's find out
so if we do get lightly for P here I
mean there's one other thing that could
be wrong right the other thing that
could be wrong is we could be picking
the correct index and then when we jump
to it no we can't because we're actually
pulling them out here alright nevermind
so I think I think that means our get
distance to Vox squared has to be wrong
which is fine and if we look here at it
I feel like this is probably fine that's
going to be in the get closest point in
box part meaning that when we do get
closest point to in box if we assume
that this returns the correct value it
would be pretty hard for this to be
wrong because all it's doing is saying
well the length between these two return
that right so if we look at get closest
point in box here where we've got the
box and the P like is that actually
producing a reasonable value for the
closest point on the box if we take a
look at the maximum of the minimum and
the P vibes that's put in there you know
again I I guess I should look at these
functions and make sure that these
functions are operating the way you
would expect but they sure seem to be
right there doesn't seem to be anything
untoward happening there so that that
seems fine so when we're taking the min
and the max here I feel like that should
produce the closest point on the box
let's just verify that by drawing it out
and then we'll see and then I can also
sort of draw I could draw those points
as well
just to see what's whether we're finding
them correctly which is another thing I
can do
but anyway so if we imagine so each of
these things is happening sort of on an
axis separately so I don't think it will
matter how many dimensions we use 1 2 or
3 so let's just do it in 2 just just a
double check since that should give us
everything we need so basically we're
gonna pass in some p-value here right
and that could be inside the box as well
we don't really know it's outside the
box let me do it like this
so it's completely outside then we'll
try one that's completely inside but
what we're saying is well okay so let's
suppose we look at just the x axis right
of this thing and what we're saying is
okay there's three points involved okay
this is the min this is its this is the
Max and here's the p value if we look at
the p value itself what we're gonna find
is that we take the min and the max of
it right so we're taking the mach the
max of the men and the P so here's the
min and here's the P which is the
maximum value of these two things right
and so if the P is on this side let's
take another point which is Q and that's
inside the box right so in the case of P
in the min we're gonna end up with the
minimum point right in the case of Q and
the min we're gonna end up with Q
because we're taking the maximum so
we're taking the one that's the furthest
to this way right that's what should be
happening all right so in the case of P
in the min we're gonna take this and
give Q them in we're gonna take this
right which is exactly what we would
want and then we're gonna shove that
through a minimum call for the Box Max
right so that's this guy here right so
the Box Max if that is further this way
it's going to be selected otherwise
we're just going to keep whatever we had
and in that case right so in the P case
we're gonna end up picking this point in
the Q case we're gonna end up picking
this point that is the closest point on
the box in both cases I don't see a lot
wrong with this that seems pretty good
to me
[Music]
to be completely honest with you so I'm
not really seeing what's going wrong
there so one thing I can do is break
this out a little bit more so let's
suppose we go into the get light leaf
for peak law and instead of doing it
this way I actually did it manually so
I'm actually going to do this where I
asked for the closest point in the box
first like that and then I take the
length squared myself so this should not
in any way change like this routine
should behave exactly the same way as it
was being anything all I'm gonna do is
actually take the length squared myself
in this routine and now we should get no
difference right so the the diagram that
I see now that pops up with the boxes on
the side of the map there should be
exactly the same and it is right that's
exactly what we saw the first time no
worries right
and so if I then say well okay now show
me the actual line here what I should be
able to do is say if this is a test case
right I should be able to ask for each
box that I was testing and maybe we push
this in there which one of these
actually turns out to be closest so if I
draw like the closest one the one we end
up picking in yellow and I turn and I
draw the test cases let's say in like
you know the the gray or whatever it is
right like that then when I should be
able to do is actually draw a debug line
that tells me where the closest P
actually was or you know where we think
that was so this would tell me for each
of these which one we thought was best
right
and if it turns out to be closest then
that's you know well we can actually
draw that one as well
right so we know which one we ended up
thinking was the best so I don't know if
this will be clear enough of a clear
enough diagram for us to actually look
at but we're gonna try it and see here's
us drawing
our thing you know our closest you know
which one is the closest point kind of a
thing and if you look at it you know I
would say that it seems right on this
one anyway I mean the biggest thing that
I'm noting is just the boxes are all
over there it makes me think that maybe
the problem is we're just not adding the
light sources somehow because the
closest point query seems pretty good I
don't know what to tell you
I don't I don't see a lot of evidence of
this being bad it looks like it's doing
exactly all right thing so what what I
would say might be going on there is our
thing that actually builds the spatial
partition might just not be adding all
of the actual lights that need to be
added or something like that or there
it's adding them in the wrong way like
this is not doing what it needs to do
you know what I'm saying to you so like
we should probably look and see like the
solutions scratch a thing I feel like
maybe I need to go see what the heck
that stuff is doing because it may just
not be doing the right stuff I I don't
know let's go take a look
so if we go to add box reference what
you can see here is just pushing these
onto the Box table that is what I would
expect I now need to go look at what the
scratch stuff is supposed to do so if I
look at what scratch a is supposed to do
so you can see me like recording this
thing into the scratch array and I guess
that right there would be the problem so
and in fact this right here when we do
an Box reference the Box ref count is is
the only thing that's added so again I
think that's actually fine
so add box storage is the only thing
that adds more information right so this
is a problem because this will affect
the count that we actually loop through
and so this should probably be this to
avoid this being an issue and then we
probably also in here where we do this
stuff and add these references this is
going to have to actually keep up with
that so when we add a box reference
we're going to have to make sure that
that actually does something so it would
have to look like this right it's not
pretty
but that is probably what would have to
happen and again we can kind of maybe
work on this a little bit and make this
code nicer I kind of want to get it
working the way that it's going right
now and just see if we can get it into
some better shape so let's try to work
with this and get this you know keeping
everyone happy so when we actually add
this box reference here we need to put
in to the scratch array I think at this
location I would assume anyway solution
plus root lightbox index right plus one
I would think this would actually
properly seed that array so that when we
came down here to do this it would work
maybe I'm wrong about that
so I guess another problem here would be
just this overwrite any event and I
don't really know I don't think so
but I'm not sure
in the case that there is a light we
packed these indices together by sort of
putting them off in their own thing
right and I guess the scratch array yeah
it's just really there for doing the
indices does this add box yes so these
just get appended on at the end of it
anyway and for these we just added an
actual new box for each of them so they
get their own indices right because when
you add box storage
well you know actually no you don't so
how was this exactly supposed to work am
I missing something here when you add
the box storage on you're getting back
an index to an actual box right but when
you add a reference to a box you're
adding on what what is going on because
so when you add box storage it doesn't
add an actual reference it just
increments the box count and that
doesn't really make any sense because in
that case how did we do we actually just
split these so that we don't expect
actual children to be to be sort of
referenced now because these are working
exactly the same way what the hey does
anyone else is anyone else confused by
this or am I the only person who's like
I don't get it because I don't I don't
see how this helps us I don't see how
this actually works at all right
because when you get out here you add
the Box references well okay so I guess
this is the thing that does it for you
you place these things into your
temporary and then you just add the Box
references here so I guess that does
make sense all right I can believe that
right sure so I guess that's fine and we
do that in the scratch buffer so
everyone's fine with that right
and it should be fine I guess I don't
know whether that use of the scratch
referee and the sorcerer right here
actually creates a problem for us though
looking at what happens here you can see
that they ping-pong right as they go
down but I'm assuming that that's okay
because you never really need to
it's never gonna overflow into the area
where we wrote these things
I don't think of course maybe that's
also wrong maybe there should be a
scratch sieve it's just for this
trying to think of how I want to do this
so what I might want to do is just use a
scratch see for this I think I might do
that right now just to make it easier on
us so I think I might do this where we
just say look there's gonna be a scratch
see the scratch see is gonna have these
in there it's not going to do ad box
reference it's just gonna remember them
in a scratch buffer we won't do this
we'll put this down here so that it
happens at the end just the same way as
everybody else and then this will just
use scratch see and we will make another
scratch buffer all right so I'm gonna do
that and the main reason for that is
nothing to do with anything other than I
want to make it easier this debugging
there's too many index arrays and I
don't like having them sitting around
for no apparent reason yes I'm sorry I
changed sides of that structure I didn't
remember the program was running so I'm
gonna do that to make it a little easier
on myself so this way I can because I'm
gonna have to debug that routine that
builds the indices and I think I might
have been doing it wrong in fact yep hey
what a surprise just doing that fixed it
because I was like I that looks wrong to
me because it's using references in a
place where it should have been using
hard indexes and vice versa so now it
looks like we're correctly finding the
light right you can see that I'm always
finding that light of mine and you can
see I'm properly testing other locations
of light sources so that seems better
and now maybe we can take the test cast
and and make it actually do something
useful here right so let's go ahead and
and try turning the lighting back on now
that we think we've got a reasonable
light spatial query there and see what
happens just to give us a sense of like
where we are at in the debugging process
so what I'm anticipating seeing right is
you know row
tively straightforward use of this light
source but also like things that are
closer to other light yet other light
sources use them instead right
so that actually does a pretty good job
of actually doing sort of crappy
lighting for the world and you can see
that it's it's not what we want because
we still have a lot of things where like
something is you know there's no
secondary lighting and it's kind of crap
it's doing hard shadows and all that
stuff so it's not we want but you can
now see that we're getting per-pixel
lighting actually queried even just with
this test cast but it's properly finding
like the light source to use for various
rooms and crap like this right so I
think that's better and I think that
we're off to a good start
so now what we need to do is we need to
actually move into the second phase
where we're doing our casting we want to
start using real casting there and like
I said so now we need some way of saying
when we're actually doing these casts
what direction are we casting in and we
need to figure out a way how we would
insert the light source into those casts
as well right so all this stuff kind of
has to start coming together and yeah in
order to do that I think we're gonna
have to start let's let's start by by
just figuring out how we're gonna read
our test sphere and to do that I would
like to jump over to our handmade
sampling spheres generation program
because I think we kind of don't need
like this cube side weight stuff anymore
so I think the sample Direction part is
probably all we actually will need and
we can load in those sample directions I
don't know exactly what we're gonna do
about shoving the lights or stuff in
there but we'll you know take it one
step at a time and so if I go to the
light sampling sphere part of things
actually I guess I want to do it this
way then what you can see is we have an
HH s-- fear app that we use that we made
that the base little sign app it's just
a little program app is infected
everything it's just a little
utility and what it does is it generates
a nicely distributed samples fear for us
and the only thing it doesn't do yet is
clump these things by direction what we
want to do eventually is clump them by
direction so that's a big to do that
we're gonna have to do here but what we
can do right off the bat is we don't
have the cube side weight nonsense
anymore that's not actually gonna have
to be in there so we can delete that and
delete the printout for that as well so
all of the stuff for like weights can
just go oops all the stuff that had to
do with weights is it doesn't have to be
in here and that's good because it
simplifies the process down for us so
you know get rid of that get rid of this
this
and now our HH sphere app is ready to
generate something for us that will
presumably not have this in it anymore
let's kill this buffer and ask for that
so this thing oops right so what we want
this thing to do is is generate us well
we want to generate our our sort of test
sphere if we look at how it was called
originally I hope we saved that
somewhere I don't know if we actually
did let's take a look looks like we
didn't but what we need to know there is
how many array bundles you want there to
be and how many different spheres you
want there to be and if we look at what
we've got in our INL at the moment which
I guess I will have to load again
handmade code now it looks like we were
doing 16 Spears and 18 ray bundles purse
fear now in terms of how many ray
bundles we actually cast I would say you
know I don't know 18 does seem kind of
high to be completely honest I'm not
sure that's necessary but okay so let's
suppose that was the case you know I
think what we're gonna do is say that
the Ray bundles purse fear we're just
gonna do 16 18 and now and I think I
know what I want to do after that so
we're gonna say this fear count is 16
the Ray bundle count is 18 the
destination INL is obviously the same
place that's handmade sampling stairs
dyno and off we go
I'm gonna kill this buffer this thing
will hopefully do a pretty good job
relaxing all of our relaxation Abul
relaxers as you can see it is trying
that right now and this is just trying
to produce a nicely uniformly
distributed sphere
and I don't actually know am I supposed
to terminate this when it's low enough
or does it terminate itself because I
don't actually really remember
so it will look for a min separation
distance and it looks like we are not
super convinced about that but and
what's it printing out the max closest
point min closest point distance min Max
separation last min max separation right
and I mean that number is still going
down so it is still getting better right
I guess
which I don't know what that is so
that's just the the measure we ended up
using which was not particularly
fantastic I guess is the min/max
separation so the the distance between
the minimum to the closest two points
and the furthest two points is what
we're using and and I guess that value
there is the improvement and so it is
still like improving it just keeps on
improving and improving right
and if the min/max separation is less
than 0.25 so I guess we just assume this
will eventually get down there do we
really need our sphere to be this
tightly packed I guess we do I have no
idea I mean Who am I to say it's crazy
like it does seem to really go down
quite low I probably should have
compiled in release mode now to think
about it because we're actually probably
quite slow because this is all in debug
mode but I don't know that I want to
actually stop it now because it's almost
there right although I am kind of
curious company I want to see how much
faster it is
there yeah yeah well release notes a bit
faster just a bit alright so anyway that
should have given us our INL right so
oops now we've got one that just doesn't
have the weights so you can see here
we've got just our big table and all
this table has on it is the sample
direction right so if we want to do that
let me see here how we're actually
producing this yeah so all we're doing
is just just taking the point in there
so looking at this inside handmade
lighting if we wanted to start sort of
doing these raycast what I'm gonna do is
maybe just drop that right into here as
a test so you know maybe we start by
taking for each light probe will
actually just do a ray cast the way that
we would be doing it inside the normal
rake a stir and we'll sum those together
and that will give us the sort of the
light result well I guess we don't we
can't believe that because we need we
need to start distributing the light
around so assuming that that's our new
lighting sample sphere that just does
doesn't have the the weights involved
there so maybe I won't start this today
we can now start considering calling the
actual real function and the only thing
we don't have now and you know we want
to start targeting light sources as well
but the only thing we don't have now is
in compute light propagation the only
thing we can't do is we can't actually
use the voxel irradiance from the
previous frame to contribute to this
frame and this function doesn't actually
do anything right and so this function
has to be written
and the other thing that has to be
written and I don't know if we actually
even sketched it out yet is that every
time we go to initialize the lighting I
think we just clear the voxel and what
we need to do is actually be keeping the
voxel around so what you can see here is
when we go to begin lighting computation
and here's the stuff that computes where
the voxel is we don't actually do
anything here to try to update the
contents of the voxel so here's what we
need to do next weekend right here we
need to do a thing that like copies
contents of the old voxel to the correct
location in the new voxel and then the
other thing we need to do is compute
irradiance and here we just need to run
the same basic algorithm as we're
running in the pixel shader you know to
a first approximation it doesn't have to
be exact but something similar to that
to get whatever the irradiance would
have been at this point using like a we
probably what we'll do is we'll take the
specular bounce part out of it so we'll
just be using basically diffuse
transmission for the second for
secondary lighting and so in the case
where the thing hits a emitter it'll
just use the emitter and and if it if it
doesn't it doesn't so then in the
raycast here where we're doing so you
know this for example where we're doing
the raid erection for dirt to light
right and then in here we're picking up
the directions on our sampling sphere
what I want to do here is is have us do
have us find a random light source that
we're gonna pick out of the light
sources that are close to this light
probe right and I again not totally sure
exactly
we would want to do that but I guess
what we'd say is anything that's close
enough to expand we expand and put in an
array and then we randomly pick someone
from the array to sample would probably
be how I would do it just just when I'm
kind of vaguely guessing so you know
we've got the sample point entropy here
that we're using and so you know we do
something like use that sample point
entropy you know like this this
basically to randomly pull from a light
source or something so instead of doing
direction to light like this instead
what we would do is we would pick four
random points on the light source since
these light sources are area light
sources or whatever and we'd cast
towards that right and so in here we
would say well alright let's you know
let's build an array of the end closest
lights to us or something so if you
imagined here you had like you know and
closest lights or whatever and you know
I don't know how many there would
exactly be but there would be some and
we would have a find closest lights and
we would do this sort of thing right and
then coming out of this we would say
okay let's pick one of those and I guess
actually we need these to be the actual
boxes right so these probably need to be
like something more like that right and
then what we would do is say all right
so coming out of that we've got the end
closest lights and what we now need to
do is pick a random one so we would say
n closest lights and we would take you
know something like this
right so pick a random one of the lights
out of here
to do the you know the starting sort of
sample and maybe we need this thing to
be slightly different right we may not
want it to be based on the same thing
that's picking these directional samples
for some obvious reasons because that
that may affect like you know maybe we
want that so they're just jittered
separately in here we would say okay we
pick out one of those you know for our
bias towards light and then what we
would do is pick some random points on
that light source so you know we
probably wouldn't want to do this
exactly although right now we maybe will
but in the future we'll want to like
pick random points inside the actual
light volume itself and so then what we
will do is bias towards those so we will
you know for now we could pick it where
we do bias towards light here's the you
know the position and then off we go but
in the future what we do is we'd pick
for actual points on there and I don't
know if we have any functions for doing
that but that's what we would do we can
expand this out a little bit and say
that well the raid erection I also don't
know if this needs to be normalized to
be completely honest I'm not sure why it
would have to be I don't know that
there's anything in here that actually
cares about that
you know I really don't know that there
is this inversion I would think would
take care of any non-normalized aspect
of the t-value
so I want to say that you probably just
don't even care I mean I don't know
we'll have to double check that because
when we wrote that routine I don't
remember whether whether we needed to
end up with that that inversion should
presumably just take care of it so I
think what you could really do here is
actually just do like a point on light
right and then the REA direction would
actually just loft up the light probe P
which we already have so this thing here
we could really do the REA direction is
just the point on light - the REA origin
right and that would give us the initial
ray Direction bias towards the light
source and off you would go so in order
to get this working what we would need
and this is also a to do here like this
needs to sample one extra right so
really what has to happen here and this
is kind of nuts is this maybe needs to
do that I guess
well that even that won't really work
because we need it to update it at the
end and the point is like when this
thing updates its gonna it's not gonna
do the last one right and that's the
problem so I don't know exactly how we
want this thing to play out but we have
a problem there where we would be
sampling off the wrong part of the
buffer right so we need there to be like
an extra maybe there to be like padding
in here if that makes sense so like to
do you know add padding and increase by
one to account for the extra slot used
by the light bias so that would all just
work but we need to kind of just add
some padding there otherwise will fetch
off the end of this array which we don't
want to do
who knows what that will do right so in
here when we do point on light you know
for now we can do this as actually that
but in the future we can pick some
different random points in that light
volume and and obviously I think that
would be better so really what we'll end
up with is this we're fine closest
lights needs to actually do something
yeah and I think that's basically it so
we'll leave it there
and next weekend what we'll have to do
is actually push through this part of it
which is mostly I don't think there's
going to be that much debugging of this
stuff because I think we've already
spent a fair bit of time to bugging this
stuff now but what we're gonna have to
spend all our time on next weekend is
figuring out how the heck to do updating
of our voxel field right because that's
the big thing we don't know this stuff
here spam voxel we just don't know how
we're gonna do it right and so until we
get that straightened away we're kind of
dead in the water and so that's gonna be
the thing that's that's really that
we're gonna have to then pull onto and
and and you know and figure out how to
do let's go ahead and go to the QA here
what does the go-to assembler for 64-bit
code on Windows these days is Masum
still maintained or people moving to
NASM it's yeah so the answer there as
far as I know is NASM so if you want to
do assembler typically it's NASM so it's
this thing I guess I don't necessarily
know why but I believe the reason is
because it's actually been updated to
support like generating stuff like
PlayStation 4 fineries and stuff like
this or you know that's not the NASM we
men
so I don't actually know look I want to
say that some some of the rad folks like
help with it too
I'm not sure I don't know how to
actually search any of this stuff
why does SourceForge even still exist is
the real question
yeah I don't know my understanding was
like that's what people use I don't
really know why necessarily but I think
it's because it's had the most updating
and so like if you're going to assemble
code with it you've got the highest
chance of it actually producing binary
that can be linked with modern
executables so things that are you know
have to go through code signing things
that have to that have to pass some kind
of a like check LLVM check that you know
that Sony requires before you ship a
PlayStation binary crap like that right
and so I don't actually know I don't
actually know if there's any other
reason why people use it other than it
kind of just got settled on for that and
it's the one that's been the most patch
for that because I mean like there's
also just like why azzam and stuff right
and I don't know why like you wouldn't
use this one and you would use the other
one or something I just I just don't
know they both like for my purposes like
building now hash and stuff things like
that that I wanted to use an assembler
for I didn't notice a huge difference
between the two like it just kind of
works either way
and so I don't really know like I'm
guessing again that it cuz an assembler
is not a particularly crazy thing so I
don't really know exactly where the
where the differences are that matter
I'm gonna go ahead and assume that X 13
pixels answered the question about
remedy BJ since he is the person who
wrote it do you think with all recent
processor vulnerabilities being found
that future processors will use a
fundamentally different optimizing
architecture
I guess I don't know I really am not
sure I guess what I would say is my
guess would be that in in the future I
could see a switching to some kind of
thing where we actually had partitioned
cores you know I could imagine something
where like you actually just have these
like security cores that are running
like code from the web and then you have
like actual secure cores that insecure
core is that that are fast or something
I could believe it because I feel like
they're gonna keep squeezing more and
more sort of leakage like like black
hats are gonna be able to take advantage
of every last little bit of leaky
execution and at some point what that
means is that fundamentally the
optimizations you can put into a
processor core either they're always
making the chip faster or you can't use
them because anything that makes a chip
faster only in some circumstances is now
a security hole for like it leaks
information right which was going to be
exploited by someone at some point and
and so I I don't know I do think that
there there's a possibility that we just
won't have symmetric optimizations
anymore and you'll end up with things
where it's it's largely asymmetric
perhaps so it's like hey you know if you
know you're doing scientific computing
and you're the only person on this
computer and it's unplugged from the
internet anyway you just maybe you just
run
the on the fastest possible core setting
whereas if you're like a datacenter
running like multiple things on one
machine you're gonna have to set the
dial over to paranoid mode and all of
the cores are slower because they can't
actually do you know any of the actual
things that you want for for
opportunistic optimization right I don't
know what's the go-to thing for learning
assembly no idea read the read the
disassembly of your compiler I mean
would be one big way right god bolt you
know look at look at what your compiler
is generating because that kind of
teaches you how anything that you know
how to type and see how it comes out as
assembly and so you can kind of get a
really quick understanding of what's
going on doing that and just playing
with it if assemblers are better when
you consider programming an x86 arm
directly whichever you're trying to
target primarily for everything maybe it
would auto translate on the back end and
you could rewrite critical sections for
secondary platforms I mean the answer is
no because a sufficiently good assembler
is a high level language right if the
question is would I like my language to
be continuous from assembly up to high
level constructs the answer is yes
absolutely it's the primary problem with
modern languages is they don't provide a
continuous way to refine your program
down to manual assembler right I mean
that's what all languages always should
provide and so I definitely think that's
a good idea but you wouldn't call that
an assembler anymore
I mean because this an assembler is a
term specifically used to refer to
something that does not do any advanced
language constructs really right macro
assembler is about the most advanced
thing you're really supposed to be doing
before you would have to
call it a language its own language
right and I mean to a certain extent I
don't really even know if you can call a
macro assembler and assembler because at
some point if those macros are powerful
enough they're really constituting a
language and so you really shouldn't
call it assembly language because it's
not it's assembly language plus at the
very least right and so I think you're
really we're really splitting hairs
there if we want to look at it but I
mean that's my that's my opinion any
sufficiently advanced assembler is now
its own language which is great and I'm
interested in looking at it but I
wouldn't call it an assembler anymore
it's it's a new language called whatever
you called it right do you never write
ups to learn to how to avoid CC poses
runtown on windows by martins mosaic Oh
on the handmade hero forum but for Linux
I don't I think that would be a good
article but no I don't I don't know
all right that's it for the Q's let's
wrap things up close down remedy oops
didn't actually mean to close that but
will close that as well alrighty thank
you everyone for joining me for the
episode of handmade he wrote sort of
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with a
series at home you can always pre-order
the game at hand meteor organ it comes
with all the source code right now
so you can play around with it yourself
maybe you want to try doing your own
averaging of the voxel and that probably
good exercise for the week it's a tough
problem though I don't know the answer
offhand we're gonna try and figure it
out next weekend but you could give it a
shot and see what you come up with until
then have fun programming everyone and
I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody