there we go hello everyone and welcome
to handmade hero the show recode a
complete game live on stream no engines
do libraries it's just us and we do all
of the programming on the game so every
last little bit anything in the game
that needs to get done we do it and we
show exactly how it gets done so what
we're doing right now is we're actually
working on kind of the last piece of our
asset system it's the memory management
and I talked a little bit yesterday
about the kinds of things that we need
to do with this asset system and today I
wanted to kind of do a very simple
implementation of it just so people
could kind of see the very basic nature
of it and then from there we'll kind of
move on to what we sort of think we
might need to do for a more serious
shipping version right and so yesterday
I kind of prep the code for it and today
I'll just go ahead and do sort of the
obvious thing and off we go all right if
you would like to code along with me
today is day 1 58 you can go ahead and
unzipped a 157 source code into a
directory and that is the source code
that I'm starting with today and so I
will go ahead and get started and what
we can do today you know there are some
questions in the pre stream someone was
asking if you can just use virtual
memory to solve this problem with of the
of the address spaces and so on and I
was saying that well you know if you if
you want to require a 64-bit address
space for the game that's totally you
know that that could be but if not then
you run the risk of blowing out the page
table like like running out of space in
the in the virtual page table and
windows you've got like other issues to
worry about in 32-bit that make it maybe
potentially not such a good idea now
we've never decided that we have to ship
a 32-bit version of handmade hero right
so I don't want to say oh you know don't
do that or or whatever because we need
to ship 3d vision I don't know you know
when it comes time to ship handmade hero
we can you know sort of think about
things like that so what guess what I'd
say there is you know we could decide to
just program primarily 260 for a bit and
then worry about downgrading to 32-bit
at the end of the
logically we want to ship it if we
decide we need to you know that's not
the end of the world you can do that
sort of stuff our code will not be
architected in such a way as to make
that an impossible thing to do but like
I said I don't know you know I don't
know if we want to do that or not it's
certainly something that's a plausible
decision these days like you could very
well make reasonable money on a game
that only supported 64 a bit operating
systems but at the same time it's like
well you know are you willing to
potentially give up a certain segment of
the market who just simply can't play
the game now because it's it's only 32
bit right because we know it's out there
we know fifteen percent of the Steam
users don't have 64 bit operating
systems right and so it's just something
to think about there but what I could
show here since i already said like I
want to do one version of the system
that's very basic just so you can kind
of see what the idea is what i could do
is show you how to do it doing it that
way with the 64 bit memory face that you
know something that would work with
64-bit memory space for sure but that
probably wouldn't work so well in 32-bit
and then you know we can maybe move on
from there that way people who want to
do it that way you can see how to do it
it's very very straightforward you've
already seen the virtual alec call and
that's really all you really need is
virtual alec and virtual free so i can
show you how to do that and maybe that's
what to do today because like i said we
need to build the simple version first
anyway so here's where we're at here's
the asset system right and if we run the
asset system I've intentionally oops we
already loaded that I've intentionally
made it so that we really constrained
the memory for the asset system so that
because it's not capable of doing any of
this virtual memory stuff that I've
talked about what happens now is as soon
as i try to instantiate a hero we
immediately hit the assertion that says
we're out of space in the asset system
right you can see here this it's on a
push size call in the arena so basically
what happens is the load bitmap call
tries to load in some of the hero assets
it goes to do the push size and it's
just plain out of memory in the arena
like that's the end of it right and so
what are you gonna do right
so if we want to try to address that
problem what we would need to do is we
need to start coming up with ways of
seeing whether or not we're running out
of memory and if we are running out of
memory we have to evict assets you know
older assets or something so that we can
ensure that we always have enough memory
to load in new assets that we know that
we're going to need shortly right so
let's go ahead and change first to doing
an allocation scheme that just gets the
memory from the operating system and
then releases the memory back to the
operating system every time that we want
to load an asset okay because we can do
that very easily by going through
handmade platform and on a 64-bit
operating system this is probably
something you could just go ahead and
ship like I don't suspect you would have
a lot of problems with it virtual Alex
should probably be reasonably fast on
you know on on Windows I would think I
don't know we could certainly time it
and make sure that that's the case but
if we wanted to hear right we could just
go ahead and say that our platform api
was going to get the ability to
generically get memory from the
operating system and return memory from
the operating system right and that
would look something like platform you
know allocate memory and platform
deallocate memory and we could actually
leave these in here as well for another
reason which is that one thing we might
want to do a little later on when I kind
of wrap up memory stuff because we're
going to go over a few things sort of
towards the end of the engine work
another thing I can show you how to do
once we have the concept of platform
allocate memory and dll cape memory
right is we can go ahead and make it so
that instead of allocating all the
memory up front in the game we can make
it so that it just grows ad infinitum so
that if you want to do a run of handmade
here where you just say you know what
use as much memory as you want just keep
on going have a party we could do that
right it's actually really easy we
wouldn't we don't have to change any of
the code that we've got it will all just
work there just a couple of minor
modifications and since I know that
people ask about that a lot
it's something I could show so I'm not
even going to call these debug because
I'm just going to say that we may just
allow them to be actual platform calls
and you know whether we actually ship a
version that allows it to ever call it I
don't know if we'll do that or not but
point being it'll be fine with me either
way so let me show you how these would
work they're really really
straightforward most of you probably
already know what that's going to look
like really all this is is we would take
and an ad in here some kind of a
platform allocate memory call and all it
would do was return you a pointer when
you pass it a size right so you would
call in and you would pass it a size
like so that and then we would obviously
need the corresponding deallocate call
which just does a standard free right so
here we go this is going to be platform
okay memory and we're going to need the
same thing for deallocate memory right
and all that's going to do is take that
pointer and create the corresponding
call right so if we wanted to be able to
get more memory for the operating system
on demand that's the only thing that
really needs to happen it's very very
straightforward and in order to
implement that in windows again you've
pretty much already seen the call the
calls happen that we would need they are
also really straightforward so again
this is really just for everyone who's
watched handmade hero since the
beginning this should be a total walk in
the park really really really
straightforward so if you take a look at
how this works we'd have our platform
allocate memory platform deallocate
memory and there they are win32 allocate
memory and then to to deallocate memory
and so we really don't even have to do
anything new you've already seen it it's
just this virtual Alec idea right and I
assume we also did virtual free at some
point yes we did
okay and so if you take a look at how
these work again super super basic we
just have a call to the operating system
that says we would like to allocate some
virtual memory we go ahead and you know
ask what the size of it is we know that
that's been passed in now so just
whatever the user asked for we can
commit it right and then we return that
and if it fails it fails we return a
null pointer doesn't matter it still
works just fine the caller that knows
they couldn't get anymore remember from
the operating system which is what we
would want same is true for D allocating
memory and again these are just so
simple there's nothing to them we don't
even need to think about this API it's
just totally basic and there's really
much yeah there's really absolutely
nothing to it so we've got the virtual
free virtual free takes whatever the
memory is and releases it right that's
it and we could double check there I
don't know if virtual free allows you to
pass 0 pointers but we could double
check that's all she wrote really really
straightforward so if you come in here
and add those to our platform api table
we've got allocate memory empty allocate
memory 32 allocate memory and through to
deallocate memory right and that would
be all we would need to do now we can
just go ahead and allocate and
deallocate memory all we want and off
you go so there's a couple things to
think about here right temporarily if we
did this we would no longer be able to
use our looped live co-editing correctly
right because when we do those virtual
Alex virtual freeze those pieces of
memory are not going to get written out
right if you think about it so when we
reload memory the memory is going to be
the same as it was at the end of the
loop point right so that's something
think about just just for a second I'm
going to push forward because you don't
care about that particular thing right
now but that's going to be something
that we have to address in a little bit
if we decided to keep this scheme going
if we replace the scheme with a block
allocator like I was sort of saying then
we don't care because it just gets
written that properly so just keep that
in the back of your mind that this would
break loop live code editing because
we're not saving these buffers out now
it's still pretty easy for us to fix
that and you know that's sort of a
separate issue but yeah all right so
here we go let's go into our handmade
asset stuff and show what we would do
now to start to sort of a to start to
address the problem that we were having
so when we do our load bitmap call again
we end up in a situation where doing the
load bitmap call we need to make sure
that we can actually get the amount of
memory that we need and at the moment we
don't really know very much about well
we don't really know much about any of
this we don't really know what we can
safely free all we know is how much
memory we're actually going to need and
so what I talked about at the end of
last stream is that what we need to do
here is we need to make there be a safe
way we can free enough memory to allow
us to load the bitmap that we want to
load and so the question becomes how
much of that you know how do we want to
approach that problem we can't just
start freeing memory inside load bitmap
because load bitmap is called in the
middle of frames which may be using some
of the bitmaps that are on our list
right so we can't very well go and just
free some memory arbitrarily because if
we were going to free memory arbitrarily
like that we would end up in a bit of a
bind so we have a couple different
options certainly we have a couple ways
we could choose to try to address that
but you know i'm not sure what would be
the most efficacious way one way to
address that would be to buffer up all
the requests to load bitmaps another one
would be and i talked about both these
would be to always key
some amount of memory free that's like
roughly commensurate you know basically
always making sure that we kind of do
the allocates and then do the freeze
later and since we're just showing the
simplest possible way to do that I'm
going to take the approach that we're
not going to hit a hard limit just yet
we're going to have basically a soft
limit if that makes sense so let me show
you how to do that inside the asset
system what I'm going to do is I'm going
to start tracking how much memory it's
actually using right so going to make it
in you 60 for here that's like total
memory used okay and when we start up i
am going to initialize that so that
assets total member used is 0 right
pretty straightforward what I will then
do is every time we load something I'm
going to have it go through a call that
actually accounts for the memory that
it's going to get right so something
like you know allocate or acquire asset
memory right and in that call you'll
pass like the game assets thing and you
will pass the size that you wanted and
then what we'll do is we'll just do the
allocation there and we'll increment the
amount of memory used by the size right
so we do something like result equals
flat allocate memory at that size and
then we will add the size and I guess we
should assume that only if we actually
allocate it you know return that size
okay so that's that's pretty
straightforward right
okay so that'll do you acquire asset
memory and then what we want to do here
is do something where we release memory
so we'll do a release asset memory and
give it back to the system so what we'll
do there is say okay we'll call that
here is our void pointer right and the
problem that will have here is we
actually need to be able to know what
the size of that memory actually was
right so we need to pass the size into
our freeing function as well which is
kind of a little janky but you know we
just that's what we need to track it so
for now we'll just actually go ahead and
pass that in and so what that will do is
that will call platform release memory
right oops sorry deallocate memory
rather with the memory and assuming that
memory was non zero right we'd also do
assets total memory used minus equal
size right now since this is always
going to be is this is not gonna be
threaded at the moment we don't have to
worry about that fact but if we were
going to start calling from multiple
threads we would have to make sure that
we actually did sort of a atomic add or
atomic decrement for these but since we
don't currently have any plans to do
that that's actually okay but just keep
that in mind that you know that would
not be safe if we started calling it
from like up in here it with load asset
work started to do you know stuff with
that or that sort of thing if that makes
sense um you know what's kind of
interesting here is should also put it
to do in here to do Casey this doesn't
actually handle the file stream down
case does it because the memory stays
and so on so I feel like this actually
needs to be something I feel like I feel
like this kind of needs to happen
regardless or something like that in
fact you know what I'm just going to do
this I think what we actually wanted is
this it's the final state but assuming
that the file read failed we would do
something here where
were like you know if there was an error
reading the file we should put a bogus
data in there whatever right like maybe
just zero the memory something like that
you know this I feel like that's the
same thing to do zero size do we have a
zero size like we do we do anyway moving
on so inside platt what is that actually
called they're inside platt we should
have that pointer obviously we don't
know it's called platform sorry platform
there we go okay so here we've got a
thing that will allocate memory for us
and here we've got to think that will
release memory for us right and so what
we can do is we can do something that
allows us to quickly allocate free our
memory so what we can do here is say
okay in this case when we want bitmap
memory instead of doing this push sighs
we'll just do an acquire asset memory
will pass it the game assets and the
memory size all right and the same thing
would be true inside our sound thing
instead of doing the push size we just
do a acquire asset memory and we pass it
the assets and the size that we actually
wanted right and that's pretty
straightforward he now our game would
just run and it would just get more
memory from the operating system so now
everything just kind of works and we
don't have a problem anymore but we
still do have the problem of we're
actually just taking in our returning
amount of memory right which is not what
we wanted certainly so let's go continue
down this path so now what we need to do
is we need to take a look at that actual
amount of asset memory that we have that
we are actually using and potentially
start to free things in the case where
it gets a little bit too high right and
so how would we do that well what we'd
want to do is do this at a control point
during a frame where we know that we
don't have any risk of anyone using
any of the assets for hot like being you
know currently working with any of the
assets right so if we if we went into
handmade cpp and we basically you know
at the end of the frame when everything
is all said and done and we end all the
temporary memory and everything's kind
of cleaned up right what we can do at
that point is say okay now would be a
good time for the asset system to
jettison any assets that it thinks it
needs to to get it back down to a
reasonable working set size right so we
could do like free assets as necessary
right or like evict assets as necessary
and we would call that the trans state
assets we would just do it like that
right and so what we are essentially
doing is creating a fixed point in time
so that we can again avoid having to
make everything super multi threaded
blocking light stuff for no apparent
reason we can just make it so there's a
particular point in time after
everything all's been done for the frame
where we just allow the asset system a
little bit of quiet time for itself to
come in here and evict assets as
necessary right so that's it and what if
Vic tacit says necessary is going to do
is it's just going to sit in the loop
right it's just going to sit in the loop
trying to figure out how it can get
below total memory used right so while
total memory used is greater than
whatever the the target memory is right
target memory used like some some amount
of memory we specify right while it's
greater than that we try to free an
asset right we tried it to free
something and will you know assuming we
could free it than we do if not we break
and it's like an illegal code path
that's like this should never happen
right but you know if it should for some
reason happen we want to know about it
so we could fix it because that's
obviously a bug so what we need to do
here is basically get the least recently
used asset right so we need something
cure that's like a something like you
know the assets lot right
something that would be like get least
recently used asset or maybe it's a slot
index right get least recently used
asset you know we would call that and it
would return us the slot index of
something that we could free so assuming
that that slot index comes back as
something other than the zero asset we
would then grab that slot right and say
asset scoops we would say that that
particular slot we would like to
basically shut that asset down so like
free the memory associated with that
asset so we would say evict asset right
I guess we would just do a victor ectly
of slot index and then that would
probably all be in one thing right
internal void evict asset and this just
gets the asset out of the system right
it just says go away mr. asset you know
yupz you don't really belong you don't
belong anymore it's kind of like you
know Rudolph the red-nosed reindeer this
assets not allowed to play with the
reindeer games anymore on account of his
horrible nose mutation cetera et cetera
anyway so we pass in the slot that we
want here and then this evict asset call
will take care of getting an asset from
a state of being loaded to a state of
being freed right and what we would want
to do there is we want to say okay the
assets slots let's grab out whatever the
slot is this is where that asset lives
we want to check its state to assert
that the state is in fact loaded because
there is no other state that is actually
allowed to be evicted locked assets
can't be evicted cute assets are not
very unloving scheduled to be there so
at the very least it's going to be an
error to try to evict an asset
that isn't even loaded right so assuming
the slot state is loaded really all we
need to do is transition the slot state
to being unloaded and free the memory
right so in order to do that all we have
to do is again use that release asset
memory call and so our problem here is
going to be we don't actually know how
big of an asset this actually was when
we release it so we want to do something
that makes it easy for us to pass this
size parameter here right memory is
pretty easy for us to pass because we
kind of know that whichever kind of
asset it was we you know we have the
memory in there and you know the other
thing we can do too is we can kind of
make that a little easier on ourselves
by by making the assets lot memory
situation a little more regular that's
something we probably should do I kind
of feel like we should unify the way the
memory goes in here I I kind of want to
do that so let's actually do that as
well so what I want to do is say okay
will free the slot memory like this and
there we just need to know I guess what
the size actually would have been and
here we can have had this problem to of
like not again we kind of get back into
a situation where we want to know
whether this thing is a bitmap or a
sound because we kind of want to know
where the memory would be and if we just
knew which one it was we could just do
it instead of having to unify them any
further mm-hmm I say so it's a little
bit frustrating right it's a little bit
frustrating to me just because I'm not
entirely certain I'm not entirely
certain how I want to approach that
let's take a look at the file formats I
want to see how it's actually done in
here
so it just stores the data set but
that's it of the data in the file and
then we always where we always like
compute the rest of the information from
residual stuff and you know I I just
don't know what I want to do about about
this aspect of it I feel like there's
been enough thing so far that we just
want to be able to you know we want to
be able to know whether something is a
bitmap or a sound and I'd kind of
studiously avoided that so far but it
seems like something that we would like
to take care of you know it seems like
something that it would just be nice to
know anytime you look at an asset slot
which one is going to be and I don't
really know like you know we could even
packed that stayed in here right so we
have these we could also do assets they
sound and ss8 sound could be like you
know just one of the high bits of the
thing an asset state bitmap could be one
of the highest states of the thing and
it's just it's a little janky because
then people have to remember to actually
set these when they transition to load
it or locked they don't need to try and
do it any other time but it seems like
something it seems like something
let's take a look let's just see what
would happen if we were going to do that
right because you can kind of see that
it's only in these two places right and
so the final state would just be like oh
you know it's a bitmap or a sound and
when we load the final state now we know
what's actually in there and we don't
have to do you know any other kind of
monkey business right we just kind of
know so I don't know that does seem kind
of interesting right and maybe I'll
leave it that way and so nobody else
ever looks at asset State loaded right
besides the people who actually get the
thing out so all we would have to do is
is make sure that in here we just mask
it off right so we do something like get
state that of the slot and we would make
in line 30 to get state from an asset
slot would just return whatever the slot
state was masked out by whatever the
those bits were right so instead we
would do you know just take the bottom
bits like so so that's certainly
something we could do again I don't know
that it's a good idea but it's certainly
an idea and we could just say that you
know asset state mask even we could just
say that the bottom eight is that asset
state and then the top is for whatever
we want right so yeah a little janky
right but gets the job done so there we
go we would have a way now of knowing
which one it's going to be and so we
could just now checked see it's acetate
loaded assuming it is we unload it and
then really all we have to do now is
figure out how much memory it takes for
this particular slot and and release
that memory right so in order to do that
we need to compute that size so we want
to do something like yet
sighs of asset and that would take you
know whatever the asset index actually
is like this and maybe we would also
pass when we do get size of asset we
would pass whichever one it actually is
right so we'd go ahead and say like oh
okay we've got asset sound and asset
bitmap right so what we would do is we'd
say there'd be another thing which is
asset state like type mask or something
like this which we can use to just grab
just that part right so we can say all
right you know get type of slot so we
also have the ability to get that there
we go and Tim made file formats not what
I wanted but I wanted this and I wanted
to add that call there we go so you
could say get type of s of the assets
lot and that's just the asset slot type
mass there and this could be the state
mask just to make them a little bit more
explicit about which was which right
pretty straightforward stuff yes tech
cleats all that okay so i'm not totally
unhappy with that I just don't love it
but you know you don't always love all
the code right that's not the way that
goes that's not how programming usually
goes so anyway if we go ahead and make
its size of asset be something that can
tell us that you know for a specific
assets lot you know how big it actually
is based on you know assuming that you
actually know what the type is right we
can go ahead and do this where we say
alright let's take a look at the type I
guess we only have to type so we just
say you know if the type is a sound
it'll compute it one way else it'll
computer the other way and will assert
you know the type is a bitmap at that
point in case we add something else and
like forget to fix this or something at
least that way we'll get an assertion in
there and it'll be fine so what we'd
want to do is we want to do exactly the
the stuff that happens here right we'd
want to be able to do a thing that
computes the memory size like so so we'd
have a memory index memory size and then
we would have it do whatever the correct
things are for sound vs vs bitmap okay
and so looking at what how that actually
works it's it's just going to be you
know this code for the bitmap where is
that at there it is it's just going to
be this code for the bitmap so we're
going to get you know that info Jim
times the other info dim x 4 right oops
that's really oh that's even computing
so pretty straightforward and I just
need to be able to get that info so it
would just be something that kind of
works like this right so we'd go ahead
and take the slot index of the asset we
would then grab the bitmap out of that
and compute it very simple and we can
also make sure that that's always what
we actually use here as well right we
can always do something where we would
do memory index memory size equals you
know get size of asset so that we kind
of already always know that we're
dealing with with the asset directly so
we do get size of asset we would pass it
the slot index that we're talking about
here which is just I devalue we or we
always know that we're dealing with a
bitmap so we don't actually need to do
any determination there and so that we
could just always use so we know that
the size is the same that we're not like
doing two different computations of what
that size is which is kind of nice right
and so here it would be the same thing
right we'd go ahead and replace that so
in here we'd actually do the channel
count times the channel size sort of a
thing and I don't know if channel size
channel so I've even used and it is yet
okay so we would do something up here
where we would compute those but
we would do when we actually go do the
memory size is we would call get size of
asset and that's what we would use for
the memory size going forwards and it
would be sound right so doing that we
would just do again grabbing that info
out HHA sound and there's the sound
again so in order to compute the memory
size we just need to figure out I guess
we don't know that's just info in both
cases yeah so same exact thing is the
bitmap case use the info that we look up
oops to figure that out and we can do
something here you know again I don't
want to be doing lots of computations
that I don't know if they're being done
in the same the same way in multiple
places it just makes me a little bit
nervous right you can see that the
channel size is is getting used in
multiple places here and kind of the
pitch was being used the same way there
too and so one thing that that kind of
you know suggests to me is that may be
what you would want to do is you'd want
to have a thing that's like you know
asset memory size or something like this
that actually returns a little bit more
so it's like you know total size is one
of the things but then like you know
something like a row size like that's
that's up and that would return like the
pitch in that case or whatever something
like that or the channel size in the
case of a sound that seems like maybe a
little bit slightly better idea to me
right and we can you know before we were
saying you 30 tues for these so maybe
we'll keep it to that and say that they
have to be you 32s instead of being able
to 60 for a bit but so if we did that we
could say okay asset memory size the
result of the asset memory size
computation is going to include these
other things right so here we go and so
now we could actually do something more
like this where you know we get the
bitmap out and then we say all right I
you know I guess we don't care about the
width and the height so much but we do
care about computing the pitch so what
we'd say is the result row size is going
to be that that sort of
could even call something a little bit
better like section size or something
like that right so the thing has
multiple pieces that computes that so we
do section size we go ahead and do that
that safe truncate for the width and the
height like so right and then when we do
section size we can just use the width
from that and then when we do total size
it's just going to be the section size
times the height right so that allows us
to do that computation in a way that now
when we return that as a result we can
actually just rely on that to do all of
the stuff that we actually wanted it to
do in terms of the memory layout which
is a little bit better in my opinion
right so now we call this when we get
the information back we can set the
pitch equal to the section size right
and we can set the the memory size equal
to the total size I guess we don't need
size because we already know it's a size
right so that's just you see what i did
there like I just I just wasn't
comfortable having that kind of
duplicated code because i was afraid
that there might be times when that
would cause an error like somebody would
you know maybe go in and change that
code not realize that it was done in two
different places and you know you just
over time you kind of try to take those
things out one by one because it just
makes the code just more reliable as you
go you don't need to be paranoid about
it right but you do kind of want to swap
those things and just take care of them
when you see them because tends to pay
back later if you're if you're kind of
you know you're kind of helping yourself
out basically right so there's that
section sighs and that's going to be the
the sample count times the size of a
sample and then the total size is just
going to be however main channels there
are times that section size right
so that's about it I think that's all we
really need to do there I'm just going
to go down here and again change this to
do asset memory size like so and then
channel size can just be driven off of
that so that's going to be size section
like so and then the the memory size
would be the same memory size equal size
total like that and I think that's a
that's kind of a more sane way to do
that okay let's take a look at how this
goes i don't know why i typed slate
there but it has been fixed let's see
conversion viewers who converted from
you 32 2 s 16 so this is actually i
guess a safe truncate 2 u16 right
although wait conversion from to s 16
guess we don't really have a safe
truncate for that do we I don't feel
like we do platform safe truncate yeah
we don't I have 14 truncating to an s 16
I wonder why we didn't do that before
seems like you would want to do that
right so I'm going to go ahead and
define that there where we can actually
you know do something that's going to do
a safe truncate and in order to do that
again I'll just do 65536 divided by two
so i'll do the two bounds there why did
it not leave that up leave that up there
we go 65536 / to paste so what I want to
do here is I just want to say like okay
as long as it's within the bounds of in
a you know and in 16 you can go ahead
and in truncate it and we never expect
our pitch to be that big but we just
want to make sure
okay so if we go that gets done yeah we
need to make sure that the state objects
i guess since they're going to be bored
together there now actually not asset
state values let's see get size of asset
this is going to be asset memory size
now and we do sighs total so we can free
it and the slot memory is now the only
thing that we don't have let's see
anything else target memory used is a
functional assets and so let's go up
here to and set a target memory used to
something reasonable what guess we'll
call that size there we go and so now
really all i have to do is is fix fix
this guy so that we know where the
actual memory is and in order to do that
i think i can just do a get type of the
slot right and figure out where the
memory is like like this right i can
just say like okay if get type slot
equals sound then we know that the the
slot sound dot channels for samples 0 is
the start of the memory and if if not
it's just a bitmap memory right so i'm
going to do an assertion here as well
i'll do an assertion that just ensures
that whatever the hmm you know a case we
add against something and this doesn't
work we want to make sure that's k so
now we have only one really problem
remaining which is get least recently
used asset doesn't actually you know we
don't actually know what that's going to
do so i'm going to go ahead temporarily
just disable that because i want to test
all that those changes we made and make
sure that nothing is going
be wrong because sometimes things go
horribly wrong but we look okay here
everything still seems you loading okay
and it's all good so there we go so now
we need to do is last thing we need to
do is we need to take the we need to add
something to our asset system that lets
us know what the least recently used
asset is so I'm going to start again by
doing the simplest possible thing
because this is kind of the the low end
version of the system we're kind of
doing everything as simple as possible
so all I'm going to do is I'm going to
introduce basically like a sort of a
doubly linked list kind of a scheme to
go through our assets and this is not a
particularly good way of doing this so
we're going to have to look at something
a little bit saner well you know what i
could start i could probably start by
doing something saner to be honest it's
not actually entirely out of the
question let's think about that for a
second I mean fundamentally what I want
to do here right is I want to know when
we have an asset that is you know
whatever the asset that was least
recently asked for in a call to say load
bitmap or load sound right so we're
looking for something that's
fundamentally like a heap kind of a data
structure where you've just got up you
can pull out somebody who's sort of
number is is the worst right and I'm
just trying to think of like what the
easiest way would be to go about doing
that
and you know my my gut instinct for the
simplest way to do it it should just
thread some a linked list through it but
the problem with doing that is it takes
a lot more memory than we really need it
to you know it's definitely kind of
wasteful but I suppose it's not a big
deal if we actually only did it for the
assets that were actually loaded which
of course are the only ones we actually
need so one thing that we could do is we
could make it so that the assets had a
little bit of a header on them that
allows that that threading to occur
right so what I could do is I could do
something like this and in fact I
suppose this would have been something
we could have used to to store the size
of the asset memory as well if we didn't
want to have to compute it but it seems
like you should just compute it because
since we know it there's no point in in
storing it but basically what i'm
thinking is okay so let's do the
simplest possible thing here if i was to
go ahead and introduce a loaded asset
list right or i guess i'll call it a
sentinel here so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to make a doubly linked list
that just runs through our assets and
we're literally going to do the dumbest
possible thing which is that every time
an asset to use we're going to move it
to the front of the list which means
that the end of the list will always be
our least recently used asset right
super super simple again really really
nothing nothing to it and you know it
kind of even looks like memory could
have gone right here so I don't know if
we keep this it may be really stupid for
me to have introduced that like
computation thing because we could
probably just not do that but what are
you gonna do programming is not the kind
of thing where you always know exactly
what you should do when you start you
got to kind of get in there and take a
look so anyway if I was to do that all I
would really have to do is when you go
ahead and do asset memory size right
when it actually does that computation I
just go ahead and add to the total right
the size of one of these asset memory
headers and now I just know that anytime
after you know any time i allocate one
of these things i can just stick the
acid memory header at the end of this
thing and be done with it right and it's
and it's pretty straightforward so what
I could do for example is when we do you
know this acquire asset memory think
here right what i could do is say all
right let's also say that in the oops
where do we actually load this guy choir
esic memory memory size right there so
what I want to do is I want to I guess I
want to make this kind of like total
data and section so that actually total
is going to equal result data plus that
extra header size right so I want to
make it so because I I want to be able
to know how much I'm actually supposed
to load as opposed to the little part at
the end that's just for the asset memory
header right so instead it's going to
look like this there you go and when I
do this it'll actually just load that
memory size fit in there so instead of
size total what it's going to load is
just the data right and in fact what i
could do is now just kind of get rid of
that concept of memory size all together
and actually just access the size thing
directly with that right and what i can
do is like and then say okay i can add a
thing to the work structure which is
like the header for this thing you know
is going to be yeah the header for this
thing is going to be wherever you know
the thing actually was plus however big
the data was right so it's just going to
be if i take that the sort of the bitmap
memory right and I advance past all the
data that's where the header is going to
be right that's basically it so pretty
straightforward nothing particularly
fancy there but that gives me a header
if I want one and the same would be true
for the sound right so if I then go
ahead and say okay you know i take the
memory advance by the size now I've got
a header and so now this guy this work
at you know this this load asset work
thing this guy can now have an acid
memory pointer in it which is just going
to be the header and so now there's just
a header that we can use for that sort
of thing okay so the problem the thing
that makes this not super easy
unfortunately is we do have one sort of
caveat which is that since a lot of
these things are since this thing that's
loading the assets in since we don't
actually know I guess since this thing
itself is not really the thing that
wants to add stuff to the list when the
thing comes into existence I guess
there's really no I guess now I think
about there's really no reason to
actually store that in the asset work
it's really just something that we use
directly here right when we add the
entry in it's really just something
where we're like okay you know what the
asset memory header is just a thing that
we need to then fill out right and we
can already add the asset memory header
to the list if we want to so yeah so I
think we're I think we're okay I think
this is fine I think what we really want
to do is just something like this add
asset header to list or something like
that we're just going to go ahead and
say right when we do it we want to to go
ahead and make that happen so we'll just
do something like this right we'll say
there's the memory there's the size
structure and here's the assets
structure so yeah I think that's what I
actually want to because I don't want it
to be happening in a multi-threaded
context I think that would be bad
because you don't want a doubly linked
list happening in the middle of
multi-threaded stuff it's just a
painting the BET and error error prone
so let's go ahead and do it this way and
then we'll just have
up here internal void add asset to list
and so there we've got our game assets
and we have our asset memory header
which is constructed by taking the
memory and adding size so that's going
to be void star memory and asset size is
it called again asset memory size right
and that will do that computation when
we find one of these headers adding it
is pretty straightforward if you've
never done a doubly linked list before
it's really pretty easy it's just a
little bit weird I think we may have
talked about this on the stream at one
point or another but basically like a
doubly linked list is is really just a
list where you have a piece of memory
and it's got a previous and a next
pointer in it rank and you just got all
these links like so and the previous
pointer just points to the previous
thing so you know you've kind of kind of
got these things that look like this
right and the next pointer just points
to the one that comes after it right and
the reason that you use a doubly linked
list instead of a singly linked list or
some other data structure is if you just
have if you just want to move items
around in the list a lot aw linked list
gives you all the information that you
actually need in order to remove
something when all you have is just the
link itself right because it tells you
who is before it so you know you can
patch this pointer to like point to the
next guy and it tells you who is after
it so you know you can point this point
pointer to point to the next guy right
so you have all the information you need
where is in a singly linked list right
if you're just looking at something like
this if I give you this guy and I say
remove him you have no idea how
get back to this dude right because
there is no pointer that goes back to
the previous one so W linked lists are
kind of this like you know overkill kind
of data structure where it's just like
yet you don't even know anything just
get a link and you can do whatever you
want you can like walk backwards walk
forwards remove it do whatever you want
right so if I wanted to insert this
right I've got my asset memory header so
what I chose to do is I chose you
something called a sensible which is to
just have a dummy header and I include
that dummy header one that is not
attached to any asset I include that
dummy header in my actual a structure so
it's always there right it's just always
there and so what I can do is say okay
we've got the sentinel loops which is
this guy and what I want to do is I want
to insert this guy as the first person
list so the Sentinels next pointer
should point to this guy right so
Sentinel next should point to this guy
that's what I want to have happen right
what that also means is that if Sentinel
next whoever Sentinel next was pointing
to previously whatever then whatever the
guy after the central next was before
his previous pointer had also better
point to be right because I'm putting
someone in I need the next pointer of
the central budget and whoever was
previously in that slot needs to point
back right so I need to hook up the guy
this way like so and see how that would
work right looking at it a little bit
differently we could say that if we want
this guy to come after the sentinel on
the list we'd say that his previous
pointer is the Sentinel right and his
next pointer is whoever the Sentinels
other next point it would have been
right you can kind of see what i'm doing
here right I've got a guy who's like
kind of job it is to be my main link
right here is a sentinel and what I want
to do is that Sentinel right has a
previous pointer that points to somebody
I don't care about back here and it's
got a next pointer that points to this
guy right here yeah and what I want to
do is I want to insert this thing and by
the way this previous pointer right
sorry this previous pointer points back
to the Sentinel right so what I want to
do if I want to insert someone here is I
need to set
this pointer to point to me right this
is the new guy who's coming in I just at
this point to me but I also need to set
this pointer to point to me right so I
need to set up a bunch of pointers first
I need to set up this guy's next in
previous right so the previous points of
the Sentinel the next points to whoever
the next guy was in the list originally
but then I need to fix up these two
pointers right like I service was
showing here so how could I do that
though in a slightly more convenient way
so I've got header previous that equals
the Sentinel I've got header next that
equals that whoever was next what I can
do now is just say well I can just
semantically say what I want to have
happen right my next and previous
pointers are now both correct the only
thing that's not correct is that they
don't point back to me so what I can do
instead is say well the whoever's next
whoever is ahead of me their previous
pointer should point to me and who's
ever before me their next pointer should
point to me so I can kind of just write
it like I want it to work and not have
to think about it much beyond that so
really all I have to do to insert a guy
is set their previous and next pointers
to point to the people who are on either
side of them and then this little
nonsense here right takes care of the
rest it goes who is next okay their
previous foreigner needs to point to me
who is previous ok its next brain is
going to me right pretty straightforward
so that's really all that is and we
could you know I could show you here how
to write the remove asset header from
list as well right so remove asset
headers pretty basic remove asset header
from list it just needs to take it
doesn't even need to take any of this
stuff right it just needs to take that
asset memory header so if you have that
asset memory header and you want to
remove it from the list again you can
just say what you want to have happen
right I have a guy who's before me in
the list right that's my previous the
guy who's before me I want his next
pointer to point to whoever's after me
so it skips over me now right and
similarly I would want my next who's
ever after me I'd want their previous
pointer to point Devers before me but
that's it
right that totally takes me out of the
list nothing to it right so if we want
to now we can make it so that okay we
have things we add asset header to list
which we've got we've got remove asset
header from list as well so now we could
actually do well honestly we can pretty
much finish up I don't we want to go
maybe five minutes over and just finish
up and just not do the debugging will do
the debugging on the next stream right
but basically that's it so what we could
do here is we could come back in to our
Vic tacit when we go to evict the asset
right before we release the memory right
we would do remove asset header from
list and we would again pass that that
asset header and really what we would be
doing on a victor I suspect is instead
of a victim asset now what we would do
is we'd actually just have the header
because the header is the thing that
we're going to have anyway so we have
the asset memory header there's the
header the slot index is actually just
going to come from that header right and
and so when we do get least recently
used asset what that's actually going to
give us is asset memory header star
asset right and assuming that asset is
not know and in this case what will say
is assuming the asset is not equal to
the to that to that Sentinel I'll show
you why that is in a second loaded asset
Sentinel so assuming that the asset
isn't you know basically our our one
that just stays there and serves as our
base point we evict it right so that's
again pretty straightforward we'll go
ahead and evict assets that way and get
recently used asset now no longer has to
really be anything fancy it's just going
to be whatever the last thing was so
it's whatever that Sentinel was its
whatever its previous pointer was that's
the last thing in the list right really
really basic so we just go ahead and do
that and now our viction code is is a
lot simpler so when we do our ad asset
header to list though one thing that I
should force it to do is it needs to set
in a
mission to the previous and next we
would like it to set that slot index so
we can make sure that that's always
valid so what I want to do here is just
introduce also the slot index maybe I'll
put it right here that way everyone who
calls that has to put that slot index in
here so that we make sure that it gets
initialized and that's just a little
like insurance policy there so that we
don't forget yeah so now there's really
only one thing that we need to do which
is we need to have it reinsert assets
into the list whenever they are used so
whenever someone does a get sound right
what we would want to do at that point
is make sure that we move so you know
move asset to front or something like
this right or mark asset as recently
used and we would go ahead and give that
ID value in the header and whatever else
right of the thing we would go ahead and
have that that work here right I'll hold
off on that we've covered a little bit
too much ground I think today so I don't
really want to quite do that yet so let
me just take care of any crash eNOS that
we have here let's go ahead and fix that
first and mm oh right I have to
initialize all essential there and then
I'll kind of go over that stuff a little
bit in the QA so that everyone is on the
same page so again because i'm using
this sentinel here all of my operations
were written assuming that the linked
list always has something in it which is
at least the sentinel so at startup what
we need to do is we need to make sure
that the sentinel always points back to
itself right so basically what I'm doing
here just to avoid any kind of
difficulty oops yeah in order to avoid
any kind of more coding complexity what
I'm doing a start-up right is I'm
starting us up with a list that just
points to itself right so here's our
Sentinel and we've got an extant
previous pointer and all
here saying okay the previous pointer
points back to me the next pointer also
points back to me and that way when we
go to insert something it all just works
because our previous pointer will point
back to this thing and our next pointer
will point to whatever the Sentinels
next pointer was which was itself which
is exactly what we want and so the list
always maintains that nice integrity if
you just have sort of that dummy value
there by contrast if I wasn't to use
that Sentinel we would have had this
nasty thing happen we're basically we
always have to check to see if previous
an extra null because there might be
nothing in the list right and so this
gets us out of that by making the list
oh we circular like that where it's got
this Sentinel that always completes the
list it just gets you out of a bunch of
checking but yeah alright so let's see
what we've got here load bitmap what
happened there it did not like that
header that is not a very good header to
say the very least oh I know why that is
a very simple typo and that is because
when I was doing the allocation I forgot
to account for that let's go ahead and
make that acquire asset memory that's
total right all right like so sighs
total memory size goes away and this guy
is size data so there we go this is not
particularly useful yet you can even see
the flashing can you see the flashing
happening that's our asset system just
evicting assets randomly not in any
particularly good order but randomly
evicted assets
keep itself under the megabyte goal
right or whatever it was that we set
right oh and one other thing I wanted to
mention right on cue the other thing
that we have to do is we have locked
assets which are assets that aren't
allowed to get evicted because we
already planned for that which is that
the background when background working
tests are using them and so one other
thing that we want to do is when we do
add asset header to list what we want to
do there is make sure that we're never
adding a locked asset right an asset
whose final state is going to be locked
and so what we want to do is just pass
that final state along in fact you know
what when do we set that when when we're
resetting the locked were we never
actually setting that correct me if I'm
wrong because we planned for this we
said we wanted to do that right and we
had a locked but I kind of feel like we
never actually set anything to lock
right it never gets used so we actually
need the ability to set those things to
locked I guess we'll leave that for
tomorrow but that is exactly what i was
talking about let me see if i can get
that to happen again there we go uh
let's see here so in right here is Phil
ground chunk work Phil ground chunk is
just on a separate thread so if we were
to evict the memory that it was using it
will just straight up crash right so we
can't ever allow that to happen which we
talked about when we did it and we
introduced the asset state luck thing
but what we need to do and this should
be tomorrow's task for sure is we need
to make sure that we actually lock
assets down that are being used by the
background task right that's just kind
of an obvious that's just kind of an
obvious thing that needs to happen and
so what we could do you know there's a
pretty easy way I guess that we could do
that too which is that we can inside our
inside our are well you know what we're
way over time I'm going to go to the QA
but i will i'll talk about that a little
bit later how we're going to do that
i'll talk about that on tomorrow stream
so yeah I would say tomorrow that's what
we're going to do I'll even write it
down tomorrow Asset locking
okay all right Q&amp;A time q colon in front
of them we kind of breeze through a lot
of stuff on that stream I just kind of
in the mood so we maybe went a little
bit fast I'm just going to talk about
the link listing a little bit here in
the QA but basically so for a doubly
linked list there's really two flavors
there's Sentinel and non Sentinel right
and sewn on centinall just has like a
first at a last pointer somewhere and
the first in the last pointer point to
some part of the list right so you could
imagine like okay I've got my list right
oops
right
and what happens is the previous pointer
of the first link points to know and the
next link of the last the next point of
the last link points to know and then
first and last point to where they are
right that's one way to do a doubly
linked list and that's just a lot more
work right it's a lot more code to do
that because you got to constantly check
for the if if know if not know all that
other stuff right The Sentinel way is
way easier all that is is just says okay
there's a sentinel it's always there it
can't ever leave however big the list is
right however big the list is you just
have exactly what you would expect
always everything points to its
neighbors so exactly the same structure
as before no difference is the only time
that something actually changes is the
last pointer where this was no it just
points back to the Sentinel and the pre
pointer on the Sentinel points all the
way back to that last link right and
that makes the links the list circular
so now addition and removal is always
the same it's always looking at a case
that looks exactly like this because
there's never a case that can't look
like this it's always has a full set of
pointers and then the first and last
pointers are just implicit in the
Sentinel they are the previous and next
pointer the first pointer is that is
sorry the first pointer is the next
pointer of the Sentinel the last pointer
is the previous pointer right because
hey if that's the Sentinel the previous
pointer always points back to that end
of the list and if it's the you know if
you want the first you just look at the
next because that's what ever that was
right so pretty straightforward what
function owns the pointer to the head of
the linked list owns the pointer I'm not
sure to invite owns the pointer isn't a
linked list what you're always told not
to do if you care about the cash at all
yeah basically like if this is something
that you're heavily trafficking you
would not want to do that right are we
going to have athlete's
heavily traffic it probably not but
we'll find out and like I said linked
list I don't know that this is what will
actually use and there's a number of
ways that we can make it easier on
ourselves cash wise to if that makes
sense so like for example if it turns
out that we really care about the cash
here instead of allocating the linked
lists here we just allocate a block of
the links and use them in one nice big
block that's all cash friendly but again
you don't really want to worry about
whether your code is cash friendly if
you don't even know if that code is
actually running very often right so
it's best you know you want to use data
structures that are appropriate for the
code that you're using and you don't
really want to try and optimize them
until you know what you're actually
doing right and so you'd want to I
wouldn't discourage people from using
linked lists I'd say use link that's
anytime you want when you find that that
code is slow replace the linked list
with something that's designed for
whatever the thing is that you're doing
designed to be faster right could the
platform allocate function allocate a
few bites more than requested and store
the slides there to avoid it being
passed it to the free function yes but I
don't really like doing that because
usually you do know the size like in
this case we did right so I felt like
that's maybe the easier way to go
having a list header at the end of each
SS struct wouldn't that invalidate the
cache a lot when processing the list
since assets trucks are potentially
large well it doesn't really matter how
big the asus trucks are the cache is
based on little chunks right and so you
know touching a link that's at the end
of the assets truck is no different than
touching it anywhere else so if you
wanted to make this more cash friendly
the only thing you would really do for
the linked list is you just put the
links together so basically like right
now it looks like this asset data link
asset data link right and so all you
would do if you wanted to make this more
cash friendly is you just grab all these
links and instead just have it an
out-of-band thing like a separate buffer
that's just link link link link link
right and that way you know you'd fit
multiple of those in one cache line
right but that's it
and remove a sigh there from lifts but
it makes sense to zero out the previous
points of the header that's being
removed or as I just a necessary cleanup
it's unnecessary but there's no reason
you couldn't do it just for like
debugging purposes right so what we
could do right is is in here say okay
header next equals header previoulsy row
and that's just like a way for us to
double check you know because it's not
this is not a high frequency operation
because if it turns out to be a high
frequency operation like I said we'd
probably want to not use a linked list
if it turned out to be like a bottleneck
so i would i would say that in general
you know doing that's a fine way to do
extra sort of debug checking will there
be a fountain of head somewhere in the
actual game possibly as a halloween item
it does seem like a good idea is twitch
my full-time job know how will you
re-enable the LiveCode reloading after
this is done well it's pretty easy to
enable it even if we want to stick with
this scheme all you do is you have the
the the loop live code editing the
platform code just keeps a set of
headers on the virtual Alex that thread
them and when you do the save you just
go ahead and pull those you write those
out to disk but I might actually even
suggest not doing that and instead just
invalidating the asset cash entirely
whenever you do leap loop live code
editing so that way we don't even have
to store the transient arena so there's
a lot of ways we could do it but all
that depends on us not actually just
doing something slightly different than
this anyway eventually which is like
just doing a block allocator so you know
I wouldn't worry about that quite yet
can you briefly go over inline functions
well I don't know that there's that much
to go over if if you don't have a
specific question I mean inline function
is just a function that you've told the
compiler you would you it's like a hint
to the compiler of it says this is
probably something small that should
just be embedded where it's called
instead of actually making a function
call to it and that just allows the
compiler like it's a suggestion the
compiler to take a look at it and then
cut power takes a look at it it will say
oh maybe I can do a bunch of
optimizations by embedding this code
into where it's called rather than
having it have to be a separate function
but it's unclear that really like in
line just a hint it doesn't force the
compiler to alignment so these days it's
unclear like if you ever if you even
really care I don't the compiler can
choose or not to inline or not based on
its own subjective judgment and unless
you use other December cue ball called
force in line which makes it mandatory
to do so to the compiler unless you do
that the compilers actually is able to
use its discretion so when I type in
line it doesn't even mean the function
gets in mind which classic data
structure do you enjoy implementing the
most purely subjective um honestly
singly linked list is my favorite
because it's so darn easy it's kind of
so breezy and fun and even like some of
the operations even just work with
atomic exchange removal doesn't i think
removal requires atomic exchange and add
when I looked at that before but like
adding to a linked list singly linked
list is it just an atomic exchange which
is kind of cool
does will the system support hot loading
of assets apologies if this has already
been covered and I missed it no the
system will not support that strictly
because we don't have any artists that
work on this during the stream so I mean
I guess I shouldn't really say it that
way it certainly does support hot
loading if you wanted it to support hot
loading because you just have you just
have some way that you wanted to grab
like a bitmap I guess externally but
yeah I have no interest in supporting
that for this for the asset files
because the asset files are all
basically come to me in batches from the
artist right so we have no need for hot
loading of any kind but if you want to
do it it's trivial to do so right i mean
it should be really obvious how you
would do it basically like the stuff
that loads a bitmap we already had code
in here before that loaded a bitmap fit
from a BMP so all you'd have to do is
just add the ability to say okay the
asset file records the names of files it
should look for and then when you go to
load a bitmap you check to see if that
file exists and if so you load it from
that instead but I don't have any
interests in doing that because we don't
have a use case for it but you could do
that if you wanted let's see does it
make sense to write your own non block
non block dynamic allocator instead of
using the memory system of the Oz well
like I said at the beginning of the
stream I don't know that we're going to
use the AUSA's one if in 64-bit you
probably just can I don't really know
though I haven't tried in 32-bit I just
think it'd be pretty dicey so I suspect
that that's that you know like i said i
just wanted to show how to get this
working before having to tackle the
memory placement part of it because like
you saw today there's a bunch of other
kind of futzing around that has to
happen so i would say
you know I would say there's a very high
probability chance that that we would
not actually call the platform's
allocator you know by friday i think
we'll probably be doing our own right is
my assumption but you know you don't
have to do that if you wanted to you
could try to ship a game that just did
it this way you know so all right if
there are no further questions I will
serve the remainder of my time okay um
so yeah we've got a bunch more stuff to
do we've only just gotten started on
this but the week is young we've got
Wednesday Thursday and Friday to tackle
this problem so that is a good thing
right so let's go ahead and close things
down here go ahead and save
close all right thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always get the source code by
pre-ordering the game it comes to the
source code and I updated every night so
you can stay current and play around
with the current state of the source
code experiment and you know it's a good
way to learn we also have a patreon page
if you want to support the video series
you can subscribe there if you would
like to ask questions we have a forum
site and it also has community ports to
mac and linux and it's got an anti
episode guide done by the community all
kinds of good stuff so if you're trying
to learn for the series that's a good
place to go and we also have a tweet bot
so if you want to catch the series live
check out the tweet bot it always tweets
the schedule so you can keep up to date
with when we're going to be on the air
if was it gonna say I'll go say
something I remember what it was you
know what guess it doesn't matter
alright so that's about it will be back
here 5 p.m. pacific standard sorry
pacific daylight time tomorrow 5pm 6
daily time here on twitch so if you'd
like to see some more asset system work
we'll be doing that tomorrow getting the
locked asset stuff working and doing
some more sort of cleanup of how we're
doing stuff in the asset system as we go
towards getting ready to probably do our
own block allocator so that we don't
call into the operating system for each
allocation which is I really I just
don't think that's what we should do but
again like I said if that's what you
want to do at least on 64-bit systems I
think you should have no problem doing
the code like we did it today but I just
feel like there's you know maybe that's
not the best idea going for 32-bit we
could test it though anyway that's about
it for today so hope see you back here
at 5pm tomorrow until then please have
fun coding and I'll see you guys on the
internet take it easy everyone