hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show recode a complete game
live on stream it's the pronoun coding
complete game live on streaming today we
have an interim thing to do which is
load P and G's so we're actually going
to be writing an ID at decompressor live
on stream mmm gotta have coffee for that
my friends so what we did yesterday is
we broke into the PNG spec we figured
pretty much figured out what was going
on at the high level which is pretty
straightforward it's a very simple riff
style format basically and what we did
is we wrote something that parsed that
and found out the data that we needed
and then has the data stream sitting
there that's the actual compressed image
data but we didn't have a chance to
actually get down and dirty with that
and figure out how to decompress that
now we did read about how to decompress
that so we're kind of ready to go but we
didn't have a chance to actually code it
now again we are not trying to write a
complete or even a fast or efficient PNG
reader we just need something that reads
pngs at all and the reason for that is
we want to enable a quick turnaround
time in Photoshop and that's all we're
doing right now all right so what I want
to do here let me go ahead and load this
up here's our parse PNG so what I want
to do here is pick up where we left off
yesterday which is to say that once we
see these I that chunks we now you do
something with them now I'm fairly
certain even though the spec was kind of
caged about this I don't feel like they
set it in a very good or clear way
that's ok because we kind of figured out
we more or less figured out what was
going on what I think is happening here
is when you encounter these I'd add
chunks they're just chunked data that's
actually all one stream right and the
reason that I say that is because the
spec for an IDOT chunk clearly states
that it will have the Z live information
at the front and what we can see is this
even though it's a very simple PNG what
we can see here is that we have four
IDOT chunks and the four I'd add chunks
are not ID at compliant only the first
one is which has the zeal of information
so what that tells me
in terms of how I'm gonna approach this
first is I'm gonna assume even though
the spec I don't feel like was worded
very well so it wasn't clear on this I'm
gonna assume what they meant when they
were talking about iodide chunks was
that actually the Ida chunks are all one
stream that you parse as if it was
contiguous even though it kind of
suggested that I'd act chunks start with
this particular header I think what they
mean is the first I that chunk does and
then it did clearly say in the spec that
I that chunks all have to come together
and that they are interpreted as one
group and so I feel like that was them
trying to say there's only gonna be the
Z Lib header at the on the first one
right so I think what that means unless
I'm very much mistaken is that we read
the Z live header out of the Ida chunk
that comes first and then we just read
the rest of the stream including all
fruits or chunks and all of the data
inside those either chunks as being just
part of a Z Lib deflate stream and we
assume that they don't ever have any
others Delibes tart up information in
them now that could be wrong but that's
what I think they're trying to say and
what that means is that the PMG in this
case can only have one compression mode
or not one compression mode one Z Lib
header for the entire compressed data
section that's what it looks like I
could be very wrong about that we'll
find out as we go forward but that's
what I was able to determine so far and
so that's the assumption that I'm
operating under and you'll see me
operating under that assumption for the
remainder of the stream until we need to
counter something that gives me a clue
that I'm wrong okay
so now jumping back to where we were
when we were decoding this when we
grabbed out all of this information what
we ended up finding was that we have
these sort of Z Lib informational pieces
here and what we are told anyway in the
spec is that the Z the Z Lib information
should never actually allow us to see a
cm value which I believe stands for
compression method or at the very least
means compression method we should never
see a cm value of anything other than 8
so in other words it has to be a cm 8
here there's nothing else that it can
actually be I believe now I could be
wrong about that but if we go back here
to the compression information we'll
just reread it again to make sure I'm
not wrong but here's the compression
section and what it says is only PNG
compression methods zero is defined by
the international standard other values
compression method reserved for future
standardization that zero is the thing
that was in the header so up here right
and you can see when we actually dumped
it we we got exactly that right so then
when we come back here and we look at
the Z Lib information going forwards it
says ok so PNG compression with zero is
deflate inflate compression with sliding
window from the lvl ZZ the lz77 deflate
a standard that comes from the Z Lib
library right so then it says that it
has to come with this header compression
method flags and code is 1 byte
additional flag checkbooks one byte the
compressed data and then the check value
right that's what we're expecting to see
now it's kind of odd that we have a
check value at the end given the fact
that these blocks have a crc themselves
do the PNG don't ask me why that's just
what we've got so off we go right now
what I don't actually know is whether or
not there's additional Z Lib start ups
inside the stream so even though the I
NAT chunks might not have Z Lib restarts
maybe there's Z libri starts
l sort in there I'm not sure we'll look
at that as we kind of go forwards anyway
for PNG compression methods
Zuba compression method flags coats fest
like method eight and not more than 32 k
of window right so that's where I'm
getting the like this has to be eight
thing so I believe we only have to
support cm method eight so what I want
to do here is sort of say all right
let's take a look at this in a slightly
different way what I want to do here is
I want to make something that's gonna
allow me to read from these either
chunks as if they're continuous because
I'm expecting to see this thing want to
read a continuous stream across either
chunks so what I want to do is when I
see the first I that chunk i I kind of
wanna I don't want to start processing
here because don't know where the rest
of the Ida at chunks necessarily are now
it's stayed in the spec that the Ida
chunks have to be contiguous I could
take their word for it or I could just
build a chain of them a priori
which might be what I want to do alright
so if I wanted to do that how would I do
it well let's take a look here so I
think I've got I look up here I've got
this nishan of entire file where we've
got the content size and the contents
here right that sort of stuff I think
what I might want to do is kind of
broaden that a little bit and maybe I'm
just thinking out loud here
but suppose we were to do something like
this where we said like okay we've got
you know I don't know a streaming buffer
and it has something like this and when
we stream stuff maybe we've got a thing
that's like this so we can kind of like
chain these things together where we
could just make like a list of them and
say like oh yeah we're gonna read all
these things in right and I might want
it a little bit different than this
right I might want to do something like
this
so I can just sort of have an idea of
the stream that I'm that I'm reading in
here
I and I can just kind of like navigate
through them in some kind of reasonable
way right and so what this would do is
it would say like oh okay
you know when we read in an entire file
we want a client we want to be able to
just do one of these and and we can
write so when we have a situation where
we're doing a streaming chunk like I'm
sorry a streaming buffer like that we
can read an entire one and just get like
sort of this stuff initialized to zero
so off we go on this it will just it'll
just return exact the same thing that it
was returning and this will operate on
this right why do I keep doing that and
then what we would do is when we get an
underflow what we want to do instead
here is say look if we get an underflow
let's actually try to look at the next
chunk in the thing so what we can do is
say oh well if content size exactly
equals zero we can assume that the
person who is reading out of this thing
was reading out of it in a sensible way
and wants to just get maybe what's in
the next chunk right so what I could do
here let's see maybe I'll do it like
this
I don't really know if I want to do it
like that exactly but maybe like that so
what I want to do here is say all right
look if the content size is enough to
fill the request then do it if the
content size is zero then maybe we want
to advance and get the thing on to the
next chunk we could be even more
creative here and actually try to
assemble things together into pieces I'm
not actually going to do that but we
could I could show how to do that in a
there's other ways we could do that
there's ways to construct buffers for
streaming that do that but what I want
to do here to say looking a look if we
just assume for now that everyone's
reading the right amount of stuff in
then in that case what I'm going to do
is advance to the next one so what I'm
going to do is say in fact I can do this
like this so in that case what we'll do
is say first look we'll grab out
streaming chunk this will set file first
equal to this next and that'll knock out
to zero eventually right and then what
we'll do is say okay when we grab the
first one out of here we'll set the
content size that we're looking at now
and the contents pointer itself to be
the one in the next jump right so this
is just kind of a quick and dirty not
particularly well thought-out or
anything just a random crappy way of
making a buffer that can have multiple
chunks in it right and so if I compile
this now I should be able to do a thing
where we can just recompile what we've
got here and this should still work
hopefully let's see OOP got a bug
somewhere
ah yeah
in fact I suppose what I could do I
suppose what I could do is just do this
again it's short enough that that loop
seems kind of dumb right what I could do
is just say all right look just repeat
this like so like that and I could just
put that at the top in fact now this is
looking much nicer so if the content
size is zero and there's a file first in
fact this is what we'll do we'll just
say all right well in that case we
advanced it and then we try to do the
thing we were going to do that's much
better
right yeah much nicer so we just say all
right look if the content size is zero
and there's another one let's advance to
the next chunk first so that's this
right and then we'll keep going right
let's do what we were going to do before
that's a much saner so now what we can
do is we can build up a one of these
guys we can build up one of these sort
of chains for all the idaite chunks and
then when we're done we can decompress
the image right so what I want to do
here is say all right let's move this
stuff out to something at the end well I
guess you know what I don't need to put
it there it could just be here
so allocate pixels can come here which
is great
here we go
so here we go we say if we got the file
header while we read it assuming that we
end up with one that's supported we will
go ahead and try to decompress it later
and what we'll do is we'll just build up
the Ida chunks that we actually want to
to use here and the way that we'll do
that is we'll just say let's pretend
that we have an IDOT sort of or you know
pixel data I don't know
compressed data or something let's
assume that we have a streaming buffer
of compressed data and all I'm going to
do is every time we get in here and find
one of them I'm gonna add it to this
right so what I'm going to do is say
okay you know here on comp data I'm
going to need a streaming chunk so I'm
going to go ahead and do an allocate
chunk here like so and the reason I'm
putting these out here is because I can
I want to do stuff special with them
when we integrate this code into
handmade hero so what we do here is say
alright when I allocate a streaming
chunk
I'm gonna do it like this
that'll give me back one of those and so
as we encounter each of these I'll just
say allocated chunk and then I'm going
to set the chunk up to be the data
that's that's in this particular I'd at
so as far as I know we use the whole i
dot chunk for the data right
so we basically say okay this Ida chunk
has the the chunk data here and the
chunk size here so I'm just gonna use
that and then I just need to set the
next pointer up it's going to point to
nothing because I want to append at the
end so then when I go to set the
streaming buffer itself which is the
compression data I just need to set the
the first and the last right now that in
any case the last will always be equal
to chunk cuz I'm appending to the end
right so we kind of know that that's
always the case but the first will only
be set in the case where you know if
comp data first is not equal to
something or you know if last is valid
already so I already have one in there
then the comp data first doesn't need to
be set right it's just comp data last
next pickles chunk and then comp data
last equals chunk and then the same
token if it wasn't the case you know if
the first were if the first wasn't set
then I would send it like this right so
this is just a kind of a bigger way of
saying I'm gonna have pend to the end of
the list the next pointer will always be
0 because I'm adding it to the end of
the list but in terms of setting up the
first and last pointers well the last
pointer always needs to point to this
chunk because it is the last one now but
the first pointer only gets set the
first time I do it and the last point
gets its next pointer set if it was set
to anything right I'm in the other case
so these are the two cases I might have
this leads to my favorite ridiculous way
of compressing this code which people
hate but I don't really care which is to
say hey if compte to last is set then
I'm setting this right
but if compte the last isn't set then
I'm setting this right I'm setting these
two and I'm setting them equal to chunk
oops
makes sense right that's what we were
saying so I'm saying like look if the
last thing is set can even do it doesn't
need a parentheses right if the last
thing is already set then I'm going to
set the next pointer equal to chunk if
the last wasn't set that I'm going to
set first equal chunk but in either case
in minute set comp data last equal to
chunk so hey since this whole expression
evaluates to chunk why not
and so that's the ridiculous way of of
doing a singly linked list append at end
in one expression for those of you who
like obtuse code right again just to be
clear on that so it's right comp data
last is always going to be set to chunk
either way and then the question is just
which of these two do we also want to
set to chunk if compte the last was set
we set the next pointer because it means
that first is already set as well cuz
last and first to point the same thing
or well first we'll point something and
last we'll point to something either it
or after it and then comp data first in
this case is just the thing that is
going to be set in the case where we
haven't set anything yet and then in
that case last and first we set to the
same thing
so anyway that's all we need to do there
right so all of that information just
kind of gets buffered up and then what
we can do is from then on we can just
start to look at the stream as it comes
in so what I can do here is change this
to a consume and say well the thing that
I want to consume is the comp data I
want to consume a ping i dot header from
it and read that out and just print out
what happens there right so let's see if
we can make that work we need to store
the width and the height here actually
though those are like two things we
allow to vary and so I'm gonna go ahead
and put those here there we go
ah yeah and what is the four there we go
okay so now if we did that correctly we
should see ourselves read the ID at
chunks and then we should come in here
and decompress them which is exactly
what we did now I'm gonna print out when
I see this it--it chunk I actually want
to see a little bit of information here
as well I think I'd like to see the size
just so I can know like how long each of
these is because I'm curious so when I
do this let's see so that's so again
this gives us a little bit of insight
I guess into what's happening again
which is to say that let me just go
ahead and
what you say that I was wondering what
the idea is behind these ayats' and you
can kind of see from this pattern maybe
something is kind of being suggested
there which is that it looks like for
whatever reason writes these out in
chunks of 8192
right which is 2 4 K pages why it does
that I have no idea but that looks like
what they're effectively using these I
that chunks 4 is buffered i/o so I don't
know if maybe as a buffer if 4 K to
4 K pages so 81 92 or 8k that it just
fills up and then flushes fills up and
flushes fills up and flushes and every
time it flushes it flushes to a new I
dot chunk now why it doesn't just flush
the same might at chunk I have no idea
but it kind of looks like that's what
it's doing
maybe there's something somewhere that
would explain this I don't know what it
is but that's looks like what's
happening so then once we go to
decompress you can see that we get the
same information that we were getting
before right when we were reading the ID
at chunk directly 8 726 0 3 8 7 2003 so
now we're reading out of that stream
nicely and now we can begin to do the
rest of the compression right and so
this is the absolute decompression this
is a part we need to start there now
what the heck they're doing here and so
we know that there's a window size that
we need to be aware of I don't know that
we actually care about the window size
very much other than it may inform how
the bits are encoded as to how many bits
of window back.look we use that's the
only thing I could think of where that's
actually even going to come into play
because we actually support the entire
look back window because we're we're
decompressing this into an image and we
will allow it to look back arbitrarily
far it can look back to any part in the
image and grab any part of it because we
have it all in memory it's not a
streaming decompressor in our case so
what that means is that we don't really
care what the window size is
but it may well us something about how
many bits are encoded in the stream for
certain pieces of information so I don't
know if we might need that later but
that's the only reason we would even
need that anyway so looking at all of
this stuff I think all we really care
about here is to go ahead and use that
data at the head end to start to start
implementing this spec right so looking
through here when we see F level I don't
know that we care about this yeah it
says right here that the F levels not
need a few compression so really all
that's telling us is how hard it tried
to compress this data on the compression
side but we don't care right similarly F
dict I think we read that F nicht was
not allowed to be set so I think this
always has to be zero I could be wrong
about that but I think that's what it
said so I think in here we can actually
do something like this
so this is the this is the zeal impetus
here so I think what we want to say is
that supported is gonna get modified
here so cm has to equal 8f nicht has to
equal zero I think right because I don't
think we're allowing anything else in
here so then moving forwards when we
start to do compressing them we can
allocate the decompressed pixels and I
think then now we're good to go
so looking back at the spec here I think
there's nothing more we can really glean
from this if I remember correctly cuz
this just says go read the other
document for learning how deflate works
right yeah I think so
yep so I think we're just we're just
living here now this is this is our jam
and so this is what we want to actually
do we want to follow this rule so like
read bloc header if store would no
compression whatever like we want to do
this so what we need to do is we need to
start reading said block header right
and we need to figure out how we do that
right what does the block header look
like and how do we determine whether or
not we come we compress or don't
compress so it says each block of
impressed data bits with three header
bits be final and B type and off we go
so that's the first thing that we want
to be able to do is kind of read these
bits now I'm live to make something that
literally reads bits but at the same
time that's what we're gonna basically
dealing with so I think I want to do
something that's like the worst
thing here for a while because again I
don't really care about this code I just
need it to work and if the stupid thing
ends up working fast enough then I'm not
going to touch it right I'm just gonna
let it do its thing so I think we want
to do something that's literally the
dumbest possible thing where we can just
basically say let get bit like literally
right so I kind of want to do something
here that says be fine I'll be type
right I want to do something that
basically just says look I think I want
to do something like that right where I
can actually consume bits at a time and
write the code that way and then just
deal with the fact that that's not very
efficient because again if it doesn't
end up being a problem I'm not gonna
care because this is not code that runs
during the game if it's stored with no
compression skip any remaining bits and
current partially processed byte read
Len and n Len see you next section copy
Len bytes of data to output so this is
the uncompressed case which should be
pretty reasonable right so what I want
to do here is I need a flush byte call I
guess so when when we're doing consume
bits then we have a flush byte call and
the flush byte call is basically saying
look as I'm taking bits out I'm gonna
jump to the next eight
that's just what it says that it wants
to do for whatever reason read Lennon n
Len
I don't know how long those are but
presumably gonna tell us in a second
and this happens if V type equals
something so 0 0 is no compression then
we've got compressed compressed and
reserved right so we basically have a B
type of 0 is going to do something a B
type of 1 is going to do something a B
type of 2 is gonna do something and any
other B type because we don't allow 11
in this case is an error right and so
that's going to be B type 3 is just not
it like the spec doesn't say so we hope
to never encounter this and in theory we
shouldn't write alright so we have B
type 0 B type equals 1 v technicals - I
don't actually know if the fixed Huffman
code version is supposed to happen
because I kind of think we've read
something that says it's not so I'm
gonna assume that the dynamic Huffman
code is the only path for now but I'm
not sure about that because it was kind
of the spec again was really not worded
well I didn't think so I'm gonna just
see if we see any of these if we don't
see any I assume that's the right
reading if we do see something obviously
that was just erroneous so then we've
got the two cases here really the
dynamic Huffman code one is the same
these two are basically the same so I
guess what I could do is this
so if compress with dynamic Huffman code
so if the B type is to this reads the
dynamic Huffman codes and otherwise it
doesn't right and so sort of what we're
saying here is I guess we're saying that
I'm sorry no we're saying this because I
guess the idea here is that we're not
expecting to be using the fixed Huffman
codes but if we do encounter fixed
Huffman codes it's okay we would just
set up the fixed Huffman table here
right so this is like right and so then
we start to do the loop block here and
this loop I guess we look at B final
so in here this is really a while loop
and you know I could literally code it
that way so basically and we're gonna
read in whether or not we should stop
but even if we should stop we're still
going to process the block because the
last block is a valid block the B final
flag if it got set we will then end out
of the loop and go from there if we're
inside we're gonna take a look at the B
type we've got a pretty easy one here
that just doesn't consume and we have to
look up what these mean we don't know
quite yet what these values are how many
bits they are anything like that but
then we've got these sort of two other
things we have the B type equals three
that one is not specified in spec so we
don't know what it is and we're just
gonna bail if we see it otherwise we've
got the B type of one is the one we're
expecting
I'm sorry - is the one were expecting
one we think might not be allowed in
pngs but we don't know and then we
actually have to implement this loop
right so we needed a literal length
value from the input stream and we don't
know how to get that right now right so
we're gonna get that this is probably a
Huffman decode here right then we look
to see what the value that we get out is
if it's less than 256 we copy a literal
byte to the output stream so basically
what that's saying is if we if we read a
Huffman code and that Huffman code has a
value less than 256 it's actually
putting new data that we've never seen
before into the output stream but if
it's greater than 256 or greater than
equal to 56 then we're gonna assume that
it's actually an LZ jump back
information now let me because people
may not have done LZ before let me just
explain how these work they're very
simple but they form the cornerstone of
like call modern compression anyway even
though they're very very basic
so things that conform to LZ style
compression are really very simple in
theory the way that they work is they
basically say look we know that you've
got some data that you're trying to
compress so when you get to the
decompression stage of things you've
basically got a big buffer where you're
gonna store the output right and this
was back in the days when streaming
might've been a thing too so the output
buffer itself can actually be a rolling
window potentially but in almost all
cases nowadays it's not we're literally
talking about the whole data that we're
about to get but this works for
streaming too you just have a limp less
of a look-back this is where they look
back window stuff comes in but anyway we
have an output buffer that's going to
hold the thing so in our case right this
is an image we're trying to like output
this image right so what's gonna happen
is the decompressor is gonna want
information about what it's writing in
here four pixels right that's what it's
trying to do or if it was compressing
something else doesn't matter what it is
it's just going to write into this
output buffer what LZ style compressors
do is they say let's have two modes one
is put new data in to the buffer and
another is copy old data into the buffer
right so these are the two things we
might want to do in an LZ style
compressor and so what they have is they
have a stream of data that says which
one of these things to do am I gonna put
new data into the buffer or make a copy
old data into the buffer if it's one
then what I'll you know imagine a stream
that actually had this if it's one right
if my mode thing says mode one then here
is what's called a literal which just
means some new data right literal is
just a fancy way of saying put some new
data in because hey it's literally this
data so the stream this is the stream of
the input stream to the decompressor has
the mode value followed by the data to
put in there right so in the case of
mode 1 it's just some data this data
just gets copied right BAM wherever
we're writing to it just gets copied
right and we advance the pointer so now
we're writing here right as we're
writing again if on the other hand we
see a 2 right so maybe after this
there's a - there's a twos the Nexen
stream then what we have is two pieces
of data that follow the - which is the
distance it doesn't have to be in this
order the distance and the size right
now in this case the size may or may not
be specified so if it just is a fixed
like you could have an LC compressed or
set of fixed size
it's a byte let's say is all we do so we
output 1 byte whenever I'm putting a
literal sometimes that's true or we
could have like a there could have been
a sizer that says how big the literal is
that depends on which LZ variant you're
using and it just depends on which gives
you better compression right but either
way it's a literal in this case same
thing we could just say that the size is
always the same but usually the size has
to be specified here in order for good
compression so usually when you do copy
old data you specify two things the
distance and the size right and the
distance says how far from where I'm at
how far back into the buffer should I go
to grab the thing that I will then copy
and put here right and so what this is
the reason this is often called
dictionary compression is because it
effectively treats the output that
you've done so far as a dictionary that
you can look up into and grab whole
sections to specify new pieces of the
stream that are not new at all they're
actually old so that's why this kind of
compressor excels on things like large
sections of similar data because it can
just grab old piece
is where it was already specified and
copy it down so for example you know
large runs of the same pattern very good
right so checkerboard or anything like
that you can just grab whole sections
and move it in lots of little gradient
modifying like crazy patterns tie-dye
really bad because there's nowhere to
grab to do it right and so that's why
PNG is very good at compressing some
data and very bad at compressing others
is just because look Dictionary style
compression at the end of the day cannot
do any sorts of fanciness to try and
compress the data if it's not self
similar so it better be somewhat self
similar going into it and by the way we
can apply some transforms to try and
help it be self similar but if we can't
find a transform that makes it more self
similar it's in the PNG spec well then
we're just dead in the water and the
file be huge that's just how it goes
right now one thing that's worth
mentioning with LZ compressors is
there's the hidden ability to do RLE in
here so you know about hourly
compressors right run length encoding
well run length encoding is basically
poor-man's LZ right because run length
encoding says look I'm gonna either I'm
gonna have to same two modes right and
you project this before one is literal
and two is repeat and repeat we'll give
some fixed length thing like a byte and
just say do this byte 500 times right
so what you may ask is is it possible
for the LZ stream to do a repeat because
otherwise RLE is actually better for
some things kind of right well the
answer is yes it is first of all there's
one way it could do a repeat which is
straightforward and if you think about
it you can see that it's not as
efficient as orally that way is well
look I output one literal okay then I
output a second literal of the same kind
now I've got to then I reference the two
to create for right then I reference the
four to create eight right and
you build it up by powers of two so that
would give you a login way of specifying
it but remember our le was able to do it
in one so the question is can we do
better than that and the answer is by
coding the LZ style decompressor
correctly yes you can what you do is you
specify one literal right and then the
next thing you specify is a distance
right to that literal and a size that
actually would have right past where the
cursor currently is so here's the output
cursor right I've read from the input
stream it says go back one and get this
thing right this piece of data then I
put in a size that's one that's that's
my repeat count so literally the repeat
if there Pete was 60,000 I just put
60,000 and it's like well how are you
gonna copy 60,000 there's only one thing
to copy well as long as you copy a bite
at a time
it just works because I copy this byte
into the output position now I move my
copy pointer forward one and what's
there a copy of the byte beforehand so
it copies into the next one right and
that copies into the next one and so it
cascades forward and effectively does
the RLE for you right so it turns out in
just one mode two instruction I can
actually RLE data as well because as
long as I've outputted anywhere in my
back buffer one copy of that thing well
actually that's not true I have to do it
does cost me one literal right I have to
it has to be outputted it has to be
output right at the cursor right it
can't be somewhere else but as long as I
put one literal in then I can specify a
whole run that goes as long as I want
okay so that's just the basics of LZ
it's really just the same as RLE but
instead of always specifying the thing
to repeat like you wouldn't orally you
specify a pointer into the back data to
use it's literally that simple there's
nothing more to it so if you've ever
done orally you've basically done LZ
it's that simple the decoding anyway and
coding as always is really complicated
because you have to start thinking about
what the best way to encode something is
and that involves all these trade-offs
should I put this should I be Bachelor
repeat here should I not repeat here
right and so that's a whole nother can
of worms but for the time being we only
have to write the compressor so we don't
have to care about that we just get the
easy part anyway so we're expecting to
decode something here with the Huffman
table and then we're expected to look at
it and see what it equals so we're
staying basically if it's less than 56
we do one thing if it's greater we do
another so if it's less than 3 6 we're
supposed to copy a literal byte to the
output stream right so what that
suggests to me is we basically say okay
our output is 8 bits that we're going to
write to our out pointer and so you know
we write something there and then
otherwise we've got this sort of we've
got this loop to do here and I'm not
sure I understand exactly the transit if
the value equals the end of block but I
don't know what that means break from
loop otherwise do some stuff here and so
I'm guessing
so I'm guessing what it's basically
saying is actually this that this
I'm guessing it's basically saying this
it seems to me like they're basically
saying look if it's less than six you do
one thing
it's grating 306 you do another thing
otherwise that's the end of it right put
that slightly the wrong place there
that's what looks like to me so that's
what I'm going with so then what we're
gonna say here is like okay
decode the distance value from the input
stream so that's basically saying here
look we we've got the the length out of
the Huffman decode but now we need to
get now we need to get the the distance
that that look back value right
and then move back or just byte in the
output and copy length bytes from this
position to the output stream so then
we're just gonna go like this right
the only thing I don't understand here
is the length the length value
presumably isn't like you would subtract
256 from first wouldn't you look I'm
assuming that little in here no no no
okay
so this year is actually that right
little n presumably wants to have two
and a 56 subtracted from it here
I would think right so I would assume
even though it doesn't look like this
from the pseudocode I would assume that
this is actually what you want right
because you don't want the minimum copy
size to be 256 so in order to get a copy
size of 1 2 3 4 5 which we might want
you're gonna have to subtract from it
right so presumably we do a Huffman
decode on the distance and then we do
with the copy right we do the subtract
distance and then the copy so to do the
copy all we really have to do here again
is just well you know we'll deal with
writing later and I think that's it so
mostly what I want to know here is is
that correct and then how do we do to
the Huffman to code right we also need
to know how many bits these are so let's
take a look so here's a non compressed
block be type 0 any bits of input up to
the next byte don't ignore it the rest
of the block assists the flaw
information and Len and Len Len bytes of
literal data Len is the number of data
bytes in the block and Len is the ones
compliment
what why so that that's just for safety
sake or something that I don't
understand at all
so it sounds like emmalin is literally
useless I mean we can do this because if
it's the ones complement which is you
know not at least if I understand
correctly what they're trying to say
there I assume that that means it's the
knotted value maybe I don't understand
what they're talking about anyway so I
think that's what they mean really
couldn't tell you
so that's looks like what they're doing
there let's see here for compressed
blocks as noted above the coded data
blocks then deflate form ecstasy cos the
symbols drawn from three conceptually
distinct alphabets either literal bytes
from the alphabet of byte values or
lengths backward distance pairs where
the length is drawn from 3 to 258 and
the distance is drawn from 1 to 32 768
in fact the literal of length outputs
are merged into a single alphabet 0 to
285 where values 0 to 25 represent
little bites the value to these 6
indicates end of block and values 27th
to the 8th represent length codes
possibly in conjunction with extra bits
following the symbol code as follows so
okay
hmm the extra bit should be interpreted
as a machine integers start with the
most significant bit first bits 1 1 1 0
represent the value 14 okay so to b7 to
285 there's all so are they saying this
is literally just hard coded
it sure seems that way
it says the extra bit should be
interpreted as a machine integers store
with mr. surrett right I don't know what
that actually has to do with anything
but I guess they're trying to say
because you're talking about more bits
that are in the stream but just looking
at this
so basically they're just saying look we
have a number from zero to 285 that
gives you the base value and then we
grab some extra bits depending on what
the value is so it's sort of like we
manually made the huffman table so this
is not an arbitrary Huffman D code it's
like a fixed Huffman table we just say
we use always right and you're just
suspected to just decode it exactly this
way
what is this table
this is just I don't know what this
table is supposed to be oh this is for
the distance so the distance is just 0
to 29 and then you can have more extra
bits encoded there so yeah it looks like
basically the Huffman it looks like the
Huffman code is always just for the for
the for the distance in length it's
always these no matter what even if it's
dynamic
okay that's not know so here it says so
I don't really understand why this is
written this way here's a bunch of stuff
that talks about how you would represent
the length and distance codes right and
this is basically a fixed decoding it's
saying here's how to code it but then it
goes on to say well if you're
compressing with dynamic Huffman codes
which is be type 10 which I thought is
what we were going to be doing the
huffing codes to the two alphabets
appear in the block immediately after
the header bits and before the actual
compressed data first the literal length
code and then the distance code
so it sounds to me like this is just not
relevant but yet this was defined in a
section that made it sound like it would
always do it so I'm not really sure what
they mean do they mean to say that you
will always apply this Huffman
effectively after applying the dynamic
Huffman that you apply first I really
couldn't tell you that seems a little
odd but that seems sort of like what
they're saying I'm gonna go ahead and
start investigating that a little bit
more so if I want to consume bits at a
time here
I'm gonna actually do a thing that lets
me do that so what I want to do is I'm
gonna go ahead and put a little like
side path into my consumer thing here
that lets me consume bits and that way I
can just see what some of this data is
because that's just weird
I don't really understand why they if if
that was like that's just a really weird
way for them to describe that
so let's take a look at that and I'm
just going to implement these functions
here so we have to we have consume bits
why is it my beef final settable there
what did I do
all right so we have two functions we
need to do we need consume bits and
flush byte at the moment and I'm just
going to assume that we're not going to
do anything bigger than a 32-bit thing
here and that's all I'm gonna support so
what I want to do here is just say
alright my streaming buffer is gonna
have a little thing in it that's like
maybe something like this not
particularly good again these are not I
would not recommend implementing things
the way I'm doing them here these are
just for my convenience for getting the
file parsed if you wanted something fast
you probably would be thinking along
very different lines anyways so what I
want to be able to do here is I want to
be able to implement these two functions
in terms of consuming bits what I need
to do is make sure that I have enough
bits in my bit buffer basically is what
I'm trying to do here so what I want to
do is say alright let's do this what I
want to do here is say okay if the the
bit count in my bit buffer is greater
than equal to the bit count you want
then I'm gonna be okay I can just
subtract the bits away from there and
give you back the bits that I've got
right that's going to be pretty easy so
I'll just have a
here and I guess what I want to do so if
the buffers bit count is greater than
equal to the bit count then I'm going to
subtract the bit count away and I need
to copy the VAT amount of bits into what
I'm what I'm returning as the result so
what I want to do here is I want to copy
I want to give the results I want it to
be whatever the bit buffer is obviously
I'm just gonna make it give the low bits
right so I'm going to shift in bits at
the top so I want to give it that many
bits back I don't I assume these so I
guess I don't know what order the bits
are going in and here is the only thing
increasing bit number within the bite
are you starting with the least
significant bit of the byte so I think
we're just fine so what I want to do is
I want to take the bit buffer and I want
to mask off any part of it that's not
actually requested here so basically if
you only wanted four bits but there's
eight bits in the pit buffer I want to
just give you back that smaller portion
right so what I want to do is say well
you asked for this many bits right so
let's say you asked for only one bit
then what I want to do is mask off only
that section so what I could do is I can
do this right I can shift up whatever
you asked for the bit count let's say
yes for one or two I can shift a one up
that many places which puts the one in
the next slot the next bit over from the
last highest bit you requested right
from the highest bit you requested I can
subtract one for it which will make
fffff be all the way on the bottom so if
I and with that I'll get rid of
everything on the top that wasn't that
that that you don't want right and then
I can shift down the bit buffer by it by
that many bits right so however any bits
you read I'll get rid of that many right
so again this is the same situation as
before if for some reason I can't read
that many bits I'm gonna treat that as
an underflow well in fact you know what
I don't really need to do that because
I'm gonna call that function anyway and
so yeah I guess we don't really need to
worry about that so what I want to do
now is say well array what happens if
the bit count wouldn't have been
sufficient
so the bit amount of bits I have in the
buffer is not going to be enough right
what I want to do is I want to consume
as many bytes as necessary to get me to
the right bit number right so what I can
do here is I could do a while loop but I
don't think I really want to because I
know that my bit count doesn't really go
above 16 in this case actually so I can
just use two cases probably or I could
just always shift in I could always just
shift 16 in because if you're less than
16 and I know I can shift in 16 so I'm
not sure yeah maybe I'll do this and
I'll just say well let's just assume
gives less than 16 right something like
that so assuming that the bit count is
less than equals 16 then what I want to
do is I want to shift in the I want to
grab from the data stream the new bits
that I'm going to actually process as we
go forward right and so what I want to
do is I want to grab those bits and I
said I don't really know about the least
significant most significant part of
this so we're gonna have to see if I'm
getting the data correctly here we'll
find out as we go but what I want to do
is I want to grab the values from the
from the buffer that I'm trying to
consume here I want to kind of go right
and I think I want to go bleh time so
actually you know what I'm gonna do I'm
us to do this the pickiest way possible
so I'm just gonna keep going here and
I'm gonna say well I can't do it I'm
gonna start shifting stuff in so I'm
just gonna say that you know I've got a
you wait here that's my my bite I'm
gonna consume one you ate worth of data
from the buffer and I'm gonna go ahead
and pack that bite into the correct
location in the stream so I'm gonna say
I've got eight more bites right and I
guess before I do that I want to or in
this piece of information so that bite
I'm gonna well you know what I can do
this so that bite I can shift up by the
current bit counts and or it in so that
should allow me to read from the stream
and pack in exactly as many as as what's
requested when I go to flush the bite
that's really simple if flushing a bite
is just saying look the bit count is now
zero and the bit buff has nothing in it
right so that's really pretty trivial
and I think that's mostly all I need now
there's probably bugs in there cuz like
I said and I don't really know for
tripping spec correctly there so we'll
see what happens but that's mostly what
we want so let's just take a look at
what's going on here so if I want to
consume one bit from the data stream
oops I accidentally deleted the B final
there when I was copying it I still do
want to set B final so when I want to
consume one bit let's go in here
the buffer bit count should be zero in
the bit count is one so what I want to
do is read one byte and then what I want
to do is order that in so it should just
be equal to the byte now it should just
2:36 and it is and our bit counter now
v8 so now I should be able to read it
the bit count should go down by one to
seven the result should just be whatever
the bottom bit is and I think this was a
even value so the bottom bit must be
zero right yeah I think that's right and
so then we just say okay and now we're
gonna shift it down and process the the
new value right so I think we're good
so that just grabs a bit there is my bit
it's zero which is what we would expect
cuz this is probably not the last block
then we need to consume two bits so
let's take a look at what happens there
in here we should be fine because we
consumed a whole byte last time so here
we say alright as if we're okay
let's see what the bit count is now well
the bit count is going to go down again
it's gonna go into five yep so now let's
see what our result is a result is two
hey look that's exactly what we thought
it should be so we need to read the
hoffman codes which we're not currently
doing and then we would keep going right
so I think we're sort of starting to get
the hang of it here we're just getting
to get our minds in the space of the
pink spec now you know like I said
there's a long way to go so maybe not
but we haven't completely been sort of
confused yet we'll get there
so when we we do need to read the huff
and stuff I correctly guessed that it
would be that type so I think we're
reading the spec right there so we want
to look and see what it says about
reading that data in it was really
obtuse if I remember correctly the way
it said it but let's see
here we go
the Hoffman codes for the two alphabets
appear in the block immediately after
the header bits before the extra
compressed data first the literal length
code and then the distance code each
code is defined by sequence of code
lengths as discussed in paragraph 3 2 2
above for even greater compactness the
code length sequences themselves are
compressed using a Huffman code
so it looks like it's just saying use
this ridiculous nonsense to decrypt what
we're telling you a code length of zero
indicates that the corresponding symbol
in the literal length or distance
alphabet will not occur in the block and
should not participate in the Huffman
code instruction Agra m-- earlier if
only one distance code is used it is
encoded using one bit not zero bits in
this case where it is a single code
length of one with one unused code the
distance code of zero bits means that
there are no distance codes used at all
we can now define the format of the
block so there's 5 bits of each lit five
bits of H dist
four bits of H Glen
this is nuts
this is one of the things where I guess
they kept tweaking it they were getting
better compression or something from it
so you see a lot of this weirdness here
alright well let's start reading it so
let's read H lit first H dist n H clay
so these say the number of literal codes
- 257 the number of distance codes - 1
and the number of code lengths - 4 so
what we want to do to get those to their
actual values is we want to basically
say add in the coupe's the 257 add in
the 1 and add in the 4 we then say
h.glenn + 4 times 3 bits worth of data
for the code lengths
so I think that's just saying we're
gonna do a loop of h.glenn +4 which I'm
assuming they actually don't mean
h.glenn +4
after adjusted they that's the plus 4
that we already did so we're gonna read
3 bits that many times right then we're
gonna read H lit + 287 which we or again
already did that many read that many
read that many right all right so that
means we start here and we read 2h lit
like so and what I want to do here is I
want to consume 3 bits for each of these
and what that is is the code lengths for
the code length alphabet which is this
thing up here
I guess the lip so code length alphabet
given just above even the order 16 17 18
0 8 7 9 6 10 5 11 for 12 3 13 to 14 1 15
why would it be in that order if this
data isn't itself compressed why would
they give it in an arbitrary order
though
that's a doozy
I'm not sure I understand why you would
like arbitrarily muck with the order if
I'm reading that right I mean that's
what we're saying are we I mean is that
really what we're saying maybe they mean
something else with that the code links
our interpreters three bit integers
equivalent to zero means the
corresponding symbol it's not used
I feel like there's no reason for these
specs to be this obtuse it should just
be straightforward to explain I don't
understand this but I guess people don't
know how to explain things usually the
Huffman coach the two alphas appear on
the block immediately after header first
the literal length code and then the
distance code each code is defined by
sequence of code lengths as discussed in
paragraph 3 2 2 which is this nonsense
so all we need is the bit links which is
what we're saying here right we're just
providing how many bits per thing there
are right and then we're gonna run this
constructor on it which seems fine right
that all makes reasonable sense for even
going to compacts the code looks suits
themselves are compressed using admin
code the alphabet for codes lengths is
as follows 0 to 15 represent code like 0
to 15 16 is copy the previous code
length some number of times right 17 is
this 18 is that so that's fine
yeah I just can't quite figure that out
that the Swizzle thing I just don't get
16 17 18 0 8 7 9 6 10 5 11 for 12 313
214 115 so if those okay all right you
know what I do think I know why they're
doing that
so h.glenn probably tries to compress
how many of the litter of these it
actually stores by packing in this order
because they think that if they pack
them in that order oftentimes this is
the order that makes it so that you can
use the repeat codes maximally like 16
17 and 18 tend to be specified the same
way so we put them in there usually are
but yeah okay man oh man all right if
that's do you want man so all right
let's see how this needs to be specified
then because the h.glenn the h.glenn
is actually telling me how many of the
things i use pre like when i'm reading
all right so when i read one of these
things i know that the so the thing that
i understand was that the h i was
assuming like okay you've probably
specify all of them they don't want to
actually even specify all of these
they're trying to compress it below that
amount so I guess what they're saying is
like okay the h.glenn will probably
hopefully most of the time be less than
that so I mean I can also do this
I don't know why said H lip there
Swiss Paige clan so anyway now I say
read the 33 bit integer right and the
three bit integer is this thing so this
is like an encoded length and then I
want to say like okay if the encoded
length it's greater than equal to zero I
don't really do that if it's just less
than or equal to 15 else if it's 16 17
or 18 I'm just going to print that out
and say we're in a bad state right so
if it's 0 to 15 we just use it right if
it's 16 we copy whatever the code length
is we use last time between three and
six times and the next two bits indicate
repeat length now what I don't
understand is are you saying to actually
use that now or are you saying that will
come later right
because if that's the case then that
means that this actually gets read in
between the reads for these which it
doesn't specify here and I'm not sure if
that's what they mean the next two bits
indicate the repeat length right there
it is
[Music]
yes so I'm obviously not understanding
this correctly because let's say you
were gonna actually implement this right
off the bat so they must mean after this
I don't know about the in I so I still
don't know why this this order would
make any sense because if you're gonna
read all of these in why would you care
what order they were in right why would
you care to Swizzle them like that
I just can't get past that if thrown me
for a loop because I don't understand
why we need to switch lit each Lippo
students code likes a little a
alphabetically those both makes sense to
me so I feel like there's just there's
just one thing I'm missing in this steps
that I don't understand I don't
understand this swizzle table I just
don't understand where it where it goes
what it's whistling but it seems to me
like I would want to do when we encode
this stuff here I you know I've read H
seal and it can only be 16 plus 4 so it
can only be like 20 or whatever right I
mean it can't be you can't exceed 20 so
you know we know that effectively it
just I don't know seems like they're
telling me to do this and that those are
gonna go directly in there and then
after that we'll be the Decrypter for
decrypter zip I know the Romberg do you
compress our quote-unquote these guys
will definitely go through the other
code
the cool negatives can cross from each
lips into the H just +1 code links in
other words all code links for a single
sequence of H lit plus h2 plus okay so
the other thing it's telling me here is
that we just have one Huffman table well
and that one half a table we just have a
1 decompression block that we're
basically doing here which is whatever
this thing is so I also know that I've
got like my I don't you want to call
this my lend table or whatever and that
thing is going to be at a maximum it's
like so 64 so you know that that thing
can't be bigger than like 512 or
whatever right
so when I come in here I know that I can
use like when I start decompressing
these I don't actually have to treat
these two things separately I can just
say look the total number of things in
the length table is just going to be
equal to the H lit plus the H disc and I
can do them the whole I can do the whole
thing so that's nice there's just one
decompressor that just does the
decompression directly and that's you
know way better right so since these are
all done with the Huffman code and again
I'm just not sure how this part boils
down here the alphabet for code lengths
is this but then I don't really know
what this tells me
yes I do okay so what this tells well
you know what no I still don't because I
still don't know why you need to swizzle
it why can't you just put them in the
order zero one two three four five six
seven eight nine ten right so even the
thing that I just thought I was like
okay no I see what I still don't I still
just can't see it
because it looks like they're always
storing three bits for each one of them
so if you're always gonna start three
bits for each one of them then why would
you ever need to do anything different I
just can't get past it
I got nothing everything else in here
seems to make sense to me but that one I
just can't figure out why would you
specify a swizzle table for data that
you weren't compressing why would you
ever care what order it was in I've got
to be missing something
they must be compressing it or something
because if you're not compressing it why
would u s-- whistle it what am I not
thinking of I can stare at this 1,500
times but I'm just not say anything
different it says right here it reads
three bits for each of these but if it's
reading three bits for each of them why
would it maybe it's talking about this
order as being applied somewhere else
actually
or maybe they just Swiss 'old it just
cuz I don't know I have no idea I mean
it looks to me like this is what's going
on right that's what it looks like the
spec says what is this doing here it
doesn't do anything right I mean there's
no point to that look I just don't see I
don't see how that gets me anything so
you know we get in here and you know
assuming that we interpret the rest of
this correctly here's what we ended up
with h.glenn specified up I got it I
finally got it it's because if you
weren't going to specify all of them
these are the ones they think you're
least likely to specify okay so you are
compressing the lengths some times which
is to say you're going to truncate them
right so maybe I only specify up to
there well if I only specify up to there
their pre saying the most likely things
I need to specify are like 16 17 and 18
okay
so that's why they okay so that's what
it's there for
I should have thought of that before
makes perfect sense
it's just saying look we're gonna
truncate these sometimes here's what
happens when we truncate did I do
something wrong here
so this fills in all the lengths and
that's fine so we get to here and here
are our code lengths right for this for
the for the length compression and
that's all good and hey 18 is all of
them one two three four five six seven
eight nine 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18
oh wait no it's not
but 15 did get filled in
mmm
it just happened so when did 15 get
filled in oh that's a Swizzle there we
go
so 18 is missing 1 so 15 just doesn't
get specified can I see this table
oh of course it won't show me the table
anymore because it is exited the scope
Thank You Visual Studio worst feature
ever all right well anyway I'm satisfied
now that I was worried that helps me not
freak out about that I'm okay with that
so all right so that's all fine so
that's just telling us what the
truncated that some of the values are
might be truncated so I'm cool with that
now code nicely above code not given in
this order fine the code lecture trooper
does three bit integer zero to seven as
above a code becomes zero means a
cursing sindelle symbol literal length
or just the code is not used so
basically if you read a zero it's not if
we don't have all of them I'm not sure
what that would mean I assume it's just
a zero so it just means like we never
used one of those lengths or something
like that right okay so what we need to
do now is we need to write the thing
that builds a Huffman table out of one
of those because all the rest of these
are going to come from that Huffman
table right so what we need to do here
is we need to have something that can
take the h.glenn table that we read and
turn it into a Huffman decoder in some
way right this could really be phrased
like this because we know that's how
many we're going to have right so then
what I want to do say all right let's
produce or I don't know we want to
create the Huffman table here so we need
some way of making one of these so we
need like a PNG Huffman and this is our
length Huffman or this is a sorry this
is our dictionary Huffman
so we need some way of creating one of
these up in tables from one of these
length codes right and so we know that
this is the length codes that we have we
know that well I guess I don't know
exactly what they want they may want
this or they may want h.glenn I'm not
sure I'm not 100% clear on that aspect
of it actually so we'll talk about that
in a second but then once we're done
with that then we know that we're gonna
make another Huffman table and we're
gonna make another Huffman table out of
out of the the remaining stuff that we
get here for literals and distances
right so once we compute this Huffman
then what we want to do is we want to do
a Huffman read from our from our stream
and we need the to give it this Huffman
dictionary to operate on so this I would
say is look to code the next thing here
and that's going to be decoded as a
length that gets put into this table and
what it suggests here is that well
actually I guess this is still encoded
length so the encoded length itself is
then interpreted this way and we write
that into another table that then does
the exact same thing so we have like a
PNG Huffman that's going to be for the
actual data right and we've got one for
the literal Huffman and one for the
length those are going to get generated
out here somewhere
and and used yeah so basically this
should be looking like that more or less
and I think yeah that's it the distance
sorry it's lit Len and distance am i
right yeah yeah so we've got a little an
Huff in a distance Huffman so what we
want to do here is when we decode the
lit Len Huffman is used for the lit Len
exactly as you would expect and the
distance Huffman is used for the
distance so this actually looks like
that right and this is the thing that
produces the tables which then are used
to do the kauffman computation here so
now I again I'm just not sure about this
part I don't know whether this should
really be h.glenn here I don't know how
we want to do the Huffman in terms of
the codes because it'll just be zeros
after I don't know if it's important for
it to see those zeros after or not
that's kind of I'm gonna go ahead and
say not for now so what I'm gonna do is
I'm just gonna say that H plan comes in
here so what I'm gonna do is I'm going
to say for these the same thing is true
I'm gonna pass the actual ones here so
we know an H lit and an H dist for the
two of these
oops
so getting those two huffman tables will
be done by taking the sort of raw table
here so there's the length table and
here's the like little end disk table
for whatever know how we want it's best
for that I don't need to clear that one
I guess technically I do need to close
this one I don't need to clear this one
I guess because these go in order so
this one is just however many the
maximum would it be of these so we know
that that's not oh I already had that
right here so I know I've got this and I
could just write into it as we go so
what I need to do is do the huffman to
code and then I need to look right into
the table this way right
so yeah this index is not particularly
useful so really I want little encount
here to be sort of something that I
write to and what I need to do is I need
to do this decoding before I can do the
rest of this right now in theory if I
know how many H lit there are that
doesn't necessarily help me because I
guess is this always a fixed length
yes I'm not sure exactly how that table
gets interpreted necessarily I think
it's just H litt an H dist is the count
on each of those so I think but since
those encoded legs lengths involve reach
each yeah I'm just not sure about that
so I'm not sure exactly how they expect
the table to then be used I don't know
if what they're saying is that they
because the H lip here yeah this this
just really doesn't give you the
information you need I feel like there's
a little bit of a subtlety there I'm not
understanding as well
so here's what I think it's saying I
think what it's actually saying is that
H litt + H disk is actually the output
size not the input size so I think you
don't do this what you actually do is
this right I think that's what it's
actually saying and then you do this
does that make sense
so we're basically saying look here's
how many you're gonna get but we're not
going to tell you how many actual pieces
of information we're gonna use to encode
that because sometimes we're gonna
encode repeats in here right so what we
want you to do is just keep reading from
your huffman from the table we gave you
before
keep reading from that till you filled
up that table right and we should be
able to assert here also that it's exact
because if if we mess up the stream read
then it won't be exact so that should
tell us as well and then what I want you
to do is produce the Huffman from those
input values that I've given you write
encode it in this way and these are
encoded based on this so again if the
encoded line is is less you're gonna
feed that 15 that's actually the code
right so the little end disk table is
actually going to just include exactly
that length if the if it's if it's a 16
these are zeros both of these zeros so
if it's a 16 we read 2 bits and we can
also do a well I guess we don't laugh to
that so we we consume 2 bits from the
input stream here and we just wrap that
many times
this is like an R le so a rep file is
just whatever the distance tables
previous value was right now we can
assert here that the length count is
greater than zero because if it tells us
to repeat something and we haven't
gotten anything that sounds like a bug
so I'm just going to go ahead and say
that that has to happen then what we can
do is is do the zeros really easily
that's just this right another way to do
this that's super fancy if you wanted to
you could do this
right so this way it's always phrased as
a rep and we just rep set the rep count
and the rep value correctly in each of
these cases in this case we set it to a
rep count of 1 and encoded length and it
could and use the encoded like this the
value in this case you know well you see
what I'm doing right it's pretty basic
let me just read these here how this is
actually like 0 equals 3 3 equals 6 so I
think this is here the rep count is
supposed to be 3 plus the value that we
grabbed right I think so codes 8 16 plus
2 bits 11 16 plus 2 bits will expand to
12 codes
I don't quite get that part 16 plus 2
bits 1 0 will expand to what
I mean or that for now we're pretty good
is it for three to ten times three bits
of length okay so that's just again this
is the same thing and then for zero for
eleven thirty to seven mix of lengths so
this is just that right so that I guess
is what they want from us there and so
then we can make our next weekend's job
to do the Huffman table construction and
that'll probably be nasty but that's
like the last thing then because it
looks like we've got everything else so
then we're just on to debugging which of
course it's going to be in an envious
situation but you know what are you
gonna do I should say input count input
Hoffman results so and then
yeah and I think that's what we're
talking about if I'm not very much an
error uh so there we have it I yeah I
guess I'll go to a brief Q&amp;A but I think
that's pretty much it I'm sure we'll end
up in a debugging nightmare with it as
we try to figure out you know how all
these things are coming together but I
think I think that's everything I think
that's a complete sketch of the
algorithm unless I missed something in
there so we just need to go back and
implement now that that Huffman code
decompression step a like calculation
step and then we have to put it in some
format that we can easily actually use
to to implement the Huffman tree
I'm happy you're doing this I've had
problems making my inflate decoder for
fun work and you being a spectacle and
you being a spectra coder works out
perfectly okay cool
ratchet freak says I believe the length
of the LZ should be interpreted like you
32 copy length equals length table base
little n minus 2 to 7 plus consume bits
do you mean this length
yeah okay but you're talking about
you're talking about down in here right
which we haven't really quite gotten to
yet how have you found the P&amp;G and zeal
obsessed vacation compared to other
associations you have read and
implemented I guess what I would say is
there's two ways that specs can be bad
one is this effect can be incomplete and
one is the spec can be obtuse I would
say these seem to be relatively complete
but quite obtuse for no reason
you can compare that to for example the
PSD specification which is the opposite
it is very easy to understand the
specification but it is very incomplete
and so ideally a spec should be both it
should specify everything and it's just
specified in a clean and concise way
that's easy to understand
right so any way to fix the pink
flashing it was fairly per se you'd have
to ask Allen that's that's as far as I
know that's in for coder I can't fix it
so no the art will probably not be
iterated live it's more just for them to
be able to work on it
what do you do when you have an
incomplete specification is it then
we're just trial and error or their
takes out of community
well there's couple things you can do so
for this particular stream I'm just
going with the spec for a while and when
I hit a if I hit a we haven't yet but if
I hit some part where I cannot figure
out from the spec what they meant I can
go look at reference implementations
which is a good place to go right so I'm
just showing some different steps here
and and you know we'll go to that if we
have to but for the moment I'm just up
coming from the spec because so far
we've been able to do so and so far
we've gotten far enough with that that
it's fine right but eventually we may
have to go to reference invitation
that's the first thing to try to do if
you don't have a reference
implementation and you're kind of the
first person in there trying to like
hack around then yeah you what you have
to do is trial and error but you can
give yourself a little bit of a leg up
on the trial and error front by trying
to feed structured art into the thing at
the head end so that you can its base
like differential crypt analysis if
you've ever looked at that differential
crystal analysis is a way of fussing
with the input stream to an encrypt or
and looking how the decrypt what the do
what the data comes out of the other end
after encryption that same technique can
be used to much greater effect on
reverse engineering right when you're
trying to figure out how a file spec
works and you have an end coder you're
trying to write a decoder what you can
do is just like feed different art into
it like a block of Allred you know and
then a block of all blue and whatever
and then a block of alternating red and
blue and right and then you can hope to
try and get different things to happen
in the stream that will be clearer to
you because you know like okay the
dictionaries only should have like one
thing in it or whatever so I can help
you know right you can construct cases
that you think will create encoding of a
certain nature and work backwards from
that right doesn't that you can do is if
you're a reverse engineering kind of
person is you can reverse engineer addy
so if you don't have source to decoder
but you do have a program that does it
crack on in there right
that's a nasty business but there's
people who do that a lot and get good at
it so you can do that
what for coder version are you on on
stream I don't know is there any way
it's hell I don't know how to sell
rational cooter just caught up with a
stream but I have had a question for a
while when you come up with a reusable
data structure and want to share it
between products and other people how do
you deal with custom allocation I have
been writing some hybrid data structures
and I want to add custom allocation but
adding a template parameter seems like a
bad solution to the problem well oh
sorry just to finish the last question
you said there's a messages window which
has it there you go
402 five so yeah I guess what I would
say is the first question is are you
sure that you need to do allocation and
I know that sounds like an odd question
but I really mean it are you sure that
you need to a lot of times you don't
actually need to this is a little off
topic but for example the way I did it
in granny is there's three calls
basically for everything that allocates
data and they look like this
I so this is the way everything worked
in granny so anyone who just didn't care
where the memory went it would just go
create thingy and granny would allocate
the memory right and if you did care
where it went you would just call get
sizeof thingy and you'd pass the same
parameters you're gonna pass to create
and then you'd call put thingy in place
and you'd pass the memory that you
allocated that was you were basically
warranting that it would be whatever
size came back from this right and
that's just that worked so what would
happen is when you do construction of
something you would just say okay I know
I need this much space to store all the
parts of it or whatever so I just did
that and this actually worked for 99% of
all the things that the library needed
to do there's once in a while where you
actually had allocation that wanted to
happen behind the scenes at arbitrary
times but a lot of times that's just not
necessary so the first thing I would say
is don't actually do custom allocation
anywhere you don't absolutely have to
and buy absolutely after what I mean is
don't do custom allocation anywhere
where you could have allowed the user to
pass in the memory that you should use
almost all things can be done that way
there are very very very few that
actually need to have that happen and so
I would just real
encourage you to look at that first and
then then move on only after you've
completely assured yourself that there
is no way to implement it in that format
why does no inspect the simplest
solution possible so people can easily
implement the parsers and exporters they
need in cases where space speed does not
matter well I think the problem is that
people drastically over estimate the
cost of being under flexible so here's
what generally happens somebody
specifies a good file format and the
file formats like hey we want to start
pixel data so we said the width and the
height and like one compression format
and then that was the data right and
that's super great and it works and
everyone's happy except now someone's
like oh but I really wanted to store
like some copyright information in the
file or I wanted to store some
information about my like layer data or
whatever right and so when that person
goes to make a new file format because
they need these things in their head
what they're thinking is I don't want to
get in another situation like we got
into last time where we had to make a
whole new file format because I wanted
to add some things so what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna make a file format that's
super flexible and has all these
different pieces that can be added to it
so that we never have to have another
file format again and everything is
going to be here in the TIFF file format
right that's like the mpeg-4 spec it's
like the Tiff's back it's like you know
aughhh forbus or something right I and
these are all about packing eight
billion things into the file format that
helps nobody these are just not good
specifications because nobody implements
complete writers nobody implements
complete readers because doing so would
take years right and it's just not
useful specify something simple that
gets a job done well and use it and when
you have something
else that needs to happen do something
else right
that is way better than this whole
nonsense right I don't even think you
should do stuff like put indexed and
true color things the same file format
why they're totally different right
they're really very very different we
don't need that stuff I mean maybe
that's a bad example because it's not
that big of a change right but it's just
like pick a narrow set of things that
you're trying to solve and just do it
right and be done with it and then
everyone can use that if we need
something else we'll use something else
but that way we're clear on what this
thing does and everyone can support it
easily you know are you going to audio
formats next no I'm happy with the web
reader that we've got in there now
that's that's totally fine
alright looks like we're all done
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for those two the handmade here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with dream at home you always can peer
to the game on handmade hero or it comes
with a source code so you can play
around with it I will be back next week
when we will take a look at constructing
those Huffman tables which is the
primary thing that we're gonna have to
do in order to decode the rest of the
data I think we're in pretty good shape
I'm sure we'll have a lot of debugging
to do but basically that is the last
step in the process in order to get a
decoder functioning although perhaps not
functioning correctly and then we can go
through and figure out what what stuff
we missed but that's really where we're
at so this hasn't taken too long I'm
pretty pleased with that but we'll see
how it goes next weekend maybe creating
that and using the Huffman tables would
be a giant disaster who knows we'll find
out alright hope see everyone back here
for that next week until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet