okay hello everyone welcome to handmade
Hero a Monday handmade hero saw her back
after a weekend I hope everyone's
program brain has had a chance to
recharge and is ready to forge ahead
because forge ahead we will again
handmade hero we are in the process of
writing an entire game from scratch
using no library and no engine you know
a daring a daring feat of strength like
I said just me and a thousand of my
closest friends here on the twitch chat
and if we go pretty good
we're sort of cresting a very important
stage in in our engine design right now
we're basically at the point where we're
trying to figure out exactly how we want
everything in the engine laid out so we
can go implement the various components
and so what's interesting is we're at a
point now where we're finally getting to
where I think we need to be in terms of
like managing the entity in the world
stay in kind of a good way and we're at
a point where we're trying to play
around with that stuff to make sure we
get it right and it's just about getting
to where I'm starting to feel like it's
good and so that's that's kind of
exciting because once we can kind of
lock that down and move past that that
that's like sort of one another big
notch that we can sort of say okay we're
good so I want to get right back into
that even though it is a Monday I'd like
to get started dive right in
so the what I will say that was we are
where we at we're at day 56 so what you
want to do is if you have pre-ordered
the game on handmade hero org you should
have got a link in your email if you go
to that link you can download the source
code zip and that source code if zip
should have the the zips for every day
source code so since we're on day 56 go
ahead and unzip day 55 source code into
a directory and you'll be exactly where
I am if you want to go ahead and follow
along with what we do on today's video
so where were we basically what we had
done on Friday is we had just sort of
gotten to the point where we had our
entities partitioned into two sets a low
frequency and a high frequency update
set and we also had it so that the
entities everything was now being done
in entities so like walls like these
walls of this room here
well room and I use the term loosely are
being defined as each little individual
entities that kind of go around the
perimeter and we had started to
actually do the work of as the camera
moves around sort of move entities into
and out of that high frequency set and
so what we were doing is if you remember
let me see here if I have a yeah let me
let me bring up the editor not gonna do
much coding without an editor so we have
the set camera call and what the set
camera call would do is every time we
move the camera it would sort of look
through here and go alright we have
everybody you know who's who sort of
when the camera moves we have everyone
who's going to now become outside of the
bounds of the camera that we want to
simulate outside of the area that we
actually want to simulate so we're going
to move them into a low frequency area
and this offset and check frequency by
area call basically takes care of all
those guys it goes through and looks and
it moves them out and so that's pretty
much like there's there's not much about
that that I'm that I'm uncomfortable
with that's basically what we want to do
because this high frequency entity set
is the set that we're actively dealing
with and especially on a very fast CPU
like the one we're working with right
now that's probably fine for awhile like
we really don't have to worry about that
hardly at all because the number of
things that are in that set is is very
is very low right by the way I tried
installing someone was recommending miss
shift as a drawing program so I'm going
to try it we're trying a new drawing
program today we'll see how it works so
if you remember we had a situation where
you you basically had some if this is
the screen this is what you can see then
there are sort of an apron around there
and we're basically saying that entity
any entities that fall within this
region we're gonna simulate at high
frequency right and then everything
outside of there that's in the rest of
the world is going to be sequel to
simulate at low frequencies so people
out here are not going to be getting the
same attention to details people in here
and the reason we did that was for
scalability right so we want to have
good scaling in our game and I don't
mean things getting bigger and smaller I
mean the ability to scale up to very
large numbers of entities that are all
acting independently and so let's say we
have a game world that's very large
let's say we have huge numbers of
entities you know we've got a hundred
thousand entities out there or
more a million enemies who knows how
many right just a huge number of
entities and we want to make sure that
we can scale so I want all of the things
that we simulate at high frequency I
want that to be a bounded known low
number you know I want to have like a
sub 100 number that's the stuff that's
on the screen and just outside the
screen where maybe you could hear it or
where effects would sort of trickle into
the screen that sort of stuff
I want that number to be low and I want
it to be controlled but I don't want to
put a bound on this number I want this
number to be able to scale up very well
and not affect the runtime performance
of the game so that's what this low
frequency concept is for and so that's
why we have sort of these two different
types of entities and they're doing more
work to be able to support that it's
because we want to scale that up and
realistically we're not gonna be able to
do high fidelity simulation on entities
at this kind of scale but we certainly
could at this kind of scale right
and so what I'm what I'm getting at here
is that that means that that calls like
this that operate on all like every
single one because if you remember I can
show you offset and check that just
loops through all the high the high
frequency entities and if they aren't
inside the rectangle that's bet that the
camera you know the camera bounded
simulation which is which is bigger than
the screen it's it's you know camera
bands is perhaps a wrong term it's the
it's more like the high frequency bound
in fact we could say this is the high
frequency bound right because the camera
is actually only looking at it at a sort
of a different subset so we're looping
over every single high level entity here
but that's okay and while we could up
well we may want to optimize that a
little bit later on we really don't have
any pressing need to because the number
of high level entities is low so the
degree to which that'll tank our frame
rate is actually not high it's not
really that big of a deal
but the other one that we were doing the
other loop there which loops over all
the low entities right so you know this
was the part that dealt with the high
enemies the one that deals with the low
entities that one is definitely a
problem because if we scale up the size
of this array to be like a million
entities or something like that that we
are tracking there's no way that this is
to be performant enough right that's
just not gonna be sufficient it's going
to take too long to do this processing
and everything will slow down far too
much right and we should probably you
know we could presumably demonstrate
that reasonably well
in fact I guess one thing I could do is
just go ahead and and and and
demonstrate here you know if I've got
this you can see that this is this is
relatively performing I mean we haven't
optimized anything and it's it's it's
it's all very intentionally slow and
unoptimized code but it totally is fine
for playing right it's like there's
nothing particularly problematic about
this it's totally workable right but if
I were to go and add a lot more of those
low-frequency entities which I could do
with just a loop here that just adds
tons of the frequency entities right so
when we when we initialize the game here
what I could do is you know this this
goes ahead and creates a bunch of rooms
what I could do is say let's just go
ahead and add a ton of entities as well
right after that just a ton and you know
I guess one problem that we have is we
may mean more space for our four enemies
because we haven't really we haven't
really I think we're still at like 64
megabytes or something like that so if I
beef that up a bit if I said that that
was two in 56 megabytes so we have more
room of the permanent store for the game
and I just create you know some dummy
entity index here I just create some
really large number of these right in
fact I could just say we'll create as
many as we have room for so I'll do a
while loop and I'll do a while loop on
that low entity count and I'll just say
while the low entity count is less than
however many could fit in the low empty
array total right like so then I'm going
to just add an entity right I'm gonna
add a low entity in fact I'll just add a
wall I guess and we'll add a wall at
some location in fact I guess we could
add them all at the same location we'll
just add a wall out in the middle of
nowhere so it's nowhere near the camera
it's not relevant for it to be simulated
or anything like that but you know it's
it's it's out there right so if an AB
cell X AB style Y AB style Z right and
in fact you know I guess one one thing
that I could do is I could just say that
whatever that low empty index would be
right something like this I could say
whatever the low entity count is right
gamestate like soaps I could say that
whatever that is will make that be what
it's you know what it's I'll do this
coordinate what is call it coordinate
there we go and so we'll make that just
be you know that's a 1024 plus this and
then we'll stick it at that coordinate
that coordinate that coordinate in XYZ
right so just stick it out in the middle
of nowhere but they're gonna all be in
different locations right so there we go
that'll add just a ton of walls you know
in the middle of nowhere and I could run
this and it's only going to add a few at
this point right or it should whoops I
guess I added one too many there while
though entity count is less than array
count see then we're going to add why
was that was the assert theme state low
in D count is less than game so why did
I keep trying to add after that what was
the problem there I'm gonna take a look
at that sorry this is probably just me
it's a Monday you got to give me you
gotta cut me some slack here
so the low-end account and that's so why
didn't we break out of that Oh poop duh
we need space for the player that's good
so I guess we got to leave a little bit
of room we got to leave a little bit of
room so for the player otherwise we'll
run out of entities all right so here we
go so now we've we filled up the array
to what 4096 entities right so that loop
is gonna go over the four thousand the
nine six entities and see whether
they're inside and so let's go ahead and
start cranking that number up and just
see what we can go to now computers are
really fast these days so actually we'll
probably be able to go pretty high but
let's find out exactly where we can go
with that
so let's say that we change this to six
five five three six or actually let's
just let's just go its head and pick
that up the numbers I use I used a
hundred thousand before so we'll now
have a hundred thousand in decent here
so well yeah computers are too fast I
guess that's this is not gonna make a
very good demo it looks like it's almost
impossible for me to actually since
we're not actually doing anything than
checking the rectangle bounds of these
guys oh but you know what that's on only
on set
amaura actually so it's only when we
moved through but even so it's plenty
fast unfortunately yeah oh well so I
guess this won't make a very good demo
of why we need to do this we actually
have to be doing some actual work it
would appear in that in that low check
in order for that to to really cost us
anything
computers are so crazy fast these days
it's it's insane
like you know that's not the kind of
thing you would have been able to get
away with much too long ago but anyway
so basically this guy right here was
literally looping over about I don't
know like a million of those guys right
somewhere stri of a million is what I
typed in there and so somehow that still
manages to not be even a minor
inconvenience for us now if I had
changed the set camera to operate every
frame I don't know if that would have
been so if we were doing smooth
scrolling for example maybe that would
have been something that we would notice
in fact I could check that out as well
let's go ahead and see here it's so
amazing how fast computers are it's
great let's see map new entities in and
all the movies out new camera P so
basically this is just I guess I kind of
just want to do this where let's let's
do it this way let's do it so we just
track new camera P equals camera
following entity low P so the it just
it's just gonna be this will be just
smooth scrolling basically so that way
you'd have to check on every frame and
it still I mean that's still pretty
zippy I feel like that's that's still at
the point where it's kind of I mean it's
not a good frame rate but it's not
really a bad frame right either and I'm
gonna go ahead and and step in there and
and this is a debug mode to god intel
they saved they saved everyone basically
from themselves by making such crazy
fast hardware so basically this is
happening every frame now and the
gamestate low-end account should be very
high
count right like you can see and it's
just doing these comparisons just crazy
fast right it's just able to chew
through those things incredibly
incredibly fast you can go ahead and see
it's it's got a fair bit of work to do
but it's all relatively straightforward
it's just able to sort of plow through
this at sort of a ridiculously enormous
rate so I'm not sure I'm gonna go ahead
and try a little bit more to see if I
can get it to the point just to figure
out where are our bounds would have been
where where the breaking point would be
for the number of entities that we'd
have to go go to let's see
so how many do we have here we've got 1
million n of these so what if I was to
go up to 10 million entities I don't
even know if we've got enough room for
those but let's see yeah I didn't think
so
gamestate it's not even that big so
we'll try 5 million entities so there we
go now we've at least hit a boundary at
5 million where you can really feel it
it's it's really super sluggish now
right and it can't hit framerate anymore
its way it's way below the 30 so yeah I
mean basically once we have more work
that we're doing this'll be more
interesting of a test I was assuming
that that it would have a little bit of
a trouble doing but I guess there's it
was just so simple what it was asked to
do but so at that point five million NTS
that's kind of crazy how fast you can do
that loop so all right maybe based on
that test we really just don't care that
much if that really is the status of
things that we're just not feeling that
that much then maybe we don't have to
worry about it right now what I was
going to say was that I feel like we
would probably need to replace that and
I feel like eventually we will but man
like I said peers are so fast it's not
anytime soon I guess I really wanted to
make sure that we were only checking
sort of some smaller subset of the low
frequency entities ones that were likely
to be necessary to page in and so well
do there is put those low entities in a
spatial partition something that allows
us to query them so that we can just get
them without having to do a bunch of
work to you know to figure out whether
they were inside or not so we just
basically you know kind of be able to
ask the world what are you know if the
camera moves in a particular direction
right like let's say that the camera
moves this way be able to ask just what
are the entities in this area and not
have to look through all the entities to
do it but man like I said we just have
so much horsepower to play with maybe
that's just something better left for
when we're doing the performance pass on
things so alright this needs to be
accelerated but man this CPU is crazy
fast and I guess it only stands to
reason I mean when you think about how
many pixels we are drawing just for the
bitmap it's a lot more than this and the
operations that we're doing in here just
aren't that expensive so yeah at the end
of the day not much but we'd like to get
rid of this anyway because we don't want
to be spending a huge amount of our
frame time doing that either way so that
said that said and this is debug code
which is even better we're not even
compiling in optimizations at the moment
so that said where do we go from there
because that actually puts us in some
pretty nice in a pre nice position
so what I would say is I would still
like to go ahead and do one more
architectural change even though we
don't really need to do it for Speed
purposes what I would like to do is is
now go back and finally revisit our tile
map we made a hash table so that it
could be pop properly stored sparsely
and that is something that we're doing
at the moment and what I would be
interested in doing now is going ok
maybe now is a good time to get out of
the tile map business because like I
said I don't really want things to be
too tile oriented at the end of the day
so I just want to make you know I would
like the world to be partitioned into
sections that get loaded so that they
can be stored sparsely and so that they
can be you know paged in and out is
necessary and these sorts of
and so what I would like to do is maybe
start looking at these as just things
that hold entities instead of things
that are in a tile map because I don't
know like playing with a tile map it
just didn't seem that interesting and I
feel like graphics wise we kind of want
to have sort of more freeform stuff
anyway and so my plan was always to sort
of use the tile map as just a guideline
anyway so I kind of feel like I might
want to convert over now that we have
walls or entities I'm thinking maybe the
tile map is just a thing that holds
entities and to the extent that it is
tiled at all if just if those entities
happen to be like things that we created
that go in a timely fashion then that's
great but they don't have to be right so
that's what I was thinking and so what
I'd like to do is go ahead and sort of
change the notion of the tile map here
to sort of have a little bit more of
that right to be based on storing
entities not on storing tiles that have
data values in them right and so how the
I've got to sort of ways I could think
about doing that right right now what we
do is we store all the löwe entities in
this big giant array here right and
those low entities are then just
processed them like in that loop there
we just run over them all or you know if
you have a picture entity that you're
talking about that's fine so I've got
two things I could do here in terms of
storing the entities I could put the low
entities directly into the storage of
the world right I could make it so that
the world the way that the world stores
things is that stores the entities
directly inside it and then whenever
you're talking about entities you go
through the world to pull them out right
the other way I could do it is that the
world is just a spatial index into the
low entity set so that basically there's
just all the the world stores is is
which entities like the index of which
entities are in in a given tile chunk
now there's reasons to and not to do
both of those two things the problem
with having the entities stored directly
in the tile chunks which would make
sense for a lot of reasons
like for the example because we know
we're always gonna be thinking about
this spatially it makes a lot of sense
to be able to say let's process them
directly let's keep them all directly
there in that memory block so that when
we go to access what's in this
particular point in space we can just
run over them right there and not have
to do a bunch of chasing the problem
with that is that we end up in a
situation where referencing the entities
becomes difficult so if we want to talk
about entity 12 in a particular way like
so somebody is like following that
entity or something it becomes more
difficult for them because it's very
hard for that person to know where
entity 12 is there's no central notion
of entity 12 so we would have to have a
secondary way to look up where entity 12
is right on the other hand if we do it
the other way where this just stores
indexes into the low entity table then
we don't have that problem but we have
to chase the we have to chase those
indices so we're always looking up once
in the space position and then looking
up again and really we end up in the
same situation there because those are
basically just pointers you know those
are basically just references to those
entities so we still do have the problem
where when you reference an entity you
have to think about the fact that people
are holding references to it and if it
gets deleted they have to be updated
there and all those sorts of same things
that you would normally do so we do have
like you know it's not a it's not a
problem that has an easy right answer
there's there's different ways that we
could envision doing it and it's hard to
know which one exactly would be the
right way what I'm going to assume is
probably what we would want to do is I
would assume that we we probably don't
need references to most entities most of
the time right like most entities aren't
being referenced most of the time like
there's only a few entities that are
getting followed by some one or a few
entities that are getting chased by some
one or a few entities that are like
inside of some other entity right so the
ability to refer to entities is is a
less heavyweight operation than just the
standard spatial processing of entities
which seems probably more common and so
you know my gut feel with
you know of which one to implement first
sort of suggests to me that storing the
entities out in blocks that are a long
like we're spatial and entities that are
in the same spatial location our group
together seems to make a fair bit of
sense and so the question would be if we
were to do that what would it have to
look like in order for those people who
do need to reference entities by some
kind of permanent handle basically how
would they do it right and so I guess
I'm just gonna think about that a little
bit and see what that would look like
right so let's suppose that we have our
child chunks here right which were
previously storing tiles but now they're
storing like a bunch of entities right
so now they're storing some some low
entity you know some low entity block
that's just a bunch of entities in here
and we'll talk about how we would store
this later but we've got you know we've
got something in here where we're
storing these entities and so now
whenever we're iterating over things
spatially it's pretty easy because we
can just see all of the entities that
are stored inside this pouch chunk and
we're good to go
right really very simple not a big deal
but how do we refer to them indirectly
right and what I would assume is that in
order to refer to them indirectly we
would essentially have two choices one
is that all entities get a universal ID
right and that Universal ID is stored
either in some kind of a tree or in some
kind of array that goes along with them
so for example in here we would have
something like you know low entity chunk
reference or something like this and it
would have you know the tile chunk that
that the entity was in and the entity
right and and the entity index in that
chunk right or something like this or we
could just if we don't ever actually
need that particular piece of
information we could store just a
pointer to the entity but I suspect we
would need that piece of information so
we'd store that and we'd have
sort of a set of those references we'd
have one for however many low entities
there were right and that would be the
end of it that would be the table and so
anytime you got an entity also gets one
of these things in here and when enemies
get moved around they are updated in
this in this reference table seems
totally reasonable to me waste a bit of
space and so it's a little bit piggy so
and the reason for that is because like
I said a lot of entities are like a wall
or a tree aren't being referenced by
anyone and so we're paying the price to
be able to reference them without ever
anyone actually needing to reference
them for any particular reason and so
another way to think about it would be
is there a way that we can structure
things so that only the people who
actually need to be referenced at any
given time and only the people who were
having essentially who have references
to them that are being held right by
some other entity or something that
cares about talking about that stuff
Kennedy you know could we figure out how
to talk about that entity haven't have a
handle that essentially only when that
was true and we could do that as well
with sort of a double reference ii kind
of a scheme but the problem there is
it's hard to do that without bloating
there without basically paying the cost
in another place because let's say we
did something where we said okay we want
to do that so we'll only have this this
right here where we have like a
reference count right
you know referenced referenced entity
count and then we only have these
references for the number that there
were right so we only have a small
number of these you know maybe there's
there's some small number in a given
time there's not very many of them
there's a lot less right if you were to
do that though the question is when an
entity needs to update its location in
here how does it know which one of these
to update right because the entity
doesn't store any way to get back here
so we're zooming over these guys who are
processing them and we need to change
like their location or something like
that Wichita chime therian or something
like that so they can be found again
correctly it's unclear how we would ever
get back here because this doesn't store
the information necessary to find it in
here we could search over this but that
might be expensive and so we end up in a
situation where it's a little bit
problematic and I don't know and we
don't want to add more space here
because the only reason that we were
doing this in the first place was the
safe space if we didn't care about space
we just have the giant array that had
all the entities in it and you just
reference to that so you know it's it's
an open question and by the way someone
was asking I think a couple days ago
about about slot maps they were calling
it and this would presumably qualify in
the slot map category although I never
used that term so I'm not sure I
precisely know when people decide they'd
like to use that term but that's you
know I'm sort of talking about here is
is basically a place where you can go to
find out where an entity is when the
entities themselves are kind of buried
out into the world and and need some
kind of handle that can sort of indirect
through to them so there you go that's
my entire thought about all of that
stuff and like I said I don't really
know what I think the answer should be
yet and so again like I've done many
times is I don't want to decide at this
point I want to just write code with it
and see how it goes and then we'll see
what kind of matures from there so what
I think I would rather do is I think I
would rather go ahead and say let's
let's just do a piggy version it's not
that pig it's not so piggy that it's
time for the Hat but let's do a piggy
version which basically says here's the
top chunk that the guys in here is the
index inside that chunk of whatever the
entity array is for the guy for this
this chunk or something like that right
and then the the reference entities are
always going to be in here so we have a
low entity count like so and they end up
being referenced this way and then we're
just we're basically wasting memory at
this point right this is memory wastage
but we're not really wasting CPU or
cache because for the most part everyone
will be you know normally querying
entities spatially as we move through
the world and so for the most
all of our our stuff that actually does
work on these will should be relatively
efficient at least that's the hope
okay so I think that is what I will go
with for now and this will also solve
our slowness problem where we cranked it
up to five million of these and things
got slow this would presumably also
solve that problem so that's something
that we can think about as well all
right so let's go ahead and and do some
work here and think about how we're
gonna handle these these tile chunks and
that sort of stuff because I'm not sure
exactly how I want to store these either
and so I kind of need to go through and
think about that I suspect what I would
like to do is store entities in blocks
because I know that every screen will
have a fair number of entities on it
they'll at least be walls and and and
trees and that sort of stuff on every
presumable tile so every every one of
these table chunks is going to have some
number of entities in it so what I'm
thinking is I'll probably do something
like this I'll have a tile entity block
a tile enemy block will store some
number of entities right and it'll be
responsible for kind of being the memory
intermediary where I kind of allow
things to were things kind of coalesce
so that you know let's say that we in
general think of there as being 16
entities per block or something and you
know and these things can chain together
so we basically have some number of tile
inity blocks and as tile chunks get
filled up with entities they use more
blocks per you know you know as they go
if that makes sense something like that
I'm not sure if that's again these are
these are largely just speculative moves
that I'm making here and so yeah we're
not sure exactly if that's how I want to
do it or not we'll see there's
complexity there's a lot of complexities
in here so again just just playing
around it and see and so what we do here
is we go ahead and remove the tile
chunks entirely the tile chunks would be
gone I'm sorry the yeah the tiles and we
just go with entities from then on
we just sort of say all right we've got
a an entity block that's our first block
and that's really the only thing that we
would need here and then any as tile
chunks get filled up they just kind of
fill up with these blocks now since all
tile chunks pretty much have that
anything in them I'd probably just leave
that first block in there directly so
you always start out with one block and
that block you know probably should or
so also store its fill level so the
number of md's that's actually in the 16
but that even that may not be necessary
what we could do is actually have the
entities so that they basically have you
know a a is present not present and then
we always process them to say sixteen at
a time that's also totally totally
plausible
so just thinking this through again I'm
thinking like okay so that'd be fine I
store my entities in there that's all
good so we've got you know the enemy
blocks and and they're all good to go
but there's another thing there there's
well there's really two things that I
could do to I could also choose to store
this as just having more tile chunks so
instead of having there be tile chunks
and then off those damn enemy blocks I
could make it so that I just have tile
chunks and tile chunks are you know over
subscribe so you keep going
and you process all of the ones that you
see that have the matching top chunk x
y&amp;z not sure if that's good idea or not
but just point it out there's something
we could do so I could say what to do
here could make this just tile chunk and
then allow multiple tile chunks per half
bucket per per XYZ I should say right so
we could do that not sure if you want to
do that but we could do that so if I do
that then I'll be able to store these
guys and then you know so the main thing
that I'm thinking about now in terms of
efficiency right is I've got these high
entities and the Hyades need to be able
to write back they're low entities and
so this right here would be the primary
place where I'd have to be doing that
Porter chasing and a kind of an
inefficient way right where this is
gonna have to go look up in here and get
back there and that's really the place
where I'm most concerned about it
because
other the that's the one where it's
gonna be most heavily hit because people
snapping references to other entities
where they're like following somebody
those kinds of things I don't think are
going to be as prevalent but I don't
know so it would be interesting to me if
I could figure out some way of you know
some some technique some structure there
that would allow those two to be a
little to be a little more or logical
right that would allow it to to access a
little bit better and I'm not sure what
that way would be the one thing I will
say is that does kind of argue that
maybe maybe I really do want that maybe
okay so this is kind of interesting I'm
glad I'm glad I'm walking through every
single step of this think about that
some more that may argue for going the
other way with it right because since
since the high entities want to
constantly right back into their lows at
that point the tile chunk iteration is
only for moving things in as you move
the camera around it may mean that the
indirection really should be on the
other side so that I think maybe makes
the determination for me I think this
made this that may do it
so essentially I think this is this
might be the way it should go so these
are in fact going to be the low entities
they are gonna stay in here and they'll
be direct and then people will always
use those to directly access them and
then what we will store out here in the
talks is just for any given tile chunk
here are all of the low entities that
pertain to it right and so basically
that is what we would turn this would no
longer really be a tile map at all which
is what I was trying to get to it would
just be something where you know we we
are sort of storing that that large
spatial that large spatial partition of
our entities so that we could scale them
up as large as you want because yet like
even in here you know you did see it
eventually got slow and we scaled it up
to five million and so I'm just I don't
want that to ever be a problem whereas
we start to do more
work on those low res entities or any
other sorts of stuff like that I don't
want that ever to be something that
we're actually spending significant CPU
time on especially maybe on lower end
CPUs than the one that I'm using and
that sort of thing
so I think that's roughly what I'd like
to do so I'm gonna go ahead and do that
and let's let's say for the moment we'll
just go ahead and implement that
directly I think that most everything
that we need to do is already now done
structurally speaking we just need to
start actually operating on these entity
blocks properly so let's go ahead and do
that so first things first we need to
well why didn't I get any oh I know why
because first I've got to delete a
couple of these things so basically like
kept I'll value and Sceptile value are
now no longer useful to us right
so those things kind of need to go away
right you're not allowed to set a tile
value anymore for the most so I'm gonna
I'm gonna start vaporizing these guys
slowly you're not allowed to set a tile
value you're not allowed to get a tile
value anymore because those things are
relatively meaningless they don't they
don't mean anything right because we're
just gonna use entities for all of that
stuff so we'll go ahead and rid of that
we don't care about any of this stuff
this is all all going away so let's go
ahead and compile that and we've already
eliminated most of it from here anyway
it was like this was it the sceptile
value was really all that we were
calling right so we can continue to
vaporize that stuff pretty much all the
way up get chunk position four is
probably still important though that one
we're going to need just for doing our
own accessing so that's fine
but let's go ahead and we'll save that
guy let's see so how about you get two
value and checked and then get tanka so
I think we're mostly looking at this
right so all of this stuff would
basically go away all of that stuff
would be done so let's push that all
down let's grab it out of here right
I'll stick it kind of at the end of the
file
like so see there hopefully there's no
there comments in there yeah so it's
grayed out
everyone knows it's gone and so now we
have our get tile chunk and we have our
get chunk position for and those are
things we actually do want and then we
can start to to move forward so let's
see here
tiles yes that's true that is no longer
an active member tiles is not a member
of tile chunk let's see that's true now
what's interesting about this is when I
do that push array so there is one thing
that's a little janky about that let's
talk about that for a second so if we
talk about having this tile cashier
stored so since if we actually store
these directly in there we are starting
to balloon that out this is getting
rather relatively large right so the
size of this chunk cache is actually
pretty large I don't know that that's
necessarily a problem because like I
said you kind of want it to be direct
access like that but it does mean that
empty slots in here are starting to take
up a lot of space and so I do worry a
little bit about that because remember
the reason there's two ways we can
implement this one is that these are
pointers right so that there's a zero in
there if there's no chunk cache and not
if there's not and the other way is the
way we were doing here where the tile
chunks have some notion of whether
they're filled or not and so the only
reason that I wanted to do it where they
were where they were all there is
because that way you don't have this
double pointer chasing going on where
you look it up and you look I look it up
again but we do have a problem which is
if we want this hash table to be
relatively sparse we're paying a lot of
extra space if we don't have the extra
pointer there so I'm starting to think
that maybe this should just be a flat
pointer and we'll just bite that initial
double indirection and then we have
everything packed in there after the
double of direction happens I don't know
it's tough to say like I said this is
the sort of thing that it's really
difficult to to know
so I feel like it's it's premature to
really do it one way or the other we'd
have to start time yet to see what
whether it was expensive or not right
does that make sense so I'm just gonna
mark that and I'll say tile time cash
should probably switch to pointers which
to pointers if tile entity blocks
continue to be stored on Moss directly
in the Tile Shop right so basically what
I'm saying is if this becomes a pointer
later on depending on how we do this or
it's small then it's totally fine but if
it continues to be a large flat array of
16 or something like that
then I think we have a problem just in
terms of the space wastage for the empty
slots in the chunk cash that's my that's
my thought
so we'll see anyway moving on so we've
got our low entity indexes in here so
now what we need to do is to start
storing those putting putting low
entities actually in there and so this
can you all go away and we're done and
so like I said that the handmade cpp is
now not even using that it's just like I
said it's searching all of the entities
every time so it's totally fine
and mr. walks around here is unaffected
by these changes because really he's not
using the the what's word for it the
he's not using the tile the tile map at
all okay and so what we can do now is
this would be a good point to rename it
from a tile map as well and since we had
that world I'm gonna go ahead and say
let's let's start opening up handmade
world will make handmade world which is
the thing be be our new file and so
handmade tile dot cpp I want to keep
most of this stuff right but I'm gonna
start to rename it so I'm gonna move it
in here we're going to go ahead and vape
this file so this
goes away fleet file and made file dot H
goodbye and then handmade tile dot cpp
i'll save as well just these guys so and
then this can kind of go away I believe
Wow and goodbye and then I've got my
handmade world that's EBP and in theory
let's see save in theory that should
cause us to have to do that
there we go and okay so now that we've
got that let's go ahead and start
working on this a little bit more so now
I sort of we had this world pointer
before right we had the tile map
structure before where did that guy go
we had a struct world there it is and
holding it was tile map and now we're
I'm gonna say is alright we kind of know
what the world is now the world is a
collection of entities so I'm gonna go
ahead and say that this is the world
right and you know and longer have to
double dereference out of it
and then what we've got here is we we
just have a world chunk and the world
chunk stores everything in the world at
a particular area right and we've got
the world chunk cash and that's going to
be all referenced in here right so we've
got our roots we've got our world chunk
shift or world shock masks and now we
definitively kind of know what this is
and that's good so then here we've got
the world chunk and we've got its x y&amp;z
positions and we've got its its entity
block so I don't know what we want to
call that there's probably a better name
for this let's call this
what are we going to call this it's a
good question I'm not entirely certain
I'm not entirely certain I'm also kind
of tempted to do that thing where we
just have both of the the world chunks
there where we just have more world
chunks and you just kind of look for one
that's empty it's kind of tempting it's
one of those tempting things yeah you
know what I'm saying like basically you
know these are that right and then it's
it's this and that's the whole thing it
feels like a good idea to me feels kind
of like a good idea to me so we just
look it up in the spatial hash and then
we kind of crawl through the hash
looking for every hit mmm it's just you
know it's so crazy that it just might
work
as they say such a tough decision with
which to go with first like I said
eventually all things become clear when
you go and do them but sometimes it's
just kind of fun to think and guess and
they like which one do I think is gonna
be the one that I'm gonna like more and
I don't know so you know obviously I try
to prune and and get rid of things that
are obviously gonna be stupid but at the
end of the day trying it's really the
only way I ever know and so you know
really I probably would would have to
just try it the reason that I think this
is kind of interesting is because it
just simplifies things a little bit but
it is nice be able to pull out a chunk
and be able to hand that chunk back to
somebody and say okay you don't have to
do any more tests and you can just sort
of follow through like I'm thinking that
basically someone queries write this
thing and they get back a pointer to the
entity block and they just can like walk
through that enemy block so it's gonna
be cleaner that way I don't know so so
many hard decisions all right
anyway that's all that's all that
nothing particularly tricky
there so then what we have is in this
this is the position of a tile inside
the the the world inside those blocks
which I don't think we care any more
about I'm pretty sure I'll check
position is just not relevant to us
anymore
so I think we can get rid of that
entirely and then tile map position is
kind of interesting
what tile map position was previously
used for was basically a way for us to
determine you know where where things
were we have interesting opportunity now
which is that the chunk X Y &amp; Z does
allow us to know sort of where the guy
would be if we had the offset plus we
knew which one he was in so anytime that
we iterate over the things in one of
these blocks we could these are not
necessary we wouldn't have to store
these anymore which would be great
because that means we don't destroy them
we'd have to save them they're not
important anymore right because instead
of storing what tile you reference to
you could just store which world chunk
you're in and then the offset relative
to the world chunk in you'd be good why
am i hesitating on that right well the
reason I'm hesitating about that is
because is because come back to me there
we go
the reason I'm hesitating on that is
because what do you do when you get to
someone through a reference so I'm an
idiom following other entity I go oh
that guy I need to follow that guy where
is he
I can look him up in his lo entity
structure but I have no idea which tile
chunk he's in right so how would I go
and find out cuz I'd have no way of
literally have no way of figuring that
out right there's no way to know that
it's it's pretty tough it is pretty
tough so that's kind of why you need
this is because this is what lets you
get back to the chunk that you were in
so that you can update yourself properly
or know where you are so it's it's
frustrating because it would be really
nice to be able to store this in a
compress form and everyone who operates
on things per block wouldn't have to
worry and would able to would
able to just do that but I just I can't
think of right now how I would do it so
that when you're going through the low
entities in some other method of
indirection like from the high entities
right going through them although with
the Hyades it's okay because since we
know your absolute location at that
point actually we could figure out where
you were we could go relook you up in in
whatever towel chunk you came from so
that's not so bad
so I guess hi enemies aren't the problem
it's just if a high entity or a low
entity is referencing some other entity
that it's following or something like
that it goes and says where is that guy
it just doesn't have the knowledge to
get back there so man that's that's
frustrating so that frustrates me
because that's such a special purpose
thing that's going on but we need to
support it so the question is again is
there something we can do that's a
little clever here so that our structure
would support that and not have to store
fix this extra information right
I don't know I don't know that's a
puzzler that is a puzzler my friends so
I'm gonna go ahead and say to do KC
puzzler how can we get rid of AB style
star here and still allow references to
entities to be able to figure out where
they are or I should say or rather which
tile which world chunk they are in right
and that's just yeah like I said that's
that's really tricky that's really
really tricky so basically we've got we
don't really need to call these world
map position we could call these just
world positions now right we could just
call that world position and world
diferents I suppose because yeah world
difference will be replaced by just a
vector3 I think in the future we don't
really need that that one at all but
let's go ahead and and fix some of these
compile errors here pull that world
chunk that's the next in the hash
let's see Tom at position so tile map
position is an ad world position I get
some of this cleanup we've talked about
some of these things before but you know
I try not to do anything until it's
really obvious it's time cuz I feel like
that saves a lot of kind of a lot of
going back and forth okay let's see here
hello any chunk reference we got rid of
that that's gone
and let's see tile chunk so there's
world chunk see and this is world so
tile map is now world essentially
everywhere that's the world world world
world world world world world world
okay and similarly Thailand just for a
map is my world
so that's cute yeah keep on going there
see where we're at so tight on cash is
just world Chun cash so I guess tile
chunk becomes world chunk as well these
are the kind of things that I really
wish we had better built-in support for
us um there's some like refactoring
tools and stuff to do this but I just
wish that we had just better unified
like tools for this sort of thing
because it's just kind of stupid but but
this sort of thing even happens it
doesn't take very long it's not a big
deal but it is just kind of lame right
okay so these are let's just go ahead
and replace the world chunk with just a
chunk so cute too there we go and all
these guys can't be oops one of those
guys was not supposed to be it's not
supposed to be replaced
that's okay it'll complain it'll
complain for us there we go well John
cash I don't even know I suppose I could
just change that as well though we could
just call this cuz you know what other
chunks are there gonna be we're calling
these chunks so we'll call them show us
there we go alright so replace that and
keep going next in hash road chunk what
else we get worlds that's world chunk
position is get shot position four
we don't need this anymore do we this is
strictly so this is strictly something
we only need to compute these so world
Chuck position is really if we deleted
that guys don't actually do them anymore
what we really all we really need is the
ABS the the chunk X chunk Y and chunk Z
and I think we're probably going to get
into a situation where we don't super
care about that as much anymore either
so I'm just going to go ahead and stir
that guy
do tomorrow when we do empty insertion
we'll go ahead and deal with that at
that time okay so let's see world Chun
cash
he's just chump cash now what else we
got some cash chunk index world chunk
becomes chump yeah
easy enough tile map difference is just
world difference tile map is just world
see here again same thing
mmm and we'll be able to get rid of that
tile sided meters as well so this will
be pretty good cleanup but we'll have to
we'll have to tackle some of the more
important parts of it tomorrow
unfortunately so let's go ahead and say
that we've got world there so tile map
with those worlds wherever we see that
world world worlds of course the future
a lot of those are world Aero world so
we'll have to we'll have to clean that
up in a second so world arrow rolled
arrow world just becomes world's pretty
easy yeah and tile map becomes world as
well world world world world world and
there we go
that's true that it's not necessary I
agree with that and there we go
so let's see how badly we broke things
pretty badly it would appear so let's
see if we can go ahead and fix that
hopefully we have not broken anything
too horrible with all of my ridiculous
renaming um so let's see here
oh no oh oh but we were just almost
there
well okay what is the problem here map
into task face move player game update
what what does the what was the problem
what what is the problem
so let's let's take a look at I guess I
should look at what got initialized
let's see here world
alright so world is not being
initialized that's really the problem
that we have to initialize world let's
go ahead and see we are that is just
garbage
that's all totally garbage so that needs
to go away like so what's our world
equals that and there we go okay so now
we're back to square one so that's good
and we're in good shape so we can start
the QA so that's totally good so
basically where we're at just to give a
recap is now we've got sort of a sense
of how we're going to store the world
there's only really one large
outstanding question for me which is if
we get rid of the notion of tiles
entirely right so we still need a notion
of where things are that's resilient and
scales to very large floating-point
values and so what we're gonna have to
do is this world position is still going
to have to be relative to something now
it can be relative to the chunks but
it's going to be interesting to try to
think about exactly how we do those
mappings in other words like when we
have something like this in the hand
made here a thing where we do the set
tile and that sort of stuff
right here like when we're adding our
walls so now that we know that the walls
are not going to be at like ABS tile
locations we just need a way of like
cleanly being able to say okay I'm
working on a room like maybe like here's
the center of the room and here's where
I want to put the you know the things
and we need some coherent way of talking
about those things such that we can
create the world so it's nice and
continuous but that's you know such that
we can still have it be resilient and
not have problems with with float
precision right and so that's the
interesting thing because I'm not sure
exactly how we're gonna do that if we
stop think about things in tiles but
that's really the only thing the rest of
it is just a little
and see things that like later on when
we get to ization we could think about
more more heavily
s'alright we can do the Q&amp;A now please
put Q :
before your questions and if you could
keep the questions and things we've
talked about in today's stream or on a
previous stream because that that helps
tremendously if you want to do off-topic
questions come about 15 minutes before
the stream starts we do all kinds of
off-topic stuff man
do you such that the gameplay to be
broadly grid based even without tiles
yes to some degree like I feel like the
grid miss helps the players think about
it that way and so I I don't really know
exactly how we're gonna do some of that
stuff but I do expect to try to keep
things to be sort of grid based for a
player understanding basically but what
I want to be able to do is make it so
that the engine supports arbitrary
things so they don't have to be grid
based but you know we'll still sort of
create them on grids as necessary when
we you know for again for understanding
could you use reflection to help handle
the entities and world chunks I'm not
sure what you mean by help handle could
you be more specific about help handle
like what is it that you think that
reflection would help in terms of
handling if that makes sense
not very many questions today of course
that makes sense we were just sort of
doing some pretty basic code code
changes here although like kind of was
hoping someone would talk about that's
kind of hoping someone would figure out
how to do a good collapse for these so
we don't have to store them that'll be
kind of questing to see I hope we figure
something out eventually well everything
in the game be an entity even if it
doesn't need collision detection or a
movement so if there are things that
that don't have any aspects of entity
ninis at all then we might right but i
feel like we want most things in the
game to be dynamic and i feel like the
game gets richer if we allow everything
to sort of be entity I mean to give you
an absolute absurd example like you know
let's say you know you get a magic wand
that allows things to turn into entities
like so I wave the wand at the wall and
it like grows legs and walks around
that'd be pretty great so it's those
kinds of wacky things that I think it's
interesting to enable and so I kind of
feel like making everything in entity
it's just kind of a nice thing and then
figuring out how to make entities very
dynamic so that they can represent walls
or represent real things and scale
between those nicely is a more
interesting direction to go rather than
hard coding what the difference is
between a piece of scenery and a piece
of interactive stuff but who knows we'll
see when we actually start coding the
entity stuff how hard turns out to be to
make those things realizable do anything
most of the storage concerns done from
having just high and low entities and
would be solved by having more
granularity there so you have more and
smaller arrays of entities with some
particular aspect I don't think so and
the reason for that is because like I
said I want the constant of entity to be
very dynamic in this game I want things
to be able to very broadly be able to
support a lot of different mix and sorts
of stuff so I just don't think we're
going to be able to have homogeneity
I think homogeneity really won't be
possible with the game design if I
thought it was gonna be very
in that way we absolutely would because
it'd be much better for performance as
well you mentioned considering having
the world chunk store a fixed entity
count and then add multiple chunks to
the hash table if necessary to store
entities if you were to go that route
how would you compare one chunk to
another multiple chunks would have the
same XYZ so the answer would just be all
queries into the hash table would walk
all the chunks that had the matching X Y
Z so basically that that lookup right
this lookup right here instead of
stopping when it found a match would
just go through and actually use every
single one that it found instead of
instead of this break it would basically
process one and then go to the next one
and process that one and so on right and
so the only reason I didn't do that
is because C and C++ don't make it very
easy to do visitor style stuff like
basically normally in other languages
you just patch closures in here and they
just get executed and see those dos
Elevens a little bit better about that
but it's still just it's not a language
it's really built for that just bottom
line and so you know I was sort of
staying away from that because it'll be
easier if this hash lookup can just
return to you a chain and you iterate
over it rather than doing it the other
way around but that may change because
it's not that hard to make a little
iterator here that I would that you
would use to crawl over them and so
we'll see I may just do that
in terms of handling entity compression
decompression where would you grab store
the state of objects that are coming in
and out of the updates update scope so
that is just inset camera right so this
is the thing that basically stores stuff
back and this is the stuff that pulls
stuff in right I think that is that what
you're asking I'm not 100% sure why did
I call see compiled with a Cephas list
compliers compiler C++ well because this
isn't technically C right you couldn't
write this wouldn't compile with the C
compiler so for example if you look at
here we've you know these operators and
stuff that's all C++ so this is
definitely C++ code it's not C code it's
just we don't use much C++ because most
C++ is not particularly good but there
are some language features of C++ that
are good and so we do use them so
technically we're not C
well I can't world position just have a
pointer to a world chunk instead of all
those ab styles then offset underscore
is relative to the world chunk so the
problem is that doesn't really save us
much space right like I mean it might
save us a little bit of work so that
that's not a bad thing to do right but
this is you know this is 32 plus 32 plus
32 right so it's it's 64 it basically
would save us half right if because a
pointer is a pointer here is going to be
eight eight bytes whereas we're using 12
bytes right so it's just it's not like
getting rid of all of it which would be
much better right saving four bytes
versus saving twelve and furthermore
you're kind of in a little bit of a
rough position if you put a pointer here
that isn't really all the information if
that makes sense I mean it sort of is in
some sense but it sort of isn't isn't it
another with this you can actually
figure out where in the hash table
something is whereas without that you
can't so for example if you just have a
pointer to a world chunk
let's say you want to remove that chunk
from the hash table you wouldn't be able
to do it because it doesn't store
pointers back to where it is right so
that would be kind of a bit difficulty
and you'd go so as long as we continue
to store the complete XYZ in there
I guess that's totally fine so yeah so
it's still fine storing the pointer
would be fine it just doesn't get me as
much of the savings as I want
I would like to figure out a way just
nuke this entirely if that makes sense
but you know maybe that's not possible
I didn't get to met - I didn't get to
watch the entire stream so I don't know
if you considered it but why don't you
have a flag for about to be deleted that
every entity checks against and nulls
pointers have it visible for all
entities for one frame so the reason I
don't do that is because not all
entities will be updated every frame
especially the low entities will get
updated at a very low frequency that's
why they're called low entities so they
might be updated once every 60 frames
for example so using a deferred deletion
strategy like that really isn't an
option for us we probably still will
defer deletions to the end of the frame
for another other reasons but we won't
be able to use that as the way that we'd
get out of jail free for deleted
entities but that's not what we were
talking about here really either so just
to be clear I wasn't worried about that
I was literally just worried about the
fact that as things move spatially they
will move where they are in the world
storage right and so that was the thing
that I was worried about not the
entities would be deleted that wasn't
that really wasn't the problem
do you think that you do puzzler will be
handled tomorrow and do you often sleep
on decisions like that
I do often sleep on decisions most of
the time I never do anything right the
first time I have to sort of play with
it and then I think about it I'm like ah
that's what I should do and so that's
why I trying to think it through too
hard I try to do a little bit of due
diligence when I'm writing things I'm
like okay does this seem right you know
struggle it around and then I just go
and I make that thing and then later I
think about it look like I'm good okay I
should have done it this way and I do it
because usually I find that I have to
see the thing to really know because
there's a lot of complexity and it kind
of like sinks in and I'm like ah that's
the thing whether I don't think I'll be
handled tomorrow I think that will have
to get a little further down the road
and then we'll see how the low entities
get updated in that sort of stuff and
then we'll kind of go ah there's how we
do it and then we'll do it if it's
possible
what I was getting to is that we seem to
be working towards what's called the
entity component system where what we
call now high and low are just
components alongside anything else we
want to add two entities later yeah well
so it's hard to say I mean that may be
true but it like I said I don't really
like to pre guess those sorts of things
I'd rather let them emerge properly so
that they are guaranteed to be right for
the model that we're actually using so I
I do suspect we will have components but
those components will probably be part
of the low entity because they never get
deleted right they're going to be there
forever and so presumably the high
entity is really just a thing that that
stores like the animation state and
stuff like that and so I don't see the I
don't see much benefit in trying to
overthink that and making some generic
way of handling it when the specific way
of handling it I think will be what we
actually want and so if that makes sense
hopefully that makes some sense
see that the computer handles 1 million
entities without lagging do we really
need to worry about the performance it
coming from one extra point or
dereference so yes and no I mean you're
right
probably not but what you have to
remember is the poor dereferences are
the really bad things a lot of the times
that case where we're looping over the
entities is the best possible case it
has no pointer dereferencing it was just
a loop that's completely streaming so
the memory is read and complete
sequential order and is the perfect case
for the processor and so Porter chasing
is actually much worse than that it can
be you know up to 200 times slower than
what we were doing right and so so yeah
I am a little bit worried about it just
from the standpoint of like it what if
we actually want to scale things I don't
want there to be a lot of that but
realistically no I mean at some level we
don't care too much about some of these
things because like the tile chunks
won't be accessed at a frequency that's
high enough to make the extra point
under efference really that big a deal
and stuff like that so we'll see but
again I like this is this is also some
practice I mean the idea here is not to
just do the the sloppiest thing that
works is to actually think through
everything and program it as if it were
intended to be professional and that we
don't want to spend a lot of time doing
things that we don't have to because
again this is educational it's not the
goal here is not to ship the game as
quickly as possible in this piggy away
as possible which would be a different
skill set right it's to sort of show how
to think through problems and do
efficient systems because a lot of times
you do have to care about efficiency
this just doesn't happen to be one of
them because you know at the end of the
day that particular loop is not gonna be
a problem although who knows on the
Raspberry Pi maybe maybe we'll be we're
on the best possible case right now so
keep that in mind like things get a lot
worse when we step down to mobile or
whatever right well enemies be able to
transfer from one chunk to another yes
that's all the enemies will always
transfer from one to another unless
they're pure scenery I think so anyone
who moves will often switch between
chunks
will we start using the entity system
for something other than walls players
walls soon or will the renderer come
first we'll probably add a few more
things in there for testing purposes
like you know pickups chests at an enemy
or - something like that just to get it
working correctly so that we're seeing
roughly what'll be in there and then
we'll do the renderer does that make
sense
how are we looking here it's at the end
of the queue colons I think that may be
the end of the queue colons I'll give it
a second just to make sure just to make
sure
looks like that is the end of the queue
Cowen's I believe we have reached the
end of the queue colons so I think
that's about it for today we will wrap
it up here tomorrow what I'd like to do
is go through and actually start using
the world as a spatial partition where
we put stuff in it so we'll go ahead and
implement that code and then that'll
pretty much be you know and I'll go
through and probably pull out some of
that code that's in handmade that's EVP
right now that's that's about moving
things in and out of the active sets so
we'll kind of we'll just play around
just cleaning that up a little bit
making it a little more formal exactly
how things work trying to get it down to
something relatively straightforward
that's that's very clear and easy to
follow but I think that's about it for
playing with how the world is stored so
then we'll try adding like I said a
couple more entity types just play
around a little bit you know maybe try
to create a bit of a sprawling world
like let make a stupid generator that
generates a lot more stuff and make sure
that we handle it right make sure that
you can walk around the world with a
million entities actually placed and
that it all works ok and then we'll kind
of consider this part of things done for
now and we can move on to the animation
code which we do need to prototype as
well before moving on to the to actual
any any real straightforward work on
engine components like the renderer but
again things seem to be going pretty
well
I do wish we had like a slightly better
solution for for for the a couple things
in here but those are the kind of things
that usually shake out over time you
kind of start CEO I should have done
this way and then it's a little bit
clearer it's fine so I'm not too worried
about it but but there are a couple
things that still bug me so hopefully
we'll get you know all that stuff ironed
out at the end of the day but for now
that is the end of our coding oops oops
what did I do here edit there we go ok
make sure it's looking pilot so thank
you very much for joining me it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
with handmade hero you can pre-order the
game on hand me here org and it comes
with all the source code you can
download the source
every night after I finished coding here
on the stream I upload it so you can
play around with it and learn to program
gave yourself as much as you would like
to so if you'd like to do that Hameed
erode out or get the PR at a button and
you are good to go if you want to
support the video series we also do have
a patreon you can subscribe to that's
clickable over here on hand made here on
a tour as well and then we also have a
news and forum site that I highly
recommend people check out if they're
trying to learn from the stream
schedules here although I also have the
Twitter bot now is handmade hero on
Twitter now tweets the schedule properly
as well so that's good but it also has
an episode guide for catching up on past
episode it's got a coding resources
guide which basically has everything in
it that you might need for porting to
Mac or Linux people have done work on
moving it to platforms that we haven't
gotten to yet so that's pretty cool
place to check out and we've got a code
discussion forum where you can go and
ask questions if you have questions
however my check in and out so thanks
everyone for joining me I'll be back
tomorrow at 8 p.m. PST where we should
be able to wrap up some of this world
stuff hopefully and I hope to see you
all there thanks for joining me