hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the shows that codes a complete
game live on screen but has been away
for the past two weeks because of an
office move and a planned power outage
in the building which is you know I
guess that is exactly as its name
implies a planned power shutdown perhaps
might be a more asked term for it but
anyway we're back and if I remember
correctly from the time when we were
programming two weeks ago or three weeks
ago at this point now we had our
renderer working pretty nicely but I
wanted to go ahead and re-enable multi
sampling just for one of the passes so
that we could get rid of some of the
Jaganath because we as sort of we don't
really have any need from all the
sampling now that we do the depth
feeling we don't have a need for the
multi sampling in terms of using it for
you know screen door transparency which
is what we're using it for before we
have much better solution for that now
that works a lot nicer but we don't have
any way of reducing sort of the Jaganath
that's inherent in the line drawing for
our geometric services and let me just
go ahead and know what happened there
let me just go ahead and start up
everything here and I will show you what
I mean
all right so if you take a look at what
we've got going on here this is the this
is handmade here running as it normally
does and what you can see is you know
anywhere is that there is a sprite or
anything everything looks fine the
reason for that is that sprites
are anti aliased in the bitmaps
themselves right so the edges if we look
around like where the hero's hat is or
anything like that those are all nice
and anti-alias then that's because the
anti-aliasing is kind of baked into
sprite itself and the actual 3d geometry
that we're rendering to show that's
right it's just a little car it's like a
little rectangle right it's you know
something that that looks like that and
we never see the edges of that rectangle
because the Alpha of the texture at that
point is zero and so we don't have to
worry about the rasterization of those
edges and the alias thing that might
happen along those edges as we draw them
right that's just not a concern for us
because you'll never see those edges
with registered visible so the part that
is in danger of aliasing which is the
pixel the textures in the pixel that
that are within that card those you can
count on the artists who have anti
aliased when they initially paint them
right that's that's what that painting
process automatically does in Photoshop
as you do the brush strokes they're
automatically anti-alias so it doesn't
even really have to be something they
are to see them thinks about usually
they're just going to have it into this
if you're a pixel artists they have to
worry about interesting manually but
they will know how to do that so that's
all well and good but we do have some
geometric primitives in handmade here oh
not many and we probably will not really
have much more than what's on the screen
just right at the moment but we do have
them and so if we come take a look at
stuff down here for example you can see
we've got all of these cubes that
comprise the environment will be texture
mapping these cubes very shortly in fact
with a you know various textures based
on the location that the hero is in but
what you can see is
if the rendering of the cubes does have
sort of jagged borders right and that
may be difficult to see because if
you're watching at home you know the
video compression on Twitch or whatever
may be hiding some of those artifacts
but if you have access to handmade hero
source code if you're if you pre-ordered
the game and you you know you run it
yourself or if you just you know have a
high res if you switch to the the source
mode into which you can probably see
there's a stair stepping pattern that
occurs right along here now I can
probably go ahead and and make that a
little bit more specific let me see if I
can sort of yeah there we go
so if we zoom in here you can see maybe
a little bit more what I mean right so
what we're talking about is this little
you know thing here and you can see what
why this occurs right when you just draw
a straight line in screen space well
it's it's you know it's based on pixels
because that's the only thing that you
can set discreetly on a monitor and so
each individual pixel has to be set to
something so if all you did is just draw
a geometric primitive without any
concern even if you do it perfectly
which the graphic card does they get a
perfectly measured line in pretty much
all cases you can see that you'll see
that there's that pattern because
there's no attempt to smooth the
boundary in between them right and that
harsh edge is very clear now if you can
trust that to for example what happens
if something this anti aliased you can
see that when we get in here right you
can see how there's a lot of fuzziness
in here that is being used to hide the
fact that there's a harsh line there and
that's again just the artwork being
created in that fashion you end up
getting a much smoother result and the
it's a much more pleasant thing to look
at right it's like it when we actually
zoom out to the full level which I'll be
honest
no idea how to actually do a 100% there
we go you know the hero looks nice and
clean and smooth and you don't notice
those it looks much more natural whereas
everything that was drawn as part of
those cubes anywhere it looks very harsh
and angular now there's too
you know processes that play here and
only one of them is the one that really
concerns us now the first process that's
in play is just general smoothing and
that's something that the artist can be
doing in addition to anti-aliasing it's
not technically really a well as I
shouldn't say technically anti-aliasing
obviously it's just a broad term that's
applied to trying to get rid of the
artifacts that occur when you have too
few samples to represent a particular
function and in this case you know
that's just pretty language for saying
well look if we had such dense pixel
arrays on monitors that your eye could
literally not see them at all right so
the pixels were so tiny that your eye
couldn't make them out in any way then
you know at some level of density you
you know if you imagine that these
pixels are one you know atom wide or
something your eye just has so much less
fidelity that you would just draw
regular lines but they would look
infinitely smooth to you you wouldn't be
able to see any jaggedness because the
resolution would be so high and some day
monitors might get to that point I have
no idea but in the meantime monitors
have much less resolution than your I
can discern your I can discern the
pixels themselves fairly easily on
today's monitors especially at a
resolution like 1920 by 1080 which is a
very common resolution for a game to run
at and don't forget 1920 by 1080 may be
stretched on to a 60-inch monitor or
television I should say in the case of
play in the living room and so you're
going to have these big old pixels
staring at you in that case so again
there's two ways of combating that one
of which is analytical in one of which
is just purely
aesthetic the purely aesthetic one is
you know an artist may decide to just
close up an edge right and that is not a
mathematical process that is nothing to
do with signal processing but it's
nothing to do with analyzing the
coverage or across pixels or anything
it's just them making it smoother so it
looks better right and that's not what
we're going to talk about here we're
talking about the analytical kind of
anti-aliasing which is to say that if we
take a look here how do I get out of
this there we go if we take a look at an
edge like this one in the center here
what we could say about this edge is
that well you know we know that the edge
actually represented something that was
you know not necessarily infinitely
precise because we are talking about
floating-point numbers in a machine but
we certainly knew more about it than
just what we've shown here right and the
reason that we could say that we were
more precise than what is shown here is
because this edge actually started
somewhere sub-pixel
right we knew a floating-point location
that is not constrained to the 19 by
1920 by 1080 grid that was in here
somewhere and we knew that that line
sort of passed through this pixel and it
probably did pass through this pixel a
little bit just not enough to cover the
center of the pixel where the graphics
card typically uses the center of the
pixel to determine whether that pixel is
in or out in terms of rasterization so
what we want is the more analytical
version of anti-aliasing here which is
that as we go through pixels based on
how much of the lot how much the line or
the side of the primitive that we're
actually drawing how much of that is you
know encompasses each individual pixel
we want to blur those pixels such that a
little bit of the the primitive color
contributes there and a little bit of
what was there before you know it shows
through right
and again because we are using a
z-buffer dren during scheme that means
we don't sort the primitives in order so
it's the misnomer to think that we can
do something like drawing things on top
of other things or whatever else in a
normal scenario because the z-buffer is
worth doing a sorting but in our
particular case we're using a depth peel
rendering technique which people who
have been watching the series know how
we're doing that and so we actually have
two options for how we could handle this
and to be completely honest I'm not
exactly sure which one we would want to
do but I'm probably going to go with the
multi sampling one let me explain what I
mean so normally if you just have a Z
before rendering technique that just
does a single pass and you draw your
geometry then what you have to do is you
have to turn on what's called multi
sampling which you've already covered if
you're not familiar to go back and watch
the episode where I cover more detail
but basically what it is it just takes
more than one sample per pixel for when
you're drawing so it's basically over
sampling the screen and it has ways of
doing that
more efficiently than if you were to
just literally render at a higher
resolution so it can get more quality
out of the same amount of work than
doing something like that would then
doing a high-res render and then
blurring it down for example it can
jitter the samples which produces much
nicer results and it can also do
shortcuts where it knows for example if
a particular pixel is entirely covered
by one piece of geometry it can just
only do the work for covering it once
right so it can do sort of
short-circuits to the process that
actually save a lot of work so there's a
lot like I said there's a lot of options
there my allergies have been awful
lately by the way as those of you watch
the series now I've been blowing my nose
continuously
ah it's the worst
so turning on multi-sample a tailless
think it's probably what I'll do just
because it's the most straightforward
and I think might be what we want and
we've already done it before right we
already tried it one time for other
reasons and we decided to go with depth
feeling instead because it was much
better quality for what we were trying
to do but in this case we we could
imagine a technique that was slightly
different we could imagine a technique
that did rasterization of all of our
primitives at their maximum boundary so
normally what happens again if you just
get that centroid rasterization and that
centroid rasterization basically says
either the pixel is in or out based on
whether the primitive encompasses the
center of that pixel what we could do
instead is switch the rendering rule to
say that the if the pixel is covered at
all right so if the in the primitives at
all then we want to render to that pixel
and then we let the depth peeling
algorithm handle the blending of those
right because we're already doing that
death peeling and the only reason I
would say not to do that is because I
don't know how many graphics cards
support changing the rasterization rule
in that fashion
I suspect the best of two new of a
feature I'm not really sure we could
take a brief look to see but I'm pretty
sure that's a OpenGL rasterization will
change ah let's see
[Applause]
ah let's see
see what this is
so this is not I don't think what we
want here it is that's what I'm looking
for so you can see this is the exact the
exact thing we wanted so it's called
conservative raster and so if we were to
use something like this extension right
then what would happen is we could tell
it that we want to fill all pixels
touched by you know a primitive right as
you can see here this essentially adds a
conservative restoration mode where any
pixel is partially covered even if no
sample location is covered is treated as
fully covered and a corresponding
fragment will be shaded right and that's
what we want right it would call our
fragment shader anytime the primitive
passed through that pixel even if it
would not have normally been rasterized
under the normal fill rule right
unfortunately like I said I don't think
this is the kind of thing that's that's
mainstream enough let's find out
[Applause]
I
so I don't even know if it's supported
on AMD you know maybe it is maybe it
isn't
anyway that I'm just tossing that out
there so you know that that was an
option I this graphics card this is an
accreta credibly old machine that we use
here on handmade shirt here oh this
graphics card I was made this extension
is a 2015 this graphics card I think was
made in 2009 I'm not 100% certain if I
know exactly when it came out but I
think it's 2009 so it definitely won't
have anything like this and so that's
why you know even though that's to be
honest probably the most straightforward
thing for us to do and probably would be
the most efficient as well I think we
just can't count on that being available
in most places that we're going to need
it and so I think we're going to have to
go with the more traditional approach
even though it is going to be a little
less efficient and adds a you know an
extra step to our rendering process that
we don't actually want to have whoo-hoo
but that's just the situation so let's
just take a look at how we're going to
do this here it shouldn't be too
complicated but again because it is
dealing with OpenGL and graphics cards
it may take a long time to get working
just because it's always very finicky to
deal with these sorts of things you know
you can't step into the graphics driver
so you can't really and you can't step
into the graphic cards internal logic so
often times it becomes very difficult to
determine why something is wrong when
it's wrong as you know we've been very
lucky on handmade here Oh strangely
enough we have not really had too many
real hang-up bugs with the graphics card
but you know there's always the first
time so any time we're going to be doing
graphics card programming I just want to
make sure to mention that even though
the thing we're doing may be very simple
you may be in for a rocky ride so if you
remember how this
working currently it's very weird by the
way after three weeks to come back to
such huge texts normally when I'm
programming the text is so much tinier I
always forget on handmade here it's so
huge I select oh my god I can barely see
any of the code but anyway so here you
know if we take a look at how this this
works
where is that frame buffer there is the
way that we were doing things is we've
got this created frame buffer call and
we're creating a bunch of frame buffers
that we use for deaf peeling and right
now what happens is we create a couple
different deaf peels and then we blend
those together and that's our way of
getting nice kind of anti-alias sprites
and I was really surprised I'm sure
people have done this before but I was
surprised I had never heard of this I
kind of just thought of it as we were
doing handmade hero and we were not
getting the results I wanted from multi
sampling and I was like what if we do a
deaf peeled approach I've never heard
anyone advocated deaf peel approach for
sprite rendering but I tell you I really
like it and it seems to be a pretty
great way to get you know really nice
sprite compositing without having to do
the sorting at all and it allows you to
do a lot of special effects and have
things like things fade out just work
and you don't have to sort your
transparent objects at all which is nuts
I mean it's just it it seems like a
really good way to use the GPU resources
that you're inherently typically not
using in a 2-d game because you know in
a 2-d game you don't have to do as much
work as in a you know 3d photo realistic
game you know if you take a look at
something like battlefield 1 and you or
doom the latest version of doom that's
the original version soon you know they
just require tremendous amount of GPU
power and gamers have these machines
capable of processing all of that and
when we take a look at a 2d game where
like well where are we going to use let
CPU power you know and we typically
don't but you know this is a pretty good
example of a way you could use it you
know
you can use the extra GP part DuPont a
bunch of death deals and then you can
have this really nice compositing so
anyway I'm surprised that I haven't
heard more people advocate that but
maybe just because all the graphics
programmers are busy writing 3d engines
that's probably why so anyway you know
2d probably isn't that interesting to
them at this point right they're too
busy doing like Fox will comb tracing or
something like this anyway so if we take
a look at what was happening in our
source code here we have the create
frame buffer call and we left in the
ability to create multi sampling so you
can see here we have the ability to
create a multi sampled frame buffer
texture so if we want to we can do a
pass that have a you know a multi
sampling turned on and it does a resolve
of that path and I don't know I think we
unfortunately already delete deleted the
code
oh no we did so we've got the frame
buffer code here too that we used when
we originally did our frame buffer
compositing - this was not remember
Kramer for resolve so the thing that
takes the multi sample buffer and turns
it into a regular buffer that has only
one sample per pixel
that's this call right here and that is
great because that means we can just use
this code again and be on our way
so all I want to do here is take exactly
the same pipeline that we are using at
the moment but change it so that when we
initially render the first the closest
depth field right so the death field
that's the closest to us which is the
first one that one since it will have
the hard edges on it I just want to see
if I can take that one render just that
peel with multi sampling blitt it down
to a regular buffer and then do the rest
of the death peels the same right so so
I'm essentially just literally taking
and compositing the multi-sample that
one first all the stable slice down to a
regular buffer and then letting the rest
of the process repeat as normal so I'm
not suggesting that we do multi sampling
on all the buffers and the reason for
that is because it doesn't seem
necessary
remember our depth peel is taking pixels
that are like stepping backwards through
the depth buffer so the first thing you
draw is the one that is the pixel that
is front most to the eye then everything
you draw and subsequent death field is
behind that pixel so in my mind that
means that the jagged edges are going to
be primarily in that for a step field
because everything else has to be
something that was behind one of those
jagged edges right and so the chances
that you could tell two jagged edges
that pass through each other in some
weird way you'd have to be able to tell
if that jagged edge was jagged only in
that one pixel where it's eclipsed by
something in front of it partially right
and that doesn't seem too problematic
now that doesn't mean that it's not
problematic because you could imagine a
circumstance in which you would see it
for example where you would see it is
where we have transparent particles the
if a transparent particle passed in
front of like a line one of the
primitive lines that would be a you know
you know that would still be jagged
right so if we wanted to to eliminate
those artifacts as well we could multi
sample everything and so that's another
option and probably one we would want to
also allow and so what I would say is I
don't know that there's any real reason
to ever multi sample the
positing phase so when we composite our
def peals together I don't think there
is any reason to keep multi sampling at
that point that may just be excessive
but we may want to allow the user to
specify or rather the settings of the
game to specify how many multi sample
passes we do so def feeling can be done
where it's like how many def peels do
you want to do and then it can also be
how many of those def peels should be
multi sampled versus how many are just
straight one-to-one pixels alright so
let's take a look at what we would have
to do here so we know where our depth
feel occurs right our death peel is
right here so when we do our render
group stuff you know here is us doing
our rendering as we go through here we
you know every time we hit this code
path where we do the end peels we know
that we finished one so if we wanted to
every time we finished we could do that
blitt resolve right and furthermore when
we're at the start code right here when
we're at the start code we could also at
that point do one too you know we could
if we want to do something at that point
that was like switched to a multi sample
buffer for not already on one or other
things like that so I'm not sure like I
said I'm not really sure how we want to
do this and I'm also not sure if there's
any value in to persisting the multi
sampling in through the compositing
phase so let's start I guess with the
simplest thing to do that seems like it
makes the most sense to me because yeah
like you can see here where we do our
let me let me go ahead and load these
both up at the same time here is the
final sort of composite that we do so
you can see here we you know we
basically do our stack shading here and
yeah we don't really neat you know
this is just straight alpha blending
right
it's just alpha blending one on top of
the other on top of the other and so one
question that I have here is you know if
the GL blip frame buffer call actually
had alpha compositing built into it so
if you could do a geo blip flame buffer
with blending enabled that would
probably be the cleanest way to do this
we just loop over and instead of ever
running this shader at all we just do GL
blip frame buffer for each frame buffer
onto the back onto the main frame buffer
with alpha compositing on but I don't
know that there's any way to really do
that so I don't think we can I think
blitz lane buffer only does copies but
don't quote me on that so let's see here
lipid transfers or rectangle yes it's
just a pixel transfer so it's not gonna
it's not going to go through the
blending buffer it's not to go through
the blending algorithm at all so that's
you know there's really nothing we can
do about that
so again we're forced to kind of think
about this from the standpoint of when
we actually go to composite these we
probably want to do something a little
smarter now
I am loathe to create a separate buffer
just for mixdown but that seems like
what we'll have to do meaning you know
what we probably need to do here if
we're just going to go whole hog on it
is in this open geo frame buffer where
we've got frame buffer handle color
handle and death handle we would have to
have one more handle here which is the
like you know composited handle or
something I'm not or resolved handle
right the thing which takes the texture
that's been multi sampled and turns into
something that has a middle of exampled
we need to place for that to go and so
if we want to do the composite in one
pass which maybe we don't but if we do
then we would need to do it that way the
other thing we could do is we could read
directly from the multi sample buffer in
the shader the problem with that is that
I don't think there's any way to
actually read from a multi sample buffer
in a shader without knowing how many
samples are actually are and looping
over them which could be a lot less
efficient then letting the graphics card
do its built-in resolve which knows
exactly how to do it the most efficient
way so I am a little nervous about going
that one as well so just thinking about
it I would have to say like I guess
let's try the more straightforward one
first which is Glu int resolve handle
and then in here where we are doing our
creation so where we do our creation
we're going to want to put it in here
now I think
one thing I do want to do and I kind of
meant to do this before is the filter
type clamp to edge stuff is always the
same for any of these and so I probably
want to say in here set default frame
buffer texture parameters I probably
just want to grab these and put them
there and I'll just take that filter
type and I'll pass that in but other
than that it just works right and that
way we don't have that duplicated in
those two places so if we want to change
those parameters we can later similarly
we could look at this a slot 2d
multisample bit here you can see that
these two are basically the same as well
the only difference is the setting for
right like what the what the component
is and that's really it everything else
is exactly the same so we could actually
do that as well we could say create
frame buffer texture bat and we could
just pull this whole thing out here
maybe I do it like this
[Applause]
and maybe I'll call the frame buffer
text image like that so yeah so in this
case we just need to know the slot and
then we need to know the format that we
want that texture to be so that's going
to be you know just right here and I
guess what's a little bit confusing
about what's a little bit confusing
about this is the default frame buffer
texture format has that srgb that weird
srgb problem I forgot about this is
going to cause us a little bit of an
issue here so for whatever reason this
card cannot do srgb rendering with multi
sampling on which is very strange and
supposedly not even how it's ever
supposed to be but it just is we don't
actually know why the driver refuses to
create a surface in that way so yeah we
have the solution to that which is we do
the squares and square roots and so we
can force it into that mode if we want
to and that's fine but I forgot about
that it will not it means that we will
not be able to test the rendering
perfectly on this machine because of
course we can't test multi sampling and
srgb together which is a bit of a bummer
to say the least well putting in two
anyway so yeah looking at this though I
guess now that I think about it pulling
this out is a little bit trickier
because when we want to do the depth
version there's that switch that happens
here where you know you're you're sort
of picking a different one of these in
either case which would means they would
have to
half the both both things in that they
wanted both this and this because both
of those two things will change
depending on the circumstance on the
other hand I guess they don't really
need they only need to pass one of them
technically because this part right here
is not relevant since we only pass a
zero you could really pass anything you
wanted for these two presumably and it
wouldn't be a problem so we really only
need to pass one thing in and that thing
would be this format so it suppose
that's actually fine all right so that's
that's all good all right so there's the
format that it's going to use and what I
could do here as well as I could
preserve this a little bit and just say
format and look to see if it is a depth
format and if it is a depth format half
the depth component just to make sure
that the driver doesn't complain so
there we go and we'll just grab out that
the wrong way so we'll just look to see
hey are they you know it's just the
depth one that they're creating if it is
a diplomat they're creating then let's
go ahead and give the driver the right
information at what we would be
submitting if you're spamming just in
case it does area checking there and
thinks things have gone horribly wrong
all right so we've also got a width and
a height and we've got a slot
so what we could do here in addition is
we could kind of bundle all this
together and say well the jhen texture
is part of it we could do two so all of
this could go in here as well and then
what would happen is we just have a
return value right we'd have something
like this and then in theory we can
replace all of these pieces of code with
this so here when we're creating the
color handle we can just say why don't
you make us one of those please
wait why is the slot past the second
time that was the that was just silly so
in theory yet all of that can go away
and then we really just have this now
the filter type I has to get passed in
as well unfortunately here because again
that's based entirely on the flag now I
suppose we could pass those flags in and
have this do the switch on the filter
type and yeah I mean that could in
theory also because that would instead
of passing the slot it would just do
that automatically so I don't know look
yeah maybe that's a good idea not I
don't know that it is though so because
we're going to need to create both for
the multi samples one that is what the
sample and one that's not so at that
point that seems less good so I'm going
to go ahead and say let's get rid of fat
and put the filter type in there
so that we have slot width height format
and filter type and then I think that
should be good to go right
[Applause]
all right so we can replace this one as
well exactly the same way here's the
results deft handle that we want set so
we just want to do frame buffer text
image for this one as well with all the
same options except now instead of
passing the frame buffer texture format
we actually just want the depth
component conversion great and we can
get rid of the rest of these and now
we've got a lot less duplicated code in
there which is nice
easier to read and also has the
advantage of if we want to change it
once we we know how to do it and of
course as you may suspect the reason
that I did that was because now we have
to create a third one and I felt like
copying something three times definitely
gets the point where it should be pulled
out into something reusable so what we
want to do now is say well okay
in the case where we're going to do a
multi sample frame buffer let's just
create a resolved buffer specifically
for that so the resolved buffer is going
to be the same as the color buffer right
the only difference is it's not going to
be multi sampled so this slot here is
always going to be zero texture 2d
instead of potentially being multi
sampled other than that it's going to be
exactly the same right there's going to
be no difference between the two it's
going to be it's going to be identical
so yeah this case we don't ever need to
attach it to a frame buffer well I guess
we probably do we probably have to
create yet another frame buffer here
because we're going to have to basically
resolve it to something and without a
frame buffer we are unable to resolve it
so we need two things we need resolve
frame buffer handle and we need resolve
color handle right
[Applause]
so what we want to do here is check the
frame buffer for completeness at this
point and then this one also will get
checked for completeness for good
measure let's go ahead and turn this off
I so basically what I'm doing curious of
saying okay this is creating the initial
frame buffer and then if it's multi
sampled I need to create another frame
buffer right and that frame buffer is
used for nothing other than the resolve
[Applause]
we do the resolve color handle the same
way we did the other handles and then we
want to do is attach it to this frame
buffer again not using the slot because
we don't want it to be mobile sampled we
want to be texture 2d always and now we
have a frame before we can use for that
purpose right so the first thing we do
is run this without the multi sampling
to make sure that that still works okay
right because we made some changes there
and I want to make sure that we don't
have any issues with it right and so now
what I'm going to do is try to turn on
the multi sampling and again
unfortunately that's going to break some
stuff now what I need to do here is we
still need to do the testing that we
were doing before when we init OpenGL so
this allowed GPU srgb
I guess we have that off permanently so
I guess that won't create a problem for
us oh right we did turn that off because
of the sRGB inaccuracy because our
sprites are not currently srgb they're
actually squared so I guess that's fine
so I guess we're okay I yeah all right
so everything should work peachy then
because we're actually doing the the
srgb approximate srgb handling ourselves
so that's pretty good all right so what
we want to do now is we just want to go
ahead and implement that you know
resolving path that we were talking
about before so if we go to our create
frame buffer code here you can see
here's our depth peel flags right
and those def peel flags are I guess not
set with multi sampling enabled so
what's interesting about this is I guess
this entire time we've sort of been ah I
see so so there we go again this is the
problem of not having programs on this
go based on theory so forget that we set
ourselves up for this all right so we do
have this all in place we have the multi
sampling hint there and the multi
sampling kit will basically say oh hey
how did you want to process multi
sampling in this case right did you want
to use it or didn't you and that's what
we want so I think that'll all work good
and remember when we do free frame
buffer now we're going to have to be a
little bit more careful because we're
going to have to free the rest of this
stuff as well so we've got our resolved
frame buffer
[Applause]
and we also have our resolve color is it
resolved frame before handled yeah there
we go alright so that's all good and now
we will create a multi sampling surface
with their resolution with their
resolving frame buffer and all that good
stuff
however we are not actually resolving
anything at the moment so we shouldn't
see anything it looks like we've got a
error to look at here open Jill did not
like something about what we did
GL bind texture has generated an error
invalid operation so it looks like it's
trying to to bind oh well yeah so this
is actually expected I just didn't think
of it again
because when I said we won't see
anything that is actually true but
there's also an error that will be
generated so you know if we if we ignore
the error we would see a black screen
but the error that's generated
specifically is that again you can't
render from a multi sampled texture as
if it was a regular texture
remember OpenGL has a bunch of filtering
rules that are set up and are
specifically defined around having a
regularly sampled texture one that's
sampled in a grid and it expects that
and that's part of the rendering process
a multi sample buffer does not work that
way a multi sample buffer is a series of
scattered samples there jittered and so
sampling from that is not defined
rigorously at least not in OpenGL or not
in the vanilla case now again
you can sample from these yourself so if
you want to write your own sampler that
took lookups into the texture and did
some kind of averaging based on the
distance from the point being sampled or
whatever else you could do that it's
just not defined by default and so if
you try to bind a multi sample texture
it took the texture to read from it's
going to give you an error and that is
again specifically why I created those
resolve buffers so what we want to do
here I suspect is when we do that bind
texture here I want to basically switch
on which one I'm going to use based on
whether multi sampling is enabled so
basically I'm going to do something like
this
let's first grab Jill frame buffer I'm
going to go ahead and grab out that
particular buffer and then what I'll do
here actually I guess is let's just say
oh okay ah right I guess now think about
it we're also missing the depth buffer
in some sense I probably could have just
created two different frame buffer that
might have been smarter now that I think
about it created two frame buffers one
multi sample one not
you know what hold that thought I think
that's what I would rather do so let me
undo that change I think that's not
necessary right I think what we could do
is say let's just pretend that that is
not there like so
this should run just fine because now
we're not creating out well that's a lie
I have to turn off multi sampling there
we go
so what I'm going to do is I'm actually
just going to go in here to where we
create the peel buffers themselves which
is right in this roof right here and I'm
just going to create a resolved series
right so every time we create a def peel
buffer what I want to do is I want to
basically say if we're multi sampling I
want to create a corresponding depth
field buffer without the multi sampling
right so if the multi sampling then
create a depth peel resolve buffer and
do it with the same flag but I just just
don't want the Open GL frame buffer
multisample flag right so this makes it
creates a parallel array of Def peel
buffers that we can use specifically for
resolving our stuff so that for when we
go through free frame buffer we're going
to have to do the same thing again to
free all of our resolve buffers but
other than that it should be the same so
that's pretty great because that's much
cleaner than what I was going to do
where I was
over complicating things by making it so
there was a whole nother set of
parameters in there so let's leave it
like that I think that's much better
so anyway does anyone know where why is
my why is my little it stays 335 my
little head card is not there what I'm
going to put up a little something in
that corner to remind me that it's not
there because I'll constantly be romping
on it all right in fact let me switch
over here to avoid it
all right so let's take a look at what
happens now so I'm going to have the
same problem if I don't do anything
change it presumably which is that you
know I'm trying to bind a buffer that I
can't draw from right I'm trying to bind
a texture so what I need to do now is
actually do that resolve but you know
before we're going to draw from it I
have to actually resolve it and so in
theory what I could do is just say well
okay this is what the peel buffer would
be but if we're multi sampling then the
peel buffer is actually going to be
[Applause]
coming from the resolve path right and
now that should actually work properly
in the sense that we shouldn't get the
error because that is a texture you
combined or not but we have to figure
out why not but we won't see anything
yet because nobody's writing to it what
is the error here oh that so yeah again
that's also fine those are just the two
places that we read from those buffers
so here's the other place we read from
those buffers and again so you know what
into if we want to do that meaning if I
want to read from in two places
maybe I'll just make this a little
utility function
so you can just call it and you'll know
you'll get the right one something like
get depth skill read sucker right as
opposed to get depth field right pepper
because the writing will always be the
same no matter whether you're multi
sample or not but the read buffer will
switch alright so in order to do this
all I really need to do is pass whatever
the index is so this kind of goes away
here and so now anyone who's calling
that I can just call it correctly and
not have to do any thinking about it at
all the same is true here right so this
is looking for that color handle and so
what we can do is say alright it's got a
wants to get a peel index here so here's
that peel buffer right and now in theory
no one should be drawing should be
setting as a texture the multi sample
buffer and so now we're to the place
where I would expect to be which is
black screen because we're drawing you
know we're creating our jetseal buffers
ostensibly with multi sampling but we're
not actually using them because we never
resolve so we're drawing out of buffers
that never get anything drawn into them
so now what we want to do is do that
resolve the other thing I would point
out is you'll note we don't ever want to
actually clear these so it's okay that
we're never doing this because those
resolve buffers are never going to get
used for anything other than just
splatting the contents of the
peel buffers that are multi-sample just
drawing them directly down alright so
let's take a look when we get to render
entry and peels that means we have
produced a peel buffer and you can kind
of see here we're about to do like a
binding in one way or the other either
will bind back to the original or we
yeah either will bind back to the
original or we're going to bind to one
of the subsequent death deals so what I
might say here is when we get to the end
of our death peels then what we probably
should do is actually use the the read
buffer call and the reason I say this is
because after the best feeling is done
we don't really want to be doing multi
sampled rendering anymore right because
we're sort of saying we're doing debug
passes or UI or something that we didn't
want to use multi sampling on so in the
open field find frame buffer bit here
I'm just going to say let's go ahead and
bind the peel buffer that corresponds to
two slot 0 in that case and then in here
when we're actually coming through
render entry end peels in any case no
matter what pasture we've completed here
is where I would like to do that resolve
so what I want to do here is before I
bind whatever frame buffer we're going
to be drawing to for the next pass I
want to just do a quick bind where we
bind to read buffer and a write buffer
in the case of multi sampling so if we
were multi sampling we know we have to
do a smush down here so I want to read
from the DEF peel buffer and right to
the resolved buffer right and I want to
do whichever one is the one that we're
currently on so when we hit end here I
want to do like if we just drew to peel
index 0 I want to do
zero right so then we're going to do
this we're going to do the blit
unfortunately this is the wrong stuff
for the blip because this was for screen
bleeding which is not what we want so we
actually want something that looks like
this we're just doing a rendered lit
irrespective of screen cordis we're just
doing our render back buffer right and
furthermore we need to do a resolve of
both the color and the death buffer
because we're going to be reading from
the death buffer as part of the Deaf
dueling pass so I believe that's all we
would probably have to do
famous last words and graphics
programming so take that with a grain of
salt but I believe that's mostly what we
would want and now we'll let OpenGL tell
us what's wrong here so the error
message is must be dual nearest
you-know-what and that's actually fine
because these should be one-to-one so we
actually don't want any filtering on
here anyway so in theory that should be
fine that's probably better
oh my well I I can't say I have any idea
what happened to the framerate there
everything appears to be working but it
definitely appears to be much lower than
we would like I'm also seeing some weird
artifacting in places that I have no
idea why there would be art affecting so
I think we've got a little more work to
do
like they're super strange fringing yeah
on the side of things I mean we are
getting some of the anti-icing but yet
so I think part of the problem is the
depth buffer anti-aliasing is maybe the
problem with producing the Deaf suffer
in an anti aliased fashion is maybe that
we're not getting what we need to get in
terms of how we would def peel right
hmmmm what's interesting about that is
yeah I mean we could just keep doing him
that kind of suggests to me that we
would have to do the whole depth peeling
process I kind of suggested me that we'd
have to do the whole def peel process in
multisample
which i've got to say i feel like it's
just going maybe a little bit too far
hmm that's good about this I'm going to
take a brief screenshot here because I
do want to look at to it and what the
results look like so you know in terms
of getting the anti honest thing on the
edges it does look like that produced a
reasonable result in some circumstances
it definitely didn't produce a
reasonable result in some other
circumstances like you can see here how
it's actually darker than the gray there
and some weird ways so and that's
probably again because of the depth
artifacting there so yeah hmm so what
should we do here I'm not sure again you
know what I would really like to do is
not use multiple sampling at all and
just use conservative rasterization I'm
trying to think if there's some way we
can sort of approximate conservative
rasterization by making our primitives
bigger than they need to be and then
doing the rasterization ourselves
problem with that is we would have to do
it in screen space because we don't know
until we start I'm you know until we
actually project the stuff down how big
they're going to be how big a pixel how
big we'd have to move them to the
giraffes Reds basil
yeah and you can see when it is actually
working properly you do get nice results
there right that's much more pleasant
than than what we were seeing for
certainly a lot nice nice and smooth
well I don't know what to say I mean
what we could say is you know we could
just try doing the whole thing instead
of doing the resolves just do the whole
thing in multisample
I don't know that that's the smartest
thing to do in the world but we
certainly could try it and again the
most the reason why that's complicated
is just that the multi sampling is you
know only lightly supported in the
pipeline we have to sort of manually
access those samples very specifically
well I guess here's what you said I'd
say let's at least try it I mean you
only you know pound Yolo I guess in this
case so I guess you know we'll just
we'll give it a shot I so essentially
the problem here if we want to do
everything multi sample the whole way
down is that we need to read from those
buffers in a specific ways so let's go
ahead and grab that quick reference card
that we've used before
I'm hoping this is available in three
two so I don't know if it actually is
let's wear the Texel there we go so
let's see if it's on here I actually
don't see it on here
so if we wanted to do that we may have
what we might be required to use a
higher level of of shading actually take
a look here
oh you know what no I take that back
this is this is just me looking for it
in the wrong place so technically that's
not true it's really just that you have
to declare the sampler as a multi
sampler yeah okay sorry that was just me
spacing on that it's it's early in the
morning for me here so this is actually
all we needed access to the multi sample
texture right and that is luckily for us
in three point hours let's say I thought
it was in there so since Stanford two
DMS exists in there we should be able to
do what we were doing oops we should be
able to do what we were doing just fine
hopefully that's not what I wanted I
just want the spec for it there but that
may be harder to come by
let's go like this kill excel stack
point out
come on people
okay there's a page that has all these
specifications on them bring me to that
page I don't want the PDF I want the
actual here we go there it is this is
what I wanted so I should be able to
read OpenGL shading language 1.5
specification 1.3 specification etc so
let's take a look at this one right and
let's take a look at sampler to the MS
so it looks like that was added after
take a look is it in here yes so
basically that was added it looks like
in the change from 1.4 to 1.5 and so we
would have to go to 1.5 for that which
is probably fine right that's not going
to go up to open jail for or anything so
probably that's just okay yeah and so
you can kind of see what happens here
when we do a textile fetch what you do
is you can get the sample and say I want
to get a particular sample out of the
texture at this location which should be
fine for us with what we're doing
because we can use the sample value that
comes through in the shader which it
will define for us right let me see if
we can kill drag sample toward where are
these defined
so here's the special variable to come
through the fragment shader with the
fragment coordinate front-facing clipped
distance color frag data plain cord
primitive ID I was hoping that there was
a sample value in there and you would
think that there would have to be in
order for this to work but I don't know
where that actually is let's see
I'm interested to know if I look at the
quick reference card and I look at the
shader the variables that are listed as
built-in and none of these are specified
in there either
that does make things a little bit
trickier for us because if we just want
to say hey we need to get this whichever
sample we're shading right now that's
the one we need to get from this
particular from this particular sample
but I don't see it
let's take a look at the spec under
Texas fetch
here we go so here's all the texture
lookup functions right I don't know if
any of these are discussed in detail now
it doesn't look like it it's not the
best spec in the world if we're honest
okay
still not seeing anything that tells me
what I want to know
so I'm not sure I just want to get I
show you what I'm wanting and not
getting here so what I want is inside
these routines right we've got two
places that we actually load from these
so you can see here where we are doing
our def peeling we do a textbook set
from the depth sampler and that textile
fetch is just like hey here's the
location to fetch from and if I wanted
to fetch from a multi sample texture the
thing that the problem is I need to make
sure that I'm sampling from the same
sample as the one that I am on so if
this pixel is evaluating sample three I
want to make sure that I get depth
sample three from this buffer right
that's the key but I'm not sure how to
guarantee that that is what it will
actually do and I just wanted some
documentation that would be specific
about what would happen in that case
right so what you can see here is that
if I call it with a two DMS as far as I
can tell you have to pass an integer
sample number right I don't see any
other way that you can sample from one
of these and so the problem is if I'm
going to pass it integer sample number I
would need to know what that integer was
for the current sample but I don't know
what it is because it hasn't given it to
me anywhere right so what I would have
expected and what I'm not seeing is I
would have seen inside the sub built-ins
right that in the fragment language in
here I would have expected to see an
integer value like in like this one that
just said sample
but I do not see it and so yeah I
suspect that possibly the reason for
that is just because you don't always
run the pixel shader on all of the
samples in a pixel because if the
geometry doesn't pass through that pixel
then it's only going to render if it's
entirely enclosed if it doesn't pass
partially through it then it's not going
to call the fragment shader for every
sample it's only going to call the
fragment shader for just just once and
fill all the samples with that value
hmm
so I think I mean unless I'm mistaken I
just really don't see a lot of ways to
do this I can't think of a way out of
this really all we really want is
conservative rasterization that would
definitely solve our problem
unfortunately that's not really
forthcoming we could turn it on on video
parts or I guess I don't know there was
a really good page I can't remember a
extension support I can't remember yeah
this is it
what's this it let me see if I can
ascertain how much support there is for
that because I don't really know one
percent on this page
let's see if I can look by if there's no
way to search for conservative
rasterization I don't really want to
port it open Jill versions I want
capabilities and so let's see can be
conservative derivative so they don't
have these are just the caps fits about
here conservative there it is yeah so
that's like that's like not very
supported at all so we could get
anti-aliasing pretty cheaply on any
modern geforce card it looks like but
that's about all we would get
you
so let's take a look at Intel's got a
certain conservative rasterizer
extension it looks like - so yeah you
know we could get some anti aliasing
with the def peeling on those but not
great if we're honest not not fabulous
so I do wonder however you know so maybe
if we just return to what we've got at
the moment since it does look like going
the sampler - DMS route so first of all
I have no idea what that slowness is at
the beginning they're like look what is
going on here I have no idea I have no
idea what what is happening with that
that is kind of just nuts so I don't
know if that's something stupid we're
doing where or if s something where
we're just pushing the card a little bit
too hard because it is a at this point
seven-year-olds graphics card which
admittedly is not going to be the
smoothest thing on the planet but I yeah
just looking at it at what's going on
there I'm just I'm not sure exactly what
I'm not sure exactly what I could do to
sort of work around this problem in a
meaningful way I mean I'm pretty sure
we're not doing anything too dumb here
[Applause]
that all seems pretty reasonable
so yeah I don't know presumably we
haven't messed up anything accidentally
right if we turn mother sampling up or
presumably back to running properly go
ahead and so yeah that's all
everything's flying there no issues at
all so yeah I don't know what else one
other approach we could take I'm
thinking of what else we could sort of
do there that wouldn't be too onerous
I mean I assume the problem there is
just that creating the Deaf buffer in
the Deaf peel mode is simply not going
to be precise enough at the edges of
objects because you need to know what
the depth was at that point for blending
but you don't actually know what the
depth was because when you resolve you
will average them down right in other
words I've got an edge passing through
space like somewhere here where part of
the pixel it's going to be something way
behind and part of this could be
something up close I feel like it would
fix it if it just picked the closest
step value I don't know if that's
something I can actually have it do
meaning when I do the frame buffer
resolve I don't actually know if there's
some way to get it to that I feel I
could do it myself with some kind of
custom resolve but what I needed to do
here right is when it does the depth
buffer I needed to pick the maximum
value whichever one would have been
closest so I wonder if there's some way
I can do that
let's let's find out maybe that's
something I could do
and maybe that that would be enough to
get us over the hump
let's see filter subscribe the
interpolation method that will be
applied three sites person it must be
Jill nursery linear alright
let's hear it
claim duffer and while we're at it we
might as well bring up the stack and
take a look
so here's the speck looks like a blip
frame buffer and see if they discuss
multi sampling in here hopefully they do
come on people
that's what I wanted
all right so let's see
how do we resolve these
they don't really specify this in this
part of it it doesn't look like
well
not really getting the information I
want I just want you to tell me if
there's any way I could process this and
get the maximum depth value maybe I'll
ask Google
[Applause]
I like to visit the Qualcomm
I feel like there's got to be a way to
do this I suppose one way I could do it
is I could just write the shader myself
and do you know basically do a full
frame buffer blit the same way that
we're doing it to resolve at the end to
combine our death Neil's I suppose I
could do at that point to resolve the
depth as well but the problem is I need
the depth to be the maximum like the
closest depth value that was seen and I
would have thought that that would have
been a default operation actually
because it's kind of what you would
probably want most of the time I would
think but maybe if you're not doing a
death-dealing operation then you don't
necessarily want that but I'm still not
seeing anything here that suggests that
you could do that so that feels to me
like the only real way that I could do
it yeah would be for us - would be for
us to implement that manually so
basically what that means is this you
know this operation where we bind the
two frame buffer zone in duplet would
have to be replaced with our own custom
resolve and this right here is our own
custom resolve so really we already have
the code for it we would just need to
make that more systemic right we need to
make it so that that was something that
that we could do sort of separately so
if I wanted to do that you know we'd be
talking about something like this so
here's where the resolve goes right and
all that code has to happen I'm going to
pull that out into a function just so it
doesn't get quite so indented so I can
read it
[Applause]
so if I wanted to do this again this is
absolutely all I really need to do is
this exact process GL buffer data with
the fixed vertices and then we would
have to do something here which is like
our multi sample resolves I and we don't
really need to do a four I loop here
because we're only going to be accessing
just that one texture and then this code
remains the same so it's pretty compact
operation here but I don't know it might
be too expensive to to do just in terms
of how much it's going to cost in terms
of feeding time again only on this card
on modern cards would be no problem but
so if we want to do this we would
basically need to call resolve multi
sample unlike an OpenGL frame buffer
from and a2 and then we would need the
width and height
[Applause]
so when we bind the frame buffer we're
going to want to bind the two frame
buffer so whatever the you know
basically the target was we're going to
bind that buffer and then we would say
well okay we're going to do a result
multi sample we want to bind as the read
buffer we're going to want to bind both
the color and the depth handles together
and we would need to be able to fetch
the depth value out of the texture so
we'd actually need to set the Z value
right and hopefully that's something
that we'd be allowed to do in OpenGL
shading language 1.3 I'm not 100% sure
if we can or not see here still write
fragment Z
so it does look like you can write to
frag DEP I don't know if you can do it
in three or not but hopefully we will be
able to do that so we'll find out when
we try to compile the program so yet in
this case we have everything set up here
a which pretty much looks like what we
want
I guess the other thing to think about
here which is kind of confusing eye is
that we only want to produce sample
values we only want to use sample values
that we actually took and I mean it just
seems like I'm going to have to go I'm
just not feeling super-confident about
this because if we have to do that that
also seems pretty problematic because
we're going to have to do stuff like say
well okay we you know when we're doing
the desk deal we look to see what the
previous round output as its death value
and if it's multi sampling it's going to
have to ignore any depth values that are
older than the closest one it would also
have to ignore the colors from those
ones that were not the closest one which
I guess is fine
I mean it might just work I don't know
it's just it's a little iffy so I don't
know we'll push forward a little bit
I'll do it it'll be hard to tell if
we've got a bug versus it just doesn't
work but yeah I mean I don't know I
guess we'll try right so in this case we
have to bind two textures to read from
right so we need to bind both the color
and the depth like so and so we've got
the color handle in the depth handle
both specified for the buffer we want to
read from so this would allow us to
write a shader that could read from the
color handle and the depth handle of one
of the multi sample buffers and then
write to some destination writing both
the depth and the color value that we
desire now when we do this pass
we don't want any blending of any kind I
think at this point I so but we've got
you a blood pump 1 1 - horse alpha on so
I think we would also have to in this
case disable blending
but we always do have blending table it
looks like alright I guess that's
because we're def peeling so all of our
blending happens in that one resolved
shader so I think that's all good so
this is probably all we really need to
do here and then we just need to write
the shader that actually does this
operation so taking a look at the set up
for this program basically it's the same
as the peel composite program but we're
going to have two different samplers
here right so we've got the color
sampler and the depth sampler right so
when we do this compile
this is our resolve multisample
program and I think most of this is
going to be the same now we don't need
the vert color stuff here I don't know
why that's still there I can go away
oops and I don't think we need the vert
UV either because we're only going to be
using a direct look up
because you can't stretch in fact I
don't know why did we have vert UVs in
here I have no idea it's a good question
anyway so we don't need UVs and we don't
need we don't need any of this basically
we just need a straight path through
vertex shader that's going to just make
sure we get a perimeter that covers the
whole screen that's all we really need
at all we don't we don't need anything
else right so in this case we've got two
of these multi sample samplers so we're
going to use to read from we basically
have no inputs we just have the output
which is the result color and then we
have to write to the frag Z which I
don't know if we have to declare that
writable or not in this version sharing
language but we'll see what happens so
at this point I need to use the same
kind of texture lookup we were using
here basically this is the sort of stuff
we need but we're going to be reading
from a we're going to be reading from a
multi sampled texture so it's going to
be slightly different so we don't need
any of this stuff we may want to do our
squaring for sample so we'll leave that
in for the moment but that's basically
over we would be looking at now our
result alpha it will also need to be
computed because we do actually care
what the alpha value is for compositing
later and we're going to need a four I
loop here essentially because we need to
loop over the number of samples and so
in here we probably need an in
that's going to tell us you know how
many samples there actually are that's
probably a constant we could use
that's predefined an open jail but I'm
not going to risk it for now right
I'm also going to make sure we have
[Applause]
assumed those are what those are
normally to find ads I don't really
remember anyway so if we have the sample
count and we want that to be actually
mounted again sorry we want that to be
uniform it's just going to be set in the
constant store what we should be able to
do is do a for loop from our samples
[Applause]
right so we just go through each sample
one by one inside the for loop we should
be able to sample them like so I and you
know like I said I really don't know how
well this is going to work but we'll
find out so we can get the color we can
get the depth
like so and then we want to do here is I
think we just want to figure out what
the max depth is now we probably have to
do this twice unfortunately because we
don't want to so many color values that
aren't the maximum depth right although
I guess what we can do I guess we can be
creative here so what we could do here
is is you know closest Jeff and I
believe our depth values the way that we
set them up you can see here is that we
discard anything where the clip depth
where the frag Z is less than the clip
depth so that means that lower values
are closer right to us so you know the
closest step here I assume we want to be
one pointer which is all the way back
right and as we go through we're going
to want to compare against back so if if
the depth value that we get here is less
than the closest step then it's our new
closer step or get away so that would be
at the closest depth is greater right so
that's just a way of picking out what
the close step is now we have to do
something with the color as well
[Applause]
now here is the dilemma right we have to
figure out what we're going to do with
this averaging process so
it's just so janky so here's the part
that I can't seem to grab my head around
exactly and we're basically out of time
for this that's good we probably want to
think on this overnight if there really
is anything that we can do here so
here's the problem if a primitive passes
through a pixel then we almost need to
just know which parts are part of that
primitive look we almost need to use the
primitive ID or something like that to
tell us how to plug together because if
we just use the DEF values we don't know
if two adjacent samples with differing
depth values both came from the same
primitive and they just happened to be a
you know on a slant to the viewer or
whether the depth values are different
because it actually represents two
separate things so yeah I don't know
even just looking at this I'm just
thinking I don't need this is going to
be one of those super nasty things if
you did it this way like the screen
space anti-aliasing and stuff like that
that never seems to work right where
you're always trying to compare depth
values and make guesses about what they
mean but you don't really have the
information you actually want yeah
so I have grave doubts about this let's
put this in there just to leave things
compiling all right
[Applause]
let's go to a really brief Q&amp;A here in
fact I probably don't have much time for
the Q&amp;A actually
because I got to go soon after this but
let's just let's just take a brief
gander
play so I think it will be useful to
bind the key to topmost window as there
is a key to fullscreen then you will not
have to resize your editor for live code
editing yeah that makes sense
also since I bound the thinkI I'm a
happy panda warm recommendations
why s32 for the camp instead of you 32 i
just because s 32 is I knew that int was
a thing they supported I couldn't
remember whether what the syntax was for
unsigned is I think it's done signed in
GLSL and I just didn't want to have to
check but you can use you 32 just fine
could you up the bitrate it's really
hard to watch when there's too much
movement on the screen it gets all
blurry and pixelated not exaggerating
when I say it makes my eyes watery so I
guess I don't know where that set
exactly
I guess that would be something I'd have
to change in my in my
[Music]
so I guess here's the question
are you sure that it's not twitch like
are you sure that it's actually me did
you see the same amount of blurriness if
you run it on YouTube or not at the
highest at 1080 if you do YouTube 1080
because I'm not sure which one you guys
I don't know what artifacts in terms of
the video you're actually talking about
there but it's e it either the fact that
twitch is doing that or that the bitrate
on OBS is just too low in general
all right so it doesn't look like
there's any substitute of questions at
the moment though so I'm going to go
ahead and wrap things up and we'll take
a look at this tomorrow
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade
heroes and a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along
series at home you could always appear
to the game on handmade hero or come to
the source code so you can play around
with it and do your own experimentation
doesn't have a forum site and go to want
to ask questions a patreon page go to if
you want to sports video series schedule
box that lets you know when the Sirians
going to be live if you want to watch it
live and an episode guide with a new
pretty amazing search feature unless you
guys have seen this but SF gartner and
criminal dragon and mid blow and jaren
have all done some amazing work here so
you can actually go on here and search
for stuff now you can just go multi
sampling or whatever I don't know if I
spelled that right but you do that and
it comes up with all the times I've
talked about multi sampling and you can
click right on one of these and it jumps
right to the video which is kind of
Awesome I it's by far the best way to
find stuff in the in the series it's so
good how they recommend it alright
that's about it I will be back tomorrow
when we'll take another look at if
there's anything we could do with that
multi sampling before I just say the
heck with it we'll leave it as it is all
right thanks for joining me and see you
back here tomorrow
take it easy everybody