hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show where we code a complete game
live on stream now one of the things
that I get asked a lot because we don't
really cover it on handmade hero one of
the things I get asked a lot is what do
you do about source code control right
this is a very common question what do
you do about source code control do you
use git watch you get to store the game
you know what's what's the plan there
right and I haven't addressed it and
it's been you know we've been doing
series for a long time it's great I
loved seeing everyone in the stream
every week and I just felt like at some
point I was gonna have to I was gonna
have to talk to you about how source
code control should work what you should
do that sort of thing so the answer you
know everyone always says switch to get
whenever anyone's having trouble source
code control it's absolutely true it's
obviously the most powerful
industry-standard source code control
out there you've got to know how to use
it and personally I just think people
would be crazy to use anything else now
I understand the reticence that people
have when using git okay because it is
it was a you know it was a hardcore
professional-grade thing you know linus
torvalds or leanest Torvald I'm sorry I
don't know the pronunciations
as well as I should when he was writing
it you know he wanted something for
serious kernel development so you know
this this isn't something that's
supposed to be super friendly or you
know like all fancy GUI or anything like
that you know it's a serious
command-line utility so I understand it
can be daunting and so what I thought
I'd do at the beginning of today's
stream is I just wanted to give people a
little introduction to like if you were
on your own project right and you wanted
to use source code control for it and
you know maybe you're you're a beginner
or maybe you're even intermediate but
you don't like taking a step to get
something as hardcore as get is a little
bit scary for you I just want to
demystify you and
oh that it's really not it you know it
shouldn't be something that's that's
scary so I prepared a little thing here
I made a temp get directory and you know
I I guess folks probably know you know I
did this hash function called meow hash
and I put it up on github now one of the
things about github that you might not
know if you've only ever browse on the
web is it's actually you can use get to
interact directly with it
so if you go to any github page there's
actually this clone or download button
here right and in that window there's
there's a URL and you can use that that
URL with the git command line utility so
what I'm gonna do so I'll show you how
to get that this repository my now
hashed repository I'm going to show you
how to use git to just quickly and
easily just get it onto your machine and
if we counter any problems along the way
I'll show you I'll explain what they
mean and I'll show you how to get around
them okay so let's start with just a
simple the basic thing that you're gonna
want to do for any get thing well you
know what let me let me start a little
bit simpler so if you just type get what
you'll get is this this kind of yeah I
don't want to be pedantic now but I say
it's kind of useless this this is like a
little help screen and it only has the
really basic commands on it right so
these are like sort of the things that
you would most commonly call but anyone
who really uses get seriously knows that
there's if that's not most of the things
you're gonna do are gonna be more
advanced than these commands so these
are really just I would ignore this
screen what you want to do is focus on
this down here if you do get help - a
what that'll do is that'll list all the
commands and get so not just the common
ones so if I do a get help - a what you
can see is that'll that'll list all the
commands that get has has any in toto
right now obviously this listing can go
on for a while because there's a lot of
commands and get I mean one things you
have to understand about get is its its
industry standard now so everyone kind
of has I don't know how to say it but
it's a lot like the Linux kernel right
it started off as something small you'd
space both both
manliest rebels right started off small
then they become a lot more a lot more
widespread a lot more widely used and so
even though originally get probably had
only one hundred two hundred three
hundred commands I think at last count
there's something like three hundred
ninety five thousand commands and get
give or take it depends like do you can
install modules to it so this is just
the baseline version which has I think
the 395 okay some installations can have
1.2 1.3 million but those commands you
don't necessarily need those for
everyday use this this set of 395,000 is
are the ones that you you would
generally be using day-to-day right so I
don't necessarily recommend doing the
1.2 1.3 million route that's just that's
just too many commands and usually with
a combination of some you know 12 13 14
of those 395,000 base set commands you
can usually do what you want and so a
lot of times if you look at the 1.2 1.3
1.4 million commands there those a lot
of them are really just repackaging or
like convenience versions of ones that
you already have in the base you know
set that's they're relatively concise
you know for decay set set of commands
this this listing can take a while this
is mostly Windows it doesn't have a very
efficient command line as you know Linux
novice to the place for command line so
this could go on for a while so I'm
gonna control see out of this you don't
really need to know all of these just
yet you will want to go through every
single one of these commands eventually
and really familiarize yourself with
what each of them can do because
otherwise you're really not using it to
its fullest potential so you do want to
look at that list obviously you can pipe
it to more or something if you want to
page through it one at a time it only
takes a couple weeks to get through that
whole list obviously I've done it before
it's really and it's pretty eye-opening
because a lot of stuff in there that you
wouldn't necessarily know about so
anyway like I was saying we want to do
is you want to start with a really basic
get command it's called git clone and
what we're gonna do is we're just gonna
take this this URL here that's provided
for you you know it's part of the the
github repository I'm just gonna paste
it in and that's it right
so again people say that gets scary I
don't know why they say that it's not
you know that that line right there will
get you all the code so you just hit
return and it'll do it right and then
one of the things this happens a lot to
people is they'll start using the
repository right away after they do the
clone and I really don't recommend that
that's a source of a lot of problems for
people because typically what happens is
if you if you clone a repository all
that's doing is moving the files onto
your machine right but you still haven't
done anything yet to make sure that
those files are actually ready to be
used right it's just it's just a copy
it's not like a preparation and so what
you really want to do to make sure that
everything is ready to go and you can
actually start adding them is you want
to use the command called get less and
what get less does is it takes the
repository that you're in and it goes
through every file and make sure that in
a spiritual sense you're ready to edit
that file without get getting confused
about what the file supposed to do right
so it's kind of like it's it's like a
just like an the reason is called
blessed is kind of like likening it to a
religious sir my allow you out there
probably atheists or whatever I do so I
don't want to imply there's like any
real reason behind it anyone can use
this command regard it's
nondenominational but it's it's just
evoking that sort of preparation right
you know don't you're you don't want to
do the animal sacrifice before you have
the holy water or whatever right you
know I don't know I'm not familiar with
how these things go the same is true
with get you want to make sure the code
is blessed before you modify it
otherwise when you go to do subsequent
get commands who knows what could happen
right I mean you've more or less anger
of the gods at that point so if you want
to do is do a get bless and you can just
hit get bless return here but I'm
actually use a couple switches to get
blessed because in order to do get
blessed properly I I want to do a couple
things so I'm gonna actually do a CPP
reverse gardening on this one and what
that'll do is if you do CBP reverse
gardening so I should say first before
we get too far down that rathole I'm not
going to cover like exactly what
gardening is
but gardening involves essentially
leaving space between the files if you
normally what will happen there's a
default level of gardening so when the
files get placed in directories there's
a certain amount of empty space in
between them and that's that's if you
want your code to go to seed right after
so that it will produce smaller versions
of itself
subsequently if you want get to do that
as it you know as it builds hashes and
stories back up versions of files you
want that empty space in there I'm call
me old-fashioned I don't like to use a
lot of space on the drive so I use
reverse gardening and basically what you
do is if you say the language that
you're using so CPP and then you do
reverse gardening it'll say for all CPP
files take the amount take the space
that you would have been using and
actually reclaim that for other purposes
so I like to do a git Buster's he'd be
really starting to reduce the gardening
and then I also like to do a fallow Rose
heavy write which lets it know that on
every other row that normally you would
be saving for the next time right that
you do a get bless that these are going
to be planted at the normal density that
they would have been right so when you
do that get planting and then finally
what I like to do is I like to do this
you can do this two ways you can do it
the normal way you can do it retrograde
so if you do it retrograde it'll start
at the farthest row for gardening and it
will go backwards whereas if you were
going to do it the normal way you
wouldn't have any of that reverse motion
right so I'm going to do the get blessed
in this repository as you can see it's
just going to go through its gonna do
some credentials checks it's got a make
room for the changes and that sort of
thing and and branches and caches up ok
so again one of the things that happens
and get it it's definitely something
that people again it puts people off I
don't think they should be scared about
sort of things the error messages are a
little bit cryptic right errors and get
happen all the time especially when
you're working with a public or posit
ori because remember you're taking
you're taking a repository that was made
on someone else's machine or even on
your own which you know if you if you
have a multi machine environment you
made it but you may not a different
machine you're moving it to a new
and so just the environments are a
little bit different so even if you're
doing fairly standard stuff like get
clone or get bless sometimes you can get
basically you can get these these errors
that crop up they're just they're not a
big deal so I really encourage you to
not get scared just read the error
message and usually what it says is the
problem right so you can see here it
says that on revert mail would overwrite
previous D get tree right and all that
means is we did to get operations right
so that first clone in that first clone
operation there's a ton of stuff that
has to happen so one step of the clone
operation is called get tree right and
that's the thing that actually brings
the remote repository on to your system
okay that D get tree operation is just
the reverse of that because after you've
gotten the tree you need to like
effectively undo that operation of the D
get right that tree otherwise you still
have the tree in addition to the files
which you don't want right and so in
this case what it's basically saying is
that I didn't set up any mailing system
normally whenever you do it get bless
it'll send mail to everyone in the
blessings list so that each one of those
people knows that the source code has
been blessed right it's a little bit
like a papal edict or something so that
everyone knows within that sort of
blessing circle who everyone's been
notified so nobody thinks have to bless
it twice they know it you don't want to
waste time re blessing code that's
already been blessed so what is trying
to do here right is it's trying to Unruh
Verte the mail changes that it thinks
have happened because normally when you
do a get bless you've been through a
couple different mail cycles and what
it's realizing is that it's doing that
right after a D get tree operation and
if you try to under it the mail list the
mail like blessing list or any other
mail list there's there's something like
75 different mail list types in git and
this one in particular is talking about
the blessing mailing list because that's
the one that we're doing obviously but
you know if there's what there's
different ones for different commands so
if the Unruh Verte mail operation would
overwrite that the the situation that
would have happened with the diga tree
where it moved it out of
the way right that creates an era
scenario it's again it's easy as pie to
solve these four these are not hard all
you have to do is call the Unruh vert
mail with a force command so if you just
say look I do want to Unruh vert mail
alright cuz that's what it thinks we do
just do - - ignore D get three warnings
right that will stop that and you can
see also in there's a secondary note
that says that the latest protein or
quilt and it gives you that mail address
right the one that's that was the mail
it was on when it realized that it
couldn't unrevealing do you get tree
that occurred right so what's gonna
happen here is you need to first ignore
those bigotry warnings and then what you
want to do is look at the secondary list
and so in that case quilting is a thing
that happens and get that I don't really
it's sort of like gardening I don't want
to go down the whole rat hole but
basically what it is is it's for its for
taking disparate pieces of the source
tree and basically you know stitching
them together right it's kind of a get
term of art and so there's there's a
multiple different ways there's a pre
ignore there's a post ignore there's a
pro ignore which is basically like I
have mindset to doing all of the like
advanced feature levels so if you if you
have your get configured to be doing the
most advanced version of all the
commands you're gonna get Pro ignore
messages you can get a matured in your
messages if you have yours on the normal
level also porcelain ignore messages so
probe ignore quilt is just saying that
the the thing that was telling it that
it didn't need to worry about quilt
operations right on that particular mail
was the thing that triggered the mail
conflict the under route mail Condor
with the diga tree so even though get
under route mail - - ignored to get tree
warnings probably would work here I also
want to give it a few quilt directives
just so it knows that that's not a
stopping factor right so I'm just gonna
go ahead and do a - - quilt always which
is basically saying look don't ignore
the quilting Pro or otherwise just do
the quilt thing you would normally do
regardless of what else happened right
and then I'm also
to do a - - um skip mail and I'm just
gonna type in this exact you really want
to make sure this exact if you have this
is one of those things that people can
really get in trouble if you do a skip
mail and then you put anything other
than like a real mail hash in there that
can easily delete lots of existing work
that you've done so you want to make
sure that you really like like don't
take a second when you do a skip mail
directive and just make sure that you're
typing that 100% accurate okay so now
we're gonna do that unruhe vert mail and
and we'll just I think this will be fine
now just sometimes it'll take okay so
one of the other problems that you will
see is that get always is gonna build a
thing there's there's essentially graphs
underlying each get operation if you
think about what's happening
conceptually in a get operation what it
is is it builds sort of a set of nodes
that are the possible states that the
source tree could be in and then what
it's gonna do is this gonna build a
graph of the path through those states
it wants to take ideally to solve the
math solve to do the command that you're
telling to do like in this case the
Unruh route mail right um so in this
case it built one of those graft subsets
that it wanted to use right and when it
traversed through it when it was done it
was not able to remove that graph from
the tree that's the unset up graph pass
is the thing that removes finished graft
sections from the complete graph before
the command is over because again it
really doesn't want you to lose work I
mean it wants the work you lose to be
your fault I guess is the way to say it
obviously it loses work all the time it
wants that work to be verifiable so if
it can't set up all the graphs in the
graph step then it's not going to do it
this usually happens because the graph
state got partially held over from a
previous command there's a thing called
graph forwarding that happens
automatically
it's basically there to save you time
but sometimes it actually creates errors
like in this case so what you want
here is pretty simple it's just there's
a get reset operation what that does it
says clear everything right just clear
all the states I don't hold over the
graphs but one of the things is if you
are in pro mode so you probably haven't
set your thing up for this so you won't
have to use these switches but if you're
in Pro Mode graph reset by default I'm
sorry get reset by default won't do a
full graph reset it'll do what's called
a hermeneutic graph reset which is
basically the same as a normal graph
reset but it won't get on revert mail
items right because it assumes that the
mail cluster and who you're sending mail
to is not what you're trying to set
you're just trying to set the file state
so what I need to do here is do no
hermeneutic right so that way when it
does the reset it's not gonna do a
hermeneutic graph resets gonna do a real
full graph reset and then the other
thing you should always do here is force
right because otherwise if you did the
new hermeneutics it might warn you that
like there would have been a Herman in a
crime saying like no force right okay so
it's doing it alright so I think we're
basically done I know this is making get
probably look harder than it really is
but these are just just what happens
right you saw there's no weirdness going
on here right just when you're trying to
sync a source tree for the first time
there's a lot of stuff that can go wrong
alright so in here you can see we're
having a particular problem with the try
hash now there's three or four levels of
hashing and get you don't probably need
to consider yourself too much with each
individual one
there's the primary hashes there's by
hashes and there's try hashes now the
primary hashes are hashes that actually
come from your files by hashes are when
getting used to look at two different
files and combine their hashes into one
hash and then a try hash is when that by
hash gets combined with two other by
hashes now this is a common mistake
people often think a try hash is a
combination of three regular hashes it's
not a try hash is a combination of three
by hashes so it's really like a six-way
hash but try hash was just the term that
sort of stuck so we still call them try
hashes and there is no real get term
for three hashes that were normal hashes
combined together a lot of people call
it a 3x hash but you know it's again
it's not baked into the program so it's
kind of just
that's vernacular at that point right
now again this was happening because we
tried to do resetting of that mail graph
basically what it's saying is when it
was trying to record all of the hashes
of those file graphs that it was
producing in order to undo the
hermeneutic graph holdover from the
revert mail now obviously I use IMAP for
mail that's where you're getting this in
here right um one of the things that you
run into is it divides the mail servers
that it can talk to into a few different
types right there's direct mail servers
there's indirect mail servers there's
semantic mail servers and there's
symbolic mail servers right and so
symbolic mail servers are mail servers
that don't actually exist like they're
mail servers that are effectively
imaginary right and so what you're doing
when you use a symbolic mail server is
you're saying let's pretend there's a
mail server so that we can complete this
operation but when we're done we're not
actually going to send any mail right
and so what's happening with a try half
scribe index is it's it's trying to
record what the try hash was of that
six-way set of files right it's trying
to put that into the global try hash
index so that it can do what's called a
quad push which is taking four try at a
time this is a performance thing for try
hashes at a time to the symbolic server
right it's basically like if you were to
do each individual try hash you'd be
wait there be a lot of dead space in the
symbolic server packets so a quad push
takes four of those a time and does them
all the you know all at once
right and so what you get out of a quad
push is a lot more performance but it's
a lot riskier right in Pro Mode I want
to do quad pushes I want to be faster
moths all the time I know how to handle
these errors this is not what I'm gonna
go into too much detail because so I'm
not gonna explain how we're gonna fix it
we're just gonna fix it because I don't
think you're gonna see this one because
if you don't have pro level settings
engaged you never
get a quad push error because it's just
gonna be doing single push this symbolic
server to do those male operations when
when male is effectively sort of being
emulated during that that operation so
I'm just gonna type in the line that
fixes this and you don't have to worry
too much about this alright so once
you've got essentially all of that taken
care okay so I actually wasn't expecting
this okay I'm really sorry about this so
it divides things into two sections
it's called porcelain and plumbing so
porcelain it'sit's basically think of a
toilet right this is the analogy they
use I in a toilet you got the plumbing
which is the thing that actually does
the work then you got a porcelain which
is the thing that you actually see as a
human and interface with right so
normally because I'm in Pro Mode I turn
all the porcelain stuff off but because
I was trying to do a demo today I
enabled the porcelain stuff which is
basically the user interface like foofy
stuff it's stuff that you should turn
off as soon as you can you know once
you're familiar with a 395,000 base
commands you can turn off the porcelain
nonsense it's not useful but I had
turned it on and so you can see once we
were working with that scribe index when
it tried to do the try revert based on a
command that I gave it probably because
I said exacerbate shim but again I don't
really want to go into what that does
that caused a conflict with what it
would normally do the reverse of a quad
push is a quad read right you can see it
happening down in here so the quad read
that was trying to get back from a
symbolic server what the pretty message
was to display on this command that
failed and it failed because obviously I
the I didn't go into how you set up a
get symbolic server obviously I did that
beforehand that's kind of a more
advanced
topic I would just let one of the
default installers do it for you but
when I set mine up right I set it up a
pro level I didn't quit I didn't install
the porcelain modules doesn't even have
those messages so you're gonna get those
problems cropping up so all I'm gonna do
is we run the exact same command again
I'm gonna say no porcelain and I'm gonna
say unprincely get those messages right
let's give that one more shot this I
think this this should be fine
I think we're good here uh all right so
one of the problems that you will see
when you're trying to fix the quilting
problem like that because you noticed
before that beforehand right I don't
know if you remember when we were
executing this command @p let's go back
up here I told it to do quilt always so
what you're really supposed to do in
that particular command right if you're
doing an actual Unruh vert mail here the
safe way to do an unreal is to actually
open up a text editor and to list you
what you want to do is you want to list
all the things that should actually be
quilted which is typically not all of
them and so one of the problems is if
you have something that's formatted in a
way such that it can't be quilted then a
later command will eventually try to
verify that quilt again using the
performance mode here it's trying to do
them for at a time that's not the
problem here even the single verify
quilt would have failed when it tries to
verify quilt on something that was not
formatted for quilting which of course I
accidentally induced it to do by just
saying quilt always that's gonna fail
right again we can run the same command
we just have to add one more fit switch
which is that like if you ignore quilt
errors right and reek wilt unquoted
formats that should take care of any
like quilting is not an essential
feature so basically it's just saying
look if there was a coding error don't
worry about it just reek wilt any of
those quilt sections that were wrong
right so crossing our fingers here this
this hopefully will be the the one that
actually finally gets their posit Ori
into a good state perfect right so now
if I just do a directory you can see
there's meow hash I go in there right
there it is
it's
already for me and and totally set to go
so I hope that that gave you some
appreciation for how simple it is to
just get started on get get right I mean
we had some errors and some of them were
a little bit complicated you know I
agree but hopefully you can see from my
explanations of them once you once you
pull back the curtain and and just see
what's actually going on right once you
know about you know quilts and and
hermeneutic graphs and all those sort of
things it becomes actually very simple
to navigate your way through it you
don't have to be scared right sometimes
it deletes all of your changes or all of
your data that's okay that's just an
excuse to start over a lot of times you
know writing code fresh is better right
and so I think a lot of the criticism
level to get that is too complicated
that it loses all your files those sorts
of things I I don't really think that
that's true right that's that's just
that's people blowing things out of
proportion not learning how to use the
software you know these are people who
probably only know how to use six seven
eight thousand out of three hundred
ninety five thousand commands and get
not to mention the switches which they
probably just don't even know about
right a lot of times um so I really do
think it's worth your time to just you
know forget that stuff and say I'm gonna
commit some time to learning it it's not
that hard and and I think everyone out
there who follows handmade hero it you
can do it and the the rewards that you
will reap from learning this are immense
right like I said you know you can go
from a situation where you you know
we're doing work every day with files
and had to you know use something like I
don't know like SVN or something like
that that you know doesn't lose your
files and your store binary data and is
relatively easy to use you can go to
something like git that's way more
powerful and only sometimes uses your
files and you know only it probably
takes only two or three hours a day of
work and get to copy things from like
one machine to another and stuff like
that which is well worth the time
investment so I highly recommend it I
think everyone should in fact switch to
get and
hopefully this tutorial is enough to
like whet your appetite there's a lot of
great tutorials out there so you know
seek them out and before we get started
on actually programming today let me
just go and ask does the stream have any
questions that did it did all that make
sense I hope I was kind of talking a lot
there did anyone have any questions for
me about what we covered just there on
get any anything that you you want me to
show you in addition to that so
reductive said could you go over the get
soil archive command I've had a really
hard time understanding the docs on it
okay okay yeah yeah I could I could
definitely do that let me let me just
let me just fire that up here okay um
don't worry about that air mess is just
not important okay could you go to get
Sherlock could come in I totally can I
just I staged this repository for it so
the get soil archive command that's this
command what the get soil archive
command does is it's basically saying
much like when you see that remember I
was talking about that gardening the
reverse gardening so normally when you
do an archive what's gonna happen is
it's gonna get rid of the those those
that spacing right that gardening if you
had gardening in the art in the
repository normally when you do the
archive it's gonna get rid of that right
and so the problem with that when you do
an archive is when the person
decompresses the archive on the other
end they lose all the gardening so get
soil archive is something you do to an
archive ahead of time in order to make
sure that when you put a git repository
into the archive it still has that
padding right so in our case what we
would do is we'd say like get cell
archive like you know like now hash tgz
or
some any other archive type that you
want they're all bit in I think it has
their support for a seventy three
different archive formats so you know
you can use pretty much everything that
you want so you do get to archive the
archive to use and then you want to do
like probably gardening optimal because
you want it to look at how much should
be put in so how much you have a certain
amount of soil right you can't just make
it out of thin air so you got to figure
out how much soil do you want to leave
in the in the ground right in the
repository and how much soil you want to
put into the actual archive itself for
the receiving repository or garden as it
were right
gardening optimal will compute that but
one of the problems with so alright I I
don't want to spend too much time I get
today so I'm sorry if this is a little
bit truncated of neckla nation but
optimal gardening is a problem that
computer science hasn't been able to
solve it's it's np-complete no one
really knows
to what extent you can do literally
optimal gardening so when you supply an
Optima pass an optimal gardening switch
to get you need to tell it in addition
to the optimal gardening something
called a peeper ammeter and the peeper
ammeter is a thing that the optimal
gardening heuristic inside get will use
to know when it has gotten the gardening
optimal enough right because actually
ensuring fully optimal gardening is not
always possible so you want to supply an
optimal gardening parameter I usually
use 0.0 seven eight nine four five one
three three one two which is also with
what leanness Torvalds recommends he you
know he's I think he's right on this
there's competing camps on whether you
should use this constant or there's
other constants out there that are sort
of made about I would stick with this
one so if you pass a knife to a
gardening parameter to get soil archive
and then you probably also want to do so
normally when you do would get cell
archive what it will do is it'll soil
the archive and then it will resale
itself right
in other words
that the local repository so what you
want to do is do not resale yourself at
the and you can also do alternately you
can do like do not soil yourself but do
not soil yourself will take effect for
all future get in vacations it'll
actually update the config so what you
want to do is do not resell yourself so
that it knows that only during this
particular command right that should do
that so hopefully that makes them some
sense
does anyone have I don't like well
that's running um let's see here what if
atomization fails so atomization
failures are not a huge deal you can
just run get pre atomized with - -
ignore atomization failures and that
should take care of most of that if it
doesn't then I don't know mmm okay so
the xref server on this machine is kind
of borked so I would don't work ignore
that that won't happen
this command is fine for you to use
that's has to do with the extra service
setup in this machine which never worked
right so it's it doesn't matter let's
see here forgot anyone let's see here
[Music]
I've heard the sequel since I heard
Knuth recently proved gardening had a
probabilistic polynomial-time algorithm
it just has huge coefficients so if
that's true that could be pretty huge
forget I don't know to what it's then I
believe that I mean want if canoe says
is probably right I mean he's obviously
a godfather of computing so you know I
don't want to challenge his authority on
that but I like I said I don't know
anything about that
I'm seeing that news lone billion says
I'm so skeptical with this effect the
arrangement of my garden gnomes
rearranging them is not really something
that I'm able to do is there permanently
fixed in place okay so I guess what I'd
say about that is statuary is a very
advanced feature in get gardening
and I don't want to mislead you by
suggesting that you can just start
rearranging the get gardening gnomes to
anywhere inside the repository and not
have huge potential pitfalls awaiting
you you can I just want to make it clear
that there is no such thing as a fixed
get garden them all gnomes are movable
you just have to use the assumed mutable
gnomes flag on whatever command you
would have used so for example if you
were gonna use a get bless by gnome
command right which is to say you wanted
to use those garden gnomes as the thing
that was actually gonna do the
repository blessing if that would have
given you an error that's like error
gnomes are fixed in this case right what
you can do is just say assume mutable
gnomes a lot of people don't know about
that switch but it totally works if you
do that it will never give you a fixed
gnome error now this probably won't work
because I didn't actually set up any
gnomes in this particular garden
repository but that's I just want to
make it clear that's that so again
pretty much all the problems are getting
here with the I Maps server and the mail
servers right so I really don't want you
to be a pro CP into the column is
basically when you are trying to copy
column from one to the other in pro mode
and you want to do it without the normal
verify step you can see that it's
hazarding a problem with the with the
fact that I have more than one IMAP
server listed that's probably just
something happened when I did the config
to put in the amateur porcelain stuff
the same thing that's screwed up the
xref server probably screwed this up
right it's again fixable you don't even
need to worry about that error can you
slam the try cycle entropy option so I
mean I guess what I'd say about try
cycle entropy is unless you're working
on like literally
government grade encryption standards
tricycle entropy is really not necessary
so by cycle entropy is way way faster
it's about 17 times faster because
tricycle entropy is is going to do tons
of iterations so I would just say use -
- by cycle entropy because that's gonna
give you a way more efficient ops
entropy operation whichever one you were
doing with really no downgraded security
unless you're expecting like state level
attackers basically right plus if you're
gonna do try cycle entropy you would
also have to do I'm a - - Mossad on it
as well just to make sure that it uses
Mossad improved enclosures because other
only Mossad strength enclosures are
resistant to the kind of attacks that
tricycle entropy is designed to prevent
so again you're in state actor territory
there and you're you're gonna be wanting
to use if not Mossad level enclosures
use five eyes enclosures or something
that's that's you know state level
encryption quality because you're
basically saying I want state level
encryption because I expect state level
actor threat profiles right all right I
don't wanna spend too much more time on
get hopefully that gave everyone a good
understanding of how it all works and
and how to get started with it let's go
ahead and go on with the series all
right so if you remember last week we
sort of got ourselves to a pretty good
stopping point let me go ahead and open
up the game here I'm gonna launch
forehead and then I'm gonna go ahead and
try to remember what all the keys are
here okay I really need to update to the
new for coder on this machine but Allen
and I have kind of been going back and
forth on some changes and so I've been
in a situation where I have a one meow
hash that I'm using another machine I've
started mom you have one for code I'm
using on the other machine
one for Kota I'm using here which is not
a good idea because I made a bunch of
changes so yeah that's a bit of an issue
but let me go ahead and do a quick build
and then I'm gonna go ahead and do an MS
dev here and I just wanna give a quick
recap and okay I don't know what this is
telling me to do right what I okay um so
what is happening here I don't really
want to know so I guess we won't be
using Visual Studio
[Music]
all right so I guess what we've learned
is Visual Studio no longer wants to be
used on handmade here oh and you know
what that's fine with me I don't like
all of its garbage anyways so I guess
today is the day we switch to remedy and
we're just gonna have to hope that
George has our back on this one all
right so let me go ahead and switch to
bugger is real quick this was not
planned by the way I didn't think that
you know silly me and I realized that
I'm just crazy here you know you would
have thought that Microsoft would want
their product to look good on a stream
and wouldn't make it randomly
deauthorize itself and then produce an
error message in a JavaScript
interpreter window but you know that's
just the kind of quality that Microsoft
delivers these days so I'm gonna go
ahead and go in here and I'm gonna
download remedy which I bought and I'm
gonna download that's and we're just
gonna use that to debug from now on and
it's not really done yet it's only
version 0.1 but hey at least it will run
which is more than I can say for Visual
Studio alright
so let's see here here's remedy on the
thumb drive I will put that down here
somewhere let's make a directory for it
shall we so what I'm doing here is I'm
just gonna use the in development
debugger that George man Horne is
working on X 13 pixels if you see him in
the chat that's who we're talking about
here and I'm gonna go ahead and unpack
his debugger into this directory there
it is and I think that unless there's an
Apps remedy oh there is okay nevermind
we already had a directory for it so I'm
gonna put it in there there we go
okay uh and so in this remedy directory
what you can see here I don't need this
stuff anymore I don't think so what you
can see here is I've got the only two
files in the remedy distribution so
refreshing just it's an executable that
you run and if you run it you know it
comes up instantly
I know Microsoft has long forgotten that
there is such a thing as an executable
that you can run by itself like I don't
know that there are people at Microsoft
who still know that an executable can
run by itself without 30,000 files in a
sequel server install but turns out
that's actually true and dotnet so
remedy if you run it it's pretty similar
to visual studio and in terms of the way
it looks the only real difference is you
know you don't have project
configuration windows because it doesn't
do builds right and so what you have is
this little thing here we can say what
you want to run and so I'm just gonna go
ahead and load up hand-made here under
that and we'll just go from there so I
want to run win32 hand-made right we
don't have any command argument to the
moment but the working directory is w
handmade there we go and let me go save
this into our debug directory under
win32 hand-made I think we already did
this when we tested it out and so what
you can see here is it works pretty
similar if I hit F
I can row so I should say where you can
get this - if you want to follow along
at home you can go here so remedy BGH io
/ er maybe G that or actually can you
just do this yeah so you can just do
that and this right here you can buy it
looks like it's 10 bucks and you can get
exactly what it is it's still in
development like I said it's only
version 0.1 so keep that in mind don't
expect it to be completely polished
don't expect there to be no bugs but it
does work I've tried it a bunch I think
the only thing that I've noticed lately
bug wise is it looks like it has some
trouble displaying things that are
compound structures passed as parameters
it seemed to be having trouble with that
so like if you have a struct that's a
parameter to a function it seemed to be
having trouble displaying those properly
like it couldn't figure out where they
were or something so there's a couple of
bugs like that I haven't reported all of
them to George yet so you know I'm
getting to that I do want to switch this
eventually and it looks like maybe our
hands gonna be forced there because
Microsoft just just pooped out on us so
anyway if I hit f5 it runs as normal
here's our game running right and
everything's fine
and in here you can do the same sort of
stuff you would normally do in Visual
Studio so you know it's got like Windows
that are dockable and the windows are
similar like right there's a registers
window and the memory window and
everything right and so we can recreate
essentially what we had so you know I I
normally put like the watch window up
here right and we've typically got like
the call stack and stuff like that I
don't know what else we used to put down
at the bottom exactly
yeah so I'm not sure so I'm gonna pull
these up here because I don't really
remember how this stuff worked and I'm
going to dock them sort of separately
just so I understand exactly how it used
to go I'm just trying to remember so I
know we used to put the call stack just
trying to recreate it I know we used to
put the call stack kind of down and the
probably the breakpoints sort of down in
here so like the breakpoints wind oops
the breakpoints window I won't probably
able to get to that without shrinking
these down huh too many windows on the
screen sorry I just want to take a
second to set this up so it's basically
the same I think most people probably
will be fine with it probably won't be
too different for now okay there we go
all right so I need to put the
breakpoints window down here I think
this is how we used to have it I so the
call stack probably would have gone
there right it's probably had these two
the output window usually goes like down
here oops that's not where I want of
that registers probably went up here
maybe I don't know let's say that it did
I'm gonna put memory down here for now
because I'm not sure where it went
modules and can go up here because
that's rarely used threads is more
common so I may want threads to kind of
be here all the time like it's just a
little bit of like a thing I can do here
and then output I'm just gonna put down
at the bottom or try to I need where's
my source window well I'll step in
that'll get me one right or a break
rather break there we go oh and
disassembly so the disassembly will go
down here as well I think so I'm gonna
put the outputs and the disassembly
there let me step up to a source window
so we can get that in place and then
hopefully we're good to go
we'll see
so where this isn't handmade hero here
so there's our source window I'm gonna
put the output window down in here and
the disassembly down there so that's how
I think I'm gonna run this for now and
we'll just see how it goes from from
here on out because I have no idea how
it will go from here on out so alright
uh so let's go ahead and save this
session save and in theory I think
hopefully now I don't know if we made a
remedy batch file we did so when you
load it up again I think I should just
be able to do this and we should be good
to go so you shouldn't have to fuss with
the windows anymore and I think we're
good okay alright so Visual Studio
replaced not because I wanted to but
because it literally decided it didn't
want to be used anymore which is great
so back to our story so what our
situation is currently is you know we
did our sprite testing stuff and we're
pretty happy with it
there's just one thing that I think I
want to tackle here and it's something
that we kind of did late at the end of
the previous stream and what that is is
if you look at what happens to our hero
here all of the sprite sorting actually
worked out quite well except for one
thing that I did and I want to fix it so
you'll notice it sorts really well into
everything now like it's very very good
ignore the glove at the moment because
we currently don't we didn't do any
programming for the glove it's just kind
of sitting there now and so it it will
not keep itself in a good place for
sorting it's completely busted
but if you look at what we're actually
doing here right you can see that the
glove should be sorted down a little
lower we can fix that any time we want
but I just don't care about the glove at
the moment um what you can see about
this is it's doing really good to let us
do full 3d with our stuff it sorts
things in really nicely and yet still
presents them in a nice 2d way I'm
really happy with how we did that it
took us a bunch of work to figure out
how we should do that properly I think
we did a great job there's just one
issue do you see how we're clipping into
the ground there so we already have
solved this issue meaning we know how to
not clip
the ground we effectively disabled the
thing that would have prevented it from
getting clipped into the ground and the
reason that we did that was because we
didn't want freely rotating objects to
change their sort distance too much
right because what was actually
happening there and you can kind of see
what's going on right is we're shearing
do you see how we're shearing that axis
is getting its sheared right and that
shearing is creating something that
extends down into the plane we had
previously explicitly solved for where
to put this point so that it wouldn't
extend down in the plane but the problem
is we locked that distance so we don't
let it increase that as the user pushes
the shear or the rotation and that's
what's causing the problem so we have to
make a decision here about what we want
to do when we create those shearing
effects because we are fundamentally
basing the character at a particular
location in the world that is not where
it has to shim the sprites to if we do
fix the location we will interpenetrate
now we could choose to hover the
character a little bit to prevent that
that doesn't seem like a great solution
we could choose to not fix the distance
and that to me sounds better why does it
sound better well the reason we fix the
distance was to prevent spinning things
or other stuff like that from pulsing
right from going in and out in and out
that is a very small subset of the
things that will actually happen in the
game and so what I'm thinking is we
probably want the default behavior to be
the adjustment that we were doing before
and then if we do have to handle
something that's like continuously
spinning maybe that's just a flag we put
in there right maybe that's just
something that we handle especially
so I want to show you that code and I
want to see what we can do about it so
if you remember how this works inside
the entity set well I can't see anything
it's too bright outside
once again yeah man that's bright
too much Sun let's see Anna wasn't
supposed to have Sun um so if you take a
look at what happens during entity
rendering what you can see here is we do
a bunch of work to figure out where the
sprite should be placed and you can
actually see that happening when it
actually places the minimum P so you can
see this operation occurring here it
says look how high is the sprite right
like what you know how how high up is it
sprite and what is the the camera z-axis
right the the Z not the cameras V axis
what is the Z component of the camera z
axis right so which you know for every
step we take towards the camera
how high up would be going in Z and that
we're doing is taking the placement that
we would have used and we're sliding it
forward in you know along the camera z
axis for however long that would be so
however much we would actually need to
be for that that height us that right
and so what that's doing is that's
lifting us up so that the base of our
cells I guess will not go through
whatever the point was that we started
on if that makes sense I and so when we
do sprite values for up right which is
the call that gives us this information
here it is right there
um when we do this what you can see is
that Z displacement is a constant value
right it's it's not taking into account
the actual Z displacement based on the
rotated axis right it's just kind of
doing a constant value that will not
depend on anything in particular I
believe or am I wrong about that well
actually what's our y-axis H ah so yeah
the fact that it's using the H there is
why it's constant right so this is the y
axis we're actually using which includes
the users twist right includes the
rotation that the user is sort of
enforcing there and then this y axis H
is actually that's what's telling us hey
here's the camera version the thing
that's just constant in camera space so
this is never going to change no matter
how this right rotates right only
different camera positioning will ever
change the y axis H value and so that's
why in this case this thing doesn't
actually vary it's because of that right
of that Z value so in our case if we
wanted to figure out what that
displacement is going to be you can see
us here like we've got the aligned P Y
that's the amount of shift there is off
of the baseline you can see the world
dim why and that's that height there so
that's how much we're gonna move and
then this is basically saying well
that's the axis that we were going to
move along in Z right and the problem
that we have is that it doesn't
correspond to this it doesn't actually
correspond to the value that we're
getting here great and so if we change
this to be using the actual y axis that
includes the shearing I would suspect we
get a result that has less of the
problem right but it actually no so it
doesn't look like we actually get much
of an improvement there which is a
little weird oh so that already has the
world dim Y in it so this should I'm
gonna save this computation than what we
had before and I'm gonna remove that and
this just to see what happens if we just
used the real axis we were actually
going to render along right and so that
does in fact solve the problem which is
what I was expecting to have happen I
forgot that it would double count the
length but once you remove double
counting of the length we're good and
what you can see there is now we have
correctly we always solve correctly for
the that interpenetration and it's good
right and so the only real problem we
will ever have in this because I can now
just go through everywhere and I think
everything will just be fine right
so if I just go through any particular
place that I want to now exploring in
the world
I shouldn't ever really have any
problems with that right
and in some sense in some cases like
here well it's a little bit hard to see
but you can see that actually the arc of
the character incorrectly goes through
geometry so we will get some
interpenetration till we fix these arcs
to properly go up and down like to
always hop as large a hop is necessary
but even there it's actually not
noticeable particularly much there's a
little bit of interpenetration right
there so just a larger arc will fix that
problem if that makes sense
but you know otherwise this just solves
the problem so I think what we want to
do at least for now is say maybe that's
just how we compute this and then we
will do some sort of you know if we have
something rotating around that's pulsing
too much we'll just fix that
at as necessary right I think that
should probably be sufficient for now
and then if we need to come up with
something even more creative with how we
project it we can cross that bridge once
we actually have an example of something
that doesn't work right that seems to me
to be the most sane solution to the
problem at least that's what I would say
seems like a good plan I don't know if
other people have a better idea we can
also try something else but that seems
to me to be fine
you know I'll be honest with you I don't
remember oh right the reason that
there's two exits two things is for
placing items room so this is this is
like an item room or something so all
right so anyway I think all this is
working great I'm pretty happy with how
it looks so I think we can now move on
to other problems one thing that we do
have right now you can see we when we
introduced the hopping in actual Z do
you see how we're getting flashing of
these bricks now the reason for that is
the height of the character not the
camera is what's determining that value
and so I think what we probably want to
do there is actually let the cameras
resolve to position B the thing that's
actually going to do that clamping like
where the camera would like to stay
because the camera is like ignoring that
Z and we want the fading of blocks like
which is just our alpha Z range we had a
what's what's wrong here total weight
zero oh this is a lightning bug I don't
really care about that because we have
to redo letting anyway point being the
we want ideally not to change the Z
bounds for that information unless we
actually detect that the camera would be
moving right so if we're gonna leave the
camera at one Z level we don't really
want the we don't we don't want to
include things like that bounce if the
entity itself is just not really going
to be moving its general Z value so we
want a notion of what the ground level
point for this thing is actually gonna
be I think we need some way of making
sure that the camera understands that
and I'm not sure the best way to do that
but I think that's one thing that we
want to put on our list if that makes
sense so just looking at what I think we
should probably be working on now I'm
going to go ahead and say that yeah it's
kind of a toss-up I think we probably
want to do is finish up the asset
packing and stuff for sounds and things
like that so you can call that system
done so I think we may want to move on
that and then I think we want to do
finalize our rendering path so fix up
the lighting so that we're happy with it
because there's only that's the sort of
test lighting in there now which you can
see the barrier moving on right so we
want something that's gonna be really
nice and clean for that as we go forward
and I have some ideas about how to fix
that actually so I think it might not be
as bad as it could be but I also did
want to point out that I do think we
made the right decision doing some
pretty good lighting in there because
the difference between you know if you
look at how nice it looks with the
lighting in there it just looks much
better right
so I feel like we really made the right
decision having some realistic lighting
because it just provides so much
character I mean look at what it looks
like when you don't have lighting right
you know that's what what things look
like and there's just no subtlety to it
right so I think we definitely want the
good lighting in there we just want to
hack it hack it a little bit more than
we're hacking it right now so do us do a
worse approximation basically not so
much
casting because right now it's a little
bit too accurate so we just can't do it
at the speeds that we would want unless
maybe we start using GPU nonsense or
stuff like that but I don't really want
to go down that route so we really do
think we made the right decision putting
some nice lighting in there I just think
we now need to go in and maybe tone it
down a bit make it a little bit more
semantic and a little bit less realistic
so that we can still have just a really
nice consistent performance profile for
the game even if you don't have the
world's beefiest system and then yeah so
I think we want to kind of follow that
that path for now I'm gonna leave this
like this and imma put two doing here
that says we need to assess this
calculation and perhaps introduce a
selectable alternate version for this
scenario where we have spin right
because I really do think we're gonna
have a little bit of a problem with
spinning entities so I are pretty sure
we should go back and look at those a
little bit more carefully when the time
comes all right so what I want to do now
is start pushing again on the asset side
of things we could do some cleanup
we should get WAV files in there we have
some test WAV files right now we're not
doing anything with them so if we look
inside hand-made right now we've got
sort of this data directory and I think
yeah you can see in here and I don't
know if you can even hear these let me
see right now let me on this machine tab
over to the OBS window I just I don't
actually know what will happen if I play
a sound on here
so I'm not hearing it starters hmm so I
can't hear it either it's not just you
says USB audio device for speakers why
does it say that I just want there it is
[Music]
can you guys hear that everyone got that
perfect okay so if we want to put some
of these in there right I don't know
what these all are got some bloops all
right so we've got some stupid sounds
here that we can just use for testing
and so what I want to do because we
don't have the sound importing put into
this path like we did sound importing
before but we don't have it part of the
nice like dynamic loading system and all
that stuff that that we ended up doing
for the art assets and stuff so if we
want to start making this work the same
way as everything else is working what
I'm gonna do is I'm going to grab that
data and I'm gonna put it into the
sources directory as just a test so into
that like base game directory where
we've got the art music sound we sort of
set it up for these things to exist in
here right and so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna take the music tests and then
I'm gonna put the other things into
sound and so we've got music in one and
you've got sound in another and what I
want to do is I want to make the parser
that parses the tag files know how to
load music and sound like it knows how
to load everything else so if we look at
the asset directory right all I'm gonna
do is just add the parser for it today
and then tomorrow we'll merge in our cuz
weep this is really it's going to be an
exercise mostly and cut and paste
because we did all the work for this or
we just need to merge it into the game
so it's something that can be run
automatically right so if I go into the
I'm sorry I actually want the there's an
import direct there's an import file now
so if I go into the import file what you
can see is inside our synchronized asset
file changes right we go through and we
read each one of these hht files and
those hht files as you recall our tags
directory um and I don't know what these
are I guess you think so I guess this is
where Windows decided to put our temp
files when we were doing the temp file
stuff oh right because it will rewrite
them in that directory and I guess it
just didn't delete them so that's fine
I'll delete them for you I thought the
whole point of opening as a temp file
was that it would delete well we
probably don't pass the right flags for
that maybe I'm not sure we can look at
that separately point being if I go in
and open up the base game asset file you
know in here we've got like all this
stuff right there's like heads and
bodies and blocks and blah blah blah
right what I want to be able to do is
add sound stuff in here so you know if
you take a look at what's going on in
the handmade sources directory you can
see that inside base game there's that
music and there's music test stuff I
have and so what I would like to do is
just say well I guess we just have music
and it's music test valve right and you
know it should have tags just like
everything else has tags so like you
know the same way that we tag this stuff
with information that tells the game
what it is we can do the same here so we
could say like tags I don't know maybe
this is like intro music or something
and I don't know
so in our tags file we don't actually
have anything for tagging music at the
moment I don't think you can see here
that we just
like a bunch of tags that we use for
stuff and so if I wanted to do some tags
for this I could just say let's just
make a tag for like the title screen I
guess I think also if I if I'm honest
about it actually I suppose this should
be in the intro tags file so you know
how we have the intro cutscene so you
can see here like this stuff is labeled
with like these shot tags and all this
stuff right seems like maybe I should
just call this the title screen music so
in here what I'm going to do is say look
there's a music test in here and by the
way the author on that is not Ana record
actually I guess the author on this is
Casey Mira Torre and also this
description is wrong so all I really
want to do here is have some tags for
the music test which we'll say is for
the intro cutscene one of the
interesting things about this you can
see here we have like shot index layer
index and what we did for the title
screen is we had like a thing here I'm
kind of interested in saying look maybe
we just say this tag for the intro
cutscene and maybe we say there's a tag
for the title screen Oh God
what just happened I've gone into some
kind of screen shot mode okay fine uh so
that way I can tag these things more
properly like right now they're not
tagged with that but and so like what
I'd like to do is say look there's shot
in next one layer in next one for the
title screen so I'm just gonna say this
is the title screen like this and then
these I'm going to say that these are
the intro cutscene and that way I can
load these
by what they actually were and if I
added another cutscene I would just load
that as a separate cutscene right so I
think that's what I would rather do then
the way we were doing this before where
it's just the there's no extra tagging
per thing that just feels a little bit
better to me
I don't know like I said it's
experimental so puh knows but that's
just what seems like the best idea so
here I could just say that look this is
the music for the title screen and we
don't really need I don't think anything
else because it's not like the title
screen needs more than one piece of
music probably so I feel like that is
fine so in here where we do those tags
I'm just going to put our own tag in
here where we say that intro cutscene
again doing the magic of see where you
have to do everything yourself
title screen so these will both be
parsable now and so now we come through
here it will see this and it can tag of
a title screen of course it doesn't know
what a music directive is so if we
actually tried to run this it should
fail and give us an error that it
doesn't understand the music directive
so we have to add that directive and so
we'll do that and then the other thing
that we need is we need a directive for
sounds so like in the base game we need
some way of having sounds in here like
we need to do this sort of thing and
those also need to be tagged at the
moment we don't actually know what we
would tag any of these things because we
don't actually have any real use for
them so yeah like who knows but what we
would like to do here is I'm gonna see
do we have any tagging for this we don't
um so you know I'll add some tags for it
because why not I guess we've got a
bloop a crack a drop a slide in a pup so
sure I don't know
let's Adam so we're gonna add loops
cracks drops glides and pups don't ask
me why and then we're gonna put in these
files so we have loop 0 0 . laughs and
we know that that's gonna be tagged
thusly and we know that it's essentially
like a variant so I don't think we have
the causative variant at the moment and
I do think that's probably something we
want so we probably want also like this
so we can essentially say look this is
variant zero of this thing that way when
we do multiple of them we can just say
hey there's like several of these
imported in here that we want and so
they can just be variants off the same
thing that you query and the game
doesn't have to know about that like at
all right so that gives us a way to you
know easily put in 0 through one zero
two three four variants of those bloops
and then you know I can do the same
thing here for the crack and this one
doesn't really need a variant because at
the moment anyway we don't have multiple
variants of that the same is drop and
glide so if I do a drop and applied then
we just have poop left and that will
have variance so that has a variance
zero and one
so I think that's everything for at
least the import listing and so now we
just need to actually teach the parser
like what those mean because we don't
actually have any sort of we have
nothing in there that talks about music
or sound at all in terms of the ingest
so we kind of need some way of having
that you know be understand understood
by the parser so alright just putting
that in there we've got drop lied and
pop oops and then we've got the variant
so that's everything that we actually
need to recognize what's in the files
but we don't actually have any way of
looking at those more expansive keywords
right
so inside handmade import we've got to
start handling those directives properly
so what you can see in here is you know
there's a parse top-level block in
directive up here and we're gonna run
into some issues right this is gonna be
more complicated as I say we're going to
deal with tomorrow all I want to do is
kind of get the infrastructure in place
today so we don't have a whole lot of
time left I think we've only got about
30 minutes or so there's time do we have
so we started at 12:15 so we've got I
don't know 30 minutes 35 minutes
something like that so what I want to do
is make sure that this parser can parse
through them and it's going to require
some work the reason is because this
routine as you can see here it
presupposes that you've got a that
you've got an art block so you can see
in here when it comes to and says is
default you can see how it starts to you
know try to figure out where to get this
particular
data from it's gonna it's literally
starting like right off the bat to call
things like parse pieces but that's not
what you would want to do if the thing
is an audiophile so we kind of need you
know not necessarily two entire paths
but we at least need this function to be
aware of the fact that it's not always
getting that
so this subtor art for example would
need to be able to split into a couple
of different ways so one way we can do
it is like his music is sound for
example and these are like that right
and so we would know now which one of
these we're actually dealing with and
when we come down here to look at those
we could also do something that looks
like this where something like is art is
comprised of like the knot of all of
these right so if we know we're not
looking at a default or music or sound
then we know that it is the normal thing
that we expect to see most of the time
in terms of our block types because most
of our block types are artwork alright
so coming through here we would say all
right the subtor in this case we can
actually determine up here in sort of a
more speculative way and just say look
if it's music we'll change it if it's
sound we'll change it right we could
even do it this way right so we say all
right it's the music directory if it's
music it's the sound directory if it's
sound and it's the art groups it's the
art directory if it's art so now we know
like which subdirectory we're going to
look in to find the asset that's named
based on the block type and then in here
when we actually
load the file this match operation is
probably still fine because we probably
still do want to remember the asset
source file stuff effectively the same
way as we were remembering it before the
only difference now is that parse pieces
which would normally go in and do all
kinds of crazy stuff in terms of grid
importing doesn't actually need to be
there and the import type that we have
can can basically be handled a separate
way so another way to do it and I guess
maybe we could've done it this way
originally maybe I should push the
import type up and have that record
specifically which kind of import type
we're doing for art or music I don't
know that I really want to do that
though because like if you look at
what's gonna happen to some of this
stuff like with the grid points here and
align points and stuff this is really
stuff that's only gonna happen behind an
is art call and so I kind of just want
is art to bracket those things and force
the sort of extra stuff that happens
with art to not happen right and so I'm
just gonna do an is art call around
these and keep them from interfering
most of the time right the rest of this
stuff like author description name tags
and that stuff are all fine the
alignment stuff we can still allow it to
happen probably although we could also
just error out here we could say like
look if it's not art you know that's an
error right so we can say hey
you know you're not allowed to put
alignment points on an audio asset now
that's not the same as saying we might
not have something like an alignment
point I'm nadiyah asset like maybe in
the future we want to label a particular
sample offset you know what I mean and
we could do that but I'm not gonna do
that prophylactically like I'm gonna
wait till we actually have to do
something along those lines before I'm
gonna really look into that because I
don't want to do a bunch of work for
something there that we never use so I'd
like to at least have some indication
that we need alignment points and audio
before I'm gonna actually add alignment
points an audio but at the very least
what we do know is that if we were gonna
pass process them they certainly
wouldn't be running this path because
this path has no bearing on how you
would align audio that's for art
alignment so we still do want to make
sure that that doesn't actually occur
there so if we come down here and we
look at how the rebuild stuff's working
I think that can still work the same way
as it was working before and then what
we can do is here I can say look let's
make an import type audio and we'll will
sort of make that be a separate process
and then this again
is art and right so we can do that and
and I could change this one to work that
way as well
so you know I could do if is arc and
right oops
and so that way again we can just make
sure that these paths that are very
specific to art they're only happening
when arts actually involved but
otherwise you can basically leave this
routine exactly the same now when we
come through here and we do this import
stuff now when we if we know the type of
source imports audio we could do like a
process audio import like so and this
would probably take you know basically
the same stuff the difference here is
like this parse PNG again not really
going to be what we're talking about
because the PNG would only be for PNG
files so this
isn't is art kind of thing we can leave
it that way otherwise what we really
want to then have here is some kind of
wave parse so in effectively what we're
gonna do is say all right we've got a
sound 32 you know who knows what it is
but whatever we want to call our input
thing here you know and since we called
it image 32 I'm just gonna say sound s
16 I guess because that's sort of the
well so it's hard to say I mean a sound
can have a lot of different formats to
it I'm gonna call it sound a 16 I think
that's the most direct analog image you
32 is saying here's an image that uses a
u3q as its fundamental sample type which
is an RGB a 8 bit per channel packed
format sound of 16 is saying look here's
sound it's gonna have its fun little
sample format is assigned 16-bit value
so I'm just gonna say that's true and
we're gonna do like if it's sound or
music in this case then the sound equals
par suave and there's that content
stream and we're just gonna leave it at
that I don't really know that we want to
do a stream per se and so what I might
suggest because the PNG likes to read
things as a stream I don't know that web
really does I would sort of say that
passing the buffer directly might be
more straightforward so we're gonna see
which one of those two things is true
I'll just say look
let's see which one's easier to read
from I don't actually know and so what
we can do is see if we actually like the
content stream abstraction if we don't
we can just send down the actual raw
buffer if that's an easier way to parse
the web we'll just go with it
so then when we come down here instead
of passing image we'd just pass the
sound that would be the end of it this
call needs to actually exist we don't
have it yet same at the parse wave call
so those are you know two things we're
gonna have to add if we look at the
parse P&amp;G part of things that's out in
the handmade PNG if we want to keep that
format Ally up that that sort of a if we
want to keep that paradigm there we go
then what we would want to do here is
introduce another source file into that
handmade code directory which is just
called handmade Wow
not H and here there would be something
like this I don't remember what these
returned probably nothing would be my
guess let's take a look there it is
nothing so this would do the audio
import as necessary it looks like it
takes the game assets that it's using to
do the import the match in this case is
actually the thing that's produced up
here which is just a way of saying here
is the file that this was coming from so
you can see like it's like a asset
source file info there so I don't know
we want to call that maybe like source
something like this in this case sound
is one of these imaginary things that
we're saying we have oh does it go here
know why I did that there that's not
what goes in there so that stuff's gonna
be up in here right and so like with the
extract image get down sampling all this
stuff this is the stuff for images that
were using
and so I'm gonna stuff this right here
right there and this will be just
something that we haven't implemented
yet but yeah like I said this goes in
here so this is the sound you throw 16
rather I can just be like that probably
I don't know how we want to do eggs how
are we doing it here yeah we just fast
at you interesting it's a full block so
then inside the temper meanie here this
is just gonna be our memory arena that
we use for temporary locations if you
want it here's the process of import
this is just not so then what we've got
is the par suave so in par suave here
what we want to do by the way a lot of
people are annoyed that I say parse web
instead of parse wave I mean understand
the complaint but let's be honest about
spelling what does that spell that says
web that says wave if if this is wave
that can't also be waived
so it's web my friends parse web I don't
care what people meant when they made it
they spelled it well so anyway if I'm
doing a parse web to get one of these
sounds back then I just kind of need the
you know the analog of what we were
doing before so we need something here
that's gonna be one of these sound
sixteens and you know it's gonna have
basically the same stuff as that image
so it's this right where we'd have
samples array and probably something in
here you know like a channel count where
we say how many channels there were and
then you got the samples and you know
we'll interleave them or something and
you know maybe the way that we want to
do this I don't actually know but maybe
the way that we wanna do this is
actually like an array of samples maybe
there's the max channel count like maybe
we only allow things up to 8 channels or
something and it looks like that I don't
know we can obviously play with this
however we want to play with it going
forward but that's what we're gonna do
right and so we probably want the
equivalent of these sorts of things
right we probably want to have
effectively the same calls that we have
for our image
just for our sounds so we would do
something like what's the total sound
size and we get the exact same thing we
know that it's going to be we know that
it's going to be the sound channel count
oh and we need a sample count as well we
need a sound channel count times the
sample count times the size of each
individual sample which is 2 and that's
the total footprint of the sound data
that's you know pointed to or pointed
into you buy samples depending on how we
want do that I'm going to probably do it
this way just to keep it as close as
possible to this that just feels a
little bit better than me so in here
we're gonna say sound s 16 if we do a
push sound it's the same thing so we can
say look give me the sample count
give me the channel count and I will
create that it's flat footprint for you
so here's the sound as 16 that's the
results the sample count is the sample
count the channel count is the channel
counts and then when we have the actual
samples for our sounds we're gonna do
that push size exactly the same as we
were doing it before but we're gonna do
total sound size in this case for the
result before that that sound result
that we're giving back so that's again
just the exact equivalent and then we
just want the the equivalent here as
well we want to say hey give us a memory
ready to put this thing in give us a
sound return when you're done parsing it
parse the wav file as you would you can
give us some stream information so you
can give us the input and where you want
us to send output to if this were a
command line which it isn't but if you
wanted to we could do that as well and
then we've got the equivalent right so
now we've got that taken care of and
then in the C file this is where okay
don't ask me what just happened
okay there we go so in the C file now
we've got the implementation of this
which we will do largely by importing
code we've already written but for now
it's not implemented and the sound of 16
result that this comes back you know
here that again is just going to return
the you know pushed version of this that
we load it out of the file so it's not
particularly interesting one way or the
other so that's how our parse wave is
gonna work there and I think we can now
hop back to the import code
I'm gonna build but I'm gonna ignore
what it does that's just to save my
files and so I think we've got things
mostly straightened out here the way
that I want them to go I don't see a lot
of other stuff so mostly what we're
dealing with is just the head end when
we come through here and we get the file
by path and we do this here this import
type what I want to do there is I think
I just want to stuff that so I think I
want to do like if is sound or is music
do one thing otherwise try to do it this
way right and I'm going to set that
import type here to like import type
sound or what did I say audio so I need
to add import type audio to the list of
things that we have defined in the first
place and you know public service
announcement you want to actually do
that not fat-fingered their own but
although I believe the fact that I
haven't updated my for coder because
that normally would have been the right
thing to do I'm gonna add a counter in
here just in case we want it later so
I'm gonna argue that that's structurally
more or less what this thing should look
like so that it can just parse inline
those particular things looking at what
we've got here you can see that we're
gonna get a bunch of undefined stuff
because I didn't include any of the
so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go to
handmaid dot H and wherever the PNG
stuff ends up living I'm just gonna dump
laughs in there as well right so now we
can have both of those defined as they
normally would be and we can deal with
the errors from that code so including
those and then I'm gonna take a look at
what we've got for errors it looks like
that was no errors all right so now what
should happen is when we actually run
this code hopefully if I did everything
right it'll parse those blocks it'll
decide it needs to do some audio
importing and the audio importing will
just roll over and die because all it is
is a bunch of not implemented code which
is not what we want so I'm gonna start
down that route because I just want to
dump the coding today
and then tomorrow we start we'll start
looking at in the debugger and get it
working so inside our HHA or no sorry
test asset builder I think so if you
take a look at this code which we wrote
already we already did audio importing
like we did that right so what I should
be able to do is take this stuff and say
alright if we've got you know a wave
importer let's use it you know so I
don't remember how I structure the PNG
one is it in here yes so I just put it
in the header file I'm gonna follow that
example so I'm just gonna say look here
is the wave stuff or wave stuff and I'm
gonna define it
thus right I don't love the
capitalization so I'm gonna uncap that I
realize I know why we did it but I don't
like it so we're gonna call it something
else for now just clean this up a little
bit so I'll probably clean this up a
little bit but you know over time so
we've got the pragma pushpop in there
again because these are tightly packed
meaning if you look at evenly what
happens here occasionally you get
something like a hanging you in eighth
normally see will pad those structures
out for you I guess that's not true this
is a 16 so you know honestly these don't
even look like they need the padding it
looks like it's always got a full 32-bit
on it so I don't even know what you
would need it but the pragma pack one
here around these is because these are
getting loaded from files we don't want
the C compiler inserting any padding and
so it's just a turn it off in case there
was a header that had some like hanging
data values or interleaved data values
that would cause it to insert some
padding and then all of our reads are
wrong so that's all it's happening there
again we've done that many times the
pass so I'm just mentioning again if you
aren't familiar with that you could
probably search for that in the handmade
hero archive and go back and watch
episode where I kind of go over what
that means the first time so if we clean
up these a little bit to kind of sort of
the more modern version that we're using
now where we've we've sort of evolved
our opinion of this and now just looking
at how we're doing this wave chunk ID
for my that data looks fine this is all
fine those are the types for the reading
and what I want to do is go take a look
at the loading call for the sounds here
so you can see we've got like riff
iterator and parse junk at and next
chunk and is valid and all that stuff
get junk data get type junk data size
that's all the stuff for iterating over
the riff stuff there
and I don't actually know to what extent
we need all of that stuff but what I
will do if we actually do need it is I
will go ahead and put that those calls
into the stream handler so from now on
we can just use streams as riff
iterators and vice-versa I think I'll
try it that way first because now that
we have the notion of an incoming stream
that we kind of made for other purposes
we might as well build riff
understanding in there in case we want
to read riff data types like wave again
riff
just I believe that the IFF moniker
comes from the electronic arts original
iff which is the interchange file format
I don't know where the r comes from do
we have a definition for this so it is
it's the same last it's interchange file
format so resource is the only
difference there
uh I don't know let's see yeah so I'm
correct it is based on the original
Electronic Arts interchange file format
which is for the Amiga yeah that right
here oh okay
all right that makes perfect sense so
these says the only difference is that
they went little-endian so you can
understand why right the the comer Amiga
was a Motorola processor so of course it
was big endian so it makes perfect sense
so when they did the PC version of it
they changed a little Indian so they
wouldn't have to constantly byte swap
everything makes sense we've talked
about Indian miss any Nisour if you
haven't seen that again check the
archive uh so if we go ahead and import
this stuff you can see that the load
wave call is actually pretty compact
it's much simpler than parse PNG because
loading a raw wave is really simple it
doesn't have any compression in there
most time so you can usually just
guarantee you that you just don't care
it looks it looks like what we actually
did here
well because they asked you I don't know
we did here so
I'm just I'm not sure what the section
sample index part of things is that's
what I was I wasn't sure about is that
for streaming or was that for something
else so you can see us parse the chunks
here so we just we get all that out and
then we come down here and say let's
compute you know where this junk is
gonna go and then we come through here
and we say if we actually were gonna
load samples make sure that the part
we're gonna load out yes so I I think
that this was we had we had baked into
the load sort of extracting a section of
the song of the whatever the web was for
streaming purposes so I'm going to
assume that if I search down for load
web that we've got something in here
that would actually have done some kind
of a segmentation so you can see the
first sample index bit there so let me
see I just want to make sure I'm right
about that before I go change that
around so
I don't see I don't see any sound
chaining happening here though let me
look and see if there's any reference to
actual sound training aha
so we do load music test then we do do a
sound chain on it and we do so there's
that sampling okay so it's exactly what
I thought was going on just took me a
little bit to verify that that was the
case so effectively what we're doing
there is saying look when we load the
web out we may want to load only a
portion of the web out because we may
want to break it up into chunks for
streaming purposes right and then the
way that that works is we create
multiple wives multiple assets and we
just tie them together with like
effectively like a pointer it's not
really a pointer it's sort of just an
idea that we'd use for training so all
we really want to do is make sure we can
still do that behavior I don't really
want that baked into the wave load I
would rather that be handled on the
outside so I think I am gonna go ahead
and say that the way that I'm going to
do this is the parse wife call will
literally parse the whole lab and I
don't care if that's two gigabytes worth
of data get a 64-bit machine it's not my
problem because this is for asset
processing and I don't want to have to
care about it so then what I want to do
is say anyone who's going to use the
streaming chunking break up you can do
that as a separate work on the loaded
wave buffer right so that's my opinion
on that and that's how we're gonna do it
until something until I hit something
that stops me
that's the way we're gonna do it
let's go ahead and see how our stream
stuff might handle this if you take a
look at the way it works in here you can
see that you basically consume stuff off
of it and so when we do the parse chunk
stuff what that would normally do is
that would consume one RIF headers worth
of stuff and then if you wanted to go to
the next chunk it would skip the size of
that chunk as it went so I guess the
only thing
so I guess you know looking at this what
I would say is it does seem like well I
mean we could still use it it's just
fine the only thing is since you're
gonna want to jump around to various
parts of the file I'm not really sure to
what extent we care about that so it may
really not be worth it to integrate it
into the stream stuff I don't know I
don't have a strong opinion about it one
way or the other to really be honest
with you when we do this parse we have
here you know I'm gonna just start by
playing around a little bit and we'll
see what I decide going into it if I
delete this stuff here then we're ready
to start if I want to get a wave header
the way this would work is I would just
say consume right and I would say from
this stream and I don't know yeah that's
gonna take an address there I don't know
why we don't pass an address of that if
I look at the PNG reader what you can
kind of see about parse PNG is that it
takes a stream by value which means that
it won't change the stream that was
passed in I don't really know why we did
it that way I'll keep it that way for
this because we might as well be
consistent but it's a little strange so
I don't really know why we didn't pass
in an address of a stream we must have
had some reason anyway if I say consume
for the wave header here so that will
come back and again just looking back
the stream
consume version here you can see how
that shakes out you say give me one of
the why there give me one of these and
back comes a point of that thing from
whatever it was that I was that I
consumed it and it seems fine in here we
say all right let's make sure that it's
actually what we expected to be when we
come through here let's see we then use
the chunk parsing so that would really
just be consuming the chunks and then
skipping forward by their size as we go
when we actually want to get the data
you can see that happening here there's
an F empty chunk which tells us stuff
like what the sample rate was and how
many bits per sample there were now for
our purposes so well I didn't finish my
almond biscuit that's how into get we
were
for our purposes we have an issue with
ingesting sample rates and I don't know
exactly how we want to solve it so when
we are given a WAV file I think we
probably want to just say it has to be
16 bits per sample and it has to be 48
kilohertz right the reason that I think
we want to do that is because if we
don't do that we get into a whole issue
of how do we want to resample sound
that's given to us at formats that we
didn't expect
right there's like a whole can of worms
that you open up if you decide to go
down the digital signal processing
rathole of how do I take a sound in one
format and convert it to another and by
format of course I don't mean AIFF
versus wave what I mean is if the sound
was fundamentally recorded at one sample
rate 48,000 samples per second 44,000
samples per second whatever it was and
you want it at a different sample rate
which in our case will always be 48,000
samples per second but whatever it is
you have in a while transitioning
between those two sample rates is not a
direct conversion you have to actually
apply some kind of signal processing
because you fundamentally have a single
signal that you don't know what it is or
you have no idea what the original
signal was and all you have is sample
points spaced out at a certain distance
and now you want to know what that
signal you don't know what it was what
it would have been what the samples
would have been if they were spaced
differently right
fundamentally the answer is you can't
right there is no way to actually know
the answer because without knowing the
original signal you have no idea what it
would be sampled in different locations
but much like images get resized and
they still look like themselves the same
is true for sounds but exactly analogous
the images what kind of filtering you
choose to do to produce a different size
or a different sampling of the original
thing has artifact effects there are
things that will actually occur right
that will be better or worse quality or
have different concerns in terms of what
ends up happening to the frequencies you
hear in the sound and how they are
reproduced based specifically on how you
choose to resample now fortunately just
straight linear interpolation actually
works remarkably well to the untrained
ear but suffice to say if you really
want to know what's going on and tackle
that problem directly you kind of want
to know more digital signal processing
or DSP and so again it opens up kind of
a whole can of worms that I really don't
necessarily want to open what I would
rather do is say that anyone who wants
to put sounds into handmade Hiro should
open up a program that has good DSP
right a good sound editor may be Reaper
and resample there right like resample
in a package where you have some control
over it where someone hopefully did some
DSP work to ensure this we're gonna get
good results and only give us files that
are actually sampled at the right sample
rate so I think we probably want to
change these asserts so they're not
asserts they're just errors now but we
do still probably
error I don't want to try and handle
multiple formats now we're basically out
of time so I think I'm gonna do for now
does it make if zero this app block out
look so and then just clean up any
compiler as we have we don't have any
I'm gonna leave it there
and then tomorrow we will try to get
audio import started alright so let's go
ahead and go to QA
plus us at CSV type concurrency in
the next edition so one thing that that
hopefully everybody knows about me is I
do not follow the C++ specification so
basically not only do I not know what
they will add in the next edition but I
don't care what they will add in the
next edition because it's always
terrible so you know we'll see plus plus
add hermeneutic graph traversal to the
next edition not only do I not know what
hermeneutic graph trend graph traversal
is but I can guarantee you that when I
actually do need to know what it is and
I go learn about it I will find that the
C++ standard committees version of it is
terrible because that's literally what
always happens like pick a language
feature the day you need to use that
feature if you go look at C++ version of
it it sucks that they added the worst
possible version like they almost like
it's like they started a committee to
try and figure out how to make sure that
they would only add a version of that
thing that was lousy and I don't know
how they do it they do it over and over
this like they look at like some kind of
a master's degree or like a PhD in never
doing the best version of something
they're like let's come in fourth on
everything in fact that C++ there is a
language called fourth C++ should
actually be called fourth because if you
were to rank the languages at how well
they implemented declare feature like
C++ would always come in like fourth at
best
have you seen Brett Victor's talk
inventing on principle I have not on the
pre stream I'd asked about finding the
filter kernels and you asked where they
meant the integer or the floating-point
do you mind explaining how you found
each thanks sure so the integer filter
was found by literal just trial and
error there are so few possible filters
that are close to a sharpening filter
in integer in / 32 which is what I was
working on I ideally wanted to find / 16
I couldn't find one good enough so then
I went to / 32 that you can basically
just try them all there's just not very
many right because each coefficient
fundamentally can only be between 1 and
15 / 16 and they have to add to 1 and
they have to look like a sharpening
filter so they have to pretty much look
like a sink
sort of like something sink ish uh and
so there were only you know I don't know
20 30 candidates I mean it was so few I
just looked at them and pick the best
one a floating point I didn't do that
I just cheesed out on floating point I
just said look here's an ideal filter
quote-unquote here's one that I know is
infinite and let me just like search in
between them what's all I did you can do
other things you can use eigen analysis
on them which I was told by Fabien you
can just do an octave octave just has
this built in it's like one call to look
at the eigenvalues but even that doesn't
really quite get you where you want to
be because it's hard to know where you
want those eigenvalues to sum to one
sort of but because truncation is in the
mix you can actually push harder than
that and have them some to something
slightly over one and that's actually
usually the best filter so it feel a
little bit of a trial and error process
you know Sam
have you tried Oni no is that a language
modern modal editing powered by knee of
em oh so it's an editor no I have not I
have not tried that
[Music]
so yeah I mean just looking at it it
doesn't look like something that would
interest me particularly
so I doubt it would be something I would
be interested in but you know it's hard
to say without actually using it
obviously oops that's the wrong computer
do we want 32-bit floating-point samples
for high quality audio streams uh no I
don't think so I mean I'm not really an
audiophile I'll start with that but I
guess what I would say is I don't really
know of much in the way of audio sources
where you would need 32-bit
floating-point audio samples like what
sound would you be recording that would
require like 32-bit float as the storage
format obviously we mix in 32-bit float
because it's just fast right like modern
computers are very fast at 32-bit float
mixing so you mind as well and you don't
have to worry about like you know
overflows or things like that in the
middle but I mean I'll start with the
fact that just where we already licensed
music for handmade here the where we
licensed music from only delivers 16-bit
audio for the music in the first place
so you know our music obviously wouldn't
be a 16-bit wouldn't be a 32-bit
floating point source for sound effects
I haven't really done anything for that
but you know we would probably also
contract with someone for sound effects
at some point would they deliver a
32-bit float sound effect sources I
don't know maybe people do that nowadays
I don't know I'm not like I said merrily
an audio files I don't know but I would
I just don't I don't really know of any
reason for that I mean I guess what I
would say is what is the sound that you
think that you need 32-bit
floating-point recording for as the
storage format like like is
can you can you name a circumstance
where you can actually tell the
difference between those two like a
normal human being like not a like not a
dog what do you think about procedural
audio I think it's interesting but we
won't be doing it on handmade hero why
was the windows sync worse than the one
you found if sinks are ideal does the
kernel need slight changes from the
ideals values once it is windowed so I
guess I don't know necessarily that I
can say why per se I assume it's because
the way that the sink is windowed
constructs something whose eigenvalues
are actually higher than one but I don't
really know Fabien probably did the
analysis I'd have to go back and look he
sent me some mails I asked him to please
post the stuff he sent me to his blog I
never heard back from him on that my
guess is he just doesn't have time to do
that right and it takes time to put a
blog post he I want to say did that it's
either he or Charles did that and
probably have the answer in one of those
emails but you know that was a private
communication so I don't I don't have I
can't point you to that it's impossible
to write a graphic card to bugger like n
site or something they have to be done
by graphic card vendors my assumption
would be like yes and no you know
graphic card have like only the vendor
can provide the low level access
necessary to do debugging features but
my understanding of the way that they
work right now is that those features
are not hidden so I think once you once
you install the debug version of the
drivers that n site uses
I think you can also ask for that
information
like the performance counters and the
you know debug information that they are
getting I I think you can get it don't
quote me on that
but my understanding was that like while
you do need debug support in the driver
because obviously that's the thing that
can actually talk to grass card and
figure anything out getting access to
those pieces of information that you
wouldn't necessarily already have I
think you can do I think you can do that
on as long as you're on one of those
debug drivers already I'm a computer
science student or recently started
falling you're serious on YouTube helped
me a lot
because you explained really good in
depth I just want to say thanks for all
the work you do for us and I hope that I
never catch up with a series because you
will never stop doing them well thanks
for the kind words you're you'll catch
up someday well here's the thing
either you'll catch up to the series
someday or you'll just be good enough
that you don't bother watching anymore
cuz you already know right you'll get
you'll get to one you'll get one of
those two places anyone who doesn't give
up on the handmade Hero series pretty
much will get to one of those two places
either they catch up someday or they
just get so good that they don't really
need me right they don't need me telling
them what to do anymore
right they've they graduate so something
will happen if you keep at it that seems
to be the case
I'm touring why we chose get over travel
man despite its simplicity I'm just not
convinced this better um I don't know
that anyone did choose get over travel
man what happened was since Alan keeps
his source code on get anyway he just
gave me access to get thinking that
would make it easier for us to share
information as you saw during fur coat
or Jam that is not what it did travel
man is way better but you know get
ladies and gentlemen source code control
that's actually slower than the copy
command
no more questions you know what I should
do too I posted this on Twitter I should
I should add it to our builds you'll
notice it like when you get error
messages in Visual Studio I posted this
Twitter just because I didn't know about
this I went in was looking at it's like
they must have added by now and I went
look that it turns out they had it's
just kind of little bit buried when you
get error messages you don't get column
numbers you just get line numbers and I
always was kind of sad about that but
what I realized was that there actually
is one that they added I think in 2017
or something so if you actually add
minus Diagnostics colon column I think
if you add that to your build line it
actually tells you where the errors are
by column loops I should put the air
better it actually tells you where the
column is of the error as well right so
you can see it got that and so when you
when like in the editor now right like
for a coder can can jump right to the
token that was wrong which is kind of
nice because if you have something like
you know result sample count equals
sample count or just you know 5 plus 3
like this and you need to build it's
nice if you can just say jump right to
the air so you know like if if the if
this line was long I'm trying to give a
good example
right so you know I do some build and
I've got some big long line with tons of
stuff in it I know that's not a very
good example but imagine there's tons of
confusing stuff in it and you're like
where is the actual like error now it'll
go right to it right because it knows
comment so I don't know how many editors
support columnar errors but I suspect
many do for coder does other and it's
probably due because a lot of them work
with clang which switch which supplies
column numbers in addition to line
numbers so just public service
announcement add Diagnostics come on
column into your build line it's just a
free nice time-saving thing it can only
help right as long as your editor
supports aver doesn't support it maybe
it will confuse your editor in which
case not so good but other than that JBC
cannon you made an offhand comment a
source code control to you maybe
yourself a ticket if you have seen it
other than yourself actually yes
in technically nobody has ever seen it
but me well I guess Ana's seen it
running but
age joram they intentionally didn't make
reporting columns default behavior nor
did not break back charlie exactly yeah
like there are probably editors that
just don't know what to do with a line
of that format and so I'm sure that
visual studio couldn't just start
reporting columns because it would just
break everybody so they put it under a
switch and then didn't really publicize
it particularly well so you know nobody
knew about it but it's there so as long
as it doesn't break something that you
have it's it's great right turn it on
have you seen V Lang is it vaporware I
think I saw somebody mention it it was
like a language being made for an email
quite no like a social media client or
something I don't even know a messenger
client or something I didn't look at it
at all really
no so I paper where who died who knows I
have no idea I don't know anything about
it I've read the sequel said sister I
surf your questions cry just comments
your coding styles super pleasing just
popping out Struck's left and right so
procedural no weird stuff less isms
verbose variable and function name so
there's no ambiguity it's nice and as a
huge implement out for the better I'm
very glad to hear that I really can't
emphasize enough but like code being
clear and procedural is incredibly
important it's important in way more
ways than people realize legibility is
obviously one of them maintainability is
another one but also just efficiency
like code that's written roughly like
the CPU will actually do it is just a
really good way to make sure you're not
making something super piggy and bloated
that just runs really slowly um I like
high-level language features actually I
know probably looks like I don't I
actually do like high-level language
features the problem is that C++ as
high-level artists are just all terrible
all they do is make complicated weird
convoluted code that sucks like it's
just it's not good high-level it does
let you make good code quickly it lets
you make bad code quickly and that is
not what I want out of a high level
language feature right so I would like
to say that I don't really like the fact
that I don't get any high level language
features when I program and see what
fuss because the only ones available to
me are lousy but I would like some
eventually so it's not that I don't
think they're I think high level answers
are good I wish they were geared towards
things that I care about and written in
a way that I like they're often not so I
can't use in the C++ but barring that
even when I have high level language
features I still prefer it to be in a
procedural mode so I still like tool to
see what is happening correctly laid out
and a lot of high level languages don't
do that they just are totally convoluted
and trying to ferret what's actually
going on to the hood takes a long time
if you didn't write the code yourself
and I don't like that so I like it when
high level is still clear and I think
you can do that I just don't think
languages prioritize legibility and
efficiency when they're doing high level
languages they tend to prioritize weird
like they get into these weird like head
spaces where they're not thinking about
the CPU it's like they're in ABS
completely abstract land and that I just
don't find productive at least a bad
decision making at least a high level
programming languages that can't produce
good code right
hit a wall every company I look up
demand and not a healthy balance of
procedure but the ultra-radical oh and
nothing but yeah I mean you know what
can you do right there's a reason you
get paid to program and it's because
it's not always fun and having to use
object oriented programming is one of
those ways that can be really not fun
synth is at work I started rewriting a
Python package in seats as performance
is so bad that nobody wants it anymore I
was wondering why people do not write in
native code that that often anymore and
choose the scripting language that cause
a lot of people problems for down the
road Jeremy commonly yeah they just you
think it's too hard right
writing a native code once you're kind
of in package land where you think like
oh I'll just install these seventeen
Python packages and then it'll only be a
few lines of code to do this thing you
know that helps you get stuff done
quickly that you don't understand right
that you couldn't have written yourself
or that we're taking too long to write
yourself or whatever right and there's
some benefits to that which is to say
that you can write something that you
don't understand or you can write
something that would have taken several
months you could write it very quickly
problem is it sucks right it's really
slow and it's probably very buggy and it
probably has a lot of hidden problems
with it you don't know about because you
have no idea what those eleven hundred
packages are doing right and so it's
just a bad trade-off that people get
themselves into right and you know what
can you do right we just we haven't
gotten to the silver bullet yet where
you can write a few simple things and
get really great code out the other end
we we aren't there yet right and Adam
maybe we'll never be there but you know
assuming that someday we'd get there
it's just it's further down the line and
[Music]
you know
all right I think I'm gonna I'm gonna
ended Erica we were out of time I don't
see any other questions that are like on
what we were doing so I you know I try
to answer any questions that are on what
we actually did but you know off-topic
stuff I'm okay which is kind of skipping
for now I can always tack them another
day
all right I don't know if I mean it
changes but anyway all right thank you
everyone for joining me from episode a
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along with the series at
home you can always go to handmade hero
org and it if you preorder the game that
comes with a source code right now so
you can play around with it play around
with what we're doing learn from it
whatever you want to to do to sort of
follow on the series at that point it
makes pretty easy I'll be back here
tomorrow same time same place to
sleeping if that wave parser actually
integrated in shouldn't be too hard
already have a working version but we
got to do the massaging and then we have
to get it integrated the asset system
properly as well so when it actually
does its import those assets will be
placed in the asset system in a logical
way which again requires a little bit of
work because we kind of redid the way we
did some of our memory paging is stuff
like that that's about it I hope see you
back here for next stream tomorrow until
then have fun putting everyone I'll see
you on the Internet
techies everybody