so one of the things that I get asked
about all the time on the stream now
especially because I've had hand paid in
the past and I've talked about it on the
stream is essentially like you know what
what do you do for you know physical
problems like pain problems or you know
aches and/or you know weird nerve
sensations sort of stuff if you do a lot
of programming or a really any job that
involves sitting down and typing most of
the day you know there's sort of this
undercurrent of everyone sort of has
these problems but nobody really knows
that much about them in our industry and
we don't really know necessarily what to
do and you know you might go on the
internet and do some searches or
something and find some kind of a you
know WebMD page with some ads on the
side and you read the symptoms and
you're like oh okay maybe this is what I
have maybe I should do this weird thing
that they're saying or something but
what we do at Molly rub get whenever we
have any sort of a problem with with
physical things related to work is we
ask dr. Emily sure so I asked her to
come today and talk to all of us about
you know essentially like what's the
real beginner you know the the novice
introduction from a medical professional
to people who don't really know anything
about this about how to like diagnose
and think about these problems so that
they can essentially get the the medical
help that they need right and you know
if you understand more what's happening
with your anatomy and more what's
happening with your you know nervous
system all sort of stuff you can ask the
right professional to help you and have
some idea of where you need to go or
what you might need to do to stop having
these kinds of problems so yeah without
further ado doctor am I sure
[Music]
[Applause]
good morning so so first of all I'll
give us a little bit of background you
know since we don't know anything about
you here I obviously know you personally
but what's what what got you into this
profession what got you into like
diagnosing sort of these sorts of
problems and helping people with them
because obviously you do a lot more than
just sort of problems that programmers
might have or something I know you do a
lot of work with like circus performers
and all these other sorts of things so
give us a little background there I grew
up kind of being a very physical person
and always was an athlete and a gymnast
specifically and a dancer and got into
circus when I was a kid and I've always
been a person who watches movement and
enjoys movement and I kind of knew I
wanted to do something with human bodies
and movement so eventually after
spending too much time or to start
amount of time performing and playing
around the world I went back to school
and I am now a doctor of physical
therapy which basically means I like
movement a physical therapist what we do
which I think most people don't actually
know is we are movement diagnosticians
so we look at the anatomy we look at the
biomechanics and we problem-solve how
all that works together and place
together to give you the symptoms or
your pain or just the weird way you walk
down the street so walking in front of
my office is always interesting because
I'm always staring at everyone going ooh
that it's weird but but yeah so that's
kind of my quick background I love
working with anybody who moves which is
pretty much everybody and I just find it
really interesting it's kind of like
what you guys do see you are faced with
a problem you need to find the answer to
and you are problem-solving it's the
same thing from my end it's all physics
and engineering levers pulleys the human
body is a really interesting simple
machine so in your you run your own
practice now and I was curious so do you
see a lot of people come in with kind of
pain or injuries related to doing work
at a computer is that a common thing
that you have or is it the kind of thing
that people just don't really know to
you know seek help for or going to the
wrong places for it's really interesting
because I would say most of the people I
see have pain due to the way they are
working whether or not they know it or
not so even if my circus people are
coming in usually so I treat a lot of
circus performers both students and
performers here in the Seattle community
and most of the circus students are not
full-time circus performers and they
spend their week sitting at their desk
and then their evenings and weekends
flying around on things and usually what
they're coming in for is certainly
contributed to by how they're sitting at
their desk and all the things I do like
this and then they all of a sudden want
to do this and they don't realize it
what we train our body for every day is
the things that we do so if you're
practicing this all the time this
becomes what you're good at
even if it's not a great shape for your
body and more specifically you know what
you're asking is do people come in for
this sometimes okay oh it's it's hard to
answer because I don't know who I'm not
seeing okay that's a good point so
people that come in to me yeah
absolutely every single person that
comes in with pain from work it's
totally coming in for work
that's okay so essentially what you're
saying there is that even though someone
may not be coming in and saying hey I'm
having problems I type all day and I get
this pain in my wrist or something
you do get situations where like someone
comes in and says I'm having pain for
this thing that I do on the weekend and
I you know I think it's that and you're
like yeah okay and you're you know
you're kind of like this and Stephanie I
can see that like probably part of the
problem is just your your musculature is
not you know sometimes I see people who
come in and I'm chatting with them about
stuff we're like oh yeah and I have this
thing when I'm working I see so it's
kind of like a little bit of a doorway
question there or whatever they call it
where it's like kind of like oh you know
by the way here's the actual thing and I
you know didn't mention that as part of
the thing right because they don't think
of it as a thing because it just happens
every day or I had a you know patients
come in and they're like oh yeah and
this thing but it's been happening to me
since I was 15 okay okay just because
it's been happening you since you're 15
does not mean it's not involved does not
mean it's not it's a normal occurrence
so let's let's dive into the to the sort
of science part here I have a list of
stuff that you sort of sent me that was
like here's the sorts of things we
should probably talk about and I think
I'm just going to start with those
because you kind of knit like I don't
even have like a basic understanding
really of how these sorts of things fit
together so I feel like I can't really
put them in a good order so tell me if
I'm going out of you don't feel like you
happens or times gonna kind of go by the
sorts of things you talked about so that
I you know hopefully something up right
so the first thing that you were talking
about is diagnosis versus symptoms
that's what you were saying and you
specifically mention the fact that like
doctors label symptoms not causes or
something like that you you said
something there and I wasn't really sure
what you meant so could you maybe start
with that and telling a little tussle
about like the diagnosis symptoms thing
and what you were thinking about sure so
your traditional primary care doctor or
often orthopedist that you go into and
say hey I have low back pain
I am a computer and they're gonna go
great you have a diagnosis of low back
pain but what is that really your low
back pain is a symptom what's causing
the low back pain why is it there if I
look at someone's low back pain I'm like
well obviously it's musculoskeletal it's
how they're moving it's what they're
doing though
low back pain could be a lot of other
medical conditions that have a side
effect of low back pain or that symptom
so a lot of our medical system currently
doesn't have a good language of brown's
musculoskeletal pain and we're still
kind of learning and kind of developing
that language so a lot of the diagnoses
traditionally are not really helpful
they're a description of what you're
experiencing but they're really not
causational so again this is kind of
what I was talking about with physical
therapist says movement dies when
Diagnostics is we're kind of filling in
that void of we have it I have a
diagnosis system not all physical
therapy is growing and changing so there
are many different diagnostic systems
but the diagnosis system I use for
example with low back pain is you know I
diagnose by the cause movement cause so
okay you have low back pain do you have
it because every time you bend forward
and that's a stressor that bothers you
or every time you get a rotation which
could be because you're moving your arm
and that's pulling on your back so it's
of rotation diagnosis or reflection
diagnosis or the different movement
orientations of the back but knowing and
understanding that what you're
experiencing might just be a symptom of
something going on more globally in your
body it's really kind of important I
know
Casey's talked a lot about self
diagnosis of carpal tunnel syndrome what
kind hopefully get to that bitterness
but is that because of something
happening a wrist is that because it's
me happening your elbow at your shoulder
your neck there can be a lot of
different causes for the same diagnosis
yeah and I feel like that's one of those
sort of memes that got around was carpal
tunnel syndrome so now people just if
they're having some general problem here
they're like I must have carpal like
it's kind of this unfortunate thing
where they just think that and maybe
that has some of you that maybe it
doesn't or they don't even necessarily
know what they should be doing like do I
need to get surgery for this all of a
sudden or something
and not necessarily no but yeah I guess
we can put that down - we did - you had
the common ailments section here on the
diagnosis versus symptoms thing so is it
the case generally that you know if you
go to like a primary care physician
is it sort of like just well if you
happen to get one who knows about you
know movement mechanics or something
they may go oh I should probably refer
you to somebody who's gonna take a look
at this more carefully versus someone
who just doesn't think along those lines
and just goes like okay you know
prescribe some you know aspirin I'm like
like when you go to a primary care
physician is it generally the case that
they would be expected to properly refer
you in the case of a mechanical problem
or is that just kind of hit or miss it's
it's hard to say how to say in Seattle
we've got great okay I'm we're here docs
in general and usually they're gonna
look at it and be that and and think
okay that is musculoskeletal problem and
they're really great at referring out to
physical therapy orthopedist whatever
they think is is appropriate primary
care Doc's are amazing because they have
such a wide breadth of knowledge and
their job is really to point you down
the correct Avenue and the correct
pathway so a good primary care doc yeah
is gonna is gonna either say yeah I
think this is solvable with the
contribute of treatment whether that's
take these NSAIDs go home ice whatever
or and come back later and then we'll
see or send you on to another
practitioner my feeling is why try to
mask it again with Ison comeback that
whatever you every generally if it's a
it's a more long-term problems
repetitive stress injury they tend to
come back if you fell down the stairs
you don't tend to fall down the stairs
repeatedly so that's gonna be something
that if you do fall down the stairs
repeatedly so yeah and again just
finally on that note there it's like so
if you want to get diagnosed for
something like this like if you want
maybe you don't have access to a good
primary care you know wherever you are
whatever or you you just you would like
to have someone take a look at your
movement mechanics I is physical therapy
something you can
go to directly or is this something that
you have to go through Amanda thought
about it for like you know after we're
sort of done talking about about all
this stuff today if people are like I
would like to talk to specialists in
this because obviously it in you know 90
minutes they're not going to now
suddenly be able to do this themselves
how you know how do they go about
accessing that that care or even
figuring out who a good practitioner in
their area might be is there something
they can turn to yeah so legislation
varies from state to state most states
have some form of direct sac direct
access to physical therapy so in most
states you can show up at your physical
therapist and make an appointment and
get seen I am NOT up to date on which
states are which at the moment
Washington is one of them Washington is
absolutely one of them some states are
like you can see a PT for 30 days as
long as there's progress and all that
stuff
other states that I not sure about they
do require doctors referral and if you
have a good relationship with your
primary care doctors you can basically
usually pretty easy depending on their
relationship with you and how well they
know you there was a second part to that
question well be the second part
question was sort of like let's say that
well and I guess this is sort of guess
the fact that if you're going to get
help for something like this obviously
you may have preferences or you may want
to know that you know you're going to
somebody especially you mentioned
there's many different systems of
diagnosis which is a question I wanted
to ask you about later you know is there
some reading you can do or a place you
can go online to find out more about the
physical therapists or other people who
would do this sort of thing in your area
so that you can make an informed
decision about who you go to because I
mean just like any medical care not
everyone is going to be the same kind of
you know treatment so I didn't know is
there like a some kind of a resource you
can use to find physical area or even if
it was something in just a case of like
I want to go to you know say I'm out of
state or like I like the way Emily
diagnoses problems I want to go to
someone who follows that same school of
this kind of you know choice that make
sense yes it absolutely does there are
resources there's the American Physical
Therapy organist
Association and they have state chapters
and there's often listings of providers
on their site it doesn't it tells you
who's still involved in the national
organization but doesn't tell you much
more about them I certainly love the
word-of-mouth network if you really are
lost and don't know where to go often
that's where a primary care provider can
be a good resource as well but like hey
I've heard good things about this person
or that person because they're in your
local community and and know a lot of
the different kind of schools of thought
may have their own referral basis and
kind of lists on different networks mine
does not though we do have our own
spreadsheet that we have internally so I
can open up if people are interested
they're welcome to email me and I can
see if I can make that available and/or
possibly personally respond depending on
what the demand is but yes the the
school of thought that I was trained in
is movement system impairments so it's
really looking at things on a movement
centric model so some physical
therapists practice more joint centric
model they'll look at the joint or the
tissue that they believe to be injured
and kind of work out from there and I'm
generally looking more movement and
working kind of inward and that is not
necessarily unique to the school of
thought but I am part of but it's just
kind of different mentalities to kind of
get the same problems so just I I mean I
sort of understand what you're saying
but I'm not totally clear so you keep
you have like sort of a subnetwork like
that you guys know about it we have a
Facebook group it's really okay so
basically like that's so so that there
is sort of sort of a professional it's
not an organization technically but a
professional sort of network where
people do know each other but that's not
necessarily exposed to the patients who
just is generally browsing but if people
really wanted to they could email you or
talk to you about the okay
so let's move on to talking about the
actual nitty-gritty here so someone
comes in with this kind of a problem
like something
where it's gonna probably be
work-related or use baby they don't come
in with some this work later but you
suspect based on what you're seeing that
it's gonna be work-related so what sorts
of things do you start looking for like
how do you what is this kind of you know
when you just first start looking at
someone how they're moving I know as
someone who's gone through this process
like you do it very much like a software
engineer actually would approach well a
good software engineer would approach
debugging a problem where you kind of go
like okay I'm gonna start doing a bunch
of testing and getting sort of
information about what's going on can
you just give us a little bit
introduction to like that process and
what you're looking for how you're
putting those pieces together in sort of
like maybe an abstract sentence
so when someone walks in the door I have
a systematic exam that I do and it kind
of almost doesn't matter what they walk
in the doorway I'm gonna do the same
exam because it's gonna help me pick up
the bits and pieces that I may not have
thought to check in the first place the
things that I don't know that I don't
know okay so by having a systematic exam
I run through everything and I can get a
more global picture and kind of see how
the pieces fit together so even if I do
test one and two and I'm like yeah it's
probably coming from this and that I
want to confirm at about ten more times
so I really have a full exam that I do
so I start almost always I have the
person in standing I just look how
they're standing before that usually I'm
talking to them in the office and we're
taking a subjective we're kind of
getting an idea of what their problems
are and all that what they don't know is
I'm generally looking at them the entire
time looking at how theirs today so so
yeah so I'm kind of doing a little
sussing out before we even start but my
official start to my exam isn't standing
and I look at their postures look how
they're carrying their body and how
they're holding themselves in space and
that indicates to me probably how
they're doing it throughout their day to
some degree what's fascinating about
specifically the shoulders because I
know probably most of you if you do have
pain it's gonna be more in the upper
body unless it's low back pain because a
lot of people was sitting all day or
standing desks now have stuff going on
the lower body but
I'll keep it to the upper body for the
moment but what's fascinating to me
about the upper body and shoulders in
particular is that they're not really
attached to our body which allows to do
cool things like spin our arms in
circles but if you think about the
shoulder girdle let's see if I can pull
it up here yes we are trying to try our
mental thing here where we actually have
an atlas of human anatomy we can search
other diagrams too many scapula there's
so many scapula's let's see if I can do
something better when I was looking
through this atlas I was kind of shocked
at the number of details in the diagrams
I don't really like to think about my
body as having all of these things okay
let's let's play with this cuz it's here
okay okay so you can draw right I can
totally relate so this is the area I'm
kind of talking about here that is your
scapula this guy that's triangle which
is your wing sticking out on your back
this here your color in between those
two works it's it's your rib cage so you
can't like just poke and get your
scapular you have to recover but what's
interesting is that you're only attached
by a joint right here and what that is
is that your sternum right there and if
you look at all of these bones and how
heavy that arm is with all that muscle
that's the only little joint holding it
up that's probably not doing very much
so you've got this giant structure kind
of pulling off your body and what's
holding it on is all the muscles which
is so very cool to me because it gives
me so much information so you've got
this arm just hanging off the body and
just by looking
have someone's holding their arm I can
see what muscles might be stiffer or
tighter what muscles are longer shorter
how they might move when they go to move
their arm overhead and all sorts of
really neat stuff just by how they kind
of hold their shoulder in space it's my
first test like I'm not even having them
do anything yet I'm just having them
stand there but you can see so much
because of how flexible this complex is
the shoulder girdle complex so it's kind
of cool and there's something can I ask
a follow-up question there and if you
want to keep going okay
can you what you're welcome to do can
you unpack a little bit because one of
the things you just mentioned there was
sort of something that I didn't used to
think about until having problems with
this sort of thing which is that I don't
think everyone realizes necessarily that
where their joints are by default has
something to do with how their muscles
have been used like I never it's not
necessarily that unusual when you say it
but it's just not something that I think
ever crossed my mind so could you maybe
like give a little bit of background on
how that works like how muscles change
how they situate things based on their
use or you know I don't even really not
ask the question cuz I'm not really sure
I understand exactly how it works but
you know what I mean I do it's a very
it's a pretty complex question to fully
appreciate what's going on you have to
appreciate how much of its going on like
you were saying you look at the fatless
and you're like there's so much stuff
that and so as you come to understand
what all that stuff is and what all that
stuff does you can start to kind of see
through the skin okay you can start
seeing like oh this shoulder is tipped
forward a bit so if the shoulders tip
forward what does that mean to me what's
going on the inside well the structures
in the front are gonna be stiffer than
the structures in the back what does
that mean stiffer than yes in the back
so stiffer means that you're probably
using the muscle more so it's probably
stronger and therefore it's kind of
winning this tug-of-war so if you think
of muscles as Springs okay they contract
and expand so you can kind of get that
analogy if you think of muscles as
Springs I mostly
use in a shortened position all the time
so if you're always using your bicep and
it's always here it's going to be
stiffer relative to your tricep and
you're probably gonna stand with your
arm in a little bit more than two
position so that's okay this is great so
when I'm moving you know around is is
that that's increased tension on the
spring at its default position like this
because we're basically saying like okay
my rest state this thing is now shorter
which means that my musculature moves
compensated the other muscles are longer
than I guess essentially in their rest
state is this a property of the muscles
size meaning does that mean this muscle
got shorter this way or does it a
property of like the brain telling this
to be this contracted at rest
like like who do you know what I'm
saying like what is actually what
causing that shortness and the longness
that that puts it into a new position at
rest so our bodies are really really
good at being efficient okay so if we
are constantly doing one thing or one
pattern over and over and over again our
body likes to take shortcuts okay so
they're like well you always are bending
that arm so let's just keep that arm a
little bit
what kind of just start there and that's
neurological meaning yes yes to all of
it um it is neurological because your
brain is telling your body to do these
things but then long-term and even
relatively short-term like if you're
sitting at a chair for like four hours a
day your body will start to make changes
okay your body will start to lay down
different tissue structure in your
muscles to help support they don't have
to constantly send that signal to fire
fire fire fire fire thankfully as we
stand back up again our body will change
that issue back to a good contractile
muscle tissue it's our bodies are highly
adaptable and super super efficient so
yes it is neurological saying yes fire
that muscle it is also physiological in
that our muscles when they contract we
kind of have these two things sliding
over each other and that's how they
shorten and they've got these little
oars and they kind of pull it very very
cool that it happened so fast
but instead of kind of hanging out here
they'll start hanging out here because
again it's more efficient because I know
you're gonna bend it again to go there
and so if you're not ever using that
range of the muscle it's not going to be
as available but as I said with standing
up after sitting all day at work it's
highly changeable so if you start in
this particular example using your
tricep and fully extending your arm and
not working in that shortened position
all the time it changes so essentially
the I guess is break down into very
short term or short term and long term
effects in that sense meaning pretty
quickly my muscles will actually pick up
new neurological starting points
basically like over you know not very
not too long they'll maybe do this thing
where as it sounds like you're sort of
saying once I get them into that sort of
rest position they may actually start to
change their shape eventually or is that
never happens well we know that will
eventually happen but usually you're
casted like you're mostly just the
actual mental where am i keeping yeah
it's mental it's also the strength of
the muscle so because you get stronger
so you're getting that passive spring
get stiffer and thicker ok and the other
spring is kind of this flimsy loose
spring and so at rest you've got a
tighter spring pulling this way then
you've got lean that way so a stronger
muscle in the sense of like literally
like a body builder stronger muscle like
I'm building muscle when the muscle
builds up it becomes tensor by default
rest so if you are always doing biceps
biceps biceps and which essentially
extend like this all day long you were
doing but if you're always doing bicep
curls for example and you're never doing
anything for your tricep you will just
have a stiffer bicep spring then your
tricep spring so it doesn't when a
muscle necessarily even when you're
talking about building muscle that has
nothing to do with like the you know
physical therapy aspects or the pain a
so 74 just building muscle normally at
that point it's not just that the
muscles capacity to pull when it wants
to pull is more it's sort of in some
sense always pulling so if it gets
stronger its base level of pull is just
gonna
stronger that's just how it doesn't yes
but ideally everything's getting
stronger together so you're trying
definitely I mean going in and doing
like one exercise is probably not the
best but global exercise is really a
lovely thing okay yeah keeping that
balance because our our body's like
balance they they are built on the
system of balance you think chemically
we our bodies want to be in homeostasis
we we don't want if you eat I don't know
a ton of acidic foods for example your
body will not become more acidic because
our bodies are always want balances and
the same things for to for our muscles
our muscles want to keep the same length
on this side it's the attention on this
side as this side so they get nice even
pull and that's how everything kind of
stays happy and healthy so let's go back
to the shoulder example that yes I think
that sorry I just want to unpack this I
think I sort of start out with me
knowing roughly what's going on yeah so
okay so back to the shoulder example
somebody has their shoulder and you can
kind of see that's you know in an
unusual position so that you know
positional information is sort of now
telling you okay now I have some
information about how the default rest
you know tension on each of these muscle
groups is and I can see that it's a
little wrong meaning one of them is too
tense at rest and that could be causing
problems why so why do they start to
let's get into the sort what our
problems at this point is now I'm gonna
rephrase but you said a little bit it's
not that passive resting tension that
causes problems it's the things that
you're doing that's causing that passive
rustic tension okay so I'm gonna kind of
go around Google and we're gonna yeah so
I found that I saw this neat little
thing so this is the shoulder from the
back so you've got your arm bone here
and oh I see a raisin that's not gonna
work the arm bone here and the shoulder
blade here and to bring an arm up
overhead for example the first 30
degrees of your arm motion is just the
humerus spinning in the socket so just
that arm bone moving out to the side
about thirty degrees
and then as that goes up overhead you
get a two-to-one ratio of two degrees of
the humerus moving for every one degree
of the shoulder blade moving as well and
that all has to work together and if it
doesn't work together that's when you
can get pain or problems at the shoulder
joint at the neck the even down the arm
depending on kind of where you're
predisposed to kind of get those issues
but as that arm goes overhead so if you
guys are feeling bold and you want to
not hit the person next to you've take
care of up in front of you and bring it
up overhead you should feel your
shoulder blade coming almost underneath
your armpit this is awesome but you
should feel your arm kind of spin and
then your filler blades spin around your
back and come up so someone who walks in
and the shoulder is already kind of
tipped forward and it can be just tipped
forward or can you rotate around the
outside or it can be a lots of different
things depending on how they're moving
that spin roll a glide of all those
joints moving together is not gonna
happen as well so they're gonna show
that in pretty much all their movements
or a lot of their movements probably
especially when they're in a position
that they have pain in so that's kind of
what I'm seeing when I'm seeing you know
something like this it's like okay well
that's gonna tell me that they're doing
something else that's strange or they're
just sitting all day like this and
they're never gonna they're never coming
back up so that I'm gonna see them find
that their back muscles aren't as strong
because what makes that shoulder blade
go around is three different muscles
you've got your upper trapezius up there
your lower trapezius going down that way
and your serratus anterior which is my
favorite muscle right now going that way
I'm sorry right now
it changes okay you have like a muscle
of the Month Club or something it's six
months or so it kind of goes with the
wind that would be a nice webpage the
muscle of the muscle where you could go
and read about this muscle
sorry continue no that's cool so you've
kind of got three directions of pull
you've got kind of an an up and because
it attaches on this corner it's gonna
pull it around a little bit and you've
got a down and again because attaches on
this corner it's going to pull it down
and around a bit and you've got forward
and again up so that pulls that shoulder
blade into that upward rotation so now
if you've got this forward shoulder
thing cuz you're sitting there taping
all day
a lot of times the back musculature
isn't it quite doing its job so the
muscles back here like the trapezius and
sometimes even the serratus here isn't
doing its job because serratus pulls the
shoulder blade forward and up but the
thing that pulls the shoulder forward
and down is your PEC muscle in the front
we all pretty much know which is
fighting it so sometimes that that turns
off he's like well shoulder blades
already getting pulled forward I'm going
on vacation
because again bodies are efficient
because so it just already knows it's
there so the brain is not trying to move
its dirty forward I've already found a
way to do that so now I'm just gonna do
this weird other thing it's not quite
that bad but when you start when you
look at it all day long you start to to
seeing these things pretty clearly so
it's not necessarily the resting
position that's doing it it's maybe the
active position of typing all day or the
active motion of doing this all day
which I don't know why you would do but
maybe if your if your career is
different you're doing more but reaching
your ask or your mousing but you're like
mousing like this for some position
which actually isn't probably that
unusual probably not too high yeah it's
it's pretty common so there's lots of
different ways to kind of create weird
postures that will do weird things to
you I wanted to ask I'm sorry I'm
putting up this yeah no it's fine cuz
bucks I'm really cool it does kind of
Akko up there
I like the muscle drawing to it the
strands I was like oh that's pretty cool
so the you were talking about sort of
the movement ratios there so essentially
the your brain has to sort of contract
these at resolved rates like it's like
this one has to contract twice as fast
as this one
to move this in position and then I've
got so this sort of the function that
we're looking at here is kind of this
like piecewise thing it's it's only one
of them is going then it's a two-to-one
ratio of two of them and then another
one might kick in this is right well
yeah I mean the two-to-one ratio is to
the end of the range to the end up with
180 degrees total 120 degrees of our
motion 60 degrees of scapula motion and
so is that is that process part of I
don't want to call it an impairment
because that's probably the wrong term
that is the term I would probably use
I'd use a movement and movement
impairment okay so if you are having a
movement impairment are we talking
primarily about the that sort of muscle
rest situation that you sort of were
describing that I'm getting a better
handle on now but probably still not
quite yet exactly it is the is that
function is the brains you know series
of things that it's firing and how
that's firing is that also implicated
sometimes all the times that are so
meaning it could be that the muscles at
rest even are okay but your brains
function for moving them as wrong and so
now instead of two to one it's three to
one or instead of two to one it kicks in
throughout time can you commute like
yeah we may not know all this stuff but
what we do know yeah so sometimes
somebody walks in the door and their
movement and their standing postures
really normal again we only got to the
first part of the exam we got to
standing and then we got sidetracked so
which is great but but this is what I do
not Susan I look at how they move their
arm for an upper of our body exams so
sometimes people walk in with a
completely normal posture but they don't
have the right neuromuscular
coordination to make the movements
happen at the right time in the right
place sometimes you know everything fits
and you see it all together but usually
it's not the resting posture that's
causational it's a symptom it is a part
of the entire square lay of symptoms
that you see or patterns squarely what
is that you you okay this is a regular I
don't know
I use it it's a a grouping of symptoms
okay sorry
Lucas Thomas
so yes the rusting posture is almost
never called the cause the resting
posture is occurring because of how the
person is moving in their daily life
okay yeah well I guess if we sort of go
further into the second part of the exam
thing so when you are you know starting
to ask that mean because a lot of times
that exam is sort of like you know try
doing this or you will sort of position
the person right you'll like put them
into a position and you'll ask them to
like push or pull or something like this
can you talk a little bit about that
like what's that's checking for how
those sorts of things go or is that is
that the best thing to talk about next
or would you rather talk about like
nerves and stuff first I don't know
which one's gonna be better I can go
either way I'm happy to continue going
but let's talk about say for example
because sort of yeah so once I'm done
looking some at somebody standing still
I'm gonna watch how they move so I have
them do basic movements like bring your
arms up bring your arms down bring your
arms out rotate your arms and if any of
those causes pain I want to see if I can
then eliminate their pain by grabbing a
hold say of the shoulder blade moving it
where I want it to go and see if that
eliminates your symptoms because that
gives me a ton of information oh you
have pain when you do it well when I do
it for you and theoretically a better
pattern is it is it less painful is it
does it change how your symptoms are
occurring I will then have them do
things in different positions I will
test the strength of muscles and when I
test the strength of muscles I'm looking
for a couple different things I'm
looking for okay sure is a muscle strong
is it strong enough to do its job but
that's not the primary thing I'm looking
for what I'm actually looking for is are
you actually using the muscle I'm
telling you to use if I put you in a
position that is optimal to make that
muscle fire and you're using everything
else it's telling me a lot about how
you're moving throughout your day so I'm
like okay use this muscle exactly and
then you're
you know and I'm like pull your shoulder
black back and you go mm-hmm oh that's
not right
so I'm looking for how you choose to
hold the position with the muscle and
then if your position is good you're
firing the muscle properly if I resist
that do you still continue to use that
muscle to do it and how strong is it or
do you then cheat and use something else
secondarily and I kind of do that in all
the different positions of the body
through lots of different movements of
the body and I'm really just looking for
what your patterns are and how you
choose to cheat the world around you a
little bit which may or may not be
leading to your symptoms are your pain
is so one of the things that kind of I
noticed in relationship to that sort of
thing like the positioning and and
having someone use a muscle in
particular is that it seems like
sometimes at least for me and I don't
know if this is generally true for
people and more broadly there are
muscles that you can't really even
target with your brain until you've
practiced like I don't know how to say
it any other way but it's like you know
sometimes it's like okay you know you
know pull your shoulder blade back in
this way or something and I'm like I
don't know how to do that right it's
like maybe that muscle is normally
firing as part of some other thing that
I think to do but it's like I can't
think to contract just that muscle and
then I have noticed that like over time
then your brain does sort of learn to be
able to maybe target that muscle more
specifically is that am I totally
misinterpreting that or is this a is
that a really like it's a real thing
your brain and your neurological system
are again very very changeable very
adaptable and some people have kind of
an aide idea of where their body is some
people don't some people can learn it
some people it takes longer but they can
learn it eventually so during my exam
for example I'll often place someone
where I want them and then say hold this
because I want to know what they're
gonna hold it with but there's ways of
tricking the brain into kind of finding
that muscle you can tap on the muscle or
or and that kind of helps stimulate the
nerves a little bit
you can use different visualizations you
can try to equate it to a movement 30
familiar with like oh it feels like when
you do
exercise yeah so there are ways of doing
it but the brain can learn to fire
anything or fire anything in a new
pattern it just for some people it comes
a little bit more easily for some people
it's a little harder and you can try a
million different ways of telling them
showing them hands on moving them so
many different ways of cueing or we call
it cueing movement and patterns and
muscles to actually fire so I think
that's pretty good for the basics of
well there's well I guess there's one
thing we have listed on here that we
should probably talk about exams to
start talking moving on to sort of like
the actual pain part like what's causing
matter how that's working but one thing
that you had mentioned that I actually
don't think I know anything about cuz I
think you've ever mentioned it to me
just in the course of like actually
doing physical therapy spinal alignment
and plumb line you mentioned which I'm
assuming is about the thing that I was
I'm doing wrong right now or whatever
sitting but like what what is what did
you want it to say about that yeah so if
you think about your body most of us
think about kind of being anchored to
the ground either through our feet or
right now through our butts on our
chairs but most of our movement and all
of our musculature is anchored from the
kind of the center out because
everything has every muscle has at least
two ends so again we'll use the bicep as
an example because it's easy it attaches
at your elbow and it attaches up at your
shoulder so if you're not able to
stabilize the shoulder end well you'll
never be able to fire at the elbow well
so this is proper biceps firing ish and
then improper firing you'd have a wiggly
shoulder because it's yanking and the
muscle shortening and does not have an
anchor so if you don't have a properly
aligned spine you're not going to be
able to fire everything else as well
the spine does not always have to be in
its perfect neutral alignment all the
time our bodies again are highly
adaptable we are able to move it in all
sorts of different ways and directions
but having a neutral spine or neutral
can really help you kind of get the
handle on what else is going on the body
so the spine is an s-curve let's see if
I can find a picture of the spine I had
trouble finding it before but you'll see
we can get to pop up no that was the
problem the problem is that bones have
spine ain't like little out cropping of
bone is also a spine so I get like a lot
of spine no they will not but we can try
cervical spine for example thinking it
is thinking they did not fight there
they do not have the surface we didn't
find any result yeah that was very lucky
he wanted to include us in like it to be
it to be responsible for it all of us to
your sponsor I think if I could spell
company
let's try thoracic so your spine is
broken up into three different parts
you've got your cervical which is your
neck your thoracic which is your torso
which all your ribs attached to it might
be in the second if you really need it
there's two there were two volumes okay
how bad how bad do you want to have a
spine diagram I'll talk about it and
then if we get enough hooting and
hollering or something I can look at it
okay and cervical spine is the nak
thoracic spine attaches the ribcage
lumbar spine low back and a spine should
look like let's see if I can just find a
pretty blank page every somebody oh
they're good
we'll use a space cuz it's relatively
clear
so cervical spine let's do this thoracic
spine lumbar spine sort of cervical
spine thoracic spine in the lumbar spine
ish it's Kirby there's a the skull is
here so your spine acts a little bit
like a spring and it absorbs and our G
comes we walk and move throughout our
day but this alignment is kind of
important because and this is true in
sitting or in standing and the plumb
line I was discussing drops basically
from the ear down the body and it's felt
like how much of your body's and further
behind and it should be about half and
what things are you cheating or
compensating with there's some really
neat different examples of poor posture
if you just look up spinal alignment and
you google it it'll show you like a ways
of posture like if you're leaning back
or leaning forward or all sorts of
things but let's use sitting because but
if you're sitting and let's say it's the
end of a long day and you're like this
not only have you changed your spinal
posture my shoulders have rounded and
come forward and now my head's gone
forward now my neck musculature here is
gonna be tighter my neck musculature
here is gonna be tighter this is gonna
influence how my nerves are coming out
of my neck see segue into news back
great and down your arms and into your
hands or maybe the end of the day you're
more like this soon you're shaping like
that I've seen this one a lot again your
lumbar spine may or may not be that bad
it may also be curved but your spine is
kind of taking on this C shape your
shoulder blades are moving up and around
your back your shoulders are gonna
forward
your arms are internally rotated so
really how you're sitting makes a big
difference on all the structures
throughout your body so that was kind of
a long way of getting to the point of
like hey know what you're doing and
change positions frequently so look
let's talk about one thing that you said
there that I I totally forgot about what
not the shoulder actually the
stabilization part of it is kind of
interesting like I had not thought about
this previously until you had explained
it to me actually which is that I
typically think of friend for some
reason because having done character
animation for a living for five years
you think that I would have thought
about this before ever but I didn't or
maybe it's because of that I tended to
think of muscles in in isolation meaning
even if I was thinking like oh this
group of muscles is doing something I
neglected to think about the fact that
whatever they're doing muscles upstream
from them are going to have to counter
because if they would didn't do that it
would pull the rest of you in to
wherever that muscle was going or away
from it or something so can you just
just cement that you mentioned the
stabilization powers like actually like
wait a minute
many people may not actually have
internalized this because especially for
people for being computer graphics we
don't have this like Reedus you know we
just move the thing and it moves we
don't have to think about the ripple
effects yeah so can you just talk a
little bit about that just I mean sure
for fun everybody a Reacher I'm out in
front of you and make a tight tight
tight tight vest and see if you can feel
what's going on at your shoulder blade
behind you and then open your hand we
could take this together you should feel
the muscles around your shoulder blade
contracting in the back which is just so
cool but our bodies just do that
naturally but every muscle when it fires
live if you look at a picture of a
muscle you see like the stripes kind of
like I was drawing on that on the
overhead there when you see those
stripes those are the angles of like the
lines on which the muscle contracts
which means it's contracting on both
sides
so it's not just contracting and pulling
the arm up it's pulling on both sides
which means every time you have a muscle
firing here you have a muscle pulling on
the other side back the other direction
specifically for the shoulder blade and
why the serratus anterior is currently
my favorite muscle is I love to think
about how the shoulder blade is
stabilized because it is just so neat
like I was saying before the arm is a
really heavy structure you've got all
those bones and those muscles just
dangling off that shoulder blade pulling
the arm down and away from the body so
if that's all pulling this way you need
to have
muscles pulling this way but to counter
that you need to have muscle pulling
this way and most importantly because
that arm is pulling downward because
it's only attached at the top of the
shoulder blade here you're like we lost
it okay since the arm is only attached
to the top of the shoulder blade here
you've got this whole rest of the
triangle it's gonna pull the arm just
from the weight of it in that downward
rotation see now I'm just making a mess
let's see so this arm bone here is only
attached at the top corner of the
triangle which means just at rest
just hanging if no other forces were
present you'd have this downward pull of
the scapula into downward rotation so
you need your middle trapezius to be
pulling in against that outward force
your lower trapezius is gonna pull into
a little bit of the upward rotation like
we talked about before and your serratus
anterior which is gonna pull in outward
and into a little bit of that upward
rotation so you've got this counter of
pulling going on you've got input in
pull and out pull and they're both
helping it upwardly rotate against that
arm and that's just at rest so every
time you then go to move that arm
everybody's kind of got to recalibrate
exactly how much energy they're putting
where that same thing is happening okay
now I'm going to flex the elbow and I'm
gonna bring that up okay I've got the
biceps pulling here so I need to
stabilize more with this pull here as
this pulls the arm up there and now I'm
just creating a giant mess on my butt
well actually that's really fascinating
because it's essentially like well we
have this you know rigid body dynamics
problem basically where we've got to got
this thing there we've got points that
we're pulling on which will induce
torque as well as linear motion and it
all has to balance out properly
you only can exert certain directions on
it right because you I'm simplifying
things there's also Tilton yeah and
there's lots of different muscles that
that correspond to that but yes you are
but you have yeah you have quite a lot
of options so it sounds like to I mean
just just from the physics of it that
means that essentially when I'm sitting
or standing or anything else the contact
points with the rest of the world are
essentially where all the energy has to
flow back to in some sense meaning
whatever I do all the muscles up to the
point where I'm grounded have to be
involved otherwise I would you know the
inertia I guess takes something out of
it well challenge you to now think about
an aerialist in space a circus performer
ok yes they do not need a grounded
contact with the outside world they just
need their core and their spine and all
their stabilizer muscles to be doing
their job so it's not necessarily about
the contact points I'm not sure and
you're standing it's about how it
interacts with your stability internally
but so is does that mean that the body
is just heavy enough on its own that we
don't really have to care about that
external kind because even an aerialist
they will change or their whole body's
orientation as a result of those motions
there right meaning do you know what I
mean like so it all ends up physics so
class yes so does that mean just trying
to get to the whether those are
important or not if you are standing
does the series of muscles that are
involved in say moving your shoulder
when you consider all the contractions
eat no matter how tiny that would happen
are they different because they can stop
at your tailbone then if I'm then if I
was what I'm sitting sorry then when I'm
standing when they cannot stop at my
tailbone because they have to go all the
way down to my leg before they hit solid
these support till don't stop your
tailbone even sitting okay so your legs
are still counter but your legs are
still involved in some in some way so
like oh nice thing just now with my legs
crossed I'm exerting a force probably
inward a little bit there's a little bit
of outward force as they're crossed and
I'm getting stability from all of that
in addition to what's going on at my
core so it doesn't stop kind of at your
sits bones it really does turns out all
the way down it does change a bit when
you're standing because it changes your
leg position changes where you're
exerting forces but any little motion
you're doing is somehow affecting
everything
[Laughter]
ideally your core is kind of a
transition point you'll still get some
effect up and down but your core is kind
of your should be one of your most
stable structures I see so that's like
the place where a lot of the energy kind
of dissipates by that point we've gotten
to people don't have to do too much
contraction or weight which is why when
you're sitting you're not really feeling
your legs do you much then okay they're
active but they're not yeah okay that is
a lot to digest but we've got a whole
bunch of stuff to go through here so
let's start talking about the actual
like I mean those are sort of the cause
of the problem perhaps you might say in
terms of like what you're doing this
this making problem happen but the
problem you're actually feeling ends up
being something nerve related or blood
flow related or something like this can
you start to give us an introduction
into like that's like I'm having pain
what is pain mean like there's different
ways in which that might manifest itself
or discomfort right can you start to
start giving us the intro of like what
what's that part of it about and where
is that coming from
okay well the whole conversation about
what is pain but that could be a whole
nother hour to go but it is really a
creation of the brain to sensation that
it doesn't quite understand but so pain
is kind of a vague overarching catch-all
for most of the public but I really kind
of break it down to a couple of
different types of pain numbness burning
tingling those are gonna be your nerve
symptoms and usually are coming from our
neurological source whether what's a
nervous being compressed a nervous being
[Music]
pulled that's usually gonna be a nerve
inner sanctum dull achiness is often
muscular mustard pain when it's a more
of a spasm can be a little bit more
sharp a little bit more cute but you've
got different kind of categories and
qualifications of pain that you're
feeling and that can really manifest
anywhere in the body
the you know as we're talking the causes
of all that even if you have say your
pain or nervous symptoms in your hand it
could be because of what you're doing
your shoulder and kind of how that's
translating down or translating back up
and it's sort of focus it in for you
because I've got a bunch of oh yeah
great so um all right so you sort of
listed I think five things they're
basically three three right you said
numbness burning tingling yep right and
then you said aching yeah so all of
those I guess are I mean the brain
doesn't get information back from
muscles directly right it only gets
information back from the nerves I
assume meaning all of these are
traveling on the nerves all of these are
traveling on the nerves okay so can you
and some of these may be I mean
obviously some of these are more
neurologist questions so please if I'm
going outside of the discipline I I
apologize you can just tell me sorry I
probably should know it somewhere back
in my right it's like someone asking me
about some programming language I
haven't you know seen in many many years
but can you give us any sort of a
understanding of like those things do
they indicate a particular thing that's
happening with the nerve that we
understand meaning that medical science
kind of feels like oh right when you're
seeing tingling that means the nerve has
had X happen to it somewhere along the
line if you're experiencing adult ache
that means the nerve is picking up this
like what is happening there do we know
the tingling tingling or numbness is
usually neurological compression it
means the signal is not getting through
clearly okay so it's signal meaning
electricity yeah why you're essentially
no wire
yes the the information that is being
transmitted along the neuron because
that's where our information highway of
our body is is not getting through
clearly
so numbness is nothing's getting through
you can't you can't feel anything cuz
there's there's nobody's traveling so
that's a complete break for some reason
either it was cut or compressed or
something yeah it could it could be
anything it could be
was just laying on it that's why you
know if you're laying on your army or
your something falls asleep you go from
that numbness that tingling to that
burning and then it goes back to normal
so like you could have it even on that
minor scale and that kind of is what
that nerve pain is oh so those are all
actually essentially the same thing just
a different amount so it's like how much
electricity was able to travel through
or not how much electricity but how you
know yeah is is where you are on that
line is that correct
kind of yeah and everyone what kind of
experience a little differently but
that's kind of the general and then what
about the other ones that you said okay
this is the nerve is functioning fine
meaning all the informations flowing you
know back to the source and the amount
that it's supposed to but I'm still
getting pain how is it picking up like
what is the dull aching or the muscle
spasm pain is that something the nerve
is sensing or like how does that or is
that really no it's a good question and
it's a very big question oh it is one
that is currently being studied more and
more but we do know a lot about pain
pain and that dull achy feeling is how
our brain is translating that it's
trying to figure out what's going on
okay there so it's not the muscle that
really feels that way it's your brain
trying to make sense of what's going on
there so it's a constant contraction say
at the muscle because the spasm and your
brain is trying to figure out how to
interpret that signal and so the signals
that it's getting this is me completely
making something up so when you say
tries to figure out what's going on is
that in a sense saying well okay I've
got these nerves that are going out to
various parts of my body my brain is
used to the signals coming back this way
all of a sudden I see that they're
coming back differently from this and
I'm worried so now I am just the your
brains way of saying I don't see the
right signals coming back is yes the we
only have certain types of
we're suckers for sensation in the body
so we don't have like I feel water
bottle you know you feel you feel cold
you feel hot sorry you feel hot hot but
not cold oh really
so the absence of feeling hot do you
feel is cold so like things like that
are it's it's pretty binary like you
don't we don't have as much sensation we
interpret sensation more broadly than we
actually sense it okay so the brain is
filling in a number of gaps here and I
suppose that is probably why these sorts
of things are difficult in the diagnosis
phase because it's like well you know
it's such a blunt you know instituted
that the the the information the patient
can give you about what they're feeling
is really kind of fuzzy because their
brain is just sort of looking at some
not particularly great signals and just
producing an output and it's like well
we can try it you know you can try to
figure out what that means by how we've
seen it happen in the past but it's it's
just not really as precise as we would
like to know and some people are just
better verbalizing than what they're
feeling because you know it's also an
interpretation problem of okay I can
feel it I know what I'm feeling what but
how do I say it that words and then you
know honestly I don't find people's
ability or inability to describe their
symptoms that limiting diagnostically
okay because I'm looking again for all
these other indicators so if you're
saying I
I have weirdness when I do this thing
that's usually enough okay so you just
maybe any indication that the brain did
something is probably like okay like
well that's the clue I need and now it's
weird oh nothing you've come into my
office yeah that's good enough that's
good enough okay I don't really need
somebody generally she described that
much further other than you know I think
it's more this or that but it's usually
how they're moving that I am looking at
more than what they're saying I don't
have this written down but I meant to
write it down and since I'm thinking of
it now I'm just gonna say it
so can you also briefly just mention or
discuss referred pain to the extent that
we would need to know it for the you
know stuff we're gonna talk about here
like the idea that the pain maybe is
misplaced in terms of what the where the
patient thinks it's coming from yeah so
there's different types of referred pain
and this is a great place to to say
something that I'll get to in a second
because doesn't matter yet different
types preferred pain so usually refer
pain is symptoms you're feeling that are
not from the place that you are having
an issue so I'm a simple musculoskeletal
level something that I deal with almost
on a daily basis is if you have pain in
a straight line here at your shoulder
it's your rotator cuff which is which is
the deep muscles of the shoulder that
actually controlled the spin and glide
of the actual humerus they don't run in
a vertical line on your shoulder but
that's where you feel it on a more
global medical scale you can have pain
referred from your organs and to
somewhere external on your body in the
Maya tomes meaning on the skin and that
may or may not be actually
musculoskeletal you can have pain from
the inside of your body expressing on
the outside and that's kind of what I
want to talk about which was
musculoskeletal pain including
neurological pain tends to change with
the position it tends to change with
time of day your activity or what you're
doing pain that does not go away no
matter what you do you're gonna want to
get checked out by your primary care
doctor first because there might be
something else going on so even if it
appears to be in a location that would
suggest that it couldn't be something
like an internal organ that may not be
true at all may be true may be that it's
actually you know something that has
nothing to do with your your body
mechanics yeah for example like a
gallbladder will refer pain to like the
back and people will come in with back
pain and oh it hurts it hurts all the
time whenever I do I can't get it to go
away and I'm like no that's probably not
your back look I mean you could have is
your back is fine the bad news is you
need to go I mean you might have back
pain all the time but it should at least
change intensity it should there should
be things you can do to mitigate the
symptoms so it's just another it's just
an indicator to me that there there
might not be a musculoskeletal thing
going on there might still be but it's
worth checking out usually there's other
red flag indicators or things like that
that make my little ears perk up but
it's just another thing to think about
so I guess let's since we've kind of
grabbed them I think most of things well
actually no we did not talk about
vascular things at all and I part of
that as I think because I don't actually
know anything about these I don't think
I've ever heard you mentioned them to me
either so could you just tell us to what
degree that's important for these sorts
of ailments and and what we should be
aware about or what we should be aware
of in terms of those pathways yes I'm
going to just take this where I want to
go so let me see if I can find a picture
that I might want
Jesus has that on there no hold on we
could bring up the second PDF which
maybe has some of the spine stuff on it
I don't know if they were separated in
the book I grabbed the one that's upper
limbs and stuff and the other ones you
want me to bring it up well let's let's
see if I can try something else here
because I think I saw something good
with it before with the scalene so let's
see you look at all that beautiful
vascular bundles that's not bad but not
if you don't know you're looking at
that's kind of cool
okay so this is somebody from the side
the shoulder has been removed so the
stripe things that you're looking at
here are the ribs it look like ribs what
else has been removed so if you see this
little white disc here that's where your
collarbone attaches okay so your
collarbone would sit right here blue in
this case means vein red means artery
yellow here in this block are your nurse
coming up your neck so here you've got
your collarbone here you've got your
veins they're gonna come down around go
down your arm that way you're honoring
so you go down around down your arm that
way technically your arteries going down
around your veins coming back up but and
your nerves are gonna come out and go
down that way too so everybody is now
passing under this collarbone so your
nerves are passing under your arteries
are passing under so sometimes what
people are feeling as nerve pain or
muscle pain is the fact that they're
knocking the blood flow to the muscle or
to the nerve that you need for things to
process properly or to function properly
because you need those nutrients flowing
you need oxygen going to the to the
muscles to produce contractions so
everything comes out so you've got what
I pulled up was the the scalenes so
you've got these muscles that come
across the nerve see the herbs come
out there coming across the artery let's
see if I can get a better picture of it
even ooh yeah see that's cool again the
yellow is the nerve the red the artery
coming out and you can see the scalene
or the muscle of the neck they're coming
up crossing over all of it and then
you've got the collarbone that would be
all that's been removed but that would
be coming out here across it as well so
this just kind of shows you how
intricate and how integral your posture
and movement are because if your heads
doing this even out tightened your
scalene muscle which is the guy I just
drew in he's no tighter trying to hold
your head up and try to figure it all
out
which can put pressure on your nerves
and arteries if you are shoulders are
kind of pressed and hanging out because
you're down here and your arms are kind
of hanging and you're using your laptop
on your lap kind of thing now your
collarbone has been depressed and it's
pushing down on your nerves and arteries
and that can lead to having symptoms
weigh down your hand that you didn't
realize was because you feel like that
or something like that so that's kind of
what I think is really important about
your blood flow is that it can really
cause all sorts of symptoms because if
you're not getting the nutrients you
need out to the peripheral periphery of
the body you're not gonna be able to
function properly and is that sort of a
property just of the fact that the
further something is a way like the
essentially the whatever the body is
trying to carry out to its systems de
plena sh'zazz it goes out so if I start
to reduce the flow it means the furthest
out things are the ones that get the
least of it or is that an incorrect
characterization yeah you know that but
I haven't thought about it that way but
that's probably pretty good there's also
the chance that multiple things can go
wrong
so if okay your head is doing something
weird which puts more tension on your
neck muscles and then your shoulders
doing something weird which more
attention on the structures themselves
and then you're not stabilizing properly
so you've got something going on with
the elbow because you're overworking
your forearm musculature
now that's working too hard cuts trying
to stabilize your elbow and move your
hand and then you come down and you've
got the narrowing at the wrist and like
we get to your fingers so there's lots
of different places where things can be
less perfect is that I've heard you use
the word double crush before yes that is
that is the idea behind double crush but
you know double crush just means like oh
there something going on up here and
something God doing down here but really
it could be it ain't see bit here and a
bit there a teeny tiny bit there and a
little there and you end up becoming
table crush now quadruple a quadruple
splash or whatever crush I think is just
so dramatic
yeah it does sound a bit dramatic okay
so I think that's all of the I think
that's all of the stuff for just like
basics of you know the functioning so we
can get into some of these because we've
got about 20 minutes left so I just
wanted to kind of go through like the
know I wanted to go through some of
these ones that you that you had down
here and maybe we can pick which ones
are probably most important or maybe you
can just kind of touch on each one
briefly so people know about them you
sent me a list of common ailments that
people who you know sit like this all
day might get and first one was medial
or lateral epicondylitis am i
pronouncing basically it's pain at the
inside or the outside of the elbow we
used to call it epicondylitis or tennis
elbow or golfer's elbow or probably
terms you're more familiar with we're
just moving to the OSIS because it's
more accurate
I just meaning inflammation of what's
going on there osa smeeting mini tearing
well tearing but mini tearing it's not
things flying apart basically it means
you're overusing the things in your
forearm to either over using your finger
flexors do you make that tight fist
again you'll feel everything tightened
up by the inside of the elbow and if you
pull your fingers back you'll feel
everything tighten up by the outside of
your elbow and so if you're using that a
lot and not stabilizing properly of the
chain I call that up the chain back
towards the center you are now asking
those muscles to do a ton of work
and they would probably be better served
with better support up here so they
don't have to work as hard down at the
finger level so it's I find it is common
with trackpad oh really
sometimes it kind of laughs yeah so
you're doing like a swiping motion a lot
so using a lot of finger flexion and
you're probably resting your I'm
somewhere doing something weird I'm not
supporting you no again this one right
so carpal tunnel syndrome couple times
an action and then you said you had a
parenthetical that was high-end other
nerve issues I'm not sure what that
means but good well I know because I
I've heard most of this from Casey so
when people walk in my door they may or
may not they just sent me like oh I
think I have some carpal tunnel or they
might do something like that but usually
it's either self diagnosed or not
diagnosed or and you've said like oh
everyone thinks they have carpal tunnel
do ya it's kind of like well I wanted to
kind of say this is what carpal tunnel
is was my first thing so carpal tunnel
hallmark characteristics are numbness
tingling burning some nerve symptoms
generally and on the palm side of the
hand most often in these two fingers so
the pointer in the middle finger maybe a
little bit into the thumb if you're not
if you're having pain it's probably not
carpal tunnel if it's unless it's also
accompanied with that burning and
tingling and carpal tunnel again because
it's defined as basically its median
nerve so it's the median nerve bundle
that comes all the way down from the
neck down the arm through the carpal
tunnel in the wrist and into the hand so
since it's that having a whole long
pathway it may or may not be the actual
carpal tunnel that's the problem
it could be something at the neck or
something kind of down the chain it can
be caused by leaning at your wrist it
can be caused by spending too much time
with the wrist flexed flexed or extended
I believe flexing the wrist increases
the pressure in the carpal tunnel eight
fold and extending the rest increases at
ten fold so having a relatively neutral
wrist when you're working
is actually important so that whole
ergonomic setup thing is kind of cool
that's why those wrist braces tend to
help because they're just cheating and
helping you get there I was actually
talking to a patient the other day
totally unrelated injury but it just
kind of came up in conversation that he
had used to have carpal tunnel he's like
it's funny I put on the wrist brace and
it made me use my shoulder more I'm like
aha so you can put a wrist brace on and
then we take it off you might go back to
your old habit so you might have learned
but and you know for him he put the
wrist brace on and he realized all of a
sudden he was doing he was doing
electronic so he was more in like this
doing doing stuff and he realized that
he changed how he's using his shoulder
he's like oh yes I used my shoulder much
more instead of doing this all day long
so just kind of being aware of your
movement can be one of the biggest
changes you can make and that's really
where I come in my goal if I can give
someone like no exercises and just tell
them the things to change in their daily
life they're much more likely to do that
then do all the exercises I tell them to
do when they go home so I am much
happier to say okay so stop doing this
whole the whole unit and the reason I
put other nerves stuff in there is
because if it's not this but it's still
that I miss tingling burning it could be
one of your other nerves all our nervous
more on the pinky side of the hand
radial nerve is more on the and the
thumb side of the hand and the back side
could you I think this has a diagram of
the mouse and because I saw it when I
was slipping through down there and I
meant to mention that before because
this is this is one of my favorite
diagrams anyway that I had no idea about
worst search it's you know it's it's
user you know I I'm not searching for
the right thing pretty sure is in here
somewhere there is second one of the
ones with this is this is cool we were
just talking about the carpal tunnel
this is the carpal tunnel no so you've
got this retinaculum there so if they do
carpal pulses your surgery that's what
they're gonna snip but you've got all
the flexor tendons so all of these guys
here is this hand this is hand palm up
this is hands this is your hand looking
like this way okay so palm up from the
from your side of the hand from the
owners side so if you look at that it's
actually sorry it's looking down into
the rest of it
okay so we've cut off the fingers
[Laughter]
anatomy so you've got all of these
things in here are all your flexor
tendons so they're the the muscles
themselves are actually way up here in
the forum that's why you get your
epicondylitis up here the muscles
bellies themselves are here then they
send down the tendon to actually attach
into the hand and cause things I think
are flexion so they're all passing
through there and then you've got your
nerves and arteries trying to pass
through there too so just kind of cool
my way I think it should be it might be
further down in the next I so the here
we go so your median nerve is your
traditional carpal tunnel nerve thing
and that's here in the red and that's
traditional tone because that's the one
that can't literally cannot be
compressed at that time great okay and
then here's where you get your older
nerve and green and your radial nerve in
blue and then you can see on the back
side of the hand it's all blue radial
nerve and all our nerve
median nerve on the tips of the fingers
but rarely if that gets bad enough in
the medial nerve distribution you'll get
some aching in the forearm that's
usually just because the nerve which
sends its signal down to the muscles to
contract to the nerves do all the
information transfer um transmission
isn't working properly they can get a
key
because but so yeah so that's where
you'll feel the different nerves the
most common ones anyway in in the hand
so if you someone says a no misen
tingling I'm always like where and if
they're telling me the whole hand I'm
like well chances are starting way up
here because that's the only place you
could crush them all at the same you
know in the same in one fell swoop yeah
otherwise you're gonna get to do it here
the kind of branch out once they kind of
come through that thoracic outlet if you
guys have heard of thoracic outlet
syndrome again you're describing symptom
why do you have that pressure what is
the rasa classic outlet is that pushing
down oh okay that that outlet is getting
it's getting stricter constricted that
but again I care about not that that's
where the constriction is why is a
constricted there yeah okay so was that
all for carpal tom and really other
nerve issues for d yeah that's kind of
the general unless people have very I
really don't know how to pronounce this
okay there we go yes the equivalent is
another common one this is one that
people have pain when they're hanging
space bar it does this it's it's
inflammation of the tendon right here
see if I can just do it by this hmm it's
not gonna come up with that I'm pretty
sure that but the tendon they meant but
yeah this book doesn't have almost any
yeah and based things I don't think I
actually cross off the ones we've gone
over here so I'll be able to
what is that what Oh slicing through the
hand here we're getting we getting down
to the good stuff rather gruesome it's
like a scene from a mafia movie or
something
from a different angle someday we will
have a fully rotatable human atlas
someday I've always searched with us
online they have kind of like some
really not particularly good ones
oh why that came when I was looking for
a pollicis with me um I don't really
know can we send this back in time okay
we just had that drawing of the of the
smiling guy sitting though here's what
I'm looking for so these two tendons
that kind of form that triangle
information of those tendon sheaths is
de Quervain's but again it's often the
spacebar action but it usually is
indicated like it indicates of people
are moving weirdly and generally
actually a nice example of this just so
you can kind of get an idea of what I
see is a young woman who had this
diagnosis this medical diagnosis and
whenever she would turn her hand over
she would turn her hand over like this
she lead with her thumb and she wouldn't
be able to turn it over as far as the
other side should kind of look like this
when I had her turn her hands over it's
like well you're working way too hard
stop that so her treatment was keep your
thumb in neutral and rotate your hand
back and forth that was it that was it
and she eventually learned that like and
she was able to then rotate her arm
further didn't have to work as hard to
turn her hand over and that worked for
her in her circumstance but it's just
very interesting you can see where
people are kind of trying to find a way
she's like I like just can't get there
so she would use her thumb to kind of
make up the difference and it's like
okay let's make it so you can get there
so you don't have to use your thumb so
shoulder impingement shoulder
impingement children just like the speed
round I know I'm just discreet shouting
out a children's event again where
that's their medical diagnosis it's not
a physical therapy diagnosis physical
therapy diagnosis
what's causing the shoulder impingement
shoulder impingement is the catch-all
for like when I move my arm like this it
pinches up my shoulder I have that pain
in the vertical line it usually means
the rotator cuff is being squished so
the rotator cuff again from what you
described before is it's gonna look at
it muscles okay like that are on the
interior so ones you can't really see
that's a shoulder from the outside
that's your deltoid not your rotator
cuff your rotator cuff are these muscles
that are really right attached to the
scapula which is this again this
triangle here and then your humerus
coming down that way and they kind of
hugged that humerus into that into that
joint let's see if I can
yeah these are just hard to understand
if you don't already know what you're
looking at is part of the problem where
is what I'm looking for them this is
pretty good so this is looking top-down
as if we were looking through the top of
the head kind of at the shoulder
so again in the front here collarbone
back here top of the shoulder blade and
in that top of the shoulder blade is the
superspinatus muscle so that's where
these stripes are that pink bit is the
muscle this bulge here is the head of
the humerus it's a head of the arm done
the supraspinatus comes under so if you
feel top of your shoulder your field
bone right there the supraspinatus goes
under that bone so you've got your
collarbone comes across
you've got your acromion process that's
the thing that sticks out and if you
come then back on the backside of that
you'll feel soft squishy muscle tissue
maybe there's a knot or two there but
self-security muscles if you that is
your supers under that is your
supraspinatus which comes out underneath
that acromion process so if your scapula
is not doing that nice motion where it
swings up like we were talking about
earlier you're super super nice gets
squished underneath that acromion
process and that's classically known as
shoulder impingement but again
that's great but why is that happening
so it's great so maybe it's falling so
much that you're getting a pinched
minute matter what you do but chances
are that's capulet's not moving properly
so that's real good then you just have
neck pain and shoulder pain yeah just
generalized neck pain shoulder pain
because again those are the diagnosis
that you got but you're good right so
neck pain could be from doing this could
be from doing this could be because when
you turn your head right you do a weird
thing to point your elbow do a weird
thing
shoulder pain again things not moving
properly in there basically it usually
comes down to how you're holding
yourself and how you're moving you there
are some really cool great studies out
there right now about MRI results and
say neck pain or low back pain and it's
basically like yeah your MRI looks nasty
but you're part of us yeah group that we
tested that's completely pain-free so in
normal populations is something like
depending on the
age group and I'm going to screw it up
so please look it up it's something like
in your in your 30s it was like 70
something percent had it a weird anomaly
on their MRI that if you went in and I
said I had neck pain and you get imaging
done and they're like oh yeah you got
this thing it's definitely that it's
like well but normal population has that
too so again though you may have
anomalies on imaging they don't
necessarily correlate to your pain or
symptoms portents correlate to Campagna
symptoms is what you're doing in the
rest of your body that may have caused
that anomaly as well oh interesting so
it could be that the cause of the pain
and the cause of the anomaly are
actually are the same nothing to do with
the anomaly at all yes I see or you know
so just because you have a bulging disc
it does not mean that is you have pain
so though we all especially anybody
who's science-based brain loved to have
answers and images and all that it we
need to kind of come to terms the fact
that's just not how our bodies work so
we want to learn what it is that's
actually causing our symptoms and kind
of understanding scope so we kind of
need to just get em our ID all the time
so that we can see when these things
actually develop and then go well
alright you know occasionally just
single-handedly blew up our healthcare
sorry we're trying to say is that
conservative care consumes its
management which saves both the
insurance companies money and you money
are actually the better way to go fair
enough
so we've only got a few minutes left
here so let's just end on so obviously
this is sort of all of the the sort of
stuff that's with diagnosis figure out
where the pain could be what it might be
coming from that sort of thing so at the
end of doing all of that work you then
obviously give people sort of activities
to do right that's kind of the goal like
you were saying it might be as simple as
just like hey try to learn how to turn
your hand over more or something like
this or it may be like a set of
exercises so it cetera so I just wanted
to ask sort of the question are there
preventative exercises that you
recommend or preventative
that you recommend because obviously if
someone has one of these problems
they're gonna have to go to somebody
like you to sort of get the actual
movement stuff worked out and go okay
here's the exercises you need to do to
correct that specific impairment but
prior to having a problem are there
things you can do that just keep your
body in shape better than you know
decrease the likelihood of things
getting into these bad positions knowing
that the person probably is like this
most of the time how do you counteract
that you know what what do you recommend
for that and are there exercises you
recommend people do daily or anything
like this yeah so like I said before I
don't tend to love giving exercises so
I'm going to start with the two simplest
things you can do number one as part of
your daily life
try to change positions frequently don't
get really settled and comfy in one
position stand up sit down lean back
lean forward you don't need to be like
this all the time I'm not one of those
people it's going to tell you to do this
because it's not realistic you're at
your computers a lot but changing
positions is really good for your body
it's really healthy for your body you
don't get stuck in that one shape so
that's number one number two is do
anything any activity any activity
that's not sitting down go for a walk go
for a run I don't really care what you
do but do something cardiovascular
getting your blood flowing everywhere
and getting your body working globally
and coordinating movement all together
is the best thing you can do for your
health musculoskeletal and global health
so those are my two like everyone should
be doing those things and they're
relatively easy to do as far as specific
exercises go I know everyone likes the
specifics to makes them be able to say
they can point to that one thing it's
like it's that thing haha my I will
again go with just one I'll pick just
one okay um because I think it's easier
I don't love to give people giant lists
of things to do because people don't do
giant lists they do one thing
some people are exceptional I find my
tech workers sometimes like my circus
people love to go to extremes so
sometimes I have to bring them back in
but basically computer work all day
you're here
so that's relatively rounded in the
torso relatively shoulders forward
relatively internally rotated the arms
the wrists could be doing all sorts of
weird things cuz I like to take people
completely out of that and my absolute
favorite favorite actress that exercise
I call the reverse wall wall slide or a
wall angel as possibly you can find it
involves sticking your back flat up
against a wall which may mean your feet
have to be a little further away your
arms out to the side about 90 degrees
hands on the wall but your elbows not on
the wall because most of you are stiff
from doing this so you to get those
elbows back on the wall your children's
gonna pop out this is why I don't like
giving exercises because I'm so specific
about how I make people do it's really
difficult so back flat against the wall
hands on the wall elbows forward
shoulders relaxed lacks neck relaxed if
you can achieve this position which is
not going to be easy for everyone then
you can slide your hands up the wall and
overhead and the idea behind that is
that you are opening the chest putting
the arms out to the side just can bring
your shoulder blades together which is
the opposite of here so you'll be firing
the muscles between the shoulder blades
you're working your arms into external
rotation again fighting this internal
rotation position it's also an active
stretch for the pectoral muscles just to
get you back there which is why the
elbows will probably have to come
forward and then as you go up overhead
you're gonna trigger in your middle and
lower trapezius in your back so back
here you're going to be stretching your
PEC muscles again as you go up overhead
your lats are gonna have to let go your
external rotators are firing it's a lot
of information but the global idea is
you're doing the opposite of this so
that's probably my number one favorite
end of the day or lunch time do five or
ten of them exercises and they'll keep
you kind of moving on healthy awesome
well we are out of time thank you so
much and also you're going to be at the
reception or throughout the visit okay
so there's a there's a pure motion
banner which is your you
company and there's a peer motion banner
up there and so if people wanted to talk
about specifics or get a business card
or something like that yeah make sure
you actually find happy to answer
questions thank you so much
[Applause]