hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero show we code a complete game live
on stream we may take a brief digression
here at the opening of of handmade hero
because we wanted to see last night I
was playing children of Merida which
came out recently and one of the things
that I noticed a lot of times when I
play at least unity games that are pixel
art games they have this this sort of
problem where the shaders are not
written properly I don't know if this is
just a problem with unity or what the
problem is exactly like why they don't
have proper shaders but basically what
ends up happening is you don't actually
get to see the pixel art in all of its
beautiful glory because they haven't
done sub pixel sampling of the pixel art
itself so it's it's really kind of it's
really kind of sad because it's
literally just a little bit of change to
a shader and you get way better results
than you would have gotten if you you
know if you do it the way that it
happens in unity so I was curious to
take a look at that today so I thought
what we might do today is just play with
insight a little to see I don't know if
we can but I figured it might just be
fun as something we don't normally do on
handmade hero to do a little reverse
engineering potentially to see if
there's any way we could fix the shaders
in children of morta without actually
having access to the source code to make
it so that it was actually rendering the
pixel art properly kind of try and fix
unities code for them I don't know maybe
I should ask them to pay me but what I'd
like to do is just see if that's at all
possible so the first thing I'm going to
do here is just see if it's possible to
attach n sight to a running Unity game
and get anything meaningful out of it
now I'm going to kind of explain how
this works and if nothing else if this
part works
well at least get to show how to
deconstruct a games rendering pipeline
which i think is interesting anyway
because it's a good thing for people to
know how to to do in general because you
can learn things about graphics
programming and how people accomplish
certain things a game like children of
mordor probably isn't one you'd normally
do because it's not really a graphics
game but you know if you have something
like the latest Unreal Engine game on
your machine and you're playing it
you're like wow how did they do those
graphic effects
well reverse engineering the graphics is
something that is a very easy way to go
look at how they're accomplishing the
rendering passes that that they do to
create those effects that you see so
what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna
launch the game as I normally would so
I'm gonna go ahead and see if I can just
launch it here directly it looks like I
can't so I may have to just run it
through Steam yeah so I'm gonna go ahead
and run steam here or try to there it is
so my Steam is now running I'm gonna
click on children of morta and have it
run and then what I'm gonna do is once
it's running I'm gonna try to get to a
point where I can see sort of the the
issues with the pixel art happening
which may be hard for you to see because
the video compressor on Twitch
compresses it into a real mush but but
hopefully I can get to a point where you
know at least I can see it hopefully you
can see it too and then we're gonna go
ahead and take a look
all right I don't know if we can
actually skip this I hope so
all right I don't know if we can skip it
so I'm gonna go ahead here and while
that's playing in the background I'm
gonna go ahead and open up insight all
right Margot awoke startled a cold sweat
clinging to her she gathered her
thoughts I guess this is a fine location
for it
[Music]
I really don't want to watch just
cutscene but I can't find any way to go
there to school to be like there we go
that's what I wanted so you can see I
don't know if you can see it but there's
all kinds of artifacting just as I'm
like zooming in it's super artifacting
and in fact I want to say I think we
might actually be seeing it just in the
I can just move the mouse and see it but
I think probably if they're doing this
procedurally meaning they're moving like
this a actual which we'll be able to see
when we deconstruct the frame when we
when it's moving like this we'll be able
to see the pixel problems in here I can
see them right now hopefully you can't -
where it's just like stuttering across
pixels and you can also see the sort of
shimmering that happens as I move around
the mouse because all of the background
is also being sampled improperly as well
again don't know if I'll be able to help
with any of this because I only have a
limited ability to do so doing reverse
engineering but what I'm going to do is
just going to end site and anyone could
download insight you can literally we've
done it on the m8 here oh we downloaded
it live I think so if you don't know how
to do that you can look for my stream on
it but really all you have to do is just
go to Nvidia's website they actually got
rid of the having to have an account
which is awesome so you can go to
invidious website you can go to the
insight page just type in Nvidia insight
on like Google or something download it
as long as you have the your drivers
up-to-date it should just work you
should be able just launch it like I
have it here and then we're gonna create
a new project and just hit OK and then
we're gonna try now you look at here
again I'll try to explain this in a sort
of a beginner friendly way so don't know
who might watch the stream about reverse
engineering at some point what we're
doing here is insight is essentially a
utility that allows us to capture what a
application is sending to the graphics
card right because it has to send it
through known EPISD through the 11-12
OpenGL
Volken right you can see them right here
these are the ones that might be running
on Windows what this app allows to do is
insert ourselves into that pipeline and
capture the commands that were sent via
OpenGL or D 3d or whatever it was right
now there's two ways we can do it one is
we can launch the executable ourselves
right I can put children of morta in
here as an executable and launch it via
insight insight will then run the exe
and capture it that way I'm not going to
do that this time the reason I'm not
going to do that is because children
morta is a steam application the way
that I have it installed now I bought it
on Steam so it runs through Steam what
that means is although the children of
Morda executable exists on the actual
hard drive you can go see it it's in the
steam apps directory under you know C
program files steam steamapps or
something like that I don't remember
exactly the path well you know what I'll
show you the path this is this is meant
to be a beginner friendly stream here so
I'll show you I'm talking about if you
actually open up your your okay so say
in x86 if you open up your Program Files
x86 directory you can see there's a
steam directory inside there there's a
steam apps directory inside there
there's a common directory and here's
all your games right so if I go into a
particular game in this case children of
morta you can see that the unity
distribution is just sitting there so
it's not magic I can run it directly
from here right but what typically
happens at the startup of a standard
Steam application if I remember
correctly it's been a while is that the
first thing they do is check to see if
steam is running and if steam is running
they actually thunk back to Steam tell
steam to run them through steam so they
get the overlay the steam overlay in the
communication with friends lists and all
that stuff and then they exit so the
children were to eggsy actually just
becomes a steam launcher that launches
steam and tells steam to run children
amorta okay and that's a little
confusing but you have to remember
players when they run a particular game
and they want to have that Steam
experience right they want to have the
like voice chat and they want to have
the steam friends list and they want to
have
achievements and all this other stuff
that comes with steam and so typically
when there's a steam game it installs an
executable at the front of the
executable it says is steam running is
or is installed in this machine if it is
then just tell send a message to seem to
say run childen amorta and it is exit
right and that ensures that you're
always running a steam game through
steam because that's presumably what the
player wanted otherwise they wouldn't
have bought it on Steam right so just
keep that in mind so the reason that I'm
not going to do the launch here and we
might try it later but the reason I'm
not starting with that is because I'm a
concerned that that won't do anything
basically what will happen is it will
launch the executable and the executable
will just send a message to steam in the
exit and then we'll have children more
to running but we won't be able to
capture it because it's actually a
different instance of that executable so
what I'm going to do instead is use the
second way that you can attach insight
to a process and that is to oh nevermind
I guess so I can't do that only updates
lost from Anniston come here oh well I
guess we could try I was gonna say
hopefully I can attach it here but it
looks like you can't actually do that
within sight or you can't do it anymore
so I can't actually do it that way I'm
gonna have to find a way to actually
launch children of morta directly
without steam being involved we'll try
it it's pretty dicey what I could do is
launch steam through insight that might
work but I don't actually know if it
will so this is gonna be harder than I
thought it was gonna be but we'll give
it a shot
let's go out here and and exit steam and
I must see what I might be able to do in
that regard just to see what we just to
see what we can come up with so the
first thing I'm going to do is I showed
you that that launch directory here I
want to see if I'm right about it
thunking esteem it may or may not do
that I'm not sure but I'm gonna see
first what actually happens so if I
double click on the executable let's see
what goes on here does it try to thunk
through steam or doesn't it and I'm not
sure it looks like it didn't
so I'm hoping that that just means
that's not something that this app will
actually do and if that's the case we're
in luck we don't have to worry about the
thing that I was talking about because
they didn't do it right so I'm just go
ahead and go ahead and try launching
this executable directly so what I'm
doing is pasting in the full path to the
executable here and I'm also gonna
launch it from its directory just in
case it needs that because I don't know
what it's expecting but I'm assuming
that it aspects to be launched in the
directory of its executable we're not
gonna pass any command-line arguments or
set any environment variables because as
far as we know it should just work
hopefully this creates a project for us
right I'm hoping I can just save that
project and save these so that then if
we a crash or something we'll be able to
load it back up and then I'm just gonna
say launch and we're gonna quit we're
just crossing our fingers right so it
looks like it's using something called
child resources which it says it doesn't
necessarily support which is and it also
says I'm toward OS detected so we're
yeah we're I guess we're gonna in a
little bit of a a rough spot here
so it looks like insights very unhappy
with this capture we may have to try
render doc again all we're trying to do
here is just just get a general capture
of this thing it's looking pretty
difficult to do but we'll see
oops I didn't mean to do what I just did
so I'm just gonna try and skip these
cutscenes here I don't know if I can or
can looks like I can I don't know why
sometimes holding escape skips a
cutscene sometimes with death but I
guess I don't care the question is does
the think it's running it doesn't I'll
get the lok startled so it's gonna allow
me to attack because I didn't launches
in here so I'm gonna go ahead and try to
attach a frame debugger to it but I'm
gonna wait till we get to the point
where I actually want to try capture so
we'll see but again not looking
particularly not looking particularly
happy alright so if I can get a frame
capture anywhere in here I'm gonna be
happy so I'm just gonna go ahead and try
and attach it and see we'll see what we
can do
so it looks like it's sort of attached
looks like it don't know but since we've
got an attachment I'm just gonna try it
so I'm using alt tab right now to switch
back and forth and normally if you have
two monitors you would put inside on one
monitor and you put the game on the
other but that's you know all kind of a
separate issue so here is our frame that
we're gonna try and capture what I'm
gonna go and do is go into children ward
I hit frame divider capture for live
analysis and cross my fingers that it's
able to capture any of this stuff even
though it keeps complaining about all
sorts of API errors I don't really know
exactly what that's about but we'll see
so now you can kind of see we've got a
frame capture who knows if it's correct
or not but as we go through here what we
can see is that it did actually capture
a d3 D 11 stream so the first thing we
know about this game is it doesn't use
d3 212 use d3 11 that's just something
we now know that makes sense because
this is a game that probably wouldn't
benefit much from d3 d 12 and d3 a 12
only runs on a subset of systems this
here is if you look at the the different
panels here again trying to make this
somewhat beginner friendly we've done
this on handmade hero so I don't want to
belabor the point too much but what you
can see in this layout is we now have
the ability to kind of look at what's
happening during a frame now this window
here the scrubber view tells me what's
happening in the frame over time and
what you can see is and when I say time
I mean time of a single frames execute a
P eye state right so if you imagine that
this is essentially all of the calls to
the API that have happened and all of
these lines here are ones that actually
issued like a rendering call because
remember graphics API is they typically
set a bunch of state and then do an
issue of a call so you do like set the
viewport set some texturing up and then
like sync a bunch of triangles that sync
a bunch of triangles actually now does
work those previous commands didn't
do any work they were just setting state
up in order to do the work so all of
these empty areas in here are things
that were setting up stuff and all of
these notches are things that actually
did work what this scrubber view lets me
do is jump anywhere that there was work
and see what got rendered so here you
can see rendered some kind of a circular
region and you can see in here the color
buffer I'm not sure what that actually
was if we jump to the end of the frame I
don't know if if there's maybe some kind
of I don't know what's actually there if
I look maybe right before yeah I don't
know if that's some kind of fogging
bloom or something it's hard to say but
what you can see is it's pretty nice as
I jump around here you can see if I
actually expand this out wait so you can
it one of the unfortunate things is it
doesn't subsample these marks well so
there's actually marks you can't see if
you zoomed in more you would see them I
don't know if we kind of zoom in like
this right here you can sort of see
where those actual marks all are so each
of these blue ones is something that
actually synced some some render you
know something that could render so what
it looks like here it looks like they're
rendering some kind of like fog in there
right you can kind of see it happening
if I if I pull back out and maybe get
this window a little bit bigger here so
you can see it you can sort of see as it
comes through all of those render
commands it looks like maybe that's fog
it could also be like texturing ground
passes I'm not sure hard to say
you can see here we're tiling the ground
with stuff there I guess not sure where
we lay down the actual ground splats
okay so those are ground splats so you
can kind of see what's happening I guess
this right here laid down a base coat on
the ground it looks like and now we're
splatting down ground textures if I go
ahead and and take a look at this guy I
don't know if I can zoom this in at all
looks like I can't for whatever reason
that's too bad my frame image I can't
really zoom this in much so I I'm gonna
maybe try just make it bigger here so
you can see it you can see that it sort
of rendered a base repeating pattern
onto the ground that's very dim I'm not
sure what that was meant to do it might
have something to do with other types of
rendering would happen but you can see
these ground slats there's a ground
splat there's a ground splat so what the
game is doing right here is it's laying
down those initial ground patterns in a
way that blends them together so it's
just doing a lot of overdraw there to
splat the ground together into something
so it's not fog it's just placing ground
right placing ground tiles you can see
it doing that we're now rendering that
right there is the player marker so for
whatever reason the player marker got
rendered this time that may just be
happenstance it's hard to know why
because the texture in the terrain
hasn't been so here's probably why it
got rendered at that time if that makes
sense
it looks like they've broken up into two
passes rendering a flat ground plane
then putting stuff on the ground plane
then putting stuff over it right so it
probably got rendered because it's just
part of the flat ground plane that
marker is sort of supposed to be sitting
where the player is sitting right and so
now we're putting like trees and other
sprites on there that we need to kind of
stack up for the player to experience
right and you can kinda see
a little bit of bugginess there that
probably isn't I mean it might be but it
probably isn't in the actual game that's
probably because of some of the API
capture bugs we were seeing before that
was warning us about that's probably
just or you know it might just be an
artifact of how it's redrawing cuz you
can see it's not there when we go in
here so I don't know what's happening
there exactly but those those are
probably not things to be concerned
about
probably just artifacting from the
capture here you can see drawing the
dude you can see that we're composing
the world upside down by the way the
dude is standing upside down from where
they are and those trees are upside down
but anyway if we now look in here let's
take a look at one of these trees
specifically because this is an example
of the kind of shader that we wanted to
look at where is that large there it is
so this tree here if I if I look at it
in more detail I don't know if I can
zoom in on this so anyway to zoom in on
that I don't think I can zoom in on this
view unfortunately I can zoom in on the
texture like here right so we can zoom
in on this thing and one of the nice
things about it too is you know they've
made the check boxes that we actually
want you can see where they've got flip
image because they know a lot of times
things get rendered upside down so we
can sort of see that this was one of the
things that was flickery when it moved
and it's hard to say to what extent
they're shifting this but you can see
that it is for whatever reason more than
one triangle pair for that it's not just
a quad I'm not sure I'm really just not
sure exactly why I don't quite know
what's happening there why it looks like
that it may have to do with something in
the way unity works I don't I don't
really know but anyway I'm gonna stop
there and I'm gonna go look at what
shader was used to draw this to see if I
can gain any insight and whether we will
be able to improve the sampling quality
of the pixel art here so if I go into
pixel shader and I take a look at what's
going on here
I can see all of the stuff that's
happening in in the you know in the
pixels trading pipeline right if we step
through this list I guess I should again
just to be clear for folks who have
never used a utility like this before
this API inspector view is basically
once I've dialed in up top here once
I've dialed in that's the particular
render call that I want to inspect and
by the way we didn't mention it but this
right here updates to match this this is
just a listing of what the api's
actually were so on this issuance this
was the command
this was the direct3d 11 command that
was being called draw index it's drawing
12 indices it's just this tree right
it's a very small batch render issue and
you can see anything else you want to
see about the particular call we don't
care about that right now what we care
about is all the state that was set for
the call specifically up here you can
see it's setting up the shaders and the
samplers by the way crazy how much
overhead there is here I would have
expected unity be more optimized than
this this is kind of ridiculously bad
far far worse than handmade hero which
is something that we did on a stream by
ourselves that is not meant to be a
reusable engine that I just don't
understand how it's that looking that
bad but it is there's a map on map
before every single one of these this is
to update these constant but like
there's no batching at all from what I
can see it literally draws a little
chunk at a time really really bad not
sure whose fault that is but you know
maybe that's why unity games are so slow
all the time anyway moving back over
here taking a look at this this issuance
here this window the API inspector view
is basically a break out of the
information for the thing that we're
stepped to so remember we're stepped
here at 5:22 and then get back there
we're here on this call this API
inspector view is a breakout view of
everything that happened on that call
again allows us to see what's going on
if we take a look at this this list here
these are the stages of rendering
as they occur logically not necessarily
on the chip but logically so here is the
input assembler what that's saying is
what are all the inputs to this command
that are relevant you can see here this
tells us how the vertices were coming in
there's a position a normal a color four
sets of texture coordinates and a
tangent frame why on earth you would
need all that for a single batch of
something that needs none of those
things it's probably only this one this
one in this one actually who knows again
just largesse from unity who knows
so probably looking at the fact that
these are all it offsets zero it looks
like maybe they just forgot to turn them
off or maybe there's no cost to leaving
them on because the shader doesn't fetch
them I'm not sure so that's fine but
it's using probably at least these two
so you know what I take it back
there might not be any largesse here it
looks like they're offsets are properly
set to zero for all these so they're
enabled in some way but not actually
being read I would suspect so it's not
actually wasteful it looks like it's
only using position colored text cord
which is what it should have so no bad
there all right here are the vertex
buffers that are coming in it looks like
there's some kind of global sampling
buffer coming in here this is a
secondary vertex buffer this looks like
the primary vertex buffer we're actually
sampling from this one has a stride of
zero and so it looks like this is just
constants that are coming in here as a
perfect buffer instead of as a constant
buffer same thing with the index buffer
so these are the two buffers we're
actually looking at here we don't care
about those because we don't need to
adjust what's being drawn we have seem
to be adjust how it's being drawn so
those really won't concern us this so I
just walking you through this but we
don't care about the input assembly
stage pretty much at all at the vertex
shading stage probably same thing I
won't really have to modify the vertex
shader but if you did have to look at
the what was going on the vertex shader
this is the place to do it here I
believe is how you would actually look
at those shaders you can see in here
you've got the disassembly of the shader
and the statistics and so on right and
so you know that's that's what's
happening the vertex shader if
we pop out the disassembly you can see
here what's going on in the actual a
shader what I don't know is if there's
any way so this this is pretty much what
what's going to stop us right so that
answers our question whether we can fix
what's going on in the shader if I can't
edit the HLSL bytecode or produce source
and then change it then then there's
really not much I can do right because
what I want to be able to do is edit
this shader not this one specifically I
want to be able to edit that I wanted to
be able to edit that that pixel shader
so let's take a look let me close this
actually I don't really know how to
close that probably there we go
so let me finish walking through this
and then we'll see if there's any way we
can coax this thing into a mode where we
actually could somehow use it so we look
here you've got a few more things these
are stages that we're not using so these
are not enabled in the game right now so
you can see you've got like the geometry
shader dimension these are not being
used so that's why they're grayed out
we then get to the rasterization stage
the rasterization stage is just a thing
that basically tells you how it
determines which pixels were filled
there isn't a shader that operates at
this stage on the Nvidia part and so
really all you've got are settings and
these are those settings there are
things like whether it was solid or
wireframe fill or things like that
whether or not there was culling turned
on for back face culling things like
that you can see it's not turned on that
sort of stuff again don't need to change
any of that here's the money this is
what we actually wanted to edit doesn't
look like we'll be able to because if I
go to the disassembly here I'm assuming
you'll say the same thing which is that
I can't edit it and what I would like to
be able to do is edit it and change the
way that it's actually doing its
sampling to get me better results now I
can't do that so we're gonna have to
transfer in a way that we could actually
change that that shade
so looking in here at what's going on
you can see the pixel shading happening
this is all the information that was
going into the pixel shader again we
don't really care because everything
that's going in is what we want the
texture and so on but if you were trying
to figure out like you know which well
you can see actually also in here
information about what was happening
with the sampling you can see that it's
just doing point sampling on everything
which is why you're getting that Chris
penis instead of like bilinear which you
know makes makes perfect sense obviously
so anyway the bummer is we can't edit
the shader so we're gonna have to try
and figure out some way to coax it into
allowing us to edit that shader I don't
know if maybe render doc would let us do
it or not but there is another way we
might be able to do it I don't think
there's any way to tell unity to run in
opengl mode but maybe there is and if
there was that might help us because
OpenGL doesn't really allow you except
with extensions to submit compiled
bytecode so I'm wondering if there is
some way to force open jail on a unity
executable I'm not sure but that's where
we're at now if we actually were to look
at this disassembly here I think if we
could have edited it we would actually
have so anyway to get this there it is
it's like I wanted this to be a pop-out
window um so if we actually looked at
this you can see the disassembly of the
shader you can see here that there's
basically an if clause that stops the
actual shading from occurring here and
just dumps a standard like value out to
the stream and skips the shading here we
have another one of those happening here
right and so if we take a look at what's
going on you can see that there's
samples being taken from s 1 and s 0 and
s 2 and so if I look at my actual try I
don't want this thing to dock there you
go if I look at what's actually coming
in on those slots that should give me
some idea of who
I actually would need to update here so
let's take a look at those three
textures in order so here is the first
texture this first okay so this just
looks like the map honestly yeah so for
some reason the map is active in slot
zero if we look at what texture might be
sampled in slot zero just to get some go
ahead and make this a little bit more
more visible if we were to look at
what's which texture operations were
targeting that if we look your sampler
zero I I believe there's nothing special
about any of these samplers and if we
look at the samplers here
here are the the textures that went into
those slots which I believe are just
bound per sampler so I believe like this
would be sample zero this would be
sampler one of this would be sampler - I
believe so if we look at where those are
actually getting sampled if we pull down
to places that sample from slot 0 which
is the map you can see that there's
really it's it's kind of out in here
same with this other texture that looks
like some kind of a bloom effect maybe
that's some kind of lighting or you know
some kind of special effect that's going
on there that maybe got rendered for
lighting purposes those two are getting
sampled in the top branch I'm sorry the
bottom branch and what you'll notice is
the actual sprite itself is not being
sampled here so this looks like
something we wouldn't really care about
because it's not actually sampling us
right this looks like it is the thing
that sampling was right and if we take a
look at that texture here you can see
yes
I almost want to say the animation is
baked in is there any way to flip this
guy around
guess I could do it in the shader I was
hoping there was a nice little I was
hoping there was a way to just do a
one-click flip like we were doing and
the other one there it looks like there
isn't but anyway if I look at these the
so a couple things about them really
kind of confused right now as I look at
this I'm not sure what to make of it for
a number of reasons so I'll to start and
I'll go through them kind of kind of all
together here so the first thing is it
looks like that waving was actually just
done in an external application so I
can't actually fix this stuff it looks
like the bad pixel sampling is built in
to the actual image which is unfortunate
right but maybe that's okay because hey
the panning and zooming part I could fix
right but looking at it that that's
definitely a problem the other thing I
would say is looks like this game
couldn't have mipmapping turned on
without it a bunch of work as well so
that was another big source of the
sparkles the reason is because it's not
using premultiplied alpha so the reason
I can tell that it's not using
premultiplied alpha is you can see that
the colors are smeared right they're
smeared out and what that means is that
if I look at how the Alpha Channel looks
I'm not sure how to get the Alpha
Channel
probably oh it does have flip upside
down just didn't know where I was
looking so there's our upright actual
plant so if I look at the Alpha Channel
with the Alpha Channel on you can see
that if this was using a premultiplied
texture people apply to alpha texture
then when I clicked this all of this
would be black and the reason we black
is because if the Alpha is zero
somewhere then when you do premultiplied
alpha it means that your RGB channels
are multiplied by the Alpha Channel so
everywhere that there's no alpha there
would be black in the color channels
that's not what's happening so I know
that this is not a premultiplied alpha
texture which means it cannot be MIT
mapped properly without an additional
shader so I wouldn't really be able to
fix that part either without doing
multiple samples from the texture I
wouldn't be able to use the MIT mapping
hardware which is kind of a bummer but
that's not the end of the world I could
just add those extra samples get slower
but get correct mipmapping on my on my
plants here so yeah let's take a look
though we know that that is the thing
that's actually being sampled as the
sprite we go in here and we look at all
the samples taken and you know there's a
heck of a lot of information in this
side of the sampler I'm not sure what it
all does and it might be a bit laborious
to go through the whole thing but you
know we're gonna have to try and at
least make some sense of if we want to
understand how we would necessarily
modify it so you know coming in here
we've got some registers that are you
know getting used here I assume those
registers are just scratch registers
probably you can see them being used
here and then we've got like our vertex
inputs you can see like vertex input
happening here and then we've got like a
constant buffer happening here and so on
so if you take a look at what's
happening with this
sampling in this part of things I'm
guessing just looking at what's going on
here
and this is taxing my I'm not a reverse
engineer so my brain is not like sort of
set up too quickly guess correctly
what's going on in a lot of cases but
I'm guessing what we're sort of seeing
here in terms of taking these samples
the fact that we're taking multiple
samples is a little confusing because
I'm not sure why we would be doing that
in order to take multiple samples you
would think we would have to be doing
some filtering but I'm not seeing any
filtering right if I jump back to the
actual children of morta well I guess I
can't necessarily maybe if I do resume I
don't know if that will destroy my frame
though
I don't know to what extent exporting
this as a C++ capture would actually
work it would be interesting to see if
if that did work that would it allow us
to potentially edit the shaders as well
so maybe we could do something like that
I'm not sure anyway the point is I
wanted to kind of show you the sort of
the Chris penis that I was seeing there
but the fact that I'm seeing all that
flickering and Chris penis I don't
understand what all of these samples
could be because if you're taking
multiple samples you should be getting
at least some filtering if you're only
getting completely unfiltered results
why are we taking so many samples of
that texture and I really don't know so
that's a real puzzler that's a real
puzzler let's try to take a look here so
the first thing we're doing is we're
taking an input from v2 right and you
can you can look here and you can see
that these are the inputs from the
vertex shader right here's our textures
right I'm sorry
here's our texture coordinates yeah
here's our texture coordinates I don't
normally use D 3ds so it's hard for me
sometimes to back map here's our
samplers SCR s1 s2 it's s1 that we care
about as far as I know unless maybe I'm
reading this wrong and s1 doesn't map to
this texture I mean it could be but I'm
not sure how else to interpret this
because you have the samplers in slot 0
1 2 I believe slot 0 1 2 here
corresponds to the samplers which means
that anywhere you're using sampler 1 you
are sampling from this texture as far as
I know unless I miss reading the D 3d
there but I think that's how this would
look and so I believe that this is the
only thing we actually care about is
this T 1 s 1 I believe although actually
the team
so looking at this we're doing sample oh
no no no no no no no no no I'm reading
the d3d wrong so that's yeah lesson
learned I believe that actually it's
pairing the samplers are being paired
dynamically prob mystery solved okay you
learn something every day
so if we look in here what we can see is
the DVD disassembly the samplers are the
S is the textures are the t's that's how
this disassembly is being looked at
that's just my bad again I don't
normally use DVDs so I have no idea how
to read these readouts I kind of know
how the graphics cards work but I don't
know how to necessary map that to it so
that was just a piece of the puzzle here
all right so these slots and these slots
are being paired using this Naumann clay
Chur that means actually what we're
looking for is people who sample T one
that makes things so much better because
what that means is that anywhere we were
seeing T zero here and you can see T 0 T
0 T 0 T 0 T 0 in this first branch
that's actually sampling the map that
sampling from texture 0 it's just using
sampler 1 which again is is this one so
it's sampler 1 pit paired with texture 0
just throwing you for a loop there big
deal we figured it out so it is the
simpler case that we're looking at and
that makes so much more sense cuz like I
said I could not figure out why we would
be sampling 4 times now I still don't
know why we're sampling the map 4 times
but that's kind of a separate issue
maybe this isn't the map maybe this is
some kind of an assembly thing that they
act who knows what that's worth maybe
it's a depth I really don't know doesn't
matter because we don't care this is the
branch we actually care about it only
does sample once which is exactly what I
was expecting
based on the results I saw so you can
see why I was nervous that my god I
don't know what this would really need
to do for the output I was seeing
doesn't make a lot of sense now it makes
a lot more sense here we can see our
texture samples and we can interpret
them properly t1 and t2 are these two
textures right here we
don't care so much about the t2 that
looks like a lighting overlay some kind
of a light contribution sample that we
don't really care about
so this t2 sample we can effectively
ignore r2 we don't care about this is
the sample we care about sample r1 and
this multiplied here basically what
that's doing that multiplied is probably
applying a vertex color channel so it's
probably saying hey I might want to
change the color of this thing you know
maybe it's if I'm flashing it or
whatever oh we got a push we got a push
hello how's it going what's up today we
saw the prime puss on a little bit
earlier on the stream and the puss has
rejoined us I think the puss wants to
look out the window so I'm gonna put her
in her little feet there you go puss
there you go pull this look out oh
there's so much good nature today so
much good nature out there isn't that
true yeah that's a good place alright so
I'm hoping the puss will maybe just make
herself comfortable and enjoy some of
the outdoor sites I don't know she might
want attention in which case we might be
in trouble
alright so again I think this is just
taking and doing some colorization of
the sample so this is sampling the
sprite this is coloring the sprite using
an input and then a bunch of stuff here
you know looking at this we got a DP 3
on here that's probably used for some
kind of well no it's not because it's
hard-coded so it's probably not actually
doing that so we got two DP 3s this
might be a lighting one might not be
hard to say I don't know exactly what
they're doing that they're trying to
pick out some some channels of the color
there so I don't know so this stuff we
don't necessarily care about this is
like the post filtering doing some
presumably working with how these two
samples want to get combined or
something like this so all we would
really need to edit is right here you
can see that T 1 X Y Z W right and you
can see on how we're taking the sample
this one
sample coming from texture one because
we're only taking one sample from it and
bilinear and mipmapping or both turned
off it means we will get no filtering
right so all we would really need to do
is expand this sample this line right
here to first figure out some more
places to take a sample from and then we
would sample it multiple times now
normally you can be a lot cheaper than
that normally if you turn mipmapping on
which we can't do because we're not in
control of the unity pipeline because we
don't on source code you can just take
one sample and what you do is you
precondition your UV coordinates and
then take a single bilinear sample and
that gives you perfect pixel art
upscaling but we can't do that but we
can't approximate it by just forcing the
GeForce to do a crap ton of extra
texture samples now fortunately they're
all from exactly the same place in the
texture so they're very very fast
texture samples but again you still
wouldn't want to do this you'd want to
just use the bilinear hardware and so
all I would really need to do is update
this sample line and what I would do is
I would take the sampling from the
texture and I would take the UV
coordinates and I would just add the
differential UV offset for sampling
inside the pixel I'm in right and let me
draw on the whiteboard what I would be
doing and then we can try to figure out
a way to coax our coax unity or somebody
to let us actually edit this shader
somehow and I don't know how to how best
to do that if this were an OpenGL app or
if they had shipped HLSL source somehow
we would probably just be able to do
that I don't think they did I think
those are like packed into the unity
files if you go out here you know the
best-case scenario is there just sitting
in some directory here but I'm pretty
sure they're not I'm pretty sure they're
like you know stuffed into this stuff
somewhere you know who knows where
but I'm pretty sure they're just kind of
you know they're probably in here
somewhere and and I don't know to what
to what extent we would ever have access
them I don't think for example there's
just an HLSL file sitting around because
they probably just compiled them unity
probably just compiles them and shoves
them in to the executable that's my
assumption I don't use unity so I don't
know
anyway let me pop over to the to the
blackboard for a second and just kind of
give you a sense
I accidentally hit the zoom there I
don't know I don't want to zoom in too
much see where we were at probably right
about there yeah let me go ahead and and
show you
so if we want a sample pixel-art
properly like I said there's two ways to
do it
I'll cover the brute force way first cuz
that's the only one we would really I
think be able to inject in the children
in Ward a best-case scenario and then we
can also just briefly mention what you
would do for the more efficient version
if you are grading your own game so what
happens with pixel are up sampling well
what happens is normally we you know
when we talk about a texture we pretend
that the texture is basically a capture
of something that had like infinite
resolution right we pretend that we were
taking like a photograph or something
and then we're trying to reconstruct
what that photograph will look like it
was stamped onto something in the world
like for example if we took a photograph
of a brick wall and then stamped it on a
flat polygon in our game we want to look
like a brick wall what that means is
when we reconstructed we assumed that
the points that we have the texels that
we have in our texture are actually just
sample points of something that was
actually much more resolute to begin
with that picture of the brick wall
might have only been 1024 by 1024 or
something but in the real world atoms
are much much smaller than that we
should have had a 80 billion by 80
billion picture of the of the brick wall
and so when we go to sample it we just
assume that well what's in between the
pixels is just maybe some smooth blend
between the two because we don't
actually have the extra detail but we
know there was extra detail pixel art is
not that way pixel art is sort of like
saying there is no extra detail the
point is you can see the pixels there
are big blocks there isn't anything in
between them they are not samples of
some more high-resolution signal
underneath they are the whole signal
what that means is that if you take some
piece of pixel art that I make let's say
I make something that looks like this
right when I go to draw that on the
screen if my screen is like way more
resolute so you know maybe I'm drawing
it on a screen that's way more resolute
as the case of pixel art I'm gonna map
this thing and let's say onto the screen
it maps quite large
maybe a little too large right so this
maps to this square here right I'll try
to draw that a little better so you can
see it here's my pixel my pixel art and
so I'm gonna change my terminology a
little bit I'm gonna call it Texel art
temporarily to determine to
differentiate between the pixels on the
screen and the texels in our texture
right so the pixel artist is really a
Texel artist nowadays they're not
drawing pixels because pixels are things
on the screen they're drawing texels
which are things in the texture map and
those texels are getting put on the
screen and ideally what we want is we
want them to look like little blocks
this is different than pretty much
anything else we do in graphics we never
want our textures to look like little
blocks that's considered ugly and bad
most of the time in pixel art games
let's call them textile art games we
actually want to look like blocks so
what that means is we can't just turn on
naive bilinear filtering why because
let's see what that will do let's
suppose we turned on naive bilinear
filtering and we looked what happened to
this grid of pixels here on the screen
well this pixel here would have gotten
basically just this color because it's
gonna hit the border and clamp out here
this pixel here would start to blend it
would blend between this pixel and this
pixel here because it is some distance
towards this side right as well actually
that's not true
I'd have to probably cause the center
line first let's talk about this pixel
in this pixel as I got to this pixel I
would start to blend between this and
this right so instead of getting solid
let's say this is red and this is black
instead of getting a solid red color
which is what I probably want for my
textile art right instead of a solid red
color I get a blend between red and
black and then here I get even more
black until finally when I'm here I get
complete black right that is not what I
wanted at all
this because this is a text alert game
this should have been full read right
because we're talking about blowing this
entire Texel up so that it looks like a
solid rectangle right so anything all of
these all of these pixels here should
have been solid red
even though bilinear filtering says that
it should be a blend between here and
here it probably would be about let's
say 15 percent black 85 percent red that
is what this would have been right and
that's precisely why turning on bilinear
filtering looks so bad with with Texel
art with pixel art right games he's
because you get this smearing effect
because it's pretending that there was a
signal in between you know that we just
weren't sampling where it wasn't just a
hard step from red to black it wasn't
this right red there black here this is
Texel art right this is bilinear
filtering so we want that hard step to
actually appear right so what most games
new and what children of mordor does if
they just turn it off right
so they take bilinear filtering and they
just turn it off they turn off MIT
mapping as well but that's a separate
thing we could timeout a second turning
off by linear means now there's no
filtering no filtering whatsoever right
so what happens in this case once you
turn off bilinear filtering well if you
turn off bilinear filtering that what
happens is it just picks the nearest
neighbor it means this will probably be
red because it looks like the center is
maybe on the red side right and this
will definitely be black problem solved
right problem is not solved not by a
long shot
why isn't the problem solved well the
problem is these pixels along the edge
turning off by linear does make this get
the correct result which is solid red it
does not make this get this
result why because there is now no
sub-pixel sampling now you could just
turn on some kind of over sampling on
your whole screen and solve the problem
that way but we can do much better let's
take a look at what's going on all right
so here's my pixel grid I should add two
to Milton because it's open-source I
believe I should add something to Milton
that allows me to just drop down a
rectangular grid anyone who wants to do
something cool add a tool to Milton
allows you just drag a rectangle grid
right it would be so useful like
rectangle grid and lines and stuff if
there were quick hotkeys you could just
hold down a hotkey draw a thing and it
draws a grid or something and then goes
back to regular pen mode so good right
so good anyway so here's what's gonna
happen
I've got this pixel Texel art right and
the problem that we have is it's not
going to it's not going to stay in one
place if it was it would probably be
okay but what's gonna happen is the
camera and the objects are moving very
smoothly through the world they're
moving at very high resolution higher
than the pixel grid through the world
and so what happens is they end up in
places that are at sub pixel locations
on the grid so for example let's take a
look at what happens right here
there and then I'm gonna draw another
one that's what happens when it's
perfectly aligned
so I'm flitting this to two places
you'll have to apologize I have to
apologize for my terrible pixel grid
right turn off by linear sampling and
then look at what happens when I'm
exactly aligned to the pixel right and I
get exactly my Texel art back this is
what you know you wanted and it happened
but shift it a half pixel over and all
of a sudden were in a really really bad
state this is exactly a half pixel over
then I'm probably going to be outside
the pixel center here because of the
rounding rule so it's gonna happen is
this is gonna not have anything right
this if you look at which ones we're
picking up here so I look at what this
actually looks like right and it looks
like something like this as I overlay it
right so if I were to actually fill this
in this is the part of the of the thing
that's filled in at a half pixel offset
right and so what happens at the half
pixel offset exactly at the half pixel
offset right is that I jump from having
my sample like this sample right here
would probably go this way and this
sample would go this way I now feel at
the half pixel right I feel one movement
to the right so as this thing is sliding
over separately at 0.5 offset right half
a pixel I jump one just immediately jump
one right and at 0.0 I'm on the previous
one right so at point five I would jump
I would then travel another entire the
next time that would happen would be at
one point five right because that one I
still then I'm aligned with the grid
again so I'm still here and then at 0.5
I jump onto the side right now if we
just turned off bilinear and then we're
totally pixel aligned all the time here
but just moving around sub-pixel that's
what you would see you would see just
shift you know and slowly jerk the
pixels around right you would just see
the pixels roll that's not too
objectionable it's better than what's
happening in children of morta because
I'll talk about that the next step now
that makes things look really bad right
but it's still not great because it
means that I see this for the entire
time right I see that for the entire
time right up till I hit point five and
then it slaps over one so what I would
rather have done is when we're sampling
this pixel I would have rather pretended
that I actually had more resolution and
say let's take the blend inside this
pixel right let's take the blend and say
let me sample between these two in the
way that I would have for bilinear and i
would have gotten a better result here
right as it slid i would have seen this
pixel get darker and this pixel get
brighter and it would have appeared that
the thing would would slide slowly
across right okay so hopefully that
makes some sense if i now go to the case
of children amorta which is the bad case
what we actually have is something much
worse and that same sort of jumping at
point 5s becomes a really objectionable
artifact what we actually have is the
textile art is much larger but not by an
even factor so what happens skin does
this we've got a zooming camera right so
there's a continuous change of size
relative to the pixel grid on the screen
so if here are my pixels what I actually
end up with is I actually end up with
this pixel art here that I drew before
mapping to something totally unaware
so now what happens is I get something
more like this
trying to actually count this in some
way that I can draw it reasonably again
those pixel grid somebody add that to
Milton Milton please it would be so good
okay
so now what you can see is the true
problem that we're seeing why we're
seeing all these sort of weird like it
looks like things are kind of made out
of jell-o and they mush together as the
camera pans and stuff the problem comes
when a single Texel which we're trying
to enlarge and this is even not as
they're much larger like on children
Morda they probably take up several
pixels right they're probably more like
you know that big or something but just
for sake of easy illustration here what
ends up happening is a single Texel
actually maps to multiple pixels but as
this Texel slides what you can see is it
and you can see this just in the fact
that I've got two of them already these
are both the same size but this one
occupies at least like you know several
texels here this one's like four by four
right but this one because of how the
grids happen to a line only maps to one
right so instead of being too wide and
too tall which is what my first Texel is
this one's only one wide and one tall
right as it moves across it will
constantly alternate between those two
as this slides into position here it
will become too wide and then as it
slides out of position here again it
will go back to one wide so as it slides
across all your sprites go to wide line
one wide line to wide line one line line
to line line one and you get this like
rubber bear right and that's happening
at two dimensions at once so you're
getting this weird like fractured thing
as it moves through the world again no
reason for this to happen all we have to
do is recognize that we're just trying
to do sub-pixel rendering again
with something that is Texel art okay so
all we want to do is when we sample
these pixels we just look is the entire
pixel covered by the Texel art of one
texel if it is don't bilinear blend cuz
that's the thing that gives us the
artifacts that we don't want right so
for it because for example let's suppose
we took a look at what should happen on
this Texel here if we just turn on
bilinear filtering we would get a nasty
smear we would get a smear of like 75%
of this thing we don't want that what we
want is a smear of only the percentage
coverage that that Texel is on this
pixel which is not what we would get
right because remember if we look at
this in 1d we want this right and if
these are our pixels okay we don't want
that line this is this right here this
line that's by linear filtering or in
this case just linear filtering because
we're looking at it in one dimension
right and this is what we wanted turning
off all filtering means that you simply
pick either the min value or the max
value right either the Texel that's
filled or the Texel next to it right you
know either this or this I get one of
the other right turning a linear
filtering means I sample the line
between them I want neither what I want
is this pixel to pick this value this
pixel to pick this value so I don't want
the line at all and I don't want any
filtering on those and then when I'm in
between instead of sampling the line at
the center point of the pixel which is
what linear filtering would do I instead
want to say how much of the pixel is
covered so I want to know what is this
percentage what percentage of the pixel
is covered by this thing makes sense
that's what we're trying to do now the
easiest way to do that and the way
that's the least efficient is just spam
a ton of samples right so let's say we
turn off linear filtering so we're not
sampling the line anymore just sample a
ton of samples and average them together
right that way I'll get you know let's
say I go sample 16 samples on this thing
all 16 will come back with this color
exactly results I wanted most will come
back with the color but some will come
with the with the neighboring color so
you know maybe it's you know something
like 12 and 4 again exactly what I want
a Burrage those together as it slides
through it gets darker as you go by the
samples right and then finally here I
get all this color so if I want to do
what is basically a you know some kind
of a grid let's say I did this would be
way too many samples but let's say did 8
by 8 right that's 64 samples way too
many samples oh well so if I did an 8x8
grid of samples in my pixel so I just
like you know sample 8x8 let me actually
draw it for you so if I actually do 8 by
8 samples right if I actually do 64
samples inside my pixel with the correct
offset on the pixel average those
results together that gives me a 64
shade right sample right which is not
great but it's a lot better than not
doing it so that's one thing to do you
could crank those up to 256 samples if
you want to again really getting very
expensive for the graphics card so you
don't want to do this but then that
would give you a full two and a six
shade sample but only 16 in either
direction right so that means you would
still see a 16 step stare as the thing
moves from one to the other which is not
as good right but it's probably the best
we can do if we have to inject ourselves
into somebody's pipeline right now
how would we do this really well so that
it's both basically free almost and
perfect right how do we do this well if
we're in control of the pipeline if we
write this game right then it's really
easy for us to solve this problem
because all we do is leave linear
filtering turned on because bilinear
filtering does exactly what we want it
blends the two colors from the two
neighboring texels the only problem is
it doesn't blend them at the right ratio
right
what's linear filtering what is it
right well linear filtering is pretty
simple it's just computing some blend
coefficient right and it's saying one
minus the blend coefficient times color
zero plus the blend coefficient times
color one this is the entire code this
is the entire thing right if this is my
blend coefficient right that's exactly
what we want remember if I was to take a
huge number of samples a million samples
one billion trillion samples inside my
pixel right and then I averaged all the
samples together what do I know about
that result well all of the samples are
coming from in between to some texels on
my texture map if this is my texture map
this pixel maps to something in here
that is only because I remember this is
pixel art it's big it's blocky right
it's coming from for total samples
there's only four total texture places
to sample from for any given pixel a lot
of times there might only be two or
something right if it's if it's like
that pixel there or something right so I
know that my entire thing comes down to
one bilinear sample and no matter how
many samples I took took I'm always
hitting one of these colors right
so for bilinear right we're talking
about two of these it's U and V right so
for bilinear i've got u equals my
horrors on
coefficient and V equals my vertical
coefficient right and so all I need to
know is that if I was going to apply by
law you're sampling right which by
linear sampling is just saying all right
I want to do linear sampling I want to
do it on four things at once so here's
my color zero here's my color one here's
my Clara - here's my color three right
I'm just gonna blend between two of them
first and then blend between the results
of those right how do I do that will I
say okay 1 minus u times C 0 plus u
times C 1 that's the linear blend it's
blending smoothly as you goes from 0 to
1 it blends between 0 0 and Z 1 in a
linear fashion right
just a regular straightforward fade I
would do the same thing with C 2 and C 3
these are my two intermediate colors
right so this is like essentially
creating to intermediate blended colors
I'll call those b0 and b1 right and then
I make my by linear filter by filtering
those so I say 1 minus B times B 0 plus
V times B 1 and this is my final color
that's the pixel right or I should say
it's the output of the blend sample so
it's the sample right that's the texture
sample this is by linear filter
filtering if I multiply this out we can
see what happens right I've got an
equation here that's actually written in
terms of this these other equations
let's just fill it in I've got 1 minus V
times my B 0 which is 1 minus u times C
0 plus u times C 1 added to the same
exact thing right 1 - you should make
sure that's
get my using please confirm sorry
one minus V I always draw these poorly
and and you have to draw them well
because they look the same if you don't
one minus V times 1 minus u c0 plus you
see one added to V times the same
equation but with the other sees 1 minus
u c2 plus you see 3 ok what can you see
about this equation well if I was to
multiply it through it's very clear that
it becomes just four colors added with
four weights what are the weights what
just distributive property just like
boring highschool math right it's
actually free huh yeah junior high
school math really right I multiply this
through 1 minus 3 times 1 times u that
becomes my C 0 coefficient 1 minus V
plus 1 minus V times you see one that's
my C 1 coefficient V 1 minus u times C -
that's my C 2 coefficient and then V U
is my C 3 coefficient right right these
are all just constants they're just
values that are two scalars multiplied
together
so really I could just say alright I've
got a blend value it's equal to that
times C 0 plus another blend value right
it's equal to that times C 1 plus
another blend value times C 2 it's that
one that one right and finally a third
blend value times 2 3 ok this is the
final equation for a bilinear sample
that bilinear sample is computed by
using this exact kind of math the 1
minus v1 minus U you know that linear
plan on the graphics card by using the
UV coordinates of the texture that you
sample right when I actually go to
sample from that texture like that one I
had right this was the texture we were
talking about before
oops suddenly I had an extra row in
there pretend that doesn't exist um when
I go to sample from my texture where do
these blend coefficients come from well
wherever I'm gonna sample right is given
to me and I probably should have you
know I used UV here because that's how
you normally write a bilinear blend it's
gonna be a little confusing because you
also have UV coordinates for your
texture I'm gonna call those UV
coordinates something a little bit
different so I'm gonna say like the UV
coordinates which are something a little
bit different right the UV coordinates
I'm gonna call those something else for
now right I'm gonna call those like a
comma B or something right so that's the
coordinates into the texture that I'm
sampling wherever I'm sampling let's say
it's right here in my texture uh
depending on how the texture sampling is
going to compute those UV coordinates
I believe it usually does them protect
from Texel sam Texel centers but i'd
have to go back and you have to actually
go back and look at the exact math every
time because I always forget exactly how
God starts used to implement Ghatak
starts don't sample textures the way I
would have sampled textures so it's
always a mental shift especially
mipmapping doesn't work the way I would
have done it so it's it's always I got
to go back and rember wait how did they
decide to do it in graphs codes again
and then go oh I don't like that but
anyway point being it's going to have
some reference where if you sampled at
that reference point you would get
exactly zero for u and V right so this
point in the center of the textile let's
say is exactly zero zero for the U and V
in the above equations what that means
is one minus U is always 1 and U is
always zero right what would happen
to my equation in that case well this is
zero so you don't get I'm sorry this is
1 because it's 1 times 1 right this is 0
because there's a u in it which is 0
this is 0 because there's a V in it
which is 0 and this is 0 because of V
and EU in it so it's 0 that means we
would just have color 0 that's the
center of the Texel it's when you're
specifically sampling it directly and
even with bilinear filtering turned on
you get the exact result of just that
texture color it's gonna be important
later remember that right anywhere else
inside this rectangle sample I'm going
to actually have different values let's
say it's right here where it's 0.5 0.5
right would be the U and V you can see
how it does it if I map into the textile
grid and I say how far am i from the
closest floor right the closest textile
I would floor to so anywhere in this in
this square of sampling I go to the min
value the minimum integer value of
sampling I could do to my textile right
where is that thing and then how far
away am i from it right so here would be
point 5 point 5 because I'm halfway in
both U and V to the next textile center
right well then all of these values
would get a value and what value do they
get the same value 0.5 1 minus 0.5 1
minus point five that's 0.5 times point
5 so at 0.25 0.25 0.25 0.25 it's the
average of all the colors right - I'm
saying so on and so forth I know how the
graphics card will do this right it will
map the UV coordinates in exactly this
way it will take the floor
step one you'll take the place where
it's at
it'll floor it to the closest tough
Texel step to find the offset right
that's saying okay I floored to this
zero zero here how far away from my
front from it Oh point five point five
right so you V equals that offset step
three
compute blend coefficients and step four
blend right so I know that I can't
control these two but I can control
these two because when I pass in my UV
value it's whatever I say it is this is
this is the world of programmable
graphics hardware that sampler it's
going to get exactly the UV coordinates
that I tell it right so the only thing
you have to do if you want perfect
pixels sampling smooth sub-pixel
rendering on your pixel art games with
no smearing just perfect textile
filtering right all you have to do is
recognize the fact that you can
precondition your UV coordinates in the
pixel sampler this is it please for the
love of God if anyone at Unity ever
watches this thing add it to your engine
I place so many unity 2d games that just
hurt my eyes make this a check box for
the love of God make it a check box
please I don't know how to beg you
enough whoever is out there
unity devs just add some proper sampling
to your 2d stuff I mean how hard I can't
be that hard there's so many there's
more 2d game ship than unity than 3d
games probably just just please but
anyway so
all you need to do is precondition your
UV coordinates right let's go back and
just take it one dimension at a time
because we can actually do this on both
dimensions separately we don't need to
take into account the 2d nature of it at
all right so again looking back at it in
one dimensions in one dimensions that's
good in one dimension I I guess I don't
even have to do in one dimension I know
that the linear filtering will basically
say it's going to compute some T value
right and that T value is going to be
the floored offset in texture space
right so I'm looking at something like
this here's a 1d representation of just
one dimension of my texture right so
it's just one row of texels in fact let
me just draw it that way to make it
simple one row of texels you know I've
got some different things in here
different colors right this is my pixel
art I know what's going to happen is
whatever coordinate I pass in on the
number line here's my one dimension
right whatever number I pass in on the
number line and I can use using v's now
because I'll use T as the blend so we'll
say U is the incoming you coordinate T
will be the Florida the T will be the
blend coefficient so I'm gonna pass in
AU coordinate that you coordinate is
somewhere like this right that's the new
coordinate right I know it's going to
take the span between the two texels
it's gonna figure out where this is and
it's going to produce a T value based on
that so it's gonna floor and then
produce the offset and that's my T value
then it's gonna do 1 minus T times the
pixel on this side right let's see 0
plus T times the pixel on the other side
right this is the blend I need it to do
but it's using the wrong T value it's
using that smearing T value so I don't
get good for pixel art it looks ugly it
looks like it's all fuzzy right I don't
want that
all I want is some pixel correction so
that at the place where the pixel art
actually goes from one block to another
block I get it nice and smoothly sampled
as if I had really good anti-aliasing on
right okay so how do I do that well all
I have to do is say where does this
pixel fall in texture space right
because remember in my pixel shader now
I'm talking about rendering a pixel that
land somewhere in texture space most of
the time because this is pixel art so
it's bigger than the resolution in the
screen most the time most of the time
I'm a small span like this sampling only
one pixel so what I want to do is
basically have effectively what amounts
to an if in my shader although it can
also be done as non if but what I want
to do is say if I'm in one will probably
do it as like clamps and stuff is all
I'm saying
but if I the pixel is entirely contained
right so the first step is if the pixel
is entirely contained within one texel
right because I know that I know that
answer if the pixel is entirely
contained then floor myself right just
do the floor myself so in the pixel
shader I will adjust my you coordinate
tool and exactly at the pixel center so
in this case I'll adjust it so it's
exactly here right so I know for example
if this thing was 256 pixels or sorry
texels right if I know my texture is 256
texels wide let's say then I know that I
want to floor to exactly you know
stepping in by from 0 to 1 to 2 right I
want to do two times one over 256 right
Plus that 0.5 offset you know I'm saying
so it's actually sorry 2 plus 0.5 times
one over 256 right so I just get 2.5
over 256 that is the exact location that
I want to be for sampling that second
Texel exactly even in linear blending
mode because I'm right in the center
right so I'll get exactly the right
result so if the pixel is entirely
contained I do the exact flooring that
the texture sampler is going to do
anyway so that when it does the floor it
gets the same answer and the offsets
zero that makes the linear go away it
gives me back entirely see zero and I'm
done right so how would I do that how
would I make that happen
right well it's pretty simple I know
what my incoming UV coordinates are and
I can pretty trivially produce this
number from them knowing the width of
the texture which I always do because
it's actually just provided in modern
samplers you know what the width of the
texture is but even if you didn't you
could send it down as part of either the
vertex data or the constants tour so
it's pretty easy to just get that
information in even if you didn't have
it readily available from a texture but
you do right so when we look at this and
we say all right we need to do this
first step of the process we need to be
able to do a route where we're actually
going to clamp sort of a floor this this
sample to exactly what it is all we have
to do is produce these values and this
you know I won't go over the most
optimal to do it cuz I have to sit here
and actually work it through but you can
imagine just doing it the reverse way
the the most simpler way to do it is
just an ample element to emulate exactly
what the texture sample is gonna do I
get a u value I know my I know my
texture riff so let's say I have a w
value that's the width of my texture and
an H value right and maybe I'll be more
specific about those so I'll say we have
a texture with it's a little bit bad
because I wanted to be my blend so maybe
we'll do something a little bit
can I change this well I I need more
values here because I don't want to step
on my own toes so I want the texture
width and height here so I'm gonna do it
this way WT height T for width and
height the texture and we'll just call
it that so let's start we come in here
we have au coordinate this is the actual
you coordinate that comes in from the
vertex shader right and that's where we
would be sampling and we've got bilinear
turned on so if we just let that flew
through and we sample right we're just
gonna get a smear that's gonna be ugly
so first step multiply out by the width
where are we right so the first thing
you want to do is find out where we are
in actual Texel space so it's basically
like our exposition in the texture right
that's gonna be u times that width okay
so that goes from something that looks
like just a random you coordinate like
you know Oh point you know oh one two
five blah blah blah it's something that
we can actually use like oh it's two
point seven right so that's two pixels
in and then point seven of the way to
the next pixel right okay makes sense
and so then I can also if I want to I
can think about this a little bit more
broadly and say well that's where I'm
actually sampling but I really would
like to know more specifically right I
really would like to know the span of
the sample because this doesn't really
tell me that so what I'd like to do is
know what the minimum and maximum values
actually are for my sample remember I
want to know if I'm completely covered
so here and here right I've got those
I've got those two points I want to know
how much of that span falls within the
pixel so just taking the center point
which is here isn't that useful for me
I'd rather have the min/max
right so what I need in addition is
something that you actually get you get
texture gradients which are basically
like
d u DX and DV DX you get these in the
shaders and what they say is if I was to
step one pixel right if I was to SEP 24
word or one pixel back
how much would my U value change so
really what I want to do is do something
a little bit more broadly what I want to
do is make a Yuman value right u min is
gonna be stepping a half pixel backwards
and a half pixel forwards right so what
I wanted to say u plus like you know 0.5
D u DX I'm sorry I mean minus minus 0.5
T u DX right and u max is going to be
equal to u plus 0.5 D u DX right and
then I can do an X min x max so my X min
is going to be my human x WT and my x
max is going to be my u max times WT and
this gives me the exact span so it would
say something like oh we are sampling
from two point five to two point you
know nine right that's where we're
sampling so now if you actually wanted
to implement implement it with an if
statement you just could you'd say if
you know floor or round doesn't matter
which one you use here if floor of X min
equals floor of X Max then we want to
set our u value to actually be the floor
right and we'll talk about what that
computation is it's really simple right
now that we have this it's literally
just take this value here this u WT all
we really wanted to do is floor that
value so you would literally just do the
floor of u WT / the texture with to map
it back into texture coordinate space
right
makes sense so if you actually wanted to
do it with an if you just could so let's
pretend we did that then all we need
here to finish is just our else we need
to know what to do when we're not in the
same Texel right so now what we have is
some kind of information about where we
actually fall in the range of textures
right so what we're gonna have here is
something that doesn't look like 2.5 to
2.9 maybe it looks like something like
2.6 to 3.1 right something like that
makes sense and so you know as opposed
to sampling direct a sampling only
inside that that one texel there that
second Texel we're sampling a little bit
of the third Texel but you can see here
we're still mostly in this one so we
want to do the computation that figures
out exactly how much of each of them we
want to sample well what is the actual
value that we're looking for here well
you can kind of see how we would
construct it if we were to floor this
thing to the correct 2.5 there right and
I should I should add that we want to be
I kind of left out a step here we
actually want this thing to be looking
at how it is arranged around the point
fives so we actually when we're in here
I probably shouldn't have written it
this way because we don't have a good
way of flooring to 0.5 so what we want
to do is do the adjustment that makes us
actually be around the pixel centers
anyway right so what we want to do is
actually add in here probably this bias
right that centers us around the pixel
the Texel centers so we don't have to
worry we can actually just use floor so
we probably want it to look like this
and then what we're looking at here is
not is what I was saying here was more
accurate right when we're entirely
inside too as our first thing we're fine
right and so when we're inside here now
we're looking at saying that spans
make sense okay so if we wanted to know
what the difference is here right how
much we should blend between these two
values well if you look at what we're
getting for sampling we can compute the
exact coverage
how much is in one texel how much is in
the other how do we do that well take
the max and floor it right so we can
just say whatever this value is here
this is our U max value whatever are you
up sorry our x max value whatever our x
max value is if we take our x max value
and floor it right that would give us
our three we then know the amount that's
in the other the the three Texel is just
going to be however far the max was away
from that right so we would say the x
max value minus that floor value right
that's going to be equal to the point
one that we had and then on the other
side we know the opposite is also true
the floor value minus the x max value
I'm sorry minus the X min value this
value here right that's going to be
equal to how much is in that one and so
that would be point four right we then
know that if we set up the ratio between
these two we know how to blend between
them we want point one of this one and
point four of that one right makes sense
so in order to figure out where to
sample this thing we know that we just
need to sample it at a point one two
point four ratio which we should be able
to normalize out so I'll crank the math
here but again not so good with with
grinding math on on stream it's kind of
tough to do I'm not good at granny math
anyway but point being so we just need
to know how we would normalize this out
and how would you do that so if you have
a point one point four and you want
these things to sum to one right I want
to do a total blend so I want these
things to sum to one again
Euclidean 1-norm we've talked about on
handmade here I'll look it up if we
don't know what it is look at norms on
handmade here we can talk about it more
but what we knew about the Euclidean 1
norm if we want our blend coefficients
to sum to 1 which we do we need to
normalize by the 1 norm what do you do
for that add up all the values and
divide right very very simple it's very
much like the Qt and 2 norm where you
add the squared values square root and
divide this is Euclidean 1 norm it's for
summing to 1 rather than having a length
of 1 in space so you can just briefly
touch on that that's what the norms are
all right so if we add these up what we
get is x max minus F plus X I'm going to
do that littler X max minus F plus F
minus X min now do you see something
interesting about this ahrefs cancel
right and we just get x max minus X min
okay so if I want to sum up these values
the F is just kind of sitting there so
it goes away drops out of that part of
the term now I said I needed to divide
to find out what I actually wanted my
answer to be right so if I want to
divide to get my T value right to get a
value that smoothly blends between them
and remember for a T value this value is
always going to be 1 minus whatever the
other value is once I make them sum to 1
so I can kind of ignore it I can just
use one of them let's say it's f minus X
min in this case then what I can say is
all right F minus X F minus x-min and
x-max was the floor that's going to give
us an equation that has an X min and x
max in it I don't really want to do that
necessarily so I think what I want to do
is equation with 2x Max's so I'm going
to pick this one which is actually the 1
minus value but that's okay so looking
at this if I said x max minus 4 of x max
right so I'm doing here
normalized
xmax minus X man makes sense
oh you know what I've got an x-men in
here anyway though and there's really no
way I'm getting around that so let's get
rid of that let me let me pretend friend
I never said that
let's just do this one the way I wanted
to originally so I have F minus X min
over X max nice x-men right and if we
take a look at what happens here this
right here is just floor x max so what
I've got is floor x max minus X min over
X max minus X man very very simple
equation that is the actual T value we
want to do for our blend which means if
we want the gravit start to do it all we
have to do is put it back into texture
space in the correct place now how would
we do that well we're gonna add right
back in our floor of X Max and then
we're gonna do our divide that means in
order to put this back into texture
space and there's a couple ways I could
have done it I wonder if I should have
done it instead by flooring x-men I
don't know that's kind of a that's kind
of an interesting question if I'm I
probably should have done it with floor
X min let's do that really quickly that
way as well again you know we've just
got this diagram basically you know I'm
saying and what we're doing is we're
saying well we've got a texture sample
that's going to come in here somewhere
let's say it comes in here right we know
that this is the center of the texels
this is that like 0.5 so this might be
like 1.5 this right here might be like
0.5 that would be like 2.5 right we know
we want a sample right here this value
right here is gonna be where we would
floor - and we're not flooring exactly
at 1.5 because we're shifting our pixel
grid over just a floor will work that's
basically all we're doing right if we
floored ex-movie floored - x max before
we Florida X min we can still do the
same computation right we can still
figure out how much is in each one of
these
pretty easily I think I don't think we
would have too much trouble looks like I
can't imagine why hmm because you don't
really even know which one you're
crossing anyway you're just trying to
figure out how much is on one side and
how much is on the other side of
whatever whatever bound for your
crossing and you know that each one is
in a different textile because otherwise
you would have you would have just not
hit that branch of the if right so
anyway if I was to do it with floor
x-men's who are producing this value
here right then all I really want to
know is how far is it from the floor
decks men to here right then from here
to here and then from here to here right
I'm trying to figure out what these two
spans right there look like and again if
you one of the reasons it's a little bit
better to floor to the xmax is I think
that always gives you the midline which
is a little bit easier to do but we
always know that this is point five away
from this so it's not really
particularly difficult I don't think to
work that math through either that's my
guess
so I don't know as I'm looking at it I
guess I don't know I guess it's not easy
that way so I'll just keep going with
what I was going alright so if this is
what we have here now what we want to do
since we have floor x max minus X min x
max minus X min this is our blend
coefficient remember that just gives us
the T value so it's a value that goes
from zero to one what we want to do now
is we've got this u value we want to
readjust our U value right our sample
value maybe was here or whatever right
we want to adjust that so that the
gravis card will do the correct bilinear
blend that computes how much pixel
coverage there was for this particular
for each side of the Texel the Texel on
this side and the Texel on this side of
our pixel boundary which is like
sampling bear or something
right so when we look at how we have to
do that what we want to do is first
create the u value in expanded space for
the x coordinate that we'd actually need
so our X sample right I'll just call
that XS right what we want to do is say
this is the T value this offset here is
basically telling us how
how much we want a sample away from our
x-men right so this X sample position is
going to be whatever our x-men was which
we know I'm sorry not our x-men it's
going to be however far off of the flow
of the texture sample for our floored
x-men right so our floored x-men here we
know we want to be that far forward from
it but since we already floored our xmax
we could also think of it as being how
far backwards from that we want right so
if we look at our floor x max which
we've already computed that's out here
we just want to say that floored x max
value we want to sample 1 minus this
value behind it right so we just want to
subtract 1 minus this expression here
again we only have to compute that floor
x max once
right so we know this is the equation we
actually want to compute for the
location we're going to sample we're
taking the pixel center of the far Texel
and we're moving backwards by the amount
we want to force the graphics card to
blend what does that end up being who
knows this this may be there may be some
sloppy math errors in here but you would
grind this through maybe use a computer
algebra system to help you but we're
going to want to multiply this out in
fact let me just start by mapping out
one minus this value that's gonna be
minus distribute to the one then a minus
tribute to this will cause us to be a
plus then we've got our four x max minus
X min over X max minus X min right this
is the actual equation now as it stands
if I want to start combining terms here
I could I would multiply through by x
max minus X min so that would give me a
floor x max times X max minus X min over
well the whole thing is going to be over
x max X min right minus one same thing
I'm sorry minus x max - my win like so
and then plus the remainder of the
equation for x max minus X min okay I so
what you can see here is we basically
have this big distribution to do now if
we look at what the actual values come
out to be we've got a minus X min in
here so we've got two of those right if
I start to group terms right this is a
minus two X min here I've got a minus x
max this will distribute out so
basically the floor x max it's going to
be floor x max times x max minus floor
x max times x min minus x max plus floor
x max minus 2x max right I've probably
already made so many math errors
this is one I would definitely want
computer algebra for but for what it's
worth so if you look at how this
actually works out these two x max is
also kind of coalesce and so we get
minus 2x max in here and 2 x max with
the floor x max so if we grouped all
those terms together we would actually
get I believe floor x max right if you
look at this we've got to don't we don't
remind that may be it so that may be it
for simplification that we can do there
that was a min not a max so that may be
all we can do for simplification by
multiplying out I don't really know that
we would want to necessarily do that
doesn't look particularly good I was
just looking to see if there's any
cancellation cuz this is pretty simple
to compute right here it's like very
very very it's it's a you know you
compute the floor once then you do a few
minuses and one divide
so it's pretty pretty strict it's pretty
straightforward there's not a lot to it
this would be our X sample value we
would then add the 0.5 offset back in
and divide by the texture width and we
be done right make sense now one of the
things that may be true is this may now
take care of our if for us as well so if
you look at what's going to happen if X
min and x max is 0 right it would be
nice if we could figure out a way to get
that into a multiply and we might
actually be able to do that I feel like
we should dig in a little bit further
here because if we did then we would be
able to just make that be a coefficient
which drops out to 0 right
so let's try and phrase this in terms of
a differential in some way
right let's try to make this something
that we just go ahead and add in a way
that will give us some kind of a
coefficient that we actually can use
that's not going to be a one over right
in this particular case so how would I
do that I think because there should be
a way to grind this math out
I would think having never looked at
this really before I think there's a
probably way that I could do this a
little bit more straightforward right
what I want to do here is basically say
is there a freight a change of reference
that I can do that just says how much is
the offset that I actually need to go
from my original you in order to get
there and if I was to assume that this
was correct then what I could do I
suppose is say we know my original you
write the original you value that I
started with is actually going to be a
value we know it's going to be X it's
going to be 0.5 times x max minus X min
right plus X min we know where it is
effectively right so if we were to
phrase the this as we want the
difference between this point and this
point right so we actually want our
sample value but to be that right I want
for X max minus 1 plus 4
xmax minus X manner plus X plus X men
probably what was it 4x X minus X man
over X max minus X Men right so the
total with x max minus X men also is
just one pixels size in texture space so
we kind of already know what that is as
well it's a pretty straightforward value
so you know now that I think about it we
don't really need to ever worry about
that because it's a known value X max
minus X min in this case is just one
pixel in texture space and is actually
just the D U value right so DX D u I'm
sorry D u DX in the pixel shader would
actually map directly to this so this
because that is one pixels wide because
we know that Max and min are one pixel
wide so really this doesn't exist this
is just a multiplication I'm sorry I
divide by the D you value that we get in
the pixel shader right so that's
actually quite simple
we know that floor x max minus one in
this case also so that we actually also
know that we actually also know right
because x max - floor x max minus one is
just moving us one texel backwards right
so that's always constant Florrick's
actually got in both places and the
x-men so really it's just it's just this
part
really it's just that part and if we got
that part it's just a sea move so really
you know I think there's probably a
subtler way to do this and maybe
tomorrow what we should do is dedicate a
stream just working out all the math
exactly but basically all you're doing
is just adjusting this value right you
can just probably see move that value
because this entire equation is just all
known stuff and so what you could do is
just say look set your X min to either
exactly B to either just be the offset
of from the from because your floor x
max right is is going to be the value
you want so actually you can just set
this to be zero in that if case so our
if is just X min right equals the actual
xmin we computed that's what we do yeah
it's pretty simple actually
where was that too much math so mm-hmm
this value here all we actually have to
do is say set this value to zero if this
is true right so it's just a C move
almost free right so all we do is say if
the floor of X main equals the floor of
X Max X min equals zero otherwise X min
stays the same then we compute this
equation and we're done right
then we get exact sampling in all cases
we do that for both ru and RV again not
it's a few multiplies and a div the divs
not great but it could be approximate I
don't know if we can get rid of it the
good news is it's constant across the
pixel shader for a particular texture so
actually we could set it this could be
set in the constant store and we
wouldn't actually do divide you could do
multiply right so again pretty simple
stuff if we actually work this out in
the pixel shader it's only if you know
it's it's a handful of instructions that
we would issue and it would solve all of
the sampling problems now there's a
little more you would want to do here if
you're going to MIT map but we're out of
time for today and in the case of
children of Morden most of what I'm
seeing is not MIT map errors it's it's
this so this needs to be fixed and again
it's in unity it's I guess it's unities
problem but before I leave I want to see
on the chat it looks like it looks like
it looks like we can set - force GL core
inside as a launch parameter for tank
potentially in children of morta and if
that's true we may be able to actually
edit the shader so before we end for the
day let's just try and see if we can do
that oops
okay
um so what I'm gonna do now is see if I
can add that as a launch parameter I
don't know that it would go here I may
have to go into steam and set it so I
may have to do I don't know that this
will work
so we'll try it but we may have to just
go into steam and set additional
parameters there we'll give it a shot
here and just see what happens
looks like that did work because
initialized graphics engine said it
failed so that suggests to me that that
that it did work but it didn't actually
help maybe GL core isn't supported
so I don't know it looks like that just
may not have gotten ship it may be
because there's no source code for the
shaders so it may be that they just pre
compiled them and they only exist free
compiled you know what I mean
but yeah so sadly not much we can really
do here I wish we could edit those those
shader parameters but it doesn't look
like we can if I pop back to two n site
here I'll do one more thing before we
stop oops
I'm gonna load up that children amorta
I'm gonna go ahead and try and launch
I'm gonna have to go through this little
dance here
there's that steam thunk I wonder if
there's a unity parameter to disable
scheme that would also help
so basically I'm just gonna go ahead and
try and capture a frame in and save it
out
[Music]
all right and so if we take a look here
all I want to do is get another one of
those frame captures in the mix and so
I'm going to pop back over here I'm
gonna try to do the attach like so and
looks like so okay I'm gonna capture for
a live analysis and let it kind of fail
a bit but it still does get us a frame
we can use weeks it seemed like it does
I'm then gonna go ahead and just save
out export C++ capture I don't know what
this will actually do and whether that
will let us actually do anything with it
but we'll we'll try and then I'm gonna
go ahead and and exit out of insight and
we'll just see I'm gonna go ahead and
also close my children amorta as well or
try to anyway don't seem to be able to
let's try it through here so what I
would like to do now is just take a
quick look at what that actually dumped
out because I don't know to what extent
that gives us anything we could use I
just wanted to see what that actually
puts in my directory here so here is
some C code it's got a big ol hunk of
binary data
[Music]
it looks like
unfortunately I want to say I don't
think it actually gave us something we
could really use because it doesn't have
the shaders in here I don't think yeah
so you can kind of see like I think what
they do is they just bundle all the
shaders up into this data bin file here
so they're probably in there along with
all of the actual data we could still go
ahead and try to intercept what that
shader was and then replace it with a
different one when it gets submitted the
problem with that is that's gonna take a
while for us to hunt down so I'm not
gonna do that today we could try doing
it tomorrow right
and and see how we go all right I'm
gonna go ahead and quickly go to Q&amp;A and
we'll just
someone says someone says here's a good
side-by-side sample of the artifacts are
talking about at shader toy okay that
would be nice
yeah that those are exactly the ones I'm
talking about you can see all that
shimmering there's no need for any of
that you can just it can just look
perfectly smooth and you would never
know that it was using filtering at all
it just you wouldn't see those
objectionable artifacts those shimmery
artifacts as it moves around and you
know what while we've got this here I
can I probably should in fact maybe this
is what we'll do tomorrow
if we just do it here we can fix it in
here instead and and then hopefully
maybe someone at unity will add it or
something it just it just sucks to play
so many games with this artifact for no
reason it's just it's just it's and it's
free once you work out the rest of the
math it's it's even simpler than what I
did because I just did the first path to
show you how to work out the math the
basic idea behind it but if you actually
sit down and have a whole day that you
spend looking at this you could probably
get it down to something incredibly
small right just like really really
really small if that makes sense alright
so what is this actually doing though
this is this is not this is doing
something slightly different because
this is not the same as turning off the
bilinear filtering which
so I'm a little confused this looks like
they're actually doing the update but
this looks shimmery to me so I'm super
confused
oh I see it's divided oh yeah okay so
that's the good version okay perfect
never mind yeah you're right
so they how do they do this in shader
toy I don't know shader toy very well
how are they making it so that it has
like two separate shaders one for each
side of the thing but yeah a perfect so
I guess I don't know why I was got too
carried away I was looking at it like it
looks like they're doing the fix-up so
here you can see the difference I mean
it's just not there's no reason you
would ever want to see this it's not an
aesthetic choice
it just looks wrong you always want the
one on the right side I mean that's what
you want and the right one is doing the
fix-up I was talking about it's not
quite doing it I don't think the same
way I would do it after working it
through but it's it's doing it right and
so this is just always wrong and this is
the what this is what happens like this
is what children amorta or generally
unity games do and you always want this
one because it's free it's it's really
no slower it's it's like slightly
there's a little more arithmetic in the
shader but very very little and
especially you saw that children of
mortis shader it was huge so we're
talking about a little tiny you know a
few additions here right
I don't so again I don't really know how
to use shader toy so I'm not sure I
understand how to have two sides screen
to other stuff I guess what they're
doing here probably is just looking at
which side of the screen you're on and
then picking one of those so it's
probably a selector in here somewhere
so yeah okay so it's right here so if I
dot X greater than center X that's
what's giving us that divide dividing
line right so if I wanted the whole
image to be right
I could I could do if the other way
around right this is what puts in the
black bar in the center I could make it
larger right um so now I can clear it
more clearly see it on the stream so the
EF statements doing that and and you
don't need so shader toy isn't doing a
thing there they that was just someone
doing it for illustration purposes so if
we look we're talking only about these
lines of code here that happened inside
the if these are prepping it and then
these are actually doing the fractional
offset there this is just adding the
black bar so if we got rid of it
it would still be exactly the same image
it's just now you can't see
why can't I delete that line that should
only be the black bar right what's the
problem oh because the else
so looking at this now we have just the
left side is still wrong I can remove
this right and now we just have the
proper way that you know a Unity game
would look if they have these if they
have the correct shaders and that just
looks so much nicer right so again like
looking at this you can see how simple
this is and it's you can see the floor
and you can see the clamping they're
going on so this has worked out it looks
like this has worked out pretty clean so
you can see if you do grind that master
you get a much better result than what
we stopped on because we still have the
if they're doing the if is the in this
clamp right here so you can just get it
into a clamp like I had sort of win-wins
whimsically stated so again very very
straightforward if we look in and see
what's going on here this stuff is just
because they need you know it's it's
shader toys have to build everything in
here so all of the motion and zooming
and stuff is sort of baked into these
lines of code so we don't really care
about those this is where you would this
is what you'd actually be doing inside
your shader and actually this part right
here is just preparing the texture
coordinates anyway so really we're
talking mostly about this right so in
here you can see the first step of the
process is we're taking wherever we
wanted to sample inside our texture and
we're flooring the the value again if
you look at this these are coming in in
in pix currents so you would have to
first multiply by the size of your
texture because that's baked in here you
can see in here this stuff is is baking
in that that pixel size so that's the
size that's that's the size of the
pixels in your texture how big you
wanted them to be right so they that
they baked that in there hmm so in here
what we want to do is say alright we've
got the UV coordinates we're flooring
where we're looking up and we're adding
that point five remember I said we
wanted to shift everything over so it
would floor down properly we're then
taking the UV coordinates and we're
doing again that sampling backwards from
the max here
so we're doing a minus of the clamp
that's the fractional value of J is the
X min minus X max I'm sorry the floor at
floor X minus X to get that fractional
value the scale value here is probably
just the how big you wanted things to be
yeah and then we're just gonna sample
normally right so so really everything
they're using for sampling is wrapped up
in here this isn't probably how you
would write it this is assuming some
stuff about the way you're sampling
textures that isn't as generic as you
would want I don't think she just they
didn't put rotation in here and I think
this is kind of I guess you could do it
this way with rotation still but we
should probably write a shader toy that
does the correct thing with just a
regular texture sampling rather than
moving it in like this but either way
children of amor looks like a fairly
ambitious game why do you think they
didn't bother to implement proper prefix
of rendering again because that's not
their job the reason they license unity
is it supposed to be the graphics engine
right so they probably don't have a
bunch of expert graphics programmers on
the children of morta team that's if
they did they would have written their
own engine potentially right so I kind
of feel like that's the problem it's not
really children of mortis fault it's
unities fault how do you learn about
this artifact how do you figure out the
cause well it's just it's not really a
new artifact it's the same artifact we
always have which is sub-pixel rendering
and the old days games didn't have the
horsepower to sub-pixel rendering that's
why you go look at really early games
and they're very crispy as thing moves
around you get all those artifacts but
as we've gotten more understanding of
how graphics works and we have more
horsepower we generally think about
things from the perspective of subjects
surrendering so this is just basic
sub-pixel rendering that's all it is
oh wow this Tori's by D seven
samurai Thank You D seven Thanks for
writing it
someone posted a link before saying
unity has a pixel perfect 2d package so
what is that
[Music]
so I can't tell if this actually helps
though this sounds more like it just
snaps sprites to the nearest pixel
coordinate which is not would not help
you right because you're trying to get
smooth motion of the sprites and you're
not going to get that right so I don't
know I don't use your use I couldn't
tell you but it's not clear from the
explanation here whether this would
actually do what we're talking about or
not
and you know what this is totally wrong
yes so this is this is nothing like what
we're talking about so and and this is
ridiculous I don't know why you'd ever
do this that doesn't even make any sense
so no that that's not that's not
relevant at all
is any extra work required for oblique
viewing no because this is all in
texture space right so it has nothing to
do with whether it's rotated or scaled
or moved or anything it's just how you
sample a texture if you want the texture
to be a step function instead of a
linear function right but everything
else just works so all you're trying to
do is do the step function and off you
go
right how is pal function implemented
how would you go about implementing an
efficient power function all of those
tend to just be basically fit you always
just fit some kind of like a you know
Taylor series or pal function you know
modern modern numerical programming is
probably Taylor series it's like old
news
so you just fit you fit quadrat you fit
not quadratics you fit equations to the
power function and you evaluate those
equations iterally till you iteratively
to you get the desired bit precision
that's how all of that stuff works how
sine and cosine works you know you could
look
isn't it called sleeve you can just look
at a generic you know math library out
somewhere out there that's set up for
this sort of thing
and you can go ahead and look at sort of
roughly the way they're doing it it's
not very it doesn't really explain much
how it's actually working I so I do
apologize for that but here you go so if
you look at how these things tend to be
implemented you can see that generally
speaking they've got some fit function
here so for example here this is the
thing that actually does the work so
every numerical function because
remember these libraries have to in
these libraries have to implement proper
handling of these functions they can't
just poop it out so they've got to look
for things like infinities and Mane's
and stuff so basically what you'll have
is you'll see something like this this
is the preconditioning then it will call
something that is basically like a
series of its basic functions so in this
case it uses an ABS a log a mall and an
X to implement it and here is an example
of one of the implementations so here is
an XP k2f and what you can see is it's
just a series expansion
so somebody fit some series to this
thing and they basically just do a bunch
of like FS or f mads or whatever you're
going to do multiplications that's all
anyone ever does that I've ever seen so
basically the process is you take the
function you're trying to simulate like
POW or anything else you figure out what
range you care about it you can put in a
bunch of things to try and like cabin
the range and precondition the number
and handle infinities if you want that
stuff but if you're just using something
where you know your inputs pretty
intimately you then fit that range to a
function somehow right and sometimes you
have to do that by breaking it into
multiple steps like multiple functions
sometimes you can just do it directly
then you compute that approximated
function and that's your result
and that's it you can see here there's
typically stuff where you do use the
exponent and the mantissa separately
that's a very common technique as well
because sometimes you can compute stuff
on just the mantissa and then do you
don't have to worry about thick problems
that have to do with where the exponent
is and so on so yeah there's a lot of
stuff like that but that's all anyone
ever does and sleep I think is a you
know I doubt it's particularly great or
anything but it's a pretty easy place to
go I think it's pretty open licensed
so basically you just have to provide a
slight notice that you used it is it
right so you know you can you can cut
and paste code from here and go nuts if
you want to
so for sine or for cosine and sine yet
some point I'd like to replace them I
just haven't gotten around to it yet
the problem is sine and cosine or power
any of those things is questions about
like should we use a table lookup or
should we do whatever I have no idea I
don't spend a lot of time working on
these sorts of numerical replacement
sort of stuff possibly right I have like
a hair in my face probably Molly here so
I really just don't know off the top of
my head whether it's better or worse to
use tables in the case of sine or cosine
what I will say is that often times
table driving and algorithm in this day
and age is made is oftentimes not what
you want not because there's some really
bad thing about looking up stuff in a
table because if it's a small table and
you're doing a lot of it the cash
probably has your back you know so small
tables are very fast the problem is you
cannot do wide operations if you are
using a table lookup right because up
until avx-512 which is barely in any
processors right now you cannot do for
wide table lookups so what happens is if
you actually try the table drive
something if you try to do if you're
trying to do is four or eight wide Cindy
tables become extraordinarily expensive
because all of the elements have to be
extracted from their lanes you then have
to do all the lookups and then you do
four separate loads and a packs to get
them back into lanes that can then be
used so table driving is pretty rough
these days and you know the hope I think
and I mean I guess I don't know
can't speak for everybody but the hope
would be that someday when avx-512 maybe
is more prevalent that penalty would go
away so if you have Lane based gather
then all of a sudden there wouldn't be a
penalty anymore for table driving and so
you know what I'm saying so I feel like
table driving at the moment is actually
very difficult to do and make it run
fast if you have to be wide right so I
doubt we would do our sine and cosine
with the table because we probably want
to be able to do four at a time that's
that's just my my feeling on it so most
of these math functions I don't really
like table driving them for that for
only that reason so if you can get away
with not table driving it in this day
and age it's usually a benefit not for
the reason people say because a lot of
people say don't table drive things
because the memory cost is high it's
probably not that's probably a lie
what's not a lie is that if you have to
be wide you're in trouble
long bullion says is there ever a reason
not to compute your pixels this way is
this a 2t only thing so you only want to
do this if the original function was
supposed to be a bunch of little squares
right if the original function is
supposed to be samples of a continuous
image then bilinear filtering is
actually more correct as an up sampler
so actually the default bilinear
sampling is what you want most of the
time right but when you're dealing with
pixel art it's this unique case where
the art itself is supposed to be made up
of tiny little squares and at that point
the sampling you want is very different
than bilinear filtering it seems that
this artifact is quite well known at
least in your circle is there a name for
it I don't have a name for it I don't
know if there is a name for it let's
make up a name for it let's call it so
since it's it's like all unity games
seem to have this artifact all the time
I'm going to call it the unity artifact
or Yuna fact so we'll call this u n--
effect this is a unit factor
actually maybe it shouldn't because
you're gonna say this something artifact
so maybe it should be the unity pixel
art artifact or u part artifact or I
guess we wouldn't put the artifact on I
need a pixel art so be the unit pics
Yuna picks artifact that'd be right
so that's going to be the name we're
gonna say that something looks unit pick
see if it's kind of like doing that
shimmering
nikka cite media the shader can only
address artifacting within the texture
but cannot address sub pixel occlusion
artifacting ie the shimmer is still
present exterior edge pixels that is not
true it actually addresses it everywhere
so what happens is when you create your
when your when you create your textures
and you saw us do this on handmade hero
when you create your textures you leave
a one pixel wide border around the
texture that is completely blank
so it's alpha zero everywhere then what
happens is when you are sampling there
you get the correct alpha coverage value
out from your sample and you do it there
is no shimmering so so it is 100%
correct everywhere even on border pixels
Brian is asking I was surprised to see
how much latency was on division square
root seems to have a similar latency but
reciprocal square root is as quick as
multiplied with just half the throughput
why is reciprocal square root square
root much faster than a regular square
root the answer is because they're at
different levels of precision just give
you a little bit more information about
that so here is square root and what you
can see here is there's no
qualifications in the statement here so
when Intel says they compute the square
root of packs of packed single precision
three two bit floating-point elements in
a what they mean is they're actually
computing the whole square root so the
mantissa is accurate out to like the
last bit possibly even with a additional
bit of rounding precision built in there
so it's a pretty precise answer as far
as can be ascertained so if we look at
reciprocal square root what you can see
is there's a very specific disclaimer
you can see here that actually it
doesn't guarantee that it's producing an
accurate result even as far as the
thirteenth bit of the mantissa now
there's 24 bits in a mantissa so it's
actually a significant number of the
trailing bits of the value are wrong or
possibly wrong and so you know you can
be faster if you're less accurate and
that's exactly what they've done here
they're giving you a really fast
basically a really fast approximate
reciprocal square root not an exact
value and hence it takes less time
because there aren't there probably in
the actual thing that produces the
actual square root there's probably a
bunch of stuff in there that's actually
that's doing like refining like it's
taking multiple steps to refine the
value or something right so this is like
the minim
quick and dirty version of computing a
square root and specifically one over a
square root whereas the square root
functions actually doing the whole
square root all the way out till you run
out of bits is there a less precise
version of square root then yes it's
called R square the reason that they
chose this breakdown is because
typically speaking if you're looking for
fast and dirty oftentimes the the thing
you're going to do with the square root
immediately after you take it is take
its reciprocal so that's why it computes
the reciprocal of the square root
instead of the square root because if
you're looking for quick and dirty
reciprocal square root is actually
probably what you want cuz you're
probably normalizing something using the
Euclidean to norm right
should you son do something similar
inspection with some ue4 game and the
engine we're for good I don't know if
there is an engine war I mean people get
very there's very different reasons why
you would use unity your unreal or
something right
unity should just fix this problem I
don't think it they should just do this
sampling properly I feel like they
should be able to put in something that
can do that
there's a lot of graphics programmers at
Unity I don't know why they haven't
fixed that
so the artifacting is still present here
is because there's no border pixel what
artifacting are you talking about I
don't see any artifacting here
so what artifact are you talking about
Giga sight media there is one other
place you can get edge artifacting by
the way but it's not really on edges per
se it's on neighboring pixels with a
high difference between them and that's
if you have gamma or perceptual gamma
problems with the blend so technically
you need to be gamma aware when you're
actually doing this work if you really
want it to be correct but you know I'm
not seeing any artifacts in this one
right now
maybe you can perceive a little bit of a
little tiny blur on the edge once in a
while but I can't really barely see it
at all
but what I would say is yet like you do
have to be careful about gamma at the
edges when you're doing your all of your
work and this shader toy isn't so it's
possible that even that bit would be
fixed but that is not an edge pixels
that has nothing to do with edge pixels
the only reason it looks like it's on
edge pixels is because the edge pixels
are black and the the background is
white so it's the highest difference
between pixel values which means it's
where you will see errors in linearity
show up the most because it's the
biggest jump right does that help and so
that's really where you're getting any
visual shimmer there I think it's just
going to be in gamma because you've got
that not only your ramp and you've got
to correctly account for that through
that ramp
so the other thing too is this isn't
implementing mipmapping so if we go down
below one pixel we would have a problem
here
and mipmapping pixel art is kind of a
separate issue because then you have to
actually think about how you want to
downsample your things as well
which is kind of a whole another ball of
wax but
so yeah any shimmering you see at this
point is almost certainly either just
gamma or at some point when you get one
to one you're going to have a little bit
of limitation just because monitors are
a limited resolution right so typically
a pixel art game wants to be at least at
two to one because you know it's pixel
arts worth to be big pixels so generally
you don't really want to go you know all
the way down but but yeah all right I'm
gonna wrap it up thank you everyone for
joining me flip side of handmade he
wrote so the pleasure coating with you
as always
we weren't really cutting today we were
just taking a look at what we could see
if there's a way to replace the shaders
and children of Merida because we were
gonna try and hack one in that correctly
did the pixel sampling but unfortunately
we weren't really able to do that so
maybe tomorrow I don't know we'll see
how we're feeling maybe tomorrow we'll
just write our own we could do it inside
handmade hero
pretty easily right or maybe we'll just
go back to working on our lighting
system either way not sure what we'll do
but I want to take a look at that
because I think it would be pretty cool
if we could have hacked in the shader
normally you can sort of intercept the
shaders and replace them in this case we
couldn't really do it there might be a
way of doing it by using some kind of
driver extension where we you know
because you could imagine us
intercepting the shaders as they go down
and just like replace that shader with
our own shader and that would you know
people people do mods like that all the
time there's like you know drivers you
can install like that would do that for
you so unfortunately weren't able to do
that but I don't know maybe maybe the
children of Merida team would let us
just replace changers for them I don't
know if you're allowed to do that in
unity probably you are but but we could
work out what the correct thing to add
to the shaders would be in that case and
and we could have a unity game that
actually looked correct that would be
kind of cool but really the best
possible outcome would be if the unity
team just added just add a mode for this
it's it's so simple yeah I don't know
and yeah if anyone on the stream knows
how to unpack so I don't work with unity
but if anyone knows how to unpack it and
get us into a part where we could
actually update those shaders I would
give it a shot
anyway that's it for today I'll be back
here tomorrow will probably see some
regular programming I don't know how
much I more have time I want to spend
like trying to fix other people's
shaders but I probably will play some
more children board it pretty soon so
yeah maybe we'll play some right now I
don't know I'm going to go ahead and
turn off the recording either way