hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Euro the show recoat a complete game
live on stream on Twitch it is a Friday
here things are kind of crazy crazy
Friday and we're right in the middle of
font stuff so I'm gonna just go get
right back into it we were about to do
stuff with language although some people
were mentioning that we we don't handle
spaces properly currently and that's
because of some stuff readable kerning
so we should probably fix that first is
your trivial things so we have some
stuff we want to do with fonts and so I
think we should try to get some of that
done today it's a Friday so we don't
want to open up anything major but we
should be able to just do some analysis
of our stuff figure out exactly what we
need to do maybe put a little bit of it
in there and get ourselves in a good
position so that we know what we need to
do next week to wrap up the font stuff
for good and then we just have fonts and
everyone's happy and we're fond thing
and it's great and everyone loves it
okay so like I said just want to get
started so if you are following along at
home and you preorder the code on
handmade hero org
I'm sorry pre-order the game on hamate
here at org you can download the source
code and unpack day 173 today is 174 so
173 source code is what I'm starting
with and so if you want to follow along
that's what you want pack and you'll be
right where I am
starting now alright so we pretty much
had fonts working to my satisfaction you
know to the level that I think we need
them to be for this particular game
which is granted not too much in terms
of complexity but some folks were saying
that spaces weren't working and I can
already know why that would be so let's
go ahead and just debug that one thing
first so that we don't have to worry
about it later well we go ahead and do
our language stuff right so if we want
to do our debug cycle count stuff I
that's probably like low counts yeah so
that's got spaces in it right and so
that should there should be space is
there and there and there not so that's
an easy test case why aren't the spaces
there let's figure that out right well
the reason I'm pretty sure I already
actually know but the reason for that is
because spaces are obviously are going
to do kerning just like everything else
and we changed the way we were doing
our kerning right the way we're doing
our kerning now is it happens inside
this character operation set and this
character operation set never actually
looks at space because space isn't a
glyph that we actually ever need to draw
right it's empty there's nothing there
so we skipped it we didn't bother
exporting it because why bother
exploring something we don't think
actually is going to be used however
that means it's kerning table will never
actually get set and so what we want to
do is we want to make sure that we
handle space properly so that it
actually gets at it now there's a couple
ways that we could do that the easiest
one is to actually store it with four
font right I'm sorry for space right we
can just do this you can't just say all
right there we go we've got a space now
it'll go through the standard path and
presumably should actually work although
I'd have to think about whether there's
anything we did in the kerning code that
would cause that not to work like for
example because of the way we were
trying to get alignment to the left edge
and stuff like that
so since we're not exactly doing the
exact same thing windows is I do I do
think we're not 100% guaranteed to have
this work but that's at least the first
fast thing to try and yep so there we go
not actually working as perhaps I should
have foretold
so anyway hmm do you think yeah
I'm gonna say I don't even actually
remember now that I think about it
I don't think I ever even actually
remember where we landed on the Curtin
thing did we use the get care wid 30 -
yeah and then when we do our kerning
tables that seems like that should have
worked you know what I take it all back
I take all of it back our kerning table
should have had the kerning value added
into it so although we may need to do
this to extract the original value I
think I revised I think I didn't really
know I thought I knew but I didn't know
I suspect the real reason is actually
because we may yeah that's the real
reason right there potentially do we
actually handle everything else probably
no we're fine we don't we don't look at
spaces but that's okay because we don't
actually need to render those spaces
right so this right here the court get
horizontal advanced repair should have
done it yeah all right
so I'm gonna have to go debug this this
may be a little trick here that I
thought was gonna be I was hoping it
would be simple so yeah what I imagined
was happening I'll just say it even
though it apparently wasn't the truth
what I imagined was happening was that
our kerning right for spaces maybe there
really wasn't any kerning for spaces for
the most part and so what was happening
was because we never actually ran the
kerning code for the space character
because it never had its glyph stuff
processed right I just assumed that that
would probably be the reason why it
wasn't getting advanced this route this
part right here is the part that
actually computes you know that does
that additional kerning and so it seemed
to me you know
I felt like that would have been the
reason why we didn't get any space
kerning you know yet when I actually did
this which should make sure that it's
called right if we rerun the asset
Packer there's no spaces right so
where'd the spaces go
so what I'll have to do to figure out
why we're not getting those since it's
not what I thought it was we're gonna
have to go take a look and and see what
the kerning for space actually ends up
doing my assumption is that the easiest
way to do that is to switch to the asset
Packer there we go
switch to the asset Packer and actually
just set a breakpoint and stop when
we're actually processing the space so
you know we could do something like this
where we set a condition on this break
point which is that code point equals
space
or not hmm well
is code-point not done that way is it
not capitalized or something no it is
huh all right well I'm gonna go a little
bit further down that road then and say
inside test asset builder CPP I'll stop
manually in that case if code point
equals space into y equals three so now
I can set a break point there well it
turns out it probably is what I thought
it was which is to say that the space is
not running but oh snap it's because
there's another reason it might not run
space contains no characters so it's
glyph will never get packed
oops looks like this has to happen
outside well so I had the right cause
but I didn't actually implement the fix
properly as it turns out so there we go
oops that's the asset builder wanted to
run handmade here Oh yep there we go
although we know still not quite right
where is our little where's our little
baby guy where is the little dude
normally comes right here right it's
debug space cycle space and there's
nothing there's nothing there so is
there some kind of really nasty big
value that's wrong in there or something
like that that we need to pay closer
attention to let's see here care
advanced crooning change that's that's
probably not okay that's that's just
uninitialized garbage there right so if
we want what we probably want to do is
set this only if we actually right we
won't we won't change the kerning if
there was no actual
to change but we will otherwise so that
way it's just gonna be care advance
it'll be minus zero and it won't update
this so that seems a little bit better
so we see you see what happened there
that was just like some cut and paste
Croft there we go alright so I think
that's probably most ly all we would
need to do for fixing spaces they that
looks fine I wonder are they big enough
though we should I guess we should
double check against the thing to make
sure that we're actually parsing those
okay debug cycle and w8 ah that looks
about right that looks pretty close so
looks like we're handling the spaces now
pretty well okay so there we go that's
where we're at
you know what I have one other thing I
want Chuck because we're gonna start
doing language stuff here I want I want
that Tokyo I was doing Tokyo they're
right I think what I was doing maybe we
should do something more appropriate to
handmade to handmade hero like you know
something like let's see search
short-eared owl long eared owl burrowing
owl Eurasian east eagle owl snowy owl
great horned owl I think we're gonna go
with this guy a short-eared owl looks
good to me
right a short year owl of shame of
course so let's go ahead and put that in
there and so what I'd like to do is I'd
like to get it so that we know like what
these code points are right because I
don't know what they are and I'm not
really sure if windows provides a good
way to do it so I I want to do two
things first of all I want to verify
that these are actually in Ariel so
Ariel actually has does it actually have
all these I don't even know right I have
no idea if it does or if it doesn't so
what I'm going to do is I'm gonna pick
some random stupid font that probably
wouldn't and do it okay so it looks like
Ariel does actually have those guys too
at least it would appear because when I
select some other font those go to
nothing so I'm assuming that if we stick
with Ariel we will actually be able to
get some characters from the kanji out
bet so let's find out what these code
points are because I don't know code
point uh let's see here where is thick
there was like a code point lookup tool
code point look up tool or tall or just
fine doesn't matter don't worry about it
so if we cut and paste this in here give
me give me to look up okay so that's it
five c0f so I'm just going to manually
enter these in at the moment
so let's see here handmade CPP and I'm
just gonna make like a little note here
for when we need them
five c0f whatever this is a t-33 and
sixty seven twenty eight
last one
five one four II okay so now we just
we've got some semblance and you know
what I'm gonna save this guy save as
desktop kanji owl dot txt Hey
oops okay sorry it didn't mean to do
that
yeah encoding
let's do utf-8 why not
desktop kanji owl all right so now we've
got our kanji owl SPECT out and there we
go okay so what do we do now let's talk
about this because we got problems as
you can see there are problems right
this is our kanji owl we've got problems
so as you can see from this right here
the span of these characters is pretty
massive right and so if we were going to
use any kind of direct look-up tables
it's gonna be pretty ugly right they'd
be just too huge we're at least got a
span between five and eight so we're
gonna span at least three and the upper
thing there which is you know shift up
by 12 bits so that's just it's too much
right we don't want to store a to you
lookup table for kerning at that size
certainly and so that's just not it's
not a good scene furthermore even our 1d
table would be pretty crazy because our
1d table would have to go all the way up
to a t-33 right which is quite high
here's me pasting an individual studio
that's a 30 mm entry table
now the
total number of Japanese symbols we'd
probably need to represent the items in
our game is probably going to be like
five hundred or something right so we'd
be storing a thirty two thousand entry
table to store five hundred things and
that's kind of ridiculous right because
almost every entry in it would be zero
so we're going to need some way of
condensing our our stuff right we're
gonna need some way of condensing down
if there's only 500 symbols that get
used we're gonna want to condense down
to things that are only of the order 500
and not things that are of the order of
32,000 right so how do we do that right
what are we actually gonna do what do we
actually undo to fix that well let's
start with the easier problem which is
just the 1d lookup okay so obviously if
we wanted to store this in a very
straightforward fashion and let me put
the day number down here if we wanted to
store this in a very straightforward
fashion right we would just do something
like okay right now we just had a flat
array and we assumed what the numbers
were so we had something like you know
ABCDE and so on and we just assumed that
like it was like 0 1 2 3 4 right and
that would work for any contiguous set
of things in fact even if this is not 0
if we want to condense down the fact
that we know we don't really need 0 you
know because we started at like 33 was
our first character or something storing
an offset of 33 would totally condense
that down because we pretty much had a
fully dense range of characters in the
ANSI set all of them were ones we
probably would have used so we could
just store a 33 over 2 tilde and be done
right and now be perfectly compact and
all the information would be nice and
it's fine and whatever however once we
start having things that look like oh
12,000 you know 3 or whatever and then
the next one is like you know 15,000 for
seventy-two there's this giant gaps in
between things and this no longer the
assumed thing no longer works so the
easiest thing to do if we didn't care
about how long it would take us to look
up right the easiest thing to do would
be to just make the table enclose the
numbers as well so instead of implying
the index we would just store the index
so we essentially tag each thing with
its actual code point right or whatever
it was and be done with it then when we
have a string like fubar we know we can
just go ahead and look up into the table
whenever you see F we go find the code
point for F you know I don't know
whatever it is it's 37 or something I
don't remember remember 39 who knows I
have no idea we go find where 39 s in
the table by searching through it and
then we pick the letter now we could do
a faster search than linear potentially
we could do like a binary search
potentially although sometimes binary
searches are kind of slow because it's
unpredictable cash wise and all these
other nonsense things but in this case I
like in fact good case point being we
could do a binary search going to
accelerate so we don't have to visit
every single item but we would still
have to do some kind of a search there
right now probably that's the kind of
thing we would have to do if this were a
game that allowed you to like enter text
right if this were a game that would
allow you to like you type text into it
because if you can type text into it
then you can enter whatever you want and
we have to be able to convert whatever
you enter right into something that we
recognize however in the case where we
actually the strings our hours
originally right we created the strings
then one thing that an option that
exists for us that would not exist
otherwise is we can actually pre process
the strings instead to map them into a
pre-collapse set of gifts of tables
rather right so if we have this and we
say we're going to map that to 0 and
that to 1 and something to 2 right
then we go in as we see oh when someone
uses code point you know 12000 0 0 3 in
a string we just go through the mapping
table map it to something and then
output the 0 instead right of the actual
number and so for this game it would
seem like that's probably the smartest
thing to do actually right that seems
like a much easier way to go because
then we would never have to do anything
expensive at runtime it's always direct
lookup and the tables are always
maximally tiny so the cost is you can't
you can't generate new strings at
runtime however even that is not
necessarily true we could also write
ship some kind of a compressed table so
oh wait maybe this is just a smarter
thing to do in general yeah this is
probably the smart of thing to do
general huh all right so I might be a
little bit stupid okay that's true let's
not harp on it all right why do you you
know why do you even bring that up you
know why would you go ahead and bring
that up are you trying to hurt my
feelings because this is not polite
right you know I'm trying to sing this
I'm doing this for you at the end of the
day you know you shouldn't call me
stupid right like in the middle of that
you know it's impolite really is what
I'm saying so rather than do that why
would we bother doing that when instead
what we could do is just have one 64k
table right says you've okay entry table
so C 4 K 2 so 128 K table we could just
have one 128 K table or rather that goes
up to whatever our maximum code point is
and then in there we just store for the
currently selected font where it
actually Maps
that would actually be pretty darn easy
then you can just enter text all you
want right and nobody cares so that
seems like it's probably a smarter way
to go so let's go that way
I think that pretty much just answers it
right there yeah seems easy seems really
trivial to me if anyone has any
objections you could voice them in the
chat and I hereby overrule them all
right so let's take a look let's take a
look at what would happen there so hmm
really not much has to change not much
has to change folks if you want to do
that so if we go in here and we take a
look at our file format so really we
only need one thing a very very simple
thing which is that in our table of
bitmap id's we've got that yeah right
here in our table of bitmap IDs what we
actually need to store is something
slightly more complicated than a bitmap
ID we need a code point plus a bitmap ID
right so we just need something that's
like you know
HHA font code point or something like
that and it just says like here's the
code point and then here's the bitmap ID
you know and then now when we store this
we just say oh okay this entry in the
table whatever entry it is represents
this code point in Unicode right so this
is the the unicode code point and then
this is the bitmap this is the bitmap ID
for that that's it
so then when we load the font in if we
want to use the font we just unpack that
table basically into into we decompress
this into into a table that's actually
direct lookup and that's the end of it I
really don't think there's anything else
there's nothing else to be done I yeah
can't think of anything else anyway I
felt like this was gonna be harder than
this I wonder if I'm just forgetting
something
I guess now the memory starts deep when
you can have 128 K table things get a
lot easier on you I suppose maybe that's
maybe that's the lesson learned I don't
know anyway let's keep going so if I go
into the test asset builder and now I'm
going to go ahead and change that so
we've got the bitmap ID here and I'm
gonna go ahead and change that over to
being an HHH HHH a font code point like
so then when I come through here
no that's fine yeah so when I come
through here and write our bitmap IDs I
need to do a few things first of all the
bitmap ID size is actually not going to
be that anymore it's going to be one of
these guys so AJ font code point yeah
and then
I don't know that there's really a whole
lot else we need to do other than set it
so when we do this we just have add
character asset will have that actually
returned one of those instead so we can
still even use this this exact format in
fact although now I think about this
gets even simpler so yeah I guess we
don't even really do that here's what we
would do we would do code point or local
index right and then what we do is we'd
set that one yeah we would set that one
each time through so we do something
like this let's see let's see we would
do HHH font code point and this would be
this the code point thing or whatever
Copley's that's not the right name what
do we call that font I guess it's just a
glyph I don't know we're gonna call it a
glyph okay so if I come in here and I
grab that out and I just say twits or
something who knows so I grab out the
glyph the bitmap ID that goes with it we
get that the code point that goes with
it I know already right it's this like
so and I think that's just about it
right and so the actual character range
for this thing it's kind of a little
confusing because it includes the space
but that's okay right and so what we
would have to do here is we'd have to
say you know we'd want to do essentially
this operation for the space as well
which is kind of a little bit annoying I
guess we could just a copy and
paste it who cares
right at some level this is like I said
this can throw away code in this in this
asset processor so yeah we could just do
it that way right we could even go a
little bit further here and do that if
we were feeling particularly enamored
with ourselves
right and you know what we could do
something else too we could we could do
something even more ridiculous you know
I say that throw away code and then I go
and do these things that's just that's
how you know that you're kind of a
programmer a sort of person I guess yeah
what are you gonna do anyway
inside here we actually could just do
that part of it now that I think about
it right we could just do this in here
so we take the glyph for that font we
take the debug font itself and do you
know something like okay debug font
glyphs debug font you know glyph count
or something like that and we increment
that we assert ahead of time that the
glyph count is less than the max lift
count or something like this you know
and then this stuff gets written in
automatically and yeah and then the
bitmap ID just gets set just get set
like that right then we don't care about
this anymore and we don't care about
this anymore and we don't care about any
of this we just say we want that and we
want these please give them to us and we
won't you know shoot the hostage we'll
be the bigger man and not shoot the
hostage okay so if we do something like
that which makes this much cleaner right
it also means that I can go ahead and
add you know we can sort of see in fact
exactly what I'm gonna add here in a
second right you can imagine our kanji
owl our kanji owl is gonna be something
that would do you know something like
this begin asset type font lift write
add character asset and then we would
literally just add the ones that we
wanted right in fact now I think about
it we could do that right inside here in
fact I'm just gonna do it right who's
gonna stop me no one's gonna stop me you
can't really stop me that's the thing
right it'd be really difficult to stop
me because at this point probably even
on the twitch stream yours is the lag is
such that by the time you hear this I
will already have actually typed it so
even if you could somehow stop me you
wouldn't have known in time to stop me
that's the thing right that's the best
the whole the whole situation I'm gonna
go ahead and say kanji owl right because
it is anyway so there's our kanji owl
and now we can just add code points to
our hearts content
yeah and so what we need to do now is we
need to back out the use of the
character which is not really so
interesting anymore and start using the
index
of the character everywhere that we were
doing our addressing so we do have a
bunch of work to do but it is not hard
work it's just sort of mechanical right
because if you look in here well so
we'll also do a thing here which is just
like right max code point cap or max
whip count max with count equals I don't
know nobody better make a font with more
than 5,000 characters in it note KC 5000
characters should be more than enough
for anybody right and you know it's true
you know what let's make it 64 K because
that's close to 600 40k I don't want to
do 640k because that actually is more
than enough for anybody so I wanna do
something that's actually kind of
slightly comically low right 64 okay
should be more than enough for anybody
right I mean can you imagine a situation
where you would need any more than that
I can't right
and so yeah is that gonna be too much
will that blow out anything 640 by 1024
x 640 x 1024 that's too big that's still
too big that's gonna be like too big for
the table all right so I'm gonna I'm
gonna actually say it's just five
thousand five thousand quid to two
thousand two thousand three thousand I
don't know how many we want calc three
thousand times three thousand nine
megabytes totally fine five thousand
times five thousand right 25 megabytes
not a problem so I'll let it go up there
there we go
all right so now that we've gotten that
crucial thing out of the way I'm gonna
go ahead and set some stuff up here
which is to say that I guess we got
loaded font which should be somewhere
there it is so we've got loaded why is
it why are these in here instead of out
here does anyone even know I don't even
know nobody knows nobody cares anyway so
if I have my loaded font here what I'd
like to do is now say all right there's
not going to be a code point count per
se there's going to be a glyph count and
a max width count and you know what min
code points and a max code point might
be good as well right so we know like
what range
it actually maps to something like that
all right so I'd like to do that we can
set the max glyph count here and we'll
set it like that font min code point
equals you know some extremely high
value int max let's say font max code
point equals zero and then we've got
this with count zero so that's good and
then in all here where we're doing like
code point count stuff like that we're
gonna use the max width count instead so
now we just know however many glyphs we
think and you can see what I'm doing I'm
changing right we were previously
counting code points which are actually
entries into the real unicode table
we're now going with glyphs which is our
own numbering for the actual Gliss
Restorick which are totally sparse
they're spread out through the unicode
code point they are not write contiguous
at all so that's why I need to introduce
this concept of two different you know
types of numbering essentially
okay so now we're you have a slightly
harder time because since we don't since
I'm not setting how many glyphs there
are ahead of time it means that our
stride is is still based on the max lift
count but it means we won't be able to
write this table out in one shot anymore
we'll have to write it out in a very
different way but you'll see that when
we get there
so yeah I don't think we'll probably
finish this by the end of today by the
way but the good news is this I think
just pretty much finishes everything for
us so once we do have a chance to finish
it maybe Monday or Tuesday it'll just be
like a good sponsor done guess what I've
got a present for you knock knock who's
there fonts are done fonts are done who
snow monster done who the fonts are just
done right
stop knocking on my door I don't know
why although in that case I would have
been the person knocking doesn't matter
it's not relevant point being what we
want to do now is we want to go ahead
and start treating this mapping we have
to we have to have our own mapping now
because we've got sort of this this this
whole kerning pair situation we need to
be able to map the actual unicode code
points into something we can actually
use I guess you know now that I think
about it that may mean that we want to
actually still index these guys by the
Unicode code points and just allocate a
gigantic table for them only a tacit
packing time
I'm kind of like with that you know what
I mean this sort of thing
yeah so here's how I'm thinking it let's
hear me out here so in the asset Packer
we allocate one big old table out to the
max code point so whatever the maximum
code point is we don't care it's 64k
let's say so this table just stores
where we actually put each one of these
guys so that we always have a mapping
table back to our own glyph type right
so basically when we when we you know
create one of these fonts we get
something in here which is and this will
just be some kind of a pound to find
which right which is like max font code
point and so the maximum code point that
we're allowing is you know this one or
something right who knows what's the
highest unicode code point what is the
highest unicode code point it's like
what's the largest number what is the
largest number according to standard the
highest code point is oh x1 0 ffff let's
jump stack overflow though can you
really trust it
the character in connection masky blah
blah blah music oppressors foresters 210
fffx unicode coasters divide 217 planes
the basic multilingual plane and 16
supplementary planes each with 65536
code points that's the total size of the
unicode Curtis packs of 17 times bla
okay
so 10 ffff hex
how much do I care about that is that a
bad size doesn't look it to me
Oh x10 FFF yeah that's nothing for an
ass for the asset Packer cuz we don't
care the asset Packer can allocate
memory like Athene and no one cares at
all right so BAM there it is folks
maximum code point is going to be that
right and so yeah so if we want to do
that then all we have to do is when we
Mal'akh this friendly little font here
our loaded font is gonna need I'm
actually I'm gonna put I'm pulling these
guys I'm pulling them I'm doing it don't
try to stop me because because I won't I
won't let you honestly that's just the
truth test I set builder H so reason
this doesn't include we does that H up
there I'm gonna go ahead and do that
that
yeah all right so it's not called that
anymore there we go
code point counts max cliff counts we
are back to where we were and so what I
was going to say is the loaded font
itself needs to store that mapping table
and that mapping table is just a thing
that's saying okay
it's our glyph index from code point so
it is just something where you can plug
in the unicode code point and get out
the slot you know the the index in this
font where that code point exists right
so you know it's gonna be something
where we just malloc some large number
of that right we say okay you know like
so we allocate however many the max
thought code point is we know that that
way we've got room for them all and then
we would presumably initialize them all
to zero which is to say that by default
none of them there none of them are in
the phone at all right they're all not
there so yeah so that's that
like so so assuming I might put that
down here I suppose so assuming that we
go ahead and make that table I should
also make a little thing that free is
the font here just gets rid of all the
tables and stuff the glyphs horizontal
advance with index from third point and
we should probably also just chart it so
not that anyone ever frees the font but
if they were to might as well do it
right seems like I don't know anyway so
in here we come through and we we go
ahead and we allocate the font we
allocate the table we clear the table to
zero gotta have a zero in there we
allocate as many bitmap IDs but for that
table this is gonna actually be our
glyphs table now right we allocate as
many of those as we can maximally hold
we do the same thing for our horizontal
advance we then clear it out and then
this you know essentially this can can
be a still be exactly the same the only
difference is that we can't do it now
because we don't have a mapping right we
don't have any way of actually mapping
the kerning pair so we need to kind of
do that kerning after we've already done
all of our mapping right
because these are supposed to be glyph
indices and they're actually unicode
indices you know and so we need to
translate them through our mapping table
but there's no way for us to do that
until we've actually extracted all the
characters right so if we were if we
were to do that how would we do it
here is where we do our kerning after
the fact we get our kerning change here
we look up the code points the way that
we do this is we just straight up add
this change to all the code points that
involved us right and so that is
something that we could actually just
bake out at the end right it's something
we could very easily bake out at the end
in fact and so I think I will the way we
would do that is we would just store
this kerning change into the actual
record for this font this font glyph
right we'd store that and then all of
this would happen separately care
advanced - kerning change we know what
care advanced is we would know what
kerning change was in fact we can just
say that we would write kerning change
directly into that table
I think that'll work
since these are somes my argument is
that this right here actually is just
other glyph index now right and it can
just stripe through the table
essentially just just doing it to
everything it can just basically pre set
the table for this character the entire
table to just have that value sitting in
it right and so all it needs to do is
say oh okay whatever the other glyph
index was and I know what my glyph index
is because now I've it's been assigned
right this should just work
I think that's good I think we're good
so if I do that this is gonna have to be
by stride so I feel like at this point
to horizontal advance you almost want a
utility function for looking up into it
because so many people are doing this
nonsense so we may go ahead and do that
later I'm not sure it's it's it's it's
it's in the back of my mind though so if
we went ahead and did that that would
just work I think the glyph index would
get assigned presumably in in this in
this sort of pass right so we do load
glyph index we would pass at a code
point and a glyph index right so we'd
say we want this glyph index it's
rendering this code point yeah and and
presumably actually could even look that
up into the code point table so it could
actually do something where we said okay
the glyph index is just whatever the
font code point table lift from with
index Brown code point it just grabs it
up yeah
so I think we could just do that I don't
even know why I'm compiling yet but
that's just pointless anyway so I think
we could just do that I think that's
fine and we don't need to do anything
special so really all we have to do is
move this thing out to the end right so
essentially we want to do that like
right before we write out the font so
that we know that all the characters
have been extracted you know so you know
like this this happens right like here
and so in order to do that you know I
don't know that we really want to dump
it in there so when it actually does the
load font I might do something like
introduce a thing here that's like you
know finalize font kerning or something
like that and just in finalized font
kerning we do this stuff now we
obviously are gonna have to actually
select the font in because we don't know
that it's the active font so we flick
the font in we'd get the kerning stuff
out of it right we'd go through and then
in here we would now be able to actually
do the thing we wanted which is like
first and second are going to be glyph
index from code point right and there we
go
so now they're converted to glyph
indices and they can be used to index
into that table which is what we wanted
right where is my free where's my free
go my free is missing and I feel like
that's bad there it is right there okay
that's not that is not where it's
supposed to go just in case anyone was
wondering not where it's supposed to go
okay so that's fine
that's where finalized font kerning will
happen and so I'll just do it here
finalize font kerning and that will take
the font like so and then further on a
lot of servers all of that this will be
the glyph count this will be the glyph
count as well this will also be the
glyph count but the code point size will
be the HHA font cliff we're then going
to write them out like so however this
will not work it won't work because this
table was bigger than the one that we're
actually going to write out right and so
really what we need to do here is do a
series of writes that only write part of
the thing so this is a slice right it's
one slice of it I don't know if this
makes sense but you know we made a table
that looks like this and we're actually
only outputting a part a subsection of
it right
we're only actually outputting some some
smaller bit right and so when we
actually output this we just want to
output you know a row then advance to
the next one and another row and we're
skipping a bunch here because the max
glyph count is not equal to the actual
glyph count so there's just a bunch of
unused space and we're not going to
write that out so yeah so
we want to just do with index equals
zero with index is less than font glyph
count click index and the slice size is
not squared it's just one of those
because now we're looping over each one
we want to write out the horizontal
advance we want to like strive it we
want to move you know forward each time
right so we want to do is say alright we
had a pointer right this is the
horizontal advance pointer which is that
and then each time we want to write that
out we're going to then add the total
size of one of these things right oops
so this is basically the same as like
the bitmap copies we've been doing only
it's not a bitmap in this case that
we're copying but it's a 2d array that
we're getting us a chunk of right so
we're starting at the top we're writing
out a partial row and then we're
advancing by the full row size oops
except that didn't convert to what I
wanted horizontal advance right
something like that yeah that way that
table then condenses down to the correct
size that the table should actually be
which is better than having it not be
the size that it actually needs to be
thing can't really argue with that
so anyway min code point max code point
we set those up max flip counts the max
discount is just going to be what we
sort of said here in fact I guess I
don't really need that to be redundant I
can just put it here and have it get set
directly like that the cliff counts
going to be zero and now these routines
will all sort of do I think exactly what
we wanted them to do there they are
glyph indexed from code point glyph
index from code point sighs that's all
good okay so moving along this stuff
actually it's just max code point max
font code point and really it's not max
font code point it slacks like it's like
count we want that or you know I could
do one past there we go
that way if you allocate a table you
have enough right otherwise your one off
anyway
so we freeing things everyone loves it
when you free things and so on this is
gonna be good oh you know what are you
gonna do all right so let's see here
other glyph index not equal to zero
index boy ran out of time
well I told you I was gonna run time I
said we wouldn't finish this till
Tuesday probably so I don't know why I'm
I'm screaming but you know it's that you
want to finish coding you know you want
to finish you know what you're doing you
know what you're doing don't you you do
and when you know what you're doing you
want to finish right that's you're in
the groove right it's like it's just
it's totally mechanical and you can just
go and like there's no reason to stop
why would you stop you wouldn't stop
except for the little thing at the
bottom tells you you have to and so you
do so yeah I mean I guess I got a wind
down don't want to have to so there's
cliff index from code point it's just
gonna be yeah saying that we have we're
entering the glyph into the table like
so that's where it's going to be stored
so then we pull out that one and then we
into the table here issue the code point
and say that map's to this lip index
right very very simple so yeah there we
go
and code point count is not a member of
loaded that's true it is not but yeah
that's actually gonna be glyph count
eventually so I might actually go ahead
and change that already it's quit count
it's not code point count
right and horizontal advance is actually
that yeah okay there we go and let's see
font code point counts that's gonna be
glyph count that's gonna be glyph counts
and there we go glyph index code points
and let's see Hamlet assets code point
count is going to be glyph count and we
are happy about that okay all that code
needs to be changed but at least for
compiling and so now I can call it Q&amp;A
but yeah we still have I we've got
another good hour left so Monday we will
have to finish all of that up but that's
fine let's go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A if
anyone has any questions about what we
did get them in quick we're only gonna
have about 10 minutes of Q&amp;A today
because I got to go at like 6:15 so
please put Q :
in front of the question so that I can
see it BK bagi I noticed that you really
comment your code your comment suppose
it consisted to do what are your
thoughts on commenting your code
considering a lot of it is pretty
complicated unless of course you don't
see it as such or do you think that
since you write good code it doesn't
require comments you readable none of
those things well okay I wouldn't
necessarily say that the code is
complicated this is not particularly
complicated code but the reason that I
don't put comments in it is not because
I don't think that they might help the
reason is because and I have I can
actually tell you that I don't know a
single other programmer who doesn't echo
this who who does you know who does
significant programming for a living at
the kind of speed that I do the comments
get out of date almost immediately and
end up being more harmful than if you
didn't have them because someone will
come and read something that says this
does blah and of course it doesn't do
blah anymore and
it's worse than if they didn't have the
comment so the problem essentially is
that comments don't go through the
compiler there's nothing checking them
and so if you wanted your comments to
always been a date you would need to put
in a process whereby you manually check
them or have them code reviewed or
something and that just slows you down
way too much it slows you down way more
than having that comment accurate could
ever have saved you and so it's a bad
trade-off to comment your code in my
opinion I do sometimes comment code and
that time is when I have fully finished
something and I'm like I am NOT gonna
touch this for like six months I will
then go in and write extensive comments
into the header that's like here's how
this works
here's what you need to be aware of
here's what you're gonna forget right
and that I think is very valuable but
commenting code that is in flux is
completely useless in my opinion it only
ever results in a net speed loss
regardless of how you do it meaning if
you don't have a review process in place
it's a speed loss because you're gonna
have a ton of comments that aren't right
and that's a speed loss if you do have a
review process the review process took
longer than it needed to and that was a
speed loss much more than the comment
could have possibly saved someone who's
reading the code so I don't see any
point in commenting code in flux but I
do see a point in commenting code that
you are intentionally putting aside for
a long time because that can be kind of
useful
why was your first calculation of the
glyph table index size too big 64 K and
reduced at UK and still later went full
on 64 K again what changed the size I
don't think it is 64 K it was five
thousand right back
yeah the reason for that was like a
table that's 5,000 by 5,000 is 25 Meg's
which isn't too bad
but a 6 5 5 3 6 by 6 5 5 3 6 table is
actually 4 gigabytes which seemed a bit
too large
I just want food would it be a good
practice to comment after writing all
your code for others um if like I said
if you know that the code is likes done
and you're not gonna touch it right
except for like minor bug fixing things
then that's an okay time to do it if
you're still working on the code just
don't comment that that's a just just oh
really of me it's not worth it it's
gonna do more harm than good and I would
also see that when you go to comment
code if you're gonna put it away for a
while don't go comment like like this is
not useful right you see a lot of
comments like this it's like that
doesn't tell me anything I didn't know
by reading this right so typically the
comments like this doesn't need to be
commented because I could read this and
I know what it's doing what needs to be
commented is anything where I wouldn't
know something about it from reading it
like something like now maybe I would
guess that because of this but that's an
interesting comment for me right like
okay this is something that runs
multi-threaded maybe that helps me write
maybe you could put that in the name
though and then it would be a little bit
better another example would be don't
comment like this these functions
because I can see what they do instead I
want to comment up here at the top that
just tells me how does this whole system
work because that's the thing that I
have a hard time knowing right I can
look at any individual like comments
that say how this function works that
doesn't matter like if I'm a good
programmer I know how the function works
I can read it what I don't know is why
this function is here like what is the
point of this function and how does it
fit into everything else so like a nice
comment at the top a nice big comment at
the top it's like the handmade asset
system is made for reading files off the
drive that are packed by an asset Packer
that follow the file format in HSA
assets whatever it's built up on a
series of tables that are flat loaded
asset types are remapped at low type
like that's a good comment right and
then I'm like ah okay see what it all
does
I can then start when I read this
function I know how the function works I
can say okay whatever right or like this
generation thing would be perfect right
don't tell me don't comment this I don't
need to see I know exactly what this is
doing what I don't know is what is a
generation like what does that even mean
why is it here so a comment at the top
that's like generations are things that
are used to make sure that assets don't
get referenced after the time what
they're evicted and so it's maintained
by the render up like that again good
comment useful comment so I don't need
to see any comments here I need to I
need the gestalt I need like the bigger
picture that's where to spend the time
commenting right if you're gonna spend
time calm anything I spend it there
cuber Caleb since the questions are slow
today when do you think you'll write a
proper RNG probably when we go to do the
world generation I would guess that's
the only time we really care at all
student I'm saying 3 or a real a
structured no we're never writing a real
hash function right as I said every game
that's ever shipped has to have this
comment in it which I assume is why you
brought it up that has to be in every
game if we ship handmade here oh and
that is not in there then I don't know
what to say we have not shipped a real
game at that point in my opinion a real
game has to comment better hash function
so you know what we could do is there's
a couple of these and they say better
hash function what we could do is like
rewrite like one or two of them to
actually be better hash functions but as
long as we leave one then I guess I'm
okay with it as long as one of them at
least says better hash function james
Widman my comment rating rule for a
while has been code should clearly tell
you what is being done comments if you
need them should only tell you why yeah
I mean I don't know that I necessary for
that because it's not for me about a
what or a why it's it's more about level
of detail I want the high the high
picture I want the the big picture
comment and that big picture might be a
what comment but I just need that big
picture it's the small it's the fine
resolution that I don't need because
that is just that's what the code does
right if the code is that hard to read
maybe you should think about rewriting
it to be a little bit easier to read you
know like name things a little bit
better or something you know but yeah
how long have you been coding here's us
31 31 years
I'm Newark hombre when will you
implement the chocolate wine fountain
probably that's where ever yangshin
thing but we will definitely you know
yangshin will definitely be doing the
chocolate fountain the question is just
will that be in the and and the answers
you're probably waiting a while right
because that's going to be in the Abner
Coimbra chocolate wine expansion pack so
that's got to wait til the end of
everything I mean I apologize but I mean
if the whole expansion pack is named
after it it can't the chocolate wine
fountain had better be in that pack
right I mean that's kind of a no-brainer
or people are gonna be like WTF so
alright guys no more questions
no more questions and call it i'ma call
it alright yeah alright everyone thank
you very much for joining me for another
episode of hand made here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you wanted to follow along at home with
the series you can always pre-order the
game on hand made here or again it comes
with a source code so that you can play
around with it at home and learn from it
and do all kinds of crazy experiments we
also have a patreon page if you want to
support the video series you can
subscribe to that we also have a forum
site you can go to ask questions get
community ports to Mac and Linux look at
a community annotated episode guide that
can help you catch up on past episodes
all kinds of good stuff up there really
great stuff for the community it's
really worth checking out if you haven't
already and finally there's a video
that's not true finally there's a tweet
bot you can check the schedule on it
tweets the schedule on weekends and
tweets every day when the stream can be
that day so it's really easy to like
catch the series live that's you wanna
do so that's about it we I think we've
more or less finished the font stuff
like I think this design will actually
be fine so it's just a question of
spending the final hour or two of
programming next week on making sure all
the glyph stuff lines up and then I
think we're pretty much good to go
we'll be able to support multiple
languages that way we'll just have to
come up with some tagging scheme so that
we can pick fonts more intelligently
because we might need something that's
like a tag you know in our asset system
we don't have a tag right now we could
define a new tag for like language so
that you know if you're trying to do you
know if you're trying to run the game in
Korean it would pick a font that has
Korean glyphs in it by setting a tag or
something just to make it so that you
know because not all fonts our problem
are gonna have all glyphs would be my my
assumption so there's some stuff we
could do there so so you know maybe
there'd be an extra hour next week or
something about just making that system
a little more of us to not really making
the system or bus but coming up with
whatever conventions we want there that
that would work well so hopefully you
join me for that again check that tweet
bot if you wanted the schedule for next
week I post it on the weekend until then
have a great weekend
have fun coding and I will see you guys
on the Internet take it easy everyone