hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream last week we
finished up our port of the handmade
hero lighting engine to work with cube
based lighting which is a step that I
wanted to take so that we can start to
work on performance optimizations of the
lighting scheme and that is exactly what
I wanted to start working on today
because we have some sort of work we
have to go through to figure out how
exactly we're going to try to accelerate
the process of lighting inside handmade
hero so that we can scale it to very
large levels and fortunately for us when
we're talking about lighting and
handmade hero
we're not really talking about lighting
the whole world at once because the
whole world could be you know incredibly
huge and there's no way we're ever gonna
compete the lighting on the whole world
but fortunately for us handmade hero
we're not trying to do that all we're
really trying to do is compute the
lighting on a small subset of the world
the subset that we can see and so in
order to do that we kind of need to just
take the light area that we can see and
perhaps a region around it a little bit
so that we can capture light coming in
from the sides as necessary through
doorways and such but that's really all
we're talking about however even just
that local region has way more stuff in
it than N squared would allow us to
really do because M squared algorithms
obviously have very bad performance
scaling so even getting up to a couple
thousand lighting elements let alone ten
thousand lighting elements well that's
not a particularly hard problem if you
have a linear algorithm ten thousand
elements might be fine
N squared algorithm with ten thousand
elements is not gonna fly at 60 frames a
second that's just not really feasible
even on today's fast hardware as long as
you're doing anything non-trivial and
the reason for that is pretty
straightforward if you take a look at
what ten thousand squared is you could
see that it's proportional right - is
there anybody to get this thing to put
commas
by the way
looks like not I find it easier to read
numbers and there's comments in them oh
yeah yeah yeah that's what I'm looking
look I don't really need comments um
okay so anyway if you take a look at
what happens if you take a numbers as
large as 10,000 and you're doing an M
squared algorithm then the number of
things you have to do to make that
algorithm complete is proportional to an
extremely large number in this case were
about a 10th of a billion here and one
of the things that you have to remember
is we're working on machines that are
around say a 4 gigahertz worth of speed
in the case of a CPU less in the case of
a GPU so in that case right we're
talking about something like this and if
you look at those two numbers together
you have about 40 of the of these that
you could do in here just cycles of the
processor right this is 4 billion cycles
that's how many I do per second and if
I'm doing 10,000 squared operations then
even if each operation was only one
cycle which is not realistic then I'm
getting into a situation where I'm not
even a multiple of 60 away from my total
number of cycles per second and remember
so at 60 frames a second this this
number drops to here which is already
less than this right so our total number
of work units that we're gonna have to
complete is less even than the number of
cycles per frame in this case at 60
frames a second that we're doing just by
comparing these two numbers you can
instantly see why squared numbers are
really bad in this scenario now on the
other hand if we took a look at the
unsquare number which is just that you
can see that there's plenty of headroom
in a number like this for a number like
this and so just in your head having
that sort of basic back-of-the-envelope
ability to see
n-squared algorithms really top out
early in a video game scenario because
of that incredibly tight cycle budget
that you get at 60 frames a second it's
just not feasible to really work on
things that are M squared in that way so
what we're looking for here is a way to
linearize to the extent we can the
lighting computations so that for
example we only have to touch every
element once instead of a squared number
of times that would be great for us but
the question is how do we do something
like that
and so what I'm suggesting that we would
need to do in order to make this work is
to try and get into some kind of a log
space where we're doing things on trees
of grouped elements for example so that
we can instead of processing every
element once which would be optimal in
this case we can maybe process the
number of each element once plus some
sort of low amount of additional
transport work that's not proportional
to the total number of items linearly so
it doesn't go in squared but rather
proportional to the total number of
items say log to base 2 or something
like that right so again what we're
trying to do is figure out something
like that this is exactly akin to
something say that you would normally do
in any other kind of algorithm if you
know you have an N squared algorithm but
you feel like oh if I sorted the
elements then I could do something with
them that was linear
well the sort is you know n log N and
then the operation is linear it's n so
that would get you down to something
that was pretty much acceptable because
log N is a very small number so
multiplying n by 8 is not really a big
deal so you know to you know something
that's proportional to to n log N or
something like that is really not a bad
algorithm at all and would be totally
feasible on the other hand and times n
is totally unfeasible in our case so
again we're just looking for a way to
break that squared piece there but we
can do other things like loop over
the all the elements multiple number of
times that would be fine as long as that
multiple is a constant two three four
five that's probably not a big deal and
we can throw in a log in there that's no
big deal
so we've definitely got room to maneuver
but we just can't go M Squared so that's
all we really need to do in order to get
us to a place where we can we can be
comfortable with it
so um let's talk about some some basic
aspects of what we're doing and see what
we can do with respect to you know
coming up that sort of plan I sketched
one out the other day that was involved
sort of aggregating things up into
bigger cubes and that doesn't seem like
a particularly bad idea let's talk a
little bit about maybe the most
straightforward way to do that and maybe
we can try something like that today so
one thing that I talked about before was
that well you know if I have a lighting
element which is a cube here and it's
got you know these points on it and I'll
just draw these in 2d for now because it
doesn't really matter the the scaling
out is gonna be similar in either case
because as we group things together it
doesn't matter whether we're grouping
them in 3d or 2d really for purposes of
thinking about the problem anyway so if
I have you know some lighting elements
and they look like this
then normally what I'm doing is when I
cast a ray out I have to look at every
single one of these elements and that's
really the problem so if I have n
elements and I know the number of
lighting points is going to be some
number you know whether it's a I think
it's like 24 or some it's some constant
times n right it's how many of these
like cubes I have then basically what
I'm looking at is I have 24 times n
times n because every time I cast one of
these Ray's out and really there's
another even another value which is R
right which is also a constant which is
the number of rays cast so it would be
24 times the number of rays cast times n
which is the number of total race that I
would be casting times another n which
is how many things I have to intersect
with and you can see why this number
gets particularly bad
well this number right here might not be
awful right
24 times you know I don't know how many
Ray's per frame we want to cast but
let's say it was 32 times n this might
not be the worst thing in the world we
may still need to cut that down because
24 times 32 times something like 10,000
it's still a pretty big number right
but even that in theory we could
probably fit inside a frame budget of
something like this because don't forget
something like the number 24 or the
number 32 is something that we could cut
down those constants we could cut them
down by multi-threading first of all
remember we've got eight threads
potentially to work with and SCIM D
which gives us a 4 wide situation to
work with as well or potentially 8 wide
as well right so we could get as much as
64 X of a speed-up here which makes this
look not as bad this is unrealistic of
course you rarely get a full 64 X P deck
so you know but even if we only got
something like a 16x feed X then speed
up then 24 times 32 divided 16 right
that makes this just 48 which is a much
less problematic number to look at if I
did that math right so we're looking at
more like 20 oops 24 times 32 times
10,000 but divided by 16 and you know
this is a much more tractable number
right so you know when you just have
constants in here multiplying it out you
can fight those constants with sort of
our standard optimization techniques and
also on a GPU the same would apply GPUs
already employ plenty of Cindy and
multi-threading automatically so if we
were to drop this into a shader the same
would apply a huge divisor on the
constant here which is actually why GPUs
are so fast right they they don't do
anything your CPU doesn't do really they
just have a ton of compute units sitting
around that can be issued in parallel
since rendering is highly parallel off
you go so um just want to give you a
breakdown analysis there so really the
problem is this that we want to start
attacking first and we can worry about
attacking this later because this is a
little bit more of a standard
optimization problem and we have a lot
of things we can do
to try and make it that workout but this
right here there's nothing we can do so
standard up standard non algorithmic
optimization is not going to help us
with this times n and that's what we
want to attack so as we're casting these
rays out here what we want to do is take
a look at what we could hopefully try to
accomplish to take something that was an
N so there's all these lighting elements
out here and we're looping over all of
them and we want to reduce that end
number to something much smaller right
so like I said a login might be nice
something proportional to a severe de
reduction in the end count so the most
basic thing we could do here is a
standard acceleration structure right so
raycasting in general typically what it
uses is some kind of acceleration
structure exactly for this purpose and
what those acceleration structures are
are things that break the arrangement of
things down in some kind of spatial way
such that when you Ray cast against them
you only test things that could possibly
hit the Ray for example let's say we've
got all of these light elements out in
space all of these things are little
cubes let's say that could intersect any
of our rays and they're just all over
the place right and there's just a ton
of them and so then we go casting a ray
at one of these things and we know that
the Ray is going in this direction well
you can see even just from your own
intuition that if you were going to
narrow the search space down here you
could probably do something pretty
straightforward visually yourself where
you just go well none of these things
out here are ever going to be relevant
because since the Ray narrowly goes in
this you know sort of shaft through
space any of this stuff that's clearly
outside of that region of the Ray is
just not relevant and shouldn't bother
to be considered so if I had some way of
quickly sort of bucketing these things
as not being relevant that would do a
lot of work towards eliminating them so
that's where the notion
of an acceleration structure comes from
it says what if I grouped these things
up into pieces so that I could eliminate
whole chunks at a time and never loop
through the sub elements of them to
check them for intersection of the array
right it's basically saying let me have
some larger element I can use and we'll
do that so for example in this situation
let's suppose that I had grouped them in
some chunky way like we've got these and
these and these over here and those and
those and those then when I see this ray
I know that if the Ray only hits this
and this that I never need to loop
through any of these so instead of
checking each of these individually I
only check one two three four five six
seven of these I just do seven checks
instead of 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13
14 15 instead of 15 checks and I've
halved the number of checks furthermore
I can continue this process right of
grouping it up further and here I will
just do three checks at the head end and
then start looping through these other
ones and so I can eliminate all of these
and never do even these three checks at
all by just doing one check or something
like that you can see how it gets more
and more powerful as you group in the
course or in coarser
pieces now what's more is we can make
other assumptions about this once we
actually get to the point where we've
got an acceleration structure in place
there's also some other things you can
do that don't reduce the worst case n
but do reduce the best case n which
again can give you a further speed
increase it's not clear we want to
necessarily do that but we could and
what that is is to do ordered traversal
of the acceleration structure the way
that that works is that let's suppose I
had a situation exactly as you see here
where I've got two spatial partitions of
some kind whatever they are and they
have a bunch of elements in them and the
Ray is going through those like so in
this case what we know is that if we
process these in a biased order so we
processed you know if this is
we processed a first and then we
processed be right if we process a first
we know that if we hit something in a we
don't need to process B because all the
elements in a come before all the
elements in B another way of saying this
is that if we have a bounds on this
structure and we know when the Ray
enters the structure we will then know
the T value along the rate at which the
Ray enters a particular bounding
structure if the intersection of one of
the points in a that we find the best
one if that is pre prior to the T value
of entry into B then we know we don't
need to test it that way even in
scenarios where the Ray enter and exit
points may be misleading so for example
if I had a spatial partition where there
was some way of crossing the partition
earlier so I'm trying to see how this so
let's say we had overlapping spatial
partitions that looked like this all of
these X's are in this one and the O's
are in this one right so if we wanted to
have overlapping spatial partitions and
I cast against them and I see here that
I have you know an X that I get that I
am checking against here an X here and
whatever and maybe it's this X that I
hit well this Oh technically comes
before this X and maybe the Ray actually
hit that one what that means is that if
I check this a first and this B second I
will find a hit on a but I can't
necessarily not check B because I have
to know whether I hit this one or not
again you can even do it in that
scenario just by having a notion of when
you possibly entered B and whether that
is always after the greatest hit you
found in a so in either case we can
always determine whether we need to
continue traversal or not and that can
get you an extra speed increase as well
another way of stating this kind of a
problem and the kind of thing that you'd
see in more of a space partitioning tree
like a KD tree rather than a bounding
tree like a sphere tree or an a a B tree
is that if you have something like a KD
tree which just splits
then you really don't know much about
when you are traversing your elements
you may not necessarily know
specifically although I guess well know
in this case you do still know in a KD
tree because KD tree is not loose if you
had something like a loose KD tree which
I guess you yeah would actually not be
that uncommon in the case where you
don't actually split elements along the
tree boundary which we probably wouldn't
if you have something like a loose KD
tree then you've got the same problem
because here is like a cage wheat KD
tree example and if we have things in
there that span across two different
nodes in the KD tree then when you end
up with a situation where you've got say
this for example is sorted into this
node what's a good I got to create a
scenario here that's actually gonna
demonstrate what I'm talking about
this will do it so let's say this is a
node a and this is in there'd be right
so when I cast here what I'm gonna find
is the the race starts in node B so I
would start by checking against the
elements in B I would find a hit on B
right B would be the element that I
would hit first now if I therefore stop
checking any other of the nodes I would
be in trouble because I don't actually
know that I hit a which is kind of
overlapping into it right so if you have
a tree that happens to be loose you've
got extra work to do because you have to
know whether or not the bounds of this
thing actually extend inside or not and
I'm not really sure to be honest I've
never really done much work with a loose
kthe so thinking it through right now
I'm not even really sure exactly how you
handle those things maybe you push the
boundary of the tree out to the largest
element in either case you actually have
two bounds on the elements I'm not sure
I feel like traditionally KD trees and
BSP trees you always with the elements
so for example if you have an element
that's sitting across the boundary you
split it in two one on each side that or
you just have a pointer on each side to
the element so you always would have the
element in each so I'm not sure it's
really a relevant concern because I
don't think I've ever seen it done that
way but either way I just want to get
the point across that you can always
kind of determine the information you
need to know for whether you can safely
early-out or not you just have to
construct your raycasting algorithm to
make sense of it I guess is what I'd say
all right um so there's a lot of ways
like I said we could do this and I'm
going to talk a little bit now about
which I'm going to do first and why so
something like a KD tree is
traditionally what you would use for ray
casting a scene if you're talking about
actually ray casting the scene the
reason for that is because it's it does
the sort of the minimal amount of work
per step necessary to eliminate some
elements in that
tends to be the most useful thing so
Katy trees are very popular in rate
racers that are actually trying to do
ray tracing of the whole scene down to a
very high level of accuracy however I'm
just not sure that some of that kgt
exactly what we want and the reason for
that is I don't think we're interested
in actually ray tracing the scene what
we want to do is get approximate
lighting from stuff that's far away and
accurate lighting from stuff that's
close and that's why I think more of a
multi-resolution tree maybe more what we
want and that's why grouping I think is
a little more useful here because what I
would like to do is not actually
traverse the tree what I would like to
do is say okay let's suppose we've got a
bunch of course lighting elements here
that number in the very small numbers
like 5 or 10 right and then when we cast
array out of one of them let's say we're
computing lighting for things in this
region we've got a little lighting
element here that we're computing and I
want to cast array out of the service of
that and it goes in this direction well
the elements in here are obviously very
relevant to that because they're very
close to it and so I'm gonna expand this
tree down pretty coarsely perhaps down
all the way to the bottom where we've
actually got individual lighting
elements and I will collide against
individual lighting elements but what I
would rather do for stuff out here is
just treat them all as one big aggregate
lighting element right I would rather
not even traverse the tree this is what
I mean when I say that I want kind of a
coarse lighting approximation excuse me
because I really just don't want to
focus at all on this part of the problem
right I don't want to try and get
accurate hit detection weight out here
what I would rather do because again I'm
just spending a lot of time producing
individual hits about specific lighting
elements in here when those lighting
elements are not really that relevant to
me all I wanted to know is generally
speaking how much light is coming from
this area
so what I'd rather do is build up these
trees sort of in some way that gives me
aggregate lighting elements that say how
much light is leaving that region in the
general case and then when I do lighting
and I gather the lighting from external
areas I want to just go okay tell me
roughly how much light is coming from
this area and I will use that amount for
any ray that makes it this far because I
really just don't want to know about
every little piece of minutia this would
not be what you would do in a non
real-time non app sort of in a thing
where you were interested in computing
very accurate lighting this becomes a
problem because maybe what you were
trying to do is capture some very long
shadow cast by something over here and
in a film rendering scenario you you
want all that information but we don't
want that what we want is a general idea
of how the lighting is flowing through
the scene and we don't really care
whether or not that lighting is accurate
we care whether it is plausible and
feels good in the space at a high speed
right so we're trying to come up with
approximations
this is crucial we're trying to come up
with approximations of how much light
would come from an area so that we don't
have to spend all of this time ray
tracing all of the individual things in
the area to figure that out because we
know ahead of time we're not gonna be
able to cast enough rays to do that if
we were no problem but we know ahead of
time we're never gonna radiate this area
with enough rays to really figure it out
so instead let's figure out how we can
get a course or estimation I think this
is the way to do it
so what I want to do is I want to start
by doing something where individual
elements can be clustered up into larger
elements and those elements can have
their lighting considered in aggregate
as if they were just bigger elements
right that is what I would like to do
so there's a lot of ways we could try to
do this since our since our game already
has sort of the concept of a spatial
partition in the world in general I
think we could probably do some kind of
leveraging here where we caught where we
can lean on the fact that it's already
coming out of a spatial partition to
know roughly where it needs to be put
placed for consideration in terms of the
lighting algorithm itself in other words
I don't think we have to do that work
more than once what I do think we need
to do is we need to have some way of
knowing how coarsely we need to
subdivide any particular region because
sometimes certain areas may simply not
have very many elements in them and
others might have a lot more number of
elements in them as far as again those
facial partitions are concerned so
that's something that we need to kind of
think through a little bit better and
I'm not sure exactly how I want to do
that so for starters what I think I'll
do is is not try to be too fancy and
we'll just build this on the fly but
with an I want to keep an eye towards
maintaining a spatial partition through
the entire pipe because I think that's
probably the easiest way to do it we
know our game is sort of grid layout
like we know that we want a spatial
partition for storage on the back end
because we already have one right we've
got go ahead and open up the code here
yeah if we look at how handmade is
working already way way way back in the
early days even just a sigh loaded
handmade ray that's not what I wanted
okay if we take a look at how the world
storage is going right we've got this
sort of chunked representation of the
world where we pull chunks out of the
world here and those world chunks
themselves are exactly one of these
kinds of spatial partitions so at that
point I feel like we could leverage
where how the world is being stored to
give us a leg up on this as well and
similarly for collision detection in the
game we're gonna want something very
much like that so I feel like we could
sort of be doing this in a single pass
at some point and and as we weld those
things together I think we'll get speed
improvements throughout the entire chain
so that's the only thing that I'm
talking about here is this sort of fact
that we were doing chunking of the world
already into into these chunks here
where you can kind of see we've got
these chunk whatever this dimension is
here this chunk Dimond meters is
creating a natural sort of gritting of
the space that we've already partitioned
things into and so at that point I think
it remains it's pretty trivial for us to
say can we sort of create a single
unifying scheme where we store things
based on this partition we collision
detect them based on this position and
then we light them based on this
partition as well because that just
saves a lot of extraneous work that we
don't need to do all right so what I'm
gonna do for the time being is I'm gonna
instead of trying to unify those before
we really know what we're unifying is
I'm just gonna say well we've got all
these lighting elements in the world I'm
gonna trying to sort of grid them up
into groups right and I'm gonna do that
sort of just again based on a very
simple bucketing scheme nothing
particularly fancy and that way we can
start with something pretty basic and
work our way up from there what I can
then do is say well once we know what's
going on with
with a sort of a group of nodes there is
I can sort of produce a little more
information about those about those
nodes and how much light leaves enters
or leaves them and so on right so that's
really all I want to do to begin with
and I don't have much of an idea of how
big those should be or really what they
should contain but that's mostly I think
all I really want to do for starters so
let's start with that I'm gonna go into
render group and at this point I think
probably rather than having these in
render group it might be a reasonable
time for us to go ahead and add a
handmade lighting file in here because
you know we can and the handmade
lighting files I'll cut and paste a
little header in there the handmade
lighting file can can sort of store all
of our lighting stuff here let's see
what we've got for that I think it's all
in here we've got these in platform dot
H and I could probably move this out so
if I take a look at what we've got in
here we've got all of this stuff
lighting boxes letting surfaces blah
blah blah so there we go right and in
here if this is stuff that needs to get
included I feel like we can just include
it in here for the time being and I
guess to be honest we don't really need
to include it directly in here either I
think we could kind of move it move it
into the other code as well so I think
the only reason is because of this stuff
then the game render commands need to
have corners to it of the lighting box
in the lighting point
so I at some point probably after we
finished the lighting we'll want to sort
of isolate our render a little bit more
clean it up and just kind of finalize
all of our rendering stuff at that point
I think would be a good point to sort of
clean up the fact that this has leaked
into the platform layer because the
platform layer contains the renderer we
don't really need it to do that we can
have the renderer contained outside of
that and that's probably something we
want to do a little later on it don't
want to do it right now because it's not
really relevant right now it's not
really what we're trying to accomplish
right now so it's a little premature to
start doing stuff like that but that is
some architectural work we'll probably
want do a little bit down the road
that's like a day what we're not day but
like a one episode of Hannah here oh so
I call them days they're like two hours
or whatever um that's one episodes worth
of work it wouldn't be a huge deal to do
so and so we should probably do
something like moving that out anyway
so in here in handmade lighting that H I
can pull out some of these calls that we
had and so that we can sort of keep them
in a place that's a little more clear
and we can see where most of the letting
stuff is actually happening so I'm just
gonna grab this out here and and drop it
into the lighting file I'll pull this
out as well and then we can have
something a little more sane when I
compile this we're going to end up in a
situation where of course we don't
actually have a bunch of these things
that we need that's okay because now I
can just go ahead and include it in
handmade dot CPP so let's go ahead and
drop that in here include handmade
lighting and this probably needs to be
up above the people who are going to use
it so we're probably talking about
something that's right under render
group there and then now we've got it
sort of pulled out into its own file and
it's a little bit easier for us to kind
of like concentrate on what's actually
in there right again no real reason for
this at all it's it's not there
no I get asked about the file separation
stuff sometimes there is no rules or
dogma that you need to follow for
separating things into files it's that's
just the kind of thing that people go on
about and clean code and these sorts of
things that are not really real they've
never measured it they've never proven
anything about it it's Dogma and so I
always try to encourage people as much
as possible to just be sensible and
apply your own personal opinions to how
you should separate things into files
personally I just separate things into
files based on logical groups I like to
look at and what makes it easiest for me
to get around the code and that is
exactly what you should do it there is
no there there is no proven universal
scheme for separating things into files
and anyone who tells you there is it has
literally does not have the proof for it
they have not done that because we don't
even know how we would go about proving
that yet and so claiming that there's
one right way to separate things into
files is absolutely ridiculous and I
would never tell you otherwise so I am
doing that separation strictly because I
want to be able to look at the lighting
things as separate pieces that kind of
live on the side because I don't really
want to have to like look at them
intermixed with the rendering code
because it's kind of its own little
separate pass so at that point I felt
like it would just be easier to have
them in separate files if somebody
didn't want them in separate files that
does not mean they are wrong
that just means that they have a
different preference for how they like
to look at the code all right
so taking a look at what we've got here
you can see that we sort of have no no
real multi-resolution mists happening
here oh and that reminds me in world
mode here we've also got this lighting
solution let's let's go ahead and pull
that out because I think we should be
able to pull that out here as well right
so random series is not defined is the
only problem in the platform layer where
this stuff has to get included due to
the fact that it needs to know the size
of those pointers what I could do here
is actually you know what I could do and
this seems kind of compelling as well
it's not really include this file there
and instead do something a little more a
little more fluffy right what I could do
to make this a little bit cleaner is
inside platform dot H because like I
want to go this route anyway maybe just
say hey let's not really specify what
these things are at the moment let's
just say they're abstracts trucks I
don't know if we could do that with the
textured vertex as well we might be able
to for now I won't and I'm just curious
if I could then say at that point once
we come through here we could do this in
a little bit more traditional way we're
in handmade dot H we are including it
along with the render group and so on
again this is just partitions it a
little bit more nicely letting solutions
should have been in there why wasn't it
Oh cuz world mode comes before a render
group why does that happen was that
necessary
no it wasn't so at that point all we
really need to do is make sure that we
also inside our win32 handmade stuff
since that stuff has to happen now we
can include the lighting and that should
in theory work hopefully
so that's again just keeping it a little
bit more isolated I haven't done
anything to it yet we we have not done
any changes to it but we've just kind of
pulled it out a little bit so that we're
working on it in sort of a particular
location and now we can run it and see
what we've got here this is you know the
lighting running non multi-resolution so
now we want to do is try to figure out a
way to again group things together into
aggregate elements and then do something
sensible with the aggregate elements
right that's what we're trying to do
here and I think to a certain extent we
could if we wanted to probably I feel
like we should also be able to when we
split things into elements I'm sorry
when we group things into elements we
could actually we can actually split our
elements in in half as well anytime we
want to meaning if we have a particular
lighting element that's long and doesn't
fit nicely into one of our buckets we
could split it in half there isn't
really anything that stops us from doing
that out think we can have to like sort
of virtual lighting elements that do not
correspond directly to a single lighting
element that originally came down the
pipe that is if we wanted to split an
element up we don't really want to split
elements that often if we can avoid it
because splitting elements just adds
more elements to the mix than we really
want to deal with so it's not desirable
in most cases but we could prevent
having to deal with overlap elements in
the way in that way by actually just
splitting up elements into smaller
pieces I think that actually works
I don't quote me on that but I don't see
any reason why I wouldn't um so we
definitely gonna have a lot of options
when we do this here and so now the
question is just alright how are we
going to
actually sort of break these into pieces
and the answer to that is I don't really
know you know one way to do it is to
just apply a fixed grid to the world and
let it go another is to try and actually
sweep over the elements that we've got
and figure out where a reasonable split
is in them and then split them to either
side of that split things like that
that's the more KD tree approach
obviously and I'm again I'm just not
really sure how I want to do that I
think probably
I think probably what I want to do is
start with some coarse notion of I think
at the highest level I want to start
with some coarse notion of how the world
should be divided probably I mean it's
really hard to say so traditionally what
happens is you know you kind of sweep
over the elements and you take maybe the
bounding box and you split it in half or
something like that and you just class
you know people are the elements and you
put them half into one side half into
the other side and then you you know
sweep again this sort of a thing I just
don't know I I don't have a good feel
for yeah what I I not having any really
good ideas about how to guide this
process more intelligently than just
like try some stuff and see what what
works because again we sort of have an
unusual you normally when you're dealing
with ray tracing you're dealing with
fairly arbitrary shapes and in this case
we know we're dealing with very highly
regularize shapes these shapes are all
specifically cubes and a lot of them are
packed fairly densely together so that
there's not a lot of they're not like
overlapping in weird ways or anything
like that either so it's kind of hard
for me to conceptualize because it's a
very specific scenario and I feel like
there's probably some there's probably
some best you know specific elements of
the way these Street scenes are
structured that should or could be
exploited to create the spatial
hierarchy in a way that makes a lot of
sense for this particular type of scene
and that is what sort of tripping me up
a little bit meaning I feel like there's
probably something very smart to do here
I just don't know exactly what it is but
it's
probably not let's apply a hundred
percent generic solution to it because
this isn't a generic scene you know most
ray tracing spatial partition algorithms
are based on the understanding that you
just have some arbitrary collection of
triangles that represent some
complicated scene with lots of
heterogeneity in it but we don't have
that we have a homogeneous world filled
with cubes so at that point I kind of
feel like we should probably be doing
this in a cube based way
so let's just do that I mean let's just
I don't know I mean III don't since I
don't have a particularly strong ID here
I guess what I'd say is let's go ahead
and and sort of break this into some
number of elements at the top that we
sort of prescribed that's the minimum
number elements that we're gonna
consider and then we'll just do
something basic on the way down I'm not
gonna try and overthink it right now
because since I'm not there's nothing's
jumping out at me I feel like I don't
want to spend too much time thinking
about it before I just do something and
get some information for how for how you
know this sort of thing might go so if
we take a look at our lighting solution
what we want to do here is have some
idea of like aggregate lighting
information so for example you know if I
was to have a lighting partition
something like this then what that needs
to haves it needs to have some
information about you know it needs to
have some information about what's in
the partition and we know for every
lighting partition there's going to be
sort of an array or something or a
linked list or who knows what but
there's going to be a collection of
elements that are in it so something
like a lighting partition would have
some some count like a child count and
then it would have something like a
pointer to the children right
in each of those would have children as
well right so you would have something
like this each one of these would
probably have a lighting box in it that
had the information it was using
something like this only in this case
this sort of thing is probably going to
be some kind of a union because we would
have two different situations one would
be where we have child children that
we're using for lighting and the other
where we have just an actual lighting
box at the end and so we'd probably have
something more like okay so we've got a
struct here this has a pointer to where
our children are stored for example and
we might do something more intelligent
than a pointer in the future but that's
sort of separate issue
so we'd have like a pointer to where the
children are stored and we know how many
there are from the child count but if
the child count was zero then we know he
is something else in this case we would
have you know our min and Max pounds and
then just the children and and maybe
that's all we actually have in this case
although I think yeah we probably would
also have more information here about
the the individual lights that were sort
of coming out I'm not sure you know
maybe we would we might even sort of
still have lighting box as our thing
that looks like we're using P and radius
here so so it's hard to say maybe this
would get welded in and this would just
be a lighting box and we'd have this
sort of information here in fact what we
could do here is actually call this pad
this pad could be the child count in
fact I suppose because since that's up
to zero and we've got a spare thing
there we would know that the children
could be stored the child camp could be
stored in that
yeah something to consider um so what we
could do yet is say alright couple
pieces of information here we know we we
need to have letting box screen down
than broken into pieces we could just
make it so that a lighting partition is
just one of these and then it just needs
that extra pointer beyond just what's in
the lighting box so it seems like we
could actually do that and maybe you
know we could even find a way to sort of
sneak that in here I yeah so give me a
second to kind of think this through how
this would actually work because those
lighting partitions really just need the
exact same thing as letting box so maybe
we use lighting boxes the whole way down
that does seem plausible to me I think
we would just need a little bit more
here
the only thing that we're not getting
here is the only thing that doesn't fit
in here is the index that would tell us
yeah we're where our children are but
that's pretty simple to figure out right
so suppose we were to do something like
this so in this case now we've got six
of these like if we just took a look at
this we could easily pack the
transparency in in a more convenient way
and keep this structure size down a bit
right so even if that's not we wanted so
even if we did have to expand that a
little bit we easily could and still
keep it in a pretty pretty
straightforward fashion so we know we've
got three floats times four bytes per
float here times two elements plus we've
got seven times two there plus another
two plus another two plus one plus one
equals a forty four byte structure
so it looks like we just need we have
room for one more D word there so this
must have been a kind of a weirdly
aligned thing because 48 would be the
normal number we'd be shooting for there
32 would be ideal right because then you
get 2 per cache line but if the moment
doesn't look particularly like we would
get that in there in any real way
because we can't really get down to 32
given the the hard requirements of the
stuff that we need to put in there I
don't think although you could imagine
overlapping these pieces of information
in an interesting way that maybe does
get you down to 32 if you were really
Squinkie about it right because there's
an extra element stored in light index
which you use for differencing there so
I don't know they're you know maybe if
you wanted to be you if you wanted to do
more work computationally you could
probably get it down so since we don't
care about that then I suppose this is
okay the way we had it before at the
moment right so we've got 3 times 4
times 2 plus 4 plus 7 times 2 plus 2
oops
what's 2 plus 2 it's one that which is
47 so yeah it's just this is just now
regular pad so I think that gives us a
48 byte struct which seems reasonable in
terms of how these things would be
aligned memory again a cache line is
usually 64 bytes so you know would have
been nice to get done 32 for those two
per cache line but whatever so the
lighting box could easily have this
information in it
and if that was the case then we don't
really need a lighting partition right
we can just use lighting boxes the
entire time and just operate on those
sort of more directly and then what we
would do if we wanted to kind of go
full-bore on it is we just say well okay
so we've got a lighting box that is sort
of our root box and we start at that box
and we just see where we you know
whether we intersect that box if we do
we subdivide the box down until we get
to the leaf nodes and that would allow
us to do
you know pretty straightforward sort of
thing on it I again I'm just gonna start
pretty easy here and use a standard
space partition and then we'll kind of
look at how we go so I'm going to go
ahead and just just treat it like that
I'm gonna say that's the way it goes and
and then I'm going to go ahead and make
the render group there where it used to
set the pad only least I think it uses
at the pad where did it set waiting box
so here where it's setting the stuff I'm
gonna go ahead and initialize these
things child count to zero that way it
knows if it sees a child count equal to
zero it knows that this is a leaf node
that doesn't that can't be subdivided
any more and off you go right okay so
I'm gonna start off by collecting some
statistics here so I can kind of see
what's going on during this process so
because I I want to sort of now sort of
start to take this a little bit more
seriously and say okay I want to know
how many boxes can we're considered
during raycasting right so I want to
have a thing that's sort of like boxes
checked or raycast box count or
something like that so what I'm gonna do
in here is I'm going to go through and
in my lighting code where I was doing
this before when I sort of do my ray
casting I know every time I consider a
box I could also do something like point
point count
number of points number of originating
points for raised or number of times a
point got used as an origin and number
of times a box got considered or
intersection and so what I want to do
here is when we actually do the lighting
test here I want to start by
initializing my solution to have those
values set to zero like so and then at
the end I would like to say what they
are and what you can see here is that
inside my computer like propagation
called and in here we loop over lighting
points for emitters and so what I want
to do is say all right every time we get
in here this is a point count increase
because we're saying we're taking this
particular point and we're going to
emanate something from it as a set of
rays so that's an increment there we
could also ask what the total ray count
is
and so inside here we know that we cast
array like so I suppose it perhaps a
smarter way to place that would be to
put it in the actual ray cast call like
so because then we know every time we
call this we did it now inside here when
we go to do this lighting box
computation then we know that our box
count gets increased and I think that's
probably all we really need to do now
let me go ahead and include that other
value here and the statistics that we
just added and again I will initialize
it to zero
so now when we run the code I should be
able to see some just just really
coarse-grained statistical information
using the debug system and you can kind
of see where we're at
right so what you can see right here is
we're recasting from around you know
let's say it varies but it's you know
somewhere in the 1500 range and we're
recasting something like 30,000 Ray's
which leads to about two million box
checks right so again you can see why
the CPU as fast it is is already
struggling with this amount and it's
running in real time but not even quite
the can't even quite hold 30
frames/second you can see why this is
occurring because we end up with a
situation where the total number of
boxes it has to check is starting to
creep up on that number in a really
nasty way so again if I just redirect
your attention back here for a second we
look at this box count it's around 2
million remember I said the total number
we were gonna have of cycles per frame
at 60 frames per second would only be
about 6 million that means we'd only
have about 33 cycles to test each box
we aren't we're using way more than that
to test a box so you can kind of see
why we're already not hitting our 60
frame a second budget that's really all
you need to see is that number so that
number you know we want to be trying to
get 10x on or something right we want to
we want to produce a really significant
dent in that number in order to sort of
make our letting get it more into the
plausible range now to be honest I think
we need more than 10x I think we almost
want more like a hundred X here because
we're gonna multiply the number of boxes
pretty significantly so we really need
to make a dent in that mmm a very
significant dent in that number if we
want this to run except ibly on you know
a modern computer and this is a fast
modern computer so we have to make it
run really well on this computer because
older computers you know that maybe
you're only going to run the game at 30
frames a second you know we'll only have
twice as many cycles to deal with so
it's still not really gonna be a walk in
the park
either way so it's we want to be really
really fast on our computer because we
know that we're kind of at the high end
here all right uh so when we're doing
our lighting test what we want to do is
focus on getting that number down so
what I want to do now is say well okay
so if we were going to do that inside
this ray cast here what could we do well
like I was saying we're looping over all
of these boxes here what I want to do
instead is turn this into a sort of more
hierarchical traversal of these Ray's
instead so when we're looping over this
this set of boxes what I want to be able
to do is turn this into something that
is going to be looping over a spatial
partition so if you imagine something
more like this
we're instead of looping over all of the
boxes together we can loop over sort of
well in fact I guess maybe I don't even
need a for loop here this may be
something more looking if and we can use
this as a recursive function potentially
although we may want to use it as a
stack so you know we'll see how that
goes in a second we'll start with
recursive and we'll maybe switch to
secular later on but um we're gonna loop
over instead of all of the things in the
entire solution let's loop instead over
something that's a spatial partition so
for example what we want to do here is
say hey let you pass me the lighting box
that I should be using
so in here we'll say hey what's the
lighting box to use is the root or
something like this and so then what I
could say is you know if I hit the root
box which I guess maybe we're assuming
that we have here I don't know that's a
that's a tough to say so yeah maybe
maybe we do something where we just we
leave it in the same level of nesting
that it was before we assume we hit
there oops that's no good yeah
too many keys we assume that we're going
to pass it some box to use and so what
it'll do with that root box here is it
will assume that this has children and
it will loop over the children so it'll
go in to again that lighting this
information here and we could even by
assuming that the child count is modest
enough we could even expand this to a
32-bit index if you want to we've got
the room for it I don't think we want to
yeah but I'm just saying we could so
anyway inside here we say the source
index is no longer going to be zero
instead the source index is going to
come from our root box and it's going to
be the first child index then we're
going to say okay that root box child
count is gonna tell us how many to do
that's so we do it like that and then
we're gonna proceed as we were
proceeding before we go through here we
do our ray casting and what we're gonna
see is in here when we hit a particular
box what we'll do now is say okay we'll
actually go check the raycast
in the Box later when we would be
producing the results instead of pursuit
for instead of producing the actual
result in the case where we have
children we will just recursively call
the function so in this case here for
example what we'll say is okay we want
to get this closest hit back from a sub
call instead and for the moment we're
not going to worry about this path here
at all
this was the unrolled path which got a
little faster and to be honest I guess
we don't really want to keep this in the
mix any more we know we can pre produce
this anoint - couple seconds to do it
before we know we can produce that
trivially but right now we need to just
focus on the multi-resolution stuff and
that that function would have to that
unrolling would have to change rather
dramatically either way so in here what
we're gonna say is okay ray cast result
is going to get one more piece of
information it's going to get
the closest hit like so-and-so in here
when we're coming over these we would
produce the closest hit and maybe what
we do here even is say okay when we know
the closest hit let's instead of
tracking all of the result information
let's instead let's not do that let's go
ahead and produce this information in a
slightly different way let's go ahead
and produce this information at the end
only right so when once we know who the
hit actually was maybe we just return
the index of the box and we don't return
any more of this information so that all
can be taken care of outside so given
that maybe let's just do this just real
quick let's let's make sure that this
will still work if we do it this way if
we change the the return structure a
little bit here and we say that raycast
result just does u16 box index right
that's all it does or maybe it produces
the pointer so that's it right that's
what the rake the raycast actually tells
us it doesn't tell us this information
so this stuff has to be found on in a
different way
after you do the raycast which happens
right here then what it does is it has
to produce this information in different
way so what it'll do is it'll say well
okay I needed this piece of information
so what I can do is just get it like
that right pretty straightforward and
what all I really need is the the Box
surface index here I need to note this
actually doesn't need to be done this
way either because now we would have
this as a null pointer if nothing got
hit so actually what we can do now that
I think about it is this can be
simplified slightly as well which is
this can just be if ray box
right alright so then we need to know
the point count results which again is
going to be this piece of information
here like so
so that hit point count again it's just
the Ray box box surface index like so so
this is really one I guess one more
piece of information that we need
so just reorganizing that code slightly
to use this piece of information looks
pretty straightforward
and I think that's it right open oh one
more thing
the rapey here so we know what we cast
so we should be able to do this directly
since we do the raycast from the omit p
and we know the omit direction then the
rate the T along the Ray should just
give us the the Ray hit point so off we
go right just piece of information right
here so I think that's it and that
should just work hopefully all we have
to do is actually fill that information
out this is no longer get set
we can ignore that for the moment and
then in here what we would do is when we
track the closest hit we could also just
store which box surfaced it next we were
on and which source index we were on
I think that's it right so boxes an
undeclared identifier here that is
correct
although we could just do lining box hit
box it goes ray that box that we can
just say hit box everywhere and we know
we're talking about and that is off of
the tier a so unfortunately that should
probably slow us down a little bit
it didn't really much to be honest but
probably a little bit because again
we're probably not quite as efficient as
we were depends on the circumstances
because there's a little more fussing
going on here the needs to but I have to
do that temporarily at least in order to
make sure the raycast can now be called
sort of as a recursive function so in
here we're gonna say all right let's
take the lighting box that's the root
box now we'll switch back to calling it
in this fashion like so and now what we
can do is when we get down here and we
find a particular box what we can do is
say well let's go ahead and call this
this function sort of recursively and
what we'll do is instead of the closest
hit being reinitialized every time what
we'll do instead is say that the closest
tip gets passed in right so now what we
can do is say well we start with the
closest hit value that's whatever gets
passed in here if you don't specify it
it'll it'll be initialized
to the nothing volume but when we call
through here then what we'll say is well
when we get it closest tip value back
from anybody we remember it right so
what we can do here is say great cast
results or actually I guess we can just
do is say our results equals call the
raycast again with all the same
parameters that we were calling it with
before and again this is why I say we
want to probably turn this into just AK
based because we don't want to keep
duplicating this work and pushing it on
there's no point to it it's just a waste
of everyone's time so we probably I'm
doing is recursive function the davidic
at the immediate moment because that's
just a simpler way of writing the code
first but we probably want to expand it
out later because this is a performance
critical part of the code and we're
gonna want to massage it as opposed to
just letting it be written in the
simplest possible form you need it in a
more performant form all right so once
we do this we get our recast result back
we do it like so so what I need to do is
determine do I need to do further ray
casting or don't I
so in the case and it looks like here to
what I want to do is for closest hit
what I'd like to do is actually make
that just probably be part of the
raycast result that I'm returning
so I want my t ray to be part of the
closest to it what I could do is
actually also make all of these just
operate on the same red cast result in
fact now that I think about it that's
probably the best way to do it so the
result is just something that we're
gonna fill out here right and what I'll
do is say okay we're not going to touch
any of this we're just going to say that
we pass this in here we can initialize
it this way in fact you know what I'll
do I'll just make one of these works the
old way
so when we call this we initialize the
raycast result by saying the box equals
zero which means there's no hit and the
tear a value that we're working with is
f-22 max we don't even name the other
information because it won't get used
unless the hit happens right then we
call raycast recurse with the root box
and the result that we're trying to
produce we go ahead and produce that
result and we're off to the races
so closest hit is now going to be result
tier a and you can see now that we're
updating that information here like so
so what we want to do here is call
raycast recurse directly and i want to
move this raycast call down there we go
so in the case that we find that we
actually hit one of the surfaces of this
box then what I want to do is I want to
call the recursive check of the box and
furthermore what you'll notice here is I
don't really want to be inside this
truck anymore because once I've
determined that I'm going to recurse a
box
I don't need to recurse the box anymore
right so if I hit one side of the box
and go I'm gonna go down into this box
then I don't this doesn't need to occur
anymore I'm done at that point with what
I was checking so yeah I I should have
to do this because technically speaking
I can only hit one side of the box and
we're not checking the exit side of the
box anyway so it shouldn't actually ever
happen
but it also means that if we happen to
hit access on X is zero we could skip
the checks for access one and two it
just speed this up a little bit I guess
now that I think about it we can
probably actually just do this period if
you hit one of the corners we don't need
to check any of the other corners of
that obviously that's just kind of you
know a property of a solid a convex
solid that you only check the front
faces of you can only hit one of them
with array that's just common sense
right there's no array is gonna hit it
at a single point and that point cannot
be on more than one face of a convex
solid I would have to be in a concave
solid in order to to enter an exit and
enter and exit the shape so that was
probably something we could have done
earlier anyway and just didn't do so if
the box in question has a child count
then we will recurse that child count
the way we look stress that recruits the
child kind of by spending sending all
the same stuff through but now we're
going to use this box as our source for
getting the information and we're going
to pass it the same result that we've
been working on for it to fill out right
and I think that's all we really need to
do right now we can get rid of this now
because that's sort of done in line and
I think that's everything
science unassigned a mismatch I don't
really understand why this integral
promotion does this this way it's kind
of a little bit weird to me that it does
I've never really been at one with C's
internal promotion rules they always
seem a little bit not what I want but
you know it's it's fine doesn't matter
uh so this is an arrow and so are these
this no longer has to be in equals
because we're just operating on it
directly right here so that's good
and I think that's everything we need so
all we have to do now is actually have
one of these sort of root boxes which we
don't have yet right all right so what
we need in order for this to work is
actually building a spatial partition so
I'm going to make something here a
function that will do exactly that's
here it is and so what I'm going to do
is before we get into any of this
nonsense I'm going to go ahead and say
you know okay
I'm gonna print out both of these
because now we might expand the number
of boxes and points right so anyway I'm
gonna say let's build a spatial
partition apart Isham for lighting here
and let's have that go ahead and build
up these things now the way that I'm
gonna do that it's again very
straightforward here we've got I'm just
gonna start by saying everything's in
one node so it's giving the exact same
thing it was before just to make sure
that our routine is working properly
I'm just really exact same thing as we
did before and verify that we can still
get the lighting out because like I said
baby steps with code that's complicated
like this so I'm going to go ahead and
create a lighting box that lighting box
is going to be whatever the next box is
and and this box is going to be my root
box so I guess I can also do this
and this box will have a p-value of 0 0
0 and radius value of you don't just
realized is we don't have a check for
whether we're inside the box which we
would also need right
[Music]
so there's two ways we could do this and
and one of them is pretty clever and I'm
just wondering if it's a little too
clever or what so we know we want to
check boxes that the REA passes through
so that's the check that we're already
doing what we don't currently do is go
if the race started inside this box then
we need to subdivide the box we don't do
that yet so the problem here is that you
know we don't really want this routine
to have to think too hard about that and
so one thing we could do is make that
work on the back faces of the cube and
I'm just not sure if the checking in
other words if we said the radius was
this all raised inside would always hit
it they would hit it as they exited it
instead and it would trigger it to work
I just don't know whether the check for
being inside the bounds works or not so
we don't have to work that out but it's
just I'll explain that in a second it
would be kind of cool if it worked is is
a is the only thing
so instead of setting the same thing
real again I'm just gonna set it to
something that causes all of them to be
checked right and off we go okay
so let me talk a little bit about what I
was just saying and and I guess I don't
really know because we did some
optimization here on this so if we set
the radius to be negative then some
interesting things occur what ends up
happening is that the locations move
backwards to the opposite sides of the
cubes and the only thing I'm not sure
about is whether those radius values
create a problem here yeah so you can
see the problem that we would have which
is these values need to be absolute
valued that's about the only thing that
it looks like we've got a problem with
so really it looks like if we just be
the absolute value of these two if we
just do this I think that's all we need
to do we'll find out in a second I
thought I might be completely full of it
so here we go
looks like we're doing okay um so let's
let me just say what I was doing there
and why I was like okay this is a little
bit overly clever
you know sometimes clever things clever
things are fun to figure out because
well they're clever oops I forgot did I
put I did I put a 423 up here anywhere I
didn't I didn't
so anyway what I was saying here was
let's suppose we have one of these cubes
that we're talking about so what we had
optimized for before is and not even
optimized but actually wanted was we we
know that we're always ray casting from
outside because we're trying to gather
light from things that are away from us
so all we needed to go was let's take
the things that were you know sort of
directly facing us and ignore these
faces here and let's produce a hit right
let's produce a hit that tells us what's
going on the problem is once we start
talking spatial partition now there are
much larger volumes and some of them may
include the point that we're casting
from and we need to test whether we're
inside it so what I was saying is well
okay this won't work for that because if
I'm inside it and I'm going this
direction all of the faces that would
have been front facing to me are behind
me and I'll throw them out as not being
valid hits but instead what I can do is
say oh if I set the radius to negative
then my front faces actually become my
back faces so this face gets moved to
here and I will hit it right if I was
inside in fact anything that was gonna
be passing through here will hit the
back faces and furthermore I know that
I'm not even if I was outside it passing
through I know that I have to pass
through the front faces and the back
faces so I know I miss no rays in this
case checking against the front faces of
a cube only tells me whether or not I've
hit anybody who striking against the
front faces of a cube only tells me if I
enter the cube but check against the
back faces tells me whether I left the
cube right and so for a bounding volume
I want to know whether I could leave
cube because any ray that starts inside
or outside that passes through the cube
will have to leave it but only things
that start on the outside of the cube
have to enter it does that make sense so
this was just a cheeky way of doing this
that I think holds up it's not so clever
that I won't do it but we'll see if that
comes back to bite us in the backside
again this seems to be working ok so
let's just say all is well
yeah so what I want to do now is is try
to figure out yeah what to do here for a
building a sensible spatial partition
right I think what I'm going to do first
is just do something relatively crude
and then we'll work on expanding it I
don't know how much time I have left you
know what I you know what though the
bots probably does so we have a half an
hour so yeah I'm not gonna what I'll try
to do is build them a basic spatial
partition first that's not particularly
good and then what we can do is tomorrow
start to think about how to build
something that is maybe good and go from
there so here is our build spatial
partition call and what I want to do is
yeah again make this a little more
sensible and systemic here and we'll
kind of go from there so we've got some
issues that we have to address and I'm
not sure exactly how we want to address
them so
here are our problems right now we don't
have to take a hit on in direction in
order to iterate right when we iterate
through here we just go through and say
okay let's go ahead and raycast these
boxes and we get the sources by just
reading them out linearly there there's
no indirection here at all we just say
take the index and we directly read it
out of solution boxes if we are going to
spatial partition we have a problem
our boxes are stored continuously here
right and you know they're stored in
just a big array there's no indirection
there one right after each other
when we go to spatial partition then we
will have to either rearrange them in
that array which evolves a lot of memory
traffic to put things into their correct
locations in order to keep them so that
they are contiguous per sub box or what
we would have to do is have an
indirection that basically says read an
index and jump to that location to
figure out what it is and it's like
that's one of those things that you
really just don't know what the right
thing to do is
I think I'm gonna go with the I'm gonna
what I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna test
the in Direction speed first and I'll
see how bad it is I think that's what
I'd like to do first so let me go ahead
and try that so at the moment you know
we are running around in the steady
state we're getting about 35
milliseconds here something like this if
we take a look at the profile right you
can see that we're getting somewhere in
the order of 148 million cycles being
spent on the light propagation
computation so okay 148 million I want
to make sure I don't take an appreciable
hit for this and assuming that I don't
we'll probably use it so I'm going to go
ahead into the lighting solution here
and I'm going to add an indirection and
what we're gonna do is we're going to
look up into this box table every time
we go to actually reference a particular
box so inside here we have lighting
boxes you can see that there's a few
places where we do this so we do one
there that we do one here that we do one
here and we do one here yeah so output
lighting points that loops over the
boxes that one can still do it because
it's just looped blue looping over the
raw boxes themselves and that's fine so
that doesn't really affect anybody no
real issue there and furthermore we can
make this do loop over the commands
light box camp here for the time being
so it won't actually loop over the other
boxes which don't really have light
indexes associated with them yet right
so that's fine
there we go so everywhere we do solution
boxes now we want to do is have a little
inline function here
that's like get box and have a box index
here and instead what this is going to
do is return boxes plus box index right
and you see what I'm talking about where
it's it's in directed it's a little
nasty right it's adding some work there
that we really rather not do and we just
don't know how much that's going to
confuse the processor in its cashing
scheme alright so from now on in here we
need to do this
and I think that's all we're really
talking about so then all we have to do
is initialize this into something that
actually just mimics exactly what we
have right now and we should be good to
go
so for example in here I can just do a
four I loop like so I guess this could
be you 32 it doesn't even matter
what oops
do that alright so all I did was build
an interaction table that literally does
nothing and so yeah and hey that didn't
work at all so that's not great what did
I miss up there because I I wanted to
just make it so that it literally
doesn't do anything weird
uh so the box table is initialized - oh
yeah this has to be after we're done
sometimes it won't get this one so
that's fine
and honestly it looks like that didn't
have any effect
so actually adding an indirection there
does not appear to have been a
particularly problematic situation it's
still right hovering around pretty much
exactly where it was so yeah if it had
any kind of a performance impact it was
not a significant one so I don't feel
particularly bad about that so the
reason that I want to do that then as
the solution rather than moving things
around is it will reduce the memory
traffic to just reorganize u16s
and also it means that we can include
the same light box in multiples like if
we want to we can put a box in more than
one hierarchical box right so now we
have complete freedom to play with our
spatial partition because the same child
node could be put into it can be
completely loose basically if we want to
be right the same child node can be
placed in multiple places because since
there's an indirection table that
interaction table can point to something
twice it could be a one-to-many or I
should say many to one relationship in
that case
okay so once we've gotten that now we
can actually build an actual space
partition if we want to what we can do
here is say well alright let's just do a
standard thing where we subdivide these
boxes and we'll see what happens right
so what I'm gonna do here is I'm just
gonna say let's let's do something
that's right split box is probably the
wrong call what I probably want to do is
say add overlapping boxes and what I
want to do here is I want to pass a
lighting box that is the container and
then I'm gonna pass a range of boxes to
check and anything that overlaps the
container box we will add to the
container box right the dumbest possible
thing so I'm just gonna say like first
box index and box count as we've been
doing in here so what I'll say is okay
let's loop through for our test index
for our box index first last test in mix
first Boston if test index is less than
first block - is this plus box counts
right plus plus test index so then we
have our test box which is just whatever
oops
so in this case we have an a call
that'll just loop over all of the boxes
you give it an arranged and then it'll
pull out each of those boxes and then
all we have to do is say okay do these
two boxes overlap right so does does
does the box that we're testing touch in
some way the box that we're overlapping
right so what we want to do is say if
boxes were like we'll call these like
radius boxes right
if radius boxes overlap and we'll say
container P container radius test P
tests radius then what we need to do
here is we just need to say if they
overlap then what we're going to do is
we're going to target the
[Music]
we're gonna go ahead and target I just
thought of something else interesting
actually that I hadn't considered before
we're going to target the box to the the
box that we just tested we're going to
put that into the child list of the box
that we that we are adding to so we
found this container box here and it
needs to have its child count
incremented and it needs to have that it
needs to have this test boxes index
added to it so it's going to add to this
container this this testing mix that
would be the entirety of the overlapping
box pass and so what we can do here is
we can just say well you know as we go
through producing boxes that subdivide
the space what we can do is create new
boxes add the overlapping things to it
and just recurse down so will basically
say we'll sweep through all the boxes
that we have we'll split them into at
least two new boxes add them correctly
to whichever box to the box to which
they belong and then from there we'll
continue subdividing right so that seems
pretty straightforward nothing
particularly weird there and we'll just
stop when we get to some small number of
boxes contained I and that'll be the
last subdivision we do so that seems
fine to me
what we need to do is actually make that
happen so let's figure out how we're
gonna make that happen even right from
here what we would like to do is have a
tighter bound here potentially but yeah
we'll get to that later
all right so let's see how we're gonna
do this exact
Clee
you
so I think what I want to do here is say
that after this sort of special case
start up where we've created our initial
box with everything in it then from then
on I think we want to do something where
we yet where we start subdividing where
we start subdividing yeah all right so
we do space petition I'm going to do a
call called subdivide box here or let's
just call it split box and I'm gonna
pass the Box this is the root box and
the solution this code is going to be
really crappy because we're just playing
around with it now so I'm not gonna try
and actually think through how this is
going to be fast or what it's going to
do it's just going to be crappy that's
just the truth all right so then what I
want to do is say okay I've got this box
that I'm trying to split so this is my
like splitting box let's say or maybe
this is the parent box and what I want
to do is produce child boxes
something like this oh well um maybe I
don't have time to do that so let's not
do that here we go all right so we are
currently testing against the spatial
hierarchy we are just not building a
spatial hierarchy that includes more
than one parent node so it's not going
to do us any good tomorrow what we can
do is we can come back and actually
build a little bit of facial hierarchy
there and start to tune it to see if we
can get some better performance out of
it and specifically we want to try to
get to some better performance where we
have a lot more light sources so for
example if we take a look here you know
this isn't the worst framerate in the
world but it's because we're using a
subset of the scene if I was to go back
into handmade world mode and where we do
our screen stuff where we you know have
something here if I was to make this a
very large number where we're actually
creating a world that's more
representative of the number of elements
that we would actually have here oh I
guess that's even more than we can do at
the moment I think that's probably cuz
we don't actually have a good creation
called there but you can see how slow
this gets once there's more stuff in the
world so that's that's the part we're
really trying to tackle more than
anything else is that slow down and so
what you can see here is that when we
get our lighting solution scaled up a
bit too high looks like this even did
this wrap this wrapped the total value
that's how many boxes there were in the
world so we're more than 64,000 ooh
that's tough so I wonder if we're going
to have to expand those even to 32-bit
indices which is pretty tough if we were
gonna expend as it's a 32-bit indices
the places where that would have to
happen where I care about it is like
right here that's the part that's kind
of a little bit bad
but yeah
I mean I am okay with it but it's not my
favorite thing in the world but it looks
like we will have to do that
hmm so I guess that's what we'll
actually first do tomorrow's will let's
just ban that because that's going to be
too many of these assuming that is
actually what's going on which I assume
it is although I'm not sure why we
didn't hit an assertion there because it
should have asserted on trying to add
more than the number that that are
actually allowed to be in there which I
thought was yeah I'm not that's that's a
little confusing I'm not sure I
understand why that number is doing what
it's doing
so if I come up here and I take a look
at the call that actually pushes one of
these on here
quad bit mass for disarray we get these
crossed normal direction where's my push
cube call
really push cube call so this right here
[Music]
what is light data with
so as long as light data width is still
less than 64,000 it should have asserted
their which means we're not passing more
than that number of boxes so why was
that number so low you see what I'm
asking right like why was that number so
low that was getting printed out there
I'm super confused about that
because it says that the total number of
boxes is 358 but we know that couldn't
possibly be true could it
no no I guess that could be true
hmm nevermind so I guess we're fine
we're fine I panicked for no reason so I
turned the lighting off temporarily I'm
gonna go ahead and move to the other
area here so looking at here yeah so I
guess the box count really isn't that
bad so that's okay never mind I panicked
for no reason all right let's go ahead
and go to the Q&amp;A because I would really
like to keep that under so that they can
be packed a little more tightly for this
routine if possible at least that's my
preference so yeah so I'm hoping that we
don't actually have to go up above the
64k boundary not to mention the fact
that's that's a heck of a lot of
lighting points to be considering yeah
can you try lighting as it is in a
release build yes I could that might
take a second so in a release filled we
would have to get rid of all of these so
in a release build we're like this and I
don't know even that might not really be
getting rid of all the stuff that we
need to get rid of so I'm not 100% sure
but there you go
so I mean it's still you know again it's
still that N squared is just too slow it
doesn't matter what mode you're in it's
too much for the computer to handle you
know I'm saying so yeah that's just not
it's just not gonna happen
but that's that's what it'd be like I
can also try if you wanted to know what
it's like when we don't have a lot of
rooms
so framerate wise that seems fine
you mentioned something with the need to
handle concave and convex cells
differently when raycasting do - I
believe the phospholipid and leaving a
single face of a concave solid multiple
times any chance you could explain a
little more how this could affect us if
you have Congress less sure it's it's
not a single face it's just the object
itself so hmm there are certain
properties of convex solids that make
them different from concave solids in
the case of Ray casting so you know for
certain things concave solids and convex
solids they don't differ in other things
they do and so it depends on Witt
whether the algorithms are using happen
to depend on the properties of concave
solids I mean of convex solids you're
not recasting happens to for most
optimizations the reason for it is as
follows here is a convex solid here is
almost the same solid but now I've made
it concave so the problem here that we
face is that when we're ray casting
against these and let's say I take the
exact same ray so this is the ray in
space
when you take a look at array and you
say what phases of an object do I need
to consider when ray casting this ray
against a solid a convex solid has the
property that in order to enter the
solid you must enter through a front
face that's just true of convex solids
because you know for a convex solid that
a face that does not fake point at you
always has some other face pointing at
you that comes before it right so for
example here's a face that points away
from you and you know that the entire
region where a ray could be hitting this
face right no matter where it is there's
always some other face there that is
pointing in in a facing direction to
whatever the Ray is and there's never a
way to construct an another ray that
could hit this face but not one of the
front facing rays the way to think about
this is that any way that I might split
this into two sets of faces requires me
to pick two vertices right and split
along the plane that connects those two
vertices right that is the only way I
could possibly ever split this into two
sets of faces without splitting a face
in half right so all of these faces are
on one side to split all these faces are
on the other side of the split for a
convex solid I know that once I have
performed that split for any face on
this side the angle of the face relative
to the split plane is always one it's
always strictly on inside the bounds of
this faces angles right so for example
if I took a look at right here this
split point and right here what I can do
is I can take this direction and this
direction which are the two faced
directions that are there and I know
that
nothing on the other side can ever be
right any further inside than those two
angles they can never cross past that
winding so all of these facing
directions are all outside of the range
specified by these two imagine it in a
circle I took these two here's the down
one and here's sort of the out one when
I split the faces I knew that I produced
a set of angles of faces that fall
strictly within this region and one that
falls strictly within this region and
there's no overlap so when I ask about
array that's coming in and I say what
are the the faces that I could possibly
consider here well I know that if I was
to go ahead and split the Ray in this
way and say I'm only gonna deal with the
front faces here right then what i knew
about convex solids is that those front
faces create a single unified front
right whatever they are those front
faces produce a range that produce a
single unified front such that there is
no other face outside of the range that
might be there is no face on the other
segregated part of the object that whose
whose direction could fall in that range
right so what that means is I have a
clean split and I know that my first
intersection
my earliest intersection will only fall
inside that range because no face out
here could even be involved in it right
for a convex solid the same is not true
for a convex solid when I split the
faces if I was to slip them into front
faces and back faces I don't have a
continuous range anymore so for example
if I was to split these into front and
back faces relative to this rate I would
get this one and this one but then I
would also get this one so now there's a
hole in the rain
where this back face is occurring right
does that make sense
when ends up happening now is I end up
in a slightly weird scenario where now I
cannot consider my object to strictly be
based on the front faces for purposes of
total consideration of what's going on
in this volume right because I don't
necessarily know what happens in these
external areas so if I was for example
trying to test to see whether array
passed through this particular object
right and furthermore whether certain
things inside the object needed to be
tested I'm at quite a bit of a
disadvantage because I don't really know
until I do testing on all the faces
whether what the Ray really did right
relative to it or where a point really
was relative to it for example let's say
I gave you a point right and I said does
this point is this point inside or out
of this concave object well if I wanted
to know that information well you know I
guess
so there's a couple of different ways to
think about this
so here's what I'll say
in the case of the specific thing that
we happen to be using it for where I
said the back I'm just gonna test the
back faces to see whether the Ray ever
passes through this thing in that
particular case I think I may have
misspoke when I said that the concave
objects couldn't use that property
because it might be that they always
actually also can I'm scared to say that
because I don't know if it's actually
true but the thing I was about to say is
it necessary is relevant let me finish
so if I wanted to know whether or not a
point let's say is inside one of these
volumes in the case of a convex volume
all I really have to know is whether or
not I am on the inside
of all of the of the points all the
planes right so if you know all of the
normals of these faces all point in
towards me then I know that I am that I
am completely inside of it right so
because I know that there's always a
perfect classification of all of these
of all of the planes and if I'm on the
same side of all of them that I know
that I'm inside the solid similarly if I
want to test for outside I can do the
same thing if I want to test to see if
I'm outside all I have to do is find a
single plane pointing that I'm on the
outside of and I'm done right even just
one plane telling me I was outside the
solid and I know that I'm not outside
the solid but and I know that I'm not
inside the solid right for a concave
things get a lot more complicated for
concave I can't tell because I'm always
gonna be outside of some part of a
concave shape and inside of another part
of the concave shape no matter where I
am because it's concave so what I have
to do is I have to go ahead and say well
let me count how many crossings I have
in a particular direction to see whether
I was inside or outside right like I say
well okay I crossed it once I must be
inside
I cross it twice and now I'm outside
right so things often get a lot more
complicated when you go here but when
I'm thinking just thinking it through
the concept that I literally said which
is that if
this is what I said I think you may be
right to call me on that because I think
that may be true for concave because as
long as you test the back faces like the
way we've got this routine set up right
now it wouldn't fly because if you look
at the way we have this routine set up
now
we only ever test three back faces we
just assume that there's only three back
faces because we know how the shape is
and so it's you know it's highly
optimized for the fact that we know
exactly what we need to know about the
cube so this is like highly optimized to
just check these three back faces we
know are the back faces of the cube and
we know it's concave and all its so
optimized to take all that into account
but if he has had a generic shape I
think you might if it was closed as long
as it's closed meaning it doesn't have
holes in it I don't say that as long as
you know that it actually produces a
solid with no cracks right so if it if
it was cracked so like for example let's
say you know this is a closed convex
solid right let's suppose it was cracked
with a solid like that now I don't you
have there is no definition of inside or
outside of it so you like forget those
kind of shapes temporarily because I
don't really want to talk about those
because there's no I
you'd have to start coming up with what
you mean by inside or outside of it
right so ignoring that if we just said
well we just want closed convex solids
to work I think it still works I think
if you have array and you just test the
back faces right that's a front face
so if you just taste the faces that are
back facing to this thing and you hit
one of them then you pass through it and
whether you're inside or outside I think
that works so I think I shouldn't have
said that I think that technique would
work for concave as well we don't need
it - so if I'm wrong about that it's
okay cuz we're only doing concave anyway
and I promise you it works for concave
because I don't see any way it could
fail the concave con I'm sorry I promise
you it works for convex for concave I'm
thinking it through here I guess I don't
know it seems like you could just apply
the same technique I think it I think it
would just work so never mind never mind
and you know and if why do we skip the
part with placing cubes over entities
such as trees in the hero and also they
should receive light in some way right
yes we will eventually do that we just
don't it doesn't matter right now
so I'm just focusing on getting the
lighting working and then we can worry
about how we want to place it because we
will do that when we do the world
generation stuff we'll play with a
little bit more we notice your fur color
and males are color coded what are the
values yes they I tried to sort of make
them similar I don't know what the color
is because it doesn't print it out here
necessarily but in for coder you can see
them
so I believe this is probably the color
that you're talking about
and so in mean Milton doesn't have I
don't think RGB sliders so I couldn't
set it directly so what I did there is I
just tried to get it as close as I could
[Music]
okay so I think that's it for today
tomorrow we'll finish building that
harking and then we should be good to go
on playing with getting the lighting up
to a reasonable speed and we also have
to end up making a decision at some
point about whether it's gonna be on the
GPU side the CPU side because that's
sort of a separate issue as well all
right thanks everyone for joining me for
those sort of handmade hiro-san a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along streams
at home you can always go to hammer here
org and pre-order the game it comes with
a source code as it is every day after
we finish it so you can play around with
it and do your own experiments we also
have an episode guide you can go to if
you wanna catch up on old version of the
series and we have a schedule but you
can go to if you want to fight we're
gonna be live we will be back here
tomorrow for more handmade hero hope see
you there for that till then everyone
have fun programming LCM internet take