all righty hello everyone and welcome to
another edition of handmade Hero the
show recode a complete-game live on
stream today is day 280 so if you were
trying to follow along with stream at
home you should start with day two seven
nine source code and you should get
ready for some debugging because what we
are doing today is getting all of our
changes working that we made as far as
the way that entities are stored in our
system because we're starting to make
that be a more realistic part of the of
the game now more a real system that can
actually handle what we need it to
handle for our game and so due to this
we obviously need to to think that stuff
through and make it work a little bit
more reasonably so
what we did at the end of yesterday's
stream is we'd sort of gotten everything
compiling instead of but we haven't
debugged anything I guess I fixed a
little bit of something because just I
like couldn't quite let it go I fixed a
few little things so it would run
properly but we're not actually running
correctly we're just not crashing so we
have a bunch of work to do to go verify
that things are working right and also
somebody already posted on the forums
who I guess is following along every day
said we had a size of problem which
sounded pretty much like exactly what I
would expect for when we were packing
stuff in I believe it would have been
size of source like here so you can like
the the pack size here when I was doing
this I was careless we actually want the
size of the the thing we're packing is
an entity not the pointer so this should
technically be look like this remember
we're not actually doing packing at the
moment all we're doing at the moment is
we are sort of using the we're just sort
of block copying entities into world
chunks when we sort of pack them and the
idea is that we'll just keep doing that
for a little while and then eventually
once we actually care we'll come in here
and do some work to like sort of compact
them down because eventually I think
they'll be too large and you won't want
to do block copies like that so that's
how that works
and so there was definitely a bug in
there and there was another one problem
with stored index stored index though is
kind of janky at the moment and so
stored index really doesn't want to be
called stored index anymore stored index
just wants to be called ID there's no
such thing as like storage indexing or
anything like that what there used to be
so really the name stored index itself
is erroneous and we haven't really fixed
that yet so rather than debug something
that's not quite correct this we might
as well do one more change here since
we're gonna do go through all the
trouble of debugging it all I kind of
want to go through and say well from now
on we'll actually have a notion in here
of the correct thing which is a set of
storage index this is actually the
entity ID which is what we actually want
right so then we'll come through here
and we'll take a look at where all the
stuff is being used right and we'll
change storage index to an ID so in
store entity reference this is what we
want meaning we'll be grabbing out of
the ref what the ID actually is
similarly when we pass these things in
here that makes sense that we would be
taking a look at those storage indexes
like so when we record that for adding
an entity that is also what we will
store there is that ID same here you
know what I should probably be doing
that I should probably be doing that not
in this I should do it in this window so
we don't go behind my head it needs to
be a thing in for coder since we're all
using it to stream that like is it you
can put a little thing that knows that
there's a square down there or something
but anyway
alright so storage index ID do we
actually have any more is that it
let's see so get hash from ID let's
actually change the name of that get
hash from nowhere that actually is there
it is alright
get hash from let's see storage index D
yep yep yep yep yep yeah when we add in
the yeah I guess that's still looking at
it we don't really need to pass that
anymore when we do add entity in fact I
might as well take care of that now so
when we do an identity to the to the
thing really we can just sort of pass in
the lo here because this will be the
unpack operation in the future and in
fact you know we could actually make
this be a thing do we do we get rid of
the non spatial flag I think I said I
wanted to so we could also get rid of
that non spatial flag entirely and and
just say that this isn't going to be a
thing anymore either
so it's always going to do you know
something like this where it checks the
MD overlaps rectangle code and it's
going to do that ad and be something
more like this so this is actually an
unpack operation and so we might want to
start calling that I guess there's
really no no need to do it immediately
but that's where that's gonna happen let
me go ahead and get rid of these as well
do we need to call make end of the
spatial to be ever call make entity
spatial I don't even know if we do if we
don't again a lot of these things are
gonna kind of be changed now so this is
always going to complete like so but
again a lot of this stuff even that is
really not a necessary piece of code
anymore that gets sim space P we can
sort of streamline that because it's
only gonna happen during the unpack so
no one should ever be calling that
function anyway it's gonna be directly
done in the pack unpack phase so a lot
of that stuff is gonna get a lot cleaner
I think all right so let's take a look
at entity here we know that we were
passing sort of redundant information
like the ID and the source but we don't
really need to do that because if we
want the ID we can just get it out of
the source let's take a look at the rest
of these so storage index is going to be
ID now here obviously that's all fine
checking for things like
illusions is fine right these are all
IBA IDs all right
so non-spatial if if non-spatial is not
set property based logic goes here
better hash function so this is saying
if non-spatial is not they neither of
them are set then the result is that
they can collide I guess is what we're
saying
which I guess is always gonna be true
now right and then you know you would
need more logic here but again that this
is all stuff that I think we're probably
going to start to clean up in a
different way anyway so let's take a
look at those rules now I think those
would probably be in the world mode so
where is the pairwise collision rule
there it is so these this is just gonna
be ID a and ID B okay so then we've got
let's see non-spatial we don't have to
care about that that goes away because
it's gone now we don't care about this
at all here and then all of this can get
uninvented because everybody is now a
spatial entity by default yeah and let's
see so we've got storage indexes it's
got ID here and I guess these can all
just be storage index B yes yes yes yes
go there we go
nothing to see here just changing all of
these to the correct word yep yep okay
so when we say make entity non-spatial
this is the sword to the sword I wanted
to get rid of so the sword should not
even be here anymore and in fact in the
entity types I don't really know where
we were specifying that probably instant
Legion skill because again this code is
kind of all old but I don't ever even
want the sword to be there right I don't
want to me that so let's see we want
stops on collision is always going to be
true it would appear because it's true
for everyone but the sword and there's
no such thing as a sword anymore
so we'll get groups so we'll get rid of
that
and we don't care about any of this even
in fact all this stuff is just nonsense
and most of its gonna go away it was
just from when we were sort of playing
around in getting things working
if non-spatial is not set and entity
flag movable so we know non-spatial is
never set so really all we're checking
here is whether it's movable right any
type sword is not a thing and off we go
I want to double check that when I was
in the same region stuff I want to make
sure I didn't mess that up when we did
there result equals true code so if set
collides and collides we assume it's
true then we look up to see whether we
have a rule and then we if we do we put
can collide so yeah I think that's
correct
right it's like you always assume that
the two things can collide if they are
you know if they are set to be
collidable unless you have a rule that
tells you otherwise so that's fine all
right so I think now we're a little bit
closer to where we need to be let's
start running things and probably start
stepping through things as well like
creation and stuff to figure out what's
going on now you can see that we're in
the red screen when that what that means
in general is that we don't actually
have any heroes active because if
there's no heroes active it'll it'll
sort of dump back to the main screen so
we kind of have to make sure that we
have the rest of our stuff working
properly but hold on one second well we
sort of figure that out now let's see
move entity
all of this stuff should be fine and so
I think I just need to go into handmade
world mode and start looking at the code
where we create entities and pack
entities and stuff like that because
that's presumably mostly where we care
about this so yeah and so this code here
begin in beginning to be where I put in
the ID we do a zero struct here so
really this needs to happen immediately
after this and these have to be bound
together because otherwise we would
clear the ID value that we were just
setting so that also has to be set in
order for stuff to work obviously hey
we're getting a little closer we're
still not seeing anything though so now
it least believes that there are heroes
in the game so our stuff is getting
created but we still have this problem
that we are that we're not actually
seeing anything so we got to work on
that this is obviously an assertion
because we haven't talked about how
we're going to delete and entities yet
and so that assertion should stay in
there because we're gonna want to
address that right away
basically like that this assertion is
something we need to as soon as we get
our bugs out that's the first thing we
want to implement because right now we
don't have the notion of deletion and
like I said deletion is now going to
just be in the in the stream out you
just don't stream those enemies out so
if an entity gets like marked well
basically it mark deleted and then when
it gets time to stream it out it won't
get streamed out and so that's what we
want to do sort of immediately after we
fix the bug we currently have which is
that we're not actually working right
that we don't actually see at these
entities so let's let's also just double
check because I don't actually know I
want to look at the the sort of used
debug camera and I want to make sure
that like we don't see anything nearby
like we're not just slightly wrong right
and as far as I can tell we're not
because it looks to me like you know
there's there's nothing in any of here
so we're we're pretty wrong right now
all right so what I'm going to do here
is just go and double check how we're
doing our and the spatial stuff and then
I'm gonna start
through the code to see like what we've
actually created and what happens when
we start a sim so I can kind of get a
feel for it so what you can see here
when I do the begin low entity and the
end of these stuff we take this world
position P and that's where the entity s
sense was going to be and when we do PAC
entity into world we're calling into the
the world code here to do that so when
we call a PAC entity in the world you
can see what's happening there we get a
world chunk out of the world and it's
wherever we were told that this thing
was and then we go to the World Arena
and say if you can't like we pass it in
so if you can't find one that already
exists at this location create the chunk
so that's how we know we'll always get a
chunk back and then when we get the
chunk back we call packed entity into
chunk we could also assert this here
because this has to always come back
valid then when we go into packet into
the chunk we take a look at what the
pack size is we've got it we look to see
if we can fit if it can't fit then we go
ahead and make room for it otherwise we
assume that we can and we go in here and
pack the the entity in at the end of the
information so I guess what I would say
is right off the bat I can see a pretty
obvious problem here which is that we're
not actually storing the entity's
position during this packing process
where you can kind of see that we don't
record that location in any way right so
we need some way of we need somewhere
central that that actually occurs so
when I pass in a world position for pack
entity into world I'm assuming that what
we should probably do is make sure that
at is reflected in the actual entity
information so that's obviously a
problem right so here's sim region and
you can see that we've got our RP here
and we've got our chunk P our chunk
position here so at least for right now
since we haven't really started working
on this part of the code which is how
we're storing the entities in you know
the actual data inside the entities we
should at least say that in here when we
do our PAC entity code we should update
that piece of information so we want to
be able to say like okay the
entity that we're packing its chunk P
should probably be set to to act and
it's a p-value which is its displacement
I guess that does can can just be
ignored because when this is unpacked it
can it's gonna do the mapping to get it
to get it back out right and I assume
that the way that that happens let's
double check that is in sim region it's
going to read that chunk P out again so
when we do the call to identity right
here you can see get some space P and we
pass that low that's what I want to see
so what does get some space P do at the
moment so it yeah it looks into that
chunk P and gets it back out so that
should keep that piece of information
stored properly at this point but but
yeah so again we're still not there yet
not seeing anything so let's go ahead
and start stepping through I want to see
a few pieces of information just to give
me an idea of where the bugs are at this
point which is that when I come into
this code here handmade world mode I
want to see what happens when we do that
first unpack so I want to see I want to
restart before anything else happened I
want to jump in here and see the very
first time we go to begin sim I want to
see if we get any actual entities out
and if we do what they are right so when
we come through here I'm gonna set a
breakpoint here to make sure we don't
fall out of the loop and then I'm I set
a breakpoint here to see if we get any
so you notice we didn't get anything so
what that means is that our initial pack
and where we're looking so are like our
camera for example is not actually
looking at where we put our entities or
something similar right so one problem
with that is well right now it's true
that we wouldn't update the camera if we
didn't call the sim code I want to just
make sure quickly and this should have
been happening before if it was a bug so
presumably it's not but I just want to
double check because since we're coming
back to this code after a long time we
want to make sure I kind of know what's
going on when we create the world which
actually should be appear somewhere
right where is it
there must be a place where we create
the world in order to create the world
you must make an apple pie from scratch
so here you go you can see we do this
rule this world mode counter P equals
new camera P and here's where we set
that up so in theory the camera should
start off looking at those entities in
theory so it we probably should check to
see what we're doing wrong in terms of
why we're not seeing any of that because
I don't know so let's see we have we
have a bunch of stuff here where we do
our sort of add code and we generally
always send the those positions which we
use we use map into chunk space for that
and we use the sort of the very basic
stuff for that when we're doing that it
seems like that should be done correctly
and when we do pack entity into world I
did double-check that that was doing it
so I want to step through to see if
maybe there's something about the
packing that isn't working the way that
I would have thought so when we do pack
into let's see down upon a pack entity
in the world I'm gonna call the game or
just I'm going to restart it and see
what actually happens so let's see first
of all what we are think we're doing
here we're calling add standard room and
so we're kind of going through these
these ABS tile X's and Y's here right
and it looks like those are you know
that those should be relatively close to
the zero because they're they're pretty
they're pretty nearby so when we call an
entity what we're passing for P is zero
zero zero which is a totally reasonable
place to want to put something and
something that should be visible on the
screen so that's actually close that you
know that's close to where the camera is
going to be looking so in theory this
should be okay so when we come in here
and we're asking for the zero zero zero
chunk let's see what we actually get
back looks all reasonable for the most
part
and then we initialize that sort of that
source entity that we're packing we
initialize its position we jump into PAC
entity and chunk and we look through
here we can see that it doesn't have any
room for anything because there isn't
even a block to begin with and so what
I'm going to do here is just step
through here and say okay there are no
free blocks obviously so we create a
fake free block and put it on there so
that we can use it we grab it out and
and then we clear it right so now we've
got a block we can use here it is and
it's got sort of these residuals things
in here that we're gonna get rid of
eventually but then it has entity data
which is what we actually care about so
we make sure that it has room which by
now it should because we've basically
ensured that it does and then we've got
this destination pointer which is just
going to be basically the beginning of
the entity data so we we take we snap
that so we can use it to pack and then
we advance by the amount of pack size so
we're basically like pushing something
on there now as you can see we're going
to set cold set that right there and we
can double check now to make sure that
our desk pointer actually contains a
reasonable entity which is oh it's a u8
by default so I have to actually cast it
to an entity so let's let's go ahead and
do that here is it casted to an enemy so
you can see it's ID is one which is what
we would expect for the first entity we
can see that it's location 0 0 which we
want is a floor element which seems good
so all of this seems fine right that
seems totally fine no no weirdness there
so then we pop out here and this part
yeah is just gonna create more of these
and off we go so as that happens I don't
think anything particularly ODS going on
but let's jump in just to one more here
and see if we can't watch it pack into
something where there was already one
hopefully right so we should be able to
catch one it's getting packed into a
chunk that existed and I don't know you
know how long it'll take us to find that
but I'm just gonna set a breakpoint and
watch so there you go so in this case
we're now packing into one that actually
already existed you can see that it's
had one entity packed into it and now
we're packin another end
into it and so I want to go in and
verify that that actually works it's not
that that probably has all that much to
do with our problem but I just want you
to see so here we are we've got you know
we're gonna go through and we're gonna
take a look at what the block looks like
here we can see that the entity data
still has you know a certain amount of
size considered on it we are going to
grab the desk out but what I'm going to
do first before we do that is I'm going
to past this guy this entity data to an
MD star so I can see what it looks like
and I want to verify that there are
going to be two entities after this is
done so here's the two entities that I
would expect to see one is a valid
entity one is not yet about in me and
now when I do this pack I should see it
write directly into here and not touch
anything in here just make sure the
pointers are set properly and it looks
like that all worked exactly as we would
expect so so far the packing looks
pretty good not a lot of mystery there
so that seems reasonable when we come
through and do the rest of this stuff
we're just going to be creating a lot
more entities in exactly the same way
and so let's take a look now it begins
Sam and CY maybe that's having a problem
now we've watched for example an entity
get packed into cells 0 0 0 or I should
say chunk 0 0 0 so I'd like to see you
know do we ever try to iterate over 0 0
0 and if we do why are we not seeing
anything there right so I'm gonna set a
breakpoint here and you can see our
chunk values so I'm gonna go chunk x y&amp;z
and I'm just gonna let that loop on
through right and in fact I guess I can
I can do it out here I can wait till my
Z value gets to 0 then I can wait till
my Y value gets to 0 and then I can wait
until my x value gets to 0 now I know
that this value I watched it have an
entity packed into it so now I'm gonna
see what happens when I actually step in
does that occur so we call get world
shrunk internal here we go
we do not find anything unusual about it
we did find a chunk it matched the first
time so we didn't have to enter this
loop at all we now have a pointer to the
pointer to the chunk we grab the result
out of that here is that result it does
aha well that makes it easy so yeah I
don't even know if we need this value
but we are using it currently and that's
the problem I don't know if you noticed
that I saw it maybe I saw it a little
bit before you did if you were not eagle
eye or if twitches compression was not
letting you see the screen well enough
but if you notice what happens in here
is in these worlds we still had a
residual value that's how many entities
were in there and we are using it right
now in the future I don't think we will
we'll just probably stream I don't know
maybe we will cuz maybe that'll be the
easier way to tell when the stream is
done I don't know we'll see but at the
moment we are using it which means that
every time we pack an entity we had
better well actually increment the
chunks entity counter because if we
don't then we won't actually know how
many are in there and we'll always think
there are none so that's probably what
was going on
oops and that's the block method chunk
sorry and so that's probably why we
weren't getting any hits in that main
part of the code okay so let's keep
going now and we'll see where we're at
okay so now we're actually back to good
we've actually got all the stuff going
that we were having before although
there are still some weirdnesses like
for example we're not getting correct I
did idea of the head and the body
they're exactly like you can kind of see
the body stop tracking the head for some
reason so we've got a little more work
to do but we're getting closer to having
completed this change in its entirety so
that's always good and yeah
let me go ahead and exit out of this and
what the causes of that would be
specifically uh is kind of odd so I say
so if we go to our sim region the way
that we were doing this and it'll
probably remain somewhat similar to this
throughout the course of development is
we have this notion of an entity
reference here and you can kind of see
what's going on with that right and what
we want to do with the entity reference
is we want to make sure that the entity
reference is not getting cleared in some
kind of unreasonable way and I think
what probably in fact I can almost
guarantee I know what happens here
those entity references are resolved now
at the incorrect time in fact I think I
even mentioned this when we went through
it if you look at get entity by ID you
can see that it does a get hash here
that process of unpacking the entity
needs to wait until the very end it
needs to wait until the sim region is
done unpacking all the entities and have
put all the entities into their hash
buckets otherwise if it just gets
unlucky and the head is before the body
or the bodies before the head one of
them will not be able to identify the
other right and so we need to make sure
that all the entities have gotten
unpacked and their pointers added to the
hash table before we start looking up
anything in them so I'm assuming that
it's an ADD entity that's our problem
here you can see in add entity raw we've
got this code to call load entity
reference and load entity reference is
really probably is is almost certainly
where our problem lies right you can
kind of see what's happening here we
call get hash from ID right there so we
don't want that sort of thing to be
happening at all
furthermore I'd like to take a quick
look at this we've got identity and
identity raw and I think now since we're
focusing on the streaming being really
the only way that you're allowed to put
any these into and out of the sim I
think we can start to collapse the
down a little bit so if we take a look
at a Dundee and a dandy raw the only
difference between them is one of them
you pass the ID and the other one you
pass the actual entity pointer right and
so I think we probably want to clean
this up a little bit and collapse those
down since the cases we were handling
before for this were we're simply not
relevant anymore or are simply not
relevant anymore I should say so if you
look when we're calling identity which
is the only way we ever call it anymore
we do a entity overlaps rectangle of the
total volume sim bounds soul situation
right so I'm gonna take a look here at
atom D and just make sure we know where
we call it so you're gonna see we're
calling identity and I'm just curious it
seems to me that we're basically double
counting oh wait no the updatable flag
is just the thing that tells us whether
it's internal in the inner area so
that's fine so what I'm gonna do here is
I'm just gonna take where we were
calling at NV raw before I'm going to
take and I'm going to grab this function
and I'm going to sort of stick it in
into into this one here so we don't need
to call get hash from ID for this guy
or any of that stuff because that's
already been taken care of right that's
something that we already know where we
already know the entity's dest or
whatever although no I take it back
we still need to we do still need to do
that we always need to actually get that
ID and fill it out I suppose so I'm
gonna put that in here and I'm gonna say
we just do that upfront so here we get
the ID I'm sorry we get the hash from
the ID and we make sure that it's
actually something that we need to fill
out which is entry pointer equals zero
this is really an assertion now because
you can never have to end these with the
same ID come out that would be like a
major major problem if that I ever
actually occurred so that's really an
assertion that it better never happened
we then come through and make sure that
we can actually store this thing by
checking it against the max count we're
allowed to sim and assuming that that
actually works then we can go in here
and start to actually do
other stuff to it you can see in here
if the simpie pointer there is valid
we'll go ahead and and set that location
now the sim it seems to me that that
should always be set so I'm not actually
sure what it should either always we
said are not set in other words like we
only have one place that calls it now
and so I feel like that sim space thing
yeah is has already been called and
we're already getting a pointer to it so
I feel like this is kind of a bit
redundant at this point and we really
don't need to worry about this case
anymore
this should be working oops
this should be working this way all the
time there should never be a case where
it's not going through that path and so
then we can come down here and say this
part where we do you know this simply
that's that's done alright so when we
come up here now we still have a bunch
of work to do obviously I'm just doing
that very simple count there let me see
here Emily this is guest entity I guess
let's go ahead and take a look at where
entity is called so this is desk and the
desk equals source load entity reference
guest head is set enemy flag siming
source add flags to sending so we don't
really want to be doing this to the
source because the source is a fake
thing now and the siming thing is not a
thing anymore that's all just you know
we were using that for protection before
but we're not doing any of that anymore
because you can't if you were going to
lock you lock on the chunk level you
don't have to lock on a per entity level
anymore so that's all gone this is just
setting the desk stuff up correctly
there setting the simpie the ID the
updatable stuff will be set by doing the
check that it was doing before and so
now I think that's all much cleaner and
and doing the correct thing okay and if
we need to return the entity I don't
think we're returning entities anymore
right so we would just have this would
just be a void because we're not
actually doing any that work on them
outside after the after the
decompression step
okay so now we should see exactly the
same thing but we should have the same
bug we have not touched the bug we just
cleaned up that code right so we should
still be able to get the body to detach
like there we go and so now we have to
actually focus on fixing that problem of
making sure that everyone decompresses
first and then we do a separate step so
again it's not the most efficient thing
and maybe we need to think about how we
might solve that but at the moment we'll
just do the simplest possible thing at
first and see to get us sort of to where
we need to go which is we need to have a
like connect entity pointers a phase or
something right and what we would do
there is we pass the sim region and what
it will do is it'll just loop over
because remember we've got the way the
sim region works here is it just has
some number of entities in it right so
all we're going to do is we're gonna say
okay for every entity that was actually
in this sim region we're going to go
through we're gonna grab that NV and we
want to remap the pointers in it now so
it would be after the fact so this thing
right here where we do load entity
reference load entity reference is
actually going to be done external like
this okay and so now when you know if we
just ran it at this point what we would
expect to see
oops missing - plus there what we would
expect to see is well two things first
of all we would expect to not have to I
don't even know that load entity
reference needs to be an actual thing
anymore
but if it does it certainly doesn't need
the world mode for any particular
purpose
so we can fix that we go but what I was
going to say is if we ran it now we
should see your head and the body should
be completely well and of course we
can't even get past that because we just
these things don't even have connections
so the head is is pointing to not
or at least should be pointing to
nothing and any head pointer well that's
actually oh no that's okay
right yeah because it's just it's it's
just invalid it's garbage data because
this function is never getting called
right so what we need to do now is after
all of our stuff has been unpacked and
we can now know that we can remap
everything then we can just call connect
entity pointers and let it run through
that list just one time to connect
anything that needs to get connected via
the hash table so now we should be good
to go and in theory now you would not be
able to disconnect this little fellow
anymore right
all right so that's good so let's
continue on this a little bit further
let's just try to clean up some more of
this and just again we're just trying to
get rid of some of those vestigial
remains that we have before we start
digging into the entity stuff a little
bit more specifically and maybe creating
some more stuff right that we can play
with and and so on and so forth
so at the moment we've got renamed sumit
identity as a to do well that's been
done so that's great and consuming maybe
I'll move this up to the top as well so
people can always talk about it
underneath if they would like to again
so now if we have this entity flag
swimming is no longer a flag so we can
delete it and presumably nobody is
looking for it and we that is actually
true so now we have our entity code this
entity code
I don't really know can we move this
entity code out into into something more
into like the entity file for example as
well so I'm gonna go ahead and do a
little bit of cleanup there just make
that any mode I want to see cuz we have
a hand-made entity H and I'm just
curious to know if it would be possible
for us to move this guy to start moving
some of these things out
because we have all this stuff that's
ostensibly entity related and it's all
in the same thing I just want to know is
that actually necessary so I'm going to
grab this all of this and I'm gonna sort
of grab that out and I'm just going to
put it in NV dot H so there it is
we'll see if that works so let's see
here this is struct entity yeah entity
IDs so it looks like for some reason the
order of these maybe there's a reason
for it but looks like the order of these
is a little bit backwards so hand made
entity it comes after sim region I'm not
sure why that is
yeah that doesn't make any sense all
right so we've got hand made entity now
and that's all set in here and that now
has
all this code that we wanted to be
isolated over in the entity file so it's
a little bit easier for us to keep track
of right
and we've also have our entity that's
EPP which basically doesn't have
anything in it but we'll probably start
to have a lot more stuff in it as we
start to build out the logic for the
game and they'll just be tons of
different entity code stuff that we want
okay so let's go in the sim region here
and take a look at what actually remains
in some region this point we can now
delete this forward declaration I
believe so you can kind of see how this
all plays out nothing particularly
unusual here in the end the sort of code
that we have in here is now more
isolated to the sim which is good but we
still you know if there's a fair bit of
gentleness here but it's it's you know
it's starting to look a little bit more
reasonable we've got you know we've got
the simulation there we've got the world
storage we've got the entities we've
broken it down into some pieces that
seem relatively like their systems that
would work and grow you know sort of
isolated from each other in a certain
sense and so that's feeling relatively
nice now the next thing that I want to
do is I guess I would like to go back to
sort of the physical way that we were
the the way that we were creating things
in terms of their like their location
and they're sort of physicality like
they're the Box NISS of them and their
movement I think that's the next thing
that we kind of need to start looking at
so what I would like to do is I'd like
to go to handmade world mode and just
start looking at exactly how we're
creating these like the worlds and so on
for example I'm going to take out the up
and down the the Z up and down kind of
situation I believe you can do that just
by going like this and then I'm gonna
let us create you know eight screens or
something like that and I want to just
see if I can get us to a point where
we're roughly like being able to explore
like we would in a normal situation
because I believe do you have a bunch of
problems here so you can see what
happened we already have a kind of weird
problem there and I remember we had this
thing - if you
over the edge and stuff we just have
some weird stuff going on so I think the
next thing we have to do is just go fix
the bugs that we have in that oh no you
know what we need to do that can wait
till tomorrow what we need to do is we
have an assertion we can fix this one
right here so how do we delete things so
what I'd like to do for deleting things
again I think we already pretty much
know how that's going to work it's a
very simple problem for us what we can
do is have an entity flag deleted and if
the enemy flag deleted is set then that
just means and see here we go we don't
care by this because all this stuff is
gonna get reworked a little bit anyway
the enemy flag deleted gets set then we
simply just don't we just don't stream
that entity app right so that it just
gets deleted as a consequence of the end
of the the sim right so then it's really
easy to delete things too but let's go
ahead and implement that part first so
when we do our I guess it's the package
world here so when we do this code what
we need to do is say all right as we go
through these entities what we want to
do is say okay before you do anything
else if whatever this entity is if it's
flags have been mentioned that it's
deleted then we we aren't going to pack
it right so basically it can never
cannot have the deleted flag set if it's
got it set we will not pack it and that
way just it just gets cleaned up
automatically at that point in the
process what that means is it's trivial
for us to have a delete entity right
delete entity is literally just a thing
that on the entity and will force you to
pass the sim region just because we want
to make you aware that I mean obviously
you would have to have a sim region
because otherwise would be no in and you
begin with but that's beside the point I
suppose so what you want to do here is
just say all right if it's supposed to
get deleted we just or in at the entity
flag deleted and it's gone so now we
should flags up we should be able to
re-implement
so that assertion no longer is a problem
when we do that operation we can say I
would like to delete this Kennedy and
I'll pass
whatever the here is now it's a little
bit tricky because all we have at this
point is the entity's ID we don't
actually have the entity itself and so
we need to again do that deferral to the
actual simulation we this is just the
controller code and so what we want is
con hero like exited or something right
we want to set that to true and then
when we come when we come through to
actually process that we can do the rest
of it so in here where we do the the
hero processing you can kind of see in
here we have the controller stuff this
is kind of janky code we could probably
clean some of this up as well but point
being whatever we're doing here bla bla
bla bla bla at the very end we can also
just say like oh hey by the way once we
have that entity that we've loaded we
can delete it if this was the situation
where the person exited
okay so all that's required to implement
that properly is the ability to mark the
fact that somebody asked for an exit
again very very simple and that's all we
should actually have to do so there's us
exiting the game and here is the sorry
entering the game exit the game the
enter the game so now we're back to the
bug that I was talking about before
we've got about 10 to 15 minutes left I
think on the clock so I'm not sure
exactly what the best thing to work on
is at the moment ground buffers hey
guess what they're not there anymore
but you know what we could do is we
could just go look for what that bug is
so that we'd have a head start tomorrow
on reworking how some of that movement
and and and world stuff is concerned so
like why does that do what it just did
for example is a good thing and I
believe where I had gotten to before is
I was like oh right the reason for that
is in the entity structure if you look
at the way that I did this we have this
notion of a bunch of these p-values here
right so movement from movement to and
really all of those values are
essentially erroneous once you've been
packed so position values have to get
packed just like everything else they
have to be made relative to their chunk
right because when you pack and you
unpack you're doing this thing you
repack into a local coordinate system
and you unpack back to a different local
coordinate system and so these movement
values we need to actually process the
same way that we would process the p
value right so I guess I can start on
that right away effectively it the first
thing that I would like to point out is
that this world position chunk P
actually isn't a value that we need
anymore
right we we can get rid it in fact this
this entire concept the the concept here
of this world position is now no longer
even necessary at all the only reason
that we actually need it in any way is
if we want to use it for enduring the
construction phase so I'm going to leave
it for now
but technically it's not even necessary
anymore and here's why so if I come in
here right first of all old chunks
should be able to go away right because
we're not using that anymore and if I
wanted to delete chunk P as well I
should be able to do that too and here's
why
so watch what happens when I compile the
chunk P you can see that it's getting
set in here and the reason that it's
getting set is because we have this
world position at come through but what
does world position at eutz that's no
good
what does world position at have
actually in it right well here is the
real thing it's got a chunk extant like
MC and an offset so actually the world
chunk that I'm in already contains the
chunk X chunk lion chunk Z so the only
thing I actually need to store right is
the offset because the other things are
already in the world chunk that contains
me so I don't need the entity to
remember when the entity gets packed it
never needs to recall where in the world
it was chunk wise because it's in there
right and so we can just ignore that
part entirely now let's see what happens
when he continued compiling okay so get
sim space key where is get Sims face
feed called well if you'll note there's
only one place it's called now which is
unpack time which is exactly what we
want so all we have to do is make sure
that when we're doing this operation we
just need to pass in what that basis
chunk X chunk Y chunk Z is that's all we
really need and furthermore we don't
even really need that we just need the
offset between that chunk and
shunk that were in the chunk the camera
is in right we just need to know that
offset so really get sim space P is just
an ad it's an ad of an offset so this is
all garbage it doesn't matter at all and
we can eliminate it remember when I said
this was going to get really good well
this is the kind of stuff I was talking
about basically all those things that
seemed like owners things that were
difficult to do keeping the giant world
having things be offsets having those
things all of that stuff just falls out
once the architecture starts to get good
and that's how you know that you're on
the right track right so in here we can
do exactly that right let's take a look
at what that code was doing we can say
okay what we need to know is we've got
the sim region origin and we've got this
storage trunk P we're trying to get
difference between those two right well
what I can do instead is say well I know
what the world chunk that I've got I
know what its world position is so I
could reconstruct that right I could say
chunk position I know exactly what that
is right I could reconstruct that I
could reconstruct that because I know
it's chunk X chunk by chunk Z okay so
then I can do this subtraction on the
chunk itself I can just say well tell me
how far away the chunk this will be like
the chunk Delta right tell me how far
away the chunk was so we can take this
this origin of the of the camera which
we know or of the same region we just go
ahead in here and say well whatever that
chunk position was do the subtraction on
that please
now all of our positions when we unpack
them do not need to go through anything
particularly unusual instead all they
have to do is just add the offset that's
it right so instead of having to pass a
sim space P here or any of this nonsense
what we can do instead is just pack a
pass a chunk Delta like so right and
then get rid of this entirely
although I suppose since we want to be
able to do the overlap check here
I should really continue to compute it
just by doing low P plus shock Delta
right like so but yeah once I pass the
chunk Delta here then basically everyone
inside here can use the chunk Delta to
take their positions and turn them into
real positions ok so that means that now
I can go to to my entity and all of the
stuff that was in the entity struct that
needs to get unpacked so all of these
VIII's right like movement from and
movement to that we were having problems
with before which are not relative
values their absolute values and that
was the problem
those can just be adjusted just like
everything else so in here where we do
desta simpie or that nonsense right we
can also just do def movement from right
trunk Delta Delta Delta so the
decompression step now becomes very
simple and again we'll sort of will
coalesce this into a little bit cleaner
style of thing in a minute here but you
get the idea right so if we do that now
this becomes very straightforward what
is the problem if that needs to be an
address there you go and what is this
from new camera chunk P that
and here we go all right so now what the
problem we have is when we do our PAC
entity in the world that process is
obviously a problem as well the reason
that's a problem is because all those
position values are wrong now write all
those position values in the entity are
relative to the sim region they need to
be relative to the chunk but again not
particularly difficult because once we
have the chunk view we can do the
inverse chunk Delta so what we can do
here is say like oh okay we know what
the chunk P is so what we can do is
issue that subtraction call this is not
as clean and it's because we do the
chunk sort of out of order here this I
think will be I will be able to make
this much faster much better code not
kind of going forward but point being if
we want to here we can actually make
this code be relatively straightforward
which is to say that once we have the
chunk Delta we can just do the inverse
of the one we were doing I could flip
this track there but I'm going to keep
it the same so that's the same in both
piece of the code and then what we can
do is when we do all of our pressing
right we can just go ahead and say oh
right
add the chunk Delta again to to
everybody who who needs to to have it
right needs to not there there we go
uh so let's see let's see ooh didn't
quite get that right yet so all right uh
where are we at here on time I got five
bits so I'm gonna go ahead and debug
this guy because then I think actually
we might have fixed them most of the
movement problem anyway so let's take a
look here we've got our chunk Delta on
the way in and the way out that we have
to deal with what is happening with the
PAC entity into world chunk P this this
now needs to not do what it was doing
before like this code needs to not do
this if that makes sense
so we got to get rid of that and that is
something that would probably now be
done
where are you world mode that's
something that wants to be done on end
entity right to initialize this code so
there it is kilo equals P offset okay so
that that needed to be fixed I don't
know if that's the most of it though oh
oh dear what did I do
Peck entity into world why did that
change that should not have changed
anything this is what you get when you
try to make quick change with the end of
a stream what do you do though
so entity loan comes in we're calling in
in the which everyone has to call we
call pac---- entity into world but first
we take the end of the lows P and we
take its the world position that we're
being passed and we set the offset in
there which all we were doing before is
just groups
here we go all we were doing before was
just that piece of code as well so why
would that change have changed anything
because right that should not that
should not have done anything oh right
duh it's because moving it out here
means that we're not that the sim region
is not calling back code path anymore
and so I suppose that could obviously be
it all right so if we come in here and
assume if we assume that that's what it
is let's keep going here fine so if we
assume that that's what it is
if I take a look at what's going on here
we get the chunk P which is that's
actually the entity's offset so that's
the problem is I just wasn't paying
close enough attention here so what we
actually need to do is is figure out
which chunk this is in - any of the -
any of the other values right so we want
a world position that's you know this is
actually enemy P and we want chunk be to
be enemy P with the offset set to zero
right so that's actually what we want to
have happen there and when we're we were
using chunk P before we would use enemy
P for working with the camera right
and again we'll do another pass through
this to clean it up a little bit nicer
okay so there we go and so now we're a
little bit better here we can go off the
screen okay but we're not tracking the
camera move and I'm not sure exactly why
so let's double check that one because
we may be able to again like I said just
finish that up so when we create the
entity P here what are we doing we check
to see this is supposed to be entity P
that's why
or maybe not entirely why room aced map
into chunk space and this is using the
entity px yeah so so really I guess if
we want to do this camera coach probably
rewritten but if it's going to use the
world P this actually this camera code
needs to execute before we do any more
of this right so this stuff actually has
to happen down here like so
all right there we go so not quite right
yet you can see it's a little bit janky
there so I don't think we're going to
call that done but at least now we have
the stable position packing and
unpacking so we're getting a little bit
further there which is good but you can
see it kind of it's kind of a little
nasty it's it's still not quite right
alright not sure what exactly that's
doing I need to slow it down so I can
watch there's like it's a quick frame of
it being of the camera not being in the
right place I'm pretty much at that time
though so I'll go to the Q&amp;A that's you
know we're gonna be working on this code
soon anyway so I'll just I'll just leave
it there and we'll we'll do some more
tomorrow I'm gonna go ahead and go to
the questions and the answers so if you
have questions about where we're at at
this point feel free to ask them now
are there questions
is there any real difference between F
and F and if not defined not really not
defined allows you to use it in more
complicated expressions but that's about
it
do you feel like we take stuff backwards
when we get into code we haven't been in
a while
aka the problems with moving the screen
not really if anything I feel like we're
massively further than we were before
because this code was pretty awful
before and now it's getting quite nice
so it's it's usually more like as it has
a chance to marinate then when you
couldn't kind of come back to it you're
like ah this is how it'll all work and
it's nice and that's pretty much exactly
what's happening do you use a lot of
header files well I mean we we just
break since we compiled everything in
the same we compile everything is one
translation unit effectively I mean
technically - because we have a platform
one but basically we just choose to
break things up into files based on what
we want to see like what we want to keep
bucketed together for convenience that's
really it so and actually so one thing
that is true - regarding those panda
finds is we don't actually need them so
we could get rid you know like we could
just get rid of those they're only
necessary if you were actually going to
build out with multiple translation
units so technically like if we just
look at all of their RH files we
wouldn't need oops
any of that anymore that's just it's not
necessary it can all go away right and
yeah it can all go away
so like handmade H that and
handmade world that H get rid of that
right none of those things need to be
there at all
when 32 handmade that H does not need to
be there
there's some weird thing in for coder
where for some reason caged up doesn't
go to the top it stops at the first like
before the top or something it's weird I
got to go find out why that is I don't
really know why there's some reason why
it does that I should write down it as a
book but I keep forgetting world mid-age
test asset builder down age oops H see
if there's any others Jared that H touch
shader
random that H we should do a real random
number generator sometime soon that's
probably that would be a good I feel
like that would be a good thing to do
one of these streams because we're going
to need one of those at some point so
indeed H doesn't have one and that's
fine same reason that H have one mascot
H yeah
what else is there intrinsic study H
oops
file formats DWI interface bug that H
cutscene almost done
Big O yo and last one yeah so those are
all
we're totally superfluous they were just
from the old Emacs thing that used to
insert them but they're really not
necessary so
let's see what else we got
why not pragma once because pragma once
was slower so those pound ifs were
faster than pragma once the reason for
that is pragma once actually still for
whatever reason and do not ask me why
because it doesn't it shouldn't have
needed to be well okay we'll say a few
things first of all Visual Studio is
like you know it's an amazing how slow
they managed to make a compiler
especially because they're older
compilers used to be faster they get
slower and slower and slower right and
so when in in 1999 I profiled build
times very extensively back then and I
found that by far the fastest thing to
do was redundant include guards so the
reason that I have those in there the
way that I had them where you do if you
know not defined who pound to find foo
and if right and here's the header it's
because then later in a CPP file what
you do is you say if not defined foo
pound include food H and that's what my
includes used to look like when I didn't
used to use when I used to use multi
file builds right and I timed those and
those were faster than pragma once so
that's always what I did and hilariously
after I left rad game tools and I think
it was Dave Moore who was I took over
grannie after Tom Forsythe took it over
for a while and then Dave Moore took it
over he was like do you still need to
use the redundant include guards on the
build can I get rid of those and I was
like well I don't know you'd have to
profile it
he profile it again in like I don't
remember when it would have been twenty
two thousand seven eight and pragma once
was still slower so you know it's just
like what can I say so yeah the fastest
thing by far though is the way we build
on handmade hero now which is unity
build right it's all one translation
unit that's way faster
than all that so we don't have to worry
about pragma once or pound it or any of
that stuff anymore but if you are
worrying about them then the reason not
to use pragma once is if you haven't
actually verified that packing watts is
faster on your compiler then you may
actually be slower than doing it by hand
which is hilarious because it probably
shouldn't be right
let's see would you see the architecture
of the NA system is based more on
experience than an exhalation the
opposite I've never done an entity
system similar to this one ever before
in anyway it's completely different I've
also never heard of anyone doing an ende
system this way so it is both new for me
and new period as far as I know it's a
completely different one so it's it's
100% exploration zero experience at the
moment do you have a plan for the
components of the entities just use
flags like you are now like I kind of
explained before we are not having
concept of components all entities can
have all things always that's the goal
of the system anyways
as a code base for those new functions
are created and others are no longer
called anywhere are there any good ways
that you recommend for finding out which
functions of code are never used other
than just when you spot them not really
no I mean technically that's probably
something that would be really easy what
so you should be able to turn on a
linker warning of the form like combat
bla was not called and has been removed
or something so if you set it to compile
like individual functions to individual
combats and like and and ask you to give
that warning you could probably get
visual studios linker to tell you what
but when you turn on full optimizations
right opt ref and all that stuff you
could probably get it to tell you here
are all of the functions I got I threw
out because nobody called them because
it will do that it'll do the call graph
analysis and go I can never get to this
thing so get rid of it so that that
might be one way if you're looking for a
way to do that I don't know why you
would bother necessarily because if you
don't know about it and you haven't it's
not like it's taking any of your time
right and if you stumble upon something
you're like hey I wonder if I need to
keep maintaining this does anyone call
it just delete it and compile and if it
compiles then the answer was no right
du Roi is there a way to run the game
entirely and find out what parts of your
code isn't being used to get rid of
there isn't there isn't obviously you
can do what's called coverage profiling
and coverage profiling different
profilers have it depends on you know
it's a it's a code profiling operation
so you need a profiler for it and
basically what that'll do is it'll tell
you what code paths have been hit in
which code pass haven't but the problem
with that is in a game you don't know if
that's because the player who did that
test run just never got to the part of
the game or did the thing that would
cause that code to run so while coverage
testing can be very useful for letting
you know what parts of your code haven't
been run what it really just tells you
is these haven't been run it doesn't
tell you they could never be run and so
you kind of need to augment that with
some thinking of your own and designing
you know how you're going to play tests
to make sure you actually find out if
those things ever get called you can't
just assume that because they didn't get
called in a particular run through that
they're never called because that's
probably not true
so let's see someone said the the
dynamite Jack entity system is similar
but without the compression well the
compression is kind of the important
part it's like the thing that actually
makes this system what it is right
obviously there's been plenty of games
before that just have one entity type
that's not unusual the unusual part is
making an entity type that has so much
stuff in it that you couldn't actually
store it that way but you compress it
down dynamically as you go right
have you checked lock recently yeah we
did the other day
15,000
how is your arm now any chance of a
stream Athan I'm not super in the mood
for a stream Mathon but my arm is doing
okay
jujin basements see time needs clock
built in well it can't really do that
right because it doesn't know what
you're compiling so at Molly I actually
am pretty close to having that probably
the next Rev of our tool train will have
that because everything will be going
through the meta programming system
instead of only some things going
through them at a program system and
then it will keep both timings and clock
because it knows all the code at that
point but it hasn't gotten there yet so
eventually we'll have that Molly for
sure but see time can never really have
that because it doesn't require you to
give it that information in any way and
it would actually be problematic for it
to gather it because the work it's doing
to gather it would actually increase
your build time because it has to read
it all now probably not very very much
but
jiron says recode coverage when far
brush was trying to cut down science of
K Krieger they wrote a quick code
coverage tool called Lecter and because
someone didn't use a certain key in the
menu the code to handle it was left out
of the release version yeah that's well
that's exactly the problem right and
it's it's a really difficult problem to
solve because there's two types of
unused code there's the kind of code
that can never be reached and that kind
of code is relatively easy for the or I
should say there's the kind of code that
mechanically could never be reached
nobody ever takes its address ergo you
can never get to that piece of code
barring some kind of a bug or a hack
right
and that kind of code is easy to remove
and the linker can remove it for you the
other kind of code is code that could
technically be reached potentially like
someone does have the address of it and
it is compiled it would be compiled into
the program but it turns out that the
state of the program as it is can never
really get set in a way that you'll
reach that code and the problem is
that's impossible to tell right I would
imagine that a computer science student
could probably prove that that's
analogous to the halting problem like if
you could write something that would
tell you whether a particular line of
code could ever be reached then
presumably you could solve the halting
problem because I just asked you hey can
the final line of this program ever be
reached and now I can solve the halting
problem because you will have told me
whether the thing will ever exit right
so I believe it is a literally
unsolvable computer science problem to
tell you whether a particular piece of
code can ever be reached and so it's a
very difficult problem and especially
like in a situation that like for
example that Fabrice was in in that case
it's like especially if you're gonna
rush like that like they were trying to
get finished for a comp
competition River and that's similar in
games right oftentimes you made have
some tight deadlines or something try
to figure out how you can put in some
kind of instrumentation to tell you all
of the code that might be hit is really
pretty difficult because you just don't
know how to make sure that you're
testing of that hits all of the right
things that could happen right you don't
know what things are sort of unusual now
one of the things that you can do
obviously is when you are programming
the game you can try to avoid the kinds
of code that happens extraordinarily
rarely you can try to make sure that
most things go through the same code
pass so at least the code path has some
coverage now that doesn't necessarily
help have the code the code pass be
tested within the bounds that you're
expecting because you know values can be
drastically bigger or smaller and maybe
you never hit those cases or something
that go through so that parts is a
little bit of an issue for sure but you
you kind of see what I mean just in
terms of of it sort of being something
that you can kind of design for a little
bit when you're programming but on the
whole it's it's it's not just a hard
problem it's like an unsolvable problem
so you have to you're you're always
dealing with some kind of approximate
way that you're planning to attack it
and you don't there's not some magic
bullet we can just be like ah I just run
it through this program it tells me all
the places all the code that is live and
all the code that's dead that's not
possible
and I think like I said I strongly
suspect that a computer science persons
would be able to tell you that that's
that's kind of a halting problem it's
analogous to a halting problem and you
can't actually solve it in the grand
scheme of things like I said linkers
will do the basic version of it and
compilers do dead code elimination all
the time so anything that's reasonably
easy to conclude that you can't get to
that's already being removed for you but
things that are more subtly not possible
to get to like can this menu item ever
be reached like does this menu can you
even pop up this menu who knows right
like that's such a complicated thing to
figure out well I don't know like how
big was the screen and maybe it's
something that's so far off the screen
it's almost never possible to click on
but if the user has a big enough
monitor then it turns out you can get to
this weird button that we forgot about
and you can't actually get to it right
all those sorts of things are weird and
then you also have the question if
should you have been able to get to it
was a mistake that was up in there so
even when you're answering the question
correctly you could still be wrong in
that well it should have been removed
because that's supposed to be there bla
bla bla bla bla right so
alright looks like there's really not
any more cues that need paying so I'm
going to wrap it up alright thank you
everyone for joining me for an episode
of hand made here at some pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always pre-order the game on handmade
hero org it comes with the source code
so that you can follow along there's
also a forum site if you want to ask
questions a patreon page you want to
support the video series a schedule bot
that lets you know when the episodes air
or I should say when the stream is live
and an episode guide if you want to
catch up on old streams where if there's
something that we've already covered
that you want to go and figure out how
it how it works you can go watch that as
well that's about it I will be back here
tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
when we will go over our camera code and
kind of figure out how we want that to
work I feel like we're gonna want to do
interpolating cameras because now that
I'm doing room locked that we'll
probably want to do like a thing that
kind of like slides quickly from room to
room so we'll probably get that going
tomorrow that's about it I hope all of
you have fun programming and I will see
you on the Internet take it easy
everyone