hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream i today actually I'm just
gonna do what I said I would do in on
the the Twitter I posted in the middle
of the week or not I you know what
actually was in the middle of the week I
think it was like right after the stream
or something or I don't know but last
Sunday we had tried to put in some debug
visualization of the lighting values at
various locations in the lighting voxel
and they were just like wildly weird and
wrong and during that stream I said even
as I was debugging it in fact there was
a whole section of that stream where I
was just lamenting how bad programming
languages are at managing indexes and
how if you want to actually have some
protection or guarantee that you're
indexing schemes are right it requires
writing all of this additional
structures and code that just like piles
up and is a waste of your time and what
you really want is some way more
efficient way of checking your indexing
to make sure that you're doing it
consistently and I said I bet this bug
is going to be an index bug and then
maybe I don't know how long after a day
after oh maybe it was only a few hours
after I don't remember I was sitting on
the couch and I realized like oh wait it
just kind of popped into my head I was
like oh I know what our bug was and it
was exactly what I said it was going to
be it's an indexing scheme bug and I
posted a link to the line of source code
so what we're gonna do today is just
talk about well we're not gonna talk
about it I guess I'm just gonna show you
what it was and then we're gonna go from
there so if we get our drive substance
and also I'm kind of like a little bit
off kilter here my keyboard is not set
up the way I would like okay so if we go
ahead and load up handmade hero here I
can show you well first I can show you
what the bug actually was which I don't
know if we left where we left the
compile so I may have to flip a few
switches on the compile to get us back
to
the bug actually was but I can show you
what the bug was and then I can explain
why a simple indexing error produced
this bug so you can see this is actually
the the lighting solution from the
previous round this is not the grid ray
tracer we're we're in the process of
Devon yet this is the old AABB tracer
and you can see that the lighting in the
world is relatively correct like as I
move this one light is that the light is
this cage is being drawn around the
light there as I move this light around
you can see you know that it that it
responds the way you would expect
lighting wise for the most part we you
know haven't done a lighting quality
pass on it so there's probably some
issues with it but it's not nonsensical
like you can see that the light relative
you know behaves relatively sanely as we
move throughout the environment when we
look however at the debug values you can
see that they make like effectively no
sense at all so looking at these values
you can kind of see that as I you know
just sort of look at their
directionality they're pointing in
completely completely nonsensical
directions relative to the light source
so you know I just don't know like
what's going on right and that's where
we left the stream last time I was like
it's really weird and I tried to look
you know at a couple things that maybe
could cause that we didn't find anything
and I said you know this is gonna be an
indexing bug because all bugs that take
you no more than 30 minutes to solve our
indexing bugs and you know that's
exactly what happened at least I think
so you know maybe I'm wrong but if we
look at what was going on here my my
realization and I won't quite pull up
the code yet my realization was wait a
minute we're trying to draw a subset of
the grid but did we ever actually offset
our sample and what you can see if we go
look at the actual code now we made a
special piece of code for this I don't
remember what it was called let me take
a look at the functions I think it was
just like debug it was head debug in
front of it and it was like draw maybe
octahedral values it's this so if you
look at what happens you can see we're
looping over the X Y Z of the debug dim
so that's the region that's the size of
the region we want which is a quarter of
the voxel we are producing the
coordinates by taking this Vox start
value and looping over it right but then
what you can see here is when we go to
draw the value look it's just X Y Z
right so we're using a zero based offset
to pull the lighting values out but
we're using an offset value to draw them
so we're drawing them at the right place
but we're loading them from the wrong
place right and so we needed to do this
right in order to get the correct values
out of our system oops those should be
lowercase and so again assuming em right
just a simple indexing bug leads to
something that's very hard to
troubleshoot because either you think of
looking at it or you don't
so once we've made that change hopefully
you can see now we're actually getting
very same results out of the system
right so you can pretty much see like
all of these lighting values coming and
they're pointing back at the light
source which is what we would expect we
probably want to constrain the length of
these values a little bit more than we
are right now we had kind of just played
around with that while we were working
on it because we didn't really know what
was going on but now that we have a
saying you know effect we can truncate
these lines to something a little bit
more sane so that we can just make sure
that we're only really looking at values
that are there with you know values that
are within the range of what we expect
for the lighting will be drawn you know
with a reasonable size relative to their
to their grid
and so you can kind of see as I hop
around now you know the lighting values
actually make perfect sense you can see
now that when we look at the direction
of you know remember these octahedral
maps are encoded in such a way that they
point in a direction and say how much
light is coming from that direction and
these lines are just drawing the values
of those octahedral maps that might be I
don't know how do I feel about that that
might be fine in terms of lighting size
I don't know how we want to look at it
but so now what I might do is go ahead
in as well and just just to make sure
that everything is is sort of kosher we
in our room generator we turned off the
lighting so we didn't have anything in
here that would add lights to the system
whereas before we did so we only had the
debug light here is a system that has
multiple lights so basically like you
can see now there's a number of lights
hovering around and so you know looking
at this I guess I would say I don't know
if I can't say that that looks
particularly convincing I mean you can
see that there's a little bit more there
but it doesn't really look like we're
getting much lighting from some of these
ants Larry lights not as much as I would
expect anyway maybe they're very dim and
I guess that is kind of true like if I
look at the lighting there there's
there's not maybe as bright of a patch
as is around me so it could be that it's
just a little bit of that in the mix let
me move over here a little bit just so
we can see well I guess I don't know
maybe I can't so you can kind of see
there as I move through here you know
yeah there is still light coming from
there and I just like I said don't
really know if that's just because those
light values aren't enough I mean you
can sort of see that it's coming from
there so so I don't know it's not
obviously correct I'm not psyched about
it to be completely honest so it's hard
to say you know I couldn't really tell
you if that was if that was right or
wrong I mean maybe it is I don't know so
hard to say but you know whatever
at least at this point I feel a little
bit more confident that we're drawing
the actual values and that was really
the part that I wanted to get to let me
see what happens if I jacked up the
lighting value here so if you look at ad
piece light it oops well it's probably
right here yeah here's our values so
here's the radius here's the location
relative to the base and here's the
emission value so I don't know like
what's our debug light because I don't
know if we go to the world mode and just
look at the debug light part so where
does that actually get recorded so what
you can see here is this does a push
light and it just pushes one when one so
you know I'll be honest I don't quite
understand why the emission levels there
would be oh well okay so actually I
guess I do if you look at these numbers
these are not one one one so I guess the
lamp does have like a lighting color
associated with it so I suppose that's
maybe where that comes from
so if I doubled this it would be back up
towards a 1 1 1 light so maybe we can
look in that and see what that looks
like
so there you can see a little more
clearly that there is light coming from
that direction so maybe this was just
that these lights were a little too dim
to show up in the system as well as you
know as they as the debug light
yeah and so that's a little bit clearer
you can see you know getting more light
gathering from this from here what I
will say is that you can kind of see
however that that there is a fair bit of
just just overall bad targeting and this
is one of the reasons that you know we
sort of had that brief thought and we we
put in a little bit of work towards but
we never really it was never really
quite something we wanted to do
particularly specifically but you can
kind of see that for lights that happen
to have sphere values that are very
close to the where the thing is then you
you hit them in other ones don't I
wonder if we might need a denser
covering of the sphere to ensure that we
actually hit these things because right
now we may just not be producing enough
right like we may not be producing a
sufficiently large number of shots in
that direction you know I'm saying so I
think the the important thing here is
just to like it's just to remember okay
we we don't really know to what extent
we're doing a good job with targeting
and or with you know with any of those
ancillary parts so let's just keep that
in the back of our mind and we may want
to augment some things to improve to
improve that behavior but otherwise I do
think we're roughly okay here like this
this looks you know better but I
definitely think there's improvement
there
the other thing that I think is this to
me
argues that maybe our Cube caster as
well can can definitely be a much better
solution than the AABB one and the
reason I say that is because that caster
the cube cast the you know the voxel the
grid stepping one the grid stepping
tracer is capable of doing things like
bucket-brigade movement of lighting from
cube to cube that this tracer is not at
the moment although I guess we could
augment it to do so
and because of that I think we'd have a
better time of taking hits to bright
lighting and moving them backward you
know so propagating them to other to
other squares and that I think would be
a good improvement right over this
system so I think we've got what we want
now and so I think now the main thing we
need to do is start the lighting quality
work and get the cube caster working
well and we may have to do some
debugging of specifically the cube
caster I don't know if there are some
bugs in there at the moment that are
causing us problems we know that we're
getting way too bright results from it
but we don't actually specifically know
why so it could be and you can kind of
see here what I mean mmm when we switch
to the cube caster the the the numbers
drive towards infinity so they keep
getting larger and larger and larger and
larger until they're just you know
basically you know in or whatever
they'll there's a positive feedback loop
that just adds energy to the system
effectively forever so the question is
what do we do about that because we
don't really know exactly where that
feedback loop is coming from and we
don't know to what extent that feedback
loop is just the result of
not having gone through and actually
done the lighting quality pass where
we've managed the values properly and
know what they all mean and how they
should propagate or if it's just the
case of there's bugs in the actual cube
caster that themselves are creating
artificial feedback loops or positive
energy injection that shouldn't be there
right so we the key thing here to
understand is that we don't really know
what kind of bug we have yet and so
we're gonna kind of start the lighting
quality work but the reason we're
starting the letting quality work is not
because we think the cube caster works
it's because I don't think there's any
particular way that we can debug the
cube casters current issues without
actually knowing we have a more robust
definition of what should be happening
to the light so we need to start working
out real measures of what we expect to
happen and a solid definition of how it
should happen because without that we're
never going to be able to debug the
system that's what I would argue because
something like a positive feedback loop
can just as easily happen from a poorly
thought-out mathematical scheme for
distributing the light as it can from a
just a straight-up bug so it could very
well be that this system is working
exactly as intended and maybe it's just
a better system for gathering light than
our previous caster and it just exposes
an underlying mathematical issue with
the way that we're treating light and
it's expected that it should blow up the
way it does right and so differentiating
between those two scenarios is our news
our goal now and so we want to have ways
we can visualize what's supposed to
happen and that's why I started you know
that's that's why I wanted that drawing
we also added something that I think
will be very useful if we go to the
world mode
code I also have an F key press thing in
here where I could do f9 each time to
update the lining and so that's another
thing that we're probably going to want
to make use of and just augment so if in
here I hit f9 what you can see is here
is first of all an example raycast which
is useful and second you can see the
lighting values after one step of the
lighting propagation and I'm still the
game is still running right but it's
just not running the lighting solution
it freezes the state of the lighting
solution in place and then I can go
ahead and I can just step right single
step the lighting each time and you can
see the light propagate through the
world via the cube caster and so there's
a couple things that you can see
happening here and I guess what I would
say is even just that is probably
sufficient for me to to see a particular
type of what I think is is a bug or at
least something we have to rectify and
it's probably where we should focus our
attention first because it will be the
the most straightforward place we can
measure our success so if I run the game
and I look and I and I think you know
what I should do this and I think if I
go back to the if I turn off all the
lights so we can just simplify our
problem
turn off all the lights except the one
that's just centered around the hero so
exactly the way we started the day we go
back there so if I start there what I
should be able to do now is in the game
itself I should be able to single-step
the lighting we know that all the lights
coming from here and distributing out to
the cubes as I step it what you can see
is you get the lighting
from these parts bleed through the wall
quite dramatically right so you know as
I'm single stepping this you can see the
light leaking through the wall and you
know moving bucket by bucket sort of
forward and that's what's going on here
right like this is hitting these Ray
casts are hitting here gathering light
from here and moving them backward right
you can sort of see that happening right
now there's a couple things about that
so the very first thing that I think is
clearly buggy about this and so what I'd
like to look into first is let's take an
example of how that would have to happen
so if you imagine going back to the
original lighting solution I should put
in a key for clearing it - shouldn't I
so if you were to look for example at
specifically maybe like this part and I
guess it's a bummer that I can't see
those I should probably like clear the
depth buffer at some point here and so
that I can see these drawn through where
the occluders are you know the other
thing I could do is just not put them on
there so one thing I could do is in the
world's mode I'm sorry in the entity
system one thing I could do really
quickly is just turn off the drawing of
the cubes themselves so when it adds an
occluder I'll let it keep adding the
occluder but I won't actually draw the
you know the actual thing itself so let
me see I don't know how easy that is to
do but I'll take a look here
so it looks like the way that it looks
like this is the draw sprite code which
I don't care about so it's really this
so here's me pushing the occluder if I
just don't push the cube right what I
should see is all of the the sprites
will still be in the world but the cubes
just won't be right and so that allows
me to sort of see through the walls here
so here's where those wall points would
be and as we run these what you should
hopefully see right is that you know
this is just garbage I mean this thing
this thing is inside geometry at the
moment and you know it's it's getting
light from here somehow I'm not I guess
I'm not sure I like how did it get
information that light was coming from
over here
you know I just don't know and
and I guess that kind of you know if I
if if I look at the distribution of who
is having these sort of ridiculous ideas
about where the lights coming from it's
it seems like kind of overwhelmingly
people who are embedded in geometry and
it's not necessarily a bad idea to let
people embedded in geometry cast out
from that geometry which I believe we do
allow currently right like you can cast
outward which is what what's supposed to
happen there but well you know more
specifically let's do something else
real quick to let's take a look at what
happens in the non grid lighting for
that exact scenario because I'm curious
so here's the non grid version and it's
like I mean at the very least you can
see that those do not record light
coming from the other side right
so at least what it sort of suggests to
me and maybe this is just a trick of the
eye but what that sort of suggests to me
is that we should take a look at what
happens when we are casting out from
inside things because I have a couple
ideas of how that probably would create
issues and in fact in fact I think I
think we may even want to gosh yeah we
may even want to make a special code
path for casting out from inside of
things and the reason that I say that is
because we do need interpolant for
everywhere in the world like we need to
be able to know what the lighting values
should be as they blend because it's a
sparse sampling right I mean it's a
sparse sampling of stuff here and so we
kind of need to always have a sample
even if that sample is erroneous is in
an erroneous location someplace or our
shows impossible like a place where you
can't sample the lighting because inside
geometry but what I'm thinking is
happening effectively is you know these
cubes let's say I draw them just so you
can see as for an illustration let's
suppose I do instead of a push cube if I
just do a push volume outline because I
think I kind of starting to get a better
idea of what's happening here I don't
remember what that takes as parameters
so let me just take a look here at what
it actually wants so it takes a
rectangle and a color and that's really
all I need to specify I guess so if I
was going to do a push volume outline it
would be a rect centre-half dim on those
two parameters no bitmap ID and the
render groups so I think that's all I
would need
to draw these cubes so looking at what
you get when you draw them here you can
see all of the cubes as like a lattice
right and and maybe I should pass like a
thin thick like a thin thickness a
thickness of significantly less than 0.1
maybe I do a point O 1 here or 0.025
just to make it a little easier to see
those those lines were a bit overbearing
so we find draw the grid here you can
see where we've placed these volumes and
you know what's going to happen and then
if I do the f9 2 step the lighting once
so when we start to look at what's going
to happen for these lights that are
contained here so here's what I'm afraid
of and what I think might be happening
when this it's casts outward yes we may
have written the code properly so that
it will allow you to cast out from a
volume like this because I believe we
ignore hits that are in the same facing
direction as you we may not and so that
may be an additional bug but let's
suppose that that was correct even if we
are handling that correctly when this
casts backward in this direction it will
hit this face of this cube and because
we are not respecting the fact that this
occluder will prevent us from going
backwards we're going to record that as
a hit and we're going to sample the
lighting from here going that direction
but we never should have been able to
sample lighting coming from that
direction right so when we are inside
something I think what we probably need
to do is we need to make sure that when
we are going to sample the lighting we
just sample the lighting going in the
same direction as we cast in other words
we we just want this
have the lighting value that came from
this direction because that's what this
Square will have and we just want that
to continue probably or I mean maybe we
just want things inside to be zero is
the other option right maybe we don't
want them to have anything in particular
but either way just treating them as
nothing I don't think that's going to
work so we may need to consider what to
do when things are inside and we may
need to just nullify them I don't know
but I think that things inside existing
structures I think we're going to have
to take certain care to just do
something different with them so again I
really don't know what the best plan is
for that but I think the first thing I'd
like to try is let's start by maybe just
zeroing those so you know at the head
end we before we do our raycast
we just check the square before we start
any ray casting on it whatsoever and we
just if that cubes inside one of our
occluders we just zero it you know I'm
saying we just we just blend in zero
lighting at that point I'm not sure
that's the right answer
I'm just that's what I'm gonna try and
if I go ahead and remove the in here if
I go ahead and remove the the world mode
stepped lighting so we just do that if I
remove the stepped lighting I should
actually you know what that's not the
right way to do it why not just do it
this way
so they go ahead and remove the step
lighting and let this run and do it sort
of over braiding that happens
oh well no sorry we have to also switch
back to the grid base lighting I'm gonna
go see what happens if I add something
to nullify all the stuff that's inside
the the walls just to see what effect
that has on at least the light leakage
so I don't suspect that will necessarily
help me with our lighting growing
without bounds here but this this part
here where this leaks outside I'd like
to see if that starts putting a damper
on that process and it might not but
we're gonna see so in order to do that I
think the most effective way is inside
the lighting system I probably want to
make it so that the I just ideally don't
want to spend any time thinking about
those so I think I want to do this as a
pre pass that basically says look when
we dispatch to do a full cast on a cubed
so you know if we
[Music]
here so if you look all of these are
going to come from the same location so
we pull the Ray origin out of the light
probe p-value here that we're getting
when we do that I think what we're gonna
want to do is do the check right here
right so we'll want to take this light
probe P we already know because when we
come through here we're literally going
to pass exactly where you would start
your grid walk so we know what the grid
index is for this location that's just a
known quantity right in fact we we have
it right here so if we know we can load
the initial grid index we should be able
to do a pre pass on each cell just for
the cell itself and check to see whether
we're inside and if we are we can take a
different route and avoid the entire
grid cast altogether which will probably
actually save us time in the grand
scheme of things I don't know why I'm
looking in the wrong file so if we take
a look at the grid ray caster which is
right here you can see this piece of
code where we loop over the leaf indices
and check them so here's an example of
that code what I'd like to do here is
say once we've pulled the Ray origin
which is which is just this light
p-value we're just going to go through
and we're gonna check to see if the
light probe p-value is inside one of
these boxes right so we don't actually
need all of this nonsense here we should
be able to do this by just directly
taking the comparator and saying are we
inside and if we are then you know
we can literally just go if not is
inside or something like this right and
we will just not do anything if we're
not right so if we're not inside we
wouldn't do anything now that's not
exactly correct
we would rather at that point write
zeros in and if we look at the way that
we're updating the the parts of the map
we still kind of need to do this process
right we need to pull the texels here
and and update them so we may want to do
something more like this in the long run
but right now because these things and
just to be clear just to be clear we
don't care about this when we first
start because we aren't moving any of
these voxels we aren't moving the the
volumes around so because we're not
moving the volumes around if something's
inside it will just be inside always and
if something's outside it will be
outside always so we don't have to worry
about the case where a voxel cell was
getting values and then it's not but we
don't know that it's always going to be
that way for all we know we may have a
bunch of levels at some point where we
are going to move those around which
will cut will mean we'll have to handle
extra stuff so we may say like
so we may need to do a loop toward zero
scheme here where we make that happen
and again like I just don't know how we
want to address that but we're going to
have to do that and furthermore I don't
know if we actually do our clears
properly we might in fact I think we do
so I think we're fine even though the
grid moves around I think we're fine
because we do clear it but the point is
we want to handle looping towards zero
here in case we ever have moving
occluders which you know we we might
want and there's probably other work
we'd have to do to make moving occluders
not look stupid but again we just want
to make note of that so at the moment I
won't actually do that and all we really
need to do is look at this routine when
we come through here and we have this
rate origin now we have a box mint in
box max all we need to do here is do a
comparison we want to know if this thing
is both inside is in is less than the
min I started greater than the min less
than the max because if our Ray origin
is less than the the Box Max and it's
greater than the Box min that's going to
give us and you know honestly I said
don't guess I don't know if we have
these operators but it gave me still
having coronavirus problems I don't
actually know if I have coronavirus
basically what we have here is a test
for each of the bounds x y&amp;z
each across four lanes and what we need
to be able to do is we need to be able
to collapse the x y&amp;z down into one set
of lanes and then we need to look at
what the mask actually tells us and as
long as we're inside on any of them then
we're inside because each one is a
different box so we should be able to
just do a single move mask and record
that value so if I say use 16 is inside
equals zero we should then have what we
need
I just have to collapse it down so if we
go ahead and say well there's an F 3 to
4x mask oops
and that's in bounds X or in bounds Y or
in bounds Z or sorry not or and that
should give us what we need I think
right and don't quote me on that now we
don't actually have the node that we're
looking at here is there it's
complaining to about this so we don't
have one of these for the v3 4x well you
know I guess I don't know that I care
about writing something like that I mean
we could but I think this is fine right
because again we don't really even know
how we wanted we might want to try and
do this in a more efficient way I mean
who knows what we're gonna do in the
future so I'm not going to go make an
operator just for that because I'm not
sure I really need it so I'm just going
to do the testing here where we do in
bands X Y and C and then we get the mask
and we end it together and honestly you
know that's probably I haven't actually
looked to see if that's the smartest way
to do that it may be that you actually
want to do three moves and do the ants
separately because you're gonna loop and
bubble is not this is not performance
critical at the moment so you know we'll
leave that for another day but at the
moment what we need to know is what is
this node
right and so if you take a look at the
way that we were doing it before you can
see we want to load up the node from
something and the answer here is that
well we actually get past what the grid
index is that we're starting in right so
we should be able to just do this is
inside testing very simply and that
should allow us if we go to bug this
code path that should allow us to stop
getting those values getting anything
set on them right and what you can see
there is actually although eventually
the light did penetrate through the wall
you could see that it actually held off
for quite a bit longer so I think this
is starting to I think that probably did
work at least a little bit and let's
take a look at it in single step now
where the heck did I put this code
wasn't I write on it before there it is
so if I go ahead and single-step now and
just take a look at how that propagation
is working so let's take a look here's
our grid and I'm gonna do the first pass
so hopefully what we'll see now is as we
go these well those are outside so they
should be okay but these along the wall
here should get none right and no matter
what even when these explode these
should never get anything right and it
looks to me like that's exactly what
happened right so that that seems really
pretty good right yeah so so I'm I'm
pretty pleased about that I think that's
again I think that's really good I think
that's a positive step but think we
probably want to keep that now what I'd
like to do is really quickly just so I
can see what the effects of this are
since we know that our other ray caster
gives a better approximation towards
usable lighting at the moment because
it's more debugged I'd like to go ahead
and see well all right so I can't really
I wanted to just try the other ray
caster but I guess we can't because we
remove the entire path which which was
the thing we would need to do the
testing mm-hmm I just wanted to see what
would happen to the the lighting in that
case when we knocked those out just to
see what it looked like so what I would
like to do now is focus on the actual
light directional propagation elements
because there's a bunch of things I'm
seeing in here that make me suspicious
of how we're doing the sampling now
there's a couple of things we want to
look at if we take a look here at these
light values so another thing I can do
is I can turn off this now and the
reason for that is we
now I can I've I've visually verified as
well as having the code in there that
people on the interior will get set to
zero so I think I can safely go back
into the entity code now and remove this
volume outline switch so that we can
just see the actual world again because
I know that anything inside that I can't
see is going to be zero whereas before
it wasn't so that's a good step and if
we take a look at what's going on in
here I guess one thing I would also say
is it's looking pretty promising too as
we go I mean you know we're a far cry
away from having good lighting but you
know if it gave me this when I'm looking
at right now and said you got to get
that to a really good lighting solution
I'm like wow we're almost all the way
there like we really just need some
better like spreading interpolation to
hide that voxel boundary a little bit
more but other than that like we're in
really great shape you know I look at
that and that just looks awesome right
so I don't think we're in that far and I
think we're going in a promising
direction but obviously we still have a
bunch of things to address so the first
thing I'd like to say is let's start
looking at this because this indicates
very clearly to me that we've got some
issues when I'm casting up through this
you know this wall a floor panel this
rain cast we at least believe and you
know we have inspected many of these and
it does always seem to produce the
correct answer you can see here the
normal that our ray caster has been
producing seems pretty solid and I'll
you know I'll do another verification
where will you know we'll try looking at
this and we'll see if maybe these
normals are wrong but I'm assuming that
if we inspected one of these we would
see the normal facing back at us right
and if that's the case that means we're
asking what light is coming down this
way right and the way that we're pretty
that's not true if we're looking at the
sample here right that means we're
looking at what light is coming from
this direction so the downward facing
direction right and I guess the problem
that we're gonna have and I don't really
know I mean it actually just looks
erroneous to me but I don't know is when
I look at what is supposedly coming from
that direction there's not much light
there right now part of that maybe I
think we're still drawing the spec map
and I don't really know right I mean it
could be but I'm not sure so if we're
still drawing the spec map and let's
take a look what happened here why can I
not see did I delete something I'm like
I'm like stuck over that was weird I was
like stuck over on the other side let me
go ahead and jump to the lighting code
here here we go so if I do the draw - he
drove al use you can see me here drawing
the spec atlas so what I'd like to do is
I'd like to draw the other Atlas as well
and in order to do that again I have to
fix this bug that we had in both places
right so we're want to use the Vox chord
for each case so if I was to draw
specifically draw the yep if I was to
specifically draw the diffuse Atlas
instead of a spec atlas what I want to
do here is see is the blurring step
creating like way too much light coming
from that direction and that's what
we're seeing there and I don't know so
what you can kind of see here
is if I take a look at where this light
is gonna get sampled from so here's
here's an example of what it probably
looks like now unfortunately we're not
quite getting the exact one although I
guess we are yeah we are because this is
gonna cast like upwards right and so if
you take a look at at how this this
right here is getting blurred I guess
what I say is you know it does seem to
have quite a spread on it there and I
and I I can't say it's necessarily wrong
you know but it's definitely
dramatically power increasing and and so
you know I guess I I guess I can't
really say that I should start debugging
these quite yet because that that part
alone does look kind of wrong I mean I
don't know
I guess it's just it's pretty hard to
say is my problem right I really just
don't know what I should make of that
just to give you a little bit of
perspective on what I'm thinking so when
we're going to produce the updates for
this right so you can see as that grows
like what what did it look like we're
gonna cast we're gonna get a normal that
comes back this way and so what we're
gonna want to know is for the cast that
went out this way we're gonna want to
know what kind of light for this
location was coming back from sort of
straight down right the diffuse
component of like a straight down light
and so when we look at what that would
entail you know it's it's gonna be it's
gonna be showing you know this this
downward facing part here I guess is
what what we would think would was
coming from that direction right and so
and so I don't really know what I think
of there's a lot of ways that I could go
on this right so if the first thing I
want to do is focus on what's happening
to this there's a lot of ways I could
address that so one way I could address
that is by saying every time I go to do
a cast if I'm going to sample from a
particular light probe if the light
probe is on the other side of the thing
that I've hit
I don't sample it right so in other
words when I do the eight voxel samples
I only sample the things that are on the
side of the so there's I would sample
these and I wouldn't sample these
because they're on the other side of the
hit so I know that they can't be
included right and it's a pretty trivial
thing for me to do like compared to how
much work we're doing for all of the
other ray casting operations really not
a huge deal and it's just a really tough
decision so if I want to focus on that
that's the first thing I could do and I
suppose maybe we should just do it it's
not a particularly difficult thing to
create it's fairly cheap and then at
least we can turn it on or off and see
what's going on there right let's just
do that and then we can maybe see if
that prevents and in and I guess here's
my other thinking just to give you a
little bit of a perspective on what's
going on here
Oh Abner has shown up hello Abner all
right are you here to talk about
handmade Seattle I have not heard
anything about handmade Seattle yet
other than the post I saw from you so
did everyone see that
we'll talk about it at the end of the
stream if Abner's around so basically
this so this environment in my mind
gives me a good opportunity to actually
do the thing I just said which is why
I'm thinking maybe we should just do it
now instead of later and the reason for
that is because right now we're in a
situation it's at least undesirable
perhaps it's buggy but it's at even if
it turns out that it's not a bug it's at
least you know a defect right which is
that we're getting this massive over
brighting but the nice thing about that
massive over brighting is it really
quickly and dramatically shows us where
light leaking occurs right so as we
drive these numbers up to be absolutely
huge we can see the light leaking
happening down here and one of the
things that we might not have another
good clear opportunity for is seeing
light leaking really clearly right and
so because this is a very pronounced
situation I'm thinking why not just use
it to help solve a light leaking problem
I knew will have anyway rather than
trying to tackle it when it's more
subtle so rather than trying to solve
the feedback problem first I think on
maybe we'll focus on this part so let's
add something to our octahedral sampling
to allow us to do some kind of masking
so for example when we actually do an
a voxel sample I don't know what we call
it I think it's just yeah compute voxel
irradiance app so when we actually do
our voxel sampling here what I'd like to
do is say if you you look at this luring
that we're doing here and what we want
to do is maybe transfer or transform the
way that we're computing this to be
based on single coefficients rather than
lerp s-- and if you remember correctly
what'll URP does right let me just pop
over because so if i just quickly remind
people because i feel like you can never
really remind people enough so whenever
you're doing any kind of a weighted
blend all of these things are linear
operators right so if I am going to do a
standard lerp like a standard lerp which
is a I guess in this case it's a it's
actually a trial URP so allure p-- is
just a linear blend but in this case
we're doing a trial herb and that's just
you know three linear blends
and the important thing to remember here
is that when you're dealing with linear
operators you can do whatever you want
with the order in which you process
these coefficients so if I take the
linear blend which is traditionally
going to be like a blend between two
things we'll call them a and B if I want
to know the resulting point that I'm
going to create is 1 minus the blend
factor times a plus the blend factor
times B right if we look at this
fundamental equation if we start to
apply it multiple times I mean first of
all you can already manipulate it right
I mean you've seen some people will
rewrite this or depending on what you're
trying to do with it you can multiply
the a through for example and you'd get
a minus T a plus TB right so you can
create different versions of this
equation as well but for our purposes we
only really care about looking at this
particular version and the reason for
that as you can see that these two
values are scalar values and we could
just rewrite this as a generic weighted
blend right we could have just said well
there's a W a a plus a WB B and we're
just doing a weighted blend of two
things and we just happen to know that
these two weights sum to one so we know
that W a happens to equal 1 minus T and
W B happens to equal T right but once we
start to apply this equation recursively
which is what we're doing in a try
linear blend
you know trilinear blend and we'll just
take the maybe the bilinear case for
simplicity we're expanding the notion of
this so rather than talking about two
values a and B and we're blending
between them by picking a T value and
the T value you know gets us some
distance of the way there so you know
the T value gets us to here when we
start talking about for example
by linear blend we're talking about four
inputs so we're talking about a B C and
D for example and if we're talking about
using a T value to get somewhere we do
it on two of the bars and then we talk
about using some other value and you
value maybe we use u and V I don't know
so maybe this is a you value it did you
can letter them however you want but
that produces a new intermediate bar and
then the second value let's say V
produces the the new point right and
that's the conceptual framework so we
certainly can do something where we say
well alright if this is going to be p0
and this is going to be P 1 and then we
produce our final p value from those you
know then we're just doing two of these
equations 1 - oh sorry 1 minus u times a
plus u times B and then p1 in this case
was 1 minus u times D plus UC right and
then we took those results and said P is
equal to 1 minus V times p0 plus V times
p1 right so this is replying this
recursively but hopefully what you can
see here is there's nothing preventing
us from just doing the substitution back
into this equation we know that p0 came
from an existing blend 1 minus UA plus u
B so we know that p 0 in this case if we
plugged it back in this would actually
be 1 minus V times this whole equation 1
minus u oops you a Plus u B right and
the same would be true over here so the
V times p1 this p1 is really just this
whole equation it's 1 minus u d+ you see
right and so if we actually multiply
these out you start to get pretty
obvious answers for what the actual
coefficients are without needing to
think of it recursively anymore
this is the recursive formulation but
because it's linear we can just think of
a flat formulation which is this because
if you look at what happens we just have
1 minus V times 1 minus u a plus 1 minus
V times u B plus V times 1 minus udy
plus UV C right and lo and behold we
just now have each of our input points a
B D and C they're all here right and
they each have a weight and that weight
is some combination of U and V either
the 1 minus version or the regular
version and we have each of them
appearing exactly once so now we just
see that well this whole equation is
just weight of a plus weight of B plus
weight of d plus weight of C and I could
have just written them in order because
we don't care what order they come in
they're just terms on a line so this is
just a very simple weighted blend right
it just so happens that these are formed
the weights are formed by the trilinear
coefficients right so each of these just
becomes whatever it was up here 1 minus
V 1 minus u 1 minus V u u V and V 1
minus u right so you can imagine doing
this as many times as you want we could
do a 8 dimensional linear blend if we
wanted to and we could literally do that
just by taking all of the input points
in our 8 dimensional blend and
generating all the weights for them and
they would just be a single sum equation
where it's just F mad F mad F mad F mad
right you multiply and add multiply and
add multiply and add right and so
the sum of weighted coefficients will
build us any order linear blend we want
any dimensional linear blend we want
whether it's linear bilinear trilinear
or any other higher dimensional linear
and this allows us to avoid using that
recursive formulation now you may ask
yourself why would anyone care about
everything I just said for the routine
that we actually are looking at and the
reason for that is because if you
flashback to routine here what you can
see is in the recursive formulation it
would be incredibly difficult for me to
figure out how I would produce a
reasonable blended result if I wanted to
pass in effectively an arbitrary bit
field that said which tiles could be
used and which tiles couldn't right now
one way that you could think about doing
this would be to say well actually no
cases it's very easy what I'll do is
I'll just take whichever of the tiles
are supposed to not contribute and I'll
zero their value right but the problem
is that's not the same thing as not
using them that is using them as if
they're lighting was zero so all of the
lighting will be darker than it should
have been because we are actually using
those values we're just using them as if
they had no lighting but that's not what
I wanted what I wanted to do was I
wanted to say build me an N way blend
where the N the number of things I'm
blending are just the ones that I can
use and if there was only one I just
want you to use that whole one as the
value right so hopefully you can
understand what I'm saying here like we
need a way of constructing an N Way
blend where we're really only blending
between the N elements were never even
using an element that's out of bounds
because if we were to just set it to
zero we would get darker I wrote
we would get results with a lot less
light than we should have right but
hopefully what you can see is based on
what I just said on the blackboard you
can see where I'm kind of going with
this if instead of doing it that way
where we had the if what we had were
individual bit field or weight values
that told us what we were allowed to use
in what we weren't then what I could do
is take that weight vector which is
eight weights which by default would
just be exactly what I did back here so
it'd just be combinations of uvw right
so it would just produce the standard
linear trilinear blend we were doing if
I take those values and I knock some of
them out so I just knock them out to
zero then I can use which we've talked
about many times for the Euclidean 1
norm to say how do i boost the remaining
values back up so that they sum to 1
right and then what I'll have is a blend
that is fully weighted but only using
the actual the actual sample values that
I'm allowed to write so I can do exactly
what I want and I can actually do it
quite easily as it turns out so when we
do compute voxel irradiance at let me
first translate this routine into
something and you know what I may be
could do this here let me just go ahead
and restore our ability to do this
so our is inside can just really be
nerfed here it can just say if lighting
use grid and if there so we can use our
old lighting if we want to this this
will be compatible either way and what
I'd like to do is just say all right
here's
what we expect to see as the sampling I
should probably turn back on the let me
go ahead and and and remove that so I
can just run the lighting and not have
to use the f9 where was that world mode
there so if I go ahead and run now I
should be able to modify this routine
such that it allows me to pass and what
I can do is I can literally just leave
it exactly as it's doing it now by just
changing the form of the equation but
using the coefficients that I know the
equation will produce right so that's
the first step because we want it to be
working when there is no occlusion we
want it to be working exactly the same
we want to be working exactly the same
way so don't want any difference in
value so I want to change this routine
and I want to use it by effectively
taking you know it's essentially the
same thing here but I want to use
weighting values so if we use the tiles
here as as such I don't know that it
makes a lot of sense to still use the
leg to-to-to-to scheme there it's it
seems a little bit unnecessary but you
know and I guess we'll leave it for now
so if I go in here you know does it
really make sense let's just fix that so
you can see here that we're using the
to-to-to-to scheme what if we just
compressed these values just down to
being in order right and so zero zero
zero comes first zero zero one comes
second right and you can see like these
just go in order anyway I mean they're
already literally in order in here so I
feel like we should be able to just
compress this down and say look there's
eight tiles and there they are right I
mean at least I don't see any reason why
we couldn't and then this would just
become
right and that just seems a little more
sane than trying to deal with three
separate arrays subscripts which at some
level is going to be a little bit
annoying right
and so we've packed these specifically I
guess in this order I don't know why we
chose that order to begin with but I
guess we did you can see it just goes X
firsts always and then Y seconds and
then Z thirds and then we did the blend
in that order so off you go right so if
we were to build now you know my hope is
that I didn't change anything and we
don't get you know completely ridiculous
lighting results here from all the
sampling and whatnot but you know
certainly looks okay I think again it's
kind of hard to tell because we don't
really have a lot of good ways of
analyzing whether lighting is looking
correctly that so from there what I'd
like to do is I'd like to just go ahead
and introduce a flat weighting scheme so
let's suppose I just do like a W maybe
and I say there's going to be eight of
those and then we'll just produce
whatever those should be now what you
can see here is we transition on X first
so basically we're going to have X and 1
minus X each time now I'm going to show
you a little trick that I like to use
here to make these things more readable
right
and what I like to do is let's just say
we'll use the lowercase versions of each
of these to produce the weight values
for each of these but what I like to do
is I like to have sort of a minus a plus
and a minus version of each one right so
I like to do something like this right
and you can even do it this way if you
want to
so like positive u and minus u or
whatever or negative u either way and so
each of these is like which one of these
you wanted so if you wanted a positive X
right I could even do X Y
z would be another one to do it so I
don't know you can choose whatever names
you want for these but what I'd like to
do is I like to make the negative
version of the thing as just a variable
right and the reason for this is it
makes it extremely easy to see what the
heck is going on without actually
hurting your eyes right so in this case
I know that the negative version of X
right the one where it's inverted is
going to be on the zero two four and six
side right because you can see that they
would have been getting one minus the X
blend so if you look at what we've got
here and I can even put these in so that
you can see them literally if you look
at what's going on here we can say well
zero two four and six they should be
getting the negative version of X right
and then one three five and seven should
be getting the positive version of X
makes sense so then we have to look and
say okay now who's getting the positive
and negative versions of Y well zero and
one get the negative version of Y right
and four and five get the negative
version of Y so I know that there's
going to be a negative Y on each of
these oops
right so it's negative positive negative
positive negative positive negative
positive and then negative negative
personally positive positive negative
negative personally positive positive
and is it you know yes it is two and
three have the positive version six and
seven have the positive version right so
there's my you know positive Y positive
Y and then finally on Z you can see
there's just one Z blend zero one two
three all have the negative and four
five six seven all
the positive so we're negative Z on each
of these and there were positive Z on
each of these right so hopefully you can
see it's really simple for us to build
this weight table when you look at it
this way instead of some giant tangle of
crap that's really hard for you to
understand you can just see it's like
negative positive negative positive
negative negative positive positive
negative negative negative negative
positive positive right it's much easier
to see what's going on in this case and
then once we have those weight values
now the result just becomes the sum of
the weights so it's just tiles zero
value right and each of those is going
to be multiplied by its weight and I
guess in this case we might want it to
look like that just cause it's a little
easier and so we can just now sum all of
these up and that's the actual equation
that we needed right so that should do
don't ask me why there's a semicolon
there so that should do exactly the same
thing right so this should produce
literally no change unless I've screwed
it up which you know often happens but
basically that's exactly the same
sampling it's just being computed in a
slightly different way and you know the
compiler probably turns these into the
same thing once it does all of its SSA
and you know expression elimination and
so on
but the reason that we want this
transformation is that once we've put it
in this form we can now for free do
normalization or knock outs or anything
else so for example if in here where we
do compute foxes or radians at we have
two choices we can do really any number
of things but what we can do here is say
look how did you want to compute this
voxel irradiance do you want to just
pass me in for example an f32 pointer
where you're going to say look here's
where the knock out values come from or
something right and I don't know exactly
how we'd want to do this but I'm
guessing instead of a 32 I probably just
want to take a you thirty-two mast
probably even just a you 16 mask here
I'm guessing that would probably have
come from you know one of the external
values we would have gotten right and so
I don't know exactly how we want this
mask to come in but I think that's more
or less what we would want and probably
what we want to do here is we just want
to use the mask value to knock out
certain elements of the voxel so you
know something where we loft the mask up
into some kind of a usable a usable
multiplier there's some it's kind of
hard to say exactly how you want to do
this because we haven't written this
routine in Cindy yet so again I'm really
just not sure how we want to do that try
to think because probably what's going
to happen is you're gonna do we would do
the classification wide and then yeah so
you know honestly I think it probably
will be something more like this it
probably will be something more like
this so you'll probably just use
coefficients that come in the
coefficients will go like this so
they'll multiply on the back here
so you can devalue ones that you can't
reach and then when you're done with
this what we want to do is 1 normalize
these values so we need to do a sum
where we take each of these and add them
together right so that we can produce
the total value that we're going to get
and then once we know what that total
value is it's pretty cheap for us to
invert it and the only thing I'm not
sure about here is like you know if
you're doing like a fast reciprocal do
we have yeah so you know we have
approximate one over and you know I'm
guessing that that's would probably be
what happens here and I guess we didn't
ever actually do one that doesn't use
f/32 for X's which may be fine you know
[Music]
man so I'm not sure how I feel about
that or if I care so for right now maybe
we'll just say all right you know maybe
we do in our CP PS at some point so
we're expecting that will do this for
right now maybe we don't I mean
maybe we'll just do over this and let's
put it to do here like to do widen this
path and use our CP because you know at
the moments like okay we could still use
our CP even just because it's a scalar
but we don't actually need to because
we're not really trying to improve the
performance of this particular path
right now we will eventually probably
want to but it's sort of a separate
discussion so we're going to have an
inverse sum here and we want to use that
to multiply each of these values and
again really all this is is just saying
look we need to boost all of the nonzero
values to account for the values that
got zero it out or lessened by the
coefficient that the caller requested so
we're just it's really just this right
it's really just an additional sum that
tax on the end and because we know that
that sum will distribute across all of
the W's we don't actually have to do it
at that time right what we can do
instead is just say well after we do all
of the multiplied sums we can just do it
at the end right because whatever the
lighting value that we got we know that
all of the weights would have been
multiplied by this inverse sum so we can
literally just do one multiply at the
end of the production and that would
produce everything we needed better yet
it makes it pretty easy for us to do
this because since we probably won't be
taking 4 samples at the same time
because the Intel chips have the
absolute worst scatter gather
performance of any chip
the known universe in fact doesn't even
have instructions for it to lay VX we
know that we can't really do this path
for wide very efficiently anyway so at
that point it's like well since this is
going to be a lateral some actually
doing RGB at the same time is a cheap
way to get 3x the performance through
here since I don't think we're going to
get 4x the performance through here so
this whole thing could be done wide and
you could do the RGB zall at the same
time and so that's a nice way to think
about how to widen this path in the
future in a way that might not be
horrible because we'll get 3 X naught
for X but hey it's 3 X with literally no
work that's pretty good ok so if I go
ahead and build now what we will find is
that the f32 C pointer is not going to
be supplied by the people who actually
need this to happen so if we take a look
inside the a B raycast responds pretty
that's currently running you can see us
doing our compute voxel irradiance and
what we have is you know a missing
parameter here now the cheapest thing to
do obviously in this case is just to say
look there's eight of these right here's
the I don't know we want to call this
but basically the like the gather
coefficient or something and we know
that if we just set this to like all
ones that should be sufficient to
reproduce the exact same thing that we
were getting before so if I were to do
this I should see no change if we didn't
screw up the previous path by the
changes I just made we will see the same
rough lighting occurring as we march
through the world and that you know that
does seem to be roughly what we're
getting I don't see really much evidence
of any change at all
you know don't quote me on that but it
seems about right from what I can tell
and remember I think we turned off all
the lights so there's no lights where
where there actually are lamps like
they're normally were because I think we
stopped adding those so we're literally
just looking at
spread from this particular light and at
the moment it looks about the same as it
used to
I don't see any indication that it's
different so hopefully we're basically
getting the same thing but I don't know
you know it's always kind of hard to
tell but bounce lighting wise I don't
know like it sure does look like like
these tiles are getting brighter there I
don't know but maybe that's just it yeah
it's really again it's really really
difficult unfortunately to know like
kind of what you're getting we probably
should put some strongly color altering
occluders in here so that we can see the
difference between the direct lighting
and the bounced lighting so you know for
example if i if i went into the push
occluder code you know you pass a
separate color in here so what I could
do and I don't really know if this will
work particularly effectively but what I
could do is say like what if I just you
know instead of pushing include er of
the actual correct color I just knock
out all but the red component or
something right so if you imagine doing
that then at least I could see a little
bit what is the complaint oh why does it
take a v4
it doesn't use it so that's odd but okay
so anyway if I knock out the other color
components I should now be able to tell
the difference between things that
directly sampled the white light source
and things which bounced and yeah I mean
you know that's bounce lighting right I
mean kind of obviously is in the sense
that you can see it right there getting
affected you know by it
I could turn off the moonlight just as
another just to force so uh so that we
kind of know we're looking at I could
say you know moon color
x equals zero and that would that would
just knock out any inbound lighting from
anywhere else so then you would get you
know this and all of the bounce lighting
that we see now is coming from just this
one light source right so you know it
looks reasonable you know it's hard to
say
it looks reasonable and you can see
people doing back sampling here right
that's what you're getting in some of
these so you know I think I think that
we're doing the sampling but again it's
really hard to test so as we do lighting
quality we're going to have to invent
good ways of generating test cases
because it's really hard to say right
and so as we move through the world
using this particular test you can count
yet you can kind of see what's going on
here and I mean it sure seems like it's
working but again it's really hard to
say I mean I guess one thing we could do
to test it is say well okay so what if
we went into this code and we we
intentionally knocked out a particular
blend so you know suppose we said we
only wanted reflections from one side so
we knock out you know all of the things
on the left side of the blend and only
allowed things on the right side of the
blend you know that's one way of poking
at this thing and seeing what happens so
I mean that's a good test right that
clearly screwed up so I think that's
good really because it means we've
gotten an error in here and we can go
look at what's going on in there right
so if we set these if we set these C
zeros to knock out certain parts of the
of the blends somehow that gave us a
massively over contributed lighting
which again might not even be wrong it's
hard to say because we we actually don't
know if that's just because it caused us
to like overweight certain values
quickly right or something like this so
we don't really know but it certainly
shouldn't be the case that like an our
goal was to stabili blend these together
so it's possible that this is just buggy
right like this is doing it wrong and
when these all added up to one which
they were previously going to do when
they don't add up to one
somehow this produces some kind of
erroneously weird result right so since
we have that I'm gonna go ahead and
switch to a debug build so I can look at
that routine and just see what's going
on because maybe I just made some stupid
error that won't take very long to find
I don't know it could be much more
complicated than that obviously but
let's go ahead and try it so if I run
the program now and I guess I'm looking
for compute Vox Iranian sat there so
where was my lighting code lighting
lighting lighting lighting lighting so
if I want to take a look at that compute
voxel irradiance at code that should
probably be right here yeah and I think
we're running here yeah we are so if I
wanted to look at this I'm just gonna
just gonna stop here and I just want to
produce what these weighting values are
so that I can look at the weighting
values look they look somewhat
reasonable
I should think right it's a little bit
hard to say because since the C values
have pre knocked out the other values I
can't see what they are but I can just
do this and see if that would have been
a large value and it was so once we
produce the sum here you can see what it
actually is that's the sum of all of the
values that have been added up I'll be
honest that doesn't Oh cuz I haven't run
it yet look it doesn't look right that
looks right and then we can see what the
inverse is and there we go now I guess
one problem that we'd have is if for
some reason we were saying if we ever
got a sample value where we knocked out
the only values that actually were non
zero then this inves inverse sum would
be a problem so I guess one thing I
should take out I don't really expect it
to be happening but you never really
know is I could just say well the
inverse sum in this case needs to be
guarded so if the sum is greater than
zero we do it if it's not we don't and
maybe we even just give it a tolerance
so we're never going to produce
particularly egregious values and we'll
have to see how we want to deal with
that
a little bit later but let's suppose I
did something like that because I'm just
curious if we were what we were actually
seeing is just one case where we landed
right on the dividing line which you
know could have happened I'm just
curious what is going on
stop build
yeah and run okay so I guess that was
all it was was we literally did have
some that landed right on the boundary
because here's the lighting and it's
working okay with that now one of the
really disturbing things about this as I
hope you can appreciate is although you
can see the sightedness so let's suppose
I stop right here you can see the
sightedness that is in there right you
know as I move over here you can see
that it's really unlikely that you'll
get stuff happening on the side but it's
very likely that you'll get stuff
happening on this side well actually
that's not actually probably the
sidedness to be completely honest with
you
so I'll ignore that part of it for now I
was gonna say you can see and hear how
we get some red sampling coming in and
we don't get any on this side whereas if
I was to change it back we will probably
get that so if I actually look at the
gather see and I change it back to all
ones I should see now red fringing on
either side but again the the thing that
I wanted to underscore there was like it
was so subtle though and so it's really
kind of disturbing because you're like
it's so hard to see if these things are
working properly right so now you can
see some red fringing on this side but
man is that like hard to tell and so you
know it's it's really kind of one of
those things that I think we're really
gonna have to you know put our thinking
caps for because it's like crazy that
you can literally sample like totally
wrong and it's still really it still
kind of looks like lighting you know
that's just not that makes it really
hard to find the problems and I just
don't
like you know I just don't know how to
verify that this is even remotely right
at this point right it still could be
like totally busted
and we just don't have a good way of
knowing so I do think that's another
quality issue it's like we're going to
have to actually have a solid
explanation of how the heck we know if
this stuff is working properly and at
the moment I really don't think we do
but I'm gonna now go ahead and say let's
switch back over to the previous method
and I'm going to add in a thing that
allows us to block light from coming
from certain locations now if I do the
gather see here again and I just stuff
in the garbage values that we had I
think we're almost out of time too so I
probably won't have a chance to finish
this today but we can finish it tomorrow
if I go ahead and and just do a quick
builds and run the game what you will
see right oh and that's kind of nice you
can see that the propagation is all
happening in the secondary bounce cuz
it's all red right that's pretty handy
actually that change you made so what
you can see happening here again is like
that spreading to outside the wall I
want to see if I can contain that by not
allowing any of the light to propagate
past the boundary that got hit and this
is actually not that complicated as a
basis for for producing this gather C
value and the reason that it's actually
somewhat simple is I know where each of
these gather C values comes from because
they're known voxel locations so they're
just wherever I hit is a particular
voxel location and I just need to take
the normal and I need to determine and
in fact you know now and I'm thinking
about it I don't even know that I need
to
um I don't even know that I need to
really pass this in I mean if we're
honest about it I think we could
probably produce it up here I think it's
a fairly straightforward computation
that's just based on the position and
the normal right because I think all we
need to do is take the wherever the
voxel would have been and we just look
to see whether or not the thing you hit
is on the same side or the other side of
the place you're going to sample I think
that's actually all we need right
because again if we just pop over to the
board for one quick second I can explain
what I mean if we were to do this and
just think about doing it in 2d because
it's always easier to think that in 2d
than 3d and they're the same in this
case they're not the same in general if
you imagine we have four sample points
that represent the lighting samples of
our voxels so here are like what the
cells of the voxel would look like right
what we're fundamentally asking is if we
have a point and that point has a normal
we know that we're in one voxel cell or
rather I shouldn't say where we don't
really care that we're in one box we'll
sell we know there was some origin point
and we know that we are viewing this you
know location we know that we're viewing
that from this origin point right so
what we fundamentally want to know is
could we have seen each of these things
that we're going to sample could we have
seen them from this origin point based
on this hit right and what you can see
is
if I was to consider this to be a plane
passing through here based on the normal
what I would immediately see is that for
the origin looking at this point any of
the voxel cells whose sample origin
happens to be on the same side as the
Ray origin of this plane is something
whose lighting probably could have
contributed right now we don't know for
sure the full the most aggressive
version of this sample gather is to
actually ray cast back from the sample
point to all of these to see if you can
see them and people do that that's an
actual thing but because we don't have
the horsepower for it we're just gonna
say look classify it based on the normal
assume there weren't things like hanging
around in here but definitely don't
sample things on the other side because
if if we couldn't make it past here we
sure don't want to sample it right so
it's just a basic simple heuristic to
prevent light propagation in cases that
we think are pretty solidly obviously
not going to work as opposed to doing
the more aggressive version which is
very expensive right so let's take a
look if we then go and look at the you
know what we were doing over here we've
got our gather see and I'm just gonna
say look what we need to do is and I
guess I guess what we can see here is
that hey we don't have the origin as a
classifier in this case
we kind of don't need it though because
we know that that we know that the
normal has to point in the direction of
the ort so it's really just a
classification on the normal like it's
really just a classification to say what
it what's going on with this right and I
think that should be sufficient let me
think about that for a second I mean
there are other ways to think about it
than that now yeah so you know what
maybe we should think about this a
little bit more carefully so what are we
going to be doing eventually eventually
what we're going to be doing is saying
we have a normal we have a raycast
that has hit this point right and we
want to know therefore you know what
would have the what would the bounce
gather have been right and for a
diffused surface at the moment what
we're saying it's like well we're just
going to use how much light it would
have given here and we probably need a
cosine fall-off in there right and
interestingly enough we like don't have
one at the moment but I think we do it
on the outside so you know let's again
that's a lighting quality pass thing and
so if we're talking about light that
could have been gathered from here we
kind of know that lighting coming from
here is not super relevant because
obviously it could not have produced a
bounce because it's on the wrong side of
the surface so I think all we really
want to do is just classify based on the
normal could it have come from someplace
out here and we could even be so
aggressive as to co-sign wait those
contributions if we wanted to right
so we could set the W values to actually
be like these C values to not just be 0
or 1 they could even be cosine fall-off
angles I don't know if we really want to
do that but you can see where I'm
with that right so if we wanted to do
that what we could do is say well for
each of these and you can see this get
tile clamped thing here right if I go to
get clamped you can see what I do here
is it's just producing this the it's
just looking up into the voxel for each
of these positions and since I can
pretty much directly determine what the
actual voxel value is in each case and
you know I don't even really need to
because I can just do it in relative
voxel space I kind of can just use the
normals I can probably just even use the
the sample P well can I do that I'm
trying to think if there's a way to
avoid actually doing the subtract so if
you think about what's gonna happen here
right the sample P is going to give me
you can think about the sample P as now
having been mapped into the voxel right
so what I'm gonna end up with is I'm
gonna end up with something where I I do
have a normalized inside of oxley I mean
I can even just look at it this way I'm
going to have a normalized coordinate
that's the uvw right so I'm gonna have
one in here that's like UVW right and
then I'm going to have a sign of my
normal right and I think because it's
already been mapped into the space of
the voxel I think that means all I have
to do is just read the sign right
because I've already put it so that this
is the basis the corner for I've already
figured out which corner it is because
we mapped it into the voxel so I think I
already know well whichever direction
this thing is pointing I just need to
grab the things that are cited properly
with that so if the if the voxel X is
positive I'm sorry if the normals X is
positive then I think you just grab
these and if it's negative you grab
these would be how that would work right
trying to think if there's how this
would work exactly so I guess the
problem is depending on how far this is
you don't really know so I mean let's
suppose it looks like that right versus
the same exact plane but up here you
would produce different results so
unfortunately I do think you have to do
the subtract I think you have to do the
subtractive the uvw I just don't see how
else you could really do it right I mean
you know man I just I don't really
I don't really see a lot of options
there and I could be missing something I
could be missing something but I don't I
don't see really what else you could do
so I think probably what we need there
is just like you need to do the inner
product of the two directions so you
have the normal and you do the subtract
you do the inner product and then you
Clint you can see if it's if it's less
than zero you know so again I don't know
exactly how we want to do that and
whether we want that to be a fall off
base thing or not but if you imagine
building this set of results here you
know you're gonna end up with something
that looks like this which is like the I
guess the product and in fact I could
actually just do it this way so here's
our coefficient values and we know we
have the UVW and so then we know like
each of the different locations that
we're doing a subtraction from so in
this case we would know that it's like
you know it's UVW whatever it is minus
the v3 0 0 0 which of course will
produce exactly the same value and we
just need to take the inner product of
that direction with the normal that
we're actually sampling right so this
sample normal that would tell us that
would classify each one of these things
relative to the surface right so if we
take each of these and we know you know
we do an X move for each of them here we
know we do a y move for each of them
here and a z move for each of them here
to line them up with how we did these in
theory this now gives us that inner
product fall-off and we just have to
then decide what we actually want to do
with that inner product fall-off do we
want to use it and just clamp it to zero
or do we want to to force it to be
either zero or one meaning we would we
don't actually smoothly fall off and I'm
gonna go ahead and say since we're
bothering to calculate it let's just try
this muth fall off so I'm gonna say the
heck with it
let's just do a clamp zero one on this
and and we'll just kind of produce those
values like so at that point we don't
need to pass in the weights because it
looks like we can just produce
reasonable weights directly from that
process so I guess this just goes away
which hey that's great if it turns out
that's really something we don't have to
worry about I'm pretty happy about that
means that these just aren't necessary
and the less things are necessary the
better the code so I think that's all we
need and we can now see to what extent
that's working properly we probably have
to do some tests I don't know exactly
what we want to do there but so here's
it with the barrier in place and one of
the things you'll immediately notice is
this I believe was the code that was
spiking directly so that did the
feedback the bad feedback loop and one
thing you can see is it's not doing that
now and these are not getting those
values right so that's a pretty dramatic
quality improvement you know not only
did it do the thing I wanted to do which
was to prevent light leaking into the
bottom but it also like kept the spiking
down dramatically in fact it still
spikes a little in certain places but so
that's that's just a really good sign
right we're still pretty far from having
a good results but it's pretty great
that that just that alone is is doing it
and you can see look at those those are
all nicely clamped now and we're not
getting any leaking to the outside so
that's a pretty dramatic improvement I
think that's a good place to stop for
today and tomorrow what we can do is
take a look at the cube casting to start
to work on
how the actual light values should be
maintained because it looks like we're
sort of getting a little bit closer to
having those values be sane as we go
right and I think that's good so again
just to recap a little bit too I said
this last week I'll say it again not a
big fan of unit tests I think they're
mostly useless a lot of the times and
when you can isolate a circumstance
where you really can write one
effectively they're great and I don't
dislike them at all I think they're
fantastic for that but most of the time
the more productive type of coding to do
for testing is visualization and the
reason for that is two-fold one is it
can help you debug things that unit
tests just can't address because it's
very hard to figure out how you would
ever write a unit test but the far far
far far more important aspect of it is
it gains you insight into the problem
and unit testing never really does that
so when you spend time on visualization
code you start to see things immediately
like I saw the inside the wall part of
things I saw the fact that these things
down here we're getting lighting those
immediately allow me to start improving
my algorithm that have nothing to do
with whether it was behaving in a way
that I could have defined ahead of time
because this is all approximate I don't
know what the correct definition is for
the lighting in this case I really don't
I could compare it against a ground
truth reference raycast but I know we'll
never be able to produce something that
matches that sort of thing closely right
so at the best possible case the thing
that the unit tests could have done is
just told me that I had the lighting
wrong there but it wouldn't have told me
what would have been the ways to start
modifying my algorithm to get it closer
this kind of visualization is so good
precisely because it allows me to start
attacking the problem using entirely new
insights I didn't have before I started
right and so I think the challenge for
our next step as we try to get the
lighting looking really nice is to
figure out what kind of visualizations
we can use to
utilize how the lighting is flowing
through this the voxel so that we can
sort of build our intuition about how
those values should work and how they
can say stable over time right and
that's really something that I think
will push it forward
further but I'm really happy with where
it's at at the moment anyway
it's also not that expensive and I think
we'll be able to run it at 60 frames a
second without too much effort as well
in fact it might already might already
be running at 60 frames a second
actually because if you look at how much
time is currently spent on the debug you
can see that actually if you chop that
off you'd probably be it's experience we
should draw 60 frames a second bar in
there but it's pretty close and at the
very least you run this on an i-9 9 i9
9900 and and this is 16 this is 16
milliseconds no problem because we have
we would have a whole bunch more threads
to use as well so I think because I
don't remember I mean correct me if I'm
wrong but it's this yeah this is a fake
course for real cores right so for real
for real cores but eight hyper threads
modern the modern intel line not to
mention the AMD line which is way better
on core account is already at eight real
processors so you know as machines get
faster our lighting gets dramatically
faster because it's completely paralysed
and so I feel like you know to a certain
extent we've we're already at 60fps in
software just by upgrading the machine
right so that's a good place to be as
well let's go ahead and go to a brief
Q&amp;A and then let's also talk if Adam I
don't know if abner still here but we
can also talk about handmade Seattle
that's the cube ray-tracing that was
just running so if you look that was the
cube raytracer that I was just running
to have any suggestions regarding how to
study and better retain information I
remember you said you learned math only
because you realized you needed it to
program things so particularly relation
to math do you have any advice on how to
learn in ways that are more efficient um
so I guess I don't have a lot of
specific advice because I think it
depends a lot on how your brain happens
to retain information different people
have different affinities for like how
they will retain information and so I
don't think there's a universal wrong or
right way for that reason there are
certainly probably ways that will never
work for anyone and there are probably
some ways that work pretty well for
everyone but then I suspect there's also
for every individual they probably fall
into one of a few camps of learning and
if you happen to pick a technique that
works well for your camp you're going to
be a lot more effective than if you say
so you know if you and I have slightly
different learning you know brain
chemistry's or whatever then if you
follow exactly the way that works best
for me it may actually be slightly
slower for you than if you follow the
way that works best for you which would
be slightly slower for me so I do think
you have to be careful taking advice
from people because if those people
don't happen to learn as in the same way
that you do as effectively you may just
be artificially hindered by that advice
so I think the broader advice I can give
you that hopefully would apply to
everyone is try to self-analyze as much
as you can your learning processes
because if you randomly try some stuff
so read the chapter of a book on math
that people say is a good math book
right how well did you retain the
information do the exercises how well
did you retain the information now try a
different scheme pick a programing thing
that you want to do that involves math
learn the math for that and write the
program that does that solves a problem
working it through till you get the
right answer right how well do you
retain the information now how much time
in each of those take versus how much
information you write spend a month or
two doing the experimentation to see how
you retain the information right because
learning how you learn is something you
can then apply forever and it will
always be worth your time to spend a
month or two figuring out which way
helps you retain it best so I would
advise against taking someone else's
recommended approach and I would instead
recommend trying a number of approaches
because it's obvious that there are a
number and you can just like read a
whole bunch of people's opinions on it
and just write down all the things you
that they said as different possible
approaches try them and see how it
sticks in your head for a variety of
different learning methods and then
whichever one seemed like the best bang
for the buck so took the least time for
the most amount of retention that's
probably what you're looking at for me I
learned programming when I was
incredibly young compared to most people
I guess even today I started programming
when I was 7
what I think that means for me is that
my brain is probably more hardwired to
think in terms of code than most
people's so for learning math for me I
have to write the code that I simply do
not learn math from math ever at all it
doesn't happen so for people who learned
math first and programming second like
something like that could be inverted
right but for me because I learned
programming incredibly young way before
I knew math at all like I don't even
know if I knew addition let alone
multiplication I mean when you're 7 in
the US
you're a long way from being at the
point in school where you learn
multiplication tables right I think you
learned multiplication tables I want to
say in fourth grade in the US League did
for me and I had been programming for
years by the time I learned the
multiplication table the multiplication
tables like forget algebra just how to
multiply you know nine times seven right
so if you think about the difference
between those two things it's it I think
becomes fairly obvious why for me I've
got to write the code because I think my
brain just it's just that's how it works
it's a procedural brain it thinks in
terms of steps it doesn't think in terms
of equalities so if you present me a
bunch of stuff in equations I just don't
think that way it's not gonna help me
equivalence isn't a thing my brain
understands natively it's a thing it had
to learn later that's kind of foreign
procedural like the way a CPU works is
native to my brain like my brain thinks
through problems as assignments not
equivalences and so at that point it you
know it's just for me math is inherently
foreign it always will be and so I
always need to translate it into some
procedural version that events is the
concept in order for me to really I
think fully internalize it as a thing I
can use and that may be completely
inverted I bet for some people if you
learned a lot of math or spent a lot of
time doing math before you ever learned
programming I I would be shocked if the
opposite wasn't true for you right but I
I could be wrong
when you're building the weight table
why were the negative values 1 minus u
VW x instead of 0 minus u VW x sorry if
you already answered this I tuned in
late yeah you should probably go
re-watch this episode when I post the
vaad hopefully later today because I
walked through exactly how the linear
blend works in this case and you're
gonna probably want to watch that whole
thing I explained it in like in complete
detail and I think it hopefully will be
clear if you go watch that so yeah I
mean I guess what I would say is if you
if you go take a look at the complete
explanation from this episode I think it
should should tell you exactly why it's
1 minus but if it's not you can always
come back tomorrow hint and ask me and
I'll happily go over the part you didn't
get from from today the video paper
you're using in the beginning was using
depth info on the light probes to avoid
light leaking is this something you
might also want to try so I I want to if
I can I want to get away with not doing
so the reason for that is that storing
that information is going to be an
additional cost for us and I'd really
like to not do it if I can get away with
it the Nvidia paper has loftier goals
than do we write there they were doing a
research and they were trying to produce
a they were trying to do as high quality
work as they could right but I don't
want to do additional ops that I don't
have to do and if you if you have to
start storing the depth map that's just
a lot of extra work right so I'm hoping
we can get away without it because we
don't need to produce particularly
accurate lighting we're just trying to
produce lighting that we think looks
good for our game and it's already
getting there so I'm hoping that we can
just not if we have to we have to but
you know
Oh Abner said the info was on the site
he had to go okay so I guess it's too
bad Abner is not here because I was
gonna ask him some questions about about
the conference but I'll just mention it
anyway I'm sure there'll be a lot more
information and I'll mention it on
stream more prominently in the future
when it's when it's more of a going
concern I guess but I just wanted people
to be aware of the fact that handmade
Seattle I think that's the web address
is it an org yes no it's a comm I don't
know
so handmade Seattle which was the
conference that Abner organized last
year which everyone said they loved as
far as I could tell I heard you know
many people say that they thought it was
great was going to be done again he even
said at last year's conference he was
like I'm going to do it again next year
obviously because of pandemic concerns
everyone assumed including me that it
would not be happening this year but it
turns out it is happening this year and
they he's just going to do it as an
online event instead of as a as a thing
where you actually go in person which
obviously would have a tremendous amount
of risk associated with it both in terms
of the air travel lots of people come
from overseas for handmade Seattle and
so this just got announced it was like
yesterday I saw the email and what
they're doing or I guess I should say
what Abner specifically was doing this
is Abner what they're doing is it is
going to be free which is kind of
awesome but there are going to be
tickets to help fund it and of course
pay for average time he does all of this
basically just out of the goodness of
his heart
if you
go to the page for tickets here which
will be going on sale I guess where is
the I don't actually know there was
thing so I guess they'll be going on
sale in three weeks if you go look at
the the tickets what's gonna happen is
basically there's sort of a virtual
attendance that will happen and it's
like kind of to gate it so that it's not
a twitchchat disaster it's basically
like if you buy a ticket to the
conference you will be able to like ask
questions like as if you were attending
right and so everyone can see it for
free but if you want to actually attend
and ask questions and participate then
you buy a ticket and the ticket will get
you access to like the private chat
server where peas are asking the
questions and interacting with the
people who are presenting and so on
which i think is a great idea so i just
wanted to let you know that that's
coming up put it on your radar there'll
be a lot more announcements about it as
it actually comes a thing as you know
now it's just it's literally just a
website right now you can't even buy the
tickets yet so when it gets closer to
the time and the tickets are actually
available I'll make sure to mention it
again but just so you know if you want
to interact with that or whatever check
out the Twitter feed or look at what's
going on that's what's going on right so
that's the basically the this is the
situation
any thoughts on the nanite and real
engine demo yeah I covered it previously
it's just we didn't record it because I
didn't know if there would be like I
went through the demo with people and I
kind of explained what was going on I
didn't record that at least I don't
think I have it recorded it might be in
the twitch back capture it probably is
actually so if you're a subscriber to
the Trish channel you can probably go to
the back catalogue Ince and watch me
discuss it and it was actually kind of
funny cuz amusingly I was like what
they're probably doing here is this
thing and I pointed to a paper and then
someone on the chat was like actually
they posted that they specifically were
using that technique and I'm like oh
well good good to know my guess work is
still on point so apparently they are
doing exactly what I said they were
doing but I didn't actually know that
when I said it my common way to see math
and programming is to see the sub
concepts of the concept trying to learn
and do like a tree until I get the Leafs
which are concepts I already know or
axioms then I go upward from there and
try to specifically understand the how
and why of the concept connections works
well for both furthering in math I can't
say I really do it that way but it does
sound like a reasonable option build you
strong could we just create a distance
limit to stop bouncing light we could
but I don't really want to because light
bounces as far as it bounces I mean
light itself doesn't attenuate absent a
participating medium so why you can see
stars so you you don't really want to
simulate light that way if you can avoid
it but you know we we actually do have
some stuff in there to make computation
an easier we do use a sort of bucket
brigade approach to avoid having to
traverse long distances on the ray casts
we already do that though
in what way tis a custom engine effect
the field of the game is it always a
question of having better performance or
allowing for my flexibility I've always
thought there's nothing you can't do and
you
real is just going to be slower um so
that's a that's a really I want to say
deep question or rather the answer is
kind of deep so here's what I would say
I think people don't appreciate just how
bad it is to use a premade engine for a
game and here's why
while it's totally true that there's
plenty of circumstances in which you
just don't have a choice right because
it's a tremendous way too much work to
build an engine these days come like
computers and gaming are just too
complicated so I don't begrudge anyone
the decision to use unity or unreal like
it's an it's a very difficult choice to
say we're going to make our own custom
thing right so I don't think it's a bad
decision to do so but what I do think
people have to understand is just how
costly it is in terms of what you are
capable of making and the reason for
that is because when you sit down to
make something what you are given as
your medium has a dramatic effect on
what you can create because all of the
decisions that were made in every aspect
whether it's how you make models for the
game how you import them how the world
is created how the world is stored what
the representation for the logical
entities are in that world what the way
in which the scripting works or how it
is then put all of every single one of
those things each one of those decisions
make some game designs hard and some
game designs easy and when you're
talking about an engine with literally
hundreds of thousands of decisions
having been made in something like
unreal or at Unity you're talking about
a situation
we're a whole swath of possible games
are very hard to create while a whole
swath of possible games are very easy to
create and I think it overwhelmingly
leads games made in these engines to
feel the same and I think the proof is
kind of in the pudding they're like I
don't know about you but when I play
games these days they all feel the same
it's weird right
you play 10 games that look completely
different like the graphics are
obviously completely different they have
very different styles and when you play
them it feels like you're playing the
exact same game it's it's it's eerie and
you can't even necessarily put your
finger on it because they're definitely
different right but I think the problem
is once you make this decision that's
like well I'm using unities system and
I'm creating the entities in my game
with unities entity system and it's
definition of an entity and what an
entity can do I think it just
overwhelmingly funnels people towards
making things that feel a particular way
and one of the most interesting
experiences that I have had in recent
memory is I went home to visit my
parents a year ago two years ago I don't
remember how long ago it was obviously I
go to visit my parents you know often
but one this was one particular time I
went home to visit my parents and I
happened to take out a colecovision now
a colecovision is is one of these it is
a video game console and it was the
video game console that I had as a child
so when I say we took out ColecoVision I
literally mean we took out the
ColecoVision that I had that my parents
literally bought in like 1982 or 1983
right like we had one
and when I played the games on this
ColecoVision I had to like try to sort
of repair the controllers they were kind
of corroded and not really working and
broken but you know I repaired the best
I could
I played maybe ten cartridges or twelve
cartridges that we had for the
ColecoVision and every single one felt
completely different it was shocking
like frogger - felt completely different
from venture felt completely different
from pepper - felt completely different
from ladybug and the variety of games
that people seem to end up with when
they had to write the whole game there's
something wrong with our current way of
doing things and it seems kind of just
obvious right and so the main thing I
would say is not so much that using
unity or unreal or something like that
is a problem because there's some better
performance or something you're going to
get out of your engine and that may be
true I mean if you write a bespoke
engine for something and you're really
good at it obviously you can outperform
unreal or unity I mean there's no
question making a general-purpose engine
is much harder than making a
special-purpose engine so their job is
harder than yours just by definition but
I don't really think that's the biggest
concern these days I'm thinking the
biggest concern is that the tools you
are given to make these games force you
into making the same damn game and the
result is 7,000 games a year literally
and I feel like there's no new games a
year right and it's really depressing so
I don't know right and so that's
unfortunate but that just feels like
what's happening and I don't know it
could just be not that it could just be
that because there's 7,000 games a year
it's really hard to find the two or
three that are actually different
whereas on the ColecoVision when there
was only a hundred games a year you were
probably going to find the two or three
that were actually different right so
that's another possibility it could just
be that the signal to
his ratio has become so terrible and
that's a reason why I wish engines
didn't exist in that case because then
there'd be far fewer games maybe but you
know I don't really think that's the
case cuz I feel like I would probably
hear about them if there were really
interesting games coming out and and I
and I don't so I don't know I mean I
could be wrong but
and and just in terms like someone was
saying like I would argue it's not the
fault of engines but rather lazy devs I
mean not again I don't really think it's
appropriate to blame somebody for it
right it's just how it is and I don't
necessarily think you can accuse
developers of being lazy because I mean
they may not even have the capability to
do otherwise right I mean the if you
really wanted to make a creative new
game design inside unity or unreal well
you're basically rolling your own mini
engine inside their engine and then
having to make a shim that that converts
kind of to their idea of how everything
is stored and all this other stuff right
and that's incredibly difficult I mean
the the point of having pre-made engines
was supposed to be that people didn't
have to learn all of the stuff that we
cover on handmade hero right like that's
the point
and I think the unfortunate reality is
you really just can't have it both ways
like if you are capable of doing all
this stuff then yeah sure you know your
choices is pretty much anything you want
you could just roll your own engine you
could decide that well I can make my own
mini engine inside of unreal and then
just leverage their renderer or
something right you can make creative
decisions like that to save yourself
time or whatever else you want to do and
you can but the number of people who can
do that is very small all of the people
who have kind of been told that well you
just use this engine you can make your
game I mean I think unfortunately it's
not they're not being lazy they're just
they're all they know is what can be
done in that like they don't they don't
have the knowledge or capability yet to
understand that there are things that
they can't do or even that their
decisions are being forced in a
particular direction because of these
engines so I don't consider that to be
laziness I consider that to be not you
know not having provided the materials
or not understanding well enough as an
industry what the differences are and
what actually is happening there because
it's not obvious it's not clear so I
don't I don't think it's fundamentally
the case that that there are developers
that are being lazy
here I don't I don't think that's true I
think they're people who are making a
particular business decision who perhaps
don't realize necessarily what that
entails and how that will affect what
kind of games they ever end up making so
I think that's true but I also think
it's just as an industry we don't
understand these things very well we
don't really understand what kinds of
games don't get made because of all the
people going to pre-made engines right
so it's really I think it's incorrect to
call anyone lazy in this scenario I
think it's it's a question of
understanding and we don't understand it
very well
and yeah I mean I also to be honest I
also disagree with the opinion that it's
an issue of uncreative games coming from
people wanting to make money I don't
think that's true either I think there's
a tremendous number of fairly earnest
games that were that are not cynical
they're not money grabs being made in
unreal and unity and they still just
feel really derivative and samey even
from people who are developers who are
specifically trying to stand out and do
something different and and it just
doesn't and that's because the gameplay
the actual thing you feel like they may
take a bold art direction they may take
a bold narrative direction but what they
fundamentally can't do is take a bold
actual game direction because unreal and
unity are fundamentally only suitable
for building very specific types of
games that are more or less games where
there are independent entities floating
around in the world with a physics
engine underlying them of varying
degrees of responsiveness that you then
interact with by entity touches entity
events like effectively all these games
are collision oriented event driven
games and that's all we make right and
breaking out of that is very difficult
when you use these engines because you
will be forced to write everything
yourself right if you choose to do so
and most people who go into that would
not know how to do that for any
non-trivial game design I mean I think
to a certain extent you know one of the
one of the things I think is really
interesting to me just really really
interesting to me is if you take a look
at how many people have Trott have have
clearly taken the direction that John
Blow went in braid the 2d platformer but
that has a much deeper underlying set of
game mechanics that get exposed write
effectively nobody despite like hundreds
if not thousands of games that clearly
descended from this idea almost none of
them have any gameplay of that kind
right almost none and that's because
it's incredibly difficult to program all
in all this complex like the simple
thing that's in braid that all it was
was saying that the time that the t-axis
of the game and the x-axis of the game
were the same now right
that alone would be a tremendous amount
of of procedural programming knowledge
someone would have to have to do that
what even if they had unity or unreal
just the whole thing in front of them
right so almost nobody does and you can
write it's not that you can't if you
know what you're doing do these things
inside there but because people start
out and all they know is unity or all
they know is unreal and how to work with
those systems they never learn the
skills that would be necessary to do
those things and so that's a big part of
it right and it's really really
difficult to to get to those points and
I think if it were easy we'd see a lot
more games that could do it but as it is
we see few almost none maybe one or two
sometimes you know I'm blanking on any
examples right now but once in a while
you get someone who does do them and I
suspect those people probably came from
a programming background where they knew
more and so they were able to say oh
yeah like I'm gonna do this in unity or
unreal but I'm gonna write this whole
substrate that sits on top of it you
know that lets me create that kind of
interesting gameplay you know what I
mean and even those games probably don't
have nearly as much as braid had you
know
I don't think superhot did do that
superhot is just multiplying the time
step by how fast you're moving it can't
rewind like it doesn't go backwards
which in in braids in that particular
case in braids level forget the rewind
but in super hot you can't move
backwards and have the bullets retreat
right so it's not really the case so
and yeah I mean I don't have a
prescription for this and it's a samisen
I also don't care I mean except from the
perspective of being a game player
myself it's depressing to want to play a
game on the weekend and they're all the
same I feel like I've played them all
already you know and so but I don't I
don't care I guess at some level other
than the fact that I wish there's more
creativity but you know whatever but
yeah I would say maybe something that
the industry could consider doing is
actually trying to spend more time being
cognizant of what unity and unreal are
making easy and what they're making hard
and start trying to actively push on
those things like try to figure out how
you can make games that are looking at
what what am I not doing because it's
you know not something that's a checkbox
and on unity in whatever right and try
to push towards breaking more of those
barriers you know
um all right let's do last question
have I ever worked with HR TF based
audio and the answer is no I have not
I haven't actually ever seen the demo
that convinces me I care about HR TF
audio but I also haven't really been
looking so I'm totally willing to
believe that at some point we'll get to
a really high end ear response sim kind
of a thing that you know yeah I mean
that maybe at that point you're kind of
yeah I don't know I mean I really
couldn't tell you like I don't know if I
think it'll ever really be that relevant
but I'm willing to believe that it will
be at some point right so
um also I guess I would there's some
mention of cyberpunk 2077 that games not
out yet so I mean I was so you can't
have an opinion about it right but as
far as anyone shown it's just exactly
the same thing as you would expect if
you were playing any other game that was
literally exactly the same way like it
doesn't look even remotely like it's
doing anything with gameplay that's any
different from exactly what you could
have built in the Unreal Engine now
obviously I think it's great that they
do their own in-house engine because I
think the more engines the better but
there's literally nothing in the
cyberpunk 2077 demos that doesn't
suggest it's literally exactly something
you could have done in unreal and you
know I think that at least the ue4 stuff
is has a much harder time with expansive
environments and I think that the CD
Projekt RED people have done a much
better job with their engine in terms of
expansive vistas and stuff like that
then they right so I actually think CD
Projekt RED have done a fantastic job
with their engine I think they're a
great engine dev but in terms of
gameplay it's exactly the same thing
that you've played a hundred million
times before and you know I will
probably play it because I don't mind
playing a triple-a game once when I
played horizon zero dawn for example a
couple years back hmm had a good time
and so I think playing triple r games
can be fun sometimes because they hey
they present this big expansive world
with tons of art it's nice the gameplay
is exactly the freakin same it's I push
on the analog stick to move my dude
around or in Reggio dawn my lady around
and then I push on some buttons to like
fire projectiles and those things hit
and do something it's that's the whole
game it's asteroids 24/7 right and I
will be absolutely shocked if somehow
cyberpunk 2077 doesn't feel exactly the
same way right
I mean that's all that's what we write
we don't write anything else here and I
you know there's the little part of the
game that has the three choice dialogue
tree that someone's got in there right I
mean it's we just know we know what all
these things are gonna be I don't need
to play cyberpunk 2077 tell you
everything that's in cyberpunk 2077
because if there's one thing I can tell
you for sure is that a hundred percent
of the things that you saw at the PS 5
reveal our games I can already tell you
exactly how you play them right because
that's all we build it's not bad right
it's just we have to recognize that's
what it is
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the set of handmade hero sort of
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to file along a series at
home you can always pre-order the game
at handmade hero org and it comes to the
source code so you can follow along with
me as we build it I will be back here
tomorrow when I will start to look at
some other lighting quality things that
I'd like to look at with our cube caster
I was really pleased the progress we
made today everything kind of went you
know almost better than I would have
expected and so I feel really good about
our prospects for taking some more steps
down that road and the lighting is
starting to come into a place where I'm
thinking it might actually be kind of
nice and we can finally sign off on it's
one of the hardest things we've done on
handmade hero it's a really really
difficult problem for all engines even
you know the very latest game engines
cutting-edge game engines have a
tremendously hard time with indirect
lighting I mean you could even go see if
you look at the most recent Unreal 5
demo that they showed it has several
flames frames of lag on indirect
lighting changes it's just that's how
hard it is it's a very tough problem but
I think we're doing a reasonable job on
it and I think we can start to converge
now on on a good solution because
everything seems to be falling into
place relatively well it was a hard road
to get here but but I think we made it
so I'm excited for that and hopefully
you will be back here to join me until
then have fun partner everyone and I'll
see you on the Internet take it easy
everybody