hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are we've got sort of
two things we got to do we're gonna do
one this weekend and then I think next
week and we'll do the other so the first
thing we got to do is finish up the art
the different style art markup that I
wanted to do that would just allow us to
not change the file names that the
artists supply I hadn't really thought
about it until I got to that point but
once I got to that point I was like this
is probably how we want to do things and
the other thing we got to do is do a for
coder demo of the new for coder system
I'm going to leave that till next
weekend especially because I kind of
want a little bit more time to break
myself in on the new for coder
I only just kind of finished up by
fairly massive changes to it so on this
machine we're still going to be using
basically the same as the old for coder
was for this weekend and then we'll
switch next weekend we'll probably do
like one of the streams will just be a
demo talking about like how all the new
design of everything in for coder works
now and so that people aren't confused
about what I'm doing on stream and like
how the editors work it because it's a
pretty big departure now with the way
that I set everything up so I'm gonna go
get started on the parsing stuff and
we'll try to get that finished up this
weekend or at least to a good stopping
point and then next weekend I think
maybe we'll try to go ahead and change
over and we'll go from there there'll be
a little bit of learning curve even for
me cuz like I've made some pretty
massive changes and I've rebound several
keys in the process and sort of changed
the way some basic things are happening
just to be like more powerful now but
that you know everything takes muscle
memory a little bit of time to actually
get correct so we'll see I'm gonna I'm
gonna need a little bit of a
decompression on that but for right now
we're just doing the same for a coaster
that shouldn't have much problem today
with that sort of stuff so let me go
ahead and switch up to handmade
and just builds give you a quick
reminder of where we were at so you know
building handmade hero here if you
remember where we let ended up last
weekend we actually wrote a complete
parser for our tag file format which is
in the handmade tags directory looks
like this and this these are the two
ones and essentially what this is is we
just decided look let's let the artist
leave the file names the same as they
were since we know we have to parse a
text file or some other markup
information anyway to put things in here
like the alignment points we might as
well just put them all in one text file
and that way the artists don't have to
worry anymore about that they just save
stuff out and then we come in here and
say look whatever you named it we don't
care we'll just say that whatever it was
is this you know set of tags and that
way we can just control the whole
process separately and we don't have to
do anything else about it
furthermore and this is really more the
reason why I liked this better is now
inside the handmade directory there's
just a tags directory that has these
things in it
I can push that to source code control
and out to you folks in the zip file for
people who pre-order the game and build
the source at home that way that can be
updated continuously but the arc which
takes up a lot more room right because
especially imagine this director is
gonna have like 10 times this number of
things in it probably eventually nobody
wants to keep downloading that right you
don't want to have to keep dealing with
that nonsense so instead what we did is
we split it out we said okay the art
directory is gonna get next tags will be
here and then this sources directory
will just have all the stuff in it that
we need to build right you can kind of
see all that stuff in here okay so what
I want to do now is sort of expand on
that concept I want to get this stuff
parsing and I want to try and start the
process of building hhas from nothing
using just these text files and there's
only one thing I think that will stand
in our way of that and that's font
and that's fine we can address fonts
next weekend after the for coders
situation so we can really focus on on
stuff than that now the other thing I
did and and this is another thing that I
get just part of getting things to a
completion state so we can really kind
of say alright this is how it's done and
we can just move on we have to worry
about anymore is I also got uncompressed
versions of all of the layers for our
cutscenes here and so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to put those into the
into the the intro cutscene directory
and I don't know exactly how we want to
organize them per se
possibly by shots it doesn't really
matter but point being this gives us
another way to sort of test out this
system and see how it's going to be so
in the intro cutscene you know we've got
the art here we've got the the title
screen and we've got all of these like
layers here uh I don't like if you look
here in to shop too you can see that
they're all named like layer 1 layer 2
layer 3 so the problem with it is you
know I could make subdirectories here
but these names are not unique and I
would really prefer it if the names were
unique so otherwise I'd start
differentiating in my tags files so I
don't know that we really want to do
that I'm fine with requiring the artist
to make these names be unique from now
on and so that we don't have to talk
about some long directory path to say
which layer one ping you mean when
you're drawing something or whatever
right so what I'd like to do here is
just make some way of you know moving
these guys in here that that makes sense
and so what I'm thinking is maybe I can
just prepend this name to it right so
you know if I've got something like this
I don't actually know if you can I think
you can do something like this where you
know all
these have layer underscore one in front
of it but I think you can just do
something like this where you just do
shot eleven underscore right and I think
all of these rename now I guess they
don't so I thought there was a way to do
that let me double check to see there
are certainly renaming utils we could
use but I thought you could actually
change this let me see if that's true so
if I go into oops if I don't get block
about start bar if I go into users KC
desktop or sorry user KC what is it ah
see : users KC desktop and I go into
that opening directory if I go into shot
of one I feel like inside here if I do a
rename I can actually do let me see I
thought there was a way to rename
multiple at a time let me just see if
I'm wrong so if I do rename layer star
as shot a one star what happens so it
doesn't I'm so confused I swear this was
something that Windows used to be able
to do I know everyone who uses UNIX is
laughing right now because Windows is so
bad at this and you're not wrong but I
thought they had a way of doing just
this one operation and I can't remember
what it was but that you could actually
rename things while keeping part of the
filename intact but I'll be darned if I
can remember what it is
give me one more chance
alright let me search I'm so I am I just
dreaming
oh it's just cuz the star it's the star
okay see I'm not I'm not making it up
let's see the first rumor selects the
files to be copied as no effect on the
new names to be assigned incidentally
we're doing that start of star blowing
select files in the directory it will
also whoa really all right
the second parameter the second
character of the name will be changed
should be if it's question mark
interesting interesting
so let's see
renamed setteth start to question my
question my question mark 6 start up Wow
ok so I guess the problem here is that
the last part alright so let me just try
this so if I say rename startup star to
be shot 0 1 or shot one question mark
question mark startup star that works so
I wasn't wrong will will will say that
the word wrong maybe doesn't exactly
apply here or maybe it does that was
interesting to say the least so if I go
to shot Oh - UNIX people are still
laughing right now let's be honest so if
I go to shot Oh - and do the same thing
I'm good to go
uh-huh oh das so precious little
lemonsweets so precious have you enjoyed
renaming your little files what would
you like to do now yeah well you know I
I didn't see it was gonna be clean and
efficient I just said that it would work
and you know it does work maybe for the
folks at home you may be better if you
you know if you
really gonna do this in any kind of
industrial way maybe I would recommend
go ahead and downloading one of those
renaming utilities I know ant renamer
was fine back in the day there's
probably other ones now too
it's it's not that hard right but this
is probably not the best way to do it I
just I am now so thoroughly amused at
the craziness of it that I think I will
go ahead and and finish it this way but
you know don't don't do this at home
this was this is this is just das being
das it's probably not the best idea in
the world
I you know you do something better okay
and so now my understanding anyway is
I'll have to rename these manually right
because there is no actual way
supposedly to do that like it says it
doesn't have insert right so in theory
that just won't work right yeah so it
can't like it can't add more characters
so those need to have like I need to go
manually add the underscore to those
because there's like a look man what
what are you talking about what you
think computers can just like insert
characters in the middle of string is
what do you what do you think this is
right it's not Mardi Gras okay it's not
everyone's just partying and throwing
soap around and stuff right this is not
this this is this is this is computing
you can't can't do any of that
alright so that did what I needed it to
do in in a dass like you know kind of
truncated way now speaking of of Noam
Chomsky right kind of a what I would I
use the phrase for for backus-naur form
and construe grammars weak and
cumbersome that what I said no something
like that so anyway I've got all these
shots now and and really that's all
that's in the intro pack so I think I'm
just going to move them in
here and we'll just leave it at that
because again I don't really care too
much about this part of it because there
I mean that's all they are they're just
these shot plates they don't really do
anything else at all and so I'll just go
ahead and copy those in and then we'll
call it a day so let me move those in
here and these in here and the thing
that you can see about this is you know
again there's a certain amount of you
have to kind of think about where what
you're getting into that is that oh it's
right the snow blast um you have to
think about you know the point of
diminishing returns at some point right
on handmade hero will often do things
that have diminishing returns just
because I mean it's an educational
program and it's also my weekend
programming so you know I'm not sitting
around going how do I get this thing
done in the minimal amount of time right
which is something that you might be
doing if you aren't doing it as
something for enjoyment or if you don't
care or if you're you know for your jobs
on the line and so on but just as a you
know a side you can see how all of these
things are named in a way that that
gives them structure so when we if we
were going to go import them we could
add something to our parser that would
actually understand how to make sense of
the numbering scheme right and I don't
know we might want to do that and that's
the diminishing returns thing it's like
do we bother doing something like that
or do we just manually enter the text
right typing is hard I and I don't know
right every time you're faced with
something like that you have a call to
make look do you do it the long way or
do you create something that helps you
do it quicker and you have to make that
judgment call now in this case I would
say that maybe you know it's not really
worth adding
thing like that and the reason would be
because this is the only thing we have
looks like this right we don't we don't
actually have anything else that's got
this structure to it if we had tons of
cutscene art and we would have to every
time we'd have to do this that would
maybe argue for doing it the other way
right
I'm just looking in here it looks like
I've got everything right yeah that
might argue for doing it the other way
you know that might argue for saying
look you know this this is gonna be
something that we're going to be doing a
lot of and so we should probably try to
do something smarter here instead of you
know making a lot of work for ourselves
where we have to keep putting these like
plates in here or whatever but I don't
know that we really want to do that you
know maybe it's fine for us to just say
look we're gonna use a bunch of this
it's just gonna look like that and we're
just gonna manually type them in and if
I remember correctly and I remember
correctly I mean I don't remember but if
we go back and look at like our fire
file formats we haven't here this notion
of a shot index and a layer index and
the shot index layer indexed stuff
actually does have backing tags right so
we can just do like okay shot index
something and layer index something and
my recollection is that we have the
ability to actually specify numbers that
with our old parser our new parser I
don't know if they could do numbers
there and so one of the things that I
think we should do is support that as a
feature so if you want to actually have
a tag that has a number like if you want
to have a tag that rather than just
being set to true or not actually has
its own sail Ike this is shot index 1
you know layer index 2 or something
let's go ahead and just say
right if I put parentheses in there I'm
allowed to have a number that will then
tell me right and so in that way I can
just kind of put all the plates in here
that I want and I could just put the
shock layer numbers and so you can see
where I'm going with this it seems easy
enough that like maybe let's not go add
a system for doing something where we
parse the actual name when we really
don't have to because that seems good
enough so if I pop back over two dots
for a second as we've seen it wield its
mighty power today and everyone out
there at home I'm sure is just bristling
with with the raw sort of fearsome power
of das if we could go ahead and just
sort of prevail upon it one more time to
give us a show of its of its prowess
here I'm gonna go into the intro
cutscene directory just like we did for
bass game
and I'm gonna do adder /b as you can see
that gets rid of all of the adornment so
if I look at the art directory and do it
I can just get a list of everything here
that I might want and so what I can do
in this case is a pretty short list
right there's not that much there so
what I can actually do is just grab this
is it just wasn't there supposed to be a
shot 11 did I screw something up good I
did I miss one and my mind my look at
that I didn't copy those in I tell you
human error operator error people so
there's a shot 11 that was supposed to
be there let's let's do that one more
time so we can get that shot 11th there
it is right so I might just be able to
just cut and paste this from here
without actually having to dump it to a
file go I don't know if that worked but
we'll find out it did so now again
musing turd of the old for coder here so
we don't have a lot of power at our
fingertips at the moment we
get more as time goes on but what I'm
gonna do now is just kind of grab all of
these and move them over right
oops and again this is sort of where the
and to be fair for coder also probably
isn't quite there yet even with my new
modified one which is very much much
more powerful than Emacs almost in every
way the only thing that it doesn't have
yet is macro according Alan said that
that is coming down the pipe but that
would be you know macro recording would
solve this problem automatically right
because this exact process that I'm
doing and the process of extracting the
shot number and layer number would also
be automated by macro recording so it is
too bad that we don't have macro
recording yet because that's the sort of
thing that would make this process
easier but like I said there's not that
much stuff in here which is why I can
I'm just point of diminishing returns it
but that's just one of those things
that's often where you see you know
again like for coders kind of focused on
the main stuff that we had to fix in in
Emacs right and it pretty much did all
that but and I'm pretty excited to show
you guys the new one to that the new one
is pretty pretty crazy the stuff that
I've got in there there's some pretty
amazing stuff that I think is pretty
cool but yeah doesn't matter point being
it doesn't have some of those like more
esoteric features that's something like
Emacs or you know VI has from you know
centuries of refinement that are kind of
like you don't normally use them but
once in a while you do and they save you
a lot of time at that point you know
macro recording is kind of one of those
things because or you know there's other
there's you don't necessarily need
specifically Mac recording there's other
features that you could use like reg X
modifications to lines and stuff like
that that you can do but point being one
of those sort of ways of taking a piece
of text and extracting parts of it in a
a programmatic way and was writing a
little text processing sort of stuff I
find macro according be the easiest way
to do that because you can just sort of
demonstrate the change to the line and
then you just play it back I really like
that and because emacs's macro recording
allowed you to record through things
like search and other sorts of things
you could really do a lot with it that
you know made it seem like it was almost
like a little programming language
without ever doing a program so that was
pretty cool
but admittedly even that's a little bit
weak I suppose in some sense because you
it wasn't a programming language so if
you really wanted to in Emacs probably
Emacs power user resource of people
would almost possibly prefer other other
ways of doing things to you know like
the reading a little ela smacker or
something to do the replacement man
running it because that could do
anything right so it's a little hard to
say you know I don't again I don't want
to specify exactly what the best way to
have done that and it would have been
but point being if worker doesn't have
that sort of stuff in it yet but we'll
get there at some point it's just it's
not a high priority because this is not
the sort of thing that have to do very
often so you know it hasn't been the
kind of thing that's been tops on my
list but you know when you need it and
you don't have it you do notice so it's
always good to eventually get there and
have it so you'd ended up having to do
manual text processing like I'm doing
right now in those instances it's just
you know why even though it doesn't
really matter
it's like might as well just get get a
little thing in there that can do it and
then be done because you can so alright
so I think we're good to go here this is
roughly what I'm talking about right so
now this has like everything listed for
the cutscene as well and it's got the
tags for the layer index and the
it's got tax for the layer index and the
shot index in there that I just kind of
stuck in and so now we can just use this
for for everything both files are
completely SPECT out now I don't know
what we want to do with this thing you
know yeah well you know what I could do
what if I just called that you know shot
index 0 layer index 1 or something like
maybe shot index 0 is the thing probably
not you know maybe I could just give it
some other shot name I don't know like
maybe this is shot 12 I don't know I
could also just label it title screen
who knows
anyway so point being you know got all
this stuff in here this would allow us
to process those those as plates and now
all I really need to do is I just need
to add to the parse or something that
allows us to do the same thing we're
doing before where if you stuck a number
in to a tag that sets the value of the
tag to something other than one like
normally what we do at tags because you
know they're boolean a lot of the time
is we just set it to 1 because that's
sufficient in this case that wouldn't
necessarily be sufficient so let's go
ahead and look at that hht parser here
which is this what you can see is wow
this thing is so simple right this is
why I always think parser generator is
just silly because it's like yeah this
whole thing gets parsed by this you know
tylo piece of code it's like it would
have taken me that long just to figure
out why gak was like breaking and anyway
so when I'm parse the tag list so you
can see here like I grabbed this
identifier right and then we're gonna
call in to the tag system to say hey
let's get that we then check what token
comes next and what I want to do here is
I want to look instead and say let's
expand this I'm gonna look and see if
the check type equals token parentheses
or oh sorry open parentheses
and if it is I'm gonna try and get a
number out of it right because that's
sort of what we're saying we're saying
that if we parse an identifier for a tag
I want to be able to have a
parenthetical with a number in it and if
I find that for some reason you know
it's something else then I can process
it just the way that I was going to
process it before so really I don't
really want this to look like that right
I don't want to mean else I want to suck
up the open print clause first if I need
to and then if I don't
oops and this is wrong should have been
shot if I don't I can just fall through
and continue the checking I was doing
afterwards but so this is just an
additional check that can suck up a
parenthesis
right so if I see a parenthetical at the
moment because we only allow the
parenthetical the number that's the only
thing I've specified all I really want
to do is I want to say okay require a
number right this will be the value of
the tag and then require a closed paren
right because you have to close it we
don't allow anything else so it
literally has to be this pattern always
there's no other you're not allowed to
do anything else and this will be a
number and constant part some blah blah
blah so we don't have one of those so we
need token what so I don't know that we
want distinguish between like floating
point and non flying so I'm just gonna
say like number because this sort of the
suite of things we're parsing it's not
really the kind of thing where we have a
strong opinion about that right so we
really just want to say look require
token any number will do it can be a
whole number or a fractional number we
just want to get it and then go from
there
and so that seems good and I think
that's all we need however it doesn't
mean that we will need to put this in
here right so we do need to be a little
bit more Squinkie about what's going on
here with with with our parsing of
numbers so if we've seen here that we've
got a numeric type starting us off and
one of the other things that we have to
be aware of is you can see in here that
we're not parsing any operators right so
like we're not parsing things like - or
any or + but if we were and we wanted to
support negative numbers in here we
would need to be careful to make sure
that our tokenizer properly looks and
says if I get a - if the next thing is a
number then treat this as a numerical
value that has that's negative or we can
do it the other way around which says we
just return the negative back - like we
add a token for negative and we expect
that the person who receives the number
is doing something with expression
parsing where they will apply the
negative themselves right so there's a
lot of different ways you can do this
for now since we're only doing this for
tags I'm just I'm strictly going to do
the most basic one which is to sort of
suck up the part of this that is
numerical including a decimal point
because like I said I would like to to
allow fractional values potentially and
that's the only thing we're gonna do now
if I remember correctly we don't use ATO
F anywhere so actually what ends up
happening is when we're doing our
parsing we've got an STD - from Z
internal I don't think we've got an F 32
from Z internal right so you can see
here like we really only have the
forward kind for most things we haven't
really parsed it looks like
most of these other ones here so we do
have one that will parse sort of regular
regular old integers we don't have
something that'll parse things with a
decimal okay so let's see what we can do
about that this is not gonna be good
this is low-quality stuff here but
that's okay because we don't really need
it to do anything particularly fancy
right so let's take a look at how this
is working if we see a numeric value
then what we want to do is we want to
sort of get those numeric values input
into our number so we want to start with
whatever the number is right we want to
say all right
will accumulate into this number
whatever we read let's start parsing so
the first thing I can do is say well
alright let's keep going as we do our
advanced cares here right so I can write
this routine and say while the thing
that I see is a number continue parsing
you know advanced cares so if the thing
is a number then I'm going to get
whichever number it actually is like
this right and just say this is the
digit that came in and you can see that
we're already doing that kind of over
here right oops so that's the digit and
then as you can see all we need to do is
every time we read one of those digits
we just need to take and say well
whatever we already had is our number it
obviously has one more decimal place to
it cuz we just read a new one in so
multiply that by 10 to shift everything
up and then we'll insert this new digit
right so our number is just always equal
to 10 times whatever it was before plus
the new digits that we got and that just
adds things in then we go the next
character when we're done parsing those
really all we need to do is say is there
a decimal point here right so at this
point we can then say
well if whatever is that tokenizer at
happens to be a decimal point then we do
want to process the fractional part
right so we do want to process this same
loop where we just read as many digits
as we can we want to do the exact same
thing the problem is if you look at what
we've got here there really isn't any
way to do what we were doing before
because every time we go we don't want
to operate at all on the number that we
had right because if you look at it this
number is already exactly what it should
be as in terms of the part that's before
the debt that well that comes to the
left let's say of the decimal point so
I've already got exactly what it should
be I don't want to modify it anymore
right what I want to do is I want to add
fractional parts to it so really I just
want to add right the digit in whatever
it is I don't want to change the
existing number I just want to add in
the new fractional part and the
fractional part well it's you know it's
going to as I go further to the right
it's going to be higher and higher
divisors of 10 right so the first thing
that comes after the decimal point it
should be divided by 10 so you know if
it was three then it should be three
divided by 10 is how much I would add
right so what I really need here is a
divisor it would start off at ten and
every time I go down it would gain
another power of 10 so here I'm going to
do and you know I can write this the
other way so it's multiplicative you
know coefficient might be the better way
to do it so we're not necessarily doing
the divide again doesn't really matter
for this but so the coefficient is 0.1
so I'm going to add 0.1 times the digit
and then I want to say well if I managed
to go another round let's make sure that
we continue to fractionalize right now
again what I want to underscore here is
this is not a particularly good routine
for converting decimal into binary which
is what you're doing you're converting
like a decimal floating point into a
binary floating-point number
there's better more accurate ways of
doing this I'm sure it's just this is
the simplest one to type in for our
purposes right it's a very short concise
routine that will sort of work after I
do plug it anyway and so that's good
enough for our purposes but if you
really care and you're making like the
standard invitation of this or you're
gonna do a permanent one for your
library or whatever you probably want to
go more hardcore because decimal and
binary are completely different ways of
writing the number and converting using
this introduces a bunch of bit error
potentially that you could recover so if
you're really trying to be accurate
about it right this is not the smartest
way to do it once you start to really
care right so it's worth noting there's
difference from those two so once we get
this numeric token back that's all well
and good what do we do now
well we need to set the token type to
what we just said and we also need to
set all the rest of this stuff to make
some sense the first thing we can do is
exactly what we did before we just said
look let's just make sure that we record
the actual Texas right but then we also
have in our text field out if you
remember we set ourselves up for success
by actually providing here some values
we can use to store what we found out so
that people can use them directly and so
we know what the number is here we also
know here that we want to do a rounded
version so I'll go ahead and add that in
here too right and that I don't know if
we have a round two in 32 I guess we do
yeah and so what I'd like to do now is
just fill those out get this token ready
and then now when we parse that as a
number we can you know we can just go
ahead and and and finish up now is
numeric where is that oh it's is number
I don't I guess we just called that the
wrong
his number is what we actually meant
let me see though we've got some other
problem here
so round wheel through reel 32 to n 32
what are we getting complaints about 1
192 oh I see
so this is actually producing write an
integer but we want it to be a
floating-point for our purposes so we
can just go ahead and do that the same
would be true right here and then I
think we're good right yeah so that
allows us to add values to our tags and
so now inside the parser here when we
parse we now have all the information
that we actually need to do what we
wanted to do so our parser is ready to
go and it's very very tiny and so you
can see here like there's really nothing
to it
so what that says to me is I think I'm
just gonna not bother putting this in a
separate file I think I'm just gonna put
this into the assets file and we're just
kind of gonna go from there
right and so I'm gonna dump this guy
into here there's another way we might
want to do this like we may still want
this to be part of a file but what we
would do is we might pull all of the
Edit style stuff out of here and put it
into a separate file because it's
getting kind of long and it's worth
potentially distinguishing that from the
parts that are just used in running the
game window and it's occur right there
just there might be something to that
right so I'm gonna go ahead here and
kill this and I'm also gonna go ahead
and kill this and then we're gonna go
ahead and deal with the fallout from
that so if I go into this directory now
and I do a build it won't find those
parse file it won't find those include
files anymore once I go ahead and delete
them so insiders code I'm a delete
handmaid
what is it called it's like hht right
yes so I'm gonna leap those two and then
when I build you'll notice that
everything's fine except for the include
of those things which is what you might
expect because hey they are no longer
existing some are going to get rid of
those completely those are all parsers
things there we go
so this tokenizer now is relatively
important if I go look in here I'm gonna
pull some of these out into forward
declarations and that way I don't have
to care what order I do some of those
things in so I'm just gonna pull these
out real quick here we go
also yes this is not necessary anymore
because it did in fact work just fine I
grabbed that and did we get rid of temp
cast as well
I thought we finished that work yes we
did so that's good too and we just need
this this and this so now you can kind
of see right we've got a nice little
tokenizer here and the only thing we
haven't really done is hooked up the
actual error output to our error streams
which we actually do have and so we're
gonna want to do that and we'll do that
as we integrate it in okay somebody has
a syntax error complaint and you know
that's fine for them let's see where
that was at I'm not sure what that's
complaining oh it's just complaining
about that okay good
so then we're just left with the fact
that we had to check hht in here and I'm
just going to remove that and we're
gonna be done all right
let's see what we want to do now I've
got these hhe files and the main
problems I'm gonna have I can tell you
right off the bat is now that I can just
go through these and process them I'm
going to have a problem that we need our
platform layer to be a little bit better
about allowing us to find these things
because what it what's going to happen
inside the asset code is you're gonna
see block Forest o1 dot PNG but if we
jump over here what we'll see is even if
we know to look in the base game
directory because this is base game
about hht and we do that you know just
assumption it doesn't know we're in here
they will be now there's two things we
can do one is we can just hard code the
search right we can just say look you
got a automatically no to to put art in
front of it and then looking here and we
expect everything to be there the the
plus side of that is it's it has some
charm it's very simple it'd be hard to
not understand it you would know exactly
what's going on the only thing that's a
little weird about it is that you then
end up in a situation where these art
directories might have a lot of stuff in
them there could be like a thousand
files in here and while you could if you
wanted to you certainly could put
subdirectories in there but you would
then have to put the subdirectory here
right make sense
um and again that's maybe that's also
fine with you because maybe and I don't
know
but maybe you want to be able to do the
thing that we didn't do here which is
have a instead of doing the rename like
I did where now everything has a unique
name maybe you want to have everything
be called layer 0 layer 1 layer 2 layer
3 and you just have the subdirectory for
the shot tell you which one it is right
and then that would work because you
just go like that and that's actually
what you want as I'm saying it it sounds
pretty good I guess
I mean I guess I'll just say sure maybe
we do that and we just say if you want
sub-directories you put them in here for
now and I may want to change my mind
about that so I'm not gonna stick to
that particularly hard but since I don't
have anything better to say that's what
I'm gonna say for now um so if you look
here at import changed assets
essentially what we would do you can
sort of see what's going on here we call
platform get all files of type begin and
we pass it the PNG we no longer really
have to do that
so now what we can do is just say that
doesn't happen anymore so we still want
that call it's good because it's here
for this right we want it for this where
we import all of our our asset files
there and we probably want it for our
tags stuff as well
but after that we can actually just
change around to doing things by loading
them directly by name right and because
once we get those tags in that's all we
would really need I'm trying to think if
there's anything else we would need to
do there per se
[Music]
in a don't now excuse me uh so if I come
back here and I look at the win32
handmade code and I look at the platform
file type
PNG stuff so what you can see here is
that it just you know it says look I'm
gonna look in these directories when I'm
looking for stuff and off we go
and so if in here I was to say okay
there's going to be a tag file right and
that's going to be a thing or I guess I
could say hht file then we know that
that's in the tags folder and it would
do that and that would allow us to get
all of our tags files parse them and
know what we were looking at for an art
packing list my only question here is
then how exactly does the person load
the files that come from just arbitrary
file names there and that I'm not sure
so in other words these two would kind
of go away because you wouldn't ever do
that anymore
you would just do this and the names
would be implied or inferred I should
say from the information that you gather
here so my question is at that point how
do you actually load a direct file and
if we look inside the platform layer
here where we've got a you know load or
a open file you can see that you know
open file doesn't really take a path
sort of a thing it's a thing that wants
just a file info and it doesn't really
have a path it doesn't have an
understanding about what a path is in
that sense right so we would need to
have an open file name a thing that
doesn't open file that is based on some
some kind of composite of those path
names there I am
I mean I think that's just unavoidable
if we want it to go from text file
forward to you know to something and so
that you know I think that's just how
that has to work so in other words we
would read this string we would know the
actual string that we have for like look
where we expect this to be in the
sources directory right and I think we
would just go from there so let's see to
what extent that actually works we've
got this platform Open File thing right
and if I want to do a pound to find of
this in a different way like so I'm
gonna go ahead and say let's see
platform open file I let's see by name
instead of a final foot and and I guess
file info I could still do this
so what I might do excuse me I'm trying
to decide what I would want to do here
because I have this notion of the file
info I kind of want to leave maybe this
open file working the way it is and so
really what I kind of want is get file
by name and instead here this would
return a platform file info right and it
would take maybe a pointer to the
results I'm sorry a pointer to the name
and the mode flags are for opening so it
wouldn't be anything there so you know
it would be something more like this
where you can get the file info and then
release the file info and the reason
they don't what a hundred percent love
that is because it means that you have
to like acquire and release these you
know what I mean and that's maybe less
good like I would rather it have just
been something can return to forget
about so you may ask me and this is a
very good thing to ask me why not just
make it something you can release and
the answer is because if you remember we
need to handle Windows is ridiculous we
didn't use utf-8 because we didn't think
of it and we used utf-16 instead and
then the UNIX people came along and said
hey wait a minute what if we made this
utf-8 thing everything would still work
and then Windows was like oh woops we
just rewrote all our code to be bad so
we need to handle the fact that there's
a platform specific file name that
actually bears no relationship to the
actual file name that we're
thing about and it's based on utf-16 and
so that's some arbitrary size thing that
we're doing in here
and so you know I think we need to keep
that semantics as much as I don't love
it right that's kind of just what it
would have to look like and so this or I
should say by path maybe and so this way
you could say look here's the path that
I think this file should be inside our
sources and it will just come back with
you know the the file info for it and
the like I said the reason I don't like
that is that you have to close that
somehow and so here you know you call
this begin and end and you got the file
group here I don't know maybe that's a
good enough way you know we could maybe
make it so that you do it inside these
and so you don't really have to worry
about freeing it because that will clean
it all up for you that's one way to
think about it let me look inside win32
to see how that was happening at the
moment cuz I don't really know
so did that just so that literally just
returns a linked list I guess right that
you just iterate over so maybe let's do
it that way so what we would say is you
pass the file group in you just say
here's the like thing that I wanted to
talk about it'll be part of this and
then that'll just clean it up I'm ok
with that
I don't have a problem with that so all
we would really need to do then at that
point it's really not that bad I guess
this is this is pretty nice cuz it's a
pretty simple way of just extending what
we already had to work with arbitrary
path stuff if you want all we really
need to do is come in here and say well
where's the open file right here's how
that was working and get to get all file
types and all that stuff so in here I
just need a thing that's like hey yeah
we need one of these for win through to
get file by path and it needs to take
those two parameters and produce an
actual like something that works out of
that right ok so how are we doing this
before you can see it here you can see
us producing sort of the win32 find
handle version of this stuff right
here's the find data here it produces
the whole thing and it looks like we
could maybe just I wish I had more to
drink here it looks like we can maybe
just use this code right all we would
have to do is call this bottom part of
the routine a separate routine and the
wild-card function is just a full file
name
and that's it right so I think we just
have a think here that's like hey this
is called win32 get file info from wild
card because sure I and this thing is
just going to be the interior of this
routine and then we're gonna call that
right cuz that's exactly what this
routine does it says give me a path I
will produce all of the information that
you requested for the things in that
path and then I will be done right and
we've got this platform file group
result here that you know it generates
and so really all we have to do is this
file count here well even that just
works because that just tells you how
many got produced so it was add to the
so you could look at the total number if
you cared which I don't know that you
would I think that just works so here
once we create all of these looks like
they get pushed on - you can see here
like first file info equals info and the
next pointer I assume yeah just just so
it just does a chain right off of here
and so all we really need to do is pull
off whatever one is on that next pointer
so yeah again really really
straightforward just not a lot to it so
I think that means all we would have to
do here let me think for a second is we
have to set the next pointer to point in
and we have to get the first pointer out
but that's it so I think all we need to
do here is just say look we've got a
platform file info that's like you know
the nth like the
is the one that at the end of the chain
you produce put put that on there right
or set next to this right and so in here
we're just gonna save that like this is
what you're gonna set the next thing to
right I think that's basically what we
need to do so let me think about this
this is a recurrence thing so we're
basically saying look there's a pointer
here that's the head of the list each
time through here we put the head into
the next pointer right and then down
here we set the head equal to it right
and so if we want to seed that value we
just do this and then we're done and
then we return the head as our result
right I think that's it so the file
count is fine and we walk the wind three
to five you appear so we want the into a
platform flower group right to be passed
in although that is not the only thing
because we also have whatever the weird
yeah this thing right so the result
platform thing so really I could say we
put we just passed this in if I wanted
to right so we have file group here and
this can come out of this
I think that's all we need this is that
this is that as it should be all of that
just works nothing weird happening there
this is all good and off we go so then
in here when we actually want to use
this thing right this needs to return
the head of the chain which it will do
right here I'm going to call that result
now that we've gotten rid of results as
a thing right pretty easy and now we
could call it from both places so this
guy who was doing it before can just say
off you go
we're gonna set the the file group so
that's our result that's got the pointer
to the first one of these which I've now
forgotten the name of first file info so
the first file info is going to be
whatever comes back from this thing
we're gonna pass the file group to it
which I believe is just the results in
this case and this set next to because
I'm I read about that yeah the set next
to is just going to be whatever was in
there to begin with now that actually
happens to be zero in this case so
really now I think about it I guess we
never really need to pass that in
because we just don't actually use it so
really all we need is like the
information that this thing was using
now so yeah this this can just be zero
right and that result chain can just do
its thing so the final group gets passed
in this has to be the wild card right we
need that wild card data and the wild
card is a wkt pointer right
correctly yeah um and I don't know what
else it needs so hold on a second let me
compile just so I can see what it
doesn't have
so it's upset about this because I
didn't cast it properly and that's a
pretty reasonable complaint wild card is
under clips yeah that's a spelling
problem let's try that one more time
so yes stem size was being used here to
basically take the wild card and append
the correct thing on to the end of it
when we actually got the name back so we
do want to potentially pass the stem
size in so that it can do that
optimization the only thing I'm not sure
about here is how do we actually want
the other one to work so if you pass the
stem size here then that should allow us
to do that one just fine but and where's
the what's the stem is the location
right so it's stem and stem size both
get passed here and that's the W to be
care T as well
so I don't know how the other one will
work with that I have to go look at how
those names are destructed but I suspect
we can probably just pass no stem or or
have some way of saying don't bother
reconstructing the name because we don't
need to build it in any other way right
the the actual thing we hand you is the
complete name anyway right so I'm not
sure what we wanna do about that exactly
well you know what it probably just
works if we just do the part after the
slash anyway so maybe we can have it
still build the name I don't know that's
a good question
we'll have to take a look anyway so here
I think we're pretty good to go in most
cases we've got a problem everyone for
okay
so here we're we're actually passing
this this wants a platform file group
star and said I have it
taking a B actually the whole thing
which is not what I wanted so we want
file group dot 2d file group arrow here
but other than that we're good so I
think that's all we really need to get
the old one working so now what we need
to do is just make the new one work for
this where we've got PNG and web and
stuff and now I think we're gonna say is
look let's get rid of that and we'll
just have h HT be the only other thing
that's in there let me see if we use
those anywhere else I don't know if we
do just so I can find it yeah so it's
only in the import asset changes which
is the part we're removing so I think
I'm okay with just having that be out of
here now if I look back this code what
I'm going to want to do is call it here
to produce a platform file info
structure that I can return so this is
what I'm aiming for
this I believe
can just get because we know that that
gets passed to us directly so it gets
passed in here also I don't know missing
it the Senate : sauce was being there so
the file group is just something we have
so that's easy the path is in the wrong
format so it's getting passed in as
utf-8 but we don't want it to be utf-8
right we need it to be the we'd to be
chairty right it needs to be WT utf-16
and so what I need to do is I need to do
this same conversion right or well
actually it's sort of what we're doing
here right I need to to do this
preparation of the wild card text to
produce the entire string for this thing
and again when we look at what's
happening in here
[Music]
you know it seems like Moody maybe I
want to break this up even a little bit
more granular maybe I shouldn't quite
have done that it's hard to say because
it like actually this part I would have
to duplicate outside anyway to even be
able to pass the wild card handle in so
you know maybe we just want cuz this
code we want to share but that's pretty
easy to share right like the file date
and file size are pretty trivial for us
to to share and so the part where we
actually use the name I don't know like
maybe it just doesn't matter maybe what
we really want to pull out is just this
so let's at least do that part and then
we'll think about it
suing here I know that I need to do this
right and so I'm gonna grab this part
here and say this code I'm gonna see if
what I can do they're looking at the
base name stuff just where that gets
used you can see that we don't use it
anywhere below here so I believe I
should be able to grab this part here
and say that could in theory just be
done as one chunk like so and then when
I call this what I could say is all
right the part that we're actually
trying to convert here right is base
name begin base name size and it's going
into info base name base names storage
right so what I should be able to do
here is say okay we've got a results the
result is going to be this and so down
here we're going to plug it in like that
so that is the code we would need for
doing the utf-8 conversion now base name
begin in base name size base name end
and base name begin or what are used to
generate that size we could see that
maybe that part should be done outside
because it depends on who's doing it
whether you'd want to do it that way or
not so we just pass in base name size
and then we also pass in the like the
source right
yeah so this converts one way so this
will convert I'm sorry this is the wrong
way around
that's this way so this will convert
utf-16 to utf-8 if we want to go that
direction and then we need a thing that
converts the opposite direction as well
right so we need a thing that will
convert from utf-8 utf-16 which is the
exact opposite function if that makes
sense so I think that's all fine right
there's base name size
their space name begin and then if I
want to go the other direction I should
literally be able to use the exact same
function so here I've got utf-8 to
utf-16 I would pass the and you know
this this could loops did that actually
Oh weird that actually did exactly what
I wanted though so I guess I didn't want
that to do it ever
suing here right I'm just saying look
convert this from 16 to 8 I can do the
opposite that's almost the exact same
thing I say here's the name that's in
utf-8 I then need to compute how much
I'm gonna need I only need two because
if I'm going to utf-16 I know that any
individual utf-8 character can at most
expand to two utf-16 characters but
really it could probably only expand to
one but that's a separate issue so
obviously I don't need more than that I
can create this result here as a wkt
right I can do the push size exactly the
same way that I was doing it before
here's my name storage and I can Nell
terminate it if I want to although I
don't know that I necessarily do but I
certainly can and so I do the push size
here I would just need an extra two for
the null terminator right and that's
what would happen here
let me also do base name - just name and
so here we just do multibyte - white
multi flight - wide care and I believe
we can just swap the two of these also
this here info name is supposed to
adjust the result right I think we could
also say that name storage should be
results storage right and this is result
size that makes sense
that seems possibly more like what we
want
so I mean here we then have the same
thing and I'm gonna put name storage -
result storage here as well and this is
result size so if we do multi-byte -
wide care what we need to do here is
pass in the name begin name sighs I
don't remember the actual format for
this so I'm gonna grab it from MSDN
see here so we need the code page and
the code page should be the same right
we need the flags and the flags should
also be the same which is that I don't
think we care about any of that so for
the most part that's a identical
we need the multi byte string and its
length so
yep and yep
so the multi byte string and the wide
string go in the am I reading that right
the multi byte string in this case is
the result so the result comes first no
no I'm sorry that's right
so the multi byte string comes second
and that's the result so that's right
which is what we want and there's no
additional trailing stuff here right but
this is the result in the result storage
which is what we expect and that all
looks fine right so now we can convert
in either direction which is what we
wanted and all I really need to know now
is where you want the memory to go and
so that can actually be something that
you just pass in and I don't really care
where you get it from
and so people here you know they'll just
say well it goes with the file group but
if you were gonna do something else with
it then you do something else with it
and it's not gonna affect anybody so
that seems good yeah all right so here
where we've got name begin and name size
it's really just named in both cases and
I think most of that all looks fine as
well just see what other might what my
other errors aren't here don't ask me
why I did what I did right there didn't
mean to do that
and here are results storage the stupa
size this is has to do one of these oops
because it's a W care T that's coming
out of that all right and let's see ok
so don't care about that I do care about
this
this one wants to be utf-16 to utf-8
right um and you know what I should use
a better name you seem for this I should
do utf-8 from utf-16 I like from
phrasing better because you say which
thing you actually want on the left hand
side and on the right hand side so it
like lines up better with the way the
text actually goes so here it's like I
want a utf-8 I'm giving you utf-16 right
and off I go yeah so that seems good I
don't have any real complaints there and
the stem science stuff like I said now
now that that's sort of handled that way
I think pulling this out was not really
that necessary right so I think I just
aired there in thinking because really
all I needed was these two functions I
didn't really need this thing to be made
generic for really any particular
purpose I could pull this one piece of
it out where you create one of these
things and it does the conversion of
this stuff for you maybe will do that
but all the rest of this isn't actually
shared and so I don't know I I don't
know if that's really what we want to do
there so hard to say right um so what
I'm gonna do now is I'm just gonna grab
this and I'm gonna reinsert it so I'll
say look that was the mistake forget
about it pretend I never said that
erase this video so people can't tell
that I that I did it right just erase
all traces of it just you know it's just
it's gone uh and so what I want to do
here is say oops that result first file
info there and up here I want to say
result first file info and here I want
to say result file count
and then just lift that do what it was
doing before right and that seems good
so now if I take a look at this yeah
worth what's the stem sighs nonsense
what are you complaining about
okay so what I want to do now and
there's our result something here win
through to get found from rock-hard this
is gone so the only thing that I might
want to do now is this part that puts a
platformer file info on on the sort of
stack stack some up here that's the only
thing that we might really want to have
at there now first file info if you look
at it I don't know why this is being
done so far away I feel like it would be
fine to link it in early or put another
way link it in late so meaning the info
structure here as you can see it doesn't
really get it's just base name that ever
actually base name and platform that get
mucked with there so another way to look
at it would be maybe this linkage can
happen down here right and so at that
point all I wanted to say was you know
okay so if we're I mean you know what I
mean unless this isn't multi-threaded so
really again even this is fine too right
either way I think it's fine so if I do
that then I think what I could do is say
this part of the code which I do want to
be sort of similar maybe I can make a
way of making that shared even though
it's gonna be a little bit tricky for
some reasons I'll show in a second so
what I want to do is share this because
effectively what's gonna happen in this
code down here right is I want to do win
3 to get file by path and I need to
build up this path that I'm gonna you
know I've got this path I got to convert
it and then I have to grab the file
attributes of that thing so if I want
- I don't actually have to get a handle
with a file to get the file attributes I
can get them directly by just calling
get file attributes e^x on the file so
you can see here that I just need to
pass a file name and then a file
attribute data structure will magically
come back from me which actually has all
the stuff that I need right I need that
and I need that and they're all there so
if I want to I can have a win32 file
attribute data structure it doesn't have
any strings in it so it shouldn't really
be a W or not it should just be win32
file attribute data and I can do a file
data here then what I can do is say
watch you and I maybe I'll clear it
because you know i'm saucy like that
then I'll say look watch you give me
that information get Coop's file
attributes e^x looks like that's already
in here
yeah so we're already using that to get
the the right time there right so you
can actually see us calling it right
here um so we want to basically make
that call this is using a Cara start
file name so this is actually an a style
call meaning that's actually doing this
right why we didn't do that I don't know
those are both that but in this case
since we're supporting the wide care
stuff in terms of being able to you know
people want to name their files with you
know kanji in them or something right so
if we want to do that here what we
called git file attributes px what we
want to do is say look give us back this
this you know find data right and I
guess like that's one reason we wouldn't
have to clear it we could just say look
if this fails it fails what we want to
do here is pass a filename that's wide
so this is the this is the like path 16
right path that's and utf-16 and then we
can get the data out of it here and
figure out what we're gonna do with it
at that point okay so we know we have a
platform filing for results like so I
know I've got to return that and so the
question is how do I make one of those
here and furthermore the question is
where do I get this from now one thing
that's a little bit tricky in this case
right because I know I can do this if I
just pass the path here if the problem
is that path is going to be relative to
a base directory and those base
directories are sort of hard-coded
things that we just made is rules right
and we probably want to keep doing that
so meaning this data here like we
probably want that hard-coded however
you might not want it hard-coded here
maybe that lives a little further up so
possibly really this actually is exactly
that so if we add this in here and we
say that the win32 file group memory
like so is used to convert this thing to
pass 16 we
asked for that past 16 and we you know
hopefully get it right if we get it all
we need to do now is create one of these
platform file infos and we know exactly
how to do it it's this but the question
is do we want this to be a little bit
more systemic right because you can see
this stuff here would be sort of
duplicated the problem that we have is
that this right is not exactly the same
structure as this now you can see that
they're basically exactly the same and
you would have hoped that Windows would
have just used them the same structure
for the same thing right because they're
exactly the same except for this really
and you could have just left that field
blank right better yet you could have
kept it this way if you wanted to but
included this in this so that this
struct is just in here so instead of
these you acts just have that now we
could be super Squinkie right we could
be Squinkie squared and say because i
happen to know this is a D word file
time file time file time to you word e
word that happen to be exactly the same
ones I'll just pretend it's one of these
even though it's not now that's super
squeaky but you know what I might do
that
why can I do that because Windows isn't
really allowed to change we link to it
and it has to provide us those types
back right so it's like well if I wanted
to support a future compile that change
the definition of these in their header
and link to some new set of Windows
libraries this would be a really bad
idea right but if I never do that
I don't know oops so we could just do
that if we were super Squinkie and just
want to give you know big old middle
finger to Windows which you know I do
want to do most days and in fact I can
also do this here I can just take all of
this stuff this whole bit here and say
that all of that is gonna happen in one
little chunk there come to me and I can
take the foul drip for that summer in
here whoops that's enough code I wanted
so I can just take that and yeah I can
just go from there I think that just
works so we get the memory here and we
link it in here
and everything else just needs that fine
data so what we can do here is say look
this is gonna be the file attribute data
we're gonna use the pointers off of this
and we're just gonna be super naughty
like that's just what we're gonna do and
so here we'll say allocates or sorry I
went through to allocate file info we
will pass the file oops
pass the file group and we will pass the
find data and we will just straight-up
pretend that it is a win32 file
attribute data pointer even hope it is
not so let's see
there is a place mistake that I made
there otherwise we're fine go is that
really true file group is an undeclared
identifier that is true it is result
talk she doesn't take two parameters
that's true we need to get the string
length of this because we take us it
takes a size actually and then I think
we're good to go
that allocates the file info right
um so that's actually it as I took a
rather screws route because I didn't I
was kind of thinking we would need more
from the iteration routine that we
actually did but we didn't we only
really need this part and that should
allow us to get files either way which
is good so what we want what did I do
wrong there that's supposed to be that
all right so I think that's good and now
what we want to do is when we're doing
our parsing we're just going to call
this function and we're gonna have to
basically pass in you know the path that
we want to use to find it and then it'll
take care of the rest
so what we can do there is in here when
we do import changed assets what we're
actually going to do now is we're gonna
sort of change that to be the parse hht
so I'm going to take import changed add
sets I'm going to drop it down below
that and I'm gonna sort of nerf the code
a little bit at the moment right like so
this should recompile is fine I think
and let's make sure that we didn't
introduce too many bugs in the iteration
code because let's see if we can still
find our HHA files here when we actually
run win through new handmade so if I run
win32 handmade here and we go it's like
can we find the H yeah we can so we're
good right and so I just want to make
sure that iteration still worked okay so
now you can kind of see why I like this
idea better because it sort of starts to
solve some problems for us in the old
days we had no idea where stuff went we
just had to make this concept of a
default local HHA file and that default
local HHA file was like where stuff was
supposed to go but now what we can do is
say action
we know exactly what HHA is go with
which imported things because the tags
file tells us so this thing right here
has a name it's called base game text so
we know that there should be a base game
that HHA that all of the things from
this get packed into right and that
helps us understand the relationship
between these two things
now if we want to we can even take it
one step further we could actually do
this we could say that we're gonna
specify exactly where it goes and that
way we can have multiple files that
target different hhas or the same HHA
and stuff like that so maybe that's a
good idea too and then if I go over
there to our HH t parser we've got this
we can say like hey yeah there's this
other fields here that's just like the
age of J right and it tells us where if
that goes you know what I mean
so that's another nice feature we could
add where we just say what the target
isn't that way if we want everything to
pack into a single HHA we just can or we
can not do that
and later specify it or we can also have
one text file that has everything in it
even though it generates multiple hhas
by changing this periodically so that
seems good like all that seems good to
me and I think that's what we want so
now what I can do is say alright inside
here where we're doing this loop and we
parse everything I can just say yeah
let's let's set like a token for each of
these things
like so you know this sort of thing I
want to be able to do something like
this and then when I do the parse tags
list right I would also be able to do
something where I'm allowed to be honest
I'm not really sure exactly what we want
to do with that parse taxes but
something right um so what I want to do
here is say okay
what about like having this sort of
thing be something I can keep around so
it's easy for me to say when I'm parsing
the default one store any of the results
I get back as being things that will
permanently be used to set future things
when they want to know what the author
is of something right that should be
pretty straightforward to do we just
need something here that's like struct
like hht fields right and this just has
what those fields are in it like so we
know that the author is just gonna be
one string so we know that there's just
like one of each of these right because
those are basic but what we don't know
is how we would store the tags and maybe
tags are not something that you can
apply on Moss like that I don't know
again kind of hard to say so I'm gonna
keep it simple for myself the moment and
not try to answer that question but what
I want to do here right is say what
we're targeting so let's suppose I have
a default fields and I just start it by
not having anything in the default
fields then when we come through here
and I get a token to figure out like
what we're actually going to do like so
in here right and in fact I guess this
needs to be up a little further right so
when we parse a top-level block like
this what I need to do is probably say
all right here's the default fields
and furthermore I'm gonna have like my
fields right something like this and so
what I can do is say start off with
nothing for our fields if this is going
to be the default right then what I want
to do is I want to parse the fields and
set them and so I want to redo something
maybe more like this so what I want to
do now is say okay anything i parse
should should set the default fields
right otherwise if I find one of these
then what I want to do is assign the
default fields to my fields so I want to
do the opposite right like that then
when I come through here and I'm parsing
these things I can just say all right
now I'll override each of the fields
that I get I'm going to override them
with whatever I find here right so now
again with almost no change of the code
I just keep running defaults and it just
works right so each of these when I get
the string back I'm gonna sort of take
your the text from it like so
and that should do it now inside here
where I've got this tags Jimmy that is
not part of the fields at the moment
because we don't really know exactly how
those are getting parsed to real leave
that out for a moment everything else
currently now actually works so when we
parse one of these top-level blocks we
actually do know what we're doing with
them but now like we're gonna have to
actually well for lack of a better term
we actually have to do something with
them and actually make it happen
right so if we see tags here we're still
gonna do this parse tag list part
probably but if it's the default if
we're doing the default we throw them
away basically probably probably that's
what we do
I don't know again we have to think
about how we want to work with that
later but everything else would just
work so now let's think about what we
want to do as far as as far as actually
producing output from this how much time
left right I got what like 15 minutes um
um so if I come through here and look at
sort of what some of the other things
are that we're doing you can see that
I've got a bunch of like tag array stuff
when we do parse pieces here this is all
the stuff that we were doing before to
import things so we would produce like
an import type like multi tile or
whatever and we would have one of these
sort of tag arrays and stuff like this
and what you can see when we're looking
at this is since those tag arrays are
actually all the exact same we should be
able to just create them once and then
point at them right
that should be pretty straightforward
for us to do and so again it's really
just gonna be what we want to do with
the tags eventually there we can also if
you want to keep doing it exactly the
way we're doing it and just have
something that Reve Ector is based on a
type here like instead of doing the
strings are equal to part it just as a
jump like I don't know right hard to say
so I think when I I think what I'm
probably gonna say honestly is maybe
we'll just do the principle of like
least code change for lack of a better
term and we'll literally just call this
as directly as we can maybe because we
can do this really pretty directly if we
want to right and bear with me for a
second why explain what I mean so if we
just called parse pieces and instead of
passing in a file name we just actually
pass it the tag array and or pass it
break it into two pieces and do the tag
array part separately ourselves right we
can pretty much leverage like most of
the rest of this I think I mean I think
we just sort of can so instead of this
code right here like you can see the way
this is working instead of this part
right here where we do like block type
index and this sort of nonsense instead
of that what we could do instead is to
just actually use this exact code the
code that we're looking at right here to
actually do that that cracking
I'm not 100% sure about whether I like
that or not and the only difference is
to see how these always have like end
tags happening we just get rid of the
call to end tags like that's it
right
um so again I don't know how I really
feel about that in the grand scheme of
things like I don't know I I don't know
if I'm doing something stupid there but
it seems like it just works so I think
I'll just do it so if we look at what
happens here where we do this what I'd
rather do is just say like you know
parse pieces we're gonna call this we're
not gonna use this I'm gonna make sure
that all of the things that in are in
there actually for what we've got bodied
character right cover hands is head in
there yeah head was in there item
obstacles in plate right so they're all
in there and it would work right so
instead of using block type we just skip
that we don't do that we call parse
pieces parse pieces will return to us an
import type like so right and at the
moment we don't have import types for
like cover or or like item or plate or
stuff but we do actually know what these
are we just didn't create anything for
them so I'm just gonna stub them
temporarily and put it to do in here
and we know that like these do work like
this they're multi tile right we know
that this one is a single tile but it's
actually isn't they're like is there any
I don't remember there's like some other
type of thing that's like a single time
I guess we don't have to say if it's no
we do say I think of that so pleats I
think aren't limited and how big they
are something right so that I think
there's a difference in plates they
don't have to conform to like the 512 by
512 thing or whatever so a plate is its
own like kind of import that we do so if
we do this we'll get that back and
here we have like the unrecognized type
of import artwork problem that's fine
like I said we're gonna sort of look at
that in a little bit more detail in the
future how we want it to do those errors
but what we really can do actually you
know what we can do right here to say
look if the result comes back as import
type none then we can do the error on
the outside
so here in the asset list where we do
the parse hht top-level block when this
thing comes back we can just say if the
import type is none we've got an error
now we might want to do it a little bit
more like that and do the air down here
lock token is what that's called and
that way we know like hey we hit
something that someone said we were
supposed to import we don't know what it
is like it's not a block it's not an
item it's not a whatever right so like
we're just forget it we don't know
what's going on but assuming we do know
what's going on then this happens right
makes sense and furthermore I might go
ahead and and leverage this part up here
we could sort of stop talking about
sound necessarily I'm not sure how we
want to look at that but we could maybe
make this be more of like is it a
default block or not because we're gonna
do something differently depending on
which one it is right so we'll look at
that a little bit later so assuming that
we found one of these things when we
call parse pieces we need to pass it
some stuff we need to pass it this right
and we probably want to rejigger a few
of the things that are in here right
but mostly it's okay mostly this is all
fine
file name is the thing that really we
need to change the most because again
this tag stuff now we really don't want
it talking about that because we're
handling that lower down so we want to
stop passing this name at all all we
really want is just the block type text
right that's the only thing that we want
it to be doing and furthermore we could
make that be an explicit token so we
could say here that this is the you know
type token and here in we could just say
like token equals and that's how it will
check now there's a reason why I want to
do type token here the reason I want to
do type token is because if I am going
to output an error
I would like to output an error with the
actual ideally I'd like to output the
error with a marker that says here's in
the text stream where it came from right
because that will help with debugging
later on so I would want to do this and
if someone was gonna output an error for
some reason I want it to go there I
don't know that we're gonna need to
output any errors here hopefully the
answer is no but if the answer ends up
being yes that's okay all right so what
I don't want is to you know this tag
builder thing what I don't want is the
end tags to ever occur because if the
end tags ever occurs then I'm going to
end up in a situation where I I can't
put the other tags on that I wanted to
from my tag list right so that's the
real the part that we're really gonna
have to work at here to two-port as
we're sort of massaging this code right
so I'm gonna go through here oops and
just replace these real quick like so
but otherwise they're pretty much the
same
oh there we go okay so that allows us to
do all the checking we were doing before
and then really the problem like I said
is now we just have to see how we want
to do those keep those tags tag
applications working properly so I think
what I want to do is I want to have the
tag builder probably the begin call is
probably going to come outside so you
know I'd call that tag build out here
you know it'd be something like this and
then when I you know coming here and
we're trying to pass this stuff in I
would want to pass the tag builder in so
that the thing when it does parse pieces
it can just make all that tag stuff work
now if you take a look at what's
happening here with like tag basic
category and that stuff what I need to
be able to do there is this stuff what
we were doing tag ID from name and all
that right
this is the whole part that needs to
sort of happen with inside the tag
parsing code itself so the first where
we do like the parse tag string stuff
like this this part right price tag list
this this is needing to happen here
right so we want that to be something
this happening there it doesn't need the
four I loop right doesn't need any of
that it's just the interior part that
we're actually going to use and more
specifically I guess it actually it
happens here right
so that part we're going to keep and
what we need to do is solve this basic
category thing that's the part that you
know these things here when they call em
tags they say what the that asset tag
was we can throw that over to begin to
the begin tags part of things by just
adding the the category part in here but
you can see when it does this result
type ID part that's the part that is a
little bit harder because this when we
return it it needs to know what that
category actually was and so it almost
seems like that's something we're gonna
have to provide in addition or that gets
stored on the Builder now because we can
I think I might want it to be stored on
the Builder so basically what ends up
happening is in here instead of passing
category into end tags it's assumed that
somewhere you set that so it's assumed
that somewhere you said like this and I
would say
that right and so now anytime anyone
says end tags really what they're saying
is just like that's the end of it and
you know if we wanted to make again the
error stuff be sort of smoother we can
do this so that way we have a way of
producing that error kind of cleanly
right and I think that's all kind of
fine and so what I really want here is I
want to be able to pass this this is
gonna happen and it's gonna get the
category out of its private storage
swear it you know remembers what it was
and everything else can happen exactly
the same way as it was happening before
it's just now the asset basic category
needs to be stored in here along with
everything else that all seems okay
no major complaints there but what I
would like to do now is kind of push a
little bit further I know we're over
time but I kind of want to clean up a
little bit this before I end for the day
so I just don't forget where I was not
tomorrow or the things I was in the
middle of doing so if I go look at this
you know I've got this end tags call
right in here all the people who are
calling that Intex call really all they
need to do now instead of the like
result stuff or any of this import body
or any of that right they don't really
need to be doing that anymore they just
need to be able to call
well you know what that's not entirely
true either so this is a little bit more
complicated than that so each of the
tags has to get duplicated out so it
actually is harder than that meaning we
are gonna have to copy the tags into
each of these bins which is harder right
[Music]
and so I'm not really sure how I want to
deal with that so the way that we're
doing it before right is we just
repeatedly parse the file name like over
and over and over again producing the
same tags each time that's what we were
doing it would probably be nicer to just
do that once and then copy those tags
each time right because that way you
don't have to constantly like repeat
yourself so yeah that's kind of a little
bit harder to suss out how we won't do
that it does mean I guess that I don't
have to do this but it means things are
going to be a little nastier for us
unfortunately
so if you look at what's happening here
right the problem is that this needs to
be able to copy an additional block of
tags from somewhere right it needs to be
able to like block copy those tags and
so if you look at what happens when you
call add tag right we need to have some
way of saying what's the like group of
tags that have to be copied into every
one of these that's like coming from the
tag array that's in that piece of the
file and so you know we have a thing
where we are going to have a fry loop
here and we need to pass something in
that that we can use to get that to get
that data and so I guess we would need
something like
so we would need something like yeah
like this stuff so the import grid tag
right and we've got this tag array it
just says here's the array of tags to
copy and so that's sort of what I think
we would have to do meaning when we come
in here we would need to pass in tag
array to copy you know I'm saying like
that's that's what we would actually
need to do and so when we come in there
we would say like tag index equals
append tags first tag index tag index is
less than a patent tags one passed last
tag index tagging next right and then
when we do the ad tag call we would say
well you're gonna have to get the tag
first right so you got to call this and
we would look at whatever that tag index
was that you told us to copy and we'd
copy it so we'd still need a way to say
here's all the tags that you're gonna
append to this thing have a party right
and I suppose that's not terrible like
it's a little bit Squinkie
but it's no worse than what we were
doing before and this append tags
doesn't really need this type ID so you
know really there's sort of a tag range
that could be passed there that's that's
you know not that and I think that's you
know more or less this
it's this part right here and I don't
know how much I really want to make that
systemic but you know sure so I think
that's probably fine and I can collapse
these two in a second where this is just
a tag array plus a type ID right and
that's fine whatever
so I mean here when I do the in tags and
I've got the category got the append
tags I could append the tags on that
gives me a pretty easy way to work with
this really not that big a deal so it's
probably fine and off we go right and
yeah that's just where we're at so in
here if I want to continue down that
path
right then what this would look like is
when we're passing the filename in the
era string here really we wouldn't pass
it anymore like I said we don't really
want the era string maybe necessarily so
much as we want like just a tokenizer
here and we'll record our error on that
um and since we don't have a token in
question well probably what we'll do is
on our tokenizer we'll also have the
notion that generally speaking you can
issue an error without a token you're
just issuing a generic error and it will
use whatever the current position of the
tokenizer was um and so in order to do
that what we would say is okay we don't
have an on token in this case so the on
token is just equal to the state well we
don't actually need to do anything at
the moment but in the future what we'll
do is we'll look at the tokenizer it's
like line index or something and we'd
put it in there right and then we would
call through to to pass the message
along right so we'd say like okay on
token
right now again the problem that we're
gonna have here is that we need to be
able to do an out F call on that so this
really wants to look like this which
makes it a little bit harder for it to
pass through because it means you've
actually got a thing that looks like
this again see makes this so difficult
and it's just because you know
scene-stealers plus or not you know
they're not good languages anymore well
see puffs was never good language she
used to be so anyway if I want to be
able to do that what I need to do is
take a look at the odd F call for sample
you can see it cure Oh interesting we've
got a little 2-pound to find there and
what I want to do is I want to sort of
duplicate exactly what it did here and
that's why I say it's kind of annoying
right but this is exactly what we want
we want to be able to use the VAR glist
here to sort of like you know plump this
down one level and so in order to do
that what I'm going to suggest is we've
gotten that we put an out F in here
that's the same like so
but that out F call is going to take the
actual
arglist here instead so the VA list you
know argue list here that it that we're
going to use comes in so we can call
this thing directly this part doesn't
actually happen now right so we do that
and then inside this out F it actually
looks like this
something like this so that way you can
call this thing either way you can out F
if you have an art list or you can out
lift out f out F if you don't and so you
know I can even actually make this error
thing maybe a little bit more condensed
in that sense the point being if I
wanted then call an out F I can I could
call this out F directly from either of
these two things and it will allow me to
put my error message on to the air
stream like we were doing before so
again in order to do that I would need
to have a way of passing the file and
line number here and the file and line
number again should come from the
tokenizer so these are really just two
do's and in fact I guess what I could do
is say you know like that I guess what
I'm saying is the token itself is the
thing that wants to have that so what we
really want to do is say hey the on
token file name and the on token line
number that's where we want to actually
get that data from the destination
stream is going to be the tokenizer
error stream that's something that
you'll create when you do it and then
from there we're good to go
here's the format and the VAR glist
stuff is just you know looks like this
right
and so that gives us an easy way to make
this work
with all of our existing Airstream stuff
make sense so that's ideally what we
want it to look like and again like here
what I'm saying is the on soaking
doesn't really exist so we kind of need
to do that and what we want to do is you
know looking at how a def works it's
it's funny it doesn't even use the file
nine-member so we kind of need it I have
that in there yeah we'll get there
so anyway this allows us to use an
Airstream and to give us the information
if we eventually have our tokenizer
support such things so if in here we say
you know there's a file name and let's
say that we know what that file name is
then what you can see here we're also
quickly gonna run to the fact that this
file name wants to be a skeezy
terminated which we would prefer it
wouldn't but you know now we don't
really have a choice so we've got a file
name and we've got a line number which
we can put in here like so and we'll
just copy those to our tokens and again
that's really easy to do the tokenizer
itself we would have to figure out how
we're going to track that stuff but
inside get token it's actually very easy
because the token just takes that stuff
directly from the tokenizer and there's
really nothing else that we have to do
right so we just need to track those
pieces of information later but
otherwise having tokens remember where
they came in the stream is actually very
easy and so that's pretty nice right
alright so the only other thing that
token as you're needs is an ease the
actually air stream right it needs is
that but other than that it would work
the stream itself it looks like is not
defined there
yes so I don't know that I want to
bother to finding it so I might just
forward to Claire it like this and let
me move forwards here so that should
just work and out F that interfer are
not being found that is really because
this streaming stuff doesn't pre declare
this version it needs to all right so
let's see where we're at this guy needs
the same preamble easy enough and you
tell me you cannot find this but why can
you not find it because it's defined in
here oh we're in the simple pre process
or so that makes sense so the simple
preprocessor doesn't have the stream
included which it probably should
because it's going to need that for air
processing right
I think we called that streamed outage
and wrong about that yeah so I assume
that the problem there is that since
that's a memory back thing we will have
to provide it with a way to get the the
memory and don't know that that's a
problem I guess the only thing that we'd
have to do is provide a way for it to
actually allocate things right and we
actually already you know we already did
this and I don't actually know that I
care about the simple roster so for now
I probably turn it off but we've already
allowed that to happen inside the the
part the the PNG test bed so having
those things external is actually quite
easy I don't know that I care at the
moment so I'm probably not actually
going to bother with that but I just
wanted to make sure that would have
worked or is reasonable enough right
okay so let me go ahead and compile here
so in hh8 edits I don't know why I'm
still including the tokenizer is there
either because I don't need it there
either but probably just because we were
using it before
okay so let's see here that's all well
and good and this unfortunately needs to
know the size which I wasn't returning
I'm not sure why I wasn't returning it
from both of these because I really
should have so I think that really
wanted to look like that and similarly
you know this wants to look like that
right leave it it's size so moving on
overloaded function differs only by
return type you're right there we go
and so now we're mostly just back to
where we were before where you know
we've got this sort of annoyance where
we have to figure out some way of
getting this stuff to work right and let
me also real quick just make our
tokenizer right recognize the fact that
these errors are different than they
were before
so previously we kind of have that
notion but now what we're actually doing
is is allowing you to give the full set
there and so I think that's all good
yeah that looks a little good and so now
we can hook up the error stream pretty
easily that's organizer that'll just
work and it'll store everything so we
can do stuff like yeah saying like out
of tag space and so on hmm I'm gonna
leave it looking more like this I'm
gonna say that will insert the carriage
return ourself later as a sort of
separate things don't really want that
to be anything weird now for some reason
were getting an error on add tag here
and I want to figure out why I'm
assuming because we didn't actually type
that or use the right type for add tags
you can see here it wants for add tag
wants the asset tag ID and an f32 but
we're passing something that's just a
raw value that's because that's how we
were storing them in there
we didn't type this value we just made
it bu 32 so when we call add tag we
actually need that to be something that
is converted back to the enum and then
it should be fine right and so then you
can see at that point we're really just
down to the the actual reporting problem
that I was saying which is a bit tricky
right but I think we're okay I don't
think there's going to be too much more
to do so instead of passing the filename
and the stream errors thing what we're
doing here is we're saying look we're
gonna pass the tokenizer so you can
produce your errors okay and then we're
gonna pass the import tag array that's
like the append tags right and then when
you call and tags you're going to pass
those two things along and where I want
to pass them I don't know it looks like
it's just where where I happen throw
them there is fine so it's like looks
like that and the append tags come after
and that's just really all there is so I
think that's okay and and we'll finish
it this way and we'll just see if
there's some other like way we can that
we want to sort of change things around
at all I think that's okay
and that way all of the errors will also
get reported properly back at the line
that caused the file to be imported
right which is the other thing that I
wanted to kind of accomplish there so
that we'd always know like when we hit
an error because something's wrong
we'll always know definitively like who
told us to do that because that can get
really complicated once you start having
these text files and stuff flying around
that specify things you really need some
way to make sure that you know how like
when they break you need to have a way
of going like what happened right and so
that's a pretty important part of it so
right so I'm gonna say that there's an
import tag array
that's like the appendix and then we're
just going to go ahead and go from there
I'm gonna put this there for now
and we'll say that that's how you invoke
this function the source and foe I don't
remember what that actually gets used
for the answer is like nothing so I'm
going to eliminate it for now so we know
that we actually need it and we're just
going to call this the function
signature so from there every time we
called n tags really all we need to do
is say all right here's those two pieces
of information can again same thing here
so every time we call like an import
body or whatever instead of the previous
two things we're just passing it
different two things it's pretty
straightforward and then I think we've
got ourselves set so that really does
most of the stuff that I wanted and so
now I think we're down to just like okay
if we actually want to call this little
thing when we're doing our parsing we're
gonna actually have to have some state
here what I'm guessing is that we're not
gonna want to like part pass all this
stuff down arbitrarily so we're probably
gonna want to do like an you know
something like this that actually has
this stuff in it so you know we've got
the game assets here and we've got our
import source info here and you know
that sort of stuff that we can stick
things on and maybe the default fields
is in there too right so maybe that's
just stored there right and so then when
we're parsing these things we can just
say like here's the context it is hht
not HTT
and so here I can just say okay here are
the pieces of information that you need
when you're gonna be parsing and then
from there we can get that stuff out as
we need it so the tag builder begin tag
stuff is not going to happen here that
was a lie the import type as well I
don't know that anything needs to change
there yet but here we're gonna say like
this stuff comes off of the context
assets we don't pass the tag builder
that was a red herring this right here
is the result that we need for the
moment we're not actually doing anything
with that but we will need to so we're
just going to pass that in there to get
that and then we need to pouch
that's no good and then we need to also
pass the append tags and the tokenizer
and that stuff right so we do need to
pass this and we do need to pass the
import tag array and again that's
something we'll deal with a little bit
later but we just want to make sure that
it all works all right right and we just
want to get everything like flowing
properly so now I just need to redo the
default fields part again that's now
coming from the context itself so this
will satisfy that super similarly here
we're getting it off of the context
that's really all that needs to change
there and then we just need to actually
have one
so when we're creating this context
again we need the assets and we need the
info or source info or do you want to
call that and source file info asset
source file info what was that thing
called import source info and so now we
can actually call the parse top level
block with the context that's being
asked to use and I think we're okay so
at that point
I think we're good parse pieces though I
thought we got rid of that so I think
actually that doesn't really need to
happen quite yet parse pieces kind of
refer from string so parse pieces is
expecting something else in let's jump
there it's expecting assets tokenizer x'
append tag the type token so that just
needs that and so I think we're good now
yeah um so that should be all we need
it was a pretty substantial modification
nicely but we still made it through okay
so it wasn't that bad and then what we
can do now is when we run this parse we
should now be able to tomorrow make it
so that as we parse each one of these we
can go fetch the file that it
corresponds to and update it as
necessary so basically this part of the
code here where we look in Jimmy at the
match file date stuff here this part of
the code we should be able to we should
be able to make that do exactly what we
needed right that should be all we need
and furthermore I don't know that we
actually need the get or create asset
source file thing to be stable anymore
but yeah it's a sort of separate issue
um so anyway this should be fine and we
can get rid of this to do as well I'm
gonna stop there because we've done
enough I'll go to a brief Q&amp;A I think
we've kind of done all of the munching
we need to port everything over to the
way we were doing it our I should say
from the way we were doing it to the way
we're going to do it and that wasn't too
bad it was a little Squinkie but it
seems reasonable
and so we'll we'll deal with all the
bugs tomorrow and then hopefully that
will that will allow us to be importing
texts now instead
you
what are the flaws of converting a
decimal floating point number to a
binary equivalent by first parsing the
number and converting it to a regular
integer ignoring the decimal point then
using the part number as the mantissa
and an accumulated value for the
exponent for the floating-point number
so let me just make sure I understand
what you're asking you're saying if you
were to parse the number as a decimal
and then you are going to try and figure
out a way to store that number well I
mean that I guess the first thing I'd
say is you haven't really said how you
were gonna do the exponent part of that
because I guess to state the obvious the
exponent is also binary it's not a power
of 10 right so the decimal mantissa
isn't the mantissa and it's not only not
the mantissa it's not related to the
mantissa right because the exponent that
you have to remove in order to create
the mantissa is itself a binary exponent
it's a power of 2 not a power of 10 does
that help answer the question maybe so
I'm not sure it really buys you all that
much to do what you're saying it seems
like it's it doesn't really help solve
the problem you're still left with
exactly the same problem which is
converting base-10 to base-2 tell me if
I'm understanding your question
correctly though because I may not be
understanding what you're asking
I knew what you might be asking is what
if I created a giant number storage so I
use like big num so I can store as many
bits as I want and then I convert a
decimal number with the decimal point
removed into just that a giant binary
binary number right it could be
thousands of bits long then I counted
how many of those that I have and I
truncate them at the point where I can
store my exponent and then I use the
rest of mantissa if that's what you're
asking
then sure I think that works because at
the end of the day the binary conversion
has now happened prior to needing
anything fractional but by that point
you've already built like you've had to
build like big num right to give you
your it seems like really really
inefficient right so if you're asking
how to if you're asking can I do that
without the big num no because you would
run out of bits immediately right even a
very small floating-point number by
floating point standards is way bigger
than 4 billion right floating point
numbers can represent you know hundreds
of billions if they want to so that
might be one way to just to think about
it - I don't know let me know if this is
helping I don't know if that's hope if
that's answering what your question is
whatever think about webassembly
um I don't understand the point of it I
guess like I don't know why they didn't
just define an executable format or just
use one that already exists you know I
mean if you want an assembly language
just pick one you know I go go pick like
Oh an open risk or something and then
remove the parts that you think are
security issues and then use it I don't
know why they had thought that what the
world needed was like another assembly
language like thing that still is in
text format for no discernible reason
that is also not built on any existing
proofed machine code it's it I have no
idea web standards are nuts they seem to
be made in ways that literally don't
leverage any historical things we've
learned and I don't know so yeah is it
good that we have a thing eventually
that maybe will allow us to write
compiled code on the web easier sure are
they doing good job No
so I don't know I guess that's what I
would say so I don't know if web is
somebody is still text maybe they now
have a binary version of it which is at
least an improvement but I don't know if
that actually works yet or if they're
doing that I have no idea like most
things I'm sure it will be a lot like
CSS they've decided to reinvent the
wheel which I'm not opposed to if you
understand the problems of the wheel and
you're gonna build a better one a lot of
times what Webster is going to be is
reinventing the wheel without ever
knowing what a wheel was or how it works
and then you end up with like this weird
blobby square thing and you're like look
at how good I did and you're like we
already have things that were pretty
circular what have you done you know
webassembly didn't always have a binary
format unless I'm mistaken webassembly
used to actually just be rules about how
you would interpret javascript code to
generate assembly there was no format at
all actually it was just a convention
for JavaScript it did not have a binary
format unless I'm wrong about that
that's a new thing the text format like
yeah like ah some Jas that thing that's
what I'm talking about I guess if you're
talking about web assembly is not as in
j/s or like that's not part of the
lineage or whatever then okay I tend to
think of all those things is exactly the
same if that makes sense
somebody took my name how would you
convince a seasoned object-oriented
programmer on of the merits of not using
it I don't generally do that I don't try
to convince people not to program in
ways they want to program they should
just go do it it's usually just not
worth my time to try and talk to people
about stuff like that if they don't want
to do something somewhere they shouldn't
like
have you ever read any of the art of
Peter program you mean by Knuth the new
Thor I don't I you pronounce his name
but yes I have but I don't have a copy
so I haven't read much I've read it like
from other people's bookshelves I've
read parts of it but it's obviously very
large so I've never read the bulk of it
why don't you use switch in the while
parsing tokenizer loop this one I guess
that depends on which loop you're
talking about there's more than one of
those and the reason why I don't use
switch here is because I wanted to use
break and it was not very many token
types the reason why don't you switch
here is because you can't switch on
strings right you have to switch on i'm
constant values
it's the big flop success can you
explain a bit more what windows
considers utf-16 I see it mentioned
plenty of times on MSDN but usually it
just means w KR t not actually utf-16
with surrogates uh no the answer is I
can't explain more because I have no
idea I've never really looked hard at
what Windows tries to do with what you
pass it for non ANSI encoded text
basically so I know that they support
some kind of two byte character encoding
I know that it is mostly utf-16 but in
terms of the edge cases I don't know
what they do and thankfully my job never
really depends on that my sort of vague
cursory understanding is that they're
trying to kind of move towards utf-8
slowly so hopefully we won't have to
care much eventually because Windows 10
will just be like the rest of the world
and work on utf-8 but at the moment no I
really couldn't tell you the utf-16 that
is in Windows originally that they when
they first did it there really wasn't
much of a Unicode standard so it is
definitely possible slash likely that
there's a lot of cruft
there but it's just not something I
interface with so I don't know like some
parts of Windows I've worked with a lot
and so I know all the little weird like
ends in F I don't know anything about
the corner cases of Windows is utf-16
support
has the intentionally deliberate pace
for hammy hero helped you in your day
job at all as a reminder of freshers it
always just he has to program this
fashion after all these years it hasn't
helped me in that way at all it's helped
me a little bit because you know
sometimes I'll be doing stuff on stream
well even like today like someone was
saying that there's a binary thing for
webassembly right like you don't follow
things like that much so when we talk
about things on stream I'm likely to
learn something because someone on the
chats likely to know something about it
that I don't know and so I usually learn
stuff like that on the stream where it's
just like information that's out there
that I don't follow
programming wise I always kind of enjoy
programming so I always like doing
handmade here oh the only thing I don't
necessarily enjoy is a lot of things on
hand me here I've kind of like already
solved like I already have a tokenizer I
know they have error streams no that
sort of stuff and so sometimes it's a
little frustrating cos like well I'm
gonna have to implement this again and
it's not going to be as good as the one
that I have that I normally use because
that one's had more time and energy put
into it and it was designed exactly the
way I want because I designed it right
so sometimes it's a little unfortunate
because I'm like oh you know it's a
separate codebase it doesn't have all
the fancy bells and whistles maybe or
something right
but at the same time I always do think
it's worth practicing your low-level
programming chops and so writing
something a second time or third time or
a tenth time even is still good practice
for a systems programmer so I don't mind
and once in a while I hit upon something
I hadn't thought of in my own code and
that's like I'll remember that you know
just saw your talk on papers I love or
whatever they call it super impressed
has brought me back to Hammond here oh
oh well I'm glad you liked it
it was a fun lecture it was unusual
because it was a really like high-level
lecture but I also like it was a kind of
a weird audience to give it to but like
I don't know seemed alright and I'd
never really been asked to talk about
something from that point of view before
was like where have you like extended
research work in some way that ended up
being interesting and so that was fun
I'm not putting a party hat on Molly
that's just mean I don't like it when
people dress cats up because cats don't
like to be dressed maybe in the rare
circumstance where you have a cat who
does like to be dressed up okay but most
cats don't like having things around
their collar or on their head definitely
not on their paws they hate that in my
experience all right I think we're done
with questions
I say there we go
whoa what happened there we gotta just
like a black out I don't know what's
going on there we really need this
anymore anyway we kind of finish that
we'll just hide it all right thank you
everyone for joining us on a handmade
here at some pleasure coating with you
as always if you would like to follow
along series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org and it
comes to the source code so you can play
around with it maybe you'd like to beat
me to the punch and port the asset poor
handling code over to the new format
certainly got a chance to do that
tonight because I won't finish it up
till tomorrow so if you want to give
that shot go for it other than that I'll
be back here tomorrow to do that
finishing up and I hope to see you back
here for that same time same place
till then well same time same place
unless Seattle's power goes out which
you know we're in a giant snowstorm here
so far so good
assuming we have power I'll see you
tomorrow
until then have fun programming see
anyone on the Internet tegus everybody