like it's that right yes
good hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hiro the show where we code a
complete game live on stream although we
sometimes do not code a complete game
live on stream and as those of you who
were with me yesterday no regrettably we
may have gotten a little carried away
with doing our lighting when I initially
started the series I was just going to
do basic basic 2d rendering but in that
way that it just ends up sometimes when
you're programming you end up going too
far things we ended up doing 3d
rendering because why not and we ended
up deciding to do lighting as well which
of course is very complicated and
intricate so as a result you end up
using a lot of GPU stuff now yesterday
was the first time we hit this point but
we actually are able to get into a place
now where our shaders can crash the
graphics driver which is not a bad thing
necessarily because during development
it's not uncommon to crash a graphics
driver that's just something that can
happen so no real big deal there but
what that basically means is if we want
to continue doing lighting work and
debugging we are probably going to have
to finally bite the bullet and upgrade
the handmade hero streaming setup to
have a new machine and to stream from a
secondary machine so that when we crash
it's no big deal we just reboot or
recover from the crash either or and the
stream can stay live and you can still
see what I'm doing and hear me so I'm
going to go ahead and do that the
problem with that is it's going to take
a little while I'm going to take at
least you know weekend or two to order
some new parts and put together
something that's going to be able to do
that for us so I won't be able to stream
again until like two weekends from now
let's say now this is actually pretty
handy because I am going on three
vacation going actually to visit Jeff
coming up here and so I wasn't going to
be able to stream this weekend anyway so
given that that's the fact now is
probably a good time to do this anyway
since we won't actually miss a stream
weekend that we wouldn't have missed
anyway so if I do that now we can get a
new streaming setup set up by the time I
would have been back to stream two
weekends from now and so that's probably
the right call so I'll just go ahead and
get that I can get it all ordered and
then when I get back from visiting Jeff
this weekend I can put things together
and and hopefully get it working by the
time we need it to work on stream so I'm
going to go ahead and get that process
started it'll just take a little bit of
research for me to figure out exactly
what the best way is to set up an
external streaming machine but given the
fact that so many people stream nowadays
you know I I can't imagine that there
isn't some pretty well documented stuff
out there about what kinds of setups are
the best to use for something like this
okay I so that's really it what I I
don't want to do any development today
because I don't want to risk another
crash that'll take the stream down and
we almost certainly will hit one as we
try to debug this also since we're doing
some fairly had heavy graphics defective
stuff anyway having a new machine that
we could run a graphics abeggar on which
is one thing I will make sure that I get
is some kind of machine that can run you
know a like n sight or render dock
that'll also help us debug the lighting
and I can show people how that normally
works if they've never seen it before
it's not very complicated so I'm not
sure that's that valuable but at least
we won't have to debug blind like we
have been doing so that's what we will
do in the meantime today since since I
already said there was going to
be a stream I figured I might as well
show up and do some streaming if anyone
wants to we can do something else
something that does not require working
on the game right now in the state where
it is where it's likely to potentially
crash the screen out until we debug all
of our lighting code for all we know we
don't even have a bug in the lighting
code that's causing a crash it could
just be that what we wrote happens to
crash mt driver like i have no idea
because we haven't looked at it since it
crashed right we just left it where it
was so we haven't even looked at what
the cause of the crash was yet so I yeah
it's really entirely up to to you folks
and and we can just take questions for a
little while and just do a chat if folks
want to stick around for that or we can
just end the stream we can do whatever
but I like I said I don't want to run
the game anymore because I really don't
want to I really don't want to have to
try to prevent a crash or the graphics
driver if I knew that graphics drivers
never crashed when you gave them correct
code I wouldn't worry about it I'd say
let's just be really meticulous but what
I actually know from from my real
experience in the real world is that
it's just not the case that that you can
analyze code to know it's going to crash
a graphics driver graphics drivers can
be crashed with with perfectly correct
stuff so you really have no idea when
you run something whether it's in crash
zone or not
see Belva says how do you write a
program that is graphics driver crash
aware well it really depends on what
kinds of graphics driver crashes you're
trying to prevent so there's two kinds
of graphics driver crashes that you
might be trying to prevent
I shouldn't say prevent because you're
not preventing it what I mean to say is
two ways in which the graphics driver
could crash your program and you want to
prevent it crashing your program right
so one way the graphics driver can crash
and cause your program is is more
difficult one that's if the graphics
driver is just crashing asynchronously
of your program in a thread that it
spawned for your program right so let's
say that you write a program that you
know creates a you know OpenGL surface
or whatever and starts rendering to the
surface and I you know as a result when
you run the program you can see that
there are lots of graphics driver
threads that are getting started
potentially that you didn't ask to have
started but that did start do we have we
have process Explorer I'm here
let me let me just grab we just grab
that
I'm going to grab this this is one of
those mark russinovich utilities that
are pretty handy to have around so here
we go uh so you know if I'm you know in
this case it was OBS that got taken down
because that's what you know takes down
the stream so what I'm wondering is you
know hey what's what is OBS look like in
terms of threads that are run so here's
the yeah that's that's okay so here's
the thread list right and for those of
you they're unfamiliar with process
Explorer again it's just a really handy
application that uses internal windows
systems API while internals run word it
uses kernel API is basically to iterate
over the information about running
processes at any given time so that you
can get insight into how they're running
now if you take a look at how many
threads are launched right now on behalf
of OBS what I hope you can see here is
that the start address for these threads
meaning where their entry point was is
largely not entirely inside OBS a lot of
us in that microsoft visual studio CRT
right I mean look at how many DLL entry
points have been called here there's
each one of these is a separate thread
the CRT that the CRT started I assume
this is because they're using the MSB
CRT and every time they create a thread
right you're going to get this I don't
use the Microsoft Visual Studio these
visual see CRT at work myself so I don't
really pay much attention to these sorts
of things but you can see what happens
when you do and when it's a DOL
however the more important part for
sorry good down that right on in or I
mentioned that just kind of interesting
to see how many of them popped up the
part that we actually care about is down
tier right so you can see that ATI has
created a large number of threads this
is you know all of these threads for
example at a minimum were created as
part of the ATI driver and are in the
ATI drivers sitting around right those
threads could crash and they don't need
any help from you to do it right so the
first way that the ATI driver could take
down your process is you may not even be
calling the ATI driver at all you may
not even it may not even be doing work
on your behalf and if somehow the
bugginess
in the other like when the other app in
this case like handmade hero runs a
shader that causes the graphics card to
crash if that cascading crash causes
threads in your other aperture trying to
make safe if they crash then you will
literally get a whatever the kind of
crash it is like an out of bounds memory
access or who knows what that fault will
happen completely unprovoked by you so
that's the hardest kind of crash to
recover from on behalf of the graphics
driver that's thing one thing too is the
much easier kind of crash from the
graphics driver to prevent and that kind
of crash is just things that will happen
on the graphics driver that you don't
expect to happen but they do happen when
the graphics card gets reset so that
stuff like
let's say that you're going to do some
things where the graphic card gives you
back a pointer right so let's say you go
and you're in DirectX or something like
this and you lock a texture surface or
you're in OpenGL and you lock a buffer
you say let me give me a pointer I'm
going to write to the memory of this
buffer and you write to the memory of
the buffer and then you unlock it now
99.999999 9 as I said before percent of
the time that's just going to succeed
you're always going to get the buffer
lock you're going to write to it you're
going to unlock so if you don't think
about it particularly hard and you just
leave that code in there you're never
really going to crash you can ship that
and it'll probably work most of the time
however if the graphics driver gets
stalled or gets hung or gets reset as in
the case like it did on yesterday's
stream all of a sudden a bunch of calls
to the graphics driver will start to
fail they'll fail specifically because
the surface all of the stuff that you
previously allocated like your context
OpenGL context your textures all that
stuff are gone now right they just got
nuked and so all of the calls that
you're going to make will fail all of
them the graphics driver will no longer
be able to respond to them and so even
if the graphics driver itself hasn't
really had any problems that isn't
crashing it may cascade into a failure
of your app where your app crashes
because it's seeing behavior it almost
never sees so if you want to make an app
graphics card crash proof those are the
two things you need to guard against so
one of them is fairly straightforward
although somewhat time consuming that is
making sure that nowhere in your app do
you request something from the graphics
driver and assume that you will get it
back you always have to check and see
whether or not the graphics car
it has gone down so are you starting to
get failures and if you are starting to
get failures make sure you check to see
if your context is still valid and if
you know if it's not shut everything
down and restart right this is the kind
of engineering most apps just don't do
it's the kind of engineering that
unfortunately like basically all
libraries don't do so you know as far as
I know like STL those sort of things
don't do this kind of engineering so
there's really no likelihood that an app
has any of that in it so that is not a
hard problem to solve but it is a
time-consuming problem to solve and does
cuf engineering resources so most people
don't do it the first one which is the
faulting inside the graphics driver
itself that is much harder in order to
catch that you have to install a fault
handler so you're going to have to put
in like a Windows vector exception
handler for example something that will
catch false in the application and then
respond to those salts in some way so
for example if you catch a Fault in the
graphics driver you're going to want to
do stuff like shut down everything and
you know force flick try to force close
it try to force onload the graph driver
who knows and then try to reload it
right now the good news is for something
like OBS it's just supposed to be
recording in that particular case you
have a couple easy outs when that fault
handler hits all you really have to do
in the fault handler kiss is just make
sure you flush the stream properly
that's the real shame about OBS is that
they put in no protection for flushing
the stream because that's really all
they would need to do right all they
would need to do is protect em stream
flush on crash and most of these would
be fixed now I would argue they should
just flush the stream periodically
anyway I don't really know why they
don't it doesn't make a lot of sense to
me but they don't so either or
assuming you want to be grass proof
ignoring OBS if you can just shut down
gracefully that's really all you need to
do because you can shut down gracefully
and then relaunch your own application
right so for example you can write a
launcher executable that just loads
another executable let's say or create
the process and launches that executable
when that excreta bill goes down it just
restarts that executable right so then
only have to do is the executable that's
that's the real suitable the one that's
gets started by the sort of the launcher
that secondary executable all it has to
do is trap the fault make sure that it
hasn't corrupted any files right so if
there's something that needed to be
flushed flush it I say game file the you
know the movie stream then go ahead and
shut down like just exit process and let
your launcher restart you right so
that's one way you can also make it so
that forget it like pretend to assume
the gravity Stryver is never coming back
again and if you won't be able to load
it reload it from that executable anyway
just double insulate yourself right so
that's another way that you can do that
how many episodes are remaining estimate
I don't really have an estimate for how
many episodes are remaining because we
tend to decide to do things fairly
randomly like if you know I think it
might be interesting to do some lighting
we do the lighting but that's like not
some it was ever like on a schedule so I
don't really know how many episodes
there are it's just until we feel like
we're roughly done I've said probably
600 as a minimum I just thought that
sounded like a fairly recent amount of
time but you know I don't know
sargent room visas do you use C++
features like templates do you use
polymorphism in your own projects so I
don't use templates in in my own project
no the reason that I don't use templates
is because in my experience they have a
lot of negative aspects to them and
they're not very good at at meta
programming so I tend to try and just
write code that generates code rather
than using C++ as templates I find that
that keeps compile time down it keeps
readability up and it gives you much
more power than the template does
because templates are very very weak
they're extremely weak in terms of being
able to actually do meta programming do
I use polymorphism yes all the time but
we we use polymorphism on handmade hero
as well right I just tend to code it
myself I don't I don't use classes and
virtual function tables for that I tend
to just use type fields so you know you
can pass around something called a node
to a bunch of functions and the nodes
have left and right pointers or
something because it's a three or and I
can AB SEC tracks abstract syntax tree
but then there's also you know like a
Union inside it that has a bunch of
different states of things and a type
field that tells you which one it is
that's polymorphism right you know
polymorphism just a general term for
saying that you can take an object of
one type and pass it off as an object of
another type right well if you have a
struct and that struct can be used by
multiple routines regardless of which
type of thing it actually is and there's
different data layouts depending on
which one it is that's you know polymer
prism and you know in same with switch
statements right switch statements that
look at something and do a different
thing based on it that's just another
way of implementing a virtual function
right and so I don't tend to use C++ as
features for either meta programming or
polymorphism because I just don't think
they were very well designed but I don't
mind those concepts I think the concepts
are just fine
C++ just didn't do a very good job
making them making utilities for you to
use to do them right
be PAF fest what do you think about the
about the sea RTP to do polymorphism and
he linked to curiously recurring
template pattern uh so I've never heard
that term before but maybe I will
recognize the actual wait the actual
thing it's interesting that I haven't
heard of it maybe I have heard of it and
I forgot because it says here that the
name see RTP was independently coined by
Jim Kaplan in 1995 who had observed it
in some of the earliest evil assembly
code as well as in code examples of
Timothy bud created the interesting I
say it's interesting is because like I
remember reading Jim Copland's book that
I think it's called the LSD book by by
got Myers I want to say I think and I
used to read the C++ report and Jim if I
if I'm thinking of the right guy Jim
Kaplan used to write in that as well
anyway let's take a look at what this
says here the curiously recurring
template pattern I it's got a template
class T that that just in base can be
used sympathizer derived wait what
oh I see yeah yeah all right I see what
we're talking about here I should
probably put this up on the screen so
that folks can can see what we're
talking about here let me open I guess
like a dummy let me just open like a
dummy file we have a temp directory yeah
all right I so here's I'm just going to
type in the example from the Wikipedia
page you can see what I'm talking about
or rather I should say what I'm
discussing because this is basically
what the questioner was asking about so
we don't use this syntax very much on
handmade hero or at all I guess because
we don't use templates on handmade hero
so let me briefly just explain how these
work for anyone who isn't already
familiar with them so for whatever
reason in I do not pretend to know the
reason it's probably in the DNA but I
don't really know the DNA is a book the
design and evolution of C++ which is
like a history document that explains
like the reasoning behind some of the
choices in C++ which it's fascinating to
think that there were reasons behind the
design of C++ but apparently they were
so it if you put aside the why and just
deal with what actually happened what
goes on here is that there's a template
syntax you can use in C++ that allows
you to specify inside these greater than
or less than
right inside here you can specify some
things that you do not yet know about
the code that someone can then later
specify so for example you know in this
class doesn't need to be here so we can
ignore that class instructor synonymous
the only difference is whether things
default to private or public so you can
ignore that part of it especially for
this discussion we don't care at all so
just pretend these are structures
instead there's no difference for the
purposes of the example that we're going
to be talking about so you've seen the
the struct part before so here we say
struct base we're defining something
called base you know if it was formatted
like mine it would probably look like
this because you know I use lowercase
four types but again doesn't really
matter it's just that's just convention
so in the example they've got a thing
here where they're declaring a structure
called base and they're using the syntax
this template syntax the template syntax
basically says there's something I don't
know it's going to be lets say a struct
t right that means T is the name of some
type that is not yet known so inside the
struct let's say I wanted to have a
member right look I just wanted
something in the struct that was of that
type right so here we have a template
we're going to say base and we're going
to say that we've got this this type we
don't know ignoring this part for right
now let's now say that we wanted to
actually use this so we've got you know
some function in our in our program it
looks like this and inside here we want
to use one of these things and we want
it's the thing to be an integer right
well then what we can say is base
integer right my base now I can do my
base dot the thing equals five
my bass got the thing or into is my bass
up bang right and my bass thought the
thing is an integer everywhere because
that's what we asked for
right now this doesn't give you the
ability to actually do anything useful
with this
unfortunately in terms of type movement
the reason being that these bass classes
are all distinct right so this struct
bass int if I declare a struct float and
I've got two of these these are not the
same type they're completely different
types they're exactly analogous as if
you had done this and when I say exactly
analogous I mean literally there is no
difference between having done these two
things okay
so you get no bonus polymorphism out of
this you get no extra utility out of
this it doesn't really help you much
other than to save the typing of typing
this twice right so really all that part
of it is really doing and you can do
there's more to templates than just this
so I'm not trying to suggest that the
only thing to do with them but that part
of it
they're just specifying a type there
it's really just designed to do the most
basic kind of generic programming where
it like for example on handmade hero
you've seen me and I've mentioned
templates when I do this you see me do
something like this and then something
like this right well if equivalently you
wanted to write those together you could
do something like this
and now you've got a v2 that can just be
specified with whatever you want so when
you're going to go and use it you know
you can do something like this right and
furthermore you can just sit around
generating types all day right I and so
you can see why this has at least some
utility there because if you don't want
to have to cut and paste the code you
can you know just use this to
instantiate it
the problem with templates as with
everything else when people plus is the
instance you want to do anything more
complicated with the thing that you just
made it entirely falls apart so you know
if you want to start doing things like
saying well okay you know I wanted to
make it so that I've got something that
does you know a combination of this type
of template version in this type of
template version inside this routine
when I want to you know do some kind of
processing on them and I need to detect
which ones which it's like all of a
sudden all of my stuff has to start
being templatized I'm like fifty
different things and getting specialized
in all the sort of stuff and it just
creates this incredible rat's nest of
code that gets generated at compile time
that leads to super long compile times
and just really bad kind of readability
because you can never it'll never show
you the code is actually generated it's
just it's just bad news it's better now
that it was I have a stronger aversion
to templates than somebody who started
with them today with my same brain would
the reason for that is at least nowadays
at least say clang I assume Visual
Studio as well but at least clang
compile them properly one of the
interesting things about templates when
I learned to program templates back in
the early days was that the compilers
did not compile them properly not only
that but the error messages that they
gave
literally would stop working meaning
when it tries to print out an error it
would often reach the limit of the size
of an error it could print and just
truncate the error message so you
couldn't actually see the error message
I'm not making this up
debuggers often couldn't inspect them so
you'd end up with templates that were
like uninspected i'll you just couldn't
see what was inside them in the debugger
I just a lot of really bad stuff and so
nowadays I still don't think templates
are good they don't lead to cleanly
written code for doing the kinds of
things that you want to do with them
but they're a lot better than they were
which is why I say that if somebody
wants to do something like this I'm not
going to get too angry about it because
it's relatively straightforward it does
work you can inspect it in the debugger
now back in 1996 or so when I would have
been first using templates 95 96 I would
at this point say you know if I went
back to that day I'd be like do not
touch templates for a decade like until
2005 don't even think about using these
and then maybe sometime around there you
could start to think about using them
right but they were just awful at that
time not that people didn't still use
them but they were just it was a very
bad idea all right so anyway that's what
templates are enough to understand this
example so what the person wrote in to
ask about was that if I declare a
template like so what do you think about
the pattern of having a derived class
that inherits from a base class that is
templatized on the derived class itself
right
now
you may be asking and rightfully so what
is this public based arising here
because again for those of you who
aren't C++ people you may not really
know because we don't do that on we
don't really ever use those people's
hand Mahiro well if you have a structure
class and you want to essentially extend
that class so I mean that struct
classrooms are structs are
interchangeable so I I just use the two
terms interchangeably so I apologize for
that so if you have a struct like say
this this base here and I could make it
a little simpler by taking the template
out of it let's say I just have a class
a and it has an infinite and then I have
a class B and it has a y in it like so
right so normally let's say that I
wanted to extend this class and I wanted
to put some extra information in it now
you know if this is a bad example let me
do something you can actually relate to
so it's a little clearer let's say I've
got entity because that's a more common
thing that people might use for
sub-classing right
and inside the entity I have got some
you know generic information like I've
got like the position of the entity and
maybe I have something like its radius
or whatever but then depending on what
type of entity I have I want additional
information about the editing now we've
seen different ways of doing this like
I'm hand made hero will often do
something like we'll make a union and
then we'll do something like saying
entity ghost and the ghost has you know
a spookiness value and then what we'll
do on handmade heroes we'll say all
right here's entity ghost
here's enum MC type and we'll have like
entity ghost
right that's the standard way we might
write something like that on handmade
hero the way a object-oriented program
our rights this most of the time who
likes inheritance is they use this
syntax which is the syntax for
inheritance in C++ what it is is it's a
colon after the type name that says
anything that I list after that colon is
going to be something that I include at
the top of myself basically so if I say
oops okay so if I say this then what
this public entity part here means is
just that I've got this struct stuck on
top of me so this basically becomes this
right it grafts whatever you put here
onto the top and that's all it does
right it doesn't really do anything else
at this point so why do you want this
well as you can see this is sort of a
way of doing the same sort of thing
we're doing here building composite
types that have all the information in
them and furthermore C++ once you've
specified this will do you a nice favor
which is it will make it so that you
don't have to cast if you want to go
from one of the more specialized classes
to one of the less specialized classes
or in our case trucks right so for
example if I'm sitting around and I have
an entity ghost like so right and I have
something that expects an entity so
let's say I have a function
and in here we're going to do something
to that entity then when I am going to
be somewhere else with one of these
entity goes like so normally in you know
if this were just without this syntax to
public entity part normally I wouldn't
be able to do this right because this is
an entity ghost and this function
requires an entity so when I call foo
I'm going to be calling ghost here I'm
going to be passing an empty ghost
pointer it shouldn't work it's give me
an error but because I said that this
entity ghost always includes entity at
the top of it it's essentially as if I
had one of these at the top and whenever
you want to call something that would
have used it it's just cast it for you
implicitly because remember any pointer
to an entity ghost is basically a
pointer to an entity as well because the
members at the top are the same so
anything that would have been code that
would have been generated in here to
work with P and radius whether I'm
pointing to an entity or an envied ghost
wouldn't matter because they're in the
exact same places right okay so that's
how inheritance works right so now let's
get back to the actual question at hand
now that we've explained the things in
here that we don't normally see on
handmade hero
so in here where we have struck entity
we've got the P and the radius to entity
type the ghost whatever that sort of
stuff right this is the handmaid here
way of doing something we're going to
say let's pretend we're not going to do
it that way instead we want to do it you
know some other way like this
inheritance way
well once we start doing things in the
inheritance way what you can see
happening is that all the stuff we take
for granted on handmade hero suddenly
starts to go away a little bit
right because the base class that you're
inheriting from doesn't know and can't
know what the derived class actually was
so for example inside when we're dealing
with something of this base class here
let's say we have a struct derived based
derived here this this fellow right
let's say in here we have an int X right
and if inside the base class there's a
function that wanted to be able to know
whether it was actually one of these or
not right because remember you know I
should probably leave this in here
because I'm going to probably refer to
it right let me leave this because I can
show you more clearly in here let's say
that we actually built this out a little
bit more and what we wanted to do was
like inside foo we had a bunch of stuff
we wanted to do here that was like oh
yeah you know the entity P is going to
be offset by something and then the
entity radius is going to be you know
offset by one point oh I don't know
write something like this that all works
just fine a C++ right with this
inheritance model the problem now comes
if I wanted to do something like all ah
you know what I really wanted if there
was a if it hat if it did have a
spookiness to it right if it was a ghost
then i want to do something differently
so you know i really wanted to do
something like if i am a ghost right
then you know then get you know shrink
me to zero or something you know i don't
know right like imagine you just have
something special you want to do in that
case so c++ doesn't really handle these
sorts of things with any kind of great
one of the really big problems with
their inheritance model are TTI isn't
something you can actually persist
across builds of your program so you
can't really use what's called runtime
type information which is a way of
figuring out an identifier based on the
type it doesn't really work so it's
pretty much out of the question so you
can't use that to ask whether you're a
ghost there is no way to generate an
enum you know C++ was saying there'd be
a way to just generate an enum in a
predictable fashion that was stable
across runs that you could use and just
have that be a type field that you could
access in size entity if you wanted it
of course you can't get that so that's
out of the question that's of course why
I always run it this way because this
basically handles all cases you can't do
that in C++ so they start you start to
have to use these other like really
roundabout ways like saying well okay
even though all I wanted to do was check
if I'm a ghost here which should have
been a relatively simple thing to do I'm
going to have to start introducing
something to help me here
one thing they could do is virtual
function calls which are basically based
off of whatever the derived type was I
can have a virtual function call which
says like a my ghost write which I could
call and it could return a boolean the
tells you of the room goes I could
inflate the Billy's cut the base class
to actually have an mi a ghost but
that's basically like adding an enum so
at that point you've lost the benefit of
the inheritance or the virtual functions
are really the only way to do it I won't
go into detail quite about how works 100
skills no matter if this example but
that's the way you could do them the the
audit oriented programmer sort of
fallacious reasoning usually leads them
to do something like well you should
break this down into a virtual part that
will be different for the ghost so baby
it should be something like you know get
to radius that you call on the entity
that allows it to do this or whatever
also this would probably a member
function in an object-oriented
programmers world but that's beside the
point but you just going to do this
really nasty world of nastiness
right so another weird way you can
accomplish the same thing though is by
looking at this pattern that they've
that the original questioner asked about
one thing you could do is say when I
derive from a type instead of using it
as a polymorphism
as something for polymorphism in in the
top-down way right in the way where I'm
like inheriting from an entity base
class that has the basic things in it
and instead I'm you know going to and
and I'm stacking that on like at the
front of my structure that I could
interchangeably use myself as what I
actually what type of actually I'm and
that type you could instead in effect
effectively flip things around right you
could say well alright this type is
actually the type that's going to be
more primal and instead what I'm going
to do is I'm just going to make whatever
this utility class here is that I've
written I'm going to make that template
eyes on me so it can do stuff based on
what I want it to do right now you can
do a lot of different stuff is that
right like you can imagine that this
base class now can have stuff that
operates on things of this derived type
so for example if this thing does have
an int X into y in it and now we have a
thing that's like inside the space class
well first of all again member functions
are something we haven't really talked
about either member functions or things
that are part of a class that operate on
on the things in the class but AE so I'm
trying to think of like what the
cleanest way to choose something like
this is
it's been so long since I've programmed
any things like this that I'm sure I can
think of a reasonably interesting use
case for this it's just that I
my brain has long since passed by these
sorts of things so it's a little bit
hard for me immediately think of
something that's going to resonate and
be like oh yeah that that makes sense so
let's say that we have
that's going to be good I don't suppose
the Wikipedia article has an actual good
example of something that I would want
to do does it typically the base class
template will take advantage of the fact
that member function bodies are not
instantiate until long after
declarations and we use members of the
derived class within that so member
functions which is what I just said via
the use of the caste but they don't
really
yeah they don't really do anything
particularly interesting here here we go
object counters so maybe this is useful
let's see the main purpose of an object
enter is retrieving statistics of object
creation instruction for a given class
which could be easily solved using CRT P
they basically go on to yet to basically
just you know use this as a way of doing
injection I let me skip that because
since polymorphic chaining is given this
example here maybe we can just skip
directly to that which I think is what
the original question was about I and
you know we'll see if we can we can
recently get this you know maybe I
should bring this up on the screen I can
just walk through the example here to
pee
here you go so I think this and perhaps
it's related one polymorphic copy
construction is mostly what's the
original question or was asking about
but I don't really know obviously
because they just said polymorphism in
general so maybe they didn't have either
of these two uses in in mind I'm not
sure this is the more concise one so we
could look at this one first
but basically what they say here right
we're using polymorphism one sentence
needs to create object copies of objects
by the base class pointer commonly use
idiom for this is adding a virtual
cloned function defined every class
Sergi we can use to avoid having to
duplicate that function or other similar
functions in every derived class right
so you can see they've set up exactly
the same thing as we were talking about
here is the base class I'm sorry this
here is the generic class this is
actually not the specific one it's just
sort of a thing that creates the virtual
functions which again I said I guess
we'll have to talk about basically what
a virtual function is is it's a function
that is dispatched automatically based
on which actual type of object you have
so for example in handmade hero we
typically implement this behavior with a
switch statement we will have an enum
stored in the structure that says you
know I'm this particular type and so
when someone wants to do something
specific based on that type there's a
switch with the type and then you do a
different case per object type like
whatever the thing is in C++ the methods
they built-in for that with virtual
functions what they do is they add a
hidden pointer you can't see it it's not
ever shown but it's there so it adds a
hidden pointer to the top of each struct
ant well it does nothing at the top of
the structure just has to be in a
predictable location but point being
probably at the top so there's a hidden
pointer which points to a table of
function pointers that can be used to
call the different songs
depending on the type and it will just
dispatch through them so for example
when you see here we've got template
type name derived class shape CR teeth P
public shape right it creates a virtual
function here that overrides that's the
term term that's normally used for
creating one of these the one that's in
this base class so when someone has a
shape they don't necessarily know which
kind it is so they don't know it's a
shape CRT P template or any of the other
things what they will basically do is
when you hit this clone you try to call
clone it will look up into the pointers
pointer table because it's actually one
of these that pointer will be pointing
to the pointer table for this particular
type which will have a pointer to this
function and it will call this function
if you had a shape CRT P as the type you
were working with right now there's
going to be a different one of those
function tables for every one of these
different parametrize types but we'll
get that second okay so all this space
class does is set up the fact that there
is going to be a clone after that we
then have this template type the
template type takes whatever the most
derived class is going to be so for
example square or circle they're
defining these other types in the future
right I don't know why they thought they
should introduce a macro here because
since this isn't about macros it would
have been probably much clearer to not
do that but what can you do so anyway
this GOTV class it was clone 4 derived
as they say you can see how it's doing
this clone right it's saying oh okay
what I want to clone something what I
want you to do is create a new derived
class and pass to it whatever the I want
you to use it's it's effectively copy
constructor I want you to basically take
there's so many things in here that we
don't cover in him and it's really hard
for me to do explanations because every
time I want to refer to something I'd
have to explain it
every time you call the phone function
you're basically just going to call the
copy constructor of whatever the derived
class was so it's basically just a way
of saying oh okay since I don't want to
have to type this every time in every
derived class from Shape I'm going to
make this ridiculous template that will
then inject that function using the
actual derived class itself into every
of my derived classes so that they all
can do this right now the hilarious
thing about this I mean you know you
could probably predict what I'm going to
say just look at this right it's so
convoluted like what you wanted to do is
nothing like what this looks like all
you wanted to do was write a function
that said hey I'm going to write a
function called clone whenever you
derive a class from shape I would like
you to call the copy constructor on that
derived class inside clone right and
I'll just try to hammer this point home
because this is an extremely simple
example and yet it's still so laughable
about how bad B plus plus is at doing
this right so here's what I wanted to
have happen right here's what I here's
what I wanted to have happen in fact
maybe this is what we'll talk about
today because it's worth noting it's
worth examining specifics about why I
rag on C++ so often and literally any
example of how to do something in C++
using template classes whatever
literally any example shows you why it
is such a poor language you can
literally take any example that someone
gives and it usually takes only a few
seconds to see how bad they did at
creating the thing that you would have
wanted in that scenario right
so here we go let's think about what's
actually happening in the code right now
all right what we actually wanted to
have happen let's write that first so
here's what I've got and I'm going to
call it a struct because again I'll try
to keep it as friendly to people who are
used to the series as possible right so
here's what it would look like in KC
land right it would just look like
struct shape like so and all we wanted
to do in our program is we wanted to
have something that would do that
whatever that cloned function is right
so all we wanted to do was say all right
we need a function called clone it's
supposed to take a shape it's supposed
to clone that shape right so this is the
function that we wanted to write now if
there weren't any pointers in here in
particular right then the amusing part
about this is that actually it would be
incredibly easy the way we do it on
handmade hero even if it's a derived
class right so on handmade hero again
the way that we do this is we would say
shape square shape circle I don't know
seems fair we have a shape it's got a
position we've got a radius in the
circle 1 we've got a command of x and y
a wealth of square actually so let's
call it a rectangle because otherwise
you just probably still call it a radius
so at least the data members will all be
different right so anyway we've got a
shape rectangular shape circle in the
hand made hero way we would do something
like save type type right and then we'd
have a union that would be a like shape
rectangle shape circle
okay so the hand made here away if you
wanted to write a clone function well
all you would do is however you would do
the Alec you know you'd do a push struct
or something like this of shape and then
you would just do result equals shape
right that's the that's it okay
so the implementation in hand made 0
style code is three lines long pretty
straightforward right now let's suppose
there was something in here that was a
little more complicated for whatever
reason our circles have a data block the
data block pointer is going to have to
get duplicated in some way whatever so
then what we have is this right so
inside here we've got whatever needs to
happen to data block in order to clone
it because it has some kind of special
operation all right again extremely
straightforward look at that code for a
second and just consider how easy it was
to write this code also consider how
easy it is to read right now let's try
to start writing this in C++ instead
all right so first attempt at C++ to
write this we are not going to use this
pattern yet right we're going to save
this pattern for a minute go you know
get to that in a second okay so first
attempt to do this at C++ it's just
three it's a straightforward way okay
so first of all we have to change the
order of these two things and then what
we have to do is go okay we got it bring
in the shape here right so now we at
least have these types but now we want
to write a clone function so we want
something that does this right how do we
do it right what are we going to do so
mm couple options we have a first option
is we can try to write it effectively
this way but just much more laborious ly
right because we have no idea what the
maximum size of one of these this is
right so for example one thing that you
would have done in C++ if you wanted to
make things simpler for the programmer
if you would have had a trivial way of
saying all derived classes have to be
the same size right that's the way this
works so if you wanted to make things
easy for the programmer so that they
could still write this code that I wrote
before right because and again let me
just hammer this point home it's crucial
to understand that if your language
features meant to empower the programmer
to do something new cannot even let the
programmer write code that is as simple
as the code they would have written
before they have that feature you
obviously didn't make the feature right
because that that can't be correct in
other words making leaving a giant hole
in the implementation space when you
create a new feature that's supposed to
be better than the way you were doing it
before not even having its code be as
simple as the code you had before should
be a gigantic huge raging blinking
symbol on the screen that goes start
over you did it wrong right but I can't
write this code why can't I write this
code I have no idea how much memory I
would need to store one of these things
right so if I didn't care about wasting
a little extra memory which you almost
never do and you don't even know that
you actually are because most they might
all be roughly the same in fact in this
case they are exactly the same size so
there's literally no reason to even care
you can't do this you can't actually do
this because you have no idea how big it
would need to be in this case I know
exactly how big it needs to be because
the shape struck is the one that
encloses all the other structs in this
case I literally can't get that
information there is literally no way
that C++ will ever tell me how much
space I need to store the derived
classes it could be any it could be
anything so I can't write this so so
then what's the next thing I might do
well I could try to use runtime type
information right I don't even remember
the syntax or runtime type information
but effectively what it does is it would
let me write a switch statement if I
wanted to write a switch statement which
is like the RTP I of shape I think you
can do this
which I was making this up I'm not all
right so I don't remember the syntax of
RGGI but it doesn't really matter what
the syntax actually is I think you can
do this I could be wrong and you might
not even be able to do this let's see
the type ID keyword is used to determine
the class of an object at runtime it
returns a reference standard I type info
which is that yeah okay so you can
although I don't actually see them doing
it here I mean here's another way you
could do it right so you might not be
able to do a switch I think you can do a
switch though you just have now you know
you probably couldn't even do a switch
let's see it's been so long since I'd
like I mean literally it's been like two
decades
so I guess don't quote me on whether you
can do it has a switch
let's just hope you could so you just do
type by D I mean I guess you could do it
this way right so the reason I say I
don't know whether you can do is the
switches I don't know if that's
technically considered a constant that
could be switched on like a constant
integer because it suggests that it's a
reference to a type here you go oh but
that c-plus eleven only so they didn't
have this background turning it but you
know okay so now if you've got a C++ 11
compatible compiler there we go hash
code that's what we need so in here in
theory you could do this right
maybe I don't know don't quote me on
that
but like you could maybe make something
that looks like this maybe right so
again what you wanted to write was this
in fact you didn't and you didn't even
need to write that yet
we haven't gotten there yet but instead
you have to write what I just wrote over
there right now furthermore in order to
get this to work you have to have at
least one virtual function because we
don't have a virtual function it won't
create the V table without the V table
there is no identifier in the struct
so you'd need to put one of these in
there regardless it could do nothing you
wouldn't they would wouldn't actually
have to exist right but you would have
to have one so here's the first attempt
at a clone call that's just trying to
clone this thing and it's like
well okay now every time I make one of
these I have to create a new one in the
new one in the new one and a new one in
the new one right and it's like oh my
lord
because remember none of these are doing
anything yet so the only one I even
needed the only one I actually want is
circle eventually once we have data
block right so this piece of code comes
down in here so that's the only one I
actually wanted but I have to write one
for every single one because I don't
know how big they have to be and I can't
get that information any other way so
off I go right so yeah great so it's
like I can't do that this is really ugly
so now what I'm going to do well another
thing that I could do is just make a
virtual function call for clone right so
maybe I say well okay I've got this
clone function it's going to be a
virtual function call and what it's
going to do is return the correct type
now in order to do that I need there to
be one of these in every single one of
these that's going to do the actual
cloning right so this goes away and now
I've got a way to clone that's going to
be in here but again I'm massively
remember this is all I should have had
to write but now I'm writing all of this
stuff so virtual shapes are clone what I
have to do here is you know create one
of these so you know if I was going to
do a push struct here I could but you
know C++ is allocator syntax is new so
you know the way you would see it in C++
is something like this
this pointer is just a pointer inside a
member function like this that points to
beyond we're talking about so this is
like passing in the shape right and this
just has to be in everything again
massive amounts of duplication I'm
typing a ton for no reason I'm typing
the same thing at least three times I
have to type if there were 12 of these I
have to type at 12 times instead of just
typing at once like I did before
again just strictly worse all the time
right
so that's why we start to get to this
ridiculousness here because this is an
example of how you might try to solve
this problem in C++ if you wanted
something that even slightly approaches
the cleanliness and simplicity of the
straightforward way to do it in C right
which is to say okay I know that I've
got a shape and I know this going to
have a virtual base clasp on it right
I'm sorry it no it's going to have a
virtual clone call on it like so now
they use this syntax here equals zero
what that means is I never want to clone
an actual shape that prevents you from
ever calling clone on something that was
just this shape just a shape struct
meaning it never had a derived class
begin with that's a way of preventing
you from ever using shape without a more
derived class so if you never want
anyone to really use one of these you
can put an equal zero on it like that
and if it has any of these equals zero
that means you can't actually derive
make one of these and when you derive a
class you have to supply one right
that's just basically a syntax that says
hey I'm going to be using derived
classes make sure that I'm always using
a derived class and make sure that it
always has one of these functions in it
all right
so this part alone doesn't really help
us because we still have to have it in
both of these but now what you can see
is if we wanted to take this code out
and actually share it what we can do is
use this bit right here so what I can
say is all right let's suppose that I
don't know what the derived class
so I'm just going to yeah call it
derived here like in the example then
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
create this sort of shape cloner which
is going to be sort of reverse so
amazing yeah
it puzzles the mind that this is that
this is the way that the people thought
to program but anyway I so anyway I'm
going to create the simple class derived
here and I'm going to create a shape
cloner I don't know why I put derived in
there which is basically a base class
that sits underneath this original base
class and just says ok I'm here just to
clone things that's all I do I have a
clone function on me I know that I'm
templatized on the type I should be
cloning so I can do that and I can do
the copy as well by doing the cast here
right like so so now when I make one of
these instead of inheriting from shape
instead I can inherit from shape cloner
and pass it myself
that forces this to generate the clone
function that's what I want it would
have had to type here what you saw me
type manually before as the virtual
function right so let me go back to the
originally asked question I which is
[Music]
where is it which is what do you think
about the CR T P to do polymorphism and
let me look at what you said okay I
didn't want to use virtual functions so
I found this I was super happy so this
is not specifically the case that you
were talking about then it sounds like
the case that you were talking about is
more for good no there it is
is more for this one unfortunately this
is a little bit bigger so well hopefully
you already can kind of see what I think
about this but let's take a look at this
this example as well then just I make
sure I know the actual use case here
alright so here we've got a class
printer the printer is has some member
functions those member functions are
templatized on the type that's going to
get printed right so you can see here
they're declaring a template the print
function takes the template thing and it
just does an i/o stream out of that
thing right for those of you who don't
know io stream this is going to be a
little bit confusing but let's see let's
see whether we actually decided to bet
or not it might be that that's not
relevant
so let me could say prints can be easily
changed printer my stream println
println yep so that's make sense right
you're just calling prints on prints
right you're calling this and since it
generally mmm oh yeah it's okay as
weather since it returns itself I'd say
it there it is so since it returns
itself each time you can keep calling
number functions on it right so that
says if we define the following derived
class which there it is this is the C
out printer there's the printer base
class so a C out printer can have all
this stuff called on it and we want to
have this set console color call that
sets the console color it's fine it says
we lose the concrete class as soon as we
invoke a function of the base and you
can see that happening here where you're
like hey I did a print but the print is
going to return printer which is bad so
I want to be able to do set console
color on that right and so off we you
know continue going here and we say well
okay what we could do you can kind of
see where we're going to go with this
right is if we just template eyes the
concrete printer printer class on
whatever the concrete class was what
everyone actually had then we can just
make it return that class right
so we just make it return that class
then when we are using this and we call
any of these print functions they will
actually return one of these see out the
correct pointer types you have printer
pointer type and off you go
right so the question is what do I think
of that and I mean the answer hopefully
should be obvious why would you ever do
such a thing when the simpler solution
is usually available right I mean the
question usually becomes what's the
specific instance you're looking to try
and solve because it's hard to give an
example like I could show you how to do
this particular example without making
it so convoluted but it's really kind of
hard to imagine this really being a
problem because chances are the better
solution if all you wanted to do was
have a console color is just make this
struct support setting a console color
right so you're probably not really
talking about something that mundane
especially because this thing probably
in a real world scenario needs to know
the console color for various operations
that's going to be doing anyway so this
is kind of - toy of an example to really
talk about probably and I'd have to know
what the actual real world example is if
someone was trying to solve before I
could say how I would prefer that it
would be solved but no I don't think
that's very good I don't think that's
very good for a lot of reasons number
one if you look at what's happening here
you're effectively duplicating a ton of
code for no actual purpose like the only
thing you were trying to do here right
is make it so that this syntax worked
and if you just stopped using this
syntax you wouldn't have had the problem
right all you would have had to have
done was you know call these as separate
lines with a semicolon and you wouldn't
have had the problem right so you know
even like this example it's just not
very good and I would have to know like
what a more realistic one is let's see
so the original questioner gave a
perhaps an example we can actually look
at my use case is I write a library and
I want users of the library to provide
their own strux
for me to do my library business on so I
need polymorphism one way or another
and since it's a simulation I want to
remove all of the runtime cost I can
incur
so be PAF I guess I'm not sure I
understand if you have a library that's
doing stuff on strux why can't they just
take pointers to those trucks and if the
user wants they can embed those trucks
in other things where does the
polymorphism come in are you trying is
it because you have to call them back at
like a well you said you didn't want
virtual functions so so what what is the
actual reason you can't just define the
structure that you operate on and then
they just embed those trucks in whatever
it is that they're using like what is
the what is the actual what's the
problem we're actually trying to solve
you have to call them back so yeah I
guess I would ask how is that call back
like what is an example of a way you
call them back
they define a game and I define in the
library a genetic programming framework
to post our generic programming flight
framework I assume that supposed to read
to find players that play well oh no
genetic Munich programming in in a
library a genetic programming framework
to find players that play well at them
well ok but so why does that require
calling anybody back though right like
could you just restructure the program
so that you don't call them back
um so I mean for example right like to
just to give a very simple example which
I totally recognize it's probably not
going to address the full complexity of
what you're asking but it you know to
take it on faith that I do tend to
address probably things that are
similarly complex and you usually find
that there's ways to architect them to
remove that particular problem but PPF
in particular I create trees as
expressions that contain okay so now we
have an exact example in particular I
create trees as expressions that contain
terminals that are defined by the game
which operate on the game state and then
evaluate those games that contain if
less equals etc as well as the game
terminals and then make players out of
random trees and determinance between
each other okay so so these players are
like making moods I assume right like so
your is the thing that you're trying to
store in the tree moves like ways of
making a move or is it the state of the
game
does that make sense meaning it sounds
like you're saying I've got something
like this you know
yeah okay so you've got something like
this it sounds like right where you've
got I've got some kind of a game
operator here and I'm building up like a
tree of these operations and I've got a
bunch of operation pipes that I'm you
know working with or something like this
and then what I want to do is I want to
be able to allow the user to define
their own game ops whatever those are
going to be and then I want to be able
to to do stuff on them right so the
first thing I would ask is can you just
do it like this
so can you just do it where you have a
thing called a game up the game up has
your left and right pointers you have a
type field in it right the type field
says what type of OP it is and off you
go right you your library starts it's
IDs at you know whatever we are here at
you know some very high number would
that be this would be 6 5 5 3 6 so
that's going to be 16 times that so 16
times 6 5 2 6 whatever it is it starts
somewhere here right and I'd say what
type of thing it is and then we can
allocate extra stuff off the back if we
want to down here right and off you go
everything in the library just looks at
the operation types here if it's not one
of these operation types you know that
it's a game op and you just call the
game back right
makes sense so now inside the game this
is this is the user of the library right
bees inside the game they just do like
game op types op type my thing op type
thing to write
right so you know again like separating
two concerns here so one concern is do I
want to write code that works well and
easy to use and easy to debug and so on
right
oh wait
BPF how would you pass the information
you need to create random operations to
the library from the user in this
framework well presumably if the
operations are specialized meaning the
library doesn't even know what they
should be then you know you'd presumably
just have like and you know you've
probably got library handle here or
something right where you're just
passing it but you know regret that's
neither here nor there so you know
you've got a thing it's like if you want
to call be able to call them back to
create a random operation then there
just is one of those and they do
something like this well you know I
would probably even provide a macro like
we do in handmade hero so it'd be like
your library name create up my op struct
I might even make it easier for them by
doing it that way and so what they would
do is they just say my obstruct here
right and you know they can do this any
way they want to you can if you want to
again you could use this syntax if you
like it to put the game up in there I
don't generally do that so I would
probably do that right but the other
thing you can do is if you want you can
leave out this part if they don't need
to access
it so instead what you can do is here
say all right let's say this was going
to be one of these I could just create
one of these it would set this would be
a macro that creates a game op with one
of these on the end of it and so only
the new stuff goes here and if this part
is meant to be opaque to them like
they're not supposed to touch it then
you just return them a pointer to just
the base part right you just return them
only a pointer to the part that comes
after this but you've allocated and off
you go
so yeah
there's a lot of ways so basically what
I would say is library design can be
tricky and it can be tricky for a couple
of reasons number one is it is tricky to
always think through what is the actual
easiest way to use this library what
reduces the number of things that you
know that actually makes it the right
decisions for making this code easy to
use right like I would even argue
probably at this point that I would have
probably tried to get rid of some of
these callbacks maybe this game process
call back is unavoidable but this create
random op call back is probably very
avoidable would be my my thought because
you probably could create them in
batches and do a loop which I would
think would probably be a better better
idea but that's that side point I try to
eliminate callbacks where possible I
guess is what I would say but ignoring
that part of it for for a moment
creating libraries are pretty difficult
because a it's very difficult to think
through all the architectural
possibilities and what actually is the
easiest to use and and requires the
least number of special-purpose things
you know one of the nice things about
stuff like codes like this - that people
often forget is that not only is it
simpler than having weird derived
classes and people trying to trace
through these virtual function calls
going through a library and all this
other stuff but it also works on
everything right it's like if somebody
wants to run this from Python they don't
suddenly have to you know have some
binding that does nutso stuff to make a
derived class jump through virtual
function called clone whatever work
right because if you just have a thing
that takes a pointer and receives a
pointer like everything can kind of just
do that it's not very difficult right so
it makes a lot easier to bind to other
languages but but anyway ignoring all of
that you do have a secondary problem
with creating a library that is a real
problem because you are creating a
library and that problem is that other
people have weird notions about what is
it is not effective right so it would be
great if
you work these things out and you know
maybe you don't like what I put here and
that's totally fine right I'm not saying
you have to do it this way I was just
trying to give you some other ideas and
I don't even know if that's where I
would land on it right I'd have to go
see your old library think about it for
a while
decide what it is that I really thought
was the right way to do it blah blah
blah right but it would be great if
after you did that if you did a good job
you put it out there and what people
were really going to evaluate it on was
how effective it really was to just
program that how few errors did they
have how quickly were they able to do it
how easy was it for them to read how
easy was it for them to use another
languages blah blah blah
right the problem is they're oftentimes
not going to do that so oftentimes
they're going to do is they're going to
come at it and they've got just this
weird attitude of like well if I don't
see lots of templates and base classes
and things or I see someone cast
something like if there's a cast
I just decodes awful it's terrible right
like this libraries sucks in reality
that's just poor programming but that's
just poor analysis they're not doing a
very good job
realistically assessing whether this
library is good or not and unfortunately
especially if you have a commercial
library there's not much you can really
do about that you're going at the cater
to certain Prix held ideas that people
have that may be erroneous
you know I it's it's just it's not
what's the what's the weird word they
use in politics a faith based versus
reality based or whatever you know
they've got these terms that they like
to throw around it's it's very much like
programming is a faith-based discipline
these days right people don't have any
objective metrics that they ever try to
employ they don't even really test
things to see which ones are more
effective they just have like a belief
in some things that they think either
someone told them we're good or they
somehow came to the conclusion were good
and they're not really willing to
evaluate them based on how effective it
actually was for
to use right and and so I don't pretend
that these are necessarily the right
answers even if they are the best so
yeah
BiPAP said the thing I liked about the
CRSP approach that it makes somewhat
clear what the interface is you have to
implement these methods and have this
data and I can do the generic tournament
job that is your base class that you can
comment and you can have multiple
customization points with multiple
template parameters uh yeah I mean like
I said I don't know does does it is it
really worth it though it just doesn't
seem very good because again like what
if you wanted to serialize this tree
like what if you want to save this to
disk how are you going to do it right
how are you going to do that I mean
you're going to need an enum in there at
some point I would argue and you know it
sounds like you already have one once
you have an enum you kind of don't need
virtual functions anymore right it you
can just write a switch statement and
almost always the switch statement is
going to be cleaner and the same is true
for the allocation you kind of want that
to be in your library because again if
you want to serialize you need to know
how big it is and you probably want to
be able to know that ahead of time even
if you have a callback that allows them
to finalize it in some way I don't know
it it's tough to say but I would just
say unless you it just doesn't seem like
the kind of situation that really calls
for inheritance at all in the c++ sense
because you can do it with you know data
style inheritance that's just going to
be more flexible most the time I think
and bps the other thing about it is it's
not even so much that you extend the
enum because really they are sort of
defining the enum right you make sure
your things aren't even in the way so
when they do it they don't even have to
know that you've got high order stuff up
there I mean you want to document that
in case they accidentally hit it somehow
but but basically they can just define
one of the things I try to encourage you
to do is when they're making libraries
switch the enum order around so that
you're using the high values and they're
using the letter values right so like
all your stuff has this bit set for
example now and theirs doesn't so you
can also tell the difference between one
of their types and yours by testing the
bit and that's really important because
again it takes out a step of
understanding they no longer have to
think about the fact that you also have
enums in there they can just act like
they're the only one who had the enums
as if they wrote the code themselves it
feels very comfortable for them right
BPF here's the thing if I want to
generate trees for different choices
that need different languages I use
multiple template parameters in your
framework I'd have to put the enums at
precise points I guess I guess I just
don't know what it means to say that
need different languages what does what
does this mean I'm sorry I just don't
think I understand the goal
by different choices I mean you could
have two choices for a game turn and you
might want to have trees that use
terminals that look at different aspects
of the game
BPF for example imagine a game where you
have the choice to play or pass and if
you decide to play you then have to make
a move
well but aren't you just talking about
game state-dependent operations like I
mean isn't that just something here that
would say this like are we not just
talking about that
or I mean another way to say it would be
if you just want the player to be able
to generate different random things
depending on what the state of the game
is then isn't that just something they
can do inside the random app callback if
you give them that information like why
do they have to have different enum
categories because who cares that's up
to them right like they are the ones who
know what their game state is and how
many permutations that might have and
which moves make sense from any
particular point right
well BPF why doesn't the player generate
the random number I mean shouldn't they
be the ones who wouldn't they be the
ones who would know from looking at the
game state which enums are even valid at
that time
I mean am I missing something there
I agree it means it's kind of difficult
for me to really know like what you know
asking design questions about stuff like
this is kind of hard because I not
familiar with the actual library right
so I'm trying to sort of guess what's
going on but I don't really know I guess
let me just make the general point so
typically speaking it's important to
pick the things your library does and
doesn't do based on whether or not
you're getting you're creating more work
for them to have you do it right so for
example let's I'm not saying this is
actually your case so this may not be
anything like what you're facing at the
moment let's hypothetically consider
just temporarily the case that I'm about
to describe so let's suppose that I do
have a thing where I've got a move tree
that I'm trying to create I'm kind of to
create moves or something not genetic
algorithms but just moves and at any
given time only some of these moves are
valid so I only want to create moves
that are valid in that context right so
there's two ways we can go about
attacking that problem for the library
for two broad categories one category
says let me try to communicate to the
library everything it needs to know in
order to correctly guess which moves are
possible at a particular point another
one is to say let's not do that let's
instead just give the game enough
information for it to make that decision
and let it make the decision itself
right
most of the time the second option is
actually going to be better because the
amount of work the person has to do to
sort of describe their game rules to the
library is probably way way more work
than just allowing them to inspect their
own game state structure and generate
what the moves are possible at that
point for you so flipping around the way
you look at doing it there is often
times the right way to go
you can even provide them utility
functions that make it so that they can
build their random stuff out of your
random picking utility functions so that
you can provide you can even make it
easier for them to write that second
case but focusing on making it easier to
write the second case is often a better
choice than trying to write the first
case right so I don't know how close to
that map's to anything that you're
actually trying to do but I'm just
trying to say it's good to be when
you're writing library it's good to be
in that mindset of am I actually just
having to use or do something here that
they shouldn't even have to be doing
because it'd be way easier for them to
just do some other equivalent operation
that works more cleanly and could I then
provide library functions that make that
even easier to do because chances are I
probably can like with random picking us
up like that could I provide a lot of
good functions that are like pick one
out of N or pick dependency this to this
and step right like can I just drive it
functionally up there and a lot of times
where you see that mistake it made is in
data versus procedure a lot of times
what people will do in an API is they'll
make the mistake of thinking that's the
easiest way to make something complex is
by having the user create a bunch of
interconnected data objects and then
have all these callbacks on those data
objects right kind of like sort of the
things you were describing here but
oftentimes the easier way is to flip
that process upside down and say let the
user stay in charge let them create the
tree whatever the tree is using
functions that I use to make it simpler
that way they can drive the entire
process from the outside the classic
example of this
by the way I can describe it to you is
let's call it node graph disaster zone
so the classic things you see happen in
API is all the time is there like and
and I'm talking about stuff like
anything that's like a V processing
based falls into this trap all the time
no idea why it's like catnip for AV
processing people and they're like ah
all right so here's what we're going to
do we're making an audio API right now
an Audio API is like the simplest API in
the world
there are no api's that are simpler than
audio like console IO maybe maybe but
console i/o and audio are basically the
same problem because console I on audio
are both about one-dimensional input
output streams that that process out of
fixed cell size so it's it's almost
impossible in an easier ap adinath so
these you know audio api is there should
have been one of them it should have
been perfectly clean and we should all
have but used it for the past 30 years
instead we get into this node graph
disaster zone where it's like all right
all right here's we're going to do
people are going to create these like
interconnected webs of data nodes with
procedure calls like maybe on them and
it's going to create this like filter
graph thing that'll have like alright
there's an input source filter node and
it goes into like the reverb filter node
that goes into the chorus node and then
like the multiplexer node and then
that's going to like looper and you're
just like okay you look at the simple
tutorial for one of these things right
and the correct API tutorial would be
something like play food
right this is the one I would write you
know and they've got this 15 page
example program simple example program
that's like create wave source you know
you know a equals create routes of a
arrows source equals file source you
know a source and you know maybe this
maybe this takes that food out wave
right and then they're like okay B
equals create speaker you know guest or
something and be like you know probably
more there's a see here which is create
you know resampler or something and it's
like a out you know or like for like set
out of a to be you know the resampler
and set the out of C to be the speaker
and like and you're just like and then
all at the end then it's like there's
something like go you know if it maybe
plays your wav file like 15 years later
right and it's just there's a fetishism
that somehow arises about creating what
you believe to be data structures that
are themselves programs and you never
realize that just writing the program
would have been better right if the
person could have just written you know
load lab reverb waves
whatever it is you know well it's not
web it's like a equals reverb a chorus a
B equals multiplex a you know out a
right this is trivial for someone to
understand and they don't have to move
thinking about the structure that was
created because it works in the order
that it's shown and it's 100% stateless
right so I never have to
worried about stuff like Oh God like
wait a minute what if I wanted to change
this later like how do i I don't even
know I don't remember I gotta save all
these object pointers on all over the
place right so it's just don't just the
general concept here is like don't turn
something that's just a set of function
calls that could be a procedure that the
user can make their own tree if they
wanted to store this tree they could
just make this tree themselves and then
it's their structs with their own types
that can throw all the extra data they
want they can rearrange them however
they want they can do whatever they want
don't enforce the tree on the user let
the user enforce the tree on you and you
just provide them the tools to build it
can often be much more powerful right
so yeah all right so I'm going to wind
it down we've done about two hours here
I think I'm going to close this all
right whoo
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for a handmade chat I apologize we
couldn't do any programming today but
like I said based on the crash yesterday
I think we're going to take the time to
reset up the streaming setup or rebuild
the streaming setup so that we have
something where we've got a machine
that's not doing the streaming that's
the one we're doing the programming on
so it can crash and go down and do all
sorts of things and I will try to make
sure that's a machine that can run a
graphical to a GPU debugger on it which
i think is pretty important and would
allow us to simplify our lives when
we're doing our lighting development so
we'll make that happen it'll also be a
modern graphics card so we can use
opengl 4.5 if we want to or anything
else that's so we decide to do although
I don't think we should have to it seems
like we're relatively stable at three
three I don't know baby we won't be but
anyway so we'll take care of that and I
will see you folks back here once that
is we built like I said early in the
stream I will be away this coming
weekend so I won't be doing a stream
anyway which gives us the perfect amount
of extra time to try and get machine
parts delivered for the new streaming
setup so we'll do that and about two
weeks from now hopefully unless
everything goes disastrously wrong I
will be back on stream with a new setup
that we can use to keep working on the
lighting we were trying to finish up
before so thanks for joining me today
I'll see everyone back then in the
meantime if you do want to play route
the code again handmade hero or you can
always peer to the game it comes with
the source code if you want to play
around with it if you do want to stay
up-to-date with other folks who are
working on the product and ask questions
we have a forum site for that patreon
page transport the video series the
schedule bot the tweets will schedule at
you so you'll know if we are in fact
going to be back two weeks from now the
schedule bot will say so and an episode
guide if you need to catch up on old
episode series that's it for this week
see everyone back here in about two
weeks
have fun programming the meantime and
I'll see you on the Internet