word button and off we go okay hello
everyone and welcome to day two of the
handmade Hiro coding sessions yesterday
last night we learned how to basically
set up a dev environment so not terribly
exciting stuff but stuff that has to
actually happen and basically what we
did is we configure this command prompt
and we got it to the point where we
could launch our own editor which in
this case I am using Emacs but you can
use whatever you want to although the
Emacs file is included in the source
distribution if you would like to to try
it we started by making a little simple
win32 application here that just starts
up and launches a message box we made
the make file for it quote unquote which
is basically just a batch file that I
wrote which compiles something directly
into a build directory where we can run
it and we learned how to launch the
debugger which is Visual Studio
community 2013 if you have not already
downloaded it and we can do stuff like
step into our code and watch it run this
is handmade hero but a message box is
not a particularly useful thing for a
game to pop up in fact if you have seen
one pop-up in a game it usually means
that the game has encountered a very
serious error of some kind so what we
are going to do tonight is try to open a
window that is a little more useful and
what that kind of window is is we are
going to open basically just a standard
windows window because pretty much any
window that you're going to open in
Windows goes through the same sort of
path for opening it but then what we are
going to do is we're going to create a
special essentially buffer in memory
that we can write in to ourselves and do
all of our rendering into ourselves and
then we are going to show how to display
that buffer in the window now this is
not exactly how a modern game would
usually start up because modern games
often times or pretty much at this point
exclusively let the graphics card do all
the rendering for them and while that is
an interesting thing to do and something
that we will probably explore at the end
of the series when we are strictly
looking at performance optimizations and
we want to do things like play around
with out
that extra power that the GPU gives us
it is not particularly good for
educational purposes because the GPU is
basically an opaque resource where we
have very limited insight into what is
actually doing to render the graphics
for our game in fact a lot of the stuff
is just flat-out trade secrets that we
can't even know Nvidia won't tell us or
AMD won't tell us how the card is even
actually working unless we work there
and so that is the opposite of good for
education maybe good for competition in
the industry but not so good for
education so what we are going to do is
we're going to write the entire renderer
ourselves and in order to do that we
need a way to display something that we
have created rather than something that
is created on the graphics card okay so
we'll get to that part a little bit
later but for now the majority of our
work is just going to be how do we open
a windows window at all and even dating
back to the very very early days of
Windows the way that you have to start
out to open a windows is there's a thing
called a wind clasp and if you remember
from last time I said you have to get
very comfortable with using MSDN we are
going to search for wind clasp and you
will see that MSDN comes up as the first
hit and it has the definition of a wind
clasp and you know what I still don't
want to help MSDN improve right now I'm
on a live stream I cannot take the time
to do that I'm sorry so looking inside
the MSDN for wind class you can see that
it is a struct a good old sea structure
but it's got a little extra decoration
on it and I'm going to take a quick
second to explain what that is since we
will see it in all of these trucks that
we look up in MSDN so I want to cut
paste it in here and you can see that
instead of just a struct like this is
the Declaration of the struct right here
I actually cut it out there is the
struct right that's the actual structure
and if you remember from the intro
stream or if you're familiar with other
computer programming languages a struct
is basically just a record it's a
collection of variables that go together
and when you refer to one you're
referring to basically a memory layout
where each of these individual things is
sequentially ordered and usually stored
back-to-back but as we saw on the
interest ream depending on the sizes of
the
things that are in that struct they may
actually have padding in between them to
maintain what's called alignment and we
will be getting to alignment actually
potentially even later in the stream but
certainly tomorrow if not so I'm not
going to talk too much about alignment
right now but point being this is the
wind class struck and you will notice
that instead of being called wind class
which would look like this it is
actually called tag wind class and you
might wonder why that is
well the reason is because the windows
headers are trying to support basically
I want to say that they're trying to
support older versions of compliers I
guess because I don't think any current
versions of guitars have this problem
but it may also be because they've got
some kind of system that they're trying
to maintain or something like this but
basically what they want to do is they
want to support both C and C++
compilation now what happens in C++ is
that if you declare something struct foo
you can then immediately start using
food to refer to things of that
structure so if I do this and then I say
that I have one of these Foos
I basically use the word foo as if it's
just unannounced it's just a foo you
know what it is it's one of these struck
slight totally clear no ambiguity about
that but in C that was not true in
original C you could not use foo as a
word because it did not actually look up
the names of types when you did not
decorate them what you had to do is you
had to type struct foo right so that is
how you would have declared a individual
an individual one of these Foos
TARDIS that's how you declare an
individual foo is you would have to
preface it with struct now as C++ came
along they got rid of that but if you
are still compiling with C mode or
something like that they wanted to
support that with the windows header so
what they use is they use a thing called
a type def now a type def is just a way
of specifying a new name for some
existing type that can be specified so
for example if I wanted to make this
work which I had before I wanted to make
it so that I could type foo foo in C
well what I can do is I can say type def
foo - foo and basically what it does is
you're basically doing what is
essentially a variable declaration it
looks basically the same as a variable
you can even decorate it like a variable
declaration with Ray bounds or a point
or anything but basically we'll do is
it'll take the name and that name will
now refer to a type that is whatever the
type def was whatever the type death
says it was so if it's a food star then
capital foo you know what that is
actually what I meant to type sorry if
it is a struct foo pointer then
lowercase foo will now refer to a
pointer to foo and perhaps we should
even call that a P foo or something so
you can tell its point of view if I just
say struct foo foo then this basically
emulates what C++ is doing C++ is
automatically doing this so that we
never actually at the type struct foo we
just type lowercase foo and we get a
struct view in its place right so what
the windows headers are doing is they
have decided to basically compress all
of that into one very concise definition
which is they're saying type def struct
tag win class and then at the end of it
after they declare the structure the
type def write this is the type of the
type def they just put the struct
definition to write inline which are
allowed to do the type def then declares
two different types which you can do
with the comma it is basically saying
one type is wind class and the other
type is a pointer to a wind class and
they're going to call that P wind class
so this essentially creates two names
wind class which refers to struct tag
wind class and it creates P wind class
which refers to struct tag wind class
star very simple but that's just to
understand what you are seeing that is
what is going on and that's really all
there is to it now it's worth noting
that I believe there is no reason you
even need to name this truck you could
if you wanted to just get rid of the
name altogether and from now on refer to
the pointers as this and wind class as
the actual struct and you would be fine
so like I said why they put the tag wind
class in there I don't know it may be
some historical reason it may be to
support some kind of compiler thing they
need to do I do not know
I've never looked into it but this would
be the more concise way of doing what
they did which I believe works on all
modern compilers now but you know maybe
maybe in the old days it didn't who
knows we will certainly not go
spelunking to find out but
point is we now have our wind class type
that we want to define here and what we
are going to do is we are going to
define one of these wind class
structures and basically what they are
is in the win32 API this pattern happens
a lot what they do is they create a
struct and the struct is essentially
just the parameters to a function that
you're calling the structure is just a
way for you to fill out a set of of
informational variables that you will
then use when you call a function to
have that function sort of do things
with all of the settings and I think
they did it mostly I don't know if it
was for efficiency or if it was because
they just didn't wanted to make it
easier for you to fill things in but
basically what we were going to do is
we're going to fill in the members of
this with the values that we want for
our window so we are going to define our
window class here and because I'm not
going to want to set all of the actual
values here I am going to use a
initializer in C which we did not cover
in the interest REME what that is is
when you define a variable and I did
show you could do things like this in
the interest ream when you had a simple
a simple thing like if I had an int I
could initialize this way but what I did
not show is a struct a struct has lots
of value so you cannot simply say equals
5 it wouldn't mean anything what you can
do however is do
BRAC you know open in close braces and
then inside there you can actually
initialize all of the values so I could
put a condition my style here I can
visualize hope you if wind proc here
whatever these values were going to be
right I could initialize them and I can
visualize as many as I want and when I
stop all of the values that follow will
all be set to 0 automatically that's
just the way that it's defined to work
and see now spec has recently gone and
done some crazy stuff with this it used
to be that you could type this and that
was the way that you said basically I
want to initialize the first thing to 0
and the rest should all be initialized
to 0 as well and I think you still have
to do that if you're programming in C
but in C++ and again I'm not much of a
spec person anymore I think the C++ spec
is completely out of control but I
believe nowadays the actual way to say
I'm not going to initialize anything but
I would like you to
clear it all to zero for me is actually
just to put nothing in there and if you
put nothing in there then it basically
takes the entire block of memory that it
reserved on the stack for this window
class and it sets it all to zero which
is what I wanted so we are going to do
that and again I can show you the
compilation here we can go ahead in and
I compile that right in the editor I
should I should mention to those of you
who are using my Emacs file alt M does
the compile and basically what that does
is it will search from the directory
that you're in up directories until it
finds a build dot bat one of my handy
little build bat so it fine to build dot
back it will run it so that is this F
what we wanted in it bills are our thing
for us automatically so I am going to
run in here and you can see our window
class and if I go in here and I look at
the window class in the watch window we
can see that it is garbage it is just a
bunch of stuff it is not been
initialized yet you can see there is you
know all kinds of stuff in here that we
you know would not certainly want to to
pass to anything but when I step over
this line you will notice that it clears
absolutely everything to zero which is
what I wanted so all good now you will
see me do this a lot by the way if there
is not a performance concern in the code
that I'm working in I always use a thing
that I call zero is initialization and
we will see this come up a lot
but basically what I like to be able to
do is I like to be able to make it so
there is essentially no initialization
for most of my code most of it can just
be cleared to zero and as long as the
clear to 0 it will work when it goes
forwards I know that sounds a little
strange and it's very different from the
C++ model where everything has a
constructor and there's a lot of startup
B stuff going on but I won't really get
into how that all works because you'll
be seeing how it all works but I just
thought I'd point it out there because
we will be using this a lot in a bunch
of places so when there isn't a
performance concern where I really got
to be specific about how things are
getting initialized oftentimes clear to
zero is the way I'll go so off we go
what are the fields that I want well
there are a lot of fields in here and I
am going to initialize only some of them
the style is a set of binary
flags a bit filled basically that are
things that we want properties that we
want our window to have the LPF and wind
proc is a pointer to a function which
we'll get to in a second so we're going
to we're going to set that and that is
basically a pointer to the function that
we will define that defines how our
window responds to events CBC LS extra
is if we want to store extra bytes along
with the window class based our own
personal bytes we do not actually need
to do that so we are not going to use it
çb wind extra the same thing it is
basically allowing you to create extra
memory associated with your window that
you can use for whatever you want each
instance I believe we will have to set
because basically it used to know what
instance is setting setting the window I
don't know if you can short-circuit that
to zero and not bother studying it so
I'm going to check MSDN handle the
instance that contains a winner
procedure for the class looks like we
probably do there is no note on that I
don't know and I don't want to tempt
fate but thankfully we were passed an
instance right here this is the instance
out of our program it gets passed to win
main so we can put that in there and if
we do not want to this is a little handy
trick in Windows you can always call the
kernel and you can ask it for the H
instance of the currently running code
whoever you are it is a function called
get module handle and we won't really
need to use it right now but just so
people are aware that it is there if you
do not have the H instance lying around
if you did not save it from win main or
you aren't the person who wrote the win
main and you don't want to be that you
can call get module handle and instead
of passing it the name of some XE or DLL
that you would like to get a handle back
to you can actually just go ahead and
pass 0 so basically right here you could
call get module handle 0 and that would
actually work but we don't need to do
that because we actually got passed our
H instance but you might as well play by
the tightest possible version of the
rules we are not going to set an icon at
the moment but eventually for our game
we probably will want to so we're going
to leave that out for now we do not need
to set a cursor because we are you know
it's a game it's not going to have the
windows pointer floating around on it so
the cursor is going to be left 0 we do
not want to clear the background of our
of our window for us so I'm going to
leave HBR background unset that is if we
pass it what's called a brush we'll kind
of see you
those are in a little bit later to clear
the window for us we don't want to do
that because we're going to be doing our
own drawing finally there's the menu
name which is if your window is going to
have one of those little windows sort of
style menus up on it I don't even know
who has those these days everyone's
going with their fancy stuff okay here
there if you have one of these guys
that's that's how those get loaded in
one way that those could get loaded in
and we don't want that either but
finally we need a name for our window
class and the reason that we need a name
for our window class is because when we
actually go to create the window we will
need to be able to pass this name again
so that it can effectively create a
window using the class that we gave it
okay handmade hero window class that
seems like a pretty good name to me okay
so we are going to pass that and now we
just need to deal with these other three
right here so like I said always go to
MSDN there's no way you're going to
remember all of these things I don't
remember all of these things and I've
been pouring windows for a long time so
MSDN is your friend always go back and
look at it it will tell you what you
need to know so let's go back here to
the wind class and in the wind class we
have style it says it's a youant and
what a youant is is that's basically
just a type that windows has defined
using type def like before to basically
be a 32-bit unsigned integer so that is
basically just one of these right
that's all it actually is so we don't
really need to worry too much about
those windows just defines its own names
for all the types and we probably want
to do some stuff like that in the future
as well but that is exactly what that is
there so what you can see here is it
says the class styles this member can be
any combination of the class style and
it's clickable you want to click that in
there you will basically see a thing
that well well know I guess they've
added a double indirection now we will
go click on window class styles again
and finally we get to the actual flags
that you can set in this field for
Windows so CS vitelline client basically
this is the thing this is old school
this has to do with display modes you
know what I'm going to say what a bunch
of these
because we don't really need to know
what they are we don't need bite a long
time we don't need bite align window
those are those are basically
anachronistic at this point class DC is
something there's basically a thing
we're going to see in the future called
a DC we're going to see it very soon
because we actually need to use it to
draw to our window basically what a DC
is is it's a device context it's
something that windows uses to sort of
keep the state of drawing while we are
interfacing with it to draw to our
window and so class DC and there's also
own DC are both things that we sort of
need to be aware of for what we are
doing class DC and own DC in our case
are actually going to do the same thing
for the most part because we're only
going to have one window but the
difference between them is basically
that normally windows just has these
device contexts sitting around inside
windows and when people need to draw
stuff they get one they use it and give
it back that's how it works it's kind of
a weird system but that's how it works
and what these flags do is they
basically say look I'm going to be doing
a bunch of graphic stuff I don't want to
deal with any overhead there might be
with sharing these device concepts for
when I want to draw things so class DC
says I want my own device context for
any window that's created with this
window class and own DC says I want my
own DC for every individual window now
that's technically the one that we want
I'm going to go ahead and put that in
there it's probably not necessary these
days computers are so fast it's kind of
old school to ever specify that but I'm
going to specify it anyway because you
know what for old times sake let's go
ahead and specify it and what that
basically means is we will not have to
get and release DC s for our windows if
we don't want to because we always have
our own DC that we can just use okay and
class EC would basically have done that
same thing because we're only ever going
to create one window with this class but
it's kind of a little disingenuous
because if we were going to create
another window for some reason with the
same window class we would want it to
have its own DC as well all right so we
basically have a CSH redraw and chv CSV
redraw are flags that tell Windows when
it needs to repaint our window
when they are dragged around to
horizontally or vertically and honestly
I haven't thought about those in a long
time you know reflexively I type this
pretty much only always I always specify
those like redraw the window when it
gets moved around but you know I've
never really thought about whether I
still need them anymore so maybe that's
something that while we're on here I'm
going to go ahead and put a little
marker in this code you can see I have a
thing in Emacs that highlights any time
I type to do so I can kind of see where
it is let's go ahead and highlight that
and say check if H redraw V redraw own
DC still matter because we can go in
afterwards it might be fun on some
stream when we're just going through and
doing some interesting explorations we
might want to go ahead and check and see
how important any of these things even
are anymore or if they're just old
things that I always do because it's the
way I always did them and that was that
so a lot of these are the things like
sends double-click messages you know you
can look through here and you could see
all these sorts of things save that save
bits which which tries to restore the
windows and these are all like that most
of these things are just antiquated and
you don't really need to use many of
them we may not even really need to use
the ones that we're even using but
anyway there we go we have a win window
classname we have our instance filled
out we have our Flags filled out so the
only thing we need to do now is actually
define a window procedure and this is
the thing that will handle all of the
messages coming from windows which I'll
show you what those aren't sight that
pertain to us ok so what is that and how
would you have known what that was if I
wasn't here to tell you well here is an
example of again how MSDN can help you
if you go into LP FN wind proc you will
see a thing that says a pointer to the
window procedure you must use the call
window prop function to call the window
procedure for more information see
window proc well if I go ahead and click
on window proc you will see that it
actually defines exactly what the
procedure is right there which is what I
wanted to know and so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to go ahead and cut that
out this is the callback which is the
phrase callback is exactly what it
sounds like it is a thing where windows
calls us back from its code to have us
do something for it and you can see
right here what the parameters are to it
the
gets past an H wind we don't know what
that is yet a unsigned integer it gets
past a w pram and L pram all totally
mysterious to us we have not really
dealt with any of these because even the
unsigned integer which we now know is
just an unsigned 32-bit integer we don't
know what it means so what we're going
to have to do is look at MSDN and see
what that stuff is but for now we know
that this is our main window callback
this is the callback that will be called
any time we have a window of this class
that windows needs to send something to
to have it do something and we'll see a
little bit more about that in the future
so what I like to do and this will
probably frustrate a lot of people so
it's just what I like to do you don't
have to do it I hate all their little
prefixes and weird names as far as I'm
concerned this is instance this is pre
vincent's this is command line and this
is show code so I'm just going to go
ahead and just flat-out rename those
things because I don't like to look at
their weird naming convention any more
than I absolutely have to and the same
is true up here I happen to know what
these things are so I am going to name
them what I want to see them called
which is message window and then just
changing the capitalization scheme there
and what you need to understand here is
that function signatures in C and C++
are really only about the types a
function signature the definition of
that function only depends on the types
that you're trying to pass it the H win
the u into the wpm the L print that part
the name of the parameter is up to you
so even though Windows is the person
who's calling us it's only the fact that
it receives these four specific things
that are important it does not care what
they are called so you can change them
to be called anything that you want
whatever you want them to be called
literally any name here is fine so you
should name things whatever makes it
easiest for you to read and that is what
I like to read so that is what I have
called it now if we go in here we can
see the definition of these things
basically we have an H win which is a
handle to a window H win stands for a
handle window basically and what that is
is that's just a opaque thing we cannot
really look at it at all but it is an
opaque piece of data that we can pass
back to Windows that allows it to know
which window we are talking about so it
passes it to us and says hey here is the
window handle if you need to talk to me
about your window handle
just go ahead and pass this back and
I'll know what you mean pretty simple
there the youant the message so
basically what this is is this is the
message that Windows is asking us to
handle it is going to call us back with
a variety of different things and what
we need to do is we need to go look at
what those things are so system to find
messages here is the list and basically
as you can see over the ages it has
grown to be absurdly huge the number of
things that you can receive now most of
the ones that we care about are not
these kind of things animation control
messages combo boxes all this sort of
stuff since we are not going to be using
Windows hardly at all we are basically
just opening a window and then we are
doing everything else ourselves most of
the things that we care about are very
simple basic window operations that we
need to respond to so they all fall
under the WM category and we will not
really need much from anything else in
here a lot of these things are for if
you want to use the windows standard
control such as track bars the tasks you
know like these sorts of things where
you see like windows standard controls
buttons that you click on if you want to
use their standard controls they all
have special message codes that they
will pass back and forth you and stuff
like that but we're not going to be
doing in that if we make a button we'll
be implementing ourselves so we don't
need to call them so we are going to be
dealing in here and at first basically
what we need is just our window messages
excuse me so I'm going to go ahead and
look in here and see if there's anything
in particular that we want to handle I
think we may simply want just like a few
simple things yeah okay so the ones that
I think we want to handle at start here
and I'm going to use the switch
statement that I discussed in the intro
stream the switch statement of course
allows us to take any value and switch
to see basically if it equals any
constant that we want to input so here I
am going to use these codes which are
defined in Windows to be constants they
are specific numbers basically that will
be used to say which message is coming
in and I am going to field for example
the WM size command which is when the
user changes the size of the window I am
also going to field probably the W
and destroy command which is when
Windows deletes our window and also
perhaps I will field the WM close
message which is basically what happens
when the user clicks on that little X up
in the corner of the window and finally
I think I may also do just at the
beginning here I made you activate app
which is basically thing that lets us
know whether the user has clicked in us
and we are the active window or not and
now you'll remember I also said back in
the intro stream if the thing that we
are switching on does not fall into one
of the constant categories that we have
defined using case statements we can go
and actually use a default statement to
catch up all of the extra slack now what
you are seeing here probably for the
first time because I have not used this
in the interest dream is the way that I
write case statements which is a little
unusual the way I like to write case
statements is I like to actually put a
basic block in there just to find my own
block that is not required that is the
normal way the case statement looks and
this is the code that goes in it right
there but what you will find if you use
case statements often is that if you
actually define variables in here those
variables will propagate out to the
other cases because they are all in the
same block which is this one up here so
if I have it in X I could refer to it
down in here even though I did not mean
for that to happen which could be a
mistake that I would rather prevent so I
always bracket my case statements unless
I have a really good reason not to do so
and then I go ahead and put the break
outside most people put the break inside
a lot of times it will look like this I
don't do that I just think it looks a
little nicer if it just looks like a
standard basic block and the break goes
outside I also find it helps to keep it
from mixing with the other code it
accidentally so that's the way I do it
not really necessary you could put that
break wherever you want so okay here we
have the things that we are going to
actually watch for right now we are
actually not going to handle any of them
actually what we are going to do instead
is we're going to use the thing that I
told you about in the original intro
stream where I was talking about how we
can output stuff to the debug stream
that shows up in the debugger I am just
going to go ahead and print out
when I get any of these messages so the
only thing that I'm going to do is just
print this stuff out that's it nothing
else is going to happen in here right
that's it just these things okay and you
know what mmm i'ma gonna print out the
default cuz there's gonna be a ton of
messages that flood in there I don't
think I'm going to for another default
well oh it's so tempting let's go ahead
and put that in there and then we'll
just turn it on in a second we're going
to turn it on at first so if you
remember from the intro screen output
debug string is basically just a call
that allows you to output something to
this window over here this window right
here it will show up in the debugger we
can watch it and it's a good way when we
are just starting a Windows program and
we do not have anything implemented we
can not really log anything we can't use
any of our own debug services that we
may have written to do debugging it is a
good way to kind of bootstrap things
because it will be a nice little place
to print things out as you go and you
know that that code got executed so now
you will notice that there is an L
result an L result is returned from this
okay and when an L result is is an L
result is basically just a return code
something that we return back to say
what we basically did with the message
so each one of these messages Windows
has certain meanings that it will resign
to that it will assign to what we return
and if you look in MSDN you can actually
see what those are so you go in here and
it'll basically say if an application
processes the message it should return
zero right so basically what that's
saying is if we actually handle the
message which in this case I suppose we
did we should return zero so what I'm
going to do instead is I'm just going to
set result equal to zero and assume that
we handled the message because the next
thing that we have to do to finish our
window procedure is we have to basically
do a catch-all to handle all the
messages that we don't handle and in
there I am going to assign result right
I'm going to assign that return value
and I got to obviously return the return
value here eventually as well from the
function I am going to assign to that
return value basically the result of
calling Windows is default window
callback which they have defined and
what that
it's a catch-all that says if you don't
want to worry about particular messages
you can call me and I handle all the
messages in whatever the default way is
so it's basically like saying okay I am
sort of the first person on the food
chain for these messages my main window
callback will be the one who looks at
the messages and goes is it one of these
four that I care about but if it's not
one of the four that I care about I can
go ahead and pass it on to Windows and
let it do the default behavior and as
you'll see we may actually even want to
do that for some of these messages and
other messages we might handle in the
future we may still even want to call
the default window procedure even when
we do handle a message because we may
just want to do something extra than
what it does if that makes sense so the
default window procedure is documented
in all of these things basically and
it's just called def window proc you can
click on it and see its definition and
as you might expect it looks absolutely
identical to well that is if my internet
is still working let's hope that it is
since we've been having problems today
with it yeah I need to get some some
kind of guaranteed internet so my stream
can't be interrupted if that's possible
anyway the default window procedure is
literally exactly the same function
signature as ours only instead of it
being a callback where windows calls us
it is a win API which means that we are
calling it now call back and win API I
mentioned them a little bit in the intro
stream they are decoration that
specifies a calling convention we have
not gotten to calling conventions yet so
I'm going to kind of defer talking about
what those are for a little while but
otherwise you can see that it's exactly
the same it returns an L result which is
basically just again it's just an
unsigned integer I believe is all or
might be a signed integer let's take a
look we can actually take a look at what
L result is actually defined to be in
the windows headers so inside here
windows data types it does look like
it's signed there come on MSDN you can
do it I know you can return it there we
go
so if you come in here windows data
types it will actually tell you what
they all are you can actually see the
pound defines that specify the actual
literal value of these things so if we
go to an L result you can see that it's
defined to be a long pointer
okay that is not what I was expecting it
to be but I guess they want you to be
able to return pointer values in there
which means it will actually potentially
be 64 bits on our device I guess you
know what since that's interesting to me
let's pause for one second and let's
take a look let's see what's going on
here
size of L result oh you know what I
don't even have to do that here we can
just go ahead and kind of pause what we
were doing right all of this would still
be valid code looks like valid code to
me so let's go ahead and build that
everything builds fine and I'm just
going to go exploring so we go in here
this is our well you know I don't even
think I need to do that let's go in here
let's see if I can take it the size of
it right here or if it's close to pound
fine yeah there we go
so size of L result returns eight which
as you remember it's all invite so that
means eight bytes which means 64 bits
which is exactly what we thought when we
saw a long pointer so basically what
they've done here is they have said okay
main window callback returns something
that is 64 bits and that way they could
return probably the reason they're doing
that because that way they can return
anything any single value that they want
to including a pointer to something
which because we are compiling in 64-bit
mode you remember VC varis 32 we called
in fact I can show you right here in the
misc shelled up at remember this little
guy here compiling in 64-bit mode well
that's what that means
since our memory 64-bit address space
need 64-bit pointers something we'll be
getting to later because we don't
actually need to worry too much about
the size of things but point being since
windows wants us to be able to return
things that are pointer size it needs
full 64 bits there even if we don't use
the full 64 bits for most messages it
needs to be big enough to handle the
return value of the biggest message so
that is good to know I think the last
time I really seriously thought about
window procedures it was still in 32-bit
windows and those were 32 bits long so
hey there's 64 bits now the times they
are a-changin so we are going to go here
at head and call def window proc it is
just a pass-through and we are going to
pass it the exact parameters that we
were given we have no idea what they
mean we don't care we figure it we'll
figure it out so all we will have to do
is figure out what the parameters mean
for these messages so that we can handle
them alright so now we will compile this
just to make sure we haven't done
anything wrong everything compiles fine
no errors and what we're going to do now
is we're going to open a window using
the window class but in order to do that
we of course have to do what's called
registering the window class so the way
that that works is we use a thing called
register window class or register wind
class I don't remember the thing let's
let's take a look here don't remember
the exact spelling of register wind
class register window class register
class see register class that's what we
want so I was wrong in both guesses
register class we are going to go ahead
and register class and register class
just takes a pointer to our window class
the window class that we are trying to
register now you notice it returns
something called an atom and you may ask
what is an atom well an atom was just
something that was used in the old days
windows I mean they're still around but
you almost never actually use them they
were basically things used in Windows to
sort of memento as to like remember a
particular string value or if value you
wanted to refer to again and in fact I
don't know if I can I can find an actual
let me see if I can find an actual thing
to show you here where you just register
an actual atom
uh that's let me let me take a look you
know what I because I think if I dig
deep into the old thing here let's let's
let's take a look query cancel autoplay
example I think that will show us an
example of that let's take a look let's
take a look yes so here was a typical
one for example that I remember being an
atom based thing if I am not very much
an error is it not no all right
darn alright I do not know then I do not
know a good example of something where
we're still going to use an atom racking
my brain I'm sorry I can't think of it
someone in the chat probably knows and
it really isn't that important so we're
not going to dwell on it for now but
point being we probably will not see
atoms much at all you you used to use
them for things like and like I said
we're not going to use these but you'd
get an atom back if you wanted to
register a named property that you could
associate with a window and other things
like this but we have no need for any
that stuff
so racking my brain again but I can't
think of a canceled autoplay might
be one but I can't think of anything
that we're going to do besides this one
call that actually uses an atom and
we're not even going to use the atom
we're just going to register the class
and that's all we're probably going to
do so we go ahead and register this
window class registering the window
class technically could fail and so we
could check to see whether when the atom
comes back at least I think that it can
fail let's take a look
function of seeds let's see do two to
function fails return values zero so
technically if we want to we can just
double check to make sure that this
succeeds it never actually in practice
fails but if it does you know if we want
to start being correct once we actually
build a nice little logging system in an
error system which we will be getting to
later on we may want to log that why not
for complete mistake I don't know how we
will ever test it probably I guess we
could test it by registering the window
class twice because I think maybe it
would fail now we'll probably just
return it's the same atom again well I
don't know we can try anyway once we
register the window class we can then
create something of the window class we
can ask it to create a window for us and
this will be our window handle we can
call create window and create window is
a function that will create a window of
some class that you specify now we want
met want to specify extra things to it
so there's actually two versions as the
old version which is create window and
there's a new version which create
window X which has a few more parameters
so we're going to use the newer version
which is create window X which is just a
sort of a newer version of it and we are
going to call that oops there we go we
are going to call that to create our
window so here we go create window X
there we go and we are going to fill out
much like we did with the structure even
though this one is not structured you
know I'm just going to go ahead and do a
rectangular kill there to get rid of all
those guys there we go so I'm going to
use this to basically create the window
I'm going to pass it all the things that
it asks for now extended style is
another one of those bit fields like we
saw up here where you order together a
bunch of bits that tell you what style
you want I don't think we want any of
those styles just yet but we can double
check in here here's extended window
styles that we can go in here again MSDN
being so slow
a real bummer it is kind of slowing down
the stream in an unfortunate way so I'm
actually going to sort of preload a few
of those here okay here we go
so the extended files except files if
you want drag and drop we don't really
want that top of a window in the taskbar
client edge posited I don't really know
paint all descendants from bottom up
order doesn't really seem like this much
here we want we're not layer window
we don't need left alignment scroll bars
and you know activate bla bla bla bla
bla bla bla bla bla I don't think we
need any of these right now so we are
just going to pass zeroes the extended
style the class name is of course the
class that we just registered so we're
just going to go ahead and straight-up
pass it out of the the struct that we
had filled out before the window name
for now is going to be handmade hero
until we have some other reason for
changing that and now we get to the
actual window style which we do want
specify and there's a whole bunch of
things you can say like whether or not
the window has a border whether it has a
caption on it you know all sorts of
things like this but we probably don't
need to worry too much about those
because there is a aggregate style that
basically just creates a default window
that has the standard stuff that you
usually want to have on it so we are
just going to specify that which is an
aggregation of all of these different
flags that we might want to use right
all good so we're going to do that and
the other thing we're going to specify
at the moment which we may retract later
because we may want to create it
invisible first and then do some
shenanigans but we are also going to
best W specify WS visible because if we
say otherwise
it may not start visible I don't
remember overlapped windows because of
some interaction of the flags actually
will automatically do this when you
create them but normally when you create
a window it is invisible and waits for
you to show it and we are not going to
quite do that yet so now we can pass X Y
width and height for the window and what
we are going to do there is we are
actually going to pass this special
value called CW use default normally you
would actually specify the coordinates
of on the screen that you would want to
do and we don't want to really talk
about coordinates just yet because that
is something we're going to talk about
later so we're just going to pass use
default which just says open this window
on the screen anywhere that you want to
and I believe we could do that for the
width and height as well yes we can so
that will take care of for us parent
window is if you want to have windows
inside windows which we do not want to
have so we do not need to do that we can
passes zero for that and it will assume
that we are just a top-level window that
is on the desktop we do not have a menu
so we don't need that we have an
instance so we're going to go ahead and
use that instance and we do not need to
pass anything to our window there is a
way that you can basically pass a
parameter to the window if you were to
pass something here as this last
parameter it would basically come in
during a message called WM create that
comes in here oops I can't spell
properly WM create that comes in here
and you would get that value if you want
to do something special with it okay so
this is basically all we need really to
start up and if we check our window
handle when it comes back we can see
down here in the return values if the
function see the return value is a
handle to the new window the Flex fails
return value is null now null happens to
be equal to zero
so we can actually just do an if on the
value and that will be the same as
checking for now some people love to
actually type the word null all the time
just in case null changes from being
defined to be zero to be something else
I don't love it so I don't but if you
are the kind of person who really cares
about something like that you would type
this we're not going to do that okay
same deal here this will almost never
fail in any practical circumstance but
if we have a nice error handling system
that we will develop in the future
we may want to start handling that so
I'm going to mark that with to do just
so we know there's something to do there
now once we get in here we have one last
thing to do before we will show our
window on the screen and that is that we
need to start a message loop windows
does not by default start sending
messages to your window unless you
actually start pulling them off of
what's called a queue and the way this
works is anytime you have an application
in Windows it creates a queue of
messages for you that essentially starts
filling up with messages that Windows is
trying to send you or anyone else who's
trying to send you a message through the
windows system for that matter and what
we need to do is we need to loop through
our messages and we need to extract them
so that we can send them to our window
and the way we're going to do that
temporarily is we're going to use that
with the get message function now what
the get message function does is that
basically allows us to pull messages off
of our queue and if there are no
messages in the queue it will just
sit there and wait now it takes a
pointer again I don't know if you
remember me discussing in the original
screen that basically Windows likes to
use Hungarian notation so LP means long
pointer so instead of writing this which
would be much clearer in the function
signature they write this and make you
have to know that P means pointer it's
annoying but that is the way Windows
works so this is just an MSG which is
another struct that we will look at in a
second and that is an MSG pointer so we
are going to take the address of that
and pass it to window so it knows where
to put the message that it retrieves we
are going to pass the window handle
actually you know what we're not going
to pass the window handle because if we
have any other windows or messages not
bound we may want to get them so we can
actually pass zero for that or no which
will retrieve messages from any window
that belongs to us so that's kind of
handy so we'll just grab all of the
messages that are coming in and these
two filters here filter min and Max are
if we're only looking for specific kinds
of messages which we're not we're
looking for all the messages that might
be bound for our window because we might
want to process them so what we can do
there is we can pass essentially dummy
values to that to make sure that we get
all of them let's see how that actually
works here I forget the magic
incantation these are values for service
messages use W if you are both 0 get
veterans all available messages so
basically what we want to do is just
pass all zeros of this function
essentially and that will be what we
want to do now we want to keep going we
want to be doing this for a very long
time and as you can see it says if the
function retrieves a message other than
WM quick the return value is nonzero and
WM quit is the thing that would
basically be someone's posting a message
to our application telling it to exit so
what we would like to do is basically
keep running until get message returns
false right if it wasn't a WM quit now
this is not exactly how we will use our
message loop in the future so this is a
little bit of a stand-in so date don't
take anything I'm saying here
too seriously because yes you can see
this here the possibility of a negative
1 return value in the case that h1 is an
invalid parameter means that such code
can lead to fatal application errors
instead use code like this you can see
that they've they've written it here
this was the thing that I was referring
- we're actually not going to using get
message so we don't have to worry about
too much about this but at the risk of
somebody like looking at this and doing
the wrong thing maybe we'll just do it
like this just even to start off on the
right foot like I said we won't actually
be using this in the future that looks
like I've got a oh I did it again I said
I would never use Mira torii for on the
stream sorry didn't mean to do that
all right there we go there's our four
statement so we are going to go ahead
and take a look at get message here it's
funny that it says bool but it says it
can return a negative one it's kind of
fantastic right yeah what are you going
to do ladies and gentlemen but basically
what we'll do here is we'll say this is
the message result that we're going to
get back it comes and then we will check
on the message result to make sure that
it is above zero if it is above zero
then we will handle it otherwise we will
break out of our out of our loop here
and exit so that should be fine now I'm
curious to know what they actually
define bool to be they must define it to
be a integer type of some kind because
if rule was really only a boolean
somehow which it Odyssey can't be
because that wouldn't probably work in
in old's old-school sea but if that was
a boolean of some kind then we would not
be able to test it for a negative value
so I'm assuming that's an in I guess we
don't need to look it up right now but
point being I was doing pool is actually
some kind of an integer that they'd find
that all right so we are going to check
here if if we get this then what we have
to do is we have to tell Windows to
actually translate and dispatch this
message now the this is total windows
minutia basically what it does is
translate message is a thing that turns
keyboard messages into more proper
keyboard messages we do not have to
worry about this at all right now but we
will have to think about it a little bit
later because basically what we have to
do is we have to field keyboard messages
in the future and we will want them to
be translated properly now for games it
may never actually matter about a mystic
that in there anyway so ignore this for
now it's a thing that basically takes a
message that came in off of the message
queue does some processing on it and
gets it ready to actually send it out so
here we go that dispatch message
the function that will actually send
messages to windows that have them and
you can see it's just a thing that again
actually dispatches the message now
these things technically return error
codes but we have no way of actually
handling the error codes if Windows did
not want to dispatch one of this
messages there's nothing we can do about
it so there's probably not much point in
actually checking these we could exit
the application but that seems like a
little draconian just for failure so I'm
not sure what we would do there we could
log it maybe we could log it in the
future but I don't really even know if
that's necessary so this will go ahead
and loop forever until we get back
something other than a positive result
from get message let's go ahead and
compile that we have some undefined
errors we undefined code there in them
in CSU's default so for some reason that
was not there why so I got that straight
out of create window did I not so I
wonder why that was not recognized did I
spell it wrong or something let's find
out
so I wanted to pass si oh it's CW I used
class style that was that's up in here
for CS i was i was like CSM to see this
is CW which is I guess for window create
window let's say I don't know who knows
how they name things but they name them
so there we go
if we go over here and run our program
well got to unset that breakpoint first
but you will notice that we finally have
a window on the screen there is our
lovely window and if we go over here and
look at the debug output you will see
that we got our window messages there
they are
activate app WM size and that was
because as I go ahead and drag around in
here I'm generating tons of WM size
messages if I click on this we will get
the WM close message as you can see and
we will never get a WM destroy message
no matter what we do because that would
have to come basically from something
that was going to forcefully try to
close the window normally we would be
calling that ourselves so there you go
we have a window on the screen so now
what we would like to do obviously is we
would like to draw something to it just
to prove that we finally have a window
that actually has something on it and
the way that we can do that is we can
feel the message called WM paint
so inside WM paint there we go
we are going to use that DC thing that I
was talking about so basically what we
can do inside WM paint is we can go
ahead and ask windows to allow us to
paint to our window using their graphics
API because on Windows if we're painting
to a window we have to use it and so
what they have is they have a thing
called begin paint and end paint which
allow us to say we are about to update
our window here it is right and then we
are going to go ahead and use and paint
to tell it when we are done so here we
go - oops it was right there and just
click on it and paint there it is so we
are going to go into n paint there we go
and we're going to pass that window
handle that we came in that we got here
we're going to pass our window handle we
are going to pass the address of a
paints truck all right let's see paint
that it can fill out for us and it is
going to return one of those contacts
for us one of those device contacts so
let's take a little documentation of
that so we understand what's going on
inside begin paint we pass it the window
that we are trying to paint right here
right the handle to the window to be
repainted and we pass it a pointer to
one of these paints trucks which is
another one of these trucks that Windows
uses to pass information back and forth
it's passing it out to us this time so
what it's going to do is it's going to
fill this out with a bunch of
information that we need such as a
rectangle structure which tells us where
we need to paint a thing which says
whether or not should be erased this
sorts of stuff whether it's an
incremental update those sorts of things
we're not allowed to test those those
are internal to the system as you can
see here labeled that way but we are
going to go ahead and filled that in a
relatively straightforward way so we're
going to do that and then n paint of
course just takes the window and the
paints truck back so that it knows which
that you know just basically to close
off the paint there we go so all we are
going to do is we are going to do a pat
blit padlet is a function which
basically just tells windows it's sort
of a graphics utility which basically
tells it to do blackness or whiteness or
do some kind of another bit operation to
things so we just want to fill our
window with white for now that's going
to be a very simple thing for us to do
just so we can see
we are painting to our window the way
that we want to okay device context
passes the device context that we're
painting with it takes the left the size
of the window right which we already
actually will we do know what it is I'll
show you what it is in a second and then
eventually it takes a flag that says
sorry a value these are constants right
whiteness blackness DST invert these are
constants defined in the windows H and s
already sorted header files that t'elp
applet what kind of fill it should do to
the rectangle that we are going to
specify now what is the rectangle well
fortunately for us we actually know what
the rectangle is because we got it back
from begin paint remember when I said
inside begin paint there was this paint
struct here and this paint struct
basically tells us what we need to know
the RC paint if you go down and look at
the documentation for that is a rect
structure that specifies the upper left
and lower right corners of the rectangle
in which the painting is requested right
so we basically have in here after we do
that we have a rectangle we can go paint
our C paint like that and we can access
its members now what are the members of
erect they are what you might expect the
left the top the right and the bottom
positions of that rectangle right so min
and Max on X&amp;Y again don't worry too
much about coordinate systems we'll be
covering them in the next stream more
approximate even the string after that
and they are lungs which are just yet
again another definition for int windows
has a ton of definitions for integers
depending on what size they are or what
exactly they correspond to but these are
basically just integer values as we will
see when we step into this code so when
we do Pat blit let's go back to Pat blit
when we did Pat blitt oops that's the
one we actually want there it is it
needs a left it needs a basically the
left the top it is the width and the
height but we didn't have the width and
height in our rec structure we have the
right and the bottom which are maxes so
we have to subtract right from left and
bottom from top to get that width we
want to see how big those are so we're
going to have to do that right we're
going to have to do bottom and like this
- top right and we're going to have to
do right - left in order to get
those widths and Heights that we wanted
right oops
backwards height is going to be that one
and width right and then we already know
what our x and y are right because we
already know that our that our X is this
and you know what I'm going to should
probably pass ones that Pat but once
those are lungs in the air but the
defined events here so we might as well
convert them out to ends like I said
Windows has so many definitions for in
sits kind of a rat's nest most of its
historical at this point but what are
you gonna do we have the X and y for a
for the the recti light so we can go
ahead and do it wit height there we go
nice and clean see how we compile pat
blitt well we know how to deal with this
right taught you in the last stream if
something if an import symbol is not
defined we go down to the bottom here we
take a look at who it was and we grab
that library GDI 32 dot Lib is what we
need for pep lit so we are going to go
into our build up bat and stick it on
the end there we go compile and done now
when we run we should see a white window
ladies and gentlemen pretty nice huh
it's lovely
totally lovely absolutely fabulous that
is the best white window that I bet you
have ever seen now just to prove how
awesome we are because you know that we
are why don't we do something absolutely
ridiculous here why don't we just do
sometimes they'll paint it with black
and sometimes they'll paint it with
white because there is blackness and
there was whiteness right so what I
could do is like a look at pop put here
go up here and this is just a little a
little amusing diversion
that's a D word that it wants is the
last thing so what we're going to do
here is going to take our D word which
is our operation we are going to sign it
to whiteness right but I'm going to use
the static keyword now what the static
keyword is is normally every variable is
local to us right every variable is
local to where we defined it remember I
said these blocks these braces the
variables are local to us but what I'm
going to do is I'm actually say you know
what I want this variable to persist I
want you to create it and I want it to
stick around so that when I come back
through here
it will actually be set to whatever it's
the the value was the last time we ran
this thing so it's basically creating
permanent storage essentially a global
variable it's almost like we were to
declare it out here as a global variable
but unlike a global variable it is
locally scoped to this area in terms of
lexical like it lexically scoped meaning
that we can't refer to it anywhere else
so it keeps it kind of contained but it
is global now I never ever ever ever use
these they're a very very very very bad
idea in code that I actually need to
ship but I always use them when I am
debugging because it's very handy to be
able to stick something in really
quickly that is there and this is F what
I'm doing right now I just want to debug
something to make sure that we are
actually painting our window every time
so I'm going to use one now but I never
use these basically because they create
nightmares for thread safety and all
sorts of other stuff so we will see a
little more of that later but don't do
this
willy-nilly this is something I'm only
doing right now for debugging purposes
so basically what'll happen is the first
time we come through here when you sees
this this static what it will do is it
will initialize operation to whiteness
but the rest of the times through it
will not initialize it only the first
time through will it original eyes it to
whiteness the rest of the times it will
just leave it at whatever value it was
so what that means is we can every time
we go through here after we do this
clear like this we can go and say if the
operation was whiteness right remember
the if statements from our intro stream
we can then set it to blackness and if
it was not equal to whiteness we will
set it back to whiteness which will
basically create a toggle so when it
comes to through here and it's set to
whiteness it'll turn to black wet set to
black he'll turn to white and they'll
toggle back and forth and back and forth
and back and forth right good we hit run
we get our white window which is what we
expect we then drag it and there we go
don't know if the stream can keep up
with that but we are basically creating
a Epilepsy window that just to
demonstrate when we are we drawing the
window pretty good for One Nights work
at only an hour so hopefully that is
enough to tide you over till tomorrow
when we will field these messages a
little more appropriately and we will
actually create a bit
app that we can blitt to our window
which will take it up to the point where
we can actually start to use it to
render our game which is what we need so
I hope that was a good enough quick
introduction of how to get a Windows
window onto the screen within the space
of an hour there's only so much we can
do but we will be going through tomorrow
and flushing this out in more detail and
getting a nice proper window that we can
actually use for rendering our game in
good shape so thank you so much everyone
for joining me I will pause the stream
now and we will go ahead and answer Q&amp;A
s as soon as I toggle the recording