hello everyone welcome to handmade Hero
show recode a complete game live on
stream we have some debugging to do
today
what we'd like to do is put a bunch of
art in the game because we have the
opportunity to do that now and we just
have to finish up our art pipeline stuff
that is I think mostly written but it's
not necessarily working we have to go
through and debug a bunch of stuff and
there's a couple ways we can do that one
of the things that I'd like to do today
is actually do a little bit of adding
code to debug it's not new code that we
actually are gonna use in the game but
I'd like to make a little more debug
infrastructure that we can use and so
let me talk a little bit about what I
mean by that so right now what we're
doing and if I remember correctly from
last week what we were doing was just
saying look we would like to do tagging
and finding of assets but what we saw is
well actually it kind of worked but it
kind of didn't because you can see we
definitely loaded some stuff in but
there's a couple things we can see first
of all we're upside down which we do
kind of expect because pngs
are backwards from how our textures are
they go the first when you start to
decode a PNG the first row of pixels
that you get in a PNG because member we
wrote the PNG reader on stream so we're
going full-bore here the first row of
pixels in a PNG is actually the top like
physical top of the thing so you know if
you were to look at something like a
human the head would be on that first
row of pixels right would be where that
starts the feet would be down where the
last row of pixels is right but that's
not how textures work in 3d hardware in
3d hardware when you think about what's
that is the zero so the first row that
you would submit that's actually the
bottom physically of the texture so it's
it's difficult to talk really about
those things constructively because what
the other thing you have to remember in
3d is since it's a world and you're just
talking about mapping
into the world top and bottom is really
more conventional than anything else but
we chose the convention that we will
stick with the standard math axis which
is that Y goes upward not downward right
if we had chosen to go with the
convention where Y goes downward then we
would agree with PNG in the sense that
PNG has zero and then increasing values
of Y increasing row indices go down
right so you have to understand all of
these things in your head I know it's
difficult but this is where these sorts
of problems come from and obviously we
have this situation where we have to
make all these things line up so what I
mean by the upside down thing being
expected is this is something I knew we
would deal with me it's not a shock to
me that the things came in upside down
because that's just something we have to
deal with so we have to decide how
exactly we want to handle that and so on
that's not particularly concerning what
does concern me is the blue tone I do
not understand where that's coming from
that's a weird one so we have some
debugging to do there and then I think
we've got one other thing to worry about
here which is that we also have a bug
with our picking so the way we're
setting up the tags are picking with the
tags is wrong so we have a couple bugs
that we want to look into and I don't
know that they're going to be
complicated but what I do know is this
is the sort of thing that could get
complicated quickly why because we have
many steps in the process the artist
makes a PNG the PNG like exported from
Photoshop right so really they make a
Photoshop thing then they export a PNG
from that that PNG is loaded into our
game by our decoder and loader right it
is then packed into a uniform data
format that has some meta information on
it so that we can quickly load where it
is and know what it is so that we don't
have to like iterate over everything
every time we start the game and look at
all the P and G's we have or anything
like this right so we've got that and
then we've got the actual runtime code
that looks through what's loaded to find
matches for
things that we asked for right and every
one of those steps can have a bug and
there's even one more that we kind of
know isn't a problem in some sense but
you know even really kind of could be
depending on because of the lighting
maybe who knows which is the actual
rendering you know what I mean
so when we actually go to render things
we also we could easily do something
where we're screwing up the red or green
channels there or the blue Channel there
or whatever right or we're flipping
things upside down inside the renderer
when we shouldn't be and things like
this right so we have a large number of
possible failure points and so the
reason I wanted to take the particular
talk when I take today is not because I
I could now go debug those we can
probably debug them pretty cold and it
wouldn't be a huge deal but I don't
really want to spend a lot of time to
bugging these kind of issues all the
time so what I'd rather do is take one
part of the puzzle away and just go look
we've got this utility we wrote that's
HHA edit right and in here you can do
create rewrite info dump right and so
one of the things that we had was these
these two bottom ones that allow us to
look at a particular one of our data one
of our HHA files like the runtime data
for the game it allows us to look at one
of those in so if we wanted to say look
this is the imported art assets here
right this is what we're running with if
I say HHA edit and I said info local HHA
it will tell me some information right
okay so it's a version 1 file it has 14
assets in it there are 46 total tags and
it came with annotations in it right if
I then say dump right what you can see
here is we get all of the information
about these things in here that is
exactly what I want to know so for
example I can see here that like okay
here's the hand dark bones thing it says
this is the tile that it was imported
from it says that Anna is the person who
made it it says which file it was from
which is nice we have a data like
Poynter it tells us four tags and what
you can see here is the piece of
information I'm really interested in is
sort of missing right I want to know
what we tagged the thing and
unfortunately I can't see it right so it
just says unknown and so let's look at
why that's true that's the first thing I
do today because I think it'd be easier
to fix and then we could look at that
and eliminate that as a possibility one
thing the other thing I'd like to do is
I can't tell if this bitmap is correct
right I have no idea what this bitmap
looks like so the other thing I could do
is make in the like a like something
like this like dump BMP or something and
I could tell it take this local itch
it's a and dump all the bitmaps out into
a directory so I can look at them and
see if they're all correct so I can have
a round trip there so those two things
aren't particularly hard to add to our
HSA editor so I think we should because
that way we can know like what's going
on the other thing we could do is make
it so that the import path gets welded
in here too but I don't know how much we
want to I'm not gonna do that because we
don't really care but something to think
about maybe a long term so let's take a
look at the first one so we have some
duplicated code and the duplicated code
is what's leading to this problem so if
we look let me just load up the project
here so we get all our files so if we
look inside Hannah made asset one thing
we just kind of shoved in really quickly
last week without really thinking about
it with this right here so this was a
list of names that go with tags you know
I'm saying and if you take a look in our
HHA editor what you'll also notice is
that it needs that as well so if we go
look at where it dumps the tags out
which
is right here ribs not what I wanted
print contents what you can see here is
we have a print tag function and that's
what's being called to say for any given
tag in the system what it is and you'll
notice we have a thing here called tag
name from ID now if I love these two
things together you can see that
essentially what we've got here is we've
got two of the same things happening
this is a mapping of tag names where you
can put in an ID and get out of tag name
this is the opposite this is the thing
where you can put in a name and get out
a tag and you can see why these two
things are essentially the same so they
both maintain a mapping from IDs to
names or back depending on how you want
to look at them but the information
that's contained in them is essentially
the same they're just optimized for a
different direction of lookup and what
happens here is we end up in a situation
where these two tables have to would
always have to be synchronized right
anytime we add something and this is
exactly what happened we made a table
here that has a bunch of things for tags
that we never went back and added so
when you print it out you don't get the
right results so what would be nice
well what would be really nice is if C
and or C++ actually had introspection in
it in which case neither of these two
tables would even have to exist in the
first place but that's a separate issue
since we don't have a language that
actually is any good what we can do is
minimize the degree to which that
language poops on us by say let's go
ahead and make a unified place for this
to occur so we at least know if we could
read the name in and set a tag we can
print the name in you so you're never
gonna have a situation where you really
can import a tag you can't then export
right it's always gonna be the same so
what I want to do is unify these two
together and the way that I'm gonna do
that is I'm just gonna go in and say
inside the HHA file format stuff which
is this right here we've got sort of the
the definitions of everything right
here's our basic categories and stuff
like that right and we've got this asset
tag ID here and we know this is the
master list because this is what's
actually being used for compilation and
anything that's not in the master list
here couldn't be referred to by code in
any way right so we know this list is
the correct list so what I'd like to do
now is say well maybe there's a handmade
file formats dot cpp we have not had
that previously but we do have it now so
I'm gonna go ahead and create one and
maybe I put it in the wrong directory
hold on a sec sorry I don't know what I
just did there I wanted to make a new
one in the code directory maybe I made
it in the project directory and I know
let's see
so handmade file format made file
formats that's CPP there we go sorry I
think I made it in the wrong directory
there so I didn't want to save it out to
be in the wrong place anyway so if we
have a handmade file formats the CPP
what we can do is add some things in
here that will be sort of Universal ways
to look this stuff up and what we can do
is go alright so inside the HSA editor
we kind of already have like one of
those so we've got this type from ID v-0
table right so maybe that you know wants
to be moved in there just because it's a
named table and let's just put those in
here right so here's our type form ID
table and the other thing we can do is
put those tag tables in there so inside
the asset system right we've got a name
tag here we can put those in as well so
we can go ahead and and add this in
there like so
and we can also inside the HHA edit
where we had those tags we can put these
in
- right and so now what we want to do is
figure out a way to kind of unify these
two things together so the first thing I
want to do is convert I would like to
use this kind of mapping not this one
the reason for that is if you look at
what might happen when we are doing
stuff in this system what you can see is
that we have essentially a we have a
many to one kind of relationship going
on with these names there's only one set
of ID's so a tag underscore bones is
always a tag underscore bones there
isn't some other tag like tag underscore
bone without the S that also means the
same thing
so inside our code we are rigid about
always having one identifier that means
what it means and there's never two
identifiers that can mean the same thing
that's important for programming that's
what we do all the time but in art land
that it doesn't always happen sometimes
people because you know they don't have
a compiler really a lot of times to tell
them that they use the term that's wrong
they're just naming something in
photoshop and photoshop can't check it
for validity right
so sometimes we would rather be more
permissive in the exported thing rather
than say oh yeah like when you go to
import it it gives you an error and go
back to photoshop and change the name of
the thing you know stuff like that
so what we want to do is anymore premiss
is there which means we tend to have
more than one text you will name that
can go with a particular tag right and
so what we want to do is recognize that
fact and set up a mapping that goes in
that direction
so we can define lots of strings that
map to a small number of IDs rather than
lots of IDs that map to a small number
of strings because we're trying to model
a specific one of those two things
that's occurring and so that's what
we're doing here right and so what I'd
like to do and let me just I'm going to
move
down below it because it's it's not this
is some old stuff that probably won't
come into play very often what I'd like
to do here is just say okay when we're
when we're compiling this stuff what I'd
like to do here is just say let's stop
using this tag name from ID and we'll
start using this now I don't know if we
actually want to have this to this type
from ID v-0 actually in there we might
we might not I don't know we'll see
because this can go away eventually but
you know we'll see this part here is
here to stay so this is the part that we
want to focus on and what I'd like to do
is just go ahead and convert these
things that we had already into sort of
more the same format that we had below
right so all of this stuff while it's
still in the tag system we'll just go
ahead and and put in there so if I look
at what these things were you know in
terms of tags they kind of map directly
over right so we know we've got you know
smoothness flatness it's facing
Direction Unicode code point you know
font type shot index layer index primacy
and basic category and so now we know
that we've got a mapping between those
two things
done in exactly the same way that we
were doing the other tags so it's
uniform right don't really want that
indented that way let's go ahead and get
that out of here so now we've got a
table that's uniform and now we just
need to support the types of calls that
we were supporting before meaning we
need to be able to use this table in
some constructive way so if I look at
the HHA editor what we needed is tag
name from ID so we want to turn that
into you know a function right and that
function needs to return exactly what it
says it needs to return a tag name in
this case and we use strings here so in
this case I again probably want to
although we can't actually have this
return a care star as well you can use
either of those two things so because in
this case we actually define it both
ways
so it's kind of it's fine either one you
want to do so I don't remember what the
full name of what is this asset tag ID
yeah I could just call it tag ID we're
not gonna have it it's got two tags but
so there's the ID so what we want to do
is find what it is right we want to find
which one of these goes with the ID and
then we want to return that string so
we've got a result here and that result
is gonna come back so we just need to
find out what it is then we have the
opposite version in hand made asset and
what that wants to do is check all the
names so that's something that needs to
work the opposite way right so that's
gonna go through our list and and go now
remember I guess we could say from name
remember we don't actually need this to
be particularly fast neither these two
things is running in a like critical
scenario so we can just leave them
pretty cheesy
you know like if we needed them to be
fast we certainly could make them much
faster right and the way that we would
do that is we would actually use some
sort of indexing
here to jump to only asset that would
make sense right but I don't think we
really have to care linear check of
these even if there's a thousand of them
probably won't hurt us for most of the
cases we actually care about because
it's never runs at run time it's only an
import time thing so until we actually
see it show up on the profile we're
probably fine because this is not
something we're shipping to an end user
right so let's see here so I think what
we want to do is say all right we've got
an unknown string that will return in
the case we don't know what's going on
otherwise we'll run through this list of
name tags here and when we actually find
one that's equal then we return it just
as we would before so we just need to
flip the ways to doing like this ones
comparing strings and then returning the
ID what we want to do here is compare
the IDs and then return the string right
it's the exact opposite way of checking
but the code is identical so we're just
gonna do that and then return the string
like so so when we do that now what we
have to do is actually have this code be
present so the first way we do that
obviously it's just in handmade asset
when it wants to make this call we need
to actually include that file so if you
look in handmade CPP we're not actually
building it that's a new file that we
added we're not actually building with
it so I need to include in my CPP's I
need to include the file formats dot CPP
right and you can see that in the H file
we've got that up here right it's right
after random and and stream and stuff so
what we want to do is is put that in
roughly the same area which I guess is
there and should be good
so looking at the bugs we have in hand
made hero here we I said string it's not
string I don't know why I type that I
believe it's name in the actual field so
that I think is our only problem so
that's now building with the table so
the only thing we have to do now is make
the
this code HHA editor also billed at the
table if you look here it already
includes some of this stuff so I think
all we have to do to make this work is
just say okay let's include that
handmade file format dot cpp in here and
we should be good to go now I could put
that in here because the CPP that's the
only CPP it actually it's building with
hopefully that's line we'll find out in
a second alright so in here I think we
want to eliminate this and just assume
that we can do this right and then what
we'll do is we'll just take the data out
of the string here and inside the the
inside the actual file formats routine
what we what we want to do is make sure
that that check that looks to see if
it's out of balance that works remember
the reason we had to do that check for
out of bounds cuz we were looking up
directly into an array that was indexed
off of the ID so if we had had it out of
bounds ID we would just fall it and that
would be bad but here we don't have that
problem because we're iterating over a
list and looking for matches so if you
pass us an ID we don't recognize no big
deal it's just gonna return the default
so we really don't need to check anymore
and this is fine right so we should be
good to go now let's just take a look if
we've got on the other cannot okay so we
do have to convert it to the the type so
we need to change us to it that's a tag
ID it's just actually a politeness cast
it's not actually converting the value
and here it wants a care star and that's
fine because it's just a string so we
can now use the same in both cases and
the reason that that's good is because
again now for really no cost to us every
time we add something to the parser it
will also add it to the debug dump and
that's just a good way to keep those two
things in sync so now when we hit dump
we can actually see what all of these
things are right so we can see for
example that we've got a dark energy or
a bones tag on here
and we can see that that makes sense so
hand dark bones has a dark energy tag
and a bones tag on it right was what we
want now if I remember
correctly the reason that we thought we
had a bug is because we didn't see the
matching happening the way that we
thought it should and so the first thing
we could start to debug now that we've
added that is let's go ahead and turn
back on what we thought was the problem
there which is remember I don't know if
remember this we turned off these files
by naming them something that our system
wouldn't recognize I'll now name them
back to something our system will
recognize and all of these things should
now get pulled into the system so when I
rerun the game now it should try to
import those files right and it looks
like it did import those files that was
pretty quick but I guess there's not
that many files to import or whatever
and what you can see is it's picking at
the moment right some ground that's a
that's a dirt like side texture there
and again we have the weird blue problem
right so you know again weird problems
and so on we will be we'll have to work
through those and find out what they are
those are separate from the picking
problem which is what I want to look at
now so if I go ahead and just dump this
thing to some kind of analysis file like
local dot txt what I can then do is look
at that local dot txt file is my did I
not put I thought I put tab you in here
don't
no hmm I thought we put tabview in here
but I mean I know we put tab you in here
right
what's gonna what's going on here
did I just run directly out of the bonus
pack I guess maybe I did well it's in
the bonus pack one way or the other so
that's fine anyway let's go ahead and
continue what I was going to do which is
look at the contents of that dump so
here's the local hhj file here are the
assets that are supposedly in the file
here are the blocks so we've got four of
them right and if we open them up we can
see which ones they are and that they're
all doing whatever they're doing right
and they each have some tags so here's
what the tags are so right off the bat
we can see that it's busted because we
have these basic categories which are
set properly probably right but there's
no other tags so if you're looking here
you can see that we are getting actual
tags right like there's the bones tag
and we don't have any of the other tags
so that tells me right off the bat that
the problem here is actually is in the
import when we go to import we're not
getting those tags so why not here's our
begin tags call here's our end tags call
and we pass the file name in here just
like we do here but for whatever reason
we're not actually getting any parsing
so why not right would be my first
question like if we go in and look at
the art I guess now that I think about
it it's actually kind of obvious we
renamed these files cover forest hand
bones I'm sorry hand bones
and dark bones hand glove fingers we
never renamed these so I don't know why
we would think that there was any way to
pick anything that must have just been a
case of me we went for a couple we went
long and maybe I was a little delirious
like why would we think that would work
I don't know why I don't even know why I
thought something should happen there so
it looks like nothing happened wrong
that was just us being dumb and not
actually even putting any input into the
system so I don't have an explanation
for that so let's take a look at what
we're actually talking about here we've
got bones dark energy glove and fingers
those were our labels for the other
things in the system but now we need
labels for blocks what I would like to
say is this is you know it's wood you
know it's interior or you know maybe
it's mint I don't know what you want to
call it like like it's a structure it's
wood and drywall
I guess so it's wood drywall so it looks
like it's interior or man-made it's like
a like a wall you know we should also
probably have floor so some of these
tags to describe this thing right let's
try those and then again we'll just use
the system that we just made we want to
basically tack on a bunch of new words
here here they are so all we need to do
is just actually write these in here so
we've got like a constant Z with the
name we want and then the tag that we
want like so so in here we could say
well here's wood here's drywall here's
manmade here's wall here's floor
delete all those and then we can say
like wood drywall man-made wall floor
and I don't know if drywall is the right
term here I don't know what that stuff
would really be called you know probably
wasn't called drywall back in the day
either when you know in mythical times
and so on when you think about when this
game might take place in a mythical
kingdom I don't think they were like oh
and what ho good sir please to come
across your acquaintances and would you
like to do some dry walling like I don't
know that Shakespeare had drywall I mean
maybe he did but they probably had a
different name for that so I don't know
not exactly as sort of mythical world is
you might want but you know no one has
to see that so it's fine
and that's that will give us what we
need so if we then go in here we've got
sort of these block orphanages and
there's a stone one too so maybe I'll
throw that in there too you know we'll
get a stone in there like so on and
that'll be a good set of stuff so that's
like a stone floor and and probably a
man-made one right there very regular so
I think that's fine
I can't think of anything else I really
need to do there so let's just go ahead
and rename some of these to something
that actually will work for us there so
we've got this block forest I guess you
know what and I think about it while
we're at it let's add that one too so
this is great like there's a grass kind
here and and maybe so I don't know if
floor so I don't know if we want
differentiate between floor and ground I
don't think we do I think something is
probably just man-made or not right and
then it's like floor or not so if
something is a man-made floor versus a
non man-made floor is probably
sufficient would be my guess
so I don't know cuz there's two ways we
can look at that right and that's that
like man-made is a tag and natural is a
tag and floor and ground or both tags
too and you could just you just throw
all these tags in there and and let some
sort it out or you try to be minimal
about it I don't know which one we want
it might be that it's better to not try
to be minimal about it you know what I
mean
and another way to yet another way to
say that would be maybe we want this
thing to actually have more of a like
settings sort of a structure so just to
give an example you know suppose you
were to say tag ID from name and it
returned you a value as well so it could
be that like you know man-made is like
man-made one and natural is man-made
zero equals zero like you have the tag
and its value is something you know what
I mean
and so then when you say tag name from
ID you would actually pass the value in
and it would tell you what the meaning
of that thing was in a in another way
right I don't know I feel about that
when I'm looking at these right now I
don't yeah I don't know we'll have to
see as we go again
I'm okay with updating the system one
more time we have all the source assets
so rien porting everything is not a big
deal so we can play with it a little bit
and be a little bit more flexible if we
want to right um
so looking at this here we've got a
couple more we want to add there we've
got wood stone drywall man-made wall
floor we want to add that grass in here
and then I think we've got the stuff
that we need for naming this is not
really have to be forest it can just be
kind of like block or grass right this
is going to be block wall man-made wood
drywall this is going to be block war
man-made stone and this is going to be
block or man-made wood and these are
like you know doing their thing and now
when we input them they will have some
tags that can actually be used to like
pick something right so I think that's
all we actually had as a bug and I would
point out that we actually can if we
want to like when we're doing this we
don't even have to be pristine about it
it's wasteful but if we just rerun all
that's gonna happen is we're gonna get
some more blocks right and so if we then
look and read dump that file to a text
file again and I reload it here what
we'll see is we actually should have
just stacked up more assets right so we
don't actually have to go redo we can
leave bogus assets in here it doesn't
cost us anything but a little bit of
extra space so during development we
don't have to care that these things are
in their wrong and the fact that they
don't have any tags means they're never
gonna match anything anyway so it really
doesn't matter if we want to take a
harder line on that later we can but
right now it's our purview to just leave
them right so what we see here is oh you
know what I didn't recompile the file so
that actually it's not good
right I don't think I actually built
this yeah so now it should be looking
for those tags right and now when I
actually run this in theory anyway
well so now I actually do have to do it
because we haven't touched those files
right we modified the code and haven't
touched those files for parsing we could
rename them or just do a touch on them
to change their dates and then they
would get re-employed potentially but
yeah I think I'll just rebuild the HHA
because that's easy enough for me to do
um so if I go in here and I just delete
local HHA and then I do a HHA edit I can
do a create local uhha and now we have a
new one it will reinforce all of our
stuff cleanly and build a fresh pack
right now in theory that imports so
quickly I guess the optimized build is
just hey man computers are really fast
nowadays so even though we haven't done
any work to actually make oops to make
that fast it just is so there you go
oops and so looking at this now we can
see there there are tags we can inspect
it and make sure the tags are actually
correct yeah because that would be nice
here so we can see that like here's our
block for the the wall and it is a wall
it's man-made is wood drywall that's
good right so all that stuff's in there
and so now when I run in theory I should
be able to like actually control some of
this stuff right now
we have some issues though there's one
more issue that I'd like to tackle
before we really trying to that because
we're gonna end up with problems so
let's go we'll write a little bit of
code to kind of decorate like make the
world actually pick the pieces that we
think it should be picking but then we
have to go and figure out what's wrong
with our color swapping enter and then
we have to decide what to do about the
upside down this right so we've got some
more issues like we're not really done
with the importing yet we've solved the
tag issue which was that we never
actually named the files oh well like we
were we were
crazy last week we didn't we weren't
thinking so we thought there was a bug
that really wasn't a bug we just never
actually named anything and that's fine
it's good bug to have as a non bug so
anyway let's go take a look at what we
would need to do for the entity tagging
stuff so what I need to do here if
you'll if you notice we haven't here
there's sort of this notion that an
entity has you know all this stuff that
we haven't really talked about or done
anything with we just throw things in
here and that's exactly what I want it I
don't want to work on the entities until
we're pretty much like halfway through
the game right like when we were
actually kind of starting on gameplay
stuff now in a sense like we're making
out the world so we will start paying
more attention to energy structure but
again I don't really want to do anything
to clean this up this is supposed to be
messy but we do need to add a piece of
information to it which is what tags
this entity has so we need to have a tag
system in here that allows us to tag
these things on here because right now
all the only thing we have at the moment
is we just have the asset basic category
right which is not what we want to do so
what we want to do is have some more
tags in here we want to say okay we've
got asset tag ID and we've got some tags
in here you know and the entity has some
tags you know I don't know what they are
but the entity has them right and so I
want to put that in there I also want to
look to see does smoothness use anywhere
smooth this is not used anywhere at the
moment so you know what I'm gonna do I'm
just gonna go ahead and go rogue and say
that tag zero is actually just none
right so because hey we can so I'm just
gonna say the tag zero is none it gets
skipped so smoothness which was some
random thing we put in there is now no
longer in there sorry anyone who was
tagged with smoothness will make another
smoothness later if we have to
but these tags will go in here right and
then what we'll do is we'll say all
right when we loop through these tags we
will unpack them into whatever the asset
matching vector is and we'll go from
there
right so what I want to do is way we're
currently matching is not particularly
useful so there are some issues there
here's well okay let me let me talk
about a few more things so there is one
reason not to do what I just said
and this is probably why we decided not
to make there be a should I put this
there is one reason why you might not
want to make 0b none and that reason and
is probably the reason why we didn't do
it in the first place which is that if
you want to expand these things out to a
vector to match then you want each of
these to correspond to a position in the
vector right so you have like 0 1 2 3 4
or 5 right hey you don't want none
taking up a slot based on the way we're
talking about tags
I have changed my mental model of what
these things would be how a matcher
would work because if you look at it
we're gonna have a ton of tags there's
gonna be like a hundred tags so we're
never gonna want to build a vector of
them we're gonna want it to remain
sparse right and so what we want to do
here is just do something where we like
sort the tags or something right and
then compare them to each other that's
all we're gonna want to do I think so if
we sort all of our tags and like buy in
ascending order or something then we
write a matcher that works that way that
would just solve our problem and so that
seems like more what we would want to do
to me right and so I don't care about I
want none to be zero now but so that way
we just have an easy way of saying that
there is no tag there
okay so I want to put in a tag array
like this and then what I want to do is
match against that tag array and I want
to get rid of the way we're doing the
matching so we want to kind of update
the matching a little bit
we'll leave the matching the way it is
now and we'll update it to something
else another day and so I'll put it to
do in the code in the entity system for
making it work that way but at the
moment I'm just gonna go ahead and oops
at the moment I'm just gonna go ahead
and make it so that the entity uses the
same matching as it used to use because
that's more of an optimization thing and
I want to put I don't really want to go
and deal with that right now
we can deal with it a little bit later
it's not gonna it's just gonna be a
performance cost really that we
definitely don't want to pay as it gets
higher but it's not going to prevent us
from doing the work that we're trying to
do today so I'm gonna punt it to them
alright so inside update and render
entities when we come through the
entities here what you can see is that
we eventually have to do some stuff
where we do some matching and so here's
our way that we were doing matching and
that's all fine but what we want to do
now is make sure that our tags are
actually expanded in here we've set the
facing direction in here and that's fine
but now we also want to say we want to
match on some of these other things so
let's go ahead and loop over the things
in our entity tags that are actually
what we want to match on so I'm gonna go
ahead and say like here's a match index
match index is less than array count you
know entity tags plus plus match index
and then for each of these things I want
to say that the match vector of the
entity tags match index which I could
pull out right so I could say like okay
asset tag ID ID so let's say the match
vector for that is going to be whatever
the asset has so I guess now I think
about the site I also need a tag value
right so in here I need a tag value and
these two probably should be paired
together
right we will probably want to do that
but again I want to clean this up a
little bit later and so here I'll also
put this something like that so what I
want to do now is say okay we got a
match vector for this tag we want to set
it to whatever the end of these tag
value is for that thing right and then
we also have the weight vector and for
now again we'll just say okay the weight
vector for the hoops the weight vector
for that thing is gonna be one so it's
it's you know it's just uniformly
weighted all the way now but we'll you
know we might want to change some of
that later so anyway this what this does
is this unpacks the entities tags that
it's got into a match vector for use in
the system later on we'll just leave
them packed and match directly on the
packed version but that's all there is
to that
so what I want to do now is actually add
those tags to the entities somehow
because right now entities don't have
any tags that's just not something that
they actually have sir this is an e in
those cases and so what we want to do is
is give our entity some tags to match on
so that we can see if the matching is
working correctly and so if you look
here right like none of these entities
have any tags so none of them it doesn't
know that's a wall it doesn't know this
is a floor blah blah blah right so what
we want to do now is when we actually
create the rooms in here we create
entities right you can see us placing
these entities here are the entities
what we want to do is set those tags on
the entities and work through those I
don't know exactly how we want to do
that so we'll kind of rough it in right
now and then we'll we'll add some more
stuff later I probably want to maybe
just looking at it I probably want to be
able to do something like this so I want
to be able to say like let's add a tag
and let's say you know is this thing a
floor is this thing whatever right and
so in here we must have known
right because we were placing the things
so when we come through here we can say
aleko k is it on a boundary is on a
connection whatever and so when we look
at these things we should be able to say
is it a floor or not and you can see
we're kind of already doing that if it's
on a boundary and not on a connection
then it's a wall so it should add a
particular type of tag and then we need
to add one of these traversals for it
right so I can put that in here right
like so but I can add a tag one way or
the other right so this is going to be a
wall
and this is going to be a floor and what
we can do here is have the floors be we
can change what kinds they are at some
point but what I'm gonna do now just say
like wall or floor in in any case
everything in here is man-made at least
for the moment so we're always putting a
man-made one in here and again all of
these things have to become more
complicated because this room Jen
generates our outdoor rooms right now
too so we obviously don't want that but
you know well we'll cross that bridge
when we come to right now we just want
to make sure that our tagging system can
work so that's all we really need here I
think is to say these couple of things
we should probably say what kind they
are here maybe this is a wood floor
generally speaking we could also say
that in general this is just wood
construction so we could put that down
here and so that just sets these tags up
to it to work what that means is that in
here we need a thing where we actually
say what the tag count is like so and if
that's the case then in here this should
actually look at a tag count like that
right and what we want to do then is
just have a thing that when we call tag
count when we call add tag on an entity
that that actually does something so for
example in here we can actually say add
tag now I think we decided that doesn't
really go in entity I guess it goes more
in world construction because that's
where we add things like pieces and tags
I don't know if that makes a lot of
sense because it seems to me like this
stuff will have to migrate out
eventually because it has to be
something like we want to add IDs and
pieces at runtime potentially so I feel
like this stuff is probably
inappropriate
placed in a room Jen so I think we'll
have to move it out to something where
it's sensible later but that's okay it's
not really a big deal at the moment
either way so here's the tag value that
we're gonna add and there we go
so the first thing we need to do is just
make sure we still have room so we have
to make sure that for the moment anyway
because the way that we're doing this is
again kind of little ad hoc since the
entity structure is something that will
be dealt with much later on like when
the game is playable and partially done
right so we want to make sure though for
the time being that the fixed array that
we're adding it to has enough room and
then when it does we can just say all
right the tag index is whatever the next
tag is and then we just set the two
values so this entity tags is gonna be
this ID and the value is gonna be this
and so then we've got a way to stick the
tags on the entities and so now we
should be able to debug a code path
which essentially selects various things
in our game from the options that are
presented so what we want to do now is
make it so that we can see when these
entities go through that system are they
getting picked properly if they're not
gonna pay probably why not now looking
at it it doesn't look like they're
getting picked properly because
everything still looks like it's picking
just a ground tile right it doesn't look
like it's picking anything on there and
so I want to go in and see why are we
not picking now I'm gonna go ahead and
downshift a debug mode here so I'm gonna
go ahead and say look give me just the
the debug version of the code and when
we go through here I want to see why
we're not getting the matches that I
think we should be getting so I'm gonna
stop in here and I'm gonna look at an
entity that has some tags I want to see
what those tags are and and just so we
can see like what we're actually
matching and then I want to look at the
match and see is it matching properly or
is it doing something stupid so here's
an ID it says it's a floor tag right I
don't want to really match that I don't
wanna well yeah well let's do it anyway
so what's the value here that we added
match vector weight vector so let's see
here we got a match vector and 18 is set
right we got a match vector an 18 is set
into the notch as well and 18 is our is
our floor value so that that looks
correct so far we come in here we're
gonna set another one what's the we're
gonna set we're going to set the wood
tag there it is and then we're gonna set
some other thing man-made all right so
we're gonna set man-made wood floor
that's exactly what we should have set
so we now need to know why you know why
aren't we finding that so when we go to
get best match what's the deal right why
aren't we finding anything so let's look
at the tags that are on this actual
asset here we find a tight tag ID of
eight I don't know if usual student can
do this it can so that's the basic
category we don't need to match that one
so I'm assuming it will just get rid of
it yeah which is good then we've got
another tag in here 18 let's do it that
way so we this is a floor tag so that
should give us a weighted and it doesn't
alright so what did we screw up here
because this is a floor tag we should be
matching on floor oh it's a difference
so it should give us a difference of
zero yeah that's that's a that's what we
wanted right yeah
okay I think I see the problem here so
the problem is that the way yeah again
the way we were doing this matching is
just kind of dumb right so the way we're
doing this matching is we only match on
tags that the asset actually has which
does not work because basically if an
asset doesn't have it we don't count it
as a penalty that it doesn't have
something that we were trying to match
on and it should because something that
doesn't have it should actually count
against it right so I feel like that's
just kind of busted
so I may have to update the tag matching
early because I'm not sure how else I
will would go about fixing this problem
I could sort of hack a thing in here
which would look for things in the match
vector that weren't there or I could
switch it to a positive match
I guess I'll switch it to a positive
match for now rather than rewrite it
I guess I'll to switch it to a positive
match for now so what we're looking at
here is the best difference so we look
for things that are the lowest I'm going
to change it to looking at looking at
things for the highest so what I'm going
to do instead is say that right and
we'll start out at 0 and when we loop
through these assets here what we do is
we say all right what is the total match
we go through and we say for this one
we'll say for the match vector I can
convert these to our new type naming
here we look to see what the absolute
value is of the difference between these
two and what I guess I want to do is I
want to invert that so we say here's the
absolute value here's the
not sure what interesting so we have a
tag range
that's very interesting
so we actually have a way of mapping the
range in here that's even more
interesting all right well I wasn't
expecting that I don't know if we really
need that but we probably did that too
we probably did that so that we could
have directions work properly
like the facing direction it's a little
more advanced than I thought we were
being in here that's okay so when we
actually take the difference here what
I'd like to do is just say look let's go
ahead and say that whatever the
difference between these two things was
we want to give you points for every one
that you match right so we want to say
that you effectively do something like
this you know what I mean
and when we then weight those things we
add together the total match value and
then we look at whichever one is look is
highest right and so it's just a way of
saying that if you have more matches
you'll get more points rather than just
saying we're trying to minimize the
number of times you don't match and I
think that will solve the problem
temporarily but like I said we kind of
want to look at this in a slightly
different way a little later on
okay so best match sorry about that and
now let's see if we get a little bit
better matching in the short term here
just so we can finish kind of what we
were doing
so that's exactly what we wanted to see
so that's much better obviously and so
now are we I think we at least know our
tags are working in we now just have a
problem where we've sort of got a we we
know we've got roughly the right thing
happening but we have some obvious
import errors the upside down s and the
blue tinge we now want to look at
because we're in the pipeline for
importing and selecting assets looks
like it's working properly to me now and
so we want to kind of switch to looking
at that and I'm not sure how we want to
address that so the first thing I want
to do is look at our render test because
our render test does not have this
problem I want to make sure that our
render test is actually accounting for
it properly so I just want to look at
what's going on here
so if we look at what's happening in in
in our loader here when we load the
bitmap just looking at how we read it in
the bitmap might already be bottom-up so
that might be solving this problem
automatically for us here actually
but let's take a look so in here we've
got our red green blue we're packing it
in so that we've got
a on top our than G than B I thought
that was how we were using the import
here as well so I'm a little weirded out
by why we were getting a blueshift in
our current stuff and not this one
because inside the loading here that
should have been fine right so you can
see when we load things out we've got a
we do have a swap R and B let me look at
what happens in there
so in there we basically take the
existing color and we we yeah we just
swapped what's in those two that looks
pretty sane and I do think we should
have to do that right because the PNG
would be encoded and and I mean you
could see us loading it here we're
loading it that way as well although I
guess this isn't loading a PNG it's
loading a BMP
so let's look inside our PNG reader what
do we do here
because I'm pretty sure it should come
out like with like the order are GBA
rgba because I thought it was I didn't
think it was windows style so when we
actually output this we don't swap it or
anything right just want to see what
we're doing here
here's our parse P&amp;G call and we just
call parse P&amp;G that's the only thing
that we do to it before we start working
on it right so if we look in here and we
look at what happens during parse P&amp;G
it's just that loading routine we just
looked at so if decompresses the bytes
does the consume bits compute Huffman
blah blah blah right does all the work
so do you compress the PNG and it just
outputs the data right and when it calls
PNG filter reconstruct it doesn't swap
any bits right
yeah I mean I don't see anything in
there that's doing swapping so I would
expect them to be correct in that RGB
order which means we do have to swap
them right like they should have to be
swapped and so yeah so what's going on
here here's our thing that extracts the
image right there's nothing particularly
weird about it it's pretty
straightforward
[Music]
it just converts it does a alpha
pre-multiply
other than that there's nothing
nothing remarkable about that and then
we do our down sampling down sampling
doesn't do anything weird right just
blends these together so yeah I don't
really see anything weird going on there
I don't I don't really see I don't see
the problem I don't see what's up
something's up but I don't see what's up
when we actually go to submit these I'm
assuming that they just get submitted
directly through so yeah I don't know so
let me just verify a few things first
and then we'll figure out what our next
step should be I'm gonna launch insight
and I'm going to run hand-me hero
through insight like so and all I'm
going to do here is take a look
we're in looks like we're running in the
wrong directory
I have to save this somehow we know how
to save it but that's where we actually
want to run it right so if I launch this
what I want to do is look at what the
textures we actually downloaded are to
make sure that the textures themselves
are tinted blue and it's not a rendering
artifact before I go chasing down a bug
that doesn't actually exist if that
makes sense
so what I'm gonna do is do capture for
live analysis let Nvidia capture the
frame then I'm gonna go look at our
texture set and see what the textures
actually have in it so what I could do
here is let me just go ahead and make
this a little bit bigger what I can do
here is just say look give us something
like where we're end or something you
know what I mean
let's go ahead and scrub for something
like that
so there's there's some know why they're
all kind of over in the corner there but
if I look through our render passes here
we should be able to find one that's
mostly geometry and I think that's
probably one and so if I look at what
the textures are that are in play here I
should be able to see something like
some kind of texture array but I guess
the other thing to do is just look
through the the total set of textures in
fact that's probably the easier thing to
do so maybe I'll do that there should be
like a way to look at all my textures
right there it is so if I look through
the textures here there should be one of
them that's like a texture array and
we'll see what you wanna do is so here
it is
right and so what I want to do is go
look at and see like what I actually
downloaded so if I look at this tile
that pretty much tells me what I need to
know so the art and B channels are
swapped in it and again I don't know why
right I don't know why they've been
swapped if I look at the rest of the how
do I get out of this I just do that
there's got to be a way to change the
array slice right don't think
that's a histogram I change how do I
change the array slice okay so I just I
hit the right mouse button is what I
just did there to changer a slice so
looking at these you know I can see that
it's not really a problem with the
texture upload because these assets that
came from the previous import path there
right so like that's not that doesn't
have its RMB flopped this does so the
question is how how is that happening
right and I have no idea so let's go
ahead and look into it further when I go
to submit a texture
let's see what's actually happening
there so if I go to the win32 renderer
for OpenGL when we do at X sub image 3d
which is how we send these things down
if I look at what's actually happening
in there you can see here that we we are
passing the BGR a extension right so
that means that the order of bytes
that's being passed in the data field
there should be blue green red alpha so
the low is B then the next is G then the
are then a if we go and look at where
that call is actually made to submit the
texture that's gonna be in handmade
asset and we're actually gonna have a
thing for finalized at the bitmap right
here's where we passed the bitmap memory
right we add an OP to the texture Q to
do that after it gets loaded right so
this is what does that work after we do
the read from file and we're done so
we're not we're not like
modifying the data in any way when we
pass it downward is passing it directly
so it pretty much just leaves us with
the import and the import is has got to
be mucking with it somehow right so when
we call parse P&amp;G and we are pretty sure
that the PNG has those things flipped
around right but I guess I don't know
the other thing could be that we don't
that that's not true
PNG byte order
colors sooner scented by either crystal
RGB the grayscale data represents
luminance RGB data it represents
calibrated color information or
uncovered device all clever values range
from zero to most intense yep simplify
our sensor linear blah blah swear
surface is nice right okay red appears
first then green then blue so it's our G
B right
so yeah I still don't see any reason why
this thing wouldn't be coming in as our
first then G than B will have to step
into it and find out but let's assume
that's what's going on the good of
process multi tail import let's just see
what's happening so when we look at
these we're scanning over and we look at
the alpha channel that we know is in the
right place because we're not getting
any bugs there so when we come through
here and we look at these pixels and no
one has done any swapping this is just
the raw input image right there's
nothing nothing has happened so far so
when we come through here and we do a
down sample on this and then we do a
right image to HHA those are the two
places that this stuff could get mopped
up I'm gonna look at the right image to
hij function just see what that's doing
to see what what's actually happening in
there so looking through here we don't
touch the pixels at all so it can't be
happening there right
I want to look at the GRA unpack and
make sure that that's doing what I think
it's doing
so be GRE unpack does what I would
expect
RGBA it unpacks the v4 as I would expect
be GRA pack 4x8 also looks correct I
mean I can't say I see anything odd
right
it all looks fine to me
yes so I don't see anything weird
happening there
I what I will say is I don't understand
why we did it that way
like we don't need to do what we're
doing here it seems just kind of dumb so
maybe I will change us a little if we're
gonna do bug it we might as well do bug
a smarter version of it so when we
actually you know what though here's the
thing we don't call this path this only
happens on multi tile so I think all
we're really seeing is the fact that
when we actually call one of these
processed single tile imports we don't
actually we don't actually call that so
I think the problem here is really just
that yeah that's not sufficient so I
think what we want to do here is
probably do the flipping and the color
conversion in Prabhat probably a more
uniform way I don't know it's a good
question let's start with a few simple
things so if we're going to convert this
I think we should just do an RGB a
unpack on this because that way it'll
impact that and then pack it into G like
we don't need to call the swap
separately so we'll do this we can also
flip the image to be the correct
orientation here because when we're
running in the desk pixels what we could
do is just write in the desk pixels
backwards right and or read from the
source row backwards so it's our choice
so maybe we'll just do this when Bert's
flipping through the source row we'll
just say look instead of starting at the
top start at the bottom right so instead
here to say
go to max live right and start there and
read from the bottom back right and I
think that should be sufficient for
handling that path but then we need an
equivalent path in the other places that
we were dealing with this so in here
where we do process single tile import
and process plate import those also need
to have some way of handling this
problem because they don't go through
this extraction path right so what we
probably need to do there is sort of
make this a little bit more regularize
so that this actually works properly for
everybody right before the down sample
is called and we could bake it into the
down sample but I don't think we really
want to do that so what I want to do is
like you know extract image something
like this and then I want this to happen
inside there so that everyone can use it
and go from there so let's just try
doing that here so let's suppose and
here we say that there's this extract
image call and everything that's going
to be done will get done every time by
the extract image call so it'll flip and
change the RGB the way we want it it's a
little bit of an open question whether
we want to do that at all
because another thing we could do is
switch to the RGB a ordering which is
the more normal ordering and so we
should have that discussion as well
because now might be a good time to do
that and so what we would really want to
do there is just go ahead and set up a
rien port for all of our cutscenes as
well and then just do one big rebuild of
all of our HSAs for fonts and everything
and then we can just have a clean slate
that we start with and we're not far
from be able to do that so we probably
should and so we should think about that
at that time because really the BG RA is
a Windows anomaly and we probably
shouldn't keep it inherited now that we
don't really need it for anything so we
here what I would say is oK we've got we
need that temper rena because we need to
be able to push this temporary buffer on
for doing the this work here what we
want to do is say we've got an image u32
that's the source image that can all
stay the same all of that information
can stay the same here but we can return
the tile image like so and I can call
this result now
right so we make the result here by
saying extract image do all this work to
it and so now we really just need to
know the bounds that we're actually
using so we say like min x max X min Y
max Y right that's what we're extracting
and so maybe I'll do min min max max and
off we go I think that maybe all we
really need here and this computation
really though has to be done on the
outside but other than that I think
we're good right
so when we call extract image we're just
going to pass a temporariness so it can
do its allocation we're gonna pass the
source image that we're extracting from
and then we're going to say like look
here's the here's the min and Max Y that
we need and the min and Max X that we
need
oops there we go
so what we want to do is pass in here
for the X and the y just our min and Max
values that we actually want here right
so here's the tile base and here's the
min and Max extraction inside the tile
base that we want to extract I think
that gives us what we want when we go to
down sample I'm sorry now when we go
down sample when we go to call extract
image for everybody else oh and this is
tile I'm sure they can do the same thing
now and do the extraction that will do
the flip upside down right so this will
be like a prep image call like so
and we will down sample that prepared
image instead of the source image so now
when we go to do this we know that we
just when we actually do the process
plate import all we have to do is say
well we want the whole thing right so
it's just going to be zero zero and then
whatever the source image is with was
and the source image is height now the
only thing I don't like about this is
that I feel like we should be passing
one past of them in and one past the max
because otherwise we're gonna do this
here and I don't like that because
that's very error-prone it could produce
bad outcomes like by wrapping the value
if it was zero or something like that so
I think we may want to do something
where we say okay let's modify this
routine slightly so that when we come
through here and do an extract image
we're really just gonna get rid of these
plus ones here couldn't do it like this
and so we're gonna do a subtract one
when we actually grab the value there so
that should be fine because we won't
loop over anything if the if we have a
zero in these cases and so it won't
matter what we push put in here for the
source row because we'll never read from
it so I think we're okay and I think
that's probably the way it should go so
it's really this you know I'm saying and
I think that's a little bit better just
because of the way the math works out
there so then when we pass this in here
all we need to do is just enlarge it by
one which is safer for us to do and then
I think we've got that import path
worked out much more cleanly than it was
before
that's all you're relevant now it's all
welded in right and I think we are good
so in here also I think we passed source
image it's not source image there's no
source image it's just image in there
there we go okay uh so temporary nough
here looks like I put that as the last
parameter which i think is good it's the
destination so I tend to put
destinations last so I'm okay with that
we'll just say that that happens here
and then I think we're done that's whole
path yeah so let's see now what happens
when we really get so if I delete the
local ehh-ehh and I create a new one so
I'm going to force the entire re-import
path which is so much slower debug mode
I guess I never realized quite how much
the optimizer helps there I suppose all
the PNG reading and the flippin bytes
and everything just gets a huge win from
the optimizer which it's cool but it
should force the re-import everywhere
hopefully no no doesn't let's see
looks reasonable I think we're just
going through doing all the down
sampling hopefully everything's working
properly
all right um so now what I'm seeing
looks entirely correct to me go ahead
and switch to optimize filter these what
I will say is that the lighting is a
little bit the the lighting mapping is
it's a little blown out right we need to
probably work on our lighting which we
knew was true ahead of time so that's
fine but it it's looking correct now
right we're getting exactly what I think
we should be getting in terms of of how
these assets are getting picked so
that's good
and we should be able to now
differentiate like two rooms right if we
wanted to do that so you know if we
wanted to have an outdoor area be forest
like we could do that and if we wanted
to down a dungeon to be dungeon like we
could do that right if we wanted these
areas to look to be stone so I think
we're now pretty much clean with how the
assets are getting picked so if I go
ahead and and switch back to the room
Jen for example I think that's probably
all we really need to know now when we
look at the general structure right so
you know inside the genuine structure we
don't have like this room spec thing
doesn't really have any information
about what should be going on in here
but we could make just a quick
modification to it just to figure out
whether this thing is working at all and
we could just say like look does have a
stone floor or not probably not how we
would want to do that normally but we'll
just say look that's a thing so then
when we go into the general we can pull
out the spec so in here we can say the
general spec for whatever this room is
is going to tell us whether it has a
stone floor or not and so in that point
what I can do is say look in here we
know that at the moment if it's a wall
it's always wood if it's not a wall
we're actually gonna set whether it's
wood or not based on whether the spec
says that it has a stone floor so we'll
say that the floor is stone in that case
and off we'll go right now if we've run
this we shouldn't see anything happen
because we'll never have set that so it
should always be false and we'll always
have the stone floor flag set to false
right but if we were then to change and
say well when we actually go to build
the world let's give some of the room
stone floors then what we can do is say
when we actually made those dungeons
right can see in here we've got like the
bedroom spec we generate expect there we
could say that we want the bedrooms to
have stone floors that's you know just
what happens because these are orphans
and their mouths
you know mistreated you know then when
we open it up we should expect to see
bedrooms having stone floors right and
then we can test it and they do right
now these are the hero's rooms which is
also technically a bedroom but they
don't get stone floors because that's
the save slot spec so we could make the
save slots have a different kind of
floor but you know if we play the game
now we see that their stone floors
in those rooms right which is what we
wanted so I would see really we're right
where I want to be so the other thing is
this a little repetitive here so if you
look at these you can also kind of see
that the floors are not they're all the
same
tiles but they probably shouldn't be so
there's one other thing we can do there
too which is in the room Jen right when
we go in here the the the UV layout for
these cubes is not being set so when we
actually when we actually want to set
this I believe inside the world the add
piece structure right sorry that's it
here so when we do an ADD piece I you
know it doesn't set anything about that
UV mapping so what I want to do is say
well when we do an entity visible piece
and we add one of those here I would
like to be able to set the cube UV
layout in situations where I think
that's appropriate and so one example
would be like if I want to do a
randomized top right so I could say true
on randomize top and if I want to do
rant two on randomize top you know I'll
just set this cube layout
if you remember how this thing worked we
can pack you view layouts here and
there's like a default packing for each
of these things right so what I want to
do this I want to say there's a bottom
index I don't care what it is I don't
care the facing index is there's four
sign indexes I don't care what those are
either right so these can all be zeros
then the top index I want to randomize
so I want this to be a number between 0
and 3 that says which one it is and
furthermore I could randomize it's
facing direction so I could I could just
totally randomize this if I want to just
again as an example not only want to do
exactly this way but something we can
expect so when we look here I can set a
random by using the generator entropy I
can come in here and say look give me an
entropic value that I can use to set
this so I believe we have a concept of a
random count so we can just say like
give me a random count of 4 right and so
set the facing Direction randomly and
which one of those four tiles you're
using randomly as well
I don't know why deleted the a there but
I did okay so maybe we don't don't we
have a random count random choice that's
what it is
sorry naming Naaman klaich our problems
so off we go and now what I want to see
is like if we well I'm not and I'm not
seeing it unfortunately so that's not
good but what I want to be able to see
here is I want to see some variation in
these and I'm not seeing it so that's
not great when I look in here I've got
randomize top set to true oh that's for
boobs that's for the walls so it is
working actual you can see they
disappear because there isn't one in
that part of the wall my back try that
one more time
so this should randomize both the
orientation and the selection of which
one of those wood grain floors it uses
and so now that's working you can see
that happening here and I don't know
that like I said we don't necessarily
want that I just want to make sure it
worked right so we now have the ability
to decorate our room server we want to
and that's good and we can go from there
so that all seems nice
and I think that's a good place to leave
it next weekend we'll start to kind of
go a little more crazy I don't
necessarily love the color variants here
that's happening there's there's a lot
of color variants there you don't
necessarily know why I think it might be
because do we have randomized color
perturbation here
we don't so that's actually coming from
the like reflective oh right because the
walls are like red and the ground is
green so we're actually seeing all those
bounce colors no no that's not true so I
don't know why that's happening that's
I'm not sure why we're getting those
vats because that's not actually what's
happening there um if I was to turn this
off we would actually have the old
colors come back and we probably want to
fuss with that as well but right yeah so
I don't know why we were getting some of
that coloring there but looking at again
the lighting is something that now we
have to take more seriously and that's
something we're gonna have to get
working better in this case here I guess
what I would say is maybe we just want
to back off on this reflectivity a
little bit but we need we also don't
have roofs which is another problem
because then there's nothing for the
light to bounce off of so we've got we
got issues so not sure why those are
transparent oh gosh you think possibly
the fact that you set it to transparent
could have something to do with it just
maybe alright um so yes so we've got a
lot of work to do on our sort of
rendering side of things now to clean
all that up but we're pretty close now
right let's do one more thing we can set
grass let's walk in here
yeah everything looks pretty good so I
think really we just need to improve the
lighting which we knew we had to do
already distribute sample points well
and clean up the algorithms a little but
we're looking pretty respectable yeah
I'm pretty happy with that
all right uh probably don't have much
time for Q&amp;A here I gotta go today so
I'll just take any really quick
questions about what we did if there's
any specific on topic questions I'll
take them and then we'll close it down
well you update the test asset builder
to version one I think what we'll
probably do now is delete the test asset
builder and roll the font thing into our
game code will not assert game code but
maybe the HHA thing so you can just
insert a font into it because the only
thing the test hasn't builder we don't
need anymore so I'd like to just get rid
of it you know I'm saying
so what was the reason for the blue oh
so the reason we were getting the blue
was because nobody was doing the swap so
remember we have a couple different
import past because we have different
formats for our assets one of the assets
types is tiled right and in the path
that we extract tiles from a PNG we were
swapping the R and B but in the path
where we took the whole PNG and put that
in as a texture itself
we weren't swapping so it was just a
case of we needed to unify the paths to
do manipulation of the PNG always no
matter which path we went down so that's
why I pulled out that extract image
function and made it so that everyone
calls that first because that way we
know that we're not going to get any of
the paths accidentally not flipping will
you write any unit test to cure
yourselves so when I said on topic
questions I'm wondering how someone
thought that was an on topic question
but I've talked about unit test many
times you can search the archive for it
in short they're not very useful for
games except for very specific
situations and occasionally you do want
to test those you know like things like
a memory allocator or trying to think of
other typical ones
job system memory allocator these things
can often be unit tested a little bit
there's a couple of things it can be
unit tested most of the time you can't
right and the reason for that is because
games are about random player input and
so typically what games do for testing
is not unit testing because unit testing
doesn't it only helps you find bugs that
aren't really the hard bugs what you
typically need is simulation based
testing so for example one of the things
that games usually do at least at the
higher end you know if you're triple a
game and you got resources they make
randomized testers so these are things
that play the game randomly they like
simulate a player sitting there just
doing random stuff and they try to find
sequences of inputs that will produce
crashes or allow the player to get
somewhere that they've marked the player
shouldn't get you know things like that
so typically if you want to map it on
something from like other types of
development it's more like fuzz testing
input fuzz testing is more like what
finds bugs and games than unit testing
unit testing is not usually relevant
because most of the code for a game
doesn't have a well-defined input in an
output it's about all these state
transitions that happen and you're
trying to find errors in the state
transitions that only happen when you do
some set of inputs and you don't know
what that inside of input is you can't
make a unit test you have to generate
randomized testing so you can still
consider that unit test if you want to
but it's not the kind you normally think
of where you're like let me brute force
all the inputs to this function or some
set of inputs this function and make
sure it has the right responses that
kind of testing fairly useless in games
the only kind of bugs those will find
are bugs you probably would have found
anyway so you really need if you want to
try and be robust is you need the
simulation based testing and that is
very valuable if you have time to do it
I highly recommend it but it can be very
complicated to writes much harder than
unit testing that's why a lot of people
just rely on play testing right that's
the that's the the poor person
approach
I've never streamed so I'm not sure
what's going on but why are John streams
left in the videos tab and yours aren't
oh because I just I don't set that
option in twitch I only put the things
in the archive all right well you tile
the fonts as well then possibly I think
we probably should there are two routes
we can go with that and I don't know
which one we should take one is we can
tile the fonts and the other is we can
just have a separate array for fonts
that's small fonts and particles that
might be the smarter approach and then
what we would do is we batch those
together so we set the texture array
once do a whole batch of font rendering
unset it yeah I'm saying so hard to say
we could take either approach I don't
know which one we should take but you
know so we'd have like a 512 by 512
texture right at 64 by 64 texture array
all the fonts and the particles go into
64 by 64 which has a lot more right
slots that kind of thing all right let
me wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me for
less that hand made here so I pleasure
coding with you as always we are now at
the point where we've got to start
pushing that sort of world gen stuff a
little bit more so we're gonna kind of
try to pull all these things together
and that's gonna be a fairly lengthy
process of like building out the world
and we need to take that in a couple of
waves right so first thing we want to do
is start to put the art assets where
they belong make sure our systems were
doing that work well and we're
comfortable we need to add some nice
abilities in there that we don't have
right now like the ability to spread
ground-cover around and things like that
and then we need to also tie the
lighting in so the lighting is still not
finished we need to bring that in get it
looking right so that's our next goal is
to make that all happen
once that's done we've kind of got our
game really set up and then we're just
on a game play code which we'll just
kind of do as we do not we're not game
designers here on and made hero so that
part of the process is gonna be pretty
odd hock and it's not really gonna be
about learning because well I can't
teach you that someone else is gonna
have to teach you that so we're getting
pretty close I guess is what I'm saying
we've done a lot of work and we've
pretty much built an entire game from
scratch and we're almost up to the part
where we would really step back and say
game designers it's your turn now but we
still have some quality stuff to do
before then and we will actually do the
game design ourselves for better for
worse after that process and it'll be
fun anyway to just have a game that we
made even if we're not particularly
talented at that part right I mean you
make the whole engine and get everything
working and support all this cool stuff
you might as well design a little game
in it right so yeah so we're getting
pretty close and you know doing the
world-building I think will be fun
because that is about programming and so
and you know tying that stuff together
so I think what enjoy doing that because
kind of rewarding to see the world come
together as well and all that stuff
anyway
that's it for today I'll be back here
next week to start on that side of the
process hope see you back here for that
till then half of programming I'll see
anywhere on the Internet tickets
everybody