okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero the show we could a
complete game live on stream we did some
work yesterday evening to add multiple
render targets to our software renderer
but although we actually succeeded in
doing that pretty quickly was not
difficult uh we actually have not
written the code to use any of those
multiple round target so although our
back and render now renders to multiple
render targets just fine you can't do
anything with them and well let's be
honest how interesting is it really to
have multiple render targets you can't
do anything with not that interesting i
would argue uh so let's see if we can do
something this time with our render
targets so here we are on day 3 17 if
you are following along at home you're
going to want to open up day 316 source
code because that is source code that i
am starting with right now and i will go
ahead and load up for you and I am
loading this for you everyone out there
I just want you know I am loading this
for you our very own handmade hero
source code and we are going to run it
and i'm going to show you what i mean
when i say that we're not using any
render target stuff so we did some weird
stuff where we shrunk down yet we got a
lot of stuff that we did that was weird
so we have a kind of weird screen going
on right now but it is actually all
correct this is what we meant to draw
for reasons you will know if you watch
previous episodes and we're running
through the software renderer right now
and we're running through the software
renderer in debug mode and we're still
getting close to 30 frames a second so
you gotta love computers because it's in
debug mode so it's much slower than it
normally would be but it's still it's
still hanging in there good for it so
anyway what we have to do now is we have
to figure out how we are going to get
this second render target in play and so
what I want to do is I want to go ahead
and move up here so now you can see I'm
standing in between two layers and we
intentionally made these little slat so
you could see a little easier you can
see these little green slats that have
the layer above us and they're kind of
coming in they're getting outfit in and
then you know as I come up they kind of
alpha in more and I can go back down
right and I can and I can sort of
control how alpha they are by how far up
or down this like sort of weird
stairwell thing I've made is so what I
want to do now is I want to move all of
the things that are on that layer into a
separate render target for starters and
then what it's going to do because we
don't do anything with it is those
things should disappear so is going to
hold the game here right and I'm just
going to use live code editing to just
go edit the code while the game is is in
that state and those things are going to
disappear in theory so let's go ahead
and jump over to entity dot CPP we know
from the way that we've set things up
here we set up our level indices we know
that basically our last level index our
maximum level index here is the one
that's going to be fogged out and in
fact not only do we know that but I
believe we're sort of already using that
piece of information I think oops not
fog I meant alpha my bad test alpha so
there we go so you can see us using the
test alpha here of the layer index that
we're on we're doing that only when were
on the maximum level index so what I can
do in this circumstance if I want to is
I can use the render target system that
we have set up to switch which of the
clipping rectangles I'm using so what I
can do here is I can say well if I'm at
the Maxwell maximum level index set the
render groups current clip clip wreck
things x to be the whichever one we're
using for the for that top level right
so we'll do like alpha
clip rekt like that and then otherwise
in any other case we'll just set the
current clip rekt index to you know
other you know normal floor clip rekt
right so we basically have two different
clip brecks that will create at the
beginning one for the current floor I'm
sorry 14 floors to get alpha doubt and
one for the normal floor right and the
normal floor can just use the standard
clip wreck that we're currently using
and so at the end of all this too we
could set the clip wrecked here at the
end when we exit because we're kind of
doing a little thing where we where we
oh well it looks like we're already
storing it anyway so that's totally fine
so what I want to do here is say okay I
know I've got to have two different clip
rectangle X so I'm going to have my
normal for clip wrecked index and that's
just going to be because we don't
actually need a new one we can just use
the standard one that everyone else uses
we can just say whatever the render
groups current clip direct index is is
fine with us but then we need an
additional clip rekt index and we need
that for the alpha floor clip wrecked
and i don't really actually know how to
make one of those because i forgot i
know we've gotta push clip wrecked here
and let's see so here's my push correct
call i'm going to call that I'm going to
use render target one since that's the
you know we don't really have any other
need for render targets at the moment so
I've got my render group and I I want to
draw out of the whole region I don't
actually remember if there's anything in
particular I guess it's just draw buffer
width and draw before height so I guess
we can just do drop off or withdraw
before height and now I guess in theory
I have pushed the clip prepped there
these are supposed to be era science I
admit that so let me fix that for you
there we go and so now in theory yet you
can see as I pop back here the alpha
stuff is gone and so let me just
underscore that point to you so that you
can see what I'm talking about here
again I'll just lean on sort of our live
code edit stuff that we built to just
make sure that I can
and show you exactly what's going on and
in fact I should probably do it in this
window huh alright so normal flora pract
is just using the regular pip rec alpha
floor clip wrecked which is the stuff
that's getting outfit out right that's
using this other render target so if I
set that regular target 20 now it's
rendering to the main render target you
can see it right if I set it to one now
it's rendering to a different render
target you can't see it so what we need
to do now to finish what we were trying
to accomplish is we need some way of
specifying what should happen to that
second render target when we go to
resolve all of the stuff that we have
now there's a lot of things we could do
here and which ones we do depend
entirely on what we are trying to
accomplish with our graphics engine now
I'm just going to do the most simple
basic thing that we might possibly want
to do i'm just going to write it so that
all we really have in there is a
hard-coded thing which says hey I'll you
know you can push a thing on which says
when you get here blit you know to
render target on top of the other random
target with an alpha value or something
right so I'm just going to make exactly
the one thing that we need but I would
point out here that you know i'm i'm
showing sort of this process in the
general case more to just give you the
awareness that you can have multiple
render targets and so you might decide
to do something more fancy if your game
could make more use of render targets
and doing things with render targets so
for example one of the things that we
would probably do if we were going to do
a bunch of fancier stuff with render
targets is we would want to go make it
so that was very easy for us to use
something that we rendered as a regular
sprite right that would just be
something we would do as a matter of
course I probably won't bother doing
that like I don't think I'm going to
bother with that because I don't think
we need it for anything
but you can see why that would be
powerful because what you'd want to be
able to do is say like oh render a bunch
of stuff to this render target and then
use that render target as a sprite
somewhere else which could even then
make another render target so you can
understand why you would want to make
that system more general if you had some
things in mind that maybe could leverage
that like if the look of your game could
benefit from some of those things so I'm
just going to show one simple case but
keep in mind that you know render
targets are very powerful tool and if
you go ahead and pipe them through and
do some more architecture work to make
it so that render targets and textures
can be used interchangeably that gives
you some additional power that I don't
anticipate taking any advantage of but
you might write so so keep that in mind
okay so let's see what we need to do
here here's our situation I'm going to
close this now because we don't need
that up and I'm probably gonna have to
reload the render which is in the
separate piece of code there so if I go
over to render dot cpp and I take a look
at what happens here with with all of
our rendering you know you can kind of
see we have these render targets here
and we're passing those render target
arrays to our renderer and when we go
through our sort entry indices like so
we pull out all of these different
things that we think need to happen
right and what I'm thinking is we could
just make one here that's sort of like
another case which is like render
grouped entry type you know render or it
resolved render target something like
that for you know blend render targets
I'm not sure something like this I guess
what do I want to say uh maybe i'll call
it apply render target or or now it's la
blend render target and all I'll guess
I'll do here is make it so that you can
say a destination render target and a
source render target and just smush them
together with an alpha value on top of
one of the existing ones that's there
right so that's all I want to do
and so I'm going to call a function here
that's called like blend render target
or something like that and you know it's
basically going to be instead of using
output target here although I guess I
could just use output target I suppose
that that's actually something I could
just do where yah where I guess I have
like the clip wrecked so how do I pass
how do I currently pass clip Breck's to
these things anyway do i what do i do
there I'm not actually sure surely
somewhere we do some kind of clipping i
would think I mean we have to so here's
where we do our clip rekt right so we
know what the clip Brecht is so I'm
going to go ahead and pass that down so
i'm going to pass clip wrecked and i'm
going to pass two things i'm going to
pass the output target and then i'm also
going to pass like a the you know source
target or something like that and i
don't know i guess we'll just take a
full color as well probably I feel like
so I feel like we would take like a you
know a color to apply to modulate
against like the target or something
like that I'm not sure exactly how we're
going to want to do this but i think we
probably want a color you know i'm
saying we could do something like one
color that multiplies the output target
and one color that multiplies the source
target as well so you know i could do
like
something like this so it's like do this
rectangle this color times this target
Plus this color times this target
written to the second second target like
overwrite this one that seems like a
pretty generic operation that we could
do and so that's what we need to write
our software renderer to do so if we
were going to get that out right it sort
of now implies exactly what the
information is that we would need to
have coming down here we basically have
a blend render target entry and that
blend render target entry just has to
have these things in it right it has to
have the source color it needs to have
the source target but it's going to be a
source target index right so really we
probably want to do loaded bitmap source
target equals render targets and then
it's like entries source target index or
something like that right and then here
we know the output target that's just
whatever you're currently drawing too so
all we would do is grab the desk color
out of there right so I think that's it
I that seems reasonable I guess to me
yeah and I don't know how we want to do
those colors I don't know if we want to
pass those colors in RGB or linear srgb
Atlantis I feel like I feel like we're
just going to call this guest modulate
and source module eight so it's clear
what it is that they're just multipliers
that they're not going to be adjusted
for srgb or anything else like that
they're just going to be straightforward
I think that's what we probably want to
do don't quote me on that we'll see when
we get in there and maybe we'll change
it around I'm not entirely certain
anyway internal void so we've got a
rectangle to I we've got a color and we
have a source target
and a output target and then we've got a
destination so something like that and I
feel like you know we can probably just
use essentially the same code that we
were using for our for our rectangle
fill which I don't really remember
whether we actually did an optimized
version but I think we did an optimized
version of the rectangle fill so here it
is right here is I've draw a rectangle
so I believe if I come down here I
should be able to just sort of snoop why
do we haven't why why do we have an if
okay it's it's a it's like here's the
old version kind of thing all right so
I'm going to go ahead and grab this and
I'm going to put this down here like so
so there's our blend render target and
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
start I guess I'll start with just
exactly the way we're doing it before
where we've got a a reference version
that I'll run first and make sure that
that works at all and then we'll go from
there right so okay so I believe that
this is just our and I can tell that
wrecked it's not really a clip wrecked
at this point so I should be able to do
this exact same thing here where I can
just call well I don't even need to call
anything because we've or it's already a
rectangle to I so we can go ahead and
get rid of all of this we don't need any
of this color stuff yet at the moment
and so really all we're going to do is
do this exact same loop here through all
of the code let me go ahead and place
those I don't know why they look like
that so
what I need to do now is I need to do
this operation this was a previously a
rectangle fill right so we started found
the road we were starting on well it's
actually the row and picks it like that
row and column we're starting on we
would increment it by the pitch every
time and then we just go through and
romp in the colors right but that's not
what we want to do this time around this
time around we need to do an actual
operation to create whatever the pixels
going to be so we need to do like an
unpack and then a pack of the colors and
and all that good stuff right so yeah so
we need to we need to do some work here
we need to do some alpha blending work
here and we need to do essentially the
following equation so we've got our
source color is going to have to be
something and our desk lar something's
going to be something we have to load
both of these right then we're going to
have to make our results our result has
to be you know our source color plus our
desk color and we have to sort of make
that operation work with an alpha value
the Alpha value in this case is going to
come from the source the source the
sources alpha is what's going to
determine it so we're basically going to
have you know a alpha value that comes
from the source colors alpha so we're
going to do one minus the Alpha this is
a standard the standard linear blend
we've used over and over again so we're
going to do one minus the alpha plus the
Alpha time suggests color to do our
blind right and now that's non
premultiplied alpha but of course it
should in theory be okay because we're
just doing pics of the pixel so we're
not doing any other operations so in
theory that should work and not create
any artifacts for us and it would be a
lot harder for us not to do it that way
because we would need to pre multiply
all of our colors by their alpha values
which I don't think we're currently
doing right like when we write into
those buffers I have to thank are we
actually doing that or not
you know I don't know I'd have to think
about that so when we write in an alpha
value we are taking the colors I guess I
guess technically well okay but the more
important part here I guess is that it
comes from the source color so obviously
that has nothing to do we didn't pre
multiply the things by that right so
that's the more important here the more
important part here for sure so I guess
that's that's a good point so really we
wanted to say the source color comes
from modulate that's actually I suppose
the more correct thing there because
we're loading it from that so okay so
that seems that seems a little more
plausible to me
yeah so if that's going to happen this
is going to be a little bit tricky
actually now that I think about it and I
suppose we could also not do the source
color desk color thing I'd have to think
about whether maybe I'm overcomplicating
that like maybe we're just creating too
many math ops in here so i suppose what
i could do also is just say maybe all we
have is the alpha between these two so
it's literally literally just a single
lerp you know so that way we can just
load you know source color desk color
these would just be loads the Alpha is
is just whatever we pass in so then we
do the one myself at times and plus the
Alpha for the desk color and maybe
that's maybe that's better that seems
reasonable probably also we want it this
way i would guess because we're probably
saying how much we want to go towards
the source target of course if that's
the case we probably want it to look
more like this because if that's the way
we would normally write a linear blend
right we'd say go from the desk to this
much of the source so probably that's a
little bit better all right so let's
take a look at this blend render target
so let's say we were going to do that it
would look like this entry alpha and
back we go all right so when we lift
these two fine fellows out of the bitmap
we're going to get you 30 tues basically
out of it right and we're going to have
like I'm going to have to have two of
these I'm going to have to have a destro
in a source row they're both going to do
exactly the same thing essentially it's
just the buffer part of things this is
going to be a desk target in both cases
and this is going to be a source
in both places right then through here
same exact thing happens we've got the
destro in the source row and they're
going to be updated by the desk target
pitch and thesaurus target pitch and
when I am advancing I need two of those
as well okay so in this case I've got a
desk pixel in a source pixel and so
we're going to do source pixel just
pixel and writing the desk pixel all
right so that's all we're really doing
for loading everything in it's just now
we're going to have to and in fact we're
pretty much done here it's just we need
to convert from u32 packed color up to a
vector do the math and then convert back
down to packed again right and so you
know that's that's this stuff right here
and yeah we don't we have some do we
seriously not have like a call to just
do an unpack with alpha
we haven't unpacked four by eight but it
doesn't it doesn't I mean with them with
gamma it's what I meant to say we do an
unpacked four by eight but it doesn't do
the gamma but well that's okay because
the gamma is just squaring the numbers
so i suppose i can do that part after
the fact so yeah so unpack four by eight
is what i need to do here and then do we
have a pack four by eight how is it that
we have a unpack four by eight but we
don't have a pack four by eight it's a
little strange it's not a little strange
maybe I'm missing something but it seems
I mean it just seems like we would have
written that evidently we didn't who
knows why certainly not me so anyway
that's all we're talking about here so
yeah so in theory we should be able to
just use that and happy birthday yeah so
like I said this doesn't actually do
alpha properly i mean the gamma properly
so i think we also want to do here a
like a square on the way in and we want
to do a square root on the way out if we
want the gamma to be respected because
those are frame buffer values which have
been stored in gamma a hue 322 that's a
lot of bits 322 bits maybe it's for
cryptography who knows I've got a few
typos here well not really typos a non
ported code that's what it used to read
let's go ahead and get that cleaned up a
little bit there just a little bit and
see if we're any better so what are
these s 30 tues yeah all right so now I
that's some going to be some real slow
nasty not very good code that we can sse
in a second you might even have time to
do that tonight we'll see maybe not but
we've got our our our render group has
to be able to actually store the fact
that the user wants to do this thing so
i'm going to go ahead and put that in
here oops so let's do render group entry
type ren
entry lend render target uh so yeah if I
do that then I should be able to create
one of these that just has the stuff
that I just said it had right so we've
got a struct it's one of these it has a
source target index it has a output
target which we know implicitly for the
clip wrecked it's got an alpha value and
it's got a source target which we
already know that's what I put right
there so it's really just that that's it
and that's still we needed so what is
the problem something should be preceded
by something else I need a colon that
would help for starters and render
target that should have looked like that
okay so now we're good to go this won't
do anything because no one is ever
pushing on that actual call right so
it's ineffectual so you can see we still
don't see anything happening there but
what I'm going to try anyway and let's
see if we can make this happen is I'm
going to try pushing one of those on so
you know we've got sort of this where is
it at here let's see perspective and
render group orthographic so essentially
what we need to do is we need to push
one of these on and we
need to push one of these on in a way
that you know is not going to get sort
of messed with or sorted with anything
else now previously we took the clear
and we sort of put the clear out in the
middle of nowhere and bye-bye sort of
putting it into a separate thing we kind
of need that to come back because like
right now we're not actually clearing
our render targets at all so we got we
got other things we're going to have to
deal with here but point being let's
start with one thing at a time I mean I
see what we are doing for that yes so
we're we don't actually clear anything
other than the initial render target so
really we probably need to clear all the
render targets or have the user
specified when to clear them so I think
we should probably do to do Casey put
clears back into the list just use sort
barriers to isolate them it's probably
the right thing to do so anyway here we
go I'm going to do this this way i'm
going to say target index equals 0
target index is less than commands max
render target index let's just target
index
wow so this way i'll just have it so
that everyone gets cleared using the
initial clear call of course that's not
going to live code voted because that's
not actually in there but ok so inside
handmade render group if i wanted to do
a composite operation here what i'm
going to do is say well uh you know I
want to do a standard push call here
right I like I would like to do
effectively like what push a bitmap does
or actually you know probably more
probably more almost like what push clip
wrecked does i think probably something
more like that yeah so i'm going to i'm
going to grab this guy and I'm going to
put it down here I'm gonna go ahead and
say push a target blend or something
like that push blend under target and I
call this the source render target index
and what I'm going to do here is I'm
going to ask for a push buffer push I'm
going to say that I want a sort entry
and I want a render entry clip correct
I'm sorry render entry blend source
render target assuming I get one of
those I'm going to go ahead and fill it
out and this stuff is all irrelevant
so yeah so when I push and I asked for
the sword entries if the render target
stuff I don't ever want this to be
sorted I want it to just happen in the
stream where ever you say it's going to
happen so I'm going to try something
here where I just push three sword
entries on and so those three sword
entries are going to be like to sort
barriers and just one op you know this
operation basically so let's see here
how do I push a sort barrier it's really
just that and so what I should be able
to do here is set these up in that way
so let's see so let's just do a sword
entry so push sort entry how does that
happen how does that happen where is
that struct there it is I wish you to
come out to the outer side of things
there we go so our sword entry zero and
our sword entry two are going to look
like that but our sword entry one is
going to look like the actual offset
that we care about right
this value basically so I'm you know I'm
a little confused as to why this is
called header why did we call that
header because is it actually the header
and if it is the header isn't this wrong
hold please while I think about this
yeah so so isn't isn't that wrong when
we do a push clip wrecked oh I guess not
because the push clip rekt doesn't need
the header so I suppose that's actually
okay but this guy does so this is this
this guy actually does care about that
if that makes sense because he's an act
he's a real he's a real thing so I've
got this rectangle push happening here
blend render target I guess we don't
need any of these this is really blend
so this blend is going to have a source
render target index which we took and an
alpha value which I forgot to have but
that's it and the other thing that I'm
not sure about is we have to fill out
some of the other bits i think here so
you know i could also and i probably
should now i think about it i should
also probably go ahead and take rather
than doing sort of that finicky stuff
myself i suppose i could take this and
still just use it and just do a push
sort barrier just do instead of trying
to be efficient about it because it's
not something is going to happen very
often i could instead just do hey do one
of these guys where I do a push render
element oops of render entry blend
render target I see here again
and rectangle to I screen area we don't
care about and sort sprite bound sort
key these are meaningless because we're
not actually going to ever have it sort
against anything so they can just be
completely irrelevant that makes sense
and then I don't have to do this so now
that I've got my blend I can do about
whatever I want and then I just need to
put some code around it that will
prevent this from being a problem so I
can push a sort barrier here push
another sort barrier here and then I
know that nothing like when that was
said it will do the blend at that time
and it won't sort against anything else
or create problems for anybody right so
that seems good
alright so now i should be able to do
this blend if I want to so if i go into
entity dot cpp i'm going to do this in
two steps here the first step I'm going
to do is I'm actually going to re-enable
this momentarily so I can see what I'm
drawing so there they are I'm did that
so that i can go that i want to take
that alpha and i want to get rid of it
so this entity transform t color bit we
want that to just be I guess all zeros
in this case right so now it's
completely a pake and what was the
actual value there okay
so I'm going to make that be that way
and so now we know what's getting drawn
properly and then at the end we will
composite those on top of each other so
then what I'm going to do is push one of
these plans the source target index and
the test alpha and off we should go of
course what are we doing here we
actually don't care too much about this
so it's always just maximum level index
we can simplify this a little bit now
that we know what we're doing all right
oh dear that didn't go well it looks
like this is for some reason did we are
we still compiling in optimized man ah
no wonder we were kidding 30 frames
second that did seem a bit high for one
hop demise but ok nevermind I take it
back now will be much much slower ok so
let's see here it looks like our source
target is bogus I'm not sure why
for some reason the max render target
index is 0 but it definitely suck up
that's actually correct we aren't using
that render target yet so I'm going to
do alpha floor render target is one off
the floor render target and then so that
is actually a a correct crash no one
should have called that's okay so now
we're doing an incredibly expensive
incredibly slow composite step I should
probably compile in a release mode to
have any prayer of running this and as
you can see it's horrifically slow right
because we're doing this really
expensive really slow sloppy stuff for
every pixel there and that's nobody's
not good for anybody all right so if we
come up here let's get to a point where
we should be seeing some alpha like here
for example and it doesn't look like
we're getting any like okay so we kind
of it kind of looks like whenever we're
expecting to see something here we're
not actually seeing anything so I'm
going to step in well of course it's
going to be all optimized unfortunately
so I don't know that I can see too much
but I want to get a sense of what's
happening in our in our blend code
well
thank you welcome tablet I did not
actually want to do that
mm-hmm
alright so that's some fantastic typing
there so we're going to have to fix that
to say the least so obviously if the
source color is getting square I don't
even know I was kind of sleeping here
obviously i don't know what i was doing
exactly that's supposed to be both of
these were supposed to square themselves
and then this one's supposed to be
result so that was just like cut and
paste fun or copy pasta as people I've
heard call it on the stream alright so
that should at least be slightly more
sane but we'll see it still may not be
correct
not seeing anything
hmm very strange so we unpack our source
color and our desk color from the pixels
we are writing to des pixel so you'd
think we would see something happening
here but apparently not so we square of
these for gamma purposes so whatever the
source color and desk low that we loaded
our we get squared versions of them we
then do a loops yeah we then do alpha
blends I'm going to go ahead and just
see because I would like to to find out
what happens if I just hard code the
Alpha to fifty percent
so it literally does not matter what the
Alpha is it does not produce anything
interesting
I'll admit that's a little confusing
well I guess it's time to step in so
what I'm going to do here is we're going
to say i would like to break any where
the source pixel is not zero so I'm just
going to go ahead and run I did change
the build to debug did not yes so I'm
just going to set a breakpoint there and
I want to see what happens when we have
a source pixel that's actually got
something in it so I can see what
happens all right so here's our source
color here's our desk color there's our
alpha oh those are thus it what did we
pass the same target
what
ah i see what happened very clever Casey
we outsmarted ourselves this transient
clip rekt will not restore the old clip
rekt until after we're done right so
it's kind of completely useless actually
thanks for nothing transient clip
wrecked so what we actually want to do
here is we actually want to manually set
the current clip rekt to be the normal
clip rekt right there so that was the
problem we were basically blending the
render target with itself oh that is
pretty can we play the game like that
Wow I kind of like that I kind of want
to see that running in full at full
speed I was not expecting that I'll be
honest that was not what I was expecting
to see but I kind of want to see that
again
whoa
that is wicked cool
that is really really cool all right uh
well you know cool as it is it's not
correct so you know we're going to have
to stop doing it but let's just take a
look at what's going on here with that
so we should be having an even blend
here these are getting squared what is
owed is this leaving it to is this
leaving it in 255 space though yeah so
this is leaving it in 255 space so if
what after I do that unpack I'm going to
have to I'm going to have to oh there's
my weight srgb where is srgb bilinear
blend
this is what we actually wanted all
right so basically that was just me not
remembering what we had actually written
so that will take care of it for us I
was going to say I've got a ticket out
to 25 face it looks like we already have
a thing for that yeah there are bent you
know downsize to streaming one hour a
night you forget the stuff that you've
already written pretty quickly anyway so
after the unpack I guess we can just do
srgb to linear what does that do so it
does the in 255 and it does the square
so that does everything that we wanted
and linear 12 s RGB 255 does the exact
opposite okay so we did already have the
stuff it just wasn't in this file good
to know
so really all we needed to have done was
that right and now we're at least
running through the old paths in a more
correct way okay so now we're but it
were being operating in theory in the
right space where they were still
sparkly which is weird so to be 25 to
linear one after the unpack refuge for
later one after the unpack of those two
we do the blend then we do a linear one
test three be 255 and then we do the
pack oh but the pack four by eight does
the multiply so to make these symmetric
the packed four by eight should not be
doing that right that's actually the
correct operation now okay so I think
we're getting closer to being correct
but obviously we still have some issues
here I'm kind of loving whatever is
happening with some of that drawing
though that's pretty spiffy all right so
let's go ahead and put the correct alpha
value back in because we were stuffing
the Alpha value before which we don't
want to do uh yeah and then we may be
out of time so we may have to do the
rest of the debugging tomorrow or the
end the SSC version or whatever because
it looks like it's still drawing
somewhat incorrectly or something is
happening odd I'm not sure what exactly
will find out I suppose so let's go
ahead up here
why am I not seeing are we not passing
the Alpha value down I love that you
have to switch that thing tick that's
the weirdest thing why are we always
passing zero it seems like we're seems
like we're not actually passing a valid
value there
I think maximum level index is wow yeah
that's just that's just bogus what we
actually want is the array count so
really and plus I guess the other thing
too is we don't really need the Alpha
for anything else so really you know we
just I mean we could just do this this
is what we actually want right that was
just ouch to screw up ok so now I think
we're good let's go ahead and run
evidently not and the test alpha from
top starts Z to top NZ camera relative
ground
I feel like that should be going the
right direction yes from the top start
to the top end do they go yeah so they
go in in height order so it should be as
you get higher you get closer to one
right if I'm looking at that correctly
so it should be that at first it should
be very low it should be like an alpha
value of zero right and yeah so I'm not
one hundred percent sure why we're
seeing that I would like to take a quick
look at that let's see here
I love how it can't ever tell you any
values in release mode it's like I have
no idea so how did test alpha get to be
1 point 0 in this case I'm very
interested to see that so if i come
through here right i'm going to loop
through here a few times and when the
level index gets to be five right which
is how many there should be or six note
my guess is five ok I 1.5 say top end so
this is a bit strange so that's saying
that the final camera ground Z so these
why were these set to what they were did
we have some other weird bug that was
happening why weren't these when we were
using the test alpha before why were we
seeing stuff fade in like that we have
we have a bug here that's different we
have some kind of a different bug that's
going on
it must have been that before let me see
this is level index 5 maximum level
index is what one and how are we
computing which one to use before we're
using the relative layer minus the
minimum level index
so it's whatever the entities Z layer
was minus the chunk origin z
so that should equal one I agree with
the fact that that should equal one on
the maximum level index and that maximum
level index though
you would think would only have been one
floor heights worth up which I guess is
what it is you know what no so it's just
been a slow night and I guess it
continues to be a slow night so that is
actually true the higher the thing is
the less the Alpha value should be so
this is yet another case of like okay
every time we flip the meaning of alpha
we have to switch the way that range is
computed so no need for panic that was
actually the case and off we go first I
really do need to compile in Nam debug
mode but off we go all right so now
we're still slowly limping along here
limping limping we're going to have to
SSE this tomorrow as you can see
there we go now we're actually blending
that incorrectly so the current problem
just looks to me like that for whatever
reason is either not clearing or not
it's not drawing that second layer
correctly so we have some other bug in
the in the render group code that is
keeping us from being correct yet and we
want to be correct before we do any of
the optimization so we'll have to take a
look at what's going on there for
certain the clear there we go the clear
was only clearing the first one because
number it's a max render target index
not the count so the clear has to clear
both of those so that could have been
part of it as well if it just wasn't
clearing maybe everything else is
actually fine so let's give that one
more shot
okay now it looks like we're good okay
all right so that's all good we do have
one problem here which is the clear is
clearing at one point 0 alpha because
it's using that draw rectangle call so
we need to do like to do kc clear also
has to actually clear not blend because
the alpha is wrong so we have two things
we have to do tomorrow one is we have to
make it so that we're actually doing
clear and we should just go make an
actual clear and like not a blend and
the other one is we have to go SSE that
but then I think we're good let's go
ahead and QA
Geiger Lovecraft themed handmade zero
DLC ha doubtful soy sauce the kid are
you willing to are you writing to the
second buffer all the time if so is it
possible to only use when you need it
like during trans the transitions uh so
yeah we could we are not writing to the
second buffer when we don't need it in
the sense that if we just don't output
anything to it it will never get seen so
what we can do if we want to and this is
pretty easy is in here we can just do
like right so this way we just do only
if the the Alpha is actually enabled do
we bother doing any of this stuff and
then you would never actually pay the
cost of it right so the only thing that
we have to do is and I guess I could
also do that right now to the only thing
that we have to do is not draw anything
that was going to have an alpha there so
like I guess you don't know what the
easiest way to do this would be probably
something like
we just want to clip these out in the
case where we can't see them so probably
like you know we we'd have something
called likes top-level index and we just
do like stop level index equals maximum
level index stop level index so we
default the saying don't draw anything
above that layer and then only in the
case oops only in the case where we
actually know that we're going to draw
those things do we bother right so then
you're not actually paying the cost of
that except when you're when you're in
transitions like so you can see the
framerate take a huge hit there right
but you know ideally I don't know
whether that's really all that great I
mean at the end of the day because you
figure I you don't want your framerate
to be slow at certain times so you know
I feel like we should make sure it's
just fast enough to always be doing that
it's neither here nor there
andrew has how does the limbless child
limp along exactly you know just really
powerful AB strength i think inquiry how
many floors can this code support i
envision a tall tower or stairwell
peering down 20 or so floriston singh
nbc's acting as normal was that your
intent well really it's gated mostly
just by the performance and we're not
like I'm never gonna have 20 floors down
because you wouldn't you'll be able to
see them that the shrinking would be
such that you would have to have 20
floors with it's the exact right shapes
you know going down them or whatever to
make that happen so we're probably that
six I think was the number that we were
using that we thought looked neat but
yeah it's supposed to do exactly that
you supposed to be able to look down
there and see like oh there's some stuff
happening down there and maybe I need to
go down and there and do something
because I see something interesting so
that was why we're doing all the extra
work to support it in a cool way I think
it's going to be really cool once you
put some art in there and clean up all
the rough edges because we've got a lot
of nice stuff
knut goals how do you use trace files to
debug someone trying my game I had a
crash and sent me a 95 megabyte dump
file since you once said it's helpful I
don't doubt that but what do you do with
the damn thing well so unfortunately the
answer may not be super useful to you
this time around but hopefully we are
useful next time around the answer is
you need to when you do a build that you
ship to some two people two testers you
need to save the PDB file and the source
tree at that time like off to a separate
directory or something and then what you
can do is you can actually load them I
don't know if there's an easy way to
load them in here you can load them in
windbg but I think you can load them in
here I'm not always so good with
developer studio but I believe you can
actually load them in here
uh let me put this way if you search on
the internet there should be a thing
that tells you how to load them in here
you can definitely load them in windbag
windbg which is a free debugger that
Microsoft ships for debugging crashes
and stuff like that but the idea is if
you save the PDB and all of the source
code you can then load the dump into the
debugger and see in the code where you
crashed and get some stack information
as well usually depending on what kind
of crash it was so in theory anyway in
theory you should be able to do that
next time if you happen to save have
saved the PDB and the source code from
when you built the XE you sent you could
use the one that that they sent you but
if not then then not really
alright not many questions so I think we
can go ahead and wrap it up alright
thanks everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along at
home you can always peer to the game on
handmade hero org it comes with a source
code so you can play around with it
yourself and do some experimenting we
also have a forum site you can go to ask
questions a patreon page if you want to
support the video series we have a
schedule about that'll tweet the
schedule at you if you would like to
know when we're going to be live and an
episode guide if you're trying to catch
up on old episodes that's it for today I
will be back here tomorrow I believe 5
p.m. pacific daylight time until then
have fun programming and i'll see you on
the Internet take it easy everyone